Good morning.
Thank you for picking this as your first talk, not counting the keynote.
Today we're going to be talking about code quality metrics, which is something that's
of great interest to us down at Sorcery.
And we're going to be talking in particular about how to use and how not to use code quality
metrics.
So let's start off by talking about code reviews.
Who here does code reviews?
Who gets their code reviewed from time to time?
Raise your hands.
Yeah, that's pretty much everyone.
Who does code reviews?
Who code reviews for other people?
Yeah, that's quite a lot of most of us here.
Who's a solo developer and doesn't do any code reviews at all?
Yeah, I thought it might be one or two.
And who thinks their code reviews are objective?
That's what I thought.
So today we're going to be talking a little bit about how to introduce some objectivity
into your code reviews in certain situations.
So for that, we are going to introduce some metrics, then try to show how you can gain
insights from those metrics.
And we think it's very important to talk about the pitfalls of those as well.
I'm Reka and my colleague is Ben.
We both work at Sorcery on code quality tools, which includes refactoring automation and
automated code reviews.
So that's one of the reasons why we are so interested in this topic.
And in the years before joining Sorcery, I worked at FinTech APIs.
And as I said, I'm Ben and before joining Sorcery, I did a PhD in material science and
then worked as a data analyst and data engineer at a fint-ech company.
So throughout this presentation, we're going to be looking at a few code snippets.
We're going to be doing some code review, in fact.
And as we go, we're going to be normally going to write and I just want to get your initial
opinion.
And the reason for this is that these code quality metrics are sort of designed to mirror
our personal biases, our personal feelings about what good code looks like.
So when we see these things on the screen, I'm going to call out on the right and let
me know which one you prefer.
Let's get started with the first one.
We've got two snippets on screen and without any sort of in-depth reading into what these
do, who prefers the code snippet on your left, the one on my right?
One person.
Interesting.
And who prefers the one on the left, my left, your right?
That's most people.
That's kind of what we guessed.
And when we talk about these sorts of pieces of code, we've generally got several bits
and pieces of code.
Things like whether it is Pythonic, whether it is elegant, whether it is short, whether
it is flat.
We talk about naming conventions.
And all of these are very useful terms, but they fall into a bit of a bit of a region
of difficulty if we're not thinking more specifically about how to apply those terms.
So to introduce our very...
All right.
So to introduce our...
So again, very similar to what we've seen in the past.
So again, very similar question to the previous one.
Please take a look at these code two snippets and raise your hands if you prefer the one
on the left.
And please raise your hands if you prefer the one on the right.
And probably the reason is that the second one is significantly short, which introduces
our first very simple but surprisingly useful metric functional length.
And here we counted the statements in these snippets, but in Python it's even simpler
to count the lines, which is often very close to the number of statements at least.
And this can already give us some good feeling about how complicated the code is.
So if you come to the conclusion after this talk that the other metrics are way too complicated,
not worth the hassle, that is already a way to make your conversations about code a bit
more specific and a bit more numeric.
And one thing which functional length has in common with the more sophisticated metrics
that it definitely has its limitations.
As this one single statement shows, it's not always a good thing to strive for the shortest
possible solution.
So this introduces the next, a bit more sophisticated quality metric.
Which snippet do you prefer from these two?
Please raise your hands if you like more the one on the left.
Thanks a lot and raise your hands if you prefer the one on the right.
Thanks.
And here the difference isn't in size, but rather in complexity, which leads to our next metric.
Yeah, so we all know the danger of one-liners.
This next metric is a way of sort of overcoming some of the difficulty in describing code
in terms of shortness.
Cyclomatic complexity is essentially a measure of the number of branches in your code.
There's a more mathematical description, but we don't really need to get into it.
The right here shows, has seven branches.
And by a branch we just mean different routes that might happen through the code depending
on the initial conditions.
And the one on the left, the sort of intuitively nicer one, nominally only has one branch.
Now I've put, because in practice it's obviously more than one way through this code.
But the cyclomatic complexity was developed quite some time ago.
The calculation is simple for every if statement, every try, accept block, and there's a few
other conditions as well.
We just add one, and that is the total cyclomatic complexity of the code.
As I said, this was developed quite some time ago, back in the 70s.
And it was at a time when code was significantly more monolithic than it is today.
This is a famous photo of Margaret Hamilton with her code for the Apollo 13 program.
When testability and maintainability were really important.
Testability in particular is closely related to cyclomatic complexity.
The more branches you have in a piece of code, the more things you need to test going through it.
So that was why it was developed and why it's still hanging around.
It is quite useful just as that first guess of how do we go beyond function length.
But it too has its limitations.
These two pieces of code are a bit more similar than the ones we've seen.
But just as again, rough intuition, who prefers the one on my right on your left?
And who prefers the one on my left, your right?
Yeah, so that leads into the development of cyclomatic complexity into our next metric.
This is called cognitive complexity.
And both of these snippets have a cyclomatic complexity of three.
But the major difference is that on the left we have a nested structure.
And on the right we have exactly three top level branches.
And this is something which cyclomatic complexity doesn't make a difference of.
But cognitive complexity penalizes not just new branches, but every nested structure,
which gives this very short snippet a cognitive complexity score of eight.
And cognitive complexity was developed as an improvement of cyclomatic complexity.
And one significant difference between the two metrics is the nesting,
which we have just presented.
Another one is that it also penalizes recursion.
And on the other hand, it tries to incentivize good coding practices,
which it calls shorthand structures, which summarize multiple lines of code in one.
And this is something where Python really shines, for example,
with list comprehensions and context managers.
And cognitive complexity is much newer.
So it was developed in 2016.
And I encourage you to check out the Sonar's paper,
which has been updated since then regularly.
And in the introduction, they mentioned that cyclomatic complexity
does a good job of providing testability, especially branch coverage.
But maintainability is a different thing, which has a lot of other components.
And one thing which they put a lot of emphasis on is readability for humans.
And that's why, for example, nesting and
recursion are regarded as not so great features.
Of course, cyclomatic and cognitive complexity,
both have their limitations as well.
Because here, both scores for this snippet would be one.
But probably, you still wouldn't describe this as really readable.
So to motivate our next metric, we're gonna do a little exercise here.
It's not code review.
There are three numbers on screen.
And the next slide is gonna be blank.
And I'm gonna ask you to put your hand up if you'd feel confident remembering
these three numbers.
Hands up.
Good.
I'd expect nothing less.
Seven numbers on screen now.
I'm gonna give you three, two, one to remember.
Who would feel confident remembering those seven numbers after that?
Yeah, okay, about half people.
That's kind of what we'd expect.
You can see what's coming next.
Two, one.
And who'd feel confident reciting out those numbers?
I think there's 13 there.
No one, interesting.
We'll come back to that in a sec.
Well, that's cheating.
So this is a very well-known psychological phenomenon.
It's difficult to keep more than about seven things in your brain for
short periods.
So this motivates our next metric, which we call working memory.
And this is a very much work in progress thing that was developed down,
that's also by Brendan and Nick.
So there's a number of ways we could describe the calculation for
working memory.
This is the one I've chosen for this talk.
The essential idea is that for each statement,
we look at the number of variables in use.
We look at the number of variables which are no longer in use, but
you might need to keep in your brain to work out what's gonna happen.
And we also add an additional penalty for
conditions because the context matters, basically.
As we work through a function or something,
we look at the peak cognitive complexity and we use that to describe,
sorry, the peak working memory and
we use that to describe the overall working memory of that piece of code.
And as I already mentioned,
this is based on the sort of seven plus two rule in psychology.
Now, you might sort of think, well, I don't need to remember everything.
And that's 100% true.
It's one of the major limitations of the working memory as a metric.
For instance, if you knew that these numbers we just looked at were part of
the digits of pi, you might have a much easier time
reciting or being confident about those last few numbers.
Does anyone know pi to 25ish places?
Yay.
So this, as I said, one of the main limitations is it's very difficult to
specify what people need to know as they're reading code.
Do they need to remember the elements of the standard library?
Do they need to remember the context of the package that they're working in?
There's a sort of element of expertise that comes in here.
So it's subjective and it's a bit difficult to define, but
it is quite well rooted in psychology and in code style, as we'll see in a bit.
So we have just seen four different metrics.
Two of them were trying to measure the size of a code snippet and
two of them the complexity.
And for both, we have a human focused and a code focused view.
And what this small matrix is trying to show us that it's not that one of those
is necessarily better than the other, but these are all important aspects of
readability.
And it really makes sense to try to improve all of them.
So to shorten your functions and aim for conciseness,
to reduce the cyclomatic complexity and create specific methods,
which don't have too many branches, reducing a cognitive complexity by
nesting those branches, also following the Xenoph Bison.
And also reducing the working memory by being conscious about the scope
of the variables we introduce.
And we have already seen four metrics,
which sometimes perhaps contradict each other.
And sometimes it would be perhaps nice to have one single score showing whether
a code has gotten better or worse.
So at Sorcery, for example, we use a weighted average for this.
And another very interesting attempt for this is the maintainability index
in PyCon 2019.
That was an excellent about this from Anthony Show.
So if you are interested in metrics generally,
I encourage you to check out the video about that.
So let's take a look at some ways we can measure some of these things for
real repositories.
So here I've got a type of chart.
It's called a box and plot.
If anyone's familiar with Seaborn, you may have played around with this.
Box and plot is basically a sort of discretized distribution.
It's one way of, it's an extension of a box plot essentially.
And each of the boxes corresponds to a quartile.
And what we're looking at here is the function length for
all the functions in some of these repos.
We haven't picked these for any particular reason other than that they
are popular, they're well tested, and they're quite familiar to people.
Notice on the bottom, I've got a log scale.
So these metrics on the far right are particularly long functions.
We've got functions with well over 100 lines in them.
There's a couple of things I want to draw your attention to.
One is the line down the middle of the box represents the median.
And what I found really interesting looking at this, the first time was, well,
the median of all of these, the median function length in all of these packages
approximately the same, it's between five and six.
And that just indicates, well, if we want our code to be maintainable,
easy to use open source stuff, any of the five to six lines in your function,
that's a good style guide.
And that's the thing that I want to draw from this.
The other thing is, as I already mentioned, there are serious outliers.
And we'll talk a bit in a moment about why the outliers are important.
As well as function length, we can look at the cyclomatic complexity,
that's in blue, and the cognitive complexity.
I've drawn these side by side because they're quite similar.
The only thing I'm going to draw attention to beyond the last slide was, well,
as we'd expect, the cognitive complexity is a little bit more than the
cyclomatic complexity for most of these repositories, as we'd expect.
The working memory, and this is something I alluded to earlier, again,
the median of all of these repositories has an approximately equivalent working
memory. And that's really nice because, and it says, oh, whether by design or
from a happy accident, these functions have grown to have a working memory
about nine. That's within the sort of, you know, parameters of what we can keep
in our brains. So it's a good indication that the psychology that was developed
for the working memory metric is actually seen in practice even without trying.
Another interesting way to look at these numbers is to compare the numbers of the
same repository across time. And here we can see the cognitive complexity of a
specific repository. So you can find some more similar analysis at repoanalysis.com.
Here we just picked the repo, which shows a pattern which is probably a bit typical.
So we see cognitive complexity, so the lower numbers are better. And we see that
this package started out with a fairly high complexity. Then around version 0.8,
there was a big rewrite which significantly decreased this complexity.
And since then, there is a trend of sometimes going a bit up when new features
are added and then come a period of refactoring and stabilizing where it
complexity goes down. This is the repository where we show where the data
comes from because it is our own. And here you can again see the cognitive
complexity. And it looks like quite good. So since 0.8, we have added quite a lot
of new features and the cognitive complexity has been still decreasing
continuously. So everything nice. That's another representation of the very same
repo. And it tells a little bit of a different story because we see that while
the average complexity has been decreasing, we have also managed to add new
outliers in this period. And I think this is a very general pattern which we tend
to oversee that even if we really care about quality and know how to try to
improve it, we still add new outliers and it means we add new technical depth.
Let's talk quickly about code quality. And I'm going to draw an analogy with test
coverage as another metric that we're probably quite familiar with. High test
coverage, as we all know, doesn't necessarily mean that your tests are great.
There's lots of ways that we can test things badly that nevertheless cover all
of our code. However, it's important to note that low test coverage probably means
your tests are pretty bad. And there's an analogy here with the code quality
metrics. High code quality or good metrics, short functions, low cognitive
complexity. That doesn't mean that your code is good. However, having high
numbers of these functions probably indicates that your code is bad. And
that's how we interpret some of these things. The higher numbers are less
useful than the lower numbers.
So at the beginning, we mentioned that these metrics can help us in various
conversations about code. And one of these decisions is refactor or rewrite.
So for example, let's assume that you are developing an application for an online
conference and you need to handle time zones. And there is already some time zone
package in your organization which has been used occasionally. And there is a
discussion within the team members. Some of them say that, yes, we obviously
should reuse what we already have. While other team members say that, oh, no, that
code is quite difficult to understand. We are afraid that it contains some hidden
bugs. Let's just write something completely new. And this is the kind of
conversation which has the danger of getting emotional pretty quickly,
especially if the author of the library is involved. And we definitely don't say
that this kind of a chart will give you an explicit answer whether to refactor
or rewrite. But it can give some good hints that, yes, there are many quite...
So the majority of this library looks quite good. But again, we have some quite
big outliers. And taking a look at these very complex functions is probably what
should decide whether it's worth keeping working with this. Besides that,
another decision where these metrics can give us some guidances, what to refactor
and how to refactor. So regarding what, again, the outliers, like there is some
functions with complexity around 70 there. So if you have something like a
cleanup week or whatever, probably these are the ones where it makes sense to
focus the most effort. And probably these are the ones which need the more
additional test cases because they are the most probable to hide some bugs.
And regarding how to refactor, usually these different metrics tend to correlate
strongly with each other. So shorter functions are also less complex. And if
there is a big discrepancy between them, that's often a sign that some specific
kind of refactoring would be beneficial. So this is, again, an example from
thisrepoanalysis.com. And this specific... In this module, the average functional
length is just under three. But the average working memory is above 13,
which is definitely above that optimal range. And this is an indication that
we try to probably squeeze a bit too much information and too many different
variables into those short functions. So in that case, we probably are missing
some levels of abstraction and we should introduce new data structures,
new classes, something like that. So that's to summarize this section.
It seems that there is a general agreement on some elements of good code
style, like this median functional length of five, six, which I'm presenting,
and that keeping the working memory under 10 is the idea. It's very important
to say that poor quality provides more information than good quality numbers
because good quality code can be still difficult to under... So code with good
numbers can be still difficult to understand. And when you are doing such
analysis, probably the most valuable information are the outliers,
which show some areas for improvement.
Also, we've seen some ways that we can use code quality metrics,
but the title of the talk includes a bit about how we should not use
code quality metrics. So we're gonna go through a bit of that now.
One obvious problem with metrics in general is that they're typically
gameable. We all know of ways that we can come up with
systems to do code coverage, for example, that doesn't actually test anything.
I also heard a story yesterday of somebody who'd wrote a package which had
100% code coverage in their tests, but none of the tests contain any
assert statements. This is the kind of thing that can cause a problem.
We also really shouldn't be looking at using these types of metrics as developer
performance metrics. They are biased. They adhere to a particular style,
and those styles aren't universal, and they certainly aren't necessarily
applicable depending on the type of project you're approaching.
We've also mentioned something about average code quality here.
Averaging is a real problem for these types of metrics because,
as we've already seen, they tend to live on a sort of logarithmic style scale.
And the average, that dotted line on your far left there,
that's way skewed low. The thing that we're most interested in probably
is these outliers. So averaging, ranking, and sort of trying to use these things
as developer performance indicators would, I think, become a real problem.
Besides that, it's important to mention that code quality contains some elements
which aren't captured by any of these metrics. And here we see some examples
for bad naming, like not-so-descriptive names and descriptive names,
but not consistent terminology. Another important aspect is that these metrics
are all quite on a short scale, so they measure functions or perhaps
a module level, but they don't tell us anything about the structure of a project,
and also not about the external API of it and how convenient it is to use it.
So let's wrap up. We've seen a number of code quality metrics today.
This is by far, this is very much not an exhaustive list, but as we saw
from the matrix, it does sort of tend to capture a reasonable subset
of what we'd expect to understand about our code quality. So we talked
about the function length, probably one you already all knew about,
things about the cyclomatic complexity, the cognitive complexity,
and this idea of working memory.
And we have seen some areas where these metrics can provide valuable
information, so they can be a good input to various conversations and trying
to make them a bit more objective. They can also serve as code style checks,
so especially for things like method lengths or also the more complex things
for working memory. They are a great way to identifying areas for improvement
and pieces of the code which are most probable to have some problems
and bugs, and they can also help us with some more complex decisions
like refactor and rewrite.
We've been through the limitations of all of these metrics and also metrics
in general. We certainly shouldn't be using these metrics as the only measure
of code quality. We should be very careful with our aggregations,
and they shouldn't be used in rankings. There's one more final point I'd like
to make, which is that like everything, like a lot of the tools we use,
code quality metrics are just a tool. You can't determine correctness using
code quality, and that's the final line. It is a tool to help us write good.
It's not going to tell us whether or not the code is correct and is doing
the thing that it's supposed to do, and that's why we're all here.
For those who might not be able to read this, this is one of my favorite
XKCD comics, four-star rating on an app which has a good UI.
It doesn't crash. You can set multiple locations,
but doesn't warn about tornadoes.
Thank you very much.
We would like to thank you to all the sources which you have used here
and also to the developers of these various metrics. You can check out these
if you are interested in learning more about them, and you will find a list
of these sources and some metrics about various open source repositories
at repoanalysis.com. You can contact us at the Sourcery booth number 713
or in the hallway here during the conference and at GitHub after the
conference.
Yeah. As I said, come and find us. We're happy to talk,
and we're typically friendly, and we won't judge your code. Thank you.