All right.
I think we're finally ready to start.
Sorry for the bit of a wait, but hopefully we're good to go.
All right.
Let's give Miranda a round of applause, please.
Thank you.
Hello, everyone.
I hope that you are having a wonderful day so far.
I am super excited to be here today.
This is actually my first time speaking at a large conference.
Woohoo!
Yeah, thanks for the enthusiasm.
Woo!
Today we're going to be looking at animating with FuncAnimation() specifically, which is
a matplotlib class.
So a quick intro on myself.
I had a wonderful introduction already, but my name is Miranda Auhl.
I'm a developer advocate at Timescale, which is a time series database built on Postgres.
So that's kind of where I'm coming from.
And then I included my GitHub first, because I will be showing some code snippets in the
talk today, but I won't be going into super detail.
So if you want to make sure that you can see all the detail that you want in the Python
script that I'm going to be kind of walking through today, you can access it through my
GitHub account.
So don't worry if you don't.
If you skip something now, you can look at it later.
Or ask me questions also.
And I'll have a link to the exact repository at the end of the talk as well.
And then that's just my email and also my Twitter handle, so feel free to reach out
at any time.
So I want to take you on a journey, and unfortunately not a hobbit's journey, because that would
be awesome.
So I want to start my journey from taking a static graph and transforming it into a
data animation.
And on this journey, we're going to walk through, this is kind of like the setup and the path
that we're going to be following.
So first, right before we can really visualize any data, we have to understand the data and
actually grab the data.
Important.
Then we'll look at actually creating a static visualization.
And then the last thing that we'll look at is actually transforming that static visualization
into a data animation.
So we start off as you probably could expect from the name of this talk.
We're starting off with NFL and NFL data.
So in 2015, the NFL did something really interesting.
They started requiring that every stadium have RFID receivers and that every player
have RFID tags and the ball as well actually have RFID tags that track every tenth of a
second all their movement, speed, acceleration, all this stuff.
So as you can imagine, we have from 2015 to now, the NFL tracking, speed, acceleration,
all this stuff, every tenth of a second for every player for every single game.
That is a lot of really cool time series data.
And what's amazing and blew our minds at time scale was that the NFL actually gave
access to people to access this data for free.
Insane.
Like, I could not believe that the NFL released free data for anyone to analyze.
All you needed to do is have a Kaggle account.
So starting in 2020, the NFL started these Big Data Bowl competitions where they released
a subset of this awesome time series tracking data.
And you could download it, download the CFEs and analyze it.
And specifically in the 2021 Big Data Bowl competition, they released a bunch of the
tenth of a second tracking data available and with kind of a bend towards passing plays
specifically.
But they can't release, of course, all the data because they don't want to release everything
to the public.
But they did release a huge portion.
And so when my team and I found out about this, we were like, whoa, with great time
series data comes great responsibility to analyze it.
That's how the saying goes, right?
Well, we're just going to roll with it and say that that's how it goes now.
So all analysis, right, we saw this data.
We knew that we wanted to analyze it.
So the first step is actually getting to know the data.
And so this is one table that you can access through the 2021 Big Data Bowl competition.
So this is the tracking table, which is tracking that tenth of a second kind of IOT readings
basically of the players in the ball.
And this is actually a subset of the columns that you have access to in that competition.
So we see that there's a lot of data here.
First, I want to start off by just going through each column and just kind of like get helping
everyone to get to know the data a little bit.
So first off, we have time, which is a timestamp column.
And we see that it is incrementing and a tenth of a second time like stamp.
So first, we see that we have 14.599, essentially 14.6 in kind of the far left end of the timestamp
or the far right, excuse me.
And then the next timestamp is 14.7.
So we're getting tenth of a second readings in this data.
So it's really granular.
That's super fun.
That means that we could there's a lot of possibility for how you can analyze this data
and aggregate it and stuff.
And also notice that we have a bunch of repeated rows for each timestamp.
And that's because the NFL, they put RFID tags on all the players and the ball.
So each player and the ball is going to be taking in a reading for every tenth of a second.
Now in this case, since again, the NFL can't release all of the data to us, they did though
release for this data set all the most important players for a specific passing play and the
ball for each tenth of a second.
So that's why you see 14 rows here.
So that's 13 of those are going to be players, one of which is going to be the ball.
So cool beans.
Next up we have X and Y. X and Y are columns that represent X and Y coordinates on a coordinate
plane.
The NFL set up the field, the football field, so that they could take in basically as an
X-Y coordinate plane so that you could find out the location of any player or the ball
at any moment in time during any of these games.
Pretty sweet, right?
And so that's really what these X-Y coordinates are.
It's yards, it's in yards.
It's saying exactly where that individual or the ball is at any given time.
So then next we have speed, which the S is representing the speed of the individual at
that moment in time.
Then we have acceleration is what the A stands for.
Game ID, which is a unique identifier for each game.
Got to know which one is which, you know, good to know.
This play ID is specifying since this data is kind of bent on just showing passing plays,
this play ID is a unique identifier for us to know within a game a specific passing play.
So that's what that play ID is.
And then this last column is kind of important and what we're going to dig into a little
bit more in today's talk, but it's this frame.
And kind of at first glance, you know, it's not super clear what it is.
Actually this frame column is taking every tenth of a second and mapping it to an integer
value.
And it also, it's not only just mapping it to an integer value, but it's mapping it to
an integer value that's increasing continuously with time.
So as you see right, the 14.599, tenth of a second is mapped to a frame value of one.
And the 14.7 second, tenth of a second, is mapped to a frame value of two.
So we see that as time is increasing, that frame value is increasing.
And another note that when we looked at this data more is that for every play ID, it will
count every tenth of a second and map each tenth of a second to the frame.
But then as soon as you hit a new play value, so like if we were to go to 76, the frame
value would kind of restart at one.
So essentially we know from this data that that 14.599, tenth of a second, was the first
tenth of a second to occur in the 75th play.
And then, you know, the 14.7 was the second tenth of a second to occur in the 75th play.
So these frame IDs are unique to the play.
All right.
So we get to know our data.
Now right, we can get to the fun stuff.
We can actually analyze it.
We can create visualizations.
So one of the visualizations that I wanted to know was, well, we have these X, Y coordinates.
Let's actually plot these players on a field, right?
That seems kind of fun.
And we have the information.
Let's do it.
So I created a script.
And I set up my Python script kind of with an argument because I wanted to focus on one
play at a time.
And so I defined the game ID that I wanted to look at and then the play ID that I wanted
to kind of zoom in on and graph the data from.
So I define that.
And then I also pull in my data from my time scale DB database.
So I'm pulling that data into my Python script for this specific play so then I can really
dig in more and analyze it.
So then I have data in my Python script.
What's next?
Well, if I'm going to plot players on a field, I'm going to need a field.
So what I did was that I created a generate field function, which I could just call that
and get this awesome field.
So I made it so that I kind of like smoosh all of my matplotlib functions into one kind
of wrap them all up into one function so that I can call that generate field and get, you
know, the yard lines and the hash marks and all this good stuff.
So then, right, we have a field, but now we need to actually plot the players.
So I created another function.
I created a draw play function.
And this draw play function takes in a value of a frame, so it takes in a frame argument,
and it's going to draw a play, kind of plot the play from that frame.
So with the frame value, it represents, right, a moment in time.
So I can put in a moment in time and get this plot plotted.
So with this function, I made it so that I plot.
Oh, this is just, you know, showing us the frame value.
So with this plotting function, I take in, you know, that frame value, and then I can
actually plot the players.
I created a legend, and I also get a title.
So all right.
So now in order to actually create the function and plot it on a graph, I made it so that
I can just call these four lines of code and get, you know, this static plot that I wanted.
And so the first line is a figure, so I'm creating a map plot lib figure.
Second line is I generate the field, so I produce the field on the figure.
Third line is that I'm calling the draw play function for a frame ID value of 65.
And then the last line is plot show that actually shows us the plot in, you know, so that we
can see it.
So this is the 75th, 10th of a second for this specific play that I'm kind of digging
into for this script.
And so, you know, we see we have home team, away team, we have the football.
And like, you know, this is pretty cool.
You know, this is an interesting graph.
I can see that, like, I see the players on the field, but, like, you know, is the ball
being passed right now?
It seems to be kind of floating in air.
No one's really attached to it.
So really this static plot, I was like, it's not really doing it for me.
And so I asked the question, well, what if I could animate it and actually not only just
animate the players' movements as they were going through this play, but also see historically
where they went as they went through the play.
And this is really where FuncAnimation() comes into play.
And so, but in order to understand how to use FuncAnimation(), I really feel that you
have to understand how animations work in general because they play, they tie directly
together.
So let's consider a flip book.
So a flip book is, you know, traditionally it's usually a set of static drawings that
you flip through really fast to kind of give this illusion of motion.
And so that is exactly, I actually created a digital flip book with my iPad.
And so I drew a bunch of static images of this pink ball.
Okay?
Each one is just a static image, you know, cool beans.
I get this static image.
Awesome.
Now, what's super cool is that when you play these static images one after the other in
sequence, you get an animation.
You take these static images, you string them together, and you get an animation.
And that, folks, is exactly how FuncAnimation() works.
It's basically a fancy digital flip book.
So how FuncAnimation(), how the process works is that FuncAnimation() takes a static graphing
function and it iterates over that function again and again.
So it produces, you know, the static graphing function produces a graph.
So FuncAnimation() iterates over that and it's creating all these static graphs, which it
then kind of puts all together, plays one after another to create an animation.
So if we're going to use FuncAnimation() in our code, we've got to understand how to use
it, right?
So here, I took this from the Matplotlib documentation.
And this is a, just like all the arguments that we would need if we were going to use
FuncAnimation().
And I highlighted the two necessary requirements that you have to include when using FuncAnimation().
So the first one is Fig.
Fig requires a figure, Matplotlib, figure object that it can kind of produce this animation
on.
And then func represents a plotting function that matplot, or that FuncAnimation() can actually
create all those static graphs, which it will then, you know, mesh, kind of weave all together.
Hopefully at this point, you're like, wait a minute, I think we have that.
I think we have these exact two things.
And we do, in fact.
By setting up the static graph like this, we create a figure.
That's the first line of code that we do.
Cool.
We got the first requirement.
Awesome.
And then the third line of code calls the draw play function.
We know that draw play function is, in fact, an iterable function.
And that is because of the frame.
This frame is directly tied to time.
So as we iterate over this frame value, you know, we're going, you know, one, two, three,
through these integer frame values, right, we're actually iterating over time.
We're looking at the first tenth of a second, the second tenth of a second, and continually
on and on and on.
So when we iterate over this frame, we're actually iterating over time.
And that's exactly what we want to plot, right?
We want to plot the player's movements on this field over time.
And so we have the two requirements.
Well, now the next question is, can I just, you know, throw it into the FuncAnimation()
function and we're good?
And the answer is basically yes.
But we need to do just a few quick adjustments to make sure that it works.
So one thing is that if we were to animate our draw play function as it is right now,
where I, you know, plot the figures on the field, create the legend, create the title,
we would get something like this.
Not ideal, right?
This is not exactly what we want.
So like the player's movements, that's good, right?
I want to see how the players are moving over time and I want to keep their historical
movement in view.
But this legend is a problem.
And so that takes me to wanting to talk about these two types of functions that you can
use when you create your iterative function that you're going to insert into FuncAnimation().
And that is plotting functions, plotting function types versus setting function types.
So plotting function types, I highlighted the three functions that I call, the three
types of functions that I call my iterative function, my draw play function.
And this plot function that we're going to look at first, that is truly a plotting function.
It's additive.
As the animation is continuing, it's adding plots to the animation.
So every time draw play is called, this plot function is going to add a new plot to the
animation.
It's additive.
So that's what plotting functions are additive, okay?
Saying that a lot.
My apologies.
You'll just remember it now forever.
So then the next function that we're going to look at is set title.
This function is a setting function.
It's going to replace.
So plotting functions add when you animate.
Setting functions replace when you animate.
And so the title, you know, it's not really causing a problem.
Probably, you know, every time draw play is called, it's setting the title.
So maybe for efficiency's sake, we might want to move it out.
But I'm just going to leave it there for now because it's not causing tons of issues.
But the legend, the last function, this is a problem, right?
This is actually acting as a plotting function, right?
Because it's adding a legend every single time the draw play function is called.
So this is a problem.
Easiest way?
We remove it.
And we move it to the generate field function, which we only call once.
So that just makes it easy.
It's an easy way, quick fix, to remove that plotting function.
That is doing what we don't want it to do.
So then the next caveat you want to make sure is that whenever you create your iterative
function, the value that you iterate over or the argument that you iterate over has
to be the first argument specified in the definition.
So for draw play, right, it doesn't matter.
We have only one argument value.
But say that I had two other arguments in my iterative function.
I need to make sure to call frame first and then all the other arguments after.
So that's just something that FuncAnimation() really looks for.
It will not work if you don't put that iterative argument first.
Okay.
So now we can actually create our animation.
We can transform that static graph into an animation.
So here is static graph, Python code.
And we have FuncAnimation() at the top, a definition just for reference.
So first off, we need to actually insert FuncAnimation() into our code.
Cool beans.
We put it in.
The thing is that FuncAnimation(), it needs to store the animation into a variable.
And so in this case, I called my variable anim, represents animation.
And then it's just one of the requirements with FuncAnimation().
It has to have somewhere to store the animation.
So you create that variable.
Next you have the two required arguments.
So first we have fig.
We throw our fig in there.
And then draw play, which is the iterative function.
That's the next required argument.
And we just call the name.
You don't add any of the arguments.
You just call the name of the function and you throw it in there.
And then lastly, I wanted to also, sorry, the mic was there.
I also wanted to specify the frames that FuncAnimation() is going to iterate over.
By default, FuncAnimation() will iterate starting at an integer value of zero.
And it's going to iterate over integer values.
So it goes zero, one, two, on, so on and so forth.
In our case, we like the integer value.
We want to iterate over an integer value.
But we want it to start at one and iterate over the integer values.
So we can actually specify the exact range of values we want from animation to iterate
on.
And in this case, I want values starting at one, increasing by one.
And then this 113 is just the max value for the frame for this specific play.
So I just put bounds around all the frame values.
So that's where I get that one from because we're starting at one.
And it goes all the way to 113.
And then, friends, well, now we can actually comment out the draw play frame function that
we call up there and the plot show there for the static graph.
We can comment that out.
And now put plot show underneath our animation.
And oh, it doesn't get, okay, that's okay because I have another graph here.
That's okay.
I have a GIF of it, so not a problem.
Technical issues, folks.
Gotta love it.
Okay.
And I think I can go to the next slide.
You can just, yeah.
Okay.
This is an added animation that I was hopefully going to show after the first animation.
But what's cool is that I took this static plot.
And so you can ignore the jersey numbers.
Those are jersey numbers that I added.
And this is far more interesting.
Now we can actually see how this play, you know, we're not getting a snapshot of just
seeing the ball floating in space.
Now we actually see the pass being thrown.
This person is just about to score a touchdown and actually does.
This is super fun and way more engaging.
And what's cool is that once you have an animation like this, you can add to it like I did here.
So in this case, I used a setting function, a setting type function, to add the jersey
numbers for each individual so that we know who's getting past what or who's tackling
whoever.
And I also added some statistics tables.
And you could even add statistics to the individuals if you want on the graph.
The possibilities are endless.
So how can you use animation?
Well, as long as you have a figure, you have a matplotlib figure, and an iterable plotting
function, then you can animate it.
That's really all you need.
And especially if you have kind of set yourself up with avoiding kind of the full plotting,
setting type functions, and also making sure that iterable frame value is the first, like
you can animate it.
And I hope that you feel encouraged to actually try this out in your static plots at home.
And so, folks, that's it.
That's pretty much it.
Here are some resources.
So this first link is a link to my GitHub project.
I include all of the slides and also the Python script that I ran through here.
It's the full script, so you get all the code that I didn't put here.
The second is the Kaggle competition link for the 2021 Kaggle competitions.
You can download the data yourself.
All you need is a Kaggle account.
And then the third and fourth links are actually the first one is a tutorial that my team made
to help you basically walk you through ingesting the data from Kaggle, putting it into a time
scale BB database, which is basically Postgres, and then actually analyzing it.
And then the last is just a blog post kind of diving into other analytics that you could
try out.
So that is it.
Happy coding, friends.
Thank you so much for being so patient with all of these technical issues.
And I hope that you have a wonderful rest of your day.
Yes, thank you.
If anyone wants stickers from time scale, come see me.
Or if you have questions, also come see me.
So thank you.