Hello, everyone. Welcome to our next talk, Bad Actors vs. Our Community, Detecting Software
Supply Chain Attacks on the Python Ecosystem. Please welcome Ashish Bijlani.
Thank you and welcome. Thank you for attending my talk. This is on supply chain attacks. So
let's get started. I'm Ashish. I hold a PhD from Georgia Tech in cybersecurity, and this is where
you can reach me. I work at Oscillate. I'm a research scientist, and we are developing tools
to detect software supply chain attacks. So open source software is a de facto standard way of
building digital apps and services today. Modern open source software is distributed as packages
on package managers. Examples of package managers include NPM and PyPy. For example, PyPy hosts
over 300,000 Python packages, and they receive millions of daily downloads. So anybody can publish
their package on these package managers. They make it super easy. They ship a command line tool that
you can use to publish your package, frictionless single command publishing. However, there's
limited security vetting. What does that mean? That means the software that we use on our server,
desktops, laptops, other devices, is written by unknown volunteers, which we blindly trust.
And bad actors exploit exactly this trust. And this is evident from several past incidents.
According to a recent study, the supply chain attacks have tripled in 2021 alone, and these
attacks have been carried out on all ecosystems. NPM, PyPy, no ecosystem has been spared. So what
are these supply chain attacks? So attackers target less secure packages or the weak links
in your supply chain, and they inject malware in the supply chain by publishing malicious packages.
Unlike vulnerabilities, malware is intentionally harmful. It's not an accidental programming bug
in a benign code. It is purposefully harmful. For example, a backdoor that is installed immediately
upon package installation, and that steals your SSH keys or Bitcoin wallet addresses.
Such attacks pose direct and dangerous threats because the same malware can be adopted by
millions of devices. And yeah, like I said, it has a wide blast radius. So what are these
techniques that attackers use to publish malware? So one such technique is typo-squatting. So under
typo-squatting, attackers publish packages with similar names to existing popular packages and
exploit inexperience or carelessness of developers to supply malware. For example, a name typo during
a package installation can end up in malware. In the slide here, we have shown a couple of examples.
For example, Colorama impersonates a popular package Colorama. And if you make a typo,
then you can end up installing malware on your machine. So let's take a case study and let's
dive deeper into what these malicious packages are. So let's take MITM proxy 2 as an example.
It impersonates a popular package called MITM proxy. As you can see, the project description
is exactly the same, and some of the stats are the same as the original package. So an inexperienced
developer may mistake this package as an upgraded version of MITM proxy and download it. But if you
look at the code, what this package does is it removes some of the safeguards. So anyone on the
same network can execute code on your machine with a single HTTP request. Social engineering
is another technique that attackers use to dupe maintainers and inject malware. NPM package event
stream is a good example. Here the attacker first gained trust by posing as a benign contributor
and contributing useful features. And later he asked to maintain the package event stream.
And after gaining the contributor privileges, the attacker published malicious code that searched
for Bitcoin addresses. The developer of the package in maintenance mode actually trusted
because the attacker was supposedly benign and he contributed popular or good features. So this
package is a good example because it receives millions of weekly downloads. Another technique
that attackers use is dependency confusion. So enterprises, they use internal mirrors of package
managers. For example, there will be an internal mirror of PyPy that is synced with the external
package managers as needed. And the technique exploits the default behavior of this artifactory
to always use the higher version of the package as available externally. So what can an attacker do?
An attacker can go through manifest file available publicly, find out what packages are being used,
for example, at Microsoft or other enterprise. And they can publish higher malicious versions
of the same package. And as a result, the artifactory will now install the external malicious
package and the malware will be in their apps and services. There have also been cases of account
hijacking to inject malware in open source packages. A popular example is UAParser.js. It's a
JavaScript package with 8 million weekly downloads. The package is actually used in apps and websites
to discover the type of device or browser the person is using from user agent data. The attacker
here hijacked the account and published malicious versions of this popular package. Let's look at
another case study. So this is a Python package that we found and we reported to PyPy admins in
January. We found that this package downloads a malicious payload from this URL and executes
the code by spawning subprocesses. And we saw that the email address on this package was invalid and
that's why we looked into this and also we analyzed the APIs. So I'll get to that briefly.
So how do we defend against such attacks? Well, security is a shared responsibility and as a
community we must all do our parts. For example, maintainers and package managers can adopt
two-factor authentication to protect against account hijacking. Package names coping can
also reduce the risks of typo-squatting attacks. However, these measures fall short because,
you know, as we have seen with the recent protest where a disgruntled developer can sabotage their
own package and inject malware. So developers must use a zero trust approach. They must thoroughly
vet code and behavior of every package, every dependency they use. Easier said than done. This
is because manual vetting is infeasible. As packages may have hundreds of dependencies,
include direct and transitive. This slide shows a dependency of PyTorch, the popular Python package.
By the way, this graph only shows transitive dependencies that are at a distance of two or
less from PyTorch. So as seen from this graph, PyTorch includes several dependencies and manually
analyzing each one would be tedious and error-prone. We can use tools. However, existing tools only
report known CVEs, publicly known CVEs in NVD or other public databases. For example, Sneak
Advisor reports no vulnerability with clearing malicious packages here. So this is an example
package maybe uploaded by a security researcher that says, you know, this is an example package
to demonstrate a malicious code insight and Sneak Advisor reports no security risks. If you delve
deeper, you'll see that this package generates and executes malicious code at runtime that reads
your SSH keys. How about stats? Can we rely on stats like GitHub downloads or stars or forks? Well,
stats are attacker controlled. Attacker bot can easily manipulate downloads or forks. More
important, there's no verification of package provenance, source provenance. So it may point
to a popular package on GitHub. For example, this slide shows starjacking where an attacker
can easily trick users by pointing to a popular source on GitHub. So this points to a sample
Python project and has over 4,000 stars and over 1,500 forks. No verification, like I said,
no verification is done for the source by package managers. Therefore, blindly trusting such vanity
stats would be naive. So package is our solution. We are developing an automated tool to vet packages
that you adopt. So we take a zero trust approach. We vet every API. We vet multiple attributes of
packages, multiple risky code as well as metadata attributes. And we provide actionable security
insights. For example, we test for weak links by checking is the package old or abandoned. Abandoned
packages or old packages may not receive security fixes. So they must be avoided. Does the package
read or send your data over the network? As we have seen from the example malware, malicious
packages usually they read files, they try to steal your sensitive data, which will be in file,
and they'll send this to a remote server. So a package that's reading and sending data or remote
server is fishy. It must be thoroughly checked. And finally, is the source repo publicly available?
Because if it is available, we can go and check the source code and be sure that the package indeed
contains the code that is displayed on public source repo. So package is a command line tool,
and you can customize it to a threat model. For example, if you think that two-factor authentication
may not be risky for you, if you perceive as lack of two-factor authentication is not risky,
you can turn off that alert and minimize noise. So how does it work? We use static analysis.
Specifically, we look at APIs that are being used by packages. These APIs are provided by the language
ecosystem or the operating system, and malware has to go through these APIs if they want to execute
any sensitive functionality or get access to any sensitive data. For example, if they want to read
files, they'll have to call open read write file system APIs. If they want to send data, they need
to call the socket APIs, network APIs. And if they want to generate code at runtime, downloading
malicious package or malicious payload at runtime and execute them, they have to use exec or eval or
for. So we track these APIs, and depending on your threat model, we provide alerts to you. We also
look at metadata analysis. For example, we look at maintainer email. Is it valid or not? Invalid
email suggests no-factor authentication. We check for abandoned packages because they don't receive
security fixes. We check for public source repo for code verification. And we do some type of
scoring detection based on name similarity. So time for some action. Let me...
All right. Let me demo the tool to you. Okay.
Cool. So this is the source code. It's hosted on GitHub. And we'll get to that. Let's try to
wait a package here. Does anybody have a popular package that they want to wait? What's that? Twisted.
Twisted. Is that correct? All right. Some errors. Work in progress. We are fixing it. But it did analyze
the version. It found version 2240. It checked the author. It checked the email. It checked the
sufficient readme. The version is only 19 days old. The repo is found. Looks good. Home page is
also found. Looks like it's reachable. No CVs were found, which is good. And it downloaded the
package and it carried out API analysis, but it failed. We can try with some other package,
and this will be fixed. But it did say that one risk found... So the home page is non-existent,
looks like. And we can check that later. Let me... What's that? Pip audit. All right. Single word?
Okay. Correct? All right. So the author is trail of bits. 32 days old, which is good. Readme,
sufficient readme. Repo is found. Home page also points to the same repo. No CVs were found. And
three risks. So it generates new code at runtime. Perhaps it's supposed to. But you can check that
by going to these... So no line number was provided for this. Yeah, this will be fixed in
new versions. But it also reads directories and files. And you can go to these files at these line
number and then test. And you can see a lot of this is in test suite, maybe. So that can be ignored.
But it's good to know what the package is doing. All right. So the source code of package is hosted
on GitHub under oscillate-inc. And as you can see, it's a standalone command line tool to write
open source software packages for risky attributes that make them vulnerable to supply chain attacks.
And like you saw, it just takes two arguments, the name of the registry package manager and the name
of the package. And we have already seen the output. But this only supports Python 2.7 and
only tested on Linux. So it will download package metadata from registry using these APIs and also
download the package itself, the tarball from registry using APIs. And it performs API analysis
using static code analysis. It checks for vulnerabilities using OSV database. And how
do you customize this? So suppose you... Okay. So we flag inactive or unmaintained packages that
no longer receive security fixes. But if that's not a problem for you, what you can do is you can
go to this file threats.csv here. And you can see that we categorize these attributes in four classes,
malicious, suspicious, which is potentially malicious, vulnerable to code exploit, includes
cvs and a lot of undesirable attributes. So if you don't want alert, some alert because of some
attribute, you can comment that out. For example, undesirable, the old package will be undesirable.
And if that's desirable to you, you can comment this out and then it will not provide alert.
All right. Let's continue. So with this tool, you can write individual packages by yourself. But
we actually are building a large scale waiting infrastructure for detecting supply chain attacks
on open source package managers. And the service that we have created is package.dev. It's a software
service and it offers better accuracy because we have large data set. The package command line
tool will operate only on one package. We can download millions of packages and then test them
for any supply chain attacks. So it provides more accuracy. So a lot of free reports are available
on pre-edited package on the website. There's also a command line. There's also a CI CD plugin
to audit pull requests. That's also free. You'll have to create an account for that. And you can
review security reports. You can endorse and share reports as well. Let me show that to you.
Quickly. Yeah. So this is where it's hosted. If you go to your own GitHub, it will point to
package. There's a CI CD plugin that you can use and audit pull requests. You can upload your
requirements.txt. You can search for packages. And there's a CI CD. All right. Let's see some of
the reports. So this is a popular Python package. 2.6 million download, weekly downloads. As you can
see, we provide some stats on this. So we provide code related stats. What's the size number of
files? Permissions. These are important. So the package would read files and spawn processes.
These are only two are shown here. But if you go to code behavior, you'll see a lot of details. So
it will read files. It will spawn processes. It will write the files. It generates code dynamically.
And as you can see, this is being done at installation time, which is risky. So you can go to
setup.py. And you can see that it's reading file. It's reading read me. So this is okay.
All right. What else is... So it has a package anatomy. It will mention the number of files
that this package has. And it provides some popularity graph. And you can see... Okay. This
feature is coming soon. But you can see this is used by 530 packages. Just good. And this
last release was more than 12 months. So you may want to check that. All right. Let's look at BS4.
This is a PyPo guard package. This is installed by the developer of Beautiful Soup so that you
don't accidentally install a malicious package. So if you go to PyPy, you can see that this is a
dummy package. And it's just a placeholder. And if you look at the code behavior, it uses
Beautiful Soup, which is the correct package as the dependency. So if you download BS4 by mistake
because of inexperience or you thought that was the correct name, you would get Beautiful
Soup for package as dependency. So you're good. But this is how an attacker can publish a name,
a package with a name similar to a popular package name, and you would end up downloading.
So if you look at the number of downloads, this has a huge number of downloads for a dummy package.
And how do we know that this is a dummy package? It's just 2kb. And there are only three files.
It's only one function, right? And one dependency. So these stats are useful. PyTorch is another
one. This is also a dummy or a placeholder package. You try to install PyTorch. All right. And you know
that this is a dummy package because it's just 840 bytes. Three files, seven functions. All right.
Looks like it provides some good stats. Let's continue. So we did find over 35 malicious
packages in January, and we reported that to PyPy. These are some of the examples that we found.
Let's look at them. So if you go to package to malware, you'll see these malicious packages,
example malicious packages that we reported. And I think some of them have been taken down now.
Let's inspect this particular package, ChrisKian. So this was uploaded in 2021, September. And our
static analysis module flagged this as suspicious because it's trying to spawn processes. It's
trying to download data from network and read file and all at installation time, which is pretty
risky. So we looked into this and we found that this package is indeed malicious. I think if you
scroll down, you'll see what this package does. This package will do different things for different
operating system. On Windows, I think it's trying to override explorer.exe. On Linux, it does the
same thing. It doesn't override explorer.exe, but it will download the payload from this URL,
and it will execute this payload using subprocess. So we detected this.
All right. So some of the findings. And this was it. Thank you so much for attending the talk. The
source code of the package is hosted on GitHub, and we have millions of pre-read packages,
reports available for free at package.tiff. And this is powered by Ocelet. Thank you.