Welcome back. I welcome you all to the last talk of the day. We have Maria Jose to deliver
a talk on better air, better health, creating an indoor air quality monitoring and predictive
system. Over to you, Maria.
Thank you so much. Hello, everyone. I'm so excited to be here today talking about how
to create an air quality monitoring and predictive system. Before I start, I would like to ask
you how many of you are interested in sensor data and microcontrollers? Good. And what
about data analysis? Oh, good. And what about machine learning and data science in general?
Awesome. This is the talk for you. Let's start then. My name is Maria Jose. As you know already,
I have a background in plant molecular biology. And currently I am working as a data scientist
at InPharm, that is a vertical farming company. But in my free time, I enjoy doing do-it-yourself
projects with microcontrollers and IoT and kind of mixing all the things that I love.
And this is one of those projects. What is the motivation of this project? Well, with
the pandemic situation, my lifestyle changed. Before the pandemic, I was working on site
and I was having some more active life. Then I moved to remote life and some changes happened.
Some of them, it was like more be at home. I was mainly at home almost the whole day.
And someday I start to feel like a lot of headaches, some feeling of being really sleepy,
and I didn't know why until one day I was thinking to say, what is going on in here?
And I realized that when I was going outside, taking fresh air, I was feeling better. And I thought,
wait a second, maybe it's something in my air, in my apartment that is not going really well.
And then I start doing some research about to know what, how can you quantify your air quality at home?
And I realized that there are a lot of factors. For instance, the occupants and how many people
is living in your apartment. Also, there are the humidity and moisture. By the way, I think that it's really
important that you take care of what is the moisture at your apartment. This is also biologists
because the mold and the fungus are really happy once you have moisture and high humidity.
But this is another topic for another day. Then we have also the ventilation, something that you think,
wow, I open the windows and that's all, right? Well, it's a bit more complex and you're going to see later why.
Later we have the pollutant sources. For instance, it's not the same if you live in a city with a lot of
factories or if you live in countryside, for instance. That is not the same if you live close to a volcano,
for instance, in Canada, Iceland or in a desert. Also, we have odors and gases. That is quite important.
I start thinking, wow, what is my problem? I don't know yet, right? I start reading publications.
As I mentioned, I am a scientist and I love to read scientific publications.
I realized that there was a field that a lot of scientists are publishing about CO2.
All of them, for sure, this is just some collection, but there are so many publications about CO2 and the effect in our health.
All of them end up saying that it's difficult to correlate the CO2 levels with the health problems because it's more complex.
As I mentioned before, there are the humidity, the pollutants, the previous health conditions that you can have,
but all of them indicate that CO2 has an important factor in our health.
As you can see, for instance, in the first one, say that CO2 could have an impacting decision-making performance.
Good advice. If you need to make a decision, open your window sometime before making this decision because this could affect you.
Well, what is good, what is bad depends on the definition, always. Be careful because it depends on the source, the numbers change.
Let's take it as approximate values. What we have in here is the CO2 per million numbers in the x-axis,
and then we have the difference steps when we consider that this situation is good or kind of bad.
As you can see, lower to 1,000, we are kind of considered good, and higher to 1,000, we'll be bad, just to summarize the information.
Also, the difference health impacts that we can find here, you need to have in consideration that it's around 2,000,
but depends on our other factors and our previous health condition could happen before this 2,000.
Well, at that point, say, hey, I need to do something and test that if my indoor conditions are okay or not.
For that, what I did is say, I'm going to take sensors, I'm going to collect data, and I'm going to monitor these values to see what is going on in my apartment.
But then I thought, wait, what if I also could do some prediction because it's really nice to have the values in real life, but what if I could prevent this situation?
And then appeared the idea of having the predictive system.
Let's start step by step because you are going to see that this is a bit complex.
Well, let's start with the data collection.
Well, I used two different sensors.
One is for particles, the blue one, that is the PMSA blah, blah, blah.
And then we have the CD that is for the CO2.
I wanted to have as much data as possible because, as I mentioned before, those factors are always working together.
My favorite approach, I try to keep it simple.
It's like I try to do something simple, but then everything gets complex.
You're going to see, you're going to see, but I try.
I try to keep it simple, I promise.
And then what I did is to connect this particle sensor to a QGPi microcontroller, which is really, really small, it's a really compact system, and was really kind of straightforward to have it.
I was running it using Sirq with Python.
Everything was really OK until the moment that I decided that I want to collect all this data and I wanted to do the transmission of this data.
This microcontroller has no Bluetooth or Wi-Fi, and then I could not collect the data.
And then I thought, well, let's try another approach.
You can think, OK, you could change the microcontroller and choose another one with Wi-Fi or wireless.
Yeah, it's true.
The thing is that I was trying to recycle the microcontrollers that I had at home to minimize kind of everything.
Because therefore, yes.
But just to be honest, what happened?
My second idea for the CO2 was to use MicroPython with ASP32.
This microcontroller has Wi-Fi.
Everything was working really well.
Until I tried to connect the other sensor, the particle one, I had some issues with the connection, and I could not solve those issues.
And it was kind of a bottleneck to me.
And for that reason, I just decided to continue with another approach.
But you're going to see that this is one of the work in progress that I have right now.
Well, what's next?
Then I went directly to Raspberry Pi with wireless.
And that will be the setup for data collection.
Of course, I wanted to have something else.
I wanted to have a device with a screen where I could check my information.
Because it's really nice.
Imagine you are in your meetings and you can see if you need to open your window or not or how it's going on.
And also it's the perfect excuse to say, hey, we need to finish the meeting because my values of CO2 are getting high.
Well, I'm not sure if we'll work, but maybe it's a perfect excuse.
Raspberry Pi 4, in this case, also it was because I had it at home.
You can probably use another one, and it's not a problem at all.
And just added the screen that also is touchable.
It's really nice.
You're going to see later.
Then this is the project structure that we are getting.
The two sensors are getting information.
The storage information is the Raspberry Pi.
And then I have the two Raspberry Pis connected for a TCP socket, a socket connection.
And then we can start taking a look to the data.
And of course, this is just an example of some of the data that I got.
On the X axis, we have the date.
And the Y axis, we have different parameters, right?
The Celsius, the temperatures in Celsius, the humidity, and the CO2.
This is just to show you that there are some fluctuations there.
And this is not going to be easy.
This is not going to be an easy project, I can tell you.
And here are my values of CO2.
In green, it's kind of the good values, that it's lower than 1000.
Then in orange, I have these values that it could be better.
And in purple are values that are not okay, especially the ones that are in the arrow.
And the bottom, close to 2000.
This is not a good condition.
And of course, I cannot correlate it with my head age because I cannot do it.
But this is an indicative that the air quality of my apartment was not okay.
It would give me a lot of happiness to see that this project makes a lot of sense to develop.
Then we have the monitoring system by one side, that we are going to see the results later.
And on the other hand, we have the predictive.
For the predictive one, what I did is implement a time series.
If you are not familiar with the concept of time series, basically in here we have a plot not related with the CO2, by the way.
On the x-axis, we have the time, and the y-axis, we have values.
This means that we are going to get values in time, and the time is important.
The order is going to be really, really important.
And here we have a quite overwhelming plot of my data.
Please take it to time. It's okay.
It's just that, wow.
In the x-axis, we have the index.
The index is the time.
In time series, usually what we do is to take the time as an index.
It's like first day, second day, third day.
What we are going to do is one, two, three, and then we take it as an index.
In the y-axis, we have the CO2.
And what we have here is a different oscillation of time of my values of CO2.
In the arrows, I am indicating some spaces where the values were quite low.
Do you have an idea what happened in those moments?
Open the window. No.
Something else? We can... windows.
No. No. No.
Well, I'm going to tell you. I was out at home.
I was on holidays.
And then once you're on holidays, you can see that all changed.
But it's really cool to see.
Because what is important is where I was tracking also the CO2 was in the place where I work,
in the office place, let's say that way.
And then if I was not in the office, where was not problem.
In the square, I am indicating a really high number of CO2.
Do you have an idea what is going on here?
Sorry?
How about reading?
Is this a day or is this like many days?
Many days.
If I had some visits at home, then if you have visits at home, be careful and open more frequently your windows.
That is important lesson that I learned.
If you open once per day when you have visits, try to double or triple the times.
And also really the last interesting thing is the trend.
Is this orange line that we have here, that we have in here, because at some point it starts to decrease.
Any idea what happened?
Yes.
There was two things.
One is the change of season.
And as I live in Germany, where the winter is really cold,
and then you try to decrease to open the window because it's really, really cold.
And this is a problem, as you can see.
But when the spring starts, it's different.
The weather is like, yeah, yeah, let's open the window and everything will be fine.
And one thing was that.
And a second thing is that I realize, I start analyzing the data of the CO2,
and I realized that I was having an issue at home.
And I start to change it the way that I was opening the windows.
Because at the beginning, I was only opening one window and then the second, the third one, let's say.
It's a combination.
And I realized that when I was playing with the different windows opening,
the values were changing dramatically.
This means that the whole fluids are going in my apartment were affected.
Then this is really interesting to know and also something interesting to play with, in case you're interested.
Then it was OK.
Let's implement some machine learning to try to predict my CO2 levels.
There are so many approaches that you can use to do it.
In my case, I decided I saw this publication, which has a really interesting approach
because it has an adaptive approach to predict the indoor CO2.
And then also they have this table with the different conditions, different parameters, and different architecture.
And I kind of realized that there was like, wow, I can implement a lot of different architecture.
Yes, I buy it.
Of course, I did some variations in my project, but at the end, what I tried to follow is the adaptive idea of windows, of that.
I am doing so much spoilers for the next one.
Then I created the data set.
Well, I monitored before creating the data set.
I monitored different variables.
That was the CO2, the humidity, the temperature, the particles, and also the activity level.
Because, of course, as you realize, if you are not at home, then you decrease the levels of CO2.
And then if you include that in your model, the prediction will not be really accurate,
because if you are not at home, you don't produce CO2 and then that.
Yeah, these kind of things.
Then I create the data set, having in consideration of the whole time series work.
Always be careful with that.
Also needs to be normalized the data for the training and implement this idea of windows, the mobile windows.
In this case, I'm not sure if you're familiar with these kind of methodologies,
but what we have is a time, a period of time that we train our model and then we do the prediction for the next hour, days, depends what you need.
Then what you want is move this window to the prediction and update that.
We move, we update, we retrain, we retrain, we retrain, we retrain.
What we are going to have with that is more accurate results, because we are having more updated results.
Because if you have seasonality of if you are not at home or if you have whatever reasons you have, your data set will be affected.
And then at least if you have the most recent situation, you are going to get more accurate results.
Then I use CNN.
I'm not going to go into the details because if not, we are not going to be able to end the talk.
But if you have any questions later, I will be happy or at some moment just to show you how this, what is the architecture of the CNN looks like.
What I like also to share and I like to see when I go to data science talks is this whole people do this hyperparameter selections.
For that reason, I also include it, but I'm going to keep it also fast and simple in case that you are not really interested.
But I love it. For that reason, I decided to include it.
I just mentioned a couple of things.
It's like we have a convolution 1D that in this place we are analyzing what is doing is analyzing and structure the pictures.
Then we have the input shape that we are going to introduce the variables and the times and the time there in the MaxPool 1D.
What is happening is that we're taking the most important information and then we are going to have our output.
Of course, there are much more code.
This is just a part.
Just to let you know.
Well, about metrics and results, I use the RMS as our metric of performance.
I did some experiments for hyperparameters, tried to see how it was working.
But as you know, as other data science projects, you need to iterate one on one.
I didn't invest so much.
I just did some analysis and approaches because what we are going to need to do once this project is done is go back and improve and optimize all the process.
Then from the windowing perspective, it's really nice.
I love it.
You need to be aware that each window is going to have their own performance.
Because if you have a lack of data in some window or something happens, a lot of things could happen.
Here I show you some results that I just considered that could be really interesting to see and how it's going.
In blue, we have the input.
In green, we have the labels.
In orange, this crosses the prediction.
What I'm having here is a window of 24 hours.
What I'm doing is a prediction each hour.
Of course, in the final version, what we are going to see, we are not going to have this exactly.
What we are going to have is the prediction at the end.
I just wanted to share with you how it's going in each step.
As you can see, in some points it's quite accurate.
What we expect is half overlapping between the labels and the prediction, the green and the orange.
In some cases, at some moment, it's not happening.
But it's kind of normal and it's something that needs to be optimized.
But it's not bad at all.
Then this is the final project structure that we got.
Because we are going to have the machine learning predictions deployed in our Raspberry Pi.
And then we are going to have a simple Flask application in the other Raspberry Pi.
And we are going to have to display how everything looks together.
First, I thought, okay, I need to install all my sensors and Raspberry Pi in my apartment.
Let's do it nice.
And I removed a picture of my sister.
Don't tell her, please don't tell her.
And I substitute her for some sensors.
Yeah.
Well, this is how it looks like, the Flask application in our Raspberry Pi.
It is the one that we are going to have close to our seat or where you work.
And what you can see is in here is the temperature, the humidity.
This is the CO2 concentration.
In here we have the prediction and just the date.
The idea is to have the raw values from the sensors in constant, in real time.
Of course, not each second.
I think that I program every 10 minutes, if I am not wrong, right?
And then the prediction each hour.
Why one hour?
I decided one hour because it's kind of a time enough to when I end a meeting
and I can kind of take a break.
And it's time enough to me to open the window and do something.
For the other values are really interesting to have more frequently.
But of course, this depends on the criteria and the things that you need.
And this is how it looks like.
You can change your Raspberry Pi and that.
What is working for us right now?
I am doing this implementation but using microcontrollers,
taking out at least one of the Raspberry Pi.
My idea is to implement and use TensorFlow Lite.
Kind of for fun, let's be honest.
I am going to just do a bit of research.
And something that I didn't mention is that I didn't include the particles information in my model.
And maybe someone is wondering, wait, but you changed the system from the microcontrollers
to the Raspberry Pi for that, right?
Yes, I did.
The problem was that the sensor arrived late because I bought it a bit late.
And I could not have all the data that I wanted.
And I had the system running with the CO2 and the humidity and temperature.
And I did this decision and say, OK, I'm going to take out the particles.
And that's what the next iteration will be in because it will bring a lot of interesting information.
And then, of course, optimization.
This project as a data science project needs optimization.
But also from microcontrollers, it could be optimized.
And yeah, all the projects could be.
That's going to end my presentation here.
If you want to be in touch or if you have questions, just feel free to reach me out.
I will be really happy to discuss because I love all those topics.
As you can see, I enjoy it a lot.
And thank you so much for your attention.