All right, let's start the third talk of the session.
We have Jan-Hein Buhrman here who is going to talk about when to refactor your code into
generators and how.
Take it away.
Thank you.
All right, let's start.
Well, first of all, it's great to be here.
I hope everybody is doing fine here at the venue, but also perhaps the viewers at home.
So let's start with my presentation, when to refactor your code into generators and
how.
All right, so the goals of this presentation are that I hope that after this presentation
you will be able to recognize certain loop constructs as candidates for refactoring and
how to convert these constructs into more maintainable and pythonic code by refactoring
them into elegant pipelines of generators.
And finally, you will be more acquainted with the standard library itertools module and the
more-itertools package.
But first, let's introduce myself.
My name is Jan-Hein Buhrman.
You see my email address and my Twitter handle over there.
As you can see in the email address, I'm working for Ordina already more than 10 years now.
Time flies when you're having fun.
I witnessed, and a long time ago, more than 30 years ago, I witnessed the first baby steps
of Python when I was working at the Dutch Institute for Mathematics and Computer Science.
And during my career, I was working as a C++ developer.
I had also management roles.
But I always kept an eye on Python and its developments and how it progressed.
And while being a Java unit manager at my current company, I sparked the idea for starting
up a dedicated Python practice, the Ordina Pythoneers.
And I think it's quite special for a broad spectrum IT service provider to have a Python
dedicated unit within and where we combine software ethics, software development ethics,
or software development craftsmanship together with Python.
We like that combination.
And finally, the Ordina Pythoneers are a participating sponsor of the PSF.
And the last four years, I'm working as a Python programmer, as a happy Python coder.
All right.
So the topic we will be addressing is, first of all, I'm going to show you some code with
certain kind of loops which have a certain pattern.
These loops have similar codes, but they vary in start, stop, and selection criteria.
And I'll give a short address to the topic of refactoring and how you can recognize certain
patterns of loop constructs for refactoring candidates.
Then I touch upon the topic of generators.
And I will introduce you to the earlier mentioned itertools module and the more-itertools package.
So let's start.
So this is, I'm going to tell you a story, but it is a fictional story.
It's not a true story.
It's a story about that we're working in a team and we have a product owner who is
representing the Fibonacci sequence fan club.
And he would like you to make a function returning a list of Fibonacci numbers which are less
than a certain value.
So first of all, who knows what a Fibonacci number is?
I see many ands, perhaps not 100%, but close to it.
So a short introduction to Fibonacci numbers.
I'll just read it out.
In mathematics, the Fibonacci numbers form a sequence, the Fibonacci sequence, in which
each number is the sum of the preceding two ones.
So that's the essence of the Fibonacci sequence.
You start with two numbers.
Usually it's zero and one.
The next value is simply the addition of the previous two.
So in this example, you see the first numbers are zero and one.
If you add them together, zero plus one makes one, right?
So that's the reason why you see another one in the sequence.
And then the next value is calculated by taking the two previous ones of the next value, which
are one plus one, and that makes two, et cetera, et cetera.
One plus two makes three.
Two plus three makes five.
And then you get this sequence.
So that's the essence of the Fibonacci sequence.
So let's start coding that in Python.
And if you Google around a little bit, perhaps you end up with the tutorial of Python itself,
where a variation of this function is actually written out.
It has another name.
It doesn't contain type annotations, but for the rest it's the same.
It doesn't contain a docstring either.
But it works as follows.
You initialize your function.
You initialize the result value as an empty list.
And you start initializing the two, what you could call the Fibonacci registers, A and
B. And you could view A as the current Fibonacci number and B as the next to come Fibonacci
number.
And as long as your current Fibonacci number is less than the threshold that you have given
as an argument, as a parameter to your function, then you enter the loop.
You append the current Fibonacci number to the list.
You calculate the two new registers.
And that is the new current Fibonacci number is the old value of the, is the old next Fibonacci
number.
So A becomes B. And at the same time, that's nice from Python, you can make this kind of
funny, how do you call it, tuple assignment.
You can calculate a new next to come Fibonacci number by adding the old values of A and B
together.
And that's what you store in the B variable.
And as long as the condition holds, you just simply repeat that.
And then finally at the end, you return the resulting list.
So looks great.
Seems to work.
Everything has been tested, by the way.
So this is what this will be working.
And the product owner is happy with the results and he wants more.
So he now asks us, can you also make a function that returns the end Fibonacci number counting
from zero?
So it means that if you ask for Fibonacci number zero, then you get the first one.
If you ask for Fibonacci number one, you get the second one, and so on, and so on.
We programmers like to index from zero onwards.
So let's go that one.
It looks a bit the same, but also a bit different.
It doesn't return a list.
It just returns one Fibonacci value.
But again, you have these A and B registers.
It works the same.
You make a counter, but you don't need to count a variable.
You only use it to iterate certain times through this loop.
And you calculate the current Fibonacci number.
So when you have calculated that many n times, then you can return the current Fibonacci
number.
All right.
So the product owner now really gets enthusiastic and he says, okay, well, can you now make
also another function which provides the first n Fibonacci numbers?
So not Fibonacci numbers up to n, but the first n, and perhaps also a function that
gives me the smallest Fibonacci number greater than or equal to a certain value.
All right.
We start coding again.
So here's the first implementation.
Here we are returning a list again.
You use this counter, what you have seen from the construct before, and you append the current
Fibonacci values to the list, et cetera, et cetera, and then you return the result.
And the last one, smallest Fib greater equal n.
It's a bit different.
There you go into the loop, and as long as the current Fibonacci number is less than
n, you simply continue until that condition does no longer hold, and then you return the
current value because that is then equal to n or greater than n.
So now we have four functions.
In my original presentation, there were even five, but it makes the story a bit boring
perhaps, and these line up nicely together in this matrix.
So here you have the condensed form of these four functions together, and I don't know
what you're thinking, but I am seeing a pattern.
Do other people also are seeing some sort of pattern or whatever?
You see the pattern explained over here because for all those functions, the function starts
with a name, it accepts some parameter, a threshold or whatever, or an index kind of
value, and sometimes you need to initialize a container, a list in our case.
Then you initialize these Fibonacci registers, the A and the B.
Then you go into some while loop or a for loop with certain ending conditions, and then
you are in the loop calculating the new values of the Fibonacci registers.
And then at the end, you return the current Fibonacci number or you're returning the container
where you've put in all the numbers.
So that's the pattern.
So there is a bit of duplication in this code, and you don't like duplicate code because
you might run the risk that for one of the four implementations, you just missed it,
did it wrong.
So you want to try to factor out the common code which is present in these functions.
So how to get rid of the redundancy of this code, and that's where this talk is about.
It seems to be quite difficult.
But in general, if you want to get rid of redundancy, you would refactor your code and
extract that part.
So first the question, who knows what refactoring is?
Yeah, many hands.
Great, great, great.
So refactoring is about that you restructure your code without changing the external behavior.
But you usually do this to improve the design, the structure, and the implementation of the
code.
But you make sure that the original functionality of the code remains the same.
And you do this for a reason because your code becomes more readable, less complex,
and better maintainable.
All right.
You try to extract these common parts.
You can, of course, extract that single line, the A and B initialization, put that in a
function or something like that.
It's quite useless, right?
You replace one line by another line.
So that doesn't seem to work.
You can replace that other line where you are calculating the new Fibonacci registers,
which is happening in the loop.
It doesn't look very sensible either.
So you're kind of stuck.
How can you refactor it?
Perhaps you should combine the functionality of all these functions into one super function,
which is able to do all these different kinds of calculations depending on the mode flag.
You could make an enum, for example, designating the mode where the function is running in.
We could try it first with just combining the first two functions of this story and
then not using an enum, but just a Boolean designating the mode of the function.
So I should have warned you.
Perhaps you had to put on your parasensitive sunglasses on because this code really is
hurting the eye.
I hope you agree.
It starts already with the ugly type annotations.
I don't know.
Everybody has seen the keynote of Bukhash Langa.
And ugly type annotations are also an indication of ugly codes.
In this case, also, it's a bit strange that this function is either returning an int or
a list of integers.
So it doesn't make sense to explain.
This code is working, by the way, but it doesn't make sense to explain this code.
So this is not the way to go.
It's also a bit of a contrived example, of course, but it's just to demonstrate that
the resulting code is not quite maintainable and this is not the way to go.
So again, how to refactor this?
Well, I think the key thing is here that you have to take a step back.
You have to more conceptualize the things that are happening in your codes.
Perhaps fly on a higher altitude, so to say.
And if you do that and you start thinking about what is this code actually doing, actually
it's doing two things or one thing which is common for all the codes and that is that
a part of it is producing these Fibonacci numbers.
And the other part of all these respective functions is doing something else.
Dealing with ending loop criteria or the way the values are collected in a container
or that you are working towards the final calculated Fibonacci number.
So that is the separation that you can mentally make in this code.
So when you see that you have some sort of, you have codes where you do things but you
also have a data producing part in that code, then you might be thinking of this refactoring
pattern because the data producing part is the part that you can actually quite easily
isolate.
But how will you do this isolation?
Well, for that I need to introduce another concept and that are the generator functions.
Yeah, a generator function.
When you call this function it creates an iterator, a generator iterator and if you
code a function it's quite, it's just like you're coding a function except in the simplest
form it doesn't contain any return statements, it contains yield expressions.
And if a function contains a yield expression then it automatically becomes a function,
a generator function.
And the yield expression is used to give back a value to the caller but not all values,
only one value at a time.
So you can use for example such a function in a for loop or some other thing that can
deal with iterators, right?
Well, each time that you, that the caller, the consuming party needs another value, the
generator, well it starts with the generator giving its first value back, right?
And then when it does so it saves its state and it passes control back to the calling
code, to the consuming code.
And once the consuming party needs another value then the generator is revived, it's
starts where it left off, it still has the value, all the local variables still have
their own value and it can produce the next value and so on and so on until some ending
criteria is met or something else or the consuming party doesn't need any more values so that's
how it sort of works.
So then the next question is how can you code a generator function?
How can you code a generator function producing these Fibonacci numbers?
Well, that's this lovely elegant piece of code I would say.
Let's call it fibgen, a Fibonacci generator and this function generates an endless sequence
of Fibonacci numbers until your memory in your computer cannot cope with the ultra large
numbers that you're producing and you recognize some familiar parts in this code I guess because
here you're again, before you enter the loop you're initialize your Fibonacci registers
A and B to the starting values 0 and 1 and then you enter an endless loop while true
and there you yield this first Fibonacci number and then the consuming party can do something
with that number and then after that when the consuming party wants another element
then your function, generator function continues so you start calculating the next values A
and B with a familiar formula, you loop again into the same loop and you yield the next
value and it stops again so that's how it works and in my view what you see here is
perhaps the most canonical code in representation of the Fibonacci sequence when you would code
it in an imperative style.
You could also express it in a more recursive style but if you express it in an imperative
style it would look like this I would say.
The next question is how can you use this generator?
Well on the Apple, on the read evil print loop it would look like this.
For example if you want to print the first 8 Fibonacci numbers then you can write this
loop.
What you do is you're using the zip function to zip together counter a range of 10 it will
give you the values 0 to 9 you don't need those values they are zipped and they end
up in the underscore variable and you call the Fibonacci generator and those values end
up in the fib variable in this loop and then you simply print this fib variable and this
is how you can use this generator.
So you could say we're set we're ready and you have a long break but perhaps there's
a little bit more to it because we can go one step further and that is by using some
beautiful building block that's provided by the Python standard library and the Isotuse
uses provides a lot of these nice building blocks.
Here it says the module standardized core set of fast memory efficient tools that are
useful by themselves or in combination.
Together they form an iterator algebra I would say a pipeline of iterators making it possible
to construct specialized tools succinctly and efficiently in pure Python.
There's another module which is called it's not a module it's a package you can fetch
it from pypy the more is tools package and the more is tools package implements many
of the documented recipes which you can read in the in the isotules module and a lot of
more a lot more convenient helper routines.
So those tools to the rescue in the sense that you can make things even more compact.
For example let's start with the explanation of the take while function that you see here.
The take while takes a predicate function it's just a function returning a falsy or
true fee value and the function will be called with the current value that is given back
by the by the iterable and in our case the iterable is fibgen and if you write a lambda
expression you see that as long as the current number that is given back by the Fibonacci
generator is less than the n parameter it returns a true fee value in this case actually
it's actually just true and then the value is passed on by take while and as soon as
the condition does not hold any longer then the generator is shut off so to say and you're
set and all these values that have been passed through also as an iterable from take while
are collected in a list by using the list constructor.
So this first function that we have written can also be expressed in this way using the
iter tools. Same for the second function here we're going to use the islice function from
the iter tools module and there is in two forms and the islice function is just like
you would like to use slicing with lists right you remember the syntax with the square brackets
and the colons where you can provide a start a stop and the step value well the islice
is the equivalent of that but then for iterators except that you cannot provide negative values
for either for one of these parameters so there are two there are two forms or you provide
only the stop value the stop index index between quotes or you provide the start index the
stop index and the step index but there must be no negative and we have another tool from
the more iter tools package which is called one and the one function accepts an iterable
and it makes sure that the iterable only contains exactly one value not zero not more exactly
one and if it contains this value then it extracts that from the sequence and returns
it as a value so with the combination of these functions you can implement the second function
that was requested by the product owner so well we can continue like that for example
here we have the islice this is the first function here we use the islice function in
the one index form only the stop value this is the one with the first and fibs and finally
the smallest fib you remember we had the previous function where we were using the take while
and this one is using the drop while so this one also takes a predicate function and it
will drop any value as long as the condition holds and once the condition does not hold
it will start passing through the values that it gets from the iterator and the first function
from the more iter tools package just selects the first value and returns that one so that's
how you can implement the last requested function so this now we're moving towards the end of
the presentation I would say I would encourage you to read through the documentation of the
iter tools package the iter tools module and the more iter tools package it's a very valuable
collection and you can use it perhaps more frequent than you were thinking and if you
have an idea what it all has to offer then it can make your code more expressive as well
so that's my plea and part of the goal of this presentation and just to tease you a
little bit for example suppose you have a massive amount of data bulk data that you
need to put into a database and you're using some sort of ORM like a sequel alchemy to
put it in then sometimes it could be useful to put it in large chunks yeah I'm still there
in large chunks instead of all the data in one go and then for example you can use the
more iter tools chunks or the i chunked function of this module so that's it and that's the
recap so the recap is we are now perhaps more able to recognize a certain pattern of certain
loops constructs as candidates for refactoring you know what generator functions are and
how you can use them to extract the data producing part out of your entangled code and you have
made acquaintance with the iter tools module and the more iter tools package here are some
resources and links I was inspired by Wikipedia for the definition of the Fibonacci number
code refactoring the Python glossary contains generator function definition the documentation
of iter tools and more iter tools and I would like to thank you you can check my you can
check out my repository don't look into its history but it's a final result please on
the main branch and actually perhaps as an additional note I have used PyTestBDD behavior
driven development gurgling language to test all the functions that are that you've seen
actually what you the functions that you've seen in this listing are actually from the
repo as a link linked in so to say and so the code that has been shown is working code
and I've used PyTestBDD to test both the pre-refactoring and the post-refactoring variance and even
that weird combination function for its correct working and I understand that questions it's
better to get them later on or perhaps in the NL or so I would like to thank you for
your attention and hope to speak to you later.