Delighted to be here, and my talk today is going to be called Walking the Line.
I will open with an example, some example code.
Let's start writing a quick Python script.
Our script, given a sample Python program, will consider edits, adding or deleting one
character.
Python syntax is flexible, but how flexible is it?
Of all possible edits to a file, how many produce valid code?
All right.
As I was ready to start writing the example, I thought, oh, well, wait.
What sample program should the script edit?
Should it be print hello world?
Should it be something a little more indentation with an if statement or a for loop?
Then I realized, just have the script edit itself.
Then I only have to write one sample script instead of two.
And thanks to Python running from source, it's easy to do.
Let's just have it edit its own source code.
So I started like this.
Text equals open dunder file dot read.
This works because dunder file isn't a file.
Otherwise it would return an error.
Dunder file is the path to the current source file.
They should have called it dunder path.
So this tells a program to read in its own text as a string.
This was a single line until I had to format it for the narrow slide.
I do a simple list comprehension in order to loop over all of the indexes into this
large string, well, three line string.
And for each index, I construct a different copy of this code that has one character missing
each of them in succession.
And then as I was writing this script, I stopped.
When I'm ready to move from one thought to the next, from building these strings to testing
them, I have a habit of quickly stopping and checking my code so far.
So I added a line that's not going to make it into the final version of the script, I
will be a very verbose script.
But I just threw in a little line of code and went ahead and paused for a half second.
This triggers Emacs to syntax check the script.
The result, no errors.
Doing good so far.
And then I hit save.
Saving kicks off an automatic run of the script over in my terminal window.
In the old days, this was often not worth it because on old machines it would have meant
polling, right?
It would have meant having to write a little script that every second wakes up and checks
the modify time of all of your Python files in order to rerun your script if one of them
had changed.
And polling is expensive when there are no edits.
Second after second, it's having to check all those modify times, burning up our remaining
coal off of our power grid for nothing.
And it's slow when there are edits.
You hit save and then wind up waiting for the next second to turn over so that the script
runs.
It didn't tempt me back in the old days.
But today, Linux offers inotify, your own operating system if it's different, probably
has such a mechanism as well, with inotify.
A process can sleep.
Using zero CPU, waiting for changes to a file, it tells the OS, wake me up if there's a change
to one of these files, and the OS then wakes the process the instant the edit is saved.
So it doesn't waste time in CPU, and it runs instantly when you modify a file.
If you want to see the ways I've adapted that mechanism, in my GitHub repo called homedir,
where I have my scripts and setup files, I have something called watch.
I can give it any command, make or build or Python, with some arguments.
Then a double dash and the whole list of files that it should watch.
Whenever one of those files is modified, thanks to the magic of the operating system, I then
rerun that command.
I then got tired of typing this because the command was almost always Python and the list
of files was almost always all the py files beneath this directory.
So I then created a second shell script, which is an abbreviation of that.
You can look at both of those if you're interested in how I wrote up inotify powered automation.
Thanks to that automation, I hit save and can glance over at my terminal window to see the
output of the script.
And in this case, it worked.
I saw a huge list with lots of different versions of this code, all of which were missing a
single character as I intended.
So I'm feeling pretty lucky.
I wrote a couple of lines of code without an error.
We will honor that visually with a green dot.
I'm now going to edit.
We will represent that as an arrow from one state to another.
All right.
So first, remove the print line.
I remembered to remove the debugging print statement.
And now I want to loop over all of those candidate Python code and try evaling each one to see
which one of them raised syntax errors and which one of them didn't introduce a fatal
syntax error into this script.
My expectation is that I'll get a syntax error.
So I hit save.
I glance over at the terminal window.
And again, when I was younger, I wasted so much time, so much time going over to the
terminal window, hitting up arrow, hitting enter to rerun the previous command.
Then I wised up.
And now I pay a computer to do it for me.
I hit save.
I look at my terminal window and I see a syntax error.
So I'm going to count that as a success.
This might surprise you.
It's an error.
But it's the error I was expecting.
It's an error that is natural for the new state that I've brought the script to.
So I'm going to color it green because I understand what the script is doing and I can still make
progress.
I did an experiment.
I got the expected result.
All right.
Next, we don't want to let the syntax errors kill this program.
We want to count them.
And so I'm going to wrap a try except around the eval so I can count how many syntax errors
happen versus how many versions of the script are still okay.
I guess I need a counts dictionary.
So I jump up.
I often write code out of order because I'm following my ideas as they come, which isn't
necessarily top to bottom.
And then at the end, print that out.
So I hit save and looked over at my terminal.
Oh, that's not what I wanted.
Every single one character edit to this file is producing a syntax error.
That does not seem likely.
So I realize that something's wrong.
Drat.
And so I will represent that graphically as I'm now in a state I don't understand.
I've tried to add some code and it's not working.
So what's going on?
Let's back up.
I can safely comment it out, the try except, and hit save.
Let's look at this syntax error again.
What is this even?
Going and looking at the source.
So I looked at the source, looked at the terminal window.
The first line of the file is text equals open, et cetera.
The candidate string is xed equals open.
I notice immediately two things.
One, this is the very first string, right?
I'm creating a list of all possible characters that you can remove from the file.
The initial t is the first one.
So I'm failing on the very first string.
Second, I notice this isn't a syntax error.
I mean, it'll hit, if you tried running this, it would have a name error later when you
tried to use text and it wasn't there.
But ext is a perfectly good name in Python.
And the caret is pointing at the equals sign.
Not at the edit.
Oh, and suddenly I realized what I'd done wrong.
I've seen this before.
I, in my terminal window, run PyDoc eval just to check its documentation.
The source may be a string representing a Python expression.
Eval isn't powerful enough to run a whole module.
It just wants an expression.
And that's why the equals sign is the problem.
Because it's the equals sign that makes this a statement rather than simply a simple Python
expression.
All right, I see how to move forward.
I'm not supposed to eval the code.
In good grief, thank goodness it didn't work, or the script would have called itself until
I ran out of memory.
Eval doesn't just try to compile code, it instantly runs it.
So that was a good dodge there.
I don't want to call eval.
I just want to see if the code compiles.
And I need this to try to compile it, not as a simple expression, but that exact argument
is going to tell it, no, no, no, this is the text of a whole Python module.
So I hit save.
And out came the successful result.
Of all the possible characters you can backspace over, Python's fairly lenient syntax only
generates errors about a third of the time.
The other two thirds of the time, the file still comes out as one that Python can try
running if I asked it to.
Success.
Let's stop there.
The example has served its purpose.
If you're curious later, try adding a line or two to the script that also tries all possible
inserts.
But at this point, we have a rich enough diagram in order for us to proceed with the topic
of this talk.
Let's now improve our diagram to better correspond to my emotions.
My mistake with eval didn't feel to me like progress forward.
It felt like a detour.
When my code breaks, I feel like I've crossed an invisible line that separates working programs
from broken ones.
So let's make two changes to this diagram.
One, let's get that broken state, that moment when I didn't understand what the script was
doing and had to go back to debug.
And let's set that to the side of the main line of progress, my main line of development.
And second, let's draw in that line that I feel like I've crossed when I go from working
code to broken code.
Hence the title of this talk, walking the line.
This talk asks the question, how does programming feel?
So this talk discusses the two states, green and red.
Green leaves us free to make more progress.
Red leaves us stuck until it's fixed.
Let's start by talking about green.
Developers love green.
We won't have too much to say about it here in a talk on the emotions of walking the line.
It's the default starting point if you wake up and start editing a working program and
the happy end when you're ready to commit.
Generally, our only problem is wanting more of it.
Finishing, we spent more of our day writing working code.
So how could green, if it's such a good thing, wind up manipulating our emotions?
How could desire for it warp how we write code?
For me, a big problem is driving too hard and too long towards green in the mistaken
belief that I'm almost there, if only I just keep going.
I don't know if for you, the story will be a familiar one.
You start making what feels like a simple change and you're almost done when you realize
that there's a method that now needs a new argument.
Well, so you go and you start adding the new argument.
Oh, and that requires a new data structure to be created when the class is initialized.
Well, that requires the class initializer to be slightly more complicated.
And pretty soon, you're very deep into a pile of changes that all need each other.
And so you haven't yet been able to test or to see what the code now does.
And it is only after a pile of changes are complete that you finally are able to hit
save and see that what you've written is completely broken and may be broken in multiple
ways.
And you now don't even know how far away the line is as you begin the long climb back
out to understand what you've done wrong with your code.
All other things being equal, fixing code early when you're still close to the line
is cheap, while fixing code later is expensive.
So why would I write so much code at once?
Well, my drive to push harder and harder to make it back across the line to green prevents
me from stopping to properly solve my side quests.
What are side quests?
It's when you discover that the change you are making requires other changes that maybe
themselves each require further changes.
Two paths then lie before you.
Solve every side quest right there creating one single massive change.
Or stop.
Run get stash or commit to a branch to put aside your main goal and make the side quest
a first class objective that gets its own commit.
There's a famous comment by someone named Kent Beck about whom I don't know a single
thing except that he made this famous tweet.
Make the change easy.
Then make the easy change.
The idea is that instead of starting to make my big change and when the warning signs appear
that it requires even further steps, just going ahead and trying to do them all at once,
instead, as the attempt to make the big change teaches you what it needs, stop and do each
of those as smaller self-contained changes before you then try the difficult change at
the end.
That way you wind up on the productive side of the line with only occasional excursions
across.
A few people remember, though, that's not actually the full tweet.
Make the change easy then make the easy change.
What he wrote was this.
A few people remember that that's not the full text of the tweet.
Kent Beck actually tweeted for each desired change, make the change easy, open per in,
warning this may be hard, close per in, then make the easy change.
So even as he gave this advice, he acknowledged this doesn't always make things easy.
And so he acknowledged that even the refactorings we do before making a change, even doing things
in that correct order, we might still run into bumps in the road.
The point is that we stray much less far from the line if we do preparatory refactoring
before a big change than if we try to bundle everything into a single commit.
The side quests themselves can be difficult, but not as difficult as pulling the whole
world apart at once and only then trying to repair it.
So that's what I had to say about the emotions around green.
Let's now move on to the somewhat meatier topic of our emotions around red.
Do we programmers ever want red?
Do we ever want to break things?
Yes.
Oh, yes.
One obvious case is test-driven development called TDD in the biz.
It would be a whole talk of its own.
I will simply say here, if you haven't used it before, it's a technique where you start
by writing a failing test of a new feature that you're about to add.
Failing because you haven't written the feature yet.
Then you write the code to turn the test green by adding that feature.
And then you repeat.
For our purposes here, I'll just note that it does have a few advantages in situations
you're able to practice it, which I'll just go ahead and say, usually when you're first
writing something, you don't understand it well enough to TDD it.
This is for kind of the second time that you write something when you know what you're
doing.
I try writing a change.
At the bitter end of failure, I realize what it should have looked like.
Now I know enough to back up and TDD it.
But here I'll just note three things.
TDD does get the worst thing writing the test over first.
How many times does a test not get written because you save it for the end and by the
time you're done, you just want to commit.
You're not going to stop and write a test.
That's not true.
It's actually the documentation that's worse.
And most likely to be skipped, but who's counting?
TDD arranges a nice reward for when you finish.
The test goes green.
And it by its nature produces a decently well-tested code base.
It has its advantages.
But I'm not going to talk about it a lot.
Just for the purposes of this talk, let's just note that TDD just leverages your usual
negative emotions about red.
There's nothing really edgy or surprising about it.
You want the red to go away, so you write code that satisfies the new test.
Leverages perfectly normal emotions around red and green.
But it's the claim of this talk that emotions can also work the other way around.
It is the claim of this talk that there are situations where you aren't avoiding red.
You're seeking it out.
What, I hear you ask, could lead to that?
Feelings of insecurity.
Let's consider three.
Number one, too much green.
Imagine that you're performing extensive refactoring.
Each time you save, you're thrilled the result is still green.
You're just going and going along the line and never tipping over into broken code.
Your streak of green runs longer and longer until your spidey sense kicks in and you suddenly
feel a tiny bit incredulous.
Am I really this good at refactoring?
And then suddenly the thought strikes.
Hey, wait.
The tests are running my code.
Right?
Taps mic.
Is this on?
So at such moments of terror, I invoke a maneuver.
My ASDF check.
Control E jumps to the end of the line.
Return opens a new line and indents to the level of the previous one.
And I just roll my left hand across home row ASDF.
And then I hit save.
I've now added a line of code that would not be a valid line of code in any Python program
I have ever written.
What am I going to see on the screen?
If all is well, then I will see the happy result.
Name error.
Name ASDF is not defined.
And I will keep coding, confident in my own righteousness.
I really was refactoring that well.
But what if I don't see it?
What if I just see more green?
Oh, no.
Disaster.
All that time I thought my work was being checked and I thought it was excellent.
And instead, I have no idea what my state is.
Am I on one side of the line or the other?
I have no indication.
What could have gone wrong?
Some of the following scenarios might be familiar.
And this is only a sampling.
One, you are, alas, in the wrong project.
No number of edits to the models.py file in your campsite project
are going to change the behavior of your bookworm project.
You can keep editing for as long as you want.
It's not going to make a difference.
Two, you're editing the right project.
But this project is checked out twice on your laptop.
And you're editing one copy while running the other.
Three, you need to hit shift reload, not plain reload,
for your browser to see that edit to your CSS.
That's why the color's not changing.
I see someone clutching themselves in the audience.
Your editor's jump to function definition shortcut
decided to jump into site packages instead of into a repository.
So you're editing some installed copy of that package
instead of the one you have checked out.
Bonus points if you forget to remove ASDF.
And months later you run some other Python application
and see name error.
ASDF is not defined.
Five, you're editing local code on your laptop
but reloading a remote version of the site.
You thought that your browser was looking at localhost shopping cart
as you debug it.
And accidentally you're looking at the example out on a server.
And so your edits don't matter.
Six, you did open the remote copy of the file,
but your SSHFS connection automatically for things across the network
has gone down, so you are now merely saving files locally.
Seven, a disk error forced your file system to remount read-only,
but your editor isn't telling you.
Now why? That's a deep sin by an editor.
Like you rely on knowing your code has been persisted if you hit sync.
Well, because the cool fancy new color highlighted third-party error
reporting plugin you decided to install dies silently on a read-only file system.
Not your editor's fault.
All right, are you ready for the bonus round?
Eight, remember the end of the day last Friday?
Your coworkers were already gathered by the elevator
waiting for you to join them and go out and start the weekend.
When your boss hustled up and asked if the app works on leap day.
Silly question because the app isn't particularly date sensitive.
Apparently the boss just read an article about leap day bugs
and so now he's taking it out on you.
All right, so this isn't something that's worth setting up a permanent build to test.
You're just going to show locally that things work.
So you set your system clock briefly to next February 29th,
hit restart, hit reload and showed that your app still worked.
Then you were able, then you fixed your system clock,
headed out with your friends.
It's now Monday morning.
Turns out all the PYC files written during those five minutes
are dated 2024, February 29th.
Which is in the future.
Which makes those PYC files more recent than anything you save today.
So Python is ignoring your new PY edit.
Tell me, tell me I'm making this up.
My blanket advice, by the way, while we're on the subject, turn off PYC files.
It was in 2014 that I added this line to my system environment.
Python, don't write bytecode.
I have never once regretted it.
Any of these underlying causes will make you want to cross the line.
They make you want to break things and see real consequences.
They reverse your normal psychology and make you going out looking for that barrier.
Feelings of insecurity.
Here's a second one.
My tests are running.
I can see that my edits are having an effect.
But are my tests protecting me?
It's an especially important question before a big refactor.
When you start trying to change code around, add and remove parentheses from difficult expressions,
do you know that your tests will catch you if you mess up?
We see a line of code sometimes and think, oh, that's interesting.
Is this tested?
I'll give a modest example.
I always get mixed up and have to think back through what Max does if used with a constant like negative 3000.
I always have to think through, okay, if line 16 is 1000 or 2000 or 3000 or 4000,
its value will come right through as though Max hadn't been called.
Zero, negative one or 2000 will also come through.
It's only when line 16 gets so negative that it loses the little contest for who's the biggest number
that Max will switch over and start returning negative 3000 as its value instead.
Thus, and this never ends surprising me, you call Max to set a minimum bound on something.
Contrary wise, calling min with a constant sets a maximum bound on the return value.
You'll notice that big professional data libraries in Python don't use that terminology anymore.
They use things like in pandas clip upper and clip lower.
I have been known in my Python modules up at the top to just alias min and Max to those two names
so that I don't have to remember that Max sets a minimum bound and min sets a maximum bound.
Looking at this line of code, we might catch that there is a hidden if statement here.
Max chooses one of two possibilities, and even if you're running coverage.py
and it tells you that your tests do run this line of code,
you don't know whether both cases are tested, only that the line runs at least once.
How do we know whether our tests cover both cases?
Let's cross the line.
Let's deliberately step over into red for a moment before we start our big refactoring
just to make sure we're protected here from something that might mangle this code.
Let's do quick edits to disable Max.
A hint, when I do this, I find it's faster if I don't experiment on the line itself.
Instead, I make a copy.
I take the line, I duplicate it, and I comment out the first one, leaving it unchanged.
In Emacs, this is just a few keystrokes, and of course, in your editor, you could set up a shortcut for it.
If it annoyed you to type a few characters to do this, it's an important habit for me.
Here are some hints.
First, use the pound sign with no space after it, so you'll remember not to commit,
because that makes it not even look like a real comment.
Pep8 says that each line of a block comment starts with what?
Pound in a single space.
Inline comments should start with a pound in a single space.
When I go to commit, and I notice a line that's a mangled comment with no space after it,
I'll immediately realize that's something I was supposed to undo before committing and fix it.
Two, it makes it easy to undo.
Delete the experimental line and remove the pound sign.
Third, it lets you, as you edit, compare to the original.
Just move your eye up and look at what it said before.
It doesn't seem important in this case, but if I'm doing a hairy formula in one of my astronomy libraries,
I can get pretty lost as I remove parentheses and cancel out minus signs.
It's really good to have the original right there to look at.
You might think that version control could obviate the need to do number two and three here,
but I often find that if I'm in the middle of a large section of code I'm editing,
version control just can see that a chunk of code was replaced with another chunk.
It isn't necessarily easy to see which original line my modify is an edit of,
so I like using this comment technique.
Now, having scrolled away the original line, we're free to break the code.
We can start editing.
I can hard code it to line 16, kind of look over and see if any tests fail.
I can then change it to the other, minus 3000, hit save, glance over at my terminal window,
and see if any tests fail.
I'm deliberately trying to break things.
In both cases, you want the result to be red.
Otherwise, you're going to need to add a test for that case before you go doing your big refactor.
When programming, I'm happiest if I don't leave feelings of insecurity unacknowledged.
Go ahead, quickly break the code to be sure that you are safely fenced in by your tests.
Breaking things.
We arrive here at kind of a big parting of the ways.
In real life, in a workplace, in a relationship, crossing a line just to see if it's really there is bad.
So we must balance two philosophies.
We all remember that it was Gandalf who said,
he that breaks a thing to find out what it is has left the path of wisdom.
Not a computer programmer.
It was the poet William Blake, the man who, as he walked England,
could see the angels and devils and archangels that others could not,
who was told once by a devil what the proverbs of hell were.
Here's one of them that he wrote down for us.
You never know what is enough unless you know what is more than enough.
He also said the road of excess leads to the palace of wisdom.
A bit more enigmatically, if the fool would persist in his folly, he would become wise.
What's my point?
I think my point is this.
When it comes to how you treat people, be Gandalf.
But with your code, it better be William Blake.
All right, feelings of insecurity, final number three.
Some of us are haunted by a fear.
Wait!
Maybe this code could be even simpler.
Some of us suffer from a nagging fear that we might have written slightly more code than is strictly necessary.
Surprisingly, this can lead to nonoptimal outcomes.
A story.
I once worked in Georgia Tech's IT shop.
Every night our script would run SCP to copy a CSV from human resources that listed all 30,000 employees.
Any of yesterday's employees that were missing from today's list received a goodbye email.
Clean up your computer account, goes away in 30 days.
Guess what happened early one Monday morning, it ran in the wee hours, when the TCP connection died.
3,000 lines before the end.
3,000 employees were emailed goodbye.
It was a bad day.
I don't think customer support was able to accomplish anything else that day.
So many trouble tickets were open by people that wondered why their computer account was being erroneously shut off.
If I recall, it was in the S's when the TCP connection died.
So if your last name started with A or B, you were fine.
But if you were T or you were V, you were toast.
Unfortunately, in any organization as dysfunctional, especially as modern academia,
in any group of 3,000 employees, there are going to be some whose relationship with their management is bad enough
that they might, instead of immediately thinking, oh, the computer's done something stupid,
they might reasonably expect this is how they were going to be let go.
And so for those people, it was a very bad day.
What interests me now, looking back, is my inadequate response to the problem.
What did we developers do?
We read some docs, did some tests, and switched the script from using SCP to R-Sync.
SCP just gradually copies, and you get a partial file if the connection dies.
Whereas R-Sync copies to a temporary file, and only if the entire file arrives does it move it in place of the old one.
So it's safe.
Problem solved. This will never happen again, right?
Well, we were then called into a meeting with a vice president.
You know, the vice president that I'm sure had expected to do something else that Monday,
besides be on the phone giving apologies all over campus,
he ordered that HR append a new line, dash dash end, to the file,
and that we must check for it each night before using the file.
Of course, we were enraged.
We had already solved the problem ourselves.
The design of R-Sync made the extra check illogical.
And the beautiful symmetry of the poor CSV file, every line, the same number of commas,
every line, the same number of fields, is ruined by adding the extra line.
So we wound up arguing unsuccessfully against what strikes me today as an imminently sensible precaution.
What went wrong with our decision making?
Well, several things, but we'll focus here on one.
When a team lacks the expertise to control complexity through good architecture,
we tend to fall back on an obsession with writing and maintaining the least code possible.
What went wrong?
Well, we were indulging in the pleasures of the mathematician.
We wanted code to be minimal and concise, like proof.
When our role demanded the maturity of an engineer.
When engineers walk the line between success and failure by hewing as close as possible to failure,
do they build bridges that can support the rated limit, but not a single ton more?
You know, systems that are robust are also necessarily redundant.
You know, I ought to have welcomed the chance to give the machine two reasons not to disable 3,000 employee accounts on any given Monday morning.
I ought to have been happy to take a deep breath and for once to step away from the line.
In conclusion, as a programmer, I risk being driven by my emotions as if by a storm at sea.
Managed wisely, they can lead me to a comfortable harbor of double-checked code cosseted among many tests.
Or they can lead me to overly fragile systems that bring my customers to shipwreck.
Even as we are typing our code, we ride a knife's edge.
Between code that fails or runs.
Tests that are spotty or thorough.
Systems that are fragile or robust.
Whether we strain to stay on one side of the line or are compulsive in probing and stepping across, it's always there right alongside us.
And by the very nature of our art, we programmers always, always, always are walking the line.
Thank you very much.