So this talk is titled Duck Typing Meta-Classes and Recursion Building a Deep Collection Type.
What a mouthful, right?
So this is going to touch on some things a lot of developers find kind of intimidating
or scary to various degrees, but they're all in the language for a reason.
They can be used to great effect sometimes.
I'll also say at the outset too that part of the mission of the library that I made for all this
is to generalize something.
And if you're working for a company or doing a job, you probably most often don't want to generalize your code.
You want to be narrowly scoped to what you're trying to do because generalizing is hard.
You take your five-point ticket and get it done in a month because you generalized it,
your boss probably isn't going to be very happy.
So there's a time and a place for it.
You might encounter it sometimes at your work, but it's encountered very often in library writing,
all the libraries that you're used to and familiar with with TIPS.
So the thing that we're trying to generalize now is handling large or cumbersome data,
things that are deeply nested and maybe we know what they are, maybe we don't.
We encounter stuff like this all the time in APIs and infrastructures code, in data science.
Sometimes applications have internal structures and it's not just DICs and lists.
Sometimes there's tuples in there or double-ended queues, DECs, whatever you have.
But handling stuff like this is really common.
So we're going to quickly go over a little bit of prior art.
So there is this library that was made several years ago called DottieDict.
DottieDict did a couple cool things.
You can pass it your dictionary and create a new object.
And then you can start drilling down into the data in your object by dot chaining.
That is pretty cool.
It's just a little bit of syntactic trigger though for this, right?
It's like a type.
That's basically the same thing.
There's not a ton going on there that's really novel, a little bit.
So it's fun enough.
Maybe if that's your preference, you get a kick out of DottieDict.
But there's some issues with what DottieDict can handle.
So if we look at our structure we had up here,
we had company employees contact info.
So there's some fields with dots in them.
And we're using dots as a separator in this path.
So when we try to do the same thing, it fails because company dot company doesn't exist.
We need company dot company name.
So DottieDict has a solution for this.
They've got a separator object.
I'm separating our field here in the function that you can pass.
Oh, wait.
No, they don't.
Originally we made this DottieDict from a function they gave us.
But we need a different API to use a separator.
I think that's a bit of a limitation.
That's not a very friendly API to expose to people.
But it does work.
So we can give it a different separator.
And now we get our company name out of this nested dict.
Cool.
Let's try something a little bit different.
Let's start with something that is a list off the bat.
It still contains dicts and lists.
And I quickly copy that over and make a DottieDict version of that.
And we can't.
DottieDict needs a dict.
So there's a few limitations in this prior art.
Then came along Python Benedict.
I first encountered Python Benedict very recently, actually.
They announced themselves on Reddit and the Python subreddit.
So I took a look at them.
And they were doing some of the things that I wanted to see done.
Wanted to see have done.
So we try to make a Benedict dictionary out of this thing, too.
But it fails right off the bat for a similar reason.
There's this company.name thing.
But Benedict is at least eagerly erroring on it,
saying we don't know how to handle that.
So we pass it a separator again.
Okay, great.
And now we can still access something in it in this path-like way.
But they're using a forward slash separator now instead of a dot.
Okay, good enough.
Let's do a little test, though.
Let's find something else interesting about these.
We can try to find out the type of the DottieDict thing that we got.
And it's not actually a dictionary.
It's its own thing.
So if you're trying to work with dictionaries,
and you want to be able to use is instance
to know that you have a dict somewhere in your code,
DottieDict actually doesn't pass that test.
You don't have a dict.
It could be a little annoying.
Benedict succeeds here.
Benedict is a dict.
Great.
That could be useful.
And Benedict has another power.
You can search into your nested dict to find something.
And part of the deal here is we have a big cumbersome data structure,
and we either don't understand it.
We don't want to have to stare at it forever.
Maybe we kind of do understand it,
but we don't want to type the whole thing out.
We want a little shorthand.
So Benedict helps us out.
Oh, but again, there are some issues with Benedict.
Again, you can't pass a list to something
and have it become a dict.
It's not in the name.
So there's some issues.
What do we really want?
We want something that can handle any type.
We want to be able to take a nested structure.
We don't care what type it is.
And we want to be able to have certain handy features
attached to that structure that enable us to introspect
and traverse that structure.
But we also want to preserve typing.
If I start with a dict, I want it to act like a dict.
If I start with a tuple, I want it to act like a tuple.
This instance should work.
So I kind of want a subclass, basically, is what it sounds like.
I want something where I can subclass dict,
have it be this deep thing and act like a dict.
But I also want to be able to subclass list and tuple
and retain all the typing that comes with all of that.
And I want better traversal.
I don't really like having to deal with this separator thing.
This bit right here is kind of handy.
Depending on how you like to type things,
you may prefer to traverse a structure like this.
It's not too different.
But if I pass it an iterable,
that looks more natural to me as a Python developer.
And it's easier and more natural to construct.
So maybe I can actually programmatically create these paths
and dig down into it.
Now, if I really want a goal,
what I want is pattern matching in the structure
to traverse it programmatically.
Again, I don't need to know what the structure is.
I just want a thing that's inside it.
Think about the talk two talks ago.
We had all this health data.
It looked nasty, right?
I don't need to understand what all is contained in all of that.
I just want to be able to dig in and get what I want.
That'll have a little bit of an issue
if I have pattern matching like that.
Because what if the object,
what if the field contains asterisks or something like that?
So I still need a little bit of support.
But it's got a better default.
Okay, so now we're going to get into how we do all this.
There's a few things we can try.
So this is a class factory made from a function.
Show of hands, whoever has indented class before
in real code that lived, a few.
I'm actually kind of surprised by how many raise their hands,
but still most people know, right?
It's not a thing you commonly need to do.
And it's got some real benefit.
With it, we can create an object out of this list,
get something new.
We've got this deep collection object we're creating
and it is in fact a list instance.
And we can pass it a dictionary as well
and we'll get back a dictionary instance.
So we've got dynamic inheritance here.
Again, you don't normally want to do this,
but sometimes you really want to leverage
some of the strengths that Python has naturally.
Python is a very dynamic language.
I love type-inning, static typing,
when you can get it in Python is fantastic.
But some things are naturally dynamic
and if you leverage that, you can get a lot out of it.
So there's a problem here with this class factory.
This class isn't really exposed to you.
You can't get it back without creating an instance,
which means you can't subclass it
and you can't directly access the class
to add on your own methods and pass that along the chain.
So how do we get a class without a factory function
without a factory function made from a...
How do you get a factory function class without the function?
The answer is you use a metaclass.
Again, I think metaclasses are pretty uncommonly used.
A quick refresher, a metaclass is the class of a class.
So if we have just standard old class here,
it's instantiated just by typing that class foo pass.
The class exists in the namespace.
If we instantiate the class, we say these parentheses here
create an object out of the class.
So you have a class, you instantiate it to get the object.
But Python is hiding from you a little bit.
That's because you have a class
but Python is hiding from you a little bit
the fact that even just writing this, you're instantiating the class.
So if you have a metaclass, you can create how that's done.
So if I type class foo again, class foo,
class bar, metaclass equals foo,
pass and get rid of that thing right there.
Create a little in it dunder.
And for these purposes, we don't care what happens here.
All right, we get in it.
I didn't instantiate anything in the normal way.
All I did was tell Python the bar uses foo as a metaclass
and the in it function was called.
So, okay, that's kind of how metaclasses work.
You saw again a couple of talks ago the call dunder method
that is this right here.
In a normal class, if we go up just a bit again to this,
we can instantiate a class like so.
And then if I put parentheses on that again,
that would call the call dunder method.
So on the metaclass, this is the same thing that's called
when you instantiate a class in the first place.
If you can wrap your heads around that.
It's a little bit of recursion just baked into what's going on
with metaclasses inherently.
So if this is invoking call directly,
that means I can use it to pass in a new object
and the metaclass can dynamically create my class
with the object I gave it as a type.
So that's what's going on here.
I'm collecting args and quarks and call
and I'm extracting the thing I'm passing in
as the base object I'm building from.
It could be a dict or a list.
I'm getting the type of that thing, dict or list.
Then I'm using the type function to create a new class.
Use type sometimes to type check things
but the three argument form creates a new type.
So we create the new type.
We call new on it and then in it in order
and then return the instance of that new type.
It's kind of complicated but this will work here
and then finally when I'm in the type that uses the metaclass,
I'm going to call in it and pass the original object.
So the idea is if I start with a list,
I preserve that original list item
and use it to populate through the old type.
Let's try it out real quick.
Okay.
Now let's see here.
Okay, so this looks like a list so far.
It is in fact a list.
Great, that is what we wanted
and I can do the same thing with a dict.
Okay, cool.
So now all the methods, thank you.
So now all the methods that list and dict normally have
should just come along for free.
We don't need to build any of it
and it doesn't matter what kind of object
someone's going to create a deep collection with.
We're going to mimic it.
We're going to bring everything along for free.
This is a big step in generalization.
We're not done quite yet.
Because there's a little problem with tuples.
What's wrong with tuples?
Tuples are an immutable data type.
So passing in the object in the init doesn't work.
You need to pass it in up here when we call dunder new.
Easy enough, we've got it.
So we just amend our new bit right here
so we can pass that in.
And then we wrap the super call in a try accept.
Because we still need the super call some of the time
when we're dealing with a immutable object.
Just not the immutable ones like tuples.
So let's modify this a little bit more.
Let's try that tuple again.
Great, okay.
It's a tuple.
Okay, so now I'm dynamically inheriting.
But I'm not really doing much that's interesting with this yet.
What I really want for that pathing feature
that I was talking about before
is I want to have special get methods.
Get items, set item.
I want to attach a paths to key method.
A paths to value method.
And all the values for a particular key.
We'll get to all that in time.
I'm not going to go through every little bit.
But this is where the even more recursion comes into play
and a lot of duck typing.
So this is a little snippet.
See if I can.
Yeah, I'm going to have to scroll a little bit here.
So there's a paths to key function here at the bottom
that we're going to use.
And I'm cutting out a lot of logic here.
But you see there's a quick test for if the key is itself path like.
Like is the key a list?
Or if it's simple like a string.
And then there's calls to separate functions
called paths to path like key and paths to simple key.
And we have one of those abbreviated here.
So the duck typing comes in a little bit here.
We're checking if something thinks it's a dict.
Okay, great.
And then we iterate through all the keys and items of the dict.
And if it's not a dict, it's probably a list.
So we'll do that.
But if we're checking is instance, we're going to need
whoever knows how many if statements.
So it's not like really duck typing.
What's really duck typing is to just try it.
Just try to access dot items and see if it works.
If it does, fantastic.
Recurse, go further down the tree.
Because like what Al Swigert said yesterday is like
recursion is horrible, right?
We don't want to use recursion ever.
Except one real good case, which is tree traversal.
And that's what we're doing right here.
We've got this structure of whatever geometry, whatever type.
We don't know where anything is.
We need to do a search through a tree.
So recursion is the natural fit here actually.
And we're using yields and yield from.
So we can make this all generator like.
Because we don't know how long it's going to take.
We don't know how big the structure is, how deep it is.
And we don't necessarily want all the things at once anyway.
If we do, we can just put the generator inside a list call.
But anyway, we have a try and accept here to be really duck typey.
See if it's dict like.
If it's not, okay.
See if it's iterable anyway, like a list or a tuple.
And get everything out of this that you can.
Pause for a second and reiterate.
Generalizing is hard, right?
If you know the structure that you're dealing with.
And it's well defined.
You don't necessarily need all of this.
You don't need a lot of try and accepts around duck typing.
If you know the types that you're working with.
Don't do all of that.
This is going to take you a lot more time to figure out.
But there's good reason that I'm doing it.
Which is I wanted to provide a library that other people could use.
Libraries should be generalized fairly often.
And if recursion and metaclasses scare you, it might be comforting to know that they're
pretty common in a lot of the libraries you're familiar with.
Most day job Python programmers don't write metaclasses.
But it's in Pydantic.
They're using a great metaclass or two.
Django uses metaclasses.
SQLAlchemy uses metaclasses.
Some of the best Python libraries we know get some of their functionality.
Out of the fact that they're leveraging these deeper uncommonly used tools.
Python has a lot of power.
Most people don't need and shouldn't try to use.
Unless they've got a good reason.
I think this is a pretty good reason.
We talked about in another previous talk the Zen of Python.
One of them is simple is better than complex.
Totally agree.
But what does that really mean to a normal developer?
They're using libraries like Pydantic and Flask to make things simple.
But that doesn't mean the code inside Pydantic and Flask is simple.
Flack has a pretty complicated stack handling mechanism.
Pydantic is really complicated internally.
So that's what we're choosing to do often.
Is we're hiding complexity when it's necessary.
And leveraging it to get us a lot of powerful tools.
So yeah, simple is better than complex.
Definitely.
And that's part of why I'm doing this.
So if you have cumbersome data, you can use it simply.
You don't need to know how this library was built.
But it makes for a fun talk.
So, okay, so generalizing is hard, but it's possible.
So I've done some of this.
These are excerpts from the library that I wrote.
Let's see if it can actually do something.
So the real thing, I'm not going to scroll through the few hundred lines of Python that it is.
But I will prove that it actually does work.
So we had, again, remember that in the previous talk,
so we had, again, remember that data object.
It was this thing up here.
The IPython is condensing it a bit for me, but that's what it is.
And I access double star here to go down any number of levels to find company name.
And I got out a company name.
Great.
Okay, let's try a few other things.
There was zip codes in there.
Let's find all the zip codes.
And I don't need to know exactly what the name of the key was.
It's got a zip in there somewhere.
So I surrounded by more asterixes, more globbing.
And I get out all the zip codes.
I think that's pretty cool.
There's a handy function in there that'll dedupe these things for you.
I miscopied something.
Well, I'll figure that one out later.
But there is a dedoping function that even works for things that are not hashable.
There's all these things often presented to you as generators.
And again, you can just get your values out by calling list on this.
And these are then all the paths to the zip code field in our structure.
So that can be really handy.
And because they're a normal list, that's pretty easy to iterate over and modify if you want.
So if you're trying to translate that path into something else useful elsewhere in the same
structure or a similar structure, you can see I've had to do stuff like this several times for clients.
And then you can get back the values because those paths work.
Now, so that's the end of that little bit of the talk.
But I think I've got a couple of minutes left.
So I'm going to show something a little interesting.
One more bit of the library.
See if I can just explode this.
So Josh Cannon, I think in a lightning talk, you said you mentioned get adder.
Everybody uses get adder.
No one uses get attribute.
Get attribute is a little bit of a different thing.
Get attribute is its twin brother, its evil twin.
So the difference between those two Dunder methods is that get adder is lazy.
And get attribute is eager.
So when you're subclassing something, you want to use get adder if you want to check if a method
exists and then give a fallback for if it doesn't.
Get attribute seizes the first opportunity, though.
So one fun part in this code base that I can show off is that get attribute here
intercepts every method call and checks to see if that method exists on the parent class.
And if it does, decorate it so that we can check and make sure that that parent class method
did or did not mutate the underlying structure
and then sync it with the deep collection class that we've got.
So like list.append.
If you use list.append, you're going to add to the list.
Well, you can add to a deep collection list too, sure.
But we need to keep track of what that change is.
So we again call this insure post call sync method.
And that is a decorator, not with the at syntax because decorators are functions.
We're just calling it right up here.
So that if our underlying structure changes, we keep it in sync.
Sounds simple enough, but this is a complicated bit of code.
You can go and noodle over later if you want.
Took me a little bit to figure out.
So that's basically it.
And through fiddling with my laptop trying to get it on the screen,
I forgot the introduction to all of this.
So real quickly, I guess, you know some of this already because we just went over it.
But I hoped that some of what you would get out of this depends a bit on your experience level.
There's some complicated stuff in here, but a new person can get something.
Hopefully even the experienced among you saw something interesting.
And me, why you can pay any attention to me and you think I know anything about all this.
I've been a Python developer and consultant for over a decade.
I've got quite a bit of experience.
I run a company that does Python and DevOps consultation.
And I'm an open source contributor.
I've contributed to and maintained a few projects.
So I'm not scared of diving into that general world and that library world.
That's where I like to be.
I enjoy building things people can use.
That is my talk.
Does anybody have any questions about all this wild stuff?
Yeah, so this is a real library you can pip install and use.
And I'm basically announcing it today.
And it's ready to use.
It is very well tested.
And I aim to have it exhaustively test all the built-in types and collection types.
So that you have no doubt that it actually works across the board.
And it handles some third-party types.
Like you can make a dot edict, a deep collection even.
It is called deep collections.
It's on PyPI.
Search for it there.
From there, there'll be a link to the repository if you want to check out how the code actually works.
Can you say again the library name?
I haven't run across that one.
I tried searching for other similar things.
James path is an older one that's pretty similar to diedict.
But it has searching features.
Deep path is another one that has searching features.
You can basically do everything in those that you can over in here.
But with some of the extra niceties that people didn't consider before.
Like all this type stuff.
The processing speed in my library is not the focus.
It's developer speed.
It's making things easy for you to figure out.
But if you want speed, a lot of the features here are exposed as functions too.
So you don't even need this class stuff.
You can just search for the thing in the dikt and be done with it.
So I'll look at that one later and try and figure out what differences may exist.
Other question?
It does.
So the default is glob syntaxing.
And we use python standard library fn match for that.
And it's got the double wild card for traversing any number of steps.
It matches keys and dicks and indices and lists.
But you can substitute out that pattern matching for regex.
Or a different custom matching algorithm that you write.
So yes.
Any other questions?
All right.
That's my talk.