Thank you. And good morning. My name is Natalia Bugha. I am a senior software developer at Bloomberg.
Like that? Is it better? All right, thank you. Natalia Bugha, senior software developer at Bloomberg.
Before I get into the topic of my discussion, I would like to say a few words about myself and the company I work for.
Bloomberg is a financial information software data and news and media company.
We are a global company with offices in all major financial hubs and even more news bureaus around the world.
We provide financial technology solutions such as analytics, trading platforms, data services and news to our customers all over the world.
They use our solutions to make informed financial decisions and collaborate.
I don't do any of that. I work in the department that... Oh, I'm sorry. I forgot to switch my slide.
This is our main product, Bloomberg Terminal, that has all that good stuff.
And as I said, it's used by many decision makers. And now about myself.
As I said, I work in the department that provides software for the internal Bloomberg use.
During my tenure there, I supported areas such as HR, operations sales and now compliance.
Being exposed to all these areas gave me a glimpse into how such a big company operates, which I find kind of exciting.
Since I joined compliance, I was exposed to a new area in technology we call regulatory technologies or RegTech.
It encompasses... It's a rapidly growing field and it encompasses software that is used by companies to stay compliant with regulatory requirements and do it efficiently.
And some examples of the RegTech activities are sanctions screening, anti-money laundering, monitoring, client management and some employee conduct policies.
But the main aspect of my work that I particularly enjoy is having my users in the same company, often in the same building,
which lets me get immediate feedback about my releases and learn about their work and the main I support.
By communicating with my users in official and unofficial settings and just picking up the phone and calling them and asking,
hey, what do you think about this? Or getting a call from them with questions, well, why doesn't this work? Or more often, how do I do this?
And often this will lead to a more in-depth discussions and some ideas about what we want to build next.
And having this firsthand experience with coming up with these ideas and converting them into technical designs and then eventually seeing a complete product gives me a sense of accomplishment and impact.
And this brings me to my topic. I'm going to tell you about a small project that I worked on.
And I'll talk about, I'm going to use it as an example to demonstrate how we approach finding a solution by employing design thinking.
And I will also highlight my personal beliefs that good design will not only address user business problems, but will also eliminate distractions for developers and result in greater productivity and satisfaction with the end product.
So what is design thinking? Often you will hear design thinking methodology or design thinking process.
I like this quote from Michael Keeling's book because it highlights the essence of design thinking as a way of thinking and considering perspectives of the users who directly interact with our products.
So how does it work? Five steps or processes have been established to carry out this process.
And the first one is empathize, which basically you do want to understand the needs and the problems of your users and their ideal environment to achieve their goals.
And it does require a certain level of curiosity and empathy.
And when we talk about people who are directly affected by the product, we very often forget about ourselves.
And I believe we as developers are definitely affected by the products we build.
How much time do we want to spend on maintenance, on support? How are we going to operate our products?
These considerations should be taken into account when we design them.
Once we know, once we understand what the problems are and what the ideal outcome would be, we want to define our goals so that everyone is clear on the approach we want to take and what we are trying to achieve.
And once we have that, we want to brainstorm and put forward the ideas and evaluate them and sort through them and figure out what are the best ones to achieve a good result.
And after that, we want to build a prototype, even if it's a simple visualization, just so that there is a good understanding about the final product or a final process.
And then we test it out. We do want to make sure we build what we set out to do.
This process works best on the large and complicated problems, but for the purpose of this demo, I will use a simpler solution.
So to give you a background into this problem, one of the basic and pretty critical actions in Rectec is screening.
For example, sanctioned screen entities. I am in the middle of it. I provide an operational solution.
So basically what I need to do is basically is acquire our data set and transfer it to the location where screening is performed.
This is a very simple process. However, for a number of reasons, not only regulatory, this process was going to expand.
The number of data sets that we have to screen would grow. The types of screening would expand as well, and it was going to become a disaster to manage them.
And it was equally a very hectic process for us developers and for users. Maintaining them, setting up new ones, we needed a solution.
And this is the first art piece I commissioned ever from a more artistic colleague of mine.
This is what she came up with when I described the process and the situation.
And so basically every bird here could represent the process invoking at some point and carrying the data somewhere.
Just to make sure, to be clear, we do not send our data via pigeon mail or paper planes.
However, this illustrates the process very well and how hectic and unruly it is.
So once we knew, once we had an understanding of our problem, we declared our goals.
Which is basically we want to kick track off and provide visibility into all the data sets and transfers.
We want to set them up, set up the new ones in a timely manner and spend as little time and effort as possible.
And that was kind of engineering feeling about it.
And then we went into figuring out how we're going to achieve it.
Again, for the purpose of this presentation, it is a very simple demonstration.
But this shows that there were a couple of ideas.
One I think took some courage to voice, which is basically why touch this at all?
Maybe we can just enhance it because it already doesn't take a lot of time to set up a new process by duplicating the existing one.
That was not an acceptable approach, just to mention that we would have to maintain multiple code bases for very similar solutions.
And we already know the same bug would have to be fixed everywhere.
The code base coverage would have to be increased everywhere.
We have to migrate it. Well, we have to migrate all these processes.
So very quickly it became clear that, no, this is this is not a good solution.
And it was pretty clear we want to have just one process that will take care of all these transfers, probably based on the input.
However, we also saw that this would not be ideal.
We do not want to pass huge input variable list that is not very readable.
And also this approach would not give would not give us a good handle of the inventory.
And then we thought about it a little longer and came up with a little modified approach.
Well, what about if we store our input configuration somewhere and pass it to the process once we invoke it from the scheduler?
Well, that way it it does do what it's supposed to do based on the input.
But the input is stored in one place.
We do have a good inventory and we could provide visibility into it if needed.
And it's a much, much more readable and much better maintainable process.
It was, however, a little concerned that upfront it would require a little more effort to set up.
However, we saw the benefits definitely outweigh the shortcoming.
And we proceeded with this approach.
So to demonstrate, this was put forward as a prototype.
And this basically shows.
Does it work?
Yes.
This basically shows a very simple approach where we thought we were going to set up a dedicated storage location where data owners will place their data.
And we are going to pick it up with this process that will wake up on schedule as needed.
Get the configuration from the whatever storage we're going to choose and apply it and pick the proper data sets and send them to the proper location.
And it all seemed very clear and not complicated to us.
And the main thing is that to onboard new data sets, all we had to do is to enter configuration record into this repository and schedule a job.
So this would serve all the purposes.
Once we consider the prototypes, there are sometimes some decisions that have to be made immediately.
And one of the most important ones is data security.
So there are some decisions that need to be addressed.
If we don't have a solution, the whole thing should be scratched and started over.
But luckily, we were able to find an acceptable solution for that.
Scalability, of course, of the system.
Well, this is not very system heavy, system resources heavy.
However, network capabilities, because we are transferring data, had to be considered.
And the configuration management solution.
Well, this wasn't as critical, but I'm putting it here just for the purpose of mentioning it.
You do want to decide which way you want to go based on what you're planning to do with this.
So testing, testing is basically making sure you're building what is really required.
And for that, we started with minimum functionality, slowly building on this.
And with every step, we confirm that it does, we do move in the right direction and we do deliver what is needed.
And in the end, it was pretty much a happy ending.
We did end up setting up a lot of transfers successfully in a very little time, practically without any destruction to our other work.
We did increase transparency even more than than we anticipated.
And customer trust in our systems increased significantly.
The system proved to be pretty extendable.
Immediately there were needs for more features which we were able to add pretty easily.
And developer satisfaction, of course, that is important.
So to summarize, if there are main takeaways from this process, I would say that knowing your domain and your user needs is very important.
Before you set out to build something, I would make sure I understand all of these.
Clearly defining your problems so that everyone knows what we're trying to achieve and you get the buy-in.
Evaluating your options, getting the most viable one and building it out.
And definitely consider your own needs when you are designing the system.
And in the process, try to have fun.
Thank you.