I know everyone's tired, so bear with me, hopefully it's not too boring for you.
Yeah, so in this talk, we're going to talk about Holovis.
How many of you have used Holovis or heard about Holovis?
Yay, awesome.
Glad a few people have heard about Holovis.
For the rest of you, you're in the right place to learn about Holovis.
Hopefully by the end of the talk, you will be interested in exploring how to use Holovis.
You can find the talk slides in that link below.
Yeah, before we get started, I want to introduce a little bit about me.
Most of you probably don't know me.
My name's Sophia Yang.
I am a data scientist at Anaconda.
My background is in psychology, statistics, and computer science.
I'm not a developer.
I'm not a core developer for Holovis, but I'm a contributor and I'm on the steering
committee of Holovis.
I'm also very passionate about the Python open source ecosystem in the Pi data community.
That's why I contributed to some of the Python packages and even created some Python
packages as well.
Yeah, I also have a data science machine learning book club.
If you're interested, please check it out.
We read one data science or machine learning book per month and we chat with the author
at the end of the month.
Okay, so agenda for today.
We're going to, first of all, go through some pretty visualizations to see what Holovis
can do for you and the second part, we're going to talk about why you might consider
use Holovis and then we're going to talk about how and then finally, we're going to show
some demos.
I hope the demo would work.
Today, we'll see.
So let's get started with some pretty visualizations.
Yeah, so here's one of the example of a tractors, which is basically a combination of sines
and cosines with different parameters.
You can see you can do really pretty images with basic mathematical functions.
Here I have a dashboard.
It's super simple dashboard on this manufacturer card data frame and with a few lines of code,
you can get this dashboard pretty easily.
We're going to talk about the code for this dashboard in a little bit.
And then a lot of you I know probably use machine learning.
You can explore your machine learning models using Holovis tools as well.
Here is an example with k-means clustering with the iris data where we can define different
x and y and number of clusters.
You can visualize different clusters pretty easily.
This is probably one of my favorite visualization dashboards where we have 200 million ship
traffic data from the 2020 US ship vessel data.
And you can see the trajectories of each ship.
And when you clip on each data point, you can see the details of which ships are there
at that specific data point and it will give you a list of the ships.
You can define the number of ships you like to see and it will even return an image of
the ship.
So I thought that was quite interesting.
Here's another example right now.
I know generative AI is really popular.
I made a dashboard with stable diffusion, instruct pics to pics.
It's an image editing chatbot where we upload our image, we tell the bot we want to make
the mountain snowy and the bot returns a snowy mountain picture and then the fireworks picture
to add the fireworks.
So if you want to make a chatbot, it's pretty easy as well with Holovis.
And then here's another example where I use OpenAI APIs, basically just chat gbt API and
dial E. I asked chat gbt to write me a dragon story, which is pretty good, I guess.
And then I asked, can we add a unicorn to the story?
And then the bot added the unicorn to the story.
And I clicked the image button basically calling the dial E API to generate an image.
So that's another app.
So those are the apps.
Hopefully you can see Holovis is useful in many different kinds of visualizations, whether
you're in the science field, whether you want to make a chatbot, whether you want to explore
your machine learning models, or simply just explore a data set.
So next section, I want to walk you through some of my Viz journeys and tell you why I
fell in love with Holovis.
Like many of you, I started my Viz journey with MapHololib.
How many of you knows, used MapHololib?
Almost everyone, right?
Yay.
I love MapHololib actually.
It's a very powerful tool.
I think a lot of beginners didn't think MapHololib is a powerful tool when you start with, but
it's actually really powerful.
You can pretty much configure anything and everything using MapHololib.
Shameless plug, I have a intro to data visualization course and I kind of learning focusing on
MapHololib and MapHololib-based libraries.
If you're interested, check it out.
So as I was doing more data science and visualization projects, I realized that I have three needs
and I would like to explore other options.
So my first need is, I'm pretty lazy, so I want to write as little code as possible.
Even though MapHololib is really, really powerful, you still have a lot of code to write to configure
different things.
So I would like some tools to be a little more high level to get something quickly.
And second of all, I would like to interact with my plots.
I want my plot to be interactive.
I know a lot of you might say MapHololib can be interactive.
That's true.
Yes.
In Jupyter Notebook, if you add one line of code, your MapHololib can be interactive and
with the help of other frameworks, it can also be interactive, but it doesn't work interactively
in the browser natively.
So I want something that's just working in the browser very nicely.
And the third need is, I love dashboards.
Like when we communicate with stakeholders, when we communicate with our internal customers,
everyone wants a dashboard.
Even if you're building a machine learning model, people want to see the results.
People want to see what does it actually mean.
They want a dashboard.
My third need is, I need my dashboard to be able to include different types of plots.
Whether it is Plotly, whether it's MapHololib, whether it's Bokeh, I need my dashboard to
be flexible in terms of what kind of plot it returns me.
So that comes to HoloViz.
HoloViz solves all my problems.
And yeah, can't wait to introduce you.
How does HoloViz work?
So HoloViz is developed by three of my co-workers, James Spanner, Philip Rüdiger, John Luke
Stevens.
It was originally developed when they were at University of Edinburgh when James Spanner
was a professor and then the other two were his students.
And then since then, they moved to Anaconda and it's a completely open source project.
It's an Anaconda-supported open source.
A lot of you probably know or don't know, at Anaconda, we support various open source
projects and HoloViz is one of them.
So what is HoloViz?
HoloViz is not just one library.
It's a data visualization ecosystem with eight libraries.
I know when you look at the website, you might get so confused.
So how do I start?
Where do I start, right?
The answer is, if you just started to learn about HoloViz, start with Panel and HVPlot.
So Panel is the tool for building a dashboard.
HVPlot is your starting point to plot your library.
All the other tools integrate with those two tools.
For example, if you want to do big data visualization, you use HVPlot with data shader in the back
end to call data shader with one line of code to do your big data visualization.
You actually don't need to use the data shader API directly, but, of course, if you want
to do more complex things, you can dig into the data shader API.
And the same thing with HoloViz, GeoViz, and others.
So the takeaway is start from Panel and HVPlot.
Okay, now you might all be wondering, or you're talking a lot, so how do we use it exactly?
So I'm going to quickly go through seven points here.
Basic syntax, multiple back ends, HVPlot Explorer, big data visualization, streaming data visualization,
dashboard, and deployment.
I know it's a lot of content.
We're going to be high level and hopefully give you an overall picture of HoloViz.
Okay, let's go.
Okay, so this is a basic syntax on Matplotlib.
As you can see, we're just doing a scatter plot, right?
You have to write a good amount of code to get a simple plot.
And if you're familiar with pandas.plot API, you can simplify this code with one line of
code is actually running Matplotlib in the back end.
So if you're familiar with pandas.plot API, you already know how to use HVPlot because
you just change .plot to .hvplot.
But you need to remember to import hvplot.pandas to use the HVPlot version for pandas data frame.
And of course, HVPlot also works for other different types of data.
For example, if you have a DAS data frame, if you have x-ray, the scientific communities
use a lot of x-ray data with HVPlot, it works really well, and it works with many other
data types as well.
Okay, here are some other basic syntax.
If you want to group by your data by color with different groups, for example, origin
here, you just write by equals origin.
You can, with the same plot to the right here, the first row to the right, you can overlay
different plots with a star.
Of course, we don't write your code this way.
You just do the by instead of overlay all those subset of data with a star.
I just want to show you how to overlay the data with star.
And then if you want a simple drop down box of your origin, you can use group by origin.
It will create a simple drop down box for you.
You don't even need to write a, define a widget of this drop down box.
And then when you combine different plots into different layouts, you can use plus or
you can use panel with different layout options for you.
Okay, here's a function that I really like.
Sometimes when I explore data, I want to plot my data with different options, different
types of plots, even different distributions of different variables, or the relationship
between different variables.
So when I select part of my data, I want that selection to be reflected to other plots
that I have.
So this is called linked brushing.
So this is very useful for me when I try to detect what's going on with my data.
And especially saying this set of data, what's the relationship over there, it's just easier
to see.
And also the distribution of the same selected data on other variables.
It's very useful for explorations in data science work.
Okay, so here's some feature that I am very excited about.
It's called annotation.
Under development, it's pretty much developed.
It's going to have a release very, very soon.
With annotation, imagine we have a time series data example.
We want to annotate what's going on at this data point.
We want to say a gap in the data, or like a dip in the data.
So you can annotate your data, and you can even export this data into a CSV file or a
text file for you to explore later on.
So it's really useful for me to be able to work with my data, annotate my data, and tell
a story as I explore the data.
Okay, so that's the basic syntax.
Pretty straightforward, right?
The next thing I really like about HVPlot is it provides multiple backends.
The default backend is Bokeh.
To the left here, you can see a Bokeh plot with the Bokeh little logo to the right of
the plot where you can zoom and pan.
So if you want to map all that plot with exactly the same syntax, you just need to add one
line of code, HVPlot.extension mapHololib, to call mapHololib to be your backend, and
then you will return a mapHololib plot for you.
Or if you do HVPlot.extension plotly, you will get a plotly data for you using plotly
as a backend.
Yeah, so I find this very helpful because you just learn one visualization language,
and you get plots for other languages as well.
You don't need to learn mapHololib or plotly or others, just learn HVPlot, super convenient.
And sometimes when I start working with my data, if I have a new data frame, I don't
actually know exactly what I'm plotting, I just want to explore the data a little bit.
So with HVPlot Explorer, you can define your own access, y-axis, different types of data,
different element, changing the, define the title, x-label, y-label, and so on, different
styling.
So using HVPlot.Explorer, this is a convenient way for you to explore your data without writing
any syntax.
I guess you do need to write that two lines, three lines of code to explore your data,
but everyone can do that, and it's super convenient.
And when you find a perfect visualization you like to keep, you can reproduce the code
in the plot by calling this .plot underscore code function to get the code of the current
state.
So you can share this with others, or you can copy and paste this into your Jupyter
notebook to be able to reproduce the plot you like.
So sometimes when I'm lazy, I don't want to write everything out, I just do HVPlot.Explorer
to get the data, to get the visualization and the code that I want to do.
Okay, so the next big thing about HoloBiz is that it makes big visualization possible
and easy.
So here we have a, I don't remember, a few million data points of NYC taxi drop-off data.
And then to the right, left here we have a pandas.plot API with map.alib as the backend.
You can see our x-axis is the drop-off location, and the y is also like longitude and latitude,
and we want to do a scatter plot.
With map.alib, all you can see is a blob, it's really hard to extract any meaningful
information from this plot, so you can't tell anything meaningful from there.
But to the right here, we have HVPlot with data shader in the backend.
So the magic happens, sorry, not sure why that looks weird, but the magic happens in
this rasterize equals true, this one line of code where data shader aggregates all the
data in one pixel points really fast, just in memory compiled using Numba.
So the calculation is really, really fast.
So it actually calculates each pixel aggregate, the data points, and show you directly in
the plot.
And when you zoom in, you will calculate again and again.
I know when I show you those two plots, it's kind of unfair to compare those because they
actually represent different things.
One is raw data points, one is kind of aggregated data points, but with data shader and HoloViz,
this is possible to add this one line of code and let you visualize data pretty easily.
And you can add tiles to show you the background of where in New York is the data represent.
Okay, next one, streaming data visualization.
With HoloViz, streaming data is also possible thanks to the streams data frame.
Like I said before, HVPlot works with many different types of data frames.
Stream data frame is a type of data frame.
It's a separate open source package that's not maintained by Anaconda, but we use it a lot.
So just to walk you through this code a little bit, we have a mem data function just returning
a normal Pandas data frame.
You have pd doc data frame here.
The index is the current time and is returning the current memory usage of my computer.
And then this df is not a Pandas data frame anymore, it's a periodic streams data frame
and you call this function and then call the mem data function and interval is like how
many every 300 million seconds we want a record of this data in our stream.
And then as you can see, with the streams data frame, the syntax is exactly the same
we use df and we add the column that we want to visualize, which is the currently used
memory usage and dot HVPlot and you can plot a streaming data.
So this is a very simple example, of course, if you have more complicated use cases, you
can use stream streams data frame with HVPlot as well.
Okay, yeah, so the next most important thing that why I am using Holovis is to make a dashboard.
So this is an example that I showed you earlier and I wrote a blog post, there are actually
at least three ways, those are the three ways that I like to build a panel visualization
dashboard.
So let's talk about the first way in this talk, which is using HVPlot.interactive,
but I want to briefly mention the second two options.
So if you have a Pandas data frame or Dask data frame, if you already have a data processing
pipeline your Pandas data frame, the first HVPlot.interactive is the easiest way to go.
But if you have some other complicated functions, you might want to use panel.bind and then
the parameter will give you even more flexibility, so it's like the more flexible it will give
you, but the more complex the code that you might see.
Well panel.bind is actually pretty simple, yeah.
So here's an example of HVPlot.interactive, to the left here you have a Pandas data processing
pipeline where we subset our data, so this data is the car cylinder data showing you
each origin, horsepower, miles per gallon, information of each car.
And we subset the data by number of cylinders, manufacturers, and we group that by the data
with some columns and we calculate the average of those combinations of columns for the horsepower,
so this is the data looks like.
So with HVPlot.interactive, first thing we need to do is to convert or change this data
frame, Pandas data frame, to an interactive data frame, we use df.interactive.
And in this Pandas data processing pipeline, instead of defining the number of cylinder
directly or the manufacturers and so on, we actually define panel widgets for you to control
the value of the data you want to select.
Here I have a slider for my cylinder, it's not very visible, but it's a slider, yeah,
you can see there, and then you can choose the manufacturer and the variables you want
to calculate the mean on, whether it's horsepower or the weight of the car.
And then you can see the resulting table here is interactive, yeah.
So I want to show you some demo right now, I think we still have time, right?
So here's a demo, this is exactly the code that I just showed you, can you see it?
Is it too small?
Is it better?
I hope it's better, okay, thank you.
So this is what I just showed you, this is the same code, we define our interactive data
frame, and I defined three widgets, as you can see here, let me get another cell here,
show you cylinders, kind of hard to type, yeah, so this is a slider, the widget is defined
as pn.widgets, integer sliders, and then we can see some other ones, manufacturer,
this is, yeah, the options are the options of your toggle group, and the value is the
selected value in the beginning, so now, right now, everything is selected, but we can unselect
someones, okay, and then the ipipeline is basically combining the original pandas data
pipeline with the widgets, that's why it's reactive to the widgets, the table is, okay,
and then we can format it into a better looking table using this tabular extension, or you
can plot it, when you plot it, again, it's the same syntax, it's ipipeline.etcplot,
and you plot it as if it were a normal pandas data frame, and it returns an interactive
etcplot, yeah, it's a little hard to see right now, but you get the idea, okay, and then
I used a template to have all my widgets in the sidebar and have my plot and my table
showing up in the main part of the dashboard, and then to be able to serve this dashboard,
you would need to do this template, since I call this dashboard a template, if you call
it as dashboard, it's okay, you just need to do dashboard or template.servable to make
sure you can serve this dashboard, and then to serve the notebook, you just simply run
panel serve, and it will serve it, let me show you how it works, no, okay, make it bigger,
okay, so I have panel serve, and this notebook file, it doesn't have to be notebook file,
it can be a standalone .py file as well, if you run panel serve, it will serve here for you,
all right, make it smaller now, yep, so this is the resulting dashboard, with a few lines of
code, you can explore your data in a dashboard pretty easily, okay, so that's the demo, and then
finally, I want to talk about deployment, and we just talked about panel serve, could be a Python
file or a notebook file, another convenient thing is you can use PowerDial or PyScript,
to convert your panel app to a web assembly, so you don't need a server to run this app at all,
you just open your browser and it will run your Python code in the browser directly, so to do
that, you just need to do Python panel convert your app.py or app.ipymb to convert your
visualization file into a web assembly, so yeah, here are some galleries, I don't know if the
internet will be happy with me, yeah, so awesomepanel.org is a contributor, community
contributor project, it has nothing to do with Anaconda, he compiled a lot of fun panel
organizations for you to explore, and yeah, there was one web page is for PowerDial apps,
it's pretty cool, yeah, and again, panel.holovis.org, our official doc also have some interesting
visualizations for you to get started learning and exploring if you're interested, if you want
to learn more, please visit holovis.org, which will have a complete tutorial, it will normally
take like three hours to go through to learn all the holovis decks, and panel.holovis.org and
hvplot.holovis.org are the official docs for panel and hvplot, I would recommend starting with
hvplot, and then if you have dashboarding needs, check out the panel doc, and then we have a
discourse, holovis.org, if you have any questions, or if you want to showcase what you have created,
please visit there. Yeah, that's it for my talk, thank you so much.