And you have five minutes.
All right.
Well, I tell you, the first time I did a lightning
talk for PyTexas was around 2007, 2008,
one of the early ones.
And I spoke for 45 minutes.
So I'll try to do a little better today.
OK, all right.
So I'm one of the authors of Python in a nutshell.
I've joined at the fourth edition with Alex and Steve.
And this is me in the corner there.
And I've got my Twitter handle.
And this hashtag is what we collectively
use when we will tweet or post on Mastodon.
So you can follow along with news for the book
with those handles.
Watch for some QR codes.
I've got QR codes on a number of these slides
as I point to websites and so forth.
So be ready for those when you're interested.
So I'll dive right into some of the things
that we picked up while we were working on the book.
The first one, there's a chapter in the book very early on
is how to build Python from source,
or how to install Python.
And one part of that is building from source.
And doing the analysis or the survey for this,
I found this great website for Linux systems,
buildpythonfromsource.com.
And you check various switches on which Python version
you want, which Linux distro you're building for.
And then it will emit all the bash commands
to download, build, and install that Python.
And there's the QR code for that.
I'll leave that up for just 10 seconds
because I need to move forward.
Okay, the next one.
When we were doing the syntax,
I discovered that middle.is a valid identifier character.
So this is kind of a crazy thing,
and there's no key on the keyboard,
but for you Mac folks, shift option nine,
Windows people, it's alt 0, 1, 8, 3,
and you can write variables with a dot in the middle.
That is not the period for an attribute.
That is a middle dot.
We also did some analysis on Unicode characters,
normalization of Unicode down to ASCII.
And here we have just some pretty standard
kind of hello world, a little verbose maybe.
This is the exact same program using Unicode characters
because, and in fact, this will run
identically with that one on the side.
Because Python will convert identifier Unicode characters,
will normalize them back to normal ASCII.
So you'll see that it's only the identifiers,
none of the keywords, but there's a lot of identifiers
that are built in, print, all the exceptions and so forth.
So this is sort of a ransom note kind of approach.
I have a website that will actually do this.
You can play with this, play tricks on your friends,
and this is the QR code to get to that.
We'll pull up a little window to paste in some Python code.
It'll generate that code on the right.
Okay, you can count higher with ints
than you can with floats.
Here's a little loop that displays values
around two to the 53rd, and you'll see that floats,
they lose integer precision at two to the 53rd.
Sometimes the values go higher, sometimes lower.
Integers, you can count as high as two to the two
to the 63rd, it's about a two followed by
a billion, billion zeros.
That's a theoretical limit.
I tried to reach something close to that,
and I blew up my memory, so.
I've gotta hurry, so stir function surprise.
This is actually not a new feature,
but who can tell me what this is gonna print out?
L.com.
I wanted to strip off HTTPS,
but that is not the string to strip off,
those are the characters to strip off,
and that matches all of those.
In 3.9, we have remove prefix and remove suffix,
and that does the intended stripping of that substring.
We found in general discussion and surveying our network,
there's actually some latent bugs in our code bases.
Search for Lstrip and Rstrip that take no arguments,
good for stripping white space,
but if they're taking a quoted string,
hmm, you may have actually slipped into this bug,
and watch for that.
I'm just gonna do this real quick.
The sort method in Python was presented
before the Supreme Court as part of the Oracle
versus Google source code,
and there's the QR code for you can look that up.
And lastly, the appendix for the book
has all of the code changes from 3.7 through 3.11,
and there's this website where you can actually
do keyword search for changes by version.
Thank you very much.
Awesome, thank you Paul.
All right, I've gotta move to something louder next time
because that did not work, but, okay.
Next up is from the volunteer team zone, Josh Schneider.
I'll be mercifully quick.
Two things first, number one, if you were here last year
and saw my talk last year,
this will all seem really familiar.
And number two, I wanna confirm, Chris,
you and I did not talk before I came up here and did this
because it's gonna sound real familiar too.
But I talked about this, this was one of my first slides
in my talk last year, but this bears repeating.
I think these words will be carved in my tombstone probably,
but this is Josh's three, make that four rules
for user experience design.
That's fine, I don't need tiny cue cards.
No Dr. Horrible fans here?
Okay, I will start with rule number one
while I am trying to get everything duplicated here.
Rule number one is, and repeat it with me if you'd like to,
make it obvious.
Why make it obvious?
Well, because if it's obvious,
you don't have to tell people how to use it,
it'll be obvious.
And this is just not behaving, so that's fine.
I can go without slides because I can animate myself.
Rule number two, if you can't make it obvious,
make it familiar, right?
If you make it familiar, you can borrow what the user knows
about another topic to learn your thing.
So if you're implementing something that, say, parses path,
fitting the same interface as, say, pathlib,
makes it easier to translate that to other users
that are using your library.
So you can borrow what somebody knows about one thing
to use it for another one.
Rule number three, if you can't make it obvious
or familiar for the love of all that is good,
make it well-documented.
Make sure there are copious notes on how to use it,
all of the edge cases and corner cases you can think of.
You never know when that stuff's gonna come in handy.
And then those were my three rules that I've always had.
Rule number four has snuck in there
from all of the conversations I've had.
And rule number four is very simple.
Start at rule number one, not in rule number three.
Well-documented is not good enough.
If you can make it obvious or familiar,
those are better than well-documented.
If somebody has to look for your documentation
to use your thing, you've already lost a percentage
of your audience before you've even started.
Go for obvious.
And that's it.
All yours, sir.
Thank you.
And Mr. Brad.
Didn't even get to use my new alarm, how sad.
Is it working for you?
Yeah.
The technology ghosts are gonna play nice with us this time.
All right.
Al Swigert again.
Has this ever happened to you
where you're leading a three-hour introduction to Python
or something like that, and you want all your students
to install some third-party package from PiPI?
This is going to be a nightmare,
and you spend the next 45 minutes of your three-hour
workshop just getting the package installed
because some of the students have Windows,
some have macOS, somebody has free BSD installed
on their laptop for some reason, and not only that,
but they all have different versions of Python installed.
And not only that, you have to explain
how to use the terminal or the command prompt
as it's called on Windows,
or maybe they have PowerShell installed,
and you have to explain what environment variables are,
and you have to tell them, oh, you need to modify
your bashrc file or your zshellrc file,
depending on the version of macOS that they have,
and this is all such a pain.
And yes, they do need to eventually learn how to do this
so that they can run pip and install Python packages,
but you just want it to work right now.
Here's the solution.
You can run pip from the interactive shell.
Just import pip, do pip.main, and then you have to pass it
a list of the arguments.
In this case, install Django or install whatever you want.
This works on versions Python 3.5 and up.
It even works on 2.7 for some reason if you need that.
It works on Windows, it works on Macs, it works on Linux,
it probably works on free BSD, I haven't checked.
It works even if they have multiple versions
of Python installed because whatever the interactive shell
that they're using, that's the one
that it's going to install to.
If you've ever had that problem where for some reason
the environment variable was set up where pip was
for a different version of Python
than the Python thing was, so many headaches.
You can run it from the interactive shell.
This is not a best practice.
If you want your Python application to run pip
for some reason, you would not want it
to just directly run this.
And I think actually Python gives you some warning,
but hey, this is how you can do that
if you just need to get something installed
so you can continue on with your workshop,
or your class, or your blog post tutorial,
or your video, or whatever.
Pip.main and then pass it a list.
Okay, thank you, that's all.
All right.
We are moving right along, I love this.
Next up would be, is it Shreya Batra?
Is that correct?
Okay.
You need an adapter?
I think we can do that.
Let's see if that works for you.
There you go.
Don't worry about it.
Just toss it down here.
And then you might need to do, oh.
I think we're getting there.
Yeah.
Yes, awesome.
All right, all yours.
Thank you.
Hi, everyone.
I'm Shreya.
I am a PM on Azure Functions and I wanted to come
and talk to you all about kind of what we're doing
for Python these days and our investment
in the Python space.
So before I start, I just wanted to ask,
have any of you used any serverless technologies
in the past?
Thank you.
Serverless technologies.
Okay.
Awesome, so quite a few of you.
And could you keep your hand up if you've used
Azure Functions specifically?
Okay.
Some people, okay.
Awesome.
And then Azure Functions in Python?
Okay, awesome.
We have one person.
Thank you.
So yeah, before I start, I do want to talk
a little bit about Azure Functions since I know
a lot of you may not be familiar with it.
And then I'll just kind of go into what we're doing
for the Python space.
Awesome.
So what is Azure Functions?
Azure Functions is the serverless compute
from Azure.
And the idea is that you just focus on your code,
you just write the business logic,
and we take care of the rest for you.
And I'll just go over quickly some examples
of commonly used times when you might use
Azure Functions.
So here we have a database that we want
to clean regularly on a timer so we can
actually configure an Azure Function that
will go ahead and run some business logic
to perhaps deduplicate data and clean
that database for you every 15 minutes.
So this is probably a really common use case
for our customers.
A second one is real-time stream processing.
So here we start with an app that's producing
some data and we want to end that with like
the data in a dashboard where we can track
different metrics on that app.
So as you can see there may be an issue
where we need to process data between
different data sources and Azure Functions
would be a great tool to be able to do that.
So in these two examples I kind of just had
this little functions logo to represent
that code, that business logic that you'd be writing.
And I just want to go into a little bit
more detail of like what that would be actually.
So we have this trigger that would run
the code that would invoke the function that you have.
So the trigger could be something like an HTTP request.
It could be off of a database.
It could be on a schedule or a timer.
And then we have these optional aspects
of an input and output binding if you need
more data to process the code and also
based on where you'd want to put the code afterwards.
And also we are completely open sourced.
So if you would like please do check out
the Azure Functions repository.
You're welcome to contribute or ask questions
and take a deeper dive into the repository
if you are interested.
And then now I just want to kind of talk about
our new release for Python.
So one of the main initiatives that we're focusing on
in functions for Python is being able to
provide an experience that's more native
to Python developers.
Whether you're just getting started or you're an experienced
Python developer, we don't want the experience
of using functions to be much different
than what it is like to code natively in Python.
So we've released this new programming model
which is still in preview and some of the new offerings
are that we see decorators to represent
triggers and bindings.
And we also have added a lot more documentation.
So if you are interested in functions at all,
I know a lot of you haven't used functions before,
please do give it a try, especially this programming model.
And if you do want to give it a try
and you have any feedback or any questions,
please feel free to reach out to me.
Yeah, thank you so much for listening.
Next up, Josh Cannon.
I have 23 slides, five minutes.
I've not rehearsed this.
If you're using your calculator, that's 13 seconds a slide.
I talk fast.
There's adrenaline involved.
Oh, no, I want to hear the buzzer.
Can you all hear me?
I talk loud enough, so hopefully, oh, come on.
Okay, it's down there.
Oh, Lord.
Let's try that.
I'm getting like picture in picture.
A little weird.
Let's do it.
Two snakes in a trench coat descriptors.
Okay, so a lot of you might be familiar with git adder,
which is how do you git me?
It's half of a handshake.
So if I have this order instance thing
and I ask for a brisket taco, which I usually do,
if it didn't exist, you'll go for git adder.
It's great.
How do you git me?
You can also git attribute.
Nobody uses it.
But doesn't the brisket taco get a say?
I don't know, like the Chick-fil-A cow or something.
So let's take a real-world use case that I've refactored.
And the first thing is you have this my menu thing,
and it inherits from menu.
You have this class method called register options,
and here's where you do command line stuff,
and here's your brisket taco, and you say it's a type string.
Because I don't know what type of brisket taco it is.
Great.
And how you access it.
Again, this is something that already exists.
We're going to make our order instance of my menu.
And ooh, yeah.
So first I go through this items thing,
and you can't type it because it's dynamic.
Then I have to cast it.
Ah, I don't like casts.
So then I really just wanted to do this.
Give me the brisket taco from my order.
And so, OK, you write a property.
Now we've isolated the cast.
The user doesn't cast the property does.
And that looks pretty good, right?
Somebody once said, if you weren't paying attention in a meeting
and they ask you a question, just go, hmm, but does it scale?
No.
It only fits on a slide because it made it smaller.
Here's brisket taco and bean and cheese taco
and mac and cheese and baked beans.
And apparently I'm talking before lunch and dinner
and making you very hungry.
So won't somebody think of the brisket taco?
Probably Rudy of Rudy's Tacos.
I don't know.
Wouldn't it be cool if I could write this?
And you can, because I'm on a stage talking about descriptors.
So descriptors come in three little magic methods.
The first is Dunder Git.
I won't tell you the second.
It's Dunder Set.
I'm not even going to show it.
And it looks like this.
You take the instance, which on this slide
was the menu item instance that is brisket taco.
It's that class attribute.
The second thing is either going to be the instance being operated on,
in this case my order, or if it's a class attribute,
you're accessing it like that, then it's none.
And then you get the class always unconditionally.
And this is, for some reason, the defaults to none.
That's what Python docs say.
Don't ask me why.
So this is great.
This is the other half of that handshake of,
hey, how do you get my attributes?
Certain things get to say, well, how do you get me?
So great.
If object isn't none, if there's an order I'm operating on,
I'm going to use the git adder thing.
Oh, wait.
I don't have a name.
Because these were one instance for all of them.
Ah, somebody thought of this.
It's under set name, where we set our name.
And this gets called right here at the end,
when you're done defining your class.
It'll call set name for all of them.
So let's do the other half.
Oh, sorry.
No, we filled in the name.
Yay, we have a name now.
You can access me.
Wee.
Now we need to register the options.
This part's mostly just plumbing.
If the object is none, you called it on the class and not the instance.
And then maybe the menu superclass gets to go ahead
and access all of the attributes of that subclass.
And if it's this magic registration object, yeah, yeah, yeah, it's plumbing.
The cool thing is that I can sprinkle in a little bit of typing, like a generic.
And I have this code.
It's what?
Seven lines.
And now I can do the thing I want to do.
And it's typed in.
I think that's my last slide.
Descriptors.
Very nice.
That would mean next up is Leon Vance.
How's that sounding?
That was close enough.
All right.
AV roulette.
Let's go.
Ooh.
Bit, bit.
Bit.
All right, hello, nice to meet you all.
My name's Leon Vanstone, head of software at Green Software.
I know most of you are worried I'm probably a hippie.
Don't worry, it's also cheap software.
I've spoken to enough CTOs and CIOs
to know that's the only way they're going to do this.
And a quick shout out, thank you, Amy.
Thank you, Chris, for kind of making the big point
about the value of refactoring and well-maintained codes
and the very real cost of tech debt.
So I'll give you a quick introduction to Green Software.
And if anyone wants to then come
and have angry conversations with me, please do.
All right, so to give you a bit of context
to why we should even care about Green Software.
Global computing, according to Chowdhury et al 22,
global computing is going to use about 10%
of all the power in the world,
which is honestly mind boggling.
If global computing was a country,
it would be the third largest consumer
of power in the world.
It would go China, America, and then global compute.
And this study was done before CHET GPT blew everything up.
So this could well be 20% at this point.
This is also going to result in about 5 billion tons
of CO2 going into the atmosphere,
about 5% from the whole world,
which is about as much CO2 as contributed by all cars,
fossil fuel burning cars in the world will be equivalent.
You thought Bitcoin was bad, you just wait.
People will be like, I don't do my computing in the cloud.
I do it all at the edge.
I also drive a Prius.
So Green Software, some quick things then.
So basically Green Software is cheap software,
but the problem is you cannot change what you do not measure.
If you're not actually,
and there are very few tools for this,
and come talk to me afterwards
if you want to learn more about that.
But the real truth is most code
is not especially well optimized at all.
New features, bug changes, typically pretty priority.
And the unfortunate truth of that is that,
tech debt is obviously just annoying
if you're trying to maintain a code base.
But in fact, it has a very real cost
in CO2 emission associated with it.
Like a dollar cost and a grams of CO2 emission
associated with that tech debt.
And that is a problem in lieu of the numbers
that I just showed you.
And what's more, because there are no tools out there
for any of you developers,
most people believe that faster is better for software.
And this isn't actually necessarily true.
And just to give you some idea of this,
we got 36 very unfortunate developers
to agree to answer the same challenge.
And we got 36 solutions.
All of them are functionally identical.
They take the same input and they produce the same output.
And those numbers are very small.
So the lowest number, the most power efficient version
that answered this took 24 joules of power
and the worst one took 243.
It's the 10X difference, right?
And it's just without any tools to measure any of this,
you just have no idea.
Speed is intuitive, power consumption, not so much.
We went back and we asked, do we got 10?
Apparently the coding challenge wasn't great fun
because only 10 of them have agreed
to then do it a second time.
We gave them some tools to measure power.
Some of them got 60% power saving.
Some of them got 10, 30 is about the average.
So, you know, why I find this very motivating
is globally you're looking at about 10% power,
5% CO2 pool from something we all really believe in,
I think.
Yeah, computing is important, AI is important.
These are tools, we should not abandon them.
But the sheer cost of doing this, of using that much power,
the capacity is limiting, right?
If you're not optimal, if you're not optimizing,
you're losing out.
And obviously, you know, I also like breathing
and eating food.
And those are gonna be difficult
as we continue to damage our environment.
And there is this very real opportunity
for all of us to come together
and sort of push forward for the tools
to save about 3% of that, 3% of the world's power,
which is about the amount of power used by all of Japan.
That's the opportunity that's in front of us.
So if anyone wants to learn more about that, come find me.
I'm sure I'll be stood around in the networking event.
Thank you very much.
Thank you so much.
Thank you.
Last, but certainly not least, Eric Adams.
What's up, party people?
Hi, my name is Eric.
This is my quick pitch
for a piece of open source software called Seat Dealer.
So I've been running a local poker game every Saturday
for about the last two years.
So about 200 people have at some point come through my door.
And every week, that means I'm sending out
a handful of invites to try to get a number of people
to say yes.
Once I hit that number, I really can't take any more people.
There's not room at the table.
There's not really room to hang out.
So I thought, you know, I have some extra time.
I want to learn Terraform and GitHub Actions
and a handful of other technologies.
So why not just solve this problem for myself?
So I'm writing an application that will fire off SMS messages
kind of every few hours in small rounds
until enough people say yes
and then stop firing off those invites.
If that sounds interesting to you, meet me at the stage.
Bye.
Thank you.