So the tech's not working for me either, so things aren't quite the way I've arranged
it to be, so I might be a little awkward here, but we'll make it work.
So yeah, I'm Dave Klein.
I am with Quicks, which is a company that builds an event streaming platform for Python
developers.
I used to be with Confluent, who was created by the creators of Kafka.
So I've been working with Kafka for quite a bit for the last four or five years, and
I love it, and I've also been working with Python for the last couple years, and I love
that too.
For some of that, I used like 20 years or more of Java, and this has been such a relief.
I feel like I retired already.
I'm still working, but it doesn't feel like it anymore.
And I also want to mention that it's great to be back here.
Last year at PyTexas, that was my very first Python conference.
I spoke at hundreds of conferences, but it was the very first Python conference, and
it was amazing, and it still is.
So thank you all for the organizers and attendees.
Yeah, it's just a great community.
All right, so let's get started.
I hope I can keep track with what I'm doing, and nope, I can't.
So I'm going to talk about this projector.
It's really a great projector.
It's gone now too.
I can't talk about anything.
All right.
We're back.
Okay.
So event processing, or real-time processing, or stream processing, you'll hear lots of
different names for it, but it's basically talking about getting data into our applications,
dealing with it right away as it's originated, and that's why I like the term event.
You'll hear the terms event, message, record when dealing with things like this, and those
are all valid terms for different use cases or different connotations.
I like event because of the fact that it's tied to something happening, and that's really
where all data originates, really.
Something happens that generates data, and so the event tells us something happened,
and it gives us the data about what happened.
As data is generated, that's what is really most useful to us in most cases.
Now, traditionally, we get data, the data is generated, it's stored into a database,
and then we periodically run queries against the database to get the data out and do something
with it.
So the idea here, though, is instead to get that data as it's generated and make use of
it right away, doing the processing that we want to do on it, one event, one record at
a time in a continuous stream.
So you can see data becoming from different applications.
It could be coming from IoT devices, it could be coming from mobile phones, it could be
coming from all kinds of different things, sensors, all kinds of stuff that could be
bringing data into our systems, and then we run it through some whatever processing we're
going to be doing to it, and then output it, usually, to something else, some downstream
process, a storage thing, analytics engine, something like that.
So that's the common use case for these types of things.
And speaking of use cases, I want to mention a couple, there's lots of different places
where this is used, but some of the most common ones are things like recommendation engines,
right?
Recommendations are often done for, they've been around for a long time now, ever since
Amazon came on the scene, really, but these recommendation engines often early on would
be done based on pulling data periodically, sometimes daily, sometimes hourly, different
time intervals, but there's always a bit of staleness to that data.
Now most systems like Amazon, others like that, are doing this in real time.
So as you're browsing around the site, your recommendations are changing by your current
behavior or the current behavior of people that you know through social media, things
like that.
It's still a bit scary how much they know about us and stuff like that, but they're
able to make use of that, hopefully to our benefit, using real time processing.
An example I saw, though, that hits me personally is since I do a bit of traveling for work,
you have like frequent flyer programs or hotel loyalty programs in general.
And there's a hotel that I stay with, a chain that I stay with regularly.
And if I stay at a hotel, it's usually about maybe a week and a half or so before the points
for that stay show up in my account, which is no big deal.
It's not that it doesn't really matter that much, but I just noticing that recently the
airline that I fly on, I landed in an airport and I can pull up my phone, pull up the account
and I see the miles in my account right there.
So you can see one of these companies is using real time processing.
The other one's using some type of old batch system and it makes it a very different customer
experience. And again, those aren't, you know, life or death situations, but they do make
a better experience. So it's one of those things where we may not see right now.
We were talking earlier, but we may not see right now the use cases for this.
But they start to appear more and more the more we learn how real time processing works.
And also, I think it's easier to do just like machine learning.
There was a time when that was a real niche thing only for a few use cases.
And now it's used everywhere because it's gotten easier to use and we understand it better.
So when talking about this, I'm coming from the Apache Kafka background, but that's not the
only tool that's used for this type of for event processing or stream processing.
There's also tools like Apache Pulsar, which is similar in structure, but based on some
different underlying technologies.
There's Red Panda, which is basically Kafka, but written in C++.
And then Amazon Kinesis is another pretty popular one.
And there's some others as well.
But these are these are different tools for for events streaming or message brokers or
things you might want to call them. Not to be confused with message queues.
That's a really different animal altogether.
So I wasn't bringing those into it.
And then for the processing part of it, you know, I was going to say close it off by saying
Kafka really is the de facto standard, though.
So it's one I'm going to stick with.
It's one I'm most familiar with.
But it's also the one that's most commonly used.
So if you're getting into this to start out, Kafka is a great place to start with to do
the actual processing. There's there's there's whole frameworks that have been built up to
do real time processing with data in these event streams like Apache Flink, which is a
pretty popular one.
This is an application that you have to install.
You usually run it in a cluster with several nodes and you write applications in SQL or using
Python. You can use Python and you write your applications and then run them against the
ongoing stream of data.
Another one is ksqlDB, which, again, uses SQL to work it works against Kafka data.
Or if you want to include something in your applications, there's libraries you can use.
The most popular one is a Java based library called Kafka Streams.
It's a part of the actually part of the Apache Kafka project.
And it allows you to just include some classes in your application and do real time stream
processing in your own applications, your microservices or other applications.
Whoa, this thing's pretty sensitive.
But you can build those things into your application instead of having to have another set of
applications running in their own cluster somewhere.
So that gives you a lot of flexibility and saves saves a lot of money as far as the
processor operationally.
But it's Java and that's not great.
So there are some and I would end on a talk about some other libraries that are for Python
that do similar things to Kafka Streams.
But the goal of this talk is to show that you can do some some simple stream processing
things with just plain Python and Kafka.
So back to Kafka. So to do before we get started, I'm going to do I did speak on Kafka
last year, and so I actually reuse a few slides here.
I'm going to do a really brief introduction to what Kafka is just for people that aren't
familiar with it. So if you are familiar with Kafka, please bear with me.
It shouldn't take too long, but I just want to make sure everyone understands what we're
talking about.
So at the core of Kafka is a log.
Really, Kafka is a storage engine for the most part.
The real magic happens with the client libraries, which are producers and consumers.
We're going to talk about those in a bit.
But underlying Kafka really is just a log of data.
It's an immutable, append-only, ordered and durable log of events.
And these are important characteristics of it.
So it's immutable in that when something happens, it stays happened.
You can't undo it. You can add something.
It's kind of like with accounting.
There's an essay like Why Accountants Don't Use Erasers, I think it's called, which talks
about this whole idea that when events happen, they happen.
You can't undo that. You can you can do another event that counters what the other one
happened. You can adjust the entry type of thing, but you can't undo the thing.
So when something lands in a Kafka topic, it stays there.
It's append-only, so we don't insert anywhere.
It always just keeps on adding on.
And it's ordered in that what you're seeing here on the screen is a single partition
topic. So Kafka topics can be broken out into multiple partitions, and they usually
are, but they don't have to be. But for each partition, it's its own log and
the data in that log will be processed in the order it was written.
So, you know, just right to left, keep on going.
And yeah, so that's ordered and it's also durable.
And this is a real key feature and really makes it differentiate between cues, which
usually lose the data as just as it's consumed or processed.
Right. A Kafka topic keeps this data as long as we want it to.
We can set the retention through configurations so the older data can drop off and we
don't need it. But you can also just have it stored permanently, especially with
mechanisms now like infinite storage where you can have older data moved up to S3 or
something like that and, you know, cheaply store all of your data permanently.
But you don't have you can set your attention to drop it off at a certain age period.
But the data is there as long as we want it there.
It's not it doesn't disappear once it's been read.
That's the key thing there. And this comes in handy for things like replaying and
your for like machine learning models, your training model, you repeat the pipeline
with the same data over and over again. You have consistent results because you
have the same data. That number you see at the bottom of that screen of the log
there is an offset. And so you can reset to any offset and just replay from there
forward. So it's really helpful for retrying things, for fixing bugs and
replaying the data or doing what if scenarios, things like that.
All right. So here's a random representation of what an event might look like in
Kafka. It's in Kafka, it's actually just bytes.
But in our applications, it's going to usually be some type of an object that can
be serialized to bytes. So either maybe a protobuf or JSON or something like that.
Here we have a JSON example. It's got the two main components of an event are a
key and a topic or a key and a value. Sorry. So the key is normally a simple
data type, a string or something like that. It might be a UID, it might be a
customer ID, something meaningful in your domain. But it's usually a simple
value and then the or simple type. And then the value is the more complex type
that's going to have your fields in it. It's more like your payload. Now it's
also, I don't mention it here, but also every event in a Kafka or every Kafka
event will have a timestamp, which is also really important, especially if you're
working with time series data or things like that. All right. So these events are
written to the Kafka topics using a producer. Now producer is a class in the
client library. Excuse me. And we're going to talk about a couple of different
Python client libraries that are out there. They're all client libraries in
whatever language you're going to have these classes. So producer is one of the
main classes. It is one that's responsible for writing data to the Kafka topics.
It'll also handle things like compression. It'll handle retries. Also, if you're
working with multiple partitions, the producer is what figures out which
partitions to send each event to. So these are all important things that the
producer does. And the producer is just a class in this client library. So as it
writes the events one by one, it keeps appending to the next open offset, then
the consumer comes along. The consumer is another class in the client library and
the consumer is what will read the data. It's kind of, I think, misnamed because
it doesn't consume the data. We mentioned earlier the durability, right?
The data stays there, but the consumer will read the data and then do whatever
processing we want it to do. We handle the processing because it's in our
application. It's just a class we're including in our application. So we
decide what we do with the data. The consumer just reads it for us.
And so the consumer reads from left to right, just following the same path, but
they're completely independent. The producer doesn't know if someone's
consuming the data or when, and the consumer doesn't know where the data came
from. They're completely decoupled, which is really important and allows us to
build much less, less coupled applications.
And the consumer will also periodically record the offset number for the most
recent event that it's completely processed. You can do this automatically
through configuration or you can do it in your code when you know you've
completed a certain one. And this is important for making sure that you don't
skip anything and that you don't do, don't do duplicates.
So if the consumer goes down, the producer will keep on going. He doesn't
really know the difference. It'll keep on producing and eventually there is a
metric you can watch for here called consumer lag. So the consumer gets too
far behind in reading what's been, what's on the topic, then it'll send, you
can set up alerts for things like that so you know something's wrong with your
system. But the application won't fail because of it, which is, if you remember
last year in my talk, we talked about vendor of microservices, and that's
really a key thing there so that a failure in a consumer doesn't cause a
cascading failure downstream.
But when it starts back up, it'll use that committed offset to pick up at the
very next spot and keep on going. So, all right, so that's all I had on the
producer-consumer exit. Those are part of the Kafka client package and there are
two, two popular ones that I know of in Python. There's the Confluent Kafka,
which is the one that's produced by Confluent. It's based on, it's basically
a Python wrapper around a C library called LibRD Kafka, which is pretty widely
known or accepted to be the closest in both performance and features to the Java
client that comes with Apache Kafka if you download it. So it's a pretty good
option for that. It's well maintained. They keep on top of it. And it's not
fully open source, but it is. So I got to talk with someone before at a conference
from, he's from Wikimedia. They can't use this package because it's not fully
open source. It's one of those licenses where you can use it for anything you
want as long as you're not competing with them in the cloud. But because of
that little caveat, companies that are fully open source only can't use it. So
for that, there's also Kafka Python, which is just a community one that is
fully open source. And also, I haven't tried to work with it very much, but what
I've seen and heard from other people is it is a bit more Python-ic, since it's
written purely in Python and it follows more Python idioms and things. But they
both have the classes that we're going to talk about here. I keep getting confused.
I'm seeing something different on my screen when I look. It's down here. Okay,
so. So here's an example. I'm going to step back here so I can see what we're
talking about a little bit. This is a real simple example of a Python producer
writing data to a Kafka topic. So you see, we just import the producer class. And
then I'm setting up a couple of data bits there. This is a key and a value. They
could be anything, but I just want to set something there for the example.
Normally, this data would be something that's generated from a process that
you're already running. It's not something you're going to create just for
the purpose of writing to Kafka, but this is just for my example. So in the
constructor, there's only one. You pass the constructor a dictionary. And you'll
see a lot of examples. I may be off on this one, but a lot of people use like
YAML files and things like that for the configuration, and then they have a bit
that reads that in and converts it to a dictionary and then passes it to the
constructor. And I don't know why they don't just use dictionaries. I love
dictionaries. But anyway, so it just takes a dictionary, and you could put a
ton of stuff in that dictionary. There's a lot of configurations that you can set
on Kafka producers and consumers. There's only one for the producer that's
required, and that's the bootstrap servers. The bootstrap servers tells your
producer class, where can I find a Kafka broker? Now, Kafka normally runs in a
cluster. So you normally have multiple brokers, usually a minimum of three, but
some companies will have hundreds. And you only need one here, because if the
producer finds one broker, that call to the broker will return the
metadata for all the brokers in the cluster. So it'll get everything it needs
from there. That's one thing that Kafka's really good at is communicating
between different brokers, different consumers, all the different components
that are running. They keep each other in sync of things pretty automatically.
And then, so then once you construct the producer, then you just simply call
produce. There's callbacks you can give to it if you wanna make sure that
this thing was sent properly and things like that. But the basic usage is call
produce, give it a topic. Really all you have to give is a topic and a value.
The key is optional. I included here as well, but so you pass in a topic,
it's always the first argument. And then actually the second argument is value
and then key, but I don't like that order, so I put him in with named arguments
just so I can put him in the order that I'm more comfortable with.
But, and that's all there is. So that's gonna send that data to the Kafka
topic called my topic. So now this is normally something that would be done
over and over again through some of the process that you're running in.
I just lost it again, huh? It's cause my, I think it's cause my laptop
went to sleep. We're back down here. Oh, yay. I guess I'll just touch this
once more so I don't lose. You know, it shows I'm talking too much on a
single slide. We talked about it earlier, right? I shouldn't be staying on one
slide for too long. So that's getting data into Kafka. And now consuming data
from Kafka is similar. You import the consumer class and the consumer also
takes a dictionary in its constructor. That dictionary is gonna have the bootstrap
servers again. That part's the same, but there's one other required property
in the consumer and that's group ID. So we're actually, you don't always have
to use a group. Let me explain briefly what consumer groups are. They're really
a powerful feature of Kafka. A consumer group allows you so you can have multiple
instances of the same consumer application running and they will automatically
share the workload of the data that they're reading. They split by partitions.
So if you have a Kafka topic and it's got four partitions, you can have four
instances of your consumer class running, of your consumer application running,
and each of those will read from one partition. So the data stays processed
in order by partition like the guarantees are, but the workload is split
across four now evenly. If one of those consumers dies, then it'll automatically
rebalance and give that orphan partition to another consumer that's running.
Or if you have two to start with, it gives them each two and then you get busy,
you start two more up, it automatically spreads those out again. So the balancing
up and down, so scaling in and out, is all handled for you automatically with a
consumer group. So it's really a powerful feature, but to use it, you need to have
a group ID. Now if you're not using a group, you're gonna have just one
instance of your application, then you technically don't need a group ID,
but this particular client requires it anyway. So those are the two things
we put in our dictionary that we pass to the consumer's constructor.
And then the next step we have for the consumer, now we notice with the producer,
we tell it in our call to produce, we say, what topic to send it to?
With the consumer, you don't do that. With the consumer, you subscribe to one
or more topics, and then when you call poll, which we're gonna do down below,
it will poll from the topics that it's subscribed to. So here we're just
subscribing to a single topic called My Topic, so I put it in a list
of one. It does have to have a list in that subscribe call.
And then we just jump into a loop, and we're gonna call the consumer.poll.
Now poll will read from the topics. If there's more than one topic in
that subscribe, it will read from each of them, one after the other,
kind of in round robin fashion,
and with each call to poll. And then the value I'm passing in,
there's a timeout that basically says... No, I did it again, talking too much.
But I'll keep talking while I do this. So what it'll do is it'll keep...
It'll try grabbing data from the broker, and it'll keep trying until it
either gets data or until that time has hit. So after one second,
in this case, if there's no data, it'll just return none.
But if there is data, it'll return instantly as soon as the data's there.
So it doesn't slow you down to having a value here, this just tells you
if you wanna leave the connection open to give it a little time to
get data, you can do that with that value.
And then... Yeah, so the event can be none, or it can have a value,
or it could also have an error. So I didn't include it in the slide here,
but you can also check the event.error, and if there's an error,
you could do error handling. Then you could just grab the event value,
which I'm doing there. And I mentioned that in Kafka, events are all bytes,
so the value's a byte, the key's a byte, everything's just bytes.
So I'm decoding it here. The library actually includes serializers that you
can use to serialize and deserialize most of the basic types, and you can also
use serializers that work with things like protobuf or Avro or JSON schema,
things like that, to do your serialization. Or you can write your own
serializers. There's lots of ways to get the data from bytes back to something
useful. In this case, I'm just using decode, and then printing it out.
So simple example that shows you how to use a Kafka consumer in Python.
So we'll have some slides later where we're gonna show some examples
of some streaming operations, and the consumer, all this stuff will be assumed
that it's happening. In fact, that's where we're gonna go to next.
So stream processing. So the goal here of this talk is to show
that stream processing isn't that hard. There are libraries and frameworks and
all those things like that to help you with it, but you don't always need
those. And especially getting started, you don't need them. So I thought
this was important because I think that stream processing can be very helpful
to a lot of organizations, a lot of projects. But people think,
I get scared off from it, thinking they need to have all this heavyweight
stuff to do it. And I just wanna show that you really don't.
You can do quite a bit with just plain Python code.
So operations and streaming are broken into two categories, stateless operations
and stateful operations. So I'm gonna show a few stateless operations first,
some examples of those. So the first one we're looking at is filter,
which is a pretty common one, actually. And that's where you got a stream
of data coming in, and you want some of that data, but you don't want
all of it. So you want some events and not all of them. And so based
on some data, some value in the event, something maybe in the value
or maybe in the key, usually it's in the value,
but somewhere you make a decision whether you want that event or not.
And so basically, you're pulling on it, and for each one that you
get, you check it against whatever your predicate is.
So I mocked out a check predicate method. That could be anything in there.
That could open up the value, it could check a certain field if it's
greater than this or less than that. It can make whatever distinctions
it needs to, and it turns either true or false. And if it's true,
then that event goes on to the next step. If it's false, that event
gets skipped. So simple enough, and then we produce it to an output topic.
And this is a common theme, a common pattern you'll see in stream processing
is that you have an input topic and you have an output topic.
And then you do something in between there.
So that's a filter.
The next one is branch, and this is a really helpful one.
This allows you to take one stream of events and break it into multiple
streams of events. And again, this is a feature that's built into most
of the streaming libraries like Kafka Streams. I used to work for an
insurance company that had, they used to call it the fire hose topic.
It was a single Kafka topic with, I think, a thousand partitions,
and all events coming into their organization came through that topic.
And then we had a Kafka Streams application that used branch to split
those out into a whole bunch of different topics based on the data in them.
So basically, it gave them a way to log and monitor all the data
coming in before they send it off to the downstream applications,
which are based on departments and things like that.
But we can do the same thing, which is Python, we're just using either
ifs, or you could do a switch or something like that.
But if we check the different predicates, I've got two of them here.
If it meets the first one, it goes into topic or output topic A.
If it meets the second one, it goes into B.
And these are ordered, so the first one it hits, that one's gone.
It won't check the others.
And then we have a default one, which you can have or skip.
You can just ignore the ones that don't match your predicates at all.
Or you could put all of them into a default topic.
But this just allows us to take that one incoming stream and split it into multiples.
And then again, put that to another output topic.
Now, I'm showing you this going from input topic to an output topic,
and that's pretty common to do another topic for each step.
But it doesn't necessarily mean it's the only thing in that application.
So you might have multiple steps like this in one single application.
Where the output topic of one process becomes the input topic for the next process.
And you connect these together with nodes and basically in a directed acyclic graph.
What it turns into. So that's a branch.
And then map.
So the map is basically you're just going to do something over every event in the stream as it comes through, right?
And so it can be whatever you want.
So. And this I just have my func.
And rather than even doing the whole poll thing, I just have rather than reading the event in the polling loop,
I just go ahead and call my func in the poll in the polling loop and just call the pass the poll method result into that.
So that my func can do can be some kind of any kind of transformation, really.
So you might be taking something like JSON data and flattening out to CSV or something like that.
So changing the shape is a common use in enhancing the data.
So maybe if you got like a lookup table that's loaded into memory that you can quickly call and enhance the data with each event as it's coming through.
That's another thing is commonly done with map.
So this is another really popular feature.
And it's again, streaming libraries all have things like that for you, but we can pretty easily do it just with Python.
OK, now let's switch over to stateful operations.
And these are a little bit more complex because these other ones, the each event that came in as we're processing each event that came in,
we didn't care at all what happened to the event before it, right?
It didn't matter. Each one is handled independently completely.
Now we do care about what happened before, because now we're dealing with things that involve the past state, for example, counting.
Oh, by the way, speaking of counting, I'm actually using this one in my demo app if I have time to show, which I might run out, I'm not sure.
But the demo app has to do with Twitter, so you should right now be tweeting about PyTexas.
If you tweet about PyTexas, just show up on the leaderboard in a minute, hopefully, if I get that to work with the screen and all that stuff.
And somebody has to start going to beat Andy Knight, because right now he's the top.
I know, you know, I'm going to do another version that pulls from Rastadon as well.
I just didn't have time to get that together for this.
Sorry. All right, so let's take a look at count real quick and I'll try to move through these ones more quickly.
So the key difference here is that we need to have someplace to store state in between in between events, right?
For account, we're going to be accumulating an account for each key, and so we need to have some place to store that.
So dictionary to the rescue, right? It works great.
So for each one that comes in, we grab the check, the key to see if it's in the counts dictionary.
If it is, then we go ahead and grab that item in the dictionary and increment its value.
If it's not, then we add it to the dictionary and give it a value of one and just keep on going through.
And as we do each step, we also produce it to the output.
So we produce that the output at every step so that the output topic will always have the latest the latest value for each key.
And if you're if this is a little bit off topic, but Kafka has a really cool feature called compacted topics, which are topics that don't have every event ever.
They just have the latest value for each key.
They have some others, too, because there's a cleanup process takes time to get rid of them.
But they basically they guarantee you to have the latest value for the current value for each key.
And that's that's perfect for storing things like count results.
So we produce it after each call and it just keeps accumulating count like like a count of Twitter of tweets by a specific user.
So that's count. Sum is another common one.
And again, we use a dictionary to hold the sums.
So it's really some of the counting.
So instead of increment by one, we're going to just add the value for each new event.
We're going to add the value to the value before with the same key.
So it's all tied to the key of the event.
You could actually use a certain field in the value.
It'd be a little more complicated, but you could do that as well.
But the key is the most common way to aggregate these things.
So that is basically the same as the count.
And then aggregate, which, again, is similar.
It's just it's going to we're going to do some type of a generic aggregation, something that's going to work on all of them together.
So one thing is an aggregation might be used for that's different than counting or summing would be like compiling them into an array.
So you want to take a bunch of individual events coming in and you want to create a bunch of arrays of those events or lists of these events.
You could do that with it with aggregate.
So we just do the events come in.
We have an aggregate dictionary called Ags here.
We just check to see if there's something we need to check to see.
We just keep on passing the the value that's in the dictionary along with the event value.
And if it's not there yet, then it'll just have a none and work on that.
So all these ones here, I'm not doing things like error hands like that.
This can be done inside the functions that get the data or they can be done in this loop as well.
So it's easier to show here by assuming that that stuff's not being handled in the in the functions.
So that's that one. And then join is trickier, but it's still doable.
What we have here now is we have two different two different input topics.
And we're going to have two different consumers.
We're going to pull each consumer.
You can actually do this with one consumer and subscribe to both topics, but it's a little more confusing.
So I thought it's clear to show with just two two consumers.
So for each consumer, we're going to sort of start with the first one.
We pull that that topic.
If we get we get an event and we check to see if the key to that event is in.
If it's in the B dictionary.
So if the key to the event is in the B dictionary, then we can make our join there.
If it's not, we still we've added our we've added a event already.
So if it's not there, then we just go on and skip.
We actually check to see if it's in the B dictionary and if it's not in the C dictionary.
The C dictionary is going to be our out the source of our output.
We're basically taking two events that have a similar key or the same key.
We're going to join those together. Maybe we'll create a new a new type of object that has only some values from each.
You know, kind of because it was a SQL join and that new objects will go into the C topic.
And so if it's not in a the joint doesn't happen there, but the A value is stored.
So it's sitting there and then the B one comes.
And if it's the B one looks in the A dictionary to see if it's there, if it's there, it makes the join.
And also if it's not in the C dictionary.
So as soon as it lands in the C dictionary, then that's not happening again.
So you won't join it multiple times.
Now, the one challenge with this is this works fine.
I've tested it out, but your dictionary will grow forever.
So you want to probably add something in there like a scheduler or something that can remove some excess things.
But you can't even do joins.
These are all things that are that are that are challenging to do without a library to help you.
But they're they're possible. So I just want to show these things are possible.
I'll give you some ideas and I will try to start wrapping it up now.
Oh, yeah, that's the thing for the next sign, right?
Two minutes already. It's time now.
No, how did that happen? OK, let me real quickly.
You know, I've got some code on a GitHub repo, which I can send anybody they want to see the codes.
I only have time to go through it. I will only show just one bit of it.
I can't do that because the slides, you know, skip that.
I can't show the code because it doesn't show up on the screen.
I'm hoping I can drag my browser over there, at least show you the latest stats here.
Give me one second. Oh, no.
Technology hates me today.
The Internet's down, too, so. Let me just real quickly get on my hot spot.
Maybe you can come here to one of those jokes for a second here.
Oh, anybody got a joke? And don't say my talk, please.
You were thinking that?
Oh, that is good. I like that one. I'm going to borrow that one for later.
Come on now. I know I have a hot spot. It was working earlier here.
All right, here we go.
Here we don't go.
All right, let's see if we can pull this over.
How do we pull it to the other screen?
All right. So what do we got here? Andy and I still tough to be with 13.
But there we go. So this was doing is it's been pulling from Twitter every few minutes,
checking the tweets for the pie Texas string and then and then just using the account like we showed earlier.
We're using the user ID of the tweeter as the key and we're just incrementing the count every time we see a tweet from that person.
We also have a deep step because the thing I'm using to pull the tweets in just does everyone pulls in duplicates.
So it's easy to add a deep step in there as well.
So, again, you can add multiple steps to your processes.
And that's what I was going to show you in the code of high time.
But like I said, the codes on GitHub repo, which I can send anybody the link to if they want to look at it later.
But this was all done with just Python with no libraries, Python and Kafka.
They work great together and you can do a lot with them.
There are libraries, though. So I just I know just one more second here.
How do I get back to what I had? That's like that.
OK, it's a challenge. A state is a challenge.
It really is because we did dictionary. Those are just in memory.
So there's a lot of these libraries have persistent state, which is important.
And then scale. I was only working on a single topic or single partition topic for all my things.
If you have multiple partitions, those dictionaries are harder to keep in sync.
So there are things that these libraries will help you with.
I said you don't always need them, but there are times when they do come in handy.
So here's a few we can look at.
There is Faust, which is originally started by Robin Hood.
Then they kind of dropped it and the community picked it up and it's still going somewhat.
ByteWax and Fluvio are two newer ones that are out there.
I think they're both rest based, but those are also streaming libraries for Python.
And you can find those things out on GitHub.
And then quick plug for the one that my company puts out, the company I work for now, Quix.
They have quick streams that just they just open sourced it about a month ago.
So it's still pretty new, but it also handles persistent state and different things like that.
Also works with time, really works well with time, time series data.
And you can find information there about that.
And that would be great if you would check that out, because then they might keep sending me things like this.
But anyways, thank you for letting me go a little bit over time.
And that was my talk.
Thanks.