Hello. First, I want to thank the organizers of PyTexas 2023. Thank you so much for putting
on this conference. It's great to be in Austin. And I want to thank you for attending PyTexas.
Thank you. This is my talk, Recursion for Beginners, a Beginner's Guide to Recursion.
Actually, this is my talk, Recursion for Beginners, a Beginner's Guide to Recursion.
My name is Al Swigert. I'm mostly known as the author of Automate the Boring Stuff with Python,
but I have a new book that is out now. It's the Recursive Book of Recursion. And you can read it
for free under a Creative Commons license on my website, inventwithpython.com. So what is
recursion? Let's ask that website that knows all of our private thoughts.
Okay. Uh-huh. Uh-huh. Yeah. So according to these suggestions, recursion is hard, confusing,
magic, and bad. All right. Okay. So let's start with a basic definition. A recursive thing
is something whose definition includes itself. So for example, here's a fractal, which is a
recursive shape. This is called a Sierpinski Triangle. It kind of looks like the Triforce
from Legend of Zelda. I drew this one using the turtle module that comes with Python. So turtle
is this old school drawing library that lets you programmatically create these Etch-a-Sketch style
pictures. The shape we draw here is a triangle with an upside down triangle in the middle,
which forms three new triangles. And then you draw upside down triangles inside those triangles
and so on forever. A Sierpinski Triangle is made of three Sierpinski Triangles. Its definition
includes itself. So my book gives you the source code for a lot of turtle programs that generate
recursive artwork. They're surprisingly short. They're like 40 lines of code or something like
that. This is a Sierpinski carpet made of squares within squares. You can also make a 3D version of
this in Minecraft, in which case it's a Sierpinski Cube. You can draw lots of these fractals with
Python's turtle module. Here's a recursive tree. Each branch splits into two self-similar branches.
This one looks almost too perfect, though. But if we make the branches sprout random branches
instead of self-similar branches, we end up with a much more natural looking tree. There are some
fractal curves we can draw. This is the coke curve. You split a line into three parts,
and then you change the middle part into a bump. And then you repeat this by adding more bumps
to the new parts. And if you do this to the three sides of a triangle, you end up with a
coke snowflake. Notice that when you add a bump to a line, you're actually making the line one
third longer. And you can add bumps forever. So this is a fractal whose finite area contains an
infinitely long line. There's a bunch of these curves. This one's called the Hilbert curve.
You just take this shape, and then you make three copies of it, and you rotate them around and
connect them. And then that forms the new shape, and you just make three copies of that and rotate
them around and connect them. But if you keep doing that on some graph paper, you have a
contiguous line that touches every square of the graph paper. These are called space filling curves.
All of these are drawn in Python. And that's just the well-known fractals. You can invent your own
fractals. One of the projects in the recursion book is a generic fractal maker. You just start
with any shape, like this triangle, and then you specify what the recursive step is. So in this
case, we're creating a new triangle to the left, right, and bottom, and we also resize and rotate
them a little bit. And that becomes the new shape that you start drawing to the left, right, and
bottom. And if you do that for several more steps, you create a brand-new, never-before-seen fractal.
So here's the square. And in the recursive step, we draw four more squares in the corners, but we
also toggle the color between white and gray. And I don't even know what this is, but it looks kind
of cool. Or we can do it with three corners instead of four, in which case, if you tilt your head
about 135 degrees, it kind of looks like a Sierpinski triangle almost. There's no limit to the
fractals that you can just come up with by just messing around. We're not just limited to geometric
shapes either. You can apply recursion to images as well. This is a tin of a Dutch brand of cocoa
called Drost Cocoa. I actually have one of these tins right here. This image is recursive. The image
contains itself. So we can create our own by using Python and the Pillow Image Library.
So this is my friend at the Menil Museum in Houston. First, I add an area of magenta pixels.
Magenta is really nice because it sticks out, and it tends to not be something that naturally
occurs in most photos. So our Python program identifies the size of the magenta area,
and then shrinks a copy of the photo and replaces all the magenta pixels with the smaller photo.
But of course, this smaller photo has its own magenta area. So you keep repeating this process
over and over again, and you end up with a Drost effect photo. So the code that does this is in the
recursion book. Right, Al, I thought you said that this was a talk for beginners. Yeah, okay, that
all, I know that looks really complicated and fancy and everything, but I won't say that recursion
is easy, but I will say that recursion isn't as hard as you think. Let's get a simple definition
specific to programming. In programming, recursion is when a function calls itself. So here is the
shortest possible recursive function. All it does is call itself. And that's like, it's kind of
weird, right? Like, does that work? And the answer is no, no, it does not work. The error it gives
you is recursion error, maximum recursion depth exceeded. And this kind of error is called a stack
overflow. Hey, that's the name of that website. Okay, so there's this joke that everyone always
says whenever you mention recursion, to understand recursion, you must first understand stack data
structures and function calls. Yeah, so this is the main reason why recursion is tricky, because
teachers don't explain these two concepts first. Let's start with stacks. Stacks are one of the
simplest data structures in computer science. A stack is a data structure that holds an ordered
sequence of data and only lets you interact with the topmost item. So for example, you can think
of a stack as a stack of playing cards. We can add cards to the top of the stack and we can remove
cards from the top of the stack, but you can't insert them into the middle. So if you think about
it, the first card that you put on the stack will be the last card to be removed. So we call a stack
a phylo data structure, because the first thing in will be the last thing out. Okay, so stacks have
their own terminology. Adding data to the top of a stack is called pushing. Removing data from the
top of a stack is called popping. And conversations can be like a stack. So yes, there we go.
Conversations can be like a stack. So I want to tell you a story about my friend Alice, but before
I tell you that, I got to tell you about my other friend Bob, but before I can tell you about Bob,
I need to tell you about his wife Carol. So then I tell you about Carol, and then I get back to my
story about Bob, I finish that story, and then I get back to my story about Alice. So that
conversation has a stack-like structure. The story I'm currently telling you will be the one that's
at the top of the stack. So in fact, you've already worked with stacks. Python lists act the same way
as stacks, as long as you restrict yourself to just append and pop. So in this case, the last item
in the list is the top of the stack. So here's, we're appending some strings to a list, Alice,
then Bob, then Carol, then we pop the list, which returns Carol, and then if we check the list there,
you can see that Bob is now the top of the stack, or rather the end of the list. So that's how stacks
work. There's not much to them. The second thing you need to know about are function calls.
Now, you already kind of know this, but it helps to have someone explicitly tell you when you call
a function, you're not just going on a one-way trip into the function call. The Python interpreter
needs to remember where to return to when the function call returns. So if we have a function
A that calls function B, that calls function C, when C returns, it goes back to B, which goes
back to A, which goes back to the global scope. Now, the way that the Python interpreter keeps
track of function calls is with a stack, and this stack is called the call stack. So Python puts
frame objects on the call stack, and frame objects contain the data of where the execution should
return to after the function call returns. So you can think of a frame object as representing a
function call. We push a new frame object onto the call stack when a function is called, and we pop
it off the call stack when the function returns. The topmost frame object is the function call the
execution is currently in. You know, but when we look at our code, you might wonder, where's the
call stack exactly? Because you can't see it. This is something that the Python interpreter
handles for you automatically behind the scenes. So you can't point to your program anywhere and
say, there, that's the call stack. It's invisible. And if your teacher is not telling you about this,
recursion is just going to seem like some mysterious invisible thing. Okay. So that's stacks
and function calls. But one more thing, recursion is overrated. Or at least recursion is overused.
You know, people like to use recursion when they don't have to. It doesn't make the code simpler.
It, in fact, does the opposite. But programmers will do this anyway because one of the most
irritating things programmers do regularly is feel so good about learning a hard thing that they
don't look for ways to make it easy or even oppose things that would do so. This is so true.
I'm going to have it tattooed to my forehead. And I think it's really telling that there are two
algorithms every recursion tutorial uses. And they are both terrible examples of recursion.
Yes. The classic algorithms. Factorial and Fibonacci. Okay. So this is factorial. It's
a math thing. 5 factorial is 5 times 4 times 3 times 2 times 1 or 120. 2 factorial is 2 times
1. 4 factorial is 4 times 3 times 2 times 1. You can see the pattern. The interesting thing about
factorial is if you look at it, especially 5 factorial, that's the same as 5 times 4 factorial.
We can generalize this pattern. The factorial of any number is that number times the factorial of
that number minus 1. So the definition of factorial includes itself. It has a recursive nature.
So we can translate this into Python code. Let's make a factorial function and it returns the
number parameter times the factorial of number minus 1. And this seems kind of weird. Does this
actually work? And the answer is no. No, it does not. This will crash with a stack overflow. So
why does that happen? Well, if you think about it, this is 5 factorial. But our factorial function
is actually doing this. We forgot to tell it to stop at 1. So it just keeps going. So if you ever
have a stack overflow, the problem is that your algorithm never stopped recursing. Programs can't
make recursive calls forever because every function call adds a frame object to the call stack and
that takes up a little bit of memory. So an infinite recursion would eventually eat up all
of your computer's available memory and Python goes ahead and just cuts it off after about
at 1,000 function calls without any return. So this is why the stack trace right here
has four function calls and then it says repeated 996 more times. Now, to fix the stack overflow
problem, we want to stop recursing when the number argument is 1. So here's a hint. One factorial
is always 1. So let's add some code that checks if number is 1. And in that case, we can have it
return 1. And this case is called the base case. The base case is the circumstance under which you
stop making more recursive function calls. And then the recursive case is when we make a recursive
function call. Your recursive function must always have at least one base case and one recursive case.
This kind of makes sense if you think about it because if you don't have a base case,
then your recursive function is just going to recurse forever and cause a stack overflow.
And if your recursive function doesn't have a recursive case, it's not a recursive function.
It's never actually calling itself. So at least one base case and one recursive case.
You might still look at this function and think, yeah, OK. I see how that works kind of. But where
does the 5 times 4 times 3 times 2 times 1 happen? So it kind of happens across several function
calls of the call stack. That's a really bad way of describing it. You need to keep in mind
that in recursion, all the function calls are for the same function. The call stack doesn't contain
frame objects that represent functions. They represent function calls. And this is a very
subtle distinction. But maybe this will help. Let's use a stack of cards to represent the call stack
and frame objects. This is a timeline of what the call stack looks like. So we first call factorial
with an argument of 5. We push a new frame object card onto the call stack. This frame object
represents a function call that returns 5 times the factorial of 4. But it can't return yet. It
has to call factorial. So we add another frame object with another function call to factorial
here, this time with an argument of 4. This function call pushes another frame object on the
stack. Now there are two cards on the stack. But notice that this new frame object has its own
local variable named number. The other number variable is still there. It's just on the card
below. So local variables are stored in these frame objects. And one thing that you really need
to understand is that there are multiple local variables named number. They have the same name,
but they're existing at the same time. We haven't replaced the old number variable. This is another
thing that makes recursion really confusing if nobody points this out to you explicitly.
Anyway, we continue with more function objects pushed to the call stack until we reach the base
case, which just returns 1. And when that function call returns, we pop the frame object off the call
stack. So the call stack starts getting smaller. We're back to the function call where the number
parameter was 2. But now we have all the information we need to return. So that card gets popped off
the call stack and so on and so on and so on until the last card returns 5 times 24, which is 120,
which is the factorial of 5. After that, the call stack is empty and the execution is back
in the global scope. So where does the 5 times 4 times 3 times 2 times 1 happen? It's hard to
imagine all of this because it's sort of the call stack is changing across time. But here's another
way that we can represent it. Let's just hard code our recursive function as multiple separate
functions. So factorial 5 function returns 5 times factorial 4 functions return value,
and factorial 4 returns 4 times factorial 3's return value and so on until we get to factorial
1 function, which just returns 1. So if you want to know, here is where 5 times 4 times 3 times 2
times 1 happens. It's just that in our recursive example, all of this is in one function.
Now, a non-recursive algorithm is called an iterative algorithm. So some programmers might
tell you that like, oh, well, there's some things that you can only do with recursion,
and that is completely wrong. Anything you can do with recursion, you can do with a loop and a stack.
Look, I'll prove it. So you can write an iterative factorial algorithm, and you can write a
recursive factorial algorithm. Here is an iterative factorial algorithm that emulates a recursive
factorial algorithm. Notice it's not a recursive function. There's no functions in here. I'm not
going to explain all of this. This is way too complicated. But I emulate a call stack with a
Python list, and I emulate frame objects with these dictionaries that contain the local variables,
and I emulate the function calls by pushing and popping the emulated frame objects to the
emulated call stack. Emulated stops sounding like a real word when you say it so often.
This is completely ridiculous. But technically, the code works. This will print out 120,
5 factorial at the end of it. Yeah, anything you can do with recursion, you can do with a loop
and a stack. If you know where the Ackerman function is, yes, even recursive Ackerman can
be implemented iteratively by using a loop and a stack. Here's the code for that.
So if we don't need recursion, and recursion is often confusing, when should we actually
use recursion? So I thought about this, and I came up with an answer, and then I thought
about it some more, and I came up with a better answer. We should use recursion when your problem
has both a tree-like structure and backtracking. So this is a tree data structure. It's used a
lot in computer science. You have a root node at top, and it branches out to other nodes.
And those nodes will branch out to other nodes, so trees have a recursive structure. Yes, I
realize that the tree is upside down. That's because the root node is the start, and on paper,
we write things from top to bottom. It's fine. Lots of things in programming are upside down.
So recursion is really suited to working with tree graphs because they have a recursive nature,
especially like when you need to move down the tree graph, but then you also have to backtrack
up. There's a lot of problems that you can sort of map onto trees and then use recursion to solve.
For example, a maze can be solved with recursion because a maze is just really a tree data
structure. The entrance is the root node, and then every time you come to an intersection,
it branches off into multiple other nodes, and the exit is going to be one of the other nodes.
So if you backtrack from the exit back to the entrance, that's the solution of the maze.
Now, I don't have time to go into any tree traversal algorithms, but the recursion book
has the code. Just take my word for it that it's actually simpler to implement this as a recursive
function than doing it with a loop and a stack, but otherwise, you should not use recursion.
Here's a problem with recursive factorial, though. If you try to calculate the factorial of 1,001,
you're going to get a stack overflow because it needs more than 1,000 function calls.
Now, there is a way around this. It's called tail call optimization. Long story short. The
Python interpreter can mess with the call stack and prevent stack overflows. It's just you have to
make the recursive call the last thing in the recursive function because if there's no code
after the recursive call, you don't have to hang on to the local variables, which means you don't
have to hang on to the frame object, and you can prematurely pop it off the stack, and then the
call stack doesn't grow. Tail call optimization is this way that you can stop stack overflows.
But there's another problem. This recursive factorial function can't be tail call optimized
because you notice there's this one little bit of code that happens after the recursive call.
So now you have to rewrite all of your code to use this thing called an accumulator and change
the base case around. This is just becoming more and more confusing. And then there's another
problem on top of that, and that's the Python interpreter doesn't implement tail call optimization,
and it never will. Guido van Rossum has a couple of blog posts giving his reasons, but he's not
alone. Most JavaScript engines and the Java virtual machine from Oracle also don't implement
tail call optimization. You can write tail recursion if you want. It's not actually going to happen
by the compiler or the interpreter. So despite the fact that factorial is the most popular example
of recursion, you never actually want to use recursion to calculate factorials in the real world
ever. The other popular example of recursion is the Fibonacci sequence. This is another math thing.
You probably know this. The sequence starts with the numbers one and one, and the next number is
always the sum of the previous two numbers. So you can easily write a function that uses a loop
to calculate these. But if you're too clever for your own good, you'll notice that the nth Fibonacci
number is the sum of the two previous Fibonacci numbers. So this definition includes itself,
and you can write a recursive algorithm for it. The base case is that the first two numbers,
one and two, are always going to be one. But notice that every recursive function call results
in two more recursive function calls. So here's a tree diagram. If you try to find the sixth Fibonacci
number, you're going to end up with all of these other calls in exponentially growing number of
function calls. And a lot of those are redundant. You're recalculating the same Fibonacci number
over and over again. And to prevent this, there's a technique called memoization.
Long story short, you can just cache the return value the first time a function is called, and
then that way you don't have to repeat the calculation and blah, blah, blah. This is all
just more hacks that you have to put on top of complicated code just to make recursion work at
all. And you can avoid all of it just by not using recursion. I don't even know why people
use recursion. It's just so confusing and frustrating. And I hate it. I hate recursion.
I hate it so much. I hate it so much that I'm going to write an entire book on recursion and
then I'm going to give it away for free on the internet just so people can find out how terrible
it is. You should never use recursion. It's so pointless. Except there is one area where recursion
comes in handy. This is the Python instruction two plus three. We call this an expression.
Now, an expression is made up of values connected by operators. Two and three are values. The plus
operator is an operator. So we can define an expression as value operator value. But
expressions can be more complicated than this. This expression is two plus three times three.
In this case, our expression is a value operator and another expression. And a value by itself
is also an expression. It's just that a value is an expression that evaluates to itself.
Now, wait a second. This looks familiar. The definition of expression includes itself. Not
only that, but this is a recursive case and a base case. It turns out if you want to create
your own programming language, you need to understand recursion. Now, creating your own
programming language is something that most programmers never even think of themselves
as capable of doing. It just seems too big and too advanced. Where would you even start? I guess
you would start with recursion. But it's not just making your own programming language, though.
There's lots of things in programming that we feel like we're just not qualified to work on
because they seem too advanced. But if you start dabbling in these weird little areas of theoretical
computer science, you begin to see that they're not just theory. You start getting ideas on how
to build these much greater things that you would have never thought possible before.
Understanding recursion lets you have bigger dreams. In conclusion, recursion is a hack that
produces an over-engineered mess, just that insufferable programmers can show off how smart
they are. And recursion is an amazing concept that allows you to see new things in the field
of programming. It's something that you don't need to be a genius to understand. It is subtle,
it is complex, it is beautiful, and it's worth your time and effort to understand. Thank you.