All right, so thanks so much for sticking around.
I know it's been a long weekend with a lot of great talks.
I was at PyTexas 2019, but this is my first time
speaking at one.
Yeah.
So my talk is going to be a bit different than the ones
you've heard before.
I'm going to talk to you today about how you can use Python
for digital investigations.
First, I'm going to talk to you about what
a digital investigation is in this context.
Then I'm going to show you an example
of a digital investigation.
I'll show you some Python tools that my colleagues and I
have used for digital investigations.
And I'll close with some more information
in case you're interested and want to get more involved.
All right, so I've been programming
with Python for about 10 years now.
I learned it in college, mostly for computational physics.
In my current job, I am a data scientist and developer
at Bellingcat, where I do a lot of large-scale social media
scraping and analysis and developing software tools
for journalists and researchers to use.
I'm particularly interested in far-right extremist communities
online, and a lot of my research focuses on that.
So Bellingcat is a nonprofit investigative research
collective founded in 2014.
We use open source data to investigate
a wide variety of topics, including
human rights abuses, environmental issues,
wrongdoings by the powerful, the radical fringes of society,
and just about everything in between.
We publish stories, develop novel investigative methods.
We share those methods with journalists and researchers,
and foster a community of journalists
and researchers, and foster a community of people
who use those methods.
If you've heard of Bellingcat before,
it was probably when we identified
the Russian intelligence agents who
poisoned the dissident Alexei Navalny, or something similar.
Yeah.
So what is a digital investigation?
You might also hear the term open source research, which
I'll be using throughout this talk,
or open source intelligence, often abbreviated as OSINT.
The big idea here is that this is information that
is available to the public.
Everyone has equal access to the information sources.
They're not classified by government
or locked away in some company's proprietary database.
And the key thing about this is that the equal access
to information sources enables a great deal of transparency.
Investigative methods can be shared.
This increases accountability.
Anyone can verify the steps that researchers have taken,
which in turn helps in reproducibility.
Investigations can be confirmed and expanded upon by others.
And these kinds of open source investigations
have really only been around for about the last decade or so.
Previously, a lot of sources were really only
available to the intelligence agencies
of powerful governments.
But now, many of those sources are available to anyone.
For example, right now, if you have about $100,
you can buy a satellite image of anywhere
in the world with sub-meter resolution.
And that's just something you really could not do 10 years ago.
And as you may have heard or noticed,
there is a lot of information on the internet.
And that can make things challenging
when you're digging around trying
to find some specific content.
But the upside of that is that the list of open sources
is pretty much endless.
The only real limit is the ingenuity of researchers.
So some common examples of open source materials
are geospatial sources, like Google or Yandex Maps, Google
Earth, and satellite imagery.
We have media outlets, BBC, CNN, Fox News, user generated,
and social media content, like from YouTube, Twitter,
and Telegram, and data sets.
For example, for things like company registration
and legal documents, as well as archives,
like the internet archive.
Often, the really interesting thing
comes when you combine information
from several of these sources.
And also, it's worth mentioning that things
like hacking, stealing, and spying
are not considered open source.
And Bell and Cat doesn't do those.
So let's get into an example of an open source investigation.
So on July 17, 2014, Malaysia Airlines Flight 17,
known as MH17, which was flying from Amsterdam to Kuala Lumpur,
was shot down over eastern Ukraine.
All on board, nearly 300 passengers and crew
were killed.
In the immediate aftermath, the Russian government
blamed the Ukraine, and the Ukrainian government
blamed Russian-backed separatists in the region.
If we don't want to trust either of these governments
or their intelligence agencies, what can we
learn from open sources?
Turns out, we can learn quite a bit.
So in the days before and after MH17 was shot down,
there were several sightings of a military convoy
near the location of the crash site
that contained a missile launcher.
Many of these sightings were posted on social media,
such as this Instagram picture.
And by determining the location of each of these sightings,
researchers were able to piece together
the movement of the missile launcher.
So we're interested in this particular missile launcher
from this particular convoy for a key reason.
In footage before July 17, the launcher has four missiles.
After July 17, it only has three.
So this is suggestive that this is, in fact,
the missile launcher we're looking
for that shot down MH17.
So an essential step when we're working with social media
information and content is verification.
Basically, does the image or video
actually show what the post claims it shows?
This is, there's a lot of things we
need to watch out for with this.
So for example, is the video a repost of an event that
happened earlier?
We see this in war footage all the time.
Especially drone footage is constantly
re-uploaded and recycled and claiming to be
from the most recent conflict.
Is the video generated by a video game or flight simulator?
This is actually surprisingly common, especially
in aerial footage.
Has a video been deceptively edited, like slowed down,
sped up, or had some other footage spliced in?
And more recently, a more recent issue,
was this generated by AI or mid, like mid-journey?
Does everyone have the right number of fingers and legs?
So luckily, there are some well-established methods
for investigating each of these points,
but we don't have a ton of time for that.
So let's just focus on one of them.
Is the location where the post claims
the actual location of the video?
So what we see here, in the top, we
have a screenshot from Google Street View.
And at the bottom, we have the video of the missile launcher,
as well as an instant.
And if you're in Google Street View,
you can adjust the viewpoint, and you can kind of line up
the viewport with the actual video.
And we can see, OK, so there's a poll that looks about right.
There's another telephone poll.
The intersections of the wires on the poll look about right.
The outline of the trees also looks right.
So we can say, OK, it's plausible
that this video was, in fact, taken
at this particular location.
And in practice, geolocating footage
often requires either very detailed knowledge
of a particular location, being very clever,
or just brute forcing it and spending a bunch of time
driving around Google Street View
or flying around Google Earth.
But the key point is that no matter
how difficult and long it took to geolocate some footage,
pretty much anyone can verify it.
It really doesn't require much specialized skill
to look at a location in Google Street View, look at a video,
and be able to say, oh, yeah, this, this, and this match up.
Or conversely, to say, oh, no, this doesn't match up
because of this and this.
So it's very much a democratization
of an investigation.
So the key point is by geolocating
each of the sidings of this convoy,
both in Ukraine immediately before and after the shoot
down and in Russia about a month earlier,
researchers were able to convincingly argue that A,
that the missile launcher traveled from Russia to Ukraine
to an area controlled by Russian-backed separatists
and then after the shoot down traveled back
with one less missile.
They were also able to determine the Russian unit
the missile launcher belonged to and all these findings
were later corroborated by the official investigation
by the Dutch government.
And to reiterate, this was all done
without having to trust the word or propaganda
of any intelligence agencies or government.
And this is just one example of the power
of open source research.
So a common source of confusion is
the similarity of the terms open source research
and open source software.
I intentionally use the term digital investigation
in my talk to avoid confusing you all
because I assume most of you are familiar with open source
in the context of software, not research.
And though the two terms sound similar,
they have very different origins.
The term open source intelligence OSINT really originated
in the US and British intelligence communities
as kind of a catchall term
for non-classified sources of information.
Despite the different histories though,
the two communities have really independently converged
on a similar ethos, really built on transparency,
reproducibility and collaboration.
And kind of going back to Krishy's talk yesterday,
all these are ways of kind of building
and establishing trust.
And in the last few years especially,
the overlap between the two communities,
the open source research community
and the open source software community have been,
there's have, the overlap has been increasing.
And this is really driven by two factors.
One is that open source researchers
and journalists get more familiar with software tools.
For example, learning how to run Python scripts
or use the command line to automate some of their tasks
like the boring ones.
And at the same time,
developers find out about open source research.
They think it's cool, so they start developing tools for it.
And that's kind of the path that I took.
It's worth mentioning though
that there is still a long way to go.
Bellingcat surveyed researchers
and found that only about a quarter of them
are comfortable using software tools from sites like GitHub.
And that tells us that there's a lot of opportunities
both for education and for making tools
more accessible and easy to use.
So Python has become the go-to programming language
of the open source research community
for many of the same reasons that you all like it.
I'm assuming here that you all like Python
since you're at a Python convention,
but if not, sorry to hear that.
So I mean, as we know, Python is easy to learn,
especially as the first programming language.
And it has a very mature ecosystem of packages
for just about any purpose,
from web scraping to image analysis to 3D modeling.
So the first Python tool I wanna talk to you about
is the auto-archiver developed
by some of my colleagues at Bellingcat.
It automatically archives posts, images, and video
from a variety of social media platforms.
The way it works is that researchers paste a URL
of a social media post into a Google Sheet,
and then any media, metadata, and a screenshot of the post
is automatically downloaded and saved.
And we wanted to make this interface
as easy to use as possible for non-technical researchers.
Simple is better than complex.
And this kind of archiving is actually really important
for sensitive social media content,
all the time is that some social media account
will post something that is interesting or revealing
or just kind of spicy in some way,
and then take it down as soon as they realize,
hey, this makes me look bad.
This is especially damaging
if the thing that looks bad is a potential war crime.
And when they take it down,
all evidence of that content is now gone.
However, if we have archived it, then we have it, right?
So the auto archiver uses a mix of both official
and unofficial social media APIs,
basically whatever does the job the best,
and you can check it out on our GitHub page here.
So at Bellingcat, we use Google Sheets pretty extensively.
They're easy to use and set up.
They're easy to collaborate with,
with non-technical people,
and they're quick to read and adjust formatting,
which is good for manually checking data.
We typically use the Gspread Python package
pretty extensively for reading and writing to Google Sheets.
And what we have here is a screenshot
of one of the inputs to the auto archiver
that we have been using to track incidents
of civilian harm in Ukraine,
so such as attacks on infrastructure
and against the population.
So since the beginning of the Russian invasion last February,
Bellingcat and volunteers have geolocated
and verified more than a thousand incidents
of civilian harm in Ukraine.
Each incident can be visualized on our time map website.
Let's try this live.
Oh no.
Ah, come on.
All right, there we go.
Third time's a charm, right?
All right, so what we see here is a map of Ukraine,
and we can see circles that represent
all verified incidents over the last month.
If we, sorry, if we click on one of these,
it zooms in and focuses on the individual incidents.
And if we click on one, we see that on March 9th,
there was a strike on a industrial area.
It's not loading right now, but I hope you believe me
when I say that we have the telegram video of the strike
for anyone to see.
And I will say, sorry if this is a blasphemous thing to say,
the front end is not Python, it is JavaScript,
but the source of the data was all done in Python.
And several other organizations are using the auto archiver
for similar purposes.
And one thing that's worth mentioning
is that one thing Bellingcat has been working on
is developing a methodology for making open source evidence,
for making open source data accessible, excuse me,
admissible as evidenced
in international criminal law proceedings.
The goal here is that the geolocated and verified footage
that was archived by the auto archiver
will one day be used to hold accountable
members of the Russian military
who were responsible for these attacks on civilians.
Yeah.
Another Python tool that Bellingcat has developed
is a framework for scraping social media content,
not just a single specified post like the auto archiver,
but everything from a set of accounts or channels.
We developed this framework as part of a data driven effort
to better understand the ecosystem of QAnon
and QAnon adjacent online conspiracy communities in Europe,
because that's a big thing in Europe, believe it or not.
We collected a lot of data.
We have posts from five different social media platforms,
including Getter, Rumble, BitChute, and VKontakte,
which is like a Russian Facebook,
but the vast majority are from Telegram
because that's a platform
these communities are most active on.
We are archiving posts from about 2,600 channels.
So by channel, I refer to really any kind
of social media account.
So BitChute user, a VKontakte group, or a Telegram channel.
And as of last night, we're up to about 63 million posts
that have been scraped, archived, and made searchable.
The posts contain about 44 different languages,
which have at least a hundred posts.
We have nearly 6 million images
that have been archived and OCRed.
So we're using optical character recognition
to detect and index text in image.
And we have about 2 million videos.
So the way this works is that the framework coordinates
between the scrapers, the database, and the media archive.
We use the SQLAlchemy package to interface with a database,
the Elasticsearch package to interface
with a full text search index.
But we use Boto3 to archive content, PyTesseract for OCR,
and Flask for the API that communicates
with the front-end dashboard.
Similar to the auto-archiver,
researchers can paste the URL of a channel
into a Google Sheet.
And then the framework scrapes the raw social media posts
in near real time.
And in addition to scraping,
we're archiving media files attached to post,
which along with images and video can include things
like audio and PDF documents.
The scraping, archiving, and processing pipelines
are constantly running.
So even if a channel quickly deletes a post,
there's a decent chance we'll still get it.
The raw post is then cleaned and processed
into a standard format across platforms,
which makes it searchable through a front-end dashboard
we created in JavaScript.
So to better understand the overall structure
of the ecosystem, I created some network visualizations
from the data.
Let's see if this works.
Nice.
All right, so this first network shows telegram forwards.
So the nodes, the circles here, are telegram channels.
Edges between nodes, the lines,
are in one channel forwarded one or more posts
from the other.
The nodes are colored by the most commonly detected language
in the channel's posts.
So we have this German cluster in kind of teal.
Teal, English and orange, Italian and blue,
French and pink, and the node size is related
to the number of followers the channel has.
One nice thing about this network
is that the clusters of nodes are very tight
and correspond closely with the channel languages.
I mean, this makes some sense, right?
If you have a social media account,
you're not gonna repost content
from a language you don't understand.
And an interesting thing is that the positions
of the language clusters tell us
about how the different language communities
interact with each other.
So as you can see, English is at the center
of the visualization and it kind of acts as a hub
that connects the different European languages.
If we zoom in a bit, yeah, so this Dutch cluster,
kind of in green here is very close to the English cluster
indicating that there's a lot of overlap
between the two communities.
And one thing that I think is particularly interesting
and useful about this kind of visualization
is that we can identify some key nodes
that stand between clusters.
For example, this one we see, yeah, come on.
We see a lot of nodes, edges coming in and out of this one
that connect the English and French communities.
So investigating bridge nodes like this
can better inform how viral content moves
between communities and across borders.
See.
Nice, all right, so in this second network,
what we have, so the nodes are named entities.
Basically, words that correspond to real world objects
detected using spaCy, a natural language processing package
in Python.
And the edges are when one or more posts
contains both named entities.
Nodes are colored by a community detection algorithm
that seeks to group together similar nodes.
And this kind of visualization is really interesting
to see how different topics relate to each other
according to these conspiracy communities.
There are a few clear clusters in the center.
We have, in purple, we have this kind of US politics thing
with various politicians, the FBI, and patriots.
Over here, we have in green, kind of a more COVID one.
We have things like COVID, WHO, Bill Gates, Anthony Fauci.
And one thing I really like about this kind of visualization
is that it's good for finding kind of niche topics
in sub-communities.
Like, for example, there's something called
Schumann Residence, which is a geophysics phenomenon.
It's commonly mentioned in weather
and geoengineering conspiracies.
And I hadn't heard of this before,
and investigating that took me down a fun rabbit hole.
Where did it go?
All right, so the last tool I want to show you
is called SugarTrail.
It's used to find and analyze connections
between companies registered in the United Kingdom
in the Companies House database.
SugarTrail was one of the winning projects
in Bellingcat's first hackathon,
and its developer continued to work on it
funded by a Bellingcat Tech Fellowship,
which we offer to developers of tools
that we find interesting and useful.
SugarTrail has an easy-to-use interface
and a very simple way to use it.
implemented using IPyWidgets that uses,
it uses requests to interface with the Companies House API
and pandas for data processing.
You can see here, this is a screenshot of the interface,
which was developed using IPyWidgets,
which basically converts a Jupyter Notebook
into a interactive webpage, which is quite cool.
And SugarTrail, oh, oh God, okay.
So SugarTrail can do several types of investigations,
including identifying addresses that are registered,
that one or more companies are registered,
and that's useful for finding potentially
suspicious offices with lots of registered companies.
It can also, probably I think the coolest thing
is that it can see if and how two different
specified companies are related to each other
by following the chain of companies,
company officers, and registered addresses.
And these types of analysis are useful
for detecting potentially fraudulent companies
and company officers, and these are especially useful
to financial investigators who don't know programming
and don't know how to use API or use a huge database,
and this can save them from doing it for like hours
and hours from doing a bunch of manual work
tracking down the leads manually.
So taking a step back, why should you care about this?
I mean, if you haven't figured it out by now,
one of the main reasons I'm here is to get developers
like you all interested in open source research.
I can tell you my perspective.
The thing that really keeps me in this field
and interested is the impact.
My colleagues and I work to expose
some really terrible people,
whether that's military officers who program cruise missiles
to hit children's playgrounds or neo-Nazi pedophiles.
The work we do helps to hold these people accountable
and find justice for their victims.
It's incredibly rewarding work.
And the other thing that really keeps me interested
is the sheer energy of the open source research community.
This field has really only been around
for about 10 years now,
but researchers are constantly coming up
with innovative uses of open source information.
I've really only scratched the surface here.
I could spend hours talking about brilliant
open source investigations and tools,
like when a researcher identified
a secret US military bases in Syria
because soldiers were logging their runs to a running app.
Or one of the coolest things I've seen recently,
it's a tool that uses small fluctuations
in GPS satellite signals
to detect North Korean missile launches.
And another aspect that I think is really exciting
is that often these software tools
don't have to be very technically sophisticated
to be really useful.
I mean, often it's the simplest tools
that get the most usage and impact.
Something as straightforward as a wrapper
or an interface to an existing API
can be a game changer to people
who don't know how to use requests,
which let's face it, is most people.
And no matter your skill level,
you can meaningfully contribute.
And I mean, like Pandy said,
we can build anything, right?
So that's the end of my presentation.
If you want more information,
read our investigations on our website, bellingcat.com.
You can see our repos on GitHub, bellingcat.
If you really want a challenge,
we see our list of open questions.
These are difficult long-term challenges
that I'd love to see anyone make some progress on.
We maintain a list of tools used in open source research.
Check it out at bit.ly slash bcat-tools.
In three weeks from now,
we'll be hosting a virtual hackathon
where we'll be focusing
on making digital investigation tools more accessible.
If you Google Bellingcat Hackathon,
should be one of the first results
or you can follow this link or talk to me.
And if you want to get more involved,
Bellingcat has a Discord server
where you can join a community of open source researchers
who are working on a ton of really cool projects.
And if you have any questions,
please don't hesitate to come up and talk to me.
I love talking about this stuff
and I think it's really exciting
and I hope you all do too.
Thanks so much.
I hope I left, yeah.
Yeah.