Thank you. All right. So hopefully everybody's enjoying the conference so far. We're almost
done. Hopefully everybody, you know, had a good lunch. We'll see if everybody stays awake
after this talk. I know, you know, building software is super exciting and everything.
But my name is Chris Morrow. I'm a staff software developer here in Austin, Texas. I work at
a company called Q2 and or the pandemic. I was working on some open source software called
Build Magic. So I'm here to talk to you about it today. So we'll go over some issues with
building software, what Build Magic is and what it can do for you, some common build
problems and then go over some examples. So, okay, if you're here, you're probably interested
in writing software or you do this professionally, right? But we don't think a lot about building
software. That's boring, right? And often it's extra stuff that we have to do in addition
to writing our code. So let's go through a little example here. So we have a software
developer. His name is Brian. So Brian likes Python. And he works on a side project where
he creates a little Python application that saves him time and also saves the company
money. So this is great. And other devs on his team want to use it. So Alex is on his
team. She is also a Pythonista. And Brian can simply just send it to Alex and everything
just works. So Brian's getting more recognition for this within the company. And then Brian's
boss's boss, Ellie, wants to use Brian's app. Well, Ellie's not as technical and she doesn't
want to install Python. And she is using Windows compared to the rest of the team, which is
on Macs. So Brian's thinking about how do I solve this problem? So he reads about something
called Py2EXE. He's like, oh, okay, let's give this a shot. So first thing he realizes,
though, is that Py2EXE only runs on Windows. So he goes to the IT department and gets a
Windows laptop and is like, all right, let's do this. Then he realizes, okay, well, now
I need MSVCR90.DLL and I can only get that from Visual Studio or this Microsoft Visual
C++ redistributable. And he's wondering what is the newest thing here because a lot of
this info is old. So Brian decides to install Visual Studio and manages to get this to work.
It spits out a directory that has his Python application now as a Windows executable along
with some other files. He sends it to Ellie. It works. Everybody's happy. So the thing,
though, is this is all dependent on a laptop. And now the whole company wants to use this.
So Brian goes and automates this with GitHub actions and then uploads all the artifacts
to Artifactory. All right. So what are our takeaways from this? So we can, by looking
at this, we can see builds can quickly become complex. Also, in this example, Brian had
to build for multiple platforms and create separate artifacts for those platforms. But
also, I think something we don't consider that often is that build processes evolve
over time. So keeping all of these things in mind, I developed BuildMagic in late 2020.
And based off of some things I was doing at the time, and I describe it as an unopinionated
automation tool. Also, one of the key facts here is it ideally should be producing reproducible
and portable build jobs. So it's doing this through abstracting away where the commands
run from the underlying environment. And I'll talk some more about how that works.
So another key feature here is that each command you automate runs in its own shell process.
You can run everything from the CLI if you really want, but if you want to batch stuff
together, there's a simple approachable YAML format for doing that. And it runs on Windows,
Mac, and Linux. I've tested it on all three. And it is written 100% in Python. Okay, so a
little bit about the structure here. Whenever you run commands in BuildMagic, everything is
bundled together into a job. And a job is composed of multiple stages. A stage is what
runs commands and has this concept of a command runner and has optional set up and tear down
methods. So what are these command runners? Well, this was kind of the key feature that I was
thinking about when I wrote this that separates it out from a lot of other build utilities out
there. So these command runners add a layer of abstraction that separates the commands that you
want to run from where they actually run. So currently, there's four of these command runners,
the default being just run on the host machine. Also, there is a remote runner, which uses open
SSH and public-private key authentication. It, you know, theoretically could use password-based
authentication. I just chose not to support it. There is the Docker runner. So you can specify
a Docker image that you want to run all your commands inside and BuildMagic handles binding
the volume and then doing Docker run and then tearing it down when it's done. And then last,
you can run all your commands inside a virtual machine using Vagrant if people still use Vagrant.
So you there just specify the path to a Vagrant file and BuildMagic will
run Vagrant up and then Vagrant destroy for you. So, okay, this is kind of what it looks like.
Hopefully, that looks okay up there. Yeah, it doesn't look too bad. All right. So on the command
line, you run BuildMagic. In this case, I've used the verbose option and then just a simple command,
echo hello world. And you can see I've got a timestamp of when I ran it. I can see the command
that was executed. And I even get the output from the standard out of that command. So, okay,
this is fine. But you know, it's just one simple thing, right? What if I want to batch a whole
bunch of stuff to run? So the way we do that is what I'm just generically calling config files
right now. So I know like Helm has Helm charts and Ansible has playbooks. I haven't come up with
a clever name. I didn't want to call them like spells or like a spell book or anything like that.
So we're going with the magic theme. So for now, they're just called config files. If honestly,
if you can think of like a clever name, just email me and I might use it. So,
okay. So we can batch stuff together and even run multiple stages using these config files.
And it's just YAML. You can list out multiple stages. You can optionally give a name.
In this case, I've said I want to use the Docker runner and I want to run it inside an Alpine
container. And I run two commands. Both of these are used for building a Python package.
And then the second one will actually upload it to PyPI. So there are two keys before that,
this build and release. So unlike some other systems like GitLab CI or Ansible,
these directives don't impart any actual meaning. They're purely,
what is it? They're there for documentation purposes, for readability. So even though it
says build on there, that doesn't actually mean anything. You can put something else there and
it doesn't change what actually does. That's why I say that this is unopinionated, right?
Build magic doesn't care what you're doing. You just tell it what to do and what environment to
run it in. So let's look at some common problems here. So problem one, developers on a team aren't
always using the same operating system, hardware, version of Python, version of Go, et cetera, right?
So I'm a big proponent of software teams should use what they're comfortable using and what
they're most efficient in. But this creates a problem of when everybody's using different
operating systems, it gets hard to all work on the same thing. So that's where this concept of
command runners and abstraction came from. Because to address this, if you start thinking about,
well, I'll run my commands inside Docker and then use build magic to automate all that,
then I don't have to worry about, well, okay, this person is on a Windows laptop,
so I don't necessarily need to or I need to consider do they have all the same packages
installed? Do they have the same version? If it's all there inside a Docker container, then
we're good in that sense. So kind of what this looks like whenever you run it, though,
you can see some examples here of the different runners. These are all running Echo Hello World,
but this shows you kind of what it looks like whenever you run it using the remote runner,
the Docker runner, Vagrant, you get the idea. All right, so problem two, the build process is
often automated with shell scripts or extra makefile targets, which are brittle and not
portable. Okay, so that's kind of a bold statement, right? And I'm kind of opinionated here. Like I
know it's big, you know, usually people are doing build automation with shell scripts and make files.
And I'm not talking about like, you know, compiling my C or C++ program with a makefile,
please do that. I'm talking more about like, let's build a Docker image using a makefile,
or let's call like npm test npm build inside a makefile. That kind of thing is more of what
I'm talking about here. So let's look at an example here. So on the left, I've got a shell script,
on the right, makefile, and they both do the exact same thing. I'm taking the string hello,
writing it to file 1.txt, the string world, writing it to file 2.txt. Then I archive them
using tar. And then I print, created my files.tar.gz and then remove the files. Okay, so that's pretty
simple. But, you know, if you're, you know, if you're looking carefully, you might notice there's a
mistake up here. So the tar command is used incorrectly here. The arguments and the
the name of the archive file are switched. So when I run this, I get errors.
So with the shell script, I get an error from tar. But after that, I still see it says created
my files.tar.gz. It didn't do that because tar failed. So this is kind of a problem with shell
scripts is that even though a command failed, it continued to run afterwards. And that's not always
what you want to do. Oftentimes, you want to just stop whenever you encounter a problem.
And there's ways to do this in shell scripts. You have to build up some conditional expressions
to check for status code. Or you could, you know, use like I think it's set dash E maybe.
I could be wrong about that to kind of enforce the more strict execution. But then, you know,
it's not as, you know, not so much of a simple thing anymore. So with the make file,
whenever we run this, the make file stops when it encounters the error. But the problem there is
I am removing the files in another make file target. So by doing that, that never runs and
produces a side effect. Now, even though it failed, I still have these files left over
in the file system. So build magic handles this a little differently. So this is the equivalent
using build magic. I use something here called an action. And this is the cleanup action. So
what happens is whenever I specify this, build magic will scan the current working directory
and know all the directories, all the files that are there. And then after it finishes running the
stage, it looks at what new files are there and then removes any new files, new directories.
So when I run this, hit the error again, just like with the others. But the big difference here is
that it did execution stopped when it encountered the error. And it also removed file one dot txt
and file two dot txt because I used that cleanup action. So this is nice because
it becomes repeatable and it's not producing side effects whenever it runs.
All right. So probably a lot of you are thinking, like, why would I use this whenever we have,
you know, CI CD, right? Because CI CD does a lot of this stuff for us. Well, one common problem
there is, you know, as great as GitHub actions and GitLab CI is, if you are automating in there,
all of these are cloud based. So if you get something wrong and you encounter an error,
then you have to debug that and then start the pipeline again. And so then you could
get into this loop of error, debug, retry over and over again because you can't do this locally.
So really, too, like if you're working for a company where they have a dedicated DevOps team,
you might want to separate the concerns, too, of building the software from running the CI pipeline.
So here I have a GitLab CI file where what it does is it downloads BuildMagic, installs it,
and then runs it. So in this case, the application I'm building, just called My App, runs
entirely inside BuildMagic and then the pipeline doesn't care what's going on.
You know, that's the developer's concern to address that. So now we've separated the concerns
there and we're handling those things separately. Okay. So let's look at some examples of using
this thing. So we can build a Python package using BuildMagic. In fact, this config file
is the one that I actually use to build and distribute BuildMagic. So it builds itself.
So it starts off by running Flake 8. It runs unit tests. And then if all that's passing,
it will build the documentation, upload it to GitHub pages.
And then last, it builds the wield file and then uploads that to PyPI. So, you know,
before I used to have a shell script that did all this. Now I just run BuildMagic dash C and
then the name of the file is release.yaml. And that's it. You know, I still use GitHub actions
for running unit tests for Python 3, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, and checking code quality and coverage
and that sort of thing. But this is the process for actually just uploading to PyPI when I'm
ready to push a release. So example two, this is something that I had to do when I was working
at a startup or it's based off of it. So I was responsible for maintaining open API specification
for RESTful API that we owned. And, you know, if anybody's familiar with swagger or open API,
it produces these docs for you that, you know, they don't look bad. I can show you what it looks
like here real quick. So you'll get a page that looks kind of like this. And, you know, you can
drop down on this. You can see, you know, an example request body, example responses,
and you get the idea. So the thing is my boss doesn't like that. He didn't like the way it looked
and liked the look of this other thing that I found out was called Slate, which is based in Ruby.
So, you know, now I have to figure out, okay, how do I convert from open API to Slate because I
don't want to write all the Slate docs from scratch. So there's a utility called Wittershins
that will handle the conversion, but it is an NPM package. And so I was like, I don't want to
install all of this stuff just for doing this, right? So what I'm doing here is I build
Docker images for Wittershins, for all of the Slate setup, everything I need. And that's what
I do in this first stage here is build my Docker images. And in the second stage, you know,
I just run the command to pull down the docs. And then because it actually gets pulled down as
oh, well, what it's doing is it gets pulled down all in one line. So I reformat it so it's at least
nice looking JSON. The third stage is when I run Wittershins. So, you know, that Docker image is
running NPM and stuff. And that converts it to a markdown file that Slate likes,
which then I need to pass it to Slate. And Slate is very particular about how the file system
is laid out and the names of files. But you can see here, you know, I'm able to take care of that
in just a few steps. And, you know, then I build my docs and get that back out. And, you know,
all this happened in multiple Docker containers. But in the end, you know, I'm able to get,
you know, just an index.html that looks like this. Make it a little bit bigger. All right. So this
is the exact same docs now just, you know, produced using Slate. You know, I can come down here and
I can see stuff. But, you know, one thing that's nice is I get the code snippets over here on the
side. So if I look at that, let's look at Python. You know, it's using requests to do a lot of this.
It's using requests to do a lot of this. So, you know, that's cool. And, yeah, I just did all that
with build magic just a few days ago. So all right. Last example. So for a little while,
I did some data science and data engineering work. And this example is an ML pipeline. So
if anybody has used, like, Apache Beam or if you've heard or used Metaflow or MLflow. Anybody
here an ML engineer? All right. Okay. Okay. If you use. Okay. So you kind of know what I'm talking
about here, then. You know, one issue I've seen with those tools, especially, like, I think it's
MLflow, you kind of have to build up all the code for the pipeline around the work the data
scientists are doing. So you're, like, training the model in the same file where you're doing the
pipeline, right? And so I was thinking, you know, about this. And I was like, well, you know,
with build magic, actually, I can separate the concerns there. And this is nice because I can,
you know, separately work on ETL, cleaning data, feature extraction, training the model,
and then deploying all separately from one another. And so I can have a data scientist
do their part. I can have data engineer worry just about ETL. And then, you know, have DevOps
or an ML engineer or somebody just worry about deployment, right? And then automate all of this
with build magic. So that's, you know, this is a very just, you know, simple example here. But
that's kind of what I'm doing here. So the first thing it does in this first stage is it downloads
the wine quality data set and then calls ETL.py. So in this case, ETL.py, all it's doing is it's
converting a CSV file to a feather file using PyArrow. And in the second stage is where I train
my model. So that's all handled inside train.py. And I pass it some input arguments, give it my
file name, I give it some parameters for the model, which is based in scikit-learn. And then
I get a pickle file out. And just to try it out, like, I GPG sign the model. So it's signed and
encrypted. So I guess in theory, you know, if you're uploading it to another machine, then at least,
you know, it's, you know, where it came from. So all that kind of being said, you know, there's a
different syntax going on here, right? So you might see, you know, I've got things like file name
and like these double curly braces. So there's kind of a templating notation here going on with
something I call runtime variables, where when I run build magic on the command line, I can specify,
you know, the name that I've templated out and then the variable that I want to substitute in at
runtime. So every time I run this, I, you know, I specify a new file name. And, you know, in the
command up here, I'm setting the date time. So that way, I have a timestamp of every time I'm
running this thing. So then, you know, the last stage here, I am removing the existing model.
And then copying over the new one, I verify it and decrypt it and then restart my server. So my
web server is just a fast API server that just is also running scikit-learn and then serves up my
model. So nice and easy. And I've separated the concerns of everybody involved along the way. So
that being said, you know, some takeaways from this that I hope you have got from this is that,
you know, build magic is going to help you automate tasks. And it's doing this by abstracting,
you know, the command execution from the underlying host machine. And hopefully it does this in a
better way than what you get with shell scripts and make files. So also, importantly, you know,
this is designed in a way that it can evolve along with you and help you work the way that
you want to work. So that being said, you know, build magic still, it's beta, it's still under
active development. I have a feature roadmap that, you know, I'm working on. And I could use some
help too. So, you know, if you're interested in open source software or are looking to get involved
with open source software and maybe you find this interesting, you know, please reach out. Here's
where you can find the project on GitHub, on PyPI. All the examples I showed today are in their own
repo called build magic examples. You can find the docs at, I've got kind of this emoji URL.
It's the hammersparkelrobot.y.at. So if you want to try that out, I mean, everything I've tried it
out on, it works except for LinkedIn. So, and that's not entirely true. It works on LinkedIn,
on the web, I think, but not mobile. But anyway, so thank you for putting up with listening to me.
And, you know, I can maybe take a few questions if there aren't any real quick.