Hello everyone, I'm Wayne Wharton and this is Great Snake Variation Programming with
Python Chess.
To start out, I just want to say how excited and great I am to be here with all of you
at PyTexas.
It's been a long time since I got to go to an in-person conference, it's been a long
time since I got to speak at an in-person conference, but I was at the 2019 PyTexas,
had a great time, and so I'm really happy after all of this to be back here with you.
And so you might all be wondering why this talk, Chess at a Python conference.
I promise you there's something here, and the main blame I would say falls on the Queen's
Gambit.
I don't know if anyone else watched, I was definitely one of those people who binge-watched
this during the pandemic and got very into online chess.
Now, I had played chess before as a kid.
Yes, that's me as a kid before the gray hair set in.
And I had done pretty well playing chess as a kid.
This is actually a picture of chess trophies that I asked my mom to send me for this presentation.
But most importantly, I learned how to beat my dad at chess using this book, which is
actually a great book.
I did play chess.
Highly recommend it.
I did finally accomplish that.
So I knew something about chess, but after about fifth grade, I had other interests,
and I didn't really play chess.
Much after that, I didn't really play seriously for about 16 years until the Queen's Gambit
came, and the pandemic hit, and all of a sudden I decided to dive back in.
So I created an account on Leechess, which is a free and open source tool, a free and
open source chess server.
It's a great thing if you want to play online with other people.
And I dove right in.
And when I say that, I really dove in.
So here's a little bit of stats.
So I started in November 2020, and that is at least the graph until July of 2021.
I played almost 1,700 Blitz games online.
And unfortunately, Leechess also tells you how much time you've spent on it, and mine
came out to over 19 days, which I did the math for this talk, is about an average of
30 minutes per day, every day since November 2020.
I can say sometimes it is more than that, and very often more than that.
So I really got back into playing chess.
I loved playing chess online.
Eventually I also got back into playing in-person chess at tournaments, which led to me having
this very hilarious reading graph where on this side you can see was the single rated
tournament I ever played as a kid, and I was rated 914 in 2004.
Then you can see a 16-year gap where I played no chess.
But the way they render it, for some reason, it has me steadily getting better at chess
over that time, despite playing no chess.
And then here is where I started playing chess in person, and basically after 1,700 Blitz
games online, I was able to make very rapid progress once I finally returned to playing
in person.
Eventually I started asking myself, can programming help me in training for chess, and it helped
me analyze my games.
So by day I am a machine learning engineer, and so when I was approaching this problem
I thought, well I have a lot of data.
I have almost 1,700 games on LeeChess, which is the account I told you about.
I have over 2,700 games on my chess.com account, which I did not mention until now.
So that's a lot of chess games, which in this case means a lot of data to analyze and maybe
some interesting things that I can learn.
And I was already inspired by some software tools that existed that I found useful.
One of them was this thing called Opening Tree.
So this will load your games from a given website and allow you to interactively explore
different openings that you've played, ways your opponents have responded.
It's a very useful tool, but I found that it couldn't always answer all the questions
that I had.
I wanted to go further, and so I decided how can I write a program that does things like this?
So I opened up PyPI, or as our keynote speaker called it, the magic shopping list of Python,
and thankfully I found what I was looking for, which was Python Chess, a chess library
for Python, which was exactly what I wanted.
And that is how this story started.
To give you an idea of how this talk is going to go, to start off I'm going to do a brief
history of chess and programming.
Then I'm going to dive into the API and usage of this library that I found and came to love
called Python Chess.
And finally I'm going to go into a little bit about the applications of Python Chess,
how I used it, some interesting ways I've seen other people use it.
And I do want to underline after all this that I think my main idea for this talk is
not to teach you something about chess, because some of you might be interested in chess and
some of you might not care, and this is a Python conference.
So what I really want you to take away in the end is that chess is just one interesting
problem, it's one interesting domain where we can apply Python, we can apply programming
principles, and that can teach us something even if you don't really care about knights
and rooks and haunts.
And to start off, that's why I want to give you a little bit of a brief history of chess
and programming, because I think there is a lot of background to say that chess as a
problem can teach us something about programming more generally.
It started off maybe not so well with this contraption in 1770, which was supposedly
a robot that could play chess by itself.
People at the time didn't know that there was actually someone sitting inside of it
manipulating this robot, and it made a grand tour of Europe and many places and defeated
some great chess players, and people didn't necessarily catch on.
And this does actually live on with some legacy in our current tech environment as the name
of, it also lives on as the name of an Amazon service, Amazon mechanical chart, which you
can use.
So a second figure in the history of computer science and programming who got into chess
was Alan Turing.
I'll keep going.
And in 1948, he wrote what is one of the first computer chess programs called Turochamp.
Co-wrote it, there was another person.
And the problem for Alan Turing was at the time there were no computers that could execute
the complexity of this program that he designed.
And so the only way that he could play it was to actually execute the algorithm on paper.
And so there's one reported game of him playing as the algorithm against a human where he's
actually writing out the calculations on paper.
It took about 30 minutes per move, which is not very efficient or probably very fun if
you're the human on the other side.
So he was maybe a little ahead of his time with this program.
Another big figure in computer science called Shannon was known to have a great interest
in computer chess.
He wrote a very influential paper on it and later designed a machine, a robot that could
play chess.
Due to the technical limitations of the time, this machine you see here, it can only handle
positions of up to six pieces due to the computational complexity, but still was quite an accomplishment.
And he has a quote from this paper that I really liked as I was putting this talk together.
He was talking about the problem of chess programming.
He said, perhaps it's not of practical importance, but he basically thought by tackling this
problem of programming chess, maybe we can make some headway toward larger problems.
And he had in mind big AI problems of translation and other things.
But I think that this is a really fascinating idea that by learning something about this
domain, by tackling this, we can go on to learn maybe bigger, better things.
So another big figure in computer science, Ken Thompson, who created Unix later in his
career, would co-create a language called Go.
In the 70s, he was working at Bell Labs and he came up with the software for this contraption
called Bell in 1972.
And this is one of the early champions of computer software championships at the time.
And finally, I don't think I could complete my historical review of chess and programming
without mentioning this big event in 1997 when IBM built this machine called Deep Blue
and it finally defeated Garry Kasparov, who at the time was the world chess champion.
This was the first time that a machine had defeated the human champion of chess.
So this was kind of a big turning point in chess and programming and technology.
So that's a little bit of an idea of the history of how chess has influenced programming and
drawn the interest of some people who went on to do or were doing great things in general
programming and computer science.
So right out of the way, we'll get into this library.
How can you do things with chess using Python?
I mentioned that there's some program principles that you can learn by looking at this library
and I want to mention a few of them in particular.
So data parsing, object-oriented programming, very important, data structures and algorithms,
pattern patterns, and finally communication protocols.
I'm going to go through examples of how you can see all these things in the Python Chess
Library and basically how you can learn to use it by looking at these different principles.
So if you've done data parsing in Python before, you've probably used Pandas and you know that
it provides a nice API for taking a structured data set, for example a CSP, you can read
it in and you can get it as a data frame which then has a nice API to allow you to further
manipulate the data, do any of the calculations that you want to do.
Chess has a similar thing.
It has structured data in this form which is called PGN.
That was a standard that was put together way back in the day in 1994 as a portable
protocol for sharing chess games and it lives on until today.
This is the main format in which chess games are represented for processing and similar
to how Pandas has the ability to read a CSV, the Python Chess Library allows you to read
in a PGN file.
So here you can see if you have a PGN you can read it in and you get a game object and
that is going to allow you to do further analysis.
So the next question might be what is the game object and that leads us into the next
topic which is object oriented programming and some of you may have once been subjected
to programming interviews that make you do these kinds of problems.
Maybe you had to influence chess in the stress of a 30 minute interview or maybe some other
kind of object oriented game.
So in this case chess can be thought of as several classes.
So an important one is piece, obviously move, board and game.
These are all different classes with different functionalities that can help us represent
chess as a whole.
So I'm going to go through these classes.
Some of them are fairly simple, some of them are fairly complex and explain basically their
APIs in the Python Chess Library and some of the interesting methods.
So a piece is fairly simple.
A piece just has a piece type and a color.
It's essentially a data class that is holding these two things and representing them.
A move is similarly fairly simple.
A piece just has the square you're moving from, the square you're moving to and then
the piece you might be promoting to.
That's in the case of moving a pawn, you can turn a pawn into a queen sometimes so you
want to keep track of that.
And here it's referring to squares and in this library squares are also represented
fairly simply.
The square type is just an integer type and all of the 64 squares on a standard chess
board are just assigned to unique integers.
So they can be referred to 0 to 63.
So then we get to board.
And board is definitely the most complex class in the whole library and you'll usually see
that in chess programming.
Most of the functionality will be represented on the board.
And some of the things that it allows you to do is move generation, calculation of whether
or not the particular position has completed the game, a bunch of stuff is packed into
board and I looked at it in the library, the board class has over 2300 lines of Python
so it's a whopper, it's a huge class.
There's probably something you could say about that but that would probably be a whole
other talk.
But most of the functionality lives in this class.
There are a lot of interesting methods and I just picked out a few that I thought were
useful or interesting properties and methods of board.
So some of the simple ones, you can check whose turn is it, you can check what move
you're on, which full move number is what we think of as move, so one, white will move,
black will move, two, white will move, black will move again, and so on.
So these things are represented on the board class.
This one is outcome and this actually represents a huge percentage of that 2300 lines because
calculating whether a chess game is over is actually extremely complex.
Obviously most people know about checkmate, stalemate, but there's all sorts of rules
of three-fold repetition, so if you reach the same position three times, someone can
claim a draw and calculating that actually is pretty complex, you have to go back through
all the positions and see if it's been repeated.
So this is a real big part of the complexity of programming a chess representation is getting
this right and knowing whether the game is over and how it finished.
And these are some of the ones I picked out that I think are just funny or interesting.
There's checkers, which does not do what you think it does.
I really thought this was an implementation where you could just call this and all of
a sudden you're playing checkers, not chess.
That's not what it is.
It's just finding all the pieces that are currently putting your king in check, which
is kind of an interesting problem.
And then the other one I thought was kind of cool was is irreversible so you can pass
in a move and it'll tell you if that's the kind of move that you can't undo.
So in the case of normal chess, moving your pawns forward, you can't undo that because
they don't move backward.
There's some things around if you move your king, you won't be able to castle.
So this is another interesting one where there's a lot of domain-specific logic in there to
say, okay, is this a move that someone's going to be able to take back or not?
So I mentioned data structures and algorithms.
And when we look into the classes that are used to implement the chess functionality
in this library, we can see the use of some common data structures and algorithms.
So for example, the moves that are made are represented as a stack, and the board class
provides common methods, pop, peek, push, and you can also clear the stack.
And if you look into the implementation of one of these methods, it's also interesting
because it's actually holding two stacks on the class.
There's a stack of moves.
And then if you look at the implementation, there's also an internal stack of the board
representation after that move so that in processing, you can know not only the moves
that were made, but you can also go back through and see the resulting positions.
And the game class is actually a tree of moves.
So there's a game node, and they can point to various other game nodes, and that's how
you represent a game, which is a very flexible model and useful because when you think of
a game, you might think just a set of moves and then why isn't it a list or a linked list
or something.
But in chess games, people often want to add variations.
So then one move maybe could be followed by another move, but then there's a variation
that someone wants to consider.
And so that's how you get this tree structure.
Off of each move, there could be several possibilities.
So the game is represented as a tree of nodes.
And this is the basic of a game node.
It has a pointer up to its parent and then a list of variations, which in the general
tree structure would be the children.
And there are also some interesting methods on this that allow you to reverse the tree
in different ways.
So game would give you the overall game, which means going all the way back up to the root
end, which is kind of the reverse.
So it's going to follow all the way to the end of the tree down the main line.
And in that case, this means that it's going to take the first child of each node.
And the main line method also gives you an interval of all the nodes basically between
this node and the end.
So those are just some methods that are useful in traversing this particular tree, the game
tree, in a useful way.
And another thing I mentioned was design patterns.
There's going to be a whole lot of talk about this later.
But there is a design pattern in this library that I thought was pretty cool.
It's the visitor pattern.
So the visitor pattern is basically a way to specify a function that you want to run
on each element of a data structure, but you don't want to add that to the class.
So in this case, we have our game nodes, but maybe we don't want to have to modify game
node for every operation we might want to do on the node.
In this case, there's a visitor class.
And what the visitor class allows you to do is specify for each node I want to run a particular
function.
And there's one simple example that's built into the library, and this is like string
exporter.
So this is the visitor.
The visit move method is basically a method that's called on every move in the tree.
And in this case, it's basically just for each move creating a string representation
of that and appending that on to basically a running string that it's keeping.
Another I found this very interesting is the use of standard communication protocols, which
in general programming, I would say it's very useful if you've ever had to collect metrics.
You might have used statsd, which allows you to basically collect metrics and send them
on to Datadog or any other collector in a very standardized way.
One that's come up in my own work very recently is this library called case-serve, which provides
a standard interface for getting model predictions, regardless of the underlying implementation
of the model.
These are like a couple of standard protocols.
I think in programming, we can agree that this is like a super important thing, and
in chess it's no different.
So in the chess world, there's a con protocol for communicating with chess engines, which
means that if you want to write a program that talks to an engine, you don't have to
write a different program for engine A or engine B.
Someone came up with a standard protocol, and it turns out it's very Unix-y, which
is kind of funny, but all the communication goes over standard in and standard out in
a text, and that's kind of the protocol.
It's called UCI, and it's a fairly complex spec.
This is like one example.
This is the go command, and this is used to actually run the engine.
There's a lot of different options, a lot of parameters, and you can imagine that if
you had to implement a client for this, that might get very cumbersome, and you probably
wouldn't want to do it if you're just playing around and want to run a chess engine.
The cool thing is Python chess also has an interface for interacting with any chess engine
over this standard UCI protocol, so this snippet is an example of basically starting out with
Stockfish, which is a commonly used engine, and then allowing it to play a game of chess
against itself, giving it a limit of 100 milliseconds per move.
I shall also mention that Stockfish is also a free-note resource software, which is super
cool.
It's a super, super powerful chess engine, and I wanted to go back to this kind of historical
point, which is in 1997, when Deep Blue beat Garry Kasparov.
This was a huge historical moment requiring years and years of effort by a huge team of
people.
I just think it's really cool that in 2022, through open-source software, you can now
access an engine that's way more powerful than Deep Blue on your laptop using these
open-source tools, so Python, Python Chess, and Stockfish.
I think that's a really cool thing, and kind of shows the power of technology and how much
it's grown.
This is the class that is in the Python Chess library that provides you access to an engine,
and it has two main methods.
It has play and analyze, which do slightly different things.
Play is basically going to play the board that you pass it.
Analyze is slightly more flexible, so you can ask for multiple moves, and it'll basically
just return a dictionary of information.
After going through the internals of the library, the API, how to use it, I wanted to end by
going through two applications of what you might want to do with this library.
I will say this is the more like chessy part of the talk, but I hope that it'll also be
interesting to everyone.
We'll start with an application that I wrote myself, and it has to do with opening training.
Basically, in chess, there's a concept of an opening book.
It's basically, if my opponent plays X, I'm going to play Y to any various depth.
You always play E4 as your first move, things like that.
As an example, this is a representation of one, don't tell anyone my opponent's.
This is like the beginning of my opening book, so I might always play B3 as white.
This has various responses.
They can make various responses I would make back.
It's basically this tree of moves that shows what I would play in a given position, starting
from move one.
As you play more games, as I play more games, the questions I want to ask myself are, how
far am I making it in before I end up out of the book, as they say.
You're having to play on your own with no preparation.
When I reach those positions, am I the one messing it up?
Am I forgetting the moves I should have studied, or is my opponent playing something unexpected?
Maybe, what does the engine think about that?
Am I getting out of book because my opponent is playing terrible moves?
Then maybe I don't need to study those moves because they're obviously bad.
These are a bunch of the questions I had.
Like I said, I had a lot of data to work with in my games, so I wanted to do some analysis.
I ended up with an implementation that basically uses two classes of visitors.
It uses the base visitor from Pipe Out Chess.
This one is a fairly simple implementation.
Basically, on each move, it's getting two things and it's storing them.
It's getting the fen, which is a representation of the position, a unique representation of
the position, and then the move that was made in that position.
This is basically going over my whole opening book and saying, at each position, what move
can be made?
Those moves are represented as a set because in some positions, usually you'd want to have
only one move in each position for your opening book, but obviously your opponent could play
many different moves.
This visitor will go through my whole opening book, which is represented as a PGN and collects
those things.
Once he collects all those things, this is kind of the representation I get, which is
what I wanted.
It's a dictionary that maps keys that are positions to a set of moves.
This is the same example I showed before.
At the start, I will always play B3, hence there's only one move in the set.
The position after that is my opponent's move.
Many of those are in my opening book, so that's the second set you see there and so on through
all the positions that I have represented.
Once I have that, I create another visitor that basically will go over a set of games
and determine at what point in the game did I reach a position that's not in that dictionary.
I've collected from my opening book all the positions that I, in theory, should have studied
and learned what to play here.
Now I go through all my games and then I take the fan, which is the position and the move
and say, if this position is in this dictionary I just created, is the move in the set of
moves or is it not?
If it's not, then I add it to this list basically of divergences and over a series of games
you can collect many of these divergences.
Once I run this visitor on a set of games, you would end up with something like this,
which is a list of metadata about places where I ended up outside of my opening preparation.
For the first one you can see was my fault, so I played as white and on the third move
I played D4.
In my preparation, I was supposed to have learned to play D2, but then the second example
I see is where my opponent diverged, so they played a move that I never expected.
Maybe that's something you want to go study.
Once you create a bunch of these for, say, 1700 blitz games, you can start to aggregate
them.
You can start to get a sense of how far on average you are in the game, how often am
I the one messing up versus my opponent, things like that.
This is pretty useful if you're working on learning a chess opening and you want to figure
out how are you doing and actually trying to learn that and remember the moves you're
supposed to play.
I have a second application, which I think is very interesting, and it's the application
of chess puzzle generation, which before all these tools, software tools, it was pretty
hard.
You had to do a main move, you had to review a game, you had to say, okay, is this an interesting
game?
By some metric, and then you had to go through and say, okay, did the people play this correctly
and kind of find a puzzle through a very manual inspection.
But it turns out the criteria for a puzzle can be generalized, and for a chess puzzle,
you want to basically find a position where one side's chances shift very dramatically.
Usually someone has made a mistake and now someone can take advantage.
In order to take advantage, that player has to play a series of moves where they only
have one move to play, because otherwise, if there's a lot of moves, you can't really
solve the puzzle.
There might be like five solutions and then it's really not that interesting.
After that series of moves, you have to have a measurable outcome, so that might need to
checkmate Stanley or the game of material.
This is an example of a chess puzzle that I just looked at this morning.
I'm a little on time, so I'll run through it quickly, but basically, I won't explain
all the chess logic, but black here can take the rook, which is what I did.
Now white has to take back the rook, because otherwise they'll be down rook.
They have no choice.
But that means black can play the knight, which executes a classic tactic, and then
there's a fork.
In this position, the rook now can't protect from bishop.
The rook has to go somewhere else or be captured by the knight.
Now the knight captures the bishop and black is up a piece.
This is an example of a puzzle.
In this series of moves, there's really only one move for black and one move for white
in order to arrive at this result.
There's a really cool open source tool called Chess Puzzle Maker that basically puts these
criteria into an algorithm that's expressed in Python, and it uses Python Chess.
How is it using Python Chess to find these puzzles?
There's really two functionalities that I wanted to look at.
This is how it finds puzzles, and I basically just wanted to show that here it's using the
game, it's traversing the game tree, it's using some of the methods that I mentioned
that are important in the Python Chess API to basically go through the game and examine
the positions.
It's also using the engine protocol to communicate with Stockfish in order to evaluate the positions
and get the best moves.
To wrap it up, I think Python Chess is a super cool library.
I hope that you learned something, maybe not only about chess, but about Python and programming.
And as my final slide, I wanted to show a simple program.
So this is using Python Chess to play just two moves.
This is an opening C4, G6.
This is known as the Great Snake Variation, and I just thought it was a nice way to show
that Python and chess can go well together.
Thank you.
My Twitter is where you can find me.
If you want to find me on chess, there's my account.
You can send me a challenge.
Thank you all.