Thank you all for having me.
Thank you to the PyTexas organizers for having me.
Yes, so my first talk was at PyTexas in 2013 in College Station, and I think my first conference
was actually PyTexas in 2010, it was in Waco at the time.
So it's nice to be here at another PyTexas, and also nice to be keynoting.
So here on the slide, there are some details about me.
So the talk is called Python Community Growth, and that's what I'll be focusing on.
Since I've become active in the Python community, I have felt that one of the best ways that
I can make a contribution to the community was by helping to grow the contributor base
for the community.
And so the first talk that I gave in 2013 was somewhat related to that.
The content of the talk was more about sort of things you could do with Python as spreadsheets
and how that could draw non-developers into the Python community, and then those people
could become future contributors.
So that's kind of been a running theme, sometimes a less obvious theme in the different talks
that I've done in my community activity.
So currently, I'm an engineer at RevSys, I'll talk a little bit about that more later.
It's a Django shop, and we do a lot of interesting things.
Before I was a Python developer, I was an accountant and university instructor and got
an MBA.
I taught accounting in English and other things in a couple of different countries, well,
two different countries, here in Texas and in China.
And so once I decided the accounting business-y thing was not what I was going to do anymore,
I made a transition into software development.
So there are other things that I do as well, and you can see here on my slides my name
and then also my Twitter handle was probably the best way to reach me.
So among other things, I'm also a DjangoCon US organizer, I've done that since 2016.
I'm also the Defna North American Ambassador.
Defna is the Django Events Foundation North America, that is a nonprofit that is tasked
with putting on DjangoCon US.
One of the things that I do as the Defna North American Ambassador is to let people know,
A, that Defna exists because it's a relatively new organization, I think only been around
since 2014.
The 2015 DjangoCon US was the first Defna DjangoCon, and that was here in Austin, but
the second key part of that is letting people know that DjangoCon US can take place in any
North American city, and so the next time a CFP goes out, and I'll be reaching out to
people when that happens, people from your city can put together a CFP and try to have
DjangoCon US hosted in your North American city, so that is an important thing to know.
That's the Twitter handle for Defnado, or you can go to Defna.org to get more information
about the organization and what they do.
I talked about my company RevSys, and one of the reasons I'm talking about this is because,
and this isn't a, my company sponsored this type of talk, it's more a matter of, it relates
to the content of my talk, we're a small company, there are eight of us total, and then, so
on the prior slide, I talked about some of the stuff that I do, so of the remaining seven
people, we have all these things, so the DSF founder and the person who helped make Django
open source, so Jacob Kaplan-Moss, if you know that name, two former Django software
foundation presidents, so Jacob Kaplan-Moss and Frank Wiles, who is our, the president
of RevSys, and Kaplan-Moss is one of the other founders, two former DjangoCon US chairs,
there are two people who have chaired DjangoCon US in the past, but one of the founders of
Defna and his former president, Jeff, who is one of our partners, and Jeff is also currently
one of the Python Software Foundation directors, and then there's Catherine, and so Catherine
doesn't have sort of a fancy title or whatnot, but over the course of the last, I know several
years, Catherine has made a lot of things work in the background for DjangoCon US and
for Defna, for DjangoCon US and for Defna and for the DSF, she's sort of our chief admin
person at RevSys, and so at one point, the RevSys president was the DSF president, and
so Catherine helped a lot of stuff there, and as members of RevSys have been working
on organizing DjangoCon US, Catherine has also helped a lot of stuff with Defna, so
I point these things out about my company because one of the reasons I work with this
group is because we're all sort of of the same mind or of a similar mind as far as
community contributions and things of that nature, so one of the key points of the talk
here is that Python itself and Django, which I'm fairly involved in the Django community,
so that comes up a lot, but Django is itself written in Python, so Python is Django, or
Django is Python, but Python is Django, but both are open source projects, and what that
means is that they are built by volunteers, people in their free time doing all sorts
of extra work to make these things happen, but in a situation like that, more contributors
are always needed, there's always more help needed, more people working on a project or
on a process makes that process easier, more hands light in the load, as they say, and
so that's one of the reasons I've tried to focus on trying to grow the contributor base
of the Python community, and it's important to note that contributions aren't just code,
often in a developer community there's a tendency to think that if someone's going to contribute
to Python or to Django or to something else, another project, that it's all just about
writing code or adding new features and that sort of thing, those things are useful, those
things are important, but there's much more to it than that documentation and that sort
of thing. Conference organization, all the different legal issues that come up with defending
the IP of both Python and Django and other things, fundraising, if you talk to any of
the conference organizers, for instance, the people you see here in the orange shirts for
organizing PyTexas, or if you attend a meetup in your local area or your hometown, if you
talk to a meetup organizer, they will tell you that there are all sorts of things that
need to be done, and so there are a number of different contributions that need to be
made to the community, especially as Python has become such a large project, so there
are lots of things that are needed beyond just code, and so you need help, there's more
help that's needed, but then the question is where is that help going to come from?
So when you look at people who might be actual contributors, you have two necessary conditions
for potential contributors. One is they have to be people who find some value in Python,
people who actually use Python and find some value in it. I'll probably just use the term
Pythonistas throughout my talk, but anybody who uses Python and gets value from it and
realizes, hey, this is good, this helps me, this is of some benefit, but then the second
condition, which is a little more the focus of this first part of the talk, is that those
people actually have to feel like they're included in the community, they have to feel
like they're members of the community, and this is important, these two necessary conditions.
The first condition is necessary, but not sufficient in the mathematical parlance. Someone
can use Python and get all sorts of benefit from it, but they don't have to interact with
the rest of us. They don't have to actually make any contributions to the Python community
if they don't want to. They can just use Python, benefit from it, and then go on about their
day. That second part, that a potential contributor has to feel like they're a part of our community
is very important, and I think that's someplace where we can make some improvement.
When we look at people who use Python, we've got this, what I call the Python use spectrum,
and so this talk, I'm sort of one of those people who's always kind of working on talks
and that sort of thing, so I guess I probably started working on this talk in 2013, technically.
The idea is to draw from that, but certain chunks of it come from a keynote that I gave
at PyGotham in 2019, and that talk was focused more specifically on this, the Python use
spectrum. I'll be mentioning some things from that here in this talk, and you can find that
PyGotham 2019 keynote, it's on YouTube, if you want more details about that specific
area. But this idea to me is important because you have a wide range of people who use Python,
and so I've created this sort of spectrum to describe them, so on one end you've got
programming, was it my left, your left, also your left? Mirrors are hard. So on the left
you've got programming, and on the far right you've got software engineering, so these
are the users of Python, and everyone who uses Python, they're there. So everyone who
uses Python in some way or gets some value or benefit from Python falls somewhere in
this spectrum, and so here we've got some definitions. So what these look at are the
different ways that people use code. So first bullet point, so who writes the code? For
programmers, usually the code is written by individuals, software engineering, the code
is often written in teams. Who's using the code? In programming, it's often just the
author, someone's writing code for themselves, so the author of the code is using it. In
software engineering, you're usually writing code to be used by other people, not the individual
people who write the code themselves. When does the code run or how is it run? In the
programming context, you've probably got somebody who's writing code that is being run while
they're looking at it. The code is being run with supervision, and in the software engineering
context the code is designed to be able to run in isolation. You don't want to have to
write code and then deploy it and then just sit and watch it and make sure it works. In
the programming context, the primary product is the output of the code. So if you're writing
code for yourself to run with your supervision, you don't really care about the code, you
care about the output of the code. Whereas in the software engineering context, the code
itself is the actual output, that's the actual product. And then your motivations, why you're
writing this code. In the programming context, you're writing the code for utility, you're
writing code that would do something for you, and that's your primary concern. Whereas in the
software engineering context, you're writing code because that's your profession, that's your
job. And so again, dig back the spectrum, and everyone who uses Python falls somewhere along
the spectrum. Some people start at the programming end and stay there because they don't have any
need to go any further. Other people, well, everyone starts at the programming end, but some
people aspire to get to the software engineering end and stay there and to advance their skills
there. But again, everyone who uses Python falls along the spectrum. So the big problem that I
see is that our community culture is heavily biased towards software engineering, and that creates
an issue where software engineering, that approach is seen as the only way to actually do
programming, the only way to actually write code, the correct way to write code, and that
is true in some cases, but for other people who have different contexts, you don't need all of
the software engineering tools and accoutrements and details that software engineers use. So why
is that important? This bias towards software engineering often manifests itself as a bias
against programming, and again, our community culture is often very heavily influenced by the
software engineering approach. And as we've seen, Python has grown very quickly in data science,
and data science is probably the biggest, sort of most noteworthy area of growth, but there are
lots of other areas where Python has grown that aren't software engineering. There are lots of
people who aren't data scientists and don't think of themselves as data scientists, but they've
found that Python is helpful to them, the syntax is clear and straightforward, and people have
found, oh, I can use this code to make my life better, and I can write five, ten lines of code,
and it makes something better for me, and I can just go on with my day. But again, a lot of our
community culture is heavily selected towards software engineering, and that's as if that is
the one true way to do things. And so, we've got these different people who are using Python,
and they're all, they could all be potentially contributing to software engineering, so these
people who exist along the spectrum, anyone along the spectrum could be contributing to Python,
but because of the software engineering bias, we often end up pushing away people who aren't
actually software engineers, but the software engineers aren't a small portion of the community,
but software engineers are no longer as large a percentage of the community as they once were,
and that's really kind of a good thing, because Python is so helpful to so many people who aren't,
you know, who don't think of themselves as real programmers or a professional, you know, I don't
want to get a degree in computer science and blah, blah, blah. Well, no, you don't have to, you can,
you can, you know, read, automate the boring things with Python, or you can find a blog post or two
that will let you solve a particular problem that you have in Python, and so you don't need, you
don't need testing and, you know, CI and Docker and Git, you might not need any of those things,
you can just write your 12 lines of Python or your 150 lines of Python and ta-da, problem solved,
and you'll go on and live your better life. And so, the issue is we are sometimes pushing non-software
engineers away from the community. So, we go back to those two conditions of people who could
contribute, people who find value in Python, and people who feel like they're members of our
community. Well, if we've got people who are using Python that we're pushing away from the
community, then we're minimizing our contributor base. So, one of the things that stood out to me,
in Python 2019, our KM here, this is Russell Keith McGee, a former Django Software Foundation
president and someone who has done a lot of work in the area of open source sustainability and
trying to sort of figure out how do we make open source development a sustainable thing,
how do we keep it going and moving. I've got some screenshots here from his talk,
but the talk covered a number of different things, but the things I'm going to focus on
here are how do we get more support, more contributors for our community. And so,
two of the things he points out here are, you know, paying, you can pay professionals to support
a project, and you also want to try to build a team with contribution skills that are beyond
code. So, the earlier slide that I had where we talked about some of the different things,
the different types of contributions that are needed beyond code, there's some situations where
you can pay people to do that stuff, people who have those skills, and you also, again,
in building this team of contributors, you want to bring as many people with those different skills
into our community as contributors as possible, not just developers. So, I'll go through these
sort of a little quickly, but these are screenshots from Russell's talk in 2019. When money makes
things happen, expertise costs. And so, if you want people who know how to do conference
organizing or fundraising or the different legal things that are needed to make the PSF or the DSF
or a definite valid nonprofit so that people can contribute to them or any sort of marketing
information or what have you, people who have that expertise want to be paid for that expertise.
Project management, UX, UI, UX design, all these other things that are related to any sort of
software project but aren't just directly writing code, who organize the events, legal advice,
all these sorts of things. So, who does all this stuff? We need people who do these things.
This last point, who makes strategic deals? I know over several years, there has been a
fundraising thing with Humble Bundle to help raise funds for the PSF. Someone had to make that deal.
It might have been a developer, but people with CS degrees or people who are professional
software engineers aren't always the best at peopling or doing strategic business deals and
things of that nature. There's a difference between code optimization and fundraising and
making strategic business deals. So, those people are needed. And another important point here is
that these people who have these different skills, let's just say that money fell from the sky and
Google decided to just give the PSF $100 million. Let's just say $500 million, just a big number.
A whole bunch of money to do whatever the PSF wants. Well, these skilled professionals, they
have options. They can work with other people. So, the PSF's $100 million is the same as another
people's $100 million. So, why would I work with this set of people versus that set of people?
This goes back to the idea of the conditions you need for people to be contributors. People who are
getting value from Python and also people who feel like they're members of our community. So,
if you have people who have these skills that we need and are members of our community and they
feel like they're members of our community, then when there's a choice of, okay, well, I can get
paid $100,000 a year to do this thing for Python or to do it for Apple. Well, I'm a Pythonista. I'll
take the PSF's $100,000 and I'll keep my iPhone and use my Apple stuff, but I'm going to go work
with these people because I'm part of that community. Those are my people. I'm going to work
with them. And so, this idea of making sure that we are including potential contributors in our
community, it resonates because it's something that makes decisions as far as how things happen
and how things don't happen. So, how do we make this happen? This idea of making sure that we're
including people in our community and making them feel that they're members of the community. So,
here we get into the scolity portion, slightly scolity portion of the talk. The idea of senior
engineers needing to be better. So, in many cases, I talked before about the Python spectrum and how
software engineering tends to heavily influence our community culture. So, within that, our more
senior software engineers tend to have an even larger influence on our community culture. Some
of that is because they are the people, when people come in and they're looking for expertise
on, oh, well, how do I do this thing with Python or how do I make Python do what I want, they will
often try to, you would want to talk to an expert. You wouldn't want to talk to a novice. You wouldn't
want to talk to an expert. And so, those are often the first people they interact with. But then the
other issue is, as we have new software engineers even coming into the community, more junior software
engineers, those people are going to be influenced by the senior software engineers that they work
with. And so, you've got this sort of outsized impact that the more senior software engineers have
on our community and the community culture. And as such, since they're having that outsized impact,
they also bear a larger burden of responsibility as far as improving our community culture and
helping to make sure that we can have as wide a range of contributors as possible.
And with that, we start to look at our local communities. And so, the reality is, when people
encounter Python, you know, for the first time, they're much more likely to encounter Python or
the Python community at a local meetup than they are at, say, at PyCon or PyTexas or DjangoCon US.
So, to use an analogy, that might not seem flattering, but it's accurate, but it's not
might not seem flattering, but it's accurate. Local meetup organizers are basically sort of
like the Walmart greeters of the Python community. Again, for many people, the first time you actually
encounter another Pythonista is going to be at a local meetup. Now, you can just go to Python.org
and download Python or whatever, or you can, you know, use the package manager on your distro of
choice, or you can use Homebrew on your Mac or whatever. You can download Python and use it
without talking to anybody. But if you actually want to get some help with Python and interact
with other Python people, you're probably not going to think, okay, I'm trying to write this
Python program. I used to be an accountant, so I use a spreadsheet example. I'm trying to write
this Python code that will import this stuff from a spreadsheet and process it. How do I do that?
You know, I'm going to go to PyCon US and ask somebody. That's what I'll do. That seems like
the best way. Well, no. Unless you happen to live in the city where PyCon US is happening,
this year, Salt Lake City, you're probably not going to do that. You're probably going to look
for your local Python meetup and talk to someone there and get some help from some of those people.
But the people who organize our local Python meetups are generally often our more senior
engineers. There are very few people who started learning Python like three months ago and decide,
I'm going to organize a Python meetup. It could happen, but it generally doesn't. It's usually
done by people who are more experienced Python developers. So our senior engineers are often the
people who organize these local meetups, which are the first point of contact with non-Pythonistas
and the Python community. And as a result, those senior engineers often shape this culture that
happens in these meetups. So what's happening in your local meetups? Are you having a space
that is like a cool place for other senior Python developers to hang out? Or are you creating a
space where new people are welcomed and included in the community? So finding a space and having
a speaker and finding food, those are all great things in a meetup. Literally everybody likes
to go to a meetup where there's food. That always works out well. But there's more to it than just
that. And there is sometimes a tendency to maybe optimize the meetup more towards, and you get a
certain amount of unconscious bias. There's a tendency to sometimes optimize a meetup where
you as a senior Python developer are comfortable, and other senior Python developers that you know
were also comfortable in this space, and people who aren't as senior might feel left out.
Excuse me. People who aren't senior might feel left out. Or people who aren't even trying to
pursue a software engineering path might feel left out. People who just want to use Python
to solve their individual problems. But again, these local meetups, our local community activities
are the first contact with the rest of the non-Python community. And those community cultures
tend to be shaped fairly heavily by Python senior engineers. And again, more of this burden of
responsibility falls on these people. And it's important to try to make sure that your meetup
and your meetup culture is as welcoming as possible. Because otherwise we'll miss out on
a lot of new potential contributors. So we've got sort of a new criteria for senior developer.
It seems like traditionally or in the past, senior developer was seen as someone who
writes really good Python code. Or someone who knows how to architect software and has all sorts
of advanced Python skills and abilities. And that's important. But I'll add a few more points
here. As a senior developer, you should be someone who's able to advance the skills of a more junior
developer. And if you're someone who thinks, well, I'm a senior developer because I can write Python
really well and I can architect these things and write really complex software, I don't need to
interact with more junior people or help them advance. That's the intellectual equivalent of,
well, it works on my machine. Which I think we have all learned is really an anti-pattern.
Especially as a software engineer, because if it works on your machine, well, the whole point of
the code is to have it work somewhere else. So you're sort of doing yourself a disservice.
It might seem like a good thing, but it's not really working in your favor. So instead of a
senior developer being, and I'm using developer and engineer interchangeably here, instead of a
senior developer being someone who just sort of is able to write code really well on their own
or interact well with other senior developers, another necessary criteria of a senior developer
is that you should be able to help advance the skills of a more junior developer. And if you
can't or won't do that, you might need to senior a little bit better. So that's something to consider.
But also, a senior developer should be able to retain junior developers as they advance.
So if you're in a situation where, and I know some people will think, well, hold on, Kojo.
I'm a software developer. I'm not HR. I'm not the chief people person or whatever. But hear me out.
If you are someone, you're working with more junior developers and you're helping them advance
their skills, but then once they're advanced, they're like, okay, I've dealt with you as long
as I can. I've got to get away from you. Are you really senioring well? And so if you're not
doing both of these things, if you're not helping the more junior developers around your advance,
but you're also not creating an environment that they want to stay in and that they want to
continue to be a part of, you may need to reconsider some of your senioring options.
This comes up especially in light of the talk that we hear about so many people,
the shortage of software engineers and people not being able to find enough software engineers and
I can't find a good developer and that sort of thing. One of the simple solutions is, well,
if you can't find quote unquote good developers, perhaps make a good developer. And if you
are not able to help a less experienced developer become a better developer,
maybe you're not as senior as you thought. Those are the parts that nobody really likes to hear,
but the truth is what it is. This last point here is on less money. So if you're a senior
developer and you're helping advance your junior developers and you're getting to a point where
if you've got a senior developer here and a junior developer here, they should be moving to a
situation where they're becoming more of a peer. And this is, I think, should be one of the goals
for a senior developer. Now if someone shows up and says, oh, semi-junior developer, former
junior developer, I see you now become a senior developer and you're being paid X. I will pay you
1.5 X. Well, a lot of people are going to leave you in that situation. It's not personal. But if
someone shows up with a truck full of money, people may leave your organization. So regardless
of how good a job you're doing at helping your juniors advance or helping them, creating a
positive culture for you, if someone shows up and just throws bags of money at them, they're going
to leave. You don't take that personally. You've done your job as a senior well, if that happens.
Let me rephrase that. You have done your job well as a senior if you've had a more junior
developer join your organization, they have advanced their skills in your organization,
and then someone comes and throws a small bag of money at them and they're like, no,
I mean, that's cool, but I'm going to stay with my people because I've learned here, I've grown here,
I enjoy where I am. So for 1.1 X, I'm not going anywhere because I like my team, I like my people,
I know I'm going to get better here. 1.5 X, I might leave these people. 2 X, well, yeah,
you might have to go. If you've done your job really well as a senior developer,
your more junior developer advances, somebody offers them 2 X and they're like, okay, I'm leaving
and Andy's coming with me. We're both going to get 2 X. But these are, I think, things that
our more senior developers should be considering, partially to help improve the community culture,
but also these more junior developers are also people who are in that potential
contributor pipeline. So the more their skills advance, the more they're able to become,
the more likely they are to become potential contributors because they're already invested,
they already understand the value of Python because they're working in the field,
and they already feel like a part of the community. But as their skills advance,
they're better able to contribute, but then they are also able to become those people who are
closer to the senior end of the spectrum, who are more experienced developers, who are able to help
shape that community culture. So now instead of you being solo senior developer who's trying to
senior better, now you've brought along someone else, now you have another senior developer or
another more senior developer to help you with those things. So you ease the burden on yourself.
So instead of me just saying, you know, instead of me just saying, you know, senior better,
and you know, hey senior developers, get better, I tried to offer some, there's an idea that I have,
and this is something that I discussed with my own team. It's one of the reasons I talked about
my team so much earlier. One of the things that I discussed with my team, so I'm the newest member
at RevSys, and I am probably our least experienced developer. And so there's a lot of back and forth
as far as transferring information from my more experienced team members to myself. I mean, so I
have like a weekly meeting with our president just to sort of ask questions and, you know, discuss
things of that nature. One of the things, two things that have come up really, this solution
to an unknown problem. One of the things that junior developers often run into is that a senior
developer will say, okay, we're going to use this. We're going to use this tool and just, you know,
use it. I mean, the junior developer doesn't understand why. The reason the senior developer
is using that tool is because it is solving a problem that the senior developer has run into,
but the junior developer has never encountered. And so this point about junior versus senior,
the difference between, and this is the key difference between a senior developer and a
junior developer. That's the difference. A senior developer has bumped their head against problems
that a junior developer has never encountered. And at some point, they've bumped their head against
them enough where they've had to either devise a situation or devise a solution or find a solution
or come up with some set of processes. But the junior developer, having never seen that problem,
doesn't understand what this is or why. Why are we doing all this sort of extra complexity?
So simple, maybe not simple, but some of the more common or obvious examples would be things like
version control, like GIFs, like why do we need that? You know, why can't I just save my file in,
you know, like, you know, Kojo.py, you know, and then Kojo underscore 2.py and Kojo underscore 3.py,
like why, you know, and work for spreadsheets, you know, it works for other stuff. You know,
I got through college like that, you know, all of my papers, you know, like, you know, I have a
master's degree in English. I know all about Shakespeare. That worked for me there. If it's
good enough for Shakespeare, why isn't that good enough for you people? You know, why are you so
fancy? What's the deal? So version control is one example. Docker, a lot of us use Docker now
because it solves this issue of both dependency management and deployment. But as a more junior
engineer, you haven't had to face those problems. You haven't had to run into that sort of thing.
And so, again, just this issue of having bumped your head against things. This is one of the key
differences between a more senior developer and a more junior developer. And so I point this out
because I feel like, and this is the thing I talk about with my teammates, I feel like this idea of
understanding that you may be presented with a solution to a problem that you yourself haven't
encountered. By understanding that concept, you can start to look for, okay, well, what is that
problem? What is this thing that you bumped your head up against that I haven't that you're now
presenting with a solution for? And then this is something that definitely helps a more junior
developer become a more senior developer. And so maybe you don't have to bump your head against
that same thing as many times. But if someone else can explain to you, okay, look, if you go
that way, in our job, we're going to be going that way and out these doors a lot. You're going to
run into the door, the door's going to be locked. You're going to run into the door, the door's
going to be locked. What you need is something that will tell you if the door is locked before
you get to it and then you know to make an adjustment. But this idea of understanding
that there are solutions that you might be presented with, that are solutions to problems
you haven't encountered is something that can help a more junior developer move towards the
senior end of the spectrum. And then understanding, okay, understanding some of the different
permutations of that problem. Because inevitably, again, for those of us who work in software,
you know that software doesn't always work. Or a thing that works now might not work tomorrow
or next week or what have you. And so if you're presented with this solution that you don't really
fully understand, you don't even understand the problem it's addressing, when something goes wrong
with that solution, which inevitably it does, then you have no idea of how to debug that thing.
Because it's solving a problem that you don't even know exists. So senior developers can use
this context to try to make things clearer to more junior developers as they're helping them
advance their skills. But more junior developers can begin to ask these questions and realize,
okay, we're using Playwright. I just watched Andy's tutorial on Playwright. It's an end-to-end
testing tool. Why are we doing this? Python has a unit test built in. Why aren't we just using that?
Or the PyTest library. Why are we installing this other library for testing when we already have
unit testing built in? So a junior developer asking these questions, and then a more senior
developer helping explain and provide this sort of context. This last point here is that advancing
skills is not equal to hand-holding. And I point that out because in my role as the deaf and North
American ambassador, and I'll get into some of the details about that. That's sort of the fun
part of the talk, hopefully, later. I've attended my own local meetup in Houston rather, but I've
also attended meetups in at least three different countries and in lots of different U.S. cities.
And I've seen lots of, I've seen and heard lots of things said. And one of the recurring things
that I've noticed is this idea of like, well, you know, like, you know, we need to hire senior
dads because I don't have time to hold anybody's hand. Well, one of the problems with that is
you have this situation of like, I need someone to, you know, I need entertainment for my kid's
birthday party. I hope Beyonce is available, the Taylor Swift. So one, they're probably not. Two,
if they were, like, do you have enough money for those people? And, you know, they'd probably rather
play some big venue than at your kid's birthday party. And then three, you're not really that
important. You know, you don't really need like a Beyonce or a Taylor Swift. What you just need is
someone who is competent. And so this, again, inspect this idea of senior developers and junior
developers and helping more junior developers advance their skills and improve their abilities.
So, but I've heard the language of hand-holding being used a lot as if like, well, it's going to
sort of slow me down. I don't have time to sort of teach somebody this or that or the other thing.
And, look, I'll just say this clearly. If you are in a situation where you have,
where you or your organization have always been able to find all the fully qualified software
engineers you want, fantastic. Ignore me. I'm just some, I'm just some, you know, weirdo just saying
weird stuff. But I have heard more than enough times, you know, the complaint about not being
able to find good developers, not being able to find enough developers. And I feel like this is
some of the solution. All right. So we have sort of ended the sort of the scolding portion of the
program where I tell you to do better. And I tell you to do better, one, because you should.
But really, by you, I mean we, because I'm including myself in that. But also because
I have been fortunate to meet a number of people throughout the Python community and the Django
communities who have made lots of contributions. And it's a lot of work. It's a lot of effort.
And a lot of these people have helped me directly and indirectly. And so at some point,
some of it is just sort of a personal thing of, okay, I've got friends and my friends are kind
of overloaded. Like developer burnout is a real thing. We often hear about how people who are
maintaining various open source packages that we all need and use and love are considering stopping
that work because it's just too much, you know, there's too much effort happening. And so at a
very personal level, like, I have friends who are being overloaded and burnt out and my friends
need help. And the people who can help my friends are other of my friends. And, you know, people in
this room and other members of the Python community. And so by doing this sort of thing,
we can, you know, make life better for the people who are making and building these tools for us.
But also we can make sure that these tools continue to be around. So things like
new Python releases or new Django releases or things like PyPI, which is just magic.
It's like a magic shopping list. Like, okay, I'm going to make a requirements.txt file. I'm
just going to type in all the things I want. I want this and I want that. I want this package.
I want that package. And then you just run your code and then just all the things you want just
magically show up on your computer or they just magically show up wherever you deployed stuff.
That's PyPI. That doesn't happen just because hopes and dreams. That happens because people
like Ed Urban and like Dustin Ingram who used to organize PyTexas and various other people like
actually make that happen. Put in the work and the effort to make that happen. But also
money is required. And the money doesn't just fall from the sky either. Someone has to go find the
money. So these are all these reasons that helping to grow this contributor base is important because
if we want to be able to continue to type our magical shopping lists of Python and have those
magical shopping lists be, you know, Amazon, your fulfillment in next day delivery is all fantastic
or Amazon now in two hours, PyPI is faster. And it makes you money. So if you're in a situation
where you're getting paid money to write Python, we need to protect these tools and these ecosystems
that allow us to do what we do and what we enjoy. So that's that section of the talk. The idea of
what are the things that we can do to try to grow the contributor base
from that perspective. Now the other side of that coin is that even if you are a more
senior developer and you don't think that you yourself, maybe you're not sure about getting
more involved in things, things of that nature, I feel like there are benefits to be had by
developers of all ranges, all skill and experience ranges from more senior to more junior or people
along the Python spectrum from programmers to software engineers. We can all benefit from
more community engagement. And so you can do it, as the bullet point says. So this hashtag
UNORMGT, this is what I call the North American Grand Tour. So this is what I have done as the
definite North American ambassador, speaking at conferences and while speaking at conferences,
speaking to those conference organizers about the idea that DjangoCon US can come to their city,
but it has also allowed me an opportunity to meet people, to meet Python developers from
all over the country, all over North America and in lots of other parts of the world.
It allows me to see what people are doing with Python. So I live in Houston. In Houston we have
the oil and gas industry and also the world's largest medical research center. But there are
lots of other places, lots of other industries in different parts of the country, different parts
of the world. People are doing all sorts of interesting things with Python in these different
places. And so my pitch here for this part of the talk is by being more actively engaged in the
community, by actually sort of getting out and meeting the other Pythonistas in other places,
you can find new opportunities, meet new friends, but also if you are looking to hire people,
if you're looking to hire, again back to the idea of it's hard to find quality senior engineers,
the truth of that statement is almost always that when someone says that we can't find good
developers, what it almost always means is I live here and I said to myself, I want a good developer.
I couldn't find any good developers. Well, yeah, they probably all don't live at your house or
they're not all in your city. They don't all come to your city's local Python meetup. But if you go
to different conferences, meet different people in different places, now you've expanded your
network, you can eat more food, which is always nice, and you can take your family places. That's
always cool and interesting. So by being more actively engaged in the community, you can expand
your scope and do different things. So I'm going to talk a little bit about some more operational
things here. I'm not going to just say just go do more stuff and then not try to help you.
When I said senior better, I was going to just say senior better and then just be like,
okay, well, good luck figuring that out. I tried to at least offer something that I felt would be
helpful. So here, how do I go about this? Where should you go? How do you make it work? What do
you do if your job's not going to reimburse you for it? So again, I work at RevSys. RevSys has
sponsored PyCon and DjangoCon for I don't know how many years. So when I go to those things,
I'm not worried about my company being reimbursing me. When I started the North American Grand Tour,
I was working for a different company and that wasn't the case. So I had to figure out something
I had to bump my head against some things of, okay, well, how do I as one person
funded a tour of North America out of my own pocket? How do I make that happen?
So I'm going to pass some of those lessons along to you. And so now we're getting into sort of the
free and loose part of the talk. So you go to the internet. I'm going to start with
talking about your local Python meetup. And so again, when I talk about sort of community
engagement, where to go, the first place, the first logical place to start is, you know,
does your city or town have a Python meetup? And if so, go to that meetup and meet those people
and talk to those people. Now, if you get to your local Python meetup and it turns out, oh, well,
yes, we have a Python meetup, but it's a Python meetup of senior Python developers who are really
only interested in hanging out with other senior Python developers. And I don't really feel like
this is, you know, a place for me. Well, then go to some other places and meet some other Python
easters. I would say of my circle of Python friends, a lot of them now aren't just in Houston.
You know, my circle of friends is people sort of all over their place. And, you know, and we all
have the internet. And so we can all talk to each other and stuff. And so that works out just fine.
But so that's the first place I would say go try your local Python meetup. See how that goes.
Another nice thing about that, especially if you are a newer Python developer, and I'm passing
these things along to people who may be already more senior developers. But I was talking to
Jeremy, one of the biotech organizers, about this. If you were in a situation where you are a more
senior developer and you're in a position to advise more junior developers, as far as how can
they advance their careers? How can they improve their skills? These are things you can pass along.
So, you know, making them aware of some of these different opportunities. So if your local Python
meetup, you know, maybe it's meeting your needs, maybe it's not. But it doesn't hurt to expand this
and try some other things. So what I would look at next would be the wide range of regional
conferences. And so this is where we're just going to go to the internet and start looking at stuff.
Let's see. So from, let me open a map here. And just from a very practical standpoint.
So we've had a number of different regional conferences that are available from a, and since
we're here at PyTexas, we're here in Austin, I'm going to sort of start basically, sort of
physically geographically. The two sort of physically closest to each other would be
the two physically closest conferences that one could attend. We have our PyColorado,
which happens in Denver. And I think there's only been one year of PyColorado. I was, I was,
I missed the first year. And then PyTennessee, which is in Nashville, which has happened for
many years. And so, let's see, here's a website for PyColorado. So PyColorado, PyTennessee,
PyOhio, also, not just physically close, but also a very high quality conference.
PyOhio has the distinction, has the distinction of being a free of charge conference. So that's
always nice. And so there are a number of different regional conferences that you can attend. These
regional conferences tend to be less expensive. So I'll note the comparison I'm making.
Sort of the gold standard, kind of what, like if you were going to go to a conference,
people often would think, I want to go like to PyCon, you know, PyCon US, or maybe, you know,
PyCon, EuroPython, or PyCon Australia, something like that. But those are larger undertakings and
can be, you know, maybe more difficult, more expensive to attend, just because of the larger
nature. But there are a number of different regional conferences that are easier to get to,
often less expensive, often smaller. They generally tend to happen over a weekend. And so you're not
worried about, you know, getting time off or getting vacation time or getting approval from
a boss. You can just go because, you know, it's a weekend. If you have a job where you can't just
do what you want on weekends, then that's its own separate problem. I don't know that I can help you
with that. I have advice I can offer you. I'll do that offline. But, you know, changes can be made
depending on your risk tolerance and what you want to do with your life. But the nice thing about a
lot of these regional conferences is that, again, they're on weekends. They're more accessible.
They're easier to attend. But you can also look at them from a standpoint of expanding your
career opportunities and what you want to do with Python and where you might want to live at some
point in the future. I know the past two years have been very strange. And, you know, no one
has gone anywhere because, you know, things. But if you, you know, so we're here in Texas now,
but maybe you are someone who, you know, went to college at the Ohio State University. Well,
that's where Pi Ohio is. It's on that campus. Or if you're someone who is considered, you know,
maybe you have family in Tennessee or I'm very much a matte person. So there's a lot of stuff
here. It's sort of south of the Great Lakes. So Pi Tennessee is here in Nashville. You know,
maybe you know people in Tennessee. Maybe you know people in Ohio. Maybe you'd like to know
people in Tennessee or Ohio. One thing that I've noted is like at Pi Tennessee and at Pi Ohio,
I've often met people from like from Indianapolis, from IndiePie and from Chippy, the Chicago Python
Meetup, and from just from different parts of the country. And so in addition to, let's say,
if you go to Pi Tennessee, in addition to meeting people from Nashville, you'll meet people from the
state of Tennessee, but also from other nearby regions that you might not encounter here in Texas.
And the same with Pi Colorado or Pi Cascades, which is an international conference which
rotates between the lovely cities of Vancouver and Portland and Seattle.
And so if you're someone who has considered visiting the Pacific Northwest or living in
the Pacific Northwest or looking at jobs in that area, attending one of those conferences
can be a good way to do that. So again, it's sort of like the gold standard of conferences that
people want to attend. Something like something like a PyCon, a PyCon US or DjangoCon US. But again,
those are larger, more expensive. From having done NORMGT, I can tell you that often
attending conferences, one of the biggest expenses is actually going to be your hotel. So there's a
conference ticket. So you've got a few things. You've got a conference ticket, and then you've
got travel, and then you have hotel, and then food. So depending on what you're doing, the hotel can
be the most expensive portion of that because, especially for something like PyCon, this year's
PyCon is slightly abbreviated because the development sprints are only going to be Monday and Tuesday.
Usually the PyCon US schedule is, it will start Wednesday and Thursday. You have tutorials those
two days. And then Friday, Saturday, Sunday is the main conference with the talks. And then Monday
through Thursday of the next week are the development sprints. The development sprints are a great thing
to attend because, again, if you're looking at advancing your skills, or if you're looking at
maybe not advancing your skills, but if you're someone who feels like, well, my skills are good
enough, but I would like to use those skills to contribute to Python more directly, the development
sprints are a great way to do that. And then you can actually meet those people who work on those
packages. You work on the core Python itself or core Django itself or the other packages and
applications that get used in those ecosystems. You can interact with those people, learn how
those contributions get made, learn what needs to be worked on, build those relationships. But
that time frame I described from Wednesday of one week to Thursday of the next week is a lot of time
to stay in hotels. And hotels can be expensive. So if you look at the PyCon, the suggested PyCon US
hotels have sort of ranged in the $200 a night range. And if you're wanting to go to tutorials
and do that sort of thing from Wednesday one week to Thursday of the next week, it can be a lot of
money, especially if your company is not paying for it, if your company is not reimbursing it,
not reimbursing you for it. One of the things that I have done, and so there are a couple ways
to work around that. Let's say if you're looking at PyCon itself, PyCon US itself, one approach
is to just go for the talk days, Friday, Saturday, Sunday, or maybe just go for the
development sprint days. The nice thing about the development sprint at PyCon US is that they're
free of charge. And so you don't have to even buy a ticket for those. And so you can go to those.
But again, even if you were going to go to the development sprints, there's still the travel cost
and then you have to live somewhere. So that wasn't cost. One of the things that I've done
on the North American Grand Tour is I've gotten good at sort of finding cheaper hotels.
So there's this choice group of hotels and the Wyndham group of hotels, and they've got a range
of different hotels at different prices. Now, I will point this out that traveling is a
multivariate problem. And so there are things that I, as a 6'5", very heavy, large African
American man, I can go a lot of places by myself and it's fine. I'm not worried about my safety.
Now, there are other places. So let's see. If you look at my coworkers, so this is Repsys,
this is my team, and there's eight of us. So there's Catherine, the aforementioned Catherine.
So Lacey is one of my coworkers, a former DjangoCon US chair. Lacey is maybe 5'2".
So Lacey, a much smaller female. And so there are places where I'm comfortable going by myself
that maybe Lacey might not want to go by herself. And so the details as far as how you travel and
when and where you travel will vary based on your individual preferences and risk tolerances and
that sort of thing. I can tell you, as someone who has been in some less expensive hotels in
places that might have seemed like, oh, this could be questionable, it has, for the most part,
been fine. It has 100% of the time been fine. But again, I recognize that I am me and people who
might want to behave in antisocial ways, shall we say, might want to do that elsewhere. Because
if you present yourself to me as a problem, you might now find that you have a larger problem
than you wanted. So that's just sort of some of the reality of me. So I will tell you this,
for PyCon US, I'm actually going to PyCon US this year. And since I knew I'd be giving this
talk and I'd be telling people, hey, go to conferences, it's fantastic. I wanted to sort
of walk it like I talk it. So what I would have done if my company wasn't reimbursing me for some
of the PyCon expenses, I would have had to try to find a less expensive hotel. And so what I
actually did is I'm going early to PyCon. I'm going to, so I came, so that's kind of why the
search is here. I came to this choice hotel site, looked for this in Salt Lake City. I am arriving,
I'm arriving on the 26th. I'm arriving on the 26th because I wasn't, I booked, I made my travel
reservations before the tutorials schedule was released. So I didn't know if I was going to want
to go to tutorials or not. And so I, but I wanted to be able to go to tutorials. So I'm arriving on
the 26th and then I'm moving to the conference hotels, which are more expensive, which my company
has been reimbursing me for. I'm going to check out of my cheaper hotel on the 28th and then move
into the conference hotel that Thursday evening. So I can be in the conference hotel for the talks
Friday, Saturday, Sunday. And then Monday I'm going to leave my conference, leave the conference hotel
and move back to a cheaper hotel. And so, so this is what I did. This is literally what I did. I'm
not signing up. And so we've got hotels near Salt Lake City. I think I have them sorted by price.
Yeah, sorted by price, low to high. So these are the cheaper ones. This one I looked at and I was
like, hmm, like this is like 9.7 miles from destination. That seems like, from my experience,
that seems like it could be far. So if we go to Salt Lake City,
and actually what we really want is the Salt Palace, which is the convention center.
So here's the Salt Palace. And again, I have done this tour of the continent. So I have more map stuff
in my head than most people probably should. But in looking at these, I saw, okay, this address,
South 300, which is nine miles from the destination. I saw 715 West North Temple Street. And so from
looking at the maps, I know that West North Temple is near the conference center. And so,
was it, yeah, North Temple is near the conference center. So here is,
so here's the conference center. Here's South Temple Street.
Here's North Temple Street. So we've got, okay, a few blocks, North Temple Street, a few blocks
north of the convention center. So let's take this address,
put it into Google Maps, and see what it tells us.
And it's 1.2 miles from the venue. And there's a lot of Google mapping that gets done. So if you are
price sensitive, then there's a little more research time that needs to go in. But again,
this is literally how I've attended many different conferences around the world. I use this same
process when I attended PyCon Australia. This is how I found my hotel for PyCon Australia.
That was a little iffy. I ended up living on top of a karaoke bar, which was, you know,
was exciting, but maybe, you know, but I also learned by being there that there was another
sort of nicer hotel. This is like a block away. So maybe I'll stay there next time.
Next time I'm in Sydney. But so we have here, so this hotel is the train, the Green Line train,
which is also the train that takes you from Salt Lake City Airport to the conference location.
But this Green Line train will take you from that cheap hotel to the venue in 15 minutes.
And that hotel is even now still $61 a night, as opposed to like $200 or $220 for the hotels that
are very close to the conference, that are attached to the conference. So this is where I'll be
Tuesday and Wednesday night, checking out Thursday morning, then I'll be back here
Monday evening, and then leaving from there Tuesday. So at some point, there's like,
okay, hold on, we came to Pie, Texas, not to like travel planet, Texas, or, you know, this is,
it suddenly turned into an episode of like House Hunters, House Hunters International,
which is a good show. I mean, it's not a bad place to end up. But again, back to the idea of,
if I'm going to say, well, hey, just, you know, do all these cool things.
Yeah, I mean, well, yeah, it's fantastic. If you are, you know, if you have all the
monies in the world, or, you know, again, I work for a company now that sponsors PyCon,
sponsors DjangoCon, I'm not worried about these expenses being reimbursed. That wasn't always the
case. So I started speaking at Python conferences when I still worked as an accountant. And so I
was definitely, you know, footing the bill for that stuff myself. And then even in my first
developer job, I was still having to, you know, deal with these costs out of pocket. And so again,
like, just to put a very fine point on it, like, if you are thinking, if you were thinking about
going to PyCon US this year, I'm 99% sure PyCon US is not sold out already. I think we talked
about that last night. So you can still get a ticket to PyCon US, and you can stay at this
$61 a night hotel. And again, I've stayed at Econologies. I'm sure it'll be fine. Again,
for me personally, it'll be fine. You can also come and stay here too. I'll be there. And so
it's like 95% chance it'll be fine for you too, you know. Because if nothing else, you know,
I'll be there for at least a few of the nights. So to try to provide some actual practical,
actionable advice, it's like, well, if you were thinking about going to PyCon, but maybe you don't
know if your company will pay for it or your company would reimburse you for it, well, this is
a less expensive option. There's still the cost of the ticket. There's still the cost of airfare.
I can't make those measures go away. Food is a thing that you can, you can vary your food pricing.
But, you know, let's see, PyCon Cleveland, I stayed in the 2018, the 2018 PyCon Cleveland.
It was the first PyCon Cleveland. I ended up being in Cleveland for like a week and a half,
maybe longer, because I did training in Chicago for a thing. And then I came from Chicago to
Cleveland. I got to Cleveland like Sunday night. And so I was in Cleveland from like Sunday of one
week until like Wednesday of the next week. But I was staying at a hotel like this. And so even
though it was mostly coming out of my pocket, and I got reimbursed for some of it, but those costs
that had to be reimbursed weren't outlandish. So again, trying to offer some sort of practical
advice here. So there are so many choices. PyTennessee is only one of them. There are many
other conferences that you can look at. So in conclusion, I know this talk was kind of
four different small talks together, tied together with this one cohesive thread.
Hopefully the cohesive thread was that we need as many new contributors as possible
in our community, because there's lots of work to be done. And the amount of work that needs to be
done grows as Python becomes more popular. My concern is that Python's popularity and use
is growing at one rate, but the contributor base is growing at a slower rate. And so trying to
make a graph in person. So trying to make this line, this bottom line, so to come closer to
this one, that's the goal. So who needs graphs on slides? You have hands. Why would you do that?
So again, trying to include as many, trying to add as many new contributors as possible,
but again, only actual community members will contribute, people who actually feel like the
members of the community. And our current senior devs are the ones that have this outsize influence
on our community. And so it's sort of an appeal to those more senior developers to recognize that
with this impact on the community, there's more responsibility. As Spider-Man taught us, with great
power comes great responsibility. Also radioactive something something. Again, those developers help
shape our community and focusing on training and retaining the developers who are here that you
work with is an important thing. And also you go out, make new friends, meet new people, see new stuff.
If you have any questions or comments, things of that nature, this is me on Twitter. This is probably
the best way to reach me to reach out if you have feedback. Again, this is kind of a talk I've been
working on since 2013 and you know, I'll get new feedback and new information and we'll update it
and add it into some part of another talk. But that is my presentation. So hopefully it has been
of some benefit to you and has been to quality. So thank you all very much for your time.
you