Yesterday I almost died on my way here, and I'm saying that with a smile because obviously
I didn't die, otherwise I wouldn't be here.
And it's not a figure of speech.
Before going to the conference, I was actually coming down the streets and while I was crossing
the 7th street on my way to Lidlberg, at the traffic lights, a car slowed down but didn't
stop exactly at the traffic light, and so it hit me a little bit.
So I fell with my shoulder on the hood of the car, but thankfully, all good, all good,
I'm fine, I'm here.
But as you can imagine, I'm very glad to be here.
I'm very glad to be on that stage, I'm very glad to be in person for one of the first
Pi Texas in person since the COVID, and I'm really thrilled to be able to share what I
want to present to you today on this stage to all of you.
I'm David Melamed, and today I want to talk about a topic that is really close to my heart.
About a year and a half ago, despite a well-paying job at Cisco, a wife and four kids, I decided
to take one of these life-changing decisions.
I quit my job and I decided to open a startup with four other friends.
The reason for that is that I couldn't stand anymore the pain of working with security
as a developer.
You probably also experienced that, but security is hard.
Security is overwhelming, and a lot of the tools that currently are available for everyone
to use are really not dev-friendly.
I don't want to see thousands of findings when I run some SaaS tool.
I don't have anything to do with that.
I don't want to spend my time thinking of, okay, how do I fix all those things?
I want something to be easy.
I want security to be easy.
I don't want it to be a tax.
And so I started to think, how can I achieve that?
First of all, when I'm looking online for security checks and security checklists, I'm
seeing lists that are very, very long.
But where should I start?
And so we came up together with this approach of minimum viable security.
With what?
Minimum security?
How those two words can work in the same sentence, right?
This is probably what you're asking yourself.
Minimum security?
I mean, come on.
When you're thinking about security, you're thinking maximum security, right?
Everyone wants to be secure.
Everyone wants to live in a fortress, right?
No one wants to be attacked.
So I hope everyone does, right?
Yes, sure.
But you probably don't want burglars to come and break into your house, right?
That's not even a fortress, right?
Okay, okay, that's great.
And I'm fine with that.
I think that we should all start with minimum viable security.
Because what does it mean?
So minimum security means that, well, you don't want to start with a list of 100 different
items.
That's too much.
What you want is to understand what is critical and what is not.
And like for MVP, when you want to start with your first product, you're looking for the
minimum set of features that you want to define and to work on and to implement in order to
release your product the same way as minimal viable security.
You want to be able to set your minimal set of security controls that you want to focus
on in order not to be embarrassed when you're releasing your MVP.
And that's why it's not just minimum security, it's minimum viable security.
You want it to be viable.
And so how do you get to that?
How do you find MVS?
This is what I want to show you today.
How you can define your own MVS for a simple Python application.
So this is an example of a list, and probably we could debate whether or not some items
should be there or not.
But let's go over all the different areas because there are a lot of areas.
It's not only the code, of course, but in the code, you should look for code vulnerability,
of course.
You don't want to start there.
If you have secrets, you probably also want to make sure that you don't have any hardcoded
ones.
If you have libraries, and in Python you probably have a lot of libraries in your requirements.txt,
you also want to make sure that you don't have any vulnerable dependencies in your project.
And that was the code.
What about the infra?
You're running in the cloud because you're building a product for the cloud.
And so the first thing you want to make sure is that you don't misconfigure your cloud
infrastructure.
Right?
If you're building on Amazon, make sure you don't have any S3 bucket that is open to the
world.
Right?
You also want to make sure that you have a way to access remotely your account.
And that the account is set up and bootstrapped in a more secure way.
Now we talked about the code, we talked about the infra.
But now that you deploy your application, you also want to check out your runtime.
It's running on the cloud.
So what can you check there?
One of the most popular tools is pentesting.
So you want to make sure you don't have a security hole.
SQL injections, things like that.
You need pentesting.
But you also have APIs.
So not only your frontend URLs, you want to check them.
You also want to check your API endpoints.
And then you have your pipeline because the way you're actually pushing your code to production,
you have a whole CI-CD pipeline.
You have, first of all, your SCM, the way you store your code.
And you also have your whole CI-CD pipeline.
And so there, you want to check a couple of things.
First of all, you want to check the CI-CD itself, that it's set up in a secure way.
For example, if you're using GitHub Actions, Jenkins, make sure that you don't leave it
open.
And for the SCM for GitHub, make sure, for example, I know your setup MFA.
Also, because you're working with containers, like almost everyone today, you also want
to make sure that your base image is secure.
So also look there for vulnerabilities.
But that's not it.
It's minimal, but still, you have a couple of other things.
Your data.
Your customer data, your user data are really important.
You want to make sure that they're encrypted.
You don't want to see a GitHub token, for example, lying around in plain text in your
database.
Multi-tenancy.
Most of the SaaS platforms today are multi-tenant.
You want to make sure that there's no way you can read data from one end to the other.
Otherwise, you will probably be very embarrassed.
What about third parties?
You have a lot of services today that are connecting to your product.
It could be things like GitHub, if you have a GitHub integrations, it can be Datadog for
analytics, it can be Epsilon if you have serverless.
There's a lot of services that are connecting to your product.
You need to make sure that they're secure.
Otherwise, someone can take over your account there.
And maybe there's some data that are sensitive.
Now, we talked a lot about the code, the infra, everything that's very technical.
What about people?
We almost forgot that we had people that are working on the code and on the product.
They're one of the things that is very, very common, but sometimes forgotten, is use password
manager.
Seems like very basic.
But still, how many developers here are saving or manipulating passwords in plain text, storing
them in their local laptop saying that, well, that's fine, or in some notepad?
No?
Anyone?
That's great.
So you should start with a password manager.
And if you think that passwords are only, I don't know, username and password for your
accounts, maybe there's more than that, and we'll get to that in a moment.
And finally, there's another area, it's the operations.
How do I make sure that when an employee leaves the company, well, I'm removing
his access to GitHub, I need to manage that.
And also, there will probably be some security incident in the future, and so I need to make
sure that I have some process in place, because that's something that is very stressful, and
I don't want to add to that if I don't have a process in place already.
So these are the different areas that are related to product security, and what I want
is to focus on a couple of ones, the ones that were actually highlighted.
So I'll go really quickly through each of them, and I'll give an example of the tool
that we'll use.
All the tools that I will demonstrate here are open source, and you'll see at the end
a demo that everything will be integrated into the CI-CD, and so you can really clone
the code that I will give at the end, and you can have the start of your minimal viable
security today.
So the first area is called vulnerability.
We want to make sure that we don't have any vulnerability in our code.
For that, the most popular tool is SAS, static code analysis, looking for specific patterns
in the code.
We'll use Bandit.
Bandit is an open source linter for Python, and you have 35 rules that are already built
in the tool.
Then you have the secrets, but that will use a great tool that's called GitLix that is
supporting a lot of different regexes of well-known patterns for secrets, for social networks,
for AWS credentials, SSH keys, API keys, and so on.
And the advantage is that it's also looking in Git history, so that even if you removed,
you deleted from your repo, it actually looks back in the history and makes sure that you
remove it completely.
For dependencies, we'll use Safely.
Safely is an open source slash commercial product.
If you use the open source version, the updates are only monthly.
If you use the commercial, you get updates all the time.
But it's very, very easily integrated into the CI-CD.
And we'll use that to check if we have vulnerable libraries in our project.
Next, we'll also try to deploy our project in the cloud.
And for that, we want to make sure that we don't have any misconfiguration in our infrastructure.
We'll use infrastructure as code, Terraform, in order to deploy and to create some buckets
in S3.
And we want to make sure that there is no vulnerability in our code.
And for that, we'll use a tool that was written by Checkmarks called Kix, open source, that
has support for a lot of different languages, and right now includes 2,000 checks.
Then we'll use some pentesting.
And for that, there's a great tool that is open source by OWASP called Zap.
It's both a web application scanner, looking for very popular top 10 OWASP vulnerabilities.
And also, it can check for APIs when you're providing some open API specification or some
swagger definitions.
And for that, we'll use an interesting setup, because we will build the container of our
Python application, and then we'll run Zap against this image.
Talking about Docker image, we also use Trivi in order to check if there are some issues
in the Docker images, the base image that we'll use.
Then we also want to check that in that specific case on GitHub, we don't have any user that
don't use MFA, because in that case, maybe the account is vulnerable and can be attacked
by someone.
For that, there's not really a tool, and that's why in a few lines of code, we'll build our
own tool.
And at the end, a word about password manager.
So you probably all use password manager, but how many of you are also using the command
line for the password manager?
So here, I want to show you how to use one password CLI, which is a great way in your
bash profile to load some secrets into memory so that you can use them for a lot of different
things that you need without having to store them in plain text in your bash profile itself.
In the same way, if you're using Amazon keys, you don't want them to be stored in plain
text in your laptop in AWS credentials, for example.
That's the way they recommend.
You want to use AWS Vault, which allows you to actually store them in an encrypted way
in your own laptop.
So I will just show you how to do that.
Terminal.
First example is a dummy password that I saved in one password.
And by...
No, it's not logged in anymore.
Okay.
So now I'm logging the first time on one password, and then I can use the OP command line in
order to retrieve some password.
The nice thing is actually to save that into your bash profile so that you really never
see the value of the password.
The second example is using AWS Vault, and this is an example of how I'm using it.
So I don't have any secrets stored on my machine.
Everything is actually encrypted, and I just need to use AWS Vault exec at the beginning
in order to retrieve my policies and run any command for Amazon.
And now let's talk about the different tools that I want to show you inside the application.
So these are different tools I talked about, and now we'll see them in action.
So the demo will be a very simple, fast API-based application that displays move information.
The actors that are playing in the movie, for that we'll use a simple data persistence
using SQLite.
The SEM will be GitHub, the CI system will be GitHub Action, and our goal is to integrate
the seven tools that I showed you in a few minutes.
This is the demo repository if you want to check that out afterwards.
It's public.
You can clone it, fork it, whatever you want.
First, let's see the application in practice.
So it's a very simple application.
I'm just starting it using UviCorn.
And now, yeah, these are the number of movies in the database.
I want to search for a specific one.
Let's search for Titanic.
Okay, there are three versions of the movie.
I want the one from 1997.
So let's see the actors in the movie.
Okay, so movie, store, and then I can see the different actors in the movie.
Very simple application, right?
Now let's see the code of this application.
We'll see that it's very simple.
So we have a few endpoints and a bunch of SQL queries.
Now I want to show you, oh, this is the Dockerfile.
It has some AWS credentials because the guy who actually wrote that didn't know that it's
not the best way to pass environment variables to get access to Amazon.
And so what we'll focus for a few minutes is the way I configured the GitHub Action
workflow, which includes all the seven tools.
Let's see how it works.
So basically you have a couple of jobs here.
You have the SAS one, secret one, DAST for API security.
You have infrastructure, SCA for dependencies, the container, and MFA.
These are all the jobs that I want.
Now I can see here static vulnerability scanner.
I'm using an action, GitHub action that someone actually already wrote, and it's encapsulating
the Bandit tool.
And this is the way I'm running it.
And at the end, I want to upload the artifact, the results, to GitHub itself so that I will
be able to review the results.
And then I have the secret one.
The secret is using Gitleaks.
There's also a public action for that, so it's really easy to integrate.
The DAST one is more complicated because, as I said, I built the image before.
Here I'm making sure that it's running before I run my action.
So it runs as a service.
And then, using Zap, I can go and use the Zap API scan, which will trigger the scan
against this image.
And for that, it will use the OpenAPI definition.
The OpenAPI is actually something like that that is provided by FastAPI, and it's defining
all the different endpoints and the parameters.
Then I have the infra.
For the infra, I'm running Kix.
Also here, there's a Kix GitHub action that is already implemented.
And I put my code into a Terraform folder.
And here you can see that it's very basic.
It's just a simple bucket in S3 that I want to create and a very simple DynamoDB table.
Now I have SCA, which is Dependency Check.
For that, there's no available GitHub action, so I'm just running a script myself, installing
it with pip, and then I'm running the command myself, looking to scan the requirements.txt.
For the containers, I'm building the container myself, and then I'm using the action that
is provided by Trivia itself in order to check if there's some issue.
And at the end, MFA, I actually built it myself.
I used three lines.
If you excuse me here, it's in Node.js, though it's a Python conference, because here the
API is actually easier to use.
What I'm doing here is that I'm listing all my users, all the members of this organization,
of my organization, and I'm filtering the ones that don't have MFA enabled.
And I'm going over all of them, and if there's at least one, then I want this to fail.
So I'm returning an exit code of one.
Let's see all of this in practice into GitHub.
So I uploaded my repository here, and here you can see an example of a pull request.
As you can see, everything is failing because I have a lot of issues in this repo.
And if I'm looking at the details, I can see a few things.
So first of all, I can see that some of the tools are returning here their findings.
Some are uploading their artifact that I showed.
So I can, for example, open this one, and opening the zip here, and I can see the results
of the file.
These are all of the dependencies that were found in my code, they're actually SQL injections.
For some of them, actually, the results, it's inside the action.
So for all of them, I can see the logs.
And here I can see that I have some issues with my infrastructure.
For the container also, it's inside the results here.
So I can see that I have actually two issues with my Python.
And so, as you can see, very easily, I can integrate a couple of tools, and that's the
basics of my MVS, of my security, because here I have a lot of different things that
are checked against a very simple code, and very easily, I can get them into my CI CD.
So of course, here, as you can imagine, the developer experience is not great, because
you have some of the tools that are returning the results inside the logs.
Some others are returning as part of some artifact that you need to read.
Some others are just maybe not returning directly this, and you didn't know the UI.
The experience is not great.
And what you would like to is to have some kind of unified experience, but one single
experience.
For example, what would be great if all the findings were returned inside the PR itself,
as PR commands?
And so this is basically what we did at JIT.
We tried to take this a step further.
And so, as you can see here, we wanted to be really dev native, and so every tool is
now returning the results inside the PR in one single way, in a very unified way, as
PR commands.
Also, we wanted to manage our own customized MVS plan, not in a spreadsheet, like many,
many folks.
We wanted it to be customizable, wanted to see how the progress is, wanted to make sure
that all the tools that were running are actually running and are configured correctly, because
it's easy to add a tool, but maybe it's misconfigured.
For example, maybe I think that the tool is actually checking for secrets, but maybe misconfigured,
it's not looking at the right folder.
And so everything together, we wanted to get this continuous security platform.
And this is what we did at JIT.
If you're intrigued, but what you just saw, and you want to know more, or you want to
actually test the platform, I have a great news.
Since Friday, we opened the beta to the public, so anyone can enter.
Just need to register at JIT.io.
Thanks for the dev rel guy of Elastic for the QR code idea.
That's a great idea.
If you're inspired by what you saw, and it resonates, and you would like to be part of
this task force that tries to empower the developers with security, then you're welcome
to join us.
And if you have any question, feel free to reach out to me.
My email is here.
I'll be around for the next couple of hours.
I'd be happy to discuss with any one of you.
Thanks again for your attention.
And if you have any question, maybe I have some time for one question.
Sure.
Yeah.
Yes.
Okay, great question.
So what I showed is only the beginning.
It's basically the foundations of best practices, of things that you would need to start in
order to have a product that is secure.
But there are two problems with that.
One is that if you're putting that into practice and you put that into your environment, you
need to make sure it's working all the time.
So you need to operationalize that.
That would be the first thing I would say.
And then it's only the beginning in terms of things that you need to do for security.
There are a lot more items that you need to do.
And so what we also did at JIT is we're providing this plan as a first one.
But of course, we have more advanced plan.
Because maybe afterwards you want to go further, maybe down the road of compliance.
So there you have ISO, SOC 2, all these different norms.
You have the CIS benchmark.
You have a lot of plans that are way more comprehensive in terms of number of items
and things that you need to do.
So it's only the beginning.
I didn't want it to be overwhelming.
But of course, there's a lot more things that you can do in your environment to make sure
everything is secure.
Another question?
Great.
Everything was clear?
Thank you again.
Great.
Everything was clear?
Thanks again.