Welcome everyone to Pi Texas 2022. It's honestly it's been three years since we've been able to do an in person conference and every time I say that I feel a little bit older and sadder.
It's really good to see everyone in person again. This is the first in person Python event that is happening in North America. So like we beat everyone to it, which is really exciting.
The next one will be, I believe, PyCon, US PyCon, US or PyCon, North America, which will be happening in Salt Lake City. So if you, you know, have a lot of fun today and you haven't considered going to Python PyCon or you just have this burning desire to go see salt in a lake, check out PyCon and Salt Lake City.
For today, we are highly recommending that everyone wear their masks when out in public and within the area as you have all seen our
code of conduct, but that too. The you've all seen our health requirements and stuff. So please adhere to these as much as you can.
It's very exciting. You know, Austin recently just removed a lot of the limitations because the the community transmission rate for COVID in Austin is at the lowest it's been since
almost pre pandemic levels. So, you know, it's good to see hopefully light at the end of the tunnel on this, but please be kind and courteous to your neighbors and continue to practice safe COVID restrictions while you're here. We would highly appreciate that.
We have our code of conduct is on our website. It's plain and simple. Be kind and courteous to others. Think about others, you know, and all of that. You can find it on the website.
Everything for this entire event will be on our website, but you can find it at about slash code of conduct.
And if for any reason you need to make a report or need to talk with us, you can call or text anonymously. So this year we're doing something a little bit different.
Lunch will be off site. We normally we've catered in the past before, but you know, there's such amazing food like literally within a couple of blocks in every direction that you can go.
So we've extended the lunch break to be at two hours this year to encourage you to go and just try some of the local Austin cuisine. If you're local to Austin, you're familiar with it. If you're not local to Austin, you're in for a real treat.
On our website, I made up a list of things that I like in the area. So you're more than welcome to go and figure out where I would probably be going.
But there is literally anything and everything all around you. Please enjoy it. There will be breakfast items and coffee, juice, water served
every morning before the conference. And then we will be doing a coffee refresh at 2pm after lunch. So we'll have, you know, snacks and stuff for you to snack on during the conference.
For your pleasure, please eat them. I don't want to take them home. I really I don't know what I would do with three dozen parfaits, but it doesn't sound fun.
So we're also having our after party tonight. It's at it's it's tonight at 6pm at Joe's Coffee Shop. It's up on, I think it's on second, I'll have to get that. We will be we will gather up a group and walk over like we did similar to 2019. So we'll we'll end today at like 5, 5.15 ish, we'll hang out for a little bit, then we'll all walk over. It's about a 10, 15 minute walk. There will be a lot of food, a lot of drinks and stuff. So it's really
we really encourage you to come out. If you haven't already done like an RSVP on the website for their free tickets. So just to ensure you get a spot, make sure you go on to the like our like where you would go to register for the conference and you will be able to just register a free ticket for that just to ensure that we have a proper head count.
We do have shirts for sale. We decided to buy some extras this year in various sizes. So if you didn't buy a Pitex shirt, but you like the logo,
you can go out on our registration table shirts are $20 and we will happily take your money and give you a shirt.
And finally, I do want to say thank you to our sponsors, Octopus Energy, Elastic, Rook Out, Scout APM and Dev Relate. They will all have booths out here for you to see during the breaks, you know, maybe during a talk whenever you like.
I guess the only last bit of final news is all Pitex's staff are wearing orange or in the orange Pitex shirts. So if for any reason you need you need any of us or you just need something from us, look for the Pitex's staff orange shirts.
There's myself. There's George right here down front. And then Kevin is the one with the ponytail. And then Jeremy ran off to go buy things we forgot because isn't that just how conferences work?
So we have about nine minutes to the keynote. The keynote is here. So I'm going to ask, would you like to start or you want to wait?
Okay, yeah, so we will wait. So give us about five minutes. If you need to take a quick break or something, then I will come back on and introduce our keynote speaker. So yes, thank you very much, everyone. And enjoy the conference. We're looking forward to having you.