Okay. So, every year, we kind of like to look back and talk a little bit about how PyTex
got to where it is. And this year, there were a lot of first time speakers, so maybe you
haven't seen this talk, although I've given it in the past. So, I wanted to kind of walk
through this. The title of this is Making PyTex Happen Legally, because for the first
few years, it was a little sketchy, questionable at least. So, here's just a little history
about how PyTex came around. The first PyTex-ish meetup was in Houston in 2007. It might be
the first regional conference. There's some historical references to some others. You
kind of go spelunking on the web right around that time, but it's right around the right
time. We adopted the PyTex's name in 2009, and for a long time there, it was a super
informal just get together like at a friendly venue, a college campus or something. No food,
no sponsors, just Southwestern Medical Center, Baylor. That was 2009. Okay. Sheila, by the
way, is responsible for a large portion of these earlier meetups. So, thank you, Sheila.
I appreciate it. So, in 2013, we were facing a problem which was people would say they
were going to come. We would start to get food, and then they wouldn't show up, and
that was kind of difficult. So, we started asking people to pay, because that makes people
make it. And Sheila was kind of stepping away, so more of us kind of stepped in for the first
time. The problem was we were taking in money to do things, but who was that money going to? Is
it Jeremy's money or somebody else's? And also, so there are tax liabilities, and also if we tell
a sponsor we're going to do something, who's the responsible party for it? So, taking on kind of a
lot of legal liabilities and risks. So, we kind of asked for help, and the PSF stepped up, and they
helped us by taking in payments from sponsors or from individuals who were buying tickets, and then
sending us reimbursement, which was really helpful. We're really glad that they did it,
but there was just a little bit of friction with that process, because we would have to kind of
pay money out and then wait to be reimbursed, and it was sort of a pain. So, we decided to do it
ourselves, and in I think 2014, we incorporated as a Texas nonprofit, the Pi Texas Foundation has
been around now for about eight years, and we went and got like 501c3 certification, which means if
you donate money to us, that's actually tax deductible, which is nice, and just FYI, our
bylaws state that like this is kind of an essential thing you have to do to do this, but like if we
ever dissolve any money that's left over, it all goes to the PSF. So, it's a fully Python dedicated
organization, and we got a logo, which we love, and which the PSF's like trademark board has
actually approved, which is nice. So, this is, you know, Pi Texas generally. So, stepping back in,
we started the foundation in 2014, got our 501c3 certification, had a couple of little oopsies in
2018, and then, you know, 21, where maybe we got a little busy and didn't quite do it, or, you know,
had a worldwide pandemic, and now we're in 2022. So, that's just kind of how we are. That means
that this is something like our 15-year anniversary, which is kind of cool. So, how are we, how is the
Pi Texas Foundation work? Like, what do we do? We have a board of directors. There are three of us.
As of yesterday, Mason Egger is our new president. Thank you, Mason, for joining us. Huge mistake,
but anyway. Kevin is, I think, maybe outside. No, Kevin's over here. Kevin's the vice president.
I'm the secretary. We don't have a treasurer right now. I just get to do that for fun. And then,
we have kind of committees, special committees, who are selected to run the conference,
effectively just giving them the power to sign contracts when we need them to. And then,
we have meetings every six months or so in order to check in on the finances and stuff. It's
actually kind of boring. So, if you want to help, do a boring thing, but that also is really,
really important for the longevity of Pi Texas and its legal status and keeping the things going,
and then thinking, helping us think about potential expansion options, you could become a director.
You could help us out. How do you do that? Let us know you want to do it. Come to the meetings.
Really, that's it. It's not a lot, but if you do it, it really is helpful for us to be able to push
some of these responsibilities out to others and also get ideas. There are different areas of
Texas that we maybe don't serve as well as we would like to, and so we'd love to have
more input on those kinds of things. What's that? Yeah, because the directors right now,
until yesterday, we were in Dallas, Austin, and Houston, so they've always been sort of virtual.
The actual requirement officially in our bylaws is that we have to meet at the conference. So,
when there's a conference, we have an annual meeting just to do it. Anyhow,
we can always do off-cycle meetings too, but yeah, they are virtual. Anyhow, I think that's
please come let me know if you're interested. Super happy to talk about that more.
One last thing is there's always some confusion. There's Pi Texas Foundation, which is ongoing
and a persistent entity where we have yearly obligations or all-year obligations, and then
there's the Pi Texas Conference, which is what we're here at today. Anyhow, we're thinking about
ways to increase the influence of the Pi Texas Foundation beyond the yearly conference, but
for now, this is what we've got in the Pi Texas. With that, I think that's the history. I'm all
done. Any questions, any thoughts? All right, cool. Who's next up? All right, awesome. Thanks,
y'all.