My name is Laura Santorin, I am a developer advocate at PinguLumi.
We are an infrastructure as code company, but it's also my first time here at PyTexas.
How many other people here is your first time here at PyTexas?
Don't be shy, raise your hand, nice and high.
Isn't it exciting to be here?
Y'all excited?
Are y'all awake after lunch?
No.
Maybe not.
Alright, well I'm just gonna kinda get started here.
We're gonna be talking a little bit about building a scientific computing lab on public
clouds.
Now how many people here have ever used a public cloud?
Alright, alright.
So we have some people who have, some people who haven't, basically my job right now is
teach people about public cloud,
but I used to actually study real clouds.
So there are clouds, and then there are clouds.
Clouds are the ones in the sky.
My degree is actually in Earth and Atmospheric Science.
How many people here do not have a degree
in computer science?
I promise you, you are not alone.
So I also have my degree in Earth and Atmospheric Science.
I spend a lot of time actually doing science research
on weather, and I did a lot of teaching about weather,
and I will say the most intimidating thing
is trying to give a live weather demo
to a bunch of eight-year-olds.
Just so that you know, that's probably
the most intimidating thing to do.
But I used to study those clouds that are up there,
and now I study cloud computing.
So I get to teach about those now.
One thing that we're going to find out today,
because I get to talk about science today,
in just cloud computing, is that communication is important.
When it came to actual professional science,
one of the most important things
that you need to be able to do
is share what you've learned
in a way that's understandable to other people,
that they can repeat that without necessarily talking to you
and get the same result.
So, that being said, now that I am no longer
a scientist exactly, we can start talking
about citizen science.
It's lovely to get a chance to explore
all of these data sets yourself.
And there's a lot you can do on your own.
However, there's some stuff you can't actually do
because you don't have the same tools at your disposal.
Generally, science data analysis
is extremely hardware intensive.
Most big research organizations have their own computing.
They have people who run this for you.
They have people who build it for you and set it all up.
Unfortunately, that kind of hardware is expensive.
So, for the average person trying
to do some citizen science,
it's too expensive to run on your own.
In addition, if you're trying to run it locally
on your machine, it takes a really long time.
Now, I don't know about all of you,
but I generally don't have a ton of time outside of work
to sit and wait for a data set to run.
Does anybody here have that time?
And if so, tell me your secrets.
How are you more able to do that outside of work?
Unfortunately, I'm not.
I don't know about anybody else.
The other thing, though, is that because we are not sure
what other citizen scientists have available,
it's really hard to repeat it locally on your machine.
We all know that, hey, it works on my machine, right?
How many people have said that?
I've definitely said that before.
But generally, when it comes to actual citizen science,
you do run into that case where you say
it works on your machine, but it's really hard
to replicate on someone else's.
So, how do we solve that?
You might be able to guess.
Anybody have a guess?
Public Clouds.
Public Clouds, that's right.
Yay, cloud computing.
So, the wonderful thing about the cloud
is that there's a lot of options out there.
It gives us the ability to do a lot of hardware intensive
stuff and make that more accessible to the average person.
There is a slight, slight problem, though.
Does anybody know what all these are?
Can anybody name every single one of those?
I can't, just so you know, if I do this all day long.
There's almost too many options, and nothing makes sense.
Now, some clouds are really great at naming things
in reasonable ways.
Google Cloud does BigQuery.
What does BigQuery do?
Query data, yes!
Some clouds, though, don't do great at naming things.
Name with AWS.
It's notorious for code names on all of its products.
There is a lovely video out there,
if you've ever seen Forest Brazil's video,
where he does a music video trying to name
every single AWS product in about two minutes.
It is a great video, please go watch it.
You should check that out.
And that's just some things
that all of these cloud systems have.
This is only the data stuff, by the way.
There's hundreds of thousands of other products
on each of these catalogs,
and it's so much to try and understand.
If you're looking for Apache Beam,
which is something that you actually use a lot
in data science, it's not called Apache Beam
on every single cloud.
In fact, every cloud has a different name for it.
Dataflow for GCP, Kinesis Data, and Analytics for AWS.
I honestly don't know what it is on Azure,
and I shouldn't, but you get the idea.
So this is a little bit of a problem.
How do we solve this?
Well, this is why infrastructure is code
is extremely useful, especially for citizen science.
Part of it is that you can actually go look at the API
and start to understand what are those products?
What do they do?
Oh hey, that one looks like this one.
Wait a minute, it is the same thing,
it's just renamed a different way.
IHC ensures that you have infrastructure
that is repeatable, reusable, and replicable.
Meaning, you yourself can always repeat
and bring up the same infrastructure every single time
and get the same result.
You can reuse it wherever you are,
and you can ensure that someone else you work with
can actually replicate what you're doing,
which is really great when you're doing citizen science
and data analysis.
Now, you can also move from cloud to cloud as needed.
Should you realize, for example,
that you've kind of gone over your free tier on one cloud,
you can just hop over to a free tier on another one.
Shh, I didn't actually say that.
If you actually work at AWS, don't be upset with me.
So, there are quite a few options out there
for actually doing infrastructure as code.
Today's demo is going to use Pulumi.
I'm sorry, it's because I work there,
that's what I know, it's also open source,
but there are a lot of other options out there.
There's Terraform, each of the cloud providers
have their own SDK, and you can actually do all of this
with Python, which is the fun part.
The important thing to understand is that using SDKs
and hitting these APIs with infrastructure as code
ensures that, again, it's repeatable, reusable,
and a replicable experience for other citizen scientists.
One of the harder things about working with cloud computing
is deciphering that massive catalog.
How do you decide what to use?
It's not always a great idea to basically rent a VM
and just run your code on it.
That's expensive, you're gonna pay a lot of money for it.
All of that storage takes a lot of power,
and therefore a lot of money.
So there's a lot of other options and optimizations
you can do to take advantage of each cloud's strengths.
Today, we're gonna use GCP, just because one, I like it,
two, the names actually make sense,
so when we talk about it, it's gonna make sense
to everybody.
And also, generally, it's actually pretty good
for data analysis, so we'll be using that today.
We are gonna make some compromises on choice, though,
because I want this to be accessible to everyone.
We will not be using Dataflow or Apache V.
I'm just gonna be running a serverless function,
we're gonna take a look at some data from there.
Again, repeatable, reusable, replicable,
and understandable for everyone to use.
But there's one more thing about citizen science
that you need.
It's great if you have all this computing power
and you know what code you're gonna run and all that,
but what are we missing?
Data, that's right.
So, where should we get your data?
One of the lovely things about all of these
various public clouds is that they've actually uploaded
a lot of the public data sets from various agencies,
including the National Oceanic and Atmospheric
Administration, which is NOAA, the National Weather Service,
and also Sphere Weather Data.
So, they pull all of that in.
You no longer have to pay for all of that storage,
which is actually pretty fantastic.
They host it for free, so you can analyze
the data yourself.
You don't pay for ingress ingress,
all of these various things typically have to pay for
with infrastructure.
So, we're gonna take advantage of that today.
But, what question are we solving today?
Well, March 25th, generally in Austin, Texas.
How many people were following the news
over the past two weeks?
I see like three of you.
Y'all, come on.
All right, what typically happens on March 25th in Austin?
This weather related, I'm not talking basketball.
Hail, that's right.
I don't know if anybody saw it, but there's like,
it's all over Reddit, all over the news.
March 25th, go cover your car.
Quick, put it in the garage.
I mean, yesterday was pretty sunny if you ask me.
But, we're gonna take a look and see,
is it true that March 25th is historically
the most likely chance for hail?
And with that being said, let's go look at some code.
Okay, can everybody in the back see that?
Yes.
Yes, I see thumbs up, so we are in good shape.
So, let's take a look at what we're taking a look at here.
Because I can't do this without actually
looking over my shoulder.
I'm gonna look with all of you.
So, let's just scroll up a little bit.
Here we go, hey, look.
Okay, so we're doing a little bit of the same thing
Okay, so we're doing a little bit of importing here.
Mainly the big thing is, you can take a look
at the secrets in the importing string.
That's just mostly for line 10,
which is giving me some random string
that I'm appending to my job.
The reason we do that is because otherwise
we're gonna get collisions when we push stuff up
if there's already code running there.
So, that's just something to keep in mind.
Random strings are helpful for naming
to ensure that when you actually run all of this
regularly, you never actually overwrite
something you already have.
This is something that you see pretty commonly
in infrastructure as code.
Now, this line seven is actually pulling in
my little SQL query.
There we go, that's not highlighted anymore.
I like to put my SQL query in a different file
just because it's a little bit easier for me to modify
and keep under source control.
So, you'll get a chance to see that.
Generally, what we're doing on this round
is we are pulling from the severe weather dataset.
We are pulling every year from 1950 on forward.
And we're gonna run against that
and just look for the event date that it started.
Is it actually a hail event?
And did it happen here in Travis County?
So, those are three big things
that we're actually pulling down.
Oh, did it happen in March?
Because we're gonna narrow this all down.
And now we get to the actual infrastructure.
Again, this is all written in Python,
so should be fairly simple to read
in comparison to other languages.
I've been stuck in TypeScript lately,
so I'm much happier being back in Python all over again.
But a couple things to keep in mind
when we actually take a look at any infrastructure as code
is that you are looking at, in this case,
a declarative piece of code.
I like to call it desired state.
We're basically passing this up to the cloud
and saying, hey, hit the same key on it
and give me exactly what I've asked for.
So, in this case, we've got a bucket, which is storage,
a bucket object, which is just the file that's in storage.
We have another storage bucket.
The reason we have two is one has code,
that's why it's called code bucket.
And then I have my dataset, which is what?
My data, that's right, okay.
Just making sure you all are awake.
Let me have our actual BigQuery dataset here.
Again, this is just a little test dataset
that I have just to store the data
that I'm actually gonna be querying,
which we'll then pull out to use for a cloud function.
That's why it's just called foo and bar.
Then we have two jobs.
The jobs themselves are the important thing
for the actual query.
The first one is a query job,
because if you look on line 47,
yes, I can see that upside down.
If you look at line 47, what does it say?
Query, that means it's a query job.
The next one down,
and you can see we actually have that secure storage data,
the next one down is our export job.
And the export job just takes that data
that we were actually gonna run
from the query from the table
and dumps it in my storage bucket for just a minute
while my cloud function actually is gonna run
and pull that data out.
And then it comes out as a CSV,
because we're gonna also be using pandas,
like the last speaker,
who brought that up in the very first part,
so I guess he didn't really use it in the end,
but it's there as well.
And then we have our function to analyze some data.
You'll note that I'm running an old Python 3.9,
and we are here in the central region for GCP.
So just a couple of little things here.
This storage URL is the important part
that tells us where the data's gonna be living.
And okay, one more thing about infrastructure just to know
is that unlike running it on your local machine,
you have to have permissions.
So you have to have a little system that says,
hey, this user's actually allowed you
to do what it's actually doing.
If you don't do this,
someone's gonna be able to hack into your entire system
and do everything that they wanna do.
So maybe that part's kind of important to mention.
Just a little bit.
At the end, we're actually gonna see,
when we run the code,
we'll get a chance to actually see the variables.
Let's go take a look at the app real quick.
Again, I decided not to,
can you all read that in the back?
Bigger.
Bigger?
Okay, hold on.
Put the mic down.
Better?
Excellent.
All right, so this is actually a fairly small analysis.
I'm not going through a big one
because it's gonna take too much time,
unfortunately, to actually run it.
But we are just gonna go through, pull in our data,
and we're gonna just grab the CSV,
do a little bit of parsing on there,
get my date time in the right format there on line 13.
We're gonna append it all to one data frame,
and then we're going to actually plot it
starting on line 20.
Let's go.
And one thing to note,
they don't really explain this about plot functions.
It's running Flask in the background
if you're running Python.
So even though I'm not actually recording this,
and if you go actually run the code yourself
on your local machine and try to do it yourself,
you'll see that I'm not actually installing Flask
in the requirements.
So that's only because it's already there
on the plot functions,
and I'm not really sure they really documented that.
But all that being said, y'all ready to see how this works?
Woo-woo, woo-woo.
All right, pray for the demo gods.
Because I'm doing this live.
I have not run anything.
Blimey, yeah.
Here we go.
Maybe.
Up here.
No, it's up here.
Hey, Bloopy, what are you doing?
Oh, I know what I did.
Here we are.
How many people just kind of go up and hit this?
No action taken.
What are you doing, Bloopy?
For some reason, it's deciding that I have to run.
Let me figure out what on earth it's doing.
Normally, what this would actually do
is show you all kinds of lovely information.
I wonder if I can actually run it
in this one specific one.
But let me run it locally.
Oh, I know why.
Because we're not in the right directory.
All right.
Now let's try running Pulumi up.
Actually, we're gonna do a PIPM shell real quick.
I am running PIPM.
Please don't yell at me if you have issues with PIPM.
We can talk about it later.
All right, now we're getting a preview.
And why is it all the way stuck up there?
Hello.
I don't know why it's lovingly doing that.
We're gonna make it its own window.
Maybe, here we go.
All right, so here we go.
Now we're getting what we need to see here.
Let's make this a little bit bigger.
Hello.
Here we go.
Okay, so what this is doing is it's running a live update.
It gives me a preview first.
This is important whenever you're doing
any kind of infrastructure's code.
You need to be able to see what it's about to do
to your environment before it actually runs.
So in this case, we are seeing all of these various things
in a very, very, very poor format.
But we'll see the reaction of our data set,
our bucket, our table, the bucket object,
the function, the function number, and the jobs.
So we can actually look at details,
but I'm just gonna hit yes,
and we're gonna see that it's gonna actually deploy.
Now this does take a little bit,
and then I don't know why this isn't scrolling.
Here we go.
You know, we did have the Jet Brands people here.
Maybe I need to have a discussion with them
about what this is doing when it's in
a weird terminal function like this.
Because normally it shows me a nice little table
and it shows that everything actually deployed.
Oh, we're gonna wait with it, because you know, live demo.
I don't do it, I don't do it.
This function actually does take a little bit of time
to deploy here, but actually, I wonder if we can see it.
I, oh, we're gonna go see if we can see
what it's doing in this health console.
There it is, so you can actually see my function
is getting made up there at the top.
We'll make that a little bit bigger.
All right, my computer doesn't like me today.
But it's running.
We have our code, where did my terminal go?
There it is, still creating.
While this is creating, do anybody have any questions for me?
Terry?
Is this like the Terraform?
Is this like the Terraform process?
Sort of, it's kind of like the Terraform process.
The big difference between Pulumi and Terraform
is that we use development languages, programming languages.
So if you're familiar with Terraform,
we just did a Pulumi preview,
it's kind of like a Terraform plan,
where it just kind of checks and sees what's out there.
And then we're running Pulumi up,
which is whatever Terraform's like applied.
I guess it's Terraform applied, yes?
I think that's what it's called.
Anyway, so yeah.
Well, any other questions while we're waiting for this thing
to decide to finish right now?
Yeah, Ryan?
If you run this more than once,
are you gonna create multiple resources
or does it update the resources?
Great question.
The question was, if we run this more than once,
does it recreate all of the resources,
multiple resources, or just update
the ones that are in place, right?
It's gonna update the ones that are in place.
That's actually the next part of the demo.
No, so generally, infrastructure is code.
This is one of the reasons why you use it,
is that it doesn't actually try to reinstall everything.
It does actually make sure
that you don't reapply everything,
so you're not rebuilding everything.
The reason that's really important
is that it takes less time,
therefore you're spending less money,
which is a good thing,
and you also don't really overdo it.
All right, how many people think it's the 25th?
How many people think it's the 27th?
The fourth, take a look at that.
That right there, friends, is the 25th of March.
Since 1950, we have had, what is that,
over 50 hail events on March 25th.
Now, that also includes,
because you have to remember,
this is reports of hail,
so that includes multiple reports on Sundays.
So, next year, March 25th comes around,
maybe consider taking your car to the garage.
We're covering it with pool noodles
or whatever else we're doing today.
So, go do some science.
The very first link that you see up there
will have my GitHub repo,
so if you want to go do this yourself, you certainly can.
Thank you all so much for listening.
Thank you for putting up with my technical difficulties,
and I'd love to take any questions y'all have.
Thank you very much.
Have a good time.
Good luck, everyone.
Okay.
Good job.
Bye.
Have a good one.
Ooohhh!
Bye.