All right, all right.
So I guess I'm the last one that gets to say good morning.
We'll talk a little bit about sets today.
It's good to be back in Texas.
It's been a few years.
So I'm Andy Fundinger, and this is Always Use Sets.
So I always find it's more useful than giving a year
to talk about which Python version I started with.
So when I started learning Python,
the book said, learn Python 2.2.
Then they had a little slide that said,
newly revised for Python 2.3.
And well, Python 2.4 had just come out.
So that's where I start from.
I've worked with Plone.
I've worked with Twisted.
I've worked in the financial industry.
I've done a little bit with virtual world stuff.
I've been at Bloomberg since about 2017.
In 2019, I went over to our system reliability engineering
groups.
And in 2020, to data services or DNA,
which is why they put that on my fleece.
I work on something called our data gateway.
It sits in the middle of a lot of our workflows.
We're a gateway, so all the code around me
is owned by other people.
Both upstream and downstream is other people's code.
We have billions of requests per day going through there
and millions of semi-independent code paths.
This is easy to imagine when you realize
that our queries are something like, what
is the price of this security?
Well, if the security is a stock, that's easy.
You go to the exchange to see what the last price was.
You send it back.
If it's a bond, there's this whole pricing thing
that you need a bunch of information and then you can do.
If it's an index, you need the price
of a whole bunch of other things and then to figure it out.
And then you can send that back.
And that's where our code paths just multiply.
So a lot of what I do day to day is ingest telemetry data
and process it a bit to understand what's
going on in a complex system.
Of course, today we're talking about sets.
And that means we need to talk about all the data structures.
We'll start with tuples.
Tuples we declare with parentheses.
They're ordered, they're frozen, they're immutable.
And you can have duplicate items.
Lists, we go to the square brackets.
They're ordered, they're immutable.
You can have duplicate items.
You may imagine this won't be our only slide
about what sets do.
But they use the curly braces.
They have to be a collection of hashable objects.
They are unordered.
If you want them to be immutable,
you can use a frozen set.
And all the items have to be unique.
The dictionary, we add the colons to the curly braces.
And we have a map of hashable objects to other objects.
As of Python 3.6, they are ordered.
Sets are still not ordered.
We'll come back to that.
And all the keys have to be unique.
The constraint here is not just that they're unique.
It is that they are hashable, which means
dunder hash and dunder equal.
And then there's one other that I
want to put into this talk because it completes
some rough edges.
The counter, often collections.counter,
is a map of hashable objects to the counts
of their occurrences.
And all the keys there have to be unique.
Now, the cool thing is this changes
a collection of things with duplicates,
where order doesn't matter, into a dictionary.
So if you have something that would be a set,
except it has duplicates, just refer to the dictionary
section of the talk.
So how do we use sets?
We can declare them easily enough.
There's a constructor.
We have set comprehensions.
We have an add method to add things.
We have a remove method to remove things.
Until we put in type hinting and start checking
and start paying attention to the type checker,
we can mix and match types in our set.
They are also collections from the abstract base
collections, which gives them a few properties.
Particularly, they are iterable.
Thank you, Moshi.
They have a length.
And they have the in operator.
So I can say, is this in my set?
Yes.
Is this not in my set?
Also, yes, because I chose the thing I removed.
There are also some particular set operations.
And this is where the real power comes from,
because these operations are implemented down in the C level.
We can union, which is take two sets,
and give us a set that combines everything in both of them.
We can intersect, give us the set of things
that are in both of them.
We can difference.
Take this set, and we can do the same thing.
We can do the same thing.
We can difference.
Take this set.
Remove anything in that set.
And we can symmetric difference, which
is give us all the things that are only in one set,
but not in both, sort of the XOR of set operations.
So in mid-conclusion, always use sets.
By using a set, we clearly communicate our expectations.
We tell the people that it might be changed,
but if more things are added and they duplicate, that's fine.
If things are removed, they're removed,
that we're going to check whether things are in there,
that we don't care about the order.
We communicate a whole lot by just saying, this is a set.
And this will perhaps not matter when
you write an include list that's written one time in a constant
and goes down into your code somewhere.
But as you maintain the code, as you use it later,
the fact that you made it a set from the beginning
prevents the behavior from drifting
and prevents anyone from having to ask, well,
if we put it in there twice, what does
that mean for an exclude list?
And then the other one, because of those set operations,
we can write algorithms based on discrete math.
We can go in to our data structures and algorithms book
and it'll say, oh, just union the two things.
And we can just do that.
So it's like tapping into an extra stack of documentation.
But I see there's some time.
But I see there's some time left.
So you might have some questions about speed.
I thought I'd answer those.
How do we measure the speed of something in Python?
For something as basic as this, there's
a standard library timet.
It will work for this.
If you're doing more benchmarking,
then you want to use some of the tools
that Carol talked about.
So we'll check our help on timet timet.
It tells us that we give it a statement, a setup, a number.
And then it tells us this is a convenience function
for the timer object timet method.
So we should check our documentation
on timet timer timet, which explains
that it does all the performance timing stuff
and returns in seconds how long it
took to run all the iterations you asked for, which we might
then want to divide by.
So this is what timet looks like.
We see that declaring this 10 item set gives us 10
to the negative 6 seconds.
10 to the negative 9th is nanoseconds.
So that's 1,000 nanoseconds, or a millisecond.
And I'll use that timing through the rest.
The other question is memory.
Again, we have a memory function, getSizeOf.
It's often sys.
This is probably the only time you
would want to actually use that practically.
The problem with the getSizeOf function, whatever you give it,
it gives you the size of.
Now, that sounds like exactly what you would want.
It doesn't give you the size of anything in it.
So when we're looking at the size of the set,
it's telling us how big the set is,
not how big the item's in the set.
If we took a dictionary, if you took a class that
has stuff in it that has stuff in it that has stuff in it,
it doesn't tell you any of that.
But we're talking about sets, so this
tells us what we need to know.
And if you need more, may I suggest
memory, which we open sourced.
So what's the size of a set?
An empty set is 216 bytes in Python.
But it might matter a little bit how many items
we put in the set.
So let's go ahead and take a look at that.
I am using the log of memory, so this is a log scale.
Otherwise, things get very distorted.
So we'll zoom in on 1,000 items.
And I'll take that log scale off just so we can see it.
Our set takes 32k.
The tuple or the list of the same size takes 8k.
So we do need to know set or frozen set,
just the same dictionary a little bit more,
that we are using a lot of memory when we're using sets.
So how long does it take to construct a set?
Well, obviously, that depends on the size.
Obviously, I can put a big, long,
long time graph of sets, frozen sets, sets, and tuples.
And we'll just go ahead and acknowledge
there is more than one way to construct a set.
This is using the constructor with a list,
generating, building.
But the fastest is just to go to the constructor.
If we look at 1,000 item set, what we see
is it takes about seven milliseconds
to make 1,000 item set with the constructor.
By comparison, the tuple can do it in a millisecond.
So we do have a bit of construction time.
List also takes a millisecond.
And I'm not sure if I'm hitting an optimization on that one.
Oh, did I jump a slide?
I think I jumped a slide there.
Constructing a set.
What about changing the set?
So obviously, this is going to get more interesting when
we start changing it, because it is a mutable type.
And if we take a look at this, for some basic mutations,
the set is a little bit faster than the list.
Sorry.
And we'll just go ahead and add tuples in here
and vary it both on the size and the number of mutations.
But if we look at 1,000 items and we say,
let's look at how many mutations we do, this is set.
So if we're doing really any number of mutations,
we see that doing the same mutations on a list or a tuple
is taking much longer.
We'll go ahead and pull that back out and ask the question,
so how many mutations should we do to get a payoff?
This is doing 10 mutations with different sizes of sets.
So if we're doing 10 mutations and we have a set size of 10,
it comes out about equal.
But as soon as we're doing 100, we're really
pulling ahead on sets here.
Again, this is on a log scale.
So that's basically the answer that I've found there.
If you're doing 10 mutations, you should just
go ahead and use a set for performance reasons
in addition to clarity.
Now, the next question is, what if order matters?
What if we do actually need it ordered?
So I'm adding an additional performance measure here.
This is the mutate sort.
This is do the mutations and then
sort it to get back the order.
And it turns out that while we do
lose a little bit of performance to doing that sort,
it is still faster than doing it in a list.
So even if you have to sort it afterwards,
if you're doing 10 changes, you might as well just use a set.
But then we do have dicts.
And dicts are pretty good.
Dicts are amazing in Python because they
underlie the entire class object structure.
So a lot of work has gone into making dicts faster.
In fact, sets were added in Python 2.3.
So when I started learning Python,
there were an awful lot of instructions on how to use dicts
when you probably should have used a set,
but they just came out.
So I went into the code, and I was curious.
There is separate code for sets at this point.
And there's this helpful comment that tells us what to expect.
It says, use cases for sets differ considerably
from dictionaries, where looked up keys are more
likely to be present because you're probably
going through an object asking for something
that ought to be there.
In contrast, sets are primarily about membership testing,
where the presence of an element is not known in advance.
Accordingly, the set implementation
needs to optimize for both the found and not found case, which
suggests that we should find the dictionaries are faster when
the thing is there, and the sets are faster
when the thing is not there.
Testing has shown this not to be true.
So they wind up being pretty even at a first glance.
And looking at 10 and 100 this time,
it turns out that a set search for missing
is a little bit faster than a dictionary search for missing.
And a set search when it's present
is similarly a little bit faster than a dict search
when it's present.
So either way, if you're just doing the membership testing,
you do get a benefit of sets.
So that brings us to the set operations
that we were looking at earlier.
How do those fare, set versus dictionary?
So I'm looking here at set for update and dictionary
for update.
So we find the set updates noticeably faster
than the dictionary update.
Set unions just the same.
Set intersect is faster than using a dictionary
to implement intersect.
It's all faster, but is it faster enough
like we saw with lists where we might as well sort it?
We can, of course, implement these things
so that we use a dictionary and then put it back together
after using the set operations on the sets.
So set difference looks like that.
Set intersect looks like that.
Pretty simple.
For symmetric diff, there's two ways
to do it depending on whether you care about the values.
I think if you don't care about the values,
it might be cheating, but we'll cheat.
So you can use the from keys to construct a dictionary where
all the values are the same.
And that may be interesting in one or two cases.
The symmetric diff valves, we do have
to go and maintain the values.
So what I did was I went ahead and merged the dictionaries,
did a set intersection, and then just subtracted the ones
that were in both.
Let's see how that does.
Set operations, too.
So we'll go ahead and add those.
And it turns out by taking a dictionary over to a set
just to do intersection, you lose all your advantage.
Same thing with difference.
But symmetric difference, you do get a pretty good advantage
if you can ignore the values.
Again, that's cheating, but cheating's fun.
But a small advantage still even if you pull the values back out
and put them together.
So the conclusion of this talk was written before the talk.
The conclusion is always use sets.
I hope that's not too much of a surprise.
And the big reason is to add the clarity.
By making it a set, you tell everyone maintaining it,
including yourself in six months,
more about what's going to happen and what's expected.
They are faster than lists or tuples
when even 10 items are changed.
So even if you have to sort or do some combination later.
Unfortunately, I also have to say, do not use sets.
And don't use them if you're running out of memory.
OK, about four times as big.
If a dict is equally idiomatic, you're
going to have to do some pretty heavy lifting before sets
are going to pay off.
I think of it as the line is symmetric diff.
If you can take the keys off, do some set operations
that are at least as complex as symmetric diff,
and put it back in, you will get a performance benefit.
And you and your code reviewers will have
to think about the clarity benefit.
But if you're not at least manipulating
the keys in a few operations, they're not going to pay off.
And you can just leave it as a dictionary.
And with that, I will take questions.
And I do have some questions for you.
All right, are you ready?
No.
Oh, yes, yes.
OK, we get ready in the question answering position.
How much memory do you save over a dictionary with sets?
Any good tools to profile the real world difference?
So there's lots of tools for memory profiling.
Memory will work fairly well.
And I think I have to say that.
In terms of straight saving on the set, it was, do I have that?
Straight saving on the set, it's like 30k on an empty one.
And just kind of trivial.
Let me bring this back up.
Dictionary, 1,000 items.
The set is 32,984.
The dictionary, you're saving about 4k at 1,000 items.
Right.
What did you do to measure mutation on a tuple
since it's immutable?
Oh, I took them apart and put them back together.
Yes, don't do that.
But for completeness, I did include it in the graphs.
How do you personally handle the non-determinism
of set ordering across runs?
Either avoid having it be important.
This usually comes up in your test cases
by either using PyTest's ability to just handle the compare for you
or running a sort so that you can do a compare on it.
Right.
And then can you explain what this is?
And it was where you used times 10 to the ninth power.
Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah.
So I got this tiny little number here times
10 to the negative sixth.
And I said, what is that?
I'm going to be talking in 10 to the negative six seconds
for an entire presentation.
So I said, what is that?
OK, 10 to the negative ninth is nanoseconds.
So it's 1,000 nanoseconds.
Very cool.
Oh, it looks like I got one more question that came in
while we've been talking.
Did you notice any difference between the performance
of sets and frozen sets?
No.
I did include them.
They have a noise level difference in the cases
where I included them, which are obviously
before I start mutating.
Here it is.
And zoom it in.
Next one to zoom in.
So constructing the frozen set is 7,000 nanoseconds.
And constructing the set is 6,000.
6.7 thousand.
So there is a slight difference there, but.
Frozen sets are still good for building a snowman,
but I had to let it go.
Last one.
This will be the last one.
Can you expand into that use case of exclude list
you mentioned at the beginning and any other real world
case that you've used them and liked it?
Yeah, yeah.
So if you're doing some testing and you have said,
I'm going to test everything, and in our case,
it was a number of machines, I'm going to test all the machines,
except I know this one is a special case.
So if anybody ever wants to run a test on that, just don't.
Or just return an error that says this machine is not
used for testing.
So what we did was we defined an exclude list
at a pretty high level.
And then down in the code where it actually figured out
which machines it was asked for, it goes,
I'm about to run this machine.
Is it in the exclude list?
Yes.
Then I will skip it.
Very cool.
Well, thank you very much.