Thank you, Brad.
As Brad mentioned, my name is Jason Ku.
I am a developer advocate for Neo4j,
a graph database company.
And I will be talking about using large language models
because there's no way you're gonna get away from Gen.ai,
even here, using it to create a knowledge graph.
Now, before I dive deep into what I'm gonna present here,
I would like to start off with a confession.
And that confession is I have an amazing ability
to forget pretty much everything.
I am probably, maybe arguably, if Laura is not in here,
arguably probably the person with the worst memory possible.
I have managed to, in 20 feet, go from buying a movie ticket
to losing that ticket before I got to the person
that rips it, and then subsequently losing 20 more dollars
to get that movie ticket.
Okay, so, sample of chaos is if you can't remember anything.
Okay, so, I was super excited, oop,
super excited when media works.
If not, okay, so, years ago.
Oh, we'll just show everything at once.
Yeah, let's.
Screen, do you want, and this one?
Pay no attention to the elves behind the scene.
Mirroring everything?
Let's do, not that one.
This, I believe, is my presentation.
Okay, yes, so, a couple years ago,
actually a lot of years ago now,
there was a whole spate of second brain apps
that came out, right?
Notion, Roam, and my favorite, Obsidian.
And it was great, right?
As a developer, I could write all my notes in Markdown,
and then using just some special syntax,
kind of link those documents together, right?
So, my favorite thing was this graph view, right?
And I think I can actually show you my Obsidian right here.
So, this view is, I think, very awesome.
Of course, how do I close this?
All right, I'm not gonna do all this too long.
But, anyways, you can see the sort of connection
between your documents, and I thought this was great, right?
It gives you a little bit of, not quite context,
but like memory, like, oh, okay,
so I met this person at this event,
and I also met this person at some other event.
It started to help me, like, remember folks
that I would run into a lot,
or events that I went to, or places, right?
So, question then, is this a knowledge graph
inside Obsidian?
Almost, it's not quite a knowledge graph,
because those links between the documents are,
they're kind of inferred relationships,
but the relationship itself isn't explicitly defined, right?
So, I've got one doc that links to another doc,
but what does that link mean, right?
It's like looking at a crime board
where you've got a victim, and then a killer,
and then a place, and a receipt,
and they got that red line joining everything, right?
You, as an audience, you know what the red line means,
because the whole rest of the show
was telling you what those connections are.
Oh, this is a receipt from that store
that connects the, you know, whoever to the other person.
So, just like that, in Obsidian,
those lines aren't explicit enough.
So, that's where knowledge graph is a little bit different,
right, it takes those kind of unknown relationships
and defines them, right?
So, like, we here today, we make up a knowledge graph,
right, we make up the structure of information, right?
So, I'm here, I'm talking to you,
you're listening to me, we are all as a group
at a session that is itself a part of an abstract thing,
right, Pi Texas, which is located here
at this public library, right?
And you can map that all out in a knowledge graph.
Now, why is that interesting?
A knowledge graph gives you some extra abilities, right?
It gives you context.
So, okay, I'll come back to context.
So, the links that go between us,
they are basically like little invisible threads
you can kind of pull on, right?
So, this kind of goes to the second part,
the searchability, right?
So, Carol, only she is from Encinitas.
Encinitas is in San Diego County, or maybe just outside.
It's in Southern California,
very close to San Diego where I live.
Great, maybe there's a chance
we have a circle of friends close together,
but we're both here at Pi Texas, we both like Python.
So, very likely, we've got a circle of friends
that overlap pretty strongly, right?
So, that's something you can discover in a knowledge graph.
Also, because knowledge graphs are inherently
based on relationships and entities, it's very flexible.
So, you can iterate on knowledge graphs a lot.
All right, so, great.
So, you've got a structure
for containing context and information.
How does that help us as developers?
What can store a knowledge graph?
Graph databases are really good
for storing knowledge graphs,
because the relationships that I've been talking about,
that is part of the data store.
So, unlike some older databases
where you have to temporarily create like a join,
the relationship is explicitly stored
as a first class data component inside a graph database.
And these are ranking, or this is a short list
of available graph databases out in the market.
Each has their own unique abilities, features, pros and cons.
Neo4j, in particular, is a type of graph database
known as a property graph database.
What that means is the nodes, or the entities,
they can contain properties, just like a row of data,
but also the relationships can contain properties.
So, not just names, but you could put in time info,
you could put in weights and values, right?
So, all of us, we all know Python, right?
That's sort of a shared thing.
But to what degree do we know Python, right?
Like, Ali, I would say, is probably like,
if we had to turn it into a float value,
probably like a .99, maybe a 1.0,
like all the way up at the top.
And me, I'm probably more like a .01, maybe?
So, you can add these weights to a knowledge graph,
to that data, right?
And if you come from the machine learning background,
you know that's very useful for lifting
and creating ML models with.
You can do that with data from a graph database,
which is already in the form of what more or less
looks like kind of a neural network.
Okay, so, other advantages of graph databases in general.
No foreign keys.
Like, the relationship itself, because it is stored,
it knows which two nodes it connects to.
And often, the nodes are written close together.
So, when the system is traversing through the relationships,
it's going very fast, right?
It's not a heavy lift to ask really deep,
many-to-many questions,
which is kind of the third benefit, right?
Which is, because the information is interconnected,
presumably, you can have a sparse graph
where you're just putting in entities
and they're not connected,
in which case a graph database will not do you any favors,
use something else.
But if you are using the relationships, great.
And then, of course, it's very flexible,
just like a knowledge graph.
You can just add entities.
You can add relationships.
You can modify those relationships.
So long as you are not destroying relationships
from old data, you can iterate.
So, you could create a whole data model,
whole populated graph database,
have a whole system of querying it,
and then you're like, oh, wait, I have a better way.
I should create, instead of having six hops
from a vendor all the way to a customer,
I just wanna connect them directly.
You can add that.
And then, all your new queries can take advantage
of those new relationships.
But your old queries will still work
so long as you haven't destroyed those old relationships.
So, you could have basically many operating schemas
on top of one graph system, one knowledge graph.
Okay, I'm gonna skip past this.
Because it's in all good fashion, LLM's,
the testing did not work earlier, so I'm just gonna skip.
And go right to talking about the main part of my talk,
which is how do you get your existing data
into a knowledge graph?
Okay, so one option is to use large language models,
which makes things quicker.
And so, the stack I'm gonna talk about today
is using Lang chain to act as sort of this AI orchestrator.
If you haven't played with Gen.AI yet,
there are a couple tools like Lang chain, Llama index,
that try to make it easier to work
with different components, right?
So, I'll demonstrate how that looks.
And I'm gonna use OpenAI, because everyone uses OpenAI.
GPT-4 is still one of the better models.
And then, I'll show how to push that into a Neo4j database.
Okay, so I'll try to go through all three of these workflows
so you get a sense of this.
So, we've got our data, which I'll talk about in a minute.
And the manual process would be to just take that data,
chunk it up, and have it fit into this data model
that I've got in my head, and put it into the database.
The two LLM options with Lang chain
is kind of this three step process.
You're gonna take a file, and you're gonna put it
into what is called a document loader.
It is just a general object for Lang chain
for consuming text data, basically.
So, it could be a YouTube transcript,
could be a PDF, CSV, whatever.
And when you put it into a document loader,
it then becomes kind of this generic object
that other parts of the chain can make use of.
Okay, and then I've got two options here.
I'm gonna use a vector only approach,
and then also a new module that was added by Lang chain
called the graph transformer.
So, the graph transformer is a module
that will take in this text document
from the document loader, and will attempt to break it up
into entities and relationships, okay.
All right, the data I'm going to work with,
or I'm just gonna showcase is a CSV
of the agenda data that we have.
So, I used the diff bot to take a first crack
at kind of converting this into a CSV.
It got kind of close.
I had to manually kind of massage it.
What I probably should have done
was just ask the organizers for their copy of the CSV data.
That's gonna be easier, but I thought
I'd give diff bot a try.
And then the other piece of data is just a link to video,
or YouTube video, which translates
to a transcript of the video.
Okay, so this is the part where everything breaks.
Okay, if you can still hear me, excellent.
Okay, so what I've got up and running here
is I've got a local instance of Neo4j,
and this is what the desktop looks like.
You can basically spin up a bunch of databases,
and here I spun up one for PyTexas, so it's an instance,
and the instance itself has several databases
so I can toy with manual and LLM approaches.
Okay, so I'm going to use the main database,
pardon me, and just show you that it is empty.
I hope it's empty.
Okay, so no records, this is the empty database.
And what I've done is I built this really simple importer
that is just a Streamlit app that lets me
choose my target Neo4j database,
and then lets me select one of various
experimental uploaders, right?
All right, so the first thing I'm gonna try
is this graph-simple approach.
And I'm gonna take the agenda CSV and put it in there.
And that data looks like, where am I looking?
All right, so it's just a CSV,
I guess I don't really have to find it,
but I really wanna find it.
Here it is, okay.
Okay, so CSV, probably should open that in a Excel sheet.
So it just has title, description, speaker, bio.
And I'm just gonna import that in.
How the code looks is,
so here I'm not using Lang chain at all.
So what I'm doing is taking the file
that Streamlit has handed me,
and just going to throw it into a pandas read CSV function,
and then just go through every row,
and basically pull out the row headers and values.
So I'm gonna turn that into properties.
Well, actually not properties,
I'm gonna turn those into nodes.
And then just push that into a Neo4j instance.
So yeah, just reading the rows,
and then basically writing into Cypher.
Cypher is the query language that Neo4j wrote
to interface with graph databases.
Interestingly, oh, sorry, interestingly,
the ISO standard for interfacing with graph databases,
so basically the ISO version of SQL,
came out, let's see, yesterday, two days ago,
so just recently.
So now there's a standard for even modifying SQL
or Postgres databases to be able to query graph systems.
So there's a whole standard in spec.
Now, their reference material was also Cypher,
which is what I'm cobbling together here.
So if you start with Cypher,
which there's gonna be more material on Cypher
than the new GQL, graph query language,
which as a sidebar, is not the same as GraphQL,
which is the REST alternative, right?
So the acronyms are both the same for both.
And to make it more confusing,
if you have worked with GraphQL,
is GraphQL is a good way to actually interface with data
in a graph database, if you're just pulling data.
But yes, so anyways, two different languages.
So I digress, if you start with Cypher,
you will find the on-ramp to GQL not too difficult
because they borrowed a lot from Cypher.
So the two actually look quite similar.
And because Neo4j was also on the,
or had a representative on the ISO board,
anytime they decided like, hey,
we're gonna add this feature to GQL,
Neo4j went like, okay, we're gonna add that as well too,
so that there's an interoperability that will happen.
Okay, all right.
Slightly forgot where we went.
Okay, so I'm just gonna run this
to show you what this looks like.
Okay, so uploaded.
At least I thought I uploaded, oh, okay.
So what I did is I uploaded it to the wrong database.
Let me try this again.
Oh, let's see if that worked or not.
Clearly I did not pay, oh, all right, nevermind.
Okay, so this is what that CSV looks like
using this very manual process.
All right, so I've got the document,
the agenda CSV, and all the pieces.
So basically what this did was it broke up each row
and then decided from there like, okay, what...
So basically made a node for each record.
This in terms of knowledge graph
is not really a great knowledge graph,
but it shows you how you can quickly create one
just from even a CSV file.
You can do it from JSON, text, et cetera.
Okay, now going back to here.
Now I'm gonna show you the graph trends
transformer, oh, actually, let me show you the...
Actually, yeah, I'll do graph transformer.
We might skip the vector today.
Okay, so the graph transformer.
So this is Lang chain's new fantastic module
for automatically creating nodes and edges for you.
Okay, so very similar function starting off
except this bit here.
So part of Streamlit is for the CSV loader to work,
it needs a path.
So I can't just give the file.
I had to basically temporarily create a location
for the file just to get the path
to then feed to the CSV document loader.
So as you're working with Lang chain
and these sort of modules,
be aware that they expect like very certain things
and it's not always well documented.
So be open to experimenting a lot with this stuff.
Okay, so here's the CSV loader,
which is like Lang chain component.
It takes the CSV and it basically chunks up
each of the rows and headers and properties.
Now I take that loaded CSV and using OpenAI as the LLM,
it's going to do some magic here
and cut that up into what it thinks
that CSV should turn into.
And then I'm just gonna add whatever it gives me
into a Neo4j instance.
Okay, so that's this guy.
What I'm gonna do is I'm gonna reset this database
so that it's blank.
So this is what it looks like manually.
I'm gonna wipe this out and then reload this.
And this one I'm just going to upload
like I think three of the sessions
because every time I've tried to load the entire agenda,
the LLM decides not to quit somewhere along the way.
Okay, so this is probably a little small for folks.
Let me, so anyways, so this is an example
of what Cypher looks like, right?
So match is a common keyword versus select.
And then maybe I'll showcase this later,
but afterwards it's this sort of ASCII art syntax, right?
So anything in a parens is a node,
anything in a bracket is a relationship.
In this case, I'm asking it to give me
every single node that it's got, right?
And actually this looked pretty good, right?
So we've got the CSV file and it decided to break it up.
All right, for each row.
So actually this looks quite similar to the manual process.
Oh yeah?
I think you're right.
Yes, no wonder that I was like, wow, that looked really good.
I never got that before.
Okay, all right, try this again.
All right, changes to transformer and let it run.
You'll also notice that any time you add
a large language model to any part of your process,
the time takes much, much longer.
Another reason, ah, okay.
So I had this problem earlier with the full file.
Let me just, sometimes it will just work though.
All right, I'm only gonna give this one other try.
Otherwise I'll just kind of talk through it.
Okay, I will talk through it instead.
So what I have is, boop.
So I'm gonna switch to this other database,
which I thought I had preloaded this prior.
Okay, so this bit here was what the LLM had given me
the last time I ran this.
So you can see it created a bunch of nodes
and relationships.
A good chunk of it is connected,
but you have these sort of orphaned bits
and they're not connected to this at all, right?
So you would normally think if we as a human
were creating this, we would have at least one node
that was, this is the source document
and tie everything in together.
But this graph transformer doesn't seem to be built
to do that, so it'll just create a bunch of nodes.
And so if you were to do this with a lot of files,
you would probably come up with a really like,
kind of like, like DNA that's been broken up.
Just a lot of floaties floating around.
So I'm glad that Langchain has started
building this graph transformer,
but as you can see, it's still very early on.
So it's gonna take a little work
before this kind of competes with local stuff.
All right, let me zoom back.
Oh, I guess while we're here,
I have just a wee bit of time.
Vectors, so the whole retrieval augmented generation
the whole retrieval augmented generation rag architecture
has been created over the last year
to help large language models deal with two main things.
A, that they hallucinate a lot,
and two, they have a limited context window.
So if you are working on a project
that requires some sort of permanent memory store
for the large language model to compare against,
vector databases have become kind of the mainstay, right,
of what you would use.
Now, you can use vectors with graph databases.
So this is a great combination
because vectors are fantastic with unstructured data, right?
Like lots of texts, it's like,
okay, what's the feeling about a thing?
Vectors are great at pulling that.
But vectors are, unlike a lot of traditional databases,
really terrible at math, right?
So if you want to ask a vector database,
hey, how many records do you have?
It will just choose a number
from any one of the documents it has.
So unless somebody wrote a document
that says how many files you've got in the database,
you won't know.
But a graph database and basically any other database
can give you those answers, right?
So sidebar, if you're working on a large language project,
it's okay to mix and match different technologies.
You will get much better results.
Okay, all right.
Okay, so that's my demo, basically,
since I got kind of moderate results
with the large language model.
Yeah, I guess we could just jump right to questions,
which I'm assuming people will have.
Oh.
Off the first question,
how does a graph database differ from a vector database?
Great question.
So in a nutshell,
vector databases take some data and turn it into a vector,
or you take a vector embedding,
which is basically a list of numbers, right?
And you put that and you store it
in kind of this vector space.
So if you imagine, it's not quite accurate,
but if you imagine the 3D box,
each embedding basically takes a dot,
a point in that space.
And when a vector database is asked to pull information,
oftentimes you'll grab an embedding
and try to find one that's similar to that.
So example, you have some text,
it's turned into embedding that represents
the semantic meaning of that text.
Then when you ask a question,
that is turned into an embedding as well.
And then those two are compared,
and anything that's kind of close
to the question embedding is pulled up, right?
But each one of those dots,
pieces of data in a vector database, they're independent.
They're not linked, right?
You can add in some metadata,
but there is no relationship between different embeddings.
But a graph database, it stores that relationship.
So if you imagine it as a 3D space,
it kind of looks not quite like a brain,
but you can imagine like a branch,
like a very dense tree branch
is what a graph database would kind of look like.
Hopefully that answers that question.
I got some of that.
Okay, so the next question,
I don't even understand the question,
but I think you probably will.
And hopefully the answer will make sense.
So how do you avoid LLM hallucinations when adding,
how do you avoid LLM hallucinations adding or removing data
when entering into the database?
Ah, okay.
So whether you're using like SQL or a graph database,
you can use text to SQL or text to cipher modules.
So what you're doing is you're not letting the LLM
directly interact with your database.
What you're doing is you're taking like a question
and using the LLM to convert that into a query, right?
And then you run the query against the database,
the answer comes back,
and then the LLM interprets that answer.
So you can shield your database
from being hopefully errantly like messed up.
But yeah, that's generally the process.
I actually did understand that answer.
That's helpful.
Okay.
Next one, any best practices
when building a knowledge graph database,
anything in particular to be aware of
when you're building one specifically for LLM use?
Oh, okay.
So just in general,
when you're building like a graph database
or a knowledge graph,
is you wanna think about your data model,
what it's gonna look like at first.
Don't fret that it has to be perfect.
It's going to change.
Everyone who works with knowledge graphs,
it's constantly iterating.
So you start with your best thing,
and then you kinda import and work with that.
When it comes to large language models,
we haven't found anything specific yet
that really gets great.
Oh no, I take it back.
So you want to have the relationships use words
that are very common and make sense.
So don't use relationship names that are very complicated.
And if you have very complex paths
between two entities that you always ask questions about.
Like, hey, my ultimate question is this person,
does this person like red shoes?
But the path to finding out,
maybe they purchased this, that,
and the other thing, they know this person.
Just create a relationship between the two,
and then you ask the LLM.
Because the LLM also has difficulty
in reasoning very complex paths.
Even if you give an LLM the schema,
I found that maybe only 60, 70% of the time,
it actually looks at the schema and goes like,
yes, I'm gonna write a query that matches that.
The other 40, 50% of the time,
it's like, meh, I'm just gonna write up
my own query sentence, and then it won't work at all.
Gotcha, so explicitly to find that linkage relationship,
and it can parse it.
Yes, so if you go in and you kinda simplify things for it.
Yeah, it works, that makes sense.
So we're running a little bit ahead,
so I'm gonna ask one more question,
and then we'll hand it off.
Are relationships only extracted
if made explicit in the document,
or can it add implicit relationships known to the LLM
that could be useful?
So that kinda ties off what we were just talking about.
So, okay, so is the question asking, can it?
Yeah, are they only extracted if they're made explicit,
or basically can it infer some of those?
And that sounds kinda like where we were already.
Yes, yeah, so sometimes it can.
I've not found it consistent.
It's just, yeah, it's kind of roll of the dice at the moment.
Fair enough, okay.
All right, well thank you so much.
Thank you, Brad.
Everyone, Jason.
Jason.