All right. Thank you. Can everyone hear me okay? All good? Okay. Great. So hello, everyone.
Thank you for being here. I'm really super grateful for this opportunity. So I'll be
talking about containers today. So there were, like, a couple of talks about containers already.
You'll learn something new. So that's my goal. So how many of you use Docker regularly for
containerization and everything? Okay. Quite a few. So by the end of this talk, I hope
you have a better intuition about building more efficient containers. And, you know,
for your Python apps, you know, specifically. Okay. So the way it will go is that I will
cover I will actually go over a sample Python application, which I built. Okay. Go through
the base Docker file for it. And then we'll try to improve it over time and see how we
improve the numbers, improve the, you know, image size and the build times. Okay? So let's
get started. I'm so glad the sun is out. So, yeah, hopefully we'll have a better energy.
Okay. So a little bit about me. So I got introduced to Python in, you know, 2013. That was mostly
about the data science and aspect of things. So currently I work at the star family at Intuit,
where I lead AI ops efforts there. I love RPG games, by the way, especially in, you know,
PS5. Any last of us fans, hopefully. Yeah. So I love it. And hopefully I want to become a yoga
instructor in the near future. So, you know, fingers crossed for that. So without any further ado,
let's talk about the motivation behind why are we really talking about images and containers. So
we all know that, you know, shipping applications and productions using Docker is kind of like a go
to right now, especially when you use something like, you know, Kubernetes with it, right?
Another good thing is that building an image for a Python application is actually, you know,
pretty straightforward. It's not that hard to, you know, set it up and, you know, get something
running. The tricky part is to really optimize it for your application for, you know, faster
build time and, you know, smaller image size. So we'll go into all of that soon. And this is
even more complicated when you have something which has a non-Python dependency. So maybe
something like a C extension, C++ or Rust. Okay. So let's go over a little bit about the basics,
about what is a container. We'll just skim through it. I'm sure, like, many people know about it.
So a container is basically, you know, it's about packaging the application with all of its files,
configs and dependencies and run that in isolation. Okay? So that's all it is, right? But what about
an image? So an image, so the way I like to think of it is the image is like an instruction template.
Okay? It's an instruction. It's actually a set of instructions on how to run this whole container.
So it has different layers that depend on top of another ones where we can add, remove, you know,
run, you know, run things, all of that. And it's written in a file called Dockerfile. And the
benefits are, you know, portability. So it is very portable, which means that you can, you know,
just, you know, copy from, you know, one machine to another with a different architecture. You
might have to change a little bit, but otherwise it's pretty portable. Isolation, because you're
able to isolate your application from any other system processes. Then you have scalability,
of course, you know, especially combined with something like Kubernetes. It's very, very
scalable. Now, it's also deterministic, so it's reproducible, right? Well, at least it's supposed
to be. You know, we'll see in a second that, you know, sometimes, you know, there are some
gotchas there, right? And it's very lightweight compared to a traditional virtual machine, right?
Because it's just, you know, simple, you know, Linux VM, which is running, you know, in isolation.
So in compared to a traditional virtual machine where you have a full-fledged OS running is very,
very lightweight. Okay. So why should we really care about making better images? Like,
why are we really here, right? So the main thing that we need to, you know, think about is that
if our images are not really efficient, that will lead to slower build times. And slower build times
will affect the way developers, you know, ship things to production. So it will decrease the
developer productivity, okay? And as well as it's very difficult to fail fast, which means you have
to wait for your code to really build in order to really test what is going on and if things are
running or not. Then there's the obvious thing, which is the larger image sizes. So if we have a
really huge image, it will require more storage, it will have longer download times, and if you
have a CI series set up, it will really take a long time for that image to get, you know, pushed
as well. And of course, there are some security risks as well. If you're not careful, for example,
you're using a very outdated base image with, you know, let's say a very older version of Debian or
something, then you will have some security risks as well. And of course, if you're really not
careful, there could be a performance overhead as well. Okay. And by the way, this is very easy to
make this mistake about the large images there. So when we talk about efficiency, right, how do
we really measure it? So for this talk, I'm going to focus on four different metrics, okay? So we'll
go over them. The first is the biggest one, which is the uncompressed image size. Many times when
you see, you know, like in many of the portals like, you know, Quay or maybe some, you know,
Docker, right, you will see the compressed image size, but we're talking about the uncompressed
image size. So that is the one that is the most important, okay? So this is our biggest metric.
Then we have the initial very first build time. So this is the one where we have no caching. Imagine
that you're building an application, right? And you are just building it for the very first time.
So you don't have any caching whatsoever. Then the rebuild time after a code change. So of course,
you're developing, right? So you will have some code changes. So how does the rebuild time work
after any kind of a code change? Okay. And the rebuild time after dependency change. So let's
say you install a new package or you deleted some package. How does that affect? So we'll focus on
these four metrics and we'll see how that goes. So our example application, this is what I built.
And by the way, this is all there on GitHub. So we'll give you the link later on. So it's a fast
API based machine learning application which runs on or which uses the very famous MNIST dataset.
MNIST is the handwriting digit recognition. So I just trained a very simple convolution neural
network in PyTorch. But the main thing is that I included a very simple C++ extension. So this
small extension will make the image building a little bit more spicy. Okay? So this is how
our C++ extension looks like. Okay? So on the right, you have our classify image function which
basically does take the image. So take the digit. Maybe it's four or five. It takes the image,
converts that to a tensor. It loads the model and then runs it through the prediction. Okay?
But the output that we get from the model is actually a soft max output which is a fancy way
of saying that there are ten digits. So you have ten different outputs, each of them summing up to
probability distribution, and you want to take the one which gives you the maximum probability.
So in this case, we'll have to use the argmax function. Now, instead of using the usual torch
dot argmax, I'm going to use my own extension where I wrote this in C++, and it does the same
thing. Okay? It just adds a little bit more complexity there. Okay? So we're good here.
So let's get started with building our first Dockerfile. Okay. So I would say the full
directory structure looks like this. So we have a Dockerignore file, right, which is very important,
which is similar to gitignore, and it's very important so that you don't copy some unwanted
dependencies or unwanted files or caches, right? So you have Dockerignore. You have our Dockerfile.
We have the artifact, which is our model. We have the extension directory. This is where I actually
store the argmax.c++ file, and then I have the setup.py to build that extension. Then I have
some project and then some requirements files, and then I have my source code, right? So all
is good there, and I have my requirements.txt as well. I have hard constraints in the requirements
file for deterministic behavior, right? That's what we want, so which is good. By the way,
this approach that I'm going to take is just one of the approaches. You can do it in multiple ways,
but hopefully it will make things clear on what to focus on. Okay? So this is our initial Dockerfile.
So I'll just go over it very quickly, actually, since we are short of time. So the first line,
we are basically basing from a base image, which is the Python 3.12 in a bookworm. Bookworm is the
latest Debian version. We set up some environment variables where we say the default timeout and we
disable the version check because that will just increase the build time. Then we are in the app
work directory. We copy the source files. We copy the requirements and the extension folder, and we
then install the dependencies. Okay? In the end, we have the command for actually running that fast
API application. Okay? So we are actually doing a lot of good things here. So we have a Docker
ignore file, right? We are actually basing from a very good image. Okay? This is the latest Python,
the stable version, at least. Well, as far as I know. Okay? And then the bookworm, which is the
latest stable Debian version. Okay? And we are also freezing the required packages, which is very
good. Okay? But the best part, it works. So this thing works. Okay? So it's great. And this is our
performance. So we talked about the four different metrics that we'll go over. So this is our
performance here. So the image size is a whopping 1.85 gigs. Okay? That's pretty big. So that is
something we have to really work on. The build time, it's about a minute. So it takes this much
time to build it. The first time, which is why it's without a cache, right? Then we have the
rebuild time without any changes you make. Now, this is where Docker is very powerful, because
it can really cache things up, so you don't have to spend any more time if you are just rebuilding
the same thing. Okay? So it's just three seconds. Then rebuild time with code change, it still takes
a minute. So every time you make a code change, it will take a minute for this to be built again.
And this is where we need to fix next, right? Then we have the rebuild time with dependency
change. So any time you add a package, anything, so it will also require something. So it will also
need a minute of change there, right? So in all of this, what do you think is the slowest step
of the whole process? Yeah, exactly. So it's the installation. So these installation is actually
the biggest, it's the slowest step of the whole process, right? So the bad thing is that the
image size is about 1.85 gigs. Now, builds are actually non-deterministic here, and I'll come to
that just in the next optimization. But the first thing that we need to really fix is that dependencies
are reinstalled for every code change. Okay? Which is bad. We really need to fix this, right? So what
do we do? We just change the order of operations. So instead of installing, instead of actually
copying the whole source code into the app source, we just copy the requirements file first. We copy
that, and then we install the dependencies. Now, the cool thing here is that now, any time we change
anything in the source code, it will not get reinstalled again, right? So the requirements
would not get reinstalled again at all, because everything above that is actually cached. That's
how Docker layer caching works. So if there's any change at this point, at this point when we
actually copy the source files, all the previous layers are actually cached. So we should be very
quick there. So, yeah, so we know this. And then if you look at the change in the performance,
it's huge. It's huge, right? So we can actually rebuild with any code change in less than three
seconds. That's amazing. Okay. But the bad thing is that, well, we did not do anything to improve
the size of the image, right? We just changed the order. And then builds are still non-deterministic.
Now, why do I say that? Now, the whole point of Dockers or the containers and images is to
make things reproducible, okay? But this is a non-deterministic behavior. And the reason is,
I guess many of you know it, it's basically due to the concept of transitive dependencies, right?
If you recall earlier, we did have constraints on the requirements file. We did have that. But
transitive dependencies basically mean dependency of a dependency. So I might have a hard constraint
on a package A saying that this is the version that I need, okay? Really hard constraint. But
that package A might have some loose constraints in package B, okay? And so on. So this could
actually go on a long time, right? So this is where we need to fix it. Okay. So which lets us
to the next optimization, which is we actually pin the dependencies, right? So now we use, you know,
some tool. So in some packaging tool, it could be, you know, poetry. It could be in PDM, Hatch,
in PIP tools. Just pardon me if I missed something. But really, anything would work, okay?
So I use poetry here to export the log file to a requirements file. So you see the requirements
exported.txt. This is basically the exported requirements from the log file used by poetry.
But you could really use anything. Now, the second thing that I've done is separate the dev and the
main dependencies, okay? Now, that is pretty important. Because if you recall, I had some
dependency like, you know, torch, torch vision, all of that, you know, which are required. But
I also had something like pi test and black. Now, those are basically dev dependencies,
right? You don't need them. So we separated that out. And then I also disabled the PIP cache.
Because you don't need really caching inside the image building process, right?
So we did some improvements here, right? So the image size has reduced. It's still big,
but it's still better, right? So the build time has reduced, and then the rebuild time also has
reduced, right? So this is good. So we are going somewhere, right? But the bad thing is,
the size is still big. So it's about 1.7 gigs. And yes, so we are going to tackle this, right?
So let's tackle the elephant in the room first. Okay. So a very easy fix could be
use a smaller base image, right? So if the base image is very big, then, of course,
the whole image size will be big. Now, we were using the old image, which was, you know, Python
3.12 in Bookworm, right? But the problem with that image is that it actually ships with many
things which we really don't need in production. So things like Git, Curl, you know, all of those
things. Like, unless you need it, you don't need to install them, right? So let's use a slim image.
Now, this one does not have all of those additional functionalities. So let's use that, right?
So that should do it, right? Just use a smaller base image. But life is not that simple, okay?
So the problem is that we did not install any compiler to install the C++ dependencies, okay?
So we'll really get a nasty error, and we have all seen those errors, I think, right? So that's
the ugly part. This will actually lead to an error because we don't have the compiler to
install the C++ dependency, right? So we do something else. We now install the compiler.
So here I run, you know, AppGit update, and I can, you know, AppGit install the G++ compiler.
And like a good engineer, I also remove it in the end. So that should be fine, right? I install it,
I install the compiler, I install the dependencies, then I don't need it, so I remove it.
So let's take a look at the performance. So, by the way, this actually gives a lower base image
download time as well, since the slim image is actually much smaller. So if you look at the
performance, it's actually a drastic improvement. We went from 1.7 to 1.12, okay? Now the build time
got increased. I'm sure you can point that out, like, how will that happen? That's because we are
now forced to install the compiler as well. So every time we have to run this AppGit update,
and also the AppGit install G++, right? So this should be good, right? So
I think this is where life gets easy, right? But the problem is,
are we really removing the compiler in the right way? Okay. And this is where things get really
tricky with Docker files. So the way the layering works is that layers are appended on top of each
other. So here you can see that even though we are removing G++ in the end, we are not really
removing it from the previous layers, and we need all the layers to actually get the final image.
So the compiler needs to be fetched even though it won't be accessed in our final image,
due to this purge command, right? So we are not really removing the G++ compiler in the
right way here, okay? So what do we do? We now combine the layers. So let's combine the layers,
so in one run command, now we have AppGit update, install, install the requirements,
we run the setup, and we also remove the compiler, right? So let's see how the performance looks like
now, right? We did improve a lot. So the image size is now less than one gig. The build time
has been improved, and the rebuild time is actually increased a little bit. And here's
the trade-off, right? It will always do the slow AppGit update in the compiler installs whenever
there's a change in the dependencies, because remember, we have combined everything into one
layer, right? So there has to be that trade-off, okay? All right. So the not so good part, as I
said, was that any change in dependencies will trigger all five of those run commands, okay?
So where can we go next? Or do you think is that it? Well, not so. Because Docker supports
something called the multi-stage builds where you have a builder and a runner stage. So the builder
makes sure that you install all the dependencies and the runner just runs the application. Now,
in a compiled language, it's pretty easy. So if you have a C++ code, let's say you have your file,
so in your builder stage, you just install the compiler, compile the file, you get the executable,
you copy the executable to the runner image, and then you're done. But here in Python, we have to
copy the whole interpreter environment, right? But how do we do that? We are not using any kind
of virtual environment or something, right? Because if you use the global Python package or
the environment, it actually installs it in multiple different places, okay? So there's one
way to fix it, which is either do a user-based install or use a virtual environment, okay?
So we are going to use a virtual environment here, okay? So if you look at here, we actually
are installing in a virtual environment, and then we are copying the requirements as before,
and we are installing all the requirements and then just installing the dependencies
in the environment, okay? Then in the runner stage, what we are doing is we are just copying
that virtual environment in our path, right? And finally, we copy the source, and then we're good,
okay? So there are very good things going on here, right? Because dependencies are installed in a
virtual environment, the builder takes care of installing the dependencies, which is needed,
and then the runner is only responsible for running the application. Now, another good point
about this is the builder can no longer require to be a slim image, right? It can be a non-slim
image, so it's never running in production, so we can afford to use the bigger base image there,
right? So the performance looks like this. So we reduced the image size even further,
our build time got increased by a lot, and our rebuild time as well, okay? And that is only because
that we use from that slim version to the actual bigger version there, and we don't have to
mirror run all of those five run commands together, okay? So maybe a nitpick
is that your packages are downloaded every single time this install, this pip install layer gets
triggered. So imagine that you're installing, you're actually building, so every time there
is a dependency change, you're actually downloading the packages from the internet. Maybe we can do
something about that. Which takes us to our last optimization, which is cache mount. Now,
cache mount is a newer feature in the Docker build kit. I mean, relatively new. So it basically
enables us to use a persistent package cache to be used during builds. This can be very, very
useful for, you know, packaging, like, for maybe, like, any kind of package manager, actually.
Like, you know, something like apt-get or pip or npm. So here we're using the mount cache for
the pip cache, right? So here you can see that I mount it, and then I install all of the dependencies
again. But the good thing is that we don't have to download all packages every time from the web,
but only when a new package has been added, right? Okay. So that's good. And now the performance
looks something like this. We have the image size. Image size is still the same, but the re-build
time has decreased a lot, and the re-build time with any dependency change has decreased, and
that's only because of that we don't have to download any packages every time from the web.
Okay. All right. So to recap, we, you know, we started with 1.85, you know, 1.85 gigs, right?
That's pretty huge. And most of them are actually coming from the Torch library. Okay. So anytime
you have a big machine learning library dependency, this is bound to happen, okay?
And then so we did a 56% improvement in image size, and that's pretty huge, I think.
Then we also did a 30% improvement in the re-build time with dependency change, okay? So that's
also very good because dependencies can change a lot of times, so that is very great. But of course,
just by doing that simple layer ordering, we improved the re-build time with code change by
98%. And that's something that, you know, people overlook, like, in quite a bit. I've seen that.
Okay. So there are some other best practices I really want people to follow because this will
really help, you know, in their own way. Always use a Python-specific Docker-ignore file. So we
have Python-specific Git-ignore files as well, and we also have Docker-ignore files on the same,
like, on the same level. So use a language-specific one. It will really help you there.
And always separate dev and prod dependencies. You don't need, you don't need, like, a full
fledge of dependency tree in your prod environment. Just use what we really need there, okay?
Okay. And always use the latest Debian, you know, Ubuntu or Red Hat distribution to base
from. This will actually prevent a lot of security vulnerabilities as well, and you will also get the
latest improvement in speed and memory management and all of that. And also, try to avoid specifying
the Python patch version, like, from the base image. So, I mean, something like it's very easy
to do, like, 3.1, 12.2 in Bookworm, okay? Now, what that will do is that will actually bind you
to only, like, only that version. You won't get the patch updates. So, you know, something like
3.1 to Bookworm will just make sure that when, you know, 3.12.3 comes back, it will actually
download that one, okay? And this is very ML-specific. I would say I would highly encourage
you to use a CPU-specific versus a GPU-specific image. So what happens is usually when I've seen
in my company and in my work is that you need GPU for training, but you normally don't need it for,
like, inference or for, you know, predictions like in production. So, I mean, something like
that, you know, specifically will actually reduce the size of the image by quite a bit,
because Torch actually, like, supports CPU-specific and GPU-specific images as well,
or just the, you know, just the wheels as well. So that would be all. I have the code here. I will
actually upload everything in a byte tonight. So hopefully if you have any, like, any questions,
anything, just, you know, feel free to ping me there. Well, we have lots of questions. Thank you.
Thank you, Avik. All right. We have lots of questions. You got people excited. I learned
some stuff from this. So this is great. So off the top, if you would unplug so they can set
Andy up. Keep the mic. There we go. All right. Come this way with me. All right. So first off,
do you track the size and image build time metrics in your CICD flows?
And do you have any advice on how teams could start doing that?
Yeah. Yeah. So I do really, and I've started this practice because otherwise it can get out of hand.
Okay. So the way I do it is so there is a time functionality in like in bash. So you can use
time and then build the image and you can, you know, like put different arguments. So like,
for example, I give no cash. No cash means that you're building it for the first time. Okay. Then
I just do an echo, like echo some change, echo some dependency change. Okay. And then build the
image again. That will actually give me, you know, what is the actual time taken like for that.
Yeah. Yeah. That makes sense. Awesome. So it's all just kind of manually in your, okay.
Any features of Docker that you find not being used as often as they should,
like Docker ignore file, excluding files, anything else like that?
Yeah. I think this build cache is something that I've hardly seen, right? Something like this,
you know, run cache, which is a newer, newer thing, newer thing for Docker. It can be really
helpful for Debian based images. As I said, Red Hat based as well. You know, like especially for
Python, I think, like to build the dependencies very, very quick. Given PIP and downloading is
as slow as it is. Yeah. Especially where you don't have a good internet connection. It really,
it really bothers. Oh yeah. No, I was making notes while you're talking and that's when I'm
bringing back to mess with on Monday. So any reason to choose Python Bookworm versus Bullseye or
Alpine? That's the most stable version right now. I think that's the like LTS version. So I was
using Bullseye before. So maybe I think, you know, two years or 1.5 years before I was using,
you know, Bullseye and then, you know, Bookworm came. So we, we upgraded it. We have to do it.
Otherwise, you know, companies flagged, you know, some security vulnerabilities on all the time.
Yeah, that makes sense. Have you looked at the use of distro-less images as well as new tooling
like Rye, UV, kind of some of those newer pieces to help speed up the, to reduce the footprint
and speed up build times? For some package managers and everything? Yeah. So as part of
speeding up your Docker build using Rye or UV or some of the new kind of faster tooling around.
Yeah. So I think those, so those tools will, so we'll actually see how that turns out. So right
now we use, you know, Poetry, PDM, Hatch, but when those tools actually support other, like other,
and, you know, better functionalities, we will start using them. Okay. That's for sure. Makes
sense. I'm going to give you one more question and then we'll, we'll hand it off to our next group.
Do you use VS Code dev containers for local dev? I do not. So I use something called Nix, Nix.dev.
Okay. That, that I use for like deterministic behavior, especially for data science projects
and something that really helps, but I'll try that out. Cool. Awesome. Thanks again, Avik.