Yeah, good morning, everyone.
I'm Sameer Shukla, technology enthusiast.
I like to learn and talk about new tools and technologies.
And today I'll be sharing my experience that I had when dealing with integration testing
in my application and how I end up using test containers.
So in any cloud-native microservices architecture, as we can see that there are several downstream
dependencies and the architecture can be polyglotic, where the architecture have more than one
database in the system.
We have to support RDBMS or as well as NoSQL.
This kind of architecture provides a couple of problems for the developers.
Two main, one of them are running this infrastructure on the local.
And the second one is writing the efficient integration test cases.
The first problem of running the infrastructure on local can still be solved when we use Docker
compose.
That problem can still be solvable.
But when we write integration test cases, with this kind of architecture, it is a little
bit difficult to achieve that.
So why integration test cases are important?
When we write JUnits in our application, those are written basically just to test the business
logic and we are unable to test the external dependencies in the system.
So if we have to test, say, in our application we have Kafka or Redis, what we do generally
is we mock the entire pipeline and we will test the business logic.
But we mock the dependencies of Kafka and Cassandra.
The issue that comes with that kind of JUnit is that we are not very confident in the test
cases that we have written.
Because consider a scenario that we have to publish the event to a Kafka only once the
database call is successful.
These kind of scenarios we are unable to test only with the help of JUnits.
So to handle such situations, we have to write integration test cases in our application.
The common problems that we deal with writing integration test cases, especially the architecture
that I have shared, is setting up the dependencies.
It's difficult to spin up the entire infrastructure on your local machine because we have several
downstream dependencies and as I mentioned, the architecture can be polyglotic.
So if the setup is difficult, that can force us to think about an alternative.
That alternative is to point our application to the real infrastructure.
When we point our application to the real infrastructure, it can have a couple of problems
there as well.
The problem that I have faced in my experience is that we used to have a CI environment.
That CI environment is used by almost every team in the company.
So the test cases are fragile.
Someone can come and delete the table or the brokers were down.
So more often than not, our test cases were quite freaky.
So we were unable to, our CI CD pipelines were failed most of the time.
This problem can force developers to think about another alternative.
That alternative would be to use in-memory databases or use some embedded tools like
Embedded Kafka or Embedded Cassandra if we are using.
The problem that comes with in-memory databases or these embedded or simulated tools is that
we may miss certain features.
For example, if we are using a specific function of any database, that can be missing when
we are using in-memory databases or any specific feature of a message broker, they might be
missing if we are using those embedded tools.
If suppose we are unable to solve these problems, the other two problems that we still face
is the data management.
Because when we used to run the integration test cases parallelly, we need a proper set
of data.
We still have to manage the data, the consistent data in the environment.
And another problem is the resource management.
We have to ensure that the infrastructure is up and we are also responsible for bringing
down that infrastructure.
To achieve that, we have to write the code that we still have to maintain.
That's where the test containers come into the picture.
So it's a testing framework, a library, that helps us in writing the test cases with the
real dependencies.
And these dependencies are available to us in the temporary Docker containers.
Test containers provide an easy-to-use API.
That API helps us in basically bringing up the temporary Docker containers, bringing
them down, and helps us in communicating with those real dependencies.
So we don't have to rely on segregating our test cases.
That we have to write JUnits or integration test cases.
Any test case that we will write will talk to these real dependencies, whether it's JUnit
or integration test cases.
The biggest advantage of using test containers is that we don't have to deal with bringing
up the containers or bringing them down.
All these throw-away instances are managed by the test containers itself.
It helps us in achieving the realistic testing, as I mentioned, the problem with the JUnits.
Environment remains consistent.
The biggest advantage is the easier setup.
So if you see this code, test containers API provides certain, you know, it has, it supports
almost every software that is available.
If you are using Postgres in our application, it has Postgres containers, Redis containers,
Kafka containers.
All we have to do is we just have to use them.
Spinning up the Docker containers will be taken care by test containers itself.
And the version problem.
This is the most important problem.
So as I mentioned, if we are using any in-memory database or simulated systems, we may miss
certain important features.
With test containers, the biggest advantage is if we are using a specific version of Postgres
in production, we can use the same version with our test containers.
We don't have to, I mean, the version remains the same for whatever tools we are using in
our microservices architecture.
This is the biggest advantage, in my opinion.
Because sometimes when you write JUnits, although it may say that everything is correct, but
we have to still test the dependencies.
So if you see this diagram, what it says is that there is a service, which I am calling
it as my service.
Test containers is an API which is responsible for spinning up these three test containers,
as I mentioned.
Like for Kafka, it has Kafka container.
For Redis, it has Redis container.
Now benefits.
Some of the benefits I have already told, but I would like to talk about three most
important benefits over here.
The dynamic configuration.
When we write Docker Compose, we have to somehow specify on what port a certain system will
work on or what kind of machine we are using.
Test containers takes care of the dynamic configuration on its own.
It dynamically allocates the IP.
It dynamically allocates the port as well.
So we don't have to deal with all of them.
All we do is just spin up the API and containers will be given to us.
Test containers, like the test cases, which we will write using test containers, can be
the part of CI-CD pipelines as well.
On local, we can have a Docker daemon, but if we are running a CI-CD, it can connect
to the Docker, which is running on the remote host as well.
So we don't have to configure anything manually.
The API provides certain functions to connect to the, like I will show you with the code.
So if you see here, the connection URL or host API, these kind of functions will make
sure that our test cases remain consistent in every environment, whether it is local
or the part of the CI-CD.
And support for various technologies.
So if you see the page over here, test containers have support for almost every component.
If we talk about database, it has support of Postgres, MySQL, Oracle, NoSQL, if we talk
about it, it has support for MongoDB, Cassandra.
So it is supporting almost every software that is available.
And support for these three advantages will help developers in reduced development time.
All we have to do is we don't have to segregate the test cases.
What we can do is we can simply write our test cases and test the entire pipeline without
mocking any external dependencies.
And the test containers workflow.
It is a simple three-step process.
First, we have to start the containers.
Second, run the test, clean up the containers.
After starting the containers, test container API provides certain functions like start.
For cleaning up the containers, it has functions like stop.
All we have to do is we just have to focus on our test cases.
And just provide the configuration at the time of startup.
So those throwaway instances will be start on our machine, and we can simply point our
test cases to those instances.
So it's a very simple setup.
There is not many complex things are going on behind the scenes.
All we have to do is whatever configuration we have done for our application to talk to
database, we simply have to point that or we can inject dynamically that configuration
for pointing our application to the test containers rather than having any complex mechanism for that.
So for this demo, for today's demo, I mean, I have created a very simple API using fast
API, it's a RESTful service.
It has three operations, post, get, and delete.
I'm calling it as a user service.
The first operation, which is post, what it will do is when we create a user, the user
will be created in the database.
And similarly, at the same time, the same information will be stored in the Redis cache.
When we get, when we try to get the user, first it will see whether the user exists
in the Redis cache or not.
If it exists over there, it returns the user.
Otherwise, it will go to the database and fetch the same information.
The intent here is to showcase how we can use multiple test containers within our application.
So this is a simple API that I have created.
I'll just try to create a user here.
So we can see the user has been created.
The user is retrieved.
And it's gone.
So these three operations, we are going to test using our integration, which is written
using test containers.
So as I mentioned, it's a three-step process, starting up the containers, executing the
tests, and removing those instances.
Test containers API has support for every component, as I mentioned.
So we are going to import them.
I'm using some specific versions of those libraries, like Postgres, Redis.
We can specify whatever version we are using in production.
We are going to start the containers.
And through this block of code, I'm trying to explain how we can point our application
to the test containers.
And these are the simple integration test cases.
So these three test cases were successful.
But I would also like to showcase how these containers are created for us.
If I go over here, we can see that there are no Docker containers running as of now.
I will just pause the test for a few seconds, just to showcase that test containers is creating
those throwaway instances for us.
So you can see here, we have two containers running, the Redis and the Postgres.
Once the execution of those containers is complete, we are going to start the test.
So we have two containers running, the Redis and the Postgres.
Once the execution of these tests are over, as we can see it is completed, these instances
are removed for us.
So that's how, in a nutshell, the test container works.
And if you see here, in these functions, I have written a very basic test case.
I have not tried to mock the application.
I have not tried to mock anything over there.
I'm simply calling the services that I have written, or the functions that I have written,
to talk to the database or talk to the Redis over there.
The last piece is, as I mentioned, that test containers have support for almost every container,
every tool that is available.
We can utilize them.
And some of them which are missing over there, like Snowflake or any other component, that
we can always request to the test container folks.
And they can provide us with a certain solution.
One of them is using the generic container option.
If we don't have any component available upfront, test container has support for generic container.
What it does is, it will allow us to inject the dependencies into the generic container.
That support is pretty much alive.
You can talk to them, and they are very responsive.
So that's all for today.
If you have any questions, please let me know.
Okay.
So some of the questions that we have out here in Slido.
Can you please reiterate why test containers are better than Docker Compose with regular
integration testing?
Yes.
Because of the dynamic configuration, when we create Docker Compose, we have to make
sure that there are no port conflicts.
And we also have to ensure that the test that we are running on local should be the part
of the CI CD as well.
So to avoid all those conflicts, we should always use test containers rather than Docker
Compose.
Right.
Get right up on that mic, by the way.
If you want to grab it, you can take it with you.
We have a second one.
There we go.
Thanks.
Yeah.
Hold it close to your mouth when you talk too.
Next one.
How do you handle persistent data dependencies, like databases, that contain data where the
test may have a temporal component, meaning the test data expires?
Yes.
Test container API, I have shown you a very basic demo over here.
The API has support of those features as well.
So you can use, please go to the test containers forum and you can find all those functions
over there.
It has support to all of them.
All right.
Do you see test containers as a complete replacement for end-to-end tests?
Yes, I can see that.
Wow.
Because of the support of various software that I have provided that is available, plus
it's very easy to use.
Okay.
What benefits does it offer when we work with multiple services?
For example, in a microservice setup when writing integration tests.
So as I showcase in my demo that several downstream dependencies can be used directly.
So you don't have to configure anything.
All you have to do is just focus on starting up those dependencies and point your test
cases to them.
Nice.
I'm going to keep hitting you with questions here because we've got a lot of good ones.
Was it easy for your organization to adopt test containers?
Did it help lower your operational costs or speed up the development life cycle?
Yes, I can talk about two of them.
It has certainly speed up the development time.
I have seen that because we were focusing completely on writing the integration test
cases.
We are not mocking several dependencies over there.
And yes, our organization has completely adopted test containers.
Okay.
This question is interestingly phrased, but we can still automate...
Oh, sorry.
Josh is moderating back there and has moved questions around on me.
If the API that your code is dependent on is in a different repo and is changing upstream,
what's the best practice for when and how to update your containers?
Can you please come in?
Yeah.
So if the API that your code is dependent on is in a different repo and it's changing
upstream, so they're changing independently of you, what's the best practice for keeping
those containers updated?
Yeah.
I mean, the repo...
Is this repo dependent on any other...
I mean, there are integration test cases in this repo also or it is completely a repo
that I'm using for my development purposes?
So I'm going to interpret the question.
Let me know if I interpreted it incorrectly, Lee, wherever you are in the room.
Let's say one team is maintaining one service out of one repository and your team is another
service that's a dependency, but it's independent.
Right.
So if one team is writing a service and we are utilizing that service, we can still use
them with the help of generic container.
We don't have to...
We are not completely tightly coupled with them.
Suppose two services are interacting.
Service A is developed by team A. Service B is developed by team B. So we can very well
interact with them with the help of generic containers.
It is not tightly coupled with it.
Okay.
Last question.
Have you seen more confidence of contribution from your juniors?
Yes, because it's pretty easy to achieve.
They don't have to write a lot of complex code.
As I mentioned, if you are writing a service layer, if you have a persistence layer, all
they have to do is just simply invoke them.
So it's very easy for the junior engineers to work with test containers rather than writing
the separate JUnits.
Nice.
Okay.
I'm going to ask one more question for myself.
On a scale of zero to Bucky here, how excited are you about test containers?
A lot.
I'm going to interpret that as Bucky.
Thank you so much, Savir.
Thanks.
Thank you.