Hi my name is Oliver Rew and I am a software engineer at Bloomberg in New
York City. I'm the last Bloomberg presenter you'll see at this conference
unless someone put in for a lightning talk then I'm sorry but I'm here today to
talk to you about a tool that my team built and some of the design that went
into it. So at Bloomberg I'm on a team that builds automation and tooling to
make our infrastructure more reliable, scalable, and efficient. Now without
getting into too many details a while back we were tasked with building a new
tool. Its purpose was to unify the existing tools used by our operations
teams and in doing so increase their repeatability and efficiency. Now for
this tool we knew we wanted an API to host it but we also needed a CLI for
individuals to interact with it. To achieve this there's a fairly common
pattern you might be familiar with. On one side you have a REST API it's got
various methods and paths it speaks JSON and it's designed to be interacted
with programmatically. And on the right you have a CLI made for human interactions
and it translates between the REST API operations and human-friendly command
syntax and output. Usually these applications are tightly coupled and the
CLI is purpose-written specifically for the latest API spec. However from past
experiences we knew this design presented a couple challenges. We knew
our API would have quite a few operations and might indeed never stop
growing depending on the requirements of our infrastructure. While building a
tightly coupled API and CLI might seem easier at first keeping the two in sync
can be cumbersome as the project grows. So let's talk a little bit about why. So a
tightly coupled API and CLI is a simple and straightforward approach. The API is
for programmatic access, the CLI is for human interaction and the CLI code
translates between the two. But when an API and CLI are tightly coupled every
time you modify one you likely have to modify the other. You need to continually
maintain two separate code bases with automation, deployments and team
knowledge and you often need to deploy API and CLI versions together so they
can stay in sync and you don't have compatibility issues. It was at this
point that we had an idea. We're already planning on maintaining good API docs
for other API clients so what if the CLI commands were just based on the API
documentation? With this model the CLI would generate its commands by simply
reading the docs every time it starts. So when your CLI is auto-generated new
features and fixes only require an API change and because of this the API and
CLI can never get out of sync. One major drawback is that it's a bit more complex
than the simple model we discussed and it should be noted that with this design
you still need to maintain two separate code bases and need to deploy the API
and CLI separately. But the advantage comes from how this scales over time. In
the beginning the CLI and API will likely both be getting changed very
frequently because they're under active development but when the CLI matures and
the API gets continual updates such as bug fixes, new features, etc. the
CLI should hopefully only require minimal maintenance. Effectively at a
certain point you can stop deploying the CLI but continue changing the API and the
CLI gets updated for free. So we assembled our first draft with simple
one-to-one mappings between the API and CLI. API paths would map to space
separated CLI commands, each path parameter, query parameter, and request
body field would be a single CLI flag and the CLI would just print the JSON
API response. We weren't the first people to think of something like this. It's
been done a couple times in the past. You can Google it or ask your favorite
LLM to do it for you. But let's look at this scheme in a little more detail. So
here's a sample API endpoint that's used to get a list of servers. It uses a get
method, its path is slash device slash compute slash servers, it takes an
optional cluster underscore name query parameter to filter results by cluster
and it responds with a JSON blob containing a list of found servers. Now
if we weren't to naively generate a CLI command from this endpoint it would look
something like this. To use it you need to fully type out get device compute
servers, specify your cluster with the dash dash cluster underscore name flag
and you get back a HTTP status code and a huge JSON blob. If you can't already tell
this scheme leads to a bad CLI and is not much better than just using curl. So we
realized that simply bolting the API and CLI together with some simple mappings
was not going to work. Doing that created a really poor user experience in
the CLI. The problem is that good APIs and CLIs are designed for very
different purposes. APIs are made for programmers writing computer code but
CLIs are fundamentally a human interface. The underlying issue is that we're
trying to map API concepts to the CLI domain but REST API paths were never
meant to be typed CLI commands. API parameter names were never meant to be
typed CLI flags and API response data is usually not meant to be consumed raw by
humans. As we developed our first draft and ran into these issues we kept trying
to think of different ways to modify the API so that it's directly mapped CLI
commands would be more human friendly. We could shorten our API paths so
that the CLI commands are easier to type or maybe API path parameters could
always become positional arguments in the CLI and not require flags. We had a
couple more ideas like this but ultimately we were looking at it in the
wrong way. The end result would have been a bad API, a bad CLI or both. If our CLI
was going to auto-generate its commands from the API we needed a translation
layer in between. Then it occurred to us maybe we can include this translation
layer in our Open API docs. The docs already contain all the basic
information a client needs to know to use the API so why not include a little
additional information about how to define the CLI interface as well. You're
clapping that's good I like it. One problem we saw was that typing out long
API path typing out a long API path as a CLI command is a lot of work for a
human in a very poor CLI user experience. Ideally long API paths could be
abstracted into succinct intuitive CLI commands so why not have the docs just
define a CLI command for a given API endpoint. Then you go from this to this.
Shorter commands mean less typing but they're also cleaner and easier to
understand. Another obvious problem we saw was API output formatting. REST APIs
often speak JSON or some other structured data format but they're
usually not meant to be read by humans. Even if we pretty printed this JSON it's
still not going to be easy for a human to read. But what if the docs included
instructions on how to translate the JSON into something easier to read then
you can go from this to this. To accomplish this translation but still
keep the CLI completely decoupled from the API we use Jinja templates.
If you're not familiar with Jinja it's a relatively simple
templating language with widespread use across the Python community. So the docs
contain a server-defined Jinja template for each API endpoint and the CLI simply
passes the API response through the template to get the human-friendly
output. Now there's a bit more nuance to the output formatting problem. We also
observe that CLI users often wanted the ability to display the same essential
data but in slightly different ways. For example what if the user wanted this
same output but as a CSV file instead of the table shown. It would be kind of
silly to have multiple virtually identical API endpoints whose only
difference was how the data was displayed to the CLI user but we could
have multiple Jinja templates per API endpoint and just give the user a way
to choose between them. We could have one template to display the output of CSV
triggered by the dash dash CSV flag. Maybe another template just to show
network information triggered by the dash dash net flag. And of course all
these options would be shown to the users in the command help text. We also
added a dash dash JSON flag to every command. That's to give the user the
option to get the raw API output and pipe it to a file or jq or something else.
Another issue we noticed involved how arguments were passed to the API.
Originally we just planned on adding one CLI flag per API argument but take a
look at this get server command which was generated from the API endpoint code
shown above it. The dash dash hostname flag really isn't buying us much. This
API endpoint takes a single required argument so it's just more for the user
to type. Why not include the ability to make arguments positional like this? A
simple change but it makes the command a lot more human friendly. Staying on the
topic of arguments we noticed another unfortunate consequence of mapping API
arguments directly to the CLI. It's often handy and good code hygiene to have
descriptive variable names in your code. Here on the right we have an example API
endpoint that collects logs for a given server and saves them to a location on a
file system. To represent the log file destination we have a descriptive
variable called destination underscore file path. While this variable name might
be helpful to programmers it's an awfully long and cumbersome CLI flag to type. Not
to mention that the use of underscores and flags doesn't really follow POSIX
conventions. So why not have the ability to specifically define the CLI flag and
short flag used to represent a given API parameter like this. Now to specify the
destination file path you can use dash dash dest path or just dash P. Again it's
little improvements like this that go a long way in improving the CLI users
experience. The final problem we observed with API and CLI argument
mapping was that sometimes arguments just couldn't be represented easily
using simple strings. For example what if the CLI command needed to upload a local
file? What about Boolean CLI flags whose simple presence represents true? What
about list arguments with a fixed or dynamic number of entries? We knew we
needed to build a dynamic system to represent unusual API arguments on the
CLI in a human-friendly way. So now that we have a good understanding of the
problem let's talk about how to implement it. We use many of the great
open source projects that you see here but we're primarily going to focus on
FastAPI. If you aren't familiar with FastAPI it's a great open source web
framework for Python. While there are numerous good reasons to use FastAPI
one feature that we really love is the built-in support for Open API doc
generation. Here on the left we have a simple FastAPI endpoint implementation
with two endpoints. With just this code FastAPI automatically generates the open
API docs on the right. However what we see on the right is not really the
documentation itself. What you're seeing is just a pretty rendering of the actual
documentation which is defined in JSON and looks something like this. This JSON
is the actual Open API spec and it contains all the information a client
needs to know to call the API. And as you can see the JSON contains a section for
each path in the API. This is what our CLI will be parsing to generate its
commands. Let's take a slightly closer look at how the Open API JSON defines an
API endpoint. Here on the right you can see the Open API JSON generated
for the get hello endpoint shown on the left. It contains a summary, a
description of parameters, along with a little bit more information that I left
out for simplicity. For our use case we needed to find extra information for
each API endpoint so the CLI can configure itself. So we just added a
section like this. Each endpoint gets a CLI section that can define things like
the actual CLI command, the Jinja formatters, and more. Fortunately for us
FastAPI has a neat keyword arg called Open API extra and that allows the user
to embed arbitrary information in the Open API spec for an individual endpoint
and it's used like this. You just include your arbitrary object in the
endpoint decorator and it's automatically nested in the Open API
spec. We could just shoehorn a huge dictionary into every endpoint decorator
but that would be awfully crude and not very readable. So instead we decided to
implement our own child class of the FastAPI API router but added a couple
additional arguments to include the CLI specification. Something like what's
shown here. With that now we can define our API endpoints and
associated CLI commands like this. We write our endpoints just like we
normally would with FastAPI but with the option of specifying a CLI command
in just a few extra lines. Of course you still need to define the specific Jinja
templates to pre-print the CLI output but in many cases we found that different
endpoints could use identical templates and there are tons of opportunities for
code reuse. Well this is all we need to describe the CLI command for an endpoint
we still haven't covered how to handle CLI arguments. FastAPI already offers a
rich set of tools to define API argument behavior. Here's the query class. Here we
use the query class to define API query parameters and the field class to define
individual fields and a JSON request body with Pydantic. There are similar
classes to define other types of API arguments as well. The information
defining these classes is also reflected in the generated Open API JSON and like
the FastAPI endpoint decorators it's also easy to just tack on extra
information. So just like the endpoint CLI specification we use Pydantic to
define our model, add it to the end argument declaration and it
automatically shows up in the Open API JSON where it can be consumed by the CLI.
So now that we have all the pieces to implement a CLI command for an API
endpoint let's put it all together. Here on the left we have our endpoint from
earlier that's used to get a list of servers. On the right we have the CLI
command that we want for this endpoint. To implement the CLI command all you
have to add is this. Just include a small amount of information about the CLI
command and FastAPI, Open API and our dynamic CLI take care of the rest.
Hopefully by now you have a good understanding of the implementation but
I think a live demo is a really good way to showcase the utility of it. I've given
this demo twice and it's gone really well so maybe third time's a charm. We'll
see, but just give me a moment to get it set up.
All right in this window here we're gonna run something called Infra API. It's a
toy API made to interact with infrastructure but it's not really doing
anything it's just running locally on my computer. All you really have to know
about it is that it's written in FastAPI and it includes the extra information
we just talked about to define a CLI for it. And in this window we're gonna run
something called infracli. Can everyone read that? Just want to check thanks.
infracli is a toy CLI to interact with infrastructure but what it really is is
just a front on Infra API that I just showed you. All these commands here get
server, delete server, new server, those are all based off of API endpoints in
Infra API. Every time infracli starts it calls out to Infra API, gets the open
API JSON, parses it and creates these commands. So let's take a look at one of
these. So we've got infracli list servers. It displays a list of known
servers in the system. It's got a single dash dash cluster flag to optionally
filter servers by cluster and it's got three formatters. Dash dash JSON, dash
dash CSV and one to just show network information. So let's see what it does.
You run it and it prints this nice column separated table of servers. I can
run list servers dash dash CSV. Same information in CSV. Now we get some
feedback from our users. They say first of all list servers is too much to type.
We want it to be just list servers. All right fine. They say you've got some
pretty glaring typos in this help text here. You should probably fix those. And
lastly they say you know that this CSV flag is great but what would
really be nice is a TSV flag or tab separated value flag. Cool. Let's see what
it takes to make those few changes. I'm gonna do a tiny bit of live coding here.
It's not important you read everything. The main point to take away is how
little coding it takes to make those changes.
So here on line 72 if you're at all familiar with FastAPI you can see where
we decorate in our endpoint to make our we decorate our function to make our API
endpoint. Here's our API path slash device slash
compute slash servers. And then on line 76 here we've got our CLI specification.
That's where we define the CLI command for this API endpoint. So we've got our
typo written help text here. We've got our command and our formatters. So let's
fix them.
We fix the help text. We change the command. And last thing we got to do is
add another formatter. Those are in another file. They're defined like this
but we've got a CSV formatter that's a lot like TSV so let's just copy it.
We're gonna replace all of our commas with tabs. Let's rename it dash dash TSV.
Maybe add a short flag dash T and then our help text should say display servers
in TSV format. All right go back here. Last thing we have to do is import it.
All right. Start it up and it works. So that should have gone well. So if we go
back to InfoCLI now we see that list servers is now list servers. And if we go
in the list server's help text we'll see the description typos are fixed and it's
got a dash dash TSV flag. If we use it we see it's now tab separated values.
To recap we just changed three different parts of CLI behavior without changing
the CLI code at all. The only thing that changed was the API code. I want to show
you one more thing. In this window I'm gonna run something called meal API. It's
a mock API to interact with meal APIs written in FastAPI just like infra API
includes the information to define a CLI for it. And in this window we'll run meal
CLI. CLI and interact with meal APIs. Meal CLI meals. It'll show you some meals.
Great. That's all I really want to show you about that. Except that meal CLI and
infracli are the exact same thing. They're both something called auto CLI
pointed at a different API. So if I want to run meal CLI I just point auto CLI at
local host 8002. And if I want to run info CLI you point at 8001. That's an
infinite number of virtual CLIs for one logical CLI code base. And when you want
to change the CLI behavior you update the API and the CLI gets updated for free.
That is all I got. Thank you.
Nice. I've got a number of questions for you here. I just have to roll myself up
onto the stage after lunch. All right. I'm gonna start from the top here. Although
you mentioned command line interfaces are for humans do you ever use command
line interfaces for automation via shell scripts etc. Yes all the time. That's what
a lot of our automation is. This tool wasn't really made for that. Our hope was
that like programmatic users would hit the API but yeah you do that all the time.
I could totally see its use for for things like this too. So yeah I would
same answer. What benefit does Jinja provide in this particular scenario? Why
can't we use the same logic we define inside of the template directly and
and generate a string? I'm not sure I understand the question. Okay. I mean
Jinja is used to translate what's essentially a dictionary into
anything you want. And we thought of other ways to do that with the see it
with while still embedding it in the API docs but it seemed like the best option.
Okay. Fair answer. How do you measure the user experience for internal products
such as this one? So how do you know that users like the changes or things like
that? We have a bunch of metrics and logging that are attached to this
without going into too many details. We can see what commands users type and
which ones they type incorrectly but honestly we more get feedback from
having meetings with them. Like the tools we're making are made for operations
teams that we work very closely with. So we try to set up meetings and say what
do you want? What sucks? What's good? And they give us feedback on that and we
change it. And the model inherently makes it easy to do that because we change we
add a little bit to the API and it automatically goes to the CLI. We're
really to a point now where we can increase velocity of like deploying new
commands to the CLI because it's so simple. It's one PR to the API code base
and it just automatically goes out there. Nice. Is auto CLI.py open source?
I expected this to be the first question because it's a question I get every time
I give this talk. No. But maybe. So I've gotten the okay tentatively to open
sources in my company. It's just a matter of time. How it's implemented internally
is not what I showed you. I kind of wrote what I showed you like completely
separate from what we did internally just for the purposes of this talk to do
it right and open source it under my company. I got to put some time into it
but hopefully coming soon. Nice.