My name is Moshe Zadka. My website is... Thank you. My website is
CobraDism.com where you can find every way of reaching out to me known to
humankind. I work for Anthropic and I definitely do not speak for my employer.
And today I want to talk to you a little bit about iteration. So let's talk about
what's gonna be on the agenda. I'm gonna talk about what iteration is in Python
because that's kind of nuanced and subtle. I'm gonna talk about how to do
that. We're gonna talk about how not to do it. So that'll be fun. And then I'll talk
about like you know why you should use it and like where. So okay let's get
started because we have a lot of stuff to cover. So I'm sure many of you have
heard the word iterable. You know what? Let me start with a question. How many
of you have done iteration in Python? Use the for loop comprehension or call the
list constructor? How many of you feel like you really understand how
it works internally? Great. So that's what I expected. Cool. So iterable. An iterable
is a protocol that has one method in it which is __iter__ and it returns an
iterator. I should have started with an iterator, right? Well kind of hard
because iterator is something that inherits from iterable, right? So it also
has a __iter__ method but it also has a __next__ method that
raises StopIteration. Now there's one extra kind of twist to that which is
obviously does a __iter__ method because it inherits from iterable but
__iter__ on an iterator returns self. So that's pretty cool because it means
it's always safe to call iter and that's a good segue to my next bit. We never
call Dunder functions in Python directly. We always call them through an operator
and in this case through these two things. So if you want to call the Dunder
method you call iter and if you want to call __next__ you call next. That also
works correctly with like C types and things that don't technically have the
Dunder method. So basically that's how iteration works from the inside in
Python. So let's write something iterable, right? We know what we need to do. What we
do is put a __iter__ method on it and return an iterator. Well, luckily we have
something that returns iterators really efficiently, right? So we snuff iter from
Python and that's an iterable thing, right? Like I have implemented an
iterable class. Great. Now let's implement an iterator.
Oops, sorry. Before we implement an iterator, here's how we use it, right? So we call
iter on it. That's called the __iter__ method. That's an iterator and then we
just call next on it and we get, you know, one and ten, right? So that works, right?
That's like, you know, the basics of iteration. That is the iter method. Okay.
So now let's see if we want to write an iterator, right? I'm kind of cheating and
I'm not implementing the __iter__ method because it won't fit on the slide.
But I'm putting two things and whenever I call next I just grab the next thing
and pop it out of the list. But you notice that when I, if you remember like
when I talked about the protocols, when this ends it has to raise a stop
iteration error. This will stop an index error so I have to translate the
exception and now it's a proper iterator. Well, how do I know that? Because I did
this, right? So I build the iterator. You notice that I didn't have to call
iter because it's already an iterator. I called next. I called next. It gave me the
numbers. But, ha-ha, what happens when I call next again? Well, it raises stop
iteration. That's great, right? So that means we've implemented the iterators
properly. And you will notice that like implementing an iterator was kind of
annoying and weird and I had to do weird stuff for that and we'll get back to
that in a few minutes. But first, like, you know, I called next an iter manually
here and like you probably have never done that or maybe done it like, you know,
half a dozen times in your life. Probably most of the time you're going to call
for. So, okay, for for I basically also need to implement under iter and I'm
also going to add a lot of prints. Why am I adding the prints? Because I want you
to see how for works. So you see I have a print from before, a print and after
the for. And notice that for already swallowed the StopIterationException
that we raised. It's a reason exception. There is no try catch here. That
exception got swallowed. That exception is what signals for to be done. So it's a
very critical exception to remember and remember to kind of raise the right
exception. But then you see that like, you know, every time it calls next
internally, right, you know that because it prints out from the next and then it
actually gets a value and prints out from the for. So this is a good way to
kind of get visibility into like actually how for works from the inside. So if you
remember in the poll in the beginning, I mentioned that, like, you know, if you
have iterated in Python, you might have used one of three ways, which is to use
for loops, list comprehensions and remember the third thing. Use the least
constructor. So the least construction is an iterator, right? It will iterate over
your stuff and put it into a list. You can see that, right? It does all the
iteration before. It swallowed the stop. Look, I do not have an explicit try
accept here. But if you remember, I do raise an exception. So it called all of
these things. It swallowed the exception. It gave me the list, right? So that's
another way to iterate. And that's important because you often don't think
of it as iterating, right? And this calls arbitrary code. Arbitrary, right? I did
print, right? I could have, like, you know, connected to the internet, you know,
for the same price, right? So it's really important to remember that the least
thing can call, like, arbitrary code. Okay. So I'm sure that if you've heard of,
like, iterators, someone, like, threw away the word generator. So what's the
connection between an iterator and a generator? That's very nuanced. An iterator
is a protocol. It says what you're supposed to do. What you're supposed to
do is you're supposed to have __next__. They're supposed to obey certain
constraints. But you remember that I wrote an iterator myself, right? And it
barely fit on a slide. It was the simplest iterator you can imagine. And it
was annoying to write, right? I had to, like, you know, put state and I had to,
like, you know, put a pop and remember where I am. And it's kind of annoying. If
you ever want to write an iterator yourself, you probably want an easier way
to do it. Luckily, so Python has generators. Generators are a facility, a
language construct that will let you implement iterators much more easily. So
why is it so easy to implement iterators with generators? So, you know, basically
this is very equivalent to, like, the previous one, right? You know, we turn
the same things, one and ten. And it also does a bunch of prints for more or less
the same reason that we did prints before, so that you can see the prints when
they come out. So, well, we all remember how to iterate through that, right?
Because I did a few slides ago. So let's iterate, right? Like same thing I write
before and after. And you'll see, like, you know, it's the same flow, right? And
when it gets to the end, again, remember four only stops when it sees a stop
iteration exception, which means there's a hidden throw or, like, a raise at the
end that raised a stop iteration and then four swallowed it and returned. So in
this case, both the raise and the try and accept are invisible for different
reasons. The generator has a hidden raise and the for loop has a hidden try
accept, so you don't see any of them. But it's important to remember that earlier
on, before I used any of these, like, you know, nice language constructs, they had
try and accept and raise, and that was explicit. This is the same thing, but
they're invisible. Okay, so yield form is really, really nice in generators
because it is the equivalent of calling a function from another function, right?
Except nuance, yield form, the input of that does not have to be a generator. In
fact, it does not have to be an iterator. It only needs to be an iterable, right?
That's important. Remember, iterable is something that you can call iter on it to
get an iterator. Every iterator is an iterable because if you call iter on
iterator, you get itself. Every generator is an iterator because we saw that
earlier. So often, right, especially if you have, like, a recursive generator, you
know, then it will call itself. And if you have a recursion, usually that's the
form it will take, a yield form. But the yield form can do anything, right? You can
yield from one comma two, and that will be fine, right? Because it's a tuple and
tuple, blah, blah, blah. So it's kind of weird, but you can do that. Anyway, so you
see, I do a list of that, right? It prints begin, middle, end. Those come from the
yield form. I probably should have added another print before the hundred, but you
see, the result is 110, 100. Right? So this is pretty cool. So now we get, like, a sense
of, like, why generators are so useful. Because, again, imagine implementing this
logic yourself in a class with, like, a dunder iter on the next method. It would
be a lot of code, lots of annoying code, you have to remember. Am I still doing the
yield form, so I need to continue that? Or am I done? Like, you know, you'd have to
have, like, very complicated state. You basically be implementing kind of a
mini interpreter. This way, you get to use the Python interpreter, sort of, you
know, implement your own mini interpreter. So remember I said list is a way of
iterating? So I was not lying, but I was not being completely truthful. Every
single sequence constructor is a way of iterator, right? So list is a sequence
constructor. It constructs lists, which are a sequence. Double-ended queue, also a
sequence constructor. You can make a double-ended queue with a length of zero.
But still, when you call the constructor, it will consume your iterator. And that's
occasionally very useful. Sometimes you want to kind of eat up the iterator
without taking any extra space, maybe because you want the side effects, right?
For example, in here, the side effects are printing, right? So it prints, but it
takes zero space. Again, kind of an esoteric use case, but it's important to
hold this use case in mind, because there are very similar use cases to that that
will be important, and it's important to remember that these two have like almost
nothing to do with each other. Okay, so any sequence constructor is a way of
explicitly iterating to the end of your iterator or any iterable, because it will
implicitly convert it to iterator. And as I said, every generator is an iterator.
I think it's important to repeat that because people will often kind of use these
things informally and say this is a way to consume everything from a generator.
No, this is a way to consume everything from an iterable. A generator is an
iterator is an iterable. So like I said, like you can convert an iterable to
iterator, but what what other ways can you take an iterable and convert it to
iterator? So there's a lot of fun functions in Python. The signature is
take iterable, maybe take several intervals and return an iterator. It does
not promise you that it will return a generator, but usually you don't care
about the implementation. It does promise you that it will return an
iterator. And that's very useful. It will be on demand, right? So it doesn't take
any extra space. And so why do I mention that like there's a lot of functions like
that? So I'm going to go fairly quickly to the function because of a gazillion of
them. And if I went to like all of them to take most of the talk, I have a lot of
other stuff to get through. So there's like, you know, lots more details in the
handouts later. But I'll kind of cover like some of my favorites. So there's
enumerate, which give you indices, which is a good alternative whenever you see
someone doing form I of range len, enumerate, better. Map, really useful,
right? And again, always returns an iterator. It doesn't do all the things in
the beginning. It does things on demand. Let's see one arbitrary functions on
your iterables, which might be an iterator. So for example, or you can use
filter. It's kind of nuanced with filter and especially with partial because
partial has the order. So greater or equal to five means five greater or
equal to the thing, which means it will give you all the things that are less
than five. In this case, one and three, it skips the 10. Zip takes a few
iterable and gives you an iterator of the tuples. Again, very useful when you
need to kind of combine. And remember, these two can be completely different
generators, which means each of them might have a different flow and zip kind
of coordinates them. Super useful in many use cases. And then if you're like,
if you don't find exactly the right stuff you need, we have arbitrary generator
expressions, right? So if you can think it, you can code it, right? Like if you
can think of a way to combine several iterables into an iterator, you can do
that this way and just do it in line, right? So that's very useful. Now
sometimes, like I covered the language and the built-in, there's a
useful module that's called itertools in the standard library having functions
like, so it's a standard library module and basically has like, you know, even more
advanced iterator algebra. So it has chain, which will combine iterators one
after the other. Extremely useful, especially if you want like a little
prefix before you do the real stuff to kind of, you know, warm up something. You
can have islice, which is a really, really good way to deal with infinite
iterators. As you saw earlier, I can do infinite iterators just by not ever
raising a stop iteration. This way, you can kind of like limit the potential
size. You have count, which is an infinite iterator, which just count from
zero to infinity. Very useful, especially if you zip it up with something.
And if those are not enough, there is a library in PyPI where they took all the
suggestions from itertools documentation of like what cool stuff you
can do and just did it so that you don't have to like, you know, copy and paste
from the documentation to your code. So basically like a lot of like really
useful stuff like chunked, which will give you chunks. Very useful if you want
to batch process something, especially if it comes in via stream infinite.
You can distribute, which is the opposite, right? So again, if you kind of
want to give something to like, you know, several threads or several kind of
async flows or stuff like that, you can kind of distribute like that.
There's peekable, which is very useful when you want to kind of look into the
future. You know, so I want to stop one before I get to three, right?
So like zero, one, but I want to get, no, not do the two, right?
Like as soon as three is closed, I want to stop, right?
Again, there's some use cases where this is useful.
Pickable is like super useful and you don't have to sync, right?
You just pick and use, otherwise you use the iterator as is, right?
So this is amazing. I love it.
And this is windowed, which I really like for like doing ranges, right?
So if you have like timestamps and you want to know the differences between
the timestamps, like, you know, for example, like, you know, for like
something like meantime between failures or stuff like that, that's basically
all the code you need for that kind of stuff.
So here are a few gotchas, right?
Like so far I was like, you know, super enthusiastic about the iterators, right?
And I was like, you know, here's like, you know, all the things that are really
useful, but they are like weirdly mutable.
And I kind of mentioned that because you'd often see iterators kind of mentioned
right next to like functional programming, right?
Because you saw the code I wrote before, right?
Like, you know, I had map and filter and kind of like very abstract flows.
That don't really kind of like, you know, mutate everything and everything
kind of flows, so it looks very nice and functional.
You remember that like at the end point, it's not functional.
It's like the opposite of functional.
It's like super stateful, right?
And this is like the example of how stateful it is.
Once you consume an iterator, it has been consumed.
If you try to consume it again, you'll get zero.
This is a source of many subtle bugs.
If you see a subtle bug like that, that means you did that.
How do you avoid this bug?
There's two ways.
One, make sure you pass in the sequence.
This would require you to refactor code from being iterator focused to like
passing in a sequence that might be a lot of refactoring.
So, you know, a lot of code, but pretty efficient.
The other way fixes it at like the point of consumption.
So you don't have to refactor, but in return, you have to kind of freeze
the free the iterator, which can be very heavyweight in memory and time wise.
Right.
At this point, have to do all the computation to freeze it.
There's like more sophisticated solutions if you use more-iterator tools.
But that's probably enough.
But like, I want you to kind of just be mindful of the bug and mindful that
there are ways to fix it as long as you think very, very carefully.
Cool.
And then my favorite bug, this is like everybody's favorite bugs.
If you have a dictionary and you have an iterator on it and you try to
use the iterator after you have mutated the dictionary, it will do this.
Uh, this will be the sign that you are in a sad place.
There are ways to solve it.
I don't really have time to delve into all of them, but like potentially using
like, um, immutable data structures instead of dictionaries is a good
way of solving that, uh, it is important to like, no, no, the shape of the bug.
This is kind of the, the abstract shape.
Usually that's not like the, um, pure form of like how it would look.
Usually there'll be a for loop somewhere in the middle.
Like I said, four is a much more popular way of doing iteration.
So usually this will come in a for loop where in like one of the sub sub
branches, you call a functions that modify the dictionary.
That's like, you know, like usually how this bug looks, but this is
kind of like the back condensed.
So I want you to see that.
And remember that like, whenever you see that it's basically this
except spread probably of course, like five files.
So now you have to track it down, but at least now you have kind of a, a
thread, a memory hint to kind of, you know, know what to look for.
And, oh my God, this is my favorite bucket because, uh, this happened at
the worst time, what do I mean by it happened at the worst time?
Let's say that you have kind of complicated code and there's some issues.
Okay.
Well, let me kind of reduce like, you know, some variables.
I'll comment out some of the complicated flows so I can concentrate
on like what's really happening.
So you know what?
Okay.
I have this function, it yields hello, and then does a print and then it
yields goodbye and potentially it's like being used in a very complicated
unit test.
Um, and like the hello just causes a lot of printouts and like some
trying to figure out what's going on.
So I'm like, okay, let's call it out the hello.
I don't actually need it right now.
That's fine.
I call it out the hello and I want the unit test and there's still
a lot of printouts, right?
There's still kind of a lot of junk.
And I'm like, you know what?
I actually don't need anything from this function for like, you
know, debugging my specific bug.
I can call it out the goodbye too, cause I don't need it.
Those of you who have experienced it know what's going to happen after
I call it out to the last field, this is no longer a generator.
Now it's a function.
Now when I call it, it does stuff.
When you call a generator, it doesn't do anything, right?
It returns an iterator that will do stuff when you iterate through it.
You'll see that I, and now I get the printout of going and the return value
is none, so if I try to iterate through it, it'll just fail.
The last yield you comment out stops it from being a generator.
That is something you will encounter often.
If you kind of do this kind of debugging by kind of commenting out flows that
you don't care about to kind of focus on the flow that you do.
There is a trick.
This is a trick.
I do if false yield, right?
Cause like for Python, that's enough.
I don't care if it's true.
It just gives it as a yield somewhere in the function for you.
That's also great.
And luckily, because it yields a none, that will also trigger the type checker.
So if you forget to undo it before you check in, you'll remember.
So a very neat trick.
And when you run into that, that might be the difference between you being
very sad and you not being very sad.
So I like showing that.
Cool.
So let me kind of, I think I'm very close to the end.
So I want to go over like, you know, what I talked and like where I want you to
take it from here.
So we covered iterators and generators.
Interactors are a very useful interface in Python, right?
Like you saw that like, there's like a lot of stuff that focuses on this
interface between different flows.
It's a good way to express some sort of something that kind of, you know, gives
you one value after the next kind of in a, in a reasonable way implementing
in used to be annoying, but with generators, implementing them is very nice.
So if you use generators, you can easily implement iterators and you get a good
way to use that interface.
You have basically a whole algebra that focuses on just in time stuff, right?
You take stuff that you wrote that is just in time and you combine it, you
know, with stuff like zip and map and chunked and windowed and you still
everything is just in time, right?
As long as you just call these functions, nothing happens and they only respond to
like being iterated on top of and say, if you islice it, it will be like, you
know, kind of limited amount of time.
Right?
So, so like, like everything here is like very just in time, which is very useful.
You write, get to write your abstract code and the implementation just in time.
That can also be confusing.
Right?
And that's based on functions that that's kind of actually like, uh, more
on us than that.
They accept intervals and return it to us.
Right.
Um, and the composable tools, right?
You can use map of a zip of an ice slice of account of like, you know, and
like do all of these things.
Right?
So, um, basically all these tools are like super, super composable.
Uh, and luckily because it's like such a useful interface, it's a huge ecosystem,
which means if you want to do something with iterators, your first instinct should
probably be not reach for like, you know, kind of a really complicated, um,
generator expression.
Your first instinct should be to do some research.
Someone has probably solved this before.
Right?
If you're starting to like implement something like windowed or chunked,
well, like these things are like very twiddly to, to implement.
You don't need, right?
And those are just for me more into tools as tons of ecosystem outside of that.
Right.
Consume that ecosystem, right?
You're probably already used to that.
You probably already have a lot of stuff people install, you know, after you use
it, consume it and okay, that's very confusing.
Um, and finally, if you don't find something that is exactly what you need, um,
you know, you might have stumbled upon one of the missing parts.
So definitely contribute back.
Let's see what question they have.
Um, have you implemented the customer iterator that is already in production?
I'm curious to know the use case and your thoughts of it or tool.
So itertools and the stdlib is absolutely amazing.
Have I implemented an iterator that is in production?
Uh, quite probably, like I, I don't really think about it, but I'm pretty sure that
like, I wrote some code that works like that, uh, probably like, you know, like
part of my data analysis involved, like an iterator that does that.
So yes, I can think of like a specific code that works like that.
I can think of like a specific example, but it's because I do it so much that
like, you know, it just like, I don't even think of it as kind of a separate activity.
Um, I also got a question of whether I'm swapping is hiring.
The answer is yes, we are hiring, uh, um, catch me later.
And I'm happy to give you my email address.
Uh, what's my favorite iterator?
Wow.
Uh, I would say I have like a special weakness for windowed, right?
Like, you know, like, like it makes like implementing stuff, like, like rolling
average, just like almost mindless, right?
And like, you know, implementing these things are like, you know, typically hard.
I'm used to like, you know, cause there's so much work to kind of implement these
things now implementing a rolling average is basically just map of windows or like,
you know, map some of windows and like, you know, then like, you know, map the
division and that's it, right?
Like, you know, I can implement it in like two lines of code.
So windowed is just like magical and I love it so much.
Um, how would you approach delving into these tools to learn them deeply?
Just to read code and reach for those tools.
Um, I would not say even read code, right?
Like when you have to write code, think, you know, is this a natural, like, like
if you see yourself iterating on something and you see a lot of code inside the
for loop, that's your signal to think maybe there's a good abstraction I can do.
And one of the reasons I like this good abstract, these abstractions,
they're extremely testable, right?
If you test every bit of it, then you barely have to test a combination.
So, um, if you see a lot of code on their for loop, that's your kind of sign to
like, say, should I look into like, you know, implementing it with the iterators?
Um, isn't using a lib just for chunks encourage the J?
Well, so more-itertools is not just for chunks.
It has a lot of use stuff, like, you know, window chunked and I didn't even cover
half of it because like, you know, uh, there's tons, um, I basically reached
for more-itertools like the alternative is basically like, you'll end up implementing
it yourself, probably worse and probably with more bugs.
I do not think it's left bad.
Uh, chunks is actually like not that trivial to implement.
If remember all the annoying edge cases, like what happens if you could, you know,
if the stuff you have is not, you know, directly divisible by the chunk size
and stuff like that, so I would say, yeah, um, cool.
I think, uh, that is all the question.
And I'm also out of time.
Am I?
Okay, cool.
So, uh, thank you.