All right, so I'll be your host before the lunch break, so I hope you're ready.
Today I want to have a quick introduction about what I learned in maintaining an open source project,
but this will also be hopefully help you how to interact, could be like a tutorial,
how to interact with open source project too, and also encourage you to actually become maintainers yourself
and do some open source project whenever you have some free time for it.
So let's get going. So first, who am I? So as the teacher could give away, I work at Bloomberg
in the data technologies department at the software engineer, but I'm currently based out of Los Angeles.
However, for my weird accent, the reason is because I'm originally from Transylvania.
For those who don't know, that's around that little green blob in Europe, so quite centrally in there.
Okay, so but more importantly for this discussion, I'm a quite prolific open source contributor on Github mostly.
You can find me under that handle. I have a blog, but more importantly, I'm also a member of the Python packaging authority.
I maintain mostly these three projects on virtual and Ppex build, but also I have some other popular projects
I maintain such as platform build stocks or PIP depth tree, PIP apps. Those are the, I would say, the most popular ones.
I'm also a parent to these two lovely Yorkshire Terriers, and I'll call them on throughout the call
just to lighten up the mood a wee bit. So let's get the journey started.
Okay, so let's start with kind of like the original definition. What is a maintainer?
So when we talk about maintaining project, what do we talk about it?
Per the dictionary.com definition, it's this long worded to bullet point ones, but I think from our conversation,
this is kind of like the definition I would go on, basically keep an appropriate condition operation.
The goal of a maintainer within the open source project is to make sure that this happens for the project no matter what.
Everything else is kind of like secondary, including, as some people might think it is the maintainer's primary goal,
is to add new features to the project, fix your bugs or issues. No, that would be a contributor.
You can do this, and most maintainers will kind of like swap their heads sometimes to some of these two,
but no, that's not part of being a maintainer. That's more like when you have free time, you can take that on too.
Okay, so the first thing, if you have a project and you want to maintain the project,
is to make sure that that project is actually discoverable and the users can interact with it.
And within the Python world, this primary means that, hey, upload it to the PyPI project, if it's a library or a tool,
make sure it's installable, and more importantly, make sure that the user can find information about the project
that is important for them using it. Some of this project, as shown for the demo from the TOX project documentation,
is that link to the documentation, link to the home page, link to the release notes, and a link to the source
and an issue tracker where they can interact with your project, submit feature, get bugs, stuff like that.
Now, another kind of like primary goal of the maintainer is to make sure that the consumption and contributing
to the code is familiar. This is important because people are busy with their lives,
they have a lot of things going on, so you want to make sure that it is as easy as possible for them
to actually help out with the project and consume the project. So when it comes to like consuming the project,
it mostly means make sure that it's installable via PIP, or if your project especially is mostly data science-related,
then you want to be able to have like a conda installation, and then the code is available in some widely used
GitHub, such as GitHub. You can use GitLab also, but this kind of like goes against the law of list surprises.
Okay, so another core responsibility of a maintainer would be to send ground rules. This is Python.
We all are consenting adults, but even then adults sometimes misbehave. So when that happens,
it needs to make sure that whoever is interacting with your project knows what are the rules to follow
and why what they will be maybe banned or not. So make sure that your project has a code of conduct attached to it,
so then when people don't interact how maybe you wish they interact, you can sideline them on actual rules
rather than just arbitrary rules. Okay, now another kind of like primary job of a maintainer would be
to actually try incoming bug reports. Oftentimes users don't actually know what they submit is a bug or feature
or maybe both. So it's kind of like the maintainer's goal, or not goal, but job to make sure that when they submit
a help request, you can tell them, hey, this is a bug or hey, you're just using the tool incorrectly,
stuff like that. So a lot of the time you're going to spend on basically just priorging the incoming bug reports
and giving kind of like a judgment on them. For this one, I recommend to use templates. GitHub templates,
for example, are very helpful, which can make sure that your users are filling all the required information,
such as in this case on the toxic projects, where I can kind of like fill out, hey, if you want to submit
some information, make sure to submit all this because it's going to minimize the interactions we're going to
have back and forth. Okay, now I think at this point is where I should remind all of us that communication
is deceptively hard. NatBachelor had a great keynote at the last year's PyCon US where he talked about it
more in detail, but I would like to just highlight two points out of his presentation. One, we have all different
communication styles. This is kind of like visualized here by the fact that each of the heads look kind of
different, so our heads operate differently. Keep this in mind whenever you're communicating through like
any kind of issue tracker with someone. And also remember that whenever we communicate, we have a lot of
nonverbal communication that we can pick up. Of course, when we are communicating over like written format,
it's even harder because you look at context, attention span also might be, like this actually might be me
whenever I'm reading your issue. Maybe I just have 20 seconds before my deployment finishes and I decide to
have a look at the bug tracker and I might be just kind of like a bit short on attention, so to say.
So if, for example, I reply to your issue in just five words, that doesn't mean that I don't care about your
issues, that maybe just that's how much time I have at the moment. Okay? So in general, to sum it up, be polite
and patient. Always give benefit of doubt. Remember, it's not that they hate you, they might just communicate
differently. And finally, and this is kind of like maybe like my pet peeve, but please refrain tagging the people
when you open the issue. Most of the maintainers will follow their projects and they'll get to it when they'll
get to it. That being said, if I don't reply a week later, now you can tag me because maybe I just missed it,
but don't start with the tag because it just comes across as you're a bit entitled and you're kind of like pushy
about it and you're like, okay, I get it. It's an open source project. You don't actually get paid to do it,
so keep that in mind whenever you're interacting. Okay? Now, just to go back to work beforehand,
if you're a user and you're submitting a bug report, make sure that whatever you're kind of like trying to communicate
is easily reproducible. First, always check if there's already an issue open, and if there isn't,
then make sure that what ideally my preferred issue is when someone submits kind of like a docker built
repo, because then it's very easy to replicate it and I can see exactly what's happening. But if that's not possible,
at least have a GitHub repository that demonstrates the problem and it's easy to reproduce again.
And also provide detailed description of exactly what's happening. And just a general rule of thumb,
more information is better than less. I'm at the maintainer who will be able to ignore all the parts
that are not relevant for this bug report, but if you don't provide information, that just means that I will need to
ask for that information and we're just having a lot more back and forth and we're wasting both of our times
rather than just have one time interaction with each other. So one interesting thing, which I think many people
kind of like forget, if you submit a stack trace, please don't submit the final three lines,
because the other five above it might be just as interesting for me to find out what's happening actually.
Just because the error stack trace shows the last two lines, that doesn't mean that's the one that you should actually
post in the issue tracker. Okay? So generally, more is better than less when it comes to this.
Now, another kind of like important job for a maintainer is to actually drink, kind of like groom the incoming feature request.
What I mean about it, if someone is asking a feature, you're the one that's going to be saying that,
hey, cool idea, get it in. Or you're going to be like, nope, this is not for us, but thanks for participating.
Okay? So like in the previous issue, you can see like for example, I say like, yeah, this is something we should do it,
and I even added the help wanted label to it to kind of like signify that. Or in this one, I say like,
this is out of scope of the project, but you can write the plugin to work around this problem for now,
and maybe later we'll reconsider it. Okay?
Now, another thing when it comes to feature request is I think we all need to remember the cute puppy metaphor, I want to say.
Whenever you're bringing, even if you create a pull request and like, hey, this is implementing this lovely feature,
you might see the shiny cute puppy, but I actually see all the work. I need to take it to the vet. I need to give it food.
I need to walk it every day for the next 20 years. So I have to consider the entire package,
not just the cuteness that they have. Okay? So if I say no to it, it doesn't mean that I don't like the cute puppy.
It just means I decided I have enough on my plate to deal with this for the next 20 years. Okay?
But yeah. Okay, so thanks for filing an excellent feature request.
First, read the documentation to check if there is an alternative solution for it.
Sometimes we can do things in many ways and kind of like the Zen of Python is to try to have just one way to do something.
So make sure that there's not another way of doing the thing.
Another thing is if in doubt, before you can open a GitHub as this great feature, which is called Discussions,
maybe just open a discussion to kind of like have a back and forth with the maintainer about how we can best solve this problem.
And only then, if you open the full request, please indicate if you're willing to do the work.
You're just asking for this to who would like it.
If you're actually willing to do the work, it's more likely that it's going to be accepted because then I'll be like, yeah, sure.
I can review it because maybe I can kind of like spend half an hour to actually review it and land it
rather than I have to spend a day to actually implement it and test it. Okay?
So another job for maintainers is to actually review the pull request.
Once you put in that feature request, I'm the one that has to go through and make sure that what you put in looks good,
and I'm actually happy to work with that for the next five years or whatnot.
The maintainer is also the one that actually decides when and how to cut releases.
As you can see, for example, here through GitHub releases.
And I think also for maintainers, it's important that whenever someone puts in a field request,
at least try to thank them in a nice way for their work and be like, hey, thanks for doing this.
That kind of like encourages them to do more open source in the future. Okay?
So another kind of like job of a maintainer is to actually make sure that the project doesn't turn into mayhem and chaos.
You want to make sure that kind of like the project has kind of like a set of unified rules
and kind of like the code that looks mostly same-ish.
This is important because if every corner of the codebase has a different structure, different style,
it's going to quickly turn into a nightmare to actually try to maintain it
or actually try to make changes across multiple layers of it.
This is more of an art than an exact science, but generally what you want to do is make sure that
follow a unified set of rules that mostly lives in the maintainer.
Perhaps if you can codify it in a written text, bonus points for you,
but generally I don't think this really lives in there.
If you're... I think I went a bit too ahead.
Okay, so another kind of like important thing is make sure that your project also has a changelog.
I don't really care if your changelog is a GitHub release, as in this case, or it's actually like a release page.
Doesn't really matter at the end of the day, but make sure somehow people can find out what went in each of the releases.
So they can actually interact better with that project.
Okay, now as you can see from up to this point, there's a lot of work involved in actually maintaining the project.
So it is important that you kind of like... so you don't burn out too easily,
make sure to let other people help you out.
Now this is a bit of contradictory because in order to let other people help you out,
you actually have to put in a lot of work.
But it's one of those where you're hoping that in the long term the investment pays off.
What do I mean by you have to do a lot of work?
For example, you need to actually write a contributing guide.
This will help your people actually do contributions to your project.
Basically, in the contributing guide, you should sell out,
hey, how to set up a quick development environment, how can they run the test,
just so that they can quickly get off the ground and check whatever they are doing looks sane and works correctly.
If you get really fancy, you can even have a dedicated page in your documentation,
as in this case, where you can even kind of like codify more non-exact requirements.
But another thing that you need to make sure is that your CI remains green.
If you see a CI like this that is all green, everything is great,
you know if you put in a bug request or a bug fix or a feature addition,
it's going to be very easy to accept it because the CI is already green,
I just have to review it and if I like how it looks, I can land it.
However, if you're more like a project that every third one fails or maybe doesn't pass it,
you're like, even if you make that improvement, you're going to be like,
well, I can't actually land it until the CI is green, so now you have to do other work for them.
Another thing is that people are easy to get distracted.
And if your CI takes a long time to run, it will mean that by the time the CI,
they don't even stick around to check that actually whatever pull request they put in actually lands.
So you want to make sure that the CI runs as fast as possible, so you have this kick feedback as possible,
so they're still around by the time the CI fails to see,
oh, okay, I need to do one more change before I go off and do my other work.
Okay, like for example in this case, this is not always possible,
but if it takes 20 minutes to run the CI, you know 20 minutes later everyone's at the coffee shop by then
and they're still at their computer checking if it's fine or not.
Now, another important thing, remember to always run your documentation build too as part of your CI,
and for this one, the Read the Docs is actually quite really good.
It allows you to set up documentation builds on your PR,
and as you can see here, you can actually have a nice warning at the top of the documentation that,
hey, this page was created from a pull request.
This means that if people do bad documentation, you can see them before merging it,
and you don't have to do follow-up work for it.
Plus, this is also good for the user who's doing the documentation build
because they can actually see as they are doing even the documentation improvements how it's going to end up.
Okay, this, what I said before, make sure the CI remains green, also apply for the documentation build.
So for example, you should either set up automated email alerting,
or at least check periodically that your documentation builds are still working or not,
for example by logging into your dashboard in Read the Docs.
Okay, so as I said, another thing that I think is a great rule to release often and small,
and to achieve this, it's your job as a maintainer to make sure that releasing is easy and trivial.
And the way you achieve this is to actually make it very simple,
make basically the release kind of like a one-button press,
and also at the same time define a versioning policy,
so anyone who's around, any maintainer, can easily decide what should be the next release version.
Okay, this can be achieved, for example, if you go for semantic versioning,
and then you can see are there any bug fixes, feature requests, breaking changes,
that's how I have to bump the version number, or you just use calendar versioning,
and then it's kind of like whatever the date is today is the version.
Okay, now another thing that as a maintainer, you will thank your life,
and I find it very helpful that even though users hate it and contributors hate it,
I always infer that whatever change you do, it needs to have at least one test to it.
Because it might be easy to merge it without a test today, but in one year's time or two years' time,
it's going to save me from breaking someone else or breaking yourself.
So kind of like enforce that, hey, tests are required every pull request.
Otherwise, thank you, but I'm not going to merge your PR no matter how great it is.
And I'm just going to close it because it's part of the job.
Okay, and also every changelog should have a changelog attached to it,
and this is primarily because you want to make the releases quick and easy,
and you want to already have the changelog ready by the time you want to cut the release
and not as part of the pull request rather than at a later point in time.
Okay, now another thing, we are all very sentimental when it comes to code quality,
so let's take the emotional out, do use projects such as rough or pre-commit
to kind of like standardize how the code looks, and then it's not that,
hey, I say that your code looks ugly, it's that the CI broke.
You can blame the CI, not me, that whatever you made, it doesn't pass it, okay?
So, and generally when it comes to the architecture of the project,
remember that a consistent architecture is better than a great one.
You want to be consistent, kind of like a unified rule,
rather than each different section of the code have a different architecture,
I mean, better for that sub-problem.
And also, if you and I disagree, the maintainer always wins.
And the reason it's not because the maintainer hates you
is because the maintainer is the one that will have to work that code
in six months or years' times, and they are the ones that will be more heavily impacted
if it doesn't behave how they want it to behave.
Okay?
Another thing that I kind of like ran into is that we're all bad at naming,
but not just naming, also just making good commit messages and PR titles,
and that's fine.
It's up to the maintainer to whenever they are merging the pull request
or the bug fix to use the GitHub UI, for example, to reword it
and make it look nicer to whatever they like better.
And, yeah, don't let some bad PR titles discourage contributors
from your project or commit messages.
Okay, so another thing that we, as the maintainer, you want to do
to actually let other people out is to create a community.
And the way you do it is generally use your issue tracker for most of the things,
your discussions on GitHub.
Also, you can create a sync channel.
You don't have to create your own Discord server.
For example, the Python packaging authority has a server.
Any project under the authority can have there,
and that the other Python packaging authority Discord server
can help other people whenever they get holed up or lost.
Remember to advertise your project by any of the, what you'd call,
popular channels, such as forums, in this case.
And also occasionally go on Stack Overflow and answer some questions
and maybe just encourage people on Stack Overflow
to post their questions on the GitHub issues
to kind of like have a unified place.
But Stack Overflow still is one of the go-to places whenever,
especially new people out of college tend to go
whenever they run into some project rather than issue tracker.
Okay.
Now, how to track maintenance of your project?
I think this kind of like boils down to like encourage people to contribute more.
If they came around, they did want a few contributions,
just give them more responsibility.
Generally people are, I think more, a lot of people think that
something is too complicated that it can't help out.
But remember, you don't become a maintainer by suddenly from day one to day two.
It takes time.
And the longer you stick around and the more you interact with the project,
the more you will be able to become a maintainer.
I generally like to be quite liberal with giving out maintainer flags.
Now, that doesn't mean that I just give them the project and I drive off to the sunset.
I stick around and help them out on it.
But it tends to work whenever someone makes like, I don't know,
like five, ten pull requests over two weeks.
I'm like, hey, do you want to be a maintainer?
I'm happy to get help out on it.
And then slowly introducing them to some of the maintainership tests,
such as encourage them to maybe make a pull request, look at some of the issues,
do a release, basically pull them in and mentor them.
Maybe have a quick health and art chat on them.
Hey, do you have any questions about the project?
Stuff like that.
Make them sure that they get help on it and remind them that this journey
is not going to be kind of like a linear one where you're just like,
I'm here, now I'm a maintainer.
I know everything.
It's more like, I'm here, oh, now I know a bit.
Then you find out that, oh, I don't know anything.
And now you do another hump and eventually like if you stick around
after like a few months, you're going to be like actually expert on it.
But it's going to take those time.
And it's fine if you are a maintainer from day 20 rather than day 600.
Okay?
So as you can see, there's a lot of work with this kind of like maintainer shop.
Why would you do this?
Well, it looks good on your CV.
It broadens your horizon.
You get to communicate with a lot more people and stuff like that.
You also get some mentoring experience out of it.
You can get also opportunities to your new technologies and libraries
that maybe you don't get to use on your work.
And finally, you also get a handy source of topics for your conference talk.
Pointing question.
Okay?
Now, this is the final one.
This is the final one.
You also may potentially get paid for it in some way.
For example, in my case, my company allows me to work like 20% of my time on open source stuff
so I can basically during work hours actually do some open source.
I can also set up, for example, GitHub sponsors.
And people occasionally when they're happy that I accepted the feature,
I guess I might give you a few dollars.
Anyway, there's also tightly fixed gate at giving out monthly funding,
especially for more popular projects and widely used projects.
So you might be able to get, I don't know, maybe a few hundred dollars every month
for just doing that what you might do either way.
And also thanks to that, it's a great source where you can get some of this
enumeration for your heavy work.
Okay?
Now, in general, accept that no project will ever be done.
Be patient with the users because users are always bad at reading documentation.
And that involves me whenever I read other project documentation.
Okay?
And generally speaking, it's your own dog food.
Don't try to cut shortcuts just because you are the maintainer.
Remember, I work with all of those forks and everything as everyone else
just so that I can easily discover any kind of problems that I might have otherwise
with the project's contribution that other people might run into it.
Okay?
Now, this is kind of like my advantage.
Okay.
You got sold on the dream that you want to now become a maintainer.
How do you become a maintainer?
I say to contribute and all that, but where should you start?
My recommendation generally is to always pick something that you use on a regular
or semi-regular basis.
What I mean, for example, if you use Fast API at work for whatever reason
and you debug it enough, you probably know the code enough.
You might sometimes even maybe debug in their Fast API's code base that you're
going to be at least semi-familiar with the code base.
It's a great starting point.
You don't have to start from zero.
Plus, you're also have been encouraged to make it look nice because you're going
to be using it next day at work maybe.
Okay?
Read the documentation in detail.
This is kind of like a heavy.
You don't have to read the documentation and understand it on day one,
but it's helpful to kind of like go over the project.
Read mostly the documentation, at least skim through it,
so that when you look at an issue or a bug, you can kind of like answer,
is that even a thing that this supposed to do or not?
Okay?
Now, generally speaking, also another kind of like recommendation
that I didn't put here in the slides, but it's true that we...
I actually think that bug fixes are probably one of the most misleading
and hardest things to fix.
I would encourage people to do like a small feature
or maybe some documentation change before they do bug fixes
because bug fixes often kind of end up being spread around in five places
in the code base, and you're kind of like lost,
how do I actually fix this?
It might seem simple, but often it tends to be quite complicated.
And then just rinse and repeat whatever I said until now
and give it a few weeks at most,
and you're going to become a maintainer of the project,
assuming that you do consistent and good work at it.
Okay?
Now, if you stick around for a few weeks
and you decide it's not for you, that's fine.
No one is making...
Remember to pick something you enjoy,
not something that you think might look good on your CV.
Ultimately, it's still something that you're going to do
on your free time on the site.
You need to get some excitement out of it to keep doing it.
Okay?
Now, one kind of like advice for maintainers in general,
I did all this, but remember, always prioritize your mental
and physical health over anything else.
No open source project is worth you losing your physical
or mental health over it.
It's better if you just go on a two-month break
and don't do anything than just burn out in a month
and you're not going to do anything for the next five years.
Okay?
Now, how long should you expect doing this?
Well, as long as you enjoy it.
If you stick around for a year and you're like,
eh, I don't find this anymore enjoyable,
it's fine to just drive off into the sunset.
Do let other people know that, hey,
I'm no longer interested in it,
so they're just kind of like aware of that,
but you don't have to keep doing it.
Okay?
Thank you for your time, and I'll take some questions.
Thank you.
All right.
We've got a lot of questions.
I've got a lot of questions here.
First one, and this one's kind of near and dear to my heart
ripped from today's headlines.
What are the potential solutions that open source can use
to solve the issues presented by the XZ package backdoor?
I don't think there's anything there, too.
Like, no amount of process.
Like, that person didn't just...
It wasn't the case that someone showed up on day two
and, hey, can I maintain it?
Yeah, cool, it's all yours.
The guy actually sticked around for a year
and helped out consistently.
It's built kind of like...
It was in the long run, built the long run game.
So at that point, I don't think there's anything we can do
to stop that other than maybe requiring people IDs from them,
but I don't think it's also realistic.
So I think those are the kind of, like, things
that occasionally will happen,
and we'll just have to kind of, like, find it out post-mortem.
We can do a better job at maybe encouraging people
to pay more to maintainers.
More maintainers mean that the maintainers will be
less likely to stick around
and will be more people around to discover such issues.
But other than that, that will also just decrease
the amount of exit cases.
It doesn't necessarily eliminate it.
But yeah, encouraging your companies
to pay open source maintainers
is definitely a good thing.
And it doesn't have to be that they literally pay it.
If you can convince your boss to spend some of your time
maintaining open source projects,
it's just as much of sponsoring open source
that if they would give, like, $10,000 to GitHub
and just say, give it to whoever you want it.
Right. I'm a big fan of the many hands make light work.
So the more maintainers on a project,
the less strain there is on any one maintainer.
Exactly. Which is good.
Any tips for convincing an employer to let you contribute
to open source software on company time?
I mean, yes and not really.
It's a bit of, like, people...
You can kind of, like, present actual problems.
And you can say that, hey, we're using this tool
for x, epsilon, and z, and we want to add these features.
It would be great if we could help out on it and stuff like that.
And maybe that way you kind of, like, get the whore in the door
and then you can just keep doing it
because your team keeps using that tool or product.
That's one way.
Ultimately, some people are just more open than other people.
And maybe sometimes, if you can't convince your boss,
maybe it's just time to change teams or move on.
I find that pretty please with sugar on top sometimes works.
Yes. Sometimes.
It doesn't have a 0% success rate.
What got you started as a package maintainer
and what keeps you going?
Well, I got the old...
The way I started is basically one day I showed up
to the TOX project, and I was like, hey, I come from Java.
I use Gradle.
Gradle has this lovely feature where you can see
the description of the task.
This tool doesn't have it.
And they're like, yeah, but if you do it, we'll add it.
And I was like, okay.
And then I just did that after a while.
They were just like, hey, now you're a maintainer.
So I guess I stick around because I still mostly enjoy it.
But yeah, actually I started with maintaining the TOX project,
and you have seen the first slide.
Now I'm in like 18 slides or like 18 projects.
Out of those 18 projects, five projects I maintained
because TOX depended on them.
And I went to the maintainer and they were like,
well, I don't have time.
I was like, cool, but the bug in TOX is in your tool,
so I'm just going to need to do it.
So then I picked it up because it's like a downstream dependency of me.
That sounds like how I got involved with the PyTex's conference.
Any package recommendations for those of us
who would like to dip our toe into maintaining or contributing?
Really, as I say, pick.
I mean, you can come and contribute to any of my projects.
I'm happy to help you out, maintain you.
I'm not going to do all the work for you,
but I'm going to guide you through it.
But generally I still think what I said on the slides,
pick something that you use on a daily basis.
It can be tool, library, whatever you want.
Because then you're going to be kind of like incentivized to make it better.
And once you're incentivized to work on it,
it's going to be...
I imagine 99% of the projects on the PyPI,
you're probably putting in two weeks of work to becoming a maintainer
because maintainers are kind of like a dying breed.
So if you're doing work for it,
it's going to be fairly quick to become a maintainer of it.
I'll editorially add something that I think Mason has said before too.
A good first contribution can be documentation.
Yeah, definitely.
See, documentation lacking, like that's a good first foray.
Okay, I'll do two more.
When evaluating open source projects for use in your code beyond quality and fit for purpose,
what signals do you look for?
Anything you haven't already talked about?
I mean, I tend to look at how well it's maintained.
And here I kind of like look at how many issues it has,
how often is the pull request.
Like, I don't know, for example, I discard...
I know everyone likes, for example, maybe hot take, controversial take.
Everyone likes poetry.
I look at their...
I try to contribute to it,
and I look at how often they try with their issues and pull requests.
And it's something I was like,
I'm not comfortable with how slow it is to actually get the fix in and stuff like that.
So I kind of was like, nope, no, thank you.
Because ultimately, I don't think any project is perfect or done or good.
I just look it to be easy to fix if it breaks.
Right.
Okay, last question.
And by the way, all of these questions were great.
We'll get them posted up to Discord so we can answer the rest of them.
You mentioned requiring unit tests with contributions.
Do you have any opinions on code covering metrics?
Yes.
I am a very firm believer 100% or it doesn't matter.
Now, I don't...
I also am concerned...
I don't say 100% code coverage means that your tests are great and you're done with testing.
100% means at least everything has been looked at,
maybe not in all the facets, in all the ways.
But I do think that 100% is a lot better than 90%.
And there is such a thing that I changed the code coverage from 100% to 100%,
and now it's even better.
So the more tests, the better.
The only kind of caveat I would add to that,
that keep in mind that fact that you still want the CI to be fairly fast.
So you joined us to add tests for the sake of adding tests.
But if there's something that covers an actual test case,
I think even that may be a great opportunity for first pull requests.
Maybe just add some tests that are not there.
And I don't think any maintainer would be like,
no, I don't want tests, thank you.
Well, thank you very much for answering all the questions for the great presentations.
Give them a round of applause.
Thank you.