So I was a Lotus Notes developer in the beginning.
Please don't hold that against me.
And then I went to SharePoint.
So I've kind of been a GUI guy.
And when I got into Python, it really wasn't that great of a
GUI thing.
But I found something a couple weeks ago that I'm just
really excited about.
So there's a library out there called Flat.
I don't know if you've ever heard of it.
I've Googled it on YouTube.
And there's like five videos on it.
But it's really cool.
And I'll get more into that after I show the demo.
So basically, you import Flat.
And I'm doing it with the Pandas database, because
that's what I do in my job.
So I'm grabbing this Pandas database.
And then from the data frame, I'm getting the headers from
the columns here.
And then for the rows, I set up a list.
And then I loop through the rows in the data frame and
fill in the list.
And then I start the main method.
And this is a Flat data table.
And so I set the columns to the headers from up above and
the rows from the data frame.
This is the hard part that I've been working on, is
getting it to scroll.
So basically, I take on the data table the last column.
I make it scrollable.
And then I take that column and I add it to the row, which
is another control within Flat.
And I make it scrollable so I can scroll the whole nine
yards.
Then I add them to the page.
And so from there, all I've got to do is run this, and
boom.
You have a GUI.
And if I collapse that, I can scroll across vertically.
So anyway, I did this because I work with this stuff.
And I have people that all the time, they just, David, give
me my data.
And so what I really wanted to do was just build a GUI that
I could give to them with an easy button on it and says,
get me my data.
And it would just automatically download the data.
And they wouldn't be calling me up all day long.
So this is just one thing.
And now we'll go to the rest of it.
So this is all built on Flutter.
How many people know what Flutter is?
Flutter is a cross-platform language built on Dart that
Google built for mobile development.
And so you're probably saying to yourself, but David, we
only use the web.
Same code base.
I didn't change anything here.
Same thing.
On the web.
But wait, there's more.
So we come over here to the docs,
publishing your flood app.
You can publish with the same exact code base to Android,
iOS, Mac, Linux, Windows, and the web.
With the same code base.
Not any changes.
I don't know about you guys, but that impresses
the heck out of me.
I think it's really cool.
I've done this.
Let me show you this real quick.
I think I got 23 seconds.
This is a native Mac OS app that I built and compiled into
native Mac code with the Flutter, or the Flet library.
And you can just.
So I mean, in five minutes.
That's awesome, David.
Now I need to figure out what I can make.
That's pretty cool.
All of that from one code base.
Very cool.
Awesome.
All right, we're going to get Bo McDermott set up on the
stage here.
Do you need to plug in, or are you just talking?
Just a brief moment for tech set up.
Who has a computer and phone in front of them or in their
hand, raise your hand.
Raise your hand.
OK, if you could pull up the standard library reference,
Python standard library reference.
You can Google that.
And then we'll wait while the rest of my tech set up happens.
Thank you.
You've been patient.
All right, we can begin.
Let's go, George.
I'm Troy McClure.
You may remember me from such films as Python, Strings on a
Plane, The Iterator, Iterator 2, Datetime.day, Method Max,
Dunderdome.
And now I welcome you to my new talk, Python Documentation,
An Actor's Guide to Getting Off Book.
My name's Bo McDermott.
I'm not.
Troy McClure.
Oh, I wish I were Phil Hartman.
He's cool.
20 years ago, I was a huge computer nerd.
I did like a year and a half of CCNA and CCNP and college and
all this stuff.
And then I didn't want a desk job, so I went and did other
stuff.
And then I've been living my life.
And then a couple years ago, third of the company got laid
off that I really liked, and I was one of them.
And then two weeks later, one of my best friends of all time
died very tragically.
And I was like, huh.
And so I did a lot of life rethinking.
And I found myself last year just diving into code.
It's my first time to ever pick up Python or any programming
language, aside from HTML in the 90s or Cisco switches.
But my son here, he's 12.
He's been block coding since he's eight.
Block coding.
Clap.
Very impressive.
So it's been a bonding experience for me diving into
the code.
I don't have programming friends, so I do it the old
way.
I'm also an actor.
So I took it the actor's approach, where you memorize
your script, which seems kind of crazy because it's like
encyclopedias for Python if you've looked at all the
documentation.
But why does an actor memorize a script?
It's not to get hired.
After all, that doesn't make you any good at acting.
They memorize, the best ones that I know, because once you
have it in your mind and body, the material, you can play.
So I figured, why not?
That's what I'll do.
If you have the built-in standard library stand up, I'm
just going to test, because I think I've memorized
everything from the built-in functions part.
If you look at that introduction there, there's
intro, built-in functions, all the way to the end of
exceptions.
So I pull up the built-in functions.
And just throw some out, and let's see if I can remember
the arguments, because I did this in December.
I just memorized all this stuff.
And I just want to see.
Anybody?
Yell at a function.
Enumerate.
Let's see, it ends with the flags equals zero, right?
Or the steps equals zero.
And it starts with a, is it iterable?
OK.
Anything else?
What else?
Come on, you people.
Filter.
Let's see if I can do filter.
Yes.
No, I've forgotten filter, because it ends in what?
Value?
No, I don't remember.
I know that I memorized what?
Range.
Multiple variations for range.
You give it the, so I'm putting myself on the spot.
Start, stop.
You give it the number.
Start.
Stop.
Well, anyway, I'm on the spot here.
So instead, I'll just do this.
Abs-all, any, callable, bool, divmod, sum, pow.
Those are the logical, mathematical, bytes, numeric.
They're all just sort of sitting in there.
Functions, iterators, generators, all these things
is the documentation memorized.
If you were to go into, say, the functions section,
or the iterator section, how I memorized those
was not by really understanding them, but by memorizing
the pictures, just the imagery of the words.
So I'm just going to show you how,
if you want to learn a new module, or the way
that I learn a module, you just pick, read the docs,
pick five things that you like, five things that
are really important to you.
And then walk around a room or town and point.
For abs, pick a really stimulating image.
Somebody really, really sexy is working out
without their shirt on.
They've got their abs, and they're doing their abs things.
It's got a little x on there, so they got a tattoo of an x.
And remember, for iterators, I use a cow.
It's a bull.
For an iterable, it's an utters and bull.
And for iterators, it's actually like the Terminator,
but it's a cow.
My whole point is that if you have just a couple images,
you have an index of terms.
And then you have a checklist.
And that's all I do.
I just have a checklist of terms that I go through.
And I'm not really worried about speed,
because I'm sitting in the middle of this.
Five minutes.
But that's how you do it.
All right.
Thank you, Bo.
Go ahead and get set up up there, Walker.
Yeah?
All right.
I will hand this off for something more exciting to Walker
Hale and automatically running tests.
OK.
Eating the mic.
Yeah.
So there's the title slide.
And there.
OK.
So this is my motivation.
I'm telling a story.
I want to run linters, formatters, tests, et cetera.
All of that.
I want to run all the things.
And I want to run them whenever I make any change.
OK.
I don't want to rely on continuous integration,
because that means I've got to wait till I push a branch.
Who's got time for that?
I don't want to just rely on a pre-commit hook.
I've got to actually get add and get commit just to run.
No.
I'm too old.
I don't want to touch the mouse.
I'm running out of time.
I want to just, and I want to be able to easily change things.
I want to be able to change my mind about what tests I want
to run, if it's generating some test files in a temporary
directory, and I want to be able to look at a particular
file because something failed.
I want to be able to quickly make changes and see what's
happening, and I want it all now.
Now.
OK.
So here's my trick.
So all of you have already seen your project layouts.
There's a source directory and a test directory, and here's
like a little toy example.
And so yeah, I could just like PyTest, and it's going to run
test my code.
Great.
And there's my module.
So what I do is I just add another directory, and I've
got two files in there.
And one file is the thing I start up at the beginning of
my session.
The other file is going to get run every single time I do
Command-S. Every time I save, that's the trigger to
run everything.
So there's the magic at the top, that first file.
Watch files.
Now that's based on, this is inspired by a previous now
deprecated project called rerun.
And it just will monitor a directory.
Every time it sees a change, it will run the
command you provided.
Of course, you've got to be a little clever, filter out like
PyCache, otherwise it'll go into like an infinite loop.
And so you're a little clever how to do it.
This is not the only tool that does that.
You pick one.
And then you've got this other script.
This is the script that runs every time.
And you make sure that your system is sensitive to that
script, too.
So whenever I make a change to that loop body.sh,
everything reruns.
I say, oh, I want to change my PyTest arguments.
There we go.
It's going to rerun everything all the time, just
because I made a change somewhere.
So this is it running.
And if I just go in here, loop body, I don't know, just and
save, it's rerunning.
And I could turn black on, turn black off, whatever.
That's the trick.
Watch files or any competing product, and
it becomes your IDE.
The operating system is now your IDE, and
your trigger is save.
That's it.
All right.
So let's hear from Devin and Max on why you
should do a game jam.
Let's make sure it's on.
Can you hear me?
We can hear you.
Awesome.
All right.
Hi, everybody.
Thank you so much for your patience.
My name is Max Logan.
My name is Devin Brainer.
We're friends, if you didn't already know that.
Yep.
And today, we're going to talk about why you
should do a game jam.
So raise your hand if you've ever participated
in a hackathon.
And raise your hand if you know what a hackathon is.
So for anyone who didn't raise their hand, it's basically a
time-constrained event for building a project under a
specific theme.
And that's what a game jam is.
The theme is specifically a game, but they will often have
more specific themes as well.
Last summer, Max and I participated in the Game
Maker's Toolkit game jam, which is a 48-hour jam.
Yeah, and we just want to talk about, first, why we did it.
First off, we love video games.
That's part of what got us into coding in the first place.
And we wanted to make one together.
We were friends for a long time, wanted to get some
extra experience, all that sort of thing.
But we needed a reason to actually
get started on the game.
It's hard to make that first step and just get started on
what you're working on.
And we also needed an idea to get behind.
And fortunately, the theme for the game jam was kind of the
perfect prompt.
Last year's theme was roles reversed, which was very fun.
So during the jam, we faced quite a few challenges, one of
which was we decided that we were going to take this
opportunity to learn a new game engine.
That is the Godot game engine.
It's an open source game engine.
We had never touched it before.
And we thought, well, we'll make a whole game in it in 48
hours, that'll go great.
Time management was difficult.
And scoping was also a challenge.
Coming up with an idea that we could execute within the
time frame and have success with was pretty difficult.
We did our best to plan out our days at the start.
But as it happens, bugs can get in the way.
Also, due to the time constraint, we didn't have a
lot of opportunities for breaks.
And focusing can be difficult under those conditions.
And we got pretty tired at night.
So how'd it go?
Well, I think it actually went pretty well.
Turned out we did actually scope appropriately.
And we made this game, we called it Invasive Species.
Very low art.
We're mainly coders, not artists.
But this game, you act as the weeds on the farm with the goal
of destroying all the crops before the
farmer eradicates you, which we thought was very clever for
the roles reversed theme.
And the reception was surprisingly good.
So these were the results for the game.
We ended up in about the top 11% in terms of enjoyment,
which was our highest stat.
And then, of course, the top 37% in presentation, probably
due to our tutorials.
There were about 6,800 entries about.
So that's our placement under those statistics.
And then just one example of some of the
feedback that we got.
So why should you do one?
Well, we found it pretty rewarding.
It was really fun to build something cool in a short
amount of time.
It was a great opportunity to improve skills.
The constraints of the topic and the time limit force you
to be creative with the skills that you have.
And you have to use them in an interesting way, especially if
you want to get noticed by people reviewing.
It's also really fun at the end of the jam when you are
looking at other submissions.
A lot of the teams came up with some really cool ideas that we
never would have thought of.
There was one that was one of the winners, and it was you're
a dog trying to get pets.
And last, but certainly not least, you can use Python.
You don't have to learn a whole new game engine in two days
like we did.
You can just use PyJam, or PyGame, which is an open
source library for multimedia applications,
specifically games.
That's why it's called that.
Yeah, thank you.
That's it.
Thank you guys so much.
All right.