Panny Knight. What's up family? How we doing by Texas? My lightning talk I'm
going to talk about BDD. Who here knows what BDD is? What is it? You're
wrong. It stands for Bulldog Driven Development. This is my bulldog. Her name
is Suki. She is a French bulldog. Did you know Frenchies are the most popular dog
breed in America? I mean just look at this thing. She is thick and juicy like
a steak. Oh so cute. My wife and I, this is our first dog. People ask do you have
children? We say no. We have a bulldog. This is Suki. This is our baby child. In
Chinese we call her ma hai zi meaning fur baby. She is very much the favorite
child of the family. Just oh my gosh look at this having so much fun. Suki gets to
travel the US. We've taken her down to Jacksonville to see the beaches of
Florida. We've taken her down to Savannah to see the beautiful trees. We've taken
her to Seattle. These are the spheres in the Amazon district. They go by another
name. This is also some some park out in the Pacific Northwest. She's an adventure
puppy. We love it. She's even been to Bucky's. Yes Suki has been to Bucky's.
She's having a good time. When she's not traveling the US she's
pooping around the house and yes poop is a verb. P-O-O-K. I want to turn this
picture into him like an Andy Warhol print you know. Sometimes you can hear
pictures. Look at her trying to bark. Or sometimes if she's not pooping around
the house she's sitting there silently judging you. She is the master of the
side eye. Sometimes she's a grumpy pants. I think her spirit human is Wilfer
Brimley trying to tell me about diabetes.
Sometimes she we think she might be a bullfrog instead of a bulldog. But we
know that's not true because she doesn't like getting wet. Poor puppy. But at the
end of the day we love this dog. She is our baby. She is a gift from God. Suki the
Frenchie has made our lives so much better.
Awww. You know we're all driven by something and I know this is a Python
conference for in a software context. I mean there's behavior driven
development, test driven development, data driven development. I don't know
whatever the else driven development right. But I think it's important to
remember that we make software for humans and it's important to remember
what drives us right. I'm driven by my family, by my faith, and by my bulldog. So
never forget what drives you to do what you do. Thank you very much by Texas. This
is Bulldog Driven Development. My name is Pandy Knight. It's been an honor.
Better? Okay. All right. So I'm going to talk about strings. Who uses strings in
their Python scripts? Okay everybody that's right. And what I'm going to talk
about are a couple of things that you'll find about using strings in your
production applications. Strings are everywhere and they have everything in
them. They'll have what you expect. I'll have what you don't expect. They'll have
spaces. They'll have character turns. They'll have new lines and so forth.
Control characters. Sometimes nothing. So there are a number of common less than
best practices for working with strings. I've got three of them on this list. And
why are they common? They're common because this is what's in the tutorials
that you'll find online. Because the tutorials are written back in time
before some of these newer features are there for better practices with strings.
So I'll start with the first one which is how to remove leading and trimming
literals with string, Lstrip, and Rstrip. Actually that's the anti-pattern. And for
those of you who are here last year I actually did a lightning talk and this
was one of the slides out of this so I'm rerunning this this particular hint. But
in this case we're using Lstrip to remove the leading www off of this web
address. Unfortunately Lstrip is a more aggressive than you think because it's
not using a string. That string is actually the list of characters that
we're going to remove from the source string. So removing www dot is actually
going to give us lsfargo.com. Solution as of Python 3.9 is to use remove
prefix and remove suffix which now are smarter about removing those segments
from the source string. The next one I have is to use string dot split to split
a string into two parts. The first example here isn't really a
surprise it's actually doing what we expect. We want to split on the letter B
and we get everything before everything after. The variability is that if the B
isn't there we're just going to get a single element list which which has the
entire string in it. In the following two examples where we give it an empty
string or a string containing just a B we get either a single element or a
double element but we don't really we have to have a more code we have to
figure out was the B even there and what was in place around it. So for production
use you want something more predictable and that's partition. With string dot
partition you always well in fact there's the advantage you always get a
three-string tuple and the center tuple or the center value is the separator if
it was present or an empty string if it wasn't and corresponding our partition
partitions from the right side instead of from the left side of the string. So
using partition instead of split gives you more predictable data results and
you don't have to write as much inference code to figure out what it was
you're actually working with. The last one is logging string values and here we
have an F string which is I have no such value key. In this case the first
example aabcc we get a message no such value aabcc the second one our log just
shows no such value aabcc it's a little hard to see that there's actually a
leading space on that that key value and it may be that that leading leading
space is why it wasn't found in the database or in the source. The third
case is one that I've seen happen in a couple of companies already where data
that was originally passed through as aabcc was colorized by somebody who
thought oh it will look prettier if I colorize this and so now I've got an
escape sequence but I don't see that here because I've only printed it as the
string value. If instead I log the repr of that value I get a couple of things
one is I'll get surrounding quotes around the value and I'll also expand
control characters to be more visible and interpretable so I don't have to
guess why is it in red or why is the red value not matched. So repr is the log
string values oh and by the way you should double and triple check your
messages in your accept handlers because a lot of times you know those
don't get logged until the exception happens. Five minutes. Okay. Thank you Paul.
I have one more slide which you're gonna want to see. Wow ah yeah. So this didn't
realize I was going to go over though. As one of the authors in Python in a
nutshell O'Reilly has given us a discount code and I have cards that you
can get have these codes on as well but from Google Play you get 40% off the
online version of Python in a nutshell. All right thank you. Y'all scan fast or
see Paul after. Thank you Paul. That was awesome. The title of this is using a
large language model with your data retrieval augmented generation
RAG in five minutes. I don't think I could read that title in five minutes
Will. Okay how do I get the right screen here? You may have to set it to mirror
where you can drag it over either one.
Good. Oh I can see it down here. Okay. All right let's go Will. Okay I have five
minutes so I told you the title my name is William Horton I'm a staff MLE it
included health you can find me on Twitter so I'm gonna teach you about
retrieval augmented generation RAG it's a very hot topic my goal by the end of
this five minutes is to make you all sound like geniuses because I'm telling
you all your bosses are talking about RAG if they're talking about AI and it's
actually a somewhat simple concept so I'm gonna show you okay so I'm using the
Python SDK from open AI specifically chat completions there's two main
parameters I set my model and then I send this message so my role is user and
I have content it responds to me messages is a list so it can contain
your whole history so I put the models response into the list I add a second
message I continue the conversation I got a not that funny joke they're still
working on that part of AI anyway that's just to show you the tools that's not
the content so I've written a simple function wrapping that to be able to
send one user message to the LLM so LLMs know a lot they know some geography they
know math maybe they know language and they know history this is what we would
call world knowledge it's knowledge that's been baked into the model
through training but they don't always know what we want them to know what day
is it today I'm sorry I can't provide that okay thanks GPT what is my job
title that would be useful at work they don't know who is speaking at PyTexas
2024 does it know now I can tell you it does not know it has no idea so there's
some good news this is what rag is about you can actually just add to the
knowledge by telling them a new things yeah it really is that simple people
ask me if they can train or fine-tune models using their own data and the
secret is that in today's paradigm with these super large models people aren't
often retraining what they're doing is just passing more information to the
model in the prompt especially in the system prompt which is special
instructions that you can give to the model so revisiting the questions above
but with the necessary context so here you can see I'm sending a system message
and I'm actually telling the model the current time is whatever the current
time is when I run this and the model will actually be able to answer it now
tells me it's oh Friday that's actually interesting I did not vet that that's
called a hallucination everybody but it knows that it's April 20th that one I
did not catch in prep okay so I've written a second function here in
iteration of my call LLM where I can now pass in a system prompt this will give
the context of the model so if I tell it my name is William Horton and I'm a
staff Emily blah blah blah and then I ask it what is my job title it knows and
that might seem very silly but I actually use this to work all the time I
tell it what my job is and then I ask it to read a document and it can use that
context that you've told it to inform how it responds here's another one I
downloaded the HTML for the talk schedule it's about 35 hundred thirty
five thousand characters it looks like that it's all HTML now I ask you who's
speaking it's gonna take some time on that so I'm gonna move on and come back
so rag really what it gets at is what if we have many documents so I gave it HTML
but what if it was multiple documents well I want to get the documents that are
relevant to my query okay so that worked this I want to delete yeah here we go I
already created some docs there were all the presentation information they look
like this they're stringify JSON one for each talk I'm gonna turn them into
embeddings if you don't know what embeddings are I'm not gonna be able to
cover that in the talk let's just say they capture something about the
semantic similarity of these strings so each embedding for each talk description
will help me figure out how similar it is there's the embeddings they're just a
bunch of numbers go go go go I'm down to less than a minute okay I'm just gonna
prove that the model does not know this it would be cool if it did but I'm sorry
Andy Python conference famous does not get you into the knowledge of DPT
apparently okay but I can create an embedding for my query now if I have a
query embedding and my document embeddings although you find the most
similar documents using some cool numpy these are the indexes of the documents
that are most similar how many documents should I get I chose three models can
ignore irrelevant stuff so I get my context it's a bunch of strings and you
can see at the top is the actual relevant one about Andy now I call it
again and it knows that Andy works at Bloomberg that is rag in five minutes it
does not work with the wrong documents you can do you can factor it into a
function all the code I just wrote fits in 17 lines and if you don't want to
write it you use something like LOM index as a framework find me on Twitter
on github I'll post this stuff now you can go back and sound like a genius just
say rag awesome thank you al swagger ladies gentlemen all right hello hello
okay so for the blast two months I've been in Brooklyn attending the recurse
center what is the recurse center oh wow okay people have heard of this yeah how
I describe it it's sort of like an artist retreat but for software
developers and it's great you go there and you're working on a software project
of your own but you're also surrounded by a bunch of other people who are smart
and motivated and also working on projects of their own they also have a
remote option as well so you don't actually have to go all the way to
Brooklyn I encourage everyone to just kind of check it out it's it's I mean it
sounds sort of weird for me to say it's life-changing but I've definitely
become one of those people who now talks about the recurse center and encourages
everyone to apply which is how I got sucked into it so it's not a cult but so
the recurse center has a code of conduct of course but one thing that I found
really interesting was it also has four social rules and these are rules that
unlike the code of conduct they actually kind of expect that from time
to time you're going to accidentally break these rules it's these rules are
really great it's giving me this language to talk about things that I've
noticed before in in social situations but I didn't really know how to describe
so here's the here's the four rules the first one is no well actuallys this is
probably one that people can understand it's basically when somebody makes a
statement and then somebody else butts in says well actually with something
that's you know it might be technically correct but it's not really relevant and
it kind of just derails the entire conversation so in these cases right
here it's like hey I just installed Linux on my computer and then somebody
else says it's like okay yes you know thank you for that information but it
kind of just like disrupts the whole thing and this sort of thing again it's
it's not a big deal is this is you know from time to time we'll all do this
because we're all excited about the knowledge that we have and we want to
share this knowledge including correcting other people but it is like
this kind of like tiny death by a thousand paper cuts thing and so
basically somebody can then say like oh well hey you're doing the well actually
thing and you can say oh sorry yeah I didn't mean to do that the next one no
feigning surprise this is a big one I was once at a monthly tech meetup and we
were talking about the x11 window system for Linux hands up if you know what the
x11 window system is okay and now hand up if you've never heard of this before
right some of you have some of you haven't there was one person who just
said like oh yeah what is that and the other person who was talking to him said
you've never heard of that and I want to say like it really doesn't take much to
make a person feel unwelcome at a space especially when they're at a technical
conference or some meetup and they're already really afraid that they don't
know enough or they're not they're somehow like not qualified and it can be
really just little comments like this like feigning surprise that can really
just drive people away actually there's there's a lot to do in life and there's
you know there's more to life than Python people can just say like well
maybe tech isn't for me and I'll just do something else with my life so no
feigning surprise no backseat driving that's another one this is where you
have added information but you're not really part of a conversation you just
kind of like throw this little tidbit into the discussion and again it derails
and disrupts the conversation okay I'm running out of time no subtle isms okay
so things like harassment and discrimination those are covered by the
code of conduct codes of conduct are not optional the social rules though
these are things where like yeah from time to time unfortunately we might
break some of these rules so the example here is oh Windows is hard to use is
like no Windows is easy my mom can use this and that's like oh that's like the
subtle racism sexism ageism these things that can also make people feel
incredibly unwelcome so no subtle isms and you know there's a lot of like room
for for judgment calls on what technically counts as a violation of
this but the general idea is that you want to make a space where people feel
welcome where they're not going to be I don't know psychological safety I feel
is the the main word for this it's really important to have in
organizations you want to be able to tell bad news to your boss you want to
be able to view your co-workers as people you're cooperating with rather
than competing against you want everyone to feel like they can contribute without
being negatively impacted anyway I'm running out of time so Google this the
four social rules at the recurse Center thank you very much
nicely done all right hello everybody my name is Peter and this talk is called so
you want to give a talk five ways to keep your audience off their phones you
might have seen me up here just about four hours ago this is what it looked
like if you remember me hi again I'm gonna talk about five rules up top here
the first one is be engaging then the second one is be loud third one is be
big fourth one is be prepared and the last one is be considerate I only have
five minutes I'm gonna rush through but all five of these you can remember with
this handy acronym just a little bit okay all right let's start at number one
be engaging so this is all about making sure that your audience is on board with
your talk you start by introducing yourself then you start by introducing
your topic after that which I just did then you get to the point which
hopefully I'm doing right now the point about all of this is that your audience
is going to quickly lose attention if you you know go off on a tangent or start
to fiddle with your laptop a little bit or you're not really sure what's going
on there when you are telling your story it's really handy to use a very classic
story structure like this you can start with exposition here's the problem I
want to solve here's the rising action here's all the interesting stuff you
want to know about here's the climax here's the falling action here's the
resolution it's all just telling a story but make your audience familiar with the
problem before showing them the solution don't start with how you solve the
problem before they even understand why they care another thing that I used to
be engaging I use presentation software like keynote that's my favorite I use
this all the time I'm using it right now and I use a concept called object
constancy which you just saw there I'll do it again because it's really cool
you do transitions and all this kind of stuff you add more things to the slide
and then as things move around on the slide you make sure that they stay
visible you never fade something out and fade it back in you never put it off the
screen and then pop it back on and that animation seems like it's just sugar on
top but it's really handy to help your eye track that and keep keep it in view
I use this feature called magic move to do that it's built into keynote you
should use it it's really easy and also speaking of transitions even obnoxious
transitions can be useful for dramatic effect if you really want to make a
point use something really really visually catchy to get people's
attention speaking of getting people's attention be loud I'm currently speaking
into this nifty device called a microphone it looks like this it's got a
couple parts to it it's got a pop filter on top you can hear that because I can
pop the filter by by really doing that with my mouth it's got a capsule
underneath which is picking up my my voice and actually transmitting it to
the speakers and it's got a body that you hold on to there's a couple ways you
can use a microphone you can speak directly into it like this and you can
hear that's very loud very clear I hope at the back you can hear that maybe
excellent so I would say this is a good way to use a microphone you can also use
it like this vertically underneath your mouth that's okay too however there is a
slight downside here if I exhale with my nose you can hear that so holding it
horizontally kind of avoids that problem what I would not recommend is doing this
or doing this doesn't really work that well even having it up here and then you
know kind of speaking off to the side you need to be right on it people say
that they eat the mic sometimes and that's not a misnomer you can get really
up close there and it sounds loud and clear okay one other thing I want to
talk about is being big what I mean by that well that text is big all text on
slides that I put up must be at least 60 points in size that text is 60 points
it's pretty easy to read I hope but at the back if you've got I don't know not
the best vision like I do that's hard for me to see so 120 points is also pretty
good usually I go as big as I can this text is 240 points that's even better
make it as big as possible don't waste a single pixel on your slides you've got
extra space there why would you waste it the bigger you can go the more people
that can actually read your content also don't show me the window chrome if you
can please there's no need to have all of that extra space there I don't need
to see the other slides are coming up next that will distract me also sometimes
it's very useful to not show anything at all right if I'm talking to you and I
really want to engage with you and tell a little bit of story there's nothing I
need to show on the screen there's nothing you want to read at the same
time I'm not gonna hold the last slide up there that's not very useful I hope
you're listening to the words I'm saying right now instead of being distracted by
the last slide that was on the screen and also side note don't forget to turn
off notifications very very important I've got 30 seconds left so I also want
to say be prepared run your talk over and over and over again I ran this just
sitting there probably three or four times before giving this just now if
you're doing a live demo that is presenting on hard mode just fake it
this looks like it's real it's not it's part of keynote to gotcha and finally be
considerate of your audience's time one second of time wasted times 60 audience
members is wasted blah blah blah blah blah you don't want to waste people's
time so that's all I've got be engaging be loud be big be prepared to be
considerate wait wait wait before you drop before you drop the mic confirm
something for the audience we have not spoken before this no we have not
spoken before this no okay keep that in mind before Josh starts all of you laugh
I do want to say Raghu and Aaron if y'all want to see already next okay okay
that if you haven't seen enough of this guy yet you're gonna see more of them
you're gonna see more of it I'm gonna do my best to gesticulate wildly okay five
quick short tips for presenting your ideas which I give to like interns and
stuff like that all the time well number one tell a story stories have a
beginning in a middle in an end so stick to a story have a narrative have a path
that you're taking the users on tip number two is find your signposts take
your story split it up into parts those signposts are the the spaces between the
different parts those are time for you to stop and if you're doing a more
interactive presentation it's time to take questions from the audience but
either way it gives you a distinct section so you can kind of gauge the
room and figure out where you want to go next tip number three practice practice
practice practice your presentation multiple times know where your signposts
are know about how long it takes for each of the different sections know
which sections you can skip if you're running out of time know which sections
you can skip if you're losing the audience number four energy you give is
the energy you get if you don't sound excited about your topic the audience
won't be excited about your topic so if you're excited about something feel free
to just healing wildly I'm really excited about this library that I'm
talking about yay it gives the audience permission to be excited just like you
are and the fifth tip is expects and prepare for the unexpected especially if
you're doing a live demo the live demo gods are fickle and we never sacrifice
enough USB drives to make them happy so make sure that you have backup plans if
the internet's out if the projector doesn't work you should be able to
interpretive dance your presentation if that's all you have available and there
you go mercifully short
hello everyone yep yeah I'm Raghu I'm a mechanical engineering background and I
just wanted to introduce panel a dashboarding library in Python so why
panel or why interactive visualization so I got into Python mainly because of
like the interactive aspect of visualizations in general mainly because
like if you want to describe complex systems it's very tough for the end user
to understand what is the underlying physics behind the system so what we do
is like try to build interactive web applications so the end user can toggle
various aspects of the widgets and try to understand the system so later you I
will show some examples and you can understand and why you would like to
explore panel is like I think how many of you use matplotlib and you understand
like matplotlib is not interactive in nature but by using panel you can make
your matplotlib plots interactive and within panel you can basically build
plots in bokeh matplotlib plotly or seaborn alter and combine everything
into one so here for example is like a k-means cluster and you can see like you
can interact with the features and change the number of clusters and
interactively see how the system works and panel also interacts with chatbots
for example like an end user does not need to know Python at all and he can
basically talk to a chatbot and build plots so he can also he or she can also
like ask the plots to be changed from matplotlib to bokeh or plotly or any
backend can be switched easily so how do I use it in my work so I work for
pattern Miller it basically is our main background is in motorsports and we have
driver in the loop simulator it's basically a million dollar video game
and what we are trying to do is like describe the vehicle how the the vehicle
physics which runs on this particular hardware and what we are trying to do is
understand like develop testing which basically is easy for the end user or
our simulation engineers to see what is working what is not working so one
implementation in bouquet is a static HTML report which is generated to
compare like if any developer makes any change he can quickly understand like
what is going wrong in which aspect of the model so it basically generates a
report comparing signals with related to the develop branch or the production
branch and you can generate interactive plots in static HTML and try to see like
where there is generated one other implementation which we have implemented
is in the stem education so this is actually being used in chemical
engineering curriculum at Lehigh University and this is the basically
assignments for students to understand chemical engineering so I I get
like you need to communicate physics or engineering education in different ways
for different folks so that they can get a better idea of what is going on so
here this is like a sequential reaction of A going to B going to C and a student
can basically so I need to refresh
so yeah so a student can play with the parameters and a professor or faculty
can design assignments basically to get students to understand like how the
system behaves so we have many examples of different simulations so we have like
infectious disease model which was motivated by COVID and they can
understand like underlying epidemiological models and we have
data science digital lab twin model and one of the other thing is like this one
is how to build a zero energy cool cooling chamber so without access to
electricity how you can preserve food for a longer time and this one is
teaches physics and so basically you can basically all right here we go okay
hi guys my name is Erin I'm currently a master's student at UT Austin studying
data science before thank you before becoming a full-time student I was
working at tax act which is turbo tax adjacent we all just filed our taxes
recently so I'm sure we know what that is but I was noticing that with a lot of
business processes we would build models and then have to integrate them and
retrain a lot of models and so when I took reinforcement learning I noticed
that this type of learning is much more seamless with what businesses tend to do
and I kind of wondered why more businesses didn't do it I think it's
just novel people aren't as familiar with it actually out of curiosity raise
of hands how many people know what reinforcement learning is okay there you
go so more people than I thought I'm just to intro for those that don't
raise their hand it's generally considered the third paradigm of machine
learning so along with unsupervised supervised learning it's kind of the
third type of learning it's generally made up of so what I have on the screen
this is a article I wrote on a hands-on project I did with implementing an RL
system and optimizing customer engagement with an online tax filing
system so the way I structured the problem and the way most reinforcement
learning problems are structured you have an environment which in this case
is our online tax filing system then you have a reward which you create and you
create this reward so that an agent will is incentivized to do the thing you want
it to do so in this case we want to keep customers from leaving our website and
you have states actions and then okay there we go you have your agent which I
mentioned previously so those are your four or five main parts of your RL
system so with this system the actions I used were recommending an upgrade to
your customer when they seem frustrated or pausing having targeted incentives
like offering discounts having a chat pop up with personalized recommendations
and then progress tracking which TurboTax uses and it has proved to be
helpful with customers when they know this isn't gonna take forever it's gonna
take two hours that's very motivating so next looking at algorithms that you
can use I think if you know reinforcement learning you might have
heard of Q learning it's kind of the most popular reinforcement learning
system or algorithm out there so that is a type of temporal difference learning
the other major type of temporal difference algorithm is Sarsa so the
difference between those two Q learning is off policy and Sarsa is on policy and
one big recommendation our professor made was that Q learning can be very
aggressive because it's off policy whereas Sarsa can tends to find a more
safe policy and what I mean by that is with this system we start from a place
where we take no action and then we're moving towards taking more and more
action you find that as you interact more with the customer they tend to like
that support and want to stay but as you can imagine with a more aggressive
algorithm if you're constantly getting pop-ups and recommendations it can kind
of get annoying so you have to be careful with that for that reason I opted
for Sarsa oops and I opted for the temporal difference lambda algorithm
which layers on eligibility traces with Sarsa so I kind of explain all the
intricacies of why I chose all these algorithms later on if you're interested
this article is on my medium blog but the takeaway what we end up doing here
and like 50 lines of code we're able to automate finding the best action for a
user given a certain state that's what these temporal difference algorithms do
they find the most valuable state action pair and you're able to use this system
to learn dynamically and five recommend the best state action pair so there you
go