We have a special treat for you. I'm gonna hand you off for story time. Yes with mr. Josh Cannon, please welcome him to the stage
So I now get to be Dunder Seuss, I know we've all had lunch and it's now story time to ever speaking after this
I'm sorry half the audience might be asleep. It's a nice warm setting
All right, let's begin
Oh
Our programming does require us to read the about the author page
So Josh Cannon aka Dunder Seuss has written no books so far has been on a single podcast and done exactly one talk before he
Decided to write this book
Josh is a developer productivity engineer by day a maintainer of the pants build open
Sorry pants build open source build system also by day and sometimes participates in other open source projects Python community discussions and conference speaking
also by day
He's a lover of getting to know enough Python to make expressive readable and intuitive code
He wrote this book to teach others of the power and magic that you can bring to your objects to make them expressive readable and intuitive
And exciting for us. There is a 2024 AI addendum
Although mid-journey was used to create the whimsical graphical art
Absolutely
No AI or any other kind of text generation was used for the content the author feels like it would ruin the artistic value of this book
Enjoy
And it is dedicated for Devon Dottie and Teddy with love if my magic clicker works. There we go
Congratulations today is your day you will soon learn you some magic the good and proper way
You've chosen a wise way to spend your precious time by learning from a clay crazy loon going on and rhyme
About a list of methods that are nicknamed the Dundas and how we'll use them to code great wonders
They start with two underscores and end with two more thus dunder which is short for double underscore
The runtime of Python calls them in many situations allowing your objects many customizations
You'll learn all about how to emulate a container and iterators and numbers from a great explainer
Comparisons callables oops and descriptors to and how to make attributes appear out of the blue
You'll learn some new names and I know you'll learn many at least one if not two
Maybe up to 20 by the end, you'll know magic. You'll know magic galore. You'll be so full of magic. You'll yell, please sir. No more
So with great skillful skill and lots of caffeine, let's start off your learning with a method you've seen
Let's pretend you're new to Python just for a minute. You'll then learn the first magic dunder in it
It is almost every objects initializer allowing you to be an attribute organizer adding new attributes to your fresh new object
The most common magic I truly do suspect
but
This is a delay. Where did self come from? You'll soon start to wonder
Then you'll learn it's created by just another dunder one that constructs the blank object to give to you and its name
You'll soon find out is dunder new
It's a special static method. You'll maybe define in your class which returns some object then onward
To whom it turns out depends on the return objects type if it's an instance of your class
Including a possible subtype. It goes to dunder in it. You'll hear from the scholar, but otherwise he'll say it's back to the caller
You'll see this in action and it'll be more clear II by looking for its use in the standard library
pathlib path
Uses this method to help it perform constructing an object specific to your platform
The type as you'll find has defined under new to return a subclasses instance specific to you
Now with great careful care and with great tactful tact
You'll see using it is a great balancing act a magic with the power to create objects that are new is something to avoid
misuse of too and
Speaking of balance the opposite of dunder new was not oft employed dunder Dell is called right before your object is destroyed
You'll use it to release resources you've acquired but only if you want its definition isn't required
But if you do write it heed this warning as well, you must call your supers
dunder Dell
Now the next set of magics involve conjuring illusions of attributes giving your callers
Delusions that your objects has more or less than it does. Well, why friendly interfaces is the because
First on your journey through attribute emulation dunder get adders the proper incantation
you'll type it out with a flick and a twist and you'll synthesize attributes that don't exist it's called when default
Attribute access fails the attribute simply wasn't in the details. You'll get a chance to pretend it existed
However on your object the attribute isn't persisted
Now if you wish to pretend you don't recognize this name raise attribute error emulates that all the same
Emulates that all the same
It has an alter ego named under get attribute you'll see which is called for all access
Unconditionally, it gets called for names both existing and not but beware infinite recursion is easily got
If you happen to type out self dot
So remember when you need access to your attributes inside of your thing, you won't use self dot you'll give your super ring
To juxtapose get dunder set adder is how attributes setting your classes allow again by default the attribute isn't
Persisted you get to choose whether it becomes listed. This is also called for all attributes without any condition whether it exists or not without your permission
The last of the adder methods you'll maybe leave off if you define dunder delatter people might scoff as you'll probably guess
It's good for emulation of the removal of a name from your objects formation and just like dunder set adders unfortunate asymmetry
It gets called for all names
unconditionally
You'll then find out soon enough that when it comes to illusory stuff attribute names is just where it starts there's more you'll learn another two parts
Yes, like all good things these magics come in three and more ways than one
You'll actually soon see the first way is the trio of names get set and del
Then how they're used for other illusions as well. So the second in our trio trios, I'll teach to you now
These methods are so powerful
You'll see how an attribute gets to customize itself instead of sitting static on some other objects shelf
Descriptors is the name given to this technique of attributes themselves using double speak first
You'll see these things works as attributes of a class you'll see Django and SQL alchemy use this in mass
The descriptor is the attribute and it gets a say on how it gets got it said it and deleted per se
Dunder get is the first of these spells. You'll want to perfect conjuring values for attributes based on the owner's object
Or sometimes the class a sometime as callers sometimes will do so your dunder get should support that too
And usage of descriptors you'll see sooner not later they're used for several built-in decorators
Static method class method and property all use this technique to customize your attributes for you
And just like dunder get adder dunder get has two brothers dunder set and dunder delete are the others
They act just like dunder get and proxying a call and can do anything they want both big and small
You've maybe had wondered or even had a theory how SQL ORMs quickly fire off a query
When you access certain attributes in the class you set the column descriptor is leveraging dunder get
To run a SQL query using the instances database ID and return to you the value and maybe cash it you see
You'll see dunder set gets called for attribute assignment a SQL update is likely used for new value enshrinement
Lastly dunder delete when an attribute is told to go bye-bye a SQL delete you will likely see fly by
There is one more method that plays in this game and it's a method that goes by dunder set name
Our trio is really for oh well what a shame at the end of your class definition you see
For all of the class attributes that be if they define a dunder set name the attributes name Python will disclaim
And thus the attribute shell game now comes to a close the illusions of attributes we have now exposed
The last of our trio of trios you'll learn from your trainer is emulating items inside a container
You'll see this time our trio suffixes item to help like containers with things inside them
They are given the key and in one case the value implementing container semantics are then up to you
Dunder get item has different behaviors on the radar depending on the type of container that you are
Your sequence types which quack like a tuple or list will accept keys as integers and slice objects
Negative insupport is something you can choose to allow or not it's simply up to you
If the value provided is out of your bounds an index error your code should resound
Otherwise if your container has a mapping background you'll raise key error if the key isn't found
And in every case if you reject the keys type raise type error you'll then want to gripe
You'll likely learn to those rules still hold true for the other methods too
And as far as containers go there are a few more dundas you'll want to define lest you commit several blunders
So although our trio of trios may have come to a close you'll want to learn the other container methods I suppose
A quick one that you'll want to define is dunder len which helps python define the length of your container
So when people call len python can return the number back to them
The second one is dunder iter which should return an iterator over the objects that all live inside your container
Unless it's a mapping then what your caller sees is simply all of the mappings keys
There's also this trivia a bit of python fun if your container isn't iterable set dunder iter to none
Now the third on our extras is named dunder contains to test if an object your container maintains
Although technically you don't have to define it python won't be bitter
Instead it'll test membership first using dunder iter
Going over every possible object that your object can contain and asking if any of those objects are equal or the same
But if you don't define it dunder iter method dunder get item is called and repeatedly tested
Using incrementing indexes from zero until then it gets an index error exception or an equal same object
So it's best to define it so you'll have control of just how the object membership test will unroll
And if for optional methods you'll have soon started a thirst another one available is dunder reversed
It returns an iterator for doing backwards iteration
But you'll only define it if you beat the default computation that python uses combining dunder get item and dunder len
Indexing backwards to zero and then there's one more optional method if you subclass duct
Dunder missing can be defined so that dunder get item can predict what value to use if the key in your mapping isn't there yet
It's how collections default dict or counter with care support operations on items conjured out of thin air
Python just returns to your caller the value itself so if you want to don't forget to store it in yourself
You'll find that you're done you've mastered container emulation but your next set of magics form quite the formation
See you briefly dipped your toe into a few operators however you'll find the list of ops to support is oh so much greater
You'll think about plus and minus and start figuring that the list of operators is bigering and bigering
So on to the mathematic ones that you can define dunder add lets you support the plus sign when your object is on the left
With whatever is on the right you return the added value except when you might reject the operation because you don't know what to do
And instead return the not implemented singleton value such as the case if you don't recognize the type of whatever the thing is on the right
Then dunder sub for subtraction, dunder mole for times, dunder trutive or floridive depending on the kind of division you want
True or integer respectively using one slash or two for division collectively and speaking of operations that come in pairs
Modular arithmetic is a double dunder affair with dunder mod for modular support and then dunder div mod to support the div mod built in
The last pairs of magics of method gifts is dunder l and dunder r shift
The next up is dunder power for to the power of support whose operator is two asterisks side by side for short
And then although this list was already so long three more dunder methods then came along dunder and zor and or
Oh come now don't gripe they're how you support ampersand carrot and pipe
And then when your object supports the at symbol the method you'll want is named under matmul and then that was it
Thank you
There won't be more later 14 methods for mathematic operators
Unless
Unless you think this isn't enough here. Let's take a poll. Is there other numbers stuff? We need to define if yes, raise your hand. I
See I suppose our list should expand
You'll maybe be asking yourself. Oh teacher. How come you'll ask yourself where these new methods are from and how come my methods sometimes return?
Not implemented if to my caller a type error is presented
And so our list of methods then expands to support the same thing with swapped
operands, but only if the result is not implemented and
If two different types are presented Python tries again, but this time with an R at the front of the name
It's not that bizarre and calls this other method on the thing on the right. Let's see an example of how this works to bring it to light
Let's say someone subtracts from a list your foo
Well list doesn't know what the heck to do
So it's done their sub then returns not implemented and then the runtime continues on is documented
Noticing that list and foo are two different classes and calls foos
Dunder our sub and it passes the list object on which we've acted so that foo can say how it should be subtracted
Now remember you'll have to be dexterous and deft and try not to mix up a right op with a left
When in an R method you're the one on the right getting this correct will make you seem right
How about another poll that last one was fun who thinks our mathematic operator list is done
Me neither as it turns out you'll soon enough see all but one of these operators support requires three
Three dundas at most for each of these things. Oh what joy to us supporting math operators brings
So what sets these apart you'll groan and you'll grunt the last set of 13 has an eye in the front
The last set of 13 has an eye in the front they're meant to support doing the math in place mutating the object
Giving in the left space for instance plus equals uses dunder I add completing the addition support triad
However, these methods you can actually omit they're used to help avoid copies a bit
If one of these methods your type is lacking than X equals X plus Y will be the fall backing
If you kept watch you might think I left one for later but no dunder div mod has no in place operator
Now oh baby oh how the operator list will still grow regardless of lengthy class definitions you know
You'll complain and you'll curse and you might even swear but you still need to learn the dundas to compare
The names of these methods aren't really all surprising the brevity of each name is actually what's quite appetizing
Using only two letters to support each operator for operations equality lesser and greater
They're exactly like the methods that I just reported they return not implemented if the comparison isn't supported
And if you want dunder ne you can simply omit dunder eq will defined will be tested a bit
And the return is inverted unless not implemented
However this time there's no crazy switcheroo in this case a type error is raised onto you
And if the comparison is okay a truce or false value as a return is the way
Or anything truthy or falsy is okay it's turned into a bully in the pythonic way
Oh wait forgive me that's actually a new dunder magics on magics isn't python a wonder
If you want to make your object seem falsy or true you'll have to define dunder bool too
Unless perhaps you've defined a dunder len an empty container is falsy then
Last ones on our list and yes it's still growing brevity at this point we are simply foregoing
You'll only need four more so no need to get wary to support the operators unary
Dunder neg pause abs and invert you'll learn for minus plus abs and tilde x in turn
That's it you'll think our list is complete
And you're right I think now isn't that neat
55 ish methods to support the operators no list of magics in one section is greater
Actually not true as you'll find out emulating a number gets to tout the longest list of required magic capitulators
Because in addition to most of those operators there's even more you'll want to support you'll see
Numbers I guess just have a lot of flexibility
From mathematics the list adds on four dunder round trunk seal and floor
What these methods each do you'll notice is visible truncating the value into an integral
Then from a number you'll have several excursions if your object supports any of several conversions
Dunder complex and float bites and stir are magics which python will look and refer to make the type conversion occur
And speaking of strings they've got special magics too dunder repper and format will be waiting for you
Dunder repper returning the official string representation of your object
And executable string of your object is what your callers expect
And for dunder format you'll choose exactly how to track through formatting your object based on the spec
The other magics all come in small lists and in this tome some of them won't exist like the 11 methods for copying and or pickling
Yet here are some more for you coming in at a trickling
If you want your object to quack like a function dunder call is the callable magic junction
Or maybe you'll quack perhaps like an iterator dunder next is the method for that imitator returning the next value
Or the specials terminator which goes by the name of stop iteration you'll raise it when there's no more values in your formation
And if you want something that supports use with with dunder enter and exit says the word Smith
The former is issued right before the inner scope return self is usually the trope
The latter is called when the inner scope is done whether it finished or ran into an exception
This method has power in multiple ways it can release acquired resources always
But it also gets a chance to suppress an exception return true to complete the interception
And then there are some which feels kind of wacky defining them sometimes feel a bit tacky
Dunder in its subclass if defining it you have dared every time a subclass of yours is declared
It receives that subclass as quick as molasses and it was actually added to wean off some use of meta classes
And speaking of meta classes there's dunder prepare on second thought you'll not want to go there
The last set of magics on this magical list of tricks are hooks into instance and subclass checks
That's right the objects you write actually gets a say on the answer of his instance in his subclass yay or nay
However these are looked up on the type of your class meta classes how about we pass
And actually that's it no more magic I'll disclose your journey you've journeyed now comes to a close
To know most of them including the ones this talk doesn't entail read
HTTPS colon forward slash forward slash docs dot python dot org slash three slash reference slash data model dot HTML
Or just ask Google for the URL since most of these magics that page does it detail
Now since your magic is waiting since your mountain is waiting and as you go on your way
Remember the things I remembered to you today and write all of your code the good pythonic way
Yes
Dunder sues ladies and gentlemen all right so I do actually have one question
Oh man that was a brave person
And it wasn't just what the heck in case you were wondering
Oh yeah I did say that was valid
The one question that came in is are you ever going to publish this book
Oh I get that actually a few times so I have like a prop
I did tell myself if I got into PyCon this year I'd publish it but that did not happen
Maybe is the best answer I can give I gave a confident yes at North Bay Python and then I was wrong so I'm trying not to give it but yeah
Fair enough
If I get to go to PyCon this year you might see it as a PyLadies auction item so auction it if you see it
Lovely awesome thanks again Josh or Dunder Sues