Joe Schneider.
Yay!
Hi!
All right.
I'm going to do my best not to suck because I'm the only thing standing between you and
the lightning talks and getting out of here.
So I can hold you all hostage.
Okay.
I need to tell a story.
Back in the olden days, when I was but a little lad, there was this little game called Doom.
And it was really cool at the time because it not only put out the game, but it put out
the tools for you to make your own levels.
And I thought that was really cool at the time because we didn't have anything like
that except maybe board games where you made up your own rules to sorry and everybody was
sorry.
I love expandable architectures like that.
It got me super interested.
Of course, I grew up on Legos.
I was before Minecraft or I probably would have loved it if it was around when I was
a kid.
But I love this idea of being able to take something and extend it and make it something
of my own.
I've been a big fan of plugin architectures.
And so I'm going to talk a little bit about how to make a plugin architecture.
Really I'm going to talk about three libraries that I don't think get a lot of play, but
they're kind of cool and kind of interesting.
And that's package, util, import, lib and inspect.
But I'm going to do that by taking you through building an expandable application with plugins.
So let's level set on what we think a plugin is.
A plugin by my definition is you have an application that's a host application.
It raises events.
It says when it's doing something.
Plugins are optional components that can respond to those events.
When user does this, I can go do this other thing as a result.
The classic example is extensions in your browser, right?
The host application, the browser, provides buttons for you to interact with as the user.
Provides the URL bar, provides back buttons and forward buttons, and it raises events
when the user interacts with those things.
Those extensions can interact with those events and do things on your behalf, right?
We've all used browser extensions before, right?
Right.
Plugins are designed to be optional.
They can be there.
They cannot be there.
They are loosely coupled from the regular application.
I like this diagram as kind of a shorthand of a good way to explain how plugins work.
The user interacts with the host application.
The host application sends signals that a thing has happened and the plugins can respond
to that thing happening, right?
What plugins are and plugin architecture.
Everybody understands why plugin architecture is cool?
All right.
Talk done.
Bye, y'all.
No.
There's a little more to it than that.
Okay.
So, plugins are designed to be optional.
Well, what's the best way to explain how plugins work?
How about we build an application that uses plugins?
Sound like a good plan?
Sweet.
I like to start my applications with requirements because I'm boring.
This is the way that I am.
But I like having an idea of what I'm going to do.
So we're going to go on a quest.
We're going to build an application.
We're going to build a little command line application called file info.
Guess what file info is going to do?
It's going to print out information from files.
I am not on the naming committee.
It is going to send a single event whenever it encounters a new file.
What it's going to do by default is it's going to print out the basic information of a file.
How big it is, the full path to it, and what type of file it is, right?
Because those are common to every file.
But I want to make it expandable so that you can create a plugin to give more specific
information about more specific types.
Like say you have an image file and you want the dimensions of that.
Say you get an Excel file and you want to know how many rows and columns and how many
worksheets there are in there.
You should be able to get that information, right?
A plugin author should be able to create a plugin to give you that information.
So file info is going to expose a single event.
Now we talk about how we want to deal with plugins.
Since I'm covering dynamic stuff, I like to, kind of like Lynn was saying, think about
the user experience of these things.
And I have two users that I have to worry about.
I have the user that's actually using file info and I have the plugin developer who's
developing a plugin for file info.
They both, I need to make a good experience for both of them, right?
Right?
Right.
Okay.
This is the audience participation portion.
Feel free to, I don't know, whatever.
So for plugin, I want to make things as easy as possible.
So for the user, I want file info to discover plugins by itself.
I don't want the user to have to tell it where the plugins are.
I want my file info to just go find all of the plugins.
So the rules that I'm going to have here is that a plugin is going to be any top level
module that's name begins with file info and ends with plugin and has one of my plugin
functions in there.
Everybody with me so far?
Okay.
Plugins for file info are just going to be functions.
They're going to be simple functions that are going to be past the path object to the
file that they're finding and they're going to return an iterable of strings.
They can return a list, a tuple, a set, they could return a generator, whatever, as long
as it's all strings because that's what I'm going to print out to the user.
With me?
Yes.
Sweet.
Any exceptions raised by calling a plugin are going to be logged at the debug level
and then squelched because I don't want the host application to crash.
I want it to be as robust as possible.
I'm going to log those things at debug level and move on.
All functions that can respond to a file will respond to a file.
And since we're doing logging, we're going to use the Python logging library.
I use the Python logging library in everything.
What I'm letting the plugin developer know is anything that you're not logging to the
user probably should be logged at debug level otherwise it will get logged to the user.
As far as the plugins, we're going to build two plugins.
We're going to build a text plugin.
It's going to be called file info text plugin.
Again, I am not on the naming committee.
It is going to print out how many lines and how many words are in there.
We won't get cute or pedantic about the definition of lines or words.
Lines are the number of substrings separated by new lines and words are the number of substrings
separated by spaces that are not empty.
Good.
Then we're going to do a CSV plugin.
This is going to be using the CSV module.
It's our special guest star of this talk.
We're going to use it to extract the number of rows and columns in there.
Everybody with me on this one so far?
Everybody like?
All right.
So we got our requirements in hand.
Yay, our product owner is happy.
Now we can set off to designing.
There's a lot of different ways you can slice this.
So let me talk about some of the things I didn't decide to do.
Thinking about the requirements.
Spoiler alert.
I'm going to do a decorator to decorate functions.
But let's talk about through all the other things I didn't do.
Plugin classes.
Classes for plugins are really, really great if you've got multiple events or your plugins
are going to need to manage state or both.
If you're not going to need to do those, then a class is probably overkill.
If I were going to do a class, this is my OJ Simpson, if I did it, I would probably
do an abstract base class for the interface.
This is just so we can ensure that all of the plugins fit the interface that I need
them to.
And then I'd create a concrete class that implements that ABC.
That's a simple class that anybody can subclass.
Basically the idea is any subclass of my ABC is a plugin that I can go and find and load.
Yay.
I have done this for something that I have written.
This program is much simpler.
We don't need all that overhead, so we're just going to skip that.
I could do like PyTest does and do specifically named functions.
They're really more hooks than plugins.
If thine has a function named this with this signature, then by golly, it looks like a
plugin and I will run it.
I don't like doing those.
I don't like them because, number one, there's no easy way to pass metadata.
There's no way for me to say this is only valid in these certain contexts and not in
others and there's no good easy way for it to manage scope.
You basically have to use the global or the module scope to do things and that's icky.
That's a scientific term, icky.
I just learned about entry points about three months ago.
Here's why I eschewed entry points.
It puts a lot of effort on the plugin developer.
It gives them a lot of power.
They get to say what is and isn't a plugin, but it also gives them the responsibility
of having to say what is and isn't a plugin.
The way that I'm going to do it is easy.
Any function that's got my decorator on it is a plugin.
Developer doesn't have to do anything else.
There's examples and stuff in the documentation.
There's way more documentation that I'm going to go through in here.
You're welcome to go back.
There's even a whole bonus section that I'm not going to go through today unless you all
just really want me to keep going.
I love decorators.
If you don't believe me, go see my talk from last year where I gave about four different
types of decorators and places that I use them.
I think decorators are amazing.
This is a really neat type of decorator that I call a tagging decorator.
It's like one of those little tags that they put on animals that they're tracking out in
the wild.
I'm going to tag a function with an attribute and then release it back into the module so
that I can find it later.
Here is the code for that decorator.
Because you all have made me zoom in, I'm going to have to scroll through it a little
bit.
I'm going to walk through what it's doing here.
First off, note this.
Remember it.
Sear it into your brain.
You want to look at it later.
I created a string constant for the attribute name.
This is so that I have that code in one place.
If I decide to change the attribute name, like I find out that this isn't working for
some reason, I only have to change it in one place and everything works.
This is good practice.
You should do this.
I also created my logger.
This is my decorator.
Notice my decorator collects more than one pattern.
It can take as many patterns as you want to give it for different types of files.
You're marking this plugin matches these types of files.
I don't want to get bogged down in explaining regex, but these are regex patterns.
It can take one or more.
Makes it easy to use.
What it's going to do is it's going to return a wrapper function.
What that wrapper function is going to do is take whatever function you put this decorator
on.
It's going to create an attribute that is a set of those patterns.
If there's already an attribute with a set of those patterns, it's just going to add
the patterns to it.
Cool, cool?
Anybody want to guess why I did that that way?
So if you want to stack more than one decorator on there, they'll just add on to it.
Makes it nice and easy.
Very portable.
Then we're just going to return the original function without doing anything else.
Most decorators return a function in the function's place that they're decorating.
This one doesn't.
But now modified, changed, if you will.
It didn't come out the same.
It has seen some stuff.
All right.
So we've explained how that works.
Now let's talk about how we're going to apply the decorator.
Fun part, I used the stones to destroy the stones.
I used the decorator to do the default case.
Everybody knows that regex.star is anything, right?
So this will match any type of file, even files that have no extension.
Yay!
And this is the default case.
I'm using a simple generator to return the full path, to return the file type.
And I had to handle the case where there is no extension, so I just return the word file
in its place.
And the size in bytes.
Cool, cool?
By the way, pathlib, use it in everything.
It is fantastic.
All right.
Now comes the fun part.
This is where I get to explain all the fun things that I learned.
All of this I learned through trial and error.
This gray hair and this gray hair and these gray hairs came from some of the things that
I learned here.
In order to find plugins, we got like a four-step process here, right?
We need to get a list of all of the accessible Python modules, right?
For each module that we find, we need to import that module so that we can get at all the
sweet, sweet objects inside, right?
Yeah?
If the module has sub-modules, then we probably want to go crawl all of those recursively
as well, right?
Because somebody may have stuck their plugins in a package, in a module that's inside the
package, so we want to be able to go and find all of those, right?
Right.
That means as the developer, you can put your plugins wherever you want in your code, and
we will find them.
We will Liam Neeson those things.
And fourth, we want to iterate through all of the objects in the module's namespace to
find the plugins.
We want to go through everything that's in there.
So enter my three amigos, my friends here.
This is the Steve Martin one, PackageUtil.
What it does is it provides functions and stuff for navigating the package structure.
There are two methods that we're going to talk about.
There's walk packages, and there's iter modules.
Walk packages, use with care.
Walk packages goes through every module in namespace, imports it, looking for sub-modules,
and returns each one along the way.
Here's the important lesson that I learned the hard way.
It imports them.
Hey, guess what?
What happens when you import anti-gravity?
Your browser pops up a window with an XKCD comic.
When you're looking for plugins, you don't want that to happen.
What happens when you import unit tests?
It tries to start running unit tests.
You don't want that to happen.
So you probably don't want to import every module that's out there.
Enter iter modules.
What iter modules does is just returns the names of the top-level modules without loading
anything.
The trade-off is you can't see what sub-modules are inside, because in order to see what sub-modules
are inside, you have to import the original package, right?
Everybody's with me so far?
It's all clear as mud.
So what we do is we use iter modules to skim along the top, and if what we get is a package,
then we can use walk modules to get all of the other ones down there, right?
Walk packages to go get all of the sub-modules underneath there.
That way we can do it with care, right?
And that way we can do it without importing any of the other things that aren't something
that starts with file info and ends with plugin.
There we go.
I have to keep you guys awake.
It's late in the afternoon.
Next thing we're going to talk about, this is the Chevy Chase of the modules.
This is import lib.
Import lib provides you a really simple function called import module that you give it a string
with the name of the module, and it returns to you the module object.
It loads it.
Everybody's familiar with that first box, right, where you do import os.path?
Everybody's done that before?
Right.
What if os.path is in a string?
Well, then you need import lib in order to pull it in.
It's really simple.
We just do import lib.import module.
We give it the module name as a string, bada-bing, bada-boom, we get a module object back.
Cool, cool?
Sweet.
All right, last.
This is the Martin Short of the group.
Inspect.
Inspect is Python's module for inspecting live objects.
This is a live fire drill.
You have been issued actual ammunition for this.
What it does is it provides a lot of different methods and functions for being able to find
specific types of objects from an object, a module, whatever is loaded at runtime.
It is able to introspect and reflect everything to go find something.
That was a lot of words to say it can look at things and find things for you.
In this particular case, I'm going to use some really useful functions that are in there.
I'm going to use get members to iterate through all of the members that are in the module,
all of the things that are defined at the module level, and I'm going to use its is
function predicate function to go find things that are functions, right?
Things that are defined with a def keyword in our functions.
Not things that are bound to classes or anything like that.
Straight functions.
Everybody's with me so far?
All right.
So, let's put all of this together.
First, we want to be able to identify a plugin function.
This is the simplest thing we need to do, right?
So, we want to create a little simple function that given any object tells you whether it
is a function that has our attribute on it, right?
So what we're going to do is we're going to create this little function, the is plugin
func.
Again, I'm not on the naming committee.
Okay.
I was the naming committee for this one.
That's going to take an object and it's going to return true or false.
True if it is what I'm looking for and false if this is not the droids that I'm looking
for.
They can go about its business.
I'm going to use inspect.is function, so it's got to be a function and it has to have my
attribute on it.
Cool, cool?
All right.
So, the first thing I'm going to do is I'm going to load plugin functions from module
given its name.
So, this is I'm given a module name as a string and I want to get a list of all of the functions
with their associated pattern.
Make sense?
I'm going to return a list of two element tuples.
That first element is going to be that regex pattern.
That second is going to be that function that can be called.
Cool?
I'm going to do that by importing the module and then I'm going to iterate through each
of the members in the module looking for the ones that pass my is plugin func test
and for each of the type patterns that's on that attribute, I'm going to go add to that
list of tuples.
Is anybody mystified by any of this code?
Good.
This is good easy magic.
All right.
Step three.
Now we need to go find all of the modules working backwards, right?
So, we can identify a function.
We can now find a function within a module.
Now we have to go find all the modules, right?
So, I created this function called find all functions.
What it's going to do is it's going to go through each module.
It's going to test if that module fits my naming scheme.
If it doesn't, it's just going to skip and go to the next one.
If it matches that naming scheme, it's going to check to see is this a package?
If it's a package, it's going to go walk and call itself recursively, right?
And if it's not, it's going to go look for all of the functions that are in that module.
If there's any exceptions importing anything, we're going to log those quietly to debug,
indicate that we're skipping it.
We're going to move on to the next thing.
Again, we want our host application to be bulletproof.
Pandy's going to try to crash it later.
He's going to find some way.
I'm not going to be happy about it, but it worked on my machine.
All right.
Everybody with me so far on all of this?
This is magic code.
All right.
So, now that we have all of our plug-ins, there's one other line I want to call your
attention to, and that's this line.
This is how we get our default case.
Our default case is in a module that does not begin with file info and end with plug-ins,
but we want to make sure it always gets loaded.
So again, I used the stones to destroy the stones.
I used my own function to find something in the current namespace.
Yay.
Okay.
So, this gives us all the nuts and bolts we need to load plug-ins.
Is anybody mystified by anything with loading plug-ins?
Because it gets really easy from here.
Let's go through implementing the plug-ins.
Hey, these are quick and easy and dumb.
I import my little decorator, I create a function, I decorate it with my decorator, and then
I do what I need to do inside the function.
Easy peasy?
Easy?
Cool.
Same with comma separated value ones.
This one was a little harder because I actually had to use the CSV reader.
Okay, it wasn't that much harder.
It was one extra line of code.
But easy peasy.
You get everything that you need.
For anybody who's interested, by the way, all of this code is actually in the files.
These things that you see here are excerpts.
MK docs is just excerpting the actual code out here.
This is all working code.
We're going to run it in just a minute.
All right.
So, now that we got our plug-ins, now we're ready for the main event.
We have to put together a command line interface to do all of this stuff.
We can load plug-ins.
Now we need to do things with plug-ins, right?
All right.
So, let's think about how the user is going to use this stuff.
I'm going to do a dunder main.py so that I can very easily do python-m file info.
Cool, cool?
If anybody's not come across dunder main.py, when you run python-m and you give it the
name of a module, so in this case, file info, it goes and finds the package file info.
It goes and looks for a dunder main.py, and if it's there, it goes and executes that module.
Cool?
So, we use that to do it.
I am going to just go ahead and create a command line processor, so this is a little simple
function for getting a command line.
It uses argparse.
I think argparse is fantastic because it's in the standard library, and once you read
through the documents and understand how to use it, it's pretty easy-peasy to use and
very powerful.
So, I'm going to create one with a simple, it's going to take an argument that's going
to be one or more paths, understanding that users are fickle things and may give us, they
may give us paths that coincide or inside each other, like they may give us a parent
and a child path, they may give us a path to a file or a path to a folder or a path
that doesn't exist.
They may give us a path to nowhere.
So, we need to be able to handle all of those scenarios.
If we run it with dash dash help, we get this.
This is our really simple command line interface, easy-peasy, right?
Cool.
Next thing we're going to do is we're going to use our find all functions to load all
of our plugins.
We already did all the heavy work there, so we just got to call that function.
It'll give us a nice list of two element tuples with all of our regex patterns and all of
our functions.
Cool, cool?
Next, we're going to turn paths into lists of file paths.
Remember when I said users are evil and would like to do evil things to you?
Let's handle all that evilness.
When they give us all of those paths, we're going to go through each of those paths, we're
going to go test and see if it's a file, and if it's a file, we're just going to add it
on there.
If it's not a file, then we're just going to assume that it's a folder and we're going
the recursive glob to go find everything that's a file inside of there.
If the path doesn't exist, it's fine.
Our glob will just give us back nothing.
This is a really simple way to get us a list of all of the files, and since users may give
us paths that are inside of each other or things like that, I'm going to go ahead and
just use a set to store all of those paths in so it nicely deduplicates everything for
me, and then I'm just going to sort all of that stuff so I get a nice deterministic order
every time.
And then for each file, there's a simple function that's going to process that file.
What it's going to do is for each file that it comes across, it's going to go load, it's
going to go pull all of the plug-ins and it's going to go through each one, testing does
this plug-in work for this file, if it does, it's going to go call it and add all of the
things that it outputs into the output.
And then we just do a little main block using all of those functions that we've defined,
and now I can go here, y'all get to see how much of a spaz I am when I type, all right,
I'm going to do Python dash M, file info dash dash help, so far so good, right?
I created a folder with some sample files that is assuming I can find said files, oh,
yeah, I have to remember, I'm not on Windows, and it doesn't like backslashes, but hey,
simple case, it worked.
Notice our text file has the number of lines and words, our CSV file has the number of
rows and columns, cool, right?
Does anybody want to see like behind the curtain?
Does anybody want to see more about how the sausage gets made?
Let's run it with dash V. Dash V gives us all of the logging output.
So I'll start from the top.
We're going to try to load up all of the plug-ins.
We're going to do this, and we're going to see that we're importing file info dot plug-ins.
We found a plug-in, so we're adding it.
We're going to skip file info because it doesn't end with, there we go, we're going
to import file info CSV plug-in because it does fit our name, and we're going to find
a function that matches CSV.
Pretty cool.
Go through all of this stuff.
You see all of these other ones that we're skipping?
They don't start with, and they don't end with, sweet, see, y'all are getting it.
That's all right, we're going to be singing around before long.
After we've done all of our plug-in loading, now we go through and actually process all
of our different files.
So we loaded our three plug-in, our handler functions, and then we start processing each
of the different files.
You can see here where we're calling each of the different plug-ins, and you can see
how it's working.
Cool?
All of this code is up in GitHub.
I encourage you to download it, play around with it, break it, remake it into something
else, address problems and stuff that I put in here.
I probably put a few in not on purpose, but maybe.
There is also an entire bonus section in here.
I put a bunch of references to everything I went and read, and I did go and read all
of this stuff in preparation for all of this.
And I even put in a bonus thing for how to write events in Python, because Python doesn't
have a native event type like C Sharp and Java and a bunch of other languages do, but
it's really easy to make one.
So I showed how to make one, and then I give you here some mods for some common problems
that you might have with this really, really simple implementation.
So feel free to take a look at those, and I'm around if you have questions.
There we go.
We do have questions, including, by the way, and I haven't paid close attention to this
But this might be the most upvoted question I have seen all day.
Maybe all weekend.
Are you ready?
I am in the question answering position.
Go.
Was that Comic Sans in your ID?
I love this.
So it is actually a font called Comic Sans, which is a version of Comic Sans.
Oh, Josh.
It would help if I could type.
But yeah, Comic Sans.
It is a nerd font.
I'm happy to share my prompt configuration for Oh My Posh if anybody wants to play around
with it.
Be sure to link that font on Discord, because I know everyone's going to want Comic Sans
in their VS Code.
Having Comic Sans as your IDE font is a lot like doing technical with this accent when
you start talking about decorators and iterators and people just deduct 50 IQ points, but it
works against it.
Oh my goodness.
Okay.
I don't know what to do with that.
The question, and I don't remember where you were in the talk when this came in, but is
this more or less how Flash Blueprints work?
I've never worked with that before, so I have no idea.
I have used Flash Blueprints before, but I don't think I ever looked at how they're implemented.
My original idea for the talk, so this came out of I wrote a scripting framework where
I work that has a plugin-based architecture.
I wrote this.
The reason why I wrote my own plugin architecture rather than using one of the existing libraries
like Pluggy or some of the others is, number one, I wanted full control over how plugins
and plugin loading worked, and number two, I didn't want extra third-party dependencies.
I work in an environment that is very, very security-conscious.
Every third-party dependency that we use is another third-party dependency I've got
to keep up with security information about, license information about, maintainer information.
Every time there's some pie chain attack, I've got to go check through all of my packages,
so I wanted to not have to deal with it for this particular case.
I might be aping what some other frameworks and stuff already have.
I did it so that I could have my own, and that's the reason why you might want to write
your own.
You may not want to introduce the extra third-party dependencies and have the extra load.
Related to that, are there any resources or best practices you recommend to help limit
plugin functionality for user safety?
Ooh.
I mean, since you control the system here, you can go as wild with that as you want.
There's a lot of things that I could have done and things that I have done in other
systems.
Plugin classes, since I can use the class hierarchy and all that stuff to find plugins,
but it's also nice because I can also use it to limit what plugins do.
If I define what methods are going to be called on events, then only those methods are going
to be called on events, and I define the signature that those expect.
I define all of that by my main class, and everybody that subclasses it has to follow
that if they're following good, solid principles.
If they're not, I make no guarantees that their plugin's going to work, and that's when
I log stuff, debug, and move on.
Last one.
Can you put flags for your plugins in the CLI with this architecture?
I think what they're asking is, how would you tweak that to support parameters coming
in from the CLI for the plugins to access?
I have done similar things before, like in our scripting framework.
I can control with which paths.
By default, I'm looking on Python path here, but I could just as easily add in command
arguments to say, these are the paths I want you to go search for plugins, and thereby
control where it's loading plugins from.
The other thing that I could do is add in something to say maybe dash dash exclude and
give a regex pattern, and anything that, any module name that matches this regex pattern
will just get skipped and moved on, and we don't load plugins from that.
Or a regex pattern for these plugin names, if you see them, just don't load them.
Just ignore them.
It's not hard to do, it's just more that has to be wired in, so more information that has
to be passed.
Again, if you live in mine and Pandy's world, unit test the snot out of that stuff to make
sure that it works correctly.
You'll actually probably want that type of functionality for unit testing to be able
to unit test your plugin specifically.
Awesome.
That helped.
All right.
Sweet.
I need a few things from you guys.
First and foremost, help me thank Josh for his presentation on plugins.