Soundarya, are you ready to take it away?
Yes, I am.
Rock on.
Let's go.
Thank you.
Hello, everyone.
I'm Soundarya Khanapur.
I'm currently pursuing a master's in computer science at NC State, and thank you.
And I previously worked as a software engineer at Mercedes-Benz Research and Development.
And today I'm going to talk with my friend Shivani on PySecOps.
So this is intentionally prepared for those who are beginners with Python or web applications
or you are just getting started with security.
And those who are experts, well, I mean, it doesn't hurt to have a quick recap, right?
Okay.
So yeah, let's get started.
So we'll go through a couple of contents.
So yes, coming to random values.
So well, it all depends on your seed.
So like when you use pseudo-random number generators, which can lead to predictable
numbers if the generator is known and the seeds can be guessed easily.
So a good starting point would be to use a seed which is like of 256-bit.
And coming to SQL injection, well, this is when you mess up with SQL, where you never
know what the user enters, right?
So a best way to prevent this is to have input validation.
And another approach would be to use prepared statements, which just abstracts the SQL syntax
from the input parameters.
Next coming to XSE processing, well, this arises from XML parser.
So usually web applications which use XML libraries are particularly vulnerable to this
kind of attack.
And based on the parser you use, you are supposed to disable the DIL field.
And one way to do this with Django is to just let the parser entity to false.
Well, next coming to command injection.
This again occurs when untrusted input is passed to the system commands.
So as you can see, this can be easily prevented by just user input validation.
So next coming to session fixation.
This lets the attackers to use the user session.
Well, as you can see, this happens when you do not flush the previous session and just
like assign the user with the new session.
So whenever you are dealing with this, just flush the session and generate a new token.
And when you generate a token, then again, how random can your token be?
So one way to do this to use Python's get random string method, which lets you generate
a good enough alphanumerical number.
Next coming to reflected accesses.
This lets the attackers to execute the malicious script in user's browser.
So here, this can be easily prevented by just removing the safe keyword.
And the same goes with the stored accesses.
And next coming to DOM accesses.
So here, this usually happens when you write inline script to get the user input.
This again can be prevented by adding input validation.
And next coming to directory traversal.
This can be exploited when the attacker kind of uses, kind of is used to have access to
the unintended directory structure.
So here, when you are using, you can just restrict the path which you want the users
to have permission to by making it mandatory to start from a starting point.
So the next part will be covered by Shivani.
So hello, everyone.
I'm audible.
So this is Shivani Shetty here.
And I used to work as a full stack developer back in India.
And I used to work as a, you know, I used to work mainly with the young products that
is KFC and Pizza Hut.
And some of the issues that I'll be talking about, I have seen them, hackers doing it
on the back end.
So some of them, I'll be talking about them, what actually happens over there.
Currently, I work as a cyber security consultant.
And so, you know, I come with a blend of software engineering as well as cyber security.
So the first thing that I'll be talking about will be, you know, leftover debug code.
As developers, when something breaks, the first thing we do is, you know, we start to
debug the code.
And sometimes we don't uncomment, you know, since we put the comments on our code and
we don't actually remove those comments.
And if the company is like new, and if the only person who is developing the whole code,
there won't be a CI CD pipeline to check all the things that have been happening.
So in order to avoid that, you know, I can give an example of, you know, here, if you
can see, there is a commented code which has debug is equal to one.
What that is doing is, it was given to the QA testing team so that, you know, the testing
process is fastened up.
And, you know, they don't have to add username and password.
They can directly log in.
But as a developer, you know, the developer forgot to uncomment that before putting it
into production.
So when a hacker visits this website, and when they go through the document, they notice
this debug code, which is the flag, if you enable the flag, then something will happen.
So in that case, you know, when we do that, we can directly get into the admin panel,
and we can play with different kind of, you know, we can use the data of users and also
misuse them.
So making sure that, you know, we always have code that is very, like, you know, safe on
the production side is something that we should always look into.
The next thing that, you know, one of the things that I noticed people doing when I
was working at KFC was people used to add, like, you know, let's say I can give an example.
Let's say we have redirections, log in redirections, and what people used to do is they used to
just enter email and password on the URL to check what happens, right?
So this can be avoided if you use post methods instead of using get methods.
So what is happening here is if you see what passing authentication credential URL exposes
a lot of various kind of risk, and if we are having get requests, get request response
added to our code, it will display, it will display on the logs, it will display the username
password of the user that they have put in the web application.
So it is very important to, you know, use post requests rather than get requests.
Another important aspect is, you know, a lot of people save their sessions, let's say a
lot of them store their username passwords on Google, you know, so that you don't have
to log in all the time.
There are chances that, you know, the sessions can be hacked, and a lot of your information
can be, you know, can be retrieved from just getting through your session.
So what actually happens here is if you see the URL here, there is something called as
a demo website, which we have just created, and on the function that we are running, we
are also using session ID, which when we use it on, let's say once we log in into a
particular website, it will generate a particular session ID for you, for a particular user.
So when that happens, and if someone, if you're using get again, yeah, if you're using get
again, what that would do is at the back end on the log, all these get commands are shown,
if someone gets access to the log, then they can access your session, and let's say you're
operating on a banking website, and earlier you'll be logged in, if they directly put
this link onto the URL, if the banking application doesn't have a security in place, like good
security in place, what that would do is it will directly log you in rather than asking
them to log back again.
So that way, you can, you know, hackers can steal money, and this is something that we
need to make sure we rectify it when using post again.
Post response is always helpful rather than using get.
Session user enumeration is when people want to find out things about yourself.
Let's say I'm working at Google right now, and when we do a simple, you know, let's say
LinkedIn search, how many Shivani's would you find?
Let's say you find out five Shivani's, and my surname is Shetty.
So you know, if I want to, someone wants to hack my email ID, what they would do is they
would just go with Shivani.Shetty or at Google.com, and if things at the back end are not configured
well, what that would do is, you know, it would tell us that this user ID exists, and
that would give a hint to the hacker that, you know, okay, we already have a user ID
with this name, let's try to crack it using brute force or any other method.
So it is very important not to, you know, have a specific username, specific error message
if you're trying to log in.
And we also have, you know, a factor, we also have a feature of forget passwords on many
of the websites.
So if we don't have an email on place, and if the person doesn't know an email of anyone,
and they just tried Shivani.Shetty at Google.com, they will know that, okay, this user is there
in the database now.
Instead of displaying, we have already sent the forget password link to this user, we
can generalize this link to something else, the error message can be generalized, and
a lot of things can be saved by that way.
And if you, you know, a lot of hacking takes place through this method, and a lot of our,
you know, information have been already on the dark web, and they are being sold.
So again, you know, here we are just putting up a message and how it can be implemented.
Vertical privileges escalation is when, let's say, I'm logging in as a user, but, you know,
I want to see what would happen if you can see the website URL on the top.
Now that I'm logged in, what if I replace that user with the admin?
If proper redirecting thing is not enabled, what would happen is it will directly put
me on the admin panel, and with that, I can change and make changes to anything that I
want.
Let's say I want to increase my salary.
I can do that, because I have the admin privileges now.
So all these little, little things play a very important factor when it comes to, you
know, while you're developing a website or, you know, applications.
And if you want to, you know, make sure that all of this is handled very well, make sure
there are steps that are already in place, like, you know, if this user is a super user,
do they have the admin access?
When you refresh it, it should not redirect you to something else.
Click-jacking is something that is very commonly used when you visit a website and you'll see
a lot of ads popping up, and, you know, you are tempted to click on the ad because it
shows you some kind of, let's say, some kind of deals, for example, you know, you have
some graphic card deals are going on and you're getting graphic cards for, like, 200 bucks
or some deals on clothes, Macy's is giving 60% off, and you're tempted to click on the
link.
But you never know what would happen when you click on the link, right?
So most of the time what happens is when you click on the link, it redirects you to something
that is created, a website that is created by the hacker.
That will be a mimic of what Macy's is or, you know, any other website is.
So what that is, why that is done is they want to get your username and password, and
through that, you know, a lot of information can be retrieved.
And on records, you know, until last month, I was going through a survey and found out
that around 80 to 90% of the cyber attacks that take place around the world are because
of phishing.
Phishing is nothing but when you click on the link and, you know, this clickjacking
is embedded as a phishing email, phishing, and when you click on that link, it will try
to retrieve all the information from you.
So we should make sure that, you know, we have everything in place, and here we are
explaining this with an example of another way of clickjacking would be, let's say we
are working in a trading industry, and there are two uses.
One of the best examples that I can always think of is Alice and Bob.
So Alice has some assets in the trading assets, and she wants to trade in a few things, but
Bob wants to make sure that he gets all the trade and, you know, he can make the most
out of it.
So what Bob does is Bob sends an email to Alice saying that, you know, if you can go
through this website, and that website will have this iframe ID, which will be hidden,
you know, because if you can see, the opacity is zero over here.
So what that means is the whole frame won't be visible to the user who is using the application.
It will be in the background, and it will be just hidden, and the things that, you know,
Alice don't want to do, she'll be doing it unknowingly, and, you know, by that, Bob will
make use of it and have the trade in information.
Another important thing is, you know, insecure URL, there is one thing whenever you are configuring
your, you know, buttons with any of the applications, make sure they are redirecting properly,
and if they're not going to any other links, other than that is not intended to.
And make sure you always use HTTP, yes, to be more secure and protected, rather than
using HTTP.
All the old devices, most of them have HTTP, and it is very insecure right now.
So making sure that, you know, all the things are updated, and that is why, you know, having
things updated, you know, we get updates from, let's say, on our iPhone.
Making sure we have it updated is very important because they release a lot of security, you
know, flaws that have been released, and all those fixes have been already been made, and
that is the reason you get a lot of updates.
So making sure that, you know, whenever you are configuring, you know, a button, and if
that button is taking you to some other URL, making sure that it is not taking you to an
URL that is not intended for you, we need to make sure that all of them are correct
and we can have a code to check if something is going wrong somewhere and the hacker has,
you know, changed something, there will be a check in the function that is being made.
Coming to the last topic that I will be discussing would be, you know, insecure TLS validation.
It is very important to have certifications with whatever applications you are using.
Most people, you know, ignore it, and now Python is coming with, you know, it has its
own build TLS validation certifications, but if it is available in open, you know, open
sourced, then even hacker knows about it.
So making sure that, you know, you invest something in certification is also important.
So rather than using a free certification that is available on with the Python package,
it's better to use a certificate that, you know, is valid, and if the certification expires,
making sure that, you know, the certifications are up to date is very important.
So if you can see on the first picture on the top, it says, you know, the certification
is not valid anymore, and making sure that we have a valid certification is very important.
And generally the code that is associated with certifications is given below, and if
you can see the import request on the second line, that is verify is equal to false.
On that particular website, I won't have any certification requests, and, you know, that
is a major security flaw.
So I would like to end by saying that, you know, as a developer, always make sure whenever
developing something, you also test it out yourself before giving it to the testing team.
So yeah.
Thank you.
Excellent.
Well, here, I'll get you both back up here.
We've got a number of questions.
Got some great questions up here, so I'll get both of you back up on stage, and I'll
let you all decide who takes what.
There's only one question that was directed at a person.
So do you recommend any code analysis tools to determine if these exist in code?
So some of the vulnerabilities that you've talked about here, are there any particular
analysis tools that you recommend?
Yeah.
So there's a website called OWAPS, top 10.
You can go there, and when you are developing something, you can see the top 10 vulnerabilities
that are available, and there are software like SNOT that can be used to analyze things.
Excellent.
And to add that, you can always make sure, like, all your employees know how, like, know
the security measures with respect to web applications, like, just how you can prevent
them, like, basic, like, input validation, or, like, using, if, just in case, if Python,
with Python, if you're using external libraries, then Python is not responsible for something
that external library does.
So make sure the external libraries you do, and what all external libraries you install,
make sure, like, those don't cause issues.
Okay.
Excellent.
This was directed at you, Shivani.
What's your opinion on using password tools like OnePassword?
OnePassword has reached recently, so, you know, nothing is safe.
I would say making sure that you remember things is the best way forward, I feel, because
you can't trust any software, there will be data breach happening one or the other way.
I've always been a big fan of saying, you know, all security is a compromise on the
user experience.
The easier something is to use, the more insecure it tends to be, the more secure something
is, the harder it is to use.
The shorthand is you can secure a house by filling it floor to ceiling with concrete.
It won't be very useful, but everything in there will be really safe.
But the corollary that is, anybody sufficiently motivated will get a jackhammer and get at
that stuff.
Are there any categories of security vulnerabilities that Python is particularly susceptible to?
Like, for instance, C and C++ are kind of prone to risks for, like, memory leaks.
So when you're using Python with external libraries like XML and that is written in
C, then the strings you pass in, as C won't do the reallocating of the memory, so that
would lead to a vulnerability.
Are there any other particular types of vulnerabilities you think Python is particularly risky to?
I would say, you know, there are vulnerabilities, you know, there is one famous vulnerability
called log force G, in which the Python, you know, again, third-party imports that we use,
that has to be secure enough, and if that is secure enough, then, yeah, we are good
to go.
Agreed.
On third-party dependencies, by the way, safety has been a good library for checking for vulnerabilities.
Have you submitted this talk to DjangoCon US, which will be in Durham, North Carolina
from September 22nd to the 27th?
No.
I think somebody thinks you should.
How does it, oh, go ahead.
Thank you for the information.
How does an attacker access get request URLs?
Yeah, so, generally, what happens is, it happens at the back end.
If you go to the log engine and check out what are the logs that you're getting, you'll
have get requests, and which will expose your username and password if you're using get
requests.
Okay.
I'll do one more question, and I'm going to skip down to the bottom one here.
How can developers mitigate click-jacking in their website?
You talked about that as a vulnerability.
How can developers defend against that?
So like click-jacking that you talked about, how will developers defend against that?
So with click-jacking, we can disable iframe, which will, you know, which won't allow iframe
to run on the background, or, you know, so we can deny that.
So there are ways you can prevent all of them.
You just need to, you know, do a research about it, and you'll be at what you want
to achieve.
Excellent.
Okay.
Well, another round of applause.