Hello. Hello, everybody. Today we're going to be resting easy with JupyRest. I tried
to find, so I know a lot of cool open source projects have like a mascot or a logo, so
I used some AI to come up with what a logo would be, so that's, I'm calling him Jupy
and he's asleep, so he's resting. All right, and who here has used a Jupyter notebook
before? Yeah, okay, great. We love notebooks. So a bit about me. I am an engineer at Microsoft.
I work on the Azure Cosmos DB database. It's a distributed NoSQL database and it's a lot
of C++. So on the side, nights and weekends, I call myself a code artisan where I explore
in more fun things like Python and that's what I'm here to talk to you about. There's
no databases today. So before I get into what this whole thing is, I want to talk about
this concept of serverless. So if you don't know, serverless is this new way of deploying
your code and making it available to everyone. You have products like Azure Functions, AWS
Lambda, et cetera, and what it is really is nowadays, if you just want to deploy your
code as a web service, you can take your main.py, your Flask app, Fast API and literally upload
it somewhere and someone will take that and make it a web service all over the world and
you don't have to worry about how much memory your server needs or what the CPU is, none
of that stuff. It's so-called serverless. And it's been a pretty popular paradigm for
deploying web applications. These people, they handle the scaling, authentication, monitoring
and a whole lot of other really annoying things. So the problem is that I like to write code
in Jupyter notebooks, especially Python code. To me, it's the superior development experience.
I mean, it's the only place where you can actually interleave code with documentation
and have interactive widgets, tables, charts. It's just as approachable for a beginner as
it is to an experienced developer. So it really is a wonderful way to write code, share code
and visualize what you're doing. I think it's amazing. But there's no way to take a notebook
and really productionize it. I mean, once you've written a notebook, it kind of stays
in that prototype, you know, POC kind of mode. If you really wanted to turn it into a product
or turn it into a website, you'd have to rewrite it, you'd have to strip away all the goodness
that is the notebook. So that's where I came up with this thing called Jupy rest. It's
a tool to turn your Jupyter notebooks into rest APIs, hence the rest. So I like to call
these Jupyter notebooks as notebook functions. What the library will do is it will let you
define some inputs and outputs for your Jupyter notebooks. This library I developed working
at Microsoft starting around early 2020, and now it's used extensively by pretty much all
of Azure for various different things. And I've built it in a way that you can deploy
it as your fast API or Azure functions or really however you want, even just running
it on your own laptop works as well. So there's no like lock-in or any proprietary stuff.
About a year and a half ago, I got the approval to open source this under MIT license, so
now anyone can use it, which is why I'm able to talk to you about it today. So what is
a notebook function? So a notebook function is basically like any other function. It's
got an ID, an input schema, and an output schema, just like any, you know, web endpoint.
So I'm going to show you how you take a very basic notebook here and turn it into a notebook
function. So I've got a Hello World notebook. It doesn't do very much. You have your name
world here, which is basically like your input, and then you have an output here. And you
can see here in that last code cell, we're importing the save output function from JupyRest.
And whatever you put into that save output function becomes your notebook's output, or
it's like return type. Imagine you're writing a normal function. So now that we have our
input and output marked in our notebook, the next thing we need to do is to define the
input and output schemas. So in order to do that, you need to go write this config.json
file alongside your notebook. Basically, it just needs to have the same name. That's how
the library knows what it is. The first part of this file is the ID, the name of your notebook
function. The next part is the input schema. If anyone's used Swagger or OpenAPI, this
should be familiar to you. It's the JSON schema here. So it's basically saying this function
takes an object where the name is a string, and it's required. And same thing for the
output. We also have a JSON schema spec here. So you include all these things, and now you've
successfully turned your notebook into a notebook function. So in order to start the JupyRest
server, I've added a little code snippet here. But rather than go and explain all this stuff,
let's go do some demos. Okay. So I have this notebook here, because of course I'll do a
demo in a notebook. All of this is on the GitHub page, by the way, the full example
project. So I'm just literally taking and running this as is. This piece of code here
is just some helper functions for this presentation. But essentially what we're doing is we're
instantiating our JupyRest client. That Hello World notebook I was showing before is right
here. And so we're just going to demo how we can invoke our notebook function.
So this client, it lets us get a list of all of our available notebook functions. It
also lets us get the details about any notebook function, like right here we've got the Hello
World notebook and the input and output schema. Now let's try and execute this notebook here.
So what I'm doing intentionally is providing a set of parameters that is invalid. Remember
we needed a name, and here I'm passing a foo. So as you'd expect, we're getting an
error here. And let's fix this. What's that? Okay. Now let's actually execute this notebook
with the proper schema. And so what this is doing, the library, it's taking our notebook,
it's adding our input parameters to the notebook, and then it's running the notebook from top
to bottom. And when that happens, we're going to get our output here. Hopefully this runs
a little bit faster. I think it's running. This is the fun part about demos. Let me,
oh, I think it finished actually. Okay. Okay. Okay. Anyways, it finished. So here we can
see we've got our JSON here of our completed execution. And I have this little helper thing
here for us to visualize. The first thing we get when we execute any notebook is that
JSON that I just showed you, pretty standard. The next thing we get is the full HTML output
of the notebook. So you can see here, I've, the parameters that I passed into that execute
notebook function, they've been added as a code cell into my notebook and then run from
top to bottom. So now my inputs have now shown up, you know, my notebook's running with the
inputs that I configured. The next thing we get that I'll show you here is the output.
And so what this is, is this is actually whatever we pass into that save output command, we
get that back as JSON. So I pass in, you know, hello, PyTexas in the save output command.
And so now I'm able to get that as a JSON output. So I've effectively converted my
Jupyter notebook into a REST API. So it's got the JSON in, JSON out. But in addition,
I also get the full notebook HTML as well. It's an extra benefit of the notebook. So
any charts, graphs, even documentation I can put in here, I get that as well. So you get
both the input output as well as the notebook itself. So these are some of the, you know,
artifacts I just mentioned. The other two here. So this is the HTML report, which is
just the same thing as the HTML, but it has all the code cells removed. So this you could,
it's kind of like a report if you don't, if someone doesn't know, doesn't need to look
at the code. So the output here, I already showed you, but you can basically get that
output JSON from your notebook. So now the next notebook I'm going to execute here is
a notebook that I've purposely put in an error. So as we know, when you deploy or write any
code, you're going to have exceptions. So I have a notebook here that is going to fail.
We see that it's failed. Now, normally when you debug a web service and there's some error
happens on the server, you have to go scroll through your logs, look up some telemetry,
try to find out what happened and then try to reproduce it on your laptop and then make
a fix. With this, it's way easier. So now I've executed this notebook and it's failed.
First thing, I get the HTML. So I don't need to go look at any telemetry. I can just look
at what happened in the notebook. Secondly, I get the actual IPI and B. So this is your
notebook JSON file. If I want to reproduce this error, I can download this file, open
it up in JupyterLab and try writing it on my computer. I don't need to do anything more
than that. It's very easy to reproduce. So even that, even just by using the notebook
as the function unit, we get all the benefits of the notebook. Debugging in a notebook is
way easier than debugging using Datadog or some log system, looking for all the red text
and try to figure out what the heck happened. So with this ease of use and ease of debugging
and ease of authoring has made this library very popular within Microsoft. We've enabled
lots of data scientists and people who normally don't know how to write production code. We've
enabled them to now share their logic as notebooks to the rest of the company, which has been
great and it's really made the notebook so much more powerful. So what happens is when
you have, let's say, hundreds of notebooks that you've deployed, what you end up wanting
is to put some structure to your API. So what I'm going to go over here is a little bit
advanced, but when you see how cool it is, I think you'll appreciate just how awesome
this feature is. So we have this ability to share input and output models across your
notebooks. So what I've done for this example, I've taken a notebook straight out of a GitHub
repository here. It does some portfolio analysis, and I want this notebook not to take in just
JSON, but I actually want it to take in a Python object as input. So I've defined a
Python object here called portfolio. It has a start date, end date, and some holdings.
And in my portfolio analysis.config.json, what I'm going to do is I'm actually going to reference
this portfolio object here. So basically what this is is I've given it a name here in the
application builder, and in my portfolio analysis.config.json, I'm referencing the name of that model.
So what does that mean? So when I get this notebook schema, you can see here the input
schema is actually getting resolved to a still standard JSON schema. So it's your definitions,
and the portfolio object here is this is all very standard JSON schema. So from the client,
it has no idea that this input is a Python object. So now let's go and execute this. So I'm
executing this notebook. I'm passing in straight JSON, and I'm going to pass in a JSON, and
I'm passing in straight JSON, and this JSON is adhering to the schema of my Python object.
And what will happen is, you know, we're going to be parameterizing this notebook with the
Python object that I just provided here. So let's take a look. When I open this up, you
can see this is the, these are the input parameters I just passed into the notebook, but they've
actually been converted into Python code. So this notebook does not need to know it's
actually being used as a web API. All it knows is Python. So it's Python in, Python out.
But from the client side, the client is sending JSON. This is not a Python, this is just JSON.
So what Jupyter.js is doing is it's smart enough to say, okay, you're passing in this
portfolio object. I'm going to convert it into this Python object that you want me to,
and then in your notebook, I'll make it so that when you run it, you're just, you're
getting your Python object as is. There's no JSON serialization or any kind of, any
of that stuff. Which is great. So this notebook, it's a little bit more involved. It has a
bunch of stock stuff here. Honestly, I don't actually know what any of this means, but
there's some nice graphs. And you see here, I've, I'm also saving some output. So just
like the other notebooks, I'm able to get a JSON output as well. So if all you want
is to just look at some condensed information from a, from your notebook function, you get
that. But if you want to see the details of, you know, how the sausage was made, you can
actually go and see exactly how the notebook arrived to that final result. So it gives
you a superior introspection to your web APIs. It also lets you write your web APIs in a
much more Pythonic way. I'm just dealing with Python objects here. And it lets you hold
on to all the amazingness of the Jupyter notebook while still being able to deploy
your code as a web API. So that's pretty much all I had for the demo here. I will say, just
for context, this, while this is a very popular library, it definitely has, it is good for
certain things and not good for certain things. So you definitely wouldn't want to use this
for any performance critical service. Like if you really need like 10 millisecond response
times, this is not the thing to use. But if you're, if you're trying to build something
and share some analysis or share some notebook with other people where you're, you're okay
waiting maybe like 10 to 20 seconds for each of these notebooks to execute, it could be
a great way to take any of your work and share it with other people. So it's a great tool
for prototyping. It's a great tool for automated reporting. And it's, I think it just makes,
it makes writing in Jupyter notebooks even that more powerful. So that's all I had for
you today. Feel free to check us out on GitHub. Give us a star and, you know, find me on LinkedIn
if you want to hit me up after that. That's, that's I guess the social media I use. So
thanks, everyone.
Awesome. Thank you. We have a bunch of questions. People are excited. This is good. So let's
run through some of these. The first question opens. Very cool. Thanks. Which is not the
question but had to pass that along. Okay. Now the actual question. How's the tooling
around diffs for code reviews of notebooks? Also, how do you test notebooks?
Great question. So let me show you. In our GitHub, so diffing notebooks is always, that's
always a pain, right? Because they're just JSON. So in the example project that I have
here, I've actually included this pre-commit hook. And what this pre-commit hook does is
that any time you commit a notebook, it commits the, it generates a Python file, you know,
of your notebook. So all the Python code is also alongside your notebook. So any time
you're doing a code review, you'll of course get the diffs for your IPY and V. But really
the more readable diffs will be for this Python file here. So that's how I've gotten around
that problem. I know there are other tools for that. But just for myself and, you know,
at Microsoft, this is how we solve that problem. The other thing is testing notebooks. So that's
a good question. I know, you know, you could do two ways. One way is you could still use
PyTest, you know, any individual modules or libraries you use in your notebook. Of course
you can test those with unit tests in PyTest. The other way is actually in the JupyRest
source, I do have a way to do integration tests. So in our, this CONF test here, I have
a thing that just starts up the local HTTP server and then I can use that same client
to execute the notebooks and test them.
All right. Sorry. So the next question. How, see, Josh keeps moving them on me right as
I go to answer them. How does JupyRest deal with interactive components like a plotly
graph or Jupyter widgets?
Yeah, that's a good question. So for plotly graphs, you'll have to make sure doing, you
know, as long as all the data is saved in the notebook, then the interactivity can work.
The problem is that, you know, this HTML file that you get, of course there's no running
Jupyter kernel in the back. So if you're going to click something and it's expecting to call
some Python function in the kernel, that won't work. So if it's something that's static or
something, like I know plotly charts, you can, as long as all the data is in the notebook,
then you can filter it and zoom in and out. So you are limited to that. But yeah, that
would be how that would work.
Okay. I like, oh, there it went. I like this one. What original problem were you working
on when this idea came to you?
Yeah, good question. So the problem I was working on, so I'm a site reliability engineer
and as a SRE, we have a lot of these runbooks that we have to follow whenever a certain
incident comes about. And you go anywhere and most companies will have a set of these
runbooks, usually are markdown documents or whatever, word documents, something like that.
And you just have to follow these step by step to resolve an incident. The issue I found
was that a lot of times I'm going there and copying, pasting code snippets, changing a
few things about the timestamps and then running them. So I thought, okay, why don't we just
make this into a Jupyter Notebook? And then I thought even more like, okay, if I have
to, if I'm already going to be writing this as an executable Jupyter Notebook, let me
slap some parameters on there. And then basically what I did is I built this and then I hooked
it up to our internal incident system. So any time an incident was raised, one of these
Jupyter Notebooks would be executed with the parameters of the incident. So then if
I was on call, by the time I get out of bed and go to my laptop, a bunch of these runbooks
are already executed for me. So I don't need to go do any of that. So I can just open them
up and see like, oh, this is the problem or maybe a graph of some CPU history or whatever.
It'll just tell me what I need to do. And it makes it so much easier for onboarding
because now I don't need to, I can now test my runbooks. I can now make sure that they
work in like our staging environment, our dev environment. So that was the original
problem. But then it, you know, a lot of other people started using it for various other
things. But that was the original intent behind this.
Okay. That is cool. I do have a few more questions. I'm going to unplug while they're setting
up. But I do have more questions for you while they're setting up because we're getting some
really good questions in. Thank you all. You're being creative. I don't know if it's like
the after lunch, the sugar, but y'all are helping. This is awesome. Since you open source
this, are there any uses that have surprised or delighted you?
I don't, I think the, I mean, there's a lot of people who are using it to automate whatever
like AI stuff that they want to do. So of course, you know, notebooks, you can, because
they're in Python, you can, you know, every AI library is in Python. So it's like a really
simple way of turning an AI notebook into like an AI web app. So that was something.
Of course, you would need to run this on a platform that had GPUs and such. So it's much
more resource intensive. But I thought that was an interesting, I mean, especially recently,
that was an interesting, you know, four years ago, no one was really doing that, but now
they are. Awesome. Last one for you.
It looks like a lot of extra artifacts are created per request compared to what you would
often see from like IPINB or with the IPINB file and all of that. Do you have any concerns
about that at scale? You know, like I said, you can't, at scale,
I haven't really seen any problems. Like all these artifacts are being stored in, you know,
Azure Blob storage or S3. So those are pretty cheap. And, you know, those are pretty, you
can store a lot of data in those systems without any problem. The only thing is just
make sure, keep in mind that running a notebook, there is some latency there. So as long as
you're okay waiting, you know, up to a minute for your notebook to execute, then, you know,
you should be okay. Awesome. Thank you so much, Kaushik, everyone.
Thank you.