Yes, thank you.
Legacy code's everything before you, right?
Yes, everything I wrote two seconds ago, basically.
And I do mean that, actually.
I think that's one of the big misconceptions about legacy
code is that everyone thinks it has to be something that
was written six months ago.
But that's not always the case.
It could be something you wrote a minute ago, a week ago,
something like that.
OK, great.
Yeah, so I'm going to be talking about that.
So a little bit about me.
I'm Joe Cabrera.
I'm lead software engineer at an AI startup based out
of New York called ASAP.
I've been a Python programmer since 2009.
And I've been working on various legacy code bases
for the last five years.
So the goal of this talk is really
to give you the tools to succeed when dealing with legacy code.
And I'm really going to tailor this talk specifically
towards those of you in the audience
that this might be your first time dealing with legacy code.
Again, it's probably something eventually you'll
deal with in your career and definitely
a ride worth taking.
So let's start off with a little definition.
What exactly is legacy code?
Because a lot of you probably want to know what that is.
Really, there's a lot of definitions
floating around on the web.
So let's start talking about what some of those definitions
could be.
It could be code without documentation.
So here's an example of some random class.
And we know that it has a build tree function and a query.
But we don't exactly know what it does.
We know it's called segment tree.
That's not really helpful.
Legacy code could also be code without test.
So you probably see this a lot.
If you've jumped into some legacy code,
and there's no test, and you don't know what it does,
that's kind of scary, right?
Also, it could also be code that has poorly written test.
So it's pretty hard to update the code.
This is a terrible example of some tests
that we wrote for this function to add numbers.
And we're asserting a couple different things in here,
have a couple different sub-functions we're calling.
This really isn't a great example of a test.
So this is going to be hard to modify in the future
as we make changes to the code.
Legacy code could also be code you're not familiar with.
And often, legacy code is not your idea.
Maybe you joined a new team, or you
joined a new part of the company,
and they just threw you on a project and said,
here's the code base.
Good luck.
And you don't know what you're doing.
Really, the best definition of legacy code
is it's valuable code, which you're not comfortable changing.
That's pretty scary.
So we want to improve our code.
However, we don't understand it.
We don't want to break existing functionality.
And really, we don't want to make things worse.
So our plan.
Basically, first, we're going to start
with understanding the code we want to improve.
And then we want to check that our understanding of the code
matches what is expected.
So we expect this code to perform in some way.
And we want to actually verify that what we expect it to do
matches reality.
We're going to add some tests.
We're going to make our changes.
And then the most important step is
let's communicate those changes effectively
to others on our team.
Great.
So starting off with that first step, what can we do?
We can increase code documentation.
It's going to be really helpful to fellow developers.
So some things we can do add some class doc strings, maybe.
So to this indexer class, we added a small comment
saying what this class does.
It's a class that adds new documents to our index.
We put some information about attributes.
In this case, there's an attribute name
that's a string that contains the name of the index.
And then there's another attribute,
which is .count takes an int.
And this is the number of documents in index.
And maybe there's a method on this, say, for example,
index that takes index directory configuration.
And this just creates a new index.
So with this information, now someone
knows exactly what this class does.
This is very helpful.
Another thing we can do is add function doc strings.
So we can take each function, break it down,
and say exactly what happens there.
In this case, there's a function index.
And this creates a new index for documents
starting at a given directory.
It takes a couple of parameters.
And it returns an object of the newly created index.
So now the person looking at this code
knows exactly what this function does.
We can add documentation to explain logic
when it's not obvious.
And by this, I mean you don't have
to add documentation to every single line of code.
In fact, that would probably take a very long time.
You probably just want to explain
sections of the code that aren't extremely, again,
obvious at first glance to the person looking at it.
So that first example from before at the beginning,
I added a few doc comments in here
to explain what it's doing.
And now the person reading this code
could more easily understand exactly what
this function should be doing.
Also, we want to explain mysterious variables.
Because obviously, usually, you're
going to run across variables.
I mean, this is a very contrived example.
What does x do?
It's equal to a plus b times p.
It's probably usually not that bad.
But you get the idea is that you do want to explain.
And I know this is one of the big programming.
One of the hard things in programming
is how to name variables correctly, that in caching.
So the idea is you want to try to have some variable names that
are pretty self-explanatory.
Great.
So now we're going to get to adding some tests.
So when we're adding tests to legacy code,
what we want to really start with doing
is identifying seams in the code.
And a seam is really just a place
where you can alter behavior in your program
without changing the code.
This could be calling an external library.
This could be calling an external API,
a database in this example.
So in this example, we have this class, production class.
This is just an example.
And there's a function database connector.
It takes a database object, and we're calling this connect
function on it.
So we can easily just write a test around this section
of code, because we can mock out that database object.
And we can just do this very simply by creating a mock.
If you were here for one of the previous tutorials,
they did some more explanatory stuff
on how to do unit testing and mocking in Python.
So you can just create this mock.
And in this case, we're just asserting that the connect
function was called.
So there's other examples of different seams
that we can use in various different programming languages.
We probably won't go into all of them in this talk,
because some of them would deal with parts of other languages
that wouldn't be a thing in Python.
For example, pre-processing, linking,
these are something you might see in another language
like C++.
But mostly in languages like Python
and other object-oriented languages,
you're going to have object seams.
Here's another example of a seam.
And this goes back to that first point that I was talking about.
In this case, we have this shipping services functionality.
Maybe it's an external API that we talk to.
And we want to mock that out.
And so in this example, we created a mock object
for that shipping service.
We're calculating the price.
And we're going to set what the return value should be for that.
And then we're going to assert what we expect that to return.
So a few trade-offs to consider when using seams.
Again, the pros to this, we're breaking this code
into really smaller sections that are easier to test.
And this just helps us get enough test in place,
really, to support more aggressive changes.
Because we want to make all these additional changes.
But we need to just have some initial layer of code
initial layer of tests in there.
So we trust the section we're modifying.
Some of the cons to using seams.
These tests could be hard to maintain by others in the future.
And sometimes you can create too many seams in your code.
So it becomes very fragmented.
And so this is something you're going to have to think about
when you're dealing with large chunks of legacy code.
And sometimes you just maybe need to refactor
and kind of like do it from scratch a little bit.
Obviously, that's not something you want to do.
But when you're using the seams model,
this is something that could happen.
So with legacy code, it's hard to understand in many cases.
And to understand it more easily,
we can use a characterization test.
These are also called golden master test.
With this type of test, basically what you're doing
is just writing a test that exercises
the code you want to test.
And you're comparing the output to the golden master output.
In this example, that function add numbers.
We're writing a test for it.
And we're adding two numbers together.
And we expect five and five when added together to return 10.
And so we're really just checking the output of that.
Something we know it's going to produce.
And we put that in our test.
So great, unit test.
However, many times you get the answer from someone else,
maybe on your team, or for someone else
higher up in management that says,
we just don't have time to write all these tests.
Not the answer you want to hear, but it does happen sometimes.
So I have a couple of examples of things
you can do when that is the case.
You can use two different models, the sprout and the wrap.
So for the sprout, we're going to start
by creating the code elsewhere.
And then we're going to unit test just that section
of the code.
And then identify where you should
call the new code from the existing code.
And then call that new code from the legacy code.
So here's an example of this diaries update class.
And we have this new functionality
we want to add to dedupe these entries.
And so we can write a unit test just around that one function.
And then we're basically just going
to call that function from our existing function,
in this case, add entries.
And this is great because we've just isolated
that one functionality of the code,
and we don't have to worry about the rest of the code.
So we definitely trust that new functionality we added.
In the wrap case, we're basically
just going to rename the old function that we'll be wrapping.
And then we're going to create a new function
with the same name and signature as the old function.
So a similar example of add entries.
We're going to create this new function, add deduped entries.
And then we're just going to call that
from our existing function, and add the new functionality,
and add unit tests around that.
Great, so once you made all your changes,
you can share those with the other on your team, everyone
team, and everyone wins.
And that's it.
All right, let's see if we have any questions.
Yes, we do.
Excellent.
Sorry, I was waiting for it to refresh.
So let's start with, do you have any advice
for how we can convince management
to allocate time and resources for managing legacy code
for technical debt?
Wow, if I knew the answer to that,
I probably should get paid a lot more money.
No, seriously though, I think you really
should make a really good pitch to management.
And it's hard to say, hey, we need time
to add these tests for the legacy code.
But the easiest way, I think, to paint it to them,
because I've done this myself, is say, look,
how many incidents do you want this year?
And guarantee their answer is going to be like none.
And so, hey, if you don't want those incidents,
we're going to have to add some tests so we trust the code.
Yeah, it's one of those things you either pay upfront
when it's easier or pay later when it's an emergency.
Do you have a resource you recommend
for writing good doc strings?
The Python docs are great for looking at that.
That's my biggest hint for that.
One other thing I will say, if you
want to know more about legacy code,
there is a really great book on this,
specifically about legacy code.
I don't have a link to this, but I'll
drop it in the Discord channel.
The next question I think might touch on this.
Working Effectively with Legacy Code by Michael Feathers
is one book on the topic.
Do you know any other books or resources you'd want to recommend?
Yeah, there's another book that I could recommend, too.
I'll drop that in there.
OK, awesome.
How do you suggest testing legacy code, which
is heavily reliant on database records in production?
Yeah, mocking stuff that's dealing with production data
is always really tricky.
I think you want to try to get it as close as you can
to what would be in production without having to actually use
production data.
It's hard.
Yeah.
Do you think that even extremely well-documented code
can become legacy code?
Definitely.
And by this, I mean that even if it's really well-documented,
sometimes those document notes that are added aren't the best.
And so maybe it might even be another step
of going in there and making that documentation
or those comments better, if possible.
OK.
Do you have any tools to recommend
or that you like that would auto-generate basic doc
string from a template for all the methods and classes, which
you can then go in and update and fill out?
Yeah, I think there's some really great tools
for doing that.
Can't think of them off the top of my head.
Yeah, I was trying to pull.
I know I've used one before, and I can't.
But yeah, I feel like there's one I've used before.
If I think of it, I'll drop in the chat.
I know they exist.
That's a start.
Yeah, they definitely exist.
When writing unit tests, is it better to mock the database
or actually create records to test your queries?
I always prefer to create the records using the mock
and then test it that way.
Just using an ephemeral database?
I've done it with an ephemeral database before,
but there's libraries you can use
that will create records in this temporal database,
and then you can query against that.
Yeah, OK.
Thoughts on type annotations for documenting legacy code?
I think type annotations are always great
for dealing with legacy code.
I know that's a more recent thing to Python.
So if you see some legacy code, definitely add that.
Awesome.
All right, that is all our questions.
Thanks, Joe Cabrera.
Appreciate it.