All right, Lauren.
Teachers about system design on easy mode.
Hi, folks.
I'm Lauren.
I came here from Brooklyn, where we
don't have scooters everywhere.
It's so nice in Austin that anywhere I go,
I can take a scooter and go around.
And it's such a nice, easy way to move my body around.
So thank you, Austin, for having scooters, allowing them
on your streets.
Thank you to Mason and the PyTaxis team for having me.
Thank you all for your attention.
I'm happy to be here to share about something called
durable execution and how it substantially simplifies
a wide range of system design problems.
So I'm Lauren.
I'm a consultant and open source maintainer.
Previously, I worked on Temporal's JavaScript runtime
and wrote a book on GraphQL with John Resig
called The GraphQL Guide.
Today, I'll start out by defining what durable execution is,
talk about some new possibilities
for how you can code that it opens up,
talk a little bit about how it works,
and then go through some system design patterns.
And I won't assume knowledge of any of them,
so I'll try to give a concise summary of what it is
before I talk about how durable execution either obviates it,
makes it unnecessary, or makes it easy to do.
So what the heck is this thing called durable execution?
So an important property of normal execution
is that functions fail to complete executing
in a number of different situations.
For instance, the process crashes, maybe it
divided by 0 or unhandled exception.
Maybe the process is killed by the OS or the pod
is killed by the Kubernetes node because it used
too much CPU or RAM.
The machine could lose power.
I might deploy new code, and usually I
have a graceful shutdown period for the old code
to finish running before I switch over to the new.
But maybe I'm doing something that takes a long time,
and I'm still running by the time
I get the SIG kill at the end of the shutdown window.
So then there's lots of transient failures
that could happen, seeing downstream dependencies,
maybe the database I'm talking to.
It can't reach the moment, or some downstream service,
or a third-party API.
And maybe I need to retry that.
And if I take a long time retrying,
then maybe I'll get cut off when I get a new code deploy.
So it's more likely, the longer I take,
that I won't be able to finish.
And then, or if I don't handle the failure,
then I might have a crashed process.
So in durable execution, functions are guaranteed
to complete executing.
So if I have this process order function with three steps
reserved from the inventory service
and then charge some payment and then send a package,
if the first two steps run successfully
and then the process running this function dies,
I'm guaranteed this function will
continue running on line four in a different process.
So I'm guaranteed that no matter what
happens to the process running this,
it will continue running and complete.
And then when it continues running on the new process,
all of the state, like what's happened previously
and local variables, call stack threads,
everything is intact.
Also in durable execution, transient failures
are automatically retried.
So let's say in the charge step, I'm
trying to talk to the Stripe API and it's temporarily down.
Then it'll automatically be timed out and retried.
By default, exponential will back off forever.
And then whenever that completes, that charge step,
maybe it took minutes or days.
Whenever that completes, you'll reliably
run the next line four and send the package.
So durable execution is coding at a higher level
of abstraction.
Sort of like in high-leveling language like Python,
you don't have to worry about memory management
like you do in a level language like C. Durable code
is a higher level abstraction than normal code.
You don't have to be concerned about the infrastructure
that the code is running on or the availability of anything
downstream that you depend on.
Because everything that you depend on,
if it's not reachable now, it'll automatically
be retried until it is reachable.
So there are a lot of ways in which
we code that is predicated on the fact that what we're
working with is this primitive of a normal volatile function
that might die any time.
So we don't trust functions.
We don't trust that some set of statements will complete.
We only trust things that we've stored to disk,
have we persisted, probably replicated on multiple disks.
And that has a big effect on how we write code.
And when you have the primitive of a durable function,
it changes a lot about how you write code.
And it opens up some new possibilities, one of which
is you can sleep for an arbitrary period of time.
So here, we're sleeping for one month.
And normally, you can't do that because you
don't have confidence that your process will
be around in one month.
And you don't want to take up resources for that time.
Let's say like one thread per sleep.
I'm going to run out of threads.
And in durable code, you can write this in a production
function, and it will work fine.
You're guaranteed that this sleep will resolve in one month,
and then you'll go to the next line of code.
And you also don't need to take up resources during that time,
except for like a timer entry in a database.
The system will automatically unload this code.
And whenever that timer goes off in the DB,
it will rebuild the state of the function
and continue running.
Once I have these functions in production
that are running for very long periods of time,
I might want to be able to send them RPCs.
They might want to tell them, hey, do something different
or do something new now.
And I might want to get their state, like, hey,
what's your current state of your function?
So you can send RPCs to durable code executions.
They can also run forever.
So I don't need to return at the end of the function.
I could wait for an RPC to come, or I
can wait for this sleep to happen in a loop,
like I'm modeling a subscription.
And I sleep for one month in a loop
and charge the user every month for the lifetime of the user.
So it lasts indefinitely.
I also don't have to use a database in many cases,
because I can send information to this function
and get information out of it.
And the function can, like, in Python,
it's modeled as an annotated class.
And each function execution is like an instance of a class
with a run method and other methods for each RPC handler.
So you might save some state in the run method
in an instance variable, and then access it,
change it in the RPC handler methods.
So you could have some data that you return from, like,
a get current state RPC and not have to use the database.
You're storing it in a local variable or instance variable,
and you don't need to store it in the database.
And you're guaranteed that for the life of this function,
and even afterward, that value will be correct,
always be there and always exist and always be correct,
based on whatever has happened to that function previously,
like whatever the arguments were when you started
or whatever RPCs you sent since then.
So in summary, Drupal execution is process-independent
with automatic retries and timeouts,
sleep for arbitrary periods of time, send it RPCs,
have functions that run forever,
and you can use local variables or instance variables
instead of a database.
But how the heck does this work?
So here is a system diagram of temporal,
which is the one I'm most familiar with
and where I used to work.
There are a number of different durable execution systems,
and most of them have a similar diagram.
On the left side, we have application developers,
so us writing our application code.
And on the right, we have a platform team
that hosts the open source temporal service cluster
of Go services and databases,
and each part of this is MIT licensed open source.
And the temporal service side
takes care of the durability for you.
So if I want to start a durable function,
I'll use the client library in the top left,
somewhere in my application,
like I've got a new user subscribing,
I wanna start a subscription function.
You connect to the service,
and you say, okay, I wanna start this thing.
The service adds it to a queue,
and there's workers that you have pulling on the queue.
They pick up, okay, I need to,
and then the workers have your durable code.
So they pick up the task, okay,
I need to run the subscription function.
And here's the arguments,
like the user and the payment method,
and it will run that code.
And any step that it takes,
like a sleep or other things,
it reports back to the service what happened,
so the service adds it to the log
of everything that has happened to this function,
or anything this function has done.
And whenever new things happen,
like a sleep timer goes off,
or you get an RPC from a client,
it gets added to a queue,
the worker picks it up and continues running.
So for instance, if it gets a RPC,
it'll run that method handler.
So here's a family tree
of some of the main durable execution systems.
It was invented at Amazon,
so they were one of the early adopters of microservices.
They realized that, okay,
I can't call synchronously
between microservices reliably in production,
so they went to a vendor for an architecture
communicating asynchronously through queues,
and they were like, oh crap,
that gets really complicated really fast,
and they developed something called
Simple Workflow Service,
which is EWS-SWF,
which was the first version of durable code,
and a much nicer way of communicating between services.
Azure Durable Functions
has a similar durable execution service.
Cadence is used by Uber
to communicate across over 1,000 of their microservices,
and Cadence was forked in 2019 to become Temporal,
which is now a company
with over 200 people working on improving it.
It's used by a ton of companies,
including Stripe, HashiCorp, Netflix.
Every SnapStory is a durable function,
every Airbnb booking, Coinbase transaction.
So the last section, system design patterns.
We have 10 minutes.
Let's see.
So I highly recommend microservices.io
for listing distributed system patterns,
and Byte by Go is a great newsletter for system design.
Circle breakers.
Let's say I have a service-oriented architecture,
and I'm secretly calling between services.
Service A calls me, I'm Service B,
and I call Service E.
When I get a request from Service A,
I need to do something and then call C,
and if C is taking a long time to respond,
then I might, let's say, have a thread per open request,
then I might build up open requests or threads
until I have some resource exhausted,
like number of threads,
and then I'm gonna stop responding
to requests from Service A.
So then A will get backed up and resource exhausted,
and you can have a cascading failure.
So one solution to this is called the circle breaker pattern.
So I'm Service B.
Instead of directly calling Service C,
I will have a proxy that forwards,
usually, the request to Service C for me,
and it'll keep track of how often C is timing out
and stop sending, stop forwarding on requests to C.
The proxy will immediately return failure to Service B,
and then set a timer,
and then after a while, try doing requests again.
So it gives a break on Service C,
and it gets immediate failures from me and Service B.
In a durable execution, you don't need to do this,
because every call that you make
is automatically retried for you with exponential backup.
Event-driven architecture.
So we saw one of the problems
with synchronously calling between services.
So a common solution to this
is to have them communicate asynchronously
by a message of bus,
and that's event-driven architecture.
Here's an example.
A client on the top left creates an order.
You post a slash orders.
You have the API server that writes order created event
to the message bus,
and then there's a payment service that listens,
consumes that event, order created event,
does something, sends the order paid event to the bus.
Fulfillment service listens to that event,
does the fulfillment, and sends order fulfilled to the bus.
And there's other services,
like the analytics service that consumes all of them.
A great part of this, a great aspect of this,
is that it's very decoupled at runtime.
So in this scenario,
the fulfillment service can go down,
and the payment service can continue running.
In the synchronous case of like service B,
it's not finished until it successfully calls service C.
So it's like depending on service C being up and running.
Here, it's not depending.
Payment service can continue doing its work
and publishing order paid events to the bus,
even if the fulfillment service is down
and not consuming them.
And the fulfillment service isn't missing work,
because when it comes back up,
it can go through the backlog of order paid events.
So in Drupal execution,
you also have decoupled runtime.
You don't need any particular step
or downstream service or dependency to be up at the time,
because you'll have retries with exponential backoff
that'll eventually get this to work.
And so you have decoupled runtime,
but you also have much a better developer experience
at design time when you're building.
So an issue with EDA at design time is that
it's not decoupled, it's like tightly coupled.
You have to like make changes in lockstep.
So if I'm the API server
and I wanna change my order created event
to like a order submitted event
or make some breaking chains to the data format,
then I have to figure out all of the other teams
in my company that are depending on this event
and ask them to update their code and push it to production.
And then I can make my change.
So you have to do things in lockstep,
and it's also hard to understand
what's happening in the system.
Like here, there's only one business process
and I lead it out like sequentially for you.
But in reality, in production,
you're gonna have lots of services,
lots of different events that are hard to observe.
Like hopefully you have distributed tracing set up
and you can see, but sort of like
the behavior is emergent and complex
and can be hard to understand.
First is in the durable execution land,
you can look at a business process logic in code
and read and see what it does.
And you also have a log of every production function
execution so you can see what each function does
and every step that it took.
Or currently running functions,
what step they're currently on.
So it's much easier to rock and understand and edit.
Edit your code, change what steps happen when,
and redeploy.
So easier to change, understand, evolve,
and work with than EDA.
So sagas.
Let's see, oh 15 minutes, okay great.
Sagas are long running transactions.
They are when I have some data that I need to update
and the data isn't in like a single partition
of a single database.
So I can't use a transaction,
like a database level transaction to update it.
I need to split up these state updates into multiple steps
and if any discrete step fails,
then I undo all the previous steps that happened.
What are called compensating actions.
Compensate for this failure by undoing
each of the previous steps.
So it's a type of transaction that is an atomic
and doesn't hold blocks and is eventually consistent.
So it's a way of updating data that's across multiple
like databases or services.
And the main two ways of implementing sagas
are with choreography and orchestration.
Choreography is the event of an architecture way
where you're writing messages to a bus.
Orchestration is like a central orchestrator
that has the logic of like what the steps are
and it takes care of scheduling, executing
and retrying each of the steps.
Chris Richardson in the book Microservice Patterns
recommends using orchestration for all
but the simplest of sagas
because of how complex it can get, choreography can get
as we talked about earlier
in the event of an architecture section.
So recommends using orchestration
and the problem with orchestration is that
you are defining logic in a DSL
like a YAML file or a JSON file.
You have like this step and this step
like if, thens and loops are all done in like JSON.
And that's not nice to work with.
It's hard to write and read and debug and run.
And it's much better to when you're defining logic
to define logic in code
because you have the full expressivity
of a Turing complete language
and you can use your normal software development lifecycle.
You can run it locally.
You can debug it locally.
So much nicer DX to use code than a DSL
and durable code is basically automatically orchestrated
for you.
Each step is scheduled and retried for you.
So you can think of durable code
as code-based automatic orchestration
and it's a great way to do sagas.
So we have this process order function process
from before with three steps.
If we wanna make this into a saga,
then we need to add compensating actions.
We need to catch any failures and undo previous steps.
So we try and catch.
Let's say the reserve step on line two succeeds
and then charge succeeds and then we have to send package
and it has a failure.
And it's not like an intermittent retryable failure.
It's some application level non-retryable failure
like USPS returned address doesn't exist.
So this isn't gonna work through retrying.
So instead of continuing to retry, it throws.
I catch it on line nine, I refund.
So I undo the charge step and then I raise
and then I catch and then I unreserve the inventory
that I reserved in line two.
So if this is a durable function,
this is a accurate complete transaction or accurate saga.
Or accurate saga.
If this is a normal function, then it's not
because it's not correct because I could say
the process could die after line seven
and then I never refund the user
and never unreserve the inventory.
So saga is really easy to implement
when you have a durable function.
Transitional outboxes, okay.
So if I'm doing EDA, oftentimes if I'm a service
and I get an event, I make some state update
to my local state in my database
and then after that I submit another message to the bus.
The issue is that if after I do my local state update,
I crash, then I'm gonna fail to write the message
to the bus and everything after me
that depends on that message won't happen.
So my system will be like an inconsistent state.
For example, if I'm the payment service,
I write my successful payment record to my DB
and then I crash before I send the order paid event,
then fulfillment service won't have to fulfill.
So I'll have a user without a package
but having been paid.
And a solution to this is called
a transactional outbox or transfer queue.
So in the payment service, in a transaction,
when I update my local state like adding a payment record,
in that same, in the transaction, in the same partition,
I'm gonna add the event that I want eventually
to get to the bus in a sort of mini queue
in that for each partition has its own mini queue
and then have some separate process
that goes through all of the transfer queues
into each of the partitions in my data store
and reads them and sends them to the bus
and if it successfully sends to the bus,
then it takes it off that transfer queue
and you have deduplication and retries on failure.
So assuming you implemented that correctly,
then you have this guarantee that
because it's in a transaction
and because it eventually gets sent to the bus
that you have like this eventually consistent thing.
So that's a transfer queue or a transactional outbox
and you don't need to do it in durable code
because the entire pattern is predicated on the fact
that I don't know when I have multiple steps
that all of the steps will complete running.
So when, thank you a lot,
when I have a durable function
and I have one step is right to my local database
and next step is published to the bus,
then that next step is guaranteed to happen.
So I don't need a transactional outbox.
Event sourcing.
So this is a way of like storing state.
On the top, we have the normal way without event sourcing.
This is in three rows.
This is a single row in three different states.
So I insert a row with order ID 1001, quantity five,
and then I update the quantity to six,
and then I update the state to paid.
And so I'm left with one row with quantity six
and state paid.
With event sourcing, instead of doing these updates,
I am appending events to an immutable log
and each event is like what happens.
A new order row is the event ID 2001,
and then I modify order event and then order payment event.
So a downside to that is in order to know the state
of this order, I can't look at the last event
because it doesn't have the quantity.
I have to read through all the past events
for a certain domain model.
So you usually have some other view,
like a read view or materialized view
where you're reading the current state of the world.
But some benefits that event sourcing gets you
is that you have a complete visibility or audit log
of what happened to this business object in the past.
And you can also replay to any point in time
to see what the state of the world was.
And most durable execution systems
are implemented with event sourcing under the hood.
So each production function execution has this event log
and so you can see what happened.
And you can also, you have some bug
that's hard to diagnose in production.
You can download that event log
and run it locally against your code
and replay your code to see what happened
and run it in a debugger.
So you get great visibility and great debuggability
with sort of like automatically event sourced
function execution.
CQRS, we'll skip in the interest of time,
separating the commands of the writes from the queries,
depending on which level you're applying this to durable code.
Either it's unnecessary or it's done for you.
Distributed cron jobs.
Let's say I want something to happen periodically.
I can have a cron tab on analytics machine in production.
Issues with that are like,
it depends on this one machine being up
and has limited throughput.
So if I want something to be reliable and scalable,
then I want some distributed cron solution.
Durable execution is a great fit for this
because it scales horizontally in the number of executions.
So I can have billions of executions
and all of them could be sleeping
for arbitrary periods of time.
So waking up whenever I want them to run the next job.
Task queues.
So there was a article from last year
that was voted up on Hacker News
called Too Many Problems with Celery.
And one of them was Celery prefetches jobs
so it gets four at a time.
And if the first one takes like a day,
the next three are delayed,
even if they're like take a few minutes
because it's working on one at a time and gets four.
In durable execution, you have many slots in parallel
that a worker can be running,
like many function executions that can be doing.
And it only fetches one at a time.
So it's much better in this scenario.
Celery loses jobs by default.
So if a task raises an exception or a worker process dies,
then you lose that task.
In durable execution, you don't.
Whenever there's a failure,
it'll automatically get timed out and rescheduled.
Celery retried defaults are bad.
So they recommend doing exponential back off,
which is what durable execution does by default.
No transactional job enqueuing.
So talking about the transactional outbox pattern,
and author says like, don't use Celery if you need this
because you can't.
You don't need it with durable code.
Canvas cores and friends encourage brittle pipelines.
So if you have some pipeline of multiple jobs
that you need to happen together, like in a chain,
the author says it's a recipe for losing jobs
or having broken workflows
because Celery doesn't have transactional job enqueuing.
So you could have like the first step in a chain happen,
but the rest won't happen in various error states.
So it's like, they're like, don't use Celery for this.
Don't use these EPIs.
Versus if in durable code,
if you have a function with multiple steps,
they're guaranteed that they will all complete.
Another complaint was that the EPI isn't Pythonic.
And I don't know about all durable execution systems,
but for temporal, the Python runtime is very Pythonic.
Talk to Chad who built it,
who's at the temporal booth today.
State machines.
So a common pattern is I have some business process
that has multiple states that it's in,
and I want it to be done reliably.
So I split this process into multiple steps
that I put on job queues,
and I update the current state of this process
after every step.
And that can be a lot of work, a lot of code to write,
like in queuing and polling and updating a database.
And I guess it's a lot of code to write
and to get correct.
Versus in durable code,
you don't need to do all that plumbing work
of talking to the database or talking to a queue.
You can structure your code if you want as a state machine,
but you don't need to be talking yourself to a database.
So to recap, we defined what durable execution is,
talked about some new possibilities for how to program
that it opens up, a little bit about how it works,
and then some distributed system patterns
and how temporal either makes them unnecessary or easier.
So we had circuit breakers don't need to do,
event-driven architecture,
same decoupled at runtime, better DX.
Sagas, really easy to do,
transactional outboxes, don't need to do.
Event sourcing, done for you automatically.
CQRS, partially don't need, partially done for you.
Distributed cron jobs, really easy to do.
Task queues, automatically done for you
in a better way than celery's defaults.
And state machines, easy to do.
And Timbroil.io for more info.
I'm at laurendcr on Twitter if you have any questions.
Also laurenagraphql.guide is my email.
I'm a consultant with Bandwidth,
so if you'd like any help building your thing,
I'd be happy to take a look and see if I can help.
And those are the slides.
(*audience applauds*)
Awesome.
I've got a couple of questions for you here
that have been coming through.
And by the way, Lauren is also on the Discord,
so you can chat with him there as well.
Okay, first off, how can you tell
if a failure is transient or non-transient?
What's your criteria there?
Sure, so I guess each step is like a normal Python function.
And if you let something throw,
it's treated as a retrivable error.
If you catch something,
then you can throw a non-retrivable error failure.
So it's a class that you import from the library
to indicate that whatever happened is not retriable,
don't try to reschedule this.
Okay.
Can you talk about the data persistence layer
and any concerns around PCI, PII, GDPR rights,
and any of those things that need to be considered?
So I guess there's a number of different options
for persistence layer for Temporal at least.
Like I don't know about some of the hosted services
like AWS, SWF, or other drivable functions,
like whether they're PCI compliant
or what database they use.
But for Temporal, you can use MySQL or Postgres or Cassandra,
usually Cassandra for higher rate throughput and scale.
And I mean, if you want to go through PCI and GDPR
in that open source cluster that you host,
you can do that.
Wander over this way with me.
How do durable execution workers know
what function to pick up and in what order?
Sorry, say it again.
How do durable execution workers know
what function to pick up and in what order?
How do they keep track of the state of what needs to be?
So the workers don't need to keep up much state.
The service is taking care of when to add things to the queue
and the first, and like all the workers are polling
whenever they have like an open slot,
like I can do a hundred executions in parallel.
If I have one of those open, I will pull.
And whichever the first one that gets a new task on the queue,
we'll get that.
Well, I'll take care of that.
Yeah.
Okay.
How does the durable execution handle it
if the code has changed while the function was suspended?
Sure, so if you are changing the code
of a execution running in production,
there are a couple of different ways to do it.
You can, so if the code, if the execution
hasn't gotten to this point of code,
then you can just update it.
If it's already gone through it, then you can't update it
because the way the system is implemented
is that it has to, in order to rebuild the state of a function,
has to replay all previous events.
And if you try to replay the event log on different code,
it'll not work.
So there's a couple of different ways you can solve this.
One is you can deploy a separate worker
that only takes the new version of the code
that only takes new production function executions.
So all the existing ones will run in the old code.
Then whenever those are done, you can retire the old code.
Another way is to like have an if-then statement,
depending on what, like if version is one,
do this logic, otherwise do some other logic.
OK.
How do you see durable execution affecting game development?
Game development.
So I guess like for the trade off for durable execution
is that you are writing to disk a lot.
So you have a higher latency than if you
weren't persisting anything.
So there are certain things like for real time gaming
where you wouldn't want to use it.
But for anything where you can wait like 20 milliseconds,
like I don't know the information about the user
account, anything in non-real time
you could use a durable function for in gaming.
I think that also helps answer the question,
is durable execution used in real time critical systems
like air and spacecraft and their support systems?
And if not, why not?
I would guess that the high latency
would probably make them not well suited for that.
Yeah, I mean, it depends on how you
think of as high latency, like tens of milliseconds is fine.
But if you're trying to do like single digit milliseconds,
then it would be hard.
Right, right.
All right, I'll do one more here.
How can I trust that the durable execution workers are not
malfunctioning?
How can you trust the workers are not malfunctioning?
I guess the system.
The workers.
Pardon?
Who watches the workers?
It's fine for the system designed
to not trust workers, to only trust what's in the database.
So if a worker dies, everything that the worker does,
every task that it picks up has a timeout associated with it.
So the server will notice that this task hasn't been had.
There's no result from this task in a while.
So it'll treat it as failed and reschedule it.
I sent this assignment out a little while ago,
and it never returned.
Guess I should dispatch that again.
Nice.
OK, well, thank you, Lauren.
Sure.
Fantastic.
Thanks, everybody.
Thanks.