All right, okay, you can hear me okay?
Cool.
Good morning.
I am super excited to be here because, yes, you've been asking me for so long.
I feel so very honored, but you've been pestering me because I'm just so happy to be here.
I love regional conferences so much, and I didn't know that Pi Texas was the oldest regional
conference.
Yeah, so I'm just excited to be here and to meet you all.
So I don't say technical keynotes that often, but when I do, I thoroughly enjoy them.
I'm not sure if this meets the bar of keynote level, but I really like this talk, and I
hope you do too.
I even learned Blender to make this cool slide.
So yes, hi, my name is Len Root.
I'm roguelike everywhere except for GitHub.
I'm econchic.
I'm GitHub.
I don't know what happened there.
Yeah, you can find me in Macedonia on Twitter, on Instagram, wherever.
Yeah, and I am a staff engineer at Spotify, and I'm based in New York.
I've been at Spotify for over 10 years now, and most recently I've been working on infrastructure
for ML, experimentation, and governance.
I also actually teach at Columbia, which is rather a new gig.
You might also know me from Pi Ladies.
I am the chair of the Global Council of Pi Ladies, and if you want stickers, you can
come find me for stickers later.
And yeah, as a heads up, I'm not doing a live Q&A session, but I'm just honestly too nervous
to be up here and actually hear questions, even if you are loud enough.
I just can't physically hear people when I'm up here.
I'm super nervous in these lights.
But I'm more than happy to chat afterwards, and for a bit true of folks, I will hop on
Discord later and answer anything.
But yeah, let's jump to it.
About 10 years ago, I bought an electric kettle.
It had this plug, and it blew my mind.
I found myself asking, you know, why don't all plugs have a stand like this?
It's probably because of patents.
But not only does it make it easy to unplug, like you don't have to like, you know, wiggle
around, try and get leverage, maybe like electrocute yourself.
But it's also very easy and obvious to me how to use it.
It allows for easy grabbing and pulling, right?
So the simplicity and the thoughtfulness of this design, this made me think, what else
am I unknowingly struggling with?
This found me to this book, The Design of Everyday Things by Dot Norton, which you might
notice is the inspiration for my talks, Titan.
And it's got this nice coffee pot.
It's dubbed the coffee pot for masochists.
And the penance of this book is how design serves as the communication between object
and user, and how to optimize that communication for a better experience.
So Don Norman writes, design is concerned with how things work, how they are controlled
and the nature of the interaction between people and technology.
The range of things is not limited to physical objects like the Bremer plug that I'm so
familiar with, or the masochistic coffee pot.
It includes artificial creation as well, like software and digital interfaces, or the
layout of a conference room, organizational structures, whatever.
So what then makes design good?
Don says, Tim, the most important characteristics of good design are discoverability and
understanding.
So breaking this down further, discoverability is described as, am I able to figure out
what actions are possible and where and how to perform them?
So the author lays out five key elements of discoverability.
The first one is affordances.
So affordances determine what actions are possible.
What's, it's what a user can do with an object based on their capabilities.
Affordances aren't a physical property, it's the relation between the user and the
object. So a door affords opening if you can reach the handle.
So for a toddler, a door doesn't afford opening if they can't reach it.
So building on top of affordances, the second element is signifiers.
A signifier is some sort of perceivable cue about the affordance.
Signifiers communicate where the action should place.
The term signifier exists in this context to make a clear distinction between the
signal and a flowless might provide to a person, which is entirely in the visual
perceptible part of an affordance, and the actual affordance itself.
So they are like similar as their latest sounds, some sort of like physical
indicator. So for example, a flat panel or like a bar on a door would signify
that you need to push the door open.
The third key element of discoverability is constraints.
Constraints are limitations or restrictions, and they give us clues that
allow us to determine coercive action by limiting the possible actions available
to us. There are a few types of constraints that could be physical, like
a mailbox slot that only allows letters and suit packages to be dropped in.
Or it might be logical, like where the last case of the pizzer might go in to
only the last space left.
And then there's also like cultural and semantic constraints, like a red roadside
typically means stop.
The source is mappings.
A mapping is the relationship between control and election.
So when a mapping uses spatial correspondence between the layout of the
controls and the device being controlled, it's easy to determine how to use them.
So a good example of a good mapping would be where you'd have like two lights
and two light switches, and then like the left light switch would control the
left light and the right light switch would control the right light.
I have a couple of bad mappings in my own apartment that I should try and fix,
but it's really annoying when they're not mapped correctly.
The final key element is feedback, where the results of an action is
communicated back to the user.
So feedback should communicate clear, unambiguous information back to the
user in order to be effective.
Immediate feedback is ideal.
Delayed feedback can be disconcerting and lead to a feeling of
user abandonment or failure.
And then there's a delicate balance between the amount of feedback.
Too much feedback can be annoying and irritating to the users or, you know,
too much to even like want to read through it all.
Too little feedback could be useless and as good as no feedback at all.
And then feedback also needs to be prioritized.
So you have important messages and alerts versus like unimportant messages.
And so these are the five key elements of destabilizing.
We have affordances, signifiers, constraints, mapping, and feedback.
And then build up to the second part of good design.
Understanding.
So understandably, it means is it possible or easy for users to figure
out how the product can be used?
So understanding is developed by swan-naming a conceptual or
at-time model of how something works.
A conceptual model is just a collection of explanations,
often pretty simplified.
And so the user builds their own conceptual model of how a system or
product works and the designer designs the system or product using
their own conceptual model.
The designer expects the user's conceptual model to be identical to
their own, but it can't because they cannot communicate directly with the user.
So the burden of communication is with the system and its design.
So good conceptual models are the key to understandable, enjoyable products.
And good communication is the key to good conceptual models.
And then that communication comes from those key aspects of discoverability.
The affordances, signifiers, constraints, mappings, and feedback.
And so maybe you can start to see how these ideas, essentially human-centered
design, can start to apply to software, to designing a library for others to use.
My first instinct when thinking about this is to think about libraries that
I've worked with, maybe that are not so fun to use.
I'm not going to name and shame any Python libraries here, but there's
one non-Python library that I do load.
It is ffmpeg.
If you don't know, it's a well-known tool that is designed for processing
audio and video, so the screen recording is just me running, like, let us punch.
So just with some documentation.
And so whenever I use ffmpeg, the way for me to figure out how to do something,
seemingly simple, like creating a looping gif from a video, I end up
meaning to go copy commands from Stack Overflow, because I'm solving
because I'm sorry, the documentation sucks.
It's so powerful and I know that I can do many things with it.
And I will continue to reach for it just on its ubiquity and its performance,
but there will always be this reaction.
So this made me think, if I am an engineer who develops tools and
infrastructure for other engineers, how many masochistic keypots
have I unknowingly shipped?
How many size have I caused?
So there are much, much better people to give talks on this,
better ideas and theories.
So I'm not an authority on API design, but for me, it is a missing
connection between a theory of good design and the actual implementation.
So this brings me to my talk.
I'm not sure if anyone else has seen my previous talks, but I have a habit
of writing talks for myself, particularly ones that I really wish I saw years ago.
So this talk is mainly for Kathleen that tries to take key elements of good
design and apply them to a real world example.
So I was aiming to condense this into a through-tennis or through-chain
principles that make it really fun to work with API.
So first I'm going to set the stage.
In a previous talk of mine, I went through building what's called
like a KS monkey system, and it uses a Pub-Sub queue.
I kind of want to stick with that theme.
And so let's like design a library that works with a Pub-Sub queue-like service.
I'm just going to call it a KS queue, because why not?
And it has nothing to do with this car.
I just like it.
All right.
So let's look at some code.
So first we have this class that defines a message object.
And all it does is contain data to be passed to and from a KS queue.
And we have a second class, a client that essentially publishes to and
consumes messages from our Pub-Sub KS queue.
And so this is our starting library.
Perhaps you are already thinking of some things that you want to change,
which is great, but just, just don't type.
Which in order to develop a little bit of empathy for my future users, I want
to write a little bit of user code that interacts with this library.
So on the user side, I have a Pub-Sub queue client, and then I try and create
a topic, create a subscription as well, and then catching if they already
exist and continuing on.
And then we start interacting with our client.
We have a silly week that publishes five messages to a grass Pub-Sub queue.
And then a while true to consume those messages.
We print the message.
Maybe it's, you know, swept over a debugger.
And then we do some sort of processing on the message data.
And then we acknowledge the message from the queue when we're done processing.
And then finally, maybe the client has some network connections that we need
to clean up and close or some methods to flush.
So this is what we have.
So let's improve this for the user and start iterating on our library.
We'll start with my first of three principles.
An API should be intuitive and note that I mean intuitive for the user, not
for you, the equipment or maintainer.
So with an intuitive API, a user can be easy.
They don't have to think too hard about how it works.
They need to remember complicated details because their intuition
correctly explains it to them.
They don't have to spend a lot of time learning new parts of the API
because they all work pretty similarly.
And so an intuitive API builds on the user's pre-existing conceptions.
And tries not to do anything surprising, nothing that unnecessarily works
against any logical or domain constraints.
And so with that, I have three changes that I want to make to RKS queue
to improve the intuitiveness of the API.
So we're going to start with some loan manuals and naming the methods
in our client class using the domain's nomenclature, like publish a message,
cloud a message from a queue, acknowledging a message is complete,
and drain a queue of messages.
So right now we have add message, get message, art message, die, clear
message queue, and so we're going to need to publish, cloud, direct, and drain.
Now I also dropped the noun from the method layers since I found them
a little redundant because I didn't want them to be in the same
since I found them a little redundant, particularly because in my layer,
the noun that we're operating on is in the function signature already.
It's the message.
And then now look, I have room on my slide to indent four spaces in the two.
So why are we doing this?
So this plays into the mappings element of discoverability.
Naming your functions, something similar to the domain that they're supposed
to work in can help result in immediate understanding of what your API is supposed to do.
So the next suggestion kind of steps back a tiny bit to think about appropriate
abstraction levels, so clumsy naming hints at clumsy abstractions within
the slides, kind of a little clumsy.
If you recall, our PubSub client, we have a few Q&As and events.
We have create topic, create subscription, and click as client.
But this point seems to manage all in one object.
From the user's point of view, what if we want to just consume messages and not publish them?
Do I have to create a topic for some reason, or will there be
connections managed by the client sound unnecessary?
So let's not add any unnecessary confusion to the user and break up those client into two.
So one that works with just publishing and one that works with just subscribing.
So this allows us to clean up the method names a little bit as well.
And then this creates natural constraints on what the user can do.
If the user must create a topic, then they have to instantiate a PubClient.
And that will lead to only those actions provided with the PubClient's methods.
However, our clients also create some unnecessary constraints on our users.
So that brings me to microchange.
Let's make sure our API has symmetry.
So we allow the user to create a topic or create a subscription.
Well, what does the user do if they want to change an existing topic or
subscription or even delete one?
So let's not limit them unnecessarily.
Let's not limit them unnecessarily and provide symmetry with our methods.
So just having a create method without its logical symmetric pair or tripling or
whatever, gives a misleading center file to the user.
It can be certain that users have worked with other APIs that provide both a create
and a delete method, a set and a get method and upload and a download method.
And so it would be counter-intuitive to either not provide such functionality,
or to provide that functionality, but not file convention and symmetric naming.
So some of these changes may seem a bit contrived.
It was really hard to come up with a super succinct example that is also
relatable, but hopefully the message is starting to come across here.
And some of these changes later on in the talk could very well apply with being
intuitive, and I'm sure the changes I'm addressing here may apply.
And again, I'm not really an expert here, but anyways, let's move on to the next
unit. An API should be flexible.
And again, I mean flexible for the user.
It's a whole other talk about writing flexible APIs for a maintainable
country. So basically a flexible API lets you do what you want.
In my point of view, a flexible API lets users to get started quickly with the
more basic use cases, and then it allows the user to adjust as they need to solve
more and more complex problems.
So flexibility comes down to the question of how many problems can users solve
once they learn the API?
So for this time, I have four changes I want to make to a chaos queue.
The first is to provide same defaults to the most common use cases.
So recall that we have some methods to work with publishing and consuming
messages. The main resource these methods are working with is the message.
The timeout and the retry arguments aren't required to the core functionality
of publishing or acknowledging a message.
And then I often find myself as a user to not know what a good number of seconds
a timeout should be or how many retries I should be making.
And so as the API designer, I should make optional behavior as optional keywords
with some defaults. So maybe 30 seconds is the most common timeout value, or maybe
it comes from the default of the server side.
And then maybe having a zero as a default for retries makes sense too.
So by moving a lot of optional settings into keyword arguments, it allows the user
to focus on just what is required of them.
This change also goes a bit beyond the flexibility of an API.
By forcing users to use keyword arguments and providing same defects,
we limit the number of and the order of positional arguments that the user
has to remember. So for instance, both timeout and retries are integers.
If they were positional arguments like before, the user could easily inverse them
when calling a method, and then that would safely pass type checkers.
We also have more optional keyword arguments in our methods, like request ID and
publicity rebel with a bunch more of them. If you have many, many arguments, positional
or keyword, you might want to step back a little bit because it might be providing
another hint at clumsy code. It might be unnecessarily exposing some
complexity. So with slide pants and a lot of arguments, if folks can't understand
type annotations, maybe you need to rethink and refactor.
So for the sake of my slides being readable, I'm rolling all of these keyword arguments
into star quarks, but don't do this at home, particularly for your public API.
For libraries with automatic generation, instead of finding a list of arguments
and their meaning in the documentation, users will absolutely see no information
about some keyword arguments. And then if the library does not have automatic
generation or any documentation at all, which is a shame on you, but then the user
can actually just simply look at a function signature. You must dive into the code,
but they still have to try and understand what these quarks are.
So again, these quarks are just to make my slides readable.
Anyways, moving on. The next change I want to make is to increase flexibility of our
APIs to minimize the user's need to repeat themselves. So we saw in the user's code a
loop for publishing each message. So in the PEM client, our published message has one
positional argument for message. To minimize forcing the user to repeatably publish each
message, we can accept multiple message arguments in the function signature by collecting them into
star args. And then we can do the repetitive work for them. So hopefully you're writing some
code as you are building your API. So you can look for common patterns in the user code that
you could minimize away, like loops and repetition. Then as I said earlier, the
tenet of flexibility is, again, from the user's point of view. Providing flexibility to any user
requires you to be predictable and to be precise in what you do for them.
So part of building that conceptual model, the understanding for the user is defining constraints
and feedback. So we provide flexibility in what we accept as input. There needs to be a clear
constraint in what we do time. We shouldn't make the user figure out what object type that they
get back from a method of ours. So we'll call our subscription client by returning a consumed
message when we call it. Or it returns none. So this doesn't seem too predictable or too precise.
So the user has to check if they got a message out or if they are dealing with none.
So now what's the use case here? It's when there are no more messages in the queue to consume.
Now, if they look at preexisting APIs like the Python queue library, it raises an error when
the queue is empty. That seems pretty easy to do. So let's update our function signature to
only return a message object and then raise if there are no more messages in the subscription queue.
So this goes back to what Don Norb was saying about feedback, that it should
create third, ambiguous information back to the user and for it to be effective.
So this last change of flexibility is kind of supporting the user's being lazy. Basically,
not force users to provide data that you can generate yourself. So recall our message object.
It has an ID, it has some data, and a public timestamp of some sort. Now, when creating a message,
there's no need for users to supply their own unique ID. They probably shouldn't even be.
Or even to timestamp it when it's published. We can do that ourselves. We probably would not
have a timestamp. Generally, at the time the message is in student sheet, probably when it's
actually published, coming up with real examples is kind of hard. But now, let's say we have a bit
of user understanding. So often, a user might want to print or log the message for debugging
purposes. And for them, we should provide a method to make it easy to just print out the instance.
So now the user doesn't need to worry about printing necessary attributes on the message,
but just the message itself. So this is just one approach at redefining our message object
to help out the user. We could also use data classes. This removes some boilerplate for us.
It does get a little clumsy with setting defaults in our case with post in it. And yeah, the code
kind of goes off the slide a little bit, but it's still nice. A third option would be just
the third byte I could just adders. This actually allows me to go back to the force space and
location. But also, if I needed adders, it would provide me the flexibility and constraints for my
users. Since not only does it give me a clean way to set dynamic defaults, it also has validation
and convertives and even the ability to abuse in it more so if I need it. Now, I'm not a paid
shill for adders. I'm just a happy user of it. So if your API is not flexible, you'll find yourself
saying, I'm sorry, I know our API should be able to do that, but for reasons that you don't care
and that are within our control, we can't. So if the API is not flexible, users will eventually
ditch the library and go to something else that does solve the problems. And so for my last tenet,
an API should be simple. The complexity of an API can be measured by the cognitive load it requires
to actually use it. Complexity hurts our understanding. So we've already made some
changes to reduce the cognitive load of our API, like consistent and appropriate method naming,
learning the number of propositional arguments in our function signatures, and minimizing the
amount of verification that the user has to do. But we can make a few more changes to make it
more simple. So the first change is to provide composable functions. APIs that follow the
mathematical closure property tend to be simple as well as flexible. So loosely, an API plans that
closure property when every operation returns a data type that can be set into another operation.
This means that different operations in your API should be composed with each other. For example,
in Python, we're able to chain a bunch of string methods together since the output of many string
methods is another string. So the closure property makes it easier to combine multiple operations to
get the desired result. Maybe users don't do it that often, but following this, we're able to
allow users to not have to remember different function signatures operating on the same object.
So looking at our subscription client, we have ternethics that operate on the message that they
act. And it's pretty reasonable to think that once you pull a message from the chaos queue,
you'll want to acknowledge it. Otherwise, it'll just get redeliberated after some time,
and then you have unnecessary duplicate work. So there is no reason for us to be restrictive in
our function signature for acting and requiring a string, but adds to the cognitive load for the
user. They basically have to remember that they must give an ID of the message and can't actually
pass in the object that they've been working with. So let's change that to the message object,
and we can figure out how to get the ID of the message. And so now it's simpler for a
user to pull a message from the subscription and then act it. So while we're at it, let's also
accept the ability for users to give us multiple messages if they wish to batch up their
acknowledgments. It certainly adds to the symmetry of our method signatures and
also removes unnecessary loops in the user code. Now, while we're on the topic of loops,
the next change I want to make aligns our API with some Python idioms, making it more Pythonic.
Now, leveraging language idioms also leans into what a programming language affords.
Different programming languages allow you to or afford you different approaches to solve the
kinds of problems that we solve. So like supporting deflection and introspection,
or supporting default values for the function parameters, or how they're defined.
So looking at our subscription client again, the user has to call pull to get a single message,
and then you might recall that in our users, part of it is a wild true loop.
So let's make that easier for the user and provide an iter method that returns an iter.
So providing an iter is helpful for cases like this where the user is consuming a stream of
events or data. It's also helpful when users might need to page through results like a search query
with hundreds or thousands of items. This iter method also happens to simplify the
user's code even more. The iterable just stops when there are no more messages.
The user can now remove a try and accept around for different dequeues around the consuming code.
So in continuing on leveraging the language idioms, you might remember that both clients
have a Cliffhills method, managing any connections and buffers underneath the home.
So this forces the user to remember to clean up after themselves,
adding to the complexity and cognitive load. You might see where this is going. Let's make
use of a context management and provide an easy way for users to not have to remember
any finalization or cleanup behavior. And then there is a third adjustment that we can make
to align with existing idioms and habits. We have two methods in a pub and sub client
that the user would have to put a try and accept on because it blizzes if the topic or
subscription already exists. So let's follow the convention of other APIs like os.migdur
or even SQLs create terrible. And allow the user to not care if something exists already
and make sure that and just make sure that it does exist. So we'll add an exist okay
keyword that'd be aborium. And we'll default it to false, since it might not do what the user
expects. So we kind of force them to opt into it. Now, so the last change, we can also think of
simplicity as, is it convenient to get started? How much do I have to learn to start being able
to use this library? What do I have to do right now to get it working? If an API is not convenient,
if it takes many steps to get started or I have to page through a lot of documentation in order
to get a very basic understanding, then the choice adoption will suffer. So provide your user with
convenience. And you can do this by treating your readme like you would a newspaper. So given the
most important details first, like above the fold, and then if users want to learn more,
they can turn the page or they can read the rest of the readme document or other docs.
And so when I'm looking at a readme, I want three things above the fold. How do I get your library?
Do I need any system level or non-Python dependencies?
What are one or two examples that I can copy and paste immediately to try this out?
And as a side note, potentially reconsider if your examples are using the repend or having
the bash prompt. It makes it annoying to copy and paste those particular examples. Maybe that's just
a pet peeve of mine. And then say, where can I go to get more information? So give me those three
things at the top and then I'm good to go with getting started with your API. So creating a
simple API is all about reducing cognitive load on the user, reducing what the user has
to keep in their head while working with your API. All right. That was a lot. I'm going to
rewind and review a little bit. So we started here with a very simple API for a library that
contains only two classes. As we moved on, we built our code into three classes and now this
slide is unreadable on purpose. And that's okay because we started with a lot of user code, 29
lines to be exact and the data down to 13 lines. Now the code can actually fit on the slide and be
readable. This should be the goal and not necessarily the number of lines of code words
that can be on the slide, but it's about user empathy when designing a delightful API.
And so to recap, is your API intuitive for the user? Is it flexible for the use cases? Is it
simple enough to essentially learn once? So you have to keep in mind that your software will
become a part of a larger system. Your only choice is whether it will be a well-behaved part of a
larger system. The how can be a little elusive. So hopefully this example progression
in improving a dummy API was helpful. It's a lot. All right. I understand. So if you only
remember one thing from this talk, besides my awesome cheeky synthwave theme, is to remember
this. If all else fails, standardize. So Don Varnon leaves us with a good catch-all.
When no other solution appears possible, then design everything the same way so people only
have to learn once. All right. So that was all I had.