All right. Thank you, PyTexas. My name is Peter Sobot, and I'm here to talk to you today about
working with audio in Python. So first off, who am I and why am I up here talking to you?
Well, I'm a staff machine learning engineer, and I work at Spotify in what's called their
audio intelligence lab. That's a machine learning research team that uses machine learning to
try and build systems that understand music and understand audio. We use a lot of Python
day-to-day, which is why I'm here talking about Python, and we also build a lot of stuff that
ends up in the Spotify app itself. So if you're a user, thank you. You've probably seen our work.
If you're curious about other stuff we do, though, we publish APIs such as this one that
allows you to find out the tempo and the key and the beats and all sorts of stuff like that about
every song that you might hear on Spotify. But we also publish machine learning models. We publish
open source software like this called Basic Pitch. Basic Pitch here is an automatic transcription
model. So you can put music or an audio signal in, and you can get notes out the other end. So it'll
tell you which notes were played in a specific piece of music. Super cool, totally open source,
totally free to use, runs in the browser, runs in Python, wherever you want. Find that on GitHub.
But also, and more related to Python for today, we build audio software like this. This is Petalboard.
You can find this on GitHub. It's a Python library for working with audio, and we'll be touching on
this later on in the talk. But first off, this is Pi Texas, not Audio Texas. So I'm going to set
some kind of ground rules to start with. I'll talk about how digital audio works to begin with.
Then once I've done that, I'll talk about how to read and edit audio in Python, how you can use
audio in your own Python code. Then I'll talk about different problems you might run into working
with audio in Python, gotchas or, you know, issues that you won't find out until it's four in the
morning and you just got paged. And then I'll finally talk about how to make your audio code
simpler by using Petalboard, that library I just talked about. So let's start at the very top. I'm
going to assume that you know nothing about audio whatsoever, and we'll talk about how digital audio
works to begin with. Audio is really just a recording of sound, and sound is what you're hearing
right now, I hope. And so to get that sound from the air around us into a computer, we're going to
have to measure it in some way. So I'm going to put a two-dimensional graph on the screen here,
and along the x-axis, we'll have time in seconds, and on the y-axis, we'll have pressure in the air.
The pressure can move back and forth. You can have no pressure. You get a pressure coming towards
you or going away from you. It doesn't matter too much. But I'm going to play a sound here,
and we'll see how the pressure changes on this graph. Cool. So we just measured a whole bunch of
points on this graph here. Each of them doesn't really have much meaning on its own. We can't
tell what's going on without looking them all together. But what we can do is measure both where
they are on the x position and on the y position. On the x position here, we can see that we measured
one point roughly every 0.4 seconds or so. If I take the reciprocal of that, that gives us a rate
of 2.5 points per second, and we can call that our sample rate. That's going to be super important
later on. This is how we can tell how fast these points came in, and if we want to play them back
through a speaker again, we need to know that number. Also, you might notice that these are
spaced evenly around some middle point, and that's actually the silence point or the zero point on
this graph. And that's because, like I mentioned before, pressure can come towards you or move away
from you. And so maximum loudness or maximum pressure is actually at the top and bottom of
this graph, and that's how we can read this. And then we can just measure each of these points.
So on the left here, this point is maybe 60% amplitude or 60% of the maximum in the positive
direction, so we could give it 0.60 there. And this point here is negative, sorry, 90% amplitude in
the negative direction, so we'd give it a value of negative 0.90. So I could join all these points
together and try to reconstruct that original sound that we just heard of that saxophone,
but you might notice there's not really that much detail here. We can't tell much from these
10 or 12 points, and that's because we didn't sample often enough. So let's try sampling the
signal again, recording it again off the microphone, but this time I'm going to sample at a rate of
44,100 points per second, or 44,000 kilohertz, or sorry, 44.1 kilohertz, and that's actually the
rate that most digital audio systems use today. And let's see what the difference looks like.
So we've got a lot more data there, and we can already tell that visually because there's so
much more detail in this waveform here. I can zoom in, and we can go from kind of the grand scale
where we see multiple seconds at once all the way down to the millisecond range, and at this range
we're actually going to be able to see the individual waveform, or sorry, the individual
waves that make up the waveform here. If we were to measure the distance between these peaks,
that would actually give us the pitch or the frequency, but I don't want to stop there. I
want to keep going even further down to see exactly what the computer saw. And so we're
going to go down to the microsecond level between each of these points here. We're actually looking
at only 22 microseconds of time, which is a very, very, very small amount. And what the computer did
here is that it measured the amplitude, or it measured the pressure at each of these 22 microsecond
samples here. And so if we take just those numbers, well, that's really the secret. That's digital
audio. That's all there is to it. Digital audio is just streams of numbers, plus also that sample
rate I mentioned earlier. So we've got some digital audio. We recorded this off a microphone.
Technically, this is part of a saxophone clip. That's great. What can we do with it? Well,
we could save these numbers on disk, and we could save them as regular uncompressed floating point
information if we wanted to. We could use NumPy and Python to save these if we wanted to, and that'd
be great. But that would cost us a lot of data. That would be about 21 megabytes per minute of
audio, which doesn't sound like a huge amount if you have a laptop that has a lot of storage on it.
But if we're talking about streaming music to your phone, 21 megabytes per minute is a lot.
So instead, back in the 1990s, some extremely smart people came up with compression algorithms,
and you might have heard of some of these before. Things like MP3 and AUG Vorbis and AAC and so on.
And these compression algorithms throw away part of the signal. So instead of storing every single
number in its full resolution, we're instead storing a compressed version of that. That is
a little bit less high fidelity. It throws away stuff that our ears can't hear super well. But
it gets our data rate down to less than one megabyte per minute in many cases. So that's how
most audio is stored nowadays, and if we want to read that, we're going to have to use some
sort of tool or some sort of library to decompress the audio for us. So let's start writing some
Python. This is where I start to bring in actually Petalboard, which is the library I mentioned
earlier. So let's at the very top do import audio file. Now, I don't want to talk too much
about what Petalboard does just yet, but here we're just going to pull in a class that can
read the audio off of the disk and decode it for us. So if you've ever opened a file in Python,
you're probably aware of using a with statement and the open constructor or the open function.
And here we're going to do the same thing, only we're going to use audio file instead.
So I can say with audio file, myfavoritesong.mp3 has F, and I've just opened a file pointer that
points into this file. Now, F has a couple properties on it that you won't find in a regular
open file. For instance, you can find out the sample rate, which we talked about before,
and see that this audio is recorded at 44,100 samples per second. We can also find the number
of channels that are available in the audio file. In this case, it's a two-channel audio file. It's
in stereo, and that's because we have two ears. Usually we record in stereo. And just like a
regular open file, we can do F.read on this file. And here we're going to ask for three samples,
rather than three characters or three bytes, and we end up getting a multidimensional array back.
Now, if you're not familiar with multidimensional arrays, that's totally okay. They just look like
this. You can think of them like lists of lists of numbers. And the only property that's important
is that the inner lists all have to be the same shape or the same length.
So here, because we have two channels, we have a multidimensional array of two dimensions.
The first is the number of channels, and that's two. And the second is the number of samples,
and that's three. So here we have the left channel up top and the right channel at the bottom.
So we'll touch up on this again in a second. If it doesn't make sense yet, don't worry about that.
Okay. So let's try to do some more complex slicing and reading of the audio here.
Let's start by opening up the file again, and then we'll read the entire thing in. Instead of
just reading three samples, we'll read all of the samples in the entire file. And again,
we end up with a multidimensional array. The first dimension is the number of channels, which is two,
and the second is the number of samples, which here is 1.3 million, which sounds like a lot,
but if you divide that by the sample rate, that's really only 30 seconds worth of audio.
So it's not that much. Then we can use standard Python array slicing tricks here. We could do
audio at zero to give us the left channel and audio at one to give us the right channel.
We can also do multidimensional array slicing like this. So we can pass an empty slice for
the first dimension and then pass up to 100 samples for the second dimension, and that'll
just chop the audio down to only 100 samples in both the left and right channels. And we're
just dealing with NumPy arrays here. So if you're familiar with those, everything transfers to this.
We can also work in units of seconds instead. So we can say audio in both channels up into
10 seconds by multiplying 10 by F dot sample rate, and we get a buffer that just contains the first
10 seconds. Standard Python slicing tricks apply, so we can do negative F dot sample rate times 10
and so on, and everything just works as you'd expect. But just like a regular open file,
why would you read the whole thing in if you only want part of it? Well, you can also deal
with that here too. You can do F dot seek to move around the file pointer in the file,
and then you can do F dot read just to read a certain section that you care about,
and Petal Board will just avoid decoding the audio that you don't need.
So that's how we can open these files and read from them and play around with the data inside.
But now let's change how they sound. I'm going to delete all of this,
and then we're going to try to add an effect to some of this audio. So here,
still dealing with my favorite song, dot IP3, we'll read the whole thing. I'm just going to
take one of the channels, so I'll just take the first channel, doesn't really matter which one it
is, and let's add an echo effect or a delay effect to this audio. I'll define some parameters up
front first. So we'll say delay in seconds is equal to 0.2. We'll add a delay here of one
fifth of a second. And we'll also convert that from seconds into samples because we're indexing
this array in units of samples rather than seconds. So this just makes it easier for us
to do our math here. Then we'll set a volume parameter. This is how loud we want our echo
to be. It'll be 75% of the original volume of the signal. Then we're going to loop through
each of the samples here. So for every sample in our original array, we're going to do a little bit
of calculation. I can explain this really quickly. We're just going to take the sample value at the
current index, multiply it by the volume that we want, and then add it to the signal in the future
moved forward by delayed samples. And if that doesn't make sense, that's okay because we're
dealing with audio code, which means we can listen to it to find out if we did the audio
code correctly or not. So here's two samples. The one on the left has not been run through our code,
and the one on the right has. So let's take a listen to these.
So that's before we run our code, and then here's after.
You can hear that, right? That's definitely an echo effect. We've just added this kind of
almost musical galloping kind of effect, and all we had to do was add the signal to itself here
with these six lines of Python code. So it's not too complicated to add these effects,
but let's try a different style of effect. Instead of a rhythmic effect, let's change
the character of the sound itself. And in this case, I'm going to use a totally different sample
as an example. Let's load up cool guitar dot wave here. I'm going to read just the left channel as
well, and then let's set some other parameters here. Let's set a parameter called gain to 200.
This will be some distortion that we want to add to the signal. Then let's set volume to 10%.
This is just going to make sure that we don't blow out the speakers in this auditorium
because distortion will make things a little bit louder. Then for every single sample in the
audio file, we're going to apply a mathematical function here. This happens to be math dot tan
H or the hyperbolic tangent function, but that doesn't matter too much. If you don't know what
that means, I don't really either. That's fine. All I know that this does is it'll make the sound
much more distorted. And so let's listen to a before and after here as well.
So hopefully you could hear the difference there. What we did was really just multiply this signal
by the distortion factor, put it into a function, and then reduce its volume. And that added a lot
more aggression, a lot more overdrive to the signal. And all we had to do was write these five lines of
Python code. Okay. So we've seen how to open audio files, how to edit them, how to manipulate
them in Python. That's all pretty simple. But let's talk about some problems that you might
run into when working with audio in your Python code. These are probably only going to bite you
once your code has already been deployed and once you think everything is going well.
So let's write a very quick five line application that can open up an audio file and make it louder
and then save it back to disk again. So let's start by opening up my favorite song on IP3 again.
And let's read the entire thing into memory here with audio equals f dot read, f dot frames.
Then once that's done, we'll multiply every sample by two to make every sample louder,
and the whole thing will come out sounding much more loud. That's it. And then we'll save back
to disk again by opening up audio file again. We'll pass W as the second parameter, just like
you would with a regular open call in Python. We'll pass in the sample rate, and then we'll do
O dot write louder audio. Side note, this will encode in MP3 for us. So if you want to do MP3
encoding in Python, those two lines will do that for you, no problem. And then you deploy this code
and you send this to your users, and everybody uses it, and they're happy, and that's all great.
But this code will probably crash eventually if you accept any user input or deal with audio files
that you don't control or anything like that. And that's for one very simple reason. It's that MP3
is a good compression codec. So are many other compression codecs. And if my favorite song on
IP3 here is two hours long, then as soon as you're reading the entire thing, you're going to have to
decompress that audio. And in this case, a two hour input clip is going to require 2.3 gigabytes
worth of memory. And you would have no idea because all you're doing is opening the file and
reading it in. So instead, we can write much more robust code by avoiding the need to read
the whole thing into memory. And let's try doing that here. We can do that in only two extra lines
of code. So I'll start by defining a chunk size. We're going to process the audio in chunks here
because there's no need really to read the whole thing in at once. We'll open our input file,
then we'll open our output file and keep them both open at the same time. So now we're able
to read from the input, do some processing, and write to the output. Then as long as we have more
input to read, so while f.tel is less than f.frames, we're going to read one chunk of the file,
we're going to make it louder, and then we're going to write that to the output file. So this
is seven lines of code instead of five lines. Those two extra lines, I mean, that's a penalty
we're going to have to pay here. But the benefit is that we're never going to use more than four
megabytes of memory. And that's because we're only ever reading in one chunk of audio at a time.
So my favorite song could be a full collection of symphonies that's 12 hours long,
and this code would process it just fine. So my takeaway for you here is you should always,
always, always think of audio data as a stream. Audio is a stream. It's a representation of sound,
and sound goes on over time, and time continues indefinitely. So you should always make sure that
your audio code can handle any size of input. Okay. So that's a memory problem you might run
into. Let's talk about a different problem, though. Let's talk about a performance problem.
Here's that example that we used earlier to add distortion to a guitar signal. This sounded just
fine. It actually ran pretty quickly. Everything went well. But let's time part of this code.
In fact, let's time this hot loop here, where we're going through every single sample of the
audio file and applying map.10h. If I time this on my MacBook here, we see that it takes eight
seconds per minute of audio to process this audio. That's 7.5 times faster than just playing the
audio in the first place. Or what we would say is it's 7.5 times real time. And that's great.
Faster than real time is still really good. But if I were to rewrite this using something
like NumPy, let's say, we'd find that NumPy performs a little bit better. And just writing
it like this, almost the same exact code, this runs in 23 milliseconds per minute of audio.
So let's do the math on that. We find that it's 338 times faster to use NumPy here instead of
for loops. Which should be no surprise to anybody who's dealt with Python for a while. It turns out
that Python code is very, very slow if you're doing repeated numeric operations like this.
Of course. Because every line of Python you run has to invoke the interpreter,
has to do a whole bunch of overhead that you don't really need if you're just doing the same
operation on audio samples or doing math like this. So what I want you to take away from this
is that for pure audio code, Python is slow. If you ever find yourself iterating sample by sample
or operating on every individual data point here, you're probably doing something that's
not going to scale and that will become a bottleneck in your code. Instead, you should
find a way to outsource that computation to another library. Either something like NumPy
that's very efficient or something much more specific built for audio like this one right here
called pedal board which I happen to maintain and which does a lot of this stuff for us.
So let's take a look at how this can simplify your audio code. Now a quick aside, though,
if you're wondering why this is called pedal board, do we have any guitar players in the room?
I see one. Okay. There's a lot of guitarists here. Do any of you guitarists have pedal boards?
Yes? Okay. Good. A lot of people enthusiastic. Great. So for those who are not guitarists,
let me show you what I'm talking about here. Pedal boards are tools used by guitarists to
change how their guitar can sound. Each one of these little boxes here is a different effect pedal
and these get chained together so you can say I want some distortion. I'm going to click on this
with my foot. I want some chorus. I'm going to click on this with my foot. And you chain those
together in different ways. And pedal board here is actually a library that was built originally
to add audio effects to your audio. And so we called it pedal board. And it was a nice little
metaphor. But let's take a look at what that looks like in Python code instead. So let's add an
effect here using pedal board. Let's read in cool guitar.wav again. Even though I just told
you in the last section never to read the whole file in, well, I'm going to do it because this is
a demo. And here let's do from pedal board import reverb. Now reverb is an effect that makes your
audio sound like it was played in a larger space. You're kind of hearing some reverb right now in
this room. But you'll hear even more in just a second. So I can do reverb equals capital R
reverb here to create a new instance of this class. I'll set the room size to 75%. And then
I'll pass this audio into the reverb plugin by just calling it like a function. So reverb,
pass in audio, pass in the sample rate. And now I've just applied the reverb effect.
So let's listen again to a before and an after here. Here's the before.
And here's after that effect.
Hopefully you can hear that. That's definitely a different sound. It sounds like we played that
same clip in a big boomy cavern. And all we needed to do there was really apply three lines
of Python code. But it doesn't really stop there. It's rare that you want to apply a single effect
to your audio. It's much more common that you need to apply multiple effects or you want to
chain them together in some way just like those pedal boards I talked about earlier.
So pedal board has a facility for that, excuse me. And all we need to do there is create a
pedal board object and pass multiple plugins into it. So we'll start by adding a distortion plugin
which is actually doing the same thing under the hood that we wrote in Python earlier.
We can then add a delay plugin which does the same thing as we wrote in Python earlier.
And then we'll add a reverb plugin which we just heard on the last slide.
So with these three in order here, we're now able to apply the effect,
all three of these effects to the same audio all in one fell swoop. And all we need to do
is apply that to the audio by calling it like a function. And so we do that. And again,
let's listen to the before and after. So here's the clean signal going into this function.
And now with distortion and delay and reverb applied with these five lines of Python code.
So that's definitely a very noticeable effect. It's a very musical effect. It has this huge
wash of sound. And all we had to do was import these effects from pedal board and call them on
the audio data that we read in from that file. So very simple to do. But it doesn't stop there.
If you've ever dealt with audio software on your laptop or online or anything like that,
you've probably noticed that there's this vibrant community out there. All these people
that are building what are called plugins or VSTs or audio units that you can import into your
software to change your sound or to create new sounds. And pedal board actually supports
using all of those too. So let's load a third party plugin here that was not written in Python
at all. I'll do from pedal board import load plugin. We're going to open up that clean guitar
dot wave again. And then I'm going to load one of those plugins. I'll do plugin equals
load plugin. This happens to be an open source guitar pedal emulation plugin. You can find this
on GitHub. It's really, really nice. But it's also something that was designed to run in a
digital audio workstation. It's not designed to run in the Python environment here. So it's
got a UI. I can even do plugin dot show editor here and a window will pop up. And I'm able to
use my mouse to go and click on each of these knobs and turn them around and set the parameters
how I like them. But if I don't want to do that, that's okay. I can also set the values for each
of those parameters in Python code itself. So here I can print out the value that already exists
for plugin dot gain. I can set it to some new value. And I can also just pass audio into the
plugin like I did before. So I do plugin, call it like a function. Send in the audio and send in
the sample rate. And it's applied to the audio. So let's take a listen one more time to before
and after for this plugin. And just to remind you, I didn't write any Python code here for this
plugin. This is someone else's native code, probably written in C++ that I just downloaded
from the internet and imported here with load plugin. So that's the clean signal. And then once
we put it through the plugin, that actually sounds pretty good. And again, no DSP code had to be
written in Python. This is someone else's code, which is great. Okay. One more thing I want to
show off. In the past year, there's been a lot of improvements in Petalboard for doing things that
are not just audio effects. For instance, now we can host instrument effects or instrument VSDs
and instrument plugins. For those who know audio software, that's a very, very different paradigm.
We're not just changing the audio. We're instead creating new audio by passing in MIDI notes and
telling the computer what to play at what time. So let's see that in less than 10 lines of code
here. Let's load a plugin here called magical 8-bit plug, which is an 8-bit synthesizer plugin
that emulates the sounds of old Nintendo video games from the 80s. And I've just loaded that
instrument. I can open its window again here by using show editor. And we can see, yes, that is
a different plugin there. Then instead of passing audio in, I'm going to have to pass in a list of
notes or messages. So here I'll do notes equals this list of MIDI notes. These correspond with C,
E, G, B, you know, musical notes. And I'll change those into MIDI messages here. So I'll send on and
off messages for each of those notes to say here's when you should start playing this note and here's
when you should stop playing this note. Then I'll open up an audio file to write to and I'll render
those notes by just passing them in like a function to the instrument and passing the output of that
into F dot write. And here's what that sounds like. So we just invoked a third-party plugin. We didn't
write any of that rendering code ourselves. And that was less than 10 lines of Python.
Okay. So I've got about one minute left. So I'm going to spend that last minute on a bonus round
here. Some advanced pedal board topics for anybody who is curious about audio or deals with it day
to day. Some really cool things that you can do in pedal board that you might not have expected
or might not have thought about. So so far in this talk, we've been opening audio files by using the
audio file constructor here or the audio file function. And that's great. But it's very common
for you to need to open an audio file and then read it in at a different sample rate than it was
saved as. So instead of maybe 44,000 or sorry, 44 kilohertz, you might need to add 22 kilohertz
or something like that. Well, pedal board lets you do that by just adding a little addition on
the end of the call here. You can do dot resample two and it will give you a file pointer that
behaves as if the file was saved with a different sample rate altogether. This is super useful. We
use this all the time at Spotify. Extremely performant and extremely useful in production
situations. On top of that, though, let's say you want to take some audio and time stretch it. You
want to change how long it is or how fast or slow it is without changing its pitch or vice versa.
You want to change its pitch, but you don't want to change how fast it's playing back. Well,
all you need to do is from pedal board import time stretch, call this function with your audio,
set the appropriate parameters, and you get the results there. Huge shout out to Chris Canham,
a breakfast key for implementing the rubber band time stretcher that we use here. It sounds great.
And one last thing, all of the functions you've seen so far have been talking to files on disk,
but you can also pass in file-like objects here. So you can render to a bytes IO buffer,
you can render to a network stream. Doesn't matter. It's all available right there in your
audio file constructor. So I barely scratched the surface here. You can find it a lot more on
GitHub at github.com slash Spotify slash pedal board. And I also have five minutes for questions,
so please feel free to use the Slido to submit some questions and find me after the talk to
grab some stickers of this cool pedal board logo. Thank you so much by Dexis.
Awesome. Thank you, Peter. I'm intrigued. I'm not a guitar player, not a musician, but now
I'm inspired. I've got a stack of questions, so let's walk through some of these while they're
getting set up for the next talk. First question, can pedal board work on live audio like a real
pedal board would? That's a very good question. So we got this question so much that I actually
put together a new feature in pedal board that does allow you to use it on live audio,
actually just for a demo last year. It is now merged in and you can use it with some restrictions.
Look for the audio stream class online in the documentation if you want to use that.
That's awesome. We're going to unplug you here. Okay. And if you want to grab the hand mic or
pull that one out. Okay. So next question. Any reason, let me think about this. Is there any
reason for a stream not to just always use a chunk size of one? That's a great question. So
you could use a chunk size of one if you're processing audio like this. At that point,
the overhead of reading each chunk starts to dominate the runtime. So a larger chunk size
will allow you to be a bit faster, but it'll use more memory. So there's always a sweet spot in
there between processing speed and memory use. Where do you find that sweet spot? Does it depend
on sample rate, I guess? It depends on the sample rate, depends on the machine that you're using.
If you've got lots and lots of memory like on the server, you'd choose tens of megabytes maybe
for your buffer. If you're working in an embedded environment, maybe something much smaller than that.
Gotcha. Makes sense. Next, why choose Pedalboard over like a traditional DAW like Audacity or
Bandcamp? Yeah. Traditional DAWs are really great tools and they're very good at allowing you to
work with audio visually. Pedalboard is much more scriptable and much more easy to get integrated
into your own software. Okay, cool. Do you want to talk for a minute about the API design process
for the package? And did it start as open source or did that come out later? Great question. So
I'll tackle the second part first. Pedalboard was not open source to start with. It came from
internal needs that we had at Spotify. And then we realized, oh, we built a tool here that many
people could use and we kept adding more and more to it. But for the API design process,
I really came up with a lot of ideas from what you saw in Lin Root's talk earlier about how to
lean on familiarity when designing an API. So it tries to be as Pythonic as possible. And the idea
is that if you know Python, all you need to do is swap out a couple of functions and everything
behaves like you would expect. Yeah. I love the structure of opening it as a file and treating
it like that normal file context. That's pretty smooth. You showed down sampling. Is it possible
to upsample? It is also possible to upsample. If you do upsample, there's no additional detail
that will be added to the sound, though. Fair enough. Last one that I think, Josh,
were you about ready? Does it use FFmpeg internally? I like FFmpeg, actually. But it
does not use FFmpeg at all internally. It's all completely compiled code. There are no external
dependencies. You just pip install it and it works. Fair enough. You good? All right. Once
again, thank you, Peter. Thank you.