We have Jessica Ross from Optimizely, one of our gracious sponsors, and she's going to tell us a little bit about her personal journey as it's developed.
Hi, thanks for coming. My name is Jessica Ross McKinney, and I'm a software engineer at Optimizely.
I want to take this time to tell you about some formative experiences I've had as a female minority engineer, and ways that you, if you're in a situation like this, can mitigate them.
And I also hope that I can convince you that these things that I'm going to tell you about, they're real, and they're actually problems, and that you, whether you're actually a minority or a woman or just an ally, there are things you can do.
So, the things I wanted to talk about, I want to give you some more background about me, and then I want to talk about some three big things that have really affected my journey as an engineer.
Bro culture, sexism, and microaggressions, and then what you can do to help as an ally or even another person.
So, about me, I'm a senior software engineer at Optimizely. I have a BS, computer engineering and mathematics major that I don't really use.
I'm a huge Python fanatic. I've been using it since Python 2.1, and I can't seem to just leave it behind entirely.
I also work with other languages like JavaScript, Ruby, Ecolang.
I generally work with small to medium startups, so maybe these things are really more problems there where there may or may not be an HR department, but for fun, I power lift, I make artwork, and I rescue small dogs, like dachshunds.
So, the first thing I want to talk about is bro culture. Anybody work at a bro culture? Nobody? Okay, it's amazing.
They usually occur at smaller startups. Bro culture is dominated by hyper masculine macho exclusionary culture dominated by men.
I don't know if it's intentionally exclusionary, but it can work out that way if you're not like that.
It's generally characterized by a lot of open drug and alcohol use, a lot of partying, some inappropriate discussions during work, as well as exclusionary social tactics like,
oh, just these people go over here and talk about work without roping in the rest of engineering.
This is actually a pretty pervasive thing, something like 90% of women who have been in tech as long as I have have reported saying something like this.
Before I throw this company that I'm about to talk to under the bus, I would like to say that this place was a really amazing experience for me.
I worked there for two years. I had two different people who were majorly jockeying for me and for my interests.
I met a lot of lifelong friends, people I still talk to a year and a half later for meeting them, as well as this particular company had a pretty good diversity balance on their engineering team.
Three females, another black person, a bunch of Latino people, so it was really good.
That said, this particular place had an open liquor closet, not like a liquor cabinet, a liquor closet that was big enough to walk in through, and it actually also held a server rack.
That's how big it was. It's open all the time. People just went in there and got beer, went to the bar, went to the bar and drank beer.
It actually also held a server rack. That's how big it was. It's open all the time. People just went in there and got beer, whatever, vodka, whatever they want.
In addition to this, there is also some casual sexism in how people who weren't in engineering treated women. I don't know how to explain this, but can you not hear me?
No, it's your slides.
Oh, horrible. I wonder if the slide changed or anything.
There's just some sexism in the form of objectification, just looking at people like they weren't real people or real employees.
Another problem I had with this particular company is offsides and inappropriate behavior that happened at the offsides.
We'd have these multiple day strategy or team building excursions. Sure, we would do the strategy and team building during the day, but at night it would just devolve into binge drinking and marijuana smoking.
There's a time and a place for that, but I don't think it is at a company sanctioned event.
The same place also had Christmas parties in buses loaded up with different types of booze. I think the big thing was Fireball. It's a big thing that they used.
In addition to this, there's a different party that was a lot more sane than these booze bus parties, where there was an engineer who was passing out Molly for an after party.
So, not that appropriate.
Finally, this is more of the exclusionary part. Roughly half of engineering had a group text, and apparently these people were friends, but also there are a lot of engineering emergency and other things that are relevant to work that were discussed over this.
I was lucky, and I was actually part of that, so it's not that bad to me, but it's still exclusionary.
The last thing that happened at this place is that there tended to be really inappropriate meetings.
We would have an official engineering meeting, and we would talk about what we were going to talk about, and then we'd BS afterwards, and the BS would turn into talk of things like sugar babies or hookers.
The company was mixed. There were three women in this, so that was extremely uncomfortable.
Anyway, I was kind of complicit in working here because I didn't really try to stop much of anything except for that last example.
I also picked up a lot of bad habits. I noticed after leaving that job, I drank a whole lot less.
Anyways, if you're in this sort of situation, what you can do is you can call out this inappropriate behavior whenever you see it.
It might be difficult to talk to somebody who's at a higher level than you, who supervises you or something, but it really needs to be known.
You can talk to other leadership, like go up higher than the person who's doing the inappropriate behavior.
The big thing you can do is not participate in the boringness, like I did, and advocate for more women and minorities in leadership.
These sorts of things tend not to happen in places where there are alternate perspectives on things. Does that make sense?
Another thing I dealt with was a lot of sexism, being spoken over, having my ideas stolen right before I state them, some questions about my competence,
as well as being referred to as aggressive while doing behavior that would get a male labeled as assertive or a go-getter.
Stories.
There's a particular person at another job that I worked at who would talk over me all the time.
When I was able to get a word in, I would talk, and then there would be silence, and then he would rephrase what I said, and then everyone would agree.
It was really, really bizarre. I had to talk to my manager to understand that I wasn't just in the twilight zone or something. It was actually a thing.
What I ended up doing...actually, I'll tell you about this other thing. As far as being assumed to be less confident, I remember there was a person who I'm going to refer to as M who attacked every design decision I made.
He blew up all of my PRs, and sometimes he was right because he was actually an excellent engineer, but oftentimes I was right, and it just didn't need to be a thing.
Another example of that is I was working on switching a bash script to being a Python script so it was much easier for other people to read.
I got buy-in from other engineers on my team about how to do this, and so I submitted a PR, and that particular person said, this is a good start, but why don't you write it in pure Python?
It was a script-wrapping PG jump and P SQL. Why would I do that in pure Python?
I handled all these differently. With the guy who was attacking all my decisions, I ended up making an effort to know him as a person and let him know how I felt in ways other than what I showed when he would do this to me.
I feel like that worked out really well because he's a human being and a great engineer and also really fun to play board games with.
With that other guy who used to talk over me, I ended up leaving the company because he never really accepted that he was a problem, and management didn't do anything about it.
To fix this, there are a lot of things you can do. Just let people know how you feel is probably the biggest thing you can do, and if they continue doing it, you can get other engineers to call that person out when they do things like that.
My engineering manager at this one place that I can't name, every time that person who kept talking over me and stealing my ideas did that, he would say, that's what she said. I really appreciate that. That's a really validating thing.
If you're anticipating a fight on your design decisions, you should come up with really, really good arguments for your design decision and come up with a couple of arguments as high as you have to. There's no reason why you should have to live like that.
Also, it says sexism, but this is not a woman only thing, so if this applies to you, this is what you can do.
This effectively washes out to, we didn't hire this person because they're old. This company was relatively young. I was one of the oldest people there at 32.
Also, assumptions about who developers are, what they look like. Generally, what do you think of when you think of a software developer? Anybody in the audience?
Yeah, so a dude, white or Asian, nerdy, gamer, things like that. That's just not how developers are as a whole.
This is a picture of my husband. He looks like a developer. No one ever mistakes him for not being a developer. People see me and they think I'm in sales or marketing because black women don't go into software development.
To get rid of this, there's really not a lot to do because it's implicit and people are often unaware that they're doing this. Even I am guilty of these things sometimes.
If you see this, you can call out that behavior and let that person know this is not appropriate. This is what you said implies. This decision seems kind of fishy.
Then you can educate others about the fact that implicit bias exists. I think that's really important. Even I'm guilty.
Finally, I'm going to talk about microaggressions. Microaggressions are kind of everyday, minor, slight insults, things like that, that are sent to women and minorities. This could be things you say, attitudes you have, decisions you make.
I have a really white sounding name and I have a really white sounding voice. People will generally do that when they hear me on the phone. There have been a couple of times I've come into interviews and the person who's interviewing me is taken aback by the fact that I'm not white.
That feels really bad. Another thing that's happened, multiple times I've heard people say, we should hire the most qualified in response to being told about diversity initiatives. What do you guys think that implies?
Yes, that we're hiring people just because of those special attributes, not because they're actually qualified. Another thing that's happened a lot to me is that people ask me to be a representative of my race or my gender.
I think these groups of people are individuals or groups of individuals. I don't think there is somebody who can speak for all.
In order to hiring the most qualified person, there are occasionally questions about how someone got their job. If you're the only woman on an engineering team, why did we hire this particular person? I bet there's a more qualified dude.
At night, there's some heterocentric things that people do sometimes like ask about opposite sex partners or kids when there are people who don't have opposite sex partners or kids. It kind of implies that you are not normal because you're not in a relationship like that or you don't have kids.
To address these, these are really similar to implicit bias and maybe they are things that happen in response to implicit bias, but whenever you hear somebody do that to you or react to you like that, you should let them know. Let them know what they did and what it implies and how it made you feel so they don't do it against someone else.
At the same time, give them the benefit of the doubt because I don't think anybody intentionally says things like this. I think it's just like, oh, I'm in my world. This is how things are and I'm going to say this in response to how I see things.
Here's what you can do to help. You don't have to be a woman or minority or anything. You can be any sort of person. You should be a mentor or not a mentor, a sponsor for somebody. Sponsoring is different from mentoring in that a mentor will help you in your career. A sponsor will actively try to put you forward or advocate for you.
I had two people in different stages of my life that worked for me like that and it made all the difference. This one place, the Bro place where I had the sponsors, I made more career progress in two years than I had in the seven years previous, if that tells you anything.
Sometimes you don't have enough power to be a sponsor, then you should be a mentor. If you're a senior level engineer, you could mentor a middle level or junior level engineer or even a high schooler, which is better.
Finally, be aware of your unconscious bias. Everyone has them. Just think, how can other people be different from me? Why do I do these particular things? I've been saying this over and over again, but when you see some problematic behavior, you should call it out. You should let people know that this is happening.
If it's somebody that's a supervisor of yours and you can't directly speak to them, you could go above them and just let it be known that this is happening and this is a problem. A lot of women just let this stuff slide.
I let this stuff slide for a long time just because women are socialized not to stir the pot. That's basically all my talk. I left some things out, but that's okay.
On the right here, I have some resources that you can read to understand more about what happens to women and minorities in tech. On the left, I have my contact information. You can message me at deathweasel on Twitter, my GitHub is deathweaselx86, and my email is just at deathweasel.io. Please don't give that to spammers. It's the best email address I've ever had.
That's all of my talk, unless you people have questions.