Here is Belinda Venom.
She's going to tell us about Cloud Made Simple
with Serverless Python.
Let's give her a round of applause.
Woo!
Thank you.
Thanks.
Can you guys hear me?
OK, perfect.
So my name is Belinda Venom.
I'm a developer advocate and software developer at IBM.
Right now, my current focus is on both Cloud and Serverless.
Prior to this role, I was a software developer
on the IBM Cloud Functions project, which
is based on top of Apache Open.
Oh, it's kind of coming in.
Based on top of Apache OpenLisk.
So who here has heard of Serverless?
OK, cool, less people.
Is anyone using Serverless in their projects?
OK, so less people.
Anyone like projects in production with Serverless?
OK, so same people.
Awesome.
Today, we're going to talk about some
of the benefits of Serverless.
And then we'll also check out a real life use case.
And then I'll show you guys a quick demo
of running some Python code on a Serverless platform.
OK, cool.
So let's say I've been working on a project,
and I'm ready to play my code out to the cloud.
In the past, me or someone else in my company
might have needed to purchase bare metal servers
to run my application on.
You have to manage the security updates for the servers,
install all the required software,
and keep the hardware up to date.
Then virtual machines came into the picture, right?
We were able to let someone else, like Amazon or Rackspace,
start to manage those machines for us,
and we just get a virtual machine
to run our application on.
You'd still have to manage the operating system
and the software dependencies of your application,
but you didn't need to physically own or house
those servers anymore.
Even more recently, we've had containers enter the scene
where we're only managing the application code
and its dependencies.
We package everything up into a container.
We give that container to the platform to be run.
So that made things a lot easier,
but we're still managing some of the infrastructure there.
We need to manage our own runtime
and our own application dependencies.
Building a container to run your application on
is still a somewhat manual process
that could still be abstracted away.
So software developers really need to focus
on that core business logic
and not get distracted by infrastructure management
or configuration.
And these abstractions are ultimately what serverless
or functions as a service offerings are promising you.
So the execution environment for the code
is provided for me as a developer,
and my code can just be run in response to events
or in response to actions that I care about.
So I should note, I'm positing this as an evolution,
but all these models are still available today,
and they might even still be the right choice,
depending on what problem you're trying to solve
or what your requirements are.
So you'll notice on the x-axis,
it says decreasing concern over your stack implementation,
but it's also decreasing control.
So if there's a security vulnerability
or an environment update that you need to make,
you have to wait for the platform provider
to make that required environment update.
So if you need that additional control,
one of the others might still be the right option for you.
I'm gonna get this over.
So I think this is a really,
just another nice way to visualize
the increasing levels of abstraction.
So as we're moving through each of the deployment models,
we're seeing less and less
that the end user's responsible for.
So on the far left, we have on-prem,
where you have your own machines
and you're managing everything,
and then we go through infrastructure as a service,
platform as a service,
and then ultimately functions as a service,
where you literally only write, manage,
and deal with functions.
So these changing deployment models
have also affected how we write
and think about our application.
We used to write code as these big monolithic applications.
The entire application gets deployed as one unit,
and introducing any new code changes
means a completely new deployment of the full application,
even if you're only changing one or two lines.
So from there, we moved more to this microservices paradigm.
We started to break that monolithic application
into various services
that are communicating with each other over RESTful APIs.
In a store application, for example,
you might have a microservice
that manages the accounts for your users,
one for placing orders,
and one for maybe managing interactions
with your shipping company.
So you could deploy each of those microservices
either as an application on a pad solution,
like a platform as a service solution,
or maybe you deploy each one of those microservices
into their own containers.
And then finally, as we've moved more towards
the service model, there's been further decoupling
and shrinking of the size of the unit of code.
So instead of creating microservices,
we can literally just write functions
that we wanna deploy to the cloud.
And each of those functions have the goal
of doing one thing and doing that one thing really well,
perhaps in reaction to a particular event.
So as we said, Serverless promises
that you can just spend your time writing business logic
that has a direct positive impact to your users
and not focus on that configuration or management events.
Even though it's called Serverless,
yes, there are servers,
but the idea is you don't have to see them
or deal with them.
So from a developer's perspective,
the functions as a service platform
is gonna provide a runtime and an execution environment
for the code that they're writing.
So you just write the code,
and then the Serverless platform runs it for you
in the cloud on demand and within milliseconds.
And this may be actually abstracted away from you,
so you typically won't see it,
but usually what's happening under the covers
is that the code is ultimately being run on a container
in the cloud provider's environment.
So one of the goals of Serverless
is to provide developers with scalability out of the box.
So let's say that you have a set of APIs,
and you've represented each of those API endpoints
as different functions.
Maybe suddenly your app gets featured on Reddit,
you have millions of requests from your UI
to these backend API endpoints.
The only thing that's gonna happen
is that the platform will start up multiple instances
of the backend API code
to process those requests in parallel.
And it kinda gives you that horizontal scaling for free
without any additional programming
or server management from you.
So we talked about your code scaling out
or up to end instances when it's required,
but it also scales back down to zero
when it's not being used.
So what that means from an app developer's perspective
is that you're not paying for the time
that your code is not being run.
So you're only charged for the amount of time
that your code is actively running or doing some work.
So you're no longer paying for that idle time.
You have to do the testing for your particular scenario,
but this can actually mean really big cost savings
compared to having a server up 100% of the time.
So it really just depends on the project,
it depends on the workload,
but it can be really good cost savings.
Other promises, most serverless solutions provide support
for some kind of event-driven scenario.
So this is literally anything where an event happens
and you wanna react to that by some code.
Some examples, like maybe you have a new user
who signs up to your app,
and that results in their information being stored
in your customer's database,
and then you wanna execute some logic
in response to that new database item.
So maybe send them a welcome email
or do some processing of their input data.
You could have like a user uploads an image to the app,
maybe you wanna generate a thumbnail
as soon as that image is stored in your object store.
And you can do other things,
sentiment analysis on text that a user has input,
literally anything you just want your code
to react to a particular event.
So typically, serverless platforms are gonna provide
that infrastructure for you to easily react
to those events with your code.
So many of the cloud platforms offer
a number of different services you can integrate
with your applications.
So these are things like artificial intelligence,
IoT platforms, object storage, or databases.
So think of some of the things you can do
if you connect up with, like I'm writing them,
so the Watson APIs, or maybe the Alexa APIs from Amazon.
You're using those in conjunction with your application.
Most of the serverless solutions provided
by the various cloud providers really wanna make
that connection very seamless.
Like they're really incentivized for you to go off
and use their other services, right?
So if you're using their platform,
they wanna make it super easy for you to connect up
with their various services.
So I think as you're looking at maybe moving some workloads
over to serverless, definitely look into
what integrations are provided.
See what other services you can easily
and seamlessly connect up to and react to.
So ultimately, all of these promises are trying
to achieve this overarching goal
of decreased time to market.
And they're all attempting to help developers focus
on just business value and their value to the users
and not on infrastructure or configuration.
I really like this quote from serverless.com.
It says, serverless abstracts away the most menial parts
of building an application, leaving developers free
to actually spend their days coding.
So I think that's kind of the dream of serverless
that people are hoping to realize.
So there's a few use cases that are emerging
as really a nice fit for the serverless space.
First one is web application backends.
So you have a front end and it's making some calls
to some backend APIs.
Each of those endpoints for your APIs can be functions
that are created in a serverless platform.
A mobile backend super similar
to the web application use case,
except the front end is mobile.
Internet of things, so just because a lot
of the serverless platforms can help you connect up
with some kind of IoT platform on the provider's cloud.
Scheduled tasks, so let's say you maybe have some code
that you wanna run once a week or maybe once a month.
You can set up a chronological trigger for that code
to be spun up on maybe Wednesdays to run.
And then after it finishes, it spins back down.
You're no longer being charged for those resources
that are being used.
So you don't have to have the server up all week
just to run that code once a week.
Conversational scenarios, so this is things
like chat clients where you maybe wanna do
some additional processing on the chats
that are coming through.
So like maybe translating the text
or filtering out bad words
or doing some other processing on that text.
And then finally, data processing.
So this is literally anything where you get that new item
in your data store and you wanna react to that
with some kind of processing.
So this can be things like normalizing audio inputs,
image resizing, address verification, anything like that.
So today, I wanted to quickly check out
a real life use case on a mobile backend architecture
so you can kind of start to get an idea
for how you might architect your serverless apps.
So the application I'm gonna talk about
is called Weather Gods.
It's this kind of cool, creative way
for people to interact with the weather.
I think it's like 2.99 on the app store.
And they have this kind of creative way
to interact with the weather.
So the weather is represented as various gods.
So there's like a fire god for heat,
there's an ice god for winter weather,
water god for rain and precipitation, et cetera.
I think there's like six gods.
Maybe I can't keep up with them all.
But users can click through the various weather events
or they can subscribe to specific notifications.
So I actually used to live here in Austin.
So when I was living here, I think it's pretty unlikely
that I would subscribe to notifications for high UV
since that's basically all the time.
It was always high here.
But downtown where I lived,
there would sometimes be flooding issues
or sometimes there would be like hail here.
So I'd probably go ahead and subscribe
to like water god notifications or ice god notifications.
That's kind of how the app works.
This is the architecture for how they did their backend.
Obviously they have a mobile front end
that interacts with this backend,
which isn't pictured there.
Oh no, actually this is over on the right.
So each of the little green functions
are the functions that they created.
I'll kind of quickly walk you guys through this
and then we'll take a step back
to talk about why they chose serverless.
So the first thing that happens
is they have this chronological trigger
that's gonna query a subset of their users
which are stored in a Couch NoSQL DB.
And then the group scanner action
is gonna determine the locations and weather conditions
that those particular users are interested in.
Then the next action is just a weather checker
and that makes a call out
to the weather channel data service,
parses and handles the data that it gets back,
gets it into the right format for their next action
and goes ahead and writes that into the weather database.
And then as weather gets updated into the database,
that will trigger a scanner for each user
that's interested in that particular type of data.
So let's say a user's interested in snow in New York
and rain in Austin,
only those two scanners are invoked
for that particular user.
The scanners are run in parallel
so that gives them some performance benefits
and then of course they're also able to scale up
and back down independently.
And then once the scanner finds interesting data
for the user, it'll send a notification
using the push notification service.
So what about this architecture makes it
a really nice fit for serverless?
There's a few different points I wanna highlight.
Integrated platform services,
so they were able to really easily consume
some services from their cloud platform.
In this case, a notification service,
a database as a service and the weather company data API.
So those are all pieces of their app
but they don't have to wait,
they're just consuming some services.
They were also able to regularly schedule their code
to run in reaction to a trigger every three minutes.
A bunch of their code was running in reaction to events.
So they want to run weather checks
when a new user location is updated,
they wanted to react to new users in their database
and of course whenever there's a new weather item
of interest, they wanna react to that as well.
And then finally they had the really nice scanner section
where the code could be executed in parallel
and independently.
So if a ton of their users are only interested in rain,
then that rain scanner code can be scaled up
independently of the other events.
Alternatively, let's say no one's interested
in a particular weather event,
that code's not being called
as ultimately they're not being charged for it.
So finding those elements of your application
where you can really benefit from running in parallel
and scaling out independently can make a good use case
for serverless for that particular piece.
And then the last thing I wanted to highlight
about weather gods in particular
is that they didn't actually start out
as a fully serverless backend like this.
They already had their item and they realized,
okay, certain pieces of this would actually benefit
from being run on a serverless platform
and so they kind of transitioned those elements over
piece by piece as it made sense for them.
So let's say you're ready to write your next serverless app,
how do you get started?
So you have some options.
These are some of the major players in this space
and listed them in alphabetical order.
So the first one is Azure Functions from Microsoft.
They have a Python runtime, but it's currently in preview.
So it hasn't fully become general availability yet,
but I would assume that because it's in preview,
they're heading in that direction.
Lambda from Amazon supports Python out of the box.
Apache OpenWhisk.
So this is an open source Apache incubator project
and this would be really nice
maybe if you need something open source
or you want to host and manage your own instance
of a serverless platform for the rest of your company.
IBM Cloud Functions is based on OpenWhisk
and it's basically just managed and hosted
OpenWhisk on IBM Cloud.
And it also supports Python out of the box
and this is the one that we'll check out
in a demo in a couple of minutes.
And then finally, I know a little less about it,
but I think it would be interesting
to check out Python Anywhere.
So I did a few minutes just kind of checking it out
and playing with it.
It seems like it's a little more focused
on web hosting and education use cases,
but I think it's just kind of a good one
to highlight and check out.
So let's take a quick peek
at what a function might look like.
You can see a really simple example up here.
It should look familiar.
It looks like Python code.
So it's a straightforward hello world function
and it's just gonna check and see
if it got name passed in as a parameter.
If not, it'll return hello stranger.
Otherwise, it's gonna return hello
with the name that was passed in.
So for OpenWhisk and IBM Cloud Functions,
the expected input and output is JSON.
So you can tie your various functions together with JSON.
So let's say you have three functions in a sequence.
The first one outputs some JSON.
That'll be the input for the next one.
That'll output some JSON,
which will be the input for the next one.
So that's how you kind of tie them together.
And then the expected entry point
is just a function named main.
So you can have other functions defined in the file,
but main is the expected entry point.
So we'll see kind of a quick live demo of this in action.
Like I said, I'll be using IBM Cloud Functions,
which is managed OpenWhisk.
You can really take these and apply it
to any serverless platform you want.
So it should look and feel very similar
to a lot of the other serverless platforms.
So for our example, we'll say we have this image.
It's a really cute puppy image.
And we'll say that it's getting uploaded
to our cloud object storage or database
from a mobile app or UI.
And we wanna react to this uploaded image
by running some code.
So in our case, maybe we wanna do some image analysis.
So what's actually in the image?
So if we upload this really cute puppy picture,
we wanna see some output like Bernie's mountain dog
or dog or animal.
So this is an architecture diagram
for how we might create something like this.
When there's a new image URL that's uploaded
into the database, that should trigger an action to get run.
In this case, I divided that action
into two separate functions.
So one function is responsible for reading the changes
that occurred in the database.
That's the read changes from db action.
And then that action will parse the changes,
output the URL to a new image in the database,
and then hand that URL off to the get tags action.
So then the get tags action will actually make a call out
to a visual recognition service,
do some parsing of the return value,
and hopefully output what it believes is in our image.
So this is a really simple use case,
but you could definitely continue building on this, right?
You could save tags back into the database.
You could add an action for compressing
a really large image if you use
or upload something too large.
You could do things like handling video uploads
by creating another function that breaks apart the video
into multiple frames, and then running the get tags
on each frame, and that would be able to scale up
kind of independently.
Each of my functions gets scaling out of the box,
so I don't have to do anything special.
So let's check this out.
This is gonna be live, so fingers crossed.
So this is just our get tags action
that I talked about earlier.
Should look super familiar,
just some Python code that we have.
And I'm gonna kinda walk through a couple pieces of it.
So the first thing that's happening
is we're gonna pull in this Visual Recognition SDK.
So what that should imply to you
is that Visual Recognition SDK
is provided as a part of the runtime,
so it's just already there in the runtime.
And then we're gonna do a couple of things.
I need to instantiate that with an API key
and a version number.
The API key will actually pull in
from parameters for this action,
so we should be able to pass in parameters into our action.
In this particular case, that API key doesn't change,
so I can actually store it as a stored parameter
for this particular action.
So if we click on parameters,
you see, okay, I've got this API key that's stored in here
and it'll just be safe for that action.
I'll make sure I revoke that right after this.
And then the next thing is
that we'll wanna pass in an image URL,
so that's the image that we wanna get the tags for.
And then finally, we'll make a call out to that
visualrecognition.classify right here.
And then we'll just do a little bit of parsing
the return data, because it has some info in there
that we don't care about,
and then we'll print out the tags.
So let's try that out.
This is our little puppy picture, so it's cute.
And if we do change input,
we can go in here and make sure
we have that image in there, and it is,
so we can click apply.
So we're passing this in as a parameter.
And then if we click invoke, we should hopefully see, yes.
So we see some tags back.
So it says puppy, dog, laboratory retriever dog,
retriever dog, golden retriever dog,
so just some different tags
of what the visual recognition service thinks
is in that image.
But that's not all we want it to do.
We actually said we want it to react to the image
when there's a new image stored in the database, right?
So let's see how we set that up.
This is inside of a sequence,
and that sequence contains two actions.
So there's the read from database action,
and then there's the get tags action.
And so the sequence gets kicked off by a trigger.
So if we go back and connect to triggers,
we can see, okay, there's this cloud image trigger.
So anytime a new item gets added to the cloud database,
then that trigger will be fired.
So let's try that out really quick.
So I'll grab this image,
and then I already have cloud open.
Oh, it wants me to log in again.
So you can see I already have a database created
called my image URLs.
I can create a new document in here.
So I'm just gonna create image URL,
and I'm trying to fly because I have five minutes left.
And then I'll just click create document.
And then what that's gonna do hopefully
is cause my trigger to fire,
which will then kick off that sequence.
The first action was to read from the cloud database
whatever changes happen,
and then the second action was to get the tags.
So if we go over here,
and then go over to the little monitor tab,
hopefully we should see that it was called.
Yeah, and so at 11 o'clock,
we can see, I don't know how to make this bigger,
but we can see that the trigger was fired at 11.
There was a sequence that was called,
and then the read action,
and then they get tags action.
And each action has an activation ID associated with it.
So if we click that activation ID,
we should be able to see the results in there.
So we have the logs, just the printing out,
and then of course the various tags.
That's just a little bit,
and actually, yay, that worked, live demo.
I always get nervous.
Oh, let me stop mirroring.
Okay, perfect.
So I don't have too much time left,
but I did wanna quickly highlight,
I wanted to highlight
one of the Python-specific libraries that's out there.
It's called Pyren.
So what it does, it has this goal of making a really easy
push-to-cloud experience for Python developers.
So maybe if you have a super parallel workload,
and a parallel workload is something
where you have little or no effort
that's needed to separate the problem
into these number of parallel tasks.
So common examples might be like 3D video rendering,
handled by GPU, where you want to run some code
for each frame, or maybe for each pixel
if you're doing ray tracing,
and those can all be handled
without any interdependency between them.
So Pyren is this library
where you can take your Python workloads,
scale it out into multiple functions
to be run on a serverless platform.
So really their goal, like I said,
is to simplify that push-to-cloud experience,
and you can run your algorithm
against a cluster of machines
without needing to figure out how do I set that up,
or how do I have those machines talk to each other,
how do I get the results back.
Pyren was originally built for Amazon Lambda,
and it's also available for IBM Cloud Functions,
so go check out this article to learn a little bit more.
It talks about using Pyren for scenarios
where you have a lot of data processing to do.
And the two examples they talk about
were the really large data sets like solar flares,
which can help predict storms
that can hamper power or satellite operations,
and then they also talked about
just the sheer volume of data
when looking at how neurons combine
to create behaviors or disease or cognition,
and their big goal is to really easily give access
to parallel computing to data scientists and others.
There's another article you can check out.
Like I said, it's built for Amazon Lambda
and has recently been ported to IBM Cloud Functions.
So this article is about using Pyren
for running stock market predictions
through the money car loan method.
So it uses Pyren to scale out
and then combine the results
from those simultaneously running predictions.
So that's all I had, just a couple of quick notes.
You can go check out IBM Cloud Functions.
The first link, and then the last link
is for the Apache OpenList project.
So if you're looking for a new open source project
to be a contributor on, it's a really fun one.
The community is really nice.
So that's all.
Thank you so much.
Thank you.