Because the user sent in bad data, the application can error
before it even gets to the database, possibly tell the
user something a little bit more useful in terms of what
they did wrong if they're using an API.
And then there's a lot of simple patterns that just come
with the ORM that make it easy to build out a
new application quickly.
That's why things like Django and Rails and stuff are so
popular, because you can type a few things in and you get
an application really fast.
And that's definitely really cool.
But there are other ways to get at this.
So I wrote functional composition here, but even
object composition is good, generally better than
inheritance, not always, but generally.
Being able to compose things makes things more flexible.
It also lets you hide things.
So instead of a subclass, you contain a class.
You can hide that class from the external world.
And you can trust that I've got my model class, but only
my model class can talk to the database.
Nobody else can talk to the database.
And I don't have to worry about queries leaking in
somewhere I wasn't expecting or things like that.
So composition is a great tool for abstracting away
complexity that you don't need to know about in the
function you're writing or in the module you're writing.
There's a lot of built-in data structures in Python that
provide a lot of these, have a lot of power to them.
You can also, like I said, you can just write a class.
You can build your own class hierarchy, et cetera.
There's one more thing, which is going to be the main focus
of my talk that you can use, and that is MyPy.
So talks about MyPy, talks about ORMs, what do they have
to do with each other?
They actually have nothing to do with each other.
MyPy has nothing to do with databases.
MyPy is a static type checker.
Has anybody used MyPy?
Mostly on that side of the room, OK?
A few people back there.
So it's a static type checker.
You can use it to tell.
It will tell you if you're doing something wrong in your
Python code without actually running your Python code.
And it uses type annotations.
If you're using a version of Python that supports type
annotations in the syntax, alternatively, you can run it
against old code, you can run it against Python 2 code, and
you do your type annotations in comments, and it can parse
the comments out and figure out the types.
So let's show off a little bit of what it's
going to look like.
So I'm going to open up a file here.
Sure.
Nope, hitting the wrong character.
So I'm going to write a function, and I'm going to
annotate its type.
So this is just from the MyPy example.
So we see what it is.
I've got greeting.
It's going to take some name.
We're going to give it a type, which is a string.
The colon means this is its type.
And then the function has a return type, and that's what
the arrow means.
This is what it's going to return.
It's also going to return a string.
And there we go.
So right now, there's no errors because the function
isn't actually doing anything.
Even though if you call this function, it would return none.
MyPy is saying, that's OK.
You haven't actually written anything yet.
If I return an integer, it will tell me incompatible
return type.
I expected a string, but I got an integer.
You're doing something wrong.
I can say, OK, well, how about just saying hello?
And it says, OK, cool.
One thing to note here is that I'm taking the name.
I'm not doing anything with the name.
That's probably not what I intended.
MyPy is good at checking to make sure that you're handling
conditions, that you're not accessing things that aren't
there, stuff like that.
What it can't do is tell you if you're doing the right thing,
because it doesn't know what the right thing is.
So there's a lot of discussion about types and tests and
which is better.
You really kind of need both if you want to be really
confident that your code is working correctly.
So it's not a replacement for writing unit tests, but I do
find that it's helpful for guiding you, saying, hey, you
forgot about this case.
Maybe you need to handle this case.
Probably want to test to say that the right thing happens
in that case, but it will at least tell you that you handle
the case, you don't handle the case.
So here, similarly, if I say hello plus five, it's going to
say, I can't do that, because you can't add strings and
numbers, but if I say hello plus name, it's totally fine.
So down here, I just have my editor telling me what's
wrong with the current file I'm working on.
So let's start using MyPy instead of an ORM.
So the very first thing we want to do is
define sort of our model.
I'm going to use something called a typed dictionary.
It comes from MyPy type extensions.
I think at some point in the future, this is going to be
merged into the standard typing module, but for now,
it's in an extension while they're sort of
solidifying the API.
I'm going to define, let's say we're building an application
for dealing with books, because books are really
cool and modern, et cetera.
So I'm going to use a typed dictionary.
A typed dictionary is just, it says, look, at runtime
represent this object as just a dictionary, but I want to say
what attributes it has to have and what types those
attributes are.
And so books have authors.
Sure.
And they've got titles.
OK, so there we go.
I should probably type out the code correctly every time.
OK, so that's useful, maybe.
Haven't done anything with it yet.
Let's write a function that can take a dictionary.
Maybe it's coming from the user JSON request somewhere
else and return one of these things.
So we get a dictionary coming in, call it request.
It's a dictionary, but we want to get a book back out.
So we can return a book, not a book, and it has an author.
And a title.
So we've eliminated all of our typos.
And it says everything's cool.
Now, one thing you'll notice here is that this function
won't always run to completion.
If I pass a dictionary in that doesn't have these arguments,
it will raise an exception and won't return anything.
It won't return a book, it won't return anything.
Maybe that's fine.
Maybe we want to do something a different way.
We can talk about other ways to do it at the end of the talk
if I get that far.
But just be aware that static type checking works great
on functions that return values.
It doesn't work great on things that raise exceptions.
It can't tell you that you mutated state necessarily.
It's really about pure functions or what it handles best.
So we've got this function.
We can give it a dictionary, a generic dictionary.
We have no idea what's in it.
And it will either return a book or it will raise an exception.
So let's say we want to be able to save this book
into our database.
So I have written a fake database here
that I'm going to import.
And it has an insert function.
So I want a function that saves a book, takes a book to save.
The book has to be a book, not a book.
And it doesn't return anything.
And then I'm going to insert the book into my database.
I'm going to pretend like it's sort of Mongo-y,
except I called it insert instead of insert or whatever.
I want to save the title, and I want
to save the author in the database.
OK.
Everything's good.
Cool.
Now authors are good and all, but the publisher
is where the money is.
So we really need to keep track of the publisher
because they are the people with the money.
So we are going to, first let's pretend like, you know what?
We need to remember to save the publisher.
OK.
Oh, that's interesting.
It's actually telling me that I can't do that
because books don't have publishers.
So I can come up here and I can say, OK,
books have publishers now.
But now it's saying, I can't create a book without a publisher
because I said books have to have publishers.
So now, so you can see what it's doing here
is it's kind of guiding my refactoring.
It's sort of telling me, you forgot about this,
you forgot about that.
It's keeping track of what you can and can't
do with the values that are passing through your code.
And it's telling you if you're doing something that will
potentially fail at runtime.
So that's kind of cool.
So let's add something else.
So some books come in series.
Not all books come in series, but some books
are a book in a series.
So let's try to model that.
So we're going to start out by just defining
a new class, book in series.
And it's a kind of book.
You can inherit from it.
It's not really inheritance, because remember, at runtime,
these are just dictionaries.
But it's sort of a hint to the type checker.
By inheriting from book, it gets all of the attributes of book.
And then it can have new attributes.
So I can say, I also have a series.
It's just the name of the series, the ID, whatever.
I'm just going to store it as a string.
OK, that is cool.
But it's not really doing anything useful right now.
But we can use it to add a new feature.
Let's say our website, we want to be
able to find books related to books.
Recommendations engines were a really big deal 15 years ago.
Still are, probably.
People don't brag about them as much,
because they all just bought them.
So we're going to write a function called findRelated.
And it's going to find one related book,
or it's going to tell me that there aren't any related books.
So it's going to take a book, it's type is book,
and we want it to return a book.
Makes sense, right?
But I don't really know how to implement it yet.
So I'm just going to pretend, I don't know.
I'm going to figure something out.
So how could we go about finding a related book?
Well, if the book is in a series,
then we can just find another book in the same series, right?
They're presumably related.
So we're going to write a function findInSeries.
That's going to take a book, but that book
has to have a series, so bookInSeries.
And it's going to return a book in series.
OK, so we want to somehow do this.
I've got this database class.
It has the select function, or not class, module.
Has a find, I actually called it find.
And I want to say, again, sort of pretending
like we're writing against Mongo.
Mongo is interesting in this case,
because it doesn't enforce anything.
So you really need to enforce things at the application level
if you want anything enforced at all.
So I'm going to find a book here.
Got to return the thing I find.
This is interesting.
So the find implementation I wrote
says, I'm not always going to find
the thing you're asking for.
Maybe that thing doesn't exist in the database.
So it uses something called optional.
So I'm going to go import optional here,
because I'm going to need it.
Optional.
And then this is returning an optional bookInSeries.
Still not right, because I'm trying to return an optional.
If you look at the very bottom here,
I'll tell you the whole problem.
It got an optional dictionary of anything to anything.
But I told it I was going to return
an optional bookInSeries.
So that's because I need something similar to a parsed
book, but for a book that has a series attached to it.
So just copy paste.
That's a good programming practice.
So I'm going to do this bookInSeries,
and I want it to return a bookInSeries.
OK, I'm probably done right.
No, I'm not.
OK, so we need to return.
It says I said I would give it a bookInSeries,
but I gave it a book, so bookWith a series.
OK, and then I'm going to also break this up,
because it's starting to get a little long.
So I should be good, right?
No.
OK, so bookInSeries.
OK, so bookInSeries needs a series.
I told it it needed a series.
It's telling me that.
It's saying key series missing from type dict bookInSeries.
So let's do that.
OK, so now parsed bookInSeries is written correctly,
but this still isn't written correctly.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to say, well,
I'm going to parse bookInSeries, and that
will turn my JSON object thing dictionary
into a bookInSeries.
Seems like it should be a good idea.
Still won't let me do it, because I typed it wrong.
Because I typed book twice.
Book, book.
OK, but it really wasn't supposed to let me do it anyway,
because parsed bookInSeries expects to get a dictionary,
but the database may not return a dictionary.
It may just return none.
Optional means you're either going to return this,
or you're going to return none.
It's a sort of a subclass of another type
called union, which is one or the other.
But the other is always none.
So here, again, it's telling me, hey, you
forgot that sometimes the thing you're looking for
isn't in the database, and you don't get anything back.
And if you run this, you'll get a null, like none type has no,
blah, blah, blah.
Very annoying error.
So let's save this off.
Save off what we get.
And then we can say if row is not none,
return parse bookInSeries row.
Otherwise, we'll return none.
OK, cool.
So we can actually go to the database
and say, hey, find a book in the same series.
If you don't find it, return nothing.
If you do find it, turn it into this bookInSeries thing
and return it back to me.
OK, that sounds cool, but we still
haven't implemented this findRelated thing,
so let's figure out how to implement that.
So what we want to do is be able to say, hey, look,
when you ask me to find a related book,
if the book belongs to a series, I know how to do that.
I can just find another book in the same series
and tell you to buy that book.
If it's not in a series, I haven't figured it out yet.
We've got to do some machine learning thing or something,
and I don't know, whatever.
We'll just say nothing.
So I am going to here say, let's try this.
Let's just say findInSeries book.
OK, there's a couple of things wrong with that.
So we're trying to return the wrong thing,
but also findInSeries wants a book
that has a series attached to it.
We're not sure if the series is attached to it,
because we haven't checked.
So let's try this.
If series in book, let's do that.
Otherwise, I return none, because we didn't find anything.
OK, so the first thing is sometimes we return none,
and we said we'll always return a book,
but we actually know that we're not always
going to return a book.
Sometimes there is nothing related to the book.
It's just like a magical unicorn book.
It's genre defining, and nobody has
caught on to the hot new genre.
OK, so findrelated has to be optional.
We can't always find something related to it.
There's still a problem.
The problem is that findInSeries
wants a bookInSeries, a book with a series attached to it,
but we only have a book.
So this is actually one of the places that MyPy has trouble.
We know by looking at this code that at this line here,
the book has a series attribute, but MyPy doesn't.
It's gotten confused.
Fortunately, there's a way around that,
which is cast.
So if you've ever written any C++ code or Java code,
you know what that does, and we have to import it.
OK, so we've told MyPy, look, trust me, I checked.
I'm very certain that bookInSeries
is the right type.
One thing we didn't have to tell it,
though, is that a bookInSeries is a book,
because we inherited the types from each other,
even though here I'm saying, I want to return a book,
and here I'm saying, I'm going to return a book
with a series attached to it.
MyPy knows that a book with a series attached to it
is also a book, so it lets us do it.
So that is that.
And then one last thing that we need to do,
we need to be able to save the book.
So I want to save the book.
I want to save the bookInSeries, and I should probably
save the series, huh?
Right?
No, because I forgot to update the type.
So there we go.
So the type checker is kind of assisting me
as I'm refactoring my code.
And it's saying, hey, you forgot about this.
You need to check for this attribute.
This attribute doesn't exist.
But the other thing it does is it says,
you can trust that this attribute exists.
If this was some whole very complicated submodule that
dealt with books that belonged to a series
and it needed to find an image that's the series image instead
of the book's cover image or give you
a listing of all the books in order,
you can trust, no matter how many other functions you call,
that the book has that attribute.
And if you make a mistake, as I did many times up here,
the checker will check it for you.
So that is it.
And I don't know if there's time for any questions or not.
Thank you.
OK, one or two questions?
I don't have any questions.
So I really liked your workflow where you added the field to your database query and then just fixed the problems until it stopped complaining and you were successful.
That seems sort of backwards from normal workflow.
Am I going to add a field? I'm typically going to go to the class.
Is there a way, like if I add a field to the class, it's not going to complain.
I'm going to have to go find all the things manually rather than relying on MyPy for that?
Yeah, so if you go add a field manually, any code that doesn't access the field, MyPy doesn't know you're supposed to be accessing the field.
This is a little hand wavy here.
I think that what you would probably want to do is build out that interface layer between your code and your database.
You want to unit test that, right?
And so you're kind of doing this in conjunction with writing tests.
So at some point you'd have a test that says, hey, look, if the user gives me a book that has a series attached to it, I better save the series attached to it in the database.
So you're going to have to go update the database saving code to write the series out.
At that point, that sort of drives you to go start adding the type annotation.
And then MyPy helps you find all the places that you might have broken and go in and sort of fix them up.
So it can't do everything for you, but it can help guide you and show you places where maybe you forgot that you did something over here or whatever.
So that's what it's really good at is discovering those things.
OK, I think that's time.
All right, let's give one more round of applause.