So without further ado, I'd like to introduce Emily Morehouse.
Emily is a Core Python contributor,
and she's going to have a great talk for us today.
Let's give her a round of applause.
Thank you.
All right, everyone, welcome to PyTexas.
I'm really, really excited to be here.
Sort of one of the interesting things about my Python regional
conference journey is that every other regional conference
that I have attended, it has rained,
which is a very lovely, lovely welcome to this city.
But I live in Denver right now, but I grew up in Florida.
So we see these really, really incredible thunderstorms.
And so any time we do get rain, it always
kind of reminds me of home.
So all right.
So a little bit about me.
My name's Emily Morehouse.
I am the director of engineering at a company called
CuddleSoft.
We are a digital product development company.
So we make anything from web and mobile applications
to CI-CD pipelines and cloud architectures to embedded
systems and sort of everything in between.
I'm a Python Core developer, which, as you may have guessed,
is actually one of the reasons why I'm here today.
A couple of other things.
I consider myself to be a polyglot.
I work with a lot of Python and JavaScript
and a lot of other languages.
If you are in the JavaScript world,
I help maintain a package called Axios, which
is basically like the requests of JavaScript.
I'm also a huge proponent of visual testing.
I really like screenshot testing.
I really love auto formatting, including black.
And I am just, in general, a really, really huge language
nerd.
But aside from all of these things,
I really like playing video games, doing yoga,
going hiking.
And I also have a really cute dog.
So outside of all of these things
that you kind of see listed here as my pedigree,
I'm just like all the rest of you in this room.
So a little bit about why we're here.
I'm going to talk about my path to becoming a Core developer,
how I got here, a bunch of kind of lessons and things
that I observed along the way, and some other things
that you don't get to know about yet,
or else that would spoil the ending.
So I want to start at PyCon Montreal 2015.
And actually, to get a really good sense of why PyCon
Montreal 2015 was important to me,
I have to step back a little bit.
And so in 2014, I had finished my bachelor's
in computer science, along with a couple of other degrees
at Florida State University.
Because of some timing issues, I wound up
starting my graduate school program
at FSU, which was not necessarily what I had intended.
And so I was in a state where I didn't really
know what my next step was.
I was being recruited by a lot of large companies.
I was thinking about transferring school
so that I could finally move out of Florida.
But I didn't really know what I should do.
And so a bunch of things sort of fell together.
And I actually wound up dropping out of grad school,
staying in Tallahassee for a few more years,
and starting a company with my boyfriend at the time,
now my husband.
And so getting to the point where
we were able to attend PyCon 2015
was really a validating experience for us.
Cuddlesoft had matured at that point
to where we could actually support us financially
going to this.
And it really made me feel like I was at least
taking a step in the right direction for what
my future was going to be.
In all of this, I did have some doubts.
I really, really loved programming languages.
I was working on building compilers and parsers
and doing some really cool research in that area.
And I was pretty unhappy that I was leaving all of that behind
because I didn't necessarily see where
that could fit into my future of building
a company like Cuddlesoft.
And so at PyCon Montreal 2015, Guida Van Russum,
our BFL emeritus, beloved creator of Python,
made an announcement.
And that was that he had made the observation
that there were no female core developers on the CPython team.
And so he had this sort of call to action to everyone
that by the following year at PyCon,
he wanted to have at least two female core
developers on the team.
And so I think Frank was sitting next to me at this point.
And he was just poking me.
And he's like, do it, do it.
This is exactly the thing that you felt
like you had been leaving behind.
And now you have a way to contribute and find that again
in this new path that you're taking.
And so I stopped the gift for you.
But at this point, I was able to meet Guido at a post-conference
event.
And it was in this very stereotypical, not Python
necessarily post-event.
So it was at this bar.
It was really dark.
And so Guido was there.
And Frank and another attendee that we had met
kind of encouraged me.
They were like, there's Guido over there.
You should totally go talk to him.
And I'm like, OK.
And so I kind of have to get up my nerves to go talk to him.
And I think that I just went over and word vomited and was
I really love Python.
I really love compilers.
And I want to do this thing.
And very, very shortly into this conversation,
we're maybe two minutes in.
And the other conference attendee
that we had recently met walks by
and takes a flash photograph of me talking to Guido
in this very dimly lit bar where it is very, very obvious.
And so I just immediately turned bright red.
I feel paparazzied.
I feel very embarrassed and very put on the spot
and have a lot of attention brought to us
that I really didn't need at that time.
And so I very quickly concluded the conversation.
And Guido was like, email me.
And we'll figure out next steps.
And I was like, yeah, OK.
And just backed up and just immediately started burrowing
directly into the ground.
And at this point, I didn't email him.
I didn't move forward.
I really sort of let this experience really sort of
envelop what I had wanted to do moving forward for myself.
And so we get to PyCon Portland.
Keeping Portland weird in this picture.
We get to PyCon Portland.
And there are still zero female core developers
who have joined the team.
And so at this point, one of the things
that I really have grown to admire about Guido
is that everything about our Python community
really is top down.
And one of the things that Guido has always done
is if he recognizes that there is a problem or something
that he believes in, he is one of the first people
to step up and put in the work to make those things happen.
So what actually happened is that Guido
offered to personally mentor anyone
who is interested in becoming a core developer.
And so at this point, I had already
gone through about a year of this kind of feeling of regret
and this like, is somebody else going to step up and do this?
Me feeling like I had really sort of backed away
and painted myself into a corner where
the longer that I didn't take any sort of action
to move forward, the harder it was for me
to actually step forward again and say,
hey, remember we talked about this thing?
I do really want to do this.
And so at this point, I reached out to Guido and said,
hey, remember that really embarrassing time
we met in a bar and this guy took a flash photograph of us?
And I really had to make a joke out of it
to get myself mentally past the barriers
that I had set for myself.
And so honestly, I don't think Guido had even
thought twice about it.
And he was like, oh, yeah, I totally remember you.
Where have you been kind of thing.
And so at this point, I got to start meeting
with Guido every few weeks.
And so I started this process with Guido and mentorship.
And so one of the first things that they
tell new contributors to do is go read the contributing
guide, try to fix documentation, fix typos,
like learn the process of contributing,
find bugs and fix bugs, that sort of thing.
But to a certain extent, some of those things
didn't interest me.
I wasn't really drawn to contributing to CPython
to fix documentation.
And I started to try to fix bugs along the way.
But one of the really, really difficult things
about bugs in CPython is that they're fixed really quickly.
Or CPython has been around for so long
that a lot of the low-hanging fruit and easier bugs to fix
are already kind of picked off and knocked down.
And so the things that are left are
these things that have a really, really high barrier
to entry for new contributors.
A really great one is Unicode, for example.
We've been fighting with Unicode for how long,
and we still are having issues with it.
It's not a great place for somebody
to be able to come in and feel any sort of validation,
because you can't really come in and make an impact very quickly.
And so I tried to take this experience and learn from it.
So what I started doing was, if I started on a bug fix
and somebody else wound up kind of beating me to it
and submitting a patch before I did,
I would try to go through and still finish my implementation
and go through and see what I could learn
from how my implementation maybe differed
from somebody who was a core developer submitting a bug fix
and really learn from that.
And so what that allowed me to do
was see different things about the CPython environment
that I wouldn't necessarily have known otherwise,
whether that was a helper function,
a different way of doing things, different impacts that
changes in one area of the code might have in another place,
ways to see these edge cases that I wasn't maybe
thinking about.
And so I tried to take that and turn it
into a really positive experience.
The thing was that still at the end of the day,
I didn't feel like I was really truly contributing anything.
I was just kind of learning on my own.
So I kind of ditched that very quickly
and started reading the source code.
And so I kind of made the decision
to go back to my roots of what I had been interested in.
And I started kind of stepping through the compiler
and the interpreter and the parser
and really figuring out how all of these CPython internals
worked under the hood just by putting
a bunch of print statements or debug statements in there
and just learning.
And so one of the interesting things about Guido's
mentorship was that I had never really
had any sort of technical mentorship in this way before.
And so what I expected coming in was Guido to say,
you know, here's this bug.
I've found this bug for you.
Go fix this bug and come back to me with your bug fix.
And that's really not how it went.
He came to me and said, how can I help?
What do you want to learn?
And really, really left the door open to me.
And I was like, oh, OK.
I have to drive this ship, but I don't
know what on earth I'm doing.
So at this point, Guido asked me a very, very kind, high level
question that wasn't really meant to guide me,
necessarily.
But he asked, what do you see yourself
doing with this process that you're going through?
And he warned me that a lot of the code and things
that I was working on didn't really change very often.
And he was like, there's not really anything
that you can go in and improve or change.
There's no bugs here.
And basically, I realized that what I was looking at
was 15-plus-year-old files that hadn't been
touched in that many years.
And so I was kind of like, well, this is fine.
I'm enjoying what I'm doing.
I feel like I'm learning a lot, so let's keep going.
And so not having any idea what on earth I was reading
turned into this process of reading and learning
and discovering and getting to find new things.
But still, on this journey, I would get really, really
introspective.
Because I felt like I came in and had this expectation
for myself of, I'm going to come in and I'm going to contribute
and I'm going to do really awesome things.
And that wasn't at all what I felt was happening.
So I would have these highs and lows of feeling
like I'm doing something really cool,
but then I don't feel like I'm doing anything at all.
And wondering if I had made the right decision.
Should I have just listened to the guidelines that
had been set out?
And should I have just been fixing documentation?
And was I trying to do too much as a new contributor?
And maybe at the end of the day, I
was worried that I just wasn't cut out for that type of work.
And so throughout this process, one of the things
that I am very gracious that I was able to learn
is that there is a lot of unwritten history, especially
with projects that are as old as CPython's implementation.
So much unwritten history that doesn't get communicated
to contributors or the general audience of the project.
And so one of the things that I would really enjoy
is that I would come across something
in my sort of meandering discoveries,
and I would find something confusing
or not really understand it, and I would ask Weedo about it,
and he would say, oh, no, that's interesting.
And I would find these very innocuous pieces of the code
that wound up having a really, really interesting backstory
as to why they came to be that way.
And there was no other way that I would have known or learned
about these things if it hadn't been finding it
and asking Weedo about it and getting a chance
to actually interact with the people who had shaped
and written that code in the very beginning.
And so I learned that having a respect
for the history of a project is really, really important.
So especially with something like CPython,
it would be really awesome to have
something like CPython, it would be really awesome
to come in and rip a bunch of things out and do it better
and do it in a more modern way.
But if you don't have that respect for why
it is the way it is, you're going to come in
and you're going to break things,
and you're going to wind up taking something
in a very wrong direction.
And so this whole process for me went on
for about a year and a half.
And during these times, I was really worried
that he would cut me off, that he would be like,
hey, yeah, so it's been like a year and a half.
I'm not really totally sure what you're doing.
I don't know if you really know what you're doing yet.
So I was just very worried he was going to sort of
reclaim his time back from me.
And don't get me wrong, I had absolutely
zero reason to think any of this.
It was all in my head.
Weedo had never given me any sort of reason to doubt myself
or to doubt his support of what I wanted to do.
But there was still this like inkling
in the back of my head that something
that I wasn't doing enough.
And so in that time, we also got our first
two female core developers.
Marietta Ujaya and Carol Willing were both
promoted to core developers, which was a really,
really monumental step for CPython.
So we fast-forward to PyCon Cleveland 2018.
And so this was actually the second year
that I was able to attend the Language Summit.
I attended in 2017 and really didn't interact
with a lot of people, just kind of like snuck in the back,
listened and soaked up everything
that everybody was talking about
and then just like crept right back out.
If you might have guessed, I'm an introvert.
Just throwing that out there.
And so the second Language Summit,
I was feeling a little bit better.
I felt like I was really keeping up to date
with some of the major happenings in CPython.
So I really kind of forced myself out of my shell
to talk to other core developers at the Language Summit.
And so there were a couple of really monumental things
that happened around the time of PyCon 2018.
And one of them was that PEP572 was accepted.
So if you don't know what PEP572 is,
it is assignment expressions.
It is one of the most recent changes to Python syntax.
These things don't really roll around very often.
But that was accepted.
And right around that same time, Guido stepped down as VDFL.
And so at this point, I wasn't really sure
what the path forward for CPython was.
I wasn't sure what my mentorship relationship
with Guido was going to happen.
But at that point, he reassured me.
He was like, no, yes, I stepped down,
but I am still going to mentor you.
And actually, I wanted to see
if you wanted to implement PEP572.
And so at this point, it was really this moment
of everything coming together.
All of the areas that I had spent so much time meandering
and learning and not really being able
to do anything with it, all of that came together
for this really, really lucky situation
where I was the perfect person to move forward
and implement that because I had been researching
and learning so much about it.
And so he basically said, I know that this is going
to be really, really tricky.
As they wrote the PEP for this, they were like,
well, we don't really know how this is gonna work,
but we'll figure it out.
And so he said, it's gonna be really tricky,
but I'll be here to help you if you get stuck.
And so this is where I got into some of my favorite moments
because this is where any of those doubts and uncertainties
that I had had, had evaporated.
And so I got to sit and, so this is a photo
of the whiteboard conference desk
in one of our old office spaces.
And I would just sit there and figure out,
how am I gonna do this, how does this work?
And really just got to dive head first
into figuring all of this out.
And so I was actually able to get my 90% implementation
completed within the first couple of months.
And at that point, I was very, very graciously invited
to attend the Python Core Developer Sprints,
which was sort of a rarity.
Typically, that's only reserved for core developers,
for them to kind of get together and work on implementations,
talk through details together.
And I was very, very grateful
that I was invited to attend this.
And so at this point, I got to kind of see
all these people again that had turned into friends
and colleagues from attending the Language Summit.
And I also got to sit and work through all of the like
really, really hairy implementation details
of scoping for assignment expressions
with Guido in person at the sprint.
So one of the things that I had to remind myself was that
my path didn't wind up being the one
that I expected myself to have.
I realized that I had to give myself time.
And honestly, you can look at this timeline
and sure it took three and a half years
from that initial inception
for me to actually become a core developer,
but there's a whole lot of other really, really small ticks
on this timeline that happened along the way
to get me where I am.
And so I had to give myself time and give myself the space
to let the process happen as it needed to
and not how I wanted it to.
And so one of the other really important factors
when promoting somebody to becoming a core developer
is trust.
We have to have trust that they will kind of uphold
the CPython name, that they will be good community members
and kind to other people, whether they are core developers
or first time contributors.
We have to trust that they won't merge in PRs haphazardly
and that they will take care in the code
that they're crafting and the code that they're merging in
from other people.
And that's something that you can't really measure
in the number of commits.
You can't look at someone and say,
oh, well they have 30 commits and 30 PRs to CPython
and therefore they deserve to be a core developer.
There's so much more that goes into that
and being able to interact with people
and establish that trust in an online distributed environment
is something that is really, really tricky
and at the end of the day really does just take time.
And so I wanna talk a little bit about
internal versus external motivations.
And so a lot of people come to me and they're like,
oh, you're a core developer, that's so cool.
Well, I mean, yeah, but it's also like a lot
of really hard work and a lot of tedious work
at the end of the day too.
So keeping up with the bug tracker,
giving beneficial feedback.
It's all things that are not necessarily
always very fun or very glamorous,
but it's things that all core developers have to do.
And so if you go into something seeking
some sort of public recognition
or if you are the kind of person that decides like,
oh, one day I want to be a director of engineering
or I wanna be a CEO or I wanna make a certain salary,
I would really encourage you to kind of look
inside of yourself and try to figure out
why you want to do those things.
Because if you're looking for external accolades,
the longevity of your motivation is not going to be there.
Whereas if you find something
that you're really truly passionate about
as an internal motivation,
you will continue working towards that thing
for years and years to come.
Okay, so I really love this GIF of Alison Brie.
So one of the things that I also had to kind of
really like solidify myself was that you don't have
to be the badass all the time.
You don't have to be the person that comes in
and always has the great ideas or the best implementation
or the most elegant code.
And so these things really take time and process.
And if you try to kind of walk in there
and be this really awesome person,
I don't think that you're being very true to yourself
and I don't think that you are taking care
to build your team and your colleagues up around you.
And so I wanted to be very clear that it is very, very okay
and it is very, very human to be the person
that has doubts and insecurities and uncertainties
and that you're okay to have moments
where you don't know what your path is
or what your next step is or how to solve that problem
and that all of those things are very, very normal
and very, very okay.
And so this leads me into imposter syndrome.
And I think that that is a lot of what I was going through
and probably what a lot of people go through,
whether they put this sort of name on it or not.
And so imposter syndrome can be really, really crippling.
And I think that a lot of that probably played
into that first year where I had met Mido
and then stepped back and was too scared
to kind of take that next step.
And I think that having an excuse for,
oh, well, this embarrassing thing happened
and so therefore I'm not gonna reach out to Mido again,
really got in the way and also really fed
into allowing myself to feel a lot of imposter syndrome.
And one of the things that I also think is important
is that there are a lot of pieces of our communities
that play into imposter syndrome.
I'm gonna show you a couple of tweets in a second
that I think really illustrate this.
But even after our tech communities are fixed,
we're still gonna be talking about imposter syndrome.
And so this is a really great tweet.
It says, imposter syndrome will have you questioning
your place in the spaces that you prayed about being in.
And so this really kind of spoke to me
because you can put in so much work
to get to somewhere that you really, really want to be
and you can still have this little like demon
in the back of your head telling you
that even though you put in a bunch of work
and that other people think that what you're doing
is beneficial and great,
you can still feel these insecurities
even though you've worked so hard.
And so this one's a little bit more relevant
for happenings that have been going on in the last few days
with the really, really awesome depiction of a black hole
that we were able to see.
And so I think that reframing imposter syndrome a bit
in terms of how our communities impact
our own personal feelings is really important.
Being able to separate the two is important.
So if I'm getting a bunch of external feedback
telling me that I'm not necessarily worthy
does not mean that you should listen to those people.
And so I think that for most of us in this room,
we're really, really lucky
because Python has an absolutely incredible community.
But in a lot of other tech communities,
these things aren't necessarily as guaranteed,
especially for women and minorities
who are part of those groups.
And so I've heard throughout my journey
from a lot of different people
who are either first time contributors to see Python
or who have been contributing to see Python
for five to 10 years.
And they all have expressed feelings of doubt
and feelings of imposter syndrome.
And even the people who,
I think that it's expected when somebody is new
that they feel imposter syndrome,
but it's less expected that once somebody reaches
a certain level of success or acclaim,
that they no longer feel these things.
And so I've really been grateful for the people
who have been at it for a long time
and who are still really willing to open up and say,
yeah, I've been trying to work on this problem
for the last six months
and I don't feel like I'm getting anywhere.
And I've been working on this for five years
and I still don't really feel like I know what I'm doing.
Because at the end of the day,
if you don't feel that sort of uncertainty
or doubt moving forward,
you probably aren't doing something
that's really, truly challenging yourself.
And so I wanted to bring this up.
There's a lot of different versions of this image
circulating on the internet,
but I think that everyone needs to hear this again.
And that's that the things that I know
are not a subset of what I think everybody else knows.
And that really, at the end of the day,
I don't know anything more than you do,
I just know different things than you do.
I'm gonna grow up somewhere.
And so throughout all of this,
one of the things that really kind of stood true to me
was that the fear of regret has to be greater
than the fear of failure.
And so even though we might be placed in these situations
where we have really, really high stakes
and there's something that we really, really wanna do
and we don't know if we can do it
or we don't know if we'll have the support for it, et cetera,
the fear of failure has to outweigh the fear of regret.
And so this really ties back
to these internal motivations that we have.
And you have to be really, really passionate about something
to be willing to put yourself out there and take that risk
and especially to be willing to fail publicly.
So I kinda wanna go back and wrap this up a little bit.
And I wanna talk a little bit about why it was so important
that people like Mariana, Carol, myself, and our other,
we now have five female core developers.
And so I wanted to talk a little bit
about why diversity matters.
And so I wanna show you a couple of pictures.
So this is from the PyCon Language Summit 2017.
I don't know how well you all can see it from your seats,
but basically what you can see here is
there's myself, Carol, and Mariana in this photo,
and everyone else in the picture is male.
And this is again from the PyCon Language Summit 2018.
And again, Carol, Mariana, and myself,
and everyone else is male.
So when I started contributing to CPython,
there was literally not anyone else who looked like me
who was a CPython core developer.
And the thing is is that role models who look like us
are really important.
I'm not gonna go down that path
of trying to convince you why diversity matters,
but there have been a lot of different studies
on why diversity matters and why having role models
who look like us matters,
whether that is a Barbie doll
that has the same skin color as you do,
or somebody that you can identify with,
whether on like a gender or race level.
And there's studies that have been done
that say that students who have teachers
who look like them in different ways
actually wind up feeling a lot more cared for,
are a lot more interested in their schoolwork,
and ultimately perform a lot better at the end of the day.
And so today we have approximately 100 core developers.
I think we're just under that number at this point.
And actually this is an older slide,
five female core developers today.
And so you can kind of see that that ratio
is still pretty sad.
And the other thing that happened is that
a lot of people, not a lot of people,
but a couple of people came forward and said,
oh well she was promoted because she was female,
or why would you want to bring somebody
into the core development team
just because they're female?
And so one of the things that started happening
is that the successes and the work
that we had all put forward was then sort of denigrated
by these people who decided to doubt us,
or try to attribute our successes to our genders.
And so I have to point out that increasing diversity
is not equal to lowering the bar.
And that just because I had a lot of doors
opened up for me because I was female,
whether that was mentorship, whether that was sponsorship,
whether that was just somebody else
who was a little bit more willing to listen to my voice
because I was different.
But all of these things at the end of the day
really can only make us better,
and can only help our communities grow
in the ways that we want them to.
And so through this process,
I've really had a chance to kind of look back
on my journey over the last four years.
And I really recognize how much community
has played into that.
And a lot of that is specifically
how incredible our Python community is,
and how devoted to diversity all of us are.
And so the thing is is that if I hadn't met Guido,
like if I hadn't happened to be in the same event
that he had been at,
or if I hadn't had the guts to send that email,
or hadn't let myself fall prey to my imposter syndrome
and given up,
if all of these things hadn't happened
in the way that they did,
I wouldn't have made it here today.
And I also got to really witness a lot of other people
going through the same process
that I didn't know they were going through.
And so I think moving forward,
what my sort of call to action is for all of you
is to be more open with each other.
Especially if you're somebody
who is in a position of leadership,
or is running a team,
I really, really encourage you
to say, I don't know, a lot more often,
and to really encourage everyone
to work together to find a solution
and foster that community
and those relationships with people.
I also think that it's really important
to tell other people when you're feeling doubtful,
or you're saying, man, I don't know,
I just don't know if I'm doing a great job today,
what do you think?
And really sort of open the door
to that sort of feedback
that you can get from other people.
And that sort of support,
because if you come in one day
and you're feeling bad
because you pushed something into production
and broke something or whatnot,
if you don't open up to people
and tell them how you're feeling,
you're never gonna wind up
getting the support that you need,
and you're never going to grow your team
to be a very empathetic, understanding group of people.
And so by supporting each other
through all these sort of highs and lows,
by making the decision
to make conscious choices
with how we interact with each other,
I know that at the end of the day
that we will always go further
when we have each other.
Thank you.
Applause