All right, first landing talk is Ali Sevji.
He's going to talk about Busy Beaver, the Chicago Python
Community Engagement Slackbot.
Let's give him a round of applause.
Hi, everybody.
My name is Ali Sevji.
I'm one of the organizers of the Chicago Python users group.
And I'm here to talk to you about this community engagement
initiative I've been working on for the past few months called
Busy Beaver.
So we're really fortunate to have a fantastic community
of Pythonistas in the Windy City.
And at the heart of this community
is the Chicago Python users group, or Chippy.
With over 4,600 members, Chippy is
one of the largest tech-focused communities
inside the United States.
We've been around for 15 years, and at that time,
we've had around 150-plus monthly meetings.
In addition to our general meeting
that happens once a month, we have a lot of special interest
groups for more niche interests.
So we have one for data, web development slash DevOps,
finance.
We recently started one on algorithms and coding
interviews to help people whiteboard.
We have one for lunch, so people that
can't make our evening meetups can attend that one.
And we recently started doing some open source spreads.
So last month, we sprinted on chippy.org.
We also have a monthly project night.
And this project night has two tracks.
There's a challenge project night track.
And here, there's a group of four people.
They mod program on an assignment together.
And we also have a BYO, bring your own project track,
where people just work on projects,
and they get help if they need it.
We also have a world-famous mentorship program.
This is a 13-week, one-on-one, project-based mentorship.
There's two cohorts a year.
There's around 20 to 30 people every single, sorry,
20 to 30 pairs every single cohort.
And at the end, the top 10 mentees
present their lightning tots at a Chippy May meeting.
The next one's going to be on May, May 9th in Chicago.
So if you're around, please come on by.
It's going to be a lot of fun.
So like most organizations, Slack
is our primary means of communication.
And it's really become ingrained within our community.
So we have a lot of channels focused
on different conversations.
Some of my favorites include Book Club.
There's one for Advent of Code.
And code review is always a lot of fun, too.
Slack has a lot of plugins.
And we use these plugins quite extensively.
But they don't really solve the specific problem that we have.
We're trying to build a tech-focused community.
And we have a different set of problems.
So try to foster conversations around technology
to keep people coming back.
So our Slack is only as good as our integrations, only
as good as our community.
So nothing really fit our specific use case.
So we got a team together.
And we let them loose on the problem.
After a little bit of design and a lot of hard work,
the end result was Busy Beaver.
And it's a Slack bot built specifically for the Chicago
Python workspace.
So the bot's mission is to increase engagement
within the Chicago Python community.
That's a pretty broad scope.
So what does it really mean?
What are some ways we can engage your community?
GitHub seems like a good place to start.
It's a social coding platform.
A lot of developers use GitHub.
But as an organization, we didn't really
have a lot of insight into what our community was working on,
what projects they were doing, what open source contributions
they were making, what things were they starring.
So working with GitHub seemed like a good place to start.
So the first feature we created was a GitHub summary bot.
And so what this did was, if you register with this bot,
every day at 2 o'clock, it goes out to GitHub,
collects all your public activity in the last day,
and it posts it within a channel.
It got a lot of great publicity, mostly from me.
So we decided to add another feature.
Over the past few months, the Chicago Python
at Chicago Python Twitter channel
is becoming a little bit more popular.
We're sharing more content.
So we decided to integrate this within our Slack workspace.
So the second feature we built was,
since not everybody on Slack follows us on Twitter,
we just reshare our tweets inside of that one channel.
So we released in January.
So far, we only have two features.
But we are an open source project,
released under the MIT license.
We have a lot of documentation showing
how to get started contributing.
We also have a project board with a lot of issues.
I've been tagging them with a good first issue,
how hard they are, how much effort they're going to take.
There's also a CI CD pipeline built in.
So if you get a feature out there, write some tests.
We can get it shipped into production really quickly.
So if you want to start getting contributing,
look at or read me.
Join the Chippy Slack.
I'm going to be sprinting on this project Monday
if anybody's around.
I have stickers.
If anyone wants to get stickers,
there could be some out there.
Find me.
If you make a PR, I will give you a button.
So there's some incentive there.
So thanks for your time.
But before I go, I just want to acknowledge
all my Chippy organizers.
Couldn't be up here without all their hard work.
And also to everybody on the busy work teams.
Thank you, everybody.
Thank you.
Thanks for having me.
So 21 seconds left.
Very good.
Paul, are you ready to do your crap at the end?
Paul, are you set up for that?
I'm just holding the mic for you.
Oh, you're loved.
Do that.
It's OK.
I'll have a high five, because that's sweet.
OK.
Okay, I can do it without notes.
I can do it without notes.
Okay.
Choo, choo, choo, choo, choo, choo.
Hello?
Why is it going?
Oops.
Whoops.
Computers are really hard.
Yeah, who knew about computers?
Okay.
That's a preview of slide number five, you all.
All right.
Microphone?
Yeah, thank you.
All right, Veronica is going to give us a talk about get hooked on images and up your documentation game.
Let's give her a round of applause.
All right.
We're going to do a 30 minute talk in five minutes.
Are you guys stoked?
Hold on to your hats.
All right.
So how many of you use Git and GitHub for your programming files?
Almost all of you.
That's fabulous.
Okay, so how many of you have explored different ways of documenting your projects?
Could be creative use of comments, man pages, images, anything.
All right, all right, all right, all right.
I see some hands.
So we talked a little bit about this earlier today.
Remember our cat.
We got to label our cat.
So you could have ASCII to explain where you are in a particular piece of code.
You could create whole man pages describing sections of your code.
But it's possible that some of these obvious comments aren't so obvious to you.
So the best docs are the ones that help you.
You need to learn to solve the problems that you have.
And your problem solving is going to be with you throughout your careers.
Certainly longer than any particular flavor of JavaScript.
And I'm a self-taught second career developer.
And I manage to try on a lot of different hats.
So today I'm going to talk about a problem that I encountered as I started to shift from scripting to front end roles.
How I developed a solution.
And how we can learn to build the tools that we wish we had.
So this talk, while it's about tools, is really about opening yourself up to making the software you need to make your Git workflow work for you.
So not everyone uses Git the same way.
So before I talk about my Git venture, I should tell you where I was when I got started.
So when I learned Git, I learned it the way many people do.
A kind and loving friend told me, there are these five commands, okay?
Don't ask me again.
It's been 72 times that you've asked.
Just write down the five commands.
Okay, okay.
So maybe I got a little bit into that person's hair.
I never did a Git intensive.
And everything that I've learned since then, I've learned as I've needed to do it.
So as you can guess, when I started to work on my own projects, I was a little uncomfortable with the whole Git time travel thing.
So I tried to keep things linear.
So I could push, pull, check out.
But anything fancier than that didn't feel like it, you know, it kind of felt out of the question.
However, there's a lot of things you can do with Git.
And I made a partial list right here.
So at the time I was relying, as I started to move to more visual work, I was continuing to rely on commit messages to guide this time travel.
And I researched how to write good commit messages.
But because I was making these small visual changes, sometimes just color changes.
Do I add in hex values to my commits?
And I was making small changes and experimenting.
And so I had a lot of trouble finding the right commit to mix.
I started to wonder if there was a better way.
So I'm a super visual person.
I've always been a super visual person.
This is my second career.
I used to be a geologist.
We look at rocks.
Rocks have orientations and we take pictures of them.
And we use these as documentation.
So as I was shifting, I started to look for ways that that visual documentation would show up.
One of my first open source projects was I was applying to Outreachy.
And I was trying to create a dashboard.
And I found myself really wishing, as I was looking at these requests, to know where the dashboard had been in the past.
Because I was not only trying to learn a new language.
Yes, I tried to apply to Outreachy using a language I hadn't worked in before.
So I was trying to learn that new language.
But I was also trying to kind of see where the dashboard had been.
And so I talked to the developers and said, do we have screenshots of this?
I'd really love to see it.
And they said, well, no one does that.
And I said, oh, wow.
There's a whole industry that doesn't think like me.
How amazing does that feel?
So I could have felt kind of bad about that.
But I realized that I wanted to make something.
Is it five minutes already?
It really is.
That's really depressing.
Sorry.
Let's give her a round of applause.
Is that talk online tonight?
Yeah.
The full version of that talk is online.
So you can also just go and watch it.
It'll be good.
I'll post it.
So next up, Mason.
Paul, are we set to do a raffle prize?
Another five minutes.
OK.
We do have raffle prizes.
Our funny Python script to raffle them off
has not happened today, I guess.
The irony there is not lost on anybody.
Anyone know a Python developer?
Oh, that is really hyper contrast.
Can y'all hear me?
Talk right close to the mic.
All right.
So Mason is going to talk about Teal's program,
computer science, in every high school.
I love it.
Let's give him a round of applause.
OK.
So in my talk earlier today, I mentioned
that I am a volunteer for Teal's.
And I'm going to take this quick time
to do a five-minute spiel on what Teal's is.
So Teal's is a nationwide program
that aims to pair industry professionals
with teachers who do not have the experience
that they need to be teaching computer science
in high schools, but are being forced
into these situations because of the demand
for computer science educators.
A lot of these statistics that I'm going to use
and put out here are going to be mostly
strictly based on Texas because I gave this talk
at HomeAway with my regional manager literally
yesterday, and I have all of those stats,
but I guarantee you these apply across the nation.
From what we've actually heard,
Texas is actually doing a little bit better
on the computer science education than most.
So I think a couple years ago there was a poll
that came out that 85% of parents want their children
to be learning computer science in high school,
or in some form of primary education.
Currently today in Texas, as it stands,
60% of schools do not offer a single computer science course
through their entire primary school curriculum,
all the way through secondary school and all of that.
So no CS whatsoever.
You get a typing course on how to use Word,
but you don't get any sort of programming.
And what ends up happening, and I give a similar talk
at Texas State University, my alma mater,
where I usually poll who's a math major,
and I tell them, congratulations,
you're now a computer science educator
because you're going to take this class in college
and you're going to know computer science
and you're going to be asked to teach this.
They basically pick a random teacher
who has had some sort of programming experience
in their collegiate career, and they go,
oh, you now have to teach AP Computer Science A,
which is the advanced Java course that basically covers
all the way through data structures
and object-oriented programming,
and oh, you only get one year to teach it.
It's extremely difficult.
I'm currently doing that right now at a school
about 20 miles that way in Idea Montopolis,
and I will tell you right now,
I came out of a program from a high school that did this,
and we're talking getting from Hello World in Java
to abstract classes and interfaces
and being able to implement them in a timed test
by the end of the school year.
It's insanely difficult.
So what we need is we need educators,
or what we need is we need professionals
to pair with these educators
who have the professional experience
that can teach and help us teach not only the students,
but the main goal is to help educate the teachers
so that way after a couple of years,
the teachers would be able to teach this class on their own
without our help anymore.
I guess the example that we use is
imagine that you had a single AP French class,
or you had a single French class in college,
and then you are told you're going to be given
10 weeks over the summer to learn French,
and now you're going to be teaching French AP next semester,
oh, and I hope all your students pass that test.
That's the reality of what's happening.
But what if we also said,
well, also what we're going to do at the same time,
we're going to put four native French speakers
in your classroom,
and they're going to help you not only teach the course,
but they're also going to help you teach how to teach the course.
Makes it a little bit easier, right?
So that's what TEALS aims to be.
So there are varying levels of volunteership that you can do.
I myself went in, you know, deep end
with the I teach three times a week
from 8 to 9 o'clock before I go to work every day.
You can be a teaching assistant,
and that's kind of at the same level.
That's at the co-teach model.
If you don't have that kind of time to develop, to dedicate,
that's awesome.
You know, I understand we all have busy lives.
You could also do what's known as the lab assist model,
which is where, you know,
maybe the teacher has a little bit of experience in the classroom
teaching this,
but doesn't need like a full-on co-teach environment
to learn how to teach those courses.
So what we end up doing is you'll just be a lab assistant
two times a week.
You come in, the teacher teaches the course,
and you're there to answer questions during lab,
maybe help with some of the other stuff.
If that's still too much, and you don't have,
like you have very little time,
they offer things, a classroom enrichment program,
which basically turns into a guest lecture program
where you go in every other week,
maybe once a semester,
and enrich the class with your experience.
Any level of time you can get,
they will find a place to put you.
And this is not also only in person.
They have an amazingly built remote classroom system
that they demoed for me yesterday at my talk at HomeAway,
and it's like unbelievable.
This is where education is going to go in the future
with remote educators,
and they're going to be leading the way with this tech,
because it's really cool.
So if you don't have a school in your local area,
and you still want to dedicate,
and you have this time to dedicate,
that's fine.
If you can get a webcam and a microphone,
they can set you up in your home,
and you can teach remotely.
So the main thing that we need here
is we need people to sign up.
If you are interested,
I would say go to teals12k.org slash volunteers,
or just check out the website, teals12k.
It has been worth everything.
It's really been worth it for me to get back in the classroom.
I came out of an extremely strong
high school computer science program.
Three years in high school, computer science,
high school, got all the way through
computer science four and three years,
and did multiple competitive programming things.
I have more medals that say I know Java
than I care to admit.
Also, this curriculum is not all Java.
There are multiple classes.
Java is kind of like the end course.
It's the top level AP.
There's a computer science principles AP course,
which teaches more about what the internet is and stuff,
and there's an intro course that they're piloting
that they're starting just in Python,
and they need Python developers to help with it,
and I'm out of time.
Round of applause for Mason.
I can breathe again.
I have to leave this plugged in for him.
Take it.
Mason, stay right there.
You're going to be the prop in the next talk.
Okay, so our next talk is Carl.
Carl is our videographer.
So let's give Carl a round of applause
for doing a great video.
And also for this talk,
and my answer to, can you teach me some Python?
Round of applause.
I used to hate that question.
Now I love it because...
Not enough hands.
I whip one of these out...
I whip one of those out of my backpack.
I hand it to the person.
They say...
Wow, how did it do that?
It didn't do it.
Now it did it. Whoa!
It blakes.
At all.
I have them plug it in.
It's a USB thumb drive.
Oh, by the way, it's Adafruit product 3333.
Circuit Playground Express.
And then their file manager comes up.
It's a thumb drive.
They open code.py with an editor.
That's it.
So if you can right click and pick open with editor,
you can put that over there.
Put that over there.
Oh, well, that makes sense.
If we would just have done rehearsal, this would have worked.
We're rehearsing.
And there you've got some Python code,
and you can show them if you touch the things,
lights turn on, and if they say,
how do you make it turn off,
you can talk to them about Python code,
and within five minutes, they're engaged in programming.
No virtual environments, no downloading,
no project management,
none of that boring stuff.
It's boring compared to, hey, how did that do that?
So there you go.
I'm done.
All right.
So next up is Paul.
Paul, what was your talk?
I was going to talk about custom argument types with argpars.
We're going to fix your mic first.
Get a little closer to your mouth.
Custom arg types with argpars.
All right.
Let's give him a round of applause.
So the last time I gave a lightning talk,
I went for 45 minutes.
So I wrote a script.
And I wrote it.
I wrote a script.
I hope I can get it done in five this time.
So I learned to use argpars
the last few months at my job.
And we needed to do some custom types.
Who uses argpars in here?
Writes CLI scripts
with command line arguments? Great.
So you can see I have
some sample code here
showing a simple parser.
I'm just going to run that.
And there's actually several arguments
that are defined.
Let's just look at a few of them.
So the first one is name.
And if I put in a name
Alice.
We can see that
unrecognized arguments AliceO
because it didn't do dash dash.
I don't know why
this is
being honoree.
Okay.
So we see I put in Alice.
It's a default argument. It comes out as a string.
No big deal.
Pretty basic.
If I want to say the type is going to be an integer
then I can add
And now
if I see the quantity is not in quotes
it's actually been converted to an int
and I can use it as an int.
I can also define other
custom arguments, argument types
if I write a method
that takes a string and will return
will check the contents.
So here's a case where I want to have a percent type.
So in my case I want to do a percent type
and it's going to be
So sometimes we want to give 110 percent
or our managers do.
Sorry.
110 must be in the range
from 0 to 100.
So that's the first test we have.
Let's make it 50 percent.
And so now percent
has been validated to be 0 to 100
and also converted to a float
so that I can now just do direct
multiplication with it in my function.
But the big interesting one
is that we have a lot of enums
in our test environment.
Large, small, medium,
brief
and testing for these arguments
we test for the name
and then we have to test for the string
of the enum and so forth
and then I thought that was very clunky.
I like using is for testing enum values.
So I wrote a
mixin
to go with our enum class
that allows me to use it directly
or almost directly as an argument type.
And in this type we
define a method.
It's going to take our string.
It's a class method. It's going to take a string
and it's going to try to actually use the
indexed access on an enum to give me back
the enum that matches.
If not I get a key error in which case I'll return
not valid.
I also have the string because
what I want, I think if you notice here
that if there's
no color provided
we're actually getting the list of the valid colors.
So I can say
let's say color is
some bad color. It's going to say
sorry that's not a valid color.
If I can say red
then what I got was actually not the
string red. I actually got the enum
color.red
and then if I want to
when I use that in my code
I can treat it
as an enum. So here I've got parsed
the arguments and now I'm going to say
if the color is
color.gold
I want to print pretty
and
oh I'm still doing 110%.
That's not so good.
Color is gold
and we're pretty.
So that little mixin
is sufficient
to take any enum
add it as a mixin
for archetyping and then I can
treat it as an argument
saying type is
color.argType and the choices are
color and that's all I need
to do to make that enum work
as a valid archetype for
argPars.
And this is a gist on github
gistgithub.com
slash PTMCG so you can
pull it down from there. Thank you.
Forty minutes.
Jay's going to give us a talk.
Title's not there so I need to look up over here.
Ask him.
Oh okay. So Jay's going to give us a talk
building and deploying a
site for beginners. Let's give
him a round of applause.
Okay so my journey with
coding has really started in
2012. It was with this
2014 with this online
programming class called Team Treehouse.
So who here has been coding with
Python for about a
year or less?
Okay very few of us.
Who knows someone that they
want to tell
Python that hey this is a good programming
language you can learn about for a
complete newbie? We got
some people right? So how would you
introduce that to them? There's some bootcamps you can
take in different areas
in different cities but what if you're
really remote somewhere? So my
journey started like with here.
It didn't end here actually.
But what I love about this system
is with Team Treehouse
they have so many different languages.
I was actually on a tech to be
program of theirs. This is a subscription
based model, $24 a month.
First I was actually trying to be
a full stack of JavaScript.
But I like how
Python is typed and how
I was reading it. That actually switched over
to there. And I was actually
learning how to build my own website.
So I'll show that to you right now.
And
it was, it was
it started with this program
but it turned into
a series of YouTube videos which I'll show in just a moment.
But this is what I built.
This is just, I built this
with Flask. I'm running this on SQLite
server. I deployed it on the node.
So
then I also used Bootstrap to
design the interface.
It's very simple but I have
an account. I can reset my email if I don't
remember it. I can change
my photo anytime. So for someone
who you want to show Python to
and say hey you can build your own website.
So who here has
their own website?
Who here has designed it and built
it on their own? Good.
Yeah so that's the power of
Python and if
you know someone who wants to demonstrate their work
this could be the place
for it. So what ended up happening was
I didn't need to use Team Treehouse.
Actually there's this
guy, I think he's the best
as far as step by step tutorials
on YouTube. It's free.
He does, he starts actually
with a lot of basic Python
language concepts
and in his videos
it's kind of a rabbit hole like for example
what is a
closure? Before that he talks about
what is a first class function and before that
he talks about what is a
decorator or something like that in that order.
So he has
this amazing class tutorial series and there's also
a Django tutorial series
that it's about maybe
five to six hours total
but I mean I love to dive
into things deep
when I'm looking at them. So
it ended up being maybe
ten hours in total. But this
will get you from
zero to knowing how to
access Linux, build SSH,
encrypt and make your site
secure because that's
kind of a complicated process.
This should not be so but
it was. But that's okay.
I also have
so with that
what I learned along the way
just for
someone like me who's learning
Python really on my
own, I've been
using OneNote to build a glossary.
I know there's a glossary and there's documentation
online already for these
different packages. But what
I've done is sometimes I just say
things in my own words. So for example
you can see here I was trying to learn about
SQLAlchemy.
Before that I actually was reading just
about SQLAlchemy itself.
So this is what
I would use as reference because
instead of having to access a website I can do this
offline. And like I said
it's in my own words. I also put down procedures
there.
And so that was a lot of help.
Next
this is
I don't know if anybody uses this but
at least for Windows this is a great
command line interface
called Commander. You can have multiple tabs
open. This is in PowerShell.
You can just also add
another one. Let's say it's
Command
Commander. So
that can be there as well.
You can have all these tabs open and available.
And I've been using
GitHub for my code.
And apart from that
I did a lot of this on my own
in my house, in coffee
shops.
So if you know
someone who wants to learn this language
they can learn it online
and actually do it pretty much
for free at the start. But eventually
you want to get to know
people and that's what I did. So
that's why I'm here. I just found out about this
convention two days ago. So
that is all for me.
Alright.
I have an idea
what the answer might be.
Let's have a round of applause.
Hello again everybody.
This will be a quick talk.
I get this question a lot of times
being a test guy and I gave the whole talk about
EGAD, how do we write better tests. So which
one is better? Unit test or pie test?
What should we pick for writing our tests?
Before I give my personal
opinion of answer I want to just compare the two
and just kind of
shake out things. So has
everyone seen the Python developer survey from
2018?
Yes, no, maybe? Yeah, yeah. If you haven't
just Google it, it gives a whole bunch of cool
statistics on the Python developer
community that was done in collaboration
with the Python Software Foundation as well as JetBrains.
If you look at that survey
it's interesting. Of the people who
are using test frameworks in Python
46% use pie test
whereas only 32% use unit test.
Unit test
is pretty nice. The best thing about
unit test is that it comes with the standard library.
You don't need to install anything extra, it's
there from the get go. There is nothing wrong
or particularly bad
about unit test.
However, when you look at pie test
pie test is a little bit more powerful
and a little bit cleaner. When you
write your tests in pie test you can
write them as functions. Whereas in unit
test it shoe horns you into a class
structure. Personally I prefer
the functional style of writing
test functions.
Some other things, with pie test you get those fixtures
that are more reusable.
You also can scope fixtures
to individual test level
versus module level, it's really nice.
And pie test also has plug-ins
galore. If there's a plug-in
for something you want, pie test
probably has it. If you want parallel execution
pie test extest. If you want code
coverage, pie test cub. If you
want integrations with Django or
Flask, it's there.
I also just want to shout out, in case you missed it
Nose is dead. I strongly
recommend not using the Nose framework.
So
now to my opinions. Overall
I think Python is one of the best languages
for test automation period.
It's because it's Pythonic, it's
easy to pick up for beginners, it's powerful for
power users. I also personally
think pie test is one of the best frameworks in
understanding language. Particularly because
it has test functions, because
of its plug-ins, and also
because of its fixtures. It's a very, very
nifty way of handling things.
Personally, I also like pie test BDD2.
BDD,
behavior driven development. If you don't know what that is
I recommend you look it up. It's a really cool way to write tests.
And so with all that to say,
personally I prefer pie test over
unit test. Thank you.
Alright, let's give Ernest
a round of applause.
Hello, I'm Ernest.
I like to bicycle because it makes me feel strong
and beautiful.
I also work for the Python Software
Foundation. If you're not aware of what the
Python Software Foundation is, we're going to do that
really quickly. First off, it is
a legal entity that takes care of the copyright,
trademark, and intellectual property
for the Python programming language.
We also support the Python
community via infrastructure, both technical
and fiscal. From a technical
perspective, it's things like Python.org
and PyPI.org. From a
fiscal perspective, we can support any
project that aligns with
our mission by letting them sort of
hang out under the umbrella of our 501c3
status. We also
provide grants worldwide.
Over $300,000
in counting and sort of going up with time.
And 75% of those grants
are distributed outside of the US.
Those grants go to things like
the Django Girls, PyLadies
workshops, meetups, and
regional Python conferences
like...
There's one in Texas. What's it called?
Yeah, oh, PyTexas.
Right.
Additionally, the PSF puts on
PyCon every year. If you're not aware
of what PyCon is, PyCon is a
conference that happens in, I think it's
Cleveland, Texas.
So it's only three hours
from here.
Oh, I'm sorry. It's actually
in Cleveland, Arkansas.
So it's eight, nine hours
from here.
Oh, Tennessee. Cleveland, Tennessee.
Which is
fourteen hours from here?
Sixteen? Oh, here we go. Okay, so
Cleveland, Ohio.
So it's a twenty hour drive.
And it's not too
late to come. And as a matter
of fact, if you want, you could just like
take a caravan with me. I'm heading back
that way in my car after
PyTexas. So you could just get in your car
and come along with me.
But sincerely, there are some tickets left for PyCon
if you haven't made
arrangements yet.
And in preparation for this
lightning talk, I realized that next time
I do a road trip, there are a lot of
Cleveland's I could go see.
Alright, round of applause.
Let me introduce you
and then you can go.
Michael. Michael put his talk title as
Senior Network Security Infrastructure
Engineer. I think that's your title. I thought I was asking
my title, not my talk's title. I was confused
why there wasn't another field. I thought you'd want
to know what the talk was about, too.
So I went back to edit it and there was no other field.
Anyway, that's who I am.
Alright, so the talk is actually
it's not how good this happened to me.
No, it isn't. It's Python Unicode
Adventures. Let's give him a round of applause.
So spoiler alert.
This talk is recycled
and also you're getting the five minute version of a
thirty minute talk.
But anyway, this is about Unicode
and the problems that I've had with it.
And just the simple
fact, first of all
not doing live coding demo here.
These are the kinds of
problems that you run into
trying to deal with Unicode
versus ASCII in Python.
The long and short of it is that
back in the day we all used ASCII
and Python was built back in the day
and it still wants to use ASCII
most of the time. The hilarious
thing about this particular error
is that the program
crashes while trying to
print a Unicode
character and then successfully
prints the Unicode character
in the stack trace.
Now you may
have noticed
that the problem here is that I'm using
Python 2 now if you're like me
and you have to maintain some legacy code
it's a fact of life, you have to live with it
and at least not break things that were already
working. But assuming
that you switch over to
Python 3, that should fix all
of your problems, right? Because Python 3
uses Unicode by default instead of ASCII.
So it's a lot
simpler, we just print and we get the
same crash and now in Python 3 it fails
to print the stack trace correctly.
So
I'm not sure that I have time
to get through all of the reasons why this
is a problem and continues to be a problem in 2019
so let me see if I can
give you the short version.
ASCII was nice because
it skipped a lot of steps. We had a direct
mapping of characters
to numbers
and those numbers were all
one byte.
With Unicode though
things get a little more complicated.
We have direct mappings
of characters to numbers
but those numbers are not
mapped directly to bytes. There are
actually a lot of different types of encoding that you can get
for Unicode. Some of them represent
all characters. Well, not
all characters. Some of them represent more characters
than others. And the one that you're going to be using
most of the time is going to
be UTF-8
which will
I don't know what's going on
here. There's some problem with it.
You know what?
I would explain it.
So anyway
when you're working in Python specifically
Unicode is a type of variable
although if you're on
Python 3
skipping over a bunch of stuff here
this is the nice little disambiguation table
that you should use.
Basically in Python 3
strings by default are representations
of Unicode code points
so they don't map directly to bytes
until they have to.
In other words until you're outputting them
to something outside of the Python language
like a file or your
terminal or the network
and at the point where you have to convert
a Python Unicode
object into some bytes
you have to go through your encoding
and you have to basically settle
on how that character should
be represented in bytes.
According to the official
Python how to
on how to use Unicode in your code
basically don't
care about encodings as much as
possible. Just use the built in
Unicode objects that the language gives you internally
and let the interpreter
handle the encoding
when it needs to talk to something else.
But as we saw earlier that actually
doesn't work a lot of times.
You can handle the encoding yourself
manually by using
Unicode or .dcode on your
string objects.
To make
a long story short
Python does its best
to detect the preferred encoding of the file
it's writing to.
So when you're running a script
in a terminal it's going to actually
ask the terminal, hey terminal what kind of
encoding do you want?
I don't know why it's
doing that.
And so the
reason that
the reason we can still get this
crash even on Python 3
is that it's possible to misconfigure your terminal.
If any of you have worked inside of
you know like Docker containers for example
if you just build like the default
Debian Docker container and you go in there
and you try to use Unicode you may get a crash.
Because out of the box it doesn't
have a lot of environment variables
set and there's one
in particular
here we go
lcctype is an environment
variable that is going to signal to
not only Python but to a lot of programs
what type of encoding they should use when they're
talking to the system. And so if you
explicitly tell it that it should use Ascii
then it's going to try to use
Ascii and it's going to fail to print
this multi byte number
in one byte.
So yeah that's kind of
the long and short of my talk or I guess the short of my talk
5 minute version anyway.
And there are further problems if you try to do this
at the end of the stage.
Alright round of applause.
And on that note. Okay so Jeremy is going to give us a talk
making PyTexas happen
legally.
Alright cool. So
some of you may have been coming
to PyTexas for a while.
We might be the oldest
regional Python conference
in the US
at least. Apparently the question
is whether PyOhio
happened earlier or later in the year
in 2007. That's like
the question about who is actually
the
first regional.
Anyway so we started out as PyCamp
Texas and then
two years later
adopted the name PyTexas.
And then
for a few years we carried along and
then
until 2012 the important thing to note
is there was one person running this group
running the whole thing okay.
Which is okay because it was actually only a couple dozen
people that would come to each year.
I think I started coming in 2010
and there were like 30 or 40 of us
in Waco.
And then as we grew
it became more and more difficult for people
to, for this one
person to do it. It was Sheila Allen if you
know her.
So in 2013 Sheila kind of backed away
and we had a group
organize it for the first time ever.
And that group
also decided to start charging because
we would have people say yeah sure I'm coming and then
they wouldn't come. And that by the way
is the primary reason why people
pay to go to the conference.
So that
led to a problem right. If we're going to take
money including sponsored dollars
how do we do that? Well
as
Ernest just mentioned the PSF
jumped in and helped us out with
funding. We could send our funds
to the PSF and then they would reimburse us for
charges and that worked out really well
except it took a while. And everybody
had to put dollars like you know like we
we would get reimbursed and all that.
And also
the logistics have improved greatly in the last
five years, in the last two years.
But it just took
was kind of a problematic process for us.
So we thought it would be easy and we decided
to just do it ourselves. So in 2014
we founded the Pi Texas
Foundation which is a registered non-profit
corporation here in Texas.
And the next year we got the Department
of the Treasury to agree that we're a 501C3
because if we ever go
under any profits that we make we'll actually
go to another non-profit. Guess
which one it would go to.
And
then we even got
come on
there's actually
I don't know why that would be
challenging.
Cool.
Well you can see it here. I don't know
why you can't see it up there. But
we got a logo. It's blue
and it's yellow and it's in the shape of Texas.
And we actually talked to the Python
the PSF logo committee
because they have for very good reasons
have to protect their trademarks.
They actually said they liked this one so that's nice.
So anyway here's the
world since then.
We were in College Station again in 2014
we get our 501C3
and boom we're in 2019
now. So what's the governance of the
PyTexas Foundation? There's a board
of directors. Currently there are three of us.
There are four officerships
that are sort of mandated
by our bylaws.
Interestingly if you
note that there are three
directors and four officers
that means that one person is doing
two people's jobs. And
the good news is we can grow our board.
So we have some committees
for example for the conference. Semi-annual
meetings that's all.
So we're interested in
building support for the foundation.
It is not
that much work. It's mostly
coming to meetings and making sure that
you sign things.
So if you're at all interested in the foundation
and I'm talking to some of you who've been around
in the community for a while and also
some of you who are brand new who can bring new ideas
to it. We're really
interested in hearing from you.
Can't promise a board seat but I can promise that
we will find a way to
let you contribute to
the community. So
let us know. Show up at meetings.
They're on Google Hangouts. It's not hard. And really
that's it. And then one last thing that
I think is important but
Google doesn't is
man it
really doesn't like. So the foundation
is not the conference. Every year
kind of a new group of people could
work on the conference.
There's a standing committee
that has worked on it but they're not at all
the same. So I think Dustin tomorrow
is going to be talking about how to contribute
to the conference which is a much
more immediate need every year.
But the foundation
and the conference are not the same. I'm really glad you took the picture
of the broken slide.
And that's it. That's it for me.
Thanks.
Applause
Do you think you can make it work again?
Let's try it.
We're going to get this done.
This is going to be really
awkward but it's going to work.
And
in order to do this talk you're going to have to
direct your attention to the other screen.
No it will be on the screen.
It will be on the screen right when you start.
To be fair the screen cast did work
the moment I sat down.
Laughter
Applause
Alright this is going to be hard.
I love it. I love it.
Laughter
Hold on.
You're going to see
something.
Laughter
Okay. Alright.
Let's give Josh a round of applause.
Applause
Is this working?
Everyone turn your heads.
Laughter
This is as good as it's going to get alright.
There we go.
Okay so when I showed up today
I wasn't exactly planning on giving a lightning
talk but over lunch I was talking to
and I was showing this really cool terminal emulator
program and he was like oh
you should present on this. There are a lot of
guys that like hacking with python and I go oh
that's fair. And I know when you're not
surrounded by other people who are enthusiastic
about python or actually developing on your own
computers that you might kind of get the itch
to develop in python. Well this can kind of
scratch that. Here we have
our handy dandy
boom. There we are. We are at home
on your android device using termux
on our phone. I mean we can do simple things.
You want to do some
minor subtraction.
There it is. You're like oh that's
pretty cool Sorensen but what if I want to develop
on my phone. Like I really want to
develop. I said oh I hear you.
Okay so here we are.
We're running a tmux session so
I can just simply transfer over
to another window and I go okay
I want to write something
so I'm going to pull up my faithful
emacs client and
I'm going to open my little python
development project. And this
I cobbled together over lunch.
It's a small script
that takes in a user input. Oh
is this mirrored? Oh god.
Okay.
Well it takes
in a user input and translates
it to morse code
and then vibrates the phone. It does a little
system OS call in morse
code. Just
because.
And so I'm not going to do
any of this live so we'll switch
over to another tmux window
and
go and call our
little morse generator through
python. Well that's pretty cool.
There we go. Now it's running and it's asking for
our input. Let's see what I can
spell sideways. Let's see if there's
a pytexas
and pyworks whatever.
And then we run it and
you can't feel it but I can. My phone's vibrating
and it's punching out the morse code
there. So if you're
ever just needing development public
there you go.
That's it.
Alright.
Paul, thank you.
We did it.
Alright.
We only have one last time to do.
Actually we have two last
things to do. Okay so
I'm going to
raffle off, not raffle to
the speakers. I'm going to give
to one of the speakers. Hold on.
To one of the speakers I'm going to give
this lovely water bottle
that is our speakers gift by the way.
So if next year
you become a speaker, get a talk
accepted at the conference, submit a CFP
you might win maybe not this exact water bottle
but something quite nice like it.
As our appreciation
for all the speakers that have done a really excellent job
giving a talk today. We don't have
enough for all the lightning talk speakers. We have one
for one of them. So we're just going to
I don't know why I'm showing it
twice. We're just going to random not choice this right now
and see who it is. That's Andy.
Andy, congratulations.
Thank you.
It's a very powerful water bottle.
Okay so thank you to all the lightning
talk speakers. Thanks for all the talks today.