This is Gabby, she's a Google Developer Advocate.
She also maintains an intimidating Lego collection,
which is, I think, a perfect way of describing it,
because I'm definitely afraid of stepping on one Lego,
let alone thousands of Legos.
So she's gonna talk to us a little bit
about machine learning.
So, welcome, Gabby.
Thank you.
Good afternoon.
I think it's afternoon, so good afternoon.
I'm gonna give you a spoiler.
I'm not gonna talk about machine learning per se,
because I don't know machine learning.
I'm a developer.
What I know, it's APIs.
So what I'm gonna show you and teach you here
is how to use machine learning APIs
for you to use in your own applications
without having to know machine learning.
So that's the point of my talk,
and I hope you like it.
So let's start.
So what is machine learning?
It's about solving problems without specific rules.
It's not able to learn by the example
and set up new answers based on the example
that you just gave to them.
And I have a colleague that says
machine learning is just a thing labeler, essentially.
And on the Tuesdays, it's kind of like that.
And if you can label anything,
you can process the data and then create predictions
and that kind of stuff.
So I wanna do an exercise with you first.
How would you identify the following images
that I have in here?
I have an apple, and I have an orange.
So tell me, how would you differentiate
one thing from another?
Color?
Shape, okay.
So someone said color.
And if you have this, how do you differentiate that?
Just by shape, right?
I could create a script before when it was red and orange
that could count how many pixels red I have,
how many pixels orange I have,
and then based on the ratio, say it's an apple,
it's an orange, but if I have a green apple,
those just go out of the blue.
So this doesn't work.
So what about a dog and a muffin?
That's easier to differentiate, right?
The dog has two eyes, a nose, a mouth,
and a muffin just looks nice.
But what if you have this?
Is that a dog and a muffin?
That's a bit different, difficult.
And this, it's a mouth, or I don't know the brain,
but like this one here, it's my favorite.
So machine learning comes to solve this kind of problems
to help you identify these kind of differences
without having to have a human eye to look at it.
So it's loosely based on how the human brain works.
It's to solve the problems without knowing specifically,
setting up ifs to know the answer for it,
or trying every possibility to know the answer for it,
and enable systems that improve over time.
So when you have a prediction on machine learning,
you have a confidence level of that prediction
is true or not, and I'm gonna show you later.
So at Google, we have five machine learning APIs
that's for vision, the vision one's for processing images.
The cloud video intelligence processing video
gives you timestamps on the video,
what was said, and that kind of stuff.
Cloud speech is similar to the video,
but it can do live also.
And cloud translation also, it does about a thousand pairs
of different languages to translate.
And cloud natural language that helps you identify
sentiment analysis, for instance,
on a given sentence that you give it.
So the cloud vision API,
that's the first one that I wanna talk.
I wanna talk about three.
It's for detecting images that are complex,
just with a REST API request,
and you can do label and write detection
would be saying, hey, this is an elephant,
this is gray, and that's gonna give you the tags
around the image to get the text out of an image
using OCR to detect logos that you have.
If there is a popular logo that you have around,
it's gonna detect and say, hey, there is a logo here.
Landmarks also detect for you.
You take a picture of a landmark
and you can detect where it is.
Crop hints is like what you do in Instagram.
It gives you a hint of how to crop the image to be square.
And then explicit content detection,
because a lot of the content we get sometimes is from users
and we don't know what they are doing.
So instead of just showing you can't see
is this image safe, it's gonna tell you it is or not
with a confidence level.
So I have a demonstration here of the cloud vision API.
This first cell here, just ignore it,
is just to break it nicely, and I want your help here.
I hear I'm importing the cloud vision API
and then sending which file it is,
sending out the file URL and getting the image annotated
and showing up the image in the end.
So this is image.
Where it is?
Okay, Golden Gate Bridge.
So let's see, I'm executing, no.
It's the 25th of April Bridge in Lisbon, Portugal.
It's similar, but it's not same.
And you can do it with another one too.
Now you don't trust me anymore.
But like, what is this?
Okay, let's see.
No, it's a fire and hotel and casino.
So even images that are similar,
that looks like landmarks,
you're able to detect that's different.
So you can also get different labels around the image.
It says it's a landmark, it's a tower.
Tourism, because it's Las Vegas,
so it's involved with tourism and other tags.
And here I'm getting a random image
because we have this thing called web detection.
And you can say, hey, I want to see visually similar images
to the one that I just uploaded here.
This is useful if you're looking,
you can have full match images too.
If you're looking, let's say you took a picture
and you wanna see if someone in the web
got your picture copied on their blog
or something like that,
you can look for copyright infringement with this
to know if someone took the same picture as you
and put on their content.
So that's unused for that.
This one is to get visually similar,
not necessarily the same, and showing off here.
So it's executing, go internet.
And this is not the same image, but it's similar.
You see it's the same monument.
And I'm getting a random image.
And if I get it again,
it's another picture of the same thing.
So it's able to detect not only,
there is a landmark, which landmark it is,
and find similar images to it too.
There's also a cool thing called auto email
that I'm gonna talk in the end.
And if it is, if there's time, I'm gonna show it to you.
So the Google Cloud Vision, the code is near,
it's just this, it's 13 lines with comments.
And with that, you can put anywhere in your code
to just figure out what you're being uploaded,
or if it is a safe image, for instance, or not.
And in this case, getting a landmark.
The next one, oh, I'm sorry.
If you use Giphy, you probably use Cloud Vision,
you're not, don't realize.
And if you wanna read a bit more,
just look at their engineering blog.
They have a blog post saying
how to use Cloud Vision in production.
So when you search by sometimes,
there you probably are using a Cloud Vision API
to get that answer.
Second one, the Google Cloud Translation.
It translates over 100, actually 120 languages now,
and you can have 1,000 pairs or so more,
as I said before, of comparison.
And you can use to translate text
from one language to a target language,
or detect the language that a text is from.
Let's say you got a flyer, a post,
and you don't know what is written
and what language it is,
so someone sends you an email,
you don't know the language,
you can use the Vision API, the Translation API,
to detect which language is being said there.
So one of the examples that we have
is the Google Translate app,
and you can just show an image
and kind of combine the Vision,
get in the OCR, and translate whatever is in there
to another language, so you know.
I have a little demonstration here.
So this, I'm gonna just say something in Japanese,
which I don't know how to pronounce,
I'm not gonna try,
and I'm gonna target translate to English.
And once I say, after instantiating the client here,
once I say which is the text,
or what is the target language,
you'll notice I didn't say it is Japanese at the beginning,
it's gonna figure out that it's from Japanese to English.
And that's gonna be what it's written there.
And you can translate to any language that you want.
Just that, if it is possible,
we have a, on the website there is a list
of the languages that are possible to be translated.
So you can use this to translate any text that you have,
that user input that you got,
and you can get it in different languages,
especially if you're using a multi-language application.
So this is the code with comments and the print,
it's about 18 lines,
and that does the translation for you.
So you don't have to go to the Google Translate itself
to translate for you, you can just use the API.
And my favorite one is the natural language.
The natural language API helps you understand,
with a simple request, things like extract entities,
and entities here are not like entities on the web,
it's like, oh, I went to a restaurant and ordered sushi,
it's gonna say that restaurant is a local,
and sushi it's a food, and that's a type of entity.
And detect the sentiment on a sentence,
and when I was, I'm Brazilian,
so when I was learning Portuguese,
Portuguese is not an easy language,
it had like this thick book on analysis, syntax analysis,
and I could never get that thing figured out.
And with this API, you can actually get,
say, this is a verb, this is a conjunction,
this is adverb, and you can stop having to worry about that.
And in the end, classify content, but there is a caveat.
The classifying content API only works with English,
it doesn't work with other languages.
So, first off, I have the sentiment API here,
I just said I went to the restaurant and ordered sushi,
the food was really good.
Even though it was negative, the score,
it's still on the neutral zone,
because it's, I'm not saying anything bad about it,
it's just a bit, see, it's neutral.
But the overall score of the whole document,
it's positive, it's 0.3.
And the magnitude says, like, it's from zero to infinity,
it tells you how much intention and sentiment
is on that thing.
So, 0.9 is the whole overall magnitude of document.
The food was really good, I think,
because of the word good, is 0.8, it's a bit higher.
So, as I say, syntax analysis,
and analyzing that sentence that I just wrote before,
we can see how the words depend on each other.
So, you see here that root, the root word is go,
and that's the lemma, which means like,
it's like the main thing on a sentence,
and this case is go and order,
that's two things that you couldn't,
if you remove from the sentence, it doesn't make any sense.
And the food was really good,
it's the B for that,
and tells which word depends on each thing.
So, I would have totally cheated on my exams
if I had that before, but that's available for you too.
Content classification, as I said before,
it's only in English, but notice here,
I don't mention, it says it's baseball,
and I said before, I always have a confidence level
that says how much confident it is on the prediction.
You don't see baseball mentioned on the news there,
you just see some names of a team maybe,
and a player, but he knows that that player,
it's from a baseball team,
and that he has this probably with 99% chance,
it's a baseball article, so that's part of it.
I have a demonstration here to integrate the three APIs
that I showed you before.
So, I'm gonna get the Google Cloud Vision API,
and gonna import an image from our article,
translate it to English, detect,
and see what that article it's about.
So, if you know Portuguese,
you may know what this is about,
but if you don't know, you can figure it out.
So, I took a picture from the newspaper,
and I have this article here.
So, I'm gonna translate, let me execute this first one,
okay, I'm gonna translate, not translate,
I'm gonna get the OCR of that image.
So, notice that it came with the same break things,
break lines as the article came,
and it has all the text from there,
but when you translate, the break lines doesn't matter,
because I'm gonna tell you, it's not 100% accurate,
but it's good enough just to be able
to be used formally as a translation.
So, here it's a translation, and it does a translation
even though the text was not well formatted,
was able to do the translation,
and on the language classification,
it's gonna tell you what it is about,
and with 82.9%, it's about jobs and education
with regards to education.
So, the article actually was about SATs in Brazil,
how students were gonna take the SATs.
So, it is about education.
So, that's one of the demos.
And as I said before, if I had time,
I was going to talk about AutoML Vision.
So, AutoML, it's like, let's say you have,
this is all pre-trained models with Google data,
public data sites that we got from the internet.
But let's say you don't wanna use that,
you want to use your own data to classify content,
and if you use that, that data belongs to you,
it does not go to the Google's model, only for your model.
And in this case here, I wanted to train clouds.
And what best place to predict the clouds than the clouds?
There is no other place.
So, I wanted to predict clouds.
I know there is way more than five types of clouds,
but for simplification purposes, I only did five in here.
Yes, I only did five in here.
And once you do that, you can train your model
because you import the images as a upload,
you can upload from your computer.
If you have a bucket on Google Cloud Storage,
you say the CSV, you say the image URL and the label,
and you can import that.
And once you train your image, you can see here
the confusion matrix of how that thing performs.
And you can see that outer stars,
it's highly confused with cirrus and cumulus.
But here, the higher the volume on the diagonal,
the better model you have.
Probably the problem is with that,
it's because I don't have much outer stratus pictures.
I only have, you need at least 800 of each to train a model,
but I only had 135 and all the other ones I have over 400.
So, that's why it's confusing for the model.
And I took a picture, not here,
because I tried to take a picture outside
and there is no clouds outside.
So, I took a picture and I'm gonna show you the picture.
When my, where's my mouse?
So, this is a picture in Florida, which was nice.
And I'm gonna try to predict what type of cloud that is.
I'm not sure if the prediction is correct
because I'm not a cloud specialist.
I once was on a talk that the guy,
my guy was specifically a meteorologist
and he's like, your prediction is wrong.
I was like, I'm sorry.
But, let's try to predict it.
And there is a thing called, you need to warm up the model.
I hope the model is warmed up to predict.
Yeah, it is.
So, this image was not in my collection.
It's a picture that I took myself.
And with 97.3%, you can see that's a cirrus type.
And everything here is trying to sum to one in the end.
But like, it can have at most one as 100% confidence
but that's not always possible.
So, if a high confidence level,
you can see that's a cirrus type of cloud.
And with that, I'm gonna go with questions.
And that's it.
uz
Zap
Thank you for the great talk.
Is it possible to take out images
like, for example, in sign language,
images like train the using learning here?
Yes, so it was interesting that you said sign language
because one of the examples we have,
it's with sign languages, but one of the difficulties
is because I don't remember which letter
was really complicated to make and was hard to get images,
so we had this friend that,
I'm not the developer advocate
that usually does machine learning,
I do as a sidekick sometimes,
but she was training the model,
everybody had to learn a bit of sign language
to take pictures of her so she could train the model,
so yes, you can do that, but you need to have data,
that's the hardest part, you know.
If I did, I mean the signs and stuff?
You need to train the model, to train the model,
you need to have images and the label,
for sure that you know for sure that's right,
so you can train the model, so yes, it's possible,
without any code.
Okay.
Well, I have two questions.
Go ahead.
You mostly use Google Cloud,
so can you talk a few words about how easy it is
to set up something like this,
because it's something which I'm very busy
for the user who doesn't do it much.
How hard is this set up process?
It's really easy, because you need to go through,
if you use Google Cloud, you need to go through a project
and enable the API, because the API can't disable,
so enable the API, and then once it is enabled,
if you deploy inside Google Cloud,
you don't need to have credentials,
because you can set up, you can say,
if it is on the same project, you can say,
hey, it's the same project, it has access to these APIs,
but the problem is if you're doing local,
you need to create a service account,
and that's the hardest part,
and what you would do, extra step here,
would be on the, when you call the client here,
you would say, credential file,
and pass the file path to the code,
so that's the hardest part, it would be,
everything else is the same.
I have a question, a few questions, please.
So the classification, you said is only English right now?
Yes.
Are there any plans to expand that?
I don't know, I really don't know.
And then my second question is on classification.
You had categories in there,
is that something that you picked,
or does that come with the service?
It comes with the service.
You can actually, there is AutoML for natural language too,
so you can create, let's say you have tickets,
support tickets, and you wanna categorize
which category it is, and you wanna be able
to predict that kind of, for future tickets.
So if you know the label that it is currently,
you can train the model based on that,
and you get the category, not me,
and in the end have that predicting model for you.
Without code, again.
Any other questions?
Well, thanks.
Thank you.