All right for the next talk we have Eric and he's going to talk about solving the internet problem another thing that's here
Okay
Spoiler alert no, I've been working in public health overseas in
Botswana
Conducting clinical trial research in HIV AIDS using electronic as academics like to call it data systems in
remote areas of Botswana and
Doing that despite having not necessarily no internet, but no reliable internet
Just a little bit about Botswana. It's a middle-income country
landlocked in Southern Africa
population now just over 2 million and
It is landmass about the same size as Texas and although a bit drier
In the drier parts of Texas that are kind of looks the same
That's me at the last icon I was at in Namibia last year
I'm the
Former director of data operations and IT. So it's a pretty broad
job of the Botswana Harvard AIDS Institute
headed data management and IT teams there for over 25 NIH funded clinical trials and
during that time we developed clinical trial data management systems laboratory information systems and interface some of the analytical
laboratory equipment and
Right now I'm finishing up a trial that oddly enough. I'm running from the cloud
which is
We're enrolling people in Botswana, Malawi
Uganda South Africa and Zimbabwe and I'm not a medical person
But I've been surrounded by them for for a lot of years now
Clinical research in HIV AIDS, so this is an academic endeavor
Our investigators and research teams were built from or made up of international and local
people
Our work is funded by competitive grants
Almost exclusively from the National Institutes of Health here in the US
All of our trials were conducted in Botswana. I worked for
Max Essex at Harvard and being a virologist that he is all of our
Trials were had a heavy laboratory component
So in
Included in collecting all the data. We also collected
Probably a little bit over six hundred thousand blood specimens
to go with that a
little bit about HIV AIDS in Botswana
They I'm sure you know
Well, I would say that the real excuse me. The real problem is not no internet. The real problem is
The HIV epidemic
You probably know a lot about it
You also probably know about the epidemic even starting here in the 80s
but that was followed with a heterosexual epidemic in in Africa and
In Botswana around 1995 even though it already had started ramping up
It was very clear that there was a very serious epidemic underway
And by 2000 estimates were that 15 to 20 percent of the population was infected which is
amazing
life expectancy in Botswana was around 70 years and had dropped or expected to drop to around 40 and
there were projections from the McKinsey group that
Population of Botswana which at that time was about 1.2 million would half within the next 10 to 15 years if nothing was done
So in 2000 the president of Botswana stood in front of the UN and basically
Stated that his population is looking at extinction if nothing is done
We had already started
in a
trial funded by the NIH and
Bristol Myer Squibb
Bristol Myer Squibb where we were
Looking at ways of rolling out already approved adult treatment and that sort of merged in 2002 into a
National program which meant that the government agreed to then
fund
free
treatment
Testing monitoring whatever was necessary to get people
On to the drugs were then available and that program which still continues today is
The probably the most successful one in the world at the moment for combating HIV
So now to shift over a little bit about clinical trial data management
Yeah, someone said to me don't worry. I won't ever need that data, but we always do
Before I get into the solutions of what we did for offline use to take a few minutes just to talk about clinical trial data
management
So that you can appreciate why given
Limited resources and so on. Why don't we just keep it simple and and flip back to paper
because paper works, but
so my role in all of this was to
Support the research trials with data management and like I said, we built these laboratory information systems already where we're receiving
Resulting specimens storing the specimens interface and laboratory equipment and we built data management systems
this is prior the data managed systems and filing paper and
All kinds of stuff like that for the research clinics that we are currently working with
But paper is very difficult to work with and if you're dealing with large trials you start to trip over it
It's bulky. It's hard to change data can't be validated in real time need to transcribe information which has a
Fixed sort of 10% error rate
You've got to store the paper and then when you want to do quality assurance or you're trying to prepare for
Some sort of interim or final analysis. You've got to drag those papers back out and make corrections send them back to the clinic
Then get them back into your data center transcribe them again store them and this process just goes on forever and it turns out that
What'll happen is you get to some point in your trial where you want to do analysis and you can take eight to twelve
months to prepare a data set
Very often these trials are underfunded you ask for $10 you get six
Kind of things so no matter what you cannot afford to have these long lag times
For data preparation and when you get to the end of a trial, you're probably out of money already anyway
So having to say oh we need another 12 months of staffing to work on a data set
It's not going to be something you want to do plus you've got a lot of pressure to publish
To because that is in some ways the main deliverable so in 2010 I introduced to my team
Python and Django I
looked at other things, but I decided to do that and
We then got underway to develop
Basically data collection that we would do at point of care
and
our main metric was to say okay if
We say you want to freeze a data set for analysis
How long is it going to take from that moment?
To the point where we can actually do a fine do an analysis and we got that down from that eight to twelve month thing
down to
In our last one just a couple weeks
So we tried this system out
on one trial
We called them a Bonner trial. This was looking at trying to completely block transmission from a mother to a child
Successful trial we were able to show do that
but it was
We deployed this within clinics our research clinic
So it's a very comfortable turf and we had control of the environment
We were able to install connections and data connections and so on but then we had another trial
which was just a small one which we did in a neighboring village where we
Where we had to go into people's households that actually is a picture of somebody's household
and
That was different because now it's not our turf. We're actually operating in somebody's house
Kick us out and we can't sit there
anyway, and there wasn't good data connection there and we the group tried to do this on paper and
within a few weeks about six weeks the whole thing collapsed because the
Handling the paper just became a nightmare. You're collecting longitudinal data
You're collecting data from one household over a number of days
And it just it just became a nightmare. So we had to stop the trial and
Finish and kind of come up with another solution
The solution was our first iteration of offline use we had learned something already from
making from the mobana trial with how to do electronic data connection and data collection and
Management and we tried some offline use then in 2012
We got a grant for about the large grant about 80 million US which
You don't see that much on the ground, but that was the total apparently
And since it was so large State Department and CDC got involved as well
The trout brought together a lot of what we as data managers or our data manager team already had experience in now
We knew how to do real-time data collection real-time validation
We knew how to do the sort of the informed consent process how to handle HIV testing data treatment data
how to do blood collection chain of custody and all kinds of
questionnaires for men women and so on
Regulatory compliance how to protect personal information through encryption and things like that. We knew how to do all this but
this trial was different in that
It wanted we wanted to operate in 30 extremely remote villages with distances of
I'll say kilometers, but you know 700 kilometers away and things like that from where we were we were sitting so this is a different
This is different
So what was the current state of Internet in Botswana at that time so in 2009 3g was introduced
But they just focused on the major city centers and the amount of bandwidth that they could actually handle on those 3d connections
Pretty poor. It's mostly about like Facebook Twitter that kind of thing not really trying to do anything
And they're always really lopsided you can bring a lot of data in but you can't push data up
So you would prefer something symmetrical but fixed line penetration
It's only about 10% in the country. So that's also no good
The cost of a gigabyte around $70 per gigabyte, so that's pretty heavy
We weren't really sure what kind of data throughput we would have
And so we also looked at satellite
Like five dollars a megabyte or something like that
But there's also the complexity of dealing with satellite because we were thinking in terms of trying to do something in real time
Because that's what we were working with we had these systems that work really well, but they were online
So we wanted to see we could work with real time
I
Put into the budget pretty big trying to work with this five bucks a megabyte satellite thing
But when we started to have discussions and the CDC moved in they said oh by the way this internet budget
Can we remove that because we need that money for something else? I
Had a lot of arguments a lot of people to explain that you know, no matter what anybody tells you 3g is not going to support this
Anyway time went on into 2013 and 30 days before we
We started the trial we had already written our solution to operate sort of offline
They decided oh my gosh because they had a component of the trial that they were responsible for they wanted internet
So they suddenly came up with a lot of money and started helping us put up towers like this
Towers like this and we would we had 30 villages. They were to to we're doing a
Comparative trial so we had a control and an intervention sites and we would so there's 15 and 15
So we would go two sites at a time and we built these
Right before we got to the next pair these were being built and so we walked along the country like this
But these connections as expensive as they were
We
Put a half a million dollars into building these or they did and and
Recurring costs of like fifty thousand dollars, but we're looking at one megabit per second is all we could sustain
Which is okay for SSH and things like that, but it was one megabit
Hopefully a lot of most of the time during the day was unusable and at the only at night could it be usable?
So it's still not a solution to real-time data collection
So what did we do
So all we really are doing we came up with an offline solution and it's pretty simple
I'm not spoiler alert. There's no magic to not having internet
You don't have internet you don't have internet or you don't have a data connection Wi-Fi. There's no solution to that
But you know through asynchronous sort of approach you can you can come up with something
so we're using Django systems and
So we've got database if we can
first thing we do is we would we wrote some a little bit to
We added to each of our system a new model an outgoing transaction models a single model
and then we would also have an incoming transaction model sort of taking a almost like mail inbox outbox and
All of the
models within
Within the system for each of the
Questionnaires and forms and so on would all serialize into us each time you would hit a save method
They would sink serialized into an outgoing transaction
That transaction at some point would be all those transactions at some point coming out of that outgoing transaction model
Would be dumped into a file
The file then when we had some availability of some sort would be
SCP to cross to a remote machine which would and then
Reverse it read the file back in
Deserialize all the transactions and everything works and as long as we maintain the order of how they played out
Originally and then just play them back. Everything is fine
So what we had were
In some cases we would have 30 or 40 research assistants fan out into a village each one has a Mac air
They would go out for about four hour shifts because they're also collecting blood
They have to come back with their blood to what we had was a community server
Which is still not connected to any remote system
They would connect to a local Wi-Fi. We had a little Wi-Fi unit right there and they would connect to a MacBook
push in all
move in all of their transactions and
At some point maybe in the night or in a few days that community server would do the same thing and push all its
transactions to a headquarter server
so
Let's look at some some code
So we have an installable application Django collect offline
Which since these are Django applications you would?
Put in your install app you migrate you'll get those two tables outgoing transaction table in the incoming transaction table or model
those models simply have one field for the the serialized JSON and then some metadata for the
administration around that that transaction and
the incoming
Model is exactly the same
Just on the other end
So
to prepare a model for offline use if you have a model like
This one I think is a Django tutorial or something like that
I just added a report date time as we're always using that and I have my own little
Utility
package which uses
I'm always working with
timezone aware dates and for that
Anyway, then you have because you're going to serialize you have to have a unique
Constraint on at least one field or combination of fields
I was just going to say for the date time stuff. I use the arrow package would recommend that
So now and this is pretty much you can follow this pretty well in the end well described in the
Django documentation you're preparing a model for a serialization, so you have to add
Well what we did was we would make sure we would switch from a integer primary key to a UUID
So we wouldn't get any clashes
and
That's now has become part of Django, so you can use that but previously it wasn't
add a custom managers
Plus the natural key so you can do the full circle of serializing and deserializing
So that would be a model and this will we can you can also
Add foreign keys or in Django you have the sort of many to many
So it'll support all that kind of stuff
then the next thing is to
add a offline models module in your app and
That's just where you're going to register which models you want to include in this process
You don't have to include every model
You can either register them explicitly in that offline models py or you could be safer if you want the whole
application and all its models to to
to be a part of this, then you just register with the the app name and
That module will be discovered on boot up just like if you're familiar with Django Django has an admin
Has admin classes and when you boot up the system looks for an admins py and registers any classes in there
This uses the same the same approach some of the same code
so that as soon as you boot up, it'll look for that and it have a
a global site offline global that will you can refer to later in registry and
Then the last thing is some sort of post-save signal. So once every time you for any model that's registered if you save it
It's going to inspect to see if that model by name is registered in the global
And if not, it'll just raise an exception and pass or if it is then it's going to fire this to outgoing transaction method
And it will then serialize it and stick it in that outgoing transaction table
We also encrypt it for security purposes as you should
Yeah, so that takes care of
Everything that's happening on a client machine and everything that will happen in reverse on some remote server
and
The next thing then is to handle the sort of file events what's going to happen there. So that process is started by
One of our research assistants with their machine
They have a we had several different interfaces
so but it's basically just click and then that will export all those outgoing transactions into a file and
then we use a
module called watchdog
which will just monitor a
Directory for any events we had used this for some of the laboratory equipment that would drop
result files and just pick them up and pull them into a database so this worked well here as well and
Any sort of event you just pass it an event handler. This is just some simple code coming from the
From its own documentation, so we had different event handlers one was to
Export the outgoing transactions to a file another one would be to transfer files to a
Remote system so the files created and then it can move to the remote system
And another one would be that as soon as a remote system file gets dropped into a directory
It then pulls it up into the incoming transaction model
So that takes care of
database file get it across
Into they get the file across and then pull the file up there
So the watchdog is on a community server, or it'll be on the final node however many you want to have
but we only ever had
client community server and then
headquarters server and then obviously on the last database or whatever not the last one, but
The incoming there would be a post-save signal that would then deserialize all your models as I described earlier
so
That's kind of it, so I told you wasn't a little shocking solution, and so what does it look like in the field?
So
This is actually some people working in the field so you can see them with their little Mac air there
they actually came with the table and the chair and the CD4 counter and all the
equipment to
Collect blood and cool box and everything they they would had everything with them with they were going in
They have some discussion they collect the blood like that
they pack it all up and walk away and
This whole process with the data collection the blood collection everything like that and the testing the counseling and everything that could take
up to an hour hour and a half
And in some cases we would have families of like ten because old ladies would tell all their relatives to come
because they're coming to
participate in the research then
We had trucks like this which were our data center and laboratories so when
Sorry when he
Finishes then he goes to this truck. This is parked next to our laboratory
But this would be parked also in the field and we have a laboratory there for him to bring in his blood specimens
They would then be processed spun down
The data would be sync synchronized into our data center, which is just on the other end of the truck
The lab technician would then see the data on the server that they're accessing scan in the physical
The physical specimens to verify everything's okay
Then the research assistant will go back out to the next household and we're basically done and then up here
We had a little wireless bridge that would connect in some way to
That tower that you saw earlier when the connection was available and the data would end up
Where we wanted it
So we did exactly that
Across 30 villages for four years. We would collect serialized fine working internet transferred deserialized this whole process
and
We did our first
Enrollment in October of 2013 and got our first publication out in 2016
To show that Botswana actually
Had the best
Program available
Except I think Switzerland might have beat out with their point one percent prevalence
In the world's
Yeah, and that's it that's what we did so, thank you
You