Hey everybody, I'd like to thank the PyTexas organizers and also thank you for
coming to my talk after lunch. I know it's a little late, a little tired, let's
talk about some testing. So my name is Ali Sipji. I'm one of the organizers of the
Chicago Python users group and when I'm not doing that I'm writing backend code
for Numerator. It's a market intelligence company. So I love testing.
Writing tests gives me the satisfaction of a job well done. Tests help me confirm
that the change I made works exactly as expected. Tests also give me confidence
that my change didn't break existing functionality. It wasn't always this way.
I used to hack together spaghetti code around chunks of answers I found on
Stack Overflow. I didn't really care that I solved the problem, only that I
solved it enough to cross it off my to-do list. If I ever went back to the
project, I was afraid of making changes. I didn't want to upset that delicate
balance. Things worked. If I changed it, would they still work? Probably not. And
then I read Code Complete and this book changed the way I approached software
development. Steve McConnell made me realize doing things in a method,
methodical way is a lot more important than simply just solving the problem at
hand. I became deliberate about my approach and I started breaking problems
down into smaller and smaller chunks. After ensuring that each of these
smaller pieces worked as exactly as I intended it to, I can put these together
and create an entire system. And with tests, I can ensure that everything I did
worked exactly as I expected it to. So tests allow us to move fast because they
give us confidence in our code. Confidence that we're producing expected
results and confidence that we're able to modify our code base without
affecting existing functionality. In short, test-maker code more agile. I think
it's important to see testing in the context of a real application. So I got a
startup idea. It's called Word Count as a Service. So you send in a URL. It's
going to calculate some stuff and send you back language statistics. So right
now for MVP, we're only going to do one endpoint. It's going to be a top word
endpoint. And so you're going to send in a URL. It's going to return a response
with the most common word and the number of recurrences of that word. And so our
plan for world domination, we're going to build this MVP, get some funding. I'm
not too sure what. And then we got IPO. It's going to be great. So the
architecture of this application, it's a fast web app. It receives requests. It's
going to forward it to the, after processing, to the right business logic
module. That's where our secret sauce is. Once that's done, it's going to send
back results to the endpoint. Flask is going to save it to, or my web app is
going to save it to the database. And then it's going to return a response to
our client. So this is our secret sauce. I'm going to download this webpage using
this little known library called requests. I'm going to extract the text
using Beautiful Soup. And then the standard library's collections.counter is
going to help me count the words. And then I'm going to return the most common
word and the number of occurrences. So let's see that in code. And so here I'm
just going through some Flask configuration. I have my database model.
So I'm going to have the URL, the word, the number of occurrences. I have a helper
method to save to the database. We'll come back to that in a bit. These are my
Flask routes. So my webpage, sorry, my top word route, it parses a request, gets
our URL. It sends it off to our business logic module. So let's take a look at
that. So here we're going to download the webpage using requests, extract the text.
So I'm just going to be pulling all the things out of the paragraph tags. And I'm
going to flatten it out to get a list of words. And then I'm going to count the
words using the collections.counter. Going back, we're going to save to our
database. So here we just have, create an instance of a model, set the
attributes, add the record to the session, and then save it. And then we're going to
return back information to our user. Pretty standard web application.
So now let's talk about some testing fundamentals. So we all have a common
vocabulary going forward. So a system under test is a system that's currently
being tested. This could be a line of code, it could be a method, it could be
the entire program. And testing refers to the process of entering inputs into our
system under test, and then validating outputs against an acceptance criteria.
If our outputs are okay, our test passes. If our outputs are not okay, our test
fails. Hopefully we have enough contextual information to find out what
we should do to fix that test. So there are many different kinds of tests, but
they can be categorized into two broad categories. Black box testing and white
box testing. Black box testing refers to testing in which the tester cannot see
the inner workings of the system they're testing. And in contrast, white box
testing is a technique in which testers can see the inner workings of the system
being tested. As developers, we wrote the code so we could be doing white box
testing, but that's not to say there's not a need for black box testing. We
wrote the code, we wrote the test, we have those blind spots. So we can think of
all of our tests as a feedback loop that lets us know that our tests are working
and producing expected results. If our tests are passing, that's great, make your
commit, make a PR, go on to the next feature. If the test fails, we have to
figure out exactly what's going on. And the simplest form of testing is manual
testing. And this is something like refreshing a web page or doing something
in the REPL. And as the name implies, manual means you have to do something
yourself, like the developer has to do a specific kind of action. And this is not
really sustainable because if there's one universal truth in programming, it's
that developers are efficient. We need to make testing as easy and as barrier-free
as possible, otherwise developers won't write tests or they won't run their
tests. So this is why we should write up our tests as code and then we can
automate the process of running our tests. So what we'll do is we'll use software to
control our test execution and the comparison of the result with what we
expect the result to be. So some benefits of automated testing are you have a
faster feedback loop, we can reuse and rerun tests without too much effort.
Automation increases efficiency, our testers can actually do things like
exploratory testing, which they're actually paid to do. And finally, if we
have automated tests, we can incorporate them into our continuous integration
pipeline. And so what this means is that when you make a pull request to master,
it has to pass tests before people can merge it in. It's really annoying me. Can
you still hear me? Yeah? Very cool. So this leads us to the most famous diagram
in the testing world, the automated testing pyramid. So the pyramid presents
a way of thinking about different kinds of automated tests when we're creating a
balanced test suite. So the pyramid of... So the pyramid of... So what we want is we
want a lot of fast, small, and cheap unit tests and a fewer number of big, slow,
and expensive end-to-end tests. And so it's a really good rule of thumb to start
with. It's not really set in stone, but if you want to start with something,
this is a good place to go. Okay, cool. Thank you. So unit tests are the most
granular level of tests. And they allow us to confirm that individual units of
code are working exactly as we intend them to. A unit is a testable part of
your code. It doesn't really matter about the size, but generally it's something
that's like a public function that takes in some sort of parameters, does some
sort of calculation, and returns a result. This is the most granular form of
testing, and we should make sure that all of our unit tests are independent. This
way, when they fail, we know exactly what's going on. So going back to that
example, when we want to calculate, we want to find the top word, how do we test
this function? Well, we can create a list that we know the attributes of. So here I
create a list. I know foo appears three times. I want to pass foo through that
list, and then I'm going to compare the output to what I know the output should
be. So integration tests refers to combining multiple parts of the system
and testing them together as a group. It also refers to testing at the service
boundaries. If our application makes a call to, say, a database, a file
system, or an external API, that's the kind of integration test we need to
ensure that works. So if our program does anything of substance, anything
interesting, it's going to have a lot of interactive components that are interacting
with each other. So integration tests provide us confidence that those
integrations are working the way we want them to work. So here's a function to save
information to a database. How can we test this function? So the easiest way
is to create an object, pass it through our function, and then query their
database to make sure that object that was put in there is the object we expect
to be in there. Fairly standard stuff. So end-to-end tests are tests that we write
to make sure our application meets defined business requirements or
functional requirements. We usually run these through the UI so they're a little
slower, but we can also test the subcutaneous layer, which is the layer
just below the surface. And if our end-to-end test passed, that's great. It means our
program meets business requirements. If they fail, we really don't know why they
failed. And so we have no idea where to go, so we could probably need to look at
some of our unit tests or integration tests. So in our example, our interface is
a JSON REST API, and so a functional test would be creating a test client with flask,
hitting the endpoint, and then making sure that it's actually a 200. Did it
return an OK? There's one more form of testing that we should talk about called
regression testing. And we want to fix a bug. We want to ensure that when we fix
this bug, it never comes back into our program. And so good bug reports include
code that we can use to reproduce these errors. So let's take this code, make a
test case out of it, and then we have a failing test. Get this test to pass, and
instead of throwing the code away, let's keep that test away. Let's keep that test
in our test suite, document it with, say, an issue number. That way, any time we
run our CI, we can ensure that that functionality doesn't regress. So we've
been talking about this. Well, let's be explicit. What are some of the benefits
of testing? With tests, we can ensure that our program works exactly as we
expected it to. Tests also confirm that the changes we make didn't break existing
functionality. Tests help us identify bugs earlier in the software development
lifecycle. The earlier you find a bug, the faster you can fix it. And I think this
is a little bit controversial, but if you write tests, it forces you to
write better code. It shows that you've actually thought through the problem, and
at the very least, you've used your own API. If your API is clunky, you have
nobody to blame but yourself. So we can quantitatively measure our tests in a
few different ways. So the one way is a test ratio, and this is the number of
lines of test code over the number of lines of production code. A ratio over
one means we have more test code than production code. Does it really mean
anything? I'm not too sure, but it's a metric people use. I think test speed is
a little bit of a better metric. You want to have a test suite
that's run really fast. That way, when you're iterating on features, you can
keep running your tests to make sure that you're not breaking anything. Test
coverage measures how much of our production code is covered by our test
code. This could be a really interesting metric. We should come back to that
later. But just be aware that no matter what metric we're measuring, if people
know you're measuring it, they're gonna change their behavior and affect that
metric. For instance, 100% code coverage, is it great? Yeah, sure, but does it really
mean anything? Not really. So just to recap, test coverage measures the
percent of our codebase that's executed by our test suite. It tracks the lines of
code that were exercised, but it doesn't it doesn't really measure the quality of
our tests. It's really great to find untested code in our codebase, so if we
have untested code and we're actually using that code, we should write tests
around it. If we're not using that code, we should delete it. I don't know about
anybody else, but I like deleting code a lot more than I like writing code. And so
there's a lot of testing on coverage utilities in the Python ecosystem. The
most popular one is coverage.py. So here's a sample PyTest and coverage.py
report. So at the top you got some configuration for PyTest. Each of these
represents all the tests that are run. One dot represents a successful pass, and on
the bottom we have our coverage report. So here we have all the modules we're
testing, the number of lines of code in each of those modules, as well as the
lines of code that are not covered, along with the percentage. Coverage also produces
HTML reports, which are a little bit easier to read and they show you exactly
what's going on in your program. So how can we gain test coverage? Going back to
that end-to-end test we wrote, let's just take out our assert. Then we'll run our
test. We have the same test coverage, where it's just like that. So this is
something that you should watch out for. We really don't know how good these
tests are, so this is something we should do in code review. You should at least
make sure people are asserting something and not just running like empty tests.
Just a little note, coverage.py right now lets you know what lines of code are
being tested. Starting in version 5, you're going to find out what tests are
covering what lines of code. There's currently an alpha release out. Try it out,
make bug reports. I'm sure that would appreciate it.
So before we dive into test frameworks, we're gonna have to go over a few more
definitions. So when we want to run our test, we want to run it under a known
state so we can ensure repeatable results. This is where test fixtures come
in. Fixtures set up our test environment and then they return it to the original
state after the test is run. A test case, that's an individual unit of testing and
what we want to do is want to check specific input results in a specific
output. A test suite is a collection of test cases. We can use a test runner to
orchestrate the execution and reporting of tests to users and your test runner,
if the test fails, it's going to tell you why it failed. There's going to be a
stack face there. An invariant is a condition that's always true and so we
can use the assert built-in keyword in Python to add invariant to our code. So
here I have assert is instance. Is this list 1, 2, 3 a list that returns true so
nothing happens? And on the next one I have assert is this list a tuple? It's
not so it's false. It's actually going to raise an assertion error exception. The
test framework is the execution environment for automated tests. We use
our framework to hook into and drive our application under test. Our framework
also tells us how we should have to define our exceptions and the framework
usually has a runner which executes the test cases and reports the results to our
user. So there's two big testing frameworks in the Python ecosystem.
There's unit test and there's PyTest. So unit test is part of Python standard
library. It follows the standard X unit from small talk or Java style pattern
and since it's been around and used in many languages there's a lot of books a
lot of documentation about it but at the end of day you're writing Java kind of
like testing. A lot of boilerplate. PyTest on the other hand doesn't feel
like Java. The tests are really easy to read. They're really easy to write. It
also has a lot of great documentation. My favorite part of PyTest is the plugins
and PyTest runs unit test suites so there's really no reason not to use
PyTest. And so for all these reasons I love PyTest so let's explore why I love
it. So PyTest allows us to use the Python built-in assert keyword. There's no more
messing around with assert helpers and when an assert fails there's a lot of
detailed introspection about what failed. So here I'm comparing a list of 0 to 9
which is what range 10 does to a list from 0 to 8 and the number 10. And when
it fails it tells me at index 9 the number 9 does not equal the number 10. So
you don't have to go back to your code you can actually just see it in the
PyTest output. PyTest features a fixture model that's just very
helpful in running these kinds of fixture based tests. So fixtures are
functions that PyTest runs before your test and then it runs after your tests.
We can import fixtures into test functions by specifying them in as input
arguments for our tests. What PyTest does is it searches the current module and
it's going to go out to the plugins or the Coftest.py files. We can create
fixtures of other fixtures and this allows us to compose complex test
objects quite easily. So this is a fixture to create an item in the
database. So here I'm creating something adding to the session passing control
back to my test function and then when the test functions run I roll back that
transaction. And so I got my setup I yield with the generator and then I have
my teardown to set it back to the original state. We inject this test
function this fixture into our test function as a parameter. It's a little
bit of magic but PyTest is a little bit of magic but it's really easy so I sort
of prefer going with that magic versus something like unit test. But one of the
problems with fixtures is that they don't accept input arguments so we can
take advantage of Python language features to make fixtures a lot more
flexible. So here what we'll do is we'll create a wrapper function or a factory
function and just return the fixture that takes arguments that you want. I
actually wrote a blog post about this so there's a link if you want to read it
later on. So PyTest has markers that allow us to add metadata to our test
functions and we can run those specific markers with the minus M selection of
flag. And markers are really good to identify certain types of tests. Say
tests that are slow that you don't want to run all the time but maybe those are
the tests that you want to run all the time in your continuous integration
pipeline. The implementation of markers was revamped in Python 3.6. Before there
used to be a lot of errors so if you are experiencing errors I really suggest you
upgrade. There are a few built-in markers. There's a marker to skip tests,
there's a marker to skip test conditionally, and there's also a marker
to mark test that should always fail. So we want to test our functions across many
different kinds of outputs. We can easily write a loop but PyTest is only
going to treat that as one test function. But if we use the PyTest.mark.parameterize
decorator we can enable argument
parameterization. So here we have three specific tests but just be aware that
this is spelled a little differently. It doesn't have the E which might be the
British or Canadian way. Not too sure but it always catches me up so just be
careful of that. So yeah you see here we have those two tests that passed, the
test that failed because 54 doesn't equal 42. So my favorite part of PyTest
is the hook based plugin architecture and there's a hook for pretty much
anything so if you really want to customize PyTest you can read the
documentation and find out what you need to do. We can put all of our local
plugins in the toptest.py file inside of each of our packages or sub
packages. We can also go out and get a lot of third-party libraries. We can
invoke our test runner using the PyTest command at the command line and what
that's going to do it's going to go out and find all tests that are labeled
test underscore or underscore test.py. We also have ways to run individual
tests and I've included a link for best practices on test holder structure. PyTest
has a lot of command line options so I really recommend checking out the man
page or the help. And also be aware of all the different kinds of exit codes
just in case if your test fails you want to know why it failed so you can fix it
later. So now let's look at a lot of testing tools that can make our life a
little easier. Of course number one is PyTest. Some useful PyTest plugins
include code for code coverage. I like freeze gun for freezing date time during
the test. You can test Jupiter notebooks with IPython notebook extension. There's
also one for extest which allows you to run tests in parallel. So test doubles
are objects that allow you to replace our external dependencies with objects
that we create and that we define and that allows us to run our code through
specific kinds of scenarios. I'm not really going to go into too many details
about this but there's a list of a lot of great testing utilities. The most widely
used is unitest.mock but Mockito which is a port of the Java library
that's also pretty good too. But not everybody likes mocks. I don't like mocks
I don't know anybody else that likes mocks. So there are a few alternatives for test
doubles. Vcr.py records requests and responses as XAML cassettes and then we
can replay these cassettes for deterministic tests. This was actually
based off the Ruby VCR library. I have a blog post about it if you want to check
it out. You can also test using man in the middle proxy. This is a little bit
weird and it requires a lot of setup but there's some links if you want to like to
follow along. I saw a talk at EuroPython 2018 where this company spun up
test infrastructure for pretty much every single test using DockerPy. It's a
little bit too much for my use case but it might be something that you need to
do. We can use Selenium to do browser-based testing. So here we can
actually code up our interactions with the browser, add something to the cart,
check the cart out. In my opinion these tests are a little bit brittle, a little
bit slow but sometimes you have high value features that you really have no
choice but to test with Selenium. But if you go a layer below to the API level we
can use Postman to test all of our APIs. So what we do is we create a contract
between our front end and our back end that defines how our API should work.
It's really easy to get started with Postman but in my experience it's a
little hard to scale. There are tools made for those purposes. A tool like
Tavern. So Tavern allows you to specify YAML-based test specifications and then
you can run them using PyTest. Underneath the hood it uses request but it's also
got a plug-in architecture so if you want to hook in your web frameworks
testing library or your testing client you could easily do that. And if you do
that please make a pull request. It'd be an awesome feature to have. Some more
testing tools. DockerPy can be used to ensure your containers are built to your
exact specifications. I couldn't get Kano working but there is an article if
you want to give it a shot. Data science testing. If you have not read the
Pandas testing utilities I highly recommend doing so. There's a lot of
great assertion helper for data frames. UnGuard is built around those kinds of
utilities. It's a decorator based library for data science and great
expectations is built for more data pipeline type of testing. I think it's a
little bit gross but it might fit your use case. If you have a Postgres
database I recommend checking out PGTap. It's written in Perl but it's
actually really good. Just a little note about property-based testing. This is
when you check an object has the same property before and after an action so
this could be something like serialization deserialization and
hypothesis is the go-to one in Python. Mutation testing. That's actually really
cool. What that does is it goes through your program source code, the AST and it
modifies it. So say you have a conditional that's like if X is
greater than 5 it's gonna change it to be if X is less than 5 and if your test
still passed maybe you probably don't have the best test. And I also like the
name Cosmic Ray because it's like flipping bits. I don't really have a lot of time to
talk about this but there's a lot of ways to write robust tests. There's two
patterns to structure your test. There's the arrange act and assert pattern and
there's the given when then pattern. Pretty much the same just use different
words. When you write tests ensure they only try to test one thing. This way
anytime a test fails you know that exactly what's gonna go on. And just like
in everything else in programming you have to be pragmatic. Pragmatic in what
you're testing, how you're testing, and when you're testing. People talk about
test first, test last, who cares? Just test. And on the last link is about unit
of behavior. We talked a little bit about unit like what is the size of the unit?
It could be a public function, could it be a private function? I like the
definition of unit of behavior because it sort of defines what your program is
actually doing. I actually wrote up a pretty long blog post about testing.
Let me go on those real fast if you want to take that a look at that. Martin
has a great Wikipedia on testing. That's pretty much it for me. I'm not gonna be
taking questions now but I will be outside so yeah just come find me. Thank
you so much.