Hello.
Perfect.
Wonderful.
So,
to do
this talk, I conducted
a survey, so I want to do a quick straw
poll among us right here.
I'm wondering,
alright, testing
one, two, three.
You all hear me now?
Cool.
Little too far
from the mouth there.
Alright, so I'm wondering, little
quick straw poll,
how many of us have made
a comment to
themselves as they were
working within their code base?
That's
amazing! Okay, me too.
Not alone, thank goodness.
And there are lots of reasons to want to do this.
So, maybe you have
a variable that you're scared to change,
someone else's code.
Do I know exactly what that variable
is doing? I'm not sure.
Maybe you just copy-pasted a section of
code from online, and you want
to make a quick note? Yeah, I heard a yeah.
We've all been there.
It's even easier to
forget what the code does when you
didn't write it, as it turns out.
And maybe you made a choice
that you want to make sure that
the future you knows about.
Because, you know, past you
makes choices, and future you just
whew, it's hard.
So,
since we're all on the same page,
and we've all worked on these comments,
we've come to the right place. We're going to
dive into code
comments. So, with all these
reasons to add comments, and all these hands
going up in the room, we might wonder
why we aren't making these
inline code comments
all over the place.
Come on slide, please.
Thank you.
Alright, so we're going to do a
quick critique
of two comments
I am shamefully
sharing with you today.
So, what happens when someone who is using
learning to use comments, and commenting
to hold their place,
and relieve some of this cognitive
load that they're going through in their learning
as they change direction, look up turns,
find code samples.
So, in this first example,
what do we think?
The tutorial that I used
to start the project is
cited at the top.
Anybody find that reasonable?
It's okay to do that? Do a show
of hands?
Okay, a couple people think that's okay. We've got
skeptics in the room.
Oh, yep,
I hear you. Okay, well I'll tell you
what's going on up there. What's going on
up there is there is some code,
and then there's a line at the top that says
I took this code from this lovely
tutorial, and it is turning
into this project. This is what I contributed,
and what came from the tutorial.
Because I'm an academic,
and I love citing things.
So, that's what would be on that
screen if my color were
a little less off.
So, for most of us, that comment might
survive in a code base, and eventually
be added to documentation as the project
goes. And in this second,
hopefully with even better color,
we see this person
was trying
to use beautiful
soup to
scrape a website, and
send an alert when her favorite on-campus
climbing wall was open.
And you see there's this little
little, oh boy,
badly colored green square
that would say open if we could see it.
But, you know,
our hero has not used beautiful
soup before, and the notes
that she made to herself
lists not
only what she should
be doing, her own little
to-do list,
but it also has code that is
commented out. It probably
doesn't work.
And notes
expressing her confusion,
including my favorite comment to date.
Oh, it's a list.
Thank God.
So, would you want to
contribute to a code base
that had similar pileups
of comments throughout?
Honestly, I,
when I was pulling out this example,
more, even
more experienced me, felt confused
just looking at this.
If this was file after file,
I think I'd run in the other direction.
Y'all with me on
this one? Yeah.
So, before
we dive in and we talk more about comments,
what makes
a good programmer?
We need to know
languages,
methods, there's some
amount of knowledge that we need to have.
We need to have the ability
to apply our
problem-solving and creative thinking
skills, and
last, but
definitely not least, we need to be
able to communicate and, let's face
it, write usable
code.
So, we spend a lot of time
in our industry
talking about that first point,
knowing a language and methods,
but I want
to talk about the journey
that I took through the other two,
that creative thinking and communicating,
since they're
an important part of the mastery
we all desire.
So.
Relatable.
So,
documentation is what
allows the code to be used,
expanded, adapted,
and for a community to be formed.
Avoid causing
other programmers pain.
So,
as I was approaching
my own comments
as docs strategy,
I tried to see what other
people were using comments for,
and I found a couple of different uses.
You can have comments at the top
of a file as a summary.
Not all of us use GitHub.
Any other academics in the room?
A few? Okay, cool.
That's where I come from too. We have these
nice little things at the top, and it
tells you the email address of who
you should message if it's all
messed up. And,
yeah. Everybody
loves having corresponding authors.
So, they have comments
to describe functions.
And then, you want
to be able to
maybe clarify any
tricky situations you had to
go through
when you were writing the code.
So, this will allow you to
later
be able to create your own standalone
docs, in part
using these comments.
For folks like me,
who are
very visual and enjoy
and, you know,
benefit from having all of their work in
front of them, it also could serve
as a notepad, so to speak.
And, as many
blogs helpfully
or unhelpfully point out, it's important
to tell why
you're making a certain decision,
but your code, hopefully,
tells you how.
So, there's some
confusion
about comments.
A lot
of people think that
no comment
is bad code.
But,
maybe this is also true.
Maybe
you're worried about the balance. I'm sorry,
I think this will be hard to see.
You want helpful comments,
but not distracting
helpful comments, but not distracting ones.
And, it's possible, like this
comment claims, that
the kind of
hazing around figuring out
when a
comment is helpful documentation
and when a comment is
fluff and should be avoided
is a bit of hazing that
we all have to go through as we learn
what the
proper balance is.
That doesn't sound like
very much fun.
So,
we debate.
So, we hear about comment rot.
But,
it's easy
to forget that learners
are people
our comments might be helping.
And, that you're not going to be able
to decide how many comments
or what kind of comments
are helpful until you've worked within
code bases that use them
and
been able to see them
yourself. So, remember,
we're trying to create the most usable code
we can.
If you're always having to go to source,
it's going to be
a very long day.
So, I started looking and saying,
well, are there some things in all this debate
that we can agree on?
And, there are some best practices
that we can get behind.
We generally agree
docstrings
should have inputs,
outputs, explain the
transformation that's taking place.
And, everyone will tell you
that outdated comments, that comment
rot, those are
dirty, filthy lies.
We don't like those. They're terrible.
And,
finally,
my favorite advice from the internet,
too much, how many
comments are too many comments?
Well, too much is too much.
Thank you.
Thank you, internet folks.
So, sometimes,
we can agree that the
code tells us how
while the comments
should tell us why.
Some folks say,
keep things instead of dry,
wet, don't waste
everyone's time.
And, that,
you know, if we put the further critique,
a line by line commenting
may indicate a lack of understanding.
So, the difficulty
for many of us is that there's lots
of variation in what is considered
best practices for comments
as we've discussed.
And, the explanation is clearly
enough. There's variation,
different languages,
different needs, different industries,
and different styles
of learning.
So,
companies create their style
guides and,
you know, decide whether or not we should
include doc strings, comments,
etc.
But, we can all agree
no matter what we think about these guidelines
that comments, if used properly,
if we can ever figure out
what that means, are an invaluable
part of a code base.
The thing to remember
here is that to
a beginner programmer,
comments can be magic.
If you can go back and you can
remember the first time you realize,
wow, if I put this
nifty little hashtag,
the interpreter is going to ignore it,
and I can put whatever
I need there.
Nobody, just me,
remembers that?
Okay, okay, I see a few hands.
Alright, well, I was excited. I felt just like this.
I was like, oh boy,
I'm going to use this all day.
So, people
use this power differently,
but many of the new programmers
as I started
talking to folks and mentoring,
they'll start
throwing comments everywhere.
I've seen comments for variables,
comments that hold questions
to ask a mentor later,
comments made during
pairing to record
some new
related bit of knowledge
that people are still putting their heads around,
comments used as an
outline for code yet to be written,
and
for the, you know,
code hoarders among us,
comments holding code that we
don't use anymore, but we aren't
quite ready to get rid of yet.
Even one person added
comments that record the
URL of the website
where they had found
some insight, they had stack overflowed,
done that copy-pasta thing,
and it wasn't theirs,
so they wanted to, like,
show what they had done and not.
Okay.
So, there is
a lot of different ways
that these folks found to use comments.
Really ingenious.
And there's one
thing
as we are
pushing folks to
do, to be
dry and to do things the right way
at a time when,
as newer programmers, they're taking
on
probably more than they can.
There's one thing that we forget.
I don't really know
WTF I've done
tonight.
I committed a lot of stuff to get.
Something,
something JavaScript.
You all
know this?
I don't know. Go back
to your commit messages when you're coding
too late. You'll see this person come out.
You may think that you
aren't this person, but you've definitely
been this person. And we
tend to forget that
this person
needs aids and
resources and
the ability maybe
to use comments however
they need to use comments.
So,
as I was
progressing through this stage,
and I spent a while being this person
because I jumped around a lot.
I became active in several programming
communities
and I started to see a trend.
Good code
is dry.
So,
if you go online
and you say, okay,
so I've started
learning how to comment and I want, I'm a
new programmer and I want to be the best
programmer I can. So I'm
going to find out the best practices
and do it the best way all the time
and I'll put that on top of everything else I'm
learning. You're going to hear,
if your code has too many comments, you need to
refactor. You're going to hear the very
helpful, you should just code better.
No, no, this is
real. I went and I searched and
this was advice that I got. You should code
better.
You should not use comments.
Why are they there in the first place?
You should only use like
the correct comments and you should know the
difference.
And only your code matters.
Now, if you're me
or you're someone else who is
diving deep and trying to
find the best way to do something,
what you're actually going to hear is
so the way you're
learning is an anti-
panic. I don't know
how that feels, but
okay, it doesn't
feel very good.
Y'all are less emotional about this than I
am.
All right,
so I
went to Stack Overflow and
there were too many things.
I could have made a montage,
but instead
I'm just going to show you, and it's
hard to read, this person has written
a very thoughtful, hey,
I'm just learning how to do
this and I want to be able to document my
code properly.
And, you know, on and on
and they're like, I hear this and I hear
that. Can someone give me
guidance? Can someone
tell me what to do? And you know what
the person says? This has
been beaten
to death. Why are you
here? And they got a lot of upvotes.
Can you imagine
a jerk on Stack Overflow
getting a lot of upvotes?
So,
I don't want to pick on this one
jerk, because there's a lot of them.
But this was
continuous as I looked
and it was also continuous in the forums
that I was in. So I started to
ask myself, what's going on here?
Or is this like,
you know, kind of a
beginner-beginner and then
a slightly more advanced beginner, like looks
down on the beginner-beginner and says like,
shouldn't do it that way.
Like, or
is there something
more we need to address
as a community?
I'm a scientist.
There are a few things in the world I love
as much as data.
And so I asked Twitter a question.
And I got a whole nine
respondents.
Do you know how not statistically
significant nine respondents
is? But I asked,
hey Twitter,
have you
always been dry or
is that something you came up with
as you progressed as a programmer?
And Twitter,
well,
I got nine respondents.
And
they were split almost right down
the middle. If I'd gotten a tenth, it probably
would have been right down the middle.
And I was a little
irked that so many people said
they were dry from day one because who
is?
And that really surprised me and I said,
wow, I need to look at this more.
And so
I went to places that were not
Twitter.
And I, thank you.
Thank you. I needed that.
And definitely when I started this project,
I definitely needed that.
So I read a little bit
about survey design.
And I set out into the world
of how do humans think?
And I made myself a survey.
So I asked a lot of questions.
I said,
when
do you use comments?
What causes you to use them?
When do you add them?
Are we all secretly
taking out our shameful comments
before we add them to GitHub?
Okay, I needed to get down to the bottom
of this. I saw a couple of nods.
It's not just me. Okay.
So I
asked, and then I asked a little
bit more about people's
attitudes towards commenting in general.
Tell me how you feel
about comments, I said.
And what was wonderful,
in addition to the
multiple
choice and scale responses
that I got,
is people,
you know,
I gave them a space to write about
how their commenting had changed over time.
Or to write after each
question. And they wrote.
I'm going to talk through
and summarize as we go along, because
I made the mistake later of putting too many
words on slides,
as one does.
And so, I'll
share those results with you.
So, what
best describes your current
or recent use of
comments?
Do you comment when you're not certain?
Do you comment each function
as a matter of practice?
Do you use inline comments?
Or do you comment out unused
code, shamefully?
And I expected,
because I had
so many dry folks on Twitter,
I expected,
I did not expect
so many people to say,
yes, I use inline comments.
Ninety, let's see,
what percentage is that?
It got cut off. Fifty-something percent.
I didn't expect
that at all.
And people said some words.
My favorite comment was someone said,
as a child.
And
one really neat
thing about this survey,
and I want to dive into this data more,
so there will be
more chatter about this data, and at
some point it's going to be on GitHub, and we'll all
get to play with it.
But I had survey respondents who
had been coding as little as one
month, and as long
as 35.
And I was,
and it's a really nice
spread. And I'm
really glad that I
put in the effort to
cast such a wide net.
And that people responded and really had
strong feelings about comments
that went on for paragraphs
and talked about their childhood commenting.
And how they've
grown up since then.
And in my heart, I really want to
know if this person was truly a child
when they learned to program.
Or if they're talking about their
childhood programmer self.
Which is how I talk about myself
from, you know, four years ago.
So some folks
said I
comment unused code.
Comments
clutter code.
So we've got a non-comment
person in the room.
And
it goes on.
So I asked, when do you add
comments? Because remember I had that
long list of
reasons for comments
earlier that
my newbie buddies were using.
So I said, how about
scoping? Do you have a to-do list
in your comments?
Does
it help you experiment?
Do you add them as you're
completing a program?
And a surprising number of people
said, yes, it does help me
experiment. I'll start writing
a piece of code. And
I'm not sure if it's what I'm going to keep.
And I commented
heavily. I see
what works and what doesn't.
And I know right back where to go to.
So more folks are using
that cognitive
code, you know, comments
as their little cognitive
storage bins
than I expected.
And there are more words.
I didn't
write comments as much
as when I started off, because
I wasn't confident
that what I would say would be useful.
Some folks are literally scared
of the prose element of
commenting. It's comfortable
to write code.
Writing code is what we
value.
But the act
of commenting is almost
more vulnerable. You are writing
documentation.
You are explaining yourself.
It is difficult.
You have to...
If you have pulled
something offline that you don't
quite understand, it's
sometimes hard to say
so.
And so I had
asked a series of questions
that said, how positively do we
feel about comments?
And
one is disagree, and
ten is strong agree.
So a whole lot of folks
say,
comments help me remember what my code
does.
We see a similar distribution
for comments help me clarify
my thinking, a little more spread
out, a little whiter tail.
And then we
get to, comments
help me learn.
And I'm interested
to see here what the
distribution is for
how many of these folks have just been
programming so long that that's
not the aid that they use anymore.
And it's possible
that there are a whole lot
fewer newbie
programmers who are using
comments in the way I
and some of the people I've mentored
have been. So that will be an
interesting thing to look at in the future.
We almost
all agree, comments, you know,
the good ones, will save
current and future developers
time.
We disagree
that comments
are helpful to you,
but should be removed
from GitHub. So all those folks who earlier
said that they take out their comments
before going to GitHub, you're good.
Go ahead and add those in. You can show the world.
It's fine.
But interestingly,
when I started
talking
about clutter
and what was acceptable and not,
my distribution
wasn't quite so clear anymore. That's
a pretty wide tale considering what we
were seeing before.
And when I get to
clear code is self-documenting
and doesn't need comments,
we're a lot flatter.
So it's clear that
despite all this positivity
towards comments among my respondents,
we're actually still,
we've really internalized
this idea that
good code is going to be so
clear that you don't need
the words.
So
let's think about
what makes a good comment. And I'm so sorry
about what you're seeing right there.
So what this person did
is they're describing the state
of their program
in a comment. Like they have a diagram
and they say, you are here
at this point.
And I thought that was genius
because guess what?
Sometimes it's really hard to visualize
what your code is
doing at that moment.
Some folks
will create a whole man page to describe
a section of their codes.
And it's possible
that right now those obvious comments
aren't so obvious to you.
And as you get better
at naming conventions,
you won't want to put post-its
on all of your cats.
And in the spirit of this
quote, the best comments
are a huge help.
But the perfect comments
are not going to come
without trial and error.
So what can we do?
A lot of us
are really experienced.
We're probably mentoring.
We're probably talking to folks
who are figuring things out.
So our end goal
is to support learners
where they're at.
You want to praise the accomplishments.
And instead
of saying, hey, it has to be dry,
you might say,
you know, I see what you're doing
there. It's ingenious
that you're using ASCII to show the
state of your game engine.
But
someday
you're going to get to the point
where you don't need that anymore.
So you've got to remember your
overwhelmed learner,
why advise them where they're at,
and you might want to suggest
a deep dive or
reading other folks' code.
If we rethink
comments, the thing
I kept coming back to is if we were to
think about what comments were again
and we said, what if comments
are docs? Would we be having
another conversation?
So
I want to thank each of you
for coming. You've been lovely.
I appreciate your participation especially.
So thanks
to Pi Texas and thanks for all the folks
who told me their comment stories.
I would appreciate if everyone
in this room
do not take this survey because we talked
about some results and you know what that
does, right?
So don't do that. But if you
want to social media that thing,
my handle is there and whatnot.
And I'd love to
be able to hear from
you know,
more folks about
their common experiences.
So thank you very much.