All right. Our next talk is going to be Harrington Joseph. He's going to tell us about when bullions
are not enough, state machines. Let's give him a round of applause.
Thanks, everyone. Can everybody hear me okay? What about now? Louder? All right. Okay. I'm
going to talk about when bullions are not enough and how we can use state machines in those cases.
My name is Harrington Joseph. I'm a senior software engineer at Netflix where I work on the data
platform team. My work is mostly focused on data orchestration and even driven architecture. Feel
free to find me after the talk if you want to know more about what I do on Netflix or you want to
share your favorite show or something like that. Expectations. This talk is about why,
how, and when to use state machines. This talk is not about the internals of a state machine.
I want to make that really clear. Let's start with a very simple analogy. Imagine that you have a
closet where you store tools and sport equipment. But this closet is so messy that you don't really
want to look at it. You don't want to think about it. Reality hits you the moment that you have to
get something from that closet and turns out that it's all the way at the bottom of the messy file
that you have in there. You don't really know if you can pull it out or not because everything may
fall apart. Things get actually worse when you ask someone to get something from that closet for
you. That person is probably not going to find what you need and it's very unlikely that he's
going to feel comfortable moving things around. This is exactly what happens when we use multiple
booleans to represent states and enforce business rules. Our code gets messy and no one wants to
touch it. So please raise your hand if you have a class with any of the following attributes.
Right. I think everybody feels identified. So the problem. Using multiple booleans to represent
states and enforce business rules. Very simple. Very concise. So let's take a look at the code.
Here we have a video class that receives a source which is the source of the video and it
initializes a source attribute with the given source but it also initializes a boolean attribute
called isPlaying equals false because at the beginning the video is not playing. This class
also provides three functions. Pause, play and stop. I'm not going to dive into the detail how
to play or pause or stop a video file but what is important here is the last line of this function
which is self.isPlaying. So when you call pause self.isPlaying is set to false. When you call
play self.isPlaying is set to true and when you call stop set.isPlaying is set to false. So we can
go and create a video instance. We can play the video. We can pause the video. We can stop the
video and we can check if the video is playing or not. But video.isPlaying what does it really mean?
When it's true it definitely means that the video is playing but what happens when it's false? Is it
paused or is it stopped? In reality we don't have enough information to answer this question so
naturally we will go and do something like this. So we created a new attribute called isPause which
by default we initialize it as false because when we create the instance of the video the video is
not paused either. Then when we call pause now we are going to update this attribute and we're going
to set it to true. When we call play we're going to set it to false and when we call stop we're
going to set it to false. So we can continue answering the video is playing by just calling
video.isPlaying. We can answer if the video is paused by calling video.isPause but when it comes
to knowing if the video is stopped we actually have to check if the video is not playing and not paused.
This is very ugly. It's not elegant at all but it's also really fragile. It's prone to errors. The
moment you introduce a new state any condition that you have built around this logic is going
to be broken. Let's talk about some business rules. Let's say that a video can only be played when
it's paused or stopped. Rule number two, a video can only be paused when it's playing. Rule number
three, a video can only be stopped when it's playing or paused. Very simple rules just like a
regular video player. So rule number one, a video can only be played when it's paused or stopped.
We go and modify our play function and now we check if the video is not playing or if the video
is paused then we make the call to play the video, update our isPlaying attribute to true,
set the isPause attribute to false and if this condition is not satisfied we basically raise
an exception saying that you cannot play a video that is already playing assuming that the video
is already playing. So there is some assumption here that leads to fragile code again the moment
you introduce new states or new business rules. For rule number two we say a video can only be
played when it's paused. A video can only be paused when it's playing. So in this case we check if the
video is already playing. In that case we make the call to pause the video, update our flags,
otherwise we raise an exception saying that we cannot pause a video that is not playing.
And for rule number three we say that a video can only be stopped when it's playing or paused. Again
we check if the video is playing or if the video is paused, we make the call to stop the video,
update our flags, otherwise we raise an exception. So the code is rapidly becoming complex. Our play,
pause and stop functions are not actually focusing on what they're supposed to be doing. They are
checking for the state, they are validating business rules instead of focusing on playing,
pausing or stopping the video. It's bloated. We added a bunch of code and we didn't get any
functionality. We're just checking for the state. It's repetitive. We keep checking for the state
and raising exceptions. Even though it's not exactly the same condition, it's something
repetitive. It's something that could probably be automated. And it's definitely hard to test.
In order to write unit tests for this, you have to write unit tests for play, for pause and stop,
with all the possible values that this flag can have. We're talking about only two flags.
Imagine the moment that you add more flags for different states. Here's a different approach.
You can have a video class where you define some constants for your states and then instead of
having the boolean flags, you can have a state. And then just to initialize this as stop because
the video is not playing once you create the instance. Now you say a video can only be played
when it's paused or stopped. The code actually didn't change much. Instead of checking booleans,
we'll continue checking for constants and now we have to update the states. We keep raising
the exception in all the cases and also we make assumptions. We say if the video is not playing,
then we can definitely play it. But is that true? It is true at the moment with the three business
rules we have. But the moment we introduce a new rule or we introduce a new state,
this code is going to be broken. Same thing for the pause case and same thing for the stop case.
So let's talk about state machines. What's a state machine? A state machine is a mathematical
model of computation with a finite number of states, transition between states and a
machine that can only be at a state in a given time. All these sounds very complex,
theoretical and mathematical. But in reality, a state machine can be seen as a directed graph
where each of the nodes represent a state in the machine and the connections between the nodes are
representing the transitions. Basically when two nodes are connected, it means that you can
transition from node A to node B. And then you just need a pointer that tells you in what state
you are at a given time. So here's a very simple example of a state machine. This is a state
machine for when a user lands on a website. Initially, the user is in the logout state when
you land for the first time on a website. Once you are in the logout state, you can perform the
login transition to move to the login state. Once in the login state, you can perform the logout
transition to move to the logout state. In this case, logout has this blueish glow representing
that that's the initial state or the current state at the beginning. So how do we design a state
machine? First, we need to define a number of states that we want to deal with. What are the
states that our object is going to be representing? Then we need to lay down the transition between
states. What are the business rules that we want to enforce? And finally, we just need to pick the
initial state. So step one, define a finite number of states. Plane, pause, and stop.
Step number two, lay down the transition between states. In this case, what we're doing here is
translating the business rules into edges in the graph. So rule number one said that a video can
only be played when it is stopped or paused. That's why you see two incoming arrows to the
playing state, one from stop and one from pause, and the name of the transition is called play.
Rule number two said that a video can only be paused when it's playing. That's why you see
only one incoming arrow to the pause state and it's coming from the playing state with the name
of pause. And rule number three said that a video can only be stopped when it's playing or paused.
That's why you see two incoming arrows to the stop state, one from playing and one from pause,
with the name stop. And finally, we just need to select the initial state, which in this case is
going to be stop because the video is not played at the beginning. So let's take a look at the code.
So I'm going to rely on a library called Transitions. It's an open source library
that you can find on GitHub. It's really simple to read, like the code is fairly easy to understand,
but you can find any other flavors in multiple languages as well.
So the first thing that you need to do to use Transitions is to import the machine.
Then you define all the states that you want to deal with. As you can see, this doesn't look very
different to the latest approach that I showed you. Next, we need to define the Transitions.
And this is the part that looks a little bit complex, but in reality it's not. What we're
doing here is describing the graph. The trigger is basically the arrow that represents the
connection. The value of the trigger is going to be the name of the transition.
Source is going to be the origin of the transition, and this is going to be
the destination of the transition. So for rule number one, that a video can only be played when
it's paused or stopped, we basically have two rules. One going from pause to playing,
and another one going from stop to playing, and the name of the transition is going to be play.
For rule number one, that a video can only be paused when it's playing,
then we have one transition that is going from playing to pause, and the name of the transition
is going to be called pause. And rule number three, that a video can only be stopped when it's playing
or paused means that we have two transition rules, one going from playing and one going to pause,
both ending in the stop state, and the name of the transition or the trigger is going to be stop.
Another thing that is important to mention of this definition here is that the trigger name
should match the name of the function that you're going to call. And I'll go over that in a moment.
Finally, you need to create the machine. When you create the machine, you say model equals self,
and I explain why this is important. It's related with the trigger name, transitions,
the list of transitions that we want to enforce or that we want to provide,
and the initial state, which in this case is stop.
Now our code actually looks like this. As you can see, there is not much there because
there is nothing related with the state anymore. We don't have to keep track of state. We don't
have to check the state. We don't have to raise exceptions. The code is actually focusing on
what it's supposed to be doing. Pause is going to pause the video. It doesn't care about the
state at all. Same thing for play and same thing for stop. So now we can create a video instance.
We can play the video and our state should transition to playing. If we really care,
we can actually check the state of the video. As you saw, I didn't create a state attribute,
but the machine itself is injecting this attribute into the object. When we provide
model equals self, the machine injects this attribute. You don't really have to access this
attribute at all because you technically shouldn't deal with the state. The machine
shouldn't handle that for you. But if you need, for some reason, it's available.
We can pause the video. The state transitions to pause. We can stop the video and the state
transitions to stop. But what happens if we call pause again? Remember, a video can only be paused
when it's playing, but we are in the stop state. This is going to give us a machine error. The
machine is taking care of validating that this transition is valid, and we get this pretty much
for free. All we had to do was to define the transitions, but we didn't have to write a single
condition. The way this works, remember that I mentioned that the trigger name was important
and the model equals self was important, is basically when we initialize the machine,
the machine is going to look all the trigger names, and it's going to look all the functions
that match the trigger name, and it's going to wrap them. When you call play, you're actually
going through the machine first. The machine is going to validate the current state and the
state where you want to go. If that is valid, then it calls the actual play function. If it's not,
it raises a machine error. Another thing that is important is that, for example, if you call play
and you get an exception saying, let's say that you try to play a file that doesn't exist or you
couldn't, something happened trying to execute this file, if your function raised the exception,
the exception is going to be propagated by the machine, and therefore the state is not going to
change. So how do we test this? We don't. If you're using a state machine library, you don't really
have to test that the state machine library is validating that you can transition from state A
to B, and then you cannot move from one state that is not connected to the other one, because
that's the state machine job. Instead, you can test if the machine was initialized with the right
transitions and the right initial state, and then you can actually focus on testing real functionality.
You can test that the play function actually does what it's supposed to be doing. Same thing
for pause and same thing for stop. Nothing related with the state. You don't really have to
care about that anymore. So let's add a new state, and let's call this state rewinding.
I'm highlighting in red all the changes that I made to the rules when I added this state
and a brand new rule. As you can see, there is a new node in the graph
called rewinding, and you see a bunch of new arrows. So rule number one saying that a video
can only be played when it's paused, stopped, or rewinding means that there's a new arrow going
from the rewinding state to the playing state with the name of play. The rule number two that a video
can only be paused when it's playing or rewinding means that there's got to be an incoming arrow
to the pause state from the rewinding state named pause. The rule number three that a video can only
be stopped when it's playing, paused, or rewinding leads to that big arrow on the right
that is basically saying that that is going from the rewinding state to the
stop state with the name of stop. And finally, a video can only be rewinding when it's playing
or paused that leads to the two new incoming arrows to the rewinding state, one from playing
and one from pause, and the name is rewind. So let's take a look at the code. In this case,
all we had to do was this. We basically defined a new state called rewinding, and now we modify
our transitions. So in this case, for rule number one, we added one new transition
that is going from the rewinding state to the playing state, and the name is going to be play.
Rule number two, we did exactly the same, but going from the rewinding state to the pause state,
and the name is pause. Similar for rule number three, going from the rewinding state to the
stop state with the name stop. And then for the brand new rule number four that a video can only
be rewinding when it's playing or paused, we added two new transitions, one going from playing,
and one going from pause to the rewinding state. The name of the transition is going to be rewind.
That's all we have to do. The only thing that is left here is to write the rewind function.
But we didn't have to actually change any of the play, pause, or stop logic. We don't really
have to care about the state of any of these functions. And the other good thing is like the
unit tests are not going to be broken. The only unit test that can be broken is the one that tests
that the machine was initialized with the right transitions. But the other unit tests for play,
pause, and stop remain the same. So when are booleans not enough?
When you have multiple booleans representing a single state. If you find yourself checking
multiple booleans in order to decide what the state of an object is, something smells fishy
here. There's got to be a better way of doing this. When business rules are informed by multiple
booleans. Along the same lines, if you find yourself checking multiple booleans or even
multiple constants, multiple attributes in order to decide if you can perform an action or not,
then you're probably in the wrong place. You probably have to change your approach.
So when to use a state machine? When states are not binary. Do you have something more than true
or false, one and zero, yes or no? You may want to consider using a state machine.
It's not a hard rule, but you may want to consider it.
When you have to account for future states, and this is not about over-engineering,
which we are really good at by the way, it's about knowing for a fact that you're going to add new
states anytime soon, for example, or even remove some states.
When you have to enforce a complex set of business rules. As you saw in the presentation,
we were talking about three states or four states in some cases, three or four rules in some cases,
and it got fairly complex. The moment we add more states and more business rules,
the complexity simply increases. So if we delegate all these complexity to a state machine,
we can actually focus on implementing the code that we want to write. We can focus on the
like, creating the functionality that we need to provide.
So in summary, I would like you to consider using state machines to represent states and
enforce business rules. As we saw in the presentation, when we use booleans to represent
states and enforce business rules, the code gets messy, unmaintainable, prone to errors,
and really hard to test, just like the closet analogy. On the other hand, if we use state
machines, we basically delegate this complexity, and it also helps us decrease in the amount of
unit tests that we have to write. It is important to mention that state machines are not a silver
bullet. So it means that it's not a one solution to solve all these problems. So know your tools,
think about the problem that you're trying to solve, and decide if it makes sense to add a
state machine to your solution. Be mindful about it and balance your decisions. That's all I have.
Thank you very much.