Hi, PyTexas party people.
I'm here to share with you automating the boring expensive bits running Python in Lambda.
My name is Ryan Hillard, and I am a systems developer at the US Small Business Administration,
and I am also a baby Python.
By that, I mean the program I'm about to share with you today is actually my first Python
program ever to run in a production environment.
The talk today is actually about compliance and automating compliance, and I know when
I bring this up, the word kind of falls apart like this.
I imagine that most people feel like the E, their head hits the table and they don't
want to think too hard about compliance.
But I promise this talk is going to be fun and interesting, so stick with me.
To start from the beginning, there is a law called the Federal Information Security Management
Act, or FISMA.
That law does a lot of things for the federal government, but one of the things it does
is mandate that the heads of agencies or CIOs need to track their information systems
by creating an inventory or a kind of list of digital assets that exist.
Now, that law was originally written in 2002, and as you might imagine, back then an inventory
looked a little bit differently than it does today.
I like to think that there was a wooden abacus back then, and different parts of it represented
maybe networks, servers living in those networks, and maybe even storage or disks on those servers.
All of that actually got collated and collected in Excel, of course, where we tracked it manually.
That was fine, actually.
That actually worked back in 2002, and it worked well.
The reason it worked is because we thought of our digital assets as pets.
Like this pack of dogs, which are defined by the leashes here, I like to think of this
as a network, and each one of these leashes might be an open port.
Out of that network, each dog, we can think of as being like a server.
Here's Bella, here's Charlie, and then of course, here's adorable Daisy.
The reason why we used to at least think of these as pets is because if Daisy, for example,
got sick, then we would take care of Daisy.
She was a pet, and Daisy would live in the same IP space, and she would consume the same
resources, and we would make sure she was well taken care of.
Like I said, that worked for a long time until the cloud came along.
You've heard this story before, the cloud has changed everything, but one of the things
that it changed fundamentally was how we think about digital infrastructure.
We stopped thinking about it like pets, and we started thinking about servers more like
cattle.
Imagine you have a field full of cattle, and they're defined by a network, they're living
in a pasture, which is a network, and each one represents a different server, the different
IP address.
In the cloud, when one of these gets sick, like the second web server here, we don't
treat it like it was Daisy.
We don't log into it and try and revive it.
Let's say it ran out of memory or something.
We find a new one, a new VM, and we kill that old one.
We send it off to be Hamburg, and one of the things that's problematic about that is that
new server that we just brought in, we're going to filter it back in, and it's going
to consume the same IP space.
That's a problem because if you were used to counting these things with an abacus, then
you now have one bead that looks like two beads, and it's very confusing.
The second problem is in the cloud, we have this concept of autoscaling groups.
Going back to our cows, if we've got our regular load on the system happening, and then all
of a sudden we get just a rush of traffic, we have an autoscaling group that says, okay,
call in more cows.
We need to deal with this traffic.
Let's get more servers in the mix.
Since that happens automatically, that's another big problem for system inventories because
all of a sudden the system has grown in a dimension that the inventory didn't account
for before.
Imagine also that afterwards that system can shrink.
It's truly elastic.
Maybe it's even a dev environment, and good development environments, at least in the
cloud world, should get shut down on the weekends and evenings, so maybe there's an empty network
there.
In this case, the inventory you have doesn't actually represent real life, and that's a
big problem.
Then finally, there's a size problem.
When we're running in a cloud environment, of course, we've got the network, here's our
pasture, but look at this.
There are a lot of other networks out there, and we can send cattle out, spin up servers
in all of these different places willy-nilly as we want to.
To sum, there are three problems with that old way of tracking system inventories.
We're dealing at a larger scale right now.
There's a fundamentally different paradigm.
When one server goes bad, we destroy it and replace it with a fresh one.
We don't worry about fixing it.
Then it's actually a fluid system.
It grows and it shrinks, and so that inventory has to be able to account for those things
in better time than it used to.
My friend Darren Wigfield, he is an information system security officer, or one of the folks
that's in charge of making sure these inventories are correct.
He and I collaborated on this project, and I'd be remiss if I didn't acknowledge his
incredible efforts.
He also said I could absolutely call him a bean counter, so he's also the bean counter
in this world.
Darren is the business side of it, and I'm the development side of it.
But bringing it together, I'm going to tell you about how we offered the organization
a lot of value.
Darren and I sat down, and in order to assess whether or not this project was worth doing,
we did some kind of back of the napkin math here, and we figured out that it would take
about 12 hours, we thought, to solve the problem, and we thought that information security officers
were spending about an hour a week generating a weekly inventory, if they even did that.
In three months, 12 hours, we would make up the difference, assuming there was just one
of these.
We're going to do the project, basically.
We selected a tool.
Now let's talk a little bit about why.
Why AWS Lambda?
Well, for us, we didn't want to add a piece of automation that incurred more maintenance,
so we don't have to worry about a server here.
That was a huge plus.
Lambda is a function as a service offering, meaning it's a tiny little runtime that somebody
else maintains for you.
You just give it code, and it runs that code.
Pretty cool.
There's nothing to really patch.
We have a big patching problem in large enterprises, and that's reflected by all the data leaks
and all of the issues that you see in the news.
We didn't want to add to our patching problem by having another server we have to maintain.
Once again, I just want to say there's no runtime maintenance.
That's really great.
That's the huge appeal of Lambda to me.
Of course, a bonus is that it's extremely affordable.
I just want to pause here and refer to Dan McKinley, who has this great quote.
How would we solve the problem at hand without adding anything new?
Newness, sprawling technology is not without expense.
I think Dan's really onto something here.
The cherry on top for Lambda for us is we already have access to it.
It's a part of our infrastructure.
Because we're running everything in AWS, Lambda is there waiting for us.
The final little thing I wanted to mention is Lambda is so small and efficient that running
a single one is very energy efficient, and that's good for the Earth, and that's good
for us.
All right.
Why Python?
I probably don't have to convince PyTexus on this, but I'm going to try anyways.
We really were interested in Python because of the imperative coding style that it conferred.
Also, Stack Overflow Survey, I can't go wrong with this.
Python is always in the second or third most loved language.
Taking a step back again to some external wisdom here from Mr. Kinsella, Python was
interesting to us because we didn't have to worry about a bunch of dependencies.
The appeal of having a robust standard library running in this little remote runtime was
huge because we don't have to think about breaking independency or patching independency
or anything like that.
Of course, everyone knows Python is hugely popular, but I didn't realize this until I
went and checked the Stack Overflow Survey for 2020, and it almost doubles its lead over
JavaScript and Go as being the most wanted technology by professional developers.
That's really cool, and I think it says that Python is just going to keep growing and growing
and growing.
All right.
Let's talk a little bit about the architecture of our solution.
I wanted to lay out the whole picture before we get into the nitty gritty.
CloudWatch is an AWS service that allows you to define events.
In this case, we're defining a time-based event.
By that, we mean we want something to happen every so often, so every week, let's say.
That thing we want to happen is we want our lambda to run.
Our lambda is written in all Python, and the Python code is saying, hey, go out, scan these
cloud assets, put together an inventory for me.
Do what that abacus used to be done manually by someone, put it in the CSV, so put it in
the format that I'm used to, and then go save it in object storage, so save it in S3.
This part's important because we want some element of permanence to it.
This is our high-level architecture.
We're going to step through each of the steps now.
All right.
Going to step number one, one of the things that's important to understand about AWS is
that when you want to access resources in a different account, we have our systems defined
in different accounts, you have to assume cross-account access.
Basically what that means is you have an agreement with a foreign entity that you're both allowed
to talk to each other.
What's happening here is we are using Boto 3, which is the AWS SDK for Python, and we're
using that to create a resource, and we're calling the STS service or the security token
service.
We're saying, hey, allow us to assume a role in the second account, account B, and we're
the role of CA-scanner, which just stands for cross-account scanner.
It's going to return to us some credentials, some temporary credentials, so we can actually
do our work.
This is what we just described in architectural format.
We're calling out with our Lambda to STS.
That security service is allowing us to assume a role, and the account and the security service
are returning to us credentials so we can actually do work.
I just want to pause here and explain some things I discovered about Boto 3, the SDK.
Clients versus resources.
Clients are low-level interfaces, meaning you're really close to the actual AWS service
API.
Whereas resources, resources are really nice.
They're object-oriented interfaces, meaning they come with easy ways to deal with it.
What I found through this process is that I would be excited when I would discover that
a service had a resource to offer through the SDK, and then I would mentally prepare
myself if I was stuck dealing with a low-level client.
I'll show you a couple examples of that as we go through the code.
Now that we've got those credentials, we're basically going to create either a resource
or a client for each different service that we want to go through and scan.
Here, and we'll go through these individually, but we're basically looking at different services
like EC2, the Elastic Compute Cloud, which is virtual machines, or RDS, which is the
relational database service, so that's for databases for storage, or things like Elastic
Cache, API Gateway.
You probably know what those two do.
After that, let's look at one specific example.
One of the ways that we quantify our inventories is in devices.
We define a new array, and that array, because this is a resource, we're actually going to
be able to iterate through it using ec2.instances.all, which is just super easy and nice.
Preferable.
One of the things I immediately found out upon doing this project, almost in the first
hour, is that we actually had an old server running on one of the accounts I was testing
against that had an image that was so old, it was in the wrong format, and this API call
would choke and fail.
From our number one, this little automation project showed some value because we didn't
realize we had that old server and we needed to go kill it.
After writing a guard clause here to make sure that this API call didn't fail, we move
on to pulling out the tag names and also the environment details.
Then from here, because this is a resource, this is really nice.
We have access to all of these things where you can go in and just map from kind of human
readable column, like host name or private IP or baseline image, and we can pull that
off of the API itself.
Let's look at the next one.
This is another device, a load balancer, but this is using a client.
You can see here that I'm having to do a little bit more work to actually pull the information
I want out.
I'm having to understand from this lower level client exactly what's going on in the data.
This is just something to be aware of.
Those were our two device examples.
The other way we think about systems are in interfaces.
A VPC is a virtual private cloud or a network.
What's nice about this and what's interesting about this is as I dug into this, I started
to learn a little bit more about how AWS actually works.
By that, I mean VPCs are actually just kind of a subcomponent of the EC2 service.
You can see here I'm still benefiting from using that EC2 resource.
I can still use it kind of dot all and iterate over that with a for loop.
This is another easy one.
It's not like dealing with a client, but it's very telling that VPCs are part of the EC2
service.
It allows us to trace back some of AWS's DNA to figure out that EC2 is one of the core
services and one of the first ones.
You can't run much without a network, so VPCs are a starting point.
Then, of course, I just want to call out that there are a lot of fields here that are left
at NA.
Those are future opportunities for improvement.
We hope to do a lot with those.
All right, so moving on to a different interface.
This is RDS.
This is a managed database service.
Looking at this, you can see that I left a little note here.
This isn't super useful right now because one of the difficulties that we had before
when we were using the old abacus method was certain data fields didn't really map over.
For example, in this case, we didn't have a discrete name like Daisy for our database.
Instead, we were using a database identifier, and that's what actually made it unique.
We had to figure out how that worked.
The other thing I did here is I started to have a conversation with Darren, the security
officer I was working with on this project.
I started to notice data points that I thought the security team might be interested in,
like is it encrypted or what's the backup period?
We actually ended up adding more fields to the inventory process than we had originally
planned so that we can improve our security.
I think that's really cool.
That's step number two.
If step number one was assuming that identity, step number two is actually scanning the resources
and iterating through them and putting them into a human readable format.
Let's talk about step number three.
Once we've got all the data, now we can bring it all together.
We're going to actually just use a very simple function here to write out a dictionary in
CSV format, specifying the columns, and then we're going to do something interesting.
We're going to store it in local file storage for a second.
One of the nice things about Lambda is you have access to a file system, but it's ephemeral.
Once the Lambda is done executing, it's going to go away, which is fine because we're composing
a CSV, but we want it to live on.
In this case, we're actually outputting it to the simple storage service or S3, which is
object storage at a certain ID with a certain Unix timestamp attached to it.
Now, one of the final things that I would be remiss if I didn't share with you is remember,
Lambda is a function as a service offering, meaning it's expecting something to return.
It's a function.
Even though this thing is all done, it's done all of its work, if you don't return some status
code saying you did work and you're successful, your Lambda will be mad at you.
In this case, we're just saying, hey, dump this to the logs.
Let them know that we were successful.
That's number three, taking the data that we combed and turning it into something that
we can use forevermore.
Let's bring it all together and actually automate it by making it happen on a certain schedule.
This is a picture of the Lambda console.
On the left side, there's the CloudWatch event trigger I was talking about.
If you were to click that add trigger button, it would give you an interface where you can
define a cron job.
You can go in and say, hey, I want this thing to run on certain days of the week at a certain
time.
In this case, it's Wednesday at 9 a.m. Eastern for us.
You can also feed it an account number.
At the very beginning of our function, we were pulling an account out of the event object.
That's because we want to know which system we're going to scan.
This is where you would enter those details in your trigger.
As you can see, we had nine initial ones set up.
Those were all set to run and scan different systems and bring back inventories.
This is the final step.
This is taking that CloudWatch event, hooking it up to the Lambda, which was step number
one.
We did backwards, forwards, and making the whole system work.
Here's the actual output.
The output looks like this.
It's a series of files in CSV format where we capture the artifacts, the devices, and
the interfaces.
We get a weekly one.
If we were to open devices and interfaces, you can see that we're getting human readable
information in a very easy to consume and predictable way.
We're getting the same thing every week.
By doing that, we're getting to see how systems change over time.
The feedback we've gotten is very positive.
We're pretty excited about the results of this.
By the numbers, very small program, 626 lines of code, only four kilobytes, but it's doing
a lot of work.
In terms of cost savings, at one hour per system per week, we use a blended rate of
about $80 per hour per worker.
At 21 current accounts in AWS, each one needs to be inventoried.
We're talking about $1,700 a week in terms of savings and about $90,000 per year, which
is pretty amazing.
I feel bad if I didn't stop here and acknowledge something, which is that CFOs and budget people
don't actually think that this is real cost savings.
That's because that person's still employed.
We're still paying them $80 an hour.
While someone with an accountant might be suspicious of me calling this cost savings,
I actually think the benefits are bigger than cost savings because what you're regaining
is actually the opportunity to do something else.
Those people don't have to think about compliance like this anymore, like we did at the beginning
with the Eve flat on the table.
That guy instead feels more like this.
He's super happy, and he's super happy because automation means happiness.
He no longer has to do mundane menial tasks like count digital assets.
Instead, he can focus his energy elsewhere.
In conclusion, Python running in Lambda, I think it's the ultimate cloud cron job runner.
I've only written a couple of these so far, but I'm really amped about it, and I've had
great results so far.
I want to share with you some future improvements we plan on making some of the output easier
to read, enhancing it, and then we're also going to expand this script to additional
AWS services.
All of this code is going to be open source by the time you see this video, and you can
find it at our organization, which is slash US SBA on GitHub.
I have a call to action for you all.
Find a problem, do some napkin math to see if it's worth automating.
Select a tool.
Just go do it.
I'll leave you with a quote from a good friend of mine, Mr. John King, which is, what's the
actual lifetime of the decision you're making?
Are you sitting there, and are you over analyzing what's going on?
Are you thinking for four hours about a piece of work that's only going to take you two?
Just go do it.
Go automate the thing.
Thank you so much.
I hope you have a great PyTexas.