Hi, my name is Jessica Garson and I'm here to talk with you about creating sample code.
Let me know if this inspires you to create anything.
You can reach out to me on Twitter.
DMs are open and my handle is at Jessica Garson.
What this talk is about is about how you were launching the V2 of the Twitter API.
We started off with this program called Twitter Developer Labs,
which were previews of the new endpoints that later became our launching point for
the new endpoints that we recently released, the V2 version of the Twitter API.
We are committed to partnering with developers to help create and shape the future of our
API. As we were working through this process, we were releasing new endpoints that no one
had ever built with before. Therefore, they didn't have the same infrastructure as other
endpoints that had community-based libraries and a lot of different other resources that existed.
They were brand new and nobody had ever seen them before. We had to create a series of sample code.
You might be wondering, what is sample code? I like to think of sample code
as code for other humans to use. It's similar to example code. It's often code that you'll see
in documentation. You might see it on a sample repository. Sometimes you'll see it
for an open source library, but it's code for other people to use. It's different from production
code where you're building code that's supposed to run a product or code for others to extend
and build on top of. Sample code is actually created to help people accomplish very specific
tasks by creating code that helps you get started with an API, typically, or a package or a library.
Our sample code, a lot of what I'm going to be talking about today, is found on our GitHub
repository. In particular, I'll be showing a few examples from the v2 version of our
GitHub repository, which is github.com slash twitterdev slash twitterapi v2 sample code.
Also, there is other sample code available just in our main Twitter dev repository. There are lots
of different things that myself and other team members have been working on. We also have it
in our documentation. With the launch, we also launched some code-related resources. We have
a Postman collection. Postman, for those who don't know, is a REST client that helps you make your
first requests. I think of that as also sample code because it can help you create your first
requests. Then there's also an open API specification that we made available as well, too,
which can also be helpful as well if you want to build libraries or just see our spec in more
detail or even just take a look at how things are made. As we have been starting to create
more sample code, there are some questions I like to ask myself as I'm creating sample code.
The first is, can you look at the code and know exactly what's going on? Some key questions to
think about as you're going through it. Is it readable? Is the code consistent? Does it do
help accomplish one goal in one language but another goal in a different language? For example,
let's say you had a JavaScript version of the code that went through a different process to
getting a JSON payload as a Python version which exported everything into a CSV file. That would
be very different experiences. You want to make sure that your code is consistent with each other
and also consistent with other code samples that you may have released in the past as well.
I like to have my code lightly commented. The code has some instructions
and some things to help you adjust and have it meet your needs, but it's also very readable as
well. The variable names also are explanatory and it has a good README. Therefore, you can actually
make sure that there are directions and documentation around how you would use it
and what steps you need to take before you use it and any set of instructions.
With both code commenting and a README, it is important to make sure that it is lightly
commented. You might have heard me say that once before already in this talk, but by lightly
commented, it's not like a million comments where it's harder to read the code or your README is so
long and has so many different directions that it's really intense to get started because you
have to go through so many different processes. It's simple and to the point, but yet easy to
follow. Keep that in mind as you are creating sample code. Also, I like to think of good sample
code as building blocks and almost like that base layer of the block. One thing, especially
as you're going, I recently spoke at the Philly Python user group and I created a code sample
for that. I used our filtered string sample code and just built on top of it and extended it
to meet the goals of the application that I was going to be presenting on. I learned so much in
that process from a developer empathy perspective of just what it takes to build and extend off of
it because I noticed a lot of things about the code sample and there were some inconsistencies.
I noticed a lot just as I was using it in that way and it's really helpful to see how developers
will use it because a lot of times people who return to your sample code are using it to figure
out how to integrate it with their applications. Seeing if you can actually build on top of it
was a really great exercise in developer empathy. Also, how others will perceive your code. At Twitter,
we spent a lot of time editing written documents and we're moving towards giving the same
attention to our code samples. Before we launched our V2 version of the Twitter API, we actually
had a bud bash for all of our sample code which was pretty great because we were able to
give it the same attention that we actually give to larger engineering releases. A bud bash is
where there's a series of tests and you have two testers who will go through and take a look and
see is it working, is it passing each test, and then from there you can fix any bugs that may
come up if there's weird errors that come up and things like that. That's something that was really
exciting. We're also moving towards the possibility and we're starting to explore the possibility of
using automated testing for some of our code samples as well and that's something we've
considered as well. Also, just making sure that your code is following the conventions
that are established. I'm a Python developer and I use Pilant and I use Black for auto-formatting.
Love Black, happy to talk with any of you about that. It makes my code look a little bit more
polished just because it isn't auto-formatted. Making sure that you are following modern code
conventions and also documenting that as well is really important. The next thing might sound
kind of silly but it's really important. Is the code sample working? As you're going through the
process of creating sample code, you want to make sure that the code is easy to replicate without
complicated setup and make sure that it ages well. I've run a lot of code, especially in the past
year, that was working at the time and was really great but no longer works or the payloads have
changed or the libraries that it depended on have made updates or there are newer, more exciting
libraries that have come out that accomplish the task in a different way. Making sure that
that happens as well. Also, security vulnerabilities in libraries, different things that can come up as
well to just make sure that your code is aging well and working and that you have a way to
quickly make changes if things do break and that you're responsive as things are not working or
as you notice things that are coming up. You might be wondering what does good sample code look like?
I have a few examples to talk with you about. One thing that I like to think about is functions like
paragraphs. I like my code to tell a story and then I personally really like
to take a step back before I write sample code and I'm like, okay, cool. What is the
tutorial that I'm going to write about the sample code if I was going to write a tutorial?
What are the things that need to be done? Then write it down in a notebook and then create code
that matches all the tasks and think about it like that. My personal style of code tends to be
very modular and build on top of each other and then tie it together with a main statement,
which I like to think about as a conclusion. You have your introduction, which is your imports,
then paragraphs, which are each function, and then the conclusion that ties it all together
is the main function. That's how I like to think about writing sample code.
Let's take a look at an example that does that. We have this import request, import OS, and import
JSON. Those are the two things. I do have some light comments just to make sure that you have
what you need to run it. This is some sample code that we have for filtered stream inside of our
sample code repository for v2. This is for the sample stream endpoint. From here,
we want to authenticate. We just want to pass in our environment variable token for
our barrier token. We're going to want to create the URL for sample stream. Then we want to create
the headers that we're going to pass in here. Then we're going to want to connect to the endpoint.
There's some logic and an exception code that that passes through. Basically, in that function,
that's where you're actually going to do the connection. Then we have this main for the
conclusion, which sets a barrier token as just the auth function, the URL as create URL,
headers as create headers. Then since it's a streaming endpoint, it's just going to want
to keep running. There's some logic around that. That's a little bit about how I like to think
about creating functions like paragraphs. Simple and to the point. What I mean by that is that
I really like to make sure that my code is really straightforward. I had a code sample that was
originally about 190 lines. I just kept on slashing it and removing many lines until
it was as simple and to the point as possible. For those types of code samples,
I like to remove any unnecessary complexity so I can maybe live code it at a talk.
This particular sample that I'm about to show, I have live coded the Chicago Python meetup,
which was really fun, and ChiPy. Then I also live coded it at PyOhio as well.
As I'm going through this process of doing it, I really wanted to ask myself,
is every line really needed? Does it have to be there? Can I get rid of it? How can I make
this as simple as possible so that I can show this to others and they can follow along
with what's going on? This is actually a sample that is in R, but it runs your favorite Python
package in R using a library called reticulate. For that, I first wanted to install the packages
and then from here set my path to Python, create a virtual environment and use the virtual
environment and then import the Python libraries for JSON and requests. Get tweets from a given
handle, create the URL there, pass in the credentials, and then create a JSON payload
and put it into a data frame using some R packages. This is actually 38 lines and it's
turned out much, much, much longer. That's an example of how to make very simple code.
The point of this code sample was actually something that I can easily live code and talk
about at a conference. I really wanted it to be as simple as possible. You'll notice that there
aren't any functions in this. That's actually because this was mostly for a Python audience,
but in R, I wanted to make sure that that was very specific to them. I wanted to really be
able to explain each line as I was creating it. This example was made for those conferences as
well. Another thing that I like to think about as well is customizing my exemptions. One thing that
is really interesting when you're creating tried-exempt statements is that you have the
ability to create your own messages. One thing that I noticed in the bug bash that I talked about
earlier was that a lot of people were getting the same error when they tried to type in
their credentials wrong. I was like, oh, cool, I'll create a customized exemption. That's something
that I hadn't done before, but I thought was something that was really great. This comes
from our sample code for the new v2. This is hitting the get tweets endpoint using OAuth 1.0.
It creates this pin authorization. This is actually one of the longest code comments
that I think I've written in a long time. You'll notice on line 26, there's this try-exempt
statement. With that, we're first going to try to get the request token.
At this point, this is where the code was failing when people would be typing in their wrong
credentials. What I did was I created an exemption that said there may have been an issue
with your consumer key or secret just in case others experienced the same error again.
That is something that I added to try to make that a little bit more robust.
Cool. You might be wondering, what is the process that you use for writing sample code? How do you
even get started with this? The process that we use at Twitter is that we start off by creating
the code, then we do a peer review, we iterate off of that, build, so we actually start to build
and get feedback. The way that I like to think about it is that you start off with your draft
of a new code sample and then you get reviewers to think about how can you break it. I try to be
very specific in who I get. A lot of times, I'll try to get newer developers mixed with some
experienced developers or people who know the language or endpoint really well. Then from there,
I take their feedback and I take it seriously. I also try to break it a little bit more. Then
I try to build with the sample code that I've created and see what that's like. Once we release
it, we also would love to get feedback from the community. I've had a couple of pull requests
on samples that I've written where people have caused some things that we didn't catch through
peer review process or just noticed something that we didn't notice or sometimes had things
break in very specific ways. Being able to be open and receptive to that feedback has been really
important. I've learned a lot as part of this process of creating sample code for first the
labs endpoints and then the V2 versions. Most of all, it's the importance of Hello World.
Like one of the things that was really great for me about the first time that I ever worked with
the Twitter API was that I remember the first time I ever built a Twitter bot and I was like,
oh my God, my code is making this thing tweet. This is awesome. I'm like making internet happen.
I got so excited that I sent an email to a list of almost 2,000 people of women who were learning
how to code in D.C. at the same time for this community program called Hear Me Code. I was like,
oh my God, I built this thing. It's so exciting. I remember that feeling when I think about it
often and trying to help others have that feeling as quickly as possible is really the goal of good
sample code. Really thinking about that, developers come from a lot of different places and trying to
make sure that you have code that can help get them there as quickly as possible is always good.
Also, one thing I've learned this year in particular is that what is good today might
not be good tomorrow. Code can change and libraries can change and conventions can change.
Code will break and it might be working great one day and not so great because of changes that
happen for many different reasons. Keeping that in mind as well. Also, as I mentioned earlier,
your code will be viewed by people from many different backgrounds and may be viewed very
differently by different groups of people. So really thinking about how you can make code be
as accessible as possible following conventions from L.I. and also just thinking about ways
that other people may perceive it and trying to be as accessible as possible is also something that
I've been thinking a lot about recently. And really being open to feedback.
A lot of times I'll read things about our code samples and sometimes it's actually me who wrote
the code samples on our Twitter community forums or I'll see you on Twitter or I'll be talking
with folks in the community and just knowing that code is always a work in progress and being open
and receptive to feedback has been really helpful in the process. So as we're talking
about feedback, we're very open to it as a team at Twitter. So if there are code resources that
you want to see, let us know. One particular example is when we first launched Labs, we did
not launch any Node.js samples and somebody wrote in and they were like, hey, please give us Node.js
samples and so we were able to create those pretty quickly. And you can give us feedback
at twitterdevfeedback.useroice.com and we definitely want to hear from you what you want to see in
terms of resources or even feature requests or anything like that. Just let us know. There's
also some additional ways to give us feedback as well. You can file an issue on GitHub.
You can submit a pull request if you want to fix it yourself. We love pull requests
there have been some people that have really helped out in a big way by finding things that
we didn't catch, by helping us make our code a little bit more robust, by changing some things.
That is always, always acceptable and I love it when that happens. So yeah, feel free to submit
a pull request. Documentation feedback. On every documentation page, if you scroll down to the
bottom, you'll see a happy face or a sad face and you can click on the sad face if you see
things that need to be improved and let us know. And yeah, we're definitely, we have just started
releasing the first few on points of the Twitter API and we're definitely learning as we move
towards future launches. So we're definitely trying to learn from some of our past mistakes
and move forward from there. So it's been really great to kind of be part of this journey.
And also feel free to take a look at our code samples and even clone them and try them out
yourself. And again, github.com slash Twitter dev slash Twitter API B2 sample code is where
most of the code that I talked about today lives. And also I love to talk about sample code. If
you're creating sample code and want to show me what you built or want to ask me questions or
really anything or want to talk about the Twitter API or really just want to talk about Python,
anything like that, let me know if this inspires you to create anything. My
handle is at Jessica Garson and feel free to reach out to me. You can also let us know at
Twitter dev or on the Twitter community forums. And here are some other links that might be helpful
as well. Again, Twitter dev feedback.useroys.com. All our sample code is found on Twitter dev
or github.com slash Twitter dev. You want to look at any code samples. And then you can also
communicate with us via the Twitter community forums. Thank you so much and have a great day.