Hello, everybody.
My name is Moshe Zadka.
My website is Cobodism.com, and today I want to talk to you about DevPI, the tool you never
knew you needed.
I do want to start with an acknowledgement of country.
I live in the San Francisco Bay Area.
It is the ancestral homeland of the Muweka Ohlone people, and much of the story that
I'm going to talk to you about happens at Camp Twanga, which is the ancestral homeland
of the Central Sierra Miwok people.
And as I already spoiled, the story starts at Camp Twanga.
Camp Twanga is a beautiful, beautiful summer camp.
And after the summer is done, for families with kids who are a little bit too young to
go to summer camp on their own, they have what they call family summer camp during the
school year on some weekends.
And that's great.
You get, as you can see in the picture, to go on this beautiful lake with your kids on
the paddle boat.
The kids absolutely love it.
But there's one thing that's even better than that, which is, as you can see in the pictures
on the bottom, for some part of the time, the kids all hang out by themselves doing
fun things that one would do in a summer camp with the camp counselors.
And we, the parents, have time to ourselves to do whatever we want.
And especially at that time, my kids were a bit young.
I didn't have a lot of free time for myself during the weekend.
And this seemed like, oh, what am I going to do with all that time?
This is great.
So as one would, I decided I'm going to work on some personal stuff, like every normal
person.
Great.
So there's only one problem with that.
Camp Twanga doesn't have Wi-Fi.
In fact, it doesn't even have wired internet.
And it's kind of in the middle of Yosemite Park, which, to anyone who's ever visited
there, you would know that it does not have any cellular connectivity.
So no internet.
No connection with the outside world, which is actually great to kind of work on stuff
without interruptions.
But the best thing about working in Python, I do, and I'm sure many of you do, is that
you get to use the awesome PyPI.
You get so many packages.
I don't remember how many packages were there.
A few hundred thousand.
I haven't checked lately about how many packages are now probably over a million, but I haven't
checked recently.
A lot.
A lot is a good approximation.
Right?
And like, you know, the packages, right?
So I'm like, okay, I'm going to need some local package cache.
And for many months now at that point, I resisted installing their PyPi.
Why would I even need it?
I'll always have internet.
But you know, the best day plans.
And I was going to not have internet.
And finally, my friends broke me down, and I'm like, fine, I'll install PyPI.
So it's pretty easy.
I created a virtual environment dedicated for that, as I do for most of the things I care about.
This virtual environment is pretty cheap.
I created a virtual environment called the PyPI.
I installed it.
I started the server.
That's pretty much it.
Now, if you look at the official documentation, you can see how to integrate the system.
This is a modern laptop in, you know, this was in 2017, 2018.
It's a modern laptop in kind of like modern times.
I pretty much never restarted.
I always hibernate it and hibernate it off.
If I have it running in some time, it's actually pretty convenient.
You can see the log file.
I'll minimize it.
If I don't see it in the window, pretty straightforward, no need to background, all kinds of complicated
demon manipulation.
I have a server up.
That's it.
But I'm a very suspicious man.
I don't trust things very easily.
Definitely not new things that I've never experienced before.
I wasn't going to trust it with, like, you know, how I'm going to work without internet.
I wanted to kind of ramp up the trust slowly.
So, the first thing I did was, okay, I'm going to install just a couple of packages.
This is a default index it generates when you just write it up, put slash PyPI, simple.
So I install, a couple of random packages, play with them just to see that they got downloaded
correctly, that I don't get weird import errors, like, what the hell did you try to download,
like a broken package with just the headers or just the metadata, whatever.
It works, right, once, right, that's definitely not enough evidence to say it's going to work
again.
Right?
So, you know, cautious optimism.
And in the spirit of cautious optimism, my next step, I'm going to make it temporarily.
So in a terminal, I'm going to export the environment variable.
Now every time you type in this terminal, it's going to use the API if for some reason
it doesn't work.
You can just literally just access the shell, and I'm good to go.
This is great, right, and everything is awesome, and, you know, like, I try to play with it
a bunch of times, right, but now it's the default, right, so everything I run under
that is going to use that environment variable, that's my main development terminal, so, you
know, like, I would see if it's causing a problem, and, you know, like, after a few
days, if it doesn't cause a problem, I decide, like, it's time to make a firm commitment.
So and by firm commitment, I mean, let's put it in the pip.conf.
Now, like many of you, I'm sure, I didn't have a pip.conf before that works pretty well
without any configuration.
It grabs the package, installs it, everything works, right, but, you know, you see, to direct
it to the FBI, you don't need to configure it.
Pretty easy, right, I probably did it with V.I., not with cat, but you literally could
copy paste that command and it would work, right?
Simple, easy, now I don't have to think about it, I can close the terminal, I can, you
know, create new terminals and whatever, run shells, new shells, old shells, whatever,
and everything works, and, again, you know, this all helps, you know, packages get downloaded.
But do I really trust it, right, like, you know, like, how much packages am I going to
download every day, right?
Am I going to download everything I need before I go out of network range and I'll have nothing?
So, kind of scary, right, better, better prepare.
So, I did what any normal person would do, I ran talks, right, I, you know, here's an
example of running talks in Twisted, I don't even care if it succeeds, right, all I care
is that it kind of goes and builds all the virtual environments with all the packages
it gets from PyPI, right, and, you know, you care about other things, anyway, you have
to get to be able to work, it's out of network range, run talks, talks, talks, talks, talks,
a few more talks, and we're good to go, right, again, doesn't matter if it succeeds or fails,
all you need is just to download all the packages that you need, and, again, it doesn't matter
if you save them because all you want is to hit DevPI as hard as possible before you go
out of range so that it's going to get as much of the things you need day to day out
of PyPI.
So, this is great.
This works great, and, you know, I got to Camtowanga, I managed to actually do work,
I think I fixed a ticket in Twisted, it was a while ago, so I don't remember, it worked,
right, but I know what you're thinking, I'm giving this talk in 2020, hopefully it will
stay in YouTube for a while longer, so for the people in the future and for the people
in the present who need a reminder, there's a global pandemic going on, summer camps,
especially Camtowanga is something that leaves the Jewish philosophy of respecting life and
prioritizing saving lives shut down pretty fast during the pandemic, and, you know, like,
we're not going to see it open, at least in the near future, why am I even talking about
that?
Who cares?
We're all staying home, we have great networks, what does it matter?
I'm sure when the pandemic ends, maybe then we can learn about the API.
But that's not all the API can give you, right?
So, again, like, Camtowanga was like a crisis point, I had to install it, now I have it
running, let's figure out how I can use it to do more stuff.
So, turns out one of the cool things you can do is build yourself a little private area,
a little private API that you can use for all kinds of things.
Now, what can you use it?
Well, let's say that you have a package.
And let's say that's the last time you install the package, and I'm definitely not talking
about my embarrassment in my experience, this was definitely someone who is not me, let's
call you Masha, who uploaded a package, and it was embarrassing for the other person who's
not me, and I want to make sure that I will never be embarrassed in that way.
Again, so, what do we do?
Well, we can do a test upload.
Sure, it does test API, but it's kind of annoying, and, for example, uploading the same package
again to test API will not work because it's like API, and you can't upload the same package
to API, right?
So, if you think you're going to make a mistake, and, again, I would never make a mistake,
but some other people might make a mistake.
You might, if you don't know how to avoid mistakes as well as me.
You know, you might need to upload the same package more than once until you get it right.
So, the API works great, right?
You don't even have to go outside, and you can tear it down, and you can build multiple.
So, you know, here I'm building a little private area that beckons into the root API, which is
really important because what if your package has dependencies?
And, you know, your package has dependencies probably unless you're very, very, very careful
and, like, a bit focused on that, let's say.
So, let's first test it, like, you know, there's no package, right?
I haven't uploaded my package, and this is great, right?
Because this means that it doesn't exist on PyPI.
It doesn't exist in the private area, but that's great.
Just make sure that I actually remember to increase the version number.
And, again, I'm not saying I have ever made the mistake of forgetting to increase the version number,
but, you know, some other people who are definitely not me might have done that mistake.
So, easy to test it first.
Okay, but, you know, that's an easy test to do.
You could have done it with PyPI, so not a big deal.
But then I upload, you know, just like Twine, you know, obviously with a custom repo and a custom user
and a custom password, which doesn't have to be very secure because it's only a local host and who cares.
So, if you do want to care, you can, of course, do more secure things with the password.
And then, of course, when I try to pip install it, it didn't fail, it didn't succeed because I
forgot to put with me MD in the manifest.
I usually use with me RST, and I forget with me RST while it goes there by default.
With me MD does not.
This was a package that was not mandated by me.
And, yeah.
So, but, again, like, this is just between me and my computer, right?
Like, the world outside doesn't know that I made this, like, you know, snuffle.
So, I can, you know, keep face, let's say, in front of my friends and colleagues.
And real quick, you know, fix that, like, fix my manifest.in.
Upload it again.
Notice I can upload the same version again because it's just the PyPI.
You can mark something as you can't upload that again, but by default those test areas, you can just
reupload them, right?
They're not supposed to be, like, long-term persistent or have all these really good guarantees
that this PyPI would give you.
So, let's see if it works.
It works.
I can import.
And, you know, in real life, again, unless you've really gotten to great length to automate your
package creation and upload, you're probably going to make a few more mistakes.
That would be very fun.
It's pretty nice to be able to do those mistakes in private a few times.
And if you are automating the upload, you definitely want to make sure that while you're working on
automation, you're doing that, right?
So, regardless of which path you're going to take, this is a good way forward.
Now, let's say that you have a few packages that you all want to make sure all work together.
Sure, not ideal.
Ideal packages have.
But, you know, sometimes it happens.
Maybe you're not uploading to the real PyPI.
Maybe you're uploading them just to kind of your friend and colleague's internal proprietary package
or whatever.
Want to make sure that a bunch of these versions work together.
Then you can do that.
You can make an integration area.
And, again, upload from the current area to the integration area.
So, this is pretty cool, right?
You can kind of test a bunch of packages independently and then check if they integrate well.
So, this is pretty great, right?
You're, you know, again, like you still have to figure out some development workflow.
But now you have support for a lot of bits that you would need to support to get a good workflow.
And finally, one of the best things is so I started the talk while saying I'm installing the
PyPI on my laptop.
And my laptop, as always, is just a laptop.
You can, again, integrate with system CTL.
Actually run it on some server that runs on your cloud provider or whatever.
You can run Kubernetes with the right settings.
You have a bunch of options.
It doesn't matter, really.
At the end of the day, you can just run your PyPI and, you know, figure out some sort of usually your
usually you have any way of VPN.
If you don't want a VPN, you can always put it behind some username password proxy or whatever.
And you have a shared FPI.
And this is great, right?
Because now for the packages, again, you want to only share with your colleagues.
You have a FPI.
And you back end your local FPI to that FPI.
So, you don't have to configure PAP.
You don't have to, you know, make sure that every talk doesn't override the version of PAP.
It just works against your FPI.
And everything works great.
And if the AppStream ever changes, just change the AppStream, you don't have to worry about that.
So, this gives you a great area to share with your colleagues.
And while it doesn't scale to PyPI level and possibly doesn't scale if your company is on Microsoft or Facebook
or whatever, it scales for quite a while.
As long as it's just going to be one person managing that because that's all the engineering stuff your company can afford.
If I shared the FPI, the FPI would probably scale up to that level.
So, it scales pretty nicely.
And it will give you pretty much all you need to actually run like an engineering organization that is layered on top of Python.
Of course, that means you take it seriously, right?
This is your source of tools for packages.
You probably want to make sure you back up.
It's pretty easy to back up.
Again, it doesn't solve the backup problem for you, nor should it.
It's not a backup service.
What the FPI knows how to do is how to export the data to a consistent thing.
Then you can use whatever backup in general you use.
Be it some backup service or just tabling random things and sending off whatever solution you think is right for your scale and your needs and reliability constraints and so on.
But you start with exporting to the directory and then you figure out how to back up that directory.
And I hope that any of you who is in charge of some system that is somehow involved with backing up knows that you need to restore.
You need to do test restores every now and then.
Pretend like you have a crash.
Pretend you have to restore and see if it works.
So, that's how the restore.
The first step is taking whatever the S3 bucket or the crash pad or crash plan or whatever it is and dumping it into local directories.
Then you can import from that local directory and run the server again.
Then back into that server.
That's one of the nice things about having the ability to configure an app screen for the API.
And see that you could have worked this way.
Regardless of the frequency and how involved your restore exercises are.
Frequency should be bigger than zero.
Whatever it is and however they're planned, this is a good support for that thing.
Again, the API itself is not a backup solution, but it will support your backup workflow.
So, with that, I want to leave you with some parking flow thoughts about that.
Whether you're out in the woods experimenting with some open source packages locally or working in a team, the API is a tool that you never needed.
Thank you very much for listening to my talk.
And I hope you have a great experience the rest of the conference.
Goodbye.
Thank you.