I want to thank the Pi Texas organizers for putting on this conference. I was really looking
forward to coming down to Austin to hang out with some friends, talk about Python,
and eat some brisket. But unfortunately, that's not in the cards for 2020. Hopefully we can make it
happen next year. And to everybody out there, thank you for tuning into the session. I really
appreciate your time. My name is Ali Sivji. You can find me on Twitter. I am at Kaya Sivjas.
I'm one of the organizers of the Chicago Python users group. We call ourselves Chippy. Chippy is
one of the largest Python communities in the world. We have over 6,000 members, and every month we
usually hold three to five events. Normally at this time, I didn't invite you all to come out to
Chicago and attend a Chippy event, but we've had to cancel all of our in-person meetups until it's
safe to meet in large groups. But we have been engaging our community through various online
platforms. We recently started live streaming our events to our YouTube channel. Now you don't
actually need to come out to Chicago to attend a Chippy event. You can do it from the comforts of
your own home. Check out our channel, subscribe to it, hit that bell icon, and you'll get notified of
all of our upcoming live streams. Hope to see you all there. Let's get started. So this talk is titled
Everyday Design Patterns, and I really wanted to emphasize that we don't have to be designing
complex distributed systems to implement design patterns. We can go ahead and use them in our
everyday code. So I want to start off by sharing experience of how the facade pattern made my code
easy to change. In the Chicago Python Slack, we have a bot that displays a list of our upcoming
events every time we use the slash busy beaver events command. Like most user groups, Chicago
Python leverages the Meetup platform to publicize our events. And our Slack bot uses the Meetup API
to fetch a list of upcoming events. In August of last year, Meetup announced that they're
going to remove version two of their API, and they're going to require all clients to migrate
to version three. This wasn't a problem. I was using a Python API client. I probably just had to
go out and update this client. I'm going to go ahead and probably change a few calls, and I'd
be good to go. Unfortunately, the project I was using was in maintenance mode. So what does this
really mean? Looking at the documentation, it doesn't seem like there's much support for the
version three API. So we're going to have to roll up our sleeves and do things the old-fashioned way.
That is, we're going to now have to use requests. We're going to hit that Meetup API. We're going
to parse the resulting JSON. Usually this means that we're going to have to go out and update
integration code across our project. Fortunately, I had used the facade pattern when designing this
integration. In this image, you can see a diff for all the changes that are required to change the
Meetup integration from version two to version three. I only had to change this one class.
Then I updated all my contract tests, and I was done. All the code that leveraged this
Meetup.com integration, it worked the same as before. The facade pattern's pretty awesome,
but we're getting a bit ahead of ourselves. Let's talk about design patterns.
Design patterns are solutions to commonly occurring problems in software design. We can think of
design patterns as customizable blueprints that can be used to implement a solution to a known
problem. When we use a pattern, we're going to need to adapt it to our specific use case or the
specific needs for our project. There are many benefits of using design patterns. Design patterns
are tried and tested solutions to commonly occurring problems in software design. Design
patterns are not specific to any one domain or any one application area. Design patterns make
our code reusable. We can extract the functionality we need and use it in a separate project.
In design patterns, they give us a shared vocabulary with other developers,
and this is really important. Once we have a vocabulary, we can communicate with other
developers. Common language, it elevates the way we think. We can talk about architecture
by talking about high-level abstractions without focusing on low-level details.
I wouldn't be giving the full picture if I didn't talk about some of the criticisms
of design patterns. Design patterns are considered workarounds for the limitations
of a programming language. For example, in Java, there's design patterns that mimic the behavior
of language features like multiple inheritance and decorators. Languages like Python have these
features built into the language. Always relying on design patterns without thinking about the
larger picture, it can lead us to design inefficient solutions that have many levels of unnecessary
hierarchy. And finally, as programmers, we have a tendency to solve a problem using the latest and
greatest thing that we just learned about. Design patterns are great, but they're not a holy grail.
We're going to need to understand how to use them properly. I find a lot of talks on design patterns,
they try to cover way too many patterns, so I want to do the exact opposite. In this talk,
we're only going to be talking about a single pattern, and that pattern unsurprisingly is the
facade pattern. So imagine we have a home theater system that has a bunch of different components,
say we got a TV, a cable box, a Blu-ray player, a receiver, and a bunch of others.
Each of these pieces of equipment, they have their own remote, and we can use each of these
remotes to turn on and interact with each of these components. Or we can program an all-in-one remote.
In this remote, it has a simple interface. If we want to go out and just watch TV, we can click a
button, and we can program that button to turn on our TV and turn on our cable box. If we want to
watch a Blu-ray or a DVD, we can program the remote to turn on our TV and turn on our Blu-ray
player. This all-in-one remote, it provides a simple interface to all of our components of that
home theater system. This is the class diagram of a facade pattern. Here we can see that we have
multiple clients interacting with a complex subsystem through a facade.
The facade pattern has many benefits. It simplifies the interface to a library,
a framework, or a complex set of classes. If the user requires some lower-level functionality,
they can bypass the facade and interact with whatever class they need to as required.
But for most clients, having a facade is going to be a good enough interface.
The facade pattern also reduces the number of things that our client needs to know about.
The facade pattern promotes weak coupling between our subsystem and our clients. If the underlying
subsystem changes, we can go ahead and change our facade, and our clients wouldn't know any different.
The facade pattern, it provides us a way to define layers in our software architecture,
and as a side effect, we can stub out each of these boundaries and simplify our testing.
We're going to come back to that a little bit later.
And finally, we can use the facade pattern to break apart a monolith.
We do this by keeping our original functionality, but we place that functionality
behind a facade, and then we start rewriting our client logic to deal with this facade.
And then whenever we're ready to make the switch, we can replace the facade's method calls with
calls out to another service via an API or a queue. Let's explore the facade pattern
with a case study. Normally, when I cut a new version of a software that I own,
I include a changelog that describes the changes that I made since that last release.
Here's an example changelog. We can see that there's a list of changes with links to the
relevant pull requests. I generate these changelogs manually, and it's not really a lot of fun,
so let's think about how we can write a script to automate that process.
This project, it's on GitHub. The master branch is protected, so any changes that need to be made,
they can only be made via a pull request. I also squash all of the commits before I make a merge
into master. This makes generating a changelog pretty straightforward. We start off by getting
the last published at date of the release that we care about. We grab all the commits since that
date, and finally, we're going to get all the commit messages and then generate a changelog.
Fortunately, we can use the GitHub API to get this kind of information. So let's write up some code
to generate a changelog. Our function, it's going to take in three parameters. We have owner,
we have repo, we have function, also we have version, and then we're going to use the request
library to hit up the GitHub API. We're going to find out when that release was published.
If this version exists, we're going to extract the date time string and return it. If not,
we're going to raise an exception. Next, we're going to use the GitHub API to find all commit
messages since that last version was published, and finally, we're going to return the commit
messages in chronological order. We're going to have the earliest message all the way to the
latest message. Now, let's start thinking about how can we test the script we just wrote?
Our current workflow, it looks like this. We're going to make some kind of HTTP requests
to the GitHub API. We're going to get some responses back, and when we're testing,
we really don't want to be depending on this external system. If GitHub goes down,
we're not really going to be able to get any work done, and that doesn't make a lot of sense.
This is why when we go out and write our tests, we want to replace GitHub with a stub that returns
can responses. This enables us to write tests without GitHub, and we can make our tests
deterministic. Let's take a look at our test function. We're going to use a package called
responses to stub out calls to our API, and the way this library works is we're going to specify
can responses for a given URL when it's hit with a given HTTP verb. Next, we're going to run this
function that we want to test, and then finally, we're going to confirm that our function returns
the values we expect to see. But we have one problem. Directly integrating third-party libraries
or third-party APIs into our business logic, it couples our code to something we don't control.
If the thing we depend upon changes, we're going to have to rewrite our business logic,
as well as go out and rewrite our tests to make sure things work as expected.
Our current approach has a few limitations in addition to this tight coupling. Our code currently
only works for public repositories. We're going to need to use a GitHub access token
with the correct privileges to authenticate ourselves if we want to ever access private repos.
We can probably also make better use of the request library. Specifically,
we can be using the sessions feature as well as explicitly setting headers.
Also, when we directly integrate integration code into our business logic, it means that our
logic, our business logic has to be intelligent. It needs to know about things like error checking
for HTTP errors or for exceptions. It also needs to know about things like retry logic,
chase on processing logic. Earlier, we used a function to fetch a list of commits. This time,
fetch a list of commits. This time, we want to hide our implementation. We want to keep track
of internal state. We also want to implement some additional logic on top of this. This seems like
the perfect opportunity to use a class. So let's take a step back and talk about object-oriented
programming in Python. So object-oriented programming is a paradigm that's based around
objects. We try to model real world things as objects. And when we design a solution,
it involves a collection of collaborating objects that communicate with each other by sending
messages. Objects have data along with behavior. And object-oriented programming allows us to think
at a higher level. We can create objects with set data and set behavior, and then we can perform
actions on those objects to accomplish the task we're trying to do versus telling the computer
to do things in a sequential, linear manner. In object-oriented programming, we have classes
and we have objects. A class, that's a template that allows us to create objects. We can also say
that we created an instance of an object from a class. I really like this cookie cutter analogy.
The cookie cutter is like a class, and each cookie is an instance of a class, like an object.
Object-oriented programming has four main principles. There's encapsulation,
there's abstraction, there's inheritance, and then there's polymorphism.
For the problem that we're solving with the facade pattern, we're only going to be leveraging
encapsulation and abstraction. So let's just focus in on those. Let's start with encapsulation.
Encapsulation bundles data and behavior into a single logical unit, and we call that unit
an object. Encapsulation is used to hide the internal representation of an object.
Capsule pills are a great form of encapsulation. They hide the active ingredient and expedience
inside of a gelling agent. Python doesn't really have any kind of methods built into the language
to enforce encapsulation, but we do have some conventions that allow us to know how data
can be accessed and how functions should be called.
Instance variables and functions, they can be public, and this means they can just be used by
everybody. Protected variables and functions start with a single underscore. These elements,
they're not going to be part of a class's public interface. Python has a philosophy that we're all
consenting adults, so if you want to go ahead and use protected variables, there's nothing out there
stopping you. In fact, it actually might be the right way to solve the problem that you're trying
to solve, but just don't be surprised if this interface does change later on. It's something
that's not guaranteed. And then we also have private variables and private functions,
and these begin with two underscores. And when the Python interpreter sees a private attribute,
it performs a type of name mangling to make sure that these attributes are hidden. These items
still can be accessed since this name mangling is pretty deterministic, or it is actually
deterministic, but this kind of practice, it's really highly discouraged. Remember,
encapsulation is about information hiding. Next, let's discuss abstraction.
With abstraction, we're able to hide the complexity of our internal implementation
inside of an object. It's also recommended that when objects communicate with each other,
they do so by calling each other's public methods. Abstraction, it hides complexity. It also lets us
isolate the impact of changes. We can go ahead and change the internal implementation without
changing the calling code. Cars, those are complex systems with many moving parts,
but in order to drive a car, you really don't have to understand how a car works. You just need to be
able to use the interface. And for a car, this would be a steering wheel, an accelerator, and a
brake. It's the same for Python. If we're given a class, we really don't care about the underlying
implementation. The interface is the only thing that matters to us. The interface, that's exactly
how we interact with this object. Remember, abstraction is about hiding our implementation.
And just one more time, encapsulation is about information hiding. Abstraction is about
implementation hiding. Now that we have a bit more context, let's take a look at how we can use a
class to wrap our GitHub integration. Let's set some guidelines for the acceptance criteria
for our MVP. We want to use request.sessions to improve performance. Let's also use HTTP basic
auth with a GitHub access token so we can access private repos. We're going to want to set some
HTTP headers, be a good citizen of the web. It would be great if this class had some code
to handle errors. And if this class could also handle JSON parsing, this abstraction,
it would be pretty complete. This is a high level overview of what we're really trying to do.
We're going to have a GitHub client that we initialize with a token, and then we can call
functions on this client and get back the information that we requested.
So we'll start by creating a GitHub client class. This takes in an OAuth token. We set some headers.
We create a session and save that to an instance variable.
And this class has a function, getReleaseDate, and this is going to get the release date for a given
version. And so this function is going to take in some parameters. We're going to construct a URL.
We're going to hit that URL with the request.sessions that we just stored in the instance
variable. If the version doesn't exist, we're going to raise an exception. Otherwise, we're
going to extract the data that we requested. And then we're going to get the URL. And then we're
going to get the data that we need from this JSON blob that we just got back, and then we're going
to return that back to our caller. This class, it also has another function, and this is called
getCommitsMessages. It's going to get all the commit messages from a given date. So the function's
going to take some parameters. We're going to construct a URL. We're going to hit that URL
with the session that we stored in the instance variable. We're going to raise an exception if
it's not within an acceptable range. And finally, we're going to extract the items that we need from
our JSON blob, and then we're going to return that information back to our caller. To create a change
log, we're going to need to create one additional function. I usually call this function a driver
function. It's going to run our class that we just wrote. We're going to create an instance of a
GitHub client. We're going to pass in our API token when we initialize it. We're going to grab
the release date, save that to a variable, and then we're going to go ahead and grab the commits
from that last release. Now let's take a look at how we can go ahead and test this change log we
just wrote. Like before, we're going to use the responses library to stub out the GitHub API when
we go ahead and test. Here's the code to test the getReleaseDate function, and in this slide,
we're going to be testing our getCommitMessages function. This implementation, it has a driver
function. This is code that's going to be used, so we have to find a way we can test this as well.
And we're going to do this by creating a GitHub client stub that's going to return canned
responses, and this enables us to write simple unit tests for this generateChangeLogDriver function.
Now we can go ahead and monkey patch our GitHub client with the stub we just created above,
and we can ensure our function works as expected. Note that in this test, we replaced our boundary
with a known value. Instead of replacing our external boundary with the GitHub boundary
with a stub, we replaced something inside of our system with a stub.
And so wrapping these third-party integrations, you saw it requires a little bit of extra work.
We have to write a driver function, go ahead and test that driver function.
What are some of the benefits of using this approach? Libraries, they're general purpose
tools. They're meant to be used by many different types of people for many different types of
projects. We're going to provide a simple interface that only does the things that we need.
So we're taking this giant library and we're reducing it to only the things that we care about.
This makes our code a little bit easier to test.
Another benefit is that our code is loosely coupled. Business logic and integration logic,
they can interact with each other, but they don't have any sense of how each other is
implemented. This allows us to build flexible systems, and we can minimize the number of
interdependencies between all of our objects. And here we used a class to encapsulate parts of our
code that change from parts of our code that stay the same. If this GitHub API, it ever changes,
we can go ahead and update our GitHub integration code without having to go ahead and test,
or without having to go ahead and change our business logic or the tests related to our
business logic. And this pattern, as we talked about, it simplifies testing. We can replace
external boundaries with a stub. There's a fantastic talk about this by Gary Bernhardt
from PyCon 2013. It's a fairly old talk, but the concepts that Gary talks about, they're priceless.
And if this kind of way of coding looks familiar to you, that's because it's part of software
architecture methodologies, such as hexagonal architecture, also known as web architecture.
Hexagonal architecture, also known as ports and adapters, and clean architecture.
The idea behind both of these methodologies is that we want to create loosely coupled
components, and then we want to connect these components using a series of adapters or a series
of wrappers. And doing this, it's going to make our code easy to replace and easy to test.
And that's the key point. We want our code to be able to change. Software is rarely static.
When requirements change, we have to go and update our code to make sure it works for what we're
trying to do now versus what we were trying to do before. So going back to our GitHub changelog
example, our boss comes back to us. He absolutely loves what we did, but he wants us to use the
GitHub GraphQL library. So let's briefly talk about what GraphQL is so we understand the
context of the change that we're going to need to make. GraphQL is going to provide us with an
API endpoint that accepts queries. And their backend, it's going to resolve the query that
it's passed to the requested data elements. And since we're querying data, the server can fetch
exactly what the clients ask for. In comparison, when we're using REST APIs, our clients need to
go out and make multiple requests, and then we're going to have to piece together that data on the
front end or inside of our clients. With GraphQL, we can go out and extract the exact data that we
want from a single endpoint. So to solidify these concepts, let's work through an example.
This is a GraphQL query. Given a repository and a release tag, we want to pull the published at field.
These are the variables that we're going to substitute into our query. And this is the result
of the query, and it's only the information that we asked for. It's just that one specific field.
When we hit the GitHub REST API, we're sent back all this information when we only really care about
that one key value pair. Recall this is our current workflow, and we're going to be able to
use the GitHub REST client to get the information we want. And to make the request to change that
our boss wants us to do, we're going to need to replace this REST client with a GraphQL client.
The business logic that makes use of the GitHub client, it doesn't care if it's using a REST API
client or a GraphQL client. The calling code treats the integration code like a black box.
It knows it can initialize something with a token. It can ask for some sort of information
and get that information it asks for back. Let's walk through the implementation of our GitHub
GraphQL client. We're going to start off by creating a class that takes in a token. We're going to
initialize a GraphQL session. We're going to save that session to an instance variable. And in our
getReleasesDate function, we're going to pass in the same arguments as before. We want exactly that
same function signature. We're going to create our query with our known values. We're going to hit
the GraphQL endpoint, and then we're going to return the data we're looking for, or we're going
to raise an exception. And in the getCommitsMessages function, that also has the same signature as
before. Here we're going to create a query with our known variables. We're going to hit the GraphQL
endpoint with that query. We're going to raise an exception if there's an error. And finally,
we're going to parse the information we got back and return all those commit messages back to our
caller. So going back to our generateChangeLogDriver function, we don't have to make any changes here.
Our business logic, it doesn't care what kind of client it's using. It just cares that the client
has the same interface as it had before. Now we're going to go out and update our contract tests,
and we're done. We can go ahead and make a pull request and be happy that we used the facade
pattern to wrap our GitHub integration. Let's recap. The libraries and frameworks we use,
they're general purpose tools that are designed to solve many different types of problems.
If we want to design something that solves our specific use case, we're going to have to actually
go out and make it ourselves. We can use the facade pattern to provide a simple interface
to a complex subsystem. This reduces coupling between our modules, and loosely coupled modules
and loosely coupled systems, they're easy to change. And this is because we started a program
to interfaces and not to implementations. As a result, our code is easier to test. We can
replace our integration boundaries with values and let our architecture do the heavy lifting.
Hopefully by exploring how the facade pattern leverages object-oriented design principles,
we can see that the underlying concepts, they're not too complex. They're fairly straightforward.
Design patterns aren't scary. Go out, learn a pattern, implement it in the language of your
choice, preferably Python. Discover the benefits of adding more structure to your code. These are
all the resources I used coming up with this talk. Thanks, everybody, for your time. Before I go,
I do want to give a shout out to the Chicago Python users group. I would not be where I am
without that fantastic organization. Thanks again for your time. My name is Ali Sivji.
We'll see you in Austin, hopefully next year.