Hi, PyTexas.
Thanks for attending my virtual talk on gathering us as some audio data.
I'm Ryan Bales.
Let's dig in.
So, I work at a company in Chicago called Dialog Tech.
I'm a director of data science and analytics.
The goal of my team is to work in the marketing technology space, so my team is responsible
for taking phone calls from our customers and converting them into text and the transcriptions.
And then from there, we have lots of different models and other processes to convert them
into different insights and outputs that we deliver to our customers.
Additionally, I also work in the Python and data engineering space here in Cleveland,
Ohio, where I'm based.
So the goal of this talk is to discuss audio data at different levels.
We're going to talk about audio data as raw sense, we're going to talk about tools to
look at audio data and explore it.
We're going to talk about how we gather features, train models, and then we'll go to text and
talk about ways we can work with it there.
So the first thing we'll talk about is how do we hear sound as humans?
So this is a picture of your ear, of a human ear.
And what we're seeing here is that to hear things, different pressures, difference in
pressure is picked up and passed into your ear canal from your outer ear, travels down
the ear canal into the on the far right of your screen, the cochlea.
And once it travels to the cochlea, there's a lot of different hair follicles there that
ride along the what's called the basilar membrane.
As those hair follicles vibrate up against the membrane, that creates electricity, small
electrical pulses.
And those are then carried by your auditory nerve up to your brain.
That's how we hear things.
And similarly, how a computer hears things, the analog sound signal is up top.
And then when the computer does its digital to analog conversion, it's converting that
sound to ones and zeros down below.
When the sound analog is high, the wave is high, it comes as a one, and then when it
drops down low, it gives us a zero over time.
So basic characteristics here, we'll talk about a wave.
We'll talk about the amplitude is the size or displacement of the vibration.
And it typically determines how loud the sound is.
I think about it this way, when you want to make the sound louder, you're amplifying or
you're increasing the sound of the wave.
And then separately, frequency is the speed of the wave.
And that controls the pitch of the sound you're hearing.
So one of the characteristics we want to think about when talking about digital data
is sampling rate.
And two different things we want to talk about with this when we're sampling, we want to
talk about the sampling rate and the bit depth.
So what you see here is just a basic chart of an analog signal, and then each of the
red lines is a sample that we're taking.
So what can lead to higher quality audio is how fast you're sampling.
For example, a typical phone call is sampling at 8 kilohertz, whereas a higher quality audio
recording is at 44.1 kHz.
And then it goes on and on up from there for high quality movies and other digital theater
type work is much higher.
But the larger that number, the more often you're taking a sample and the more often
you sample the wave, the better representation you'll have of that wave digitally.
Additionally, the bit depth is the number of bits being sampled for each sample.
Typically, you're going to see bit depths at 8, 16, or 24 bytes, 1, 2, or 3 bytes.
That's just simply controlling the amount of data you take for each sample.
So you want to have a high sampling rate and a high bit depth.
That's going to give you the better representation of the analog audio when it comes to digital
when you sample it.
So let's also briefly talk about wave file formats or audio file formats, excuse me.
So common audio file formats are waved uncompressed, FLAC lossless compressed, and MP3 loss decompressed.
So typically a dialect that we try to work with wave, we try to record things in near
CD quality audio, but we have been considering converting them to FLAC.
So FLAC will get you about 30 to 40% smaller files, and it does so with the compression
algorithm that is built, it's built with audio data in mind, so it knows how to compress
audio very well, and you will not lose quality of the audio.
Alternatively, MP3s give you 75 plus smaller samples, smaller file sizes, but you're going
to have some loss in the process.
So it really is going to depend on your application as to how you're going to work with that.
If you're working with audio with multiple speakers, you want to do your best to keep
a speaker per channel.
So when you talk about mono audio, that is audio where every single audio channel, every
person, every feed of audio into that file is mixed down into one channel or mono, single
channel.
What I'm showing you on the screen here is a typical phone call or conversation where
you have dual channels.
So you have speaker A, and you have speaker one, speaker two, and you're seeing there
are different pieces of audio as time progresses, that's a dual channel or sometimes called
stereo audio.
And similarly, think about it with, you know, some of you may have a home theater at home
and you have a 5.1 Dolby surround, that literally has six channels of audio being processed
for each sound it's trying to display, trying to produce.
So it has your center left and right channels up front, and then it has your left rear and
right rear.
And if you have that point one, you typically have a subwoofer trying to give you amplified
sound for those deep sounds.
So let's change gears a minute and talk about some tools.
So the first tool I really like is Sock, straight out of the box.
You can man Sock inside of Linux, it's cross platform, you can install it on Macs or Windows.
It's really just a Swiss Army knife, you know, jack of all trades tool.
Typically I'll drop in here Sock stash dash I for a WAV file.
If I get a piece of audio, I want to quickly know what's going on with it, I hop in here.
From here I can tell you this audio file has one channel, it's recorded at 44.1K, bit depth
of 16, etc.
You can also tell it's about three minutes and 32 seconds, actually, sorry, 3.3, about
three and a third seconds in length.
So in Socks you can do tons more than dash dash I, you can go to the man page on it or
Google it, there's hundreds of commands you can do with Socks, but it's a super easy to
work with tool that gets the ball rolling when you're trying to start with some audio
files.
And then if you like UIs better, I've really enjoyed Audacity, it's one of the first things
I install when I set up a new system.
I typically will grab a hold of Udacity, install it, and I love to just grab an audio file,
open up Udacity, take a look at the WAV files, you can even convert these things to different
characteristics of the file, you can use Audacity to record, you can skip ahead, there's a lot
of great things you can do with Audacity.
Also cross platform.
So next up we're going to talk about different types of audio features and how you can generate
them, and we'll show some code in a minute here.
So first we'll talk about raw audio data.
Right here we're working with an amplitude measurement taking into every sample.
So in this example we have a 5 second wave, you can see the 1 through 5 on the bottom
of the time scale, and the sampling here is at 44.1K.
So on this entire file, to produce this graph, we opened up and processed 221,000 elements
to produce this data.
This is simply opening up the file and showing the data.
Separately we can then convert that raw audio data into a spectrogram.
So a spectrogram, the next few things we're going to look at here are very much just mathematical
ways of shaping and converting this information, and you're going to see a lot of use of Fourier's
transforms.
So in this case, a spectrogram is created by taking digital data and breaking it up
into overlapped windows across time, and then over each window you're going to do a Fourier
transform to calculate the magnitude and frequency, and you're going to keep repeating over each
window of data.
So in this case you're going to take, the time is across the x-axis, the frequency is
on the y-axis, and the amplitude is displayed as that heat map there, that 0 dBs up to negative
80 dBs.
This is sometimes called a MEL spectrogram, because it's based on the MEL frequencies,
and the name MEL, as we all can probably guess, comes from the word melody, which indicates
the scale this is based on for its pitch comparisons.
And then another way of visualizing and working with audio features is a chromogram, also
known as chromo features, and this is based on comparison between the 12 different pitch
classes, you know, C, C sharp, D, D sharp, etc.
So like a spectrogram, in a chromogram, we are taking the audio, we're windowing over
it, we're doing what's called a short time Fourier transform, and then we're comparing
those results against each pitch class, and if you look at this chart, top to bottom,
the top here, you're going to, if you look closely enough at it, you would see 12 different
blocks vertically.
So that's every single pitch class, top to bottom, and then the color of that is the
difference between the pitch class and how well it lines up with that absolute pitch
class.
And the next one, probably the hardest to visualize is, and even a mouthful to say,
is a MEL frequency sep stroke coefficient.
Those are made up of MFCs, and it's really a result of using inverse Fourier transforms
of the signal.
So there's a lot of steps in math to this.
Just at a high level, kind of similar to a spectrogram, you're going to break everything
up into smaller chunks and window over the data, and then you're going to do a Fourier
transform of each of those windows, and then you're going to take the resulting spectrum
into the MEL frequency scale.
Then you're going to take a log of powers of that frequency, and finally you're going
to do a discrete cosine transform to your MEL scale log powers, and at the end you're
left with MFCs.
This is actually the type of feature that's typically used inside of different speech
to text conversion systems that are trying to transcribe audio.
Okay, let's look at a little bit of that code.
So I'm going to give all my demos here and examples inside of Jupyter, Jupyter Notebooks.
So I'm not going to go through everything line by line.
At the end, I'll put up a slide that'll have all of the information and how you can get
a hold of the data, but I'm using it in the code.
I'm using a package here called Librosa, a big fan of Librosa.
We're bringing in Matplotlib visualizations, and I'm going to go down here a little bit
quickly.
We're going to go to the raw audio line here.
So this line four that you see on the screen, this is Librosa.load, and it's passing in
my audio file, and I wanted to show this because it's important that you pass in none for your
sample rate, because you don't want it.
You can use a sample rate if you want to up or down sample.
I'm doing no sample conversion here.
I'm not up sampling or down sampling.
I just want to grab it raw.
So out comes the raw audio, and out comes my sample rate of 44.1 into my two output parameters.
Then I can simply just call Librosa.display, passing that data and visualize it.
And then likewise, I can do the same thing for the null spectrogram, passing in the audio
sample rate.
To draw the plot, to calculate the spectrogram, you have to tell it the size, the number of
4HM that you want to do, your windows effectively, and then your hop links, how far you want
to move through the file as you're processing through it.
And then from here, you're going to get out the spectrogram, and you're going to convert
those from powers to decibels, and then you plot.
And then down here, we see the output below.
And then you do the same thing for chromograms and MFCCs that when you grab a sample, you
take a closer look at and look at more closely.
But that's the basic overview.
Librosa is a really super powerful tool to work with.
Cool, so to go forward, we're going to take a look at an audio classification example.
So I downloaded a sample from Freesound.
I got it through Kaggle.
And I downloaded, there's 41 sample classes, over 9,000 examples.
We're going to walk through this data.
We're going to split it into training and test sets, and we're going to train the model
on this information and see how that goes.
So we'll go to our next notebook.
And again, we're not going to go through the whole notebook here in depth, but from here,
we're loading our training data set, and we can see that we have the file name, the label,
hi-hats, saxophones, cellos, et cetera.
And you also have this manually verified column.
That's going to come in handy in a second.
So there's just over 9,000 examples, 9,473.
There's 41 categories.
You can see a list of them here below.
And then what I chose to do for when I was building this was I wanted to look at the
manually verified, how it kind of broke down.
So for acoustic guitar, we have almost 200 that were not verified and 100 that were verified.
And then further, I went down and I plotted that.
So I did a stacked bar.
And then if we look here, the orange is where we have verified that information manually
and zero.
Blue is where we have it.
So looking at different examples here, gongs and flutes, we've done not a lot of verification,
but saxophone and violin or fiddle have done a lot of validation.
So further, I took a look at and said, let's just work with our manually verified data.
And then looking at that, we have 3,700 manually verified options.
So this notebook is in here.
If you grab the data and you want to work with it, this will help you to process the
CSV and split everything out into separate folders by type.
I'm not going to go through this directly, but this is simply taking our data set.
We're splitting it 80-20 into test and train sets.
And then from here, we're outputting our results into CSVs.
These CSVs are really important for our next couple of notebooks.
And then further, the audio files, we're moving them around on disk to get everything ready.
So this notebook is really helpful for munching your data around and getting it set up for
your modeling.
But the big thing is to take away from this is that we're taking these 3,700 examples
and we're splitting them 80-20.
So then further here in this third notebook, we're going to build a model using the MSVC
features.
And again, you're going to see a lot of stuff you've seen in previous notebooks.
We have Librosa coming in.
We're loading up NumPy, and we're also bringing in Pandas and Keras.
So we're bringing in Keras to do our modeling with, and we'll get there in a second.
So again, we have all of our feature extraction code.
Everything is up here.
You've seen this code before, showing all the visualizations.
We're going to skip past this, and we're going to come down here below.
This code is the getMSVC's function, and I just want to make a note that this function
actually has padding built into it.
So what I do here is I actually pad the file out with zeros if it's not long enough, and
if it is long, if it's too long, I just truncate it at the max length of 128 windows.
That was so when training a model, of course, you want to have similar length, same length
data going in, so we're just chopping off some files and we're rounding things out to
pad things.
Then we're looping over all the files on our disk, and we're building up our features,
and then from our features, we're taking all of those.
So we have all of those words, all of the categories that are text at this point.
This two-categorical is just converting those into a Y features list, just at the one-hot
of all of the different features that we have in the data.
Then the first thing I do, and I highly recommend this before I start training, is I save everything
off to this file that has features.numpy labels, label encoder.
If this notebook crashes, if my kernel goes away, if something dies, I can come back and
restart everything.
So that's super helpful.
It's a really helpful step to do before you get rolling.
You get so far in, you don't want to go through and re-generate your data and everything.
You want to be able to just come back to the cell, load your data, and keep going with
your training.
So the next cell here is my model, and it's all here in this one cell.
This is all I needed to do.
So I'm using a sequential model from Keras.
I'm just adding a batch normalization layer, just trying to normalize the data coming in
so that the types of data is balanced amongst those features, amongst those different categories.
And then I have two LFCM layers where I'm starting off at 128 units, because that's
my size of my width that I'm truncating my files at, 128 windows.
And then I'm coming down to 32 windows, and then from there I'm going to a dense layer
where the size of my dense layer is all of the classes, and I'm doing an activation of
Softmax.
So I'm predicting the probability of that audio file 41 times.
I'm telling it 41 different probabilities.
And then I'm also using Dropout here, .05 on my Dropout setting.
I'm using that to...
So Dropout when I'm training this model is just telling the model when I'm training it
just to randomly effectively turn off different nodes, so I try to avoid overfitting to different
categories, different types of files.
So I trained on a MacBook Pro.
I was able to do 50 epochs, batch size of 16, and you can see how everything started
off here.
It started off with a fairly high amount of loss.
I trained out as we went, and you can see my accuracy getting a little bit better, .58,
.6, et cetera.
Another helpful part of Keras is Model.Summer.
You can see once your model's trained how it turned out, and it's actually like I expect
a batch normalization, two LSTMs, and a dense layer.
And then before you start doing anything else, save it to disk.
Keras comes with H5 support, H5Pi.
So Model.save between H5 file, and you're done.
That way you have your saved model.
Again, if your notebook crashes, you didn't lose anything.
So let's see how we're doing.
It's telling us here we've got about a .75 on the accuracy.
Let's see how well we're holding up against our validation set.
So I'm going to load in one file, my validation set, and I'm showing you the first five.
Actually, I skipped here, so I'm loading up this one file, this base drum.
This wave file, and I'm converting it to msccs with my get msccs function, and then calling
model.predict.
And my prediction is this.
And as you expected, there are 41 different probabilities here, 41 different floats.
And then all I'm doing is numpy argmax, and I'm indexing into my classes list with that.
And then from there, I get the base drum back, so it worked.
So for one example, held up just fine.
So now if I look at my entire validation set, and I loop over these five and process them,
well, I process the whole validation set, and I look at these first five, like, not
too bad.
This is good.
We missed the telephone.
We got three out of five.
Three out of five is pretty good.
So what we want to do next is we want to take a look at how well the model is performing.
So inside of the notebook here, I'm using sklearn, scikit-learn, and I'm just loading
up the classification report and passing in my Y validation and Y validation predicted.
And then from here, I get a per category F1 score.
So that lets me look at how well we're doing per category.
So acoustic guitar at a .8, very nice.
A bus, not so great, about a .50, really bad on keyboards, also with coughs, super awesome
on cowbell.
You kind of get the hint here.
So we're, you know, depending on the category, we're doing well on some and some not so great.
You know, overall, looking at a weighted average, we're about a .6.
So we're a little better than in a coin flip.
And again, there's some more training that we could do to work with this and improve
it.
So all in all, you know, for demo purposes, really helpful and, you know, concise way
to get started with audio data from training.
So back to a few slides.
So again, model results, .6.
As we noticed, some of the categories are higher or lower.
What improvements could be made?
Well, we could train for more than .50 epochs.
That might help.
We could go back and get more data.
We could get more data in certain categories.
We might be able to manually verify more of that data and bring it in.
We could also rework how we're truncating features, maybe if we went a little bit wider
and we took in more windows, we could do more with that to improve.
And then further, we could also tune the LSTM.
We could tune different parameters, maybe add another layer to see if that would help.
We could also do other model size LSTMs.
There are other types of machine learning models that we could use, other architectures
that we could use to work with this information with audio files.
So that's the overview on working with audio.
Let's change gears for a little bit here and talk about transcribing audio files.
So again, when transcribing, you want to make sure that your audio files are clean, transcriptions
are in separate files per speaker.
You're using lossless formats and you're working with high quality equipment as best you can.
And unless you're me, you have phone calls coming in, you do the best you can with the
phone call.
So there's different types of systems, APIs and non-prepats.
And all the big players in the industry have transcription options.
So there's AWS, there's Google Cloud, there's Azure, IBM.
They all have examples for APIs to do training.
So that's an output demo.
So I have a transcription notebook here.
We're in the middle of debates for our current election cycle, but I have everything downloaded
from 2016, all the debates there, the three presidential and one VP debate.
And from here, I'm just using the same tools to visualize them, take a look at them.
But further, inside these notebooks here, I have this transcription code.
So there's a couple of steps up to doing transcriptions of these files.
So first you want to upload the file to S3.
So this is all AWS using AWS Transcribe.
I'm using a tool called Bodo3 right here in Python.
I'm uploading my file into an S3 bucket.
Then once I upload it, I'm just kicking off the transcription job by having a transcription
client.
I'm telling that client where the audio file is.
I'm telling it's an MP3.
I'm telling it the output bucket to go work off of and to where the file should go.
And I tell it to go.
And then I sit back and watch.
I can pull the status of the job, but when it's done, all I'm going to do is download
the file and look at the transcription results.
So I come over here to my audio data, to my data file, and come in the data into my transcripts
and look at this, this debate is fine, and go into the results.
What you're looking for with transcription information is, so you get the full text of
the transcript, which you also want to look at, here it's in the items collection.
You really want to look at the different words and their start and end times, because that's
where a lot of the power shows up, is being able to search through words based on different
time, search through the whole transcript and look for certain words within X amount
of seconds between things.
You know, you get a lot more power with your modeling and work you can do when you're working
with that transcription information.
So now that we have gotten over into a transcription, we're going to talk about ways we can work
with those transcriptions.
So we're going to talk about some natural language processing techniques.
First thing we're going to look at is keywords.
So back to our, let's close this down.
Back to our notebooks, we're going to look at a couple different ways we're going to
look at keywords.
We're going to look at keyword extraction.
So from these VP debates, I can simply just do some basic keyword summarization, if you
will.
So I'm using a tool called Jensen.
It's another Python package you can download.
I'm doing some very basic preprocessing to remove stop words, and I'm summarizing and
doing keywords.
I'm also lemmatizing.
So I'm truncating the word down to just the lemmas or the stem of the word, if you will.
And then for keywords, I'm just showing the top 20.
This debate talked about taxes and Americans and businesses.
And then there can also sometimes be an interest in looking at the least 20 keywords as well.
So 20 keywords were treaties, private, stamina, et cetera.
Those words were not very much talked about, if you will.
So further in keyword spotting, that we can talk about ways that we can search.
So that was just ways to do summaries, but if you wanted to do searches of keywords,
I have some text, some code here.
Again, working with Jensen, I'm loading up all my transcripts.
I'm looping over each transcript and loading it up.
And then from here, I am processing the transcript into clean sentences, if you will.
So I'm going to, for each sentence, I'm doing get sentences, I'm removing stop words, I'm
stemming text, pulling out punctuation and removing white space.
And then I want to search for the keyword of taxes.
So again, for the same preprocessing steps you apply to the list of sentences, you also
want to apply to your search phrase.
So I'm applying my same four lines here.
That stems down to tax.
And then from here, I can loop over all of my documents and search for that keyword.
And you'll see that in a given debates, we found that tax 43 times, 32 times, et cetera,
So we're between 20 and 45 times the word tax was used within the debates.
So just a little general way you can work with that.
So also, we're going to run into a couple, we're going to finish on a couple of topics
here.
First, we're going to look at topic modeling, we'll look at ways you can generate topic
models and generate these types of really cool views and do some unsupervised type of
work with your keywords.
And then we'll look at sentiment analysis, we're going to look at polarity of the text
documents and take a look at those options.
So a couple more notebooks to open up and take a look at.
We'll go back into topic modeling and sentiment analysis, close this back down.
So topic modeling, yeah, I'm using a tool called, so again, Jensim and I'm bringing
in a tool called Spacey.
And I found a really cool tool.
I've really enjoyed working with called PyLDAViz, and we'll get to all these in a second.
So again, I'm loading up my debate files, I'm defining my helper functions here to process
the text to get text out of the files.
And then we're using Spacey for laminization.
We're loading up all of our, excuse me, our transcription files, and we're processing
them to remove stop words.
Then we're doing laminization across each one, and we're creating a dictionary of all
the words in our corpus.
And then from there, we're then generating a bag of words model.
So we're taking all of those and generating a bag of words for each document.
Then we're passing them into our latent Dirgelet allocation.
Effectively, that is a type of model where you're working with text, where you're working
with statistical differences about the text.
You're looking at different distances and calculations, trying to group text together
into known topics.
So I'm passing in different topics.
I'm passing in a topic count of 10, random state, number of passes, and per word topics
equal true.
And then I'm printing them off, and you're seeing different topics on their weights,
and that's super not helpful.
So then further, you can use this tool called PyLDAViz, and this could be really great to
give to your customers to work with their text data.
So from here, you can just prepare the notebook with the PyLDAViz, and it worked out better
for my screenshot in the slide.
But from here, I'm seeing all my different...
Each bubble is a topic, and then when I click on that topic, it shows me different words
within that topic.
So in this topic number one over here, go, say, Trump, American, President, et cetera,
and then these bubbles didn't render that well over here.
But as I scroll over to them, or I loop through my topics, I can see different words that
are in these different topics that are available to look at.
And I find this tool really helpful to see if my topic models are producing salient examples
that are helpful for my projects or for my research.
And then finally here, we're going to wrap up on sentiment analysis.
So when you're looking at sentiment analysis, you're looking at the polarity of the conversation.
So we're going to use a tool called the VADER algorithm from NLTK, and we're going to load
up the sentiment intensity analyzer and get that all ready to go.
We're going to load up our 2016 debates.
We're going to tokenize sentences, and then in front of you, we're going to loop over
every sentence, and we're going to calculate a polarity score.
So what we're doing here, we're looking for positive, neutral, and negative scores.
So we're adding up all the different types, we're dividing them by the sentences, and
we have 1,100 sentences.
For this document, you have the very much neutral leaning towards positive, but much
more neutral conversation than we saw positive overall in the document.
So that's the hand-rolled way, so to speak.
You're using different tools inside of your notebook to work on this, but if you want
to bring in some APIs, I've also had great luck.
Similar with the Transcribe API from AWS, they also have an API called AWS Comprehend,
where you can do comprehension of text.
And from here, I will note, though, it has a max of 5K bytes, so you may have to chunk
your file effectively.
So here, I'm opening up my file, my transcript.
I am starting up a comprehend session, and then I'm telling it to detect sentiment in
English, and I'm passing in the first 5,000 characters.
Outcomes as a result, this tells me overall, I had the sentiment scores for positive, neutral,
and negative, and overall, the beginning of this debate was neutral.
As you would expect in typical debates, you're going to see a lot of handshaking, welcoming,
opening statements, things like that, very neutral conversation.
But then at the end here, I started going through and detecting sentiment on the last
5,000 words in the debate text.
And again, I got my scores put out by my results, and overall, it was negative.
So this one debate that we're looking at here, as you would probably expect when things start
getting a little bit muscling you towards the end of the debate, got more negative and
got a little more on the negative side of the conversation.
So just a couple of ways to work with your transcriptions to get different kinds of
information out of them.
So in summary, we talked about analog, digital, and audio data characteristics.
We talked about audio features.
We talked about machine learning with those audio features, transcription, and natural
language processing.
Thank you all for coming and enjoying this talk virtually.
I'll leave the slide up at the end here.
And check out my github, Ryan Bales slash audio dash data dash insights.
There's my email address, Ryan at Balesofdata.com, and my Twitter is just my full name, Ryan Bales.
I'm happy to answer any questions and chat with all of you.
I'm sorry we couldn't be there together to talk about this at Pi Texas.
I hope to be there next year and talk more about other topics.
I hope you're all staying safe.
I hope you enjoyed this talk.
Please be well.
And again, let me know if any questions.
Thank you all for your time and have a great rest of your conference here at Pi Texas.