Hello, my name is Aaron Sandalani Magoro. I'm from Johannesburg, South Africa. I'm quite
delighted to be here today and thank you in advance for listening to my talk.
Just a bit of background about myself. I'm a cloud architect, predominantly working with
Amazon Web Services, Google Cloud Platform, and Microsoft Azure. I've been in the IT space
for about 15 years. I come mainly from a software engineering background. I am a founder, implementer,
and director of mycloudresume.com. Mycloudresume.com is a professional resume builder and international
recruitment aggregation platform. I'm here today to talk to you about minimizing
cloud costs. Well, we all know cloud can get very expensive super fast, especially for
startups. So the natural approach to mitigating these high costs has usually been to utilize
serverless compute offerings by cloud providers in the form of functions as a service. I'm
talking about offerings such as Lambda, in the case of AWS Cloud Functions for GCP, and
Azure Functions for Azure. These first offerings are quite attractive for many of us with a
software engineering background because, well, they let you focus on the code, mainly without
worrying about hosting environments. You don't need to worry about setting up the runtime
operating system, server, your code will run on, how your function will scale, under load,
networking, etc. You basically just code it and you run it. On top of that, it can be
considerably cheaper as well. A big emphasis there on the word can because, yes, it can
get very expensive as well, but it usually is cheaper under common use cases. Each major
cloud provider offers a considerable number of invocations with a perpetual free tier
offering each month. As shown in the table, each cloud provider offers at least a million
free invocations and 400,000 gigabyte second compute time each month. As you can see,
these free offerings may be enough for development to high production use workloads,
but they definitely wouldn't suffice for a light scale, highly consumed application.
If you were to run maybe your first API, let's say as a back end for a globally utilized web
application, you would easily run out of free tier within about three days, then you must start
paying. It can really get expensive there on. I actually heard of an instance where someone
deployed one of these first services and set up a billing alarm to notify them when they reached
$200. They were actually not even expecting to get to that high an amount since they were running a
low usage app, but to their surprise, just a few minutes after deploying the function while driving
back home, they received a notification from the billing alarm stating that they had exceeded the
$200. What this meant was that the free tier one million hits and 400,000 gigabyte second had been
exceeded, plus another $200 on top of that. Impossible, they thought. There's no way this low
volume application has consumed so much within an hour. So they continued driving, got home a while
later, walked in, said hi to everyone, had supper, then thought to go check on the deployed function.
What they saw was shocking. A whopping $900 had been consumed within a space of three hours.
Just imagine, I don't know about you, but I think this kind of amount on one's credit card statement
for a POC is enough to make a grown man cry. Funny thing is, this issue was caused by a bug
in another application. There was a bug in another system which integrated with the first function,
the bug kept executing the function in an infinite loop, spawning millions of threads in a three hour
period. So, when I heard this story, I thought to myself, there must be a way of firstly, ensuring
that your function doesn't consume real money once it surpasses the free tier cap. And second,
second, that there must be an organized way of spinning up another similar service in a different
account, or even from another cloud provider, where you can continue getting more free tier usage.
Okay, so now we're going to go through a solution I've been working on. This particular solution
actually allows you to have free tier usage for your serverless compute functions which you
design, technically perpetually, without ever having to worry about, you know, going out of free
tier and having to pay for your usage. I'm going to give you an example of a service. Let's take,
for example, a use case where in you go create a function which basically converts units,
let's say you've got a metric unit which you need to convert to an imperial counterpart.
You would go create the function as you would normally do. Let's say you decide you want to
start with Lambda, you go write your Lambda logic, you go deploy it in a particular account
within AWS. It can be in any language which you choose. You just need to ensure that
that language, the runtime of the language is supported across all cloud providers which you
want to use. For instance, if you need a particular number of hits per month,
let's say you only need a million, you wouldn't have use for something like this. But as soon
as you start needing more than what the free tier needs, let's say you need three, four million,
you just need to have as many accounts in your cloud vendor space to basically go and fulfill
those hits or those invocations which are given under free tier. In this instance,
let's say you need about three million hits a month, you can go and deploy your Lambda function
within a cloud account and have a second cloud account as well where you have the same function
deployed. You could decide you don't want to put all your eggs in one basket. You could decide that
you want your function deployed in Azure as well. You can take the same code and go deploy it in
Azure. You can do the same for Google Cloud Platform. You can basically have as many accounts
as you want within as many cloud vendors as you want who actually support serverless compute.
You may be asking yourself now how does this environment know when it's out of free tier
and how does it know when to pass on control or to pass on every service call to the next
environment or to the next account. That's where the solution comes in. I've created this
particular service which you see here. I call it the coordinator service. It's called the coordinator
because it basically coordinates calls based on which particular account still has free tier usage
available to it. What the coordinator service does is that it's got or rather what the coordinator
service makes use of is a configuration table which is a basic database table. Within the table,
you have things like endpoints. You'll have a list of items which contains
endpoints for each cloud account. If you need a particular service in this account,
it will have the endpoint for it. It will also list other endpoints which are within other accounts
and within other cloud vendors. Against each endpoint, it will also list how many hits you
are allowed on a monthly basis. Let's say in the case of Azure, you've got a million invocations
you can make per account under free tier. It will list that against that particular endpoint for
that account. Then, for let's say Google Cloud, you know you've got two million. You'll have
the endpoint and two million hits as a maximum allowed for that account per month. It also keeps
track of how many invocations or hits have been done against that particular cloud account so far
for this month. Again, in the example of Amazon, let's say you have only had a
hundred thousand. It will list it against that particular endpoint.
When this particular service or when the coordinator service is started up,
it loads the configuration and the state of how many invocations have been done against
a particular endpoint. It keeps that in mind or in track as you invoke each one.
It's got a basic configuration screen which basically saves data to this database
around what endpoints you'll be using, the limits and so forth. Nothing too complex,
it's just a basic configuration screen which you make use of. Let's go back to our use case.
Let's say you've got a web front end where people go in or your users go in and convert,
let's say miles to kilometers. What they would do is they would enter the number eight miles and
then choose the unit which they're converting from and then the unit they are converting to.
What your website does is instead of going and calling the backing service or the first service
directly, it now goes through the coordinator service with the whole payload and all the
parameters and so forth. When the coordinator service receives that call, it then checks
against its configuration and current state what endpoint still has availability when it comes to
free tier usage and then it directs the call to that particular service within a particular account.
It will continue doing that for your users until that particular endpoint reaches
its limit or its capacity when it comes to the number of invocations you can make.
After then, it will then decommission that endpoint, save it as decommissioned until the
end of the month and then continues on the next endpoint. It could be within the same cloud
provider which will be in a different cloud account obviously because your free tier usage
is per account and it will continue until it runs out and then according to how you've set it up,
it could move to another third account within the same cloud provider, fourth account, fifth account
and so forth or jump over to another cloud provider and continue doing its work as if
nothing has changed in the background. This is quite useful because now you don't actually
run out of free tier and start paying. You continue using your service until your free tier runs out
and then it moves you to another one which is still in free tier. You obviously can plug in
different sources or you can plug in different user interfaces to your service as you would
if you were going directly. That's basically how this solution works. The coordinator service
basically coordinates all your calls from the front end or from the calling service
to your different first functions and eliminates any spillage in case you run out of free tier.
Now we're going to go through the code for the solution. I'm going to show you the code for
this coordinator service we've been talking about. Just a bit of a disclaimer there before
we start with the code. I am not a Python developer. I'm from a C sharp background
mainly in JavaScript. So don't be surprised when you see a few Kelly brackets every now and then.
It is the C sharp developer in me trying to come out. But let's give it a shot. I'm sure you will
see what I'm trying to achieve and you will get the idea of what the service does and how it does
it. So we can basically start with some imports. These are all the imports that we need to get
this working. They should all come standard with your Python installation except for this one over
here. I had to do a separate import and install for this using a package manager. But that should
be it as far as imports. We are going to start now with a class. This class is a representation
of a config item within the database which I showed you. So this class
I call an API instance class.
This is basically a config item in the database which represents an API instance, which you can
call. So let's just initialize that or give it an initialization of properties which are needed.
Cool. So properties which we need there are going to be as follows. We're going to have the name.
We're going to have the URL of that endpoint. And we're going to have the
call count. So this is basically the name which you will use to identify what API or what instance of
the API you're calling. So this is basically the name which you will use to identify what API or
what instance of the API you're calling. The URL to that API instance and how many times you can call it
in free tier. Then we can just assign those properties here.
Cool. That should be it. So one API instance will basically have a name, a URL to the endpoint,
and a maximum call count. The current call count is a number which you increment every time you
call that API instance. So as soon as you get to this maximum call count, you can call it.
As soon as you get to this maximum call count, it decommissions this particular API instance,
and then it goes and grabs the next one and starts executing that endpoint until it reaches its max.
Okay. So what would happen is when this application or when this service loads,
it would go grab a list of API instances from the database and then sort of hydrate an array of API
instances which I'm going to put here. So that's an array of API instances. Just as a demo for today,
I am going to copy a list of API instances which I have hard coded together for the sake of this demo.
So you will see here what this piece of code is doing is basically appending an API instance as
you would have it in the database or pre-configured in the database. So the name of that
API instance, the URL to the endpoint, and then what is the maximum call count you have per
endpoint. So I've got these four here just for the demo. And we should be set to go as far as
config and basic supporting classes. Oh, except for we will need to keep track of what is the
current API instance we're working with. So I've got here a variable with the current API instance.
Initializing it to the very first one, but you'll see as we go, we will have the ability to
basically go and change it. That's if it has reached its maximum call count.
So the implementation is going to be in a class.
We're going to call this class redirect. What this class will do is basically redirect calls
as it receives them. Sorry about the noise. Somebody is flying over my house. I guess
it comes with a new way of working. So this class redirects any call which comes into the
coordinator service. So you will get a call, for instance, going into a particular endpoint.
You would direct it to this coordinator service, which will then redirect it to
whatever API endpoint is still within free tier. So I have a method which I created.
What this method does is basically keeps track of which API endpoint is still in free tier.
So you would call this to basically keep this variable up to date. The current API instance
is determined by checking whether it's still in free tier or if it's exhausted its maximum call
count. This is the logic here. So if you call these and you still have some calls which you
can make in free tier, it will basically just return the same API instance. If not, that's if
you have gone above or if you've reached the maximum call count, it goes and iterates through
this list of API instances which you have here. And then what it does is it finds the next one
which still hasn't reached its maximum call count. And then it will go and basically assign it as a
current API instance. So that's what it does. Just before redirecting to a particular API instance,
let's say you get a post request into the coordinator service. The do post would then
go and get the current API instance. And then after getting the current API instance,
it will then redirect to it accordingly. So here's the do post method.
It goes in and gets the data from your post. So let's say you're posting from a web front end.
It will go get the data which you are posting and then holds it and waits to get an available API
endpoint where it should post the data to. It creates a basic HTTP request and then it creates
your headers and so forth. And then it does a request now to the current API instance or
the latest API instance. And then it will do so and then get the data and then obviously return
it to the caller without the caller having to know which endpoint was available at the time and
where they called the data from. You just need to also have a set response method.
What this does is basically it wraps up your whole HTTP call and basically returns a 200 back to the
sender or to the caller and does everything to do with the response headers and so forth
and returns the response to the request. So that's it basically. You've got a
list of configged API instances. That list then is iterated through every time you do a post,
a get, every time you try to call a particular endpoint. And then this functionality here
ensures that you get an API point which is still in free tier. And that continues over and over
again until you exhaust a particular endpoint and then when you exhaust it, it moves you on to the
next instance and then you continue getting your responses in free tier. That's about it.
That's how the code works. I'm sure I have forgotten to add something here in the do post. I need to
call something. I need to basically call get free endpoint every time
I get a post. You can do the same thing for a get. Let's say you need to call an endpoint for get.
You just do a get redirected to an endpoint, the current endpoint. And that's it.
Well, that's it from me. I hope you found this talk informative and that you find useful ways
to implement this solution. If you have any improvement suggestions, questions, or comments
in general, feel free to contact me on any of these platforms. I am Aaron Sendilani Magoro from
mycloudresume.com and thank you again for listening.