When I use a word, Humpty Dumpty said in a rather scornful tone, it means just what
I choose it to mean, neither more nor less. The question is, said Alice, whether you can
make words mean so many different things. The question is, said Humpty Dumpty, which
is to be master. That's all. I love a good cold open, howdy, I'm Al Swigert. I'm mostly
known as the author of Automate the Boring Stuff with Python. I grew up in Texas and went to school
in Austin. And after a brief 12-year period in San Francisco, I now live in Seattle. But my heart
will always be in Texas, as will my cell phone's area code. This is the amazing Mutable, Immutable
Tuple and Other Philosophic Digressions. I'm pre-recording this for Pi Texas 2020, so for
those watching in the future, 2020 was an interesting year. So this is a virtual conference,
and I'm recording this from my apartment in the Capitol Hill neighborhood of Seattle, which has
been a very interesting neighborhood to live in 2020. But to recreate the feeling of a conference
talk, I'm going to record all of this in one take with no edits. Now, I make a lot of references
and recommendations for books and talks. There's no need to take notes. You can download these
slides from bit.ly slash amazing tuple, Pi Texas 2020. This talk grew from a basic question I had,
are tuples mutable or immutable? And the answer is tuples are immutable. Everybody knows that.
Thank you for coming to my talk. Enjoy the rest of your day. Okay, there's more. Let's start this
philosophical discussion and define our terms. What's a tuple? I'm pronouncing that word both
ways so that way everyone can yell at me and tell me I'm saying it wrong. Well, tuples are like
immutable lists. They're an ordered sequence of data. Unlike lists, you type them with parentheses
instead of square brackets, but if you only have one item in the tuple, the trailing comma is
required. It's really the commas that make a tuple, not the parentheses. Now, for anyone who has read
Luciano Romolo's fantastic book, Fluent Python, you'll know that tuples can serve as more than
just immutable lists. But in this discussion, suffice it to say that tuples are immutable lists.
Next question, what is mutability? Mutable means that it can change its value, while immutable means
it can't change its value. So while you can create a list and then change the items in the list,
you can't change the items in a tuple. You'll get an error message if you try. So tuples are
immutable. Kind of. I mean, you could just reassign this variable to a different tuple and thus change
the tuple, right? Well, no, technically, this isn't changing the tuple so much as creating a
new tuple and replacing the old tuple. But that's an answer that leads to more questions. What's
the difference? Why do we even need tuples if we already have lists? And are tuples immutable or
not? Now, before we go down that rabbit hole, I want to point out a common Python gotcha. Let's
say we create a list and store it in a variable named spam. Then we copy spam to a variable named
eggs. And we change the first item in spam to the string changed. What are the contents of the eggs
variable? You might know this gotcha already. The eggs list has also been changed, just like the spam
list. And this is because spam and eggs are actually referring to the same list. And to understand
why that happens, I'm going to use the visualization tool at python tutor.com. If you've never used
python tutor.com, check it out. It's great at showing what's going on in your code. Here's our
three line program. At the top is when the first line executes and creates the list for the spam
variable. You can see there's a spam variable in blue, and it's pointing to the list object in
yellow. And the middle is the second line executing, which copies the list to the eggs variable. Notice
that we still only have one list object. It's just that both spam and eggs now refer to it. And that's
why at the bottom, when spam is changed, it's changing eggs as well. Now I used to use a box
metaphor for variables like the variable is a box and the list object is stored inside the box,
but that turns out not to work so well for python. It's better to think of variables as name tags or
labels. And these labels point to objects where they refer to objects, but the object isn't inside
the variable. Now in this new example, I've changed the list to a tuple. You still have two
variables referring to the same tuple object, but the tuple is immutable and you'll get an error
message if you try to change it. So immutable objects like tuples don't suffer from this same
gotcha that a mutable list would. Now what about other data types like integers and strings? Well,
integers and strings are also immutable. You can assign the integer 42 to spam like we do at the
top and then assign spam to eggs like we do in the middle. And both of these variables refer to
the same integer object. And then if you try to change spam, like at the bottom, you're actually
creating a brand new string object and attaching the spam label to that. You're not going to run
into the gotcha that we have with lists because integers and strings are immutable objects. Now
on Python, everything is an object. Lists and tuples and dictionaries are objects, but so are
integers and floats and Booleans and strings, but also functions, classes, and modules. All of those
are objects. It's not like Java where you have primitive data types and object data types.
Everything in Python is an object. And when we assign spam to eggs, we aren't copying objects.
And in fact, assignment never copies objects in Python. It only copies the label. And there's a
great talk by Ned Batchelder on this called Facts and Myths about Python Names and Values. I draw
on some of the things he covers in this talk, but it's worth it to see Ned's talk as well. But keep
this in mind, everything in Python is an object. So that's another term that we need to define.
What are objects? And I'll get back to this in a moment when I cover the Python object model,
but let's look at one more code example first. What happens when we have a tuple that contains
a list? So the tuple is immutable, but the list is mutable. And when we change the mutable list,
we also change the immutable tuple? How is that possible? Well, let's look at PythonTutor.com
again. Remember, variables are labels, not boxes. And lists and tuples don't have boxes that contain
objects either. They have labels that refer to objects. So PythonTutor.com is slightly inaccurate
here because this slide should really look like this. The tuple and lists don't contain integers
and strings. They contain labels that refer to integers and strings. And this view makes it a
lot clearer at the bottom that the list changes what objects it refers to, but the tuple doesn't.
So the tuple is still immutable. But at the same time, it's clearly obviously changing its value.
So does this mean tuples are mutable? What do we mean by these words? Mutable, immutable, object,
value. It's easy to use these words interchangeably or inconsistently, but let's think about what we
mean when we say them. You can go a long time without knowing the exact definitions. I was
programming in Python for well over a decade before I found the data model page in the official
Python documentation. The Python data model, also sometimes called the Python object model,
describes the lower level details of what Python objects are. Remember, everything in Python is an
object, and the Python data model tells us that every object has three things. An identity, a type,
and a value. Yay, more words we need to define. An object's identity is a unique integer that never
changes for the lifetime of the object. So from the moment the object is created until it's recycled
by the garbage collector, it is the same and unique. So in CPython, which is the Python
interpreter you download from Python.org, the identity is the object's memory address,
and that's very convenient because that's an integer that's unique and it's not going to change.
You can find the identity of an object with the built-in id function. Pass it an object or a
variable that refers to an object, and it returns the integer identity of the object.
You can use this to determine if two variables refer to the same object by checking that their
identities are equal. Here we can tell that eggs and spam refer to the same list because the object
they each refer to has the same identity, so it's the same list object. In fact, this is what the
is operator does. It's a shortcut for checking identity equality between two variables.
Every object has an identity and every object has a type. In Python, the terms type, data type,
and class all mean the same thing. Like identity, an object's type never changes during the object's
lifetime. A type is something like integer or string or tuple. You can find the type of an object
with the built-in type function. You pass it an object and it returns the object's type. Remember,
everything in Python is an object, and that means that what the type function returns
is also an object, and that object has a type. It's the type type. Like the identity, the type
of an object never changes. If you're converting a string to an int, you aren't actually changing
the string's object's type. What's happening is that you're creating a new int object and the
variable now refers to that new int object. We can see this for ourselves by checking the identity
of the variable's object. The ID function here gives us different identity numbers.
Every object in Python has an identity, a type, and the third thing is a value. This is the most
familiar property. The value is one of a range of values determined by the type, so there's
effectively an infinite number of possible integer and string values, but the Boolean type only has
two possible values, true and false, and the none value is the only value in the none type type.
So is there a built-in function to tell us the value of an object?
Well, we think of value as this well-defined thing, but when I looked closer, value is kind
of nebulous. I'm going to ask a question that sounds like it's straight out of philosophy.
What is value? Now, if you want to see an object's identity, you can call the ID function. If you
want to see an object's type, you can call the type function, but if you want to see the value
of an object, there are actually two built-in functions, str and repr. The str function,
or string function, returns a human-readable string form of the object's value. This is
straightforward for objects like integers and strings, so let's use a more abstract example
with the datetime.date object. Here I have called datetime.date to create a date object that represents
January 2020, and I assign the birthday variable to refer to this object. Now, when I call string,
it returns a string of a human-readable form of the object's value. What string or str returns
is defined by the datetime.date type, but this string of the object's value is not the same thing
as the object's value. If we try to use the equality operator on them, it evaluates to
fault. str doesn't return the object's value, it returns a string that represents the object's value,
and that's a subtle difference. The other built-in function for seeing an object's value is repr.
The repr function produces a string that ideally is a representation of Python code that would
recreate the object with that same value. So passing the date object to repr gives you a string
of the code that creates the date object. The reason we have two different functions is because
the str string is useful for displaying object values to humans, while the repr string is useful
for more technical contexts like log files or debugging messages. This isn't always possible
to make a repr string of Python code to recreate the object. For example, I've created a foo class
here and the default implementations of str and repr are fairly useless. You can tell from the
angle brackets that this string would not be valid Python syntax. You can recreate the object
using the repr string. The str and repr functions return strings that describe an object's value,
but that's not going to be the same thing as the value itself. Even if we type the variable that
refers to the object into the interactive shell, that's just going to show us the repr function's
string. That's not going to be the object's value itself. Now we need to know the value so we can
tell if an object's value changes, and then we can find out if the object is mutable or immutable,
and then we can find out if tuples are mutable or immutable. So this is getting kind of complicated
because mutability isn't a property of Python objects the way identity, type, and value are
properties of Python objects. Let's look at the Python data model documentation again.
It tells us that if an object's value can change, it's mutable, and if it can't, then it's immutable,
but that doesn't tell us an exact definition of value. I did eventually find it. It's in a
completely different section of the Python documentation, section 6.10.1. It has this line,
the value of an object is a rather abstract notion in Python. Yeah, no kidding.
But it says that the value of an object is dictated by the equality operator, and I agree,
but even if this wasn't backed by anything in the official Python documentation, I think it
could make a pretty good case for this. For example, the integer 42 and the floating point
number 42.0 have the same value. The equality operator says they are equal. Now, I can't tell
you the true nature of the value 42. I'm sure it has something to do with life, the universe, and
whatever. But however you want to define value, I can tell you that these objects,
42 and 42.0, have the same value in Python. Meanwhile, the integer 42 and the string 42
have different values. The equality operator says their values are different. But if you want to
know something kind of weird, the Boolean true and false values are the same as the integer 1
and 0 values. The story behind that is Python originally didn't have a Boolean data type,
it was added later, and when they added it, it was just easy to make Booleans a subclass of
integers. So you can use Boolean values anywhere you can use the integers 0 and 1. That means you
can mathematically add true plus true plus false plus true, and that evaluates to the integer value
3. You can use true as an index of a string and get a substring. Now, you can write code like this,
but please don't. It's completely unreadable. But if you want to know something that will really
bake your noodle, check out Python 2. Capital T true and capital F false were only made keywords
in Python 3. In Python 2, you can use these names as variable names, which means you can assign false
to true, and then true is false is true. So please switch to Python 3 if you haven't already,
because otherwise you might destroy the space-time continuum or something.
So if mutability is based on value, and value is based on the equality operator,
what is the equality operator based on? And that's easy to answer. The Dunder equal Dunder
special method. Python classes, which is to say Python data types, have special methods
that begin and end with double underscores. We call them double under methods or Dunder methods.
The Dunder equal Dunder method overloads the equality operator. So say I have a cat class,
and I define a cat as being composed of a color and weight. Now, in reality, cats are much more
than just color and weight. Don't confuse the map with the territory. But this is just how
I'm defining cats here in this class for this particular piece of software. Now I'm overloading
the equality operator so that another object has an equal value to this cat object's value
if its type is cat or a subclass of cat, and it has a matching color and weight. So I can create
two cat objects and assign them the variables Zoffy and Pooka. When I compare them with the
equality operator, Python calls Dunder equal Dunder and it returns true. So these two objects
have the same value because the equality operator says they do. Though I can change that as much as
I want. Let's change the Dunder equal Dunder method so that two cats have the same value
if they have the same color and weight doesn't factor into it at all. Then I can create two
cat objects, Zoffy and Jasper, and these cats are both gray but have different weights. But
Python considers them to have the same value because the value of the weight attribute
isn't a part of the value of the cat object. Now that seems quote unquote wrong, but maybe this
fits the requirement for this particular cat class in this particular piece of software.
Let's take this even further. If I always return not other is self, then a cat object has the same
value as literally every other object except for itself. So Zoffy is not equal to Zoffy,
but Zoffy is equal to the string CheeseSandwich. Now that seems very wrong, but this is Python
programming. There is no right or wrong. There's only Dunder methods. I can't think of a case
where code like this is necessary or useful. It also breaks dictionary hashing completely,
but if the use case demands it, then this is the quote unquote right definition of value for this
class. There doesn't seem to be a consensus on what value is in the Python language. You could
argue that the integer 42 should have the same value as the string 42, but the equality operator,
that is the class's own Dunder equal Dunder method, says they don't. And I think what a type says
about its own definition of value is the closest thing that we're going to get to a referee on
this. I will now tell you if tuples are mutable or immutable. We have two tuples, spam and eggs,
and they have separate identities. They are different separate objects. The equality operator
says they have the same value though. So no matter what you say about the nature of these tuples
values or a value itself, we know that they are the same value according to the equality operator.
Now we run this code and we change the list inside the spam tuple. And when we compare their values
again, they do not have the same value. Therefore, one of these tuples must have
changed their value. Therefore, tuples are mutable. This is the part where someone says,
yeah, Al, but tuples are immutable. Everybody knows that. That someone will then point to the
Python data model documentation and say that the tuple is still considered immutable because the
collection of objects it contains cannot be changed. Yep. I mean, I can't argue with that.
I even showed that in my earlier example. The Python data model documentation continues.
So immutability is not strictly the same as having an unchangeable value. It is more subtle.
It is more subtle. I spent weeks on this presentation trying to show that tuples
are mutable and it gets refuted by four hand-waving words in the documentation.
The question is, said Alice, whether you can make words mean so many different things. The question
is, said Humpty Dumpty, which is to be master. That's all. We can argue about what mutability
means in Python because ultimately humans define words and not the other way around.
Maybe we're thinking about mutability wrong. Maybe I'm thinking about mutability wrong.
Maybe the Python documentation is wrong. Maybe data types like tuples aren't mutable or immutable,
but individual objects are mutable or immutable. And that could be a whole other talk, but I'm
running out of time. So I'm going to leave you with one final philosophical question.
How many colors are in a rainbow? Seven, right? But this isn't a rainbow. This is. So how many
colors does it have? A million? Infinite? Well, it depends on how you define color.
But a small-minded person might say, no, no, no, rainbows have seven colors. They can only
have seven colors. We all learned this in kindergarten. The colors of a rainbow are
ROYGBIV, red, orange, yellow, green, blue, purple, and a different kind of purple.
Maybe these two words, mutable and immutable, aren't as concrete as we first thought. It's
more subtle than that. Maybe having just two words isn't enough to fully describe Python objects.
Or if we do use these two words in a casual colloquial sense, that isn't the final sense.
Well, I'm a programmer and not a philosopher, and I've been talking for 25 minutes,
so maybe it's time for me to listen to what others say about what identity,
type, and value means to them. Thank you very much.
We'll meet again, don't know where, don't know when, but I know we'll meet again some sunny day.
you