My dear friends, it's a pleasure for introducing you Dr. Schweigart.
He's going to give a talk on the overview of the Python code tool landscape 2020.
Thank you.
Quite awesome.
Okay.
Thank you so much for coming to this rescheduled talk.
This talk was originally going to happen on the morning of the first day of the conference,
but on my flight from Houston, that got delayed by an hour, and then that got delayed by four
hours, and then there was engine trouble during the flight, and we had to make a 2 a.m. landing
in Grand Junction, Colorado.
So, I had to wait in line to get the hotel voucher, then I had to wait in line to get
the hotel shuttle, then I had to wait in line to get the hotel check-in, also I'd get out
about two hours of sleep before I would have to get up and go back to the airport.
And then another thing happened.
I fell in love with this beautiful stranger, like you do at airports, and I was willing
to just forget everything, the conference, my books, my entire old life, just so I could
be with her, and she told me, Al, if that thing takes off and you're not ending, you're
going to regret it.
And so, I went to the airport, and I was like, what about us today, maybe not tomorrow, but
someday soon, and for the rest of your life?
And I was just crying with tears in my eyes, I was like, but what about us?
And she told me, we'll always have Grand Junction, Colorado.
So, I got on the plane, and we never spoke again.
So, that was the Tycon Code Tool Landscape 2023.
Thank you very much for coming to this talk.
You can find a copy of the slides at ify.tycon2023landscape, or you can just take photos with your phone
at any slides that you find interesting.
I really want to thank the Tycon organizers, the staff, the volunteers, everyone who does
so much work to put all of this together.
It's really amazing, especially because I had all this rescheduling that had to happen.
Tycon is my favorite conference, and it's really the highlight of my career.
My name is Al Swigert.
I'm mostly known as the author of Automated Boring Stuff with Python and a few other books.
You can read them all for free under the Included Call Influence on my website,
inventwithpython.com.
The idea for this talk started out as some research I was doing for my book about different
tools that are available for Python, and there are quite a few of them.
I really didn't understand what I was getting myself into.
I had heard of some of them, but many of these tools have very similar names to other tools,
and I found the whole thing really confusing.
So, this is the part of the talk where I have to mention that obligatory SKCD comic showing how
complicated the Python ecosystem is.
It's really not that bad, but there is some truth to this.
You have to keep in mind that Python is 30 years old at this point, and the fact that a lot of
people have built a lot of different tools for it is sort of a symptom of its success.
It's the second best language for everything, and in my opinion, it's the first best language for
most settings.
I will be getting many of my opinions during this talk.
What does this talk cover?
A lot of packages for tools that you can download from PyTI, the Python package index.
Note that it's PyTI and not PyPy.
That's something completely different than Python.
I don't want to bore you with so many details, so I'm going to be skipping a lot of the
configuration details in case you can just look that up in the documentation.
And also, I just have a firehose of information out of you anyway, and that might be intimidating,
but especially if you're new to programming or new to Python.
But remember, you don't have to adopt all of these tools at once.
If you're experienced in Python, you might find out about something that you haven't heard before.
I certainly did find new tools that I hadn't seen before while I was researching this talk.
And if you have some experience with Python, learning about these tools is a great way to move
from beginner to advanced.
And the funny thing is, that also applies if you are a beginner, because Saturday morning,
because static code analysis tool sounds like a complicated thing, but these are tools that
point out small problems in your code.
So it's like giving you a mini code review, which is something that can really help you out as a beginner.
It's sort of like learning how to use a debugger in that it doesn't cost you time,
it actually saves you time over the long run.
So if you are interested in learning these tools, don't hold back.
Just being interested is enough of a qualification to start learning these tools.
And all of the information that I present comes from the opinionated perspective of me here in 2023.
If you're watching a recording of this talk on YouTube or wherever, in the future, hello, how's it going?
How's the future going? Oh, kind of rough? Yeah, well, you know, it'll get better.
The information in this talk here in 2023 is probably still relevant to you in the future.
And if it isn't, well, at least it's a very good historical document of what the tools are like here in 2023.
And at this point in time, it's actually really interesting to talk about static code analysis tools for Python.
This talk would have been very different if I had given it last year, because about eight months ago,
a new tool came out that has very rapidly started replacing many of the tools that I'm talking about here.
And to keep the suspense, I knew I knew of this awesome tool at the end of this talk.
Nah, just kidding. It's rough. The awesome tool is rough.
But I will tell you about what makes it such a big danger towards ending the talk.
And this talk started off as a blog post that I wrote a few months back.
You can find out at bit.ly slash pycon2023 landscape.
And it sends a link to the slide that's on the screen right now.
I'll be updating this blog post from time to time.
Okay. So there's a lot of things that I don't cover in this talk, like how to configure all of these different tools.
That would be very boring for live presentation. So I'll just leave you to look up the documentation for that.
I talk about type trackers, but I don't talk about the syntax of typefints.
I don't talk about unit tests or code coverage tools.
Those are things that actually run the code, and I'm focusing on static code analysis tools.
I don't really cover any sort of ID or source control or any virtual environment stuff I use.
Now, before I begin, I have to talk about programmers and their opinions,
because how we define really different ways to write code is often a matter of our opinion.
And we write these opinions into what our code tools will report as problems or as good code.
And programmers can be quite enthusiastic about their opinions on how to write code.
Pycon Enhancement Proposals Document Number 8, also called PEP 8, has code style recommendations for Python code.
But remember that PEP 8 is a great set of guidelines, but it's not like PEP 8 was a stone tablet that you could walk down from the mountain.
Even PEP 8 itself will tell you in the section right after the introduction if you don't have to contain yourself to every single one of the guidelines it presents.
It's a set of smart opinions that you really need to know when it doesn't apply to your project.
Neil Stevenson is a science fiction author who wrote Snow Crash, which is where the whole metaverse concept came from.
He also wrote this book called The Diamond Age, which has this line that I have gagged here.
I feel like most code style opinions that we assess are half-remembered pieces of bad advice.
And when you work on a team, you can have conflicting opinions, and you can start arguing about code style.
And the main thing that you should remember about that is that usually it's a waste of time.
And the great thing about tools like Black and Rough is that even though everyone might not be able to agree on code style rules,
they can usually agree on just referring to whatever these automatic tools will do.
It just presents a lot of arguing that wastes time.
Now, this talk that I'm giving is also opinionated because I'm not just telling you about tools,
but I'm also giving you sort of my own recommendations about them.
And keep in mind that these are just my opinions.
Maybe they're relevant to the project that you're working on. Maybe they're not. It's fine to disagree with me. It's okay.
Yeah, actually, you know what? Everybody on the internet is going to yell at me anyway, so I might as well just leave.
All of my opinions are correct.
And if you disagree with me, how dare you?
Okay, so let's take a look at some code tools.
Here are the different types of better code analysis tools. This is a very informal categorization that I'm using right here.
The first type are linters. The name comes from the link trap in a clothing dryer.
And it collects tiny little bits of lint, which helps prevent really big problems like dryer fires.
So these are tools that will point out small problems with your code going on.
I remember this was once consistent kind of right in college, which may or may not be made out.
But a bug that is, that you have to debug after a software is released will take 50 to 200 times as long to fix than if you had caught it before software release.
And that actually kind of makes sense to me. So like a problem that takes me half a day to debug, but if I had caught it sooner, it would have been fixed in two minutes.
That's a situation I've been in multiple times.
And there are also linters that check your code style. And this is really, these are things like spaces and variable names or line lengths.
This is where a lot of opinion comes in about the source code variability.
This is, these are linters that don't catch things that cause bugs, but catch things that make your code look ugly or make your code look unreadable.
Wicca, of course, is a subjective term. But the main benefit of a style linter is preventing time-wasting arguments over code style.
Software developers are expensive, time is precious, take a style linter and just deal with it.
And there are also style linters for your doc strings that are really helpful at pointing out that you forgot to write doc strings.
If you're creating a package, there are package linters that check to make sure that you're doing it right.
I've always been in the situation where I've published something to PyPI and then I publish something five minutes later that fixes something in the previous thing that I published.
There are linters to point out possible security issues with your code. There are also linters to point out any code that would logically never run or code that's been commented out.
I call those dead code linters. Formatters or fixers go a step further and they not only detect problems with your code, but they also automatically update your source code and fix them as well.
So there's no reason an expensive software engineer should be going through making text editor changes to thousands of files.
This is a perfect place where you can use a tool like Black.
Python is a dynamically typed language, which means that your variables and your function parameters and your return types, they can be of any data type whatsoever.
And this is really nice because it makes it less tedious to write Python code, but it's not so nice in that there are many kinds of bugs that result from having the wrong data type.
If you've ever encountered the error that's what none type object has there will actually be blah blah blah. That was most likely caused by a typing issue.
Python now that's an offline add-type tends to your code and means they're verified once you type type a tool.
And there are also tools that can measure how complex your code is according to some algorithms that computer scientists developed in the 1930s.
That's 1970s.
Still thinking about Casablanca. Anyway.
And then there are packages that just combine a whole bunch of other packages I call the kitchen-sitting connectors.
They're really nice if you just want to have one command that then runs a whole bunch of different tools.
So you're going to get all of these tools from PyTI, which is the Python package index.
It's the central repository where everybody publishes their third-party packages.
And you can browse for different packages from the PyTI.org website and then install them with a command line tool that comes with Python called pip on macOS and Linux.
It's called pip3.
You may or may not have done this before. You just run pip install whatever from the command line.
If you're a beginner or if you're teaching a workshop that has a lot of beginners, using the command line tool might be a bit of an obstacle,
especially because it's different for people on Windows, it's different for people on Mac,
and it depends on how their path environment variable is set up or whether they have multiple versions of Python installed at the same time you want to make sure you're installing the correct one.
You really don't want to have your three-hour learning to code workshop have the first hour spent on just getting everyone's machines working.
So there's a little trick that you can do if you just import pip and then call pip.main.
You can essentially run pip from the interactive shell.
And this is generally, for some technical reasons, not something you should do very often, but it does work.
And it will work no matter what version of Python they have, no matter what operating system they have or anything else like that.
So it's a really handy trick to keep in mind.
So you can find these tools on the PyPI website, and you can install them with pip on the command line.
To actually run them, you will have to use the command line.
And they usually have a way that you can several command line options that you can pass to them, or you can configure their configuration file so that you don't have to enter the command line up in the speech time.
All of that is going to be in their documentation.
But mostly the thing that you should do is if you use an IDE like Visual Studio Code or Python or whatever,
there should be a way where you can have the IDE run these tools, and that way you can do all the red squiggles directly into your editor.
And you're not constantly alt-tabbing between the IDE and the command line and rerunning the commands over and over, and that gets really tired really quickly.
So definitely it's worth your time to figure out how to get that working in the IDE itself.
Now, I'm not going to go into all those details like I said before because it's all in the documentation anyway.
But it makes these tools really convenient to use, and tools that are convenient to use are tools that you can use more often.
Okay, so let's look at some of these actual tools.
First off, here's a bunch of outdated, obsolete or unmaintained packages.
PyCheck or PyLava, Flake, Hell, you have AtoFight, PryFormat.
There's a package that's called Lint that seems to be really obscure and not used by anyone.
And there's also lots of packages called PyPI that just have the word Lint in their name.
You can usually tell that they're not really widely used because either their GitHub statistics will be pretty low
or maybe they only had a few releases. The last one was from several years ago.
This tells me that the project probably isn't being maintained.
It's not a guarantee of that. Maybe it's just trying the way it is.
But generally, inactively maintained projects will show a lot more activity right here.
And another thing that maybe you shouldn't use a package is if it has no project description.
There's a certain process for publishing packages on PyPI.
In general, projects that don't bother to figure out how to have a description
or they don't really have a good description probably aren't really meant for public consumption.
I like to speak so much personal tool. So not always, but probably.
And there are a couple of packages that have been renamed.
PEP8 and PEP257 packages are now called PyCodeStyle and PyDocStyle.
Here's a helpful hint. Aside from PEP8, very few people remember the exact PEP numbers for things.
So I guess not to name your package after a number.
And there are a few error linkers and style linkers that have very similar sounding names.
I like PyFlates because it's rather conservative in what it catches.
I mostly work on small products that I know and also I don't want to be distracted by false positives.
Flake8 is a very popular tool and it contains a lot of plugins and Flake Heaven is also pretty good.
PyLink is one of the oldest linkers out there that's very popular and it has a reputation for in-flow,
but I doubt that only applies if you have a very large code repository that has scosher.
Finally, next there are code form owners.
The most popular one of course is black, but I dug around and there are actually others as well.
YASF, I don't know how to pronounce that, but I'm guessing that stands for yet another Python form owner,
which is nice because it's very, very customizable.
I tend to go ahead and just use black because it has very few knobs that you can turn to customize it.
The "-s argument is there because I like to keep my single quoted strings,
I have single quoted strings, I have double quoted strings, and I like to set my line lengths to like one line or something really big like that.
AutoPep8 and Stakefit are other tools that I do have a lot of experience with,
but AutoPep8 does seem to have some popularity.
For DocString linkers, all of them are currently under way in maintaining, but they all seem great.
PyDocStyle.formatter. PyDocString.formatter.
You can see why it's really confusing to juggle all of these names.
PyDocStyle is the most popular one that I've found, but the others, from what I can tell, seem to work pretty well also.
And then there are type checkers. You've probably heard of MyPy, which is one that's community supported,
but Microsoft, Google, and Facebook have also come out with their own type checkers as well.
I've just been sticking with MyPy.
And then there are security linters. And in my experience, all of these have not been so helpful.
Occasionally, they point out something that is theoretically a security concern in my code,
but it's also a lot of false positives that they are ended, dodgy, and that PySy, which comes with PyR.
Oh, going back previously, there are some things that you should know.
For PyWrite from Microsoft, it's right as in left and right, and not pyWrite as in full scroll.
And to install Pyre, you actually have to install pyre-deck, because the Pyre project is something else entirely.
And then there's packet pointers. These are great. I've only downed one, PyRoma.
It's a very nice checklist to make sure how do you set up everything correctly before you upload to PyPI.
I haven't found any others. This is definitely one that I use a lot.
And then there's dead code linters. And these are of some value to me.
Ultra generates a lot of false positives for me.
And there are things where you have a return statement, but then you have some code after it.
It'll point out, hey, this code can never possibly run at all, because you returned before it could run.
Things like that, or code that you've just commented out, that's really not something that you should put into source control when you commit your code.
AutoFlake, which really has nothing to do with Flake. It uses PyFlake for itself,
but all it does is remove unused import statements and also unused hash statements as well.
And then complexity analysis tools. This is something that I learned about in my computer science education in college,
and I've never really used since. The main one is McCabe, which is also named after the doctor who invented the cyclomatic complexity metric.
Really, I'm not convinced that these are useful metrics in general.
Like, rearranging your code just for the sake of reducing its complexity is probably going to end up making your code harder to read.
If I was a manager, I would never make a rule that our code must have a complexity score of X or lower.
But it's actually pretty good for getting some insights about maybe what sections of your code are a bit more complicated,
maybe what are the right words you use just for those sections of code, or maybe just want to refactor them some more.
And then these are the packages I call HM SYNC packages. Flake 8 is really nice.
By itself, it has just PyFlake's PyQuant style as a style editor and McCabe for complexity analysis,
but there are also just so many plugins available for Flake 8.
There's also PyLama, which is not to be confused with PyLama with two Ls.
It also has PyCoStyle and PyDotStyle and PyFlake for McCabe.
And then it also has the packages in red you can optionally install on top of the core PyLama packages.
And then there's Prospector, which also includes a bunch of these packages.
I've listed these here in order of popularity. Flake 8 is by far the most popular one I've seen.
And then I think this is the last category. There's iSort and uSort.
And these are formatters that rearrange your import statements into alphabetical order.
And it seems really useless, but I actually kind of like these tools, especially when I just have like import this, import this, import this.
And it gives like some, once I have like 10 or so import statements, it is kind of nice to have them in alphabetical order.
And it's just nice that the tool automatically does that.
Okay, that was a lot. Everybody still awake? Yeah? Okay.
Everybody, there might have been some packages that I've slipped by me.
I really apologize to the maintainers of those projects. Feel free to contact me and I can update my blog post with them.
Who learned about some new tools that they did not know about before? Oh, wow. Basically everyone. Great. Yeah. Awesome. Okay.
Forget about everything I just told you. Yeah. You can just use Ruff.
Yeah. This entire talk is now kind of pointless. Let's talk about Ruff.
It was first released about eight months ago, and if you haven't heard of Ruff, you will.
It is very rapidly growing in popularity. Ruff is a Python linker written in Rust, and it is fast. How fast? Very fast.
These were the benchmarks after releasing the C Python repo. I tried it out myself, and I thought it had crashed because it finished so quickly.
It's a Python link. It takes over 60 seconds. Flakey, it will take 12 seconds. Ruff takes a third of a second. It is mind-boggling.
And when you have a tool that you can write constantly in the background and not just daily or as a pre-commed book, you get to actually get a massive boost in your personal productivity.
There are some great interviews with Ruff Trader, Charlie Marsh, who is also here at Python. I hope he hasn't gone home yet.
I really recommend checking out his interviews. He was also on the Top Python Podcast.
I mean, like all Wenders, Ruff is probably going to start off being a little bit more zealous about what he tells you about, but he can also configure it to read in orders for a lot of different things.
Here, it produced 19,000 lines of advice in the third of a second that it took to review the C Python source code.
Yes, I really want to stress how fast it is. Not just that, but Ruff developers have re-implemented many of Flakey's plugins.
Here's a list of all the packages that Ruff currently replaces. So, I still need to dive into it, but I think that Ruff has made my entire talk pointless.
So if you're brand new to static analysis tools, I think you can get away with just using Black, MyCon, and Ruff, and use some other miscellaneous packages as well.
And that's a pretty sweeping statement. But the more I look at Ruff and the way that it's adding new features, I think we're headed towards a world where you don't need Alice Piper compiling all of this information about different static analysis tools because everyone will have settled on just a handful of them.
And I did not have said this at last year's PyCon, so it is a very exciting time. So the ecosystem of any programming language as top-class Python is always going to be vast, but as far as static analysis tools go, the future is looking bright and it's going to get better.
Thank you for attending my talk.