Hi, everyone. I'm Sam Gross. I'll be talking about PyTorch 2.0 and the compiler in it.
This talk was originally prepared by my colleagues Justin and Seraj, two excellent developer
advocates at Meta. I will be presenting it because they were unfortunately not able to
attend PyCon. The work I'm going to be talking about is
largely done by my colleagues at Meta and in the PyTorch community at large.
So to start with, how many people here by raise of hands have experience with AI or machine
learning? That's a lot. How many of you have used PyTorch? That's a good number.
So for those of you not familiar with PyTorch, it's a machine learning framework frequently
used for training neural networks. It was originally developed by Facebook AI research
in late 2016. It's always been open source and basically from the beginning it's had
contributions from both Facebook, now Meta, and collaborators in industry and academia.
The project's now under the Linux Foundation, which the intention is to provide sort of
neutral governance for it. Yeah. PyTorch has become fairly popular. It's
probably the most widely used machine learning framework for AI research. This graph from
papers with code shows the number of new papers released with code and by framework used.
And that big orange segment in the middle is PyTorch. I think it's worth considering
what made PyTorch popular. This is especially important question for PyTorch developers
and maintainers because as we change and improve the framework we want to make sure we adhere
to the principles that helped it succeed in the first place. I think one of the most important
principles at the beginning is that it's Pythonic. This is a bit abstract and hard to define.
But one way to put it, I suggest, is that PyTorch is not only written in Python but
it allows developers to use it in ways that they might be familiar with from other Python
libraries and frameworks. So, for example, a lot of PyTorch's tensor APIs are similar
to NumPy's array APIs and PyTorch is interoperable with NumPy and other Python libraries and
frameworks. Again, it's a bit abstract. It's hard to measure and hard for us as developers
and maintainers to know what exactly it is that we want to maintain. I'll come back to
that a bit later in this talk. I think another important reason for PyTorch's popularity
is that it tries to achieve a Goldilocks balance between abstracting away low level details
that you don't really care about but still providing an API that's rich enough to let
you do things that might be slightly off the beaten path. And finally, it's important that
PyTorch is performant. So under the hood it uses kernels implemented in C and C++ and
CUDA to run on GPUs so that the neural networks that you train and run in PyTorch run efficiently.
Coming back to the notion of what makes PyTorch Pythonic, I think a big reason here is that
PyTorch really embraces sort of eager dynamic execution. What some people call like an ear
mode paradigm. One way to think about this is that every line in a PyTorch program is
executed in order with the rest of your Python program and it's mostly executed immediately.
The other bit is that it supports dynamic control flow, meaning that your PyTorch neural
network models can include if statements, while loops, for loops, all the normal control
flow that you'd expect in a Python program. And this stands in contrast a bit to some
other frameworks that were developed around the same time in 2015, 16, and 17 that really
focused on static data flow graphs. What I mean by that is that they tried to or they
do capture representation for your neural network that's independent of the rest of
the Python program. One reason that a lot of frameworks embrace this static data flow
graph approach is that it provides a lot more visibility for the framework to know what's
going on in your neural network model and potentially opportunities for it to optimize
the execution, make it run faster and more efficiently. PyTorch, when we started the
project, we intentionally did not go for this static data flow graph approach. Most of the
original developers on PyTorch had previously worked on Torch 7 and the thing that people
kept liking about Torch 7, there were a lot of other problems, but one of the things that
people liked was that it was direct, that it was the program that you wrote executed
essentially as you wrote it. It was a lot, which makes it easier to debug. So switching
back to PyTorch, in the context of PyTorch, the dynamic execution, the eager mode paradigm
means that you can use standard Python debugging tools like PDB. You can interoperate with
other libraries. And for a lot of developers and researchers, this sort of API feels more
direct and easier to use. So again, I think in 2016 and 2017, the prevailing conventional
wisdom was that deep learning frameworks needed a static graph because they needed to be able
to optimize the performance and potentially capture a program representation to run on
upcoming new exciting hardware. And I think this view was both prevalent at Facebook,
where I worked and still work at the time, as well as more broadly in industry. But it
wasn't universal. There was a bunch of other frameworks like PyTorch, including a number
that came before it, that also adopted this or also focused on this dynamic, eager execution,
among them Chainer, Torch 7, which we had worked on, and Dynet. Again, I think the reason
this prevailing conventional wisdom was prevailing was because people thought that eager mode
was slow, that the overhead of executing a Python program for every step of your neural
network training or inference would be too much. That one is Python can be slow at times,
especially compared to optimized C++ or CUDA kernels running on your GPU. And our hypothesis
was basically that this overhead didn't matter, at least not then. One reason we didn't think
it mattered was that the most common way to train neural networks at the time, still probably
true today, is on GPUs. And for your PyTorch or other programs, the Python aspect of your
program can run on the CPU while the vast majority of your computations are running
in parallel or concurrently on the GPU. So as long as the Python bits of your program
are fast enough to keep the GPU fully occupied, then the Python overhead isn't going to matter.
And this was true, I think it was particularly true in 2016, 2017, and for the few years
following it. But the problem was that GPUs kept getting faster, and they were getting
faster quicker than CPUs were getting faster. So it became pretty clear that eventually
the speed up in GPUs would mean that the CPUs weren't fast enough, that this overhead would
matter because you couldn't keep the GPUs busy enough. So basically from shortly after
the release of the first version of PyTorch, the team started looking into ways to add
a compiler to PyTorch while still trying to keep the principles that I think made PyTorch
successful and popular. Again, I think the most important principle that made PyTorch
successful was that it was easy to use. And this was especially important, I think, for
AI researchers because more so than people deploying or running inference or deploying
models to correction, AI researchers tended to have much more broader use cases and do
things that might be less well supported by a static graph paradigm. Of course, we still
want PyTorch to be fast. So the goal was can we build a compiler that prioritizes the
user experience, particularly the developer experience of someone using PyTorch. I think
a lot of people think of these as opposing goals, the ease of use and performance, and
that you're making a tradeoff between the two. And in a lot of cases you are. But we
really, for this project to succeed, we need to both have something that is easy to use
and performant. And I think in practice there's a lot more, like this, the design space isn't
one dimensional. It's not just performance and ease of use. There are other places in
this design space, different tradeoffs you can make. And I'll come back to this later
in the talk about the different sorts of tradeoffs we made that are not strictly ease of use
versus performance. So the PyTorch 2.0 API for the compiler is pretty simpler at the
user level. It's just torch.compile model, get back a compiled model that you run which
is hopefully faster. Under the hood it's doing a lot more. At a high level it's basically
doing three things. The first thing is graph acquisition, meaning it's trying to get representation
of your program. And it's doing graph lowering. Given the operations that you write in your
PyTorch program, it's trying to decompose those into operations that might be better
suited for the compiler to optimize or generate code. And finally it's graph compilation,
both the optimization step and generating code that's running on your GPU or on another
device. This diagram from Sumit's keynote at PyTorch conference I think illustrates
the three steps pretty nicely. So as a developer of PyTorch you write a typical program that's
doing a series of operations. In this case it's a neural network convolution followed
by a batch normalization operation, finally followed by the rectified linear unit. What
these are doesn't matter terribly but the important thing is you're writing a Python
program, you have a bunch of these calls into the PyTorch API. The graph acquisition means
that it's determining what these calls are and converting it into a data flow graph,
meaning that the result of one thing flows into the other. And then it's a representation
that the compiler knows how to handle. Some of these operations can be broken up into
their constituent bits. So for example the convolution operation in PyTorch is both really
a convolution plus an extra addition at the end. And breaking those up might provide more
opportunities for the compiler. And finally the last step is basically generating the
actual code that will run on your GPU. So again graph acquisition is basically trying
to do that capture that static graph representation, the representation that's used from the compiler
from your dynamic program. Graph lowering is breaking it apart and graph compilation
is both the optimization steps and generating the code for your device. This wasn't the
first attempt that the PyTorch team had for adding compiler to PyTorch. We actually, it's
the third attempt. The first one was torch.trace which work on this I think started around
2017, a few months after the first public release of PyTorch. The way the trace compiler
worked was you, well first it had a pretty simple API. Like torch.compile it was you
added a torch.jit.trace call around the thing that you wanted to compile along with a special,
an input that you represented sort of a standard input to your neural network model. The compiler
would execute your model line by line and record or trace each of the PyTorch operations
that was required to execute the model. And those operations form a graph. One limitation
of this is that it only works if your PyTorch neural network model doesn't depend on the
input size. For example, it might be common for an image classification neural network
model to only process fixed size images. But other applications, for example, segmentation
like figuring out where objects are in the image, detection, same sort of thing, or even
some language models have inputs that are varying in size. You might have images that
are wider or shorter or bigger and you might want to keep those as the original inputs.
And torch.jit.trace didn't handle these wells because it assumed that the input that you
provided during compilation was the only shape and type of input that it would see. The second
attempt at adding a compiler to PyTorch was torch.script. And torch.script still exists
in PyTorch as just torch.jit.trace. But to be clear going forward, we think that developers
should prefer the torch.compile in PyTorch 2.0 over either torch.script or torch.jit.trace.
Torch.script worked a bit differently. Instead of tracing the execution of your PyTorch program
sort of operation by operation, it would statically analyze your program and attempt to extract
the graph just from static analysis. The other goal was that although torch.jit.trace ignored
all the operations that were not PyTorch operations. So for example, if you had a for loop, it
wouldn't really work. Or if you had normal sort of Python operations on lists or dictionaries,
those wouldn't be captured by torch.jit.trace. Torch.script made an attempt to capture these
operations. But this also meant that torch.script kind of ballooned in scope to be more than
just a PyTorch compiler, it also ended up being a Python compiler. And this kind of
split the effort of the team. The team ended up focusing a lot on trying to support more
and more Python features because it's common for authors of neural network models to use
a little bit of Python features here and there. And in practice, it required that people that
authored PyTorch models either refactor their code to avoid sort of unsupported Python operations
or calls into third party libraries that torch.script couldn't really capture. So Dynamo is our
third attempt at a PyTorch compiler. And I think it's been fairly successful. It's also
traces like torch.jit.trace but with much better support for I think common operations.
And one way it does this is by not really trying to be a compiler for everything. Our
previous sort of attempts with torch.jit.trace and torch.script really tried to capture the
full program graph for your whole neural network. And one of the reasons for this was one is
people I think a lot of people thought that Python in production wasn't practical. Another
bit was that I think there was a lot of interest in sort of running these models on devices
that weren't just CPUs or GPUs. Either upcoming experimental hardware or TPUs or those sorts
of things. And those things might not be able to support Python. So the previous attempts
had these big efforts of trying to capture your whole program as a graph. And if it couldn't
succeed, well then it just didn't work. And that was a real problem because it meant that
users had to change the code. Dynamo relaxes a bit this priority on whole graph capture.
So while Dynamo still supports whole graph capture, that's not really a priority. And
for the common use case, it supports having essentially breaks in your program. What that
means is that if you have some Python operation or call into a third party library that the
compiler doesn't really know how to handle. It just handles the first bit as one graph.
The rest as sort of a black box Python call. And then the remaining PyTorch model as another
graph. So you have this break in the graph and you can't really optimize across it. So
potentially you give up some performance, but it means that it has much better compatibility.
The other bit is that unlike the original trace attempt, it adds a lot of guards to
your code to make sure that when things change, the compiler knows about it and that it can
recompile if necessary. So for example, if your input sizes change, the program doesn't
just fail. It checks that the inputs change or the shapes change and recompiles the program.
So again, you might end up giving up some performance when things aren't quite what
the compiler hoped for or expected for in terms of extra recompilations, but you no
longer give up, your program no longer breaks completely. The way this works is it uses
the frame evaluation API from PEP 523. This is a chart showing, a graph showing sort of
the normal evaluation of a Python function. So it involves both a Python code object which
contains the byte code for Python and the frame object which contains the dynamic execution
and the built-in Python interpreter uses these two things to actually execute your function.
Dynamo sticks itself in between these using the frame evaluation API. First, it takes
the code object and analyzes that function to try and extract a graph of the useful operations.
And the form of the graph is called FX which I think predates Dynamo. There's another compiler.
In fact, there's multiple compilers for PyTorch 2.0 depending on what sort of device, GPU
or CPU or other types of hardware that you're targeting. And the compiler emits both sorts
of the code that's going to be executed on, say, your GPU as well as modifications to
the Python code object. And these modifications are basically the guards we talked about.
So that if the assumptions that the compiler makes, so for example, if your input changes
size or shape or data type, the compiler is able to handle that gracefully by recompiling
rather than either breaking or giving you an incorrect result. And then finally, these
patched objects are handed back to the normal Python interpreter. So it's able to handle
all the sorts of typical Python steps that might be part of your model that aren't really
captured by a PyTorch program, excuse me, that aren't really part of the PyTorch API.
So that's the PyTorch 2.0 compiler. Not quite. The most important bits that I haven't talked
about are all the things that happen after Dynamo. One of these important steps that's
part of PyTorch is ahead of time autograd. And what that does is for neural network
trainings, excuse me, it computes the PyTorch operations that will be needed to back propagate
the loss through your model to actually update the weights in your model. And by doing this
ahead of time, it's able to provide more opportunities for the compiler to optimize these kernels
avoid duplicate code and that sort of thing. And the other really important bit is Torch
Inductor. And this is the part of the compiler that generates the code that runs on your
GPU. And Torch Inductor leverages OpenAI's Triton. I think Triton is probably the other
really important piece that made this compiler a lot more flexible and easier to develop
than previous attempts. One of the challenges with some of the previous attempts, especially
Torch script, was that large bits of the compiler were written in C++. In particular, they were
kind of messy in the way that they integrated into the rest of PyTorch. So it made it both
harder for people who work on PyTorch full time to develop, but also it made it a lot
harder for people to contribute. And Torch Inductor is a compiler written in Python,
which makes it a lot easier both for full time developers of PyTorch as well as external
contributors who might not be as familiar with the code base.
Finally, I'd like to talk a bit about the results. Can you hear me? Okay. I'll try to
avoid the feedback. So one of the reasons I think that this effort was pretty successful,
especially compared to previous efforts, was that early on the PyTorch team collected a
comprehensive set of benchmarks, basically 80 models in the wild, and used this both
for performance measurements, as well as to make sure that the compiler actually works,
that it really supports the code that people are writing in the wild. And I think the results
as of a few weeks ago is about 93% of these 80 models work out of the box without any
changes. And I think the average speed up on A100 GPU is about 43%. And one thing I
want to talk about is that even though PyTorch 2.0, even though it's like a version increment,
it's backwards compatible. You don't have to use Torch.compile. Everything else works
as it did before. All your programs continue to work. So if you've been using PyTorch,
I really encourage you to download PyTorch 2.0, try it out. Try out Torch.compile. Let
us know if you run into issues, if it works well. We're really interested in that. I also
encourage you to consider contributing to PyTorch. It's open source. A lot of development
effort from across the community. And yep, this is the contributing page on the GitHub.
Finally, a few other resources. Sumit gave a great keynote at the PyTorch 2.0 conference.
And we have an active discourse forum on PyTorch, both for support at discuss.pytorch.org,
but also on development of PyTorch itself at dev-discuss.pytorch.org. Thank you. And
these are a lot of links to PyTorch. If you have questions, please use the microphone
in the center of the room.
Okay, I got a question for you about optimizations, which is when you were compiling your codebases,
where did you notice in the codebases the biggest bottlenecks were coming up, and how
did you try to resolve that?
Unfortunately, I don't know. Yeah, although I have worked extensively on PyTorch, I have
not worked extensively on the compiler and have only returned to PyTorch recently.
That would be a great question to take back to the other team folks.
Yep, I will do that. Thanks, everyone.