Hello. So good morning and hope you have all had a coffee. So welcome to the tutorial building
human first and machine friendly CLI applications. So my name is Reka. I work for Sorcery on
various code quality and refactoring tools also in the ID and also in the command line. And I have
been using command line applications for a very long time and the first time when I started to
also develop them from the site was at the previous FinTech job where we created various
internal tools and that's what, that's where I also got to know this command line interface
guidelines which will be one of the major points of the discussion today. I would like to ask you
first of all to install two tools which we will use for today's example. So one is cookie cutter
and the second is poetry. So that would be, so these will be necessary. And then the first thing
I want, would like to mention is that the title says human first which also implies that anytime
any comment, suggestion, idea is very welcome because that should be something which we discuss
what is intuitive and what. So the first step if you have all, the first question I would like to
ask is who is familiar with cookie cutter? Okay, then let's perhaps start with a quick introduction
to cookie cutter itself. So let's just go for, so cookie cutter is basically a tool for creating
project templates and that is exactly what we are going to do in the very first step of our,
in the very first step of our preparations. So the URL what you see here, this cookie cutter,
this is just a GitHub repository and here and what it contains is a cookie cutter JSON file
which defines various project properties and then the other major part of it is this cookie
cutter project name directory and this is in ginger syntax and what will happen is that when
we run this cookie cutter then it will generate for us a project following that template. So the
first, first I would like to start with, start with omitting this parameter for replay file and
see what happens if I just run cookie cutter. So cookie cutter and then the URL of a repository
containing a cookie cutter, so this can be a URL or it can be also local directory and then what
happens that it starts to ask me for various properties, for example what's the name of my
project and if I said it's PyCon catalog then for the next property it will already suggest a name
based on that and if we could interactively fill in various fields, so if you saw the JSON file
there are like ten different fields, we could just all fill them and create a project so that
that's the basic usage how you use cookie cutter most of the time and what I would like to ask you
to do instead now is to run this command which is here and here we pass this replay file option
to the cookie cutter and what will, oh, sorry, oh yes so I should follow my own advice and see
that this cookie cutter talk JSON so this is here in the project skeleton directory so please
pass, so this is a file here in this project skeleton directory so if you run it somewhere
else then please adjust the pass of it and I'm sorry
yes
so and what now happens and please tell me if it's working for you as well is that now we just
generate a project based on that based on that template and now if we navigate to this PyCon
catalog, an directory here we can already see that we have now Python so we have generated a
poetry command line project here so as a first step so have you got that far first question
so that's a good point so the command is here and I would like so I would like to suggest to first
of all clone this repository this PyCon 2023 because that's the easiest way so the repository
is github.com reka CLI tutorial PyCon 2023 and here it is important that you have this cookie
cutter talk JSON file and this is the command which we should run and don't commit the same
mistake which I did that running the so adjust to the pass of this of this talk JSON please
it couldn't find poetry yes then do you have poetry installed okay that's a good question
why it might be what happens if you go navigate to the directory like here can you run poetry shell
here yes so the script didn't do too much just so the so the older poet
it just did a poetry install so and that's actually also a very good point which
which we have just heard so
sorry oh okay that's my my mistake so in that case in that case it means that you have already
generated the project and it but it doesn't run with but but it has it can't run is that correct
sorry okay
three nine okay
so
so if you have Python three nine then I would like to ask you to go to this project in the
generated project so in the in this Python catalog to the project and here at line 11 we are setting
the minimum Python version and this is what should be changed please if it's not so sorry
that's my mistake that three time was probably a bit too high to set this
so is it have we got that far with whichever Python version oh okay what are the other
problems with the setup a custom search pass sorry what do you mean oh I have to admit I
have no idea okay my suggestion would be to just carry on with some of the demo so with some of
demonstrations here and then in the first break we can perhaps troubleshoot some of the installation
issues I'm sorry if it turned out to be more complicated than I assumed and what I would like
to show around is this little bit what we have just generated in this in this application so
here we have we have a Python poetry application with a type of CLI so I will just activate poetry
shell first so if you have managed to let that please follow along and then the first thing which
we can we can see is this Python that that there is this Python catalog script which we can run and
with the help we can see what kind of subcommands and things we have here and we have one subcommand
which is which is the this talk and here we can and we can just install the same poetry install
and and then look look around here a little bit in the in the generated project so what so here
in the set in the set in this script this is a the first important setting here we can be defined
that this Python catalog this should run this app defined in the in the cell in the CLI app module
and the code for this can be found here and I just need to set the temperature and here we can see the various
so here we can see only this one version command that we saw and then the real bulk of the
application this can be found here in the in this talk CLI module and and first and here we we will
have various commands for creating updating deleting talks and and things like that okay
so
the next thing I wanted to show is this is this command line interface guidelines so this is this
is a site called CLIG dot dev and I really recommend it I really recommend its reading
but it's a quite I would say a lot of a lot of material is there and first of all I wanted to
ask your opinion about what do you what do you think about what can be about this philosophy and
principles which this mentions so human first design and simple what does that mean for you
for a command line application yes it has to be intuitive yes sorry well documented yes yes that's
a that's a very good point consistent okay what does consistency so where does consistency come
from what are what are the sources of consistency one way to do things yes that's that's interesting
okay consistency is indeed one of the points which they mentioned it to the use what are the
usages usually of a of a command line application so in which settings care is it used sorry
in the coma yeah
the humans who are familiar with computers yes that's a that's actually a very interesting
point because that's I think one thing which CLIG argues that many of these applications
are super intuitive if you are already familiar with this and less approachable for what we
know so so yes that's exactly one of those points and I would like to jump to this basics
first so so the whole guide is structured in a way that there are let's say four things which
they say should always be followed and then there are other additional steps or additional
recommendations which they say that okay it's nice to follow those but these are the basics
which we should always stick to and here use a command line argument parsing library where
you can this is exactly what we have done in our example so if we go back here so so what we use
here in the is typer in our in our project and this is and the one reason why I'm sorry so the
one reason why the CLIG suggests us to use to like typer or whatever library all the time is
because that way a lot of the other recommendations which they have will be automatically there and
actually that's also the reason why I suggest not just using the CLIG and typer or IPERS are really
all very fine tools but also to use a cookie cutter because that way a lot of the things are
already pre-generated in a way which is which is practical for us and we don't need to so we don't
need to add the same elements for many many applications so all the time so I saw this
following you using a command line parsing library that's something which I really even
for the smallest and finest projects I really recommend so now I want to get back again to
our brief exploration here so we have looked at the help and then we can also look at the
help of the talk command and one thing which I would like to point out that I haven't written
so that the this code what we have here doesn't really contain any infrastructure for all this so
all the help text for example what you can see are coming from these doc strings and that is that
is all created by created by typer so that is one of the major reasons why I say I think that it's
a cool idea to use such a such a library because these things all just come with without any
additional need for for setup or whatever and then I just want to explore a little bit further
that for example we can also look at the help of this command where we can see that okay you can
create many you can create a new token these are the parameters which it gets and if we
look at it again if you look at the edit it has also very similar parameters and that's
where where probably this consistency point comes into the comes into the picture that we
these these things should really look quite quite similar okay so
as a next point I would like to ask you to all of you who already have managed to set this up to
try to install a shell completion for this tool which we already have so let's say that we have
we have three minutes for this exercise so if you have already set this up and installed please
try to figure out how to install a shell completion for this you have feel free to discuss it and
sorry how I get there I generated this project with cookie cutter
for the oh that it's main where is it coming from that's an excellent question so if everything
event as planned then this should come from the cookie cutter so the post-generation
script of the cookie cutter contains so here in this post-generation we theoretically also
created a git repository and if that if something went wrong perhaps it was the the poetry part
to run correctly so the poetry installation for you sorry you think so okay yes so if you
are in the Python catalog directory now I so if you are in the Python catalog directory can
you see all the help send this stuff there okay and I just out of curiosity is it a
GitHub repository also do you know that so if you run it for this real completion okay good
question so in one of those helps so I theoretically the help should contain some instructions how to
install shell completion but the help for the root command by concatalogic self yes
okay so I think that it's it's time to discuss this so if we look at
PyCon catalog dash dash help then besides the version for which we saw the code here
and so this version this is a this is an option defined in our code but there are two other options
here as well install completion and show completion and if everything goes as planned then this install
completion this this should install shell completion and this will be very handy as you follow along
and do some do some playing around this will you will get the completion for order comments sorry
that is exactly that is coming from typer so that is why we don't even have code for it
excellent question the excellent point that is the caveat that this install completion works fine
most of the time and for example I use z shell and there it that didn't really so it didn't work out
of the box but what I can do instead there is also this show completion and if I add it to my to my
zshrc then it actually works for that's why it works for me so there are these are so the major
the default way to install the shell completion is with dash dash install completion and if that
doesn't work and you know that you are using a custom shell then this is the second way how to
try this show completion and then by appended to the
so has it been successful for okay cool then I would like to explore this project a little bit
more and I would like to just show again these help desks help texts which we have looked at so
there is a create hub there is an edit hub and I'm not sure whether you have noticed but I made
the mistake there there are so these various texts here this contained underscores which
probably isn't too nice so I would like to ask you to so the next exercise is please find the
place where this is configured in the in the code and adjust the help desk help text for all these
various options so five minutes let's say for this
yes that sounds like a good candidate
so
So.
So in the meantime, if you have any questions or any, so still things with the setup, then please, please let me know. We can look at it.
Yes.
I'm looking at anaconda, I have seen that with the install conditional.
Oh.
Which I'll comment in the description. I'm sorry, I'm struggling online, but have you ever seen that before?
No, I don't know. But instead, if you know where your configuration file is, similar to the ZSHRC, which I had, I don't know whether or not I'm a conda chef. You have something like that?
Then.
Because so instead, install completion, try to invoke it with show completion.
I'm not sure.
Sorry?
I'm not sure it is there.
So here, but here where you said install completion, instead, say dash dash show completion.
Oh, OK.
And if you run something else, like Python catalog dash dash help, what happens?
That's fine.
That's fine. OK.
I'm sorry, I am not that familiar with anaconda, but it's not that important. It's just convenient if you don't need to type that much.
So.
Have you managed to update these names? Any ideas where to look for it and how to adjust those?
Yes.
The help text of.
OK, exactly.
So at line 20, we have defined this short name option, and if I replace it with a base, then it is fixed.
And.
Here as well.
Here, perhaps it's better even that way.
Yes.
So, and if I now run this again.
Then, of course, it has been adjusted. So thanks. That's exactly the right answer. And here I want to point out one thing.
So the main reason why I was showing this exercise is that if we look at this code in the talk CLI, we didn't really edit the command.
So we didn't do anything with the add or the edit command. Instead, what we the trick what we are using here is that we have defined an option in.
In the space of this talk CLI module, and then we can see that this short name option is actually what we reference both in the create and in the edit commands.
And when I was showing the CLI G and asking for asking about, hey, what, what are some nice properties of an application?
And when somebody mentioned a very good point consistency, I really want to point out this feature from and this possibility from type.
The type of options are under the hood.
Not actually are Python objects, and you can define them and reuse them and say that, OK, I have two commands at it and create.
They are very closely related, so probably they should use the same options.
And one great point about this is that it is, of course, less code duplication, but it also also makes the application immediately more consistent.
Any idea what is the biggest advantage of this? So also biggest.
So besides having nice, consistent help text, what is what is another benefit of this using of sharing options?
So, but I sorry, perhaps the question was phrased in the wrong way.
So what we have just seen is that because we share this option, so we defined a short name option here and then both create and edit just reference it.
And this helped us with the help text that it is nice and consistent, and it needs to be edited only once.
I my opinion is that the help text is the smaller benefit, and there is an even bigger one.
Sorry, a bit louder.
So thanks a lot for this very good point.
So, yeah, exactly. There is one central place to make it instead of needing to update multiple things and very easy, very easy to oversee them, unfortunately.
And what I would like to point out that this is true not only for the help text, which we have just edited, but just as much also for the option name itself.
So if I am just defining the options here in the command itself, then it could anytime happen that in one place I say, let's say short name, and in the other one I write it as one word, and then the next one it is just called name or whatever.
So it could easily happen if we define all of them separately, that even the option name is not consistent, and having them defined at one place, this is exactly how, so this is one good technique for making them the same everywhere.
My next question is that there are some other, so here at the beginning of the file I have defined only short name and short name duration, and so these properties related to the various fields.
And I would like, but if we look at the help, there are some other options, so this plain and JSON, which we are going to play then in the next session.
And where are these coming from? So where does the create command get those last three options from?
Yes, exactly. And for this application this is a small overkill, because we have actually most of our logic is in this talk CLI, but generally I think it's a very good pattern to see.
So we say that okay, we have the common options, which contain things which are, actually these options you could have in any kind of command line application, it isn't specific for anything.
And then in the talk CLI we define the options which are really talk specific, like the duration of the talk and YouTube video ID and stuff like that.
So, and actually this is also one of the reasons why I started with Cookie Cutter. One thing is that I really recommend this. So this should be perhaps one of the, this was one of the main lessons of this workshop, that consistency is very variable, and one really good tool to achieve it is using the template like Cookie Cutter.
And the second thing is which we can really nicely observe, I think if we use such a template, that many of the, that a lot of the stuff which we have here is actually very, very common and can be used in many different domains.
And then the things which are really specific for talks and this application, so we can focus on them much more if we use a template like Cookie Cutter.
So, yes, this is where all options came from. So some of them are defined here in the common options and some, and the talk specifics here in the talk CLI.
And then one thing I would like to suggest before the break and before we are starting to actually add data to this application, and we did that right now.
So the application will use a SQLite database as a storage, and we should set up our development environment, a separate development database.
So again, this is an exercise, so please in the next two, three minutes look around in that project and try to figure out how to set up, how to configure a development database.
In for that exercise, it's not, so yes, this should be found somewhere in the internal documentation of the project.
And this should be a test whether the intuitive part, which was mentioned by one audience member, how much it fulfills this requirement.
Yes, so config.pi is.
So there was one very good comment that config.pi is something very relevant for this indeed.
Mm hmm.
So there was a question whether it's a good approach to define a second database for development database.
This has some drawbacks because we want to use this database the very same way in development and production environment, but it needs to talk to another database.
That is what we want to achieve.
And then there is a third environment, which we probably should keep in mind, and this is test.
And the way how I recommend to do it is here in the described in the readme that if we look at this config, it uses PIDENTIC.
So it uses the settings class from PIDENTIC to define the path of this database.
And PIDENTIC has, and this setting has this possibility to refer to an environment variable with this mOptional parameter.
So the way to set up the development databases, which I recommend, is to change the value of this environment variable, Python catalog DB pass.
And this is what is also described in this generated readme that before we add and manipulate any data, we set this.
And for a workshop like this, it is not such an important thing to do because otherwise we would write into this default database.
Okay, not such a big problem.
This step is, I think, very important if you are developing a command line application for own usage.
Like let's say you would have a similar thing, but not for PyCon talks, but for your books.
And in the first version, perhaps you develop something and have a kind of working version, which you start to use on a day to day basis.
And then afterwards you start adding new features, experimenting, and then it's very easy to mix it up.
And that's a point where it's very useful to distinguish between development and so to say production environment.
And so that's why I recommend this adding as a next step.
And then if we consider there is a third very important environment, and this is the test environment.
And of course, when I go here and run these 20 tests, I don't want them to put any data into my real database.
And for that, we can use a PyText fixture. Who is familiar with PyText fixtures?
Okay, so then I am not going to discuss that in great length, but for this kind of SQLite storage, this is probably the easiest way to have a fixture we don't know how to use.
And then we have set up our test environment.
Okay.
And now that we have seen a little bit around in our application, I will just commit the changes with the update help text.
And then I would suggest that before we add some data and play around with this a bit more, let's have a 15 minute break.
And if you have any questions regarding the setup or whatever, then please come to me in the break and we'll try to figure it out.
I think that so far we have mainly just looked around.
So if you want to catch up, the important and if you got stuck somewhere, the important step is really this to generate the project.
And the second thing which I would suggest is that I will just upload the repository as it is now in my environment.
And then if you have difficulties with the cookie cutter or whatever setup you can clone the repository directly and then use that instead of trying to generate it.
Oh, okay.
That's okay.
What were those changes?
Yeah, yeah.
Okay.
Okay, so we are having a break and we will continue at 10 10 please.
So should we continue?
So thanks a lot for the good questions in the break.
So here you can find this repository with the current code.
So if you if the code generation with cookie cutter didn't work correctly for whichever reason, then this is a way to so this is a possibility to just clone this repository and continue working with that version.
And then there was another great question about these.
These resource which we have discussed here the CLI G site.
I have added a link to this as well.
So what I would like us to do next is to explore a little bit this create command which we have.
And I would like and so the first exercise would be to add some add some talks to this repository and see so discover what are the various possibilities of adding this.
So like.
Let's just say take three minutes three minutes and try to use the create command and add some talks and see how that how that command works.
Good question.
Not so the question was whether it should be Python catalog create.
Well, I would suggest that.
To each talk create. Yes. And I'm just.
So.
So let's just.
Look here.
And if we look at that, that helps.
So hopefully that.
Would be the discover.
So.
Exactly.
Pick one from the from the schedule schedule I see.
So short name.
Let's say it's Python syntactic sugar.
Then speaker name is.
And the title is.
And I don't know how long it will take because this talk will be only on Saturday.
And.
We have created.
And how exactly how.
How thank you for pointing it out.
Of creating.
Creating a talk says that instead of passing in interactively.
We we can pass in options.
And say, for example, there is another token Saturday, which is called Python in terms of Python intercept scale.
And if I just pass in this option passing this, it also created a created a talk for us.
Why does it why does it make sense?
So what's what's the reason?
Why did we buy did we choose this set up for?
So these two possibilities.
Yes, you can automate.
That is a very, very important point.
And this is actually where.
So if I if I organized this workshop in a more theoretical way, that would be the very, very first thing which I pointed out, which is also in the title of this.
Of the of this session that human friendly and.
And machine friendly applications.
And this interactivity is one of the major patterns which I would like you to have as a takeaway from this from this session.
And it is it is actually again, I get back to this common line interface guidelines, which I would like to point out.
This is a so this has been this is an open source guideline.
It has been written by a community.
So I'm just keep referencing it because it's I think it's great.
But it's not so it's not it's generally a good resource and not specific to this workshop.
And here there are various principles around conversation as the norm.
For example, that if even if some required parameter is missing, it's a good idea to prompt for it, assuming that it's a human using it.
And also this interactivity point.
And this is exactly what we are going to discover a bit now in the code.
And my question is any ideas where this related part can be found in the code?
So.
Where should I go?
So if we look in this talk, see, I.
Here, for example, both for the create.
And for the and then also for several other comments, we also have defined an option.
This interactive flag, it also comes from those from those common options, which are the.
From those common options, which which we have discussed.
So from from this way and it is by default true.
And this regulates whether these whether this kind of prompts are shown.
So, for example, if I get back now.
And.
So if I just say to create and then I will be prompted for various for various properties instead, if I say to create no input.
Then suddenly I get an error.
Or also, if I say.
If I say.
To create no interactive.
So here we can see that these are so this is also a nice functionality font type or that we can define multiple synonyms for one option.
And this helps with the consistency in the sense that there are unfortunately several things where there is no real standard terminology for it.
And multiple people may find something else as intuitive.
So this is this is a good way to provide my options and.
And one important idea behind this is that we can have multiple ways how we call these scripts.
So one very obvious, obvious ways to some human sitting there and typing stuff.
Then there is another possibility that we we want to use it in a in a string of scripts.
And in that case, of course, we don't provide.
We don't want to provide prompts.
Instead, we want to rely on options being passed and everything.
Working automatically.
This is for that a very common use cases, continuous integration systems, for example.
That.
That this.
I'm sorry.
So yeah.
And then I want to emphasize this.
This.
So this is coming from the Python standard library.
This standard input is.
Whether it's a terminal and if it's if it's not, then we don't even look at the interactive flag.
We just assume that, OK, we can't expect a human to provide an input.
And I want to just get back to the.
To the code of this create command.
If you call if you pipe something into the standard input, then it will be false.
So if you call it from a script, I would suggest to add and you don't want to get prompt.
Then I then add the no interactive or no input flags.
And here, if we now look and look at the code a bit, then.
Then we can see that first we try to figure out whether any fields have been provided in the first place.
So for this we use this get field values function.
And again, I want to point out a very important feature from type for this.
And this is this context.
So if we.
Just go back there.
You can see that the first.
Argument of this create function is a type of is a type of context.
And this contains among other orders, all the arguments and options that have been passed.
And this is what we use in this get field values method.
And this is the post method where we look at the.
So we get to the options from the from the context.
And here is the important distinction that if we are not in an interactive mode, then.
We just exit with an error.
And if otherwise, if we are in interactive mode, then.
We ask the user for further fields.
And in order to do that, we use this prompt from the this is coming from the library reach.
And this gives us a convenient way to store all the various field names that are provided and.
That.
OK.
My next.
Next question about this is.
That here we.
So here we got some some error.
What are the important ways to distinguish an error from a from a from a successful outcome?
So how how can we see whether a comment has been successful?
Sorry, I didn't hear that.
The colors of the prompt. Yes, that's a very good point.
The exit code. Yes, that's also.
That's also.
Standard error. Yes, exactly.
That's what those were exactly the answers I was looking at looking for.
And I would like to switch back to these basics where last time we mentioned that we have already.
Followed the very first basic guideline by using Typer and these are and other so-called basics which we should really follow in even in the very small and not and not frequently used command line scripts.
These are these two things.
So the first is to return zero exit code on success, non zero on failure.
And then the second one is that distinguishing between the different types of output.
So standard out and and standard error.
And yes.
Map the map the non zero exit codes to the most important failure modes.
Yes, that's a good.
That's a great question.
As far as I remember, the guideline doesn't contain further suggestions.
And I have to admit that in this regard, this cookie cutter we are working at is also a bit lazy because anytime there is an error, I think it returns one.
But I would say that the so again, it depends on the use case.
But the very general guideline, which we can say for any kind of command line application, whatever that zero on access, zero on success, non zero on on any kind of failure.
And then how that kind, what types of failure exist and how to group them and what is a meaningful coding for them there?
It's more difficult to give some general advice because it very much depends on what your application is doing.
And what I would like to point out here, how this happens in the code.
So if, for example, if we didn't receive any input and we are in not interactive mode, then we call this exit.
So there is this exit with error function.
And here come here come the two other points, which the two other people mentioned.
So one is that we write to the standard error.
And then the second is that we use this red color, which is, of course, optional.
But I think that it is a really nice feature from rich and usually whatever we.
So, so, so what, whatever we print with the rich interface, we can always provide some styling.
I'm I'm usually very careful with it.
And one caveat is that especially if the application is intended for many users, they might use many different terminals with various settings.
So with the back to this, having some red, for example, for error, that is a good standard, so to say.
And then we also return the type of exit.
And it is the important part that this code has by default.
So the value one and so not zero value.
And this is one thing I have to admit that for a for a while it was for me difficult to remember that.
OK, what is success? What is fair?
What is the value zero?
So like zero, like nothing.
It means success.
It it was a bit unintuitive for me for a while.
And then yes.
Remember, there's only one way to succeed.
Exactly. That was exactly that was when when I remembered it that for failure, we have many, many different ways how that can happen.
And talking about success and failure, the next thing I would like to check out is the.
The next thing I would like to check out is our tests.
And here, for example, for this create command, we have some basic tests where we run only.
Only so we provide only the short name and then we check the two important things to check that the exit code is zero.
The only check that there is something in the standard out.
And yes.
Yes, that's a good question.
I don't know.
Now we have tried that, tried out multiple people.
So if has anybody seen something strange instead of the emoji after creating a talk?
So, I mean, it's absolutely not a non-representative simple.
I agree with you that it is it depends very much on the intended audience of the tool, whether you want to add it.
I think that often it's nice and often it's more concise way of explaining something.
Well, in that case, it's just a decoration.
But, for example, if something was successful, then having a checkmark emoji is often more informative than.
Adding something like done or whatever text so you can see the better.
But I absolutely agree that that it is not always a good idea.
And my next question is that if we look at the output of create again, I just scrolled this up a bit for a successful create actually.
We can see that. So now we can see that there is this new talk created text and then some other stuff.
And this new talk created is in the standard error and the other stuff is in the standard out.
And my question is again, why?
Exactly.
Exactly. That's the point that I just look back here to the exact phrasing that log messages are sent.
This these things should go to the standard error and these should not be fed into the next command.
And again, I would like to go back to our two different types of users, the humans and the various tools that having some kind of some kind of output that is so like a success message or even a failure message that is very valuable for a human who is sitting there and wants to see what happens.
And but of course, we don't want it to the outcome. And for that, the standard input standard out standard error distinction is a very good, very good tool to do.
And I just want to jump back a bit to this until and show that in the so for each with setting the standard or to true.
That is the way how we can create a standard error console and then right to there.
And one thing which surprised me and I would like to show it for this reason is that for the tests we use this CLI runner, which is also provided by type or and and here by default the standard out and standard error are mixed together.
So if if we want to have separate assertions in the test for standard out and standard error, then you have to provide this mixed STD are false.
When you create the CLI runner instance, I think that it's more logical with the so to test the two things separately.
But but yes, this is how I work.
And and one thing I also want to point out that in the tests.
So in so in the tests, we again see that this non interactive possibilities very valuable because testing the prompts is much more complicated.
And if you just want to have a quick verification that OK, did we manage to create something or no, it's with these options, you have much more much more flexibility there.
So.
With that in mind, my the next exercise would be to please add some more test cases.
So some more test cases to this create command and.
Come up with some ideas, but as would be worth testing.
So let's say let's have five minutes for this.
So.
So what kind of test cases have you come up with and.
It screams at you.
OK.
That's a good one.
Some other ideas.
Mm hmm.
It fails. OK.
Some other points.
So those are two very good, very good ideas.
One thing I think is perhaps often so often overseen is that.
It might make sense to add some more success test cases.
So if we look at here, it is already a parameterized test, but it has only one.
Only one.
So instead, so I would and the only test case which we test here now is that we provide the short name.
This is the only required field and nothing else, which is great, but it might absolutely make sense to provide some more.
Very data and try to figure out and try to check that.
OK, for example, what happens if I provide both the title and.
And the short name is that is that also possible.
So.
If they just go down and.
Now.
OK, sorry.
Oh, I'm missing a comma here.
I'm here for a little time, please.
Yes.
Sorry.
Oh, I think, yes, I have done the parameterizing wrong.
You are absolutely right. Thanks a lot.
And now.
Sorry, does it expect.
I'm not sure about that.
I think.
Yes, so this is the right syntax that the.
For the test cases, this should be in couples and then the.
Parameters of info should go into the list.
And regarding the inbox, I would like to point out one more funny behavior.
Which is.
For example, if we look at this test, so this is a test case for the view command and it tests that what happens if we create something with an already existing short name.
And.
So, so not to not create, sorry. So if we view something with.
If you view something with an existing ID, that is what I saw.
Then this.
Then here it is very important to have this as tier before the ID, because all the so all the.
Or the imp parameters provided to this invoke needs to be strings.
So if it if I just provide the ID as an integer, then it will fail even if.
That itself is a valid command.
So, yes, but so this is this is one of the things which surprised me with the inbox and I wanted to mention it.
I am wondering whether you have other tips ideas about the.
About this command line testing module.
And yes.
Sorry, so and then I just wanted to get back to our create tests and the two points which were mentioned verbose very, very good points.
So the so one thing was that if we try to create something with the very same ID.
With the very same short name which we have just created, then it complains.
And the other one was that OK, for the duration, we shouldn't input a text.
It should be a number. And my next question to both of these would be why varies that configured.
So where in this code can not in a test, but where in the production code are these things configured.
In the models, yes.
That's a very good point.
So we mentioned the duration total seconds.
And and yes, here this is just config configured just with the.
With the data type, so.
Nothing special, so so to say, and where is this configured that the show that we can't create a talk with an already existing short name.
Sorry.
Yes, exactly, exactly.
So.
So there we have a.
We have this function to initialize the database, and here we also create a unique index for the short name, which leads me to our next topic.
This short name.
What is the function of this? So why? Why do we have that?
Because yes, the title and the duration. These are really real properties of the talk that the talk usually has a title and.
Yes, yes.
Yes, yes. So if we.
If we go and.
List with at least this with LS.
Then we should be seeing only the short name.
That is so bad. What else is the function? So why is it better than the title or better?
So obviously it's not better, but what? Why do we have it if we have a title anyway?
And hopefully we wouldn't have too many talks with the same title. Yes.
Sorry, I haven't heard that.
Human readable.
Yes, so I am trying to summarize. Please correct me so that it is human readable. That's a very big advantage of it.
And it is, but it can be also used by tools. They may also because of this convention that we use hyphens in it and that it's for humans perhaps easier to read than just a numeric identifier. Yes.
It accepted. Yes, so there is no validation for it. That's a good point. So if we look at the.
At the models, it only just says the the length, but exactly the purpose of this identifier is as you said that it's a it's human readable and but it can be also.
Processed by by tools and if we now I just want to show that it's not only the LS which uses it, but so when we try out this view command.
Let's just see the help first what it says.
So here we need to provide an identifier for the view and this identifier can be the ID or the short name.
And so if I say one.
Or if I say instead.
Python.
Synthetic.
Sugar.
It.
It has exactly the same result and this should have a good should have that advantage that instead of so now with this example it's a bit funny because yes, we need numbers like one and two.
Obviously we can.
So it's easier to keep them in mind, but if you have a like my significantly bigger bigger numbers and more complex and first it's nice to have something.
Human readable readable additionally and the way and the quick way to refer to them, which is probably more convenient than using the whole title.
Okay.
My next question is about this view command that as we have seen it has.
Both arguments and options and.
What do you think about that design and and for the create we had only the options.
So what what are your thoughts on that when when should we use arguments when should we use options.
Yeah.
Yes, arguments are mandatory.
Well, the options here for that command, they are all for controlling output.
I completely agree.
If we look at the other command create here, we chose to have options for the input as well, which.
Is one of the things that we have to do.
So I'm not saying it has to be that way all the time, but we we we chose.
So what might be a reason reason for this setup or generally what are so when is an option and when is when is an argument to be preferred.
Mm hmm.
So what might be a reason reason for this setup or generally what are so when is an option and when when is an argument to be preferred.
Preferred.
Yes, yes, that's I think that the type of documentation even has it that arguments are usually mandatory.
There is a way in type to define optional arguments.
I would say you have to have a very strong reason to do it because it's really against all the conventions of having.
Having over arguments as much as much as optional and then the other.
Sorry, so the other thing is that with the options, they are usually optional.
But for example, in that case with the create, I decided to have the short name also as option for two reasons.
And one is to be consistent with the other fields because it might be a bit confusing if you enter this in one way and the other another way.
The second thing is that it is more explicit because that way I have to sort of say type the option name as well.
It's more visible, but it does.
And then there is a third reason, which is related to this, which is not relevant for this very small example, but really to this being explicit that let's assume that it's not a.
It's a more complex model with three mandatory string fields.
In that case, I would definitely go for three options instead of arguments because probably there is no intuitive order of those three mandatory arguments.
So my general, I would say on this would be that yes, if we have only one real parameter and it's fairly easy to guess.
So let's say intuitive. Somebody use this word.
What this thing might be, then it's probably fine as an argument.
And if we have more things, especially more things with a similar rule, like for the creator, then it's better to go for options.
And I am curious what you think about this setup for the identifier.
So for the view that it accepts both the numeric ID and this other short name.
So what are the what are the pros and cons of this design?
Yes.
The other is that you could imagine you talk to you.
Having multiple.
Identify or seven or three.
So all of them.
So.
Yes.
If it has a space, you have to put it into quotes.
Another idea would be that adding a validation that we only allow some specific format for this short name that.
I mean, that's kind of the other thing that was.
If the name of the.
Forty two.
Sometimes the name of the video is a number.
Yes, I mean, especially in that case, that short name is something constructed by us.
By us, we could theoretically add on.
It would probably really make sense to add another validation that it shouldn't be just an integer because that that really leads to leads to confusion.
That's a very good point.
I haven't thought about that.
And yes, that thing with the multiple arguments.
It's possible.
So type are definitely supported with the view.
I would be.
I don't know.
I associate view with exactly one, but it might be just so.
I don't have a strong opinion.
It's so to say.
Yes, I'm just.
OK.
So I think it's now time for another break.
If you.
Leave it that.
Should we meet at 1116?
Cool.
And thanks a lot for the great.
Participation.
I plan was to look at the command, which we haven't discussed, at least not in depth so far.
And this one is the is the LS command, which right now only this this place.
This first question is yes.
Why?
So I think everyone.
Awesome question that would have been later on the agenda, but let's discuss it now.
So what do you what do you think?
What are so now we also see all these various names on the on the screen.
What do you think about this naming?
Yes.
Right now order isn't.
I think it is possible to add it.
That's a that's a very good point that having an alias for for something more expressive is a is a good idea.
What else?
It's like universally known.
Like if someone's using a CLI, they probably know what else is.
Yes.
That that's a good very good point about conventions and whatever.
So I assumed that LS is something which is known.
That's why I picked it.
But it's a good question.
How universally it is known.
And again, my question is who the audience is of the specific application.
And one thing which CLI G of also mentions that multiple places that especially if it is so so that especially if a tool is meant for people who are perhaps not not that not that of a use other command line tools, it might make sense to go for the longer and more expressive options.
So to say and it doesn't exclude.
That was a very good point that we can always have aliases for for multiple different different cities.
There was one more.
You also had your hands up, I think.
Yes.
That's actually also very good point that it's not as much about naming but about the what the output is, which will be our next topic.
So if we look at, for example, create it has all the various fields as an option for variation.
It makes sense.
But I have seen in a similar manner.
We could have options for LS as well.
So like just ever providing every single field and then having and then show showing all the tools which are there, which are provided here.
I would like to mention that it's a bit dangerous, depending on what your application is, because even I think even with that kind of.
So so this kind of model, if I really show all the various fields and assuming they are filled, of course, but if I really show all of them, it might might be a bit too long, might get a bit too long.
But actually, the next exercise, which I want to ask you to do is a bit less ambitious than showing all the various fields and making it configurable.
But instead, just adding the title for to the output.
So how did it go?
And where where did we add and what?
Yes.
One oh seven.
Just a sec.
Sorry.
I want to.
Yes, exactly.
So very first thing, perhaps to point out about this.
Yes, that was.
Yes, yes, exactly.
So that was.
Was.
But the first thing I want to point out that there were two.
So this so this L.S. command also has some options for sorry.
So for in which format to show and the way how the Jason was implemented, it already showed everything.
But in the.
But for the default and for the and for the plain ways, we have to.
So so so that's where we we wanted to add to the title.
OK, so let's start perhaps with the easier one, which is which one was the easier if you did both.
Sorry.
The second one, yes.
OK, and why?
So how did you approach that?
Exactly.
So that was one more column to be added to this title.
And then in the row, adding the item title and we are ready.
And these are actually the two big advantages of the library rich, which provides this table.
And also, by the way, for the markdown, which we see in the view command.
And and the so these are the two big advantages.
One of them is that it's it looks very nice.
And the second one is that it's relatively easy to add because we just add one more column to the land.
Everything is and which figures out everything around spacing and that what was to do with the with the other part with the plane.
I already heard something about column with.
So, yes. So here in this line, we define what we guess because it's more or less a guess how long these things will be.
And the so so that that we add a new column.
So it's not sorry, not a new column, but just a new bit.
And then when we actually print the results here, we had to add the new for the item item.
Yeah. So for each line.
And I tried to follow the same pattern as for the short name.
And I am wondering why, why is that or why is this or empty string necessary?
Yes, exactly, because it's optional.
And if we just add it into the without any adjustment, it is an error.
So this is also something with the built in table component.
It's fairly straightforward.
So with the rich table component, it is all straightforward and takes care of it with our.
So that that way we need to provide it to ourself.
My question is that if it is so easy and nice to create the output above,
why did I bother creating this ugly thing below that?
Sorry, I didn't.
Yes, I like both answers, although I am not.
So, so yes, I agree that that the rich is a cool tool for this.
But but the major demand.
The reason was that this is the one which is easier to parse.
And for example, this could be piped into a command like a WK or whatever.
And then I think some something out and then parsing this output further with other tools.
And this pattern, which and which one we like better is as a user or even as a developer,
we actually don't necessarily need to choose.
And that's why these options are great that we can say that, OK, by default,
we pick we pick this one and then we also provide something less complicated.
One thing which I also would like to mention is it is less for the table.
But so the more complicated and nicer the default output get,
the more reason the more sense it makes to also provide some plain because, for example,
I had it once with a tool which outputs YAML and there is a really nice so syntax highlighting
and everything, which is the default output.
But unfortunately, it does it depending on the color settings of your terminal.
It works better or not so well.
And for for this kind of use case, it's really good to provide just a plain option that if something
doesn't go as planned, the user always has the opportunity to output it with dash dash plain.
And and my next exercise would be also related to this topic.
I would like to ask you to use some command, whichever, to count the numbers.
So the talks in this table.
And so the goal would be to output to at the end in some way.
And probably for that, we will also use the plain option in in some capacity.
But please, please take a look at that.
Let's say in five minutes.
I do is guaranteed to be always an integer.
Yes. So if we look at the in the both in the model and in the crowd, it is defined.
So now I am curious to hear which ways have you come up with to do it.
Come up with to get to two on the screen. Yes.
OK, cool. So let's just also show.
So so I'm just repeating in the mic.
So he saw this was a great point that because the.
So because the headers are printed to standard error and the rest to us to standard out, we can use the.
Yeah, sorry. Thank you.
So and plain.
And we can use the word count and the shell, which counts the lines and we get to.
And as you pointed out, very well, this is because the headers and separator are on the standard.
I don't understand that error. So what else?
That was.
Ah, OK. OK, so you modify the code to bring to.
OK, that is also.
Also, good, a good way to do that.
What else?
So I what I have come up with was exactly this same solution with word count.
And I just want to show that if we if we just execute word count, we know it counts six lines, because in order to construct this nice table,
the lot of other things are printed as well.
So and and for the cheese and this this can be used for piping.
And then the second very important thing, which you pointed out to that in order to make a plane so compatible with this word count,
we also had to do a.
Do a bit of a trick.
And and in order and for that.
We.
We said that we will we are going to bring us so we said that we are going to print a header to this standard error console and then everything else to the to the standard to the standard out and.
My so I just would like to go back to the place where we are, which we have looked at various times today, and it's not a coincidence that.
I. Sorry.
Yes, so here exactly to this command line interface guidelines basics that this kind of rules like the where so this one that being very conscious about what to put the standard out, what to standard error that might seem a bit.
So sometimes sometimes a bit too strict about exactly if we.
We follow this it might it enables us such capabilities as this one.
And one so.
Yes.
Because.
What.
And.
Like.
But.
For.
Right now exactly that's a very good point how would you mitigate it.
And.
that out, put all those together. So the fact that some of the table
is going to standard error and some to standard out, also you have to
worry about flooding the first as well.
Standard error is unbuffered.
Standard error is unbuffered, but standard error unbuffered is
good. It seems like you're adding, I guess I'd like to go
with the principle of least surprise.
...
Yes, that's a very good point.
I mean, one thing I could imagine to mitigate it
is to provide options again.
So yet another way that even saying that the header
is optional, and in that case if it's added, then
it's added to the standard out. If it isn't added, then we can use
word count. So that would be probably a nicer and, I agree,
more consistent way.
...