Good afternoon everyone. Thank you so much for joining me here today.
So a little bit about me before we get started. I am Chief Technology Officer at Research
Affiliates, a finance firm located in Newport Beach, California. I've been programming in
Python since the year 2000. And back then I was doing work on my team to give me the
composition and then later on I was a professor of music technology. And I was doing a lot
of work using Python for algorithmic composition and computational musicology. Since 2012,
however, I've been using Python to build financial systems and that work led me to build Static
Frame, an alternative data frame library built on an immutable data model.
So we're all here this week to celebrate 20 years of Python, right? Well, I'm celebrating
something slightly different. 20 years of CSV parsing in Python. All of you are excited
about this as well, right? Well, it turns out in 2003, 20 years ago, Python 2.3 was
released, which included for the very first time the CSV package in the standard library
and in that was a function called CSVReader. The way this worked is given an iterable of
lines, it would parse the delimited data. And the core functionality of this was implemented
in a state machine tokenizer implemented in C. Now if you go to C Python source code and
you look at CSV.C, you'll see this code right here. And this is that core state machine
tokenizer, a function called parse process char. I know this is pretty small. And what
this function does is process one character at a time with a giant switch statement controlling
the state. We all know great things lie behind giant switch statements, right?
Okay, so the CSVReader is very efficient because of the C core and it's configurable for a
wide range of CSV dialects. So in basic usage, we can take a string I.O. wrapping a string
that is representing two lines and we can feed that to the reader. It's going to give
us back an iterator and we can give that to a list and we're going to see that it's nicely
parsed out our field from the delimiter. Now a really nice feature of the CSVReader is
it's highly configurable. So here I give it a custom delimiter, a custom escape character,
a custom quote character, and we see it parses everything out just as expected. Now the CSVReader
didn't do everything. It returns parse rows, not columns. And CSV files generally contain
columnar data, data by column. So the CSVReader doesn't help us with detecting the type per
column, which is pretty useful, nor does it create columnar collections or arrays. So
since 2003, over the last 20 years, Pandas and NumPy in particular, but others, have
offered some alternatives. Now Pandas read CSV, does automatic type discovery per column,
it has full support for CSVReader dialect configurations, and it has generally very
good performance. I often think that the early growth of Pandas was in large part due to
the excellent performance of its CSVReader. However, not all D types are supported by
this tool. There's no support for Unicode arrays. All strings are brought in as PyObjects
in NumPy object arrays. And there's no support for Datetime 64 units. NumPy has a full range
of Datetime 64 units to allow you to specify the unit of your Datetime, but Pandas really
likes to bring everything in as a nanosecond. Now NumPy offers some options here. NumPy
has two functions, loadText and genFromText, that do similar things. These support all
NumPy D types and Datetime 64 units. And empty loadText, for example, works well, but doesn't
support escape fields and doesn't do any automatic type discovery. And see, genFromText does
do automatic type discovery, but it doesn't support loaded or escaped fields. So we have
a sort of mixture of solutions here. GenFromText also doesn't really show sufficient performance
at scale, and I'll show examples of that later on. So in trying to come up with a solution
for this in static frame, I put together pieces to create some kind of a monster here. So
I used CSVReader for handling loaded and escaped characters, and that gave me an iterator that
I then set into genFromText to do my type discovery and array creation. And this, as you might
expect, had fairly poor performance at scale. So this led me to create a new implementation
called delimitedToReraise. This supports full dialect configuration from the CSVReader,
supports all NumPy D types, and permits optional type discovery per column, with performance
largely better than pandas read CSV. And we'll see some examples of that later on. So today
we're going to talk about some of the challenge of building columnar arrays from CSV. We'll
look in depth at the C implementation of delimitedToReraise, and then we'll look at some performance
studies and talk about some future enhancements. Now through this presentation, I'm going to
use a lot of diagrams and flow charts to try to show you what's going on in the underlying
C code, and that's because the C is very verbose, and it won't sit on a slide here at all. So
we're not going to see a lot of C, we're going to see a lot of diagrams. Now in these diagrams,
we're going to try to isolate the pure C type and teams from those that involve Py objects,
and we see we call Py objects, not Py objects. So we're going to see some flow charts that
look like this. Now you don't have to understand this right now, we're going to come back to
this, but I just want you to notice the purple and the white boxes. The purple boxes are
places where we're interacting with Py objects. The white boxes are where we're dealing only
with pure C type, and when we're dealing with pure C type, we get the best performance.
You can see right here, this little loop, all C types. That's optimal performance, and in fact
we can even not hold the gear when we do things like that. Okay, so all of you have probably
dealt with C-NC files at some point, and they really are still a necessary evil. They are
human readable, which is great, and they're widely used and supported, but they're almost
always slower than binary formats, such as Parquet or NTV or many others. There is no
standard way of encoding metadata in a CSV, which means it can be very difficult to work with.
So when we're trying to build arrays from a CSV, we cannot know the number of columns or rows
in advance. If we just have a file, we can't know this in advance. The type per column,
further, is not encoded in the file. We have no idea what is in these files. So in general, it takes
two full iterations to get everything into an array. First, we have to load the Unicode data into
some sort of a dynamic array per column, and we can optimally discover the type as we do that.
And then once we know the size and type, then we can convert the fields to values and load them in
arrays, and I'm going to show you how I do that. All right, so the limited to arrays is a C
extension implemented in a raykit. This is a package. You can find it on GitHub. And we make heavy
use of the CPython and NumPy C APIs. And also I want to call out a hypothesis for really helping you
do extensive property testing to these functions when dealing with arbitrary input. Hypothesis really
can help you get to a good, solid implementation. So I made heavy reuse of the CSV reader in this
implementation. So I took that state machine tokenizer code and repurposed it. By doing so, I was
able to keep all of the dialect configuration options that are so useful in the standard library CSV
reader. Now as I mentioned, better than Python performance in our C code requires not using py
objects. We just write C code to do a bunch of sets of py objects, we get basic Python performance.
But if we want to move faster than that, we need to deal with C type. Now py objects incur overhead
even when we're working in C. We have to do type and error checking, and we have to manage our
reference count. So there is overhead when we deal with py objects that we don't have when we deal
with C type. So if you were approaching this, I'm just going to tell you how not to do it. This is kind
of what I do. You take the CSV reader and you create py object strings. So we've seen how the CSV
reader can give us py object strings. Then you can convert those strings to py object values, maybe
flows or booleans or integers, etc. Then you can copy those py objects into NumPy arrays. Now you
can do this, it'll work, but it creates tons of unnecessary intermediary py objects, and those
become expensive. Furthermore, it's not really what we want to do. NumPy arrays are arrays of C
type. What we want to do is go directly from the Unicode to the C type and skip all of these py
objects. So if we go back to the CSV.C module in the standard library, as I did when I was trying to
figure this out and figure out how this thing works, it's been there just a while, you start to notice
that there's two key functions that are being called as we process each character. One function is
parse and add char. It's gotten through the parsing in the various states to determine, yes, this is a
character we should keep. And then there's parse stage field. This is saying the field is complete.
We're done, we want to close this field and we're ready to move on. So that insight that there's these
two functions that are really what drives this allowed me to extend a new purpose for what I needed to
do. So this is how to do it. We recast the state machine tokenizer from CSV reader that we were just
looking at and we replace those two functions with different functions that will allow us to append
a point and append an offset. And I'll explain those in a little bit. We store characters per column,
not by row now, per column, into dynamic C arrays. And then we convert those column fields to C
types and then insert them into NumPy arrays and buffers. This we can do all without involving any py
object. None of the Intimidator py objects that we have to create and we truly can go directly from
Unicode into our C array type. So this is just a function and you can use it if you very simply.
So given an iterator of lines, it will return a list of 1D NumPy arrays. All the arguments for dialect
configuration are inherited from the CSV reader and we commit optional arguments for per column
definition. And I take those as a function because it solves some problems when writing dealing with
the second scene. So for example, to specify D types, of course it can discover D types for you,
but if you want to specify D types, you give it a function that, given a position, returns a D type
initializer. Similarly, if you want to specify excluding a function, you can have, sorry, excluding a
column, you can give a function to the line select parameter, which, given a column position, returns a
Boolean. So let's look at the basic usage of this function. This is a very simple case. I'm giving it a
list of strings representing record lines. This could be an open file or any other iterator of records.
And we start off with two records and we see that we get back three arrays, one for each column, an array
of integers, an array of Booleans, an array of one character Unicode. We see the types have been parsed
and determined for us, which is very nice. A slightly more involved example with some more configuration.
Here we provide a custom delimiter. We provide a function to make sure that everything after the first
column comes in as a string, and then we provide a second function for line select to just exclude the
third column. And we see now we get back two arrays and we see that our Booleans are not converted to
Booleans. They're just left as strings, which is exactly what we want. Okay, I wrote this use of
the static frame. It's perfectly useful on your own. You can just want to use it for NumPy, but in static
frame, all the constructors just call this when they need it. So from delimited, from CSV, from
CSV, they all call this under the hood, build the NumPy arrays they need, and then package that into the
revoking data frame. It's an additional configuration that stays with in static frame, like actually
opening a file, so I don't put that in delimited arrays. You can do that in static frame. And
interpreting the index in columns. All of that is encapsulated within static frame constructors.
Okay, let's dig into the implementation. So there's three C structs that underlie how this thing works.
There's one called the delimited reader. There's what I call a code point line, and what I call a code
point grid. And I'll refer to this sometimes as CPL and CPG. Now I use the term code point here to
refer to a Unicode character. I could have just called it a character, but code points seem to fit.
In CPython, we use the PyUCS4 pipe for this. This is a four byte Unicode character. Importantly, this is
not a Py object. This is just a simple C pipe that has a convenient alias in the CPython API.
So let's start with the delimited reader. So the delimited reader is extended from the CSV reader,
and it just iterates over the record strings. It calls the Python CHGI function pride Unicode data
to extract the underlying C array from the Python object, and does that once per record. And then we
part the fields per record. We process each character one at a time, calling those same functions for
adding characters and completing fields that I was showing you. All the while this tracks field, column,
and row positions, so we always have the context of where we are in the file. Now the code point line
stores Unicode data per column. This is what we're going to use to collect our characters as we're
moving through the file. And this is based loosely on Aero's string array data structure. So we have
two dynamically allocated C arrays inside of this structure. One of them we call buffer is just a C
array of Unicode characters, and it's going to store contiguous characters without null terminators,
so we can be maximally compact. We have a second array also contained within the CTO, which stores the
offsets, or the size of each field. So we separated these things into two arrays. Once this thing is
fully loaded, we can then go to each field per offset and convert those fields to a C type. So this
diagram here is a little schematic to try to help you understand what the code point line is. We see
here these little gray horizontal boxes, it's a representation of a dynamically allocated array, and we
see we have one array of a buffer and another array of offsets. And we can unpack this by looking at the
offsets. We see the first field is three characters, that's red. The second field is five characters, that's
green. And the third field is four characters, that's green. Now the code point grid is really there to
serve as an interface between the limited reader and the CPLs. So it dynamically creates and populates
CPLs as needed. It's really the public interface. And it exposes these two functions that we call during
distinct machine tokenization. We are pending either a point or we're pending an offset. And again, the
delimited reader knows where we are in the file, so we know which column, which CPL to populate as we move
through the file. So returning to the same diagram, we see that the code point grid surrounds and contains
one or more code point lines. All right, so next we're going to look at the processing stages. How do we
move through this and get to our final result? So we start with our input. Our input is simply an iterator of
records. This can be a file, it can be any other iterator of strings. Next we initialize the delimited
reader and the code point grid. Now we're ready to, in our first iteration, to read through the file and load
up our code point lines. So in this flow chart, I'll show you a little bit of how that works. So we start a
purple box here, a pie object, an iterator of strings. We use that to get the underlying UnicodeC
array and we can reset our field length, reset our field number, and then we're ready to iterate through
code points. So as we iterate through code points, I'm vastly since the final goes on here, but as we
iterate through code points, we say is it a delimiter or not? If it's not a delimiter, then we know we need to
append a point and we can increment the field length. If it is a delimiter, then we know we're done with
the field. We can append an offset and we can increment the field number and reset the field length.
Then when we're done with that character, we go on and say, well do we have more characters? And we loop
through here until we're done with this record. Now again, notice that this loop here has no pie objects.
That's really critical to getting good performance out of this. Finally, if we are done with that record,
we go and look, we increment the record count, and we see if we have any more records. If we do, we go back
and we repeat the whole process again. Okay, we've completed our first iteration through the elements
that we're trying to represent here. Now we're ready to essentially go to them again, but we no longer
need our records. We no longer need the delimited reader. Now everything is loaded in our code point
lines and we're ready to convert those to arrays, deliver our final output, which is going to be a list
of arrays. So this flow chart shows that second iteration in detail. We're going to start with a CPL.
We're going to walk through each of our code point lines. And then the next step is we need to create
our numPy array that we're going to ultimately deliver back to the caller. To do that, we need to know
the size and the type. We know the size because the CPL is already loaded, and the type might come from
the type parser or it might come from the user who's provided it as an argument. Once we have that,
we can create our numPy array, and it would be a contiguous numPy array from which we can pull off
the underlying C buffer. And so we're done with purple boxes. We have no after this step. We can put
aside our py objects and we can focus on just dealing with pure C type. So now in this loop, we're going
to grab the next offset. We're going to use that offset to read from our Unicode code point. We're going
to convert those to a C type, and we're going to insert that C type directly in our numPy array buffer.
And then we can continue to do that in a loop. And again, we can do that all without any interaction
with py objects. Finally, our array is done. We need to attend that array to a list. There we interact
with the py object, and we go on and consider if we have more CTOs to process and repeat this until we're
done. So as I alluded to, performance of this routine is critical, and that was the main goal of me sitting
out to do this. So we're going to look at a number of benchmarks. Now the way I do benchmarks is on
fairly large numbers of elements. So here I'm looking at 10 million elements. And we're going to use
the terministic randomly generated values via a package called FramingSixSeries. And we're going to
compare three scenarios for interpreting columns in both StaticFrame and Pandas. So one scenario is
type discovery. You've just given the CSV to the reader. It doesn't know any of the types. It's going to
figure out the type for you. The second scenario is just load everything at strings. I don't care what the
types are. Just give me all strings. And the third scenario is I know all my types. Don't do types
discovery. Just load this thing and give me back some of the reads. So there's a lot of information here.
We're going to come back to this. But right now I want you to focus on the legend over here on the right,
which shows those three scenarios. First for StaticFrame, type parsing at string type given, and
second for Pandas, type parsing at string and type given. We're going to come back to this. Now I think
it's really important when we do performance analysis of the type discovery, we're going to look at
Now I think it's really important when we do performance analysis of data frames that we explore
different states and de-type heterogeneity. I think far too often I see performance
studies of data frame operations where they just compare one table.
And you can get quite different results by having different both states of tables
and type heterogeneity. So we're going to look at three state ratios,
tall, square, and wide, and we're going to look at three types of de-type heterogeneity.
Whether we have a different type per column, whether we have mixed where we have sort of
chunks of uniform types together, or whether it's uniform. It's just all one type.
So with this we create our grid where we have the state from tall, square,
wide as columns, and we have the de-type heterogeneity as rows, column,
and mixed and uniform. And with this we get our nine data frame fixtures that we're going to
use to compare performance. So now looking back at this diagram,
hopefully you have some context to understand what's going on here. We can see in general
that the red, orange, and slightly yellow bars at the end are all
higher, and that means slower than the first three which are static frames. So in this diagram,
lower is better. But let's look at some particular details with what we see in the
performance comparison here. So in general, static frame outperforms pandas in a lot of
these cases, specifically 26 out of the 27 scenarios static frame outperforms pandas.
The one case that we don't is right there in the uniform tall scenario
where type parsing these uniform floats, pandas was a little bit faster.
Other than that, static frame pretty much outperforms pandas in all of these scenarios.
Another observation is that because pandas convert
strings to NumPy object arrays and creates a bunch of py objects,
that's very expensive. So if we look here, we see the pandas loading the data
as a string, that's that orange bar, we see in almost every case
that that orange bar takes the most time. So that is an expensive cost
that pandas is making for that choice. Now finally, we notice that
we get really excellent performance with the limited tool arrays and static frame with
wide data frames. Whereas when we get tall, our performance then
increases a little bit, and I think that might be due to me using the biggest size
Unicode, pyucs4, that may be what's hindering tall performance there.
So we see here in the wide results, we see the outperformance with static frame
in loading these files is an order of magnitude better than pandas,
but as we go to more tall, we see that it's maybe just about twice as fast
and that changes a little bit every other different type. I mentioned
NumPy Gen from text. This machine is important, it was what I used for many years.
It is the only NumPy machine that supports type discovery, but as I mentioned, at scale
it doesn't really meet my needs. So here I've added NumPy Gen from text
to these performance studies, and we can see for tall and square
tables, it performs much, much slower than both static frame and pandas.
Interestingly, on wide data frames, it's fairly competitive with
pandas, and in fact performs a little bit better than pandas in a few cases.
Alright, so hopefully I convinced you that
DelimitedArrays offers a fast, full-featured tool for creating NumPy arrays from
CSVs. If you're just working with NumPy, you can use it in isolation. If you want to use it within a
fully-featured data frame library, it's there on static frame, ready for you to use.
So in considering where else we might go with this, I had to consider
parallelization. Like is there a way we can paralyze some of these operations?
Now when we're reading the file and we're loading the TPLs, I don't think
we can really paralyze that. That would be a little tricky. But once all of our TPLs
are fully loaded, we just need to convert those to NumPy arrays, and that is
in fact an embarrassing and parallel problem. However, I don't know how to do it yet.
So multi-threading primitives in CPython that are cross-platform are
elusive. And if anyone would like to help, I would be happy to get some
insights and possibly how to do that. Now there is a good example of
parallelized CSV loading provided to us by the Polars data frame library.
As many of you probably know, Polars is implemented in Rust based on arrow array
definitions, and it offers a company called read CSV, which takes advantage of
multi-threaded implementation. Now this isn't really an alternative for me because it does
not support the full range of dialect configurations, and it's built around
arrow, so it does not really support all NumPy D types. But interesting to look at.
So if we add Polars to our performance test now as the yellow bar, we see that
it performs really well for call arrays. But as we get
square and more columnar, we see that static frames using good old
Sasson C and one thread can outperform the Polars multi-threaded implementation
at least for wide data frames. So some more work to do potentially there, but
this is a pretty good result.
Alright, in conclusion, we can go back to the piece of code. I think all of us
write code hoping that it might be useful for a month or a year or a few years,
but to have a piece of code that's been around for 20 years and continue to be
useful both in the standard library and useful for people like me to take this and build it into
something else is just really exciting and I think it's something we should all be really happy about.
Alright, thank you for your attention. If you'd like to learn more about
static frame or other related tools, you can go to this URL and feel free to come chat with me
throughout the conference. I'll be around. Happy to take any questions now or later on.
Thank you for your attention.