All right, does this work?
Can anyone, can everyone hear me?
Yeah.
All right.
Hello everyone and thank you very much for coming to our talk today.
I'm going to be talking about building large language model based agents and how you can
build smart NLP driven applications with Haystack.
But before I get into that, a bit about myself.
This is my first time here in Salt Lake City and at PyCon, so I am a bit nervous and excited.
I hope this goes well.
My name is Twana and I'm the developer advocate at Deepset, which is the company behind Haystack,
the open source tool we'll be talking about.
I have a background in computer science but have been doing dev rel since about 2020.
All right, so today's talk is going to follow roughly this structure.
At the end of the day, I kind of want to pass on the message around how agents even became,
how they were possible.
Then we're going to look into a bit about what Haystack is, how you can interact with
large language models using Haystack and then we're going to see how we might create our
own agents with Haystack.
There is going to be a bit of coding towards the end and also just a side note for everyone,
given that this is about natural language processing, there is a lot of language on
If you cannot see the text, I will be reading out the ones that are most necessary because
we will be looking at some fairly long prompts and we'll see what that is later as well.
All right, so without further ado, here is a brief history of the human, how humans search,
let's say, according to me.
So it's not very accurate.
This is more about how humans extract information.
So we communicate with each other, that's great.
Then we have books, then we have the World Wide Web.
Quite recently, I'm pretty sure without me having to tell you the exact name, a lot of
us have been relying on a very well-known NLP technology.
So I want to start explaining to you how agents even came about, how they work, the idea behind
giving an example of some interactions I might have with this NLP technology.
There are some memes in this slide deck.
You can blame that all on Jasper over there.
That's my colleague who gave me the feedback that your slide deck needs memes.
So there you go.
All right, let's start with some examples about what we can do with large language models.
Let's start simple.
And here is that interface I'm pretty sure a lot of you have already seen.
This is simply a question.
So we know we can ask questions to large language models.
And we've got back a pretty accurate long answer.
So that's one thing we can do.
Here I've asked who was the first president of the USA, and I got a correct answer, quite
a detailed answer.
That's great.
But the one thing to notice here that this is a question.
What else can we do?
Well, we can ask it instruct these large language models to do something.
This is not necessarily a question to be answered.
Here I've highlighted around my instruction, which says summarize the following text for
me.
And I've simply copy pasted the answer that I got before.
And this is where you start to see how things are getting different.
I'm instructing the large language model to do something for me.
And I've got a pretty accurate summary.
These models are generative, so you don't necessarily have to ask it for information.
What's cool, you can also ask them to create content, create previously non-existent content.
So you can achieve beautiful literature a bit like this too.
Here I say, create a PyCon event schedule in the style of a poem.
And it's beautiful.
It knows about tutorials.
It knows about talks, keynotes, et cetera.
It's a pretty good poem.
But then the next two slides is where I want to really draw your attention to, because
this is where really the whole idea, the essence of agents come about.
I know I've just started saying agents without actually having asked you, do you know what
I'm talking about when I say agents?
But hopefully you'll start to get an idea what they are.
All right, so this is the first instruction.
This one is different, because I've basically imagined up two things, which I'm going to
be calling tools.
And I said, you have the following tools, PyCon event QA, and I've explained what it's
useful for.
I've said useful for when you need to answer questions about PyCon.
And then I've also said you've got web search, and I've said it's useful for when you need
to search the web to answer general questions that other tools cannot.
And then I've given a query saying, pick which tools you would use to resolve the following
When is Twana's talk at PyCon?
And what is the weather at Salt Lake City going to be like that day?
And I've only asked it to pick the tools based on the descriptions I've given.
And what I want you to notice is that it has picked the right tools in the right order
according to what is the use that it has to learn, it has to find out.
So that's one thing to keep in mind.
The next one is quite long, so if anyone in the back cannot read this, don't worry, I'm
going to highlight what's the most important part of this one.
It is the same prompt, the same instruction, I haven't said prompt yet.
It is the same exact instruction with one key difference.
I have added a line saying, explain step by step how you arrive to your conclusion.
This is often referred to as the chain of thought methodology.
This is where we can ask the large language model to reason about why it's picking some
tools and the response I want to really draw attention to number two here, which says,
once I have located Twana's talk in the PyCon schedule, I would note the date and time of
the talk.
So you can see it's making decisions around what information is going to be important
for the next tool.
Now agents really in essence is this, the only difference is the tools do actually exist.
This question here is going to be recurring throughout my talk, when is Twana's talk at
PyCon and what is the weather going to be like at Salt Lake City on that day.
Because I've gone ahead and built this agent and at the end of this talk what we want to
get to is figuring out how we would build something that does the following and hopefully
I can actually play this because I want to pause it at the end.
You can see this running, agent.run.
It's picked a tool saying speaker search and it's invoked that tool, actually run it, looked
for Twana's talk and then picked web search and at the end you can see that it says final
answer Twana Chalik will be presenting blah blah blah blah.
We all know the title.
Then finally it says the weather in Salt Lake City on that day is expected to be cold with
temperatures between 1 and 10 degrees Celsius, snowfall and rain, not great weather for Salt
Lake City.
You can see that it's picked first a tool called speaker search.
We're going to see what this tool even is and how it runs.
Then it's extracted my talk from PyCon event data.
Then once it knows what day my talk is, it's decided okay, now I need to use one of the
tools called web search.
What I really want to draw your attention to throughout this talk actually is the importance
of the first instruction I give these large language models so that they are able to do
this.
All of those previous chat GPT screen shots you saw have one obvious thing in common which
is the quite impressive language model itself.
They also have a very well structured effective instruction which we call prompts.
I'm going to be referring to them as prompts from now on.
We're going to be looking at a lot of prompts.
This is really well highlighted by this, why can't I go to the next slide?
Also Jasper's meme by the way.
This quote by Andrej who said the hottest new programming language is English.
You're going to see how true that is when it comes to how agents are even able to exist.
Before we dive into building an agent and seeing how these tools can be described, I
want to do a quick introduction to Haystack.
Haystack is a fully open source NLP framework.
You can scan that QR code and you'll get to our GitHub page.
It's maintained by my company Deepset plus a very vibrant large community of developers,
open source developers who contribute to the project every day.
The core idea behind Haystack is what you see on the right hand side here which is a
pipeline.
It allows you to mix and match components, NLP components that you might want to use
depending on what your use case is.
A very, very common way of doing a query pipeline is what you see on the left where you would
use a retriever node which is really good at looking at a really large set of documents
and deciding which ones are the most relevant for the user's query followed by a reader.
We're not going to be looking at the reader today but the reader is basically a component
that uses an extractive model.
So it only looks at context and it extracts answers.
It does not formulate a human-like response.
You're able to use models off of depending on what you want to do, hugging face, open
AI, cohere and also decide what database you want.
You can decide to use a vector optimized database like pine cone, weaviate or you can go with
open search, depending on what your tech stack looks like.
So the whole idea is really a whole end to end NLP application will actually end up needing
a lot of tooling around it, a lot of pre-processing maybe and we try to provide all of the quality
of life features that you might need.
At the end of the day, this is what a pipeline structure actually looks like.
I'm going to come back to this slide later because you're going to see how this is kind
of different to how agents operate.
A pipeline is a predefined path made up of components based on what you have decided
before what your application is going to do, what it's going to need.
Like I said, a pipeline might look like this but you're free to mix and match.
Let's say you switch over the reader with a generator so it's a generative model now.
You can use elastic search, weaviate, quadrant, pine cone and decide which models you use
for your retriever and your reader or generator based on what you want to achieve.
And then you can also expose your application via REST API.
So this really covers most of the basics of Haystack at this point.
Now I'm going to start talking about where it changes.
Again, this is a one path system.
The path is predefined and your data is walking through that path.
All right, so I want to build a pipeline with Haystack and this is going to be important
because we're actually going to use this pipeline later on in the talk as one of our tools for
an agent.
So you saw that video I showed where it was actually running and doing speaker search
and then deciding what the weather was like doing web search.
I have actually called the PyCon event page and this is on Hugging Face.
It's a data set and you can see it's got talks, tutorials, sponsored talks, everything there
ready for me to use.
I've got two options.
I can either create a search application going through a retrieval and then a reader, so
extractive model.
Or I can basically do the same so I know that my generative model is getting retrieved documents
from that data set you just saw there and I'm going to pick that one.
I'm going to use a generative model because it's just a bit more interesting.
All right, so the two components in Haystack that will allow you to interact with large
language models with your own data are these two.
The prompt template and the prompt node.
The prompt template is basically allowing you to create a blueprint of how you want
to interact with large language models and we're going to be looking at how we build
our own.
And it's flexible because you can change, actually change what the prompt is at query time.
The prompt node is simply basically the connector to these large language models.
So this is where we say I want to, I don't know, use GPT-4 or use Google's Flan models, etc.
And this is the one that interacts with the large language model.
So it's the one that sends the query and receives a response.
All right, so we saw how, at the beginning, how instructions are important.
So I've created my own instruction to do some search on PyCon event data.
And here is my instruction.
So I'm not sure if this is readable from the back but I'm going to read it out for you.
So I've called it my prompt and I've said you will be provided a list of events, reply
to the query based on the content of the provided events.
And then the next few lines are important because I said query and then I've given this
variable called query in curly brackets and then I've also said events and I've said in
curly brackets join all the documents.
So we'll see how this works.
But basically these two things in curly brackets is where the magic happens.
And at the end of the day I want to build a pipeline that actually sends the following
prompt.
This was really long so I've actually split this into two slides.
But what's happened here is you can see that my query, what day is the talk about agents
and LLMs, has been basically injected into the prompt that I am sending to an LLM in
the query section.
And you'll see how the retriever has retrieved some documents and joined them.
And that's been where I fill the events, the curly brackets that say join events.
Again, I've shortened this.
There was a lot.
And then finally we are saying, okay, now what's the answer?
And we expect an answer from the large language model.
So all right, so how do I make this happen basically?
Well, first I declare a prompt template and I call this prompt template events QA.
And I've said the prompt text is what I just created, my prompt.
Finally I've created a prompt node and I've said your default prompt template.
So anytime you get called by default you use this prompt template that has just been created.
And I call this prompt node PyCon QA.
And then I just create a pipeline.
I say I've got a pipeline and I add my first node.
Let's assume we have a retriever.
I did not really want to dive into retrievers right now.
But the retriever has access to all those documents you saw on Hugging Face basically.
And the first thing that gets the query is this retriever.
So the first job is first I need to find the most relevant documents events out there.
The second node is my prompt node.
The second node is the PyCon QA node that already has a prompt template ready.
So it's now ready to receive documents and a query and inject this into the prompt text
that I created and send it over.
Finally I ask it the question what day is the talk about agents and LLMs?
And I receive a response a bit like this.
It's quite long.
It says the talk about agents and LLMs titled, gives the title of my presentation
and says on Thursday, April 20th.
I built this pipeline and ran it because and then I just wanted to try another query.
This was using GPT-4.
I'm going to be using GPT-4 for the agents as well.
And I asked it the question I'm interested in NLP.
What talks should I see?
And I got a pretty good response actually.
It also gave me the correct URLs for every talk.
I was pretty impressed so decided I might add this in here.
And everything you're seeing here is basically referred
to as a retrieval augmented generative QA methodology.
Another one that I wanted to share because I think it's cool and it gives you the idea
of how this works and why retrieval augmentation is important is this hugging face space.
You can scan that QR code and try it out.
Given the Twitter username it actually inserts the latest Twitter streams of that user.
And then gives you an idea, like the prompt is ready and it gives you an idea of what type
of tweets this person tweets about and what languages they use, et cetera.
Okay, now we're back to this slide again because I want to reiterate this.
This again is a pipeline.
I've added nodes.
The path is set.
Data is flowing from one node to the next and the knowledge base is also set.
I can't ask anything about weather to this application.
If I do the best thing that's happening is probably I'm getting some weird response,
complete hallucination.
The knowledge base is PyCon events.
All right, so this is where agents get in.
Also you can thank Jasper for this.
All right, so features of an agent.
So what is an agent?
An agent is in essence a prompt node, that prompt node we were looking at,
which connects to a large language model.
But most importantly, it's got a very clear, very clever initial prompt.
So we're going to look at what that prompt is.
It has access to a variety of tools and these tools actually exist and they run.
These tools might be haystack pipelines like the one we just built now.
They could be other data connectors, complete the pipelines that have access
to a completely different knowledge base.
They could even be web search.
It's really up to you.
The idea is as well with haystack that people will be able to build their own tools.
And this is important too.
Each tool might be useful to achieve one specific thing or
have access to a completely different set of data.
And again, like we saw in the first few slides,
where we said explain to me step by step how you're going to come to your conclusion.
An agent is going to create an action plan to look at a query and
say these are the tools I will use to resolve this query.
Some more QR because these are basically the two papers that the implementation of
agents in haystack is based on.
Highly recommend reading them.
They are very interesting.
One of them is called React.
The other one is called, well it's MRKL but pronounced Miracle Systems.
So if you're interested, please take a picture of that.
All right, so we know that what a large language model can produce is really,
well not completely, but it really depends on the initial instruction or
the prompt we give them.
So what is the prompt we give to an agent for it to be able to do what it does?
Well the default one in haystack is called the zero shot react prompt.
And again, this is very long, so I've split this into two slides and
I'm going to read out the ones that are the most important.
Number one, it says you are a helpful and knowledgeable agent and
to achieve your goal of answering complex questions,
you have access to the following tools.
And this is where you see the curly brackets again.
So you're going to see how dynamically we can add more and
more tools with descriptions.
And then it actually tells the model how to think in a way.
Because it says use the following format.
And it says, first you're going to get a question.
And then generate some thought, decide what your next steps should be.
Then pick a tool and we give it the tool names.
Then decide what the input to that tool should be.
And then finally observe what the response of that tool is.
And we say, we tell it to give us a very short answer, but
actually it's back there.
We ask it to continue this loop until it's reached a final answer.
And this is where you'll see how it's starting to become a bit different than
the whole pipeline concept.
And then finally we provide a way to input the query to the agent.
All right, so an agent at the end of the day, and
this is again where it starts to differ from a pipeline, is a bit like this.
It's always there.
Technically you can define how many steps it should take,
because otherwise sometimes maybe it goes on for too long.
And you're sending too many requests to OpenAI and the bill is ranking up.
So you can set that.
But effectively, you have this agent that exists,
that has an arsenal of tools that it can, at every iteration,
decide which one it should use or not.
So the path is definitely not predefined.
The path is defined on the fly by these models who are making decisions about
what to use.
Another way of looking at this is this.
Think of the agent as a loop at the end of every iteration.
It's saying, have I got the final answer?
No, back to another picking tool and creating thoughts iteration.
If I do, great, I can end this.
So I created this PyCon event agent.
I did change the zero shot react prompt just a bit, because as you saw,
it said, just give me a one to five word answer.
I did not want a one to five word answer.
I also helped it out a bit, and I very creatively called it the zero shot
react PyCon prompt.
It's very similar at the beginning.
I do tell it to correctly consider the date topic speaker constraints of the
user input.
And I simply just at the end tell it to give it as detailed as an answer as it
decides.
I don't want a one to five word, very simple answer.
And now we're going to look at how we might fill this prompt with the
following.
So in my prompt, I'm going to define something called PyCon event QA.
It's going to be useful for when you need to answer questions about PyCon.
Then I'm going to define speaker search.
There's a reason for this, because I tried this with just PyCon event QA
using a retriever that does embedding search rather than keyword search,
which is not great to ask it, like, find me Twana's talk.
Twana becomes the keyword there, so I ended up defining another one.
And then I also have web search, which simply basically Googles your
questions for you.
And then again, we're going to look at the query, when is Twana's talk at
PyCon, and what will the weather in Salt Lake City be like that day?
All right, so how would we build this with Haystack?
First thing, we define an agent.
Again, an agent is in essence a prompt, and I provide it with that prompt
template you just saw.
And I use GPT-4 here.
Then that pipeline we created before, that generative QA pipeline, I say
this is my tool.
I call it PyCon QA tool, and I say give it a name and give it a description
saying useful for when you need to answer questions about PyCon.
And then I simply add that tool to my agent.
Now my agent has at least access to that pipeline, which has access to
PyCon event data.
The next thing I do, again, because of this keyword search situation,
because I really wasn't able to ask it questions about specific speaker
names or dates without some keyword search, I won't look into how we
built that pipeline.
But basically I define another one saying useful when you want to answer
questions about specific speakers.
And then I add that, and now we've got two.
And then I can define a Web QA pipeline.
This is also a new pipeline we have in Haystack.
This simply long story short can Google your questions and return to you
the most, first of all, the most relevant web pages and then generate
answers from them as well.
So I define this and basically I've defined this as my sort of fallback
tool because I said anything that you cannot answer with PyCon event data,
this is the knowledge base you should go to.
Just Google it.
And now I've got three tools.
And now I can ask this question, agent.run, when is Twana's talk at PyCon
and what will the weather in Salt Lake City be like that day?
And I have an agent that has all the resources it needs to actually answer
this question.
So we end up with this.
Again, it's the same video basically.
And you can now see how it will first say, first I need to find Twana's talk,
and then decide the tool input for speaker search should be Twana.
And then it knows the date of my talk and it decides that the input for
web search should be weather for Salt Lake City 20th of April.
And that is the general idea behind agents.
All right, thank you very much for listening.
I hope I was able to deliver what agents are and how they come about.
If you do want to try building your own agent,
the first QR code is a tutorial that uses simply one tool.
And it's great at doing multi-hop question answering because of that.
And then the second QR code is an article explaining the agent's
implementation in Haystack, what kind of tools you might use.
And I tried to deliver the idea behind agents in this article.
Myself and my two colleagues and a few more were here throughout PyCon.
You can find us at booth 321.
If you do want to come and have a chat with us or
you simply want a sticker, that's also fine.
But yeah, I hope you enjoyed that.
And I guess we have some time for questions now.
Yeah.
What are the types of agents you support?
With the Python, I can make a custom agent that's very local-mouthful.
Actually, that's a really good question.
So there's types of agents and there's types of tools.
So I'm gonna address those two separately.
The default one uses the zero-shot react right now, but
you can completely build from scratch your own agent prompt.
So we do have examples of, so this one is called zero-shot because
we actually didn't give it any examples of how to react to questions.
There are some cases where few-shot,
where you do give examples, works really well.
But the idea is, yes, you can build a tool.
And I actually think I know a community member that's building a Wolfram Alpha
tool for an agent.
A tool can be another haystack node, a completely new pipeline that uses
a prompt node or has a separate connection to another API, yes.
Yeah, I was thinking about line change,
but it's sort of a big problem.
Yeah.
Are there any other questions?
Yes.
So I think OpenAI has a limit of characters.
I think it's like 4,000 or something like that.
Yeah.
So I'm just curious, can you use another open source?
Actually, I should have referred to this in my talk, so
I'm glad you asked this.
Yes, so my example was with OpenAI, but
the idea is you can use any language model,
large language model that can follow instructions.
So for example, I know a couple of people who use Haystack agents with
the Google Flan models, and I don't know if we support it just yet,
or I think we're looking into it.
Quite recently, Databricks came up with Dolly, which is an open source model
that, well, it's coined saying instruction following model, so
maybe that will work as well.
Yeah.
And so I'm sorry, was it blue?
Like, is it like, somewhere in the blue model?
Yeah.
I'm looking at Mattis because he's probably more likely to know the exact
answer to this one.
I think technically, yes, it's not easy to get to this, but
you did know that good questions aren't used very much in the field yet,
so you always have to look at technically, yes,
it needs to be the correct class to use it, but does it often work as an agent
for the performance model?
Okay, so that one was called Dolly, which is probably the most-
Dolly, yes, yeah.
I think I saw another, yeah.
Oh, thanks.
Oh, nice.
So you were using OpenAI's GPT-4 model.
Yeah.
If one created their own LLM from hugging,
like using hugging this as tokenizer, can they still utilize that with ASTEP?
So, Haystack already has an integration with Hugging Face,
so if it is a model at the end of the day that could follow instructions,
that should be possible.
For example, the Google Flan models I was just mentioning,
we actually just pulled out from Hugging Face.
It's not a, yeah, it's not-
Do you always have to be pulled from Hugging Face?
No, so we have connectors to OpenAI.
Kahir, even though we don't use it specifically for agents,
Hugging Face, and you can use all of the Haystack pipelines you saw before,
so the pipeline we built was Generative QA, for example.
You can also simply use a local model.
Okay, so you can build a model, download it into your laptop,
add and run Haystack with it.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Cool, thank you.
Yes.
Do you guys have any support of your own tools?
Tools, not yet, but well, actually technically, that one.
You do technically create your own tool.
It just happens to be a Haystack, another Haystack pipeline
that becomes a tool, but yes, we are coming up with more examples.
There's one coming up that actually creates Web QA as a tool as well.
Okay, so I was thinking it would be really nice to sub it like that
or something.
That's like a web search instead of like,
how do you suggest we use the server, is that it?
Yes, I think, I believe there's also another one too.
And yes, so agents are pretty new with Haystack.
We have instructions on how to build your own custom nodes,
and people who have built their own custom nodes have found
that making that an agent tool has been quite smooth,
but we need to add some instructions around that.
Okay, thank you.
There's one over there that I can see.
Hi, I'm studying now.
Can you ask someone in the field about what would you recommend
or things that I could learn, like tools or things to research?
Honestly, I would say agents are so new
that I would really recommend those two papers.
I actually have a background in computer vision, funnily enough,
so NLP is still quite new to me,
but those two papers are the React paper explains this whole
reasoning aspect of large language models,
and the Miracle paper is very interesting as well.
And if you want to build full applications,
I would really recommend looking into how tools will be built
and which data sources might be interesting for you
to build tools that an agent can have access to.
Yes?
Have you had any experience or faced building tools using
like SQL or RQL or more specific querying languages
so like you couldn't integrate this kind of databases?
Not myself, but I think he has.
So we have like this knowledge graph support in ASEC as well,
but we have to honestly say that it doesn't really deliver
the same performance that you're used to by now
from large language models.
But I think there's quite a few language models
which are good at language to SQL basically,
and that would work in a ASEC pipeline probably as well.
So as a tool, maybe a small custom wrapper should work.
I think that's about it.
Really hope you enjoyed that.
Yes, feel free to visit us in our booth, 321.
We'll all be there until the end of PyCon.
It would be really nice to meet you and see you all around.