Hello everyone.
Hi. Thanks for coming to this workshop.
We're going to start in a minute.
So just a couple of things around this.
So this URL is going to be the URL with all the information
for the workshop and it's a living workshop in the sense
that it's going to change in the next few weeks or months.
So I don't know if you've already seen strawberry.
Strawberry is quite, well it's not really new anymore.
It's been four years, but we're working a lot
to make it more production ready or easier
to make it production ready.
So there's going to be quite a bit of changes in future
in terms of less things you have to do manually to make
like a GraphQL application more production ready,
like more secure and faster and so on.
So I definitely want you to keep this URL around.
It's going to be updated in the next few months.
And yeah, hopefully everyone has it.
This, again, this workshop is going to be quite interactive.
So we're going to build things together.
I'm happy to take any questions.
There's a microphone there.
So anytime, just feel free to stop me
to ask any questions and to repeat.
We, yeah, I'm going to explain what GraphQL is,
but if you want to kick off the setup while I'm going
to talk a bit, there's two options.
One is using Gitbot, so you can click here.
It goes to the service called Gitbot, which is like a remote VM.
There is VS code and allows you to quickly spin up a machine
with Python, everything is also,
you don't have to configure anything.
A test this morning should work, but if there's any,
just let me know, we'll figure it out.
Yeah, once you open this, it's going to open a terminal.
It's going to install Python 3.10.
It's going to install other things.
I guess one difference between this and the other option,
the other option is using just VisualMV, and this one is using PDM,
which is my package manager of choice, and I'm just using
because it's convenient, but I think you don't have
to do anything with PDM, and if you have any question on that,
I'm happy to also answer those.
But yeah, basically, once you click,
it's going to install everything.
And yeah, the other option is to just do it like standard,
so you clone the repo, create VirtualMV,
install the requirements, and then run a couple of commands
to make sure that everything works, which I'm going to do now as well,
so just to double check that everything is fine.
Yeah, a couple of things more.
So we're going to use Django for this, mostly because I'm very familiar
with Django, I know how to use models and things like that,
but again, this workshop is not really about Django.
We're actually going to see things more in agnostic way,
so we're going to use Django models, but we're not going
to use any automatic generation of GraphQL types from Django models
at all, because that's one way of doing things,
but it's not really the way I would recommend to create a GraphQL API.
So I guess a GraphQL API should be a basic book on the clients,
not what you have on the database, but we'll see that in a moment.
So this is installed, so if I run PyTest, it should work.
There we go.
So the output is verbose.
At the moment I'm printing all the SQL queries, mostly to show you some
performance optimization in the future.
Yes? Again?
Yeah. I don't know if there's a good way of putting this, but yeah,
workshop.strawberrydorax.
Cool. And yeah, so once everything is set up, you can run the tests,
and then you can also import, it's written there,
but I'll do it with you as well.
You can import some podcasts, so we're going to build an API that allows you
to list podcasts and podcast episodes, and so to get some data,
we can import them like this.
So I created a small command line application that just fetches data
from SS feeds and loads them into the database.
And again, this is very verbose
because I am printing all the SQL code that's happening.
Anyway, this is going to take maybe a bit of time
since we are all on the internet.
Cool. Yeah.
So I guess, again, do a bit of introduction as well,
introduction about myself.
So my name is Patrick.
I've been working on Strawberry for about four years.
I created it, yeah, four years ago.
I don't remember the exact date, but it's been quite a while,
and it's becoming quite popular.
It's still a niche project, I guess, for especially GraphQL in Python.
It's not super popular, but I think it's growing over time.
And yeah, over the last two years,
I think there's been quite a few people using it in production,
and basically like the community around it grew a lot.
So I decided to start doing workshop
and basically help people starting with this project.
I work at a company called Apollo GraphQL,
and we do tooling around GraphQL, but we're not going to see any of that.
This is like what I'm doing here.
It's like my own thing.
It's not sponsored by my company, unfortunately.
But yeah, if you have any questions about that, we can talk about that.
But yeah, this workshop is purely on GraphQL and Strawberry.
Okay, so what is GraphQL?
So if you're not familiar with GraphQL, GraphQL is a query language
that allows you to query APIs and get data from those APIs.
You're going to see an example of that.
But basically, GraphQL is, like to put it simply, it's an alternative to REST.
It basically allows you to query APIs that you can use
with your mobile application or website and so on.
It was created by Facebook in 2012 and open sourced in 2015,
and actually now is not tied to Facebook anymore.
There's a GraphQL foundation which is fully open source
and so anyone can use GraphQL without having to worry
about licensing and things like that, which is quite nice.
And this company, this foundation, GraphQL foundation is also responsible
for growing GraphQL and updating the spec and making more,
I guess, future proof and adding new features over time.
Yeah, so in this workshop, we're going to learn how to use Strawberry
to build GraphQL APIs.
We're going to use Python 3.7 or later.
I think at some point, this workshop, we're going to use mostly Python 3.10
or more because there's quite a few typing features
that make the code a bit nicer.
But again, Strawberry at the moment works from 3.7 up until 3.11.
So you can use anything.
I use VS Code, but you can use anything as well there.
Yeah, we're going to learn, well, this is actually,
there's more things we're going to learn than this,
so don't worry about that.
Yeah, we're going to build an API for a podcast application.
This is a project I was working on while ago, then I stopped,
but I think it's quite useful to learn a few things about GraphQL.
So we can list podcasts.
We can get a single podcast.
We can list all the latest episodes for a podcast,
and we can also subscribe to a single podcast.
Okay. So I mentioned the setup.
So this is the setup.
You can follow it.
Again, if you have issues, try use Gitpod.
It should work fine.
And yeah, I did run everything here.
So yeah, this is, I have all the data imported,
and now I can run a server, and we're going to see GraphQL itself.
So there is this tool called GraphiQL,
which is a graphical interface for GraphQL, hence the name.
And it basically allows you to run API calls to your GraphQL APIs.
So I guess the first thing to note here, there is this text here,
which is basically where you can write document to test the query.
And so we do have one single query called hello.
So this document is going to be sent to the server,
and then the server is going to do, you know, its magic and fetch data.
So if I click here, I'm going to see a response, right?
And just want to show you a couple of things here of what is happening.
So when I do this request, I'm actually doing a post request.
This is a standard thing in GraphQL.
Every request is a post request.
And I think the reason why it's been always post request is
because of the fact that this document can get quite long.
And so you might end up, you know, having a document that doesn't fit
into the URL of the, well, in the network.
So they use post.
But you can also change it to be get.
So if you need to, you can change to be get,
and it makes things a bit more, they make it easier to cache.
But we can go into that later maybe.
And yeah, when I send this document, I'm basically sending the query.
And if I have some variables, like if I want to make a dynamic request,
that's also going to be sent.
And yeah, we're going to see, I guess,
this API at the moment doesn't have really much.
It's only this field.
So we're not going to see all the power feature of GraphQL,
but we'll see them while we implement everything.
On top of that, there is also like a documentation.
So this is built automatically by GraphQL.
So every time you create a GraphQL API, it has a schema.
And this schema has all the types that you can use
and all the operations that you can do.
So one thing to note here is that there is two types.
One is called query, and one is called mutation.
Query is basically fetching data.
So it could be equivalent to a get request.
In this case, we only have hello.
And then we have mutation that's equivalent to like anything that's
not get, like pause, delete, patch, put, and so on.
It allows you to do anything that has side effects on your database,
for example, on your server.
Yeah. There's also another one.
It's called subscription.
We allow you to subscribe to events.
We're not going to see that today.
Also, mutation has one field called hello as well.
But we're going to create one and see how everything works.
Okay. Just so right there, you can follow the tutorial here,
workshop.strawberrytherocks.
And yeah, so that's basically like GraphQL in a nutshell.
So you can send the query like this, and then you get data back.
If you want to use a mutation, like the syntax is the same,
but you change the operation type at the top.
So you can do query or mutation.
And if you omit it, that's going to be a query by default,
just to make it be nicer to run queries.
Cool. Let's see.
Next. So as I mentioned, like GraphQL is similar to REST,
but like the main difference is that you only have one endpoint,
which is usually search GraphQL, or it could be just slash,
if you have just an API.
Oops. Yeah.
So instead of using URLs, you send a document.
So instead of going to slash user or slash hello, you go to slash GraphQL
and you send this document like we sent.
And then the server is going to return the data based
on the request that you made.
Which is quite nice because you can basically customize the response
based on what you need.
So if you need some fields, you can fetch them.
If you don't need them, you're not going to get them,
which is what happens with REST, for example.
Yeah. This could be useful, but I think it's worth mentioning.
So when you execute a GraphQL request, there's a few steps
that happens on the server.
And this is all done for you by server GraphQL and GraphQL core.
So the first step is parsing.
So we receive the JSON.
We parse the query inside the JSON.
And that already makes sure
that you don't send documents that are not valid in terms of,
you know, the shape.
Then there's another step called validation.
And this checks that you are basically requesting fields
that exist passing the right type of variables and so on.
And so, for example, if you send a document,
which I maybe can show you, like this, this is not going to run.
It's not going to do anything on the server
because it's not a valid document.
And this happens even if you parse multiple fields.
So this query is not going to run.
This field, hello, is not even going to fetch
because the query is not valid, which is nice.
Then the last step is the, well, there's actually just two steps
into the execution, but basically when we have this document,
we parse into an ST.
We go and see all the fields that we want to fetch,
and then we call something called a resolver,
which is a Python function that fetches data
for the specific field.
And then before returning everything, we also check
that the return type is actually the one
that we're expecting.
So, for example, if I go here, I can see that this is a string
and it's required.
So if I'm sending none, I'm not going to receive none
in my response.
I'm going to receive an error because this field is mandatory,
which is a nice feature of GraphQL,
because every time you do a request,
you know what you're getting back.
And, yeah, when you receive a GraphQL request,
you get everything into data, which you can see here,
or errors.
If there's any error, you're going to see here.
Cool.
Okay, let's see.
Oh, actually, is there any question on this?
Okay.
So now I'm going to do a quick overview of how strawberry
works, because there's a few things that might be a bit
confusing.
So, yeah, maybe I'm going to do also an introduction
of the folder and everything.
So there's a couple of things here that you can worry,
and not worry about.
There's just the CLI docs and exercises.
So the rest is all, almost everything Django specific.
So there is a user folder application that has the,
all the models for the users.
We're going to use that to authenticate later
in the workshop.
Then there is one folder called DB,
which I put all the models ready to the podcast,
just because I was lazy and I put everything into one file.
But there's only two models, so it's not crazy.
So we're going to use these models to store data
into the backend.
And then inside DB, we also have a data folder,
sorry, data module.
This is kind of a service layer.
So this is an abstraction on top of what Django provides.
And I maybe go a bit more into the details,
but this makes it easier to focus just on the GraphQL part
and not focusing on Django.
Like for example, there is a couple of things
that are specific to Django here,
which then are strictly related to GraphQL.
I also created some utilities for pagination.
And we are going to work mostly into the API folder.
So there's a view, which is basically the GraphQL view.
I customized a bit to basically have a function
to get the user in async,
because there are some issues with Django
with async at the moment.
And we also see why we're using async in this case.
It's for performance reason,
but we'll see specifically why I'm doing everything
in async here.
So the URL is just such a GraphQL.
This is the schema.
This is basically where our GraphQL API starts from.
So as I mentioned, every GraphQL API has a schema.
And for a schema, there is like usually a couple
of root types.
So in this case, there's a query and limitation.
The names, I mean, usually it's called query,
but it doesn't have to be query.
But basically these two are the entry points
of our GraphQL API.
So when I'm doing a query,
all the fields I'm gonna fetch for the query
are gonna come from this query type here.
And we can see this reflects to what we were doing before.
So there is a field called hello.
And then in this case returns hello words.
I'm gonna explain this index in a moment,
but again, this is exactly the same that we are seeing here.
So there's the query type,
which has one field called hello or type string.
And ignoring this for a second,
as strawberry wrap, it's using Python type ins.
Don't know if you've seen, this is like,
the syntax is basically the same as data classes.
So you basically use a decorator to tell strawberry
that this type is a GraphQL type.
And then we go and read all the properties
defined like this.
So there's the name of the property
and the type of the property.
And this is quite useful because when you use a type checker
like mypy, which I, there we go.
So it's gonna complain, for example,
an argument is missing, but for example,
if I pass a different type, it's also gonna come, oh yeah.
It's gonna complain about the type as well,
because it's expecting a string.
And I think this is one of the best feature of strawberry
because it basically gives you the benefit
of using types in Python, but also types in GraphQL,
which then you can also reuse in your clients
if you have steps to generate the types
from the GraphQL query.
Don't know if I have time to show you that,
but I think that's pretty cool.
So yeah, and then this other thing,
this is again inspired by data classes.
So this is a way to attach metadata to a field.
So for example, you could give a custom name.
So for example, if you wanna call it from,
which is not a valid Python keyword,
you can do from underscore and then the name from.
But the main thing here that we're doing
is passing this resolver.
And a resolver is basically a Python function
that gets called when I request this field,
this specific field.
So for example, if I change this and I do a load 12,
gonna call this and I get a load 12.
So you can see GraphQL as maybe a glorified
remote procedure call.
So it basically allows you to run functions
in your server, which I don't know,
once you put it this way, I think it's quite safe
over to understand what's happening.
So you can say I wanna call the function
for the field that load and that's what happens.
Let's see if I missed something.
Yeah, I guess I mentioned we took inspiration
from data classes and we're actually using
data classes on the dude.
And data classes basically a Python built in library
that allows you to create classes that have
all the useful methods like constructor,
representation equality methods and so on,
with just a couple of lines, which is quite nice.
Yeah, we mentioned resolvers and if you wanna also,
if you have everything running, you can try this out
and change this and see what happens.
You can also see if we do this, this is gonna complain.
I think, actually no, there is a, if I do this.
Yeah, so if I'm returning something that's no null
for a field that should be non-nullable,
that the field is gonna complain,
that GraphQL is gonna complain.
So that makes safe on your clients to assume
that this field is always gonna be there.
Yeah.
Oh, and if I return like one, so there is a question step
in GraphQL that converts the types that are compatible
to one to the other.
Yeah.
Do you have any questions about this?
I know it was a lot in just a short amount of time,
so yeah, here we go.
Okay, so let's go with our first API.
So this API is gonna allow us to fetch a podcast by ID
and if the podcast does not exist, it returns none.
So in REST, use the HTTP status code
to basically tell the user what happens.
So for example, if you haven't found something
you can do for a fort.
In GraphQL, everything is like 200.
Maybe sometimes you can use 401 for authentication reasons,
but by default, everything is 200, even if you have errors.
So if I, for example, do this,
this is probably gonna be, for run,
let me do this, yeah.
This is gonna be 200 because, yeah,
the way GraphQL is modeled is always to return 200,
which makes it be annoying to monitor things.
That's why there's a lot of tools,
like the ones from Apollo for these kind of things,
but basically, instead of using HTTP for the meaning,
use the schema for the meaning.
So for example, if you wanna say,
get me a podcast, to say that the podcast does not exist,
you return none instead of returning an error, for example.
So just something convention that you can have.
Okay, so this is our data model.
So again, everything lives inside the models inside DB.
We're not gonna touch any of this, this should work.
So the podcast has an ID, has a title, subtitle,
hosted by, and it's normal things
you would expect from a podcast.
Yeah, so to expose this into an API,
we need to create a type.
So by default, I guess one misconception in GraphQL
is I expose everything, but it's not the case
like you expose what you want to expose in your API.
I mean, there's tools that allow you to create
a GraphQL API from a database, but I don't know,
I don't think it's the best way of doing that,
because it's very easy to expose things
that you don't wanna expose,
and also it ties your GraphQL API, or your API in general,
to a database, which I don't know,
I don't think it's the right way of doing an API.
Okay, so let's keep it simple.
Let's say on expose three fields,
so ID, title, and description.
So we can do this together, or I can do it for you as well.
We can go to Podcast Types,
and I just import everything here.
Let me see.
Okay.
I think my editor is a bit messed up anyway.
So to recap, I created a class called Podcast.
This is gonna be used for the name of the GraphQL type.
Again, this can be changed using the strawberry type,
so if you wanna change the name, you can do that as well.
But by default, it gets the name of the class.
And then there's three fields here.
Title and description are both strings,
and then ID is using a custom type called ID.
This is a type in GraphQL that represents
Biscuit and ID, a unique identifier
for something in your API.
You could use integer or string here,
but ID, it's helpful to tell the consumer of the API
that this is a unique identifier for this type.
Yeah, and then once we have this field,
we can create a GraphQL query.
So we go to Podcast slash query.
We're gonna go here.
So now there is an empty query,
and I'm gonna just change this to use the,
to add the Podcast field.
So here we've done something a bit different
than what we have done in our schema.
So let me put this side by side.
So in strawberry, there is two ways
of defining a resolver, mostly for convenience reason.
So the first way is to pass the resolver as a,
just as a parameter to the server, the field function.
This could be also a function like this.
It doesn't have to be a lambda.
Lambda is useful for testing and showing example.
The other way is to using as a kind of decorator
on a method.
So you can see this as a class method
or static method decorator.
And basically it's almost the same.
Under the hood, there's no difference between this
and this.
It's just a nicer way.
Sometimes it makes it easier to kind of define
resolver for a specific field in a class,
because otherwise we would need to create
the podcast like this.
Podcast.
And then we need to pass the resolver here.
So we do everything in one step, which is quite nice.
And what strawberry is gonna do
is gonna get the return type of the resolver
and put it into the schema.
We're gonna see that in a moment.
And it does the same for the arguments.
So if I go back to my API now and I refresh,
I should see the schema being updated.
And so there is this new field called podcast,
which accept ID, which is not,
which cannot be null.
So the question, the exhibition mark means
that you always have to pass this field
or this argument in this case.
And podcast in this case, there's no exclamation marks.
So it means that it can be null.
So if I go and try this now,
if I go podcast ID, something random,
and I try to get the ID and title,
this is how you can fetch nested fields.
So like that.
And if I try to get this, I'm gonna get null,
which is the JavaScript equivalent of none,
which is what we expect.
And because basically we're returning none here.
And we are allowing us to return none
by using the optional class or type from the typing module.
So inside this typing module,
there is a lot of classes that you can use
to basically say what type is something.
So for example, you can have tuple, list, unions, and so on.
And in modern Python, I think from Python 3.9 or 10,
you can also do, well, this syntax,
you can do it from Python 3.10.
So you can do podcasts or none.
It's the same, it's just a bit nicer.
And this is one of the reasons why I recommend you
to use the latest version of Python,
because it makes typing a bit nicer, a bit cleaner.
And in the past, for example,
if you wanted to return a list,
you needed to do this, importing a list from here.
But now you can do lists like it's lowercase,
so you can use the built-in.
Okay, so now we created a query
that allows you to fetch a podcast by ID,
but it doesn't really do anything.
So it's a big user.
So let's go and update this
to use our Django database to fetch data.
There we go.
So this is, we've seen this.
And now we're gonna do this.
So there is this data module inside DB,
which exposes a couple of functions
that makes it easier to fetch data from our Django database.
So I'm gonna use that.
So I'm gonna import data,
and then I'm gonna do podcast equals,
find podcasts by ID, there we go.
And so this function is gonna try
and fetch the podcast by ID from the Django database.
And it's also async.
Again, we're gonna see why that's the case in the moment.
In summary, you can both use async and sync resolver,
so I can change this.
Well, I cannot change this one specifically,
but if I wanted to make this non-sync, async, sorry,
you can do that, and it works.
The issue with Django at the moment
is that if you're trying to run a database query
inside an async context,
so even if this field is sync,
the GraphQL view that we're using is the async one,
so Django is gonna complain
because it's not safe to run database calls
inside async context.
You have to use sync to async.
But hopefully that's gonna change in future.
Django is working, it's adding,
every new release is adding more async features,
so things like this is gonna be easier.
Yeah, so if we get, let me,
just gonna copy this to make it easier.
So I'm getting a podcast from database,
then if there is a podcast,
I'm gonna return a podcast from my GraphQL API.
Just gonna do something quickly
to hide some of these errors.
Cool.
So there is PyLens, it's an alternative to MyPy,
it's a bit more straight on types,
so in this case it's telling me
that UID is not compatible with ID,
so I could just train maybe, that should work.
And this doesn't matter too much at the moment,
so we can ignore it.
Okay, so as I mentioned,
we fetching this podcast
and then we're returning a podcast instance.
So one thing that I think it's a bit annoying
from the way this API works,
or like this, the way this structure I put
is that this podcast is a podcast model,
this is a podcast type,
so there is two types named the same thing,
which is a bit annoying and confusing sometimes,
so we're gonna see a nicer way
to maybe at least prevent this,
or to make it generic,
but as I mentioned,
this is a trade off of my creating
graphical API from a database,
so you either return everything,
so you convert a Django model directly to a graphical type,
or you do this kind of second step
of creating an additional type and returning it out.
I do prefer this way,
because it makes me think more about the API
and the use case,
and this is what I would recommend you.
And the nice thing of this is that you don't have
to worry too much about database,
because you create this type,
and then inside the resolver,
you can maybe fetch multiple things if you need to,
so for example, if you needed some things
that come from another model,
you can do that as well.
Cool, so this should work now,
so I'm gonna save it,
and I'm gonna try again.
So actually, with this way,
it's gonna complain because this is not a valid UID,
so we're gonna see an error here.
So this is something that
is not something you should keep available,
so in server, there is,
oh, I just wanna explain this a bit better.
So this message is coming straight from the exception
that Django is raising.
So Django is trying to convert this one, two, three,
to a UID, and so it raises an exception,
because it's not able to do that.
So we should not throw errors like this with an API,
so in server, there is an extension called mask errors.
Let's see if I can, here we go.
This extension that you can enable,
and then this is basically gonna hide
all these errors for you,
so you don't have to worry about
leaking some parts of your code base
because they were an exception.
I'm not gonna enable this
because it's gonna be useful for the workshop,
but basically, if you're working with a GraphQL API,
hide all the errors if possible,
because the default implementation in,
I think in almost any language,
GraphQL is just to return the error message like that,
so you need an extension to hide the message.
You also get the, I should get the,
you also get the exception here on the command line.
Okay, let's actually go and get an ID.
See, I might have, yeah, I created a small
util function to get the IDs,
so we can use any of this.
Oh, sorry.
Okay, now if I try this and I run it,
I should get the old information that I wanted,
so this is coming from the database and it's actual data.
And again, one of the powerful things of GraphQL
is that you can basically decide what to get.
So if I wanna only get the title,
I can do that just like that.
Yes, and if I try to maybe fetch an ID that's not valid,
that does not exist but still valid,
I'm gonna get this empty response.
Okay, so yeah, this is where we go.
Is there any question about this now?
Okay, now we're gonna see pagination.
So pagination is a bit tricky in GraphQL,
mostly because every time there is a new,
kind of new way of doing things,
like we try to reinvent everything from scratch.
How do I do pagination in GraphQL?
But the other thing, you're basically not limited
by GraphQL, you can do anything that you want.
So you can return something like this,
so you can do a basic pagination,
which you basically can pass a page number,
and you can pass a number of items that you wanna get
for that specific page.
So I think I did implement this, yeah,
so we can see how this works in a moment.
We're also gonna see why this might not be the best,
and we're gonna see a slightly more complicated version
but it's a bit more useful.
So, but let's start with this.
So we're gonna create a new field called podcasts.
We got, I'm gonna import this here, as I mentioned.
There you go, so here, we basically did the same thing
that we've done before, but it's a couple of different.
So first thing, we are using default values for the fields.
So for example, here, page, we always say,
we wanna fetch the first page,
unless it's someone passes another one,
and we always say we wanna fetch 10 items,
unless otherwise.
Then we use this function called podcast,
which basically does all the pagination for us.
And that's pretty much it.
And I guess, once you know how to create a resolver,
it's pretty simple to create another one, yeah.
Do you mind showing the podcast CLI command again?
Yes.
Yeah, this one.
You just run that with the terminal?
Yes.
Okay, thanks.
Yeah.
Yeah, you.
That's quite moving, indeed.
Oh yes, sorry.
Okay.
Gonna make a bit.
Is there any discussion?
Okay.
Any other question?
Just feel free to stop me,
because I might be going too fast.
Again, there's quite a few things to do.
Yeah, in this resolver, again,
we pass into parameters and returning a list of podcasts.
So I can go here, and I can try this again.
If I refresh the schema,
I should be able to see this new field here.
So there is a podcast field here.
You can see that the default values
are also specifying into the schema.
So you can also see all of that.
So I'm gonna try that now.
Podcasts, and I'm gonna do,
well, I'm just gonna do podcasts like this,
and I'm gonna get ID and title.
And yeah, that works.
It's basically what we would expect.
I guess one thing to note is that
when you're working with lists,
like the syntax of GraphQL is the same.
There is no, like you don't have to use square brackets
for saying I wanna fetch all the items for that.
It's exactly the same.
Which sometimes it might be confusing
because this would be one item,
this is like multiple items.
And yeah, we can also pass parameters like this.
So I wanna do page one and per page, do two.
And now it's only getting two.
And if I go page two, it's gonna get the other ones.
And I guess maybe this is a good time
to introduce also variables.
So in, like when you're working with GraphQL,
like passing parameters like this,
it's fine if you're doing some testing,
but it's not great if you're using a query
inside your GraphQL app,
because basically that means that
if you wanna go to page two,
you have to change your old query.
And so the way to kind of fix this is to use variables.
So for example, you can do query like this,
and then I can pass,
fetch podcasts.
So this first thing is the operation type.
It's basically saying I'm gonna do a query
for our mutation, in this case it's a query.
The second thing here is a name for this operation.
And this is actually not mandatory,
so you can skip it,
but it's basically useful if you wanna do logging
and basically kind of see like a quick glance
on a monitoring tool, what operations someone was doing.
And then you can specify all the variables here.
So I wanna do page of, sorry,
there are page of type number integer,
and in this case it's mandatory.
So fetch right around this is gonna complain
because I haven't passed any variables,
and you pass variables in this case here.
So page one.
And if I check the network response,
I can see here that inside my payload,
I'm doing an operation name,
which is called fetch podcasts,
then the query, and then the variables.
So it's just a nicer way of dealing with like dynamic data
and passing multiple things.
And this is actually gonna be useful
like in more advanced use cases,
if you wanna do, other than monitor,
you can also say I wanna only allow some specific queries,
so you can use the names and the document to do that.
More than the name, you would use a document
because you can basically have an allow list of queries,
and I'd say have this query in my database or in my store,
and I only wanna allow this query to run some other way,
which I don't think we,
we might be able to see that today, but I don't know.
Cool.
Yeah, one issue of this is at the moment,
like if I'm trying to fetch page, I don't know,
minus one, it's gonna work.
Well, it's gonna turn an error,
but like, I mean, that's actually a good error.
Let me do something a bit more annoying.
So if I do per page and if I do something like this,
it's not gonna complain because we not put any validation,
and like allowing users to do something like this
is not ideal because we don't want them to fetch so much data
because they can easily DDoS our server
if there are multiple requests like this and so on.
So one quick way of fixing this
is by just doing an assert inside your code,
which I'm just gonna copy and paste like this.
So, let me just fix this.
So here, I'm basically checking if the page is less than one,
then I return an error.
If it's per page is less than one,
I also return an error,
and the same for max length.
So I only wanna allow a maximum 50 items return.
So if I go and try this,
see, per page must be less than 50.
And so if I go to, I don't know, 40, that's gonna work.
So this is a very quick way of kind of, yeah,
doing validation in GraphQL.
We do also have some support for Pydantic.
I don't think it's great at the moment.
It's a bit annoying the way I use it,
but you could also use Pydantic here.
Well, I really wanna have Pydantic
as first class support at some point,
but that's gonna take quite a while.
But yeah, basically this is something, again,
for every API that you're building,
you should definitely make sure that you're not returning
more than specific amount of data.
You can do this inside of here,
well, inside the resolver.
You can also do this inside the paginate function,
which already was doing it.
But again, just make sure that you do these kind of things
so you don't allow people to return too much data,
especially in GraphQL,
since you could even do something like this.
So you can request this field using an alias multiple times.
Let me do this.
And so you can see,
I'm basically doing this request multiple times,
and this is gonna do two SQL call in my data
and it's not gonna be great.
So just putting some limit in place would be nice.
And I'm working on another extension for Strawberry
to prevent these kind of things from happening.
So you can say, I wanna allow maximum three aliases.
At the moment, you can still do a query
that's not great like this and doing a big document.
And yeah, that's gonna be annoying for your server.
So this is some of the feature
that's coming up hopefully soon.
The gist of this is like every time you allow someone
to kind of do filters on your database,
you make sure that you limit them for doing too much.
So like fetching too much data
or even filtering too many things
that they might not be able to see
or should not be, not see.
Yeah, so one additional addition of this
is that at the moment, we just get a list of items.
So we don't have a way to basically say,
oh, there's another page or this is the previous page.
So a way to fix that is to basically change our schema
to add more, an additional level.
So you can do items like this
and inside items I'm returning the podcast
and then I can have something called page info
or this could be anything to be honest.
And you can do something like ask next, ask prev and so on.
So this allows your client to basically understand
what's in the response.
So if you have more data or less data.
I'm gonna close this page
because I'm getting there all the time.
Yeah, so again, we can do something like this
which is called paginate the podcast.
I mean, this one is a bit simpler.
So maybe let's actually implement this.
So we have this.
So again, I can spray forward to create new types.
So instead of returning a list of podcasts,
I'm returning a kind of container
like a wrapper on top of that.
And I also have an additional field called ask next page.
So here, instead of returning this,
I do paginate the podcast items equals this and
this I think this is wrong.
Let me just copy this to be easier.
There we go.
Next page is this.
And now this is complaining
because I haven't updated the type here.
So I'm gonna do this quickly here.
And now it works.
And so if I go and try this query again,
gonna refresh here.
So items works and then I need to change this.
And you can see here that now we have a nicer shape,
a shape that's more useful for our clients.
And again, this is something that you
kind of need to think about.
How is this API is gonna be used?
If you know that for example, this page,
you need to always, you have to show the next item.
This is a very basic example.
Like just try to model the query based on the usage.
That's what I'm saying.
Don't think about the data that you have,
think about how it's gonna be used.
So you make an API that's very easy to use
and very flexible.
So in this case again, we have the as next page.
We don't have a prev because we might not need it,
but we can also add that one in.
Let me check one more thing.
Yeah, this is how we tested it.
And before showing another way of doing the pagination,
just wanna show one thing that I usually do
for kind of getting rid of the duplicate code.
So here we are doing this code all over again,
like we're doing here, we're doing here,
and we might be doing in other places in future.
So one thing that I usually do is to create a class method
on the podcast, which allows us to convert this,
a Django model into this type.
And so this is what I usually do.
So I create a class method like this.
And, sorry, it's gonna be dead.
There we go.
It's gonna also fix the typing issues.
So yeah, basically I create a helper method
on the podcast type that basically knows how to convert
a Django model into itself.
And this is quite useful because you only have one way
of converting this into a Django model into this.
And yeah, there's also other ways of creating
like a generic converter, but I think this is like
the cleanest and the one I do prefer the most.
And it also helps a bit with types, because for example,
if you do something like this, it's gonna tell you like,
look, this member does not exist on the podcast model.
And if you're not familiar with types as well,
like this thing here, the reason why I'm putting
quotes around it is because this type is not defined yet.
And so we need to basically change it to be a forward
reference, a reference to a type that's gonna be
evaluated later.
There's also another way which is from
future import annotation,
which is basically changing all the annotation
to be strings for us on the dot.
So you could do this as well, but again,
it's not too important.
This is something that might change a bit in future,
like there was a big, I don't know, debate on how this
should work in future, because at the moment,
like this, again, is making this a string.
It's making the coding side strawberry in other library.
By then, it can be more complicated,
because you have to deal either with types or strings,
and it's been messy, but in future, hopefully,
we can remove some of that code that we have.
But yeah, basically, this is a way to say,
this is the type that does not yet exist,
but it's gonna exist.
And type checkers like Pylance and MyPy,
they know, or even Flakate, they know that this is a
reference, so they're gonna check if that type exists or not.
And so now that we have this util function or method,
we can change this, and we can do from db like this,
and we can do the same here.
So a bit more nicer and easier to read,
so it's a nice code there.
Cool, do you have any question about this?
Okay.
Cool.
So how do we actually get the next pages?
How do we get the next pages?
Do you wanna know how we get if there's more pages or?
No, so if we turn the next pages,
so how do we go for the next page?
Yeah, that's a good question.
So the question is basically, how do we get the next page?
So in this case, in your frontend,
you can check if as next page is true,
then you can increment this, this variable.
Another option, you can also do next page,
and this will be an integer, so you can use that
inside your variable as well,
so if you wanna do less computation on the frontend.
Yeah, so this both ways, yeah.
So either you increment the counter if this is true,
or you return the next page number as well.
Again, this is like preference as well.
I think as next page is quite common,
and then you increment things.
So the other pagination I wanna show,
it's a bit more involved,
but I think it's important to kinda see this
because this is gonna come up a lot if you use GraphQL,
which is the relay specification,
and again, this was created by Facebook
to basically solve the way they do pagination,
and this works very well if you have pagination
that has a lot of data, so for example,
feed on Facebook has a lot of data,
and using offset in most databases quite slow
because it has to scan the old table and go to the offset,
and so one way of fixing this is gonna be by using cursors,
which we gonna use a Django cursor pagination,
this library that basically implements
the cursors on Django,
so basically it's an additional paginator
that allows you to kinda use a cursor instead of a offset
to navigate to like a point in time or like next items.
I honestly forgot how it works,
but usually if you're working with this,
you don't have to worry too much how it works,
but if I remember correctly,
you basically need an ID that's stable and sequential,
or maybe a date time.
Anyway, again, this is not too important for what we're seeing.
I mostly wanted to show you this pagination
because it's used a lot in GafQL,
because again, it's being polarized by Facebook
by this relay specification,
and we also gonna see a couple of,
well, one feature that I think is really interesting
in Sorbet, which is the generics,
so we gonna see that as well.
So the way the relay pagination works
is that it's a bit verbose, it has a connection type,
which is similar to our wrapper type
that we created for paginated podcasts,
so it includes these items,
but every connection, so this is gonna be,
this podcast is a connection for podcasts,
there's gonna be a page info like we seen before,
and then there's gonna be a list of edges,
and inside every edge is gonna be a node.
Again, this is quite verbose,
but it can also be simplified,
like some people just do nodes instead of edges,
I just wanted to show you how it works,
because it's gonna be useful.
Yeah, I'm gonna go more into the details
while we implement this.
One thing of this, so there is a,
let me see if I can find it, there we go.
This request has been going on for a couple of maybe months
in Sorbet to make the implementation relay
a bit easier, so instead of doing these types
that you have to do now manually,
it's gonna be handled for you.
I don't have a code now,
so this is one of those things I mentioned
that it's gonna be easier in future,
so once that's merged, I'm gonna update this workshop
to include that feature instead of us
creating the types manually,
but again, it's not that difficult anyway.
I guess the most difficult part is to implement
the course of pagination that in this case is done
by this Django package.
Yeah, so we're gonna create three types now.
We're gonna create one, which is the connection
that returns all this information, so page info edges,
and then we're gonna create the page info type,
which is all the information for the page,
then we're gonna create the edge type,
which is basically what contains our item.
One reason why there is edges is that
like for root level things, so like things that come
from the APIs, like from the root level,
they're not too important, but if you are doing
a pagination, for example, if you have a person
that wanna do a friends pagination,
instead of having, for example, if you wanna show
the relationship type between these two friends,
instead of having inside the node,
which might not make sense, because it's a field
that's specific to a connection, you can have it on edges.
So for example, if this was friends on a user,
you would have edges, and then for example, relations type.
This is the reason why there is this additional edge field,
so you can add additional fields that are specific
to that connection.
Don't know if that makes sense, but it's basically
another place where you can put metadata
to a specific connection between types.
Okay, so again, I mentioned like we're using
Django cluster pagination, so that's gonna do everything
for us, which is quite nice, and we're gonna use
the generic type.
So Python has support for generic types
inside the standard library for types,
and that allows you to basically create types
that can be reused over time.
We actually seen a couple of these already,
so we seen optional, we seen list.
These are generic types that basically allow you to,
basically, they can be reused for any kind of thing.
So here I'm using list, here I'm using podcasts.
Well, this is not really readable,
but I'll show you an example how it works.
So we actually created already some for you.
So we do have here, we have these three types.
So let's start with page info is like a normal type.
So as all the information that we mentioned,
has next page as previous start and end cursor.
So this allow you to go back and forth into the page.
There's also a helper method that allows you
to convert the database page into a page info.
Then there's these two types here, hedge and connection.
So the first thing that we did is to create a type var.
So a type var is basically like a placeholder for type.
So when you create a type like this, a class like this,
I'm saying this is a generic class on node,
and this becomes a placeholder inside your class.
So if I go in my code and I do something like this,
edge of string, the node here is gonna be a string.
And cursor is gonna be a string as well.
So if I do, for example, this,
I can see here in the autocomplete,
it's gonna say node is a string.
If I change this to integer,
it's gonna change to integer.
So this is a very nice way of defining types
that can be reused into multiple contexts.
Because this ready pagination is generic,
you can work with any type that you might want.
So you can add podcasts, you might have episodes,
you might have users and things like that.
You don't have to create all the types all over again,
because that's gonna, this is gonna be done for you.
And I'll show you what happens when you use this in server.
So yeah, again, we created these three types,
and now we can reuse them.
So now we're gonna override the podcast field
to use the podcast connection.
The code is similar to what we had before.
There's just a couple of more things
for kind of conforming to the connection shape.
So I need to import this here from API.pagination.types.
I'm gonna import everything, here we go.
So this is what we had before.
So we're fetching, we're gonna remove this check for now.
So we're using our database utils to find the podcast
from, yeah, after this cursor,
and then we can also have a first.
So I wanna fetch first 10, first 20 and so on.
Then I'm converting the page info
from the one from database to the one for the GraphQL API.
And then finally, are we creating this connection?
And again, this is where things can be more verbose.
And this is something we did that progress
that I showed you is gonna make easier.
So this will be one line.
So you can just return the list of podcasts.
Yeah, basically that's it.
This is gonna create three more types
for you automatically from the generic types.
So if I go here and I change this query
to be the one that we just created.
So let's do, it's gonna remove this for now.
So I'm gonna fetch the first 10 podcasts.
And now you're gonna see how verbose it is.
So there is the page info has next page as prev.
Oh, well as prev.
It's gonna do first one.
And you can see now there is edges.
Inside edges there is node.
And then there's the information that we're looking for.
Again, this is a bit verbose.
It could be changed to be nodes.
Oh, sorry, nodes like this.
I just wanted to show you the full API
that's from the specification in RIDD.
There we go.
So if I try to fetch this, I can see now that there is a,
you know, there's this the page info
which has all the information that we wanted
and also all the edges.
And I can also get the start and poster.
So this is gonna be a basic C4 encoded string
of the type and the ID.
I don't know why they chose this, but I think relay.
Yeah, I think relay is using this
for caching on the front end.
So it basically has a key value store
where the ID is this one
and then the cache is the value of the node.
But anyway, this is just an implementation detail.
And then I can do after this cursor
and I should get another one.
It's all quite into me.
And if I change this again, I should get this as well.
And so this is how you can also do
pagination with the cursor.
So you get the end cursor
which is gonna be the cursor for the next page
and then you can go from there.
Yeah, and with the generic types,
you basically created this podcasts connection,
podcast edge automatically
without you having to write any additional code.
And this is gonna be useful also
like once we do for example, pagination for episodes,
we're gonna create another two types,
one for the episode edge,
one for the episode connection and so on,
which is quite nice
because you don't have to go
and create all these types manually.
So you don't have to create a new connection
for a specific type.
Okay.
There is a useful article here.
It's a bit old, but it's like the specification hasn't changed
and it explains all the information about the relay
and also the difference within the standard pagination.
If somebody shows the Google pagination here,
which is a page pagination.
This is like page pagination is something you cannot do
with relay because it uses cursor.
So there is no way to jump to a specific page.
And so that's one of the trade off
for also this pagination.
It allows you to list a lot of data,
like quite performantly,
but you cannot jump straight to a specific page, unfortunately.
Yeah, definitely recommend to read that
if you're curious.
I'm gonna pause a bit and see if there's any question.
Oh yeah.
So yeah, what are the benefits of generics?
So let me show you this again.
So if I didn't have generic,
I would need to create a class called podcast connection,
which has a list of edges.
Also notice that here I'm using the lowercase versions.
This list of edge,
a podcast edge and then page info.
So this, I would basically need to duplicate all this code.
For every connection that I need to make.
So this would be a podcast connection,
sorry, podcast edge and this would be a podcast.
This would be like this.
Yes.
Yeah, this is exactly what the relay pagination,
the relay implementation is gonna do for you.
Let me see if there is an example of this.
Actually before going into that, is that clear?
So this connection podcast.
So these three, four lines are basically done in one
using this and it's the same here.
So edge, podcast and it's fine if you have one,
but once you have more, like for example,
if you're gonna do episode,
you will need to duplicate all the code over again.
So it's quite nice.
Yeah, let me see if there is an example of this.
Again, this progress is quite big and it's quite nice.
It does have quite a couple of features
that I think are really useful.
Oh yeah, there's a guides.
Yeah, this is, I'm thinking maybe a bit more time, but.
I cannot find it now, but yeah,
basically it's gonna be something like,
let me see, sorry, the relayed of field
and then you pass this and you will return
maybe just a list of podcasts.
So you could return maybe this.
And that would be, and all the machinery that I've done now,
it would be done by strawberry itself.
We're just taking a bit of time to make sure
that we gather all the cases
because this progress is coming from strawberry Django,
which is tied to Django and it's basically useful.
It's really useful if you wanna convert something directly
from a Django model to a graphical type,
but we want to make sure that this also works
in a generic way.
So taking a bit of time to make sure
that there's all the old cases.
Like for example, if you wanna do this,
the first implementation didn't have a way to do conversion
from one time to the other manually.
So hopefully that some comes soon.
Cool.
Again, if there is any question, just feel free to stop me.
So we're gonna see now
the, just a bit of data fetching optimization.
So this is something that's gonna be quite important
in GraphQL.
So the patterns are a bit different
in than what you would do with REST.
I mean, you can still do some of the things
you can do in REST, but there's other ways of,
which are more, I guess, GraphQL native
to the optimization.
So yeah, before I guess understanding
how the data fetching works,
like we need to do a bit of work
to show an issue of fetching data in GraphQL.
For example, if I'm doing this query, here I am,
let me do this again.
I'm actually only doing one single database code,
which is fine, but it doesn't show what we wanted to show.
So we gonna introduce now a list of episodes.
So we gonna allow us to fetch the latest episodes
from a podcast.
So we gonna see what's gonna happen in that case,
or maybe the other way around.
Let's see.
Yeah.
So the first thing it's gonna do,
we gonna create a new type called episode,
and this is gonna represent one single episode.
And there's a couple of things that are interesting here.
So, and let me do that.
So podcasts, types.
From.
I'm gonna fix this as well.
Finance is very strict on some stuff.
So the couple of things that are interesting here.
So first one is we using something called survey.private.
So every time you put a property on a survey type
on a class here, that's gonna be exposed to GraphQL.
But in this case, we don't wanna expose this podcast study
to GraphQL, because it's gonna be inside the podcast type.
So there is another generic type called survey.private,
which basically it's a wrapper on any type.
So you can say, I want to put a podcast ID
onto the episode class, but I don't want that
to live in GraphQL.
And so this is a way to do that.
Yeah, I think it's also quite nice.
And the reason why we create this is so that we can
use the podcast ID inside the podcast field.
So basically this episode type is gonna have an ID,
title, notes, published art, and a podcast.
And the podcast is a field that returns the podcast.
So it's gonna return this podcast here.
And to be able to, instead of instantiating the episode
with the podcast all the time,
we only pass the podcast ID,
and we only fetch the podcast when it's requested.
And I'm gonna show that how it works in a second,
and why it's actually useful to do that way.
And also we have the same thing that we've done before.
So conversion from the database model to a GraphQL type.
I did write these things here.
And let's also add this query.
Oops.
So now if I go to podcast, query.
And I'm adding a new query that fetches the latest episodes.
So last five episodes, for example, and returns them.
Perfect.
So if I go back to my GraphQL API,
move everything, and I fetch the scheme again.
Latest episodes, and I'm gonna fetch the title
for every episode.
So I'm able to see all the latest five episodes.
And we can also see there's only one database code,
which is fetching all the episodes,
all the latest five episodes.
This is quite nice,
because it's not fetching any information about the podcast,
because I haven't requested it.
But now if I go and try to fetch the podcast,
I guess one thing, we're not able to fetch the podcast ID
because that's private.
And the other thing, we are able to fetch
all the other information straight from the podcast.
So one cool thing of GraphQL is that allows you
to nest fields.
So you can have resolvers that nested,
and they only get called if you request them.
So in this case, I'm gonna request information
for the podcast for every episode.
And I can see here I'm getting all the data
for these episodes and the podcasts.
But at the same time, I'm also doing one call
for every episode, which is not what you want,
because this is like, if you have a lot of episodes,
this is gonna do a lot of database calls.
And this is known as the N plus one problem
in SQL, I guess.
So there is two ways of solving this.
So one way of doing this is by introspecting
the GraphQL request.
So let's see.
Okay, I do have an example here.
So in Subway, you can pass an additional parameter
to the resolver, which is called info.
And this parameter is basically similar to the request
in Django or Fast API.
And it basically gives you all the information
of this GraphQL query.
So you can see an example of this here.
So if I pass info here, I need to import.
Okay.
This is not important for now.
I need to put this before.
So now when I do this request,
I'm also gonna print this object, which is here.
It's a bit hard to read, but it basically has
all the information about this request.
So it does something that's very important,
which we're gonna use when we do the authentication,
which is the context, which allows us to get the request.
And using requests, we can also get the current user.
It has, let me see what else.
It has the current schema if you need to.
But the most important thing for optimization,
if you wanna do that, is the selected fields.
To have an example here, it's a bit easier to read.
So it allows you to basically see all the fields
that have been requested in this GraphQL API,
sorry, in this API call.
Let me, maybe I can print them.
Okay, I'm gonna try again.
And hopefully, we're gonna see.
There we go.
And this is not, the way I'm printing it,
it's not super useful, but basically,
you can see that we fetching title,
and we fetching podcast.
So in this resolver, we can see that we fetching the title
and the podcast.
So this gives a lot of information to us,
to the optimization, because I can say,
oh, I'm fetching the podcast,
then I'm gonna do some additional optimizations.
So for example, I can fetch all the episodes
with the podcast with them.
So in Django, you could do select related on,
if you're not using Django, you can do a join
and things like that.
I mean, this works.
The only thing is that this is coupling, again,
your GraphQL API to your database.
So if you change the shape of your database,
you have to go and update this kind of code
that does the optimization, which is a bit annoying.
There is, if you're using Django specifically,
so there is a strawberry Django Plus,
which is done by the community, which has a optimizer,
which does all of this for you.
So basically, you can add this extension,
then it's gonna do,
doesn't show the example,
it basically is gonna do all this optimization for you.
So it's gonna check what fields have been requested,
and then it's gonna fetch those
with a single database code with Django,
or it's gonna optimize it, like, yeah, here we go.
For example, it's gonna do prefetch related,
and in some cases, select related as well,
which is quite neat.
But again, this only works if you're using Django
and Django models, or it can be implemented
for other databases, but it's not the best way
of doing this kind of optimization in GraphQL.
So we're gonna see what's actually better than this.
Oh, not better, like, more GraphQL native again.
And it's data loaders.
So data loaders are a generic way
to do optimized data fetching in GraphQL,
but they can also be used without GraphQL, to be honest.
Let's see, okay.
So the way this works is that you create a data loader,
which is a class that knows how to fetch something
from a database, and basically, this class needs to know
how to fetch something from a database in a batched way.
So instead of fetching one item,
you fetch two, three at a time.
Let's actually see that in a moment.
Here we go.
Yeah, let's do this.
Okay, so the first thing you need for a data loader
is to basically create a loader function
that you then pass to the data loaders.
So in this case, we already have a Django wrapper function
that allows to fetch a list of podcasts by this.
So we're just using id in, so it's doing select
where id is in this list.
And then what we're doing here,
we're just returning a list of podcasts by id
in the same order of the id that we're getting back from,
but that we requested.
So for example, if I'm getting, if I'm doing this,
so three, I'm gonna receive something like object one,
object two, and so on.
The order is quite important.
I think we might change this API to allow you
to return dictionary directly,
but the reason why I did this is sometimes Django,
even if you're passing a list of id's,
it might return a different order
as you need to make sure that you're returning
the same order.
So this id need to match this id here.
But yeah, basically this is a way
to fetch multiple items in one go.
Okay, and then we create a podcast data loader,
which is this, passing the function
to load a list of podcasts by this.
And that's pretty much it.
This is pretty much the API of using data loader.
So you create a function that allows
to fetch a batch of items,
and then you create a data loader for that batch.
And then the way you use it is to,
changing all the code in the,
in your resolver to use the podcast loader
instead of what we had before.
Just gonna run this.
So inside our episode here,
instead of doing this fetch one database directly,
we use the data loader here.
This might be enough.
So now double check one thing here.
Yeah.
I forgot to mention, we also doing the conversion
from the Django database to the GraphQL type directly here.
So we don't have to do externally.
Yeah, basically this is it.
The reason why I'm doing the import here
is to prevent circling ports.
There's also other ways of doing this,
but this is the fastest way for this workshop.
Yeah, and it's basically, by doing this,
we resolve the M plus one problem.
We're gonna be doing two queries,
one to fetch the episodes
and one to fetch all the podcasts by the end.
That's it.
So you can see here, first query fetching all the episodes
and then I'm fetching all the podcasts with those IDs.
And the way this works,
and the reason why we're using async
is basically the inside data loader.
The code is a bit complex,
but basically there is a function that creates a batch
and then it dispatches the batch into the next event loop.
So the way the Python, as it works, there is an event loop
and then you can say run this code in the next event loop.
And so this gives enough time to the server
and Python to basically say fetch this,
but do it just later, just a bit later.
So it allows you to basically get all these IDs.
So these resolvers are gonna be called ones
for every episode,
then it's gonna put them into the next batch
and then when the next event loop runs,
it's gonna fetch all of them in ones.
Which is a quite neat API and it basically does,
in terms of the code, it's just this in Python.
So it just get this class and does everything for you.
There's also some checks and it allows you also
to use a cache, for example, with Redis, I think.
Yeah, so you can create a cache.
But if instead of saving this data in memory,
you wanna save on Redis, you can also do that.
You can customize it and it's quite a nice API
and it's quite easy to use.
And it also allows you to prevent
from fetching too much data at once.
So for example, if you, I don't know,
fetching a thousand items,
instead of doing one SQL call for a thousand IDs,
you can do, I don't know, 10 for 100 IDs at a time.
So you can also batch them.
Yeah, again, this is something that's built into strawberry
and the theme here is to reduce the amount of code
you have to write to make all this kind of optimization.
And yeah, there is also a very nice blog post about this,
which is a bit, it goes a bit more in depth
into how to explain also as like a nice graphics.
It kind of makes it more easy to understand
what's actually happening here.
So you can see, for example, like these are the resolvers
and they're called one at a time.
And so like you can see how the optimization works.
Yeah, do you have any questions about this?
Could I give you a second?
Okay.
So this is, I haven't put anything about
other kinds of optimization here,
but this is optimization about how you fetch data
in GraphQL, so like if you're using SQL database
or an external API as well,
like one cool thing of data loaders
that this works with anything.
It doesn't have to be a SQL database.
It could be NoSQL.
It can also be a CPAPI as long as it supports batching
or yeah, basically it's a very nice API
that makes it generic to optimize things.
Like for example, if we could change this to,
yeah, this function could also do ACP calls
and I think it's quite nice that you're able
to do this kind of optimization in GraphQL.
And again, we might change this API
to just return a dictionary or allow you to return
a dictionary instead of a list to make it be nicer to use.
It's been requested, but I never had the time to do that.
Yeah.
And again, this is the reason,
the only reason why we're using async is because of this,
but this async is also very useful
if you're doing ACP calls like to external APIs,
like it's quite common in GraphQL
to basically create a GraphQL API that wraps REST APIs
or other kind of APIs.
And so async would be quite beneficial there
because it allows you to run multiple requests
in parallel as well and also batch them.
There is some work done for also allowing some of this
in a sync context.
But there is an external project,
but I don't know if it's stable yet.
So if you wanna check that,
there's also a way to do it in sync,
but that basically changes the execution of store-bary.
So there is more code involved,
which might have some issues in future.
Cool.
Oh, we're doing quite well on time actually.
So the next step, we're gonna see authentication.
We're also gonna see mutations.
So it's a way to do anything with side effects
like deleting data or even sending an email for that matter.
So in terms of authentication,
again, this is nothing special of GraphQL.
GraphQL uses HTTP, so you can use API keys,
you can use JWT tokens or cookie-based authentication
or even basic authentication.
I usually do a cookie-based because I use Django
and that's built into Django,
so I don't have to worry too much about that.
But JWT is quite common.
And there's also third-party packages for a server
that allows you to do all the things that are necessary
for JWTs like refreshing token, getting tokens and so on.
Okay.
So yeah, mutations, I did mention this.
It's basically a way to run anything with side effect.
And the main difference is that instead of doing query
or not passing anything, you write mutation here,
then you can run a mutation like this.
When this case returns an error because it's not implemented.
But in terms of GraphQL, it's almost the same as a query,
but the semantic is different.
So one thing that's different is that basically
mutation means you're doing some side effects.
So this is something that should not be cast
or not tried more than once.
And also if you're running,
if you're doing multiple field selection
at the root level in a mutation,
so this is something that you can do in a query.
So you can fetch podcasts, you can fetch podcasts and so on.
This also works in mutation, but there is one key difference.
So this is gonna be run in parallel,
like concurrently in a query in this array.
So you're gonna run those two resolvers at the same time,
more or less.
In mutation, if you have multiple things,
like if you have mutation one or two,
they're gonna be sequential.
That's the main difference between query mutation
in terms of the execution step.
And this is done so that if there's an error here,
the other mutation doesn't run.
But that's basically it.
And if you're using get,
so if you, don't know if this actually works on me,
let me show an example of this.
So again, I mentioned I can,
in most graphical implementation,
you can also do queries like this,
like via get.
You cannot do this in for mutation,
because again, you don't wanna run mutation in a get.
If I try to do this, it's gonna deny,
it's gonna not allow it.
So you cannot run mutation using get.
This is also the other thing, a mutation.
It's just, there's some safety check
that doesn't allow you to do mutations using get.
That's quite nice.
Okay, so we are going to do a mutation
for logging in a user.
Again, we're gonna use most of the things
that are built by Django.
So our mutation is gonna be pretty simple.
But the way it works, it's basically the same as a query.
So you create a type, and then you create resolvers
for the fields in that type.
So, okay, we, I'm just gonna copy this,
and I'm gonna go through every single line here.
So if I go to authentication, mutation.
Well, I did copy this a couple times, okay.
Yeah, we're importing strawberry,
importing this info type.
So this is, again, I mentioned this earlier.
This is important for, allows us to fetch the request
from strawberry.
And then we have a class called context.
Info is a generic type, and in info, there is a context,
which it's what holds the request.
So if I go here, this is a type dictionary,
which has a request and response.
So I can use this to get the user,
and I can also use this to change the status code,
for example.
And then I have a function called authenticate the login,
which basically gets a request, email and password,
and then it runs the authentication on Django,
and it's doing the conversion from sync to sync
to prevent any issue with the database.
What else?
Yeah, oh, then I have a type called login payload.
This is basically the return type of my login mutation.
And then I have the, this is the old mutation I have.
So I have a class, which is like query,
which basically holds all the fields of this mutation.
It's one field called login,
which has the info parameter.
This is passed automatically by strawberry,
and it's what we can use to get the request from the context.
And then the two parameters, email and password.
And then it returns login payload.
So we try to login, if the user is none, return false.
If it's not none, return true.
And let's actually go and try this now.
Oh yeah, one thing here,
usually we do sort of a field.
This case I'm doing mutation.
But if you go and see the implementation
is basically the same at the moment.
Like mutations are not different than field per se.
Like the only difference is the way they run,
but that depends on the fact that you're doing a mutation
and not the way you actually implemented it.
The reason why we have this as a field like this,
like as a alias,
is that in future we want to put like more safety guards.
If you're doing, if using a DOM mutation in a query,
we want to return an error
because that's something that doesn't make sense.
Just to make it a bit easier to prevent mistakes.
Okay, so now I created this.
I don't have any users, so this is gonna return false.
But oh yeah, if I try to do login here,
it doesn't work because I need to do a mutation.
So I do a mutation.
And I do email.
Just gonna use my email.
Password.
And then I'm gonna fetch the field,
which is there's only one field, it's called okay.
Oh no, I do have a user, okay.
I think I created this a while ago.
Yeah, basically once I do this, I'm logged in.
And I'm gonna show you what's actually happening here.
Like this doesn't really give you much information
because it's just saying everything is fine.
But when I do this here,
in my response headers, there's gonna be a set cookie
and also set cookie for the CRF token
and one for the session ID.
So this is basically what it's logging me in.
This is done by Django.
So the function that's called authenticate and login,
this one is gonna use this authenticate function
which is gonna create the cookie for us
based on the backend.
But the default one is the session one,
which is this cookie.
And now every time I do another request,
I'm gonna be logged in.
And if I do, for example, if I change the password
and it's wrong, I'm gonna receive false
and I'm not gonna get that set cookie.
Sorry, response headers, there's no set cookie here.
Sorry, because I didn't get logged in.
Does that make sense?
So the, just maybe for reference for the future,
like if you're doing JWT,
like for the standard basic implementation,
it will be similar to this,
but you might either get a token like this here
or you can still use cookies.
With JWT, you can also use cookies,
which is like another way to transport them.
Yeah, there's many ways of doing authentication,
which is a bit annoying.
So this is why I stick to cookie authentication.
It's just, almost everything is handled by us
for a Django or FastAPI libraries.
Okay, so we've done this.
Okay, I already created a user for you.
So we can, we already did this.
So we tested everything and we also got the cookie.
So now we also wanna do something with the user.
So we wanna check if the user is authenticated for,
for example, preventing non-authenticated user
to the mutation or wanna allow only user,
specific user to the mutation.
For example, if you wanna maybe check
if they're subscribed or not,
we can prevent them to do something.
In this case, I'm just gonna check
if they're authenticated to keep it simple.
So I created already a, is authenticated class here.
So Strawberry supports permissions
similar to Django REST framework.
And basically the way it works is that you can pass
a permission to a field and every time the field runs,
so it's gonna check for the permissions.
And if any of those permission return false,
then the server is gonna raise an error,
it's not gonna run the field.
So in this case, we're checking if there is a user,
if the user is authenticated, then we can get the field.
So let's actually go and implement this mutation here.
So this mutation is gonna subscribe me to a podcast.
Okay, so this is similar to what we had before,
we're using the info parameter to get the current user,
and we're getting the is authenticated permission,
and then we're using the permission inside
the permission classes mutation.
And this is basically allowing us to make sure
that this mutation only runs if there is a user logged in.
In this case, we could even remove it
because otherwise the user would be none,
so we could do a check there,
but you can see this having, I don't know,
this premium user, for example, something like that.
So you can make this authentication,
like these permissions as custom as you want.
And just one note here,
we might change these permissions a bit in future
to be more flexible because for example,
at the moment you cannot do like all conditions
inside the authentication, sorry, inside the permissions.
So for example, if you wanted to do something
like is authenticated or is something,
this is not possible at the moment.
We want to implement that at some point in future,
and we might also get rid of the underscore classes,
so we can just do this,
but that hopefully is gonna come sooner rather than later.
But yeah, basically we checked this,
so we now are sure that every time this mutation runs,
it's only gonna run if there is a user.
And then we can do all the things that we did before,
so we can get requests, we can get the podcasts by ID,
if there is no podcasts return false,
and then we get the user and then we subscribe to user.
And if there is an error, return false.
Let me, let's actually try that.
Reputation, subscribe.
I need to refresh this.
Okay.
Need to get one ID from.
Okay, this one.
So now this mutation is a very basic mutation,
only returns true or false,
it makes it be harder to read.
So in this case, it returns false,
it means I'm already subscribed to something went wrong.
But if I try to run this, for example, in Neutro,
so if I create a new browser,
if I try to run the mutation, I should get an error.
So this is how you get errors using permissions,
which is maybe one thing we wanna make it easier to change,
but basically you get an error into the error response
and saying user is not authenticated,
because again, I'm not authenticated in this case.
But yeah, that's, let me see.
So that's pretty much it,
like it's one line to make sure that you are authenticated,
you have some specific permissions,
which is, I think it's quite nice.
And again, this is implementation of the permission.
So you have all the information
that could be useful for you to do permissions.
Like for example, there's source, which is the root type.
So for example, if this were an asset field,
you could get the parent to check some more information
on the parent, for example, if the parent owner
is the current user, you can do something like that.
You also get the context, the info,
which allows you to get the current user from the context,
and also additional keyword arguments
for the specific field.
Again, this is inspired by Django REST framework,
and we might slightly change it a bit in future,
but it's not gonna change very much.
Yeah, so again, is there any question about this?
Because I wanted to show you something related to the error.
So like this, this mutation is a bad mutation.
This is not something you should do with GraphQL,
like returning true or false,
so that claim to imitation is not,
or it's not, I don't know, it's not a great developer
experience or user experience for two reasons.
One, this false is a bit generic,
it doesn't really give you a lot of meaning on what happened,
why did I get false, right?
Because it could be for multiple reasons.
Like it could be because the podcast does not exist,
it could be because I'm already subscribed,
and on top of that, I'm not really taking
a lot of advantages from GraphQL,
like when you're doing mutations or queries in general,
you should return like rich types,
so in this case, we could return a podcast,
so I can get also all the information back.
So for example, if I'm doing a mutation
that changes a podcast title,
I can make it so that it returns the actual podcast
with a new title, and so that I can use that title
to update the UI in my application.
And this is something that's actually handled
automatically by clients like Apollo client or Oracle.
Like if you're returning a type, sorry,
an object with a specific type and ID,
it's gonna update the cache and update all the pages
automatically in your client, which is quite nice.
But the main thing is not be able to understand
why, what this false means.
So we're gonna see how to handle errors a bit better.
And we've seen this, so we've seen an example
of using just like standard exceptions,
so returning, raising a value error,
and we get something like this in our GraphQL response,
which is okay, but it's not a great, great experience.
So like one strategy is to use something called union types.
And union types are basically a way to say
this field is gonna return not just one type,
but like to return two different types,
always one at a time.
So I'm gonna see that in a second.
So let's change this addition that we had before,
which is returning bold, to return different types
based on either the podcast does not exist
or the user is already subscribed.
I guess one takeaway of this is also like
there is two different types of errors in general
or is that expected errors and unexpected errors.
Expected errors are like this one that we just mentioned,
are errors that we know that can happen
and errors that might happen a lot
that you might want to show different UI to users.
For example, like the podcast does not exist
or the user is already subscribed.
It's a good example of that.
Unexpected errors, anything else,
like for example, database being down
or I don't know, something else like not going well
with this mutation.
The idea is that you always kind of take into account
all these expected errors or these errors
that you want to kind of present in a nicer way to your user
and then the unexpected errors you basically do,
you just leave them as it is,
like you return them like this
and then there's a generic message on your UI.
Yeah, so we mentioned that we're gonna handle errors
using union types and we have three cases.
So podcast does not exist, users are already subscribed,
everything went well and we're gonna model these three cases
using three different types.
The first one is gonna be a type called
podcast does not exist error, which has just a message
and then the second one is gonna be already subscribed
to podcast error.
They're very verbose but they make it very easy
to understand what happened
and then the last one is subscribe to podcast success
and it returns a podcast.
And then we're gonna use a union type.
Let's put those here.
So these three types are basically straightforward.
They're just like classes that have like a field each.
This type is a bit different,
it uses something that's not really Python
and we might change in future,
which is in server.union to create a union from this type.
This is actually equivalent of doing this,
which we might actually do now
because it's something I want to change in future.
So basically this is a union of these three types
and you can see here, I mean,
if you wanna use a variable of this type,
you need to check what type it is before.
So we're gonna do that as well in GaffiCode.
So I'm gonna actually put this in line,
maybe it's a bit nicer like this.
So here I'm saying that this subscribe to podcast
is returning one of these three types
and I'm already getting an error from my Python.
I need to change that.
Obviously when I'm using this on the client,
I need to basically tell,
I wanna fetch this field for this type and so on.
Gonna show you that in a second.
So if we don't have a podcast,
we return, podcast does not exist error.
If we, this is already subscribed,
we return already subscribed,
otherwise we return the subscribe to podcast success
with the podcast from database.
So let's see that now.
So let me do a fake podcast.
So if I, actually, if I refresh this,
if I refresh the schema, I'm gonna get already an error
because I need to fetch the subfields.
So, oh, when you do,
control space here,
you're gonna get the suggestion for this.
If I try to do a suggestion for subscribe to podcast,
I'm only gonna get type name.
And this is because this type returns a union type.
So when I try to fetch this, I get the type name,
but I'm not getting any other field
because in with unions in GraphQL,
there is a special syntax to basically say,
I wanna fetch this union, sorry,
I wanna fetch this field for this union.
And it's the, it's called fragment syntax.
So you can do triple dot on specific type.
So one of these three types,
for example, if there is the podcast does not exist error,
you can do message.
And we can do the same for ready subscribe.
And finally on success,
we can get the podcasts and maybe getting the,
and this could be,
we can also have maybe subscribers
and this could be useful to kind of get the updated value
of the subscribers, which I don't have now.
So when I run this, I'm gonna get the type name,
which I guess I could ignore it,
but it could be useful to kind of do a switch
in your clients.
And in this case, I'm gonna get the proper message.
So podcast does not exist.
If I try and put the right podcast,
I'm gonna get already subscribed to podcast.
And if I put the podcast I'm not subscribed,
I will get the podcast back.
And this is one of the nicest way of doing
error handling in GraphQL.
So basically you put the errors into the schema.
So basically giving your user a way to identify
what's happening in a specific mutation.
And when you go and see the docs,
you can see that subscribe to podcast has this type.
It's a Biver post,
but it's a union type of these three types.
Okay.
There's one thing that's been annoying on this though,
is the fact that we have basically the same selection
for these two fields, sorry, for these two types.
So there is a way to improve this using interfaces.
So I think I put it there.
Yeah.
So as I mentioned, these two types are basically the same.
So we can use an interface to basically model
like a generic error message.
And we can still get the GAN type,
but we can also make it easier to kind of fetch
the same field from this interface.
I think it's gonna make sense if I show you.
So I'm gonna update these two type
and I'm gonna create a new interface at the top.
Okay.
So in Subrary, like interfaces are basically the same
as types in terms of how you implement them.
We did difference that instead of doing Subrary.type,
you do Subrary.interface.
And then when you wanna implement an interface,
you just extend from the interface.
And now when I go back to my schema,
I'm gonna see that these two types here
are implementing the interface,
meaning that I can fetch the field directly
from the interface.
So if I refresh this, I'm gonna go into my schema here.
I can see that this one implements error
and don't know if I go back,
but this one also implements error.
So now instead of doing this double fetch here,
I can do onError and then I can just do this.
And this is much nicer and it gives you a generic way
to handle all the errors.
And you still have a way to kind of pull more information
on the specific type.
So for example, if you wanted to do this
on already subscribed, you wanted to fetch, for example,
subscribed on, and you wanted to show,
you already subscribed, you subscribed on,
I don't know, first of March, 23, you can do,
you can still pass additional fields
so you can make these errors very, very garner
and very powerful as well.
Cool.
That's pretty much it for the errors.
Again, do you have any questions?
Okay, just gonna keep going.
So these two sections are quite basic
in the sense that they don't have a lot of information
because this is something I want to work on more
in so that I can make it easier to,
making your GraphQL API secure and perform it.
So the first one is about safety.
And again, we already seen some of this.
So we already seen that, like if I'm allowing user
to fetch anything, I should put some safeguards into place.
Like I don't want them to fetch everything.
And so the first thing, like the first,
or the most basic thing you can do in GraphQL
is to limit the query depth.
So for example, if I'm trying to do,
let's say that we implemented a list of episodes
for a podcast.
So we could do, you can fetch a list of podcasts,
you can get the episodes for the podcasts.
But on our episodes, we also have a podcast field.
So we could do a query like this,
which can be deeply nested.
And so that's gonna be very draining for your service.
It's gonna do a lot of SQL calls, it's gonna have a lot of data.
And so one basic way of doing this is to basically say,
I'm not gonna run any GraphQL query
that has more than seven levels of nesting.
And this is pretty safe for what you just do,
an extension and implement it like that.
Just gonna show you this.
So.
And this case I'm gonna do two,
because I don't think I have something that's more than eight.
But basically when I try to run a query
that's more than two levels of nesting,
I'm gonna get an error.
Maybe not this.
So I'm trying to fetch podcasts, I'm gonna fetch the D.
Oh, I think it's, yeah.
Wait.
I need to check, oh, there we go.
Should I work with two as well?
Okay.
Okay, I think it counts from downwards, okay.
It skips the first level, which makes sense.
Yeah, so basically if I try to run a query
that's more than one level of depth,
in this case it's gonna throw an error.
And this anonymous here is the name of the query.
So again, we can see that that goes there as well.
And this works in some cases,
it might not work in other cases.
So it really depends on what you're doing.
There's another powerful thing,
which unfortunately we haven't implemented
in Soberty just yet, but it's gonna come soon,
which is the query complexity calculation.
So this is a way to kind of give you a way
to calculate if a request has the potential
of fetching too much data.
So in this case I'm saying I wanna fetch
the first 50 podcasts, and for every podcast
I wanna fetch the first 50 episodes.
And the way, in this case you can do
some kind of weight calculations.
So I'm gonna say this field is gonna weigh 50,
and then every field of this is gonna be 50 as well.
And I'm gonna do 50 by 50, and then the result
will be 2,500.
And so the total complexity would be
this multiplication here, because there is gonna be,
it's fetching 50 episodes for every single podcast.
So it would be 50 times 50.
And then the complexity of the podcast here is 50.
So the total complexity would be this one plus this one,
which is 2,550.
And you can basically have some piece of code say,
oh, if the complexity is more than 3,000,
don't try to run this query at all.
I mean, that query might request just one,
might return only one item, but it has the potential
of returning a lot of items.
So you can basically skip all the requests being done there.
Which is, again, it's a nice way of doing something like that
in GraphQL.
There is also,
this is for node, but there is also this kind of plugin
called GraphQL Armor, which I'm gonna implement
for Stray as well, which gives you all this nice way
of limiting what someone can do with your GraphQL API.
So the first one is using the costs.
I mean, this has a lot of options,
but basically it prevents you to do,
I can create that's more than X amount of cost.
But there's also like dialysis.
Like I showed you before, like you can do like this.
Let me disable that.
So you can do this like you're fetching A and B,
and basically you're kind of circumventing any limit
that your API might have.
And so like a nice way of, well,
an easy way of preventing something like this
is to have a type of code that says,
oh, you can only have maximum 10 indices in your code.
Like this is called an audio.
So it's basically giving,
it's a way to give another name to a field
and also to fetch the same field multiple times.
And yeah, so that's pretty safe for work to implement.
Probably gonna be done by the end of the spring this week.
This is something we already have, which is the max depth.
There's also a way to limit the number of directives,
which we haven't seen, but in GraphQL,
we can have directives, which is a way to change
the execution of a field.
So in this case, I wanna do,
I wanna include only if this,
this will be a variable.
So if the variable is true,
I'm gonna include that field,
otherwise I'm not gonna include it.
For example, if I do false,
this is only gonna return B,
which is a nice way to have a generic,
a generic query, but like an issue of,
of directives, that you can put a lot of them,
and those are gonna run code,
and sometimes also the parser might be slow,
and so running, this case actually doesn't,
doesn't run multiple times, which is nice.
But there are some parser that basically,
if you have a lot of directives,
they're gonna slow down a lot,
and it's gonna lead to dos attacks.
What else?
And there's also max token or character limit,
which is basically a way to say,
if this document is too long, don't run it,
could be useful in some cases,
and yeah, this is gonna be implemented
to police on in summary.
There's also one thing here, which is, again, about safety.
When you put a graphical API on production,
one of the key suggestion from people in security
is like you should hide the introspection,
so if I, what I'm doing here,
basically using the information about the API
to build the documentation,
and people say, hide that, because it might give you
information about your schema to attackers.
There's one additional thing that you could do that,
you can hide introspection,
I think we have also an extension for that,
but you can still do something like this.
Maybe let me, I don't know if this is in.
Okay.
Yeah, so if you try to fetch a field
that's a similar name to another one,
you're gonna get a nice helpful message
that's gonna tell you, oh, this is the field
that you meant, probably, and there are tools like,
let's see, GraphQL, yeah, like this one,
that basically use this feature of GraphQL
to find all the schema automatically for you.
So like, disabling the schema might not be the best option,
because there's still ways to find out.
Again, this is something that we,
you're gonna make easier to disable in,
so like, if you're running in dev,
you're gonna get this nice message,
but if you're not running in dev,
you're not gonna get any suggestion.
Yeah.
And again, this is gonna come up, hopefully, soon,
rather than later.
Yeah, do you have any questions about security?
Because I think there's a lot of things to talk about,
and I'm definitely skip some of them, so just let me know.
Okay, the last thing I wanted to show you
before doing a recap, maybe, and taking more questions,
is the tracing part, so, and this is something
that's still quite new in GraphQL,
so I mentioned, like, GraphQL,
every request responds with 200, usually,
which makes tracing and monitoring quite difficult, so.
So there is tools like Apollo Studio from GraphQL
that allow you to, oh, sorry, from Apollo.
Let me see if there is an example of this.
Yeah, so basically, there are tools like Apollo Studio
that allow you to get the metrics for all the queries.
There's quite a few others as well,
so you can see all the information, like, for example,
if the requests have been requested the most,
sorry, the operations have been requested the most,
the ones are the slowest, and so on,
and all of this is quite nice.
The only thing is that you need to use some of these tools
which are usually paid, and it's another tool
on top of what you already have,
but you can also still use tracing,
and you can also send this information
to, like, service-like Datadog,
and in Surberry, we have implementation
for Datadog Open Tracing and So-Nothing Sentry,
and they basically work the same way
as the other extension, and so basically,
every time you run a SQL query, sorry, a GraphQL query,
this extension is gonna kinda check all the things
that you're doing, and it's gonna send it to Datadog,
and you can get something like this,
which is, kinda send this is not super useful,
but you basically can see all those over there being called,
how much, how long they take, and so on,
which is the, it's the way that you would do
tracing in GraphQL, so basically, it's a nice way
to understand how long a field would take.
Something that we've done in the past
is also to add additional metrics,
and for example, using operation name
to send information about the operation,
so every time there's an operation,
you log how much it takes, and then you send it to Datadog,
which is something that's pretty simple
to implement as well.
I don't know if I have an example of this, I...
Wanna check, I wanted to try Sentry today,
but I didn't manage to make it work in time,
because it's a bit nicer, actually, I may have Sentry,
I may have Sentry for another project.
Hopefully it's Google.
Okay.
There we go.
Now, fortunately, I don't think we have it here,
but you basically will get something like this,
and here, instead of getting a generic ASG requests,
like this one, you will get one transaction
for GraphQL request, which makes it very easy
to understand the slow ones,
and the ones that you have to optimize,
so you can use things like this to basically say,
this is taking too much time, and yeah,
we do have some, like tracing here is not really pretty well,
but that's basically what you would do
for just optimizing the GraphQL queries,
and again, you can use tools like Apollo Studio,
or there's others, which I don't remember the name,
which makes it easier to optimize your GraphQL requests,
but again, it's a very supports a data dog and open tracing,
so you can use those tools to optimize all the requests,
so you don't have to use a third-party service.
Yeah, and that's, I think I went very fast on this,
so I'm just gonna take some time to answer some questions,
you might have one, I guess one thing,
additional thing I wanted to mention on this,
like we have a very friendly Discord,
so there's quite a few people there
that usually answer questions,
but otherwise I'm also there to answer anything
you might want to know, and yeah, the website,
actually working on a new website,
which is gonna be released, not gonna say soon,
but hopefully by the end of this month or next one,
and yeah, again, I'm really passionate about this project,
so if you have any questions, you can reach out to me
on Discord, you can also find me on GitHub,
if you go to Stradivari, you should be able to find me
pretty easily, and there's my email on here,
so you can send me an email there,
or any place where you can reach me,
I'm happy to take any questions.
And yeah, before doing a quick recap,
if it might be helpful, just if you have any questions,
just fire away, I'll be happy to answer.
Yeah.
Have you done any benchmarking against REST framework?
Like, like particularly in the field?
Yeah, so the question is, have you done any benchmark
against REST framework?
No, at the moment we only done benchmarks
against other GraphQL implementation in Python,
and the performance is the same,
because like all the Python GraphQL APIs
are using something called GraphQL Core,
which is the core implementation of this library,
like it implements the execution,
like we are basically like a syntactic sugar on top of this,
and so there is some performance issues here,
mostly when you return a lot of data,
so if you're returning tens of thousands of items,
it's gonna be a bit slow, because what's happening there
is it's validating every single item
against the GraphQL schema, which is quite annoying.
So this is something that we're trying to work on
to make it better.
There's a project a friend of mine is working on,
it's called Rustberry, which is replacing
some parts of GraphQL Core in Rust.
At the moment it's gonna be mostly validation and parsing,
and that's gonna make things a bit faster,
but my goal in future is to get as fast,
if not faster, than Django REST framework.
Some ideas there, it's just I don't have enough time,
unfortunately.
So what do you think the go back to the question
that you're considering going to the rest of the project?
Yeah, so drawbacks of GraphQL,
so that's a very good question.
There's different sides of seeing that.
Definitely one thing is if you never use GraphQL,
it's quite foreign, so understanding all these things
about not even just performance,
but also security and monitoring,
those things take a bit more time,
especially you have to use tools and things like that.
And yeah, it also depends why you're building.
So if you wanna, like my suggestion,
if you wanna try GraphQL in your work or for a side project,
try to do something small,
but also start from the front end.
Try to implement, maybe do a small API,
but try to implement soon as possible on the client,
because where you get the benefits, it's on the client,
because you have this nice way of fetching data.
Maybe I can show you an example of this.
Don't know if you're familiar with React,
but in, let's see if there's an example.
Yeah, in React, you can use tools like Apollo Client,
where you basically define a query like this.
So this is a query that we've been working on before,
and you can use Hook,
which is basically returning you loading errors and data.
It's like this line is basically giving you
all the GraphQL things, which is very nice,
very easy to use.
So you will get a lot of benefits
from just trying this on the front end.
That's definitely my suggestion.
But in terms of trade-offs,
like one thing that GraphQL is not really good at is,
public API, so if you're doing an API
that's gonna be used by third parties,
like for example, if you, I don't know,
for example, the GitHub API is used by other developers
that are not from GitHub.
Building an API, public API in GraphQL is quite difficult,
because again, you should make an API
that's more focused on the use case.
And when you're building a public API,
you don't know what use case is gonna be,
so people are gonna implement random things
and gonna make things that don't make sense
in the way you shape your GraphQL schema.
So public API is definitely, it's doable,
but it's not simple.
And on top of that, service-to-service communication,
I don't think GraphQL is the right place for doing that,
because if you, I don't know,
if you're microservices, you wanna communicate between them,
I will use gRPC, because it's faster
and also it's made for that use case.
And GraphQL, I don't know, the fact that you have
to specify the query is powerful for the client,
but when you're service-to-server,
I don't know if you get the benefits of being able
to specify the fields that you want.
Maybe you can reuse the API, but again,
the API should be made on the use case,
and again, use case should be done
for a client using API.
Have you ever encountered situations
where someone is using an app that's not on GraphQL
and the app is not on the API?
Have you ever encountered that?
Yeah, so the question is if I ever encountered places
where I have to have for the APIs rest
and I have for the APIs GraphQL.
Let me try to think.
We had something like that, but not exactly that.
So one thing I've seen in the past is like people creating,
which I definitely wouldn't recommend,
is creating kind of GraphQL resolvers on your front end.
So you will use GraphQL on your front end,
but also on the front end you would call rest.
So you would create an interface on top of rest
inside your front end, which is okay,
but you're still doing a lot of requests there.
So like something that's quite common is to do
tiny GraphQL API, try without, prove it that works,
and then slowly migrate things from rest
to GraphQL and you can still wrap your rest API
with the GraphQL API.
So you can do, like for example, the podcast field
could be, that we had, could be backed by rest API
and then if you wanna move it to be, to the skip rest,
you could do that as well.
But like using GraphQL to wrap rest API is quite common.
It's something I was doing in my previous work.
Yeah.
Do you have any other question?
Cool.
Yeah, so I guess the recap is basically we seen
how to kind of set up a GraphQL API with,
so we've been using Django, but Django again,
is something that's just an implementation detail.
And we, I can show this again, we had these models here,
but we were not looking at them directly.
Like all the code that was doing the data fetching
was kind of hidden by this service layer, I call it,
which is inspired by domain driven design.
It's basically like a facade on top of your database.
Makes it easier to work with these kind of things
and you don't have to think about all the implementation
of your database.
And it also makes it easier to reuse this, for example,
if you need to create a rest API for some specific use case
or if you need to create a CLI.
From this you can reuse this service layer.
And so you don't have anything that's specific
to data fetching inside GraphQL.
And we use async for data loaders,
which is a way to optimize the requests.
So to batch multiple requests into one.
And in Django, like there's some issues at the moment
with running async requests, async,
well, database call inside async context.
So I guess it's worth showing you since we have time,
there's this function called sync to async,
which converts async function into an async function.
So you can do a wait and it basically prevents
those issues with Django.
Basically what happens, like things run into a thread,
which it's a thread where the database also runs.
I'm sorry, the database connection also runs.
I'm not clear on the details why this is an issue,
but this is what's happening.
There's also, let me see.
In Django you can also do a filter.
Let me show this.
Oh, okay, no, a filter is not there yet,
but there's also things like a get,
which are the asynchronous variants of get
and a delete and so on.
This underdue that's still doing the sync to async
at the moment because the database layer
in Django is now async,
but hopefully that's gonna change in future.
And again, it's also one additional reason why,
to create like a wrapper layer
that makes it easier to work with database.
And I've done this for everything.
And you can see sync to async is done on list
in most cases because like Django is lazy.
So up until you don't use, for example,
a query set is not gonna do the actual query database.
Sync tracing is on list, which is a bit confusing.
Okay, what else?
Yeah, we've seen how to do pagination.
So you can do basic pagination using pages.
My suggestion is to think about the use case.
If you need to have page pagination,
you can use something like this,
but make sure that you can nest it a wrapper type
so you can do as next page.
You can give you more information about the pagination.
And on top of that,
make sure that you have some basic validation
so you don't allow users to fetch too much data.
We also see now to do some of those things
with the just safety features.
And hopefully this is gonna be easier
in the next version of Strawberry,
hopefully from next week.
So you can kind of prevent users to do too many fetches
in one single GraphQL query.
And we also seen the course of pagination,
which is useful for,
if you're working with a GraphQL API
that's already existing,
it's probably gonna use the release specification,
which is very common.
And again, this is something that looks like this.
So you have a field that returns a list of edges
and every edge is a node,
and every edge is also cursor,
which is how you can paginate and get things from there.
And you can also, again,
the reason why you have edges
is that you can add additional metadata here.
So for example, the user,
the friends can have relations together,
and it would only make sense in this context.
It wouldn't make sense to the single friend
to have a relation connection.
Yeah, the relay, it's a bit verbose,
but it's quite powerful.
And we've seen the generic types.
We've seen how this makes it very easy
to reuse types in Python
for creating multiple GraphQL types.
Oh, then we've seen a couple of ways
of improving the optimization, sorry,
improving the performance of application
by introspecting the query,
which is something I don't really recommend
because this time your database,
your GraphQL created too much to your database.
So I would definitely recommend you
to use data loaders when possible.
And for data loaders, you have to use async code.
Whereas we've seen authentication,
we've seen a basic way of doing authentication using cookies.
Again, you can use anything that you want.
But again, my personal,
I always use cookie-based authentication
just so much easier to use.
And I think you can also easily use them
in native applications.
And then, yeah, we've seen mutations,
synoptical mutation,
which are basically the same thing as query
with some additional changes
on how the execution works.
What else?
Yeah, we've seen the permissions.
Hopefully this is gonna be much more powerful in the future,
but it's already a good way to start.
And we've seen how to handle the errors.
So I think this is one of the most common patterns
if it's just for errors,
like just using the union types
to make sure that you basically tell your clients
how to handle multiple responses.
And yeah, that's pretty much it.
Again, keep an eye on this page.
I'm gonna update it to add more things
and also to remove some of the code
that's not gonna be needed in the future,
like for example, for relay.
Again, hopefully this is gonna be all implemented.
Most of this is gonna be implemented by Strawberry itself,
so you don't have to do all of this.
And same thing goes for the safety part.
There's gonna be a lot more options here.
And I think we're also gonna have a way
to kind of set the same defaults,
maybe even by default,
like when you install Strawberry
and you try to run queries,
there is a lot of these things enabled by default,
so you don't have to worry too much.
Yep.
Kind of going back to the,
a little bit back to the beginning,
when you were importing those podcast feeds,
how does GraphQL know what the parameters are
that it would use to get feedback on those feeds?
So the way we,
so if we go back to the CLI,
sorry, this,
well, I haven't showed you the CLI actually.
So this is just a,
it's not really part of the workshop,
but basically I'm fetching RSS feeds for the podcast
and I'm putting them into database.
And the modules,
so these are all the options,
all the things are available in the database.
So there is the title, subtitle, description, and so on,
and there's also the episodes.
And when I go back to my podcast query,
when I'm fetching a single podcast,
so I'm fetching that bad ID on the database,
and here I'm getting a Django module,
which has all the title, all the,
well, as the title, the ID, description, and so on.
And then when I'm doing the conversion,
I'm creating a GraphQL type,
which this is where you're telling GraphQL
what fields you can fetch.
But you have to know beforehand what you're getting
so you can apply the model of what the,
what it is, right?
This is my feed and I know I'm gonna get these.
And I put them in your model,
and you have to query them, right?
Yes, yes, yeah.
I mean, the way I've done this is a bit backwards,
maybe not too much.
Like I really have a data source to work with.
But for example, if you're working
with your own business logic, with your data,
you know what data you have,
and you know how to shape that for GraphQL.
Because again, it should be shaped
on based on the kind of use case that you have.
So for example, in this case, I mean, this is,
again, it's a very simple use case,
but I didn't have a hosted by field here.
If I wanted, I can add it,
but in my application, I didn't need to show that,
so it's not present in the GraphQL API.
Yeah, again, I think, I haven't mentioned this,
but in GraphQL, like, well, something that's pretty cool,
like adding new fields is very easy.
So you can do ABC and string, and that's done.
You don't have to do anything else
other than putting here when you fetch it.
I can do ABC.
I can also put a default,
so you don't have to do anything.
This is something that, for example,
in REST might be a bit annoying,
because once you add a field to REST endpoint,
it's gonna be returned to all the clients
using that endpoint.
In GraphQL, this field is only gonna be returned
if someone requests it, which is very powerful.
And so my recommendation is only add the fields
that you need at the moment,
and always add them in future if you need more.
Because once you have a field in your schema,
like you're moving, it's a bit non-trivial,
because you need to make sure that it's not being used.
Which there are some, like Apollo Studio tells you
how many times a field has been used,
for example, last week.
You can check that, but again,
it's an operation that requires some step.
And you can also deprecate fields if you need to.
So for example, if you don't wanna,
if you wanna tell user to not use the description field,
you can deprecate it.
And so they get a warning inside there,
and they say, I see it gonna work,
but they know that it's gonna be deleted at some point.
Yeah.
Yeah, that's again, pretty much it.
Again, if you have any question,
you can go to Sorry The Rocks.
There is all the links there.
Yeah, I'm gonna be around for us today
and all the rest of the conference.
I'm organizing the sprints, which I forgot,
if they're on Saturday or Sunday.
But basically I'm gonna work on,
all the things I'm missing for the safety,
and hopefully maybe improving the workshop as well,
with more information.
So make sure you take an eye on this.
Yeah, that's pretty much everything.
Thank you.
Alright, thank you.
Thank you, thank you for coming.
Oh, my gosh.
I wanna say thank you to
for all the noble love I have forG1.
Thank you very much.
Thank you very much for being here.
Go to our YouTube channel,
or to GoYouTube YouTube channel,
and take some YouTube percent less fun