Thank you so much Guido for being here, for accepting my invitations.
Each time I ask you for something, I felt guilty about it.
My personal story with Guido, which is related to PyCon US, it was my first ever PyCon in
Montreal which I mentioned that that's when I heard about Python Core developers through
Guido's keynote.
By the way, his presentation at the time contains a typo.
Now you know why I'm obsessed with typos.
But it's a special talk to me, talk for me, that's when I realized that there was no female
Core developers at the time.
And I think that's one of the things that stuck out to me and inspired me to think more
about that case.
A year later I actually wrote an email to Guido and I felt, I have to admit when I wrote
that email asking him for help, I'm interested in contributing to Python, I felt so scared
sending that email.
I was like, I thought that I didn't deserve to receive help from Guido van Rossem.
But he replied, and not only he replied, once he continued to support me.
So I'm really grateful that you opened that door for me Guido.
Now I left this screen empty because I don't want to call it DM, it sounds sad.
Instead I'll share something which I consider my PyCon US chair diary.
Chris messaged that he wished to complain there is not enough Savage Garden playing
in a keynote hall.
And I agree.
And thank you for raising this.
For those who don't know, I'm a big fan of Savage Garden.
I have the opportunity to actually meet Darren Hayes of Savage Garden and the music of Savage
Garden is a comforting music.
And I am stressed out with all of this but I will be listening to the song of Darren
Hayes and Savage Garden.
If you would like to join me you can check out my playlist of Savage Garden and Darren
Hayes.
And I am so, I feel like, why are you letting me talking about Savage Garden in a Python
conference?
So, well thank you for letting me do that.
Oh my God, oh my God, thank you.
Okay, they're going to cut that out from the recording because of copyrighted music.
But thank you, I appreciate it.
Thank you, AB team.
Alright.
Regarding the posters, I am so glad that it actually happened.
So, I'm so, again, I'm thankful for all the staff members who work hard to make that happen.
So, congratulations again to poster presenters.
Now we've finished almost everything.
What's left is the sprints.
And after my message today, Chalmer will be here to be doing the sprint throws.
Basically, they are talking about what's going to happen during the sprints and there will
be introduction of all the different sprint projects.
So, stay tuned after my message.
And during the sprints, it will be starting tomorrow until Thursday, 8 a.m. and 11 p.m.
That's not a typo.
It literally runs all day long.
In rooms 250 and 251, lunch will be included during the sprints.
So, let's check out some stats.
And I've been mentioning that, you know, there are 2,000 people joining us in person.
And I did not know this fact that what NE can testify that I just got these numbers from them like two hours ago.
1,672 are first-time attendees.
77%.
So, welcome first-time attendees.
And we have 490 online registrations.
Like that itself is the size of another conference.
It's big.
And about 733 people join in online as well because this time we're allowing, we're letting
in person, people who register in person to also access the online platform.
So, in case they are feeling unwell or just need a break from the conference, they can still follow along in a place that's comfortable for them.
And we have 110 people who sign up to do volunteering on site.
Thank you for all the work that you do.
This time we have 85 sponsors and we have eight startup roles and nine open source and community booths.
Sponsorship brought through those sponsors, it brought us to more than $1 million in sponsorship just for PyCon US.
So, thank you.
Thank you to our vision sponsors for continuing to support PyCon.
So, we were able to provide travel grants for people who are not able to attend PyCon US otherwise.
So, 270 people received those grants.
And so far we have about $261,000 has been reimbursed for the travel grant recipients so far.
And I think there are still a few more, there are still more that have not come to pick up their grants.
So, this number will be higher.
Thank you.
Pailadies auction happened last night. We got 29 items that were auctioned.
And throughout the history, we received large donations through the auctions.
So, you can see the progression of the amount that was, that received during the Pailadies auctions.
And last year, last night's result was that we received $35,000 through the bid.
The highest bid item was the Zen Side of the Moon vinyl, which brought in $3,000.
And I'm really grateful for all of these sponsorships and donations because the impact of all of this is that we get, we get to bring in people.
People who wouldn't be others be here.
This year, I received this message from Renato who traveled from Brazil who noted that this year he was able to feasibly notice there are way more women from Brazil that those travel took.
I went to Brazil last year. It took me 30 hours one way.
So, it's far. And I'm so glad that so many of you were able to come this year thanks to the sponsorships and the donations.
Thanks to the sponsorship as well. I get to meet another Indonesian woman in this conference and that's Yuri from Japan.
She was born in Indonesia just like myself. So, I was so excited that I ran into her.
I'm so glad that I did not miss the Pailadies lunch today.
So, what happens during Pailadies lunch is that all the attendees are encouraged to come up to the front and share things that they are proud of, something they have accomplished.
And I hear so many stories, lots of tears. But one of the things that inspired me is that there are so many international people.
There are a few people who are here, didn't speak English and had to read from their phone for the translation.
And it's the fact that it's okay. The fact that they felt comfortable and accepted to do that, it's so inspiring for me.
So, let's check on the PyCon US Challenge. I am wondering how many of you got lots of points.
If you want to maybe clap or shout, how many got more than at least five points?
Yeah? Ten points.
No? What? Anybody got more than ten points, fifteen points?
Well, I'm disappointed.
All right. But you still have till the end of the sprints to do more of this.
For this challenge, I really want to just give shout out to people who actually come to the PSF booth and took selfies.
It's really fun to see all the photos that you've posted there.
I also have more challenge for you in addition to Deb's homework. And this is worth, if you do just one, it's worth lots of points.
So, if you can just invite someone else to the next PyCon US and my intention is just for you to tell them about the Python community, introduce them to this community.
For myself, I've used Python for a long time, but nobody ever told me about the community.
They tell me, like, read this book, read the tutorials, but nobody connected me with the community and I wish for you to extend the invitation, bring someone else to PyCon US.
Encourage someone else into submitting a talk to PyCon US.
Do nominate someone for the PSF Community Service Award, which is also Deb's homework for you.
Nominate someone to become a PSF fellow member and attend.
Let's support the Python community worldwide. Go attend a regional Python conference.
And you have the whole year to do this and I will be coming back here next year to check on your points.
Yeah, next year. What's going to happen next year?
I have a video to share with you.
The word is out. Pittsburgh is a must-see travel destination. Plan a visit and you'll quickly find what makes our city so special.
The experiences and attractions you'll find only in Pittsburgh.
That's right. Experiences like the Heinz History Center, the Andy Warhol Museum, the August Wilson African American Cultural Center,
the Bicycle Heavens, Carnegie Museums of Art and Natural History, the National Aviary, the Mattress Factory for Contemporary Art,
our many parks and green spaces. The list goes on.
Take a ride on one of our two iconic and historical inclines to Mount Washington,
where you can pair a delicious meal with incredible views at one of the many restaurants that line Grandview Avenue.
And be sure to head into a few of our 90 unique neighborhoods for local flavors,
like a Primanti Brothers Sandwich, handmade pierogies or Pittsburgh salad piled high with fresh-cut fries.
Visit the Western Pennsylvania Sports Museum or the Roberto Clemente Museum.
And be sure to check out a few of our only in Pittsburgh breweries.
Pick up a Pittsburgh Brewery Guide to help you build your ideal brewery tour.
And that's just a start. Yes, all this and much more. Only in Pittsburgh. See you soon.
Yes. So next year we will move to Pittsburgh.
And the next PyCon US is 2024, May 15 to May 23rd.
And 2025, we will also be in Pittsburgh from May 14 to May 22nd.
And here's a cheat sheet because I want you to go to the regional PyCons.
I give you a list so you can just choose any one of them. If you can go to multiple, that's even great.
So there are so many PyCons all over the world.
There's even lots of PyCons in the APAC region as well.
So check them out.
And I want to thank our vendors, especially the AV team, Altitude C.
They're doing an amazing job coordinating with me and with all the speakers, with all the keynote speakers.
And I feel like everything is so great. It looks so fancy. So great.
So thank you. Thank you, AV team. Thank you, Altitude C.
And thank you, White Coat Captioning, for providing live captioning to all of our talks and keynotes and lightning talks.
To visit Salt Lake who came through and helped us with the poster printing situation.
They contacted different hotels. We went to contact different hotels to see who had printers.
So because of that, poster session happened today. Thank you.
And to Lux Furniture who provided the furnishing for the quiet room. It's really like comfortable, quiet space.
And Georgie, who actually all of the graphics, you see the videos, the animation, she did all of that.
So she's really amazing. So yeah, Georgie.
So first of all, I really want to thank you all for giving me this opportunity to be here and showing my part of myself to you and that you actually accepted all of that.
I'm so grateful for that. I have one more gift that I want to share with you.
I used to work in a movie company.
And one of the things they did after the movie production finished, they would invite all of us, like everybody who worked in the movie, we get to bring our families, go to the theater, actually watch the movie.
And at the end of the movie, everybody would stay and watch the credits.
Everybody who worked on it, they watched the credits and I even get to bring my kids with me.
They get to see my name in the end of Angry Birds movie and one of the Spider-Man movie.
So it's really cool and it's cool experience. I want for you to have that kind of experience as well.
So for this next part, what I like for you, if you see yourself on the screen, please stand up.
If you see someone who you recognize, who you know, and by know I don't mean, oh I know him, I know this person, I went to dinner with them.
It's just you know this person. You recognize, you say you went to a talk given by this person.
You saw them volunteering. That's good enough that you know this person.
Please clap. Alright, those are the two things. So let's play the video.
Oh
Thank you so much.
Thank you again for celebrating 20 years of PyCon with all of us. Thank you. Alright.
And that concludes all the talks and keynotes. I will have Chalmer doing the sprint throws right now. Thank you all.
Alright. If you are leading a sprint this week, we would love to have you come up and introduce your sprint to the folks who are here.
I know some people are going to go out and go get food and all that, but some people want to stick around and hear what sprints are going to happen.
You'll have as a sprint lead about 30 seconds to give the name of your sprint, what your sprint covers, and whether you feel that your sprint is beginner friendly.
For those who have never been to a sprint and are not sure what to expect, I'll be leading an introduction to sprinting workshop immediately after these folks get done talking about their sprints.
So it will happen in about 10 minutes. You can follow me to the room because it won't start until I get there.
If you want to dash out, the room will be room 151G. Again, the workshop is in 151G.
And with that, the sprints will start at 8 o'clock tomorrow.
I will caveat that. Your sprint lead may not believe that, and they may choose to show up at 9 or 10 or 11. He says 12.
Alright. So with that, I'll turn the time over to the folks. About 30 seconds and let people know what you got going on.
Hi. If you're not staying for sprints this year, you should definitely do that next year.
It's one of the best parts of the conference. You get to actually work directly live with maintainers of software you're using.
So highly recommended. I'm from CPython here. We're going to be sprinting all four days, knowing Larry Hastings until the very end of the day when they will kick us out.
Those are not mentor sprints, but if you have an issue that you would like fixing and you have an idea how you would approach it, it's the perfect time to do this.
So I highly recommend you talk to us tomorrow.
Hi. I'm Mark. I'm a GNU Mailman core developer. We'll be sprinting on Mailman all four days.
I'll be here. We have issues on Mailman core and our Django based web UIs. If you want to help with Mailman, we'd love to have you come by.
Hi. I'm Russell Keith McGee. We will be with the Beware project. We'll be sprinting on Briefcase, our tool for packaging Python code as a standalone app, and also on Toga, our GUI toolkit for cross platform GUI development.
We are particularly interested if you've got web skills because we need to build out our web back end. And when we have tasks for people of all levels of skill, and we do mean all levels of skill, and everyone who contributes gets a challenge coin.
So please come along.
Hello. I'm Shauna. I'm going to be sprinting on a new project called the Open Source Governance Project. It's an effort to collect governance wisdom, advice, resources, et cetera, and make them available to projects.
It is a good sprint for people who are not looking to do code contributions, so writers, community managers, and governance nerds of all kinds.
I also want to extend an invitation to anyone who is working on a different sprint or a different project who has a governance problem that they want advice on to come stop by our sprint, get some advice. We'll be happy to chat with you.
Hello. My name is Eric. I'll be working on a project called Django Symbol Deploy. It automates people's Django deployments and is platform agnostic. If you deal with Django deployments in any capacity, please stop by and say hello.
I'd be happy to just talk to you about it, give a demo. If you want to help out, contributions are welcome. I'll be here through Wednesday. Thank you.
Hi, I'm Jackie. I'm leading a sprint for a project I lead called Mesa, which is agent-based modeling in Python.
Recently, I did a review of literature that had used Mesa, which I thought was quite impactful, which includes COVID disease research, tumor growth, social robots for dementia patients, climate change, renewable energy markets, smart grid attacks, water security, truck and motor vehicles, and so on.
IOT network modeling, smart contract modeling, blockchain supply chains, all the chains, energetic genetic engineered insects, post disaster resource allocation, simulations for malware spread and decentralization, decentralized public key infrastructure for autonomous embedded systems.
So if you're interested in any of those things, you should come and visit me. It's just going to be me. I have a variety of work, including small feature ads, PR reviews, creating examples, speed scale improvements, geospatial improvements, and automating more stuff. Thank you.
I'll be sprinting on PEP669, the new monitoring API in CPython. If anyone's interested in porting profilers, debuggers, or anything to it, or just helping out with the documentation or anything like that, it would be much appreciated.
Hello, I'm Katnay, and I will be hosting a sprint for CircuitPython, which is a version of Python that runs on tiny computers called microcontrollers. We have a ton of libraries, over 300, and I have hardware to test most of them. We have something like 670 issues available. 76 of those are labeled good first issue, which is to say they are great for beginners.
You are also welcome to join us if you're simply interested in CircuitPython. We can accommodate folks who just want to learn about it, and we're happy to help you contribute to the project as well. We will be here Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday, and I hope to see you all there.
Hi, I'm Chris from the Pants Build project. We work on the PEX executable format and the Pants Build system. We will be both sprinting on pants tomorrow, and also we're around to help people integrate pants into their open source repos and just generally helping out people get started with pants. So come find us tomorrow if you're interested in that. Thanks.
My name is Jukka. We will be sprinting on MyPy and MyPyC on Monday and Tuesday, and we welcome new contributors. We have a list of easy issues to get started with.
Hello all, I'm Dave, and this is the largest number of seats I've ever spoken to. But in addition to that, I'm with the Conda project. We're going to have a Conda and Friends sprint on Monday and Tuesday. If you're interested in packaging, please join us. If you're interested in the future of Conda and the whole ecosystem, please join us.
And I'd like to point out that Conda sprints are about expanding the contributor community, not so much about contributions in those two days. So if you're looking for a beginner project, please join us. Thank you.
Hi, everybody. I'm Nick with the National Renewable Energy Laboratory, and we're going to work on a package called Hive, which is a simulator for electric vehicle fleets. We do have beginner friendly issues and other general issues as well as some rust stuff if you're interested. Thank you.
Hey, I'm Matt. I'm going to be here tomorrow and maybe Tuesday working on MemRay and on PyStack. MemRay is a memory profiler. PyStack is a debugging tool that lets you see what a running process is doing. I have spent the entire day trying to groom good first issues for people, so I will be very offended if no one shows up.
Hello, everyone. My name is Patrick. I'm going to be sprinting on Strawberry GraphQL, which is a library based on data classes and type ins and loves UK GraphQL servers. I'm going to work on a plan for version one, which has been a while now, and documentation and probably the new website. If you want to join, let me know. Thank you.
Thank you.
Strawberry GraphQL.
Hello, everyone. My name is Fabio, and I'm a maintainer of PyScript. We will be running a PyScript and friends sprint, mainly working on PyScript, documentation, examples, but we also have a new framework called PiperCard that you can contribute to. It allows you to write applications with S cards.
We also want to welcome everyone that wants to write examples, break code, try Python on the browser. Come work with us. If you haven't heard of it, PyScript is a framework platform that allows you to run Python on the browser. So everyone is welcome. See you there. Thank you.
Hi, everyone. My name is Zach. I maintain Hypothesis. If you have used Hypothesis, I have a number of really exciting issues for adding new features. Unfortunately, my good issues for beginners in open source got used up at the mentor sprints yesterday, so none of those left.
But I do have some fantastic impactful things for web developers to do, for people who write documentation or people who would like to add features to Hypothesis. Those who contribute get these adorable little dragonfly badges that I have stickers for everyone who wants them. Thanks very much.
Hi, I'm Junji from South Korea. I think some of you may have heard of my talk about AI Monitor Next Generation. So I'm going to host a sprint for AI Monitor and I think I will relate topics such as Task Group extensions and so on on Monday and Tuesday. Thank you.
Hi, I'm Samuel from Pydantic. We'll be sprinting on Pydantic V2. Come along if you want to contribute or have any questions. Thank you.
Hello, I'm Eric from Read the Docs and we have a lot of cool stuff that we're working on to make it easier to host documentation for your open source projects. So we're not so much working on our project, but helping you improve your documentation and get it hosted on our platform. Or if you have kind of Sphinx docs questions, we're going to be there to help you kind of basically make the documentation in the Python ecosystem better. So thank you.
Alright, thank you folks. Appreciate all the sprint leads. I'm going to walk over to room 151G, 151 Gamma and I'm going to teach an introduction to sprinting workshop. If you want to go, follow me there. Otherwise, I'll see you tomorrow when you get here. Look forward to all your shiny happy faces making lots of cool fixes.