Okay. Well, let's start. Excellent. Wow. No one told me so many people come to tutorials
at PyCon. So, excellent. Excellent. Welcome, everyone. My name is Reuven. Just a word or
two about who I am, what I do, and then we'll jump right into things. So, I have been freelancing
since 1995. I've been using Python for about 30 years now. And nowadays, I'm a full-time
Python trainer. So, I work with companies all around the world, individuals all around the
world, helping them to improve their Python skills. I do a lot of corporate training.
I have a lot of videos. I have all sorts of stuff. And I'll even have a booth here at
PyCon so you can come by and talk to me more and hear more about stuff and get T-shirts
because you are coders and all coders need more T-shirts or so I tell my family. So,
what are we going to be talking about today? We're going to be talking about comprehensions.
And I must say, comprehensions are at once one of the things that I most love using and
teaching about. They're also one of the things that are incredibly mysterious, off-putting,
frustrating, on, on, and on. A number of years ago, I was interviewed on a podcast, and the
two hosts of the podcast asked me, so what is the hardest thing for people when I'm teaching
them Python? I said, oh, hands down, it's comprehensions. And both the hosts said, oh,
yeah, we don't quite get them either. So, it is a very, very widespread frustration.
And many people are like, well, you don't need them. I'll just use a regular for loop.
Or they're just confusing. Or on, on, and on. And what I'm hoping that you're going
to find today is that comprehensions are, you know, to use the phrase, comprehensible,
they are understandable, and they're even desirable in many, many cases. And they're
definitely part of idiomatic Python. And so, we're going to be doing, I'm going to be going
through a lot of demonstrations here. I'll explain to you in a moment how I teach. We're
going to be doing a lot of exercises. And I'm very, very, very much hoping that if you
are frustrated, confused, things aren't working for you in the exercise, or you don't get
what I'm saying, that you will tell me. My job is to make sure that you understand what's
going on. And so, if you leave here not understanding, then I haven't done my job well. And so, also,
the odds are staggeringly high that if you have a question, someone else has the same
question. And so, you will be doing them a favor if you ask the question, because otherwise,
the two of you are like, well, I don't want to embarrass myself. So, if you want, you
can just raise your hand, and I'll call on you. And you can take a question, I'll repeat
it here. If you have a long, complex question, I won't repeat it well, because we'll be paying
like Python telephone, you can get up to the microphone. I like my classes to be super
interactive. I don't just like lecturing, although my children would perhaps disagree
with that. I definitely want this to be a lot of give and take, a lot of what ifs, a
lot of sort of bringing up your own experiences. Now, the other thing is I don't use slides
when I teach. Instead, I use Jupyter. I think I sent email about this. I hope I sent email
about this. And so, basically, here, I'm going to show you. This is my Jupyter notebook.
I've enlarged it so you, oh, I have this screen here. Fantastic. Wow. It's like they thought
of everything. I'm going to make this a little smaller so it doesn't seem so ridiculously
comical. I hope that those of you in the back can see this. If not, I guess that will be
the first question, right? And so, I'm going to be typing into Jupyter live coding, both
some documentation and a lot of code. And this is uploaded to GitHub on a regular basis,
about once every minute or two. In fact, let me just turn on auto save 30 so it will be
even faster than that. And so, that GitHub repo will be available to you while we are
here. And if you go to GitHub, and I'm at GitHub.com slash Reuven, spelled the way it's
pronounced, haha. All right. I can put this here as well. So, GitHub repo for this course.
And I'm using something called git auto push. And so, every, as I said, like minute or so,
whatever I do will be pushed up there and you can look at it. And you can look at it
after the tutorial is done as well, you know, if you want to refresh your memory or are
having trouble falling asleep at night. We will be using some files that I put in that
GitHub repo as well. I also sent you a link where you can download them. I think I made
them downloadable via the platform that we're using for PyCon. We're not going to use all
those files, but we are going to use some of them. And the idea is basically that we're
going to be using some files for things. So, it would be useful to have them, right? Okay.
So, let's do a little agenda here. So, the first thing is like what are comprehensions?
Right? And then we're going to talk about list comprehensions. We're going to talk
that and we're going to do that for quite a while. We're going to talk about list comprehensions
and files. We are going to then talk about set comprehensions. We're going to talk about
dict comprehensions. The word comprehensions is going to come up a lot today. Then we're
going to talk about nested comprehensions and finally we will talk about generator expressions.
These last two topics we're going to cover relatively briefly. Also, like the way I teach,
it's often a lot of flexibility here in terms of time. But don't worry, we will get to everything
and we will practice everything and we will get to your questions. And if I have to stay
a little bit later and answer your questions, that is okay too. The only, only rule is that
there is a break at three with food and if I stop you from getting to that, then there
will be no second half of this tutorial because I will be a rotting corpse after you have
dealt with it for not getting to your food. So, I recognize there are important constraints
in the universe. Okay. So, let's start talking about what is a comprehension. And let's say,
I know this is going to be very similar to the work that you all do day after day. Let's
say I have a list of numbers of integers and I want to create a list of those integers
to, you know, squared, to the second power. Right? Right? That's what you do all day.
That's what it's like in big companies, I know. So, how am I going to do this? Well,
I can say here numbers equals, I'll just say it's a range. Actually, I'll make a list.
Not that it matters that much, but I have to stick true to the documentation. Otherwise,
the next, you know, at the next meeting they'll get me. And then we can look at numbers here
and sure enough that's a list of ten numbers. And I can say then, well, I'll create output
is an empty list. And I'll say for one number in numbers, I'll say output append one number
to the second power. And sure enough, wow, amazing. The next IPO in tech is waiting right
here in Salt Lake City. So, what is going on here? Well, I'm creating a list, output
equals empty list. And then I go through it one element at a time. And each of those elements
is then squared and we append that to output. And so our list is growing and growing over
time. And sure enough, then we get that output. Fantastic. And this is where I say, as I so
like to, unfortunately, this works. You absolutely positively do get the right answer in doing
this way. And an awful lot of Python developers will say it's so obvious, it's so straightforward,
why not just stick with this syntax? To which experience Python people are like, oh, my
God, another person I've got to convince this of. No, no, no. It's natural that you want
to stick with things that are familiar and less sort of daunting. So, what is another
way to do this? Well, it's going to be a list comprehension. And so here's what I'm going
to do. I'm going to take that same code and I'm going to rewrite it as a comprehension.
I'm going to run it to prove to you that it actually works. And then we're going to go
through it and talk about what it's doing and how it's doing it and what it's not doing.
So I'm going to say here, one, let's start by spelling it right, one number to the second
power for one number in numbers. First of all, it works. Second of all, writing code
like this guarantees me job security because no one else will ever be able to understand
what I'm doing and they'll have to keep me around. But what is actually going on here?
This is, of course, a list comprehension. And it's much easier to write and understand
if we pick it apart and write it on multiple lines. And you might be saying, wait, how
can we do that? Python is so persnickety about how we do indentation. That is true except
when we've opened parentheses. Because the moment you open parentheses, then Python's
like, oh, yeah, that's part of the same line. We're just going to sort of ignore it. So
I'm going to put these on two separate lines. And once I do that, first of all, from my
perspective, it becomes much, much more obvious what's going on. And second of all, now we
can start to reason about what it's doing. And I'll tell you, the moment that I started
writing my list comprehension on multiple lines, things got way easier for me and for the participants
in my courses. This was probably, I don't know, 10 years ago, something like that. And
I remember I have a very, very, very low score on Stack Overflow, in part because years ago
I posted something about list comprehensions and I posted it using this kind of syntax.
And someone was like, that's ridiculous. That's terrible. And I was so put off, I was like,
I'm never coming back to this site, which was a lie. But fine, we need somewhere to
copy and paste from. In any case, what's actually going on here? So the first thing that you
want to understand is that there are two parts to this comprehension. We're going to grow
that over time. But the two basic parts. And the first part here is what I call the expression.
And this can be any Python expression at all, which means any function call, any method
call, any operator, anything at all that returns a value. That last part is kind of important.
And if you're not familiar with the whole idea of what is an expression in Python, it's
something that gives me back a value. So it could just be a plain old variable. It could
be calling a function or method on that variable. It could be the interaction among several
variables, whatever. But whatever that expression gives back, that's what we're going to have.
And then here is the iteration. Any Python loop. And once again, this works. And many
people look at this and they say, oh, I get it. A comprehension is just a really, really
short for loop. It's like a compact way of writing a for loop. And that's sort of true.
But it's mostly not true. Because and here's the big distinction. Well, actually, we'll
get to the distinction a little bit. Let's talk through a little more here. So one of
the things that's frustrating for people is that comprehensions seem to run backwards.
So in a comprehension, the first thing, first, boy, oh, boy, thing that runs is the loop.
And the second thing is the expression. So it's like written backwards. And that's very
sort of surprising to many people. And so what's happening here is our for loop is running
just like a regular for loop. Well, mostly like a regular for loop. And so we're going
to iterate over numbers. And so it has to be iterable. Numbers is a list. It's iterable.
So the for loop sets the numbers. Are you iterable? Yes. So give me your next thing.
The next thing is put into one number. And then we get our expression back. And then
we go to the next thing. Here's the thing. At least the way that I've written the comprehension
here, we will have so the result of a list comprehension is a list. We have created a
new list. And we can pass it as an argument to a function or assign it to a variable or
just enjoy its exquisite beauty. I don't know. We can do whatever we can do with a list.
This is a new list. It is completely unconnected to the previous list. And the new list is
the result of evaluating our expression on every element of the input. Input we'll call
a list. So basically what's happening, every single element of numbers is passing through
that expression. And whatever the result of that expression is, that's what is put in
the output list. So as a result, the output list will have the same number of elements
as the input list. So here numbers is ten elements, ten numbers. The output from this,
which I haven't named here, I'm just seeing it in Jupyter, the output is also ten elements.
And each of those elements you can think of it as mapping one to the other. So the
zero index is zero, kind of appropriate. And then the output is also going to be zero because
zero squared is zero. Let's go past one. So at index zero one two, we've got the number
two and that squared is four. So we can see them as two parallel lists, the input and
the output, where the difference between them is the expression. You can sort of kind of
think of this as working with a spreadsheet in Excel, right, where you've got a column
of numbers and you apply some expression to all of those numbers and you paste it into
a column next to that. That's kind of what we're doing here in our comprehension. Now,
the fact that so many things in Python are iterable and that we have more or less an
infinite number of expressions means that list comprehensions are huge, right? We can
use them in all sorts of places. But let's back up for a moment. Why? Why would I use
them? What is the advantage of using a list comprehension rather than just using a regular
old for loop? Like, if it's going to frustrate people, right, which is good for the tutorial
business but bad for humanity in general, then maybe we should just stick with regular
for loops. And the distinction is basically one of what do you want to do with things,
right? So when use a loop and when a comprehension? And so basically the big distinction is between
getting a new value back and having side effects. Meaning, if you have an existing list and
you want a new list and you can describe the sort of mapping from the first to the
second, then you should use a comprehension. And the idea is I want to get that list back,
right? I want the list. But if you are assigning repeatedly, if you are modifying things repeatedly,
then use a regular for loop. That's the big distinction. Am I doing it for the side effects
of what I assign and change and mutate or am I doing it to get a list back? Now, when
you start off with comprehensions, these two ideas seem almost completely like the same.
It takes time. It takes years of using comprehensions to slowly but surely see when you would use
one versus the other, right? It's not a super, super obvious distinction. And again, the
fact is you can use a regular for loop in many cases. Now, I'll tell you the other reason
to use comprehensions, which is the bad reason. And the bad reason is that it is more efficient.
Now, why is that the bad reason? Because it's not always more efficient. It's not always
hugely more efficient. When I teach people who come from a C background, they're like,
oh, well, that's why I'm going to use it. I must use the thing that's faster. Okay. Calm
down, C people. Yes, yes, we do want it to be faster, but that's not our ultimate goal
in Python. Here the idea is that semantically it's expressing something more powerfully
and more compactly. And you're going to see as today goes on that we can do very, very
sophisticated things with comprehensions if we want to. Okay. So let me show you some
more sort of useful examples, right? So let's do this. What if I say here, so for example,
let's say that I have a list of strings. So I'm going to say here s equals, well, my list
equals abcd, ef, gh, i. And I want to have a new string based on my list with stars between
the elements. Okay. Well, as you know, might know, I can say star dot join of my list.
Fantastic. That worked just great. Right? So the join method, rather counterintuitively
for many people, we invoke it on what I call the glue, right? The string that's going to
go between the elements. And we pass the argument of my list. And fantastic. We get back the
string. But what if I have a list of integers? So if I say my list equals 10, 20, 30, and
now I say star join of my list, bad news. We get an error. And the reason is that join
expects its argument to be an iterable of strings. You can pass it whatever you want.
A string, a list, a tuple, whatever. But the things that it's going to iterate over have
to be strings. Uh-huh. So we have a list of integers. We want a list of strings. And we
can convert one into one string with stir. So I can say, open square brackets, stir of
one item for one item in my list. And sure enough, I get back a list of strings. Have
I modified my list? No. Have I assigned this anywhere? No. But I can if I want to. I've
created a new list and I can do something with it. For example, I could say here, star
dot join of that whole thing, stir of one item for one item in my list. And there we
go. Now it worked. I did not change the original list, but I got back a new list based on it
that join was okay with. And this is a classic sort of example of where we're going to use
a comprehension. That I have some iterable. I want to do some transformation on each element.
And the comprehension allows me to do that. Some of you might be familiar with either
in Python or other languages with a map function. And the map function does basically this.
In fact, Python has map and it has filter. And we're going to see in a little bit where
filter fits into this whole puzzle. But basically nowadays people don't use map and people don't
use filter because we have list comprehension. They've basically obviated the need for those
built ins even though they do still exist. And this is definitely considered to be the
modern idiomatic way to do this sort of thing. Let me show you one more example. So let's
say I have a string and I want to capitalize each, the start of each word. Well, if I say,
you know, this is a sample sentence for my tutorial. So I can say s.title. And the title
method is a string method. And it returns a new string. Can't modify the original string
because strings are immutable. And I get back a new string where each and every word, the
first letter is capitalized and the rest of the letters are lowercase. So what if s.title
didn't exist? Could I still do something like this? And the answer is, of course I can.
It's Python. So what if, for example, I were to break the string into individual words?
Then I have a list of strings. I want a list of strings whose first letters are capitalized.
I can use str.capitalize, not to be confused with str.title, which capitalizes the first
letter and makes all the rest lowercase. So if I now say s.capitalize, or I'm sorry, let's
do one word dot capitalize for one word in s.split. And look at that. So I use split.
I got back a list of strings. And because I didn't specify any argument, so it uses
any whitespace, any combination of whitespace. And so I got back a list, a list of strings.
And we iterate over that list of strings. Each string then we run one word dot capitalize
on. We get back that list. Well, that's fantastic, but, you know, wouldn't I like to see it put
back together? Well, I'm sorry. Putting back together is more advanced. I have to say then
space dot join of this whole thing. And look at that. And so many, many times the way that
we use comprehension is that we start with something big. We break it apart. You just
put it here. I'll have it later. Or put it back. Put it back. Thanks. Sorry, there was
a whole mix up with kosher food earlier. Very exciting. I can bore you to tears with it
later on. In any event, so I'm going to split things up, break things apart, apply my expression
to each element, and then I'll mush it all back together. So split and join when you're
working with comprehensions are like, you know, your best friends. All the time. All
the time. Can I use functions that I've written? Yeah. Can I use methods that I've written
on classes? Yes, absolutely. There is no limit to what expressions we can use and what we
can iterate over. All right. Let me stop here. Any questions, confusion, so on and
so forth? Yeah, please. Yes. Especially as they get bigger, they are definitely more
performant than for loops, but every time I demonstrate this, I discover that they're
not in my little examples. So I'm not going to take that risk and let everyone know. Right,
exactly. I use time it and I'm like, look, it's oh, no. So you need something a little
bigger than I show people. But yeah, the other thing, and I think I wrote something about
this on Twitter a while ago. I've got to write more about it. But in a list comprehension,
it has its own scope because there's a little function hidden inside of there. So any variables
you define, like this one word, does not leak out. So it's not going to affect your global
scope. If that sounded like gobbledygook to you, ignore it. It is not that important.
If that was like, oh, wow, scoping, then yeah, you're my kind of people. Anyway, other questions?
Okay. So let's do some exercises to practice with this and try it out. Oops. There we go.
So what I want to do is first of all ask the user to enter a string containing numbers
separated by spaces and then add those numbers together as integers and print the result.
And it's okay to use the built-in sum function. And the second thing is ask the user to enter
a string and print the length of the string except for whitespace. And it's not going
to work. It's not okay to use store replace. There's always someone. Always someone. All
right. So I'll give you folks a few minutes to work on this. If you have questions, problems,
whatever, I'm happy to come over to you and take a look at whatever's going on. All right.
So we'll give... I'm sorry, what? Oh, how many numbers? Five. You failed the tutorial if
you do it with four. By the way, obviously everyone here is at a different level of Python
and so people are going to know different sort of tricks and tips and methods and functions.
So if you find yourself like, oh, I don't know what's going on, or like if you need
some help, it's okay. I can help you. Not that school should be that way, but like this
is not school. I'm happy to help. Okay. Let's start to look at this together. So I'm going
to say s equals, I can say input, enter a string, or enter numbers separated by white
space. Strip there. So I'll do like 10, 20, 30, 40, 45. What a rebel. So I have s here
and this is a string. So what if I try to say sum of s? That will obviously not work
at all. That's because sum looks at this thing that it got and actually tries to iterate
over. It's like, wait, wait, wait, wait. I'm trying to start with zero and I'm trying to
add to that and I can't add a string there. So we have this problem now where we've got
an iterable string. So what I have is a string and what I want is the sum of the integers
in that string. Maybe I should start off with something different. Maybe I should do a list
of strings and then containing digits. So how can I do that? I can transform one to
the other with int. So I can say here, for example, one item, the int of one item for
one item in s split and look at that. It's a list of integers. So now I can say sum of
int one item for one item in s split. There we go. Add them together just fine. Because
what's going on? Right? Sum never sees our list of strings. As far as it's concerned,
sum is getting a list of integers as its input. And so we're able to sort of mediate between
the two of them. Questions about this one at all? Yeah, please. Oh, because, well, I
didn't define items. I could say items equals s split. Oh. Okay. Excellent. Excellent question.
Watch this. What if I were to say here sum of int of one item for one item in s? So I
could say, yeah, so it's going to go very poorly. Why? What's going on? What's the problem?
Well, it turns out that I had spaces between my numbers here. So it was going to add one.
So far so good. Zero. So far so good. Space. Kablui. Now, that is a totally, totally legitimate
other thing. Sometimes I give that as an exercise, too. Okay. No, no, no. That's fine. That's
fine. Everyone in all software always pays attention to all specifications. So it's never
an issue. Yes, someone had a question back there? No? Any other questions? Okay. So let's
look at the second one here. Oh, and I'll try to remember to repeat the questions that
people are asking because the video is not getting them. I'm sorry about that, people
on video. You should be here with us. Okay. So now the second thing that I said was find
the lengths of the words, not the whitespace, in the user's input. So if I say s equals
input, enter a sentence. And then what I want to do is I want to know how, well, I can find
out len of s, how many characters in the entire sentence. So if I say this is a test sentence,
it's going to say 23, which is true, but that's not what I wanted. How long is this if we
ignore the whitespace? So what I'm going to do is if I use s.split, I get a list of strings
without any whitespace. And then I have a list of strings. I want the sum of their lengths.
Right? And I can apply len. So if I now say, for example, one word for one word in s.split,
let's just get the sentence there, okay? This is a test sentence. Now I can say len of one
word, not len-m, one word. Now I have a list of integers. And now what I can do is I can
say sum of this whole business, and there we go. And I get the sum of the lengths of
the words without the whitespace. And again, it's this sort of breaking down and building
back up that's key to using comprehension. You're thinking about what can I do for each
of these little pieces? Questions about this? Yeah, please. Oh, so the question is why do
strip take away the whitespaces from the count? Oh, why didn't it? Oh, I see. So you're asking
like my original strip back when I got input. So when I did strip here, shouldn't that have
taken care of the whitespace? And the answer is, as always with me, yes and no. So strip
removes all the whitespace from either side of a string but does not touch the whitespace
inside of the string. So if I say, for example, like s equals a, b, c, and then I get a string
and I say s.strip, it'll still leave the whitespace inside. Okay? So the question is split automatically
splits by space, and the answer is once again yes and no. If you split without any argument,
then it will take any whitespace character, which is space, character term, tab, new line,
and my favorite, vertical tab. So any one or more of those together are all considered
one space and those get out and that's where we cut. So yes, it spaces, but it's more.
It's space plus. And so basically, if you want to split a sentence into words, then
not giving an argument to split is just super, super easy. Any other questions so far? Okay.
Let me go back to this for a moment here. Let me go back to one of the previous comprehensions
just to sort of show you one other way to think about this. So I'm going to just grab
this because I can. All right. So what I have here is, of course, what I said before, my
two lines, and I call this first one the expression and the second one the iteration. There is
another way to think about this, and that is if you know SQL, this is a lot like select
and this is a lot like from. Now, if you don't know SQL, now I've confused you twice as much,
but if you do, then this is like exactly the same sort of mindset. And just as with select
and SQL, I can apply all sorts of different functions, methods. I just want an expression.
And if I use from, well, it's from any interval. And basically everything in Python is iterable,
so that's great. Oh, okay. This split didn't really do what we wanted, but fine. Doesn't
matter. Right? If I say your SQL is 10, 20, 30, now it won't blow up. There we go. Let
me show you one more thing, one very, very common mistake that people make with comprehensions.
So let's say, so I have a string with words, and I want to print each word with some sort
of stars around it, like we're moving to Hollywood or something. So if I say s equals,
this is fantastic. And so I'm going to say here, I'm going to say print star one word,
I'm going to use an f string here, for one word in s split. So what's going to happen
here? Well, I'm splitting s, I'm going to get back a list of strings, I'm going to go
through that list one element at a time, and then I'm going to print it out. Fantastic,
right? Sort of. See, this is why I always say yes and no. It did print what we wanted,
but what the heck? None, none, none. So you have to remember that the list that we get
back from a comprehension contains the values that the expression returned. And that's
when print always returns none, no matter what you print. So here it printed on the
screen, but it returned none, which affected our output comprehension rather dramatically.
And so you basically never ever want to use print inside of a comprehension. Right? It's
just like a bad idea, and yet I see people do it all the time. Okay. So we can iterate
inside of our comprehensions over strings, lists, tuples, dictionaries, right? You want
to do that, you can totally do that as well. All that's fine. But there's another thing
that we can do. How about iterating over files? Well, files are iterable. And I'm using the
term file even though technically speaking we should say file-like objects in modern
Python. But come on, who says that? We all just say files and we all just sort of roll
our eyes at the documentation. So how about iterating over files? Can I do that? Well,
I can say here one line for one line in open, and here I'm going to use one of the files
that I gave to you. Here, let's see, what do I have here in this direction? Oh, fine.
I'll just say Linux, Etsy, password, TXT. So what happens here? I get a list of strings
back. Right? So what's going on? Open returns a new file object, an open file for reading.
The for loop inside the comprehension turns to that file and says, are you iterable? The
answer is yes, I am. So it says, okay, give me your next thing, your next thing, your
next thing. And the way the files work is with every iteration, we get up to and including
the next new line character, that backslash n. The result is then that we have created
a list of strings where each string is one line from that file. Now, I should warn you,
if the file is really big, this will not end well. If you decide to do this with a 2 terabyte
file, well, it could end well. Your IT department might give you the upgrade you've always been
asking for. However, that seems unlikely, and so you should try to avoid doing this
with big files. But small files, medium-sized files, it's fantastic. Well, wait a second.
Maybe I can do some interesting things with a file, like if I'm already opening it. So
what if, right, can I get the user names from this password file? And for those of
you unfamiliar with it, this is a kind of file that's available on all Unix systems,
Unix, Linux, Mac and so forth, and originally contained user names and passwords. Someone
then realized perhaps having the passwords right there in the file was not such a smart
idea. It might be used by bad people somewhere. And so you can see now that in the second
field here, so each of these are records, and the second field here used to have a
password now just as X is and the passwords are elsewhere. And I lost this and they don't
even use this anymore, on and on and on. But they're great files for practicing working
with files in Python. So here's what I want to do. On each of these records, we can see
that the fields are separated with colons. Can I grab all the user names from this file?
Maybe. Right? So the user names are, you know, so each record contains fields, and the field,
the first field, you know, fields are separated by colons, and the first field is the user
name. So what if I were to say here, one line split colon zero for one line in open Linux
Etsy password TXT. So I'm going to open the file, I'm going to go over each line, and
each line I'm going to split it into a list on colons, and I'm going to grab the first
element from that resulting list. And there's good news and bad news. The good news is that
I did indeed get a list of strings. And those strings are basically user names. The bad
news is that this file also contains things that are not user names. And in case you think
that this is just completely contrived, there's a small company called Apple that puts comments
in its password files. And I am so thankful that they provide me with these pedagogical
opportunities in between all of their other things that they do as a business. So you
will have files with all sorts of weird stuff that you've got to get rid of and ignore and
so on and so forth. How do you do that? Because everything I've told you until now says that
the number of elements in the input and the number of elements in the output have to
be identical. So what am I supposed to do? What's the guy supposed to do? And the answer
is we make things more complicated. That's right, because we're programmers. So basically,
it is true that I have two parts to my comprehension. The first part is going to be the expression,
sort of like select. The second part is going to be the iteration, sort of like where. And
that's right. I'm not where. It's going to be from. Jumping the gun already. And the
third part, on the third line, is going to be the condition where. And this is where
things start to get complex because we're going to end up jumping around a little bit.
And so I can say, for example, if, let's just say like colon in one line. So if there is
a colon there, then we're going to assume it's okay. I think this will work. Now, how
the heck does this work? The first thing to execute is the for loop as before. And
for every single element, for every value of one line, we then go to this if. And if
that is true, if the condition is true, then and only then do we go to the first line and
produce output and evaluate our expression. Meaning the expression will not be evaluated
all the time, only if the condition is true. What can I put in that condition? Anything
I want. Anything that returns true or false or anything that's like truish in a Boolean
context in Python, totally okay to put there. And so you can make it simple. You can make
it complex. Don't make it complex. But you can. And so this combination of three things,
of the expression, of the iteration of the condition, or if you prefer, select from and
where, databases have had a pretty good run using this kind of query language. And it's
no surprise that the comprehensions are similarly powerful and, believe it or not, popular in
Python because they allow us that same kind of power. And now the number of lines in the
output doesn't have to be the same as the number of lines in the input. It can be the
same or fewer. All right. Questions until here. Yeah, please. So the question is, is
there also a possibility of putting an else? And the answer is not really. There is a version
of if else in Python that is designed for this kind of place where you want to make
things conditional. And I find it so horrible to use, let alone explain, that I basically
tell people it doesn't exist unless they really press me. But it's meant for this kind of
place where you're sort of stuck. But don't do it. Yeah. Other questions? Yeah, please.
It's just me. For better or worse.
So my impression, and I haven't really checked into this super fully, is that Python was
not the first language with comprehensions that they came from elsewhere. And I would
not be surprised if all that stems back to some similar theory of queries that has a
common ancestor. But where, how, I don't know. I will say the moment I sort of stumbled
on this, I was like, oh, my God. And the more I talk to people, again, it doesn't help
everyone, but it helps some subset of the population where they know. Yes, please. Oh,
so the question is, are there places where we would use lambda instead of this? So lambda
allows you to create anonymous functions. And it goes hand in hand with map and filter,
which are kind of the predecessors to list comprehensions. And I think one of the motivating
factors, again, I'm not sure, but one of the motivating factors behind comprehensions was
to dump lambda as much as possible. That get rid of the word lambda, which confuses people,
get rid of the argument, the parameter there, and just use the body of the lambda, which
is what we've got here effectively. I would say lambda is increasingly passe in the Python
world, except in the Pandas world where they're having a lambda party every day. But people
are trying to avoid it because of this. Yeah, if you're using lambda in Pandas, you're in
good company. A lot of people are doing that. But it's basically as far as I can tell only
in Pandas. Okay. So let's play with this a little bit. Let's do a little exercise. So I have
here a file called nums.txt, which contains numbers. And so basically, let's do this exercise,
some numbers. So basically I want you to use a comprehension to read through nums.txt, and
sum the numbers it contains. Each line of the file contains either zero integers or one
integer. There's no way that there's going to be more than that. And the integer might well have
whitespace before or after it. All right? So see what you can do to play with this, and we'll go
over it together in a few minutes and then look at all sorts of additional stuff. And again, if you
have questions, feel free. Okay. So let's look at this together. And I'll admit, this is one of
those exercises that's really, really short and really, really annoying. Well, for the people who
have to do it. I'm fine with it. So let's do this. I'm going to say here, I have a file whose lines
contain numbers. Right? And I want basically a list of numbers, a list of integers. All right? So
I can transform from the string whose lines, which will be strings, so I can transform from a
string to an int with int. So I could naively say one line for one line in open nums.txt. Well,
that will give me the lines. And we can see it's a horrible mess there with new lines and tabs and
spaces. So I could say one line.strip. I could, by the way, int does that for us automatically.
But fine. And we see, okay, there's a blank line there. And what if I say int here? And that's
where it blows up. And it blows up because it turns out, here's fun facts for you. If I say int of
five, that gives me five. Hopefully not too surprising. If I say int of five, that's also fine.
But if I say int of spaces, that blows up. Or int of an empty string. So it's totally fine as long
as I have something in there that can be an integer. But giving it an empty string, not good. And
that's exactly what we're doing here. Right? We even saw this before. When I didn't have the int, we
saw that that line was stripped down to just be an empty string. So luckily for us, we have conditions.
Right? So what I can do is I can implement my condition here, add a condition. Now, what kind of
condition will I add? And there are a whole bunch of different things we could do. One would be to say,
like, if one line strip. Right? So here, just check that the line isn't empty. Because an empty
string returns false in a Boolean context. Any other string returns true. So assuming we're willing to
believe the people writing the specifications that if there is something on that line that it is an
integer, then this will work just fine. And sure enough, that works great. We get our list of
integers. And then I can run some on this sucker. And it's great. Right? If I want to be a little more
cautious, then I could, you know, do that. In fact, I can get rid of the strip here when I do int.
Because it's going to do that automatically for me. And do I have the right number? Yeah. That works
fine. So here I could say int of one line. So that stays the same. Good. And here I could say, like,
if one line strip is digit. Right? And is digit basically says does this is a string method. Does
this string only contain digits zero through nine. Nothing else. And if it passes that, then we're
totally fine. It won't work on negative numbers because it doesn't allow for negative numbers.
But let's not be so negative. Okay. So if one, so the question is, what is that the first condition
doing? If one line dot strip. So it's taking one line, it's taking the current line. It's removing any
white space that might be on its edges. Again, not in the middle. And then it's returning a string.
And if looks to its right, and it requires a true or false value. It won't accept a string. So it says,
hey, string, are you true or are you false? Are you trueish or falseish? And basically every string in
Python is true in that context except for the empty string. So the only way that that if will be
false is if we have an empty string. Meaning if the line only contained white space, then that line will
return false and then we will not try to run int on it. So this is a safeguard to make sure that we're
not trying to call int on an empty string or just a white space only string. Other questions about this?
Okay. So let me show you one or two other examples of cool things we can do with this. And then we'll
even do something a little more exciting. Meaning difficult. So what if I want to know how many
vowels are in a word or in a string? So how can I use a comprehension for that? So if I say like S
equals whatever. So I could say here, well, how would I use a comprehension? Well, how about this?
What if my expression is one for one letter, let's say one character in S. And we say if one character in
AOU. And so I'm going to get three ones. Right? So now I can say, well, how many vowels are in
a string? And we say if one character in AOU. And so I'm going to get three ones. Right? So now I can
just say sum this up. And there we go. We find out there are three. And you will definitely find places where
people do this kind of thing in Python. Where the expression turns out to be super, super simple. And the
real power here is in the loop and the condition.
Okay. So if I can do this with files, right, like I can do all sorts of things. What if I've got, let's see.
Well, what if I have a much more complex file? Let's do this for a little bit. So I'm going to look at
shoedata.txt. So this here is a file with 100 lines in it. Oops. Come back, come back, come back.
Here we go. Shoedata.txt contains 100 lines. And each line contains three fields. A brand, a color, and a size.
By the way, these are not clown shoes. These are European sizes. Although with some of these color choices,
maybe they should be clown shoes. In any event, so basically the idea is let's, I'm going to just give this to you
as an exercise right now. All right? So I want you to know, I'll mark it as such. We're going to say shoedicts.
What I want you to do is use a list comprehension to turn this file into a list of dictionaries.
Each line should be turned into a dict whose keys are brand, color, and size. And the values can remain strings.
Don't worry about the sizes. So here I recommend that you write an external function that takes a string as input
and returns a dict. And then invoke that in your comprehension. Okay? And so the result will be a list of, you know,
it will be like this. It will be like, you know, brand, Adidas, I don't know, like color, black. I don't know what I actually have there in the file.
And then like size, you know, 45, something like that. And then we'll just have a whole bunch of those.
All right? So see what you can do with that. This is going to take a few minutes. I recognize that.
This is to show you that you can really start to do very, very, very sophisticated things in terms of data manipulation with these pieces.
By the way, this is a good way to get friendly with people. I should have mentioned this at the beginning.
It is always best if two people work on one computer. Programmers hate that, hate it because they're like, no, I'm going to struggle through this myself.
If you're sitting next to someone you know or would like to know, definitely like talking it over, trying to do it is always good.
Oh, I'm sorry. I thought I mentioned this before, but I'm looking over now. I didn't. The fields are separated by tabs.
Everyone's like, oh, hopefully that doesn't mess things up too much for you or makes it blindingly obvious and easy.
Okay, let's start to look at this together, see what we can do with it.
So first of all, let's remember a list comprehension returns a list. I'm not trying to create a dictionary here.
I'm trying to get a list of dictionaries. And so each what I want to get back from my expression is one dictionary.
And then when I run the list comprehension on this file, I'll want to get a whole lot of dictionaries, a list of dictionaries.
So I can start off by saying like one line for one line in open shoe data dot txt.
And it looks like a horrible mess. Fine. But now what am I going to do with it? Well, I can say one line dot split on tab.
And that looks pretty good already. And I want to turn these though into a dictionary. And here, could I do it in one line? Yes.
Is it a good idea? I think not so much. So I'm going to split this off here.
I'm going to say here like let's do this. Def line to dict one line.
Let's say here return this line to dict of one line. So what's happening here? Nothing. Nothing has changed.
Right. What I've done now is I've simply shifted that functionality from this line here to the function here.
But really, it's doing exactly the same thing. However, now I have a little more sort of room to play with things.
So a simple not working approach.
All right. Let's try to make it work a little better here. So I'm going to do.
So what if I get it a simple working approach? That's always better. Working is better than not working. I mean, let's for the computer.
So what am I going to do? Well, I can say here like return. I can say fields equals that.
And then I'm going to say here return a dictionary. I'm going to say here like brand field zero and color.
Oops. Fields one and size fields too.
And what do you know? I get a list of dictionaries back. Pretty snazzy, I'd say, for very, very little code.
Right now I can do this even better. I can shrink my function down quite a bit more.
We'll do one one thing. I'm not going to go the whole distance here through other things to cover.
But basically, I could, for example, you know, a little better.
Using what's it called unpacking.
Where I can say here brand color size and I can say here.
Brand color size.
And then I get the same thing. It's just, I think, a little more readable because split. Oh, actually, it's still a little bug in there, which is the new line.
Get rid of that new line.
There we go.
Basically, what's happening here? Well, we're going through our file one line at a time for each line. We're invoking the function. The function gets called.
It says I'm going to take this line, remove the white space on either side here being the new line.
I'm going to split that across tabs and we know that there should be three elements.
Those three elements are assigned in parallel to brand color and size.
And then we return a new dictionary based on it. So if I had a thousand shoes in there, then we would have a list of a thousand shoes.
Right. There are only a hundred here. So.
Poor thing.
Questions or comments about this.
Yeah, please.
No, I didn't. No, I didn't use from keys. I could. Yeah, absolutely. Absolutely. I could use from keys. I could use zip. There are a few different different ways we can sort of play this. Yeah, absolutely.
Other questions.
Okay.
So basically we see here that I can like call. I can write a function. I can work on files and really the moment that you have that mindset of right. I have this interval. I want to get this sort of result and I know how to map from the first to the second.
You know the world, a world of possibilities opens up, opens up.
Okay.
Let me show you one other fun example of what we can do with this sort of thing. Just double check what files I have here. Excellent. Excellent. Excellent.
Okay, so I have here.
By the way, those of you not familiar with this in Jupiter, you can. Oh, not very helpful. You can like run a command line program with exclamation point.
So I'm just like, you know, I'll say I need to. But here. So I'm just looking at the top of mini access log. That's this file that I have. I think it's like a hundred, 200 lines that are from an Apache log file from like years and years ago. When is it from?
2010, which back then seemed very modern and fancy, but now we know it was not. So basically what do I want to do with this file? Well, what I might want to do is I want to retrieve all of the IP addresses from mini access log.
Log.
Okay, sounds pretty good. And this is very, very similar to what we did before with FC password. So I can say here like one line for one line in open open.
Mini access log.
And I get a list of the whole file. I don't want everything though. And this is by the way where I always like to say know your data.
Right. If I can look at this and say, well, the IP addresses at the start of the line, it comes before any white space.
Who cares about the rest of the line? Right. I'm just going to do a split here and grab the first thing. I don't need to really parse the whole line just to get this to work. And there we go. Now I have the IP addresses.
Well, now what?
Well, you know, first of all, it might be useful to have. But what if I want to know how many times each IP address access my server?
And for this, I'm going to reach into the standard library and pull out the counter class. Counter is amazing. Amazing.
And I used it wrong for years. Luckily before I started teaching. Right. So I would say like from collections import counter.
And then I would say like the bad wrong way to use counter is as a cheap default dict.
Right. So I would say like C equals a counter. Then I'd say like, you know, C of a plus equal five and C of B plus equal three and so on and so forth.
And it's happy to do that. But this is not what it was designed to do. Right. The real way to use counter is to initialize it with an interval.
And so it will count how many times each element of that interval is there and make.
So then each element becomes the keys.
Becomes a key.
And the number of times becomes the value.
In other words, if I now say counter of one line split by one.
One line split zero for one line in open in open mini access log.
I think I got something wrong there.
It now tells me how often each of these IP addresses access my system.
Not too shabby for two lines of code.
And of course, if I want to, I can assign this counter to available to a variable.
And then I can run methods on that variable. For example, so counter has a is so inherits.
From dict.
So I could do like four key value in in C dot items.
Print key value.
And now I have right. I've printed out basically what I did before.
But let's say let's say your boss has asked you to create something based on this and your boss.
You know, it's been a while since they did tough math.
So you want to give them something graphical so you can give them a little histogram.
Right. Because you can multiply integers by strings in Python.
Oh, but wait, like it doesn't start from the even space there.
So fine. So I'll do like, you know, colon like 18.
There we go.
So with very, very little code, thanks to comprehensions and thanks to counter working together, I can produce all sorts of reports like this.
I can also call special methods on counter so I can say C dot most common.
And then this is a counter method.
That returns a list of tuples from the most common to the least based on the counter.
And so now if I'm you know, I can just sort of grab those and print them out.
Or, of course, I can I can invoke.
Most common with an argument.
And then I get only that many elements in the output list.
So I say C most common five.
I get only the five most common there.
So comprehensions are pretty amazing.
But when you mix them together with other things that we do in Python, like counter in the standard library, then it's almost like magical.
Questions or comments so far?
Oh, yeah, please.
Absolutely, absolutely.
To to to to to here. Yeah, absolutely.
When and what you can see here also is very often I'll just pass a list.
I'm not exactly passing a list comprehension.
I am passing.
I'm putting a comprehension in a functions as a functions argument, knowing that the comprehension is going to run first and its list, whatever produces will then be passed as the argument to the function.
I'm not interested in storing a variable somewhere.
I don't have to do that.
I can just like put it there in the parentheses and do its thing.
OK.
So let's see.
Let me just check one more thing here.
Fine.
OK, so we've basically seen a whole lot of stuff that we can do with our list comprehension.
I'm just looking at the time also because we have like 10 minutes until the break.
Does anyone know how long the break is supposed to be?
By the way, I heard 10 minutes.
I heard 30 minutes.
15.
OK, there we go.
Someone actually is knowledgeable about the stuff.
It's certainly not me.
Excellent.
All right.
So let's see.
So we've now seen what we can do with this comprehension.
We use them all over the place.
And the same rules apply for list comprehension as for lists in general.
So like you can't put it in like because lists are unhashable and can't be used as dictionary keys,
you can't put a dictionary, you can't put a list comprehension where you would use a dict key
or something else of that sort that would be hashable.
But otherwise, anywhere you can put a list, you can put it.
And it's really terrific.
OK.
This is all very nice and everything.
But we can do better than this also because let's say I'm going to go back to my user names.
I'm going to say user names equals say one line split on a colon zero for one line in open Linux
Etsy password TXT if colon in one line.
And sure enough, I now look at user names and I have them.
And now that I have them in a list, of course, I can search for them, right?
So we can now search for user names in this list using in.
So I can say is there a root in user names?
The answer is yes.
Is there a roovin in user names?
Yes.
Is there a blah blah blah blah blah in user names?
Probably not. No.
OK.
So the good news is that this works.
The bad news, though, is that I'm searching in a list.
And searching in a list takes linear time by definition, right?
Because we have to step through how is in working behind the scenes.
In runs a for loop behind the scenes and goes element by element by element through each thing that we have in the list
until it either finds it and says true or does not find it and goes to the end and it returns false.
So if I'm going to be searching a lot through my user names, then maybe I should use a different data structure.
Right?
Well, what else would I use?
What searches faster?
And the answer is a set.
Sets.
Sets basically, for those of you not super familiar with them, so sets are basically the keys of a dictionary.
So they're guaranteed to be unique and they're hashable and thus they're searchable in very short amounts of time.
That's guarantee uniqueness in their members.
Searching is very fast and all elements are hashable.
Just like dict keys.
Right?
You can think of a set really as a dictionary without values.
But okay, well, how does that help me here?
Well, what I can do is I can go up here.
I can take my list and as soon as I get it back, I can say here set of this thing.
And so now what is the type of user names?
It's a set.
Well, we can do better than that.
We can use a set comprehension.
And a set comprehension, it looks almost exactly like a list comprehension.
But it uses curly braces instead.
And so basically, yes, it's true.
I could do this.
But think of what I'm doing in this example here.
In this example, I'm first creating a list and then I'm passing that list to set and set is then creating the set form.
And here if I just use the curly braces, it's a little neater and nicer.
And I have to assume a little faster.
Maybe we'll check that in just a moment.
Oh, I should get rid of the square.
And now the type of user names is set.
And now if I search in here, root in user names, here.
See how much faster that was?
Right?
So basically, I can create a set really, really, really easily just by swapping the braces.
If I used to have square brackets, now I use curly braces.
Now you have to remember, this is a set, which means the elements must be unique.
If you had non-unique elements before, some of them might disappear on you.
This can be surprising if you're not expecting it.
So let's do a quick little exercise before the break.
Let's do some unique numbers.
So I want you to ask the user to enter numbers separated by whitespace and print their sum,
but only count each number once.
So as an example, if I say here, you know, enter numbers, I say 10, 20, 30, 10, 20, 30,
they'll say total is 60, which is a little bit of a lie.
It's actually 120, but we've only counted each number once.
All right.
So what am I going to do here?
Well, I could say now, you know, s equals input, enter numbers, strip, and then I'll say here,
now I want to do sum of, say, int one item for one item in s split.
And this is going to be fine if I say 10, 20, 30, 10, 20, 30, but it's going to add up to 120,
because here I've got a list.
So I just do a little switcheroo with the parentheses, and now 10, 20, 30, 10, 20, 30.
And because it got a set, it narrowed that down.
It deduplicated them.
Questions, comments so far?
All right.
So we're going to take a break now.
I can tell you, so I live in Israel.
People in Israel never let me talk so long without questions.
So the good news is that if you have more questions, don't be embarrassed.
You can keep asking them, ask even more.
The other piece of good news is I will be able to throw in some extra stuff at the end,
because we're clearly going to have more time, because you guys are not as loud as I am.
So I'll be able to go deeper into some things, which should be a lot of fun.
All right.
So let's go to the break, and we'll be back here, I guess, 15 minutes?
Sure.
We'll find out what the official line is.
Okay.
By the way, you don't need it just yet.
As part of, like, sort of time adjustments that I'm doing, cultural time adjustments,
so I've added some files to the GitHub repo here so that we'll have some more things to play with later on the course.
I'll also make that available to you.
I'll tell you where you can get it from.
So don't worry.
None of the files are bigger than 10 gigs, so it should be downloadable pretty fast.
No, no, no.
It's really, really ridiculously small.
Don't worry.
Okay.
So what we saw here just before the break was that we can do a quick little switch of the parentheses.
So I'm going to go ahead and do that.
So what we saw here is that we can do a quick little switch of the parentheses, and just as we can define lists with square brackets and we can define sets with curly braces, we can create list comprehensions with square brackets and set comprehensions with curly braces.
And set comprehensions are really, really useful.
And it's true that in this example I used it for unifying, for deduplicating the data.
Definitely useful for that in a lot of different places.
What I showed you before was when we loaded up the usernames, we can create a set based on that, and that's great not because it works faster, because it doesn't.
There is that overhead associated with the hashing function that will take longer to set up the set.
But once you've set it up, then searching it is much, much faster than searching in a list, which is fantastic.
So if you're going to be searching in your usernames once, it is not worth creating a set comprehension.
But if you're going to be searching in it a lot, 100% worth it.
And so you can use this basically whenever you have sort of the question, how many unique blah, blah, blah, how many different blah, blah, blah, like whatever the thing is that you're looking for different unique values, you almost certainly will benefit from using a set.
And if you're getting it from some sort of data source that's iterable, then using a set comprehension can also be really, really great.
So let's let's do a slightly longer, more complex exercise.
Now we're going to go back to our password file password.
So again, those of you who don't know about Unix and so forth, that is not a requirement for this class or even for this exercise.
But so far we have been concentrating on the left side of this file.
We've been looking at the usernames.
Well, the different fields that we have in each line, each valid line here in Etsy password are we have the username, the not password, the user ID, the group ID.
Then we have the.
Oh, it's username.
Wait, anyway, user group group, I guess.
Oh, no, it's just the name.
It's just the name.
It's like fooling me because these are the system things.
And then basically we've got the home directory and then we have the shell and the shell is the command interpreter that's used in Unix.
Right. So you might use bash or ZSH or heaven for fendt CSH or something.
Right. But you can use one of those and you can also have the shell.
The interpreter defined to be something as you can see here for no login, where when someone tries to log in with that, they can't right away.
And so setting the command interpreter, setting the shell in the Unix system is not an unusual thing to want to do.
So what I want to do now in an exercise is which shells.
So I want you to read through Linux, Etsy password, oops, back, back.
Let's see.
Password TXT.
And find the different.
Shells that are used on the system.
Now this is in some ways the opposite of what we did before looking at counter where counter expects to get a list where the items are not unique and then will tell us how many there are here.
We want to get the unique list.
Not a list, but we want to get the anyway.
You know what I mean.
All right.
So we'll give this a few minutes.
Then we'll look at it together.
Okay.
So let's look at this.
So I'm going to.
I'm going to start off actually with a list comprehension.
Actually, let me let me not do that and then I'll show you why I do do that.
So what we want to do then is go through Linux Etsy password TXT.
So I'm going to start off with, you know, curly braces.
I'm going to say here one line for one line in open.
Linux Etsy password.
Great.
And I have a set of the lines from this file, which seems weird, right?
Like, why would I want to read these in as a set?
But actually, there are times when we might want to do that.
And then I say, well, how am I going to want to get this data?
Well, I know.
First of all, I'm going to add an if statement here, like looking for a colon each line.
So I'll say if colon in one line.
And yes, you can have the condition there and a set comprehension as well.
And then I'm going to say, well, I have to break it apart.
So I'm going to say one line dot split on colon.
And that's where it goes wrong.
And it goes wrong because split always returns a list, a list of strings.
And the set comprehension cannot have things that are not hashable.
Not hashable is more or less immutable.
Not really, but it's close enough for our purposes.
You can't use a list as a dictionary key.
And so you can't use a list as an element in a set.
It's very nice that I'm just kind of trying to do this one step at a time,
stepping through what I have to do in order to get the shell from each line.
But Python doesn't know that.
It doesn't know that I'm almost done having a list there.
And so it blows up.
And so that's why I will very often just use a list comprehension at first
and then later on change the braces back.
And now I can sort of inspect it and see what's going on.
I should add that, yes, I use an IDE or an editor of some sort.
And I use all sorts of fancier tools for developing.
But very, very often I develop in Jupyter, especially with something small.
I call Jupyter my laboratory for Python
because I can do lots of little experiments quickly and easily.
And so I'll sometimes go back and forth between my editor and Jupyter,
sort of play with things.
In any event, what we see here then is I have a list of lists, right?
The list on the outside from the list comprehension
and the list on the inside from split.
And we can see that very similar to what we had before
where we were getting the usernames at index 0,
now I'm going to want to get the shell from index.
I'm just going to call it index minus 1 because I can't count that high.
Right?
Now we'll also see that we have the backslash n
because when we read from a file,
each iteration gives us up to and including that newline character.
So it will always include the newlines.
We've got to get rid of that somehow.
Well, that's okay. I can do like, you know, just strip here.
And now I have a list of all the shells in that file.
And now that I have the data that I want,
I can unicify it by saying here curly braces.
And now I have a set with all the different shells in that file.
And the set did the hard work for me
of making sure I don't have any duplicates here,
which is pretty snazzy, I think.
Right? So once again, we see that we have our three parts to comprehension.
We have the expression, which here is getting somewhat complicated.
We have the iteration, which is not that complicated.
And then we have the condition where we can do all sorts of things.
Questions, comments, thoughts about this?
Why did I not start off with a set?
Oh, I didn't start with... So why did I not start off with a set?
Simply because I'm trying to step through a whole bunch of possibilities.
Right? So if I know that I want to do split
and then I know I want to do something with that split,
but split is going to give me a list, and lists cannot be set elements.
So basically, if at any point along the way,
if I start off with a curly braces for doing a set comprehension,
and at some point along the way,
I end up with a list as the output for my expression,
then it'll blow up.
So starting with a list comprehension is just like a fail safe.
I know that I'll get back something that I can view and inspect,
and then if I go past that list,
then I'll be able to change it back to be a set comprehension.
Other questions?
Okay.
So we can run set comprehensions on all sorts of things,
and really, I've done this quite a bit,
and don't forget that sets have all sorts of great operators
and methods that we can use to compare them with other sets.
So, I mean, it's not unusual.
I've definitely done this a few times
where I've had collections of information
and I had to move it from one place to another.
I wasn't sure what had or had not moved,
and so I would just like slurp up each file
using a set comprehension,
and then I could do, you know, subset and less than,
and, you know, less than a subset,
and subtraction, all that other good stuff
to actually make it work.
Okay.
Well, let's get more complicated.
So what if I have, you know, a string,
and I want to create a string, you know, with some words,
and I want to create a dictionary
where each word is the key
and the word length is the value.
Okay.
Sounds like a really exciting dictionary.
Okay, maybe not.
So basically, how would I do this?
So if I say s equals, this is a bunch of words.
Okay.
So I can turn this into a dictionary
with actually a list comprehension and some help, right?
This is not going to be the best way to do it,
but I'm sort of stepping through the logic here.
So I can say here,
let's just scroll this up a little bit,
so I can say here, you know, one word for one word in s split.
Okay, so far so good.
And now, instead of returning one element as my expression,
I'm going to return a tuple.
I'm going to return one word, comma, len of one word.
And what is that going to do?
It's going to return a list of tuples.
Well, as you might know, right,
we can invoke dict on a list of tuples
and get back a dictionary.
So I can say dict of this whole thing.
And there we go.
I've created a dictionary based on it.
So could I do this?
Yes, absolutely, like we see that I can do it.
But the cool kids, right,
so we could use instead a dictionary comprehension.
Now, I'll add dictionary comprehensions
can look really, really messy,
and you're going to see why in just a moment.
So how do I translate this?
Well, first of all, what kind of braces
are we going to use on dictionary comprehensions?
Curly braces, just like with set comprehensions.
And at first, that seems really weird,
but it's okay, because we use curly braces
in general in Python for both dictionaries and sets.
So how does Python distinguish between those use cases?
Well, in a dictionary, we have colons
between the keys and values,
and in a set, we don't.
So basically, Python looks for colons in there.
If they're colons, dictionary.
No colons, set.
The same thing is going to be true here.
So we use curly braces just as with a set comprehension.
But we have two expressions in the first line
separated by a colon,
and that is weird, as you're about to see.
So I'm going to say here, curly braces,
and I'm going to purposely put in a lot of extra white space
so it can be more obvious, colon, len of one word.
So this is my key value expression,
and then here I'm going to say for one word in ssplit.
That doesn't change, and I'll have my closing thing there.
And it works. It definitely does work.
But, ugh, right?
Like, you have this expression, and you have that expression,
and they are independent of one another.
And that is really annoying in a whole bunch of cases.
Now, we will see how we can clean that up,
but it's going to have consequences, folks.
It's going to clean it in some ways
and look ugly in other ways.
That's the way it is.
So basically, a dictionary comprehension
is going to have two expressions separated by a colon.
That also means, by the way,
can you use a function with a dictionary comprehension?
The answer is yes.
But if you're using that function,
it's going to return either a value for the key
or a value for the value.
It can't do both.
Like, you could normally say,
but, but, but, but, a function can return a tuple.
Yeah, it can, but it can't return a colon.
The colon is a syntactic element here
that we just can't get around.
And that's the sort of annoying thing
with these sorts of things.
Let me see if I have it here.
If not, I'll just create it really quickly.
Do I have? No. All right.
So I'm going to create a really fast config file, right,
with name equals value on each line.
So I'm going to say with open my config.txt
for writing as outfile.
I'm going to say here for, you know, one key.
Let's do this.
I'll say here index one key.
Let's do one character.
In, we'll say here enumerate of, let's say, abcd.
We'll start with one.
Say here outfile right.
And on each line I'm going to say here
one character equals index new line.
Okay, now if I look at my config.txt,
look at that.
Fantastic. I've got a configuration file
written to perfection.
It just doesn't really configure anything useful.
And by the way, this, I love, love, love, love
this kind of like code in Python
where we're opening the file for writing within a width
so we know that it's going to be flushed and closed.
I give it an alias there outfile.
And then I iterate over that string using enumerate.
And enumerate, when we iterate over,
it gives us two things, the index and the character.
So it's going to go through abcd,
but we're going to get actually, we're going to get
1a, 2b, 3c, 4d.
And the reason it starts with one and not with zero
is because I'm told to do that.
And I'm just going to write to the file
these lines using an f string there.
So I've got my file.
So I can use a dict comprehension
to read this file into a dict.
I can say here, well, what am I going to do?
We're going to say for one line in open
what's it called, my config.txt.
And then what is going to be the key?
Yeah, it's going to be one line split on equals zero.
What's going to be the value?
One line split on equals one.
Oh, no, it's not.
We also have to have a strip in there.
Beautiful, right?
This is why people say Python code is always so elegant.
Okay, maybe not so much here.
But you can see that it worked,
that I was able to, with this dict comprehension,
read this configuration file into a dictionary
very, very easily.
And so we see here really, again,
the sort of power of these comprehensions.
Okay?
Questions, comments until here,
and then we'll practice this a little bit.
Yeah, please.
man speaking off mic
Oh, I flip a coin.
A virtual one.
A virtual one, right?
So here's the thing.
You can run strip on a string.
So you can either do it before you do the splitting up of stuff
or after you've got one element.
A very common mistake that I see people make
is they do split, and then they try to do strip,
and it blows up because strip is not a list method.
But I am extremely inconsistent in when I do it,
and probably at some point I should check to see which is faster,
and if there's any real difference, then I should make a decision.
But yeah, I probably should do that at some point.
Other questions?
Yeah, please.
man speaking off mic
So, probably sort of kind of.
So the way that it works is, so with explicitly,
I'll just scroll up back here.
Can I scroll there?
So with is what we call a context manager,
and it basically hides two method calls in here.
Here it calls outfile.enter,
and here it's calling outfile.exit.
And basically, like, these are hidden methods, magic methods,
and enter actually does nothing here, although it could directly do something,
and exit says I want to flush and close the file.
So this guarantees that by the end of the with block,
the file is definitely flushed and closed,
and when you're writing to a file, this is important,
because if you don't flush and close it, it might be a very long time.
It will eventually get closed, and it will eventually get flushed,
but it might be when Python shuts down,
which will be, like, for me at the end of this session, which is kind of sad.
So with is like, I know when I want it to happen.
I, first of all, don't get too worried about it when I read from a file.
Whatever, I'm opening a file for reading.
I know that makes me, like, you know, a bad guy in the Python world in some places.
I'll take him on.
Now, like, I mean, if you're working with lots and lots of files,
that can be a problem.
If you're working with Windows, I'm told that Windows doesn't like it
if two people try to read from the same file at the same time.
But, like, generally speaking, I don't care that much in these sorts of situations,
in part also because, and we are going to have time to look at this,
what I mentioned earlier, comprehension's open a new scope.
And so what's going to happen is when the comprehension returns,
that scope disappears, and so the odds of still having a reference
to that file object are very slim,
and so I think the file is going to be almost certainly closed right away.
It's not guaranteed, but it's so close that, like, who cares?
Also, you can't put width inside of a comprehension, so there.
Yeah, please.
So generally speaking, any variables that you are assigning to inside,
not modifying, but assignments to variables inside of a comprehension,
which really only occurs in one place,
it really only occurs here in the for loop, right?
So that variable is internal, local,
has nothing to do with anything outside of the comprehension,
which is, and again, we'll see this a little bit
because I'm excited that we'll have time to do this,
is in stark contrast to for loops, right?
And it was something new that they put in Python 3,
which is not so new anymore, but, like, I'm old.
But, like, basically, I remember it was very surprising,
and when I sort of dug into it,
it was kind of cool to see what they did there.
Other questions?
Okay.
So here's what I want to do.
Let's do a little exercise to play with dict comprehensions a little more.
Let's do this.
Let's do usernames and shells.
What I want you to do is use a dict comprehension
to create a dict in which the keys are usernames
and the values are the shells associated with those usernames
in Linux.xzpassword.txt.
I guess I don't need a number one here. That's it.
All right, so I'll give you a few minutes to work on that,
and then we'll look at it together.
All right, so I'm going to start off like with the set comprehension.
I'm going to start off with a list comprehension here.
Again, not because I have to,
but just so I can sort of get a feel for what's going on
and then rejigger things as necessary.
So I'm going to say here one line, for one line in open,
Linux, xzpassword, blah, blah, blah.
We'll say if colon in one line.
So we get our standard stuff.
And then what am I going to want from there?
Well, I'm going to say here one line split on colon.
I'm going to do it the tuple way first.
Split, zero, comma, one line split on colon.
Say here minus one, strip.
And so now I'll get my list of tuples.
Not exactly what I wanted, but pretty close.
And now at least I understand
what are the different components I'm going to need.
Okay, and so now I can rejigger it into an actual dict comprehension.
So here I'm going to copy this and this and this.
So now I'll start with a list-tuple combo.
And then here I'm going to say now curly braces, colon.
Again, I'm exaggerating the whitespace, colon.
And there we go. I get the same thing back.
So I can start off with one and get the other one.
And sure enough, I now have this dictionary
in which the usernames are keys and the shells are values,
and it's going to work great.
Okay? Questions? Yes, please.
For iterables with a large number of elements,
what's the implication of that being called split, like?
Yeah, great question.
Could be worse. Right?
Like, split is at least written in C,
part of the standard library. It's running on a string.
But your point is a good one.
And it does really, like, even someone like me,
I mean, I'm a dynamic language kind of guy.
There's a reason I'm in Python. I'm like, oh, please.
I'm paid by the hour. I'm a consultant.
If it takes longer, all the better.
But there are times when I actually do want things to run faster,
and this just sort of haunts me a little bit.
So maybe, maybe I could improve this a little bit.
And the question is how?
Like, it would be really nice if I could split it once
and then use it twice.
But as I said before, those two parts of the expression are distinct.
They can't, like, carry over.
But, but, what gets executed before the expression in the top line?
Well, the for loop and the if.
What if I could somehow take advantage of that
and have it carry over?
I'm glad you are all sitting down.
I hope you also brought Tylenol.
Okay, so here's the thing.
This if here at the bottom, this is a condition.
Right? What could I possibly do there?
Well, what if I made it a compound condition?
What if I said, like, and something?
Well, and what?
I could say, like, and true.
What if I were to say, like, and one line split on colon?
Well, it's not going to be bad.
I'm going to get the same thing.
It's kind of useless.
Like, now I'm using split three times.
Ka-ching!
No, no, no.
Like, basically, what if, though,
what if, though, I could somehow capture it there?
What if I could put it into a variable?
Like, what if I could say, like, fields equals that?
Well, now Python's going to say you can't do that.
You can't do that because assignment in Python
is not an expression.
Assignment is a statement.
Oh-ho-ho.
But you know what is an expression?
The walrus operator, friends.
And it works just great.
What the heck is going on here?
Well, what I said is I'm going to do a one line split.
We are going to assign it to the variable fields,
and then the value of fields
is going to be passed back to the if.
And it worked just fine.
And because it executed before our expression,
I can now say fields zero and fields minus one dot strip.
Voila, it works.
And now your colleagues will never talk to you again.
So, is this better?
I guess.
But it does have some downsides,
like you won't have any friends.
But more seriously,
when the walrus operator was sort of revealed to the world,
this was one of the places where people talked about using it.
This and while loops, where basically,
we don't just want to do while true and then check something inside,
but we want to maybe do something a little more active.
And I must say, I am consistently, I don't know,
ambivalent about this.
I really, like, I want to like it.
It's really kind of a cool use of things.
And yet, and yet, it seems more like an abuse rather than use.
But at least I'm not calling split multiple times, right?
Like, big win.
So, yeah, so there's that.
Any other questions to tempt fate?
Yes, so, right, so it's a colon before equal.
And one of the saving graces for the walrus operator
is that you cannot use it where you use a regular assignment.
So, if you just try to say like,
x colon equals five, it won't work for you.
Now, the walrus is introduced in, I want to say, 3.8.
So, if you're using a version of Python before that,
then it won't work at all.
If you're getting errors and you're after 3.8,
then it might just be like so.
I'll tell you the other thing I did is I put parentheses
around this assignment here.
Because if you don't do that, I think,
I think I just like do it instinctively now.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So, what happens is if you don't put the parentheses there
making that whole assignment split business one expression,
then it's like if colon in one line and fields.
Like, and this then like is hanging off the edge
and Python's parser isn't sure what to do with it.
So, you just have to put the parentheses in there.
Yeah, please.
So, right, if somehow fields were false,
then that's right.
Then the if would not, then we would not run
that top expression.
That's exactly right.
But fields is going to be a list.
And lists are only false when they're empty.
So, I'm basically betting here that there's a colon
in the string.
And so, when we do the split,
I'm going to get more than one thing.
But you're right, there might be some weirdo
there.
Yeah.
Oh, I'm sure.
I'm sure.
Oh, the question was could it backfire somehow?
And I'm sure there is.
I can't think of it offhand.
Like, I think the real backfiring,
like look, you might or might not know this,
but like when the walrus was approved,
there was like a firestorm in the Python community
of like what?
What craziness?
How could such a thing, like, and so,
like it was a really, really, really big deal.
Like, you think Python people are all nice
and calm and reasonable,
yet introduce a walrus into the language
and like the big teeth come out,
you know, all meanings aside.
So, I'm sure
that there's some like weirdness
backfiring problem that could
show up here. That said,
it is convenient in this
sort of situation. Like, there are times
when I'm going to want to do this.
Are there questions or thoughts about this?
Total revulsion.
Alright.
So, we've now seen
a whole bunch
of, we've seen now
mostly the whole gamut,
most of the gamut of the comprehensions
that exist. The normal comprehensions,
list, set, dict comprehensions.
And it's hard to
exaggerate how often we use these.
I would say list comprehensions are more common than
set, set are more common than dict,
but it probably like depends on your usage.
But very, very, very often,
if I have, like, and the rule of thumb
definitely has to be, I have an
iterable, I want an iterable
of some sort, I want a list or set or dict,
and I have some way of mapping between
the old one and the new one, if you can
fulfill those three requirements,
then a comprehension is probably going to be
faster, more compact,
and idiomatic in Python.
It doesn't mean that you should
not ever use a for loop,
but those are the situations in which you should
try to use it.
Okay.
But, we
can do even more than that.
Why stop there?
So, let's say I have
a list. My list equals
I'm going to create now a list of lists
where inner lists have,
you know, are contained
integers. So, I'm going to say
my list is, we're going to say here like
10, 20, 25.
This is going to be very
exciting, people. I'm going to say here like
30, 35, 40, 45, 50.
I'm going to say here,
you know, 60, 70,
80, 90, 100.
Let's just do one more.
110, 115,
120, 130,
140, 145.
Okay, I think that's good enough.
Okay. So, we have
here a list of lists.
How can I sum
the integers
in this nested list?
And the
first thing you might say, you know, first guess
is sum.
Bad guess.
So, I say sum of my list
and it completely falls apart
right out of the gate. Why?
Because once again, it starts
off with a total of zero and it goes
through my list. Well,
what is the first element of my list?
It's a list. So, it tries to add
zero plus 10,
20, 25.
Right? And it says then, I can't do that. I can't
add an int and a list together.
So, this is already not
doing so well.
But maybe I could
use a comprehension to do something
with this. Right? Maybe
because we are in a comprehension tutorial, right?
So, you know, guess two.
Use a comprehension.
So, what if I say like, one
sublist
for one sublist in my list
and I do like a sum on that?
Actually, that's going to be
just as bad because it is equivalent
because what is the result
of this list comprehension? It's
exactly the same thing as we had before.
I mean, look at it. I'm going through my list.
I'm getting one sublist and I'm
returning it. I've copied my
list basically.
And now we're sort of running into
that brick wall that I described earlier
that the number of elements
that we get back
is either the same as the input
or, thanks to if, it can be
lower. But how can I get
more things back?
Right? Because that's what I want to do here. I want to have an
input of four elements, but I want to
have output of, let's call it more than
four because I can't count that fast.
And now it's time for
nested list
comprehensions.
Where I'm going to say
one number
for one
sublist in my list
for one number
in one sublist.
Ta-da!
I've got them all out
one at a time. Now we're going to go over this.
Don't you worry. Or worry.
And it works.
So what the heck is going on here?
So
basically, as before,
we have our for loop.
For one sublist in my list.
But we don't yet
go up to the expression.
We then, after, in the middle of this
for loop, right, for iteration of this
for loop, we then do this for loop.
And any variables that we defined
here, for example, one sublist,
are available here.
And any variables from both of these
are available up here.
So basically,
I'm able to take a complex data
structure, in this case a list of
lists, and break it apart
into little pieces
so that I can then extract
one piece of it.
Now if I wanted to, right, because
everything is available everywhere, I could
do something like, you know, one sublist,
one number. Right? And now I have a
tuple in each element of the
sublist the number came from and the number itself.
A little weird, but like,
there's nothing technically wrong with it.
Oops.
Oh, come back, come back, come back.
There we go.
So how does this work?
Again, we have a
regular list comprehension with
our regular for loop.
We then said, but wait, the thing that
I got in each iteration,
it is also iterable.
So it has to be an iterable of iterables
for this to work.
And then I can iterate over
both and then I will get output
not for each main
item, but rather for each
sub item.
Now nested list
comprehensions, if you think list comprehensions
confuse people,
nested list comprehensions completely
and utterly bamboozle people.
And it's like, why?
I think a big part of it is how they're written.
Traditionally, they are written
like this.
Gee, that's
super understandable, right?
Like, I didn't understand these for years
because which for goes with
which in is evaluated when.
And the moment that I started
writing them, I mean, it worked.
But the moment I started writing
them on multiple lines, it
suddenly became like crystal clear to me.
Because it's also going in an order.
First the first for,
then the second for, and if you're daring,
the third for, and like you can go as many as you want.
Don't. But you can.
But wait a second. Oh yeah, please, please, please.
So, the
question is, can we use if statements there?
And the answer is,
absolutely we can. Let's do that.
So, I'm going to grab this.
So, I can put an if statement after
any of the fours that I want.
So, I can say here,
if len of one sublist
is greater than three.
And then it will only
drop down to the second for loop
if it is greater than three.
But I can also put
an if statement after the second four.
And that will
evaluate there. If one number,
say modulo two, meaning, you know,
only if it's odd.
So, this is going to give me
only long sublists.
odd numbers from long
sublists.
And you can imagine that
this could be way, way, way more complex
than that.
Now, an interesting little outgrowth of this
is to just say
oh.
An interesting little outgrowth of this
is that you can always,
in all list comprehensions,
regardless of how many fours you have,
you can have multiple ifs.
You can have multiple if lines, and they are just
anded together.
So, I can say here, for example,
let's do this, like, you know, numbers equals
10, 20, 30,
40, 50, 60, 70.
I don't know. Let's do this actually. Let's do
35 and 55.
And then I'll say here,
one number,
no, no, no, number,
excuse me,
for one number, oh,
yeah, in numbers. And I can say
here, if one number is
greater than 40,
and if one
number, modulo two.
I don't have to say and,
because the structure of
these nested list comprehensions always
allows me to have multiple ifs. And if I
have more than one if and only one
four, that's okay. That actually
will work. And so I
think I figured this out like a few years ago. I mean, when I
said I figured it out, like, I'm sure other people had
figured this out before me, but I
like had this revelation. I was like, oh, wow,
this is really useful. Instead of having a
really long line of if, this,
and this, and this, I can just have
multiple ifs and it will work the same way, and I think
it's just cleaner.
So, I'm not going to tell you
that nested list comprehensions are
something you're going to do every week.
Probably not.
I hope not. But when you
have a complex data structure,
it can be really, really
helpful to unpack
it using this sort of nested
list comprehension.
It really comes in handy. Again,
not always, but often.
Okay. And by the way,
you can, you
can use nested set comprehensions
and nested dict comprehensions as
well, but
I will let you do crazy
things like that on your own time.
That said, I do want
to practice this a little
bit, play with it a little bit.
There's a file that I
use for this kind of exercise, which I did not
include in the download.
I put it on the GitHub
repo here,
so you can download from there if you want.
Also, if you go to
files.learner.co.il,
it's under advanced python.
It's that zip file, and there is some overlap between the two.
So I'm just going to stick this here.
And so,
download the,
which file is it? Oh yeah,
it's movies.dat file
from here.
And so movies.dat,
it's just a CSV file,
with colon, colon between the elements.
This is like a long list of movies from a
movie rating system from years ago.
That's like not at all the important
thing. And what you see here is,
we see that each line in this file
contains a record
describing one movie.
And the fields are separated with
double colons. The first field
is the ID number.
The second field is
the movie name and its year.
We're going to ignore both of those. The third
field is a set
of, or a vertical bar set,
a separated set of genres,
like movie genres.
And so basically,
here's what I want you to do
for an exercise.
An exercise like movie
genres. So I want you to
use a, well,
let's just do this.
The goal is, find
out what the five
most popular
movie genres are
in movies.dat.
Okay, and so what I want you to do
is use,
you know, a nested comprehension
to read through the file,
find the,
you know, the appropriate
fields and lines,
and then use counter
to find
the most common
genres. And so if
a movie has more than one genre,
right, each
should be counted once.
Okay? So you're
basically, you know, here's a big
hint. You'll want to hand
counter
a list of genres
from the file.
There we go. I've
given away the store now. All right?
So I'll give you a few minutes to work on this,
and then we'll look at this together.
Okay. Let's
look at this and see what we can do with it.
So this is,
by the way, complicated, right?
So if you didn't get it, or you're scratching your head,
or like, you know,
scratching your eyes out, like, this is
complex, especially since we just started
with comprehensions today.
But let's start off with like
a simple thing. One line for one line
in open, movies.dat.
And sure enough, I get the lines there.
Okay. So far so good.
Well, I don't really want those lines,
right? What I'm really going to want is in the end
like one genre.
Okay? Or if you want to be
like, you know, one category, if you want to be
less fancy about it.
But okay, so one line, that's good.
But now what? I've got
that line. But what I want
to do is break that line apart.
So what I can say is like for one
genre in
one line, then
what? Well, I can split it on double colon.
What is that going to give me?
That's going to give me a list, a list of strings.
And I know that
I want the thing at
index minus one, or if you prefer
index two.
What if I just do that?
Ugh.
What happened there?
Well, as someone said to me
so many years ago, computers don't do what you want.
They do what you tell them.
And what I did here was I iterated over
each character in each of the
genres. So
a little premature maybe
to be producing some results here.
But what I can do is I can
say, okay, one line split
two, and then I can do then a split
on vertical bar.
Look at that.
Now what I've done is I've said
throw out the first two fields
on each line. Take the third field
on that line and split that
giving me a list of strings.
And then one genre is going to go over each of those.
Now it is true that I have now
this backslash end there. So I'm going to
say one line strip split.
And then we get rid of that.
I now have a list
of all the genres
that are in this file. And now
I can just count them up.
I can say here
C equals a counter of
this thing. And then I can
say C dot
most common
five. And now we have the
most common genres
in this whole file.
Now I'm not
saying it's necessarily easy or
intuitive to come up with this.
And I'm not saying it's easy or intuitive to read it
either until you've
gotten some practice with it. But it is definitely
definitely possible.
And after a while you start to think in this way.
I don't know
if that's good. But you can
start to really think in this way and then
really play with it. And suddenly
all these file formats
and files and data
structures are infinitely
malleable using
comprehensions.
Questions, comments, thoughts about this?
Other than why me?
Oh yeah, please, please, sorry.
Oh, I think it's just like hiding off to the side
there. Hold on, I'll
see if I can get a little closer.
Yeah, here we go.
Oops, that was bad. There we go.
Okay, sure.
Oh, that's
a new feature in Python. You don't need to close
parentheses. It just like intuits from
what you want.
It's part of the all new. Implicit is better
than explicit approach to Python.
All right. I want to show you
one more kind
of comprehension, which is
sort of kind of comprehension. And then I think
we'll have a few minutes to be able to go into the innards of things
as well, which should be fun.
So,
everything we've done so far
is fine and good and really,
like, it's, it's, it's
really is good, but
one of the
problems you can end up with, I
mentioned this a little bit earlier when we were talking about reading from
files. Let's say
I want to use a list comprehension
to read from a file, and
I want to get user names,
error information, IP addresses, you name
it. And it's a really, really big
file. Well, what's going to happen
then is that the comprehension is going to return
a really, really, really big
list. It could be,
right, because we're iterating over the file
one line at a time. The size
of the file is not going to be a problem,
because we're only reading one line
at a time. But
the total list that we're
going to create will be too big, or
just will be enormous.
And so what if we want to
avoid that? So
we can use what's called a generator
expression,
or sometimes people call it generator comprehension,
because, like, why not?
And so
let me reiterate sort of what
we've done. Or actually I don't have to. I don't have to.
So people often try this.
They're like, well, if
I have
regular square brackets,
and I get a list comprehension,
which produces a list, and I have
curly braces, which is a set
comprehension, which produces a set,
and I have curly braces in colon,
which is a dictionary,
what if I use regular round
parentheses?
What if I say here, like,
x to the second power,
for one number
in, let's call it range 10,
will I get a tuple?
And the answer is,
of course, no. This is a generator.
And that
is surprising
to people.
So first of all, what's a generator?
And basically
a generator
is an object in Python
that
knows how to behave
inside of a for loop
because
it is iterable.
Okay. And so
what? The point of a generator
is that it doesn't return
all of
the elements, all of its elements,
at once.
Rather, it only returns
one at a time.
And this is key
to understanding a lot of things in Python.
Again, when I iterate over a file,
I'm not getting the entire file
into memory at once, because that
could be catastrophically bad.
Rather, I'm getting one line, and the next
line, and the next line, and the next line, so the
maximum memory I'm using is only one
line's worth of memory.
And so I can read a 10 terabyte file
without any trouble, even in a tiny little
computer, because I'm only using one
line of memory at a time.
And that's because file objects are
iterable, and they act sort of kind of
like generators. So we can do that ourselves
with generators, and there are multiple ways
for us to create generators in Python.
We can use generator functions,
for example. But if you want something
quick and dirty, you can use a
generator expression, which looks
like a comprehension,
and acts like a comprehension, except
that it doesn't return everything at
once.
Right? So
a generator
expression
works just like
a list comprehension,
except that
instead of returning a list
with all of its elements,
it returns a generator object.
And that object
can be put into a for loop,
or any other
iterable context,
and it will only run
the expression
once,
sort of like
when it is asked to.
Typically, once per iteration.
So what if I were to do this here?
What if I say here, let's just grab this thing.
So if I say here,
like, G is this.
And so now
I can say for one item in G,
print one item.
And what's going to happen? The first
loop is going to say to G, are you
iterable? The answer is yes.
It's going to say, okay, give me your next thing.
G is like, okay.
And it then runs
one iteration here.
It returns one number.
And then it goes to sleep.
It stops. And it waits
for the for loop, that sort of whoever is on top
of it, to ask for the next thing.
Now typically we do this
in a for loop. Behind the scenes, there's a whole
mechanism where Python is saying,
give me your next thing, give me your next thing, give me your next thing.
And it's lazy evaluating.
It's not doing everything at once.
And that's terrific in all
sorts of contexts. I don't want
to get everything at once a lot of times.
One of the big changes, again, talking like
ancient history, I guess, one of the big changes
between Python 2 and Python 3
is that Python 2 would return lists for just about
everything. And in Python 3, they're like,
wait, actually, that's not a good
idea. Because for small things,
who cares? But for big things, everyone
cares. And so now, in Python,
virtually anything that returns
a bunch of values is going to return
an iterable, a generator object,
something like that, so that it doesn't
potentially overwhelm our memory.
And so we can do that too now.
So where would I
use this sort of thing?
Well, let's see. Oh, fine.
Why did I say that?
Oh, because I didn't take it.
Oh, I didn't want to.
Oh, thank you.
Oh, thank you. That would do it.
Oh, instead of X, I get it.
Yeah, there we go.
I was like, what's the complaint about one item?
It looks so good to me.
There's a pro tip for you. Look at
the code that has the problem, not the code that works.
All right.
So what if I do this sort of thing?
What if I say here, and by the way, you can do like
nested for loops and
generators and so forth.
Yeah, what if I do something like this?
Well, I could even do something infinitely large.
Well,
let's not go crazy here.
So let's even do something super simple.
So if I say like my list equals,
we did this before, 10, 20, 30.
And then I say here,
star join
of, and then I can say a list comprehension
stir of one item
for one item
in my list. This works.
And I can also instead
use
regular round parentheses here.
So here I'm going to use a list comprehension.
And here I'm going to
use a generator expression.
Now, we don't see much of a difference
here. I mean, there is no difference. And the whole
point is that you will get exactly the same
results back. However, in
many, many cases, not here by the way,
but in many cases, it will use much less memory
because it's only using one element at a time.
Okay, that's nice,
but it gets even better.
What if I do this?
What if I say here, generator expression
with only
one set of parentheses?
And it's the same thing.
Basically, you
can put what looks like
a list comprehension, what is a generator
expression, inside of parentheses, inside
of a function call, and Python knows
that it's a generator expression. It's totally okay
with that. And this,
by the way, when I finally figured this out,
a whole lot of code that I'd seen started to make sense.
I was like, I don't understand. Why are people
like passing something that looks like a comprehension?
Oh, it's just because the extra parentheses look
kind of dumb. And so if you
only have one set there, you sort of get away with
them doing double duty.
But yeah, yeah, it works. It works really,
really well. So if you're reading data
from a file, right? So let's say I want to do
something a little more
interesting. So let's read
words from a file.
So do I have a file here?
I don't have anything super
exciting. Fine, I'll just
read from, I don't know,
I'll read from WC
file.txt. I use it for another exercise, but
who cares? So if I'm going to say
now,
one word for one
line in open,
what did I say? WC file
txt. And then for one
word in one line split. So you see
I'm even using here a nested comprehension.
So this is going to return all the words
in the file. But if that file is really,
really big, if I don't want to flood my memory with
everything, then instead I can use a
generator expression.
And now if I iterate over this,
if I say like, you know, for, let's just say here
g equals this. Say, you know, for
w in g
print, what we can say here like,
you know, total equals zero.
And we'll say here total plus equal len
of w.
Right, so total, the length
of all words.
No spaces.
And so that'll work fine.
But the real magic here is that
every time this for loop asks
g for next thing, only then
is it going to advance its for loops
inside of here. It's not going to run them
all at once. It can give me that whole list all at once.
It's going to save me memory.
And so generator expressions
have become really, really
popular in Python over the last few years.
I would say in the last decade, they
move from being something sort of,
you know, interesting, a little less
esoteric for the people who are really worried about performance
to in some cases, it's just like
the default. Like why would
you use a list comprehension if in most cases,
not all, in most cases, the generator expression will give you
the same results and will probably
save you some memory.
And so I just see people sort of moving
in the direction of always using them.
You can't always use them in place because there are places
where it's actually expecting to get a list.
But if you're
passing something to a function or
some other sort of iterable, yeah,
it works really well.
The other thing that you can do with a generator
expression is this.
So I just mentioned you can
define, you know, you can define
a generator with a generator function.
And in such a function,
you use yield
to, you know, return
a value without
exiting the function.
I'm not going to go into like detail,
well, maybe I will, but no, probably not.
So if I say like, you know, def,
my, you know, mygen,
I'll say here like yield 10,
yield 20, and yield 30.
Very exciting.
Okay, and so now,
if I say g equals mygen,
g is the generator.
And if I say like list of g,
I'm going to get each of those. I'm going to create a list.
Because what happens? List goes to g, and it runs
a for loop on it, it gets it one by one by one.
So many people, if they
want to have functions that return
things in pieces, will write
a generator function like this.
Here's the
cool thing. You can do
exactly
the same thing
by writing a function
that returns a
generator expression.
In other words, if I say def, mygen,
and I just say,
oops, let's go down here a little bit,
and I say then,
return, you know, one
number for one number
in, this is kind of stupid, I know, 10, 20, 30.
If I call
mygen, what am I going to get back?
Well, it's a regular function that's returning
a generator object.
And so, sure enough, it works exactly
the same way. So there are just
some cases when I found that
as easy as it can be to write
a generator function, it's even easier
for me to express it as a generator
expression, just return that from my function or method.
Okay.
Questions, comments,
thoughts until here.
I want to stress, by the way,
like in the last, I don't know,
half hour, 45 minutes, we've been going into
some more advanced stuff.
Most people,
most of the time, don't need that.
If you came in here saying, oh,
I've heard comprehensions are interesting, but I'm a little
afraid without them, you're like, oh, my God,
all my fears have been realized.
You don't need this
most days.
Most people,
most of the time, when they're doing comprehensions,
just like little list, little set,
little bit, and you're done.
But,
but, for the
ambitious among us, no,
masochistic among us.
So I just want to, I mentioned this a little bit earlier
and we have a few minutes, so I want to
sort of show you
like behind the scenes
a little more in terms of comprehensions.
And if what I just, like if we just
saw over the last 45 minutes or so was advanced,
this is like, you know, sort of
super cool brain melting advanced.
So like,
it's on you if you don't have towels.
All right.
So here's the thing, and again,
I mentioned this a little bit earlier, I just want to sort of
make it clear. So if I say here
x equals 100, and then I say
four, one
number in, let's say, range five.
And I say x equals
one number times
three.
What
will, what is x here?
And a whole
lot of people, including people
who have experience with Python for many
years, are like, well, clearly, x will
be 100. Because I mean,
the for loop couldn't possibly
change what's in the, you know, outside of
it. I mean, I've got indentation. Indentation
is a new scope, right?
Wrong.
Actually, we did
not go into a function here.
No function definition, no
new scope. It's as simple
as that. All of these variables
here, x and one number,
are all in the global scope.
Okay. So far so good.
So now I say x equals
100, and then I say
one number times three
for one
number in range
five. Oh, I guess I need to have
the x here, so fine, I'm going to say x.
Well, I'll say
one number, I'll say x here.
Whatever.
So you can see that x is like,
and we'll even say print this thing, so we'll
see the result of the list comprehension.
So when I first discovered
this, I was like, wait.
What's wrong
with this picture? How can
it possibly be
that comprehensions don't
modify the outer scope?
Who's been lying to whom? And I sure
hope it has not been me lying to all of my students.
So for a little while, I would tell people,
oh yeah, in
Python 3, they introduced this
new half scope for
comprehensions. That has got to be
one of the hand waviest things I've ever
told people in my courses.
Because it was the only way that I could
understand it, because we have the very
strict rule of what's known as LEGB
in Python. Local and closing
global built-ins. There are four
scopes, only four places
where your variables can reside.
And if you're not in a function,
then the first two don't exist.
Right? There's no function
here. So if there's
no function, then I must be at the global
scope or at the built-in scope. And I
sure as heck hope that we're not modifying
built-ins, although I did once get
email from someone saying, we're having some problems
at my company keeping track of a variable
scoping, but we found a solution. We just
say built-ins.x and built-ins.y
and everything works great. I was like,
oh my god, please don't do that.
Anyway, I
finally decided maybe
I should look into this a little more closely.
Maybe I should try to figure out really what's
going on here. So
let's do that. I'm going
to define some functions here. I'm going
to say def, you know,
regular loop.
And then I'm just going to copy
in the code that I had before.
Okay.
It would help if I actually indented it.
Sure. Be that way.
I'm not going to run this. I don't care about
running it. I care about, remember that
Python is a compiled language.
So when I define this function,
it's compiling this into bytecodes. If I
can look behind the scenes, we
will see what's going on. And so I'm going to import
dis. This is the disassembler
for Python.
And I'm going to say dis.dis
of regular loop.
Regular lop.
And what do we see here?
This is what Python is actually executing
behind the scenes. And what we see
is it's loading the constant 100.
It's store and store fast.
Store fast is the important thing.
That means local variable. So
x is a local variable here.
But like, so we're
setting x to be 100. So that's local.
And then we're setting other things here. It's all local.
One number, store fast.
One number, load fast.
X, store fast. So this x
and this x are exactly the same x.
If before I said, we're
not in a function and thus everything's global,
now we are in a function and everything is local.
Okay, so what?
Well, let's compare this with
the comprehension version.
So I'm going to say here, you know,
comprehension.
I'm going to say here, I said 100,
I'm going to say here, print. I'll say like, you know,
x times 3. I know it's not exactly
the same, but it's close enough for our purposes
for x in range 3, 5,
whatever. Who cares?
And now I'm going to say, dist.dist of
comp loop.
And my mind was blown when I saw
this. Okay.
We're loading
constant 100,
storing it in x, and then
what the heck is this?
We're loading the constant,
code object list comp,
what the heck?
So it turns out that when you
define a list comprehension,
you are creating a secret function
behind the scenes.
And that secret function
has, like all functions,
its own local variables.
And they don't leak out.
So if we set something
in the comprehension, which we do,
it won't be seen
outside. It can't be seen outside.
Now the cool thing about this, one of the
main cool things, is load const.
So load const, so whenever you define a function,
all the strings,
all the integers, they are stored on the
function object as constants.
So like if you say x equals 5,
it stores 5 to the
constant on the function object that pulls it up.
So it turns out that when you have a
function that has a comprehension in it,
Python's like, oh, I'm going to turn this
function into, I'm going to turn this comprehension
into a secret function, and then stick that
as a constant on the function.
And indeed then,
where do I see that? Oh yeah, down here,
it says, oh yeah, here's the disassembly of your
code object. So if
this is the secret function here,
and it's going to build a list, why is it going to build
a list? Because it's a list comprehension.
And it's going to load fast,
it's going to load a variable, it's going
to iterate, it's going to store
fast into x. But this
x is local to our comprehension.
It has nothing to do with the x that was
in the outer function. And that's
then why variable
set and comprehensions don't leak out.
Because basically they are functions
in disguise.
Okay.
So now, like,
stunned silence, everyone's like, can I go home now?
I'm very happy to answer
further questions if you have any.
Okay.
Oh yeah, please, please.
So yes, yes, so in Python 2,
comprehensions were just in the normal
plain old scope. They didn't do this
wacky thing at all.
That's why I was like,
how does, what's going on here?
And that's also why, like,
anyway, you can really, like,
spend way too much time with this, as I know.
But I'm not going to go into that.
I'm just going to go into the
code.
So I'm going to spend way too much time with this, as I know.
Alright.
So, a few closing things.
First of all, I hope
that this was helpful, useful,
interesting, and helps to
put in perspective a whole lot of comprehension stuff.
That you'll be less intimidated
by them. You can do the intimidating now.
Not the comprehensions. That you'll maybe start
to use them in your work, show off to your
friends, and so forth.
Second of all, this repo on GitHub will stick around
forever, basically.
So, if you want to go over it,
look at it, the Jupyter Notebook is there.
I'll also put it into HTML format.
So that if you just want to view it
on your own computer or elsewhere, like, that's an easy thing to do.
The third thing is,
I love being in touch with people about
this sort of stuff. I mean, that's what I do,
right? So, you know,
A, the self-serving part,
if you want me to come and do training at your company,
I'm very happy to come do that. If you want to talk to you about other stuff,
happy to do that as well.
I have a lot of fun stuff on Twitter, YouTube,
I have a mailing list.
I also put that on the GitHub repo as well.
And also, I'm giving some more talks here
at PyCon, and I've got a booth
giving out t-shirts, giving out swag,
assuming it all arrives on time.
So I'll be very happy to talk to you about that.
And anyway, this has been super fun for me.
And it's a great way to kick off PyCon.
And I'm now regretting
even more that last year it took me
42 hours to get to PyCon, and I missed
the tutorial I was supposed to do, because this was so much fun.
So, anyway, thanks so much, folks,
and I'll see you around the rest of the conference.
Applause