Hi everyone. For this next session our speaker will talk about consistency and isolation
for pipeline programmers. Let us all welcome Jesse Davis.
Hello. So when you use a database you need to choose an isolation level like serializable
or read-uncommitted. And if you use a distributed database like MongoDB then you need a consistency
level like eventually consistent or linearizable. There are dozens of options. And to make things
worse, consistency and isolation are easy to confuse with each other and people don't
really use those terms very consistently. In all of computer science I think that this
is one of the most difficult subjects to learn. But it's important to learn this because
if we get it wrong we can lose money or data or worse. When you start learning about consistency
and isolation it's easy to get lost in the weeds. So what's the bottom line? We're going
to start off with a simple world where your transactions run on one machine, one transaction
at a time. But in the real world of course we're still going to say for now that your
transactions run on one machine. We'll deal with distributed databases later in this talk.
But in the real world transactions run in parallel and that can lead to different outcomes
than if they were running one at a time. And these visible differences are called anomalies.
An anomaly is when a client sees a phenomenon that reveals that the database is running
transactions in parallel. This is my understanding of what an anomaly is. It's not defined at
the SQL standard. The SQL standard just lists a bunch of things and says these are anomalies.
My understanding of what anomalies are in general is this one. Isolation and anomalies
took me years to really learn this. But I have an idea for what we can do today to make
this easy. We're going to build a database in Taiwan. It's not the final frontier. People
have gone here before. But I think it's going to be helpful for understanding isolation.
Here's how the database is going to work. It's going to be a telnet server because telnet
is almost as old as Star Trek. And it's got two commands get and set. When you get a key
that doesn't exist, it says not found. You can set any key to any value and then you
can get it back. That's it. That's the whole database. So let's look at the code. It stores
its data. It's not the whole code. It stores its data in memory in a dict. And whenever
a client connects the server starts a thread and processes commands. If a command is set,
then we store the data in the dict. And if it's a get, then we try to retain a value
and say not found. Now, obviously this is just demo code. It has lots of problems. The
only problems that we're going to focus on today are the anomalies. If two people use
this database at the same time, what anomalies are they going to see? We'll start off with
the lowest isolation level. We'll read uncommitted and let's see some anomalies. So let's say
Kirk is down on the planet and McCoy wants to beam them up. So he updates the ship's
computer. First of all, Kirk's on planet is equal to one, Enterprise is zero. Scotty updates
Kirk's on planet to zero, Kirk's on Enterprise to one. But McCoy, meanwhile, is wondering
where is Jim? So he checks the ship's computer. He gets Kirk's on planet zero because that's
where Scotty's already updated that. Then he also gets Kirk's on Enterprise and sees
zero there too because Scotty hasn't updated that. This is an anomaly called a dirty
domain. He is seeing data from a transaction that Scotty has not yet completed. We need
a stronger isolation level to prohibit this anomaly. So let's try the next level up called
the
Debted Locks. So we've got a Debted Locks that's a default Debt so it creates locks on demand.
When a thread starts up it creates an empty transaction that holds no locks. Then it's
got a utility function called Acquire Lock which gets or creates a lock for this key,
locks it and sticks it in the list. Then we've got the standard command loop. So if the command
is set then we acquire a lock for the rest of the transaction added to the list. If the
command is a get then we just hold the lock briefly to check the dict and return the value
to the user. We've also got a new command commit which drops all the locks so that this
transaction's rights are visible to other transactions. So let's run the story again
with read committed. Scotty strikes his transaction. McCoy gets Curves on Planet but now he blocks
because Scotty is holding a lock on this key. Scotty finishes his transaction and commits.
He drops his locks so that unblocks McCoy so now he sees that Curves on Planet is zero.
McCoy finishes his transaction and he sees that Curves is on the Enterprise. So there's
no anomaly. This works in read committed partly because Scotty and McCoy are accessing keys
in the same order. So let's see what happens though if McCoy swaps the order with his reads.
Alright, same story but McCoy checks Curves on Enterprise first. Scotty doesn't have a
lock on this yet because he hasn't written to it so McCoy is allowed to see that it's
zero. Scotty then updates it, finishes his transaction and McCoy finishes his. Once again
it's an anomaly but it's a different one. It's called a read skew. McCoy is seeing data
that were both from before and after Scotty's transaction which wouldn't be allowed if they
were doing their transactions one at a time. So let's get in there and fix the problem.
We need a stronger isolation level like snapshot isolation. This is going to be a lot of code
because it's going to be the worst slide. Alright, so let's just get through it here.
To start off we need some more global state and we'll see in a minute how all of this
is used. When a server thread starts up it gets the lock that lock, protects a global
state like the DB and this local transaction is a copy of all of the data into a local
snapshot. It also makes an empty list of writes for this transaction. It sets its start time
as the current timestamp and it increments the global timestamp. Alright, we start the
command loop. If there is a set we don't affect global state. We only update the local snapshot
and we record the fact that we've written a list key. If it's a get we also don't touch
global state. We read from the local snapshot. And then commit, this is the complicated part.
Alright, so we lock the global state and we choose a commit time which is larger than
any timestamp used so far for either a start or a commit time for another transaction.
And then we check, is any other transaction writing the same keys that we want to write
while this transaction's not running? And the specific way we do that is by checking,
has any key in the global state, does it have a write time between our start time and our
commit time? So then we abort this transaction. Otherwise we can commit and we do that by
updating the global write times with our commit time and copying all of the writes into the
global database. And finally whether we committed or aborted we reset the local state with a
new snapshot and a new start time. Alright, that was the worst. A real database would
do cover copy on write stuff so it doesn't have to copy the entire contents of the database
and be a part of the whole process. So that's the way we do it. So, we don't need to worry
about that kind of thing. What we're here for is to understand what snapshot isolation
means and I think that this is useful for that. So, how does this story go under snapshot
isolation? Scotty starts his transaction. McCoy reads Curbside Enterprise from his snapshot.
Scotty finishes his transaction. McCoy reads Curbside Planet and he sees one. Even though
Scotty set it to zero. That's what snapshot isolation means. It means that you're reading
from a consistent snapshot of the data into practice. So it could be stale. But there's
no read scale. Snapshot isolation has a few anomalies that it still allows. Let's look
at that. So, new story. New characters. It's time for some short leave but there's only
one shuttle in the shuttle bay. Sulu and Uhura, they've both won it. So, Sulu checks whether
Uhura has claimed it. No, she hasn't. Uhura checks if Sulu has. Sulu then claims the shuttle
and so does Uhura. Sulu commits and thinks he has claimed the shuttle and so does Uhura.
This is an anomaly called right skew. You can see how this couldn't happen if the transactions
were happening one at a time. But snapshot isolation allows this anomaly. To prohibit
right skew we're going to need an even stronger isolation level like serializable, which is
one of the strongest. This code is going to be almost the same as the previous isolation
level we committed. So it's much simpler. We have a dip to blocks. We start off with
an empty list of blocks for this transaction. We've got the same utility function which
gets or creates a lock for a key, locks it, adds it to the list. The set command is the
same as for read committed where we just lock the key for the rest of the transaction.
The get command, this is where this is different from the read committed implementation. With
read committed we only locked that key briefly to return it to the client. We've got the
same thing with serializable isolation. We're actually locking this key for the rest of
the transaction even for a get. We lock it to make sure that no other transaction is
allowed to modify this value until this transaction finishes. That includes even if the key doesn't
exist, no other transaction is allowed to create it. If it did, that would be called
a phantom. So this lock prevents phantoms. And then the commit command is the same as
for read committed where we just drop off the locks. So how does this story go under
serializability? Sulu checks if Uhera has the shuttle. Uhera checks if Sulu does. Sulu
tries to update. Sulu has shuttle and he blocks because Uhera has that key locked. And the
same happens to Uhera. So now we have something called a deadlock which serializability has
come to. Kirk would probably have to come in and arbitrate this conflict. In real databases
there are deadlock detection algorithms. So we have a deadlock detection algorithm. And
in real databases there are deadlock detection algorithms which abort at least one of these
transactions to prove the deadlock. Despite the deadlock that I showed you, serializability
is actually a great escalation of them. It means that transactions appear to have happened
atomically in some total order. It might not be the actual order that you did the operations
or committed the transactions, but it's as if the transactions happened one at a time in some
total order and that order appears to be the same to all of the clients. These four isolation
levels are in order of increasing strength from the bottom where there's more parallelism to the
top where there are fewer anomalies. The higher you go generally the slower you get and the less
parallelism is possible. Take your pick. You have to think about what your application actually
needs and when in doubt choose the strongest. Okay, so we've been talking about isolation this
whole time and I also promised that we would talk about consistency. These are easy to confuse with
each other and people don't always use these terms consistently. So isolation, it prohibits
anomalies in transactions of multiple items on one machine due to concurrency. The new concept
that we're going to talk about now is consistency, which prohibits anomalies in transactions on
single data items on a cluster of machines due to distributed execution. So a security database,
it's deployed on a cluster of machines. You send an update to one of those machines. Some kinds of
databases, there's a one leader on others, you can send the update to any machine. Regardless, that
update has to be eventually replicated to some or all of the other machines and then you can read the
data, either just from the leader or from any machine that has a copy of the data. Again, it depends.
The important thing for us right now is replication. It's slow. There's a lag between the update being
received and reaching all of the other machines and when this lag is visible, that's an anomaly. So
the anomaly, the distributed database version, is when a client sees a phenomenon that reveals the
machine, the database is distributed, not single machining. And again, this is my understanding of what
this term means. Eventually, consistency is the weakest consistency level. Let's tell a new story.
So McCoy is on the surface. He makes a tricorder reading and he uploads it to one of the machines.
That applies the update, replicates it to one of the machines, but the other machine, the one at the top,
is laggy. It hasn't replicated yet. McCoy sends a message saying, I've uploaded the tricorder data and that
is also replicated. And then Uvura checks her inbox. She sees McCoy's message saying, I've uploaded the
data. So she fetches the data and it happens that she sends that request to the laggy machine. This is common in
distributed databases that clients can randomly load bounds or randomly choose various machines. And this is
one of the sources of anomalies, which is that in this case the tricorder data isn't there. And this anomaly is
called a causal violation. We'll define causal in a second. So Uvura has once again seen an anomaly, so we need a
stronger consistency level. Let's choose causal consistency. With causal consistency, all clients observe
causally related operations in the same order. McCoy's two operations are causally related. He first uploaded the data and
then because he did that, he then updated the message saying that he had done so. In causal consistency, Uvura, if she
sees operation two, she must also be able to see operation one. Somebody else could be doing causally unrelated
operations and Uvura could see those before or after she sees McCoy's. This is not a total order. Any of those is possible.
A common way to implement causal consistency is to have a time stamp on every server. It's not an actual clock time, it's just a
number. In this case, they all start with t equals zero. So McCoy uploads his data and his local machine increments its
time stamp. That's replicated to another machine, which also increments its time stamp. The lagging machine still has t
equals zero. Now McCoy uploads his message, his local machine updates its time stamp, and the replicating machine also updates its
time stamp. Now Uvura checks her inbox and she gets McCoy's message, but she also gets the latest time stamp from the server she
talked to, which is two. So now when she gets the tri-quarter data, she asks for data that's at least as recent as time stamp two.
So that means she has to wait because this server hasn't reached time stamp two yet. Eventually it replicates and gets the correct
answer, so there's no anomaly. So causal consistency is a great consistency level, but it allows a lot of anomalies still, so we might want a
stronger consistency level called linearizability. Linearizability means that each operation happens atomically, it's not a single
request and not the reply, and all clients see the same total order of operations. When I say atomically, I mean that the operation seems to happen at some
instant between the time that you've sent it and got the message. So that's a great consistency level.
So now we're going to talk about linearizability. So we're going to talk about linearizability.
So we'll start off by saying that the operation seems to happen at some instant between the time that you've sent it and got the reply, so nobody ever sees
partial operations. Notice that in linearizability, unlike serializability, the system has to do the operations in approximately the order that
the clients sent them. Implementing linearizability, and not that we'll show you the implementation, it's complicated. People often use consensus algorithms
like Paxos or Raft to implement this. Usually there is a one leader machine at a time that clients have to send all of their operations to.
The leader then does some sort of coordination magic, like maybe Paxos or Raft, to guarantee that this data is available to anybody who asks for it.
Once that coordination magic is complete, then the leader acknowledges to the client that it's done.
Linearizability is particularly useful if you've got some out of band communications that don't go through the database.
So here, let's say McCoy flips open his communicator and he calls you about directly and says,
Lieutenant Uhura, I've updated the data. Linearizability guarantees that Uhura can then ask the leader for this data and it will be available and there won't be any anomaly.
But the order of operations within the database is roughly what people expect based on their real world order of things that they do.
With all of these consistency levels, there guarantees hold even if a machine dies.
So with linearizability, let's say that the leader dies and some other leader takes over.
It is guaranteed that this leader has the data if Uhura asks for it so it can give her the correct answer.
So putting it all together. On the left, we have isolation levels for transactions on single machines.
And on the right, we have consistency levels for distributed databases.
If you want to prohibit all of the anomalies that we saw in a distributed database, then you want strict serializability,
which is the slowest of these levels. And the system is most likely to go unavailable to refuse to respond to you if it can't make these guarantees.
But it will pretty much do what you expect under all circumstances.
You don't have to memorize this chart or anything that I said today.
There's lots of things that you can read. The link here will include links to the code that I showed you and lots of things that you can read about consistency and isolation.
I'm not going to take questions up here, but I'm going to be at the hall in a minute if you want to talk.
Thanks very much.