All right, let's do it.
Our next speaker is Juliana Carollini, who will present about how to create interactive games using electronics and microphones.
Take it away.
Hello.
My name is Juliana.
I'm from Brazil.
I live in São Carlos, which is a city in São Paulo state.
I moved to São Carlos to study.
I have a bachelor's degree in computer science from the Federal University of São Carlos.
And in São Carlos we have lots of technology communities.
So in 2014 I co-founded the Palais de São Carlos chapter, which is one of the oldest Palais de chapters in Brazil.
In São Carlos we also have our local Piper user group called Sanka, our group is Sanka.
And our Linux user group called Sanka Lake.
And I'm the co-founder and organizer of both of those.
I work as a software engineer at OmniFector.
And at my free time I like to play with IoT robotics as a lobby.
And I also like my cats.
So these are some of the projects that I have developed over the years.
So the first one is called Clockwise.
It is an intelligent alarm clock that wakes you up by telling you the weather forecast.
And you are advancing your Google Calendar.
I also have two robots that I made for competitions.
So one was team of minions and the other one was superheroes.
I also have some robots with Arduino.
So I have one that avoids obstacles.
And I have a robotic arm as well.
So the robotic arm and the last robot over here, they both use micro-pipel.
So this last one is the newest one that I have.
This is a robot that uses a net on her phone that you can control the color of the LED.
Turn the head of the robot and make it move around.
Both of these are with micro-pipel.
And this is what I'm going to be using for the presentation today.
So it's this gamepad here.
And you use the BBC Micro bit with it.
So I'm going to be using this for the presentation today.
So this is what I'm going to be talking.
So I'll give a brief overview about the BBC Micro bit project.
I'll also give an overview about the gamepad, how it works.
To understand how it works I'll have to get into the details about the PIO pins,
just how analog you put an output.
After that I'm going to be showing how you can program the micro-bit using micro-pipel.
And I'm going to be showing three game examples of interactive games that you can do using this gamepad here.
So a little bit about the BBC Micro bit project.
So the BBC Micro bit is this board here.
So it's really small. It has the size of a credit card.
And this was a product developed by BBC in the UK.
And their goal was to give this competing device to children at school,
so they could get interested in computer science and programming.
And this device was given for free for children at the public schools.
And they were able to get this for using both at school and at home.
So the idea was to make them have programming lessons at school,
so both the professors and the children got the board for free as well.
And it was given for children, so it's very friendly.
And it's an open source project, it's an open-hider project as well.
And here are some of the specifications that we have.
So the board has a microprocessor over here that controls the boot respect
and all the components that we have on the board.
It also has a cellular sensor over here that works as a compact as well.
We have a speaker that we can use for interactiveness.
And you also can power it using a battery, so you don't have to use an USB cable for that.
And on the back side of the board we have this LED matrix
that you can use to display images and scroll text as well.
The logo here is a touch-tested logo, so it works as a push button as well.
We have also a microphone, so you can do interactiveness using sound,
both using the microphone and the speaker.
And we have here two push buttons that you can use for input as well.
And on the bottom of the board here we have this edge connector.
So the edge connector has 20 GPIO pins hidden here.
You can access three of them using an alligator clip,
or you can expand all of them using an extender.
So what are those GPIO pins?
So for those of you who have used other boards before, like the Raspberry Pi or the Arduino,
we have those pins like for the Raspberry Pi it is a male pin,
for the Arduino it is a female pin,
but for the BBC Microbit we have this edge connector here.
So this was made on purpose because this is for children.
It doesn't have sharp pins that could hurt the children's hands.
So it doesn't have sharp edges or pins,
and it was made for that because it was thinking about children.
So how do we use those pins?
So the GPIO is used when you don't have a standard of communication with some device.
So when you need to use some kind of sensor or operator that doesn't have an interface like MGI or USB,
use the GPIO pins to control the digital and analog signals.
So the digital signal is when you only care if it is on or off.
You only care about these two values.
But the analog signal we care about the continuity here.
So you want to know how much it is closer to 0 or 5 volts or 0 or 3.3 volts depending on the board that you are using.
So we have those two kinds of digital or analog signals,
and we can use both of them with the GPIO pins.
So we have some pins that are specific for analog input and output,
and some that are for digital input and output.
So you can use the digital read and digital write to read and write those values using the GPIO pins.
So I'm going to talk a little bit about the GamePad.
So there's one over here.
So the GamePad, I bought this from Aliexpress.
It was like $15. It's a very cheap. It was the first one that I found.
So I don't have anything particular about this one.
You can get any other one, but this one was a cheap one, and it has a lot of features for the price.
So it has included the edge connector, so you can insert the microbead and use it without having to plug anything else.
It has a dual channel joystick here, so you can use it as input for the games.
It has an onboard battery charger circuit, so you can put the battery over here.
And if you want, you can charge the battery using the charger circuit here as well.
The board has a battery indicator, so you can see how much battery you still have.
The push buttons over here, the colored buttons, that you can use for input as well.
And on the top here, we have two side buttons that are connected to the buttons on the board, the buttons that I mentioned before.
So instead of using those two, you can use this on the GamePad.
And it also has a buzzer to play sounds, so if you have a game that runs on the previous version of microbead,
but you don't have a speaker, you can use the speaker from the GamePad as well.
So here is how the GamePad connects to the microbead.
So we have the 20 UPIO pins in the edge connector.
So when you connect the boards to the GamePad, each feature in the GamePad is connected to one pin in the board.
So here on the back of the GamePad, we have a table here that shows where each component is connected to the board.
So here we have the pins for all the buttons, the pins for the joystick, and the pins for the buzzer.
So you can use these in the code to know what kind of component you are dealing with on each pin.
So an example of what we have on the board is digital and analog input and output.
So for the push buttons, we have digital input.
So it only carries the button expressed or not.
So it's digital, it's just two values.
But for the analog, for the joystick, it is an analog input because we want to know how much it is turned to each side.
So we want to know how much the user presses for each direction.
So it is an analog input.
And for the display here, we can have both digital and analog output because we're going to be using this to show the information to the player.
So you can use it as a digital output if you only turn on or off the LED.
So only two values.
But you can use it as an analog output as well if you change the brightness of the pixels.
So you can use that to make the images brighter.
So I'm going to be showing how you can program the micro bit.
So the micro bit is micro pattern powered.
So when you get a micro bit, you can start using micro pattern with it without having to flash anything.
It already comes with it pre-installed.
So the MicroPython, it is a re-implementation of the Python 3.
So it is made for microcontrollers and devices that have low computational power and low power consumption as well.
So it is a target for those kind of devices.
And the VBC micro bit is one of them.
So that's why you can power it using a battery because it uses very low power.
And here is how you can program the micro bit.
So if you go to microbit.org, you have two options of programming the micro bit.
One of them is using a block editor, which is easier for children who don't know how to code yet.
So it's easier to just drag the blocks there.
But if you already have some programming knowledge, you can use the Python text editor.
So here in the editor, you have a very nice editor that has autocomplete, it has interest highlighting, it works really well.
Here we have the reference.
So if you need to know anything about any of the components that you have available for use, you can have the information right here on the editor.
And if you check the information and you want to drag the block of code to where you are editing your code, you can do that as well.
Like here you can get this block and just drag over and it's going to be copying it for you.
There is also the simulator over here.
So if you don't have the BARD, but you want to use MicroPython with it, you can use the simulator on the browser.
And it works really well as well.
So you can send the inputs here.
You can change all the parameters on the BARD using these buttons over here.
And if you want, you can also use the terminal here.
You have the REPL inside of the editor as well.
And when you finish editing your code, you can click here on Send to MicroBit.
And it's going to be downloading a hex file for you.
And you can save this file on the BARD just like a thumb drive.
So you just drag the file over there and it's going to be flashing the code for you and start running the code without having to configure anything else.
So I'm going to be showing you some examples of things you can use in the MicroBit.
So the first one is the display example.
So for the display, we can show an image and we have some predefined images that are already ready for use.
So in this case, I'm showing the happy face.
You also can set the brightness of one specific pixel.
So you pass the coordinate of the pixel and pass the brightness and it changes it for you.
If you don't want to use a predefined image, you can create your own images, concatenating strings, and you pass here the brightness for each pixel.
You can also scroll a text.
So you pass a string and it's going to be showing it for you.
And if you need to, you can also clear the display.
So a button example.
So we have these two bunch of buttons on the BARD and these buttons, they are already abstracted.
So they are called button A and button B.
You don't need to configure the pins for those.
And we can see if the button is pressed at the moment, if it was pressed in the past, and how many times it was pressed since the last time that we've worked with the method.
On this example here, or if you click on the button on the left, it's going to be showing you an arrow, which is one of the image predefined that we have.
And if you click on the right, you can see the other arrow over here.
So a buzzer example.
So in case you have an older microbeam that didn't have a speaker yet, you can plug in a buzzer, plugging it into the zero pin here.
And if you do that and use the music library, you can play some predefined music.
So it comes with some of those already for use.
You can pass a frequency and a duration to make a pitch sound.
Or you can create your own music passing the notes and the duration for each note.
As for the accelerometer, you can get the acceleration for three axes, x, y, and z.
So you just need to do an analog read on the pin for each axis.
But here it's already abstracted for us, so we can just use get x, get y, get z, and we can get the information.
And we also have some gesture predefined.
So if you want to see if the board was shaken, if you have a button pressed, you can see the button.
If the board was shaken, if it is facing up, down, if it has fallen, you have all these kinds of gestures predefined already for use.
So as a PIO example, as I mentioned, we are going to be using PIO pins to interface with the gamepad.
So for those, you need to do the digital read and you need to know which pin you are going to be reading.
So here in this case, I'm using the pin 15, which is the white button on the gamepad.
And for this one, the reading is inverted.
So if the button is pressed, it's going to be returning zero.
And if the button is not pressed, it's going to be returning one.
So here to read the value, you can pass yishtarit on the pin and it can track if the pin is pressed or not.
A joystick example.
So the joystick uses analog read because it is an analog input.
So you can define the pins for the joystick and then use analog read for those.
And you can see the reading is on the x-axis.
You have less than 400 is put to the left.
It has more than 600 is put to the right.
If it's in the between, it's because it's not turned to any direction.
And we can have the same thing for the y-axis.
So you can see if it is turned up, down, left or right.
And we are going to be using that in the games.
So let's go to the game examples.
So I have prepared three game examples to show you today.
One of them is called Genius.
The other one is called Chase the Dog.
And the other one is called Car Crash.
So I'm going to be showing each one of them.
First the book program showing how the logic works.
Then a video of the demonstration.
And then going into some parts of the source code.
So for the first game in Brazil, this game is called Genius.
I think the US is called Taiwan.
I don't know how it's called in other places.
But I got Genius because that's how we know that game in Brazil.
So the idea here is that we are going to be drawing a random direction.
So we don't have the colors here.
So I'm going to be using arrows to indicate the directions.
So we draw a direction and then we add it to the sequence and show the sequence to the user.
And then we read the input.
And if the input is correct, we are going to be drawing another direction,
adding to the sequence and keep incrementing the sequence until the user gets it wrong.
If you get it wrong, we end the game.
And then we restart the game so the next player can use the board as well.
So the games keep playing on a loop in the board.
So how did I do this game?
So to restart the game, we are going to be waiting for the user to show that they are ready to play.
So we are going to wait for them to push the two buttons on the top at the same time to indicate that they are ready.
So when you press the buttons at the same time, we start a countdown and then we initiate the game.
And in the game we have the sequence.
So for the sequence we have four directions, north, south, west and east.
And we are going to be showing the direction represented by an image.
And we are going to be playing a pitch sound with a frequency associated with that direction.
This way the user knows how they can associate the direction to the sound.
And it makes it easier when they are going to be inputting the movements for the sequence.
So we show all the movements in the sequence.
And after that, we light up the display to indicate that it's ready for receiving the input from the user.
And then to read the input.
So we have a class here to abstract the buttons because we don't have those buttons abstracted in the micropython implementation for the micro-bit.
Because we only have the A and B buttons abstracted.
So these other ones we need to use digital read for that.
So here I have an abstraction for that.
And we read which button was pressed to see the direction.
And then we play the same pitch sound and show the same image to give the feedback to the user that they pressed the direction that was shown in the screen.
And then we need to validate the user input.
So we want to do that one movement at a time.
Because if you let the user put all the movements and they got the first one wrong, we don't want to let them keep playing until you read the length of the sequence.
So here we are going to be getting the movements one by one and checking if the movement so far is the same as the sequence.
And then when the user gets it wrong, we end the game playing a sad music.
We show the score, which is the length of the sequence minus one, because it got the last one wrong.
And then we clear everything and restart the game.
And then here to run the game, the logic for this one is simpler.
So we just show the sequence, read the answer.
If it's correct, we create the sequence again.
If it's not, we end the game.
So now I'm going to be showing the second game example.
It is called chase the dot.
So the idea for this one is that you have a dot on the screen and you need to chase the dot around.
So you use the joystick to chase the dot.
You can use the mouse to chase the dot.
You can also use the accelerometer if you press a button and then you can tilt the bars to move the dot around the screen.
So for this one, we are going to be making it more harder for the user to get the dot.
So if it has passed one second and the player hasn't got the dot yet, you're going to be putting the dot in a random coordinate again.
So you have to keep chasing it around the screen.
And if it has passed 25 seconds since the game started, you are going to be ending the game.
So we have 25 seconds to get as many dots as we can.
And if you get the dot, you get one point.
And then we display the dot flashing to indicate that you got the dot.
Here on the first part, I'm using the accelerometer.
So you can cube the bars to get the dot.
And after that, using the joystick, you can move it around.
Okay, so for this one, we have the dot that has a coordinate that we generated between the constraints of the display.
When you get the dot, you are going to be flashing it to indicate that the user got the correct direction.
And when we show the dot, we start the time that the dot was shown so we can make it move around after one second.
To read the input, you are going to be having this toggle button here.
So if the button is pressed, you are going to be using the accelerometer.
If it is not pressed, you are going to be using the joystick.
And then to move the player, you are going to be reading the input.
And then we make the calculation to see if it's moving in which direction it should be moving.
And then we just update the coordinates between the constraints of the display again.
And then to check the collision, we just check if the coordinates for the dot and the player are the same.
And then here, the logic to run the game is a little bit more complicated than the previous one.
So for this one, we need to start the time that the game started.
So we can see if it has passed 25 seconds.
And we also need to know if the dot was shown one second.
So if it has passed one second, we need to update the coordinates.
If not, we only update the coordinates when the user collides with the dot.
And now for the last example, it's called car crash.
So it's similar to those old car racing games.
So you have the obstacles coming down and you have to avoid the obstacles.
So for this one, we want to use a refresh rate of the screen so the user can move the car in between the iterations of the border and the obstacle moving down.
So we have here this loop here.
We keep reading the input from the player and updating the car until we reach the correct refresh rate iteration.
When you reach that refresh rate iteration, you are going to be moving everything down.
So we check if the obstacle is already on the bottom of the screen because if it is, we need to check if the player collided or not.
But if it is not, we just move everything down, the border and the obstacle.
If the player avoided the obstacle, we create a new obstacle on the top and we increase the speed of the game so it gets faster and harder to play.
And of course, if the player collides with the obstacle, we end the game and we show their score.
Beep, beep, beep, beep.
Beep, beep, beep, beep, beep.
So for this one, we have the player and the obstacle.
So the player is only going to be moving in the x-axis on the bottom of the screen and the obstacle is going to be moving on the y-axis.
So we generate the dot on the top of the screen and keep moving it down until we reach the bottom of the screen where we generated a band on the top.
So to give the sensation of movement, we have the border.
So the border keeps moving down, the obstacle moves down and the border moves up to give the sensation of movement.
And here on the screen, we have the concept of buffer.
So we want to show the border, the player and the obstacle at the same time so it is easier to generate the customized image and display it all at once instead of displaying each pixel separately.
So we have the buffer for the screen and we also have the refresh rate to make the game move faster.
So when we avoid the obstacle, we make the refresh rate decrease so the speed is increased.
So here is how the buffer works.
So for the borders, we have the pixels on the left and the right side moving up and the obstacle is moving down on these far rectangles here and the player is always on the bottom.
So to create the buffer, what we do is that we get the obstacle space first and then we put the brightness of the obstacle in the position that the obstacle should be.
We also got the border, so the border here is a list and then we invert the list to make it go in the border.
So we are going to be going over the buffer and putting it on the left and the right of the screen.
After we put the border, we put the obstacle there, so we just concatenate the obstacle in the y axis where the obstacle should be, so one of these rectangles here.
And after that, we want to put the player on the bottom.
But to put the player, we can use the same approach here of just putting the player space on the left row because if the obstacle is in the left row, it would overwrite the obstacle.
So for the player, we get what we have before, we put the player there and then we get what we have after.
So after that, we concatenate everything and display it to the screen.
And here to run the game, we have the iteration, so until we reach the iteration, the player is going to be moving the card.
And once we reach the iteration, we check if it collided. If not, we just increase the score, speed up the game and keep moving the obstacles around.
So my conclusion for today is that the microgit and micropython are a fun combination.
I like a lot working with this board and I find it really fun to play with.
So I hope you can all find it fun as well and thank you for your attention.
So here is the source code for the games. It is on my github.
If you want to find me, you can find me using my handle.
You can find me pretty much everywhere using this handle.
So you can find me at LinkedIn and github.
Here is the complete source code.
And today we are going to be having an open space about embedded Python.
So it's going to be at room 251 AB at 5 p.m.
So I'm going to be bringing the gamepad there.
So if you want to play the games, let's go there and have a chat and I can have the Q&A session there as well.
So thank you again.
Thank you.