Good morning. Our next speaker is Burt Wagner, and he will be talking to us today about
crossover data drawings on flow networks with Python.
Thanks, Emma, for that.
Alright, awesome.
Well, welcome everyone. Hope you're having a good morning so far. I'd like to start off
today's talk with a, talking about my relationship probably many of you have had similar
relationships with data and networks in the past. I'm going to kind of do it through the decades.
And so kind of the first one I want to talk about is what I call the mom don't use the phones
era of my upbringing. You hear the laughter, which is good.
Obviously this is talking about the days of dialogue, right, where our networks' data transfer
speeds were very important, right, and I'd be talking to friends. And if someone picked up that
phone, it was a very binary decision. It went from sending data to not sending data. And even
though that data was really small, right, text chat, it made a big difference. You had to be
conscious of that. Also, there was a time of free music. I don't know if many people know that.
It's the case for music now, but it used to be free. And that used to be really important to think
about with your dialogue connections. You'd be waiting an hour to download a song and you'd find out
eventually that it was mislabeled or whatever, but you'd want that song to download. And so making
sure you're not abusing your bandwidth so that you can focus on the download was really important.
The web at the time also had lots of interesting things to look at. That's what made the web great.
So for what little bandwidth and speed I had, I wanted to spend it on fun things like that. And
those era, that era of the web, it had lots of fan sites, where band or hobby or whatever we can go
check out. Your favorite images, if they ever decided to load, they'd be really slow. But yeah,
bandwidth, whether I was thinking about it or not, was a really important part of my life, even back
then during the dialogue days. Sorry, Joey, we're not going to wait for you to load.
All right, so back forward a decade, we upgraded to DSL, cable modems,
Internet's a lot faster. Things are a lot better. Websites are in this perfect state where they have
good content, they're interesting, but they're not like bloated single page JavaScript applications.
They don't have all this privacy fracking junk embedded in them that are slowing things down.
You know, the web was nice. We had a lot of bandwidth. Things were fast. Websites were good.
Our media consumption, our gaming was pretty good for all the security flaws, like macro media flash.
They made for really great games. But they really need a lot of networking and processing power in the
background to get them to work. And then, if you were missed, but I mentioned in the early days of
YouTube, where you can go stream 240p video on a DSL connection, and you can go to the
DSL connection, it would be fun. It would be totally fun. And this is why I think this is the golden era.
Unfortunately, history repeats itself. And now we're back to this era which I like to call the stop streaming era.
I'm sure many of you can guess, but nowadays we work from home. Maybe we've got something going on in the
background. A lot of streaming services. We have kids, family members. They may be watching the TV.
Suddenly our bandwidth is becoming a lot more precious. We're all on video calls, especially if we're working from
home. We may be having spouses or other people in the house who are on video calls. Once again, more bandwidth
used up for things that maybe aren't that important to us. Gaming, bandwidth now has become much more
important. Latency is a huge deal. So I want to make sure my home network is as good as possible to be able to
give myself that competitive advantage. Or maybe I don't and then I just blame how bad I am at games on my
internet connection. That's fine too. What we just had, if you were in this room before here, is a home
automation talk. But I can't even turn a light bulb on without having the Wi-Fi working in my house.
This has become such an integral thing that now to turn on the light I have to think about the network
capacity in my house. So finally, the reason why we're all here today is probably because we needed to do our
jobs and do the fun things we like doing. We like to program. We probably like to use data that's not on our
local laptops, on our local computers at home. Maybe we're connecting through our corporate networks and dealing
with data. Maybe we're connecting to clouds or party members, wherever. Data is an important part of the
things we do. And being able to work with that data when it's having to compete for network resources with all
these other things isn't always easy. And so my goal for this talk is hopefully we all walk away today being a
little bit more cognizant about how our data is traversing our network and what we can do about it to make things
faster. So my name is Burt Wagner. I'm a data scientist by day. I also like to blog and make YouTube videos about
data performance concepts. So if you're into that, check that out. I've already uploaded these slides on my
GitHub. I've created a quick link there. Feel free to take a look at them afterwards if you want. And if you have
follow-up questions after this session. But today's agenda, we're going to be talking about how do we join data sets
across the network efficiently, across networks that maybe are bloated by all those streaming apps and everything
else. And I'm going to share three solutions, right? It's only going to be three. We're not going to get into too much
detail. We've got 25 minutes left here. There's not that much time. But we'll start with kind of a great solution.
Solutions I want to be using 90 plus percent of the time, or can use 90 percent of the time. We'll get into not bad
solutions, but you'll see there's some downsides. And then we'll end with the ugly solutions, which are the ones that you
hope you never have to use. But they're good to have in kind of a pocket knife utility in your back pocket for when
the situation arises where you do need them. Let's talk about our scenario, right? If we have these two data sets
and I'll take this example where I have a CSV file. Let's think of it. It's got some customers in it and it doesn't
have all of the columns of data that we maybe want with our customers. We need some additional attributes, because
whatever you're doing, whatever, some modeling or whatever else with it. So the rest of those customer attributes are in,
let's say, a data warehouse, some kind of relational database. I've been denoted with a little cloud. It could be in the
data center owned by our company or whatever. And our goal here is, we want to join these two data sets together.
The CSV file, maybe 100,000 rows, two gigs in size on my local laptop. And let's say 30 million rows, 20 gigs of data in a
database somewhere, not local to my laptop. So does anyone have any, what's everyone's go-to method for this? That would be
a good method for this. Shout it out. Select star. All right. Well, we'll talk about that. Reload it into the data center.
I like that. You know how to network any clock? We're talking about moving data to the data center. So let's jump to that.
That's actually my favorite solution, right? This is the one you want to use if you can. And so the way it kind of looks
at this is we take our CSV file data, customer data, and we move that across the network, right? That's our smallest piece of
data that we're working with. Let's move that to our data center or to the cloud or wherever the bigger data is, right?
This kind of technique is called moving your smaller data to where the bigger data is. And so maybe that means we're
going to create like a staging table in our, if it's a database or something like that, maybe we can create like a
temporary memory table. It's kind of up to you how you do it, right? But you create that and then you do your joins, right?
And relational databases, whatever flavor you choose to use, you know, they're really good at doing step-based operations.
They're really good at doing joins, right? So you're going to be using the right tool for the job in that case. You're going to be able to
join that data, especially if you index it and everything else. You're going to get really great performance out of that.
Once that's done, you can output your data. So here in this example, I'm doing some image join. I'm leaving some records,
but it's only outputting 80,000 rows once again. That travels back across the network to our laptops or wherever.
And then we can go ahead and process that data, transform it, do whatever we want with it. But at that point, right, we're not
working with this big massive set. We're just working with kind of our final subset. Now, this solution, there's a lot of things I like about it, right?
First of all, you're moving your smaller data to where the larger data is. You're really minimizing how much network traffic you're going to be having,
and that's awesome. It's also, you know, I'm going to assume here that your database is on some kind of server with some better specs than what your
laptop would have. You're going to be able to process that data well, using the right tools for the job. That's going to be a really good thing.
Additionally, let's see, the one thing that this solution is not great at is the fact that if you need to clean and transform your data right before you do your join,
it's going to be a little tough. Like, sure, you can do, you know, some replace functions in your database if you need to clean some data up, but that's not really the right place to do it.
Databases aren't necessarily the best tool for you to actually do that. But as an example, maybe make it more concrete. Imagine we're joining these two customer databases
on the street address. Maybe one of the files we got 123 main street fully spelled out, and then the other file we got 123 main ST, right, and abbreviated for the street.
You're not going to be able to join on those columns on their own. You're going to have to do a little bit of cleanup on them, because you will look up, make a match, something like that.
And so in this scenario, that can sometimes get tricky. It's not always the best place you'd be able to do that. So we have other options.
Before we get to them, though, I just want to remind everyone of kind of the goal of this session. I think about where your data is moving.
In this case, let's say here we are in Salt Lake City, and I'm moving that 2 gigabyte file to a corporate VPN endpoint, maybe somewhere in Los Angeles.
It's going out to the East Coast in Virginia to some cloud provider. Maybe that's where all my data processing is happening. Great.
When that data comes back, it's a small subset, right, and has to make all those talks back, not to mention all the hop in between.
So just think about that. And when you're kind of working with data with large data sets, think about how much network traversal is having to happen in order for this to be effective.
So just to summarize this, this kind of moving the small data where your big data lives minimizes network movement and maximizes the tools for what they're good for.
The downsides are you need to be able to write your data to that kind of larger database. So maybe a database administrator should really lock the database down.
You're not allowed to create additional tables on it. It could be problematic. If you're working with a little vendor or something,
read-only, it's going to be a little bit more challenging. And also, this isn't the greatest solution if you have to do a lot of transformations.
I talked a lot about this topic in the past in way more detail than 30 minutes to handle, so if you're interested in that, I've linked to some other conference talks I've had for additional tips
kind of making that process a lot more speedy. But we will for now continue to the next topic.
Those are not bad solutions. In this case, we are assuming we have a big heavy duty server in the middle there that's going to help us do our joins.
So we have our small data set in the bottom left. We've got our database with our large amount of data in the right.
We can't move our small data to our large data. So what are we going to do? Or we are going to do this join on some big heavy duty application server with hundreds of gigs of memory,
dozens of CPUs that's going to be able to handle it. And this is traditionally what you maybe would see in like an ETL pipeline solution.
You know, it's great. It gets the job done. You need to be able to have a server and procure it. For some of us, it's pretty easy.
Spin up some instance in the cloud, you're ready to go. For others, there's lots of corporate red tape maybe to get that server.
So it's kind of a key hero adventure of how easy or hard that is. Thinking about network traversal again.
We are going to have to move that giant database, you know, 30 gigs or whatever I said it was.
So it would be beneficial to still have this big heavy duty server as close to your database server as possible.
So maybe that's in a corporate data center that understands flight. They're going to be moving across fibers and then it'll be really fast.
It won't be a big deal. You know, if your big heavy duty server is in your basement, maybe you have one of those because you're a nerd like me.
That's awesome. But it's going to be really slow competing with all the Netflix bandwidth and everything else that you need to your house.
So that's a big caveat of this. You need to have that data there.
Another plus of this solution though is if we have that situation again where we need to do our join,
we have our street address data and it's not exactly lining up right.
One, two, three main street spelled out versus an abbreviated street in our other data set.
We can process that data really easily, really nicely with something like Python here before we do our joins.
So that's really cool. And if we're doing our joins, you know, for a lot of us, we might be using something like Pandas.
Having plenty of memory and disk space available to do that join is a really nice option.
You could also in this scenario, I have plenty of other Python packages out there, so if you use something like LID and DAS sometime,
so DAS will allow you to parallelize it and kind of distribute some computations to across lots of machines.
So once again, if you have more than one machine available to kind of do this data processing, great.
That's a great place to be. But obviously not everyone will have that available to them, so kind of want to focus too much on that.
So, right, let's summarize this solution. If large data is on the same network as our application servers,
or we're maybe running Python to do some joins, performance is getting pretty good.
If you have a pool of machines, even better. There's lots of packages out there, but you can utilize to make that work.
If you've ever checked out where there's a good documentation page in the Pandas documentation, I'll include a link to it down below.
Where they talk about all different kind of packages that are better dealing with large data sets and maybe the Amazon itself.
So depending on your individual use case, it may be a better option there.
You know, the downsides here are obviously servers are hard to get sometimes. And like we said, we want to be on the same network.
So, let's see. Any quick questions before we continue on with the other solutions?
So, what are the solutions that you want to get to the ugly solutions?
These two solutions, this is what you want to be doing when you're dealing with data.
Alright, great. I think we have a couple of questions at the end there.
Alright, so let's get to the ugly solution.
We're going to write our own half join. So, for those of you who are kind of maybe from computer science degrees,
or you're a computer engineer, if that's not your background, totally cool.
Well, it's my background either. I have a degree in political science.
But, this doesn't mean you can't enjoy a little theory. If it goes over your head, don't worry about it.
You don't need to know it all. You can't be able to use the Python code that I include at the end.
So, what we want to do with a half join, at a high level, we've got our key data sets, right?
That's going to be represented by these two columns with colorful data.
We have our build input data sets. That would be our smaller data set.
And we have our probe input data set. That's going to be our large data set.
And the way a half join works, this is how a lot of the relational databases kind of implement this and a lot of other tools too.
We're just going to be running it with all the control that we want in order to kind of make things reliable.
So, what happens is we take our data. Here we're going to take data B.
We're going to run it through a hash function. Then it's going to go get stored in a hash bucket or a dictionary.
We're doing the tasking. We're using this hash function on the columns that we're going to be using in our join, right?
And so, we're hashing that data to be able to quickly look it up and see if there's any matches in a minute, which we'll see.
So, we like to do that for all our data. Once we take the next probe data, we have the columns that we're joining on, put that in a phone bucket, do that again for the next data, and we keep doing that.
Now, the interesting thing with hash functions is, you'll see here, we got two pieces of data that fell into the same bucket.
So, in the implementation, I'm going to show you in a minute, I'm using Python's hash method, which I believe you can see hash under the covers,
which means collision resistant, but not collision proof. And so, what that means is, when it comes to hashing, what that means is you get two very different inputs,
and you pass them through the hash function, and they end up outputting the same exact value.
That's what's known as collision. We need to check for those. So, this is kind of an example here of a collision happening, even though A and F are two different pieces of data,
they're generating the same hash, and they're getting put in the same hash bucket.
So, something to be aware of, but we'll need to check for that in a minute, and finally do that with our last piece of data there.
Now, all of this data, just in our hash bucket that was kind of in our build input phase, needs to fit into memory.
So, if you are running this on a lower performance laptop, whatever, you've got to be able to store that in memory,
there are workarounds, write stuff to disk, page it out to disk, or take a buff if you want to, that's way beyond this tutorial and the packet that we're showing you.
This is through your small data set that's in memory. And what that's going to enable you to do is now screen all of the rest of your data across the network
to kind of compare it and see if we have a match. So, we screen that in from our SQL database, our giant SQL database, we hashed it,
it could put in the hash bucket, now we can say, oh cool, these both have hash values of two, let's actually now iterate over them and check to see if they're a match.
Cool, these values actually match, not just the hashes, but the values of our joint keys match.
And we're doing that once again because in this case there was a collision so it didn't match with F, that's why we've got to check the values one by one.
And so we do this again for the next row of data, we pass that in, we check to see if there are matches, we iterate and write, we save our matches off,
maybe we save them for our local hard drive, maybe we save them somewhere else. And we kind of repeat this process for all the rest of our data.
Now the cool thing with this is that if we get a network error, right, or our network blows up and we have to restart it, as long as we can go look at our output file
and see kind of what our last match, match record was, we can re-query our database, you know, our large data set input and have it kind of resume from where it left off.
That's the really nice thing about this. This is a slow solution, so thinking about again like network movement, we are streaming that gigantic database through our laptop,
but it is very reliable. If that thing crashes, you can have it try, accept, you know, logic to say, hey, pick up where I left off, which is really nice.
But if you get stuck in that scenario where you have to do that, it's really nice to be able to do that.
So, how do we actually implement this in practice? We are done with the theory. So, I built a package for it, so I couldn't find anyone else who had done it.
It's called Cross Screen, so you can install that. Two F's, and if you just search for my name on GitHub or whatever, you can find it that way too.
Makes it really easy to use, so let's kind of look through one example. Because this is, I've spent a lot of time with coworkers and just on my own having to solve this problem
when we get these kind of weird data sets that we can't easily move data around, we have to kind of do things this way. We don't want them to die prematurely.
We need to join the finish. So, starting out at the top, pretty basic import the package. We're going to create our, we're going to read in our files.
So here I'm using two CSV files in the demo, but the package will allow you to do an ODBC connection as well as you can just trace from a database or anything else
that you can connect to as an ODBC driver. So that works pretty well. And this is just going to kind of do a lazy read. All we're doing here, this is similar to how
packages like Dashboard, right, we're just going to get metadata in about our data sets, right, so what are the files, do they contain header columns, and what are the columns that we're going to be
joining on between our two data sets. We're just kind of telling the program that's all the info we need. And then we're going to go ahead and do the same thing with the other
data sets. So we're just going to get our output file set up, right, so maybe it's local, maybe it's on the network or cloud storage. We write out some header columns, and this is all just dealing with CSVs,
keep things simple. And then we finally, right, this is kind of what we just looked at on that last slide which puts the animations on it. This is doing that, that inner hash join.
And so it loads that first file in the memory, the small one, and then it's going to stream one row at a time from your other large data source, every single record, do that casting, do the joins, and, you know, eventually get your data to work in an unreliable network environment.
And that's where I said you can wrap this up and you can try and accept and use some error handling logic if you think you're going to have problems with just finishing out.
A couple other things I want to show here is, you know, we were talking about, hey, you have this street address where you have to convert 123 Main Street spelled out, 123 Main, you know, SQ with an abbreviation.
How do we do that? Well, this solution actually works really well. I'm trying to minimize, you know, having only one row of data in memory at a time from the streaming side, from the probing side.
And so what's in here is you can, you know, there's a function you can override that describes how you want to transform your data before you join it.
So if you just create a simple function where you cast in the value of one of your columns that you're joining on and you tell it how you want to transform it, right, so here we're just doing a basic, you know, strip out the white space kind of transformation, but you can make this as complicated as you want, right?
There's no limit to how complicated you want this object. It is slowing down your process. But you can do, you know, you can do these kind of geospatial stuff.
There's some complicated transformations you may need to do before you join your data. It could be things like street addresses, the buggy matching, whatever you need, right, you can kind of secure that.
And then so when you call your inner hash join function, you just pass in, as a named argument there, the name of your function that you created with your kind of custom join transformation logic.
So that'll just kind of do it as the data streams through.
And so finally, though the last thing I kind of want to point out with this solution is just how we can transform data before we do our join.
There's also the capability to transform your data after your join happens. And I figure, oh, well for performance, that row of data is already in memory, this would be the perfect time to do something with it if we needed to, right?
Just kind of get things to go quicker so we don't have to save this disk and read it in later. So this works very similarly.
You can create your own, you know, functions for kind of how to process the data once it's matched. Here, right, I'm just adding a static weight value of 1.0 to every single row.
And then so we're returning that row of data there as those pupils. And then so in our inner join function that we were calling, we can pass in that custom processing function as an override.
Right? And so in conclusion, this ugly solution, even though it's not going to be as fast as our other two options, and it's not as good as our other two options, it is reliable.
It is a reliable way to get this kind of problem of joining data sets across networks to work if you need to. It has a lot of retriability.
You can program that in, and it's just a network failure and it's really flexible and customizable in terms of if you need to be able to do data transfer information in order to get your joins to work.
I try to be pretty good about reading in data only once and kind of keeping memory usage as low as possible. In my case, when I created this, right, it was I only had my laptop and it was like, you know, whatever, 10 gigs of free RAM and like no disk space available.
Sometimes that's the world we have to work with. So if that sounds like a problem you have, right, then check that out. But with that said, thank you very much.
And I think we have two minutes if people have questions.
Are there ways in the library to optimize the hash function?
Great question.
No. I was, you know, just trying to get the basics working. The story behind this is we were at a deadline and I needed to get this joined to work and nothing else was working.
So this was a first pass kind of take at it. So there's no huge crazy optimizations. It was more focusing on the reliability aspect of it. Thank you, though.
All right. Well, I want to make sure we have enough time for the next speaker. If anyone else has questions, they'll be hanging around in the back or outside. But thank you for coming.