Okay, I guess it's nine, so I'm gonna go ahead and get started.
Well, if any stragglers come in, I may jump back to the startup instructions a bit.
So welcome.
Today's tutorial is gonna be on data of an unusual size with reference to Princess Bride.
To give you some background, my name's Dar Haspatina.
I'm originally an aerospace civil engineer, did a lot of work in computational fluid dynamics
and hurricane modeling, and had to handle lots and lots of very, very big data sets.
I've been part of the open source Python community for over a decade, and now I work for QuantSight,
which is a company focused on consulting in the PyData and SciPy ecosystems.
My co-presenter is Pavitra Ishamurthy, and she will be on the Jitsi chat.
Unfortunately, we had some travel complications and she wasn't actually able to be here,
but I do want to give her a big shout out because she created more than half of the
materials we're going through today.
So I just wanted to give that shout out.
She's a developer advocate at QuantSight.
The focus of today is to give you guys some intuition of how to handle large data sets.
We're specifically going to be focusing on a set of tools, Dask and HP plot and a few
other things, but the principles can apply to other big data tools, like if you use Ray
or if you use Spark or anything else.
So part of this is to get you familiar with these tools, which have a fairly low initial
learning curve, but it's also to kind of get you thinking about what changes when you go
from what fits in memory on your laptop to larger data sets.
To give some quick setup instructions, I've already gone through this for a couple of
you.
Go to this website, nabari.quantsight.dev, and that is here in larger letters.
Has anyone not registered here yet?
I just wanted to get a show of hands.
So I'll give folks a couple of minutes.
In the meantime, go to this website.
Once you go to nabari.quantsight.dev, you should see a key cloak page, and at the bottom,
if you click on login with key cloak, you'll see a register.
Just go ahead and register.
You can put fake information in.
That's fine.
We're not checking the email addresses.
And then once you log in, you'll see a start button.
I'll walk you through this flow in a second.
Before I get to that, just give a quick poll from the crowd.
How many of you have used tools like Dask before?
Anyone?
Okay.
How familiar are folks with Pandas?
Good.
So when we get to Dask, I'll talk a little bit about this more.
If you're familiar with Pandas, we're going to show you how to take your knowledge from
Pandas and then transition it to scaling up with some of these other tools.
Okay.
Let's see.
So what we're going to do now is we will, I'm going to stop my server so I can walk
you through what you guys will do.
Is there anyone who's still registering?
Okay.
I'll give you guys actually, since we have a few more people.
It would be nice if we had a whiteboard.
Okay.
So folks who came in new, if you can take a picture of this page.
So this is where we're going to run today's tutorial.
And once you go to this page, click on login with key cloak and then there's a register
button, click on that and register.
And then after that, the rest should be what I'm showing now.
Okay.
So I am going to shut down my, I'm going to stop my server.
So when you log in, you should see something like this.
We are doing today's tutorial on Nabari, which is an open source software that QuantSite
develops.
But think of this as Jupiter Hub.
is open source and all the pieces you see put together are just all open source pieces
that have been put together in the Nabari platform.
So everything, and I'll talk about this at the end, how to get the various tools which
we're going to use today.
Click start my server.
And we're going to choose, you will only see two instance types.
You'll see a small and a medium.
I actually have more because I'm logged in with my email address, including GPU instances.
There's also a GPU instance in yours.
I think you'll also see this K80 GPU instance.
In the tutorial, if you want to play around with that and do something, you can, but we're
not planning to do any GPU stuff today.
So choose a medium instance and then click start.
And what this is doing, this is running in the cloud.
It's going and fetching an instance of that size.
I think this is four CPUs and 16 GB of RAM, actually like 14 or 15 GB of RAM.
So this is sort of equivalent to the power of your laptop.
Most of our laptops are probably four to eight cores and 16 to 32 GB of RAM.
So this is trying to give you a feel of what you could do locally on your laptop and then
how we could transition to the cloud.
Now the first thing we're going to do is we're going to clone the repository.
So if we go back here, go to this URL.
If you go to GitHub, you should see this URL.
I'm going to do this slowly.
So I was hoping to give everyone sticky notes, but I didn't forget to.
I forgot to bring them.
But over here, let's click on code and choose HTTPS.
So if you click here, and we're going to choose the copy button.
And then we're going to go back to JupyterLab.
And over here, this icon here is Jupyter's Git plugin.
So we're going to go to Jupyter's Git plugin.
And oh.
Okay.
I don't remember how to get back to the original.
For you guys, since you haven't already cloned something, you should actually see a place
you can say clone and you can clone a new repo.
I do not remember how to get back to the main folder on the Jupyter Git plugin.
I don't use it that often.
So I'm actually going to do this from the command line.
So here, I'm going to hit the plus button.
And I am going to open a terminal.
And here, let me actually go back and I'm going to change this to, I'm going to use
SSH.
Okay.
So I cloned it.
And I should have this presentations folder now.
For folks who are using the Git plugin.
I really should have practiced this beforehand.
Okay.
Let's stop there.
Who has successfully cloned the repo?
Okay.
Good.
We all know how to clone things.
Anyone still having trouble cloning?
So as you can see, I don't usually use the Jupyter Git UI because I don't like it.
But anyway, that's that.
So now if we click on this folder icon at the top, you should see this presentations
folder that you just cloned.
Let's go in there and go into PyCon and go into our tutorial.
And you should see something like this on the right.
So I'm going to reopen our introduction notebook.
And you should be, most of the notebooks, you should be able to walk through them.
And at the end, there should be a link to the next notebook.
Now I will say there's one thing I need you to be a little careful of.
In case you are Jupyter experts, please don't hit run all cells.
There's a couple of places where there's a race condition.
So if you don't wait for the first cell to run, the other cells may not execute correctly
because some of these tools inject JavaScript into your front end.
There's also a, in some of the notebooks, I have a shutdown cluster command at the end.
So if you run all, it's going to shut the cluster down and you're not going to be able
to see anything.
So just go slow.
Okay.
So roughly this is what the plan is.
I'm going to be...
Oh, thank you.
Actually, if you can just pass them out.
Yeah.
So let's use the yellow as I completed things correctly and let's use the other colors as
I'm having an issue or something like that.
Just so I get a feel for if folks have completed stuff or not.
Thank you very much.
Yeah, just put it on the back of your laptop.
That gives me a visual indicator of whether I need to wait longer or not because several
of the things are going to be...
Actually, everything's going to be hands-on.
So overall, the plan is we're going to spend about 20 minutes just getting familiarized
with the interface and making sure everyone's logged in or so.
Then we're going to spend the rest of the first hour just doing Panda stuff that if
everyone's done Panda stuff before should be fairly straightforward.
We're also going to introduce you to a plotting tool called HVPlot.
Who's familiar with Streamlit or Dash or any of these tools?
So there's another set of tools called HoloViz which HVPlot is part of that is similar to
those tools.
But one of the nice things about the HoloViz things is it's very tightly integrated with
the big data tools on the backend.
So you can do very similar dashboards and stuff like you can do with Streamlit or something,
but you can also then turn a switch on and say, okay, now I'm going to do this with a
huge dataset.
So that's why we're going to go through those.
The second hour, we're going to do a deep dive, well, a dive into Dask.
And with that, we're also going to talk about storage formats.
And where your data is because once you start dealing with larger datasets, where the data
is and how it's stored starts mattering a lot.
And so we're going to go through that.
And then we're going to actually do some really nice big compute.
So the last hour, we're going to do visualization with larger datasets and building small applications.
And then if we get to it, there's some stuff about sharing with people and stuff that I
don't know.
We have a lot of material, and this is the first time we're trying to teach this, so
we'll see how far we get.
Any questions?
Has everyone logged in and cloned?
Do I need to walk through the instructions again for anyone who just came in?
Okay.
So for those who just came in, we've still got about five minutes, so let me just do
this again.
Go to this first website, nabari.quantsite.dev.
And on this website, you will see this sign in with key cloak.
Once you click sign in with key cloak, ignore the sign in with Google, but click this register
button at the bottom.
And that register button will let you create an account.
And then once you've created an account, we need to take this repo.
And so we're going to start a server, and then we're going to actually walk through
this again.
I just realized I could do it with this, then we can...
Pardon?
Did it let you log in when you logged into the Gmail account?
Oh, that's interesting.
Well, we opened up the permissions to make it easy, so we may have accidentally enabled
that, but that's fine.
We're going to delete all of you after the tutorial anyway.
Yeah, so don't tell any Bitcoin miners that this is open right now because...
Oh, that already exists.
Okay, so now if you click start my server, I'm going to pick a medium instance.
I'm going to start.
And let me find my...
So if I go to the Git repo and I'm going to choose HTTPS, copy it, and now you'll see
what the Git plugin looks like on this one.
So we've also on the back end, so this is running on GCP, and we've upped our quotas
so that all of you should be able to pull 10 medium instances at a time, and that should
give each of you 40 cores and 16 into 10, like 160 or 200, I forget, whatever GB.
Now, we tested that last week with about 10 of us each scaling up to 50 or 100, I don't
remember, so hopefully this will all scale well today.
Okay, anyone still cloning the Git repo?
Okay, so for cloning, you click this, and this is the thing you should have seen earlier,
and we can say clone repo, and we can put this in, clone, and then if you look here,
we now have this nice presentations folder.
So I'm going to shut down this server because I'm not going to use it.
Stop my server.
Okay, so I'm going to assume that everyone is doing well now.
Okay.
Okay, so one thing I'm going to do is if we, which stage are you on?
If you're in Jupiter, do this.
If we click on this little chat icon here, and if you join, if you click join on PyCon
2023, you can turn off the video, and I'm going to leave my audio on so that my colleagues
can listen in, but if you join meeting and go to chat, S Guild and Pavitra are online,
and they can try and answer some questions if I'm not able to get to all of them, and
we'll see how that works.
Okay, let me go back here.
Okay, so I'm going to close this for now.
Okay, so if you look at the introduction, so two things.
One is when we go to all the notebooks, run the first cell, wait.
When it completes, run the next cells because in a couple of notebooks there's some race
conditions.
There are a couple of sections that say your turn, and the next cell is empty for you to
try writing some code, and below that there's a cell with three dots.
If you click the three dots, you'll see the solution or a solution because some of them
are open-ended and we've given one solution there.
For support, if you want, you can try and use the Jitsi plugin, the Meet.
Also, if you want a longer discussion or more questions, we have a discussions page on our
GitHub, so you can click there and you can open a discussion there as well.
Put a red sticky, a colored sticky note up if you have a question.
I'm going to stop it several times and ask for questions, but if something's not working,
we'll go there.
Okay, so I am actually going to go to the first actual data notebook.
Okay, so this is, we're going to look at a data set which I pulled a few weeks ago.
It's airline on-time performance.
We're trying to think of a data set that everyone can understand.
It's not finance, it's not geospatial, it's not weather, and everyone can get.
We thought, okay, everyone's dealt with flight delays.
We scraped this data from the Bureau of Transportation Statistics.
The 2003 to 2022 is about 70 gig in terms of CSV.
This is a medium-sized data set.
The tools I'm showing you can go to much higher, but this is a data set that's not too big,
so we can do something useful in this class because we're only giving you 10 nodes each.
But also, it's bigger than you'd be comfortable doing on your laptop, or you could do it on
your laptop, but it would be annoying.
We've put this data on a GCS bucket, and it's divided into, okay, I'll just say one thing.
The Bureau of Transportation Statistics website is very annoying.
It took several days to scrape this data, and there's a folder in, if you're interested
in this prep, there is the, my code to actually scrape the data.
If you want to scrape it yourself and were willing to let it run for several days, you
can look at that.
Anyway, this is the data set.
You should be able to run this cell, so this is just going to connect to the Google storage
and list all the files we have.
If I look at, actually, if we look at files, you can see these are the files that are,
here, I just picked one year of data.
I'm picking like 2022 data.
So let's just import pandas.
I also have a JSON file called Dtypes, which we wrote earlier, and if you want to look
at that, it's in the prep folder.
Look at that, and it's just what all the types are for the data set.
We'll talk a little bit more about that in a minute, because it will become important
later.
This cell is going to take about three minutes to run.
Pandas can only read one CSV at a time, so we kind of have to read them all in and then
append them and then concat them.
In the meantime, let's look at the data set.
So we click on this link.
This is the data set we're using.
It has lots and lots and lots and lots and lots of fields.
The main thing is for every carrier that flew in the U.S., it has every flight they flew,
what the departure time was, what the departure delay was, what the arrival delay was, whether
the flight was canceled or not, whether it was diverted or not, and which airline, and
a fair number of statistics like that.
So this is what we're going to use.
It also tells you things like when the wheels off were, and it buckets the delays into 15-minute
increments.
Some other things it has is why it was canceled, and then what kinds of delay, was it a weather
delay, was it a security delay, was it late aircraft arrival.
Some of this data exists from 2003.
Other data was added in 2008.
Other fields were added.
We have not done much cleanup to the data.
We're using the direct CSVs without any cleanup.
If you're doing this live, you'd probably want to do some cleanup.
This is still running.
While this is running, any questions so far?
About three minutes.
This is one of the reasons we don't use Pandas for large datasets.
I'm showing this to you to show you the pain before we go to other things.
If that didn't run, I would restart your kernel and try running it again.
That was probably some kind of ... If this top cell didn't run, if this cell is still
showing a star, just restart your kernel and try it again.
You probably hit that race condition I was talking about.
The top here, you see this little circle button?
You can click that.
Okay, do I have my ... Yeah, okay.
Now I have my data.
If I look at the top of the data, you can see I've got a year, quarter, month, month
of day, day of week, the date, the carrier, tail number, wheels off.
You see there's a lot of empty data as well towards the end of the data frame.
I'm just going to make it simpler.
I'm just going to take the first 60 columns.
I think this data set has like 150 columns.
This is the first 60.
Let's see how much time people took to fly in 2022.
We spent 1,600 years in aggregate flying around the country.
First exercise.
This should be simple pandas.
Let's see what the maximum and average delays are in flight.
If we look at the key ... You can either look here.
Actually, no, actually.
If you look at the JSON.D types, or if you look here, you can see what the delays are
called.
This is a depth delay and an ARR underscore delay.
You can use that.
I'm going to wait a couple of minutes to see.
Go ahead.
Go to this top URL.
Then click on key cloak, and then click on register.
Then you'll need to clone this repo.
If you have finished the exercise, or if you're not planning to do the exercise, please put
your little yellow tag up so I get a feel.
Or if you're having trouble, do that too.
Yellow means I'm done, or I'm good.
If you hit ... If your kernel crashes, that is usually because you ran out of memory.
If you have two notebooks open ... We have 16 GB.
If you open one notebook and you've read in a bunch of stuff, and you open another notebook
and you read in a bunch of stuff, one of the kernels will crash once you hit 16.
That's one of the reasons we're going to start using Dask later.
One thing you can do is you can go to this stop button here on the side, and you can
see which kernels are running, and you can close any you don't want.
We don't need these two.
They don't have much data in them.
Another thing you can see, and I'll do this a little later.
Actually, I'll do that later.
The person over there who was trying to get started, were you able to clone the Git repo,
or do I need to show you that?
Okay, yeah.
If anyone wants to see what memory usage looks like while you're doing this stuff, look at
this little cup thing here.
If we click this, it says machine resources.
If you click that, you'll get some graphs, and you can move that somewhere, and you can
see what CPU memory.
Right now, I'm using ... I don't know.
I can't tell that's ... Yeah, right now, I'm at 11 GB of memory usage.
I might keep that open.
Okay, I'm going to move on.
Let's see.
This is just a little ... Just pandas.
We're just saying what the mean and max delay is.
The maximum departure delay is ... Is that 60 hours?
Yeah, I think that's 60 hours.
Yeah, 57 hours.
The average is about 12 minutes.
Okay, vote.
Which airport do you think has the most delays?
The most mean delays?
Pick your least favorite airport.
I would have said Dallas.
JFK.
Anyone else?
Okay, let's see where it is.
It's Atlanta.
I would have thought it was DFW, though.
DFW is massive, too.
I don't know.
LAX is massive.
Is it?
Yeah, I mean, you could.
I don't know.
This data set doesn't have ... I guess you could do it ... You have number of flights
from each airport, so you could actually calculate that.
See if there's a ... Do a scatter plot between ... If you want, you can try that.
Do a scatter plot between the two, but yeah.
Okay, I'm a little confused here.
I think we put this solution in the wrong place.
I'm just going to run this because I don't know what's in here, this section of code.
Oh, okay.
This was ... Yeah, airline.
Do you want ... Okay, let's vote.
Which airline do you think has the most delays?
Spirit.
Okay, let's see.
Anyone else?
We've got Spirit and Southwest as leading contenders.
If you want, you guys can run this, or you can try writing this.
This is just a simple group by delay.
I'm going fast on these because this is just pandas right now, so there's plenty of really
good pandas tutorials out there.
Anyway, I'm just going to keep moving.
It is ... Why is that ... Yeah, it is Southwest.
I'm going to cancel that.
Oops, that's not what I wanted to do.
Okay, I'm going to move a little faster so we can get to the Dask things.
I'm going to now try and show you why we need other tools than pandas.
Here, I'm now getting the entire dataset, like all the CSVs.
If we look at this, this is 240 files.
Each one ... If I remember correct, each CSV file is about 200 to 300 MB, and the total
dataset is about 70 gigabytes.
I am now going to try and load all the data.
If we look at this memory plot, what you should see is the memory starting to go up.
One second.
Just as a note, sometimes these plots are getting stuck, and if you tab away from them
and then tab back, they refresh.
We need to fix that.
Okay, it's not ... I'm trying to work out why it's not reading right now.
Has anyone tried running this last cell? Is it reading?
I promise you this will crash your browser. It's not doing it right now for me, but I'm
going to ... I'm going to stop this.
Okay. Let's do a quick detour into plotting.
Okay, so we're going to do some interactive plotting with HVPlot. To give you a little
background, this is the ecosystem we're looking at. There's a tool called HoloView, and it's
used that wraps several other tools, like Bokeh is a plotting tool, Matplotlib, and
then you've heard of Plotly. There's also Altair. There's actually a really complicated
diagram.
DataShader is another tool for managing really big datasets. HVPlot is an API on top of
these other tools to make it easy to use those other tools with a simpler API. But you can
also ... All the plots I'm showing you, you can go down into the lower level libraries
and plot it from there as well. This is a higher level tool, and it's designed to mimic
the Pandas.plot API. If you've ever done a .plot in Pandas, HVPlot mimics that API to
make it a very easy transition to get more features, and we'll show that. Let's just
go Pandas, and then we're going to import HVPlot, and here I'm saying use the Bokeh
backend for HVPlot. The Bokeh backend will give you interactive plots. If I put Matplotlib
there, you'd get the same plots, but it would be static. You wouldn't be able to do any
interaction.
This command here, import HVPlot.Pandas, that means replace the Pandas.plot and add a ... Well,
actually add a .hvplot to Pandas. Anything you do with .plot, you can now do .hvplot.
I'm just going to read in one year of data, and I'll just show you how big this dataset.
One year of data is about, I think, six million rows, and this will probably run out of memory
on your medium-sized instance. Actually, I'm limiting that, yes, it's about six million
rows, so I'm actually just going to limit it to United, American, Southwest, and Delta.
That makes it about three million rows, and that kind of fits in memory here. You guys
have probably done this before. This is just a group by the date, flight date, and look
at the mean of the departure delay. This gives you your standard Matplotlib plot that you
get with Pandas.
I am now going to repeat that, and here, instead of .plot, I'm just going to change it to .hvplot.
Now I get this, and it looks similar. It looks like styling differences, but now this is
an interactive plot. I can zoom. I can pan, and I have hover tools, so I can look at each
exact point. Simple. You don't need to know anything else. Just wherever you do .plot,
do .hvplot. There are some slight differences in the keyword arguments because there's more
features. In .hvplot, there's a hover column, so you can say which columns show up when
you hover, which you obviously don't have in .plot because .plot doesn't have a hover
ability. Let's try this. Let's see if you can take this plot. Take this plot you have
here where we're group buying flight date and we're showing departure delay, and let's
add arrival delay to this plot as well. You have both on here. I'll give you guys a few
minutes to do that, and we'll take any questions while we're waiting. Actually, I guess I should
look at chat. Oh. Disconnected from chat.
Okay.
While I'm waiting for you, I'm just going to check on our time.
Feel free to change things if you don't want to do a mean and if you want to do a max or
cum sum, cumulative sum, or something else.
Okay.
Yeah, if you just say what you're saying, instead of doing .mean, you can also do .ag
and how equals mean max. It's just changing the plotting mechanism, but it's designed
to mimic Panda's existing API. You guys ready for me to show the solution?
Okay, go ahead. Probably go back to the top. That's that race condition I talked about.
If you hit restart on the kernel, this button, and then run the first cell and make sure
it completes fully, and then wait a few seconds and then run the second cell. Essentially,
this command hvplot.extension injects some JavaScript into your Jupyter Notebook to
enable interactivity. Currently, I filed a bug, but there's a bug with Jupyter Hub where
there's a slight delay in the kernel being available and the JavaScript gets messed up.
You can also see this if you restart a kernel and hit run all cells. Sometimes the first
two cells don't get executed correctly. That's an issue in JupyterLab that I filed a bug
on. Okay. I'm going to ... Anyone want me to wait or I'm going to go ahead and look
at the solution here. Here, just a one-liner. I'm just adding arrival delay into the data
frame, and now I'm going to plot both. Actually, this is interesting. If you look at the monthly
arrival and departure delay, arrival delays are shorter than departure delays. That sort
of makes sense because often they can make up time during the flight. They burn a little
more fuel and go faster. You can also now click on these to shade them out. If you have
lots of them, you can kind of emphasize which one you're doing. Again, HVPlot just gives
you a lot more interactivity. Right now, I think ... Yeah. I won't go anything else
with that. I'm going to run this histogram. Again, I'll just show you that it ... The
whole point of this is this just gives you some extra powers over your existing plot
command. Here, we have the histograms of the various ... Oops. We have the histograms of
the various carriers. If I hover, it gives me actual information. Which bin it is, how
many points are in this bin. Again, same plots, just a few extra features.
The other thing that HVPlot gives you is widgets. Here ... Let me just show you something in
the command here. Here, I gave it this keyword, subplots equals true. In this, I'm doing a
group by carrier, and I'm saying subplots equals true. It gave me a plot for each carrier.
If I leave that out and just do the group by ... I'm doing a histogram grouped by carrier,
but I haven't put subplots equals true. Now, it'll give me a widget to select with. See,
instead of having four plots ... This I did on the entire dataset. Here, now we have all
the carriers. Let me look at delta. I click delta, and I'll see delta. Let me pick ... I
don't even know what NK is. Anyway, it gives you easy widgets. We'll use these widgets.
This is an automatic widget, but in one of the exercises later, we'll actually make our
own. I would like you to go ... This next exercise, if you go up ... I think I have
a link to the HVPlot doc gallery. Do I have a link to the HVPlot? Let's go here. If we
go to HVPlot, and if we go to, I think, reference gallery, let's pick the violin plot, which
is over here. I'm going to go to the reference gallery. I'm going to go to the reference
gallery. Okay, I think our internet slowed down. Yeah. You'd think the conference center
would ... Yeah, okay. Let's look at this violin plot, and see if you can take the code you
have from your box, from one of these, and create a violin plot for the delays.
In interest of time, there's three more exercises in this notebook. In interest of time, I'm
going to go through the rest of the material, and then leave the exercises for you guys
to do. We're going to take a break after this as well. You can work on it through the break.
Right now, this is all just pandas. I want to spend less time on this and move to the
big data parts. I think that's what I'm going to do. If you click the three dots, you'll
see the code for the violin plot. Two last things I want to show with the HVPlot is we
have the ability to very simply compose plots using plus and multiply operations.
So here, I'm just going to look. I've got this group by for delays, and it's just this
min-max with carrier. Now, I've got a plot, a min-max plot of areas, and a mean plot.
If you look, this is one of the things. I made this min-max plot, but you didn't see
it. If I type min-max now, min-max plot, now it'll display. This is my min-max plot. It's
got a drop down. Then, let's see if we want to see this one. Mean plot. I have these two
plots, nice two simple plots. Now, what I can do is I want to combine these two, and
HVPlot has a simple way of composing plots. If you want to put two plots side by side,
you can just add them, and you'll see them side by side, and their axes are linked. If
I zoom in on this one, I zoom in on the other one, so the axes are linked. If I just want
to zoom this way, I guess that axis won't link, but the main axis is linked. Now, instead
of putting them side by side, if I want to overlay them on the same plot, you can do
this. If I multiply them, both the plots are overlaid on the same thing, and with the same
scale, so it looks like a straight line, but if I actually zoomed in down here, you'd see
it is not really a straight line. It just looks like a straight line. Anyway. Another
thing it gives you, I don't use this as much, but HVPlot, you can just give it a Pandas
data frame, and it will give you a little Explorer interface on it. So if you click
HVPlot.Explorer, it will give you, in a couple of seconds, a couple of seconds, and then
you can see it. Okay, this usually doesn't take this long. I'm going to try kill it and
try again. I have plenty of memory. Five here, five here. Okay. So, I'm going to try to get
it. It looks like something's gone wrong. Did it come up for you? Okay. Okay. I do not
know why it's not coming up for me, but let me try restarting. Okay. So, I'm going to
try restarting. Actually, you know what? I have it up here. Yeah, I think we're hitting
some of the Wi-Fi limitations here. This should not take this long to come up. Okay. So, I
pre-ran this earlier just in case I had issues, but if you run the Explorer... Okay, this
is what the violin plot would look like if you ran it. If you ran the Explorer, you'd
get a little widget like this where it's got all the fields, and you could decide what
your X axis, what your Y axis, whether you want... What kind of... What do you want to
align, a bar plot, what do you want to group by, all that kind of stuff, and you can set
your labels and axes and stuff. And then at the end, once you have the plot looking the
way you like it, you can hit Save Plot Clote, and it'll give you the pandas code to do that.
Last I'm going to... Actually, I killed this, I think. So... Okay. So, I'm going to go back
and... Yeah. If you run the last one, I've just got... This shows you that HG plot also
lets you do geographic stuff. So, I've read the... I've got the CSP that just gives me
the lat long of all the airports, which we don't actually have in our dataset, and I'm
doing a group by... I'm finding the mean departure delay. We did this earlier. We found out Atlanta
was the worst place. But now I'm just doing the mean departure delay for all the airports.
I'm merging it with this airport's dataset to get latitude and longitude, and now I'm
plotting the points, and I'm saying geo equals true because I want a geospatial plot, and
I'm saying I'm going to use these ESRI tiles mapping service. And I also just put the latitude,
longitude limits for the US. And so now you have an interactive plot where you can actually
zoom in and see what the delays are, and these points are color coded by how much delay.
So... Okay. So, I was going to stop there and give folks time for a 10-minute break, or
if folks have questions and want to try the exercises, we can... Folks who want to stick
around can. But we'll start again at 10.10. You can install all this yourself. There's
an excellent set of things called Zero to Jupiter Hub with Kubernetes, and it's got
step-by-step, you know, do this, change this in Kubernetes, do this, do this, do this,
do this. We got fed up of doing that lots and lots of times, and so we built a bunch
of installation scripts that make it very easy to get everything you need running. And
so we've called that NABARI. We've been working on it for about the last two years, and essentially
if you have cloud credentials, and whichever cloud you care about, like DCP or AWS or whatever,
you can get this entire platform up and running in about 30 minutes. You have a guided install
that says, okay, which cloud are you on? Paste your credentials here, blah, blah, blah. It'll
spit out a YAML file with, like, you know, which you can edit, like, which instances
you want, GPU, non-GPU, and then you hit Deploy, you run Deploy, and it deploys everything
on the cloud of your choice with, you know, all the stuff you're seeing today, and then
it also integrates with GitHub or GitLab actions. So then if you want to make changes to your
infrastructure, you just make changes to that YAML file, and it'll kick off a new install.
So I don't know if any of you are old enough to remember when AWS first came around, there
was a thing called StarCluster, and it was a simple script someone at MIT wrote to just
launch your stuff in the cloud so you could run stuff. That's the vision behind this.
Get your platform installed and get out of the way so you can actually get work done.
And so that's what Navari is. It's essentially, let me see, where is it? Do I have a link?
Oh, I don't have a link here. There's a brochure here which shows you more, but it essentially
integrates, it's all the deployment scripts you need to install JupyterHub, Dask, Argo
Workflows, ClearML, and a few other tools like in the cloud, and also we do, one thing
I'll show at the end is we also give you a tool to manage environments. So that if you,
like for example, this is the PyCon environment we're using right now, and you can see that
over the last several days we made several versions of it. And so it's, the idea of Navari
is to try and get everything installed and get out of the way so you can actually do
work. So, but again, you don't have to use Navari to use any of the tools I'm showing
today. That's just a way, easy way to install everything. And in one of the last notebooks
I'll give you some other options if you want to use Dask and stuff. There are several options
on how you get things installed.
Okay, I'm going to go to this notebook three introduction to Dask. Okay. So, I'm going
to go to this notebook three introduction to Dask. So, Dask is a tool to distribute compute.
And it is very nice. One of the reasons I really like it is it mimics, it's a very
PyData friendly tool. If you're used to using Python, it maps really well to the stuff you
already know. So, there are other tools like Spark. And Spark came out of Java and came
out of the concept of MapReduce. And Spark can be very powerful if you understand MapReduce
and if you like Java. If you try and use PySpark from Python, you will get annoyed very quickly.
Again, but PySpark does do certain things really well. So I'm not saying you shouldn't
use it. Dask takes your computation, splits it up and executes it on a bunch of nodes
for you and gives you back the answer. It has four APIs. I'm only going to go through
one. It has, I'm not sure if we listed the APIs here. No, I don't think we did. It has
an array API which mimics NumPy. So if you use NumPy arrays, there's a Dask array that
is very similar to NumPy array. The main one we're going to use today is the Dask data
frame API. And it mimics the pandas API. Then there's another one called Dask bag which
is for unstructured data. Which is like if you're doing JSON files or something and it's
not really, so Dask bag can be used for that. And then they have a low API called Dask delayed
which you can use to do arbitrary parallel compute. Like for example, Spark is very specifically
a MapReduce type algorithm. So you have to transform your, whatever your compute into
the MapReduce paradigm to run it usually. Delayed lets you do kind of like say, hey,
this function I want to run in parallel. This function I want to delay it. You know, and
it just kind of lets you construct things. I'm going to run this first thing. So as I
said, we're going to import the Dask data frame as DD. Like kind of like how you do
import pandas as PD. If you notice, I said it's a similar API. It's not the same. And
this, there's a reason for this. There's other projects like moden and I forget there's one
more that try and give you the exact pandas API. The problem with it is then you're stuck
with decisions pandas is made. Like one of the things we saw earlier, if you want to
read multiple files in, you have to do this whole list concat business, which is fine
when you're only reading a few data sets. But if you're doing big data and you're going
to read 10,000 files, you don't want to do a list concat. And so while, and there's certain
things, there's certain like, one thing we're going to go into is local memory versus remote
memory. And there are some computations. So your local memory is limited. We have 16 GB
in this medium instance type. We have lots of memory distributed over our entire cluster.
Anything you bring locally has to fit in that local memory. And so there are some extra
keywords for some functions. Like if you do a drop duplicates in pandas, fine, you do
drop duplicates. If you do a drop duplicates in Dask, it can crash your local machine because
drop duplicates is one of those things where you need to see all the data. And so it has
some extra keywords in there to use an algorithm that does drop duplicates in pieces and then
puts the pieces together. So it has to go through several cycles and you can control
that. And so even though it's data frame inspired, it's not exactly the same as pandas data frame.
Okay. Let me see. I think we are hitting Wi-Fi issues. Oh, it ran the second time for me.
So, okay. Let's see. So now we're going to do the same thing. But now we're going to
read in four months of data into a convention as we call Dask data frames, ddf instead of
df, just so you know it's a distributed data frame. But you don't have to. So I'm going
to read four months of data. Oh, that happened really quickly. Yeah. The star means it's
executing or stuck, you know, whatever. So if you notice that ran really quickly. When
you try to read a year of data in with pandas, it took a significant amount of time. Four
minutes should have taken longer. But there's a reason. Dask actually hasn't read the file.
If you look at it, Dask does what's called lazy evaluation. I've told it I want to read
these four files. It's just put in its graph, I need to read four files. It actually hasn't
read them. And so this is showing that it's gone to those files, it's looked at the structure
of the files, and it's decided to divide those into seven pieces. Like you see the end partition
but it hasn't done anything yet. It's just showing you the metadata. So if you actually
want it to calculate, you actually have to say .compute. Again, now this is not something
you have in pandas. Pandas does not have a .compute. Pandas is what's called eager. When you tell
pandas to do something, it does it immediately. When you tell Dask to do something, it doesn't
do it, it just adds nodes to its calculation graph. And one of the reasons is you might
add several nodes, and by the end of it, you've done some filtering and done some other things,
and so the data set's much smaller. So maybe it doesn't need to read all the files. So
by being lazy, you have some advantages. But now I'm going to run compute, and now it's
actually going to chug, and it's going to take a few seconds. Right now it's going to
use the cores which I have on this instance, because I haven't started. So now I did a
unique, and we've got four months of data. There are certain things like head, which
so earlier I told you, I said we have to use .compute. There are certain commands that
will implicitly compute. So if you do a .head, it has to read the data to show you the beginning
of the data. So I'm going to run .head, and it gave me an error. Okay. Let's read this
error. Column 77 and 84 has mixed types. Okay. So I'm going to run .head, and it's
okay. You don't have this problem with pandas, okay, because you're reading one file. And
when you read pandas, it looks at every column, and it makes a decision on what data type
to give that column. And sometimes it may give a D type that you didn't like. Maybe
it took an integer and made it a float, or maybe it took something and made it a string.
But you can kind of specify D types. But often the first thing you do with pandas is just
say read CSV without specifying D types, and then if you care, you might transform them
or you might put the D types in. Now, as I told you, Dask is lazy. If you give it 10,000
files, if it had to open each file to check the D types, and, you know, that would take
forever. So what it does is it looks at the first file and a certain number of rows in
the first file, and it guesses what the D types are. And if you have a good data set
and it's fairly uniform, everything works fine. In our case, the first file had a bunch
of, you know, no data in one column, and one of the other files had floats or a missing
NA or something. So it made a guess based on the first file, I think this column is
a string column. But when you did head and now trying to read it and it tried to read
the second file, assuming that column was a string column, and it said, no, that didn't
work. So that's what this had. This is why we'll get to storage formats, why when you
do big data, storage formats matter. So this is a big horrible error. Now, instead, what
we're going to do, you know, I spent some time actually looking through the data and
creating this JSON file, and I gave it very explicit storage types. Now, if you look,
if you want, you can just make it simple. You can just say integer, string, string,
integer. I actually went ahead and did like integer 16, integer 8, you know, and these
are different sizes. Because when you're reading one file, this doesn't matter. But when you're
reading 10,000 files, an integer 32 or an integer 64 is four times as big as an integer
8. So if you know your number is only like a 0 and 1, use a Boolean. If you know the
numbers between this and this. So you can save a lot of memory, which doesn't matter
when you're just doing one or two files. But when you're doing 10,000 or 20,000, that adds
up to a lot of memory. And so taking some time to look at the data, explore it, and
think through, okay, what can I get away with, will really impact how well you can do big
data. One of the things I want to kind of reinforce as we go through this is everyone
wants a magic scale button. I want to take my data set and hit scale, and it just scales.
But what you'll see through this is you get some initial benefits with the automatic scale
button initially. Like, you know, oh, I can go from this data set to this bigger data
set. But eventually you have to think through the fact that your data is not local. It's
on multiple machines, and moving things between machines costs a lot of time. And so you have
to start thinking about that if you want to effectively do larger data sets. The magic
scale button will work until it doesn't. You know? And that's why some tools like this,
you know, there are a couple of tools. Moden is one of them. There's a couple of others
which try and give you a magic scale button and try and hide everything. And you can use
them effectively to a certain data set size, and then you're stuck. You know, you have
to really think about what you're doing. Okay.
So, I'm going to read in that same data set with the D types which I just read in. And
if you also look, now I'm also reading in the data with a glob. I don't actually have
to limit myself to one data set. Or you can use a glob and do some whatever regex you
want to get some complicated list, and you can pass the list of files in as well. So
very simple. We don't have to do the read each one, concatenate. And so now when we
run head, we shouldn't get any warnings or errors. Okay? So now we've got the beginning
of the data. Same thing we saw earlier. We got five rows, 109 columns. Now, here, I'm
creating an ad. Actually, is this large enough? I think, okay. I'm saying DF.sum. What do
you think when I hit enter, what do you think this will look like? What will I get any numbers
out of this? No. This is just going to give me a graph. So this basically says, I've
set a sum. To do a sum, Dask needs to do three or four things. Okay? And we're going to look
at this. We're going to visualize this. And this is one of the reasons why we're only
reading four files, because if we read all the files, this visualization would look kind
of messy. So I'm going to, well, since this is taking a long time, so if you actually
look at it, this is what the visualization kind of looks like. Oops. That's not what
I wanted to do. So if you look, we gave it four files. So there are four read.csvs. So
it's reading each of the four files. It's doing this sum chunk. So it's summing all
the data in each of the four files. And then it's aggregating that sum from each of the
four files. So this is the graph. And then it's giving you back the answer. Yeah.
0 to 6. What do you mean? Oh, okay. Yeah. Well, so also the partitions don't have to match
the files always. It's making some logic on what the best size to put each piece is. So
yeah. Okay. So now we're... Okay. So now we're... So now we're... So now we're... So
now we're... So I computed it. This took about 20 seconds to compute the sum. Now internally
this is what's happening. Internally, each partition has an individual Pandas data frame.
Okay? And if we're using the array, if we're using the Dask array, each partition would
have a NumPy array. There's also another tool which is Dask compatible called XArray, which
for n-dimensional data if you're doing geospatial
or large field, you know, like the symmetry
or weather data, that also has x-array,
non-py-array chunks put together.
So the Dask data frame is a collection
of individual Pandas data frames,
and then it automatically works out a parallel set
of a graph to do your computation
on all those individual pieces
and then aggregate them together.
And right now, I have seven partitions,
some of you have six, it's gonna do those computations
on each of those six or seven
and then kind of pull them together.
Okay, so everything you've run so far
is running on your individual medium-sized node,
and that has four cores and 16 GB.
But this model can be extended to larger machines
or larger clusters of machines.
So you could have, the way it works is you have a scheduler,
and the scheduler is holding your list of tasks
and what needs to be done.
And then you have workers, and if you're on a local laptop
or local desktop, your workers are just threads
or processes on your machine.
But if you're on an HPC machine or on a cloud machine
or something else, those workers could be distributed
in a large cluster.
And they all communicate back to the scheduler
and they say, I'm free, give me tasks.
And the scheduler parses the tasks out
and then it collects them, and if something fails,
it reschedules them, so it acts as the,
kind of that piece.
There are several ways to launch workers.
So we need to basically say, hey, here's my scheduler,
let's launch, I want this many workers, launch them,
everything connect up, give me back something
that can do the computation.
In this particular example, we're gonna use Dask Gateway.
There's also another commercial product from Coiled.
There's also Dask Kubernetes, and there's a Dask version
that works on Yarn called Dask Yarn.
There's Dask, so there's several ways to launch
these workers and the details are slightly different,
but they're very, if you know one,
you can switch out to another one.
Essentially, we're using Dask Gateway,
and Dask Gateway lets us run,
some of the advantages of Dask Gateway
is it lets you run clusters without giving end users
elevated permissions on the cluster.
For example, if you use Dask Kubernetes,
anyone running Dask Kubernetes has to have
high privileges on the Kubernetes cluster.
Dask Gateway lets the sysadmin take care of that,
and end users still be able to launch clusters.
So this, and we're going to launch Gateway
and ask for a Gateway link.
And with our Gateway link, we're going to see
what options we have to choose our cluster.
And this matters because one of the things
you're gonna find out is one of the difficult things
when using clusters, any kind of clusters,
not just this, is the software you have on your head node
or main computer has to match the software you have
on each of these workers.
And getting those two to match is half the problem
of using any tool like Dask.
So, you know, one of the commercial companies
around Dask coiled, they have a really good solution
to let you distribute these environments.
We have one built into Nabari, but you can also do it
yourself, if you make a Docker image and you make sure
the workers use that Docker image, you know, it's doable.
But here, the way we set it up with Nabari is
if you look at your, up here, we have all these
environments available.
You won't see the Quantsight ones because you're not
in the Quantsight group.
And here we have those same environments available,
the ones which have Dask in them.
And you need to choose the PyCon 2023 tutorial environment
and we want to use the medium worker, okay?
So that sets up what I'm gonna request.
And then I'm gonna call gateway and say I want a cluster.
Okay?
What happened there?
museum my
It'll be pinging.
I have a colleague watching Kubernetes on the back end, so I just pinged him.
Yeah, no, we're going to, if this runs, I'll show you the auto scaling.
You can choose to either auto scale or you can choose to manually scale.
So if this doesn't work, we're going to be in trouble.
Connection refused.
You know what? I'm going to try one thing. I wonder if something is blocked on...
Let me switch Wi-Fi to my hotspot and see if it's something to do with that.
Was anyone able to get this cluster to show up?
I don't think it's to do with Wi-Fi.
Okay, let me try this again.
Okay, let's do this. We think, my colleague thinks it might be all of us trying to connect
to the gateway at the exact same time. So everyone hit restart on that kernel and I
will connect first and see if we can connect and then maybe we'll do by table or something.
Okay.
So to give you a little background here, there is, so this is a mix of trying to do big data
and visualization at the same time. I've helped teach DAS tutorials at SciPy and other conferences
before. Typically, we don't give anyone, in those things, we tell everyone to run on their
local computer, but we wanted to try doing it at scale this time. So it's a good stress
for what we're doing. Okay, my colleague sees four people connected. So four of us got in.
Oh, I'm, no, yeah, okay, let's see. Let's go here. And it also might be the case that
one thing about Kubernetes is initially when it autoscales, it asks for stuff and it takes
a few minutes for it to scale up. So we might be hitting this issue that it hasn't quite
scaled up enough for all of us to hit it, but let's see. So he says he sees four people
connected. Do you, anyone see that you're connected? Well, it's this next one that's
getting stuck, this cluster one.
Okay. So.
So let's take a five minute break. Hopefully, I'll get this back. Once we get the cluster up
and running, once everyone's connected to it, we'll leave it open for the rest of the
tutorial, so we should be fine. But I will work on this in the meantime. If not, we'll switch
to using local clusters, which will limit how big of the datasets we can go to.
Okay. Does anyone who's got a cluster, would they be willing to swap laptops with me so
I can do the rest of the presentation with their laptop? If not, we'll, okay. We'll see if this
works. If it does, I'll switch back to you. Yep.
Okay. Let's see. Okay. What's your name again? Thank you very much, Hannah. So, okay. So for those of
you who were able to get a cluster, we are not going to shut it down anymore, but you should see
something like this. And this has two options. It has a manual scaling and an adaptive scaling.
And these are little widgets you can use, but you can also set these directly in the code. But here
we're going to use adaptive scaling. And we're going to say a minimum of five and a maximum of
ten. Okay? And that should be enough for all of us to do the rest of the exercises. So I'm going to
click adapt. And that's now going to start requesting stuff on the back end. Oh, mine came up.
Okay. We'll try this again here. So he restarted the cluster pod. So you guys might be able to get in
now. What's a demo if something doesn't go wrong, right? Okay. So, you know, I'm going to, again, do
the same thing. I'm going to say a minimum of five, a maximum of ten. Now, you could also use manual
and say I want ten, and it will give you ten. Usually I use adaptive scaling. And the reason is
Dask is fairly intelligent about how it does the compute. So if you use adaptive scaling, and it'll
start with the minimum. And so often I put minimum of zero or one. And then when you throw a lot of
tasks at it, it'll say, oh, all my nodes are full. I'm going to go grab some more. And it'll grab more
until it hits the max. And then when it's done, it'll start dropping nodes. And so it's really more
cost-effective to do it that way. But there is a, you'll see this in a second, requesting nodes from
Kubernetes and getting them can take up to two or three minutes. Now it should be fast. It depends on
the, Kubernetes has this weird thing where it's warm and cold. If no one's been using the cluster, a new
node can take, you know, two, three minutes. But if you've been using it, they'll come up in a couple of
seconds. So we'll see that. Now we're going to click on this link here. If you guys see this dashboard
link, this is the Dask diagnostic dashboard. And first time you click on it, it'll take you back through
the login thing. And just log in again. You only have to do this once. And now you'll see this particular
thing. And right now we don't have any workers. It might take a couple of minutes for us to get some
workers.
Okay. So eventually you'll start seeing number of workers, number of threads, number of memory show up
once I have workers. I'm going to now ask for clients. So now I've made a cluster. So this first step, the
Dask Gateway new cluster, depending on what tool you use, like coiled or Dask Kubernetes or Dask Yarn,
that command looks a little different, how you set the options and stuff. But then the next part, once you
have a cluster, you get a client object. And the client object is connecting your local Jupyter Notebook
to the scheduler on that cluster. So when you run stuff, it doesn't run locally, it will run on that
cluster.
I think we're learning that the pod Dask Gateway is running on is not big enough for 40 people.
Yeah. Did you get the client? Okay. So you're the lucky person today. Once I get this client, we're basically
done because we're not going to shut the cluster down for the rest of the tutorial. This is fun.
I'll leave that there. Okay. Let's see. Oh, no, you don't have any workers yet either.
Does anyone see any workers on the side of theirs? You see some? Okay. So let me walk you through the
dashboard. So here we got the dashboard. So she still doesn't have any workers. Okay. So I'll walk you through this
next step while we're waiting for the workers. But we're going to use this dash. So here you have another tab with
all these nice graphs you can see when the computer's going on. But instead of that, we're going to use this lab
extension. If you click this little red icon here, and we should, once you're, you have to wait until your client
is available. Once you've run this client cell, you should be able to click the search button, and it'll bring you,
you should see all these tabs pop up. And we are going to pick a few. I like cluster map. Okay. Cluster map is this
one. This cluster map is kind of sad right now. It says we have a scheduler, but no workers. And then usually progress.
And you can kind of just drag these around to make them fit on your screen in a reasonable way. And I'm going to pick on
task stream. Let me move that here. And let's also do memory usage. Which one do I need? Which one do I want to use for memory?
Cluster memory. I'm going to use total cluster memory. Okay. Okay.
Okay.
Yep. I guess it only works with your hands. Let's see. I have 16 cores.
I think that's the problem. I think what's happening is the pod that the gateway is running on, because my colleague just texted me
saying that pod keeps restarting. We're overloading the gateway pod. We should probably just, we're going to have to switch to more of a
demo than a live thing. I'll write some code here that some of you can use that a lot of the examples we'll work on, we'll use local cluster.
Local cluster will use the 16 cores that we have. Yeah, it'll use this. Okay. Let me actually do this.
Okay.
Okay. So I'm going to abandon task gateway so I can give this back to you. And I'm just going to use local cluster. I've also asked my colleague to enable
a larger instance size on GCP. I'm not sure if you'll have that ready in time, but if we can, we can switch to like a 16 core or 64 core machine.
But the rest of it we should still be able to do. Unfortunately, some of the bigger data sets, I'll change how much data we're reading in so we don't
overwhelm things. But instead of using...
Okay. So we're going to have to type this in. Let's restart the kernel.
So we're going to type from distributed import local cluster. And then we're going to say cluster equals local cluster.
Okay. Now if we run this... What did I do wrong? Oh, yeah. Okay.
Okay. So this is going to use all the cores on your local machine, which here is the 16 thing. And if we go here, you should be able to click...
I'll click delete this. Oh, yeah. You're going to have to do something slightly annoying.
Okay. To get the dashboard, the URL local cluster is giving you is going to be a little wrong. And so we're actually going to use this URL.
Let me make it where you need to replace your login. You can copy and paste this from your...
Okay. So to get the dashboard link, copy your URL to the user and add slash proxy 787 status. This will give you the cluster.
And so if you take this link and paste it into this field here and hit enter, don't hit search, now you'll get the same tabs.
Okay. Was everyone able to get to this with local cluster? Okay. And in the meantime, we'll see how it goes. My colleague is trying to change the instance size for the DAS gateway to a bigger one.
So if it comes back, we'll use it later. But let's move on.
Okay.
Yeah. So here, you know, see it has this dashboard link. That dashboard link is assuming you're running on a local computer, so it's wrong. What you need to do is if you look at the top in your browser bar, mine says slash user slash dark house on site.
Yours will say slash user slash whatever your name is. Copy that down, add proxy 8 787 and status. And if you click this link, it should take you to the diagnostic dashboard.
And here, if you click workers, yeah. So here you basically see I have four workers, you know, four cores, which is what I have on this instance size.
Now if I come here, I'm going to open up this cluster map again. Oops.
And I'm going to open the memory.
And I'm going to do the progress. And you can choose any of these plots you want. I'm going to use these plots just to show you what's happening. But if you want to see other things. So I did task stream.
Okay. Are we at this point, everyone?
Okay, so I'm going to go back and.
So I'm going to go back and re execute my desk data frame and my read.
Because I need those.
And now I'm going to.
Calculate the maximum distance.
Okay.
And you basically should see how much memory is being stored. And I'm going to switch to here so you can see it a little better.
Actually, let me run that again. I think it finished. Let me run this again.
Move this down here so it's less. Okay. So when I run this, you can kind of see that I have four cores right now. So I have four streams of tasks.
And if you look, it's doing it showing you all the things that's running while you're running it.
And then when it finishes, that should go down.
And yeah.
Go ahead.
Yeah, so if you're using local cluster, if you if you look you, you can if you're just using locally, it automatically uses local cluster on the back.
And if you just do from Dask data frame import, that's a frame as DD. It automatically sets up a local cluster.
The only reason I went through this way is it it falls the same format and you get the link to the dashboard.
Which finding the link to the dashboard is a little more annoying if you don't have that. But yeah.
But if our client was on the gateway, it's definitely no automatically use that on the gateway because there's no arguments that you can use the gateway for.
Yeah, no. So basically it's basically this this command. This client equals get client automatically sets the default client to the gateway client.
Now you can also do some stuff where you connect to different things, different clients for, you know, client one client two.
And you could when you do the computer could say use this client. But usually people don't do that.
So by default, if there's one client, it's going to connect to that one.
OK, I'm going to go to the next.
We're going to talk about storage formats.
Yeah, you can. I mean, just hit restart on that one.
Local cluster is going to connect to the same local cluster, so it shouldn't make much of a difference. But yeah, we can we can just hit restart on that.
OK, I'm going to go into.
Storage clusters and I'm going to go a bit fast. I'm going to skip some of the exercises, but.
OK, so we have these CSV files which we you know I told you 70 gigabytes of CSV files.
And.
If we look at them, I'm just looking at the top one. These are all the fields and then that first line of the CSV file instead of this, we can kind of just avoid.
All of this.
Just skip this entire start, task, click gateway piece and let's just put.
Import.
Dask.
Data frame.
I think this should still be up. Let's see.
No, we're going to have to let's copy that piece we put in the previous one.
So let's use this instead of.
Our Dask gateway piece.
So I'm going to do the.
Same thing.
And now this should be working.
Yeah, so the status is there. So now here.
We're going to pick our.
So again, we read all the data sets.
And we are going to find the head and if you see every every time I run something is doing compute, you can see it's doing stuff over here.
So it's going to run the head.
Here and it takes a certain amount of time.
And then completes took 8.2 seconds.
And I'm just going to count the number of unique carriers per year.
So.
I'm not going to run this because this is going to take a lot more than four minutes on with with the number of nodes we have.
But let's skip down to this one where we're talking about parquet data because this is one of the things we want to actually talk about.
So right now we're using CSV.
There are two actually lots of big problems with CSV.
The two biggest one is the size of the CSV files.
You know they're very wasteful.
Storage format that nice because you can look at them and you can you know that's fine when they're small.
But when you have lots and lots of them, they're very not good.
The second thing is we don't know what the data types are.
You have to guess them and that's.
Usually fine if it's a small file or if you just have one or two files.
But when you have lots it like you know when I was looking at this data set so we had data from 2003 to 2022.
When I was looking at the first few CSV files from 2003.
There's data columns that showed up in 2008 that don't exist in 2003.
And so all of those are just listed as blank.
So I'd have to look at a 2008 data set to work out what the format is.
Is it a string? Is it a float? Is it a thing?
So it's really annoying to work out like writing that data type.JSON file took me an hour of looking reading through the website.
And trying to understand there what they were saying and then looking at the data and that's all a mess.
So we are going to read.
So now I've read the full data set.
You know I with Dask I'm reading the full data set.
This is just.
The metadata.
Nothing's happened.
Now I'm going to do a head on that.
And it should be much faster.
So the head here took.
Two seconds.
Versus.
Over here I think we took eight seconds.
Okay.
For the same.
To get to pull out the same data.
The other thing we can do.
I'm skipping through a couple of these in interest of time.
So another thing we can do is.
Let's say who's you know how we had like a hundred sixty one columns of data in the data set.
What would you do if you wanted to read only the first ten columns in pandas.
Yeah you'd basically say use calls equals and you give it the list.
That actually reads the entire data set into memory and then drops those columns that you didn't want.
So.
That is slow.
The way the parquet format is designed it is a column of format.
So if I say I want three columns.
It will only read those three columns.
And it will not touch the rest.
So that does two things one is it improves your load time massively.
Second thing is it.
It makes your peak memory usage much lower.
Because if you think of a CSV file it has to load the entire data set into memory.
Which causes a huge peak in memory usage.
And then it's going to drop everything so it comes back down.
So let's let's do this we're going to read just the year and the unique carrier.
And I don't know how long this will take.
Oh wait that didn't take long.
Oh no I've got to compute it that didn't actually read it.
So now let's compute this took 12 seconds on the larger number of cores.
But it's a little chug longer right now.
So we'll see.
So we are reading in.
So you see this is chugging along this is reading in through the entire 20 years of data.
So we're reading through 70 gig of data.
Which actually when it's compressed is much smaller with parquet.
And this is something you couldn't have done with pandas and even with CSV it will work.
But it will use a lot more compute and a lot more memory because it's reading more stuff in.
So it's done and now that took.
40 seconds.
And I think we calculated here.
If you look at the notes here I think she put this takes about four minutes.
With CSV with more cores so it probably take about 15 minutes if we were doing the same thing with CSV.
So that's reading specific columns.
OK so now I'm going to tell you something about partitioning.
OK.
With the original data we had one file per month.
That seems reasonably logical.
When we get to these larger data sets.
The way we access the data defines how we want to store the data.
And I'll give you an example.
Five probably 10 years ago now I was working with the UK Met Office.
They had an 80 year database of worldwide weather forecasts that they put in the cloud.
And you know I was working for the Army Corps of Engineers and we were looking at trying to analyze that data to find some long term weather trends and stuff like that.
And we also trying to experiment with cloud technologies.
And so I'm like oh wow you have an 80 gigabyte I mean not 80 gigabyte it was I think 80 terabytes of data for over like a hundred year 80 or 100 year period I forget what.
The data was unusable because the way they started in the cloud was every single day.
Every single day they stored a file that had the entire globe.
Great.
What I needed was North Carolina for 100 years.
And the only way to read 100 years of North Carolina data was to read the entire day the entire world for every day.
And so the fact that it was stored.
Temporarily and I needed spatially made it impossible to use.
So when you do these data sets.
The way you access them sort of defines the way you need to store them.
And often you have to come up with a compromise because the going back to this weather data set.
If I optimized it where I stored every like you know maybe I picked some lat long boxes and I stored everything or I stored everything at single lat long points.
Then if I wanted to get the entire world on a particular day it would be really hard because I have to read all these files.
So usually this is called chunking and you usually find a compromise in the way you chunk the data.
Like you pick something and I'm going to show this with this.
So we have divided this data by year and we have also divided it.
Yeah so we with when you save it when you when you read it in the CSV data with Dask you can say to parquet and will resave the data as parquet.
And you can also give it options on how to save it.
And here when I saved it I said when I save it I want to save it by year and sort of automatically split out each year's data.
And in each year it made a bunch of parquet files.
Go ahead.
There are places when databases are useful there are places when databases are not useful.
The databases are very slow.
This data is on blob storage on a job on GCS blob storage on cheap AWS or GCS or something is blazing fast and very cheap.
So if you put all this in a database and do an SQL statement it will chug.
You know so there are places when databases are useful.
Sometimes you can put the metadata in the database and point to data but usually large data sets putting it on blob storage is the fastest.
And this this blob storage is designed for extremely fast access by multiple people.
And so you know if you have the database if 40 people hit a database at the same time it would it would kind of fall over.
But you know S3 and equivalent are designed to be extremely fast.
So here I am going to do what's called predicate push down.
And so here I'm giving it this full data set.
You know so I've got two days that one is full data set where I've not done any partitioning.
It's just I've taken the CSP data and I've just dumped it into a parquet file.
And it's picked its own breaking it up. It usually you break up the parquet files to a certain size.
And then I've done another one where we've divided by year.
Okay.
I wonder if that was my colleague trying to give you guys a bigger instance type.
Where was I.
I was down at.
Row wise filtering. Okay. So let's let's look at this here. I'm basically saying read all the files which are not 2020 because you know COVID was annoying when you're trying to analyze data.
Okay.
You just stop from the top.
So in interest of time maybe I should skip to the next section we're running late. So the big point I want to talk about here is if we will I'll leave this open the notebook open so you can guys can run it afterwards.
We'll fix the Dask gateway issue. But the basic point is the comparison we show here is the full data set partition reading the data by year is slower than reading the partition data by year.
So because the I got the data set which is partitioned by year. And so when I tell Dask actually this actually works with pandas as well when I tell pandas to
Read only 2022 it only reads the files which are marked 2022 and so it's reading less in because it's divided that way.
And then if I read the full data set it actually has to open the data set do the comparison and then subset it out so it takes longer computationally.
Now the flip side I want the other exercise which is in here which I'm going to skip is we've saved the data by year.
And then I ask for it by airline like you know I've got so the data split by year and I've asked for it by airline now it has to go into in the individual folders read all the files and then find the.
The list of carriers that we want so.
When you're reading data from the cloud again this is all stuff which when you're reading one file it doesn't matter but when you're reading 10,000 files these add up there is a cost to going connecting to a file opening it.
Once you open a file streaming the data is very fast.
Okay.
Streaming the data is very fast.
So if you have lots and lots of small files.
The cost of connecting and opening can overwhelm the compute.
But if you if the files are too big.
The individual data won't fit on a note like we're with the cluster with setting up lots and lots of notes each node has a certain amount of memory like you know if we're doing medium each node has 16 GB.
So if your individual files are so big that when they are unzipped in memory they're more than 60 GB 16 GB you're not going to be able to do anything.
So again this is where I told you the automatic scale button doesn't work if you have files that are too big to fit on a note you won't be able to run if you have too many small files things will get really slow.
So we've done that before and it really depends on what matters to you like we were working for an ad tech company that was analyzing GPS data and they had two types of data.
So we had two types of algorithms one algorithm was hyper local it was by county and another algorithm was US wide and temporal.
So for them we had the main data set which was partitioned by day and then we had a second data set which was partitioned by county because then because otherwise so so you're paying twice the amount in storage.
But if it's a regular computation it's worth doing because you know it's like compute expense was a storage expense.
Okay.
Let me check something.
Okay I am going to see I'm moving it.
Number five I'm going to see if we can get gateway running because I think they might have increased the size.
Okay.
Let's.
Actually I think it's up here.
I'm going to give it a second to see if we can get gateway running because the next notebook is going to be much better if we can get gateway running.
In the meantime any questions.
Yes.
So there's you can do this in pandas or Dask but if we look at that.
Essentially there's a particular way to write run conditions.
Let's see.
Yeah so you see here you can give these filters.
So here the filter is so I'm reading this file and I'm giving it that filter and you can change filters you can basically say you're greater than this year less than this.
So this is pushing those filters to the files so you've never actually read the whole thing in.
So this will like for example so exactly what's happening here if you did this with pandas you'd be reading the entire data set in you'd be taking that one column you'd be doing a greater than 222.
This is basically just looking at the one column in data just reading enough of that column to do the filtering and now it knows which rows to read and so it's only reading the rows that match the filter.
So it's really limiting them out your reading.
Oh I just read it with I did Dask reach CSV Dask to parquet you know so if you actually look in prep.
So this is the notebook you can't run this notebook because it uses our cloud credentials but if you look here I started I started Dask cluster.
I'm reading all the CSV files and I'm parsing the dates I think I did a sort I sorted the data by date and carrier and then I said to parquet.
So you know and.
So that's that's how that's how I did the conversion.
Yes I have a cluster OK so if you go back to 4 the top of 4 there's this started Dask gateway cluster and it's hard coded the profile and environment name run that cell.
And then come to 5 and 5 will reuse that cluster so.
Actually I probably shouldn't have told you to do that before I continued.
Got too excited.
Maybe I spoke too soon.
I think has been confirmed to.
Run these
I think I spoke too soon.
Okay, it's up.
Oh, I have five workers, okay.
This might actually be working then.
Okay.
Yeah, okay, let me see if I still have this one.
Okay, so this is actually interesting.
So I'm connected on this notebook,
but I'm not able to connect it from another notebook
because the API is failing.
So if I copy all the code to this notebook,
I should be able to do something.
Okay, let's do that.
This is gonna be live.
This should be interesting.
Okay, so.
Okay.
Okay, so now if you look at my cluster map,
you see I have five nodes, okay.
So,
and let me do the
copy,
progress,
task stream,
and memory.
Okay.
Okay, I'm going to be copying stuff
from over here to over here,
so this should be nice.
Okay.
So the point of what I'm gonna do right now,
let me just walk you through it,
I'm going to show you what happens
when you actually do a compute.
So I'm gonna do a plot with okay,
and I'm gonna do this,
I'm gonna look at all the council, you know,
sorry, the canceled things.
Okay.
I came up here, good.
Okay, so now we're up and running here on this notebook.
So I did a head, I have five nodes right now.
I'm going to import our plotting tool.
Okay.
Okay, now we're gonna try plotting this,
and you're gonna see,
see all those red lines?
That's communication between the nodes.
That's every time it's having to transform stuff
from one node to another node
because it needs to move things around.
Now, the more red you see,
the more inefficient your computation is gonna be.
So, and in a minute,
you should see my five nodes go to 10 nodes.
Like it's busy, so it's requesting more nodes,
and usually they come in a batch,
suddenly you'll get like five more coming in.
Yes, and that's part,
okay, so now I've got this plot,
and there's another reason why the plot looks terrible.
If I did the same plot in pandas, it would be fine,
but here it's doing the plot
for each pandas data frame individually,
and then it's kind of putting them together.
This data is not sorted by date.
Okay, and so the plot's a little weird
because it's got some data which is unsorted,
which if you did in pandas, it would sort it properly,
but now it doesn't know to do that,
and if it did it automatically, it'd be able to compute.
So this took a long time to compute,
you saw there was a lot of communication, okay?
We wanna minimize shuffling.
So one thing is I knew that this data
is something I would typically access by date
and by probably carrier.
So I have a second data set on GCP
where I sorted it by date.
So the first data set is just unsorted.
The second data set is sorted, okay?
And so when we run this on the second one,
you should see less communication.
Like you see there's less red in the top.
There's still some, but there's a lot less red
because I've already pre-sorted it.
So often with large data sets, you will read them in,
get it prepared for the kind of things you wanna do.
Like I expect to sort, I expect to do things in date order,
I expect to maybe do things by year,
so that defines how you wanna save it.
The other thing you can do is
what are the steps in the graph?
It's reading data from Parquet files.
Now I might sort it, I might do a group by,
I might do a mean, I might do several computations
and have my data ready for what I want to do.
So Dask has a special command called persist.
And what that does is
it takes all your compute till that point
so it's doing all this, it's doing the reading,
it's doing the group by, it can keep it stored in memory
and persisted in memory.
So even though you're done with the compute,
it knows that still exists.
Yep, see, you saw those new nodes pop up,
but they popped up just when my computation ended.
So this next time it should come up quicker.
But now
I'm going to run this compute.
I'm basically gonna say, I'm taking my ddf,
which is my data frame, I say I want these three variables
and I want to persist it.
And so what this is going to do
is it's reading all the data.
The yellow means read, get item.
There's another graph which is kind of useful.
Oh, this is not showing very well, but this,
oh yes, this shows you the graph of all the commands.
But essentially now this is reading.
If we look at cluster memory,
we've got five gig of data in memory now.
And it's gonna just keep it in memory.
So that read has already happened,
but I could also do a read and a group by
and then do .persist.
And so then it would do all of those things and stop there
and then you could do several different types of compute
on top of that data.
Now if we look at this,
so now if we use that persist,
I have my persisted data frame
and if we do the compute on this,
if we do the same group by,
it'll be a lot faster because it's not reading the data.
The data's already in memory, it's just doing the group by.
And if I do a group by a different thing,
again, that initial step doesn't exist
because we've just persisted the data in memory.
Now if you know that you're always going to do
these two things,
you could now save it to Parquet after doing the sort,
after doing the partition.
So a lot of this is often with these big data sets,
there's an initial, let me explore the data,
let me kind of find out
and then let me decide how I expect to use it in the future.
Now I'm gonna redo all that compute,
save it and the next time I can just start from there.
Okay, let's see, what time are we at?
I am going to go script right ahead,
the rest of this you can kind of go through on your own.
Let me see if I can.
So the cluster reduced IO time
because you have a longer partition file.
So I'm gonna go ahead and do that.
So you're reading a list of all the data files?
If you're reading a list of all the data files.
I always depend on where the data is usually.
If you put the, so one of the things which,
if you read from S3 it's gonna be really fast.
If you try and read from a local disk,
it'll thrash your disk, you know.
So the cluster would be a component too,
if you were reading S3?
Oh yeah, because it'd be reading everything in parallel.
Okay, so I may just go back here and do this here.
So we have DDF, right?
So this is our data frame.
Now let's say we want to plot.
How are we gonna plot?
We can actually just do this.
Let's do, let me just copy this from here.
Because I'm going to not worry
about whether that one comes up.
So I'm going to read the flight,
I'm gonna read a selected number of columns in.
And so now I have my flights, okay?
And you know, so the same data set we've been working with.
And I think we've already imported that.
So now I am going to actually plot the entire data set.
So this is the departure delay for the entire 20 years.
And if I plot that, you see it's kind of chugging along.
And this is a fun graph, because when this comes up
in a couple of seconds, that is, so here I've done a count.
So I've counted the total number of flights every day
since 2003.
Anyone notice anything interesting about this plot?
COVID, yeah, so actually if you look here,
if you look here,
you can see that the number of flights
if you look here, March 16th, shut down.
So that's the thing.
So when you can access the entire data,
you can see trends which you can't
when you're just getting little pieces.
This is 70 gigabytes of CSV files,
and it took us a couple of seconds.
So, you know, minus all the issues we've had today,
this is one of the things I want to take away is
this stuff becomes very powerful
once you can look at full data sets
instead of decimating it or doing anything else.
Now, there's one intricacy here.
If you look at what I did in this function,
I did a group by count HV plot, okay?
And if you see when I'm panning and zooming,
there's no additional compute happening.
And that's because this data set,
this aggregated data set fits in memory.
If you think,
it's roughly, the group by,
is roughly 20 years times 365 days, one point per day.
So it's not a very big data set.
If you look at this,
did this one come up?
Okay.
So the full data set,
let's look at the full data set size, okay?
The full data set, I'm just doing a length on the data.
It is 125 million rows.
If you try and plot 125 million dots on that plot,
your browser will crash.
You know, so I'm gonna tell you about a new tool,
which I saw this at a conference 10 years ago,
and I talked to the person who wrote it and said,
hey, if you can get this working
for triangular instruction meshes, I'll give you funding.
And you know, it's a long story.
There is another tool called Data Shader.
Wait, sorry.
So,
for, I'm going to make the data set slightly smaller.
Just so we don't have to wait a long time for these to run,
which is the one I was using.
I think I was using this one.
So here, I'm just pulling in five years of data,
everything greater than 2017.
And if we look at this data set,
so this has 30 million rows.
So I'm going, it's still probably more
than you can fit in a browser.
And so what we're going to do is,
we're going to use this tool called Data Shader.
And what Data Shader does is,
if you think about this,
when you look at any of these plots,
you're limited to what?
200 by 400 pixels or whatever.
Even if you plot two million dots on that plot,
you can only see 200 by 400 of them.
So there's no point sending all that data to the browser.
So what Data Shader does is,
it aggregates the data in a way
that keeps the distribution uniform
and only plots one pixel per whatever is there.
And so,
if we do this, and this is why,
so Data Shader is its own,
so I'm going to let this chug.
So if I, so I put data shade equals true.
And now it's chugging along, it's doing some calculations.
And on the back end, it's connected to Data Shader,
which if you, I think there's a link,
if you go to Data Shader,
Data Shader is its own software
that's integrated with all these.
HV plot is acting as a front end for Data Shader,
and it just, so you just add one line.
And here,
you know, I'm doing the entire,
so this is doing 30 million individual points
and calculating everything.
And then in a few minutes, I'll get a plot
that I can browse.
And as I change my zoom and pan level,
it will recalculate the pixels needed
for that zoom and pan level.
So this allows me to see a plot of the entire data set.
Actually, how many nodes do we have?
We have 10.
In interest of making life better for all of us, oops.
I am going to say scale from 10 to 100.
We'll see if I get them.
Okay, so here I have my plot.
That's every single flight for the last 20 years.
But I can now zoom in here,
and initially it's giving me this rasterized thing.
It's gonna start chugging again,
and then it'll give me a new plot,
which is re-rasterized for that date range,
and I can actually get down
to individual points seamlessly.
So this lets you look at the entire 20 years of data,
but still have access to the individual data point,
which is a lot better than calculating a mean
or median when you're looking at large data sets.
Let's see, oh, I got all my nodes.
So to be clear, I want to kind of mention one thing
because we've had a lot of technical problems today.
The technical problems were not the DAS clusters.
We tested the DAS cluster,
scaling up to 2,000 CPU cores on Friday,
actually on yesterday as well on Monday.
The issue we had here is our DAS gateway entrance,
which you ask for a cluster and get a cluster.
That is where we didn't have that sized appropriately
for the number of people,
because what we did on Monday
is we had 10 people each launch 100,
and now we have 40 people launching a smaller number.
So yeah, so now see I've zoomed in,
you start seeing the individual bits.
Now you can also do that with any plot,
like we have a scatter plot here,
and you see now it finished the compute,
so it dropped back down to 10,
because I put the minimum as 10.
And so if I do a scatter plot,
again, it'll start chugging up,
it'll start asking for more nodes.
We'll see how quick this is now,
because I have 100 nodes.
There they come.
So I will leave this cluster on for the rest of PyCon.
So if you guys want to,
when we're not all hitting at the same time,
all these should work,
since we tested them four times before this.
So here's a scatter plot,
and actually it's kind of interesting.
You see that the arrival delay,
they can make up the arrival delay
when you're on longer flights.
But when you're on shorter flights,
they have more trouble making up the arrival delay.
So that's the kind of insight you can get
when you can look at the entire dataset.
And again, this is all the points, all 30 million.
Since I have 100 nodes,
I probably could have done the 125,
but we designed, I dropped it down to 30,
30 million rows of data,
because that worked pretty well with 10 nodes.
Okay, does folks need a quick break?
I'm kind of rushing through,
because we're about, yeah, that's stuff.
We good to keep going?
Okay.
Okay, so now,
this is,
since we have good luck with that notebook,
I'm gonna stay in that notebook.
I'm just gonna copy things over.
So I'm gonna read in this airport data.
Why am I, oh, okay.
So I'm reading in this airport data,
and it's from a different source from the earlier notebook,
because some airlines were missing in the other dataset.
Let me close this.
And I'm gonna do a quick plot of the data,
just to remind you guys what it looked like.
Ah, sorry.
Really?
Okay.
Let me see.
It doesn't like me.
Anyway, I'll come back to this, see if it comes up.
Okay, so the error I got just now is,
there are two commands, import HP plot.pandas,
and import HP plot.dask.
And if you're using plots with Dask,
you need to do the other one.
And so this airline plot is using Pandas,
so I need that.
Okay, so this is a plot of all the airports in the world.
Not very interesting.
Oh, it came up.
Okay, so I can just,
let me make sure this is 10 and 100 still.
Okay.
Okay, so now I'm gonna do,
I'm gonna build a dashboard out of what we've done so far.
Okay, so till now we did individual plots, which is great,
but we're gonna build a panel dashboard.
And panel is a software that is similar to Streamlit
and Dash and some of the other things.
I actually have a blog post comparing all of them.
But panel specifically is very good at working
with really large data sets.
And all these tools which I've shown you
till now work great with it.
And there's three different ways to build
an interactive dashboard and panel
based on what you're trying to do.
I'm gonna use the simplest,
which is this concept of dot interactive.
Okay, and there's also,
if you're exploring, this is a good one,
if you're actually building an app,
there's another one where you write classes
and stuff like that that we can look at.
So here, this is how you'd write a pipeline.
If anyone's familiar with writing a pipeline in Pandas,
this is how you would write a pipeline in Pandas.
So this is a simple pipeline.
Okay, so the same kind of pipeline works with Dask.
So I'm basically saying I'm taking my flights.
I'm saying flights are greater than 2020, less than 2021.
I'm grouping by day of week.
I'm looking at the arrival array and I'm doing a mean,
and I'm just renaming the column
so it looks a little nicer.
Okay, so that's the static thing.
If I did pipeline.compute,
I would do pipeline.head,
it would generate that data.
But we actually want something interactive
where we change widgets, and as we would change widgets,
we want stuff to happen.
So we're gonna use HVPlot's dynamic interface
where what we are gonna do is,
if you look here, we have this date quantity,
we have this group by quantity,
we have this field, and we have this method.
So I want to make each of these,
date range, group by field, and method,
I want to make them widgets.
I don't want to hard code them in.
And so I am picking widgets from here.
These are all the different widgets available in Pandas.
Like for example, there's a date picker,
and so this is a date picker widget
that lets you pick dates.
And so I'm going to pick some widgets for them.
So here's a date time widget.
This is a date range slider widget.
And I'm giving it a start date and end date.
I'm giving it some default values,
and I'm giving it some how long I want it.
And if you look at it, now I get this little date range thing.
So I can kind of like play with this.
You know.
Now, when I change this,
the data from that is in date range.value.
You go to start date and end date.
If I move this, and I run it again, the dates have changed.
So fairly straightforward.
Now I'm gonna pick a radio button group
for the group by widget.
And so that looks like this.
So you pick whichever one you want.
I just gave it a name.
I gave it year, month, day.
And whatever I pick is now the value.
And I was similar for method.
You know, method I chose a different widget.
I chose a select widget for the method.
So we can do mean, max, min.
Okay.
And I think for field, I chose a radio button.
So you can, the departure delay or arrival delay.
So far so good.
These are fairly simple.
Now we wanna put everything together
and we wanna make it interactive.
So we're gonna take our flight pandas or Dask data frame.
And this also works with pandas by the way.
So if you wanna do this with pandas
with a smaller data set, exactly the same.
I'm going to basically make my data frame interactive
using HP plot by just calling dot interactive.
And now I'm calling the new interactive thing iFlights.
Okay.
For reference, this was our earlier pipeline.
I'm gonna use the same pipeline code.
I'm gonna call it iPipeline just because, you know, ting.
But wherever I had a number or a string,
like 2020, day of week, arrival delay, how,
I'm replacing it by my widget names.
Okay.
Now if I run that, now if you look at, oops.
I think I forgot to run this.
Now if I run this, now I have this nice widget thing.
If I change this and you basically,
you can interact with all these things,
but it hasn't done anything.
It just basically is this Dask data frame structure.
And it has a certain number of things.
You can use this as if it was a data frame.
So how did we Dask data frame?
How did we visualize a Dask data frame?
We did dot HP plot.
So I'm gonna do dot HP plot here.
And this is actually gonna chug
because we're gonna use the data frame.
So we're gonna use the data frame.
And this is actually gonna chug because what happens is,
and there's a way to get around this,
but the first time you run this,
it's going to use the default values of all the widgets
and calculate the graph based on the default values.
There is a way to avoid it from calculating
till you choose things, but I'm not gonna go into that.
So this is, you know, calculating, you know,
I guess this would be departure delay max by month.
And now you have this plot that's on the entire dataset
that you now can control with like,
okay, let me change it to day of month.
And it's gonna compute again.
And there are ways to make the compute more efficient.
Like right now I've got a general thing
where I change everything, it recomputes everything,
but you can actually make it more granular,
saying if I'm choosing a widget
that doesn't affect the quantity,
don't recompute that quantity.
There's some, if you use the other techniques,
you can make it more complicated.
But the simple one is simple.
They've got the new plot.
So I'm gonna do the same thing with the airlines.
So here, let's look.
I am grouping by origin, like the origin airport,
and I'm also joining the airport
so I have the latitude longitude, okay?
And if I ran this, you know,
so I'm making a new map plot.
And my map plot is hreplot.point,
slatitude longitude, geotrue.
And you know, if I uncomment,
actually I can uncomment this, I can run this.
Let's do this.
So this will make a new plot which is the map, okay?
And I'm making a couple of plots here
because I wanna show you the other thing.
This is one of the advantages Panel has
over something like Dash or Streamlit,
is a lot of the tools like Dash and stuff
require you to know some JavaScript
or some HTML or stuff to kind of lay things out.
Panel has a very simple,
I mean it has a more complicated templating system,
but it has a very simple row column grid system.
So here, I'm gonna say I want a column
and my first row in the column
is gonna be the date range widget.
The second row, I'm actually going to split it into two
and I'm gonna put the field at the beginning
and then I'm gonna put a column
with group by and method there
and the data and the map I want below them.
And so, yeah, I forgot this takes a long while to calculate.
Oh, that was just a data sort issue.
I think I was using the unsorted data.
So this is what the other plot looks like.
So now here, I'm gonna do the same thing.
Oh, I guess I should have waited
till the other one finished calculating, but okay.
This will show up in a couple of seconds
and it'll take what we did earlier
and rearrange them into a nicer interface.
Yeah, it's just column and row.
So anything you can do, column and row,
you can just very simply lay out
without having to worry about anything.
There is also a, I didn't do this,
but there's a template system
where you can basically have header, sidebar, main
and pop-ups and you can basically say what goes in each.
So you can build little websites pretty easily
without knowing any JavaScript or HTML or anything
and it's got some different template frameworks and stuff.
So you can build little applications like this.
There's actually a website called Awesome Panel
where they kind of show more complicated examples.
Again, this is really slow.
Come talk to my company.
No, there's ways you can do it on your own,
but there's no, like, you know,
Plotly has a enterprise option.
There's no enterprise option around Panel right now.
We've talked about maybe building one, but we, you know.
Okay, so if you look,
this is what it looks like with my layout.
I basically put the date range at the top.
I put the arrival departure here
and then I've got all these plots together
in one nice layout.
Now, the other thing you can do
is at the end of this, you can type .servable.
And if you type .servable,
Panel knows, go ahead.
Yeah, yeah.
So actually Panel is a layout tool
and you can actually mix HP plot,
Matplotlib, Plotly, all the plots
and just use Panel to lay them out.
It also has some ways you can,
really easy to connect the plots together.
So if you zoom on this plot
and you want this plot to update
or if you select something on this plot
and you want this plot to change,
Panel has a lot of tools for that,
but it's actually agnostic to which plotting engine you use.
So kind of like Dash only really works with Plotly,
but Panel, you can have a Plotly plot in here if you want.
And if you, actually.
Yeah, so basically you can look at the reference gallery.
It kind of gives you all these different widgets.
I will quickly do one last demo.
Actually let me, is this still really chugging?
No, it's done, yeah.
Okay, this is another thing which is sort of unique to Panel
which I like a lot because back when I was
in a different federal government agency, I helped fund it.
So it's one of my favorite tools.
I'm not gonna go through the code here,
but this is using Panel's pipeline feature.
So here, I'll just walk you through
what's kind of happening.
Here, I'm making, and this is using the class-based approach
I told you which I wasn't gonna go through.
This is making a class called LaunchDashCluster,
and it has some details in there about some widgets and stuff.
If you look at the top, there's a widget saying
number of workers, it's a range slider,
one to five, stuff like that.
And then here I have my main plot,
and then, actually, hopefully this will run,
but actually I didn't need to do this.
Okay, so this makes this little application for me,
and I'm actually gonna switch,
so this, you can prototype in the notebook.
I made three stages and I've run them here,
but I'm actually going to switch to a terminal.
Okay.
Okay, I'm gonna activate, let's see.
I'm gonna activate my environment.
Okay, so I'm gonna run, so I'm gonna take that notebook
which I had earlier, I think it's called 08 whatever,
and I'm going to panel serve it.
And this will launch the notebook,
and I should be able to get to it.
Let me see.
What was the port?
506.
I don't know what happened.
Okay, give me a second on that,
but in the meantime, if you guys go to here,
you should be able to do this.
Go to hub control panel in the file menu,
and click on dashboards, and you click on,
these are dashboards, we're using a JupyterHub plugin
called CDS dashboards, so you can share dashboards
like the one I just tried to create.
And if we click on this, Noah tides and currents,
this is one my colleague Kim made,
and this is the same three step process
where we have a, this is not using Dask,
but this lets you kind of zoom around
and pick a tide gauge, and then hit next,
and download the data from that tide gauge,
and so you can start building these little wizards
using these tools without knowing any kind of JavaScript
or anything else like that.
So I've got some data, I'm gonna generate a plot,
and then if I hit next, I should have the data set
and a download data button that will let me download the CSV.
So with that, this should also work,
let me see if I can get this, this should be the,
I see, that's the issue, I need to go here.
If this doesn't work, I'm going to stop and,
nope, I don't know why that's not working.
Do I?
Ah, okay.
Well, it's spinning.
Okay, well I'll show it to you in the notebook instead.
That should have come up on that page,
but essentially what it's gonna look like is,
if you look here, let me just make this a little bigger
so you can see it here.
So if you look here, I've basically created a little,
let's pick a number of nodes, let's pick a date range,
and I'm gonna launch Dask, and it found
that I had an existing cluster and connected to it,
and now I'm gonna hit next,
and it's gonna start computing.
Okay.
And so now I've built a little app
that lets you decide what cluster you want,
hit next, spins the cluster up, shows you your plot,
and then hit next and shut down your cluster.
And all of that can be done directly in Python,
in a Jupyter notebook or in a Python file,
without having to deal with what your company's
web development team.
Yep, so now I have my little thing.
I also embedded the notebook, the thing in here,
so if I change something like this,
you'll see it start to compute.
So this should have also come up on this,
but I'm just got the URL slightly messed up.
Oh, here it is, okay, yeah.
So now this is running on its own,
and I'm gonna click launch cluster.
It found an existing cluster.
I hit next.
And same thing I showed in the individual thing.
So this now is a little mini app
that's on the entire data set
that you can share with people.
And you can launch it locally,
or if you use a tool like CDS dashboards,
you can also share it via your Jupyter Hub.
Yeah, it is panel serve.
Yeah, this is, let me make it bigger.
So that particular application I made last night at midnight,
so I don't have the instructions fully there.
I'll improve them.
But basically, panel serve your notebook,
and since we're online, you have to say allow websocket
with our website name, so otherwise,
for security reasons, it won't let it do that.
So let's see, what was I gonna say?
Yeah, so the point with that is anything you make
with HVPlot or panel, if you add .servable,
then if you run that code with panel serve,
it will make it into a website.
So if you write this in a Python file or anything,
you put .servable next to the thing you want to display,
then you can use panel serve
to make it a little web application.
No, it's just one for the whole thing.
Yeah.
Yep, yep.
Again, this is, okay, so I have a blog post
about different ways to do this.
Well, so there are some ways to do it,
because actually, we're not doing it in a single day.
We're doing it in a single day.
So we're doing it in a single day.
Well, so there are some ways to do it,
because actually, I have a colleague
who has connected Bokeh to Dask,
so you can spin off threads and stuff like that.
So this kind of, this .servable panel.serve
is more like I want to share this visualization
with 10, 15 people kind of thing.
Or with Dask, probably, you know,
you were springing up Dask clusters.
If you actually, this is not what you want to use
when you're serving up your website on,
like if you're doing a dashboard that 1,000 people need.
So the use case is very different.
Like one of the reasons why, you know,
one of my previous federal research lab,
we funded some of this work with panel is
most large organizations have this disconnect
between the scientists, engineers, and folks,
and the web team.
And usually what happens is
you need to share something with colleagues,
and they're like, oh, you need to talk to the web team.
Oh, they're busy for six months.
Oh, yeah, now they're gonna rewrite
all your data science code in JavaScript.
And like a year later, you get back a dashboard,
and you're like, wait, that's not what I needed.
So this is about rapid prototyping
and sharing something quickly with folks.
Once you've worked out exactly what this needs to look like,
go ahead and give it to your web team and say,
hey, knock this out the park
and make me something with D3.js and everything for this.
But initial prototyping and exploration,
this is great.
I think the Streamlit and Dash website
can do a lot of things.
Yeah, you can.
Yeah, and I have a blog post.
If you go to the QuantSite website,
you can see a blog post I have about this.
But Streamlit and Dash are very good
for linear single dashboards.
When you have lots of things connected,
so when you have multi-page apps,
when you're building more of an application
versus a dashboard, panel wins.
When you're building more of just a single dashboard
on a single page,
Dash is probably the most scalable
for large numbers of people,
but you have to know JavaScript and HTML
and do callbacks and all that kind of stuff.
So there are pros and cons.
I will go to one last thing quickly,
just so as a concluding thing.
I don't know, I think it's in this one.
Okay, data science platforms.
I just want to leave you with this.
So the interface you've been using right now
is basically JupyterHub.
And with JupyterHub, you can install it yourself.
There's instructions online.
There's lots of different ways to install it.
It can work on everything from HPC to Kubernetes
to your local computer to a single server.
Dash can also be launched lots of different ways.
There's also Terraform scripts.
There's a GitHub repo called DaskHub.
So there's several different ways
to roll your own version of everything we've shown here.
We also have Nibari, which is the platform you use today.
And if you're interested, there's some things here.
It is a set of scripts to install everything for you
and to make it simple to manage.
It's also a reference architecture.
If you want to work out how to install JupyterHub,
Dask Gateway, Argo, look at our Terraform scripts,
customize them the way you want.
There's also some other companies like 2i2c
does something very similar,
but they're mainly focused on the educational space.
They work with universities,
get Dask and Jupyter installed for them.
And then Coiled is a company that very specifically
focused on launching Dask clusters.
Like we're using Dask Gateway, which is an open source product,
and as you see, it can fall down.
Coiled is designed, they don't do all the Jupyter stuff,
but they do Dask very well, and it's a commercial product.
And then Saturn Cloud and others are hosted things
where you just sign up with a credit card
and you can click launch Dask and they do it for you.
So while we did today's stuff on Nibari,
the Dask parts, deploying it can be complicated,
but there's lots of options.
The other tools which we use, like the HP plot and everything,
they can be installed with Pip or Condra.
And we install them with Condra because it works better.
But yeah, so overall, everything I've shown you today
is stuff you can use in your own organizations
and you can get set up pretty quickly.
The biggest difficulty is if you're using Dask in the cloud,
there are issues with how do you get your local environments
to the workers and stuff that solutions like Nibari or Coiled
handle that for you.
If you do it yourself, the simplest way
is to use a Docker image, but then you have to make a Docker image
every time you add a package.
So there are pros and cons there.
So we have about eight minutes left.
I will leave the access open the rest of PyCon
and maybe a day or two after.
So you should be able to run through all these notebooks
on your own and get the full feeling
since we didn't actually get to several of them.
And we shouldn't have that Dask Gateway problem.
Questions?
Thank you all for coming, by the way.
This was our first stress test with this many people.
Go ahead.
I think after the third question,
and I'm really here for my stop here,
but people that I've just been telling you
and you know I made this group, I want to mention
that there is going to be also a DMAX.
And you know, a lot of things that we made
in this project are not from this, not that.
So this is not that.
It's all based on the panel data data.
Nice.
Thank you.
Other questions?
Okay, go ahead.
No, we've been doing all the computations next to the data.
I skipped all this because this is where we have the problems.
I like to say data has gravity.
There's a reason why Nabari works on all the clouds
because we're a consulting company.
And when we go to a company, we can't tell them,
hey, take your 100 terabytes of data and move it to GCP.
It's like, no, your data's on AWS.
We have to run on AWS.
Today we worked with 70 gigabytes of data.
I've worked with five terabytes of data before.
If you are trying to download the five terabytes of data locally,
first, it's going to take forever.
Second, it's going to cost a lot because all the clouds
make it cheap to put data into the cloud,
but make it very, very expensive to take data out.
So even if, like right now, this platform,
this version of Nabari is running on GCP,
the data is also stored on GCS.
If the data was stored on AWS and we used it from GCP,
the performance would still be fine.
We would pay a lot of money because every transfer out of AWS,
they charge you a crazy amount.
Oh, they have what's called egress fees,
and egress fees are massive.
So, yeah, that's why data has gravity.
The old paradigm when Spark and Hive and all these first came out,
the idea was you move the data to your compute.
Now you move your compute to the data
because you do not want to move the data.
It's too expensive. It's too big.
I think I have a lot of colleagues or former people.
I'm from originally OceanMed geospatial type thing,
and a question came up once.
They had free credits on AWS and then they had free credits on GCP,
and it was like, well, we have this much data.
How much would it cost?
It was going to cost like 200,000 to move it from AWS to GCP
and would probably take four or five weeks.
The quickest way would be to AWS and GCP have this option
where they'll ship you hard drives.
Yeah, and then getting the hard drive from AWS
and then shipping it to GCP was going to be really the only way to do it.
So, that's a great question.
So, all this like, you talked about this thing on the right.
Could you talk about that?
Yeah, yeah, this is the Dask lab extension.
Yeah, so all the plots are part of Dask, the Dask thing,
and then lab extension lets you pull those plots into Jupyter.
And there's another set of plots.
Like, if you were using GPUs,
this would actually show you the GPU usage as well.
And actually, that's one of the things I like about Dask
because seeing the compute run
and seeing you can use that dashboard
to understand where your data is breaking.
Like, if you see a lot of red, that's a lot of memory transfer.
And so, it's very, and it also gives you,
when it auto scales up and you suddenly see like all these,
you feel good about it.
Like, you can feel the computer working for you, you know.
Oh, it's the same.
Like, you just choose GPUs and launch GPUs.
You can also use it with CUDA.
Like, there's a Dask CUDA thing,
which, so you can have a cluster of GPUs
and run parallel compute like XGBoost.
There's a Dask XGBoost, so you can,
I would say that most people use Dask
more on the data engineering ETL side.
There's another tool called Ray from AnyScale.
And it has some architectural differences with Dask,
but, you know, that kind of similar
distributed compute frameworks in Python and things.
Ray has better integration with machine learning libraries.
And especially reinforcement learning and stuff like that.
Ray's integrations to those machine learning libraries
is a bit better than Dask's, I would say.
And I'm around the rest of the conference
if anyone wants to chat about Dask or HVPlot
or Nabari or anything else.
Any last questions?
Pardon?
No, well, not exactly.
You'd have to change where you're writing the data to.
Because right now that notebook has some,
so the credentials, none of you guys used storage credentials
because we made it public read.
But that notebook also writes the data to our S3 bucket,
and you don't have credentials for those.
But if you change where it's writing to,
actually don't, because if you try
and write all that data locally, you'll, yeah.
As long as you don't write the data, you can do that.
Or if you provide your own credentials for your own bucket.
Yeah, there's quite a few, actually.
There's CDS dashboards, that's the sharing thing.
So there's the Git extension, the Dask extension,
and we dashboards.
We did enable, there's another one called execute time,
which shows you how long each cell took to run.
We disabled that because it was being a bit finicky.
And then with Nabari, we also have integrated,
so some of the things we've done is,
so Argo workflows is something like Prefect
or Airflow, it's like a workflow management tool.
We have environment managing.
There's also monitoring, which basically will just show you
what's happening on the backend with the graphs,
like as things spin up and spin down.
So this is, Nabari is more like a opinionated Jupiter hub
with integrations already done,
if you want to think of it that way.
Okay, last questions.
Okay, and also actually, if you do go,
one last thing is, on number 10,
there is a feedback form,
if you'd like to give some feedback on stuff,
and I know one of the feedbacks can be Dask Gateway,
it was annoying.
So, yeah, please do that.
This is the first time we've tried running,
we use these tools daily.
And we spin up to very large clusters,
and we do really big data sets.
I think probably we don't have more than 10 or 15 people
hitting it at the same time.
I think this is the first time we've had this many people
hit the Gateway node,
and so that's something we're gonna have to deal with
in an upcoming release.
Thank you.