Okay, good afternoon everyone and welcome to PyCon.
This is the largest conference I've been to in like three
and a half years.
It's very exciting.
So today I'm going to be teaching you all
about data analysis with SQLite and Python.
And for this session I've prepared a very extensive handout
which I'm going to be working through
which is available right now online.
So if you go to SQLite-tutorial-pycon-2023.readthedochs.io,
I'm now regretting not getting a shorter URL for it.
This will give you the exact notes that I'm going
to be working through for the workshop today.
We have two volunteers at the back, Felix and Nick,
who are waving there.
If you get stuck with anything, please put up a hand and one
of them will scoop in and hopefully rescue you.
I'm hoping this should all be quite straightforward.
One of the great things about SQLite in general is
that there are very little things that can go wrong with it.
The development environment you'll be using today should be,
I'm going to regret saying this, should be rock solid
and hopefully won't cause us any problems.
And yes, so the plan for today is we're going to talk
about SQLite and Python and how to use those just straight
out of the standard library.
I'm going to introduce you to Dataset, the tool
that I've been building for the past five years now to help
with sort of data exploration and publishing.
I'll also talk you through SQLite Utils,
which is a library I've been building to make working
with SQLite as productive as possible.
We will publish a database onto the internet.
That's going to be fun.
I'll show you Dataset Lite, which is Dataset running inside
of WebAssembly in a browser, which I still
to this day can't believe that's possible.
And then we'll talk about some advanced SQL topics towards the
end as well and lots of demos and all sorts of bits
and pieces like that.
One thing I'm going to be sort
of tangentially covering is SQL itself.
And that's because I've decided to do this in sort
of board game rules.
And if you've ever played a new board game,
there are two ways you can do it.
You can dissect all of the rules at the very start
and everyone figures them out and then you start playing.
Or you can just start playing and pick up the rules as you go along.
And I'm hoping that we can do that with SQL.
So if you're familiar with SQL, you're going to be fine.
If you're not familiar with SQL,
hopefully you'll be able to pick up bits and pieces as
and when we need them as we go through the tutorial.
So in terms of what you'll need, for the first half of this tutorial,
you will need nothing more than Python 3 running on your laptop,
running on a device.
That's it.
Nothing else.
Everything will be based on things in the standard library.
Once we get past Python, you will need the ability to pip install stuff.
So if you know how to use virtual environments
and if you've got an environment you can pip install into,
you'll be completely fine.
Just in case anyone's not set up for that,
I'm going to be running this tutorial myself using GitHub Codespaces,
which offers a free development environment entirely in the browser.
The thing I love about Codespaces is that if it breaks,
you throw it away and you open up a new one.
So it's sort of ideal for things like tutorials where the last thing
you want to do is get into a state where your development environment
isn't working and now you lose time trying to fix it
when you could be getting on with the thing that you're trying to learn.
So, first a show of hands,
who here has Python 3 running on a laptop and is already happy with that?
Okay.
Is there anyone who doesn't and is going to join me in using Codespaces,
which I'm going to use anyway?
There we go.
We have one.
Fantastic.
Okay.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to start with this repository here.
This is a repository that GitHub themselves shared,
that gives you a really quick way to get into a Codespaces environment
with Jupyter Notebook setup as well.
So I can say, use this template, open in a Codespace,
and this churns away for a few seconds.
It's somewhere it's launching a Kubernetes container and all sorts of stuff,
but I don't really have to care about that.
And now, here we go.
This is a brand new development environment that I can start working in,
at least once it finishes booting up Linux and so forth.
I'll leave that.
Here we go.
Codespaces, Jupyter, problems, output terminal.
There's a animated GIF here that shows the sort of faster version of this
for people who want to try this out themselves.
Now I've got a cursor.
And here we are.
This right here is a full-blown Linux installation with Python
and all of the bits and pieces that I'm going to need.
And I'm going to bump that font size up a lot.
I'll get rid of this.
Let's do export PS1 equals dollar space.
There we go.
So now if I run Python 3, I've got Python 3.10,
which is everything that I should need for the first section of this tutorial.
So I did export PS1 equals and then a dollar in the space.
And that just renames the start of my thing so that when I've got a big font,
I don't have half the screen taken up with the directory path.
So what happens if I run Python?
Oh, just running Python gets me Python 3 as well.
So we're going to start by talking a little bit about SQLite itself.
Does anyone here use SQLite on a regular basis at the moment?
A few people.
I'm going to turn the rest of you into converts.
That's my goal for the day.
So SQLite is a fascinating little piece of technology.
One of the, I think it's often not given the respect that it deserves.
I think part of that's because the name suggests
that it's a lightweight database.
It turns out it's actually named after stalactites and stalagmites.
The LITE wasn't the goal when D. Richard Hitt released the software
in the first place.
But the unique thing about SQLite is it's been around for at least 20 years now.
And it's an embedded database.
It's not like Postgres and MySQL run on service somewhere
and you have to talk them over a network.
SQLite is a C library that you import into your program.
And any time you're talking to the database,
you're actually just making C-based function calls to a file on disk,
which means it's screamingly fast.
Like it doesn't have any of the overhead of sending SQL queries back and forth.
And it's surprisingly powerful in terms of what you can do with it.
There we go.
It's also been built into Python since 2006.
Like this is, and anyone who has installed Python anywhere in the world
actually has SQLite as a database just sat there waiting for them to import
and start using it.
So this is not a new technology in the world of Python by a very long way.
It's not just Python.
It's got bindings for Go and Ruby and Perl and any programming language
you like can talk to SQLite.
And it's also got really strong backwards compatibility to the point
that the Library of Congress has announced that SQLite is one
of the few structured data formats that they consider of archival quality
for the work that they do.
If you put data in a SQLite database, future versions
of SQLite are effectively guaranteed to be able to open it again.
So it's actually just a great default place to put data.
My absolute favorite thing about it, a SQLite database is a file,
like data.db.
It's a file on disk.
It's a single file which will work on any platform.
You can send it over to an ARM machine or a 486 or somebody reported a bug
in data set on some IBM mainframe that I've never even heard of,
but it could run SQLite.
But that single file can hold pretty much anything you could possibly
want to stick in there.
You can put in, it does text and binary data,
integers and floating point numbers.
It's got really good support for JSON.
And the end result is that any data of any size,
anything you could possibly imagine, you could fit it into that single file.
It's almost like a zip file that you can run SQL queries against.
So super, super powerful.
Also, these days the maximum size
of a SQLite database is 2.8 terabytes.
About a year ago it was 1.4 terabytes and then one of the,
someone in the world has a database that's too big for that
and they reported it to the SQLite maintainers who doubled
that maximum size.
So now if you've got less than 2.8 terabytes of data
and a disk big enough to put it, you can stick
that in a SQLite database.
And it also has some very interesting characteristics of its own.
One of my favorite examples of that, there's this essay
on the SQLite database, many small queries are efficient in SQLite,
which points out that with MySQL and Postgres, if you're,
if you've got a webpage with 200 SQL queries on it,
you're in trouble because that's 200 round trips back and forth
to your database server.
With SQLite, 200 SQL queries is 200 function calls.
So actually once you get used to that, you start using it
in a very different way from other databases.
It's okay to have n plus one queries loop through all 200 things
and do an extra query for each one.
That kind of thing just works, which is fascinating.
I'm still, I've been using SQLite for most of my work
for the past five years and I still feel
like I'm not taking full advantage
of this bizarre characteristic of that database.
But let's actually start using it.
So I'm going to suggest we start with an example database.
If you run wget or curl or you click it in the browser
to grab dataset.io slash content.db,
that will give you the SQLite database
that powers the official dataset website.
So this website right here has news and plugins and all sorts
of bits and pieces.
Those are sat there in a SQLite database,
which you can just download right now to start working with it.
And so I'm going to do that in my code space.
Where is it?
There we go.
Let's do wgetdataset.io slash content.db.
Now.
That's a great tip.
Yeah, curl dash capital O will get you, hold on.
I need to shrink my window
so it's not behind my little sticking out.
Curl dash O, will that work for,
they said that without the HTTP, I wonder.
Oops.
I think it didn't work because I already had the file.
But anyway, that will give you a SQLite database.
It's, oh no, I overrode it.
Hang on, let's do that one more time.
Aha, if you do curl without the HTTPS,
it downloads the HTTP redirect page, I think,
which is blank.
HTTPS curl slash slash.
There we go.
And that has given us a 17 megabyte file.
So now I'm going to start playing with it in Python.
We can fire it Python again.
Import SQLite 3.
That's straight out of the Python standard library.
And then to connect to a database file,
you just pass it as the path
to the SQLite3.connect method.
And this gives us a SQLite connection.
Actually, I'm gonna go off script a moment.
The first thing I always do with these things
is I want to see what the tables are
that are present in there.
I can do that by saying select star from SQLite master,
which is the metadata database
that SQLite gives you for free.
Fetch all.
Actually, I think I probably want to do select name
from SQLite master where type equals table.
There we go.
And that right there is a list of all of the tables
in my database.
Oh, we'll do this line here too.
This is the SQLite version function.
This demonstrates that SQLite has functions.
We'll tell you what version of SQLite you're running.
I'm on 3.31.1, which I think is pretty recent.
That's within the last 12 months that release came out.
When I'm doing here, when I call db.execute,
I give it a SQL query.
It gives me back a cursor object.
One of the things you can do with the cursor object
is called .fetch all, which then fetches a list
of all of the rows from that.
And then each of these lists,
each of those rows comes back as a Python tuple.
So I've got a Python tuple with the result
of that single function call right there.
And we can also do this.
So I'm gonna do, the cursor object acts as an iterator.
So you can loop through it directly
and print out each of those rows.
So let's do that now.
There we go.
And again, each of those came back as a tuple.
The column, the database table I'm selecting here
just has three columns.
So we get three values back.
Tupes aren't particularly readable
if you're mucking around trying to figure out
what's going on.
So you can instead say db.row underscore factory equals,
and then give it a factory function
that we used to create the returned objects
from those rows.
SQLite3.row is a built-in mechanism
that gives you a weird sort of half tuple,
half dictionary object that you can work with.
So if I put that in and then do this one again,
oh, now I'm getting row objects,
which that's not crazy useful,
but you can call the dict function on those rows
and get back dictionaries.
So this is a very lightweight way
to start turning those SQL results
into lists of dictionaries,
which you can then start working with really easily.
Let's take this a step further
and actually create a database table of our own.
So SQLite's version of SQL is heavily inspired
by Postgres.
So if you're familiar with Postgres,
a lot of the things you know from Postgres
will work more or less the same in SQLite.
One of the biggest differences with SQLite
is it has a much more restricted set of column types,
which I really love.
When I'm working with databases,
one of my least favorite bits
is when you think to yourself,
should I have the titles of varchar 100
or maybe it needs to be a varchar 255?
All of those kinds of questions.
With SQLite, those just go away.
You can say everything is going to be either,
got a section down at the bottom here,
it's either gonna be text or an integer or a wheel,
which is a floating point number,
or a blob for binary data.
And that's the whole thing.
So it's very, very easy to make decisions
about how we're going to create those tables.
So the table I'm gonna create right now
is one to hold Python PEPs, P-E-P's,
the documents that define how Python works
and how the Python community operates.
And I've just selected the subset.
I'm gonna give them an ID,
a title, author, status, type, created, and body.
We'll see the data for those in a moment.
So I can paste that into here.
And that's created my table.
And if I was to run that table thing from earlier on,
this one here, oh, look at that.
It's showing me rows now.
Let's do dict r for r in.
There we go.
We now have a brand new table at the very end called PEPs.
So now that we've created a table,
we're going to drop some data into it.
I decided it would be more interesting if,
is there a way to hide this navigation, I wonder?
Doesn't look like there is.
I decided it would be more fun
to actually work with real data for this.
So I got GPT-4 to write me a quick function
to turn a PEP into a Python dictionary.
And this is perfect example of the kind of code
that I could have written in two minutes,
but GPT-4 wrote in 15 seconds.
So it saved me a whole minute and a half of time.
So I'm going to paste that function in.
This is my parse underscore PEP function.
And then I'm going to grab a copy
of one of the greatest PEPs of all time,
the Zen of Python by Tim Peters.
Published in 2004, wow, it's nearly 20 years old now.
That's, huh, have to have a birthday party for it next month.
And as you can see, the format of this file
is a bunch of key value pairs at the top,
and then the rest of the file comes afterwards.
So it's very easy to write a parser for it.
I'm going to import URLlib and do this
to get that PEP into a dictionary.
Ooh, did I mean, what happened there?
I'm going to do that.
URLlib has no attribute request.
That doesn't sound right.
Okay, it worked.
I had to change that to import URLlib.request.
So now I've got the contents of that text file.
I just printed out a summary version of it
so that we could see that.
And if I run pass PEP on the Zen,
I've now got a Python dictionary
with keys PEP, title, author, status, type, content type.
So our next step is to insert that into our database.
And this is, we will not be doing much more of this
for the durations tutorial
because my SQLite utils library puts a sort of layer
of syntactic sugar over the top of this.
But generally, when you're working with SQLite,
the way you run queries like this is you have,
the query is a string with placeholders
for the values that you want to inject into that.
And then you pass those values
as a list or tuple afterwards.
So in this case, we want to insert
into the ID, title, author, status, type,
created body columns, the values
that we got back from that PEP.
The reason we do it like this
is to avoid SQL injection problems
where if we tried to glue the string together
with double quotes or single quotes,
inside of those values might have interfered with that
and broken our SQL.
So you should always parameterize queries in this way
anytime you're working with data from another source.
So here we go, I'm gonna paste that in.
And now we should have a PEP in our database.
Let's run select star db.execute,
select star from PEPs.fetchall.
And we'll wrap that in a dict.
And there it is, our PEP is now inside
of our SQLite database, which is kind of cool.
That was a pretty lightweight way
of getting that data into a format where we can query it.
I do want to demonstrate another,
an alternative way of doing these parameters.
Here we had to put question marks
and then pass things in as a sequence.
You can also use colon syntax for named parameters
and then pass a dictionary directly to c.execute as well.
So I'm going to delete that file.
I'll delete the PEP that I just inserted,
check that's been deleted.
Yep, the SQL query there failed to retrieve it.
So for triple, so the question is,
when do you use triple quotes versus single?
So triple quotes let you split your string
over multiple lines.
That's the only difference between triple quotes
and single quotes is you get multi-line strings.
And I find just SQL queries, it's more readable
if you can see it spread across multiple lines
than if it's just a single line.
Okay, I'm going to run that again.
And once more, we've inserted our, so we've now inserted
that dictionary directly into that query
and we've inserted it back into our table.
The interesting, an interesting thing
about SQL is that to be honest, there's very little
that you need to know in order
to use it productively.
We've done create table, that's obviously important.
You need to create tables to put your data in.
We've seen what an insert looks like.
There are two more things to know.
There's updates and deletes.
So an update is a way of updating an existing row.
In this case, I'm going to think the row
that we've got right now has Tim Peters as the author.
Let's see, pet.keys.
So yeah, it's got Tim Peters with his email address.
I'm going to update that to remove the email address.
I'll do that by pasting this in here.
There we go.
And now if I do db.execute, select author from paps.fetchall
dict.
And you can see that now I've updated the author
to be Tim Peters instead of Tim Peters with the Gmail address.
This example here does use one other trick.
SQLite is a relational database that supports transactions.
So you can bundle up changes in a block of code
and then make them all available at once
to other people who might be querying that database.
And there's a nice little thing in the Python SQLite module
where you can use the context manager and say with db colon
and then anything indented inside of that block
will be run inside the same transaction.
So this is a good habit to get into
when you're making modifications to a database
because it means that you don't really have to think very hard
about how transactions are working.
You just sort of stick to this pattern
and everything should work okay.
The update there, I'm saying update paps
set author equals blah where id equals blah
and again, using those placeholders.
So this ends up being update paps set author to Tim Peters
where the id is 20.
The width is not.
No, the width there is the, that's the Python context manager.
If you were using SQL, I think you'd do commit semicolon
but to be honest, I've never done it in Python
because I always use this mechanism instead.
And then finally, to run deletes, very similar.
Delete from paps where id equals question mark.
So I'm going to delete row 20.
And having done that, now if I run that query again,
I don't get back any records.
And if you want, you can delete with where clorys
and delete everything and things like that as well.
But this, what I find, what I like about this is
that we've basically covered 90% of the data manipulation language
aspect of SQL that we need to care about.
You create tables, you insert rows into them,
you update them, you delete them.
Almost everything else you do will be in the much more rich
and complicated area of writing selectively.
And that's the bit that we'll be applying board game rules to
and picking up bits and pieces of that as we go along.
So this is because when you have question marks in your query,
that's saying that you're going to pass a list of parameters to it.
And in this case, normally, most of the time,
we've used multiple question marks.
So it makes sense to pass a list of multiple ones.
You know what?
This will work without being in a list.
I've not actually tried.
Let's see.
It's purely out of habit.
You absolutely could do that in this case
where ID equals 20 would work fine.
But then you're getting to a stage where, okay,
do we start gluing strings together to construct that SQL query,
which is a dangerous pattern because if you do
that with non-integers, you might end up accidentally injecting bits
of SQL you didn't mean to into your query.
And I mentioned transactions earlier.
We, oh, hold on.
Oh, no, that is working.
If you're interested in exploring transactions a little bit further,
there's an exercise here where you can see how those transactions are only
visible to other processes after they've been committed.
I'm going to skip over that now because I think it's more fun
to get onto the next section.
So that's Python SQLite.
Oh.
Exactly. Yes.
Yeah, oh, that's a really good point.
Yeah. One of the interesting things about transactions is you can have
multiple connections to a SQLite database
from within the same Python program and changes in one will only be visible
to the others after you've committed those transactions.
Let's do something a whole lot more fun.
I'm going to, I'm going to drop us out of regular Python and we're going
to start using the tool that I've been building
for the past few years called Dataset.
So the way you install this is you run pip install Dataset.
Or if you prefer pipx, you can use pipx.
There's home group packages.
There are many different ways that you can install it.
Pip install Dataset will work just fine for the most part.
And having done that, you get a new command called Dataset.
Oh, hold on.
Let's do Dataset version just to make sure that worked.
There we go.
So I've just installed Dataset version 0.64.2.
So Dataset is a command line utility that starts a web server running
against a SQLite database.
In this case, we're going to say Dataset content.db and hit enter.
And this will then start a web server running on port 8001.
And in GitHub Codespaces, it has a feature where it spots when that happens
and gives you the option to open that in a new tab.
So this is one of the reasons I love GitHub Codespaces.
It makes all of this stuff work.
And so now, I click that URL and I've now got access to Dataset.
Except, huh.
I was expecting this to break, actually.
I just remember that there's one extra step that I need to do.
But we'll continue.
And if it breaks, I'll fix it when that happens.
So this right here is the Dataset web application.
By default, it gives you an interface to explore any SQLite database
that you care to give it.
So this is our content database that we've been working with.
And whereas previously, we were running code inside of Python
and sort of squinting at lists of strings, now we can scroll down
and see all of the tables that are in that database.
Oh, there's our Peps table, except it hasn't got any data in it.
That's annoying because I deleted the data and forgot to put it back.
So I'm going to pop back to Codespaces.
I'm going to run Python again.
Oh, this is frustrating.
Drop in my past Pep thing.
Go.
Import urllib.request.
db equal import SQLite3.
3.connect.
What was it called? Content.db.
And now I can run this thing here,
and we should be back to where we started.
There we go.
OK.
So now if I run data on content.db again,
this time I forgot to commit.
I forgot to commit my change to the database.
You know what? I'm going to leave that.
And if you didn't delete the data, then you should have that row
in your local database as well.
But I've got all of these other tables.
So these right here are the tables that power the official data set website.
One of the most interesting tables in there is one called repos,
which is all of the...
Aha.
So the reason I got that error is I forgot to install one additional plugin.
This should be in the documentation.
Yes, in GitHub Codespaces, there's an additional plugin
you need to install to make sure you avoid those kinds of errors.
That's this one here, data set install, data set-codespaces.
And having done that, now...
This should...
Here we go.
So this right here is a database of all of the GitHub repositories
that form the overall data set project.
And it's 158 because there's a lot of different plugins and tools
and associated things like this.
The data in here is actually created by another tool I wrote called
GitHub to SQLite, which can import data from your GitHub account
and use it to populate a SQLite database.
And this is a pattern that I use a lot.
If you go to the data set website and look in the tools database,
you will find things like Swarm to SQLite and Apple Notes to SQLite
and GitHub to SQLite.
Because once you realize how flexible SQLite is,
you kind of want everything in your life to be in it
so that you can run queries against it and join it against things
and run data set against it.
So I've spent the last few years accumulating all sorts of weird
little tools that will take things from some API or some source
of information and stick them in a SQLite database
so I can then start using them with data set and other tools like that.
I've actually got one in here called Genome to SQLite,
which can import a copy of your genome into a SQL database,
which means I know what color my eyes are with a SQL query,
which is super useful, really exciting.
But yeah, so we're going to grab another database for the next section.
I'm going to...
Uh-huh?
So I don't have a route to go from here to Postgres yet,
but I have a route to go in the other direction.
So I have a tool I wrote called db2sqlite,
which uses SQL Alchemy and could be pointed at a Postgres or MySQL
database and will create a SQLite database as a backup of those databases.
And I've got a demo I'll show you later on where I've done exactly that
with a Postgres database that I do a lot of work with.
So we're going to grab one more database.
We're going to grab this one here.
This is a database of congressional legislators.
It's people who are Congress people or senators or presidents
and vice presidents.
It's this wonderful open source project where people have been gathering
information on how Congress has been structured right back to 1793, I think.
So if you're building demos for database software, this is absolute...
This is absolute...
An absolute gold mine.
And what we're going to do again is we're going to grab a link to that database.
This one is just 5.2 megabytes.
And you know what?
I'm going to open up an additional terminal so I can leave data
set running.
Export PS1.
There we go.
So I'm going to grab that as well.
And then I'm going to restart data set to run against my new legislators database.
So having done that, I've now got...
Oh, what happened there?
Surprising.
Here we go.
So I've now got a content database and another one called legislators.
And that's got tables for legislators and executives, that's presidents and vice
presidents, and when they were in office and their names and their birthdays and
all sorts of bits and pieces like that.
It's a really fun example database for playing around and learning things like
SQL.
So in a moment, we'll...
Yeah, that's a good one.
So for the next step, if there's a link from this document here to one of the
official data set tutorials, which effectively introduces data set in the
data set interface in terms of this congressional legislators data.
You're welcome to run this on your own copy of the database.
You can also go straight to the hosted copy of the database here as well if you
haven't managed to download that file.
And this will take you through a whole bunch of useful features of data set
itself. So I'll review that right now.
One of those features is that data set will give you a table of data and you
can do things like sort that by district or...
Actually, it probably makes more sense to sort by start date.
So I can sort start date, sending.
I can see that in this database here, we've got 44,000 legislative terms.
The earliest was 1789 when the anti-administration party had...
That's a fun first party for America.
That feels...
Oh, there's the pro-administration party as well.
So Richard Bassett right here.
Now, you'll notice that this is a table, but that right there is a hyperlink.
The Richard Bassett...
Richard Bassett, there is a link through to another page.
And this is using a SQLite feature of foreign keys, which are defined
in this... When you create a table, you can say that a column references
another column on another table.
Data set notices that and it turns those things into hyperlinks.
So this is getting in the sort of relational part of relational databases
where data can link through to other data.
Let's see if we sort the other way.
I'm trying to find a legislator who's a bit more interesting.
Wow, these are all one term legislator. Here we go.
So this one here, Jake Alayze, is actually referenced from two other tables.
They're referenced from legislator terms and they're also referenced
from a social media table because we've got a table of data here
that tells us what their Twitter account is.
But this is a very important concept in databases in general
and in data sets specifically, the idea to link these records together
so that you end up with more of a sort of graph of data that you can start
traversing between and really understanding how these things are all
related to each other.
My absolute favorite feature of data set is something called faceting.
And that gives... That's the ability to spot columns like the type column
and the state column and say, you know what?
Of these 40... We've got 44,000 rows here, but it's kind of interesting
to count them based on the value in a specific column.
So if we look at states, we'll see that New York has had 4,189
of these legislative terms and is the... Presumably because it's one
of the oldest states. It's the state that's had the...
Well, also it's going to be the number of Congress people they get
in their... For their state, isn't it?
We can look at like representative versus senator.
So then I can drill down and say, you know what?
Just show me the senators from Massachusetts.
And then I can say, you know what?
Let's facet by party as well and see that the state of Massachusetts
in the Senate has had 38 terms served by Republicans, 32 by Democrats,
11 by Whigs. That pro-administration party from other one shows up.
But the key thing about this is that when you're faced with 44,000 rows
of data, it can be kind of difficult to know what to do next.
You know, okay, great. I've got 44,000 rows.
My favorite thing to do with it is to start digging into it using
these facets and saying, okay, well, what can we learn about the data
at the macro level based on slicing and dicing it in different ways?
That's exactly what I've done here. I've just found out something about
the state of Massachusetts Senate population based on clicking a few
different lengths. You'll notice there's...
This interface at the top here is pretty much exactly what you would
expect it to be. This is a query building interface.
So you can select a column like state and say you want it where state
equals MA, where type equals Sen. You know what? I'm going to say where...
Is there a name in here? I'm going to say where party
contains...
Let's do Rep.
And that's given us back party, the Republican Party, the Democratic
Republican Party, the Independent Republican Democrat Party, and the Liberal
Republican Party... And the Liberal Republican Party as well.
So you can use this interface to build up pretty complicated filters
onto your data.
Does it... What's that?
Yes, it runs the full query. So if you scroll down, it's showing you
all of the rows that match those criteria. And then if it was on multiple
pages, which this one isn't, so let's get rid of that.
The query builder...
No.
It doesn't... It would be useful if it could autocomplete things.
That's not a feature that I've figured out yet.
Here's where things get really fun. You can export this data back out again
in multiple different formats. So if you want a CSV file of the Republican
Party candidates from the state of Massachusetts, you can click CSV.
And there's that data with CSV ready to be loaded into Excel or
Tableau or things like that. You can also get it back out as JSON.
This right here is that data that we were just looking at as a...
And in fact, I think if I do raw data and then pretty print,
you can see this is JSON data here, which is specifically set up so that
you can pull it into JavaScript or Python applications running elsewhere.
So you've effectively... This interface here is actually an API.
In fact, everything in data set works like that. If you can see it
in data set, you can get it out as JSON as well.
And so when you start looking at the URL, you realize that,
okay, now we've got an API where we can specify in that URL that we want
people from California, for example. And so now if I'm hitting that from
JSON, I've got an API here where I can say, you know what?
Instead of California, let's do Florida. And now I'm getting things back
from Florida. So this is effectively a very powerful API interface onto
anything that you can fit in a SQLite database, which as we discussed
earlier is everything. There was nothing that you could not stick in
a SQLite database, put up online with this interface on top,
and then start doing API automations against it.
So we've talked about facets and we've talked about filters.
So at the moment, the only way to get data into data set is to have it
as a SQLite database. So if your data is in some other form,
you'll need to write tools to get it into SQLite. If it's in Postgres
or MySQL, you'll have to export it out as a SQLite database file.
I've been experimenting with ways of getting data set to talk to other
databases directly. There's actually someone in the data set community
built a DuckDB plugin, which Monkey patched it around so that you could
run it against DuckDB as well. I haven't committed to this as a feature
yet because building software that speaks to multiple databases slows
you down a lot, you know, in terms of you have to test it against all
of the databases and write features twice and so forth. But I'm thinking
it might happen maybe for data set 2.0, which I hope to work on in the next
sort of 12 to 18 months.
Well, we'll get into that in a little bit. For more advanced stuff,
you actually end up writing your own SQL queries directly in the data set
interface. And I'll jump into it. You know, we can jump into that right now.
This is quite a good point for that. So right here, we're looking at
954 rows where the party contains rep and the state equals CA.
And if I click view and edit SQL down here, it will switch me into an
interface where I can see that underlying SQL query. Let's click format
SQL to tie that up a little bit as well. So now it's exactly the same data
coming back, but we're now in a situation where we can start editing that
SQL query. And so I can actually make changes to it. I can say,
you know what, I don't care about those columns or that one or those.
I just want those ones right here. And click run. And now I get back
that subset of columns that I've defined in that SQL query. And I can then say,
you know what, let's do, instead of rep, we'll do dem. The percentage symbols
there are because we're using a like operator. And the like operator does
wildcard matching. So here we're saying wildcard match where the party column
contains any number of characters, dem any other number of characters at the
end. Why are these ends? Oh, that's because end, I believe, is a reserved
word in SQLite. So if you take the square brackets, oh, okay, I was expecting
that to break. I think if the column was called select, it would definitely
break. So data set plays it cautious. And if it thinks something's a reserved
word, it escapes it. And actually, you can escape it using double quotes
or you can escape it using square brackets. I've been a bit inconsistent
in using both of them. I should probably just stick to the double quotes
in that case.
Yes, which is just messy. That's unnecessary. In this particular case,
I could get rid of these and it would work just fine.
So that there is because this is the named parameter trick that we used
earlier on with the insert query. What we're saying here is that I want
party to be like something called P0 and I can actually change that to be
party. And I want state to be like colon state. And data set then notices
that those are there and it adds them as form fields at the bottom.
So a trick that you can do with this, which is kind of fun, is that this
actually becomes a way of building little custom applications for people.
There's a hide button at the top that hides the SQL query. And so now,
if you've got a friend who desperately wants to be able to look at...
And let's get rid of this one here. So just where state equals state.
So if you have a friend who desperately wants lists of legislators from the
state of cap from any state they like, you can send them this bookmark,
like literally copy and paste that URL, send it to somebody else and when
they land on it, they'll get this page here with a form field where they
can change CA to FL and to run the query again. I kind of think of this
as a way of building entire interactive database applications as a bookmark.
And so it's something you can share on Slack or you can send somebody
a message or email. And it's a really fun and powerful way of working
with data, especially in a collaborative environment. Data set, the initial
inspiration for this was data journalism. I was working for newspapers where
we were dealing with all kinds of weird and interesting shapes of data.
And you want to make that available to the reporters in the newspaper
so that they can look at the latest COVID figures or look up what
some senator has been doing, things like that. And so the idea here was
to have a few people in the newsroom who know enough to load data
into this system and sort of construct these secret queries. And then everyone
else just walks off a bookmarks. If somebody says, hey, have you got
the latest COVID numbers for New York? You can send them a link.
And when they click that link, they will get that data come back at them
in this format. As before, as with the table view, you can get the stuff
out of CSV and you can also get the stuff out as JSON. So what we've
got here, which is kind of fascinating, is we've got a...
We have an API. Where's the wrap option?
I totally messed that up, haven't I?
Here we go. This right here is a JSON API that takes an argument
of SQL equals and then takes a SQL query. So effectively, we've built
a JSON API that a JavaScript application can use to run SQL queries directly
against a database, which... Oh, that's fun. Copilot's trying to suggest what...
Wow. GitHub Copilot just guessed that the response of that would be
the Federalist Party in Florida. That's quite a surprising completion it pulled
off there. But yes, so we've built an API that you can send SQL through,
which for most developers will tell you that this sounds like an appallingly
bad idea. In web application security, there's a concept of a SQL injection
vulnerability where people can use tricks to run their own SQL against your
database. And normally, you don't want that at all. But Dataset was specifically
designed for a world in which you're publishing entire databases. So you don't
mind if people can query any of it because that was the whole point.
You wanted to put that data out there. And everything... The SQL queries are run
against read-only databases. They can't cause any damage to them. And there's
also a one second time limit that's enforced on those queries, which means
despite this being a wildly unexpected thing to do, having an endpoint that
people can just run their own SQL queries against is both safe and really
flexible. I started building... I built some applications when I worked at
Eventbrite a few years ago. I built an application that used this in JavaScript
basically as a joke. I was trying to wind up the other developers at the
company by saying, hey, look, I used JavaScript to glue together a SQL query.
Only it turned out it was just a really productive way of working,
especially for rapid prototyping. So I've ended up building all sorts of software
on top of this since then. And I'll show you a much more advanced example of
that in a moment. But yeah, so that's the core of the Dataset web application.
It's got tables in it. You can browse those tables. You can filter them and
facet them and explore them in that way. You can get the data back out as
JSON or CSV. And actually, this one here is running a plugin called Copyable,
which lets you get the data back in all sorts of other formats too.
If you're writing an academic paper and you need a LaTeX table of all
of the... What is this? The Florida representatives since 1821,
you can click that. You can click the LaTeX button and copy and paste
this right back out again. Actually, I use the GitHub one here all the
time because it lets you get things out as a markdown table that's formatted
for GitHub issues. But let's jump back to the demo that I was running just
off my own machine. And I'm gonna install... I'm gonna demonstrate plugins
a little bit more. Hang on a second. What's happening there?
My Ctrl C shortcut isn't working.
Okay, I killed that. I'm gonna say... Oh, it's because I switched out
of Dvorak mode. That's why that wasn't working. So I'm gonna say Dataset...
I'm gonna say Dataset install. Now, I'm going to install a new plugin
called Dataset-ClusterMap. So Dataset is very, very heavily reliant on
plugins. There are 115 plugins available at the moment in the Dataset
plugin directory. And as an open source maintainer, one of the things I love
about this is that people can add new features to my software without me
even having to talk to them or even review a pull request. I can wake up
in the morning and somebody has shipped a new Dataset plugin that adds
some kind of feature and I have nothing to do with it at all,
which is so liberating in terms of me getting to see my software expand out
in interesting ways. A lot of the work I do around Dataset is writing plugins
myself because the beautiful thing about plugin is that if it's rubbish,
it doesn't harm the purity of the core project. I can have a weird idea
for a feature, knock out a very quick poorly constructed plugin to try it
out and then iterate on that over time and figure out if that's what I really
wanted to do. Dataset-ClusterMap is one of the... I think it might even be
the very first plugin that I ever wrote and you can install it by saying
Dataset-Install-Dataset-ClusterMap and that's actually the same thing as running
pip install Dataset-ClusterMap. The reason I have a Dataset-Install command
is it makes absolutely sure that the plugin gets installed in the same
virtual environment as Dataset itself. So if you install Dataset through
Homebrew or pipx, it'll go in the right place and you won't have to think
about how to install it. So I'll run that plugin, run that installer.
I can type Dataset-Plugins to see a list of available plugins and this says
I've got Dataset-X-Forwarded-Host, Leaflet-Codespaces and Dataset-ClusterMap
is the one that I just installed. Now if I run Dataset-Legislators again,
what this plugin does is it looks out for any table that has a latitude
and longitude column on it and if it finds one of those, it draws them
on a map. And so in this case, the offices table, this is the congressional
offices of all of these different legislators, has latitude and longitude
and so the plugin kicks in and it draws this map at the very top
of the page. And again, straight away we see some interesting things.
What's this one here? This is... Is this American Samoa maybe?
This is one of those far, far out tiny bits of the United States,
but there's a congressional office there, so instantly that pops right up.
You can see that Hawaii's got three, all of them in Honolulu it looks like.
And is it... Was it Puerto Rico is the other one over here?
Oh no, that's not Puerto Rico, that's the US Virgin Islands.
One of the fun things about playing with these tools is I always learn
new things about the world just through little things that pop up
while I'm doing demos. Yeah, so that's a... I think that's a...
It's a good example of the thing I'm trying to get to with these plugins.
Like my ideal for plugins is that they'll grow more and more abilities
like this one, where they can look at your data and say,
oh, that's interesting. This appears to be mentioning countries.
I could draw a heat map or this is latitude and longitudes or
all sorts of things like that. And I think there's a lot of scope
for really interesting data exploration features that are built around this
idea of plugins that you can run in data set that then get exposed
to your data. We talked about exporting data.
It's also worth noting that you can export the current page of data
that you're looking at. So if I'm looking at legislator terms,
I can get out, I think it's 100 records at a time.
Or if you scroll to the bottom of the page, you can click stream all
rows on the CSV export. And this will actually generate a CSV file
with everything, with all 45,000 rows in it. And I just clicked on that.
I think it's gonna open in numbers. Here we go.
So now I've exported the full 44,551 rows from that table in a format
where I can load it into any other tool that knows how to open
a CSV file. Oh, yes. No, that's a good call. It's worth talking about
primary keys in SQLite. So when you create a SQLite table,
you can give it a primary key. So you can say, this one's got an
integer primary key, for example. But I think some of these,
this one here does not have a primary key at all. It's got a
legislature ID, type text, et cetera, but it's missing that primary key.
And this is a SQLite specific feature where if you don't specify
primary key, SQLite will add one called row ID that's essentially an
incrementing, it's an automatically incrementing number. So this is kind
of convenient when you're just sort of quickly importing data. You don't
have to think about if it's got a primary key or not. You can import
it in and SQLite will automatically assign a unique identifier climbing
from one going up and make it available as that row ID. And when you
do select star, I think select star will not give you the row IDs,
but if you do select row ID, star, then you can see that column. So it's
a bit of a weird column and then it's hidden from select star. But if
you know about it and you know how to call it, you can get it
back in. And data set knows about this row ID thing and so it will
automatically include the row ID in situations where there isn't a defined
primary key.
Now, we sort of touched a little bit on that next, on the next sort of
tutorial segment, which is the idea that the data set is actually a really
useful tool for learning SQL itself. And this is one of the reasons I don't
plan to spend a great amount of time on sort of SQL fundamentals today,
is that a lot of the stuff that you need to do with SQL, you need to know
about creating tables, inserting and updating data, and then you need to be
able to start running select queries. But data set will do a lot of that
work for you, right? It will let you say, you know what, I want everything
where this and this and this. And then clicking on that view and edit SQL
button will get you into an interface where you can see how that SQL query
was working. So, and I've heard from a few... There's a couple of universities
that I've heard from who are now using this as part of their sort of
database education, because it's just a really quick way for the students
to start exploring data and getting a feel for what relational databases
feel like, and then dipping then... Starting to dip into SQL as and when
they want to get the hang of that. So, we'll talk about some advanced
SQL tricks in a little bit, but for basic SQL, you can get a very
long way just noodling around in data set with the filters and then seeing
what query that generated. So, I think we'll... So, this tutorial here,
this is the Learn SQL with data set tutorial. This goes into a little
bit more detail. So, this will talk about select from where order by
limit, the sort of key areas of a SQL query. And there's a bit of
material here as well about the named parameters that we talked about,
where you can say, you know, where start like colon P0 and type equals colon
P1, and then feed those in as separate fields. And there's a little bit
about SQL like queries and joins in here as well. You know, I think we
probably should talk about joins in a little bit more detail, because that's
something we're going to see again later on. Does... Is anyone here super
happy and comfortable joins and left joins and right joins things all the
time? I'm not putting my hand up either, because I still have to look...
I'll be honest, I don't think I've ever used a right join in my entire
career. And SQLite itself only grew right join support like six months
ago maybe, because everything you can do with a right join, you can do
with a left join and so on and so forth. But we'll review the most basic
kind of join just to make sure that we've seen what one of these looks
like. And the problem that we want to solve here is that we've got this
table of executive terms. So, this is saying that there was the president
from 1789 to 1793 was from this party and it was executive ID equals one.
That right there is a reference to another table. So, I can say select
star from executives where ID equals one and say that that means George
Washington. So, we've got a reference to George Washington in this table and
we've got details about George Washington here, but it would kind of be
nicer if we could see the name George Washington in the table that we're
looking at right there.
Ah, that's a great call. This right here is not an assignment.
This is a... It would be nicer if it was equals equals.
Exactly. Yeah. This in Python terms, this is select star from executives
where ID equals equals one. Unfortunately, SQL is not designed like that.
So, SQL confuses equals as assignment with equals as comparison.
You could actually, yeah. So, I could say where that equals colon ID and then I
could stick a one in here and that'll have the same effect.
So, we want to see George Washington's name on this table right here.
And the way we're gonna do that is we're going to do a join. So, I'll copy and
paste this query in here so we can explore it. So, first we'll run that and
you'll see that now we've got the same data we had before, but instead of
executive ID, we have a name and the name is that information pulled in from
that other table. Maybe we could do select star instead to see if that...
So, if I do select star, I now get back everything from both tables.
So, I'm seeing the executive terms columns that we saw earlier and then I'm
saying all of that stuff from the executives table. And the way this works
is through what's called a join. I can say where we're selecting from the
executive terms table and we're joining against the executives table on executive
terms dot executive ID equals executives dot ID. This is the structure of a join.
You say this table and this table are gonna get combined together and the way
we're gonna do it is on this criteria, the on criteria, saying anything where
the ID in executives matches the executive ID in executive terms.
These, you can actually nest, you can do multiple joins against multiple tables.
There's a lot more sophistication to this, but most of the time I find that
I'm using the most basic kind of join. I think this is called an inner join
or I just call it a join. But it gives us what we want, right?
This gives us the ability to start saying, let's combine
party and then executives dot name.
And when you're constructing queries like this, you can leave the tables off
in this bit here, but then it gets kind of confusing because when I look at
this, it's kind of like an import star in Python. I don't instantly know which
table these different things came from. So personally, I like to always include
the full table names. So I'll do that dot that dot that dot that dot that
and then executives dot name there. And that gives us the exact same results.
It's just easier to read that query and understand how it works and what it's
doing. That's surprising. I don't know why my... Oh, my format button is
gonna confuse by end being a reserved word.
But yeah, so that's... Honestly, this... I recommend if you want to spend...
If you're not familiar with SQL, I recommend spending a little bit more time
with this document. But as you can see, it's relatively straightforward and hope...
And we'll get into the more advanced SQL stuff in a little bit,
but it's a pretty clean language to start working with. Something I really like
about SQL is that when I started learning to be a programmer nearly 25
years ago now, I learned a whole... I learned Perl and PHP and SQL and action
script, all sorts of different bits and pieces. SQL is the one thing I learned
25 years ago that's still serving me today. I feel like it's one of those
skills which kind of like bash on Linux, pick it up once and it will be paying
for itself for decades to come. So... And I mean, as somebody who writes
software around SQL, I have some bias here, but I do think it's worth spending
time with SQL and getting to a point where you're really comfortable and
familiar with it, because it will apply to SQLite, but also so many other
technologies as well you can then tap into. And the syntax for basic select
statements is effectively the same across all of the different database engines.
Let's get into something else. Let's start to... So I've shown you a bunch
of stuff so far that assumes that you've got data in SQLite already. If your
data is in SQLite, then you can run data set against it and you can do all
of these things and that's super fun. But obviously the vast majority of data
in the world is currently not in SQLite, which is something that I'm on a
one-man quest to try and fix. But so the other major project I've been working
on for the past two years is a tool called SQLiteUtils. So this tool here,
it's up to version 3.30, so you can see I've shipped a lot of changes and fixes
to this over the years. And SQLiteUtils is two things in one. It's a command line
interface, it's a CLI tool, and it's a Python library for manipulating SQLite
databases. The specific problem I'm trying to solve with it is what is the
fastest way to get from here's some data to now that data's in SQLite and I can
start running queries against it. And so you install it exactly the same way as
data set. It's a pip install or pipx or brew or various other things like that.
I'm going to do that in here. Actually let's fire up another shell again. Here
we go.
Export. I need to figure out how to set this up as the default. There we go. Okay,
so I'm going to do pip install SQLiteUtils and this will give me a Python
library that I can import but it also gives me a new command called SQLite-Utils.
I'll run a version on that. There we go, I've got version 3.30 of that
installed now. And what we're going to do is we're going to use this to create
ourselves a brand new database from a new set of a new data source. This is
following another of the official data set tutorials. We're going to take a look
at data about manatees in Florida and specifically where manatees have
come a cropper, manatee carcass recovery locations. This is data put out by the
Florida Fish and Wildlife Conservation Commission and they have been collecting
information on where dead manatees have shown up since April of 1974. So there's
50 years of manatee carcass locations represented in this CSV file.
And it's got 14,341 records in it. It's available to CSV. I've actually got a
copy of that that I archive just in case they change their file format, which
we can download from here. So I'm going to right click on this, copy link, and
then back in here. I'm going to do wget of that. So this is giving me the file
manatee carcass recovery locations in Florida.csv. It's a 2.7 megabyte file.
Next, I'm going to load that into a SQLite database using the SQLite-Utils tool.
So, I wonder if there's a way I can pin this so it's easier to find. So I'm going
to run a command, SQLite-Utils insert, because we're inserting data. I'm going
to create a new database file called manatees.db. I'm going to create a table
called locations. I'm feeding it the path to that file. And then at the end,
I'm saying, this is CSV data. And then dash D means try and figure out the types
of that data. So if a column looks like it's all integers, treat that as an
integer column. If you don't do that, you'll get everything as strings,
which isn't quite as useful. Nulls. So this is the problem with CSV is that
a null and a blank string are completely indistinguishable. So SQLite-Utils will
always import them as blank strings. If you want to then turn them into
nulls later, you have to do that yourself. This is one of the reasons I prefer
JSON over CSV as a way of passing this data around, because JSON does have
nulls. It has nulls, a floating point number, and JSON is represented as a
floating point number. It's generally, I think, better. But most of the data in
the world is published as CSV, so we have to have tooling for working with that.
So we now have a file called manatees.db. It's 5.4 megabytes. And I'm going to open
that up in dataset as well. Yes. So that's in this tutorial here. It's SQLite-Utils
insert manatees.db locations. So that's the command, the database file, the table.
This is the name of the CSV file. And then at the end, I'm saying treat this as a
CSV file and do the type detection as well.
That's a great question. Is there a user-friendly interface for SQLite? Or are you
stuck in the command line? There are many. One of the great things about SQLite is
it's been around for 20 years. And so there are Windows apps and Mac apps and GUI apps.
And there are dataset plugins that actually add the ability to upload CSV files
directly into dataset as well. So there's lots and lots of different options for
this. I tend to do most of my analysis on most of my data manipulation on the
command line because I like that I can automate it. So I can figure out a recipe
that works for manipulating data in a certain way. And then I can stick that in a
bash script. Or a lot of the work I do, and I'll show some examples of this later
on, is in GitHub actions. So I have GitHub actions automations that download data
from here and then convert it and then do this and clean it up and all of that kind
of stuff. But yeah, so SQLite utils, you can actually use in a Jupyter notebook as
well, which I'll demonstrate in a moment. But I kind of, there's an aspect of this
where I'm enjoying the intellectual challenge of coming up with a command line
interface version of every Python method that I'm writing. So a lot of this is me
just having fun trying to explore the intersection of command line tools and
Python libraries. Oh, let's run a different command actually. We're going to do
SQLite utils schema, manatees.db. And that dumps out the schema. So we can see the
schema of that database that we just created. And actually looking at that
scheme is kind of interesting because you see things like there's an X and a Y
column that are floating point. There's a lat and a long column that are floating
point as well. So we've got potentially four different ways of representing those
locations. But it's better to fire it up in data set itself. So here is that table
that we just imported. It's got 13,000 rows in it. And it's a table. And as with
all tables, it's kind of boring when you first start looking at it. You know, it's
got these X and Y columns, the year that they were found, the state, the county,
mortality. This is an interesting one. We can facet by that and see the most
common reasons that a manatee meets their end. And unsurprisingly, it's
watercraft collisions. That's taken 2,700 manatees in the state of Florida.
Cold stress beginning in 1986, 1,233. And then floodgates and canal locks have
killed 250 full manatees. So that's something you should watch out for if
you're a manatee. But what we're going to do now is we're going to make some
changes to this data. Because that schema is a little bit untidy as a sort of
starting point. So, oh, actually, I'll show one quick other thing that you can
do. So with SQLiteUtils, you can run SQL queries. Here I'm saying SQLiteUtils
against manatees.db. I want to select those columns and out it comes. And
actually, I think I need to... There we go. If I drop the font size down, you can see
that that came out as a tab-separated table. I think if I, instead of dash T, by
default, without any options, it'll output JSON, which is useful for piping
into the commands. You can also say dash, dash format. And then I think it might
even let me format it. There we go. This is LaTeX on the command line, should that
be a thing that is useful for you. So there's a lot of stuff you can do with
SQLiteUtils just as a command line tool for querying data. But let's make some
changes. So when we were looking at this table earlier, it became apparent that...
Where has it gone?
Oh, manatee's gone. So some of these columns are kind of pointless. Like,
field ID doesn't look very interesting. The rep month and rep day is already
represented in the date. Every single one of them was last edited by user FWC,
so we don't really need those columns since they're all the same values. So we're
gonna run this column here. This is a... This command here. This is the transform
command, and what this can do is apply a whole bunch of alterations to the table
you specify. It's effectively a very fancy alter table statement. And this is
actually making up for a limitation of SQLite itself. Databases have a query
you can run for alter table that can make changes to a table. The SQLite one's
actually quite limited. There are things that it can't do. It can't reassign the
primary key. It used to not be able to rename columns, but I think they might
have fixed that. So this command here does a whole bunch of wild things under
the hood to make more complicated alter statements available to you. The way it
actually works is when you run this, it will create a brand new table called
locations temp in the new format. It'll copy the old data to the new table.
It'll drop the old table and then rename the new one back to the old one.
So there's a lot of activity hidden by that command, but the end result of this
command is that you can make all of the alterations to your table that you want
to. So we're gonna do a few things. We're gonna rename the last column to
latitude and rename that long underscore column to longitude. That's so that our
cluster map plugin can pick up those columns and show them on a map. We're
gonna drop those created user last user x, y, state. We're dropping the state
column because it's all in Florida. We don't need to know which state it is.
We'll drop object ID and we're gonna reassign the primary key to be this field
ID column as well. So that's a lot of stuff that's gonna happen.
And if I run that right now, here we go.
Oops.
It's done. So that should have changed all of those different things that we wanted
to change. So now if I refresh this page here, there we go. We've now got a map
because we've got latitude and longitude columns. We've dropped a whole bunch
of those columns that we didn't need. And having that map, and we can actually...
The map defaults showing 1,000 points. You can actually load all 14,000 points
on. So now this is a map of every single time a manatee carcass has been
discovered in the state of Florida since 1974. And oh, that's interesting.
I wonder what happened to... Huh. Not many manatees died around there.
That poor manatee got very unlucky. Also, it's nice to note that the Florida
keys look a lot safer than the rest of Florida. There seems to be a lot
less manatee deaths down there than up around the edges.
So again, it's a classic demonstration of how you start with a CSV file,
you run a couple of commands, and now you can tell stories.
You can start understanding that data in much more detail than if you
were just squinting at it in Microsoft Excel.
There is one more change that we want to make to this.
So we've visualized the locations. The date columns. So
I'm European, and I think that the way Americans do dates is completely...
The whole month, day, year thing is not good. At least in this case,
the dates are slightly better. This is year, year, year, year, month, month,
day, day, which is closer to my European sensibilities. But it's not quite
the format that I like. And so another command that SQLiteUtils has
is called SQLiteUtilsConvert, and this can be run to convert the values
in one or more columns to some other format. And I'm gonna run that
right now.
There we go. This one actually shows you a little progress bar as it whizzes
through. And having run that, if we refresh this table here,
there we go. This is much more pleasing to my eyes. We're now in ISO
formatted dates for all of that data there. You'll notice that the
command I ran there actually has a little snippet of code in it.
I'm saying, convert the values... Look at the locations table.
Look at data in these three columns. So the rep date, created date,
and last edited date columns. And for each of those, I want you to
run this little Python expression. And this is actually a snippet of Python.
You can put any Python expression you like in there. In this case,
I'm using a baked in function called pass date time, which is using...
I think it's using date util under the hood. But it basically,
you can give it any string you like, and it will try and convert
that into an ISO formatted string. So this is a really powerful way
of rewriting data on the fly. I often find myself, starting with the CSV
file, I import it. I spot that some of the values need to be converted
lowercase, or have their dates processed or whatever. And I can do all
of that as these command line invocations of that SQLite utils command.
So R stands for... It's a namespace. And I can't remember why I called
it R. Let's have a quick look. I think you're right. Yes, it's recipes.
Yep, command line tool. It's the convert. Converting data from columns.
Yes. Yep, it was R for recipes. So there are a bunch of other recipes
that are available on that object. There's like a JSON split one that
splits comma separated values into a JSON array, pass date, pass date time.
Oh, that's it. There's three built in recipes that you can use.
And then most of the time, I will use little Python expressions like this,
like value.upper will convert things to uppercase. Float value plus 0.5 will
convert it to floating point number and add 0.5 on the end. SQLite utils
has extremely extensive documentation, both for the Python library and the
command line tools. So there's a lot of stuff that I'm not going to...
There's a huge amount of stuff that I'm not gonna cover with us today.
So how many times have you covered Python with the command line tool?
Right. So yeah, the question is, how do you decide when to use Python and
when to use SQL? SQLite, SQL is very limited. SQLite can do string
concatenations and adding numbers together, but it can't even do
mathematic... It can't do math operations beyond multiplying and addition and
such. It's missing more advanced string manipulations aren't in there.
If you're used to Postgres, Postgres has a very rich SQL language that
can do regular expression extractions and just almost any string operation
you want is built into Postgres. That's not the case with SQLite.
But what SQLite does let you do is it lets you register Python functions
with names in SQLite so that they can be called as SQL functions.
And Dataset does that quite often. SQLite utils can do that as well.
And when you actually... When you use SQLite utils in this way,
when you give it that conversion function, it actually defines a new Python
function called convert. It registers that. It runs the SQL query of update
table set something equals convert bracket something else. And that's how
it all works. So your Python code is being executed effectively inside of
SQLite as a custom function. That's how the internals of the system work
anyway. There's actually other stuff you can do with SQLite utils too for
for registering functions. Yeah, you can do things like this. You can say...
That gets the right place. SQLite, when you run a query, one of the things
you can pass is you can pass dash, dash functions and actually pass it a block
of Python code that defines some additional Python functions. And those will
then become available to your SQLite query. So that's a sort of advanced
feature that I wasn't going to go into today. But if you want to use Python
functions as part of SQL, it's got you covered. That's a feature that's
available in the library too. That's kind of fun.
Okay, we're gonna do one more operation on our Manatees database. And that's
that when we take a look at the... When we take a look at our Manatees,
one of the things we notice is that this data is not particularly...
Great. Yeah, so this mortality column is duplicate data. It's the same string,
verified not necropsy, repeated thousands and thousands of times. In database
design, this is bad. If you ever hear people talking about database
normalization, one of the things that that means is that you don't duplicate
the same string thousands of times just because that's the way the data came
in. Another thing you'll notice is that there's mortality and there's a thing
called decode. And if we facet by both of those, so facet by decode and
then facet by mortality, those numbers are exactly the same because it turns
out decode of one means human related water group condition, four means
perinatal, eight means that. These are duplicate data. We've got the decode
and we've got the mortality and we really shouldn't need both of those.
So what I'm gonna do is I'm going to extract that... I'm gonna create myself
a new table that's just those mortality codes and I'm gonna rewrite my existing
table to reference that one instead. I think what I'll do is I'll demonstrate
that first and then we will... Let's go back up to here. So our Malaties database
currently has a single table called locations. I'm gonna run this command
here. SQLiteUtils extract. I'm extracting from the locations table. I'm saying
pull out the decode and the mortality, rename mortality to just name and put
them in a table called mortality. So I run that and now when I hit refresh
here, I've got two tables. I've got my locations table and I've got a new
table called mortality. If I go in here, I can see that those are all of those
unique values that we had a moment ago. And if I pop back into the locations
table, I no longer have those columns. I've now got a new column called
mortality underscore ID and that's one of these foreign keys. That's now a
foreign key reference to this new table. We can scroll down to the bottom and see
that the table is now defined in terms of mortality ID as an integer. There's a
foreign key of mortality ID referencing that other table. So SQLiteUtils has
pulled that data out, created a new table, populated that table, rewritten this
table to have a reference to it. It's done, again, a lot of work under the hood
to get you to a point where now we've got a database that is a table that is
much more normalized. We're no longer duplicating that data. We've got a foreign
key reference that we can follow. Features like faceting still work. You can say
facet by, in this case, mortality ID. And when you do that, it's data set smart
enough to pull in the official name of that. But that's kind of... This is... As
somebody who works with databases a lot, I haven't actually seen this particular
kind of refactoring tool for anything else. And I find that with... I use this
with my SQLite databases all the time. I'll start with manatee carcass locations
and then with just a few additional steps, I can get to the point where I've
actually got a clean relational... I've got a relational scheme of that. Multiple
tables, like foreign keys, all of those bits and pieces are all set up and
working together. So yeah, there's a whole bunch of other stuff you can do with
SQLite utils. This documentation here links to additional information about
those conversion functions and refactoring and all of that sort of stuff.
But hopefully this gives you a good feel for what you can start doing with that
as a command line tool for manipulating that data.
Can you foreign key from one to another?
That's a great question. So the question is, if you've got two CSV files,
can you foreign key from one to another? Yes, you can. I don't have a good demo
for that right now, but the way you would do that is you'd import the two and then
there's a command in here called adding foreign key constraints. So you can
basically say, SQLite utils add foreign key on my books.db database to the books
table, tell it that the author ID column is a foreign key to the author's table
and the ID column. So it's a bit of a mouthful, but it can do that.
And that's another example of something which SQLite out of the box doesn't have
the ability to do. You actually have to do some very weird things to the SQLite
metadata to get that to work, but SQLite utils has all of those patterns baked in.
So yeah, one of the capabilities it gives you is the ability to add foreign keys to
tables that don't have them yet, but should. So we are almost exactly halfway
through. I think we should, we take a 10 minute break now and then we'll, when we
get back, we're going to dive into some of the more advanced, well firstly we're
going to create a database of PEPs and publish that to the internet and then
we'll start diving into some advanced SQL as well. But yeah, let's reconvene it
at 3.05. Okay, we'll kick off again in just a moment. We are going to be on this
section here, the using SQLite utils as a Python library to import all of the PEPs.
So it should be linked to, I guess linked to from the index page of the tutorial
workshop. Okay, so actually what I'm going to do now is I'm going to switch to a
Jupyter notebook. And again, this is one of the things I like about code space,
it makes it nice and easy to do this. I'm going to go in notebooks, right click, a
new file, I'm going to call it SQLite.ipynb and this takes a little while
to start running because it has to detect kernels and things like that.
Select kernel, I want a Python environment, I want Python 3.10. Okay, there we go,
that's worked, great. So the next thing we're going to do is I'm going to create
a, I'm going to use the Python library version of SQLite utils. Everything that
you saw in the command line tool do earlier, you could also do by importing
SQLite utils into Python and doing things there. So I'm going to import
SQLite utils and then do db equals SQLite utils dot database. I'm going to create a
database called peps dot db. Okay, here we go, this is our peps database. If I say
db dot tables, it shows me an empty list because there aren't any tables yet. And
I'm actually going to do, I'm going to create a database of all 400 plus peps.
The easiest way to get that data is that you can git clone it. So I'm going to do
git clone of the Python slash peps repo and I'm going to put it in slash temp
slash peps. This is a habit I have for all sorts of things. I'm very lazy about
deleting files so anytime I don't think I'm going to want to keep something, I
stick it in my temp directory so next time I reboot my computer I don't have
to worry about it anymore. So I'm going to run that, I'm running it in a Jupyter
notebook cell so I put an exclamation mark at the beginning. There we go,
cloned into slash temp slash peps and there they are. That's all of those pep files.
So now what I'm going to do is I'm going to grab the, I'm going to grab that,
remember that code we wrote earlier, the the Paras pep function that can turn a
pep into a dictionary. So I've got that and now I'm going to use pathlib to get
a list of all of the files in that peps checkout that match the the file pattern
pep hyphen star dot txt. So I'll do that. Now if we look at files, len files, comma
files colon five, there we go. So we've now got 429 peps as files on disk and
each of those files looks something like that. Yes, so the code for this is all in
the handout for the workshop here. And now I'm going to pass them. So I'm going to
loop through every file and for each one I'm going to call pass pep on the text
contents of that file and stick it in the list. So we'll do this. And now if I look at
len of peps is 429 and each of those peps is a dictionary and it's got a pep id,
the title and the version, author status, all of those different fields that came out of those
those text files. So now we want to turn this into a SQLite database. So we can do
import SQL, oh we actually did this already right, we did, I'll run it again. So import
SQLite utils and I can do db equals SQLite utils dot database peps dot db.
Now I'm going to insert them. So I can say db square brackets peps, this is a shortcut for
getting a reference to a table in that database. SQLite utils will, if the table doesn't already
exist it will create it. So I can say that dot insert all peps and then we also, we know that
we've got a primary key which is the PEP column. So I'm going to tell it to insert all 420 of those
peps into a new table called peps and give it a primary key. And this failed with an error.
The error was table peps has no column named pep delegate. So what's happened here is that
we've got a list of dictionaries and it creates a table to match the first dictionary and then
tries to insert all of the data. But it turns out later on in that list there's a dictionary
with an additional key in it which breaks everything. So we're going to drop our table
and we're going to try this again. So let's do db peps dot drop to get rid of it. And now I'm
going to add alter equals true. And alter equals true means when you're inserting this, if you find
a new column that you haven't seen before, alter the table to add that column. So running this
that worked. I've now got a peps table. I can run db peps dot schema with a print to see what
that there we go. That's the column. That's the table that we've just created. And if I
switch back over to data set, where's data set? It should be in the terminal.
I'm going to stop data set and I'm going to start it again and add peps dot db to it.
And now if we go back to here, what happened there?
Service unavailable. Has it crashed or is it just taking a while to start up?
Oh, path peps dot db does not exist. That's because it's actually in the notebooks folder.
There we go.
All right. Now we've got our peps. And so this right here is the database table that we just
created. It's called peps. It's got all of the columns that we do want it. You'll see that it's
actually got a bunch of weird columns towards the end, like bdf l delegate is apparently a column in
one of these things. We've got the pep ID is that primary key. And so if I want to go and find pep
20, I can say where pep equals 20. And there it is. There's the Zenith Python in our SQLite database.
I can get an as a JSON, I can get as a CSV. All of those features we had before were available.
But crucially, creating this table, all we did was effectively this one liner. We said
create a table called peps, insert these things, set the primary key,
add any columns that you need to add. That's the whole thing. That's done.
So most of the, I showed you work that I do with command line tools earlier on.
Anytime I'm doing anything more sophisticated, I do it in a Jupyter Notebook. I import SQLite
utils. I fire up a Jupyter Notebook and I use exactly this workflow I'm showing you here,
where you grab files from Git or you download JSON over HTTP or anything like that and just
start splatting things into these, almost treating the database itself like a dictionary
where each of the keys in the dictionaries will end up being a table.
This is an amazingly productive way of working with data because normally when I'm working with
a relational database, I spend 90% of my time sweating over the schema. I'm like, okay,
I need to know what columns I've got to advance and what types of I should have in those columns
and think about the primary keys and all of that. And here I'm skipping everything in terms of
database design and just saying, I've got an array of dictionaries, make a table. And it makes
a table. It derives the correct schema. All of that sort of tedious database creation work is
done for me. And now I've got, again, I've got an API, right? This is now an API for PEPs where I can
filter and search and do faceting. And actually let's do some faceting now. So there's a thing
called status, which out of our, what, 429 PEPs, 220 are final, 96 are rejected, 31 are deferred.
There's a type column. I'm going to fast on that. Standard track informational process.
There's a PEP that's an April Fool PEP, which you click on. And this joke hasn't aged very well.
This is from April 2009. It's a joke announcement that Guido van Rossum was retiring. I think he
actually did retire a few years after that. And then he came back again. But you know, this is
preserved forever in the Python enhancement proposals GitHub repository. Yeah. So it's very,
very little work to get from data in some shape or form to a database table that we can start doing
all of the fun stuff that we've seen so far. Oh, that's a great question. So the question is,
what do you do if you want to create a data frame from this? I will be honest, I don't use
pandas habitually enough to just run that straight off the top of my head, but let's have a go.
So if I do pip install pandas, I think pandas has a thing where you can do, what is it?
And put pandas as PD, PD dot. But you can actually do from SQL, can't you, in pandas?
Well, there's a CSV thing, but isn't there a pandas?
That's it. Read SQL. This is the one. This will do it. Okay. So I can say pandas
dot read SQL brackets, DB dot con. Oh no, it's the SQL first, isn't it? Select star from peps, DB dot
con. Yep. Yep. PD. Did that work? Yeah, there we go. There we go. So what I did there is
the pandas read, the PD dot read SQL method takes a SQL query and a SQLite database connection.
Our DB object isn't a SQLite database connection. It's a special SQLite utils one,
but DB dot con, which I don't know if it's documented. I should make sure that's documented.
DB dot con is that underlying SQLite query. So yeah, this is how you would get that same data
into pandas. And you could do it otherwise as well. Pandas, you can give it a list of JSON objects and
all of that kind of stuff. But I think this is probably the cleanest way to get from SQLite or
SQLite utils into pandas. And it's kind of neat that we, again, we started with that list of
objects. We round tripped them through that SQLite database and now we've got them in pandas again.
So that's kind of cool. So this bit here talks about the error. So we're going to do one more
trick here. Wouldn't it be neat if we had a proper search engine for our peps? Now SQLite, one of the
many, many features of SQLite is it actually has a really robust search engine built into the
database. It's called the SQLite FTS5 extension, where FTS stands for full text search. And this
is a shockingly capable piece of software. It's actually, there's an aspect where this is better
than what Postgres gives you, because Postgres has a very good, it's got full text search baked in,
but the Postgres full text search can only work based on the sort of information about individual
rows. So it can give you, like it can give you matches for a term and it can use stop words and
all of that kind of stuff. But Postgres doesn't have ranking built in. Like when you're using a
search engine like Elasticsearch or Lucene, the ranking algorithm takes into account the,
how common the term is in the whole corpus. And so if you search for something which is very rare
overall, but is super common in a few rows, you'll get those rows back. SQLite actually has that
baked in. It does full blown BM25 search ranking, which again puts it a little bit above Postgres
in terms of the sort of out of the box search for search capabilities. But anyway, what we're going
to do is we're going to set up a search engine. And I'm going to do it by saying dbpeps, that's our table,
dot configure FTS for configure full text search. I'm going to make it searchable by the title
and the body columns. So configure full text search and we feed it a list of those columns.
And if I run that, now if we run db.tables, db.tables, actually let's do db.tablenames.
Oh, hold on.
That's surprising, there should be another table in there.
What went wrong?
Oh, it said configure FTS, didn't I? Or did I?
I don't know. It should be dot enable FTS. So okay, I've run enable FTS. That took 0.3 seconds.
If I look at the list of table names, here we go, here we go. So now we've got that peps table that
we started with. We also have one, two, three, four, five new tables relating to this full text
search index that we've just created. You do not have to worry about the details of these tables
at all. They're sort of effectively an implementation detail of how SQLite full
text search works. But now in data set, if we refresh this page, it spots them and it adds a
search box. So this is a data set feature. It knows about full text search in SQLite and it knows how
to tell if a table's got it set up and it adds a search box to it. So now if we look for say generators
and run that search, there are 42 peps where the title of the body matches the search term
generators. And that looks about right to me. We've got range literals. Something I'm going to do here
is I'm going to hide the body column just because it's taking up a lot of space. So yeah, this looks
spot on to me. Coroutines generators, continuations, simple generators. We've just built a search engine
on top of Python peps and it was a single line of Python code to get that to happen.
There is one missing feature here. You'll notice that this is showing a search results
for generators sorted by that ID column. So 204, 205, 219, 220. It's a search engine. We kind of
want to sort by relevance. Data set doesn't have search by relevance as a built-in feature yet
and that's just because I haven't quite figured out how I'm going to build it. But what you can
do instead is you can run a raw SQL query that does that ranking. We'll do that. We'll go to
view and edit SQL. Stick that in and run this query. And this, oh, hold on. Actually, I'm going
to put rank first and get rid of the body column just so we can see that it worked.
There we go. Look at this. Asynchronous generators is the top result. Then generators,
attributes and exceptions. This column here is the SQLite scoring column for how relevant it
thinks that document is. We scroll down to the bottom. That looks about right to me. Asynchronous
IOS support presumably mentions generators but it's not as relevant to our search term as all of
those other things are. And as before, we can click hide on this and then send somebody else a link.
And now we've built a search engine and there's a search interface. They can type the search
query in here. They get the results back ordered by rank. The query here, I won't go into detail,
but you can see that the way this works is it's a join. So it's joining the peps column against
the peps FTS column on that magic and visible row ID thing. So when we created the search index,
we actually created it such that the row ID in the FTS table matches the row ID in the other table.
And then when you say where peps FTS match colon search, match is a magic SQLite operator
that does all of the work of running those full text queries and stemming things and all of that
kind of stuff. And then peps FTS isn't actually a real table. It's a virtual table that exposes
that relevant score right there. So it's one of those things. You can just trust me that this is
the weird incantation that you need to do relevance-based searching, but it does make
a sort of logical sense once you start digging into how the internals of this search system works.
Search exactly. Well, if you say peps FTS, so that's the name of the table,
it will search against all of the columns in that table that are, it's all of the columns in that
table that have search enabled on them. I think you can say peps FTS dot title.
How many results did we get? We got, I'm going to get rid of that limit as well.
So if we run this without a limit clause, we get back 42 results. If we say peps FTS dot title,
now we get back eight results. Yeah. So you can optionally tell it that you just want to match a
specific column. And now it's just the ones where the title column mentioned that keyword.
Whereas previously we were seeing everything where either the title column or the body column
mentioned it. Basically, this is if you want to build a really advanced search interface,
if you want to say to Pete, if you want to have actually in your UI something that says
search everything or just search the title or just search the author. I very rarely use it.
For the most part, I'll just run my search against all of the available columns,
but it's a capability that's there if you need it.
But yeah, so this is, so let's see what we've got to then. We started out with a, we had that
GitHub repository with all of the peps in it. We had to write a little bit of custom Python code.
This thing here, and again, I didn't write this. I cheated and I got chat GPT to write it for me
because it's the kind of code that I can't be bothered to write these days now that there are
robots that'll do it instead. If anyone's interested, I might be doing a open space
session later in the conference talking about all of the weird things you can do to get
GPT-4 to write code for you. This will be one of the examples I'll demonstrate then.
But yeah, so we did this. We looped through all of those files and we turned them into a list.
We inserted them to a database table. We enabled full text search. We basically ran three lines of
Python and now we've got a search engine against all of the Python peps. And that's, I do this kind
of thing honestly on a daily basis. If I've got any data about anything that I think looks
interesting, I'll probably slurp it down, fire it through SQLite utils and start exploring it in this
way. It's kind of my, it's one of those things when all you have is a hammer, everything's a nail.
When all you've got is SQLite utils, SQLite Python, Jupyter Notebooks and Datasette,
everything is a problem that fits into a SQLite database.
Exactly. Yeah, I'm not a very heavy pandas user because I find that I prefer SQL,
especially with Datasette giving me an interface on the top of it. It's just, it's what I do
habitually. And it's partly, I mean, it's mainly because what I build is almost a competitor to
pandas in terms of there are problems that you could solve with SQLite and Datasette or you could
solve them with pandas. And so I tend to lean towards the ones that I'm building. Like a lot of
the stuff I'm showing you here, you could solve very effectively in pandas and you'd be, it would
be a sensible thing for you to use it for that. Why do I need, oh, if I'm using SQL instead,
what do you mean? Why do I need Python? It's for the manipulation. The bit that you couldn't do in
SQL very easily is this bit here, the bit where you take these text files on disk and turn them
into a format and then get them in. So Python is my data manipulation and sort of cleaning layer,
and then SQL is how I do the querying at the end of it. Let's publish what we've done to the
internet. So I've been playing around in GitHub Codespaces and a frustrating thing about GitHub
Codespaces is that it is private. So if I try and visit this URL, here we go. So I try to visit that
in a different browser and it says, now you've got to sign in to GitHub for this. Because GitHub,
they're giving us free development environments, but they're not giving us a free hosting
environment for us to publish our stuff with the world. But Datasette's entire reason of existing
is to help people publish data. It's all about trying to get data into a format where you can
share it with the rest of the world as easily as possible. So I'm going to try something. I'm going
to publish this Peps database that we created, peps.db. Oh, it's in notebooks, isn't it?
So I've got a 10 megabyte database and I'm going to publish it to the world. And the way I'm going
to do that is I'm going to use, aha, interesting, npm install-g-versel. Is it Versel or Versel CLI?
Versel, just Versel, npm install-g-versel. So I'm going to use a hosting platform called Versel.
And Datasette works with a whole bunch of different hosting platforms. The thing I like about Versel
is that it's the least steps to get it set up. And this is something which I would invite people
in the room to try doing yourself. Even if you haven't used Versel before, I'm crossing my fingers
and hoping that this will just work for you anyway. So what I've done is I've done npm install
Versel and the handout has all of the other ways that you can install this. There we go. I've got
the Versel command. I then have to write, type Versel login and that'll give me options to sign
in. I'm going to sign in with GitHub. It wants me to visit this webpage where I think I'll get to
authenticate and go back again. Oh, it's got a little code for me to copy and paste in.
Okay, there we go. I have now authenticated with my Versel account. And so now I can install another
plugin, dataset install dataset publish Versel. And this is a plugin that teaches dataset how to
deploy things onto the Versel environment. And now I could say dataset publish Versel notebook
slash peps.db dash dash. I have to give it a project name. I'm going to call it project peps.
There we go. So what this command is doing is it's uploading my 10 megabyte SQLite database
to Versel. It's then going to deploy a copy of the full dataset web application to Versel with,
and it gives me this little link here I think. This will actually give me a progress bar so I
can see what's going on. Here we go. It's building. So it's installing some stuff. It's going to run
pip install and install dataset. It's generating build outputs. It's deploying it to Washington,
DC for some reason. It's going to run some checks, assign some domains, and it's done.
And so now if I click on peps-simonw.versell.app, this is that database that we just created
complete with its search engines so I can search for generators again right here. But it's now
running live on the internet. It's on peps-simonw.versell.app. And you can actually,
you can point custom domain names at it or assign aliases. There are a bunch of flexibility there.
But that was kind of the, that was, I mean, that was what? About 30 seconds including installing
the software to get a database that I've been working just locally in my own environment and
put it online where other people can use it. And again, this is an API. So if you want to build
a application right now, the second that runs, that needs a JSON API for searching all of the
Python paps, that's what this is. I'm going to stick shape equals array on the end because
it gives you a nicer format back. Yeah, this is every pep that matches generators as a JSON
API that anyone in the world can now start using. A neat thing about Vercell is that under the hood,
it's based on Amazon Lambda functions. So it's very much a scale to zero thing where if your
project isn't getting any traffic, it's not costing anyone any money to use. Vercell themselves have
a very generous free tier. So it's effectively a free hosting plan for structured data. There is
one catch, which is that on Vercell, the maximum file size is I believe 50 megabytes. So if you're
doing, if you've got a gigabyte database, this won't work for you. If you do have a gigabyte
database, Google Cloud Run works more or less the same way. It can handle up to a gigabyte quite
easily. But yeah, I think this is kind of cool. This is, this was, this was actually the feature
that inspired me to create data set in the first place is I'd been looking at Vercell, which back
then was called Zite Now, it was before their rebranding and thinking, okay, this is kind of
interesting that this is, that you can host applications on this. But is that, can this solve
that problem I had beforehand back from when I was working at newspapers of wanting a really
good way to deploy, to deploy structured data in a way that people could start using it? And yeah,
it works really well. I've deployed hundreds of applications to Vercell in this way. They've
cost me like at the most $20 a month, I think I'm paying for a Vercell plan with hundreds of
different projects on it. It's a really, really powerful way of sharing data in that way.
Okay. So yeah, that's, so as I mentioned, there are other options. There's a data set out of the box
can publish to both Google Cloud Run. Oh, that, those two, there's the wrong way around, but it
can publish to Heroku, it can publish to Google Cloud Run. Heroku used to be a great option and
they canceled their free plan and so now it's a lot less exciting. There's my favorite hosting
provider was Fly. I built a plugin called data set published Fly that can push things up there.
And again, because this is based around the plugin system, if there's a hosting provider that you
like that has good API driven hosting, you can write a plugin for it.
Yes.
That's when I'm running the deploy, when you run data set publish, it actually, it bundles the
database and the application together. So it's kind of, it's actually a complete cheat. And I
was going to talk about this later on, but I'll talk about this right now. The Vercell and Amazon
Lambda and Google Cloud Run, they're all designed as stateless hosting providers. Like they will run
code for you on the internet, but if you want a database, they're no good. Like they will tell
you, yeah, you have to pay extra for Amazon RDS or Google, whatever Google's database thing is,
or whatever. Because hosting code that doesn't write to disk, that doesn't make any changes is
really easy. You wrap up a little container, you launch it when a new request comes in, you
shut it back down again, you scale it by running multiple copies. It's very, very easy in 2023
to host a stateless application online. Stateful applications with disk access and backups and so
on, those are expensive and complicated. The big realization I had is that for the stuff that I do,
I only care about read only data. Like all of these things right here, none of them are accepting
rights at all. And if it's read only, you can essentially abuse these free hosting providers
by sticking up a full database and saying, yeah, it's SQLite, it's just built in, it runs in read
only mode. So effectively you're abusing their tools that were supposed to be for hosting little
simple applications, and you're sticking five megabytes of binary SQLite data in the container
with all of the other stuff, and it just works. And this is, I'm going to talk about this at length
in a moment, I call it the baked data pattern because you're baking data into your application.
But yeah, this is the sort of perfect example of why that's an interesting pattern. And with this,
a new PEP is published maybe once or twice a month. You just redeploy the whole thing.
I have many, many projects which they deploy once a day because that's often enough to have the data
that they need. And yeah, I don't worry about trying to update them in place. I just overwrite
the application with a completely fresh deploy with a new copy of the database with any changes baked
into that. Where did we get to? So yeah, lots of other publishing options. The dataset documentation
has extensive coverage of this stuff as well. I'm going to switch gears entirely and talk about a
very, very different way of running datasets. This is a sort of experiment I did last year,
again, kind of as a joke, right? So I was looking at, so there's this amazing project
Piodide which lets you run Python entirely in a web browser by compiling the Python interpreter
web assembly and running it in the browser. And then this project called JupiterLight is, I think,
one of the most incredible pieces of engineering I've ever seen. This right here is the full
Jupiter Notebook stack, like everything that the Jupiter Notebooks do on your computer. But again,
running purely in the browser. This is astonishing to me. This is running Python's web assembly,
all of Jupiter, Pandas is in there, NumPy and data frames and Matplotlib and all of this stuff.
And I thought dataset is a lot simpler than that. Wouldn't it be interesting if dataset itself
could run inside the browser? And again, it was kind of a joke because dataset is very opinionated
in that it's not a JavaScript application. There's very little JavaScript in dataset itself. There's
like some syntax highlighting stuff here. But when you click sort in dataset, it reloads the
whole page. Everything is just boring old HTML because it's simpler and it's faster to load and
it's got better accessibility and all sorts of reasons that I built it in that way. So I thought
it would be funny if I could run a pure server-side web application entirely in the browser using web
assembly. And so I built this thing called Dataset Light. And actually what I'm going to do is I'm
going to pop open, I'm going to pop open my browser network tab so you can see what this thing does.
And now if I go to light.dataset.io, you can see that it's pulling down a bunch of stuff.
Most excitingly, it just downloaded two megabytes of pyodides.asm.js and five megabytes of pyodide.asm.data.
That's the Python interpreter compiled to web assembly. That's the Python standard library,
I believe, compiled to web assembly and such like as well. And so it downloaded those two things
and then it hit the Python package index and ran a pip install of Dataset itself. And that's not
actually showing up there. Let's see if I, maybe it's cached. I'll try refreshing the page.
Loading setup tools. Oh, that's surprising. I'm not seeing it. Well, you'll have to take
my word for it. This actually does a pip install in your browser and pulls the latest data set and
its dependencies in from the Python package index and now we've got Dataset. And again,
it's full Dataset. It's got all of the features you'd expect. It's got faceting and it's got the
ability to run SQL queries and all of that kind of stuff. And if you look at the URL, you'll see
that it's, there's a little fragment hash in it and then everything after that point is the regular
Dataset URLs that you'd be using. So I built this, like I said, as a bit of a joke. I thought it would
be funny. And I also thought nobody is going to use this because it has to load nearly 10 megabytes
of stuff before, you sit there with a loading spinner for quite a while before this becomes
usable. I forgot that these days your average React app is like five megabytes of stuff. So,
you know, waiting for a few extra megabytes to get a full Python interpreter isn't actually nearly
as restrictive as I thought it was going to be. And it's also, but the best thing about this
is that this is genuinely serverless and that there is no server-side code running anywhere
at all. This entire thing you're seeing is just static HTML, some JavaScript, some binary web
assembly files. Nothing can break about this. There is no server to fill up with log files or
crash or anything like that. It's actually being served off GitHub pages. So it doesn't even cost
me any money, but it gives you that full interactive experience. And so I ended up building a couple of
extra features for it. I built a feature where you can give it the URL to a CSV file or a JSON
file or a SQLite database. And if your browser can fetch it, it will fetch that file in and
load it into Dataset Lite directly. And that turns out to suddenly be really, really useful.
So I'll show you a couple of examples. Let's skip that one. We'll go straight to this one down here.
So 538, the blog, does this wonderful thing where they publish their underlying data on GitHub.
Let's do, here we go. It's the 538 slash data repository. And they've got one of the files in
here is called fight songs. And it's data about fight songs from various American college university
and what year they were written and all of that kind of stuff. So this is a CSV file. If you copy
and paste that CSV URL and hit the load CSV button in Dataset Lite, paste it in, Dataset will fire up
again. It will fetch that data from GitHub directly and it'll load it to a table. So now we've got that
Dataset interface on top of data that was fed in from a CSV file via a URL. And I can do things like
facet by official song, yes, no, student writer. I can run SQL queries, all of that kind of stuff.
And again, it's also bookmarkable. So if I send that link to anyone else in the world,
their browser will install Dataset in Python and get a Python to running and download CSV file and
load it to SQL. All of that bizarre crazy junk in about 15 seconds and then they can start
interacting with the data in the same way. So I used to spend a lot of time building projects
download some data, put it in SQL and publish it to Versel or to Cloud Run as a dedicated
project. These days, most of the time when I've got an ad hoc data project, I'll do it by gathering
the CSV data or the JSON data, sticking it in GitHub gist and then linking to a Dataset Lite
instance that loads that data from GitHub from gist. The reason I'm always using GitHub gist and
GitHub for this is that JavaScript can only fetch files from servers that have a special HTTP cause
header allowing that access. Most hosting doesn't have this. So if you feed this URL to most of the
things on the internet, it'll just give you an error. But GitHub do have that header turned on
for all of the content in their repositories and in their gist. So GitHub is effectively the world's
quickest cause friendly hosting provider for any kind of data that you want to throw in there.
I'll show you one more example of this. That's a great question. Is there an attribution thing?
There is not and there should be. So Dataset itself has quite has attribution built in as a
metadata mechanism where you can configure it to show data source about license information.
Dataset doesn't have that yet because I'm lazy and I haven't built it and I should build it.
It's kind of rude that I've not done that yet. So I'm going to show you a project I did a few
days ago using Dataset Lite. One of my hobbies is digging into the training data behind weird
AI models to try and understand how they work. So this new training set came out two days ago
called Red Pajama and they basically released 2.6 terabytes of data that you can use to train
language model like all of Wikipedia's in there and all of Archive and lots of GitHub data and
Stack Exchange all of this stuff. And so I wanted to do a little bit of an investigation about this
data but I didn't want to download 2.7 terabytes of stuff from the internet. The way they released
that is they released a text file with 2,000 URLs in and each of these URLs is a one gigabyte blob
of data. So if you want all the data you run WGET and you download all 2,000 URLs and you take up
2.7 terabytes of disk space. But I realized that what you can do instead is you can do an HTTP
head request against each of those URLs to get back just the size in bytes of each one. And that
you can run in 15 seconds. You can knock up a quick script, it'll churn through all 2,000,
get their sizes and now you've got URLs and sizes. So what I did then is I
turned that into a JSON file. Where is it?
This JSON file here.
So yeah, I dumped that out into this JSON file. So this JSON file has 2,000 records in and each one has the URL and the size and then I made it in megabytes and gigabytes as well just because I was feeling lazy.
And it's got the path and then I split out the top folder because that tells you what the source of that data was.
And so now I've got that gist. I can go to data set light. I can feed it in that URL.
And now I've got a table. And so this is very, very quick route from a list of those files to a list of those files in those sizes to a JSON gist. And now it's an interface that I can start playing with.
And I can do things like facet by top folder and see that in this data, Wikipedia was a single file because they put all of it in one Wikipedia file.
C4 and common crawl are the two most represented things in that list of data. Again, I can start with from raw data to starting to tell stories and understand that data in as few steps as possible is the goal here.
And I'll use this demo again in a moment when we start talking about some advanced SQL queries.
But yeah, so data set light is actually it started as a joke. It's now my default solution for when I want to start publishing and working with anything that's sort of, you know, a few thousand records, anything small.
I'll do it in a gist and I'll load that into data set light. I won't even have to think about provisioning servers or deploying a server side Python web application anyway.
So, yeah.
Oh, one last feature that's kind of fun. Data set light supports plugins. You can construct when you construct a URL to data set light, you can include question mark install equals.
And then pass it the name of a plugin and you can do that multiple times. You can say install equals this and install equals that.
And it will then on startup, it will pip install that plugin. And so now we've got a new feature.
Here's that the copyable plugin I showed you earlier on. So again, if I want latech from this test table right here, I can do that.
I can do that directly using the use just by passing install equals data set copyable in the URL. I think the here we go.
The further reading documentation here includes links to a blog entry where I talk about how the plugin support works and all of that kind of stuff.
But really the goal here, this is an ecosystem thing, right? I've got data set. I've got people building plugins for data set.
If data set light can also benefit from those plugins, then it just sort of multiplies the value that the ecosystem can provide by making sure that bits written for this aspect of it work here and all of those kinds of things.
Yeah, so the question is how much data can your browser hold? So I have not tested the upper limits of this yet.
I think it's gigabytes. And the reason I think it's gigabytes is that the other day,
somebody released, so I'm fascinated by large language models, you know, chat, GPT and all of that kind of stuff.
A few days ago, somebody released this thing called Web LLM, which runs a chat GP style model entirely in your browser using not just WebAssembly, it's Web GPU, which is a new graphics card thing that Chrome's got.
And that thing, I ran it on my browser and it was a two gigabyte model file that was loaded into the browser and it worked.
So I've got to believe that two gigabyte SQLite file would work fine as well, which is kind of it's I mean, this this laptop has 64 gigabytes.
Of RAM, so you know, a two gigabyte browser tab isn't actually a big deal for it.
I'd assume so. Yeah, I mean, it's the download speed is the bigger problem.
But to be honest, my internet connection at home will load two gigabytes in like a minute or two.
So it's feasible. You know, it's it's it's it's all it's surprising how much you can get done in the browser.
OK, let's skip to advanced SQL.
We're going to talk about and I'm not going to teach you everything there is to know about SQL in the next sort of 20 minutes, but hopefully we can cover some of my favorite advanced SQL SQL features with enough details that you can sort of dive into that dig into them more later on.
The first of these is I mean, it's hardly even advanced, but it's something that's that it sort of helps build things up later on.
And that's SQL aggregations.
We've seen select queries, select queries are very straightforward.
And aggregation is a way of calculating, so doing calculations across groups of rows together.
The easiest example is.
Here we're looking at the executive terms table we saw earlier, so we're saying every executive, every presidential term, I want to know for each party how many presidential terms that they get.
So Democrat Party got five Democratic Party got 21 Democratic Republican, who I've never heard of, had seven.
But the key pattern here is you select you do a group by the end to say group those rows where so that into sort of chunks where on that matching on that matching column.
And then you can do aggregate functions like in this case count star to do a calculation across those individual groups.
There are a whole bunch of aggregate functions you can use count star is the most common.
The other ones that I use is that I tend to use a max for the maximum value min for the minimum value and some to add things up.
And I wanted to show you data set light first, because when we when I was exploring that training data, one of the.
Something's going wrong.
Wrong. Oh, look at this. There's ampersands where there should be.
Where there should be and yeah there's an escaping bug.
Okay, but yeah so here we go so here I'm running a.
Aggregation across the top folders column here and I'm summing the total number of gigabytes as total GB so I can see that Wikipedia responsible for 111 gigabytes in the data across just one file.
Stack exchanges 74 gigabytes in one file GitHub is 212 gigabytes across 98 files these are useful things to be able to calculate so.
it's worth exploring aggregates and knowing what they can do and how you can apply them.
I'm going to show you a much more fun one of these.
So sequel there's a concept in sequel called sub queries and I missed this for years because the first like 10 years of my career I just worked with my sequel and my sequel versions prior to I forget what.
Didn't support this feature so I didn't know that this was something you can do of course sequel light and postgres and all of the other sequels have really good support for this.
So what this lets you do is it lets you do things like this, you can say select something from so and so where repo in.
And then normally when you're doing an inquiry you give it like a comma separated list of values, but here instead i'm giving it another select query so i'm saying where the repository is in.
The list of ideas from right repos where full name is in.
The list of repos from plug-in repos so what i'm going to do is grab all of that run that here i'm actually going to run those as separate steps first.
So if we say select repo from plug-in repos you see you get back a list of names of repositories just as strings.
If I then do select ID from repos where full name in that full name has now been turned into an ID and actually let's do ID comma star.
Just to show you what else is going on in there so there's that name and i'm saying I want the IDs.
For the things in this where the name is in that other table this is the kind of thing that you could normally do with the join, but I actually find that joins across multiple tables are quite difficult to follow.
Like I feel as a like reading a sequel query anytime I get to a join I have to think about it.
If i'm using these bizarre weird nested sub queries I can actually follow this a lot easier I can say okay I get this it's the name of the repos list of those.
IDs a list of those and then this is select the URL from releases where the repo is in that.
And when you run this query what i'm getting back is the URLs to the releases the most recent release because it's ordered by created.
The most recent releases of the repositories that are in my list of plug-in repositories.
So this is the data set website has two types of things it cares about it cares about plugins and it cares about tools.
I switch that tools I will see maybe it's tool repos.
Now i'm seeing like swarm to sequel light and apple notes to sequel light and DB to sequel light and so forth if I if I do the same thing from plug-in repos.
I get it back as the latest releases of my plugins so it's a little bit of a convoluted example I probably should have broken this down into into a simpler example first.
what's the question.
I can do select star.
No no that that would be a neat feature that's a really good idea for a feature yeah if you could select just a portion of this and run it on its own.
But yeah that's not that's not something it can do so that's one type of sub query the other type of sub query I think is even cooler.
And that's this type here so what i'm doing here is i'm saying for I want for each of my.
Where are we for me each of my repositories I would like to get back the name of the repository and I want to get the url of the latest release in that repository.
But the latest latest releases is over in some other table I can actually in my select clause itself say I want back full name and then I want.
This complicated query here it has to be limit one because otherwise it'll actually what does happen if you get rid of that limit one let's have a look.
Oh I was expecting that to break but it didn't.
But the key idea is that for each of those repositories that we're listing we're running a second sequel query inside of the loop to try and fetch additional related data about it.
Looking at this my instinct is that this looks like a terrible idea because you're surely you're telling it to pull back 200 results and then do another 200 sequel queries on top of that to pull in extra details.
I believe sequel I optimizes that to a certain extent but more to the point if you've got a database table with 200 rows in it there is nothing you can do that will cause it to take longer than a fraction of a millisecond to run those queries.
So often I will deliberately write very inefficient queries of this kind of shape because I know that for the size of data I'm working with it honestly just doesn't matter.
When I was when I worked for a larger company I had access to hive and presto and various like big data warehouse things and a fun thing I found about those is you can actually write very inefficient sequel against them too because their whole reason for existing is to break up complex crews into like map reduces and all of those kinds of operations.
So actually inefficient queries work about work well against the big data warehouses as well and then for I would never do this in production code for like a high traffic web application that's where I care about optimization but for this kind of data size I think you can do a lot of cool stuff just with with laughably inefficient sort of sequel loops like this.
So yeah I spend I often default to weird sub queries almost just to try them out and see what works and what doesn't and so you always end up learning interesting new patterns from those.
I've got one more super fun sub query example coming up in just a moment.
This right here is my all time favorite sequel function feature that I don't think enough people are aware of.
I think it has a terrible name that calls this is a feature called CTE which stands for common table expressions but basically it's it's sequels answer to abstraction like when we're writing Python code if we've got duplicate code logic whatever we put it in function with a nice name and we and that that that helps it helps everything be more maintainable makes us more productive.
SQL queries are notorious for getting long like you'll hear from people who have like a 500 line SQL query that was left to them by the previous employee and nobody knows how it works and everyone's terrified to touch it.
The best way to make SQL more effective I believe is to break it up and using these common table expressions and basically what these are is a way to create a temporary table that exists purely for the duration of the current query.
So the example I'm going to show here is trying to answer the question how many presidents originally served as vice presidents.
And we were doing that against this table.
It's this executive terms table which mixes the two types of of office together so we've got presidents in here and we've got vice presidents in here.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to start by creating a table called presidents and then say select staff and presidents here.
And this works right this is you could actually just do this without the CT at all you'd get the same result but we're the thing I'm trying to illustrate here is that we're giving our.
This select query here which is doing a join and it's doing a where clause so it's actually quite a complicated query we're giving it the alias presidents and then later on we can select stuff from it here.
The reason that's cool is that then we can add another one we can say that comma vice presidents as and then I'm going to select star from vice presidents.
And there's all of our vice presidents or I can select stuff from presidents and get just those.
But now that we've got these two virtual tables we can solve our problem we can say now I want
to select the distinct names to just duplicate the names from presidents where that name appears in the list of vice presidents and if I do that I get back 15 rows and each one of these people is a president who was previously a vice president.
Except I'm suspicious of George Bush because Americans are like reusing names and there was a George Bush and George HW Bush so I'd have to dig into that figure out of that that that's actually a proper relationship or not.
But the point stands that.
Using this technique you can take very complicated queries and at least turn them into something where.
If you spend a bit of time thinking about it you can start to understand what this is doing.
I love this I am I start I got a lot more ambitious with the problems I solve in SQL as opposed to Python. Once I figured out how to use this feature and how it allowed you to take much more complex logic and at least abstract it to the point where you can reason about it more reasonably and then do joins between them and unions and all of that kind of stuff.
So if you don't use CTEs I very strongly recommend at least exploring them and trying to figure out if that's.
Yep you can absolutely do that with the self join I think it would be less readable.
My hunch is that it would be harder to follow if you if you did it as self join although I'd be I'd be happy to be proved wrong by somebody doing that.
So yeah mostly CTEs are they're more of a readability hack than anything else they're a great way of making it easier to look at a query and understand what it's doing.
Let's talk about JSON I think I've got a quote so another feature that SQLite has baked in which is incredibly value valuable is it's got a bunch of functions that know how to deal with JSON objects that have been stored in the database.
Postgres has a JSON type there's a JSON and a JSON B type and it's all optimized and everything. SQLite doesn't it tells you to store JSON in a text column just like anything else.
But if you do store JSON in your text columns you can start to do all sorts of interesting things with it.
More importantly though SQLite can output JSON it can you can use functions to build up JSON values that you then then return back to people.
So this this query right here the thing I was trying to solve with this is I wanted to get back a list of all of my legislators and for each legislator I wanted to fetch all of the terms that they had served but all in one go right.
Normally if you were doing this you'd have to I mean you write might run Python code that D Jupes it or you may end up like pulling back duplicate versions of the top level thing to get one row per term.
So a bunch of ways you could do this it's kind of neat to be able to say you know what I want a single row per legislator and in one of the columns in that row should be a JSON list of objects representing everything from this other table.
There's actually there's two columns there's four columns there's the legislator's idea name there's that JSON list of all of the terms that they've served from a related table and then there's a number of terms as well which is one there and it's 13 here and it's just a count of what's going on.
So the way I'm doing this is two tricks basically this is an aggregate like I showed you earlier so it's select these things group by legislators dot ID so I'm D Juping and grouping on that ID of the legislator and it's a join against legislator terms so I've actually got duplicate records for in fact let's show you the duplicate records.
I'm going to do this as select star from legislators join that and get rid of that group by.
So the actual data that came by is full of jupes right like Watkins Abbott is represented 13 times because Watkins Abbott has been a has had 30 served 13 terms in Congress.
The first step is that we group by legislators dot ID to D Jup those things and we do a let's do a count star here.
And so that gives us back just the ID in the name and then the number of terms that they serve so 13 4 3 5 1 1 1 5.
Oh there's a limit 10 that's why i'm not getting back more than those first ones let's do this again.
So there we go there's all of our different legislators with all those counts and then the real magic here is i'm adding a additional aggregation called Jason group array so what this does is it says.
For every duplicate for each of those duplicate sort of chunks of rows build me an array that joins them all together and in that array i'm going to put a Jason object and the Jason object is these cut these labels and these columns.
So i'm building an object for each one with the type of the state and the start and the end and the party and you can see that in the output here we've got type state start and party in those Jason objects.
So the problem with solving here is one of the if you've been a web application developer for a long time.
This is something that's always is it's always frustrating like I want to pull back all of my blog entries and for each one I want a list of the tags on that blog entry and I don't want to have to run multiple sequel queries to retrieve back those tags.
Once you figure out how to use Jason aggregations like this, you can solve one of the sort of most frustrating problems in web development.
With a sequel query that does all of that fetching for you and I wrote about this quite extensively in this article linked here returning related rose in a single query using Jason and this actually shows you how to do the same thing in postgres as well, so if you're a postgres user it looks slightly different.
Here we go it's Jason and Jason build object what's that.
Yes.
Yeah so here's the exact same trick done in in postgres same idea since the syntax is very slightly different and as a coalescing thing that's explained in this article too.
But yeah this is it's a really powerful trick and it's one of my favorite sort of advanced sequel mechanism because it solves this problem that I've fought so many times as a developer just building standard web applications.
So we talked about CTAs we talked about Jason this is the final advanced feature that I wanted to mention today and this is something called window functions and.
Okay.
The problem these solve is this is sort of a much more powerful analytical problem where you want to do things like rolling averages over time or look at this is specifically important for things like time series data where you need to do rolling averages or some things by a sort of.
But in chunks of your data as it moves along.
And the best way to explain this is to start with this thing here.
What happens if I get rid of that.
Okay, so the problem I'm trying to solve here is I would like to return.
The.
I want to return for every repository in my database I want the name of the repository the date of the most recent release associated with that repository and the three most recent releases as a Jason array so previously I showed you the example with the Jason where we returning everything for each legislator.
We'd return all of that terms and we'd hope that none of them ever served a million terms because it would have broken our query here some of my projects have had over 100 releases I just want the three most recent returned in this query so we're going to start with this query here this is a.
Join we don't even need the CT for this here I'm joining the releases against the repost table and getting back all of that data and you see there's a lot of there's more than 1000 rows because data set itself has.
How many releases is data set had a lot like this is the sort of raw data that we're going to start working with but there's there's a there's a lot of de juping that we need to do here.
What I can do next is I can.
I'm going to add a rank so in order to select just the three most recent it would be useful if I have an indication of the the.
sort of incrementing integer for which release that was for those projects so i'm doing that by adding this little magic piece of syntax here.
And this is what sequel calls a window function it's a feature that was added to sequel like maybe three years ago inspired by its implementation in postgres.
What i'm doing is i'm saying for each of these releases, I want you to create a partition that's.
Unique for each of those repository IDs is ordered by that created date on those releases in descending order.
As well rank hard to sort of see what that means, but if you look at the output what we've just done is we've added a column here this well rank column right at the end.
And it keeps on going up for all of data sets releases data that has had 125 and then we switch to csv to sequel light and that's only had.
wow that's up 13 releases so it goes 12345 up to 13 now on data set cluster map that's had 12345678910 1112.
that's given us, so this is now given us in this single table for the single result we've now got something else that we can filter on to say I just want the three most the top three.
Although we're in the correct order here, I think we're in the wrong order.
No, we're in the we are in the correct order on we were with we're starting with the most recently going down, so now I can do is I can say select star from cta where well where.
Where.
I switch back to us keyboard layout.
Where well rank greater than.
Where well rank greater than or equal to three.
Well, that's less than or equal to three is now.
And this is almost solved our problem for us we're now saying for each of these repositories just show me the three most recent so for data set we get three rows for versions 64264.
Just show me the three most recent so for data set we get three rows for versions 64264164 csv to seek light we just got three rows three rows of cluster map.
Etc, etc, etc, somewhere in this a DBF to seek light has only ever had one release, so it only shows up once.
And, but most of the others we've we've had at least three a data set causes another one with just a single release, but this is almost what we need right, this is if we want the three most recent releases for each package we've now got that data and the last stage is to add that.
Here we go and again i'm taking advantage of my my my common table expression for this one.
i'm adding back in one of those Jason group raise with Jason object and that worked so now for someone is so for data set repo there's 125 releases total.
But there's only three that we care about the recent releases and that's those three that are showing up here with the ID and the name the created app again quite a complex solution.
So we're getting quite a lot of stuff done with this, but by combining the CT mechanism with the Jason group array mechanism with the windows window functions mechanism we're able to do a pretty get a pretty sophisticated result out that if we wanted to you know build a custom application that that shows us that sort of summarized data.
That's most of the work done for us just in this one SQL query right here.
That's a great question.
So the question is what's the computational overhead of doing the Jason construction in SQLite as opposed to in Python I have not measured it my hunch is that SQLite faster.
Because SQLite everything in SQL like SQLite is it's all see it's incredibly well optimized and the benchmarking they do and it's absolutely extraordinary my hunch is that.
And I've the thing I have benchmarked is things like how fast can the Jason functions in SQLite like crunch through gigabytes of data and it's just astonishingly fast at processing things I've actually got quote from Paul Ford that I dropped into the section here.
Where Paul Ford when talking about SQLite's JSON support said the JSON interface is like we save the text and when you retrieve it we pass the JSON several hundred megabytes a second and you can do path queries against it please stop overthinking it this is a filing cabinet.
Paul Ford's trick that he uses all the time is he gets JSON from somewhere and he literally just loads it into a SQLite table which has one row per object with a blob of JSON and that's it.
And then he uses SQLite's built in JSON features to extract bits of it out and convert things and all of that.
He'll often then save the results to a new database table but do all of his data processing with JSON functions inside of SQLite itself.
I'm not quite there yet I like I haven't embraced it to quite that extent but it is a phenomenally performant way of working with data and I feel like most data these days comes in comes in JSON shape.
If you've got a database engine that can do JSON really well and SQLite does do JSON really well you find yourself leaning on that more and more.
Like I always try and get things into a relational table eventually because then you can do faceting and filtering and all of that kind of stuff but there is a lot you can get done just using blobs of JSON if you've got a fast C library on top of it all.
Okay we are running close to time I can just finish this last section I wanted to show you some some fun some more fun demos the kind of things that I've been using I've been building data set with.
And basically this is a chance for me to show off some of my my my websites that I like.
So the first website I'm going to show you is this is the website for my personal my my main hobby and outside of technology I love I basically collect tiny museums.
So the goal is whenever you're in a new city and I mean I've never been Salt Lake City before and there are some very interesting tiny museums around here.
So try and find the smallest museums and go to those first because if it's a really tiny museum it doesn't matter what it's about the chances are the person who collected the stuff is there running the museum and then you get to have a conversation with somebody who collects evidence of Bigfoot or PES dispensers or little devil statues or whatever it is and it's super super rewarding.
So this website is where I put all of the tiny museums that I found and gone to and you can actually say use my location and they'll show you the Don and Memorial State Park visitor center 450 miles away is the closest that I've been to here so I've clearly not explored Utah and Colorado at all yet.
But anyway this is just data set this website right here is the same data set web application you saw earlier but data set lets you use custom templates and so here I've got a custom template for the home page that makes it look like a website about museums and I've got like this is a custom template that knows how to put things on a map and the search feature is just another canned query and you can tell that because if you go to nichemuseums.com slash browse it's data set this is this is the website there's the museums.
I think this one it's deployed on it's got plugins all of that kind of stuff is deployed on the cell so it costs me nothing to run every time I add a new museum to it it's close a new version of the site which works just fine but the one thing I did want to show you is that this website has an RSS feed.
So you can click that and you get XML back that you can subscribe to in a feed reader that's actually defined using a sequel query there's this query called browse slash feed it's this giant monstrosity of a sequel query here it's using Jason each and coalesce and all of that kind of stuff but the output of that query is this table it's got columns atom ID atom title atom updated and then there's a data set plugin called data set atom which only fires when a table has these columns.
And it adds the atom extension and it turns that into XML and I've actually got a few other plugins along those lines there's one called data set ICS that can output subscribable ICS calendar files it's kind of fun it's I'm effectively using sequel as a integration language where as developers we spend so much of our lives getting data in one format and transforming ever so slightly into another format sequels really good at that you can say select something as atom ID something as
atom link and it'll transform it into that other format and then if you've got plugins that know how to output things in different shapes you can sort of pipe it all together and now you've got a sort of an out of the box engine for reformatting data into different formats which is something I played with a whole bunch and I think is really neat.
I'm going to skip my other example from this section and jump to one last thing which is a project that sort of illustrates what happens when you pull all of this stuff together.
So I've got a blog this blog I've been running for 20 years it's been a Django app for most of its life it's a Django and postgres runs on heroku and that's really cool like it's it's it works it's got the Django admin and all of those features but these days I like to do things with sequel and data set.
So I have a copy of my blog running at data set Simon Willis and dot net this is my blog as a sequel like database and the way that works is I've got a GitHub action script running here which let's see this one's what 26 star slash two can anyone remember what that means is that every two hours.
Yes so this runs every two hours and every two hours it grabs a backup of my database from heroku as a postgres dump and it converts that into a sequel like database and it just gets those tables and it I think it would that's the password column because I don't want the password column out there runs a few little transforms drop a few tables bloody bloody bloody blah and then at the end it runs data set publish.
Where's the data publish bit somewhere way down here.
There we go.
Run Simon Willis and blog dot DB with a bunch of extra options and it stills a bunch of plugins but effectively every two hours the latest version of my blog gets published to a data set instance here which means I can run sequel against all of my stuff and run queries and searches and all of the sort of data set goodness is available to me.
But what I wanted to do is I wanted to stop I wanted to start a sub stack newsletter because I wanted people who only ever use email to be able to subscribe to my blog but I didn't want to do any extra work like I'm already putting stuff in my blog I wanted the simplest possible way of getting my blog's content into a into newsletter format.
Sub stack do not give you an API like sub stack they give you a text editor rich text editor to write content in they do not give you anything to help automate that process.
But you can copy and paste things into the sub stack editor so I'll go here I'll go new post here we go this right here is quite a good rich text editor it can do bold and links and headings and images and all of that kind of stuff.
So what I did is I built myself a tool using an observable notebook called blog to newsletter and this is basically a giant bundle of JavaScript which hits the data set API on my blog fetches back all sorts of different bits of content and all of that kind of stuff I think it's actually.
There's a terrifying sequel query in here somewhere here we go this is the sequel query that I put together which reads from five different tables and glues things together and sorts by and collect and all of the CTE tricks and all of that kind of stuff.
And based on running that thing there I get a I get this table of data so this has my titles my URLs and different types of content and so forth and then I've got a bit of JavaScript at the top that glues it together into markdown.
And so that generates HTML this previews the HTML and then this right at the very top I've got a big great copy button.
Actually let's do here we go so I can click copy and then I can go to sub stack and hit paste and that's my newsletter and done so I in this case I do that title there I'd stick that in the title at the top I had some kind of subheading and I click send and it's done and this has I mean this this is meant that sending out my newsletter which I do once or twice a week takes about a minute and a half like end to end.
But if you look at the moving pieces that are going on here this is my blogs and Django and I've got the GitHub actions that are pulling it from Postgres and converting that to SQLite and then I published that to Google Cloud Run and then I went JavaScript and Observable to pull it all together.
But it kind of just works you know once once I piece those bits and pieces together I didn't like one of the things I like about using observable notebooks this is I don't even have to like commit code to get her broken a text editor all of the all of the like the hard work that I've done.
Like the hard work that I didn't hear was done just directly in this notebook interface right here so it's kind of cool and I think that's a nice sort of illustration of what the kind of think projects you can do once you've got once you've got all of these different components working together.
So we've only got three minutes left and I've covered everything that I wanted to cover.
Let's do let's do three minutes of questions.
Yes, there's one that was back.
Yeah.
Yeah, there's something I didn't get into today is the data set actually sports or SQLite sports views right SQL views.
And there's actually there's an example of one here on the data set website. This is a view. This is the recent releases view, which does a join between the releases and the repost table a bunch of the stuff that we were playing around with earlier, but because it's defined as a view data set treats it just like another table.
So you've now got the same interface, you can like facet by topics and order by date and get things out as Jason all of that kind of stuff. So it behaves exactly like it was a table, except that it's defined as an as an extra SQL feature.
And that's super. That's something I find myself doing a lot is I'll get a bunch of raw data in a normalized form, and I'll use the views to create those sort of de normalized convenient let convenience layers.
And then you can get that out as Jason as well. So if you want a Jason API for very specific shape of data, one of the quickest ways to do that is to define a view and do it that way.
I got to stare at people until I get one more question.
Oh, yes, sir.
Oh yeah, so so if I don't want to build a database abstraction I what about using SQL alchemy. It's a good question.
I've never quite gelled with SQL alchemy like SQL alchemy is it's big and complicated. And so with data set, I've kind of been trying to minimize my dependencies. My biggest dependency for data set is ginger the templating language which I feel has sort of proved itself over many years.
And to be honest, SQL alchemy has proved itself as well. I don't think I'd be making a mistake to lock myself in SQL alchemy. The thing I'm worried about is dependencies where they might have backwards incompatible changes next year and all of that kind of stuff.
But yeah, it could be that SQL alchemy would help me help solve my database abstraction problem really well. But I've just not really dug into it enough. My hunch at the moment is that data set actually doesn't have many bits of it that would differ between different databases.
It's mainly the way the table page works, which is at least quite isolated like I'm refactoring that code at the moment. So I'm thinking maybe pluggable database backends wouldn't be as difficult as I'd initially thought they were. And if I do do pluggable database backends, the first two are going to be duck DB and postgres.
Because I feel like if you can do those two, that's 90% of the world of the sort of data problems in the world fit into SQLite or duck DB or postgres.
Okay, well, we're at time. So thank you all very much for coming along. I will be hanging around here for another 15 minutes. Happy to talk about this stuff more. The handout will stay available forever. I'm going to update it. I'll probably turn bits of it into more official data set tutorials as well.
And I'm super keen on feedback on this stuff. Like anything that didn't make sense, anything that could be easier, ideas for future projects, I want to hear all of them. And I'm here for the rest of PyCon. So again, thank you very much.