Let's go ahead and get started as folks are coming in here.
So thanks, everyone, for allowing me to present today.
And a big thanks to the Python Software Foundation for everything that they do and everything
that we can have the privilege of working with them on here at Google.
My name is Jason Davenport.
For those of you who I have not met, looking forward to some exciting Q&A here in a little
bit.
But just a little bit about me as we start to get in.
I've been at Google Cloud for about two and a half years.
I am currently the head of developer advocacy for our data analytics products.
So that includes everything from Cloud Composer, which is a large Python project, to BigQuery,
which is our serverless data warehouse that we'll get to talking about here in a couple
minutes.
And prior to that, I was a practice director for a global implementer focusing on software
engineering and cloud data engineering and warehousing for that.
In my free time, when I'm not chasing my children, I like to do things in the DevOps space.
So as folks here are thinking about how do you do more with your data across environments,
I would love to hear how you're using DevOps and DataOps in your processes when you have
the chance.
So what are we going to talk about today?
So this thing will cover some of the innovations that we've launched over the past what I'll
call six to 12 months focusing on how we bring more language interoperability to our data
analytics stack at Google.
We'll talk through some things with data frames, some different components of serverless, and
then I will do a couple different demos of each of those things just to make it real
for those in the room.
And then last, open up for Q&A once it's all over.
I'm planning just for those aware about a half hour of content demos and then questions
from the room we can start fielding as we get into it.
All right.
How many folks here use Google today?
It's about half the room.
Always great.
I would love to see everyone here using Google at some point.
No shameful promotion in that.
A couple things just to call it.
So I think folks here are aware Google is really a company that has championed contributions
to the open source community and then we do a lot of things with those that then become
our products that we actually share with you in Google Cloud and across some of our different
things like our ad stack.
Folks may remember we actually wrote a paper about MapReduce technology.
This is probably back in 2006 or 2007.
This became what was then known as Apache Dremel which is actually the backbone of
BigQuery which is our serverless elastic data warehouse, whichever word you choose to put
in front of that.
That notwithstanding, there's actually a number of other things that we have worked with the
community on and then open source and continue to contribute on.
Big table for those who may not be aware.
Apache HBase is obviously the open source derivative of that.
Who here doesn't know about Kubernetes?
That's something where we donated essentially our code to the CNCF community.
And then we've done a number of things along the way for things like data flow in the Apache
Beam community and then obviously TensorFlow and the learnings that have come from that.
So as we think through how do we continue to bring innovation to market with that, a
lot of it is driven from the community like yourself helping us to understand what are
the things that we can do with our products to make them better and then making sure that
we enable access for everyone in order to actually have that technology available.
All right, so let me do a quick overview of BigQuery because that's where we'll largely
be spending our time today once we get into it.
How many people here have heard of BigQuery and or use BigQuery?
All right, so about a third of the room.
How many folks here work with databases?
All right, I should have started with that question.
BigQuery is a large serverless database at its core and it's right off the notion that
we fully separate our storage and our compute from the layers of the database itself.
So what does that actually mean in implementation?
It means first off, you never pay for BigQuery for the compute unless you're actually using it.
So the only thing that you're ever actually being persistently charged for is the storage
and that is something that we do behind the scenes using a file format called Capacitor,
which is a columnar-based format for data.
What does that mean using a columnar-based format versus a row-based format?
Well, columnar is a lot faster for analytic workloads, so think of it as like getting
the total of all of my sales over a range of time.
Columnar is really great for that.
Other databases use row-based.
If you think of things like MySQL or Postgres, Postgres has a couple columnar things, but
those are really focused on how do I pick a record, get a record, so what is Jason Davenport's
user value that we may return in an application for that.
These are all relational databases, not to be confused with NoSQL-based.
We do have some ways that we can integrate with those, but we'll save that for another day.
So with BigQuery, I have my storage, I get all my data in.
What that means then is I can do all these different compute-based things in order to
actually analyze that, make sense of it, and then share it with other downstream either
applications or systems or people in that.
We use essentially Google's backplane here, so it's a petabit network.
You can do things at massive scale here.
We have customers that are running, I think, the largest query.
The single query that someone has executed is upwards of 250 petabytes.
It's very, very large.
What that essentially means is that we can scale up to that, but we can also do things
on megabytes of data or kilobytes of data.
It's really up to you as the developer how you want to bring your data to BigQuery and
then how you want to manage it in there.
The other thing with that is while we do support essentially a standard SQL dialect, we have
a REST API, and then we have all of our great client libraries which we support.
That's what we'll be getting into talking about here in a couple of minutes with our
Python support and extensions that we've been launching in it.
All right.
One of the things that we typically see, and this is what I'll call the history of Google
in the process, Google Cloud really started out as a way where you could use an API to
do just about anything against a database or another platform or technology that we
had.
Write a REST API request, execute a Git, get data back.
That was great if you were a software developer and you already understood things like how
do I interact with a REST API, how do I catch errors, all those different things with it.
What we realized is that how to start really democratizing access to data required us to
also add things like SQL.
We had a legacy version that essentially was a homegrown one we built.
We decided let's implement a standard SQL version based on ANSI, so it's ANSI compliant.
Then with that, we started really democratizing even more access to data because folks could
do things like write simple create table statements, write selects, export that data, and then
share all the goodness with that.
If you think about the community and how things have changed, at the same time we were doing
all this work, the other thing that started happening was that the Spark community started
really getting active and we started seeing a lot of growth and momentum, in particular
with things like data frames.
For those who are following at home in terms of the very quick evolution of Spark in 30
seconds or less, Spark started off with a concept called RDDs.
They were super fast.
They were very difficult to build.
They moved to another thing called data sets, which were slightly easier to build but still
somewhat difficult to work with.
Then they actually ended up on data frames, which is essentially a scalable way where
you can use programmatic languages to express what you want to do with data and data formats
and that.
Let's talk about what's great about data frames.
First thing with data frames is they are very easy to test compared to SQL.
If you've ever written a piece of SQL before, you know that, well, one, the code tends to
be very wet, so you have to repeat yourself for very similar things that may happen.
It's also very difficult to catch errors and to actually understand at a unit level what's
happening and then how do I validate that that unit makes sense as a part of the system.
Typically when I work with folks on pure SQL pipelines, we're focusing more on integration
tests and quality tests than we are actually being able to get down and say, does this
case statement work in the way that it's intended to for this very small unit of code in that?
Data frames allow us to do a lot more.
First we can express all of our code using the language syntax of our choice.
The other thing with that is that we can actually do a lot more in terms of testing and then
integration with that into our current application stacks.
If we think about how does a data frame enable a web application, we can write our data frame
in Python, it can be stored within our application framework, and then all that we need to do
is have something that actually takes that data frame and then translates it into our
database in order for execution.
The other thing that's great about data frames is they work really great with Jupyter notebooks.
For those here who are not familiar with notebooks, those are essentially interactive kernels
which allow you to do things like data analysis in real time.
I can do things like express different functions, maybe look at how I would calculate different
fields, and all these things, at least until very recently, were things that I could just
run locally and then do within my instance.
With that, really the question is, if you think from our perspective, how do we make
sure that if a user is interacting with a serverless data warehouse, that they can use
the programming language and the programming tools of their choice in order to interact
with it?
Great leading, right?
Here's where we start talking about data frame support.
What this really is for us is how do we enable that programmatic access to BigQuery by using
data frames and making sure that developers can pick the way that they want to interact
with their data in the process.
With that, one of the big things that we've been doing is working with the IBIS project,
which is a large data frame project in the community, to make sure that the BigQuery
support here is the best that it can be, and that we're also extending this even further
You'll have in the future very similar Pandas capabilities, Pandas being a data frame library
on top of IBIS or on top of BigQuery in that.
Let's briefly talk about IBIS and why it's really useful here.
First off, it allows us to express all of our different things as code, and not just
SQL code, but actually data frames like syntax, so we can then test each component.
It's very easy to see if we step through our code, what different things are happening
and how am I mutating a table or a row or a column over time.
Next thing, unlike Pandas, IBIS is what's called a lazy evaluator.
IBIS will not actually execute our code until runtime.
What's great about that is if you think about typically in Pandas how you may be constrained
into a node or a set of nodes if you're maybe using an operator like Dask, what's great
about using IBIS is that we can essentially hold execution until we get the final kind
of query that's going to be executed.
What that means is that we can push down all of that work to BigQuery, make BigQuery do
all of our work and then just get the results set back for IBIS.
If you think of this in a production setting, this is where we really start to harness the
power of cloud compute because we can have something that's fully elastic, scales up
when a user requests something but then shuts down at the end once the query is executed
and I can get that result back.
Last but not least, this is as of last week when I was talking to some of the contributors,
IBIS actually supports 16 different backends.
What's great about this, maybe you have BigQuery, you have Postgres, you can use IBIS to essentially
do the same sorts of expressions across a number of different databases in that process.
So I'll do a quick picture here and then we'll actually show this running here in a couple
of minutes.
But what you can see here, I pulled up just a very quick Python statement and then we'll
run it here in a second.
But what's great about this, there's some stuff up here in terms of the syntax, I'm
doing my authentication, all that.
But then I'm actually just using Python-based operators here, data frame operators to express
how I want my code to actually be executed.
So I'm doing things like casting some of my different fields, extracting different elements
of the field, doing some group buys and aggregates.
Then all of these things essentially I can just execute at the end with a simple execution
command of the database for that.
All right.
So we talked a little bit about how do I start working with data frames but really with that,
If a Python object is kind of a block that we need to execute, the question is, well,
okay, that's great, but how do I actually execute my code on BigQuery?
Because it's Python and you told me that BigQuery is a SQL-based interface for that.
So the next thing that we've launched, and I believe this is in public preview now, is
the ability to actually run PySparks stored procedures from within BigQuery itself.
So what this means is that as I build my data frame, I can now just store that code in BigQuery
from a single pane of glass, and then I can actually run that PySpark code or that data
frame code on an arbitrary set of compute.
And what I mean by that is that we can essentially take our data frame code that we have and
we could either execute it on the BigQuery compute side, so using our forked version
of Dremel, or we could actually run this on Spark.
So I don't have to take my code, I don't have to reevaluate all of it for how BigQuery would
execute, I can just use a serverless Spark instance to run that code.
It'll execute, once it's done it'll spin back down, and then I get the benefits essentially
of being able to use all these great technologies together in the same place.
So what does this look like?
Very similar to what we just looked at for the IBIS code.
I'm just using essentially a decorator block up here where I'm creating a procedure, and
then I'm just writing some Spark context code and I can put in here anything that I want,
different libraries or things that are required.
But what this allows us to do is to essentially run any code that I need against my data to
make sure that I'm getting that analysis and that activation that I was hoping for.
All right, so we've started going through, we've started building out some of the different
ways we can build Python-based compute.
But one of the next questions that a lot of our users get is, I'm afraid of lock-in, why
do I have to put all of my data into the BigQuery-based format?
And then how could I actually get access to that data but make sure it's in an open format
or an open source format where it's something that's a community-driven thing that I can
use and leverage.
So next thing there, what we've been working on is a set of storage-based technologies
which we call Big Lake.
And what Big Lake allows you to do is to interact with things like Apache Iceberg format for
your data.
And for those who are curious, Iceberg is what I'll call kind of a variant of the Parquet
format.
It allows you to actually track things like state within the file.
So as I have a table and it changes over time, Iceberg will essentially keep track of the
metadata of what's changed and then will give me essentially the ability to do things like
updates or inserts or deletes on the Parquet-based format.
So what this really means for our users or for you following along is that you can pick
whatever file format you want to store your data in.
Obviously there will be some benefits for typically speed and performance if you use
the Google format of Capacitor.
But if there are reasons for your organization to bring your own kind of files or work maybe
with Iceberg across a number of different compute engines, we're bringing that and making
that easily accessible to you as the user.
And this is just a quick overview of how the Big Lake API actually works.
And we'll see it here in a demo just with the actual code execution.
But what we essentially allow you to do is to either use our file format or bring your
own, use streaming, and then we provide a unified API on top of all that for that data
access.
So here what the focus is really on is making sure that from your perspective as the end
user, this is simple and it's open and it's easy to understand and execute in the app.
All right.
So we have all these formats.
We've talked about how we start to transform the data, how we use data frames.
The big thing now is, okay, how do I start enriching that data and then how do I actually
get to execute my great Python code that I wrote on my database for that?
And so next thing we'll talk about here is remote stored procedures.
And so what remote procedures allow you to do is to essentially execute any set of code
against BigQuery using something like a cloud function, which is essentially a serverless
function that you can run in Google Cloud.
And I can take whatever data I may have.
In this case, I'm going to select some stuff from a comments table.
And then I can execute my Python script against that data just using a remote function in
that.
So this is really, I think of it as kind of like a Swiss army knife of the ways you can
work with code.
I found this to be very valuable.
In particular, many companies and users aren't thinking about terabytes or petabytes of data.
You have 50,000 records that you need to augment with something else.
Remote functions makes it ridiculously easy to do that because I can just write a function.
I can select my data.
I can add something else to that data.
And then BigQuery will just materialize that as a new table or as the result of the select
statement in that.
So all this makes it really easy to make sure whatever Python you want to go write or to
code that you can then bring your data to that with BigQuery and make it very easy and
seamless from the execution perspective.
And then last but not least, one of the most recent things we've actually been working
on and launching is the ability to access what we call unstructured metadata as a part
of BigQuery.
So if you think about things like object analysis or image analysis, you'll end up with a bucket
which is just kind of a logical grouping of objects where you may need to pass in what
are the locator records for each of those.
What you can now do with object tables is essentially store all that metadata in BigQuery
and then allow all the different compute engines to access the metadata and then the binaries
assist you with that.
So in this case, the images to then perform additional analysis on top of that.
And we'll see a demo here really quickly about how all these come to life by essentially
using remote functions with object tables to be able to use Python to analyze all this
data but keep the access management in BigQuery and make it very easy for end users to get
to the data within it.
Here's a quick thing here.
You can see we're doing some house-based analysis.
We have all those objects but the only thing we've had to do here is actually create an
external table and an external table is just that pointer to all those files.
I think in total it's like ten lines of code or less.
So if you think about all the other processes that you may have to run, we try to make it
really, really simple to do this stuff with BigQuery and then with different Python libraries.
All right.
So we'll go through the graph slides because those are fun enough but code's more fun.
So let's go ahead and we'll walk through.
First thing we'll start with is how some of the data frame stuff comes to life and then
we'll step through each of these examples and build on that in the process.
All right.
Can folks in the back see okay?
Awesome.
All right.
So the first thing that we're going to execute, you can see that I have some code here that
I've created.
I'm just using a notebook from Visual Studio Code but what I've done is I've essentially
taken that IBIS script that we're going to execute and then we're going to actually go
through and start to execute this code against some of the different data points here.
So all that I need to do, we'll run this first one.
My auth did not have to re-happen so that's great.
Sorry, one second, let me pull up.
All right.
So you can see here if I come back, we can see that this query actually executed so I'm
kind of using a dual screen method here just to show how is my code actually being formulated
and run.
What's cool about this is if you think about what we actually expressed using the IBIS
syntax here for the data frame, you can see we've used things like mutate in order to
actually add additional columns to that data.
We've also done some order buys and group buys and aggregates.
What this actually does if I come in and look at the query that was executed, as you can
see that IBIS took all of that data frame logic and then it actually went and wrote
the SQL that needs to be executed against BigQuery.
And what's great about this is that if we think about all those different steps, because
IBIS only evaluated and executed at the very end, it was able to optimize the statement
so that I would actually only get that result and I would only incur the charge of running
that query once against the database.
So from the BigQuery perspective, we can see that we have a couple different records that
were executed.
One thing here just to call out because I was running this last night, BigQuery, we
also store a result cache.
So essentially anything up to I believe 24 hours that your user ID executes.
If it's the exact same code and there's no things like current timestamp in that, we
won't actually charge you again for running it.
We just return that result set to you again because we're already storing it in the process.
So we can see what's great about that is I've taken my code and then what I've been able
to do is actually express it within the syntax.
I could add maybe additional unit tests around this and maybe I would actually apply this
and say, hey, I want to show my end users the sum of their sales over the past 30 days
and just have that return to an ID or web interface.
This easily integrates with my microservices and all those other things behind the scenes.
All right.
Different problem.
Similar vein.
One of the things that's always really difficult is building on top of data because as I work
through these different steps, what we saw earlier was essentially the pre-built code.
As I'm building, one of the things that I'm typically doing is thinking about, well, is
what I did, so the group by that I did, does that actually make sense?
Does the join that I wrote, did I accidentally create a Cartesian product which is essentially
a many to many join?
What IBIS also allows you to do in this case is to use what's called the interactive mode.
An interactive mode based on wherever we actually go on this here will execute in real time
as we're going through each of the steps.
So the benefit here if you think about things like type mismatches are a very common one.
I can essentially iterate in real time and look at these different results.
So here what I could do, I'll just go ahead and start running this block.
We can see here that I'm creating that hour column here, but what I'm doing is actually
just looking at this in real time, so it's actually going and pushing down the execution.
It's a big query for each of the different steps that are running through it.
So what's really great about this is we're kind of solving for two worlds of things.
One is how do I do interactive analysis?
The other one is okay, I did that interactive analysis, how do I actually make this a production
thing that's going to go run?
And we can do it from a single library just using some flag changes in order to make the
process work for what we want to do.
All right, great stuff about IBIS.
Let's talk then about what we're working on at Google in order to extend this even further.
So while IBIS, if you notice, looks very similar to a data frame, it is not exact to the pandas
functions and kind of the spec around that.
So the next thing that we are working on here is how can we actually take that and then
make what we're calling big frames, which is a pandas compatible API on top of all these
things.
And what I'm showing you here, I'm just in Google Colab, which is an almost serverless
notebook that anyone here could go and open and then run against BigQuery pieces.
What we're doing, I'm just installing the big frame wheel.
But then you can see here that what I'm doing is I'm actually pulling in a data frame using
my context here.
Then interacting with this with the exact same syntax that I would in pandas.
So again, really the intent here is meeting you as the developer where you are and making
sure that whatever syntax we have available is similar to what you're using to make the
product the most accessible in that.
So here you can see once I pull that in, I'm just connecting to my context.
I'm reading that table from BigQuery.
In this case, it's a taxi trip table.
I'm doing things like filtering down based on the number of columns.
I can also do things like creating subtotals of my data, which I'm just displaying here
as a part of the code.
All right.
More to come on the big frame stuff.
Right now we are still actively developing this.
But IBIS, if I didn't mention earlier, is already available for you to go and download
today and to start using with these different pieces.
All right.
So we've done a lot of discussion here about data frames.
Let's talk about how we can start to use some of the different execution things within this
to make it happen.
Next thing here that I'm showing, and apologies, let me make the screen a little bit easier
to see, is essentially how we can take those data frames or our PySpark code or our other
code and be able to execute what we call the Spark stored procedures on top of BigQuery.
As you can see, what's great about this is I have a few things here where I'm just doing
some specifications.
This would be no different than if you were working with a Spark job, maybe providing
some custom URIs for jars or something else.
What I can do then is essentially just say, what is my PySpark code?
I want to execute this.
Then what it will do is manage everything behind the scenes, including the creation
of instances to execute the code, the actual code execution, the logging and error handling,
and then ultimately the spin down of those instances, and it's seamless to you as a
user in that process.
So once we have those executed, what's actually great about this, and for the sake of the
demo, it takes about a minute to spin up the instances and then execute the code, so I
won't go through that full piece.
But what you can see is we actually create a table here.
So we have our products, and then we could actually come and just query this table like
anything else.
What this is doing behind the scenes is this is actually an iceberg table that I have stood
up in my data warehouse.
If we come over to our bucket and click in, you can see here that I have my metadata.
These are JSON objects that essentially tell that table, okay, what are the actual files
to pull in?
And I have my data itself.
You can see here these are all of my different Parquet files that I have actually been creating
over time in that process.
So again, what we're essentially able to do in this, if you think of in your shoes as
the Python developer, is we can bring what I'll call kind of an arbitrary file format
of data.
So we work with the newest things like iceberg, obviously Parquet, CSV, JSON, all those things.
And then I'm also actually able to start bringing arbitrary compute to that data.
So in this case, we could use our BigQuery compute or we could use our serverless Spark
compute.
And what that really just enables for you is the choice to pick where you want your
code to execute and then to use the right platform for the right job in that.
All right.
So almost through here.
Second to last thing we'll talk through is how we can then use our object tables.
So here what I'm doing is, again, just using some simple SQL for the table creation.
I'm creating a object table here.
And then you can see here I've done a quick specification here that this is a directory
of object metadata.
So I want all of the metadata about the directory.
I'm pulling in data from this cloud storage bucket.
And then what we can actually do is start looking at some of the things that are pulled
into that.
So let me go ahead and run the statement here.
Here you can see what we've essentially done is pulled in every URI that exists in that
bucket.
So in this case the URI is just the file location in the object storage.
We have things like our hashes.
We have things like when was the file last updated.
And what we can actually do then is start to pass this into other things in order to
do more analysis or work for that.
And we're going to actually do just that here.
What we're going to do is we're creating a table called a vision detection.
And what this will do, and then we'll look at the code behind the scenes here in a minute.
Is that we're going to actually execute one of those remote procedures.
And what this is going to do is it's going to actually send our data or the components
of data that we request in the function out to a cloud function.
We're going to have Python essentially organize and map how that data should then be transformed.
And then we're going to return that back to our essentially materialized results set here
as a result of that.
So while that's running, what we can actually do is flip over.
And you can see here, I've just created a simple Python function.
But what this does is take in our request.
And in this case, the request, because it's a function within the select statement, is
a set of values that go in.
We're going and actually calling the vision API.
And what this allows us to do then is to do things like annotate our images with additional
information.
So one of the things that may be popular is, hey, I have images.
How do I actually know that there's a logo or something in that if there's maybe concerns
around that?
This allows us to take all those pieces and then return this back to the BigQuery results
set, store it in BigQuery, and then allow other users actually to access that maybe
in a dashboard or something else downstream.
All right.
So we can see our rows are there.
What I'll go ahead and do is just go ahead and run a quick select off that.
You can see here that what we've done is we've actually injected all of our metadata that
was associated with an image.
And you can see here that for one of the records, we actually identified that there may be personally
identifiable information on this.
So that's probably something we would want to look at and scrub depending on where this
data was going.
We also actually detected a face in this.
And then we detected something with a car in that.
So if you think about one of the big things now is obviously how do we keep data safe.
There are a lot of ways here using different technologies that we can essentially make
it very simple to identify where we may have potential issues in our data and really make
sure that it's being governed in the right way for its use.
And all of this is obviously accessible from BigQuery.
So as you think about how do I share that data downstream, we're not passing around
files right on a server or an object store.
We're actually letting everything be managed via a set of role-based access controls in
BigQuery, making it easy to share but also making it scalable in terms of the sharing
capabilities on that.
All right.
So a quick summary here.
So first thing we started off with was how do we build a Pythonic-based data frames and
how do we actually execute those against BigQuery using IBIS?
Can we also do the same thing using big frames and more of a pandas like syntax?
And then what we got into is, OK, how do we take that code and then how do we actually
execute that from BigQuery using something like PySpark or using remote functions where
we could run any Python that we wanted against our data and then get that result set back?
So with that, really appreciate everyone attending today.
And with that, I will pass it over to questions and feel free to keep it open for anything
Google Analytics or sorry, Google Data Analytics related.
The only caveat is I cannot talk about genera vea, which I'm sure everyone here loves to
talk about.
So what questions help to answer?
Yeah.
So for the remote procedure call, is it shipping all the data to the function at once or is
it making the call pretty slow?
Yeah.
So the question was how does the remote procedure actually handle record batching and other
pieces in that?
So are we shipping one really, really big thing or are we shipping one thing at a time
in that?
What happens behind the scenes is that we will manage the number of function instances
that have to be spun up and then we will start to parse that out.
So let's say you have 50,000 records.
We may choose behind the scenes that you only need one function to actually execute on that
or we may say, hey, we actually need to spin up five or 10 on that.
We manage how those things have to be batched behind the scenes for you.
So at the end of the day, what you experience is that the code returns the data that you
expected and you're not spending the time troubleshooting like why does the network
hate me in that process?
Does that help to answer your question?
Yeah.
Is there a user case where you can use SAP HANA and make joins with another database?
Yes the question may be, should I cut because I cut a little bit the door in the microphone.
Arthur used cases where we can connect to and do joins based off data that sits in like
SAP HANA and then you materialize that downstream.
Is that correct?
Yep.
We have a couple things here.
So one is that we have a actual framework called Cortex.
What that allows you to do is to connect to a number of different sources with an SAP.
I believe HANA is also one of them.
With that you can then pull that data or replicate that data out of HANA into a tool like BigQuery
and then do what I'll call kind of like a co-location of that and then do your joins,
all of your other pieces with that.
I believe it also ships back but that would just be something that I would probably want
to check in the framework component for that.
If you think for a lot of our customers like they'll use HANA and then something like Spanner
or Postgres which are two of our transactional relational databases, we can query those in
place because we control the location and how the data works in that.
Once you do that, BigQuery can essentially analyze any of that data and then send your
results set back for activation to the SAP platform.
Other questions?
Yeah.
Yep.
So, as it stands right now, remote function essentially runs in Cloud Functions or another
Cloud Run.
And Cloud Run for the technically interested actually powers remote functions.
It's our fully serverless stack for running containers.
As it works right now, what happens is that you'll deploy the function and then it would
execute all of those stacks.
Now there's exploratory things where we're looking at how can we make that even simpler.
So it's literally like you just tell BigQuery here's the Python and we figure out even the
underlying components.
But right now you would deploy that and then the function or Cloud Run would execute that
job.
It's still relatively easy to set up.
I do recognize in the deployment it's one additional step because you've got to ship
that code to like Buildpack or something for that.
Any other questions?
All right.
Well thanks everyone.
I hope this was useful for folks learning more about BigQuery.
I'll stick around here until obviously the end of the session if you have other questions
that you'd like to ask.
But really appreciate your time.
Hope everyone here has a great day at the conference.
And best wishes.