All right. Hi, everybody. Thank you all so much for coming. Really nice to see you all.
My name is Mansi and this is Kevin and we're really looking forward to presenting this
tutorial for you all on analyzing coastal erosion using Python and satellite imagery.
A little bit about each of us. As I said, my name is Mansi. My background is kind of
varied. I have a background in environmental science and also data science and we are both
currently at Planet. So at Planet I work as a software engineer on the developer relations
team and in my spare time when I'm not working I'm also a musician. So I love playing music
and connecting with people that way. Hey. Does this work? Nice. I'm Kevin. I'm also
a software engineer on the developer relations team at Planet. Also the strange background
not in earth imaging at all. In fact, in astrophysics. So basically the same thing but pointing the
camera the other way. And on the spare time I do a lot of mountain biking and just exploring
nature and hopefully if the weather holds up I can try and ride some mountains out here.
So we wanted to mention this because neither of us had I guess maybe Kevin a little bit
more than me but specifically, specific experience working with satellite imagery before we came
to Planet. So we just want to stress that we're really excited that you all are here
even if you've never worked with geospatial imagery before or don't know the first thing
about it or maybe you've never even heard the word geospatial before today that's totally
fine. We sort of came to it at Planet and we're really excited to share it with you.
So in today's workshop we will first talk about some core geospatial and computer vision
concepts that are used in remote sensing. And then we will use this understanding in
the context of Python to use Python tools to do some of this raster and imagery processing
and analysis. And this sort of example section we're going to be using flood data for this
part of it and then we're going to take everything that we've learned and then Kevin is going
to take us through a real world example of analyzing coastal erosion using all of this.
So before I get into this further, I'm just curious, can I have a show of hands who is
totally new to Python in general? Okay, cool. And anyone new to geospatial imagery? Awesome,
yeah, great. All right, so before we get into this, I think it's important to talk about
why we're talking about coastal erosion in the first place. So coastal erosion is defined
as the loss or displacement of land on coastlines due to waves, currents, tide, wind, waterborne
ice, storm impact and other natural and unnatural forces. So the natural weathering of coastlines
is normal but human-led activities has unfortunately made this worse. And bad news, it's going
to get a lot worse. According to the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, risk related to
sea level rise including erosion along all low-lying coasts is expected to significantly
increase by the end of the century without major adaptation efforts. So it's not looking
good unless we do something about it. And this also has long-term environmental and
financial impacts. The long-term impacts of coastal erosion include things like loss of
habitat quality, degradation of coral reefs, increased turbidity of water, reduced tolerance
for communities in the face of these natural disasters and reduced sand volume. So these
environmental impacts are in addition to the millions of dollars that are going to be lost
or spent annually on coastal property loss, tourism collapse and erosion control measures
and that's in the US alone. So overall, a bit of a downer of a slide. But I think it's
important to talk about why these issues matter and why it's really important that we are
looking at this data. All right, let's take a second to talk about Planet's imagery.
Thanks, Melzi. Yeah, I couldn't really see earlier. Has anyone worked with satellite
imagery before? Yeah, has anyone worked with CubeSats? Yeah, cool. A few of you. Cool.
So here at Planet, well not here, well at Planet, we have two different types of satellites.
We have small little CubeSats which we have little builds of here. They're like the size
of a shoebox. They're not very big. They're like 5 kilograms, 10 pounds each. And they're
pretty powerful cameras. They have eight bands, everything between blue and near red, which
we'll talk about later. And they allow you to image stuff like roads, cars, crops, that's
sort of stuff. Then we have larger satellites. SkySats. Actually, I'll mention the doves,
the little ones. We don't tell them to do anything. They just take images all the time.
Whereas the SkySats, these guys are larger. They're the size of like a mini fridge, pretty
heavy, like 100 kilograms, 200 pounds. And we can tell them what to do. So we'll say,
hey, image this part of New York over the next month with these sort of parameters.
And it'll do that. And these things are pretty high resolution. We can image stuff like helipads,
pools, smaller objects. It's used a lot for disaster relief, for instance. And they're
they have the SkySats have different types of bands. They have specifically a really
high resolution band called a pan band. But we're not really going to get into that today
because we're going to look at doves, satellite imagery. Also, if you have any questions about
any of this stuff, please just shout out your question or raise your hand because this can
get kind of technical. And here's a little video of how our satellites work. So here's
the Earth rotating around. And then this is a gif of like how our satellites go around
the Earth. So the cameras are always on taking multiple pictures every second. And as the
Earth goes around, the satellites cover more and more of the Earth. And the same goes with
the SkySats. They're in a similar type of orbit. And then we have the SkySats go into
another orbit. Again, we're not really talking about SkySats today, but it's just kind of
these are meant just to cover more parts of the Earth. Or like let's say you want to take
pictures of the Earth multiple times in one day. It's kind of fun. These purple lines
that you see here, if you can kind of resolve that with your eye, are just imaginary strips
of images that just are composited into one picture of the Earth. You can kind of picture
as like a Google Maps image once a day, which is pretty sweet and pretty powerful tool.
It can be used to monitor forestry, like deforestation or crop yields or different things that you
might want to monitor every day or flooding, for instance, that we'll talk about later
today. Do you guys have any questions about that? No? Cool. I'll hand it over to Manzi.
Thanks, Kevin. All right. So we're going to start by talking about some core geospatial
concepts that will come in handy when we get a little bit further along. So the first
thing to note about geospatial data is that it's special and behaves differently than
maybe a regular image would. Geospatial raster imagery, first thing to note is that it can
be multispectral, meaning that one image can be made up of different bands, and we'll
get to this in a second. Geospatial raster imagery is also spatially referenced, which
means when you see an image of the Earth that's a geospatial raster, that image is tied to
a very specific place on the Earth's surface, and that information is also included in that
image's metadata. So it's an important part about how we work with that image. So the
next slide. All right. So multispectral imagery. Here we're looking at an image of San Francisco
on the right. That image, you're looking at it, it's a color image, it's how you might
see it with your own eyes. That image is actually made up of bands. In this case we have the
red band, the green band, and the blue band. These bands represent different areas on the
wavelength spectrum. So the red band is representative of the red wavelengths, green for green and
blue for blue. A note here is that we can also have bands that we can't see with our
eyes. An example of this is near-infrared. We can't see that, but we can have that as
information with our data. Another thing to note about working with this imagery is that
because these bands are part of the image, you might need to work with it slightly differently
than you would a regular image. So for those of you who have worked with geospatial imagery
before, if you've ever had the experience of downloading an image, then you use your
preview app or whatever the equivalent of that is on Windows. And you try to look at
your image and it's all black or all gray and you can't see anything. And I've definitely
been there where I have a mini freak out and I think that, oh my gosh, my computer's broken,
what's happening? Your computer's not broken. It's just because the image has these bands
that not all programs can process. So you would need to put this image into like a
QGIS for example or similar program for you to be able to see it properly. Another thing
to note is that the pixels in raster imagery can be represented as arrays. So take this
image here on the right. Say it's a beach scene. So we have forest, we have sand, and
we have water. You can imagine that all of the water pixels are represented with similar
values. All of the sand pixels have similar values to each other and then all of the forest
pixels also have similar values. This is especially important to consider because to manipulate
a raster image, we can manipulate it by manipulating the arrays that make up that image. And so
we'll see this in action in a little bit when we use NumPy and Rasterio to kind of work
with these images. All right. Let's talk about resolution. You might have heard this word,
idea of resolution. It's a term that's used a lot and kind of thrown around when we're
talking about satellite imagery, but there are actually several different types of resolution.
So just want to break that down for you all. Let's take this image on the previous slide.
So let's pretend we're looking at this. If we have spatial resolution, say that we're
on this beach that we just saw in the last slide. If we're curious about what area on
the ground is taken up by one pixel on that image, that would be spatial resolution. Spatial
resolution is talking about the ground area per pixel. So say in that image, one pixel
is a three meter by three meter square. The spatial resolution of that image is going
to be a three meter spatial resolution. Then we have temporal resolution. This is talking
about the frequency between image captures. So say we go to this beach, say we went to
this beach in COVID 2020 and then we went to the beach last year, 2022, and then say
we're planning a trip to that same beach next year, 2024. The temporal resolution, and we
take images at each visit to the beach. The temporal resolution of these images is going
to be two years, a two year temporal resolution because we take images every two years.
When we have spectral resolution, this is talking about the number of spectral bands
that are being measured. So say in that image, let's just pretend that we have a red band,
a blue band, and a green band, just a simple visual image. Our spectral resolution would
be three because we have three bands. And then finally, radiometric resolution. This is talking
about bit depth of pixel values. Another way to say this is how much information, how much data
is captured by each pixel. And this can be a little bit confusing to understand, but I think
something that helps us thinking about this as color resolution. So the more data that a pixel
holds, the higher the color, the better color you'll see. And I like this example. I can pull it up
for you guys. If I can find my mouse. All right. So this is just on Wikipedia. So you can see,
you'll see this. Yes. This image down here, this it's the same image of the leaf. This one at the
bottom has a one bit resolution. It looks kind of gray. You almost can't tell it's a leaf because
none of the reds or greens or purples are showing properly. But if you look at this higher resolution
here, you can see all the colors. You can tell it's a leaf that has water drops on it, all this
stuff. So that is kind of bit depth in action. Any questions on any of that before we move on?
Great. Okay. So let's talk about some of the geospatial tools and libraries we are going to
be using as we look more at this data. So we have some foundational software. We're really big,
especially at Planet, about using open source tooling. So we have things like GDAL and Proj
that are kind of the base level foundational software. And then today we're specifically
going to be using a few libraries. Rasterio and NumPy which are used to read and write raster
data and arrays. And then mapplotlib for plotting and then OpenCV as a computer vision library for
some image processing. All right. So this, we promised that y'all this would be an interactive
workshop. So here's where we get to the interactive piece of it. If you all could please go to this
link. It's go.planet.com slash coastal erosion. I'm going to try to make this as fun as possible.
I know it's the last day of tutorials. Post lunch food coma setting in probably. All right. So here's
that link again. So when you get to this page, you should see something, oh, not like that. Avert your
eyes. You should see something like this. Is everyone generally here? I can put that link back
up if y'all need it. Good. Okay. Great. So we are going to run through some examples of working with
imagery and some of the analysis steps that we will use and sort of put together for the full coastal
erosion analysis that Kevin will lead us through later. So what you're looking at right now is a,
it's our notebooks repo at planet. It has a bunch of code examples and things. We'll talk about this more
generally later. But this is our coastal erosion folder. So for this tutorial, we're going to be going
through this using Jupyter notebooks and specifically Google Colab. Who has never used Jupyter notebooks
before? Awesome. We're all very familiar. Yes. Okay. Oh, yeah. Sure. Here's the link again. Yep.
Okay. So since you're all familiar with Jupyter notebooks, we're going to be doing this in Google
Colab. So this will make it so that you don't have to download any data. You don't have to worry about
any of that. It's all just going to be there. So if y'all wouldn't mind going to this first notebook,
one underscore rasterio underscore first look. And if you could open this in a separate tab because we
will be coming back to this page later. And when you get there, it should look something like this.
And then when you're here, you want to click on this blue button that says open in Colab. And that will
open this notebook for you in a Colab instance. So you should be looking at something like this. Is everyone
generally here? Feel free to flag me down at any point if you want a link again or anything like that.
Okay. So in this first notebook, we are going to be looking at reading multispectral data with
rasterio. Things just like grabbing the bands and sort of initially starting to work with it. So in
working with Google Colab, just a quick note, if you would like to change any of this code here,
maybe experiment with stuff on your own or you want to save the output that you get, nothing will
automatically save. But if you want to save it, you can go to this file and then save a copy right
there. So that's one way to save it. Another thing to note about working on this in Colab,
every notebook we work with, we're going to have to grab the data. So to do that, you're going to
have to run this first cell where it says option one, run Google Colab. So to run a cell, you'll
notice if you hover over the cell, there's that play button looking thing. Just click on that.
It will give you a warning saying notebook was not authorized by Google or authored by Google. You
can run it anyway if you trust me. I know you all just met me, but it's fine. I'm not trying to put
any malware on your computers or anything. Yeah. Oh, yeah, sure. Let's see. Is that better?
Okay. And then the way to tell that a cell is finished running in Google Colab, I know it's
kind of difficult to see, there's this green check mark right next to the play button. And if you see
that, that means that cell has run. So we're all good. Okay. So first thing we're going to do is
we're going to load our data set. So we're going to import our Rasterio package. And then we're
going to point this image file variable to our image file. And then we're going to establish our
open data object using Rasterio.open. And we're going to call that open image satellite data.
So you can see here that that's the name of our open satellite data object. And then we can look
at some basic information about this object. So we have the name of the data set. This looks like
a random string of numbers. This is actually the date, the beginning part of this 2017-831
is the date that this image we're working with was taken on. For context, we're going to be
working with imagery from Hurricane Harvey in 2017 in Texas, in Houston. So this is real imagery
that was used to aid recovery efforts and sort of help people on the ground at the time. And we're
going to be using that imagery for this series of examples to kind of help guide us through.
And then you can also see the number of bands in this data set. So here, set.count, we see we have
three bands. And then we can look at the indexes of the bands. One thing to note here, if you're
used to doing stuff in Python, Python indexes by zero. So if you have a list of objects, the first
item in that list is going to be in the zeroth place. For bands, they are one indexing. So the
first band is one, second band is two, and third band is three. Just something quirky to know about
working with bands. And because we know the kind of imagery we're working with, in this case,
a planet scope three band image, we know our band order. So we can kind of establish that,
and then call our bands by name. So here, we're just assigning blue, green, and red to our bands.
Then we can print the data type of our bands just to check they're stored as numpy arrays.
And then using the blue band as an example, we can just look at the width and height of our
image in pixels. So this particular image that we're working with is around 8.3
thousand pixels wide and then almost 4,000 pixels high.
Any questions about this first notebook? Just kind of bringing up the data in Rasterio?
Great. All right. Moving right along. So now we're going to work with Rasterio
in our image to extract bands and compose a scene. So we're going to take our different bands and
then bring them together to kind of see in action how the bands come together to form an image.
So now you'll want to go back to this page. If you didn't open it up in a different tab,
I'll pull up the link again. Here's that link.
So we're going to go back there. And now we're going to do the second notebook. So open up this
to underscore Rasterio notebook in a separate tab and then click on that blue open in Colab
button and you should be looking at this.
All right. Everyone generally here? Okay. Great. So again, we're going to need to do this every
time. So if you're running this in Colab, go ahead and run this first cell. That just grabs our data
for us.
Okay.
Taking a while.
All right. Great. So we've got our data. Now we can install our packages again. So we have
our stereo again, but we're also going to be using NumPy this time and matplotlib.pyplot.
So again, we want to grab our image. We're going to open it.
And we have our open data set object. Now we're going to look at the image metadata. So we can do
this by doing sat.crs. So we see here that it says this is to get the images coordinate reference
system and we see the output is EPSG32615. This is not something that I know. This might be looking
to you like some gibberish something. This corresponds to WGS84 world geodetic system
84 UTM15 north. This I wouldn't know unless I had just looked it up before this. So it's not
something that I have memorized. It's just this EPSG code corresponds to this projection.
And because we know this projection, we know that the units, the projected units of this are in
meters. So then because we know that, we can look at this minimum bounding box and these units are
in meters. So this is the bounding box of our image in meters. We can also get the
dimensions of the image also in projected units. So the dimensions of this image in meters are some
25,000 ish meters by 11,700. We can also look at the dimensions of this image in pixels like we did
in the previous notebook. So we see those numbers right here. And then because we know the dimensions
of this image in meters and we also know the dimensions of this image in meters, we can also
look at the dimensions in pixels. We can use this to figure out our spatial resolution. So if we divide our
meter units by our pixel units for height and width, we see that we have a three meter resolution,
three meter by three meter. Just a quick check, are the pixels square? Yes, they are. I don't know
a case in which the pixels won't be square, but I guess good to see. So yes, they are indeed square.
In this case. And then we can convert our pixel coordinates on our image to geographic coordinates
on the globe. So we take the upper left pixel, the lower right pixel, this minus one is here because
the rows and columns are zero indexing. And then we can transform them. And then here we have our
UTM coordinates in meters. And then all of this information, or at least a lot of it, is captured
here in this SATA.profile. So we can see the width and the height in pixels. We can see the band count.
We can see the coordinate reference system, the transformation, all these things are right in here.
All right. So let's figure out how we can compose a scene now that we know how to get to our bands.
So again, we're just going to do a quick look. Yes, we have three bands, one, two, three.
And again, because we know that we are looking at a three-band planet scope image, we know our band
order. So that's what this is, just assigning the names here. And then to construct our visual image,
all we do is we do numpy.dstack and we put all those images together, or all those bands together.
So that is our visual image. And then we can view it.
All right. Here is our image. Was everyone able to get here?
If you didn't stack them like that, or if you stacked a couple, could you look at the individual
bands? Would that be a strategy?
If you switch the order, the colors would also come out differently.
Yes, you could play around with it. One thing to note here, so this is the flood area. This
brown stuff here, that's actually water. That's the sort of flooded area of Houston. Is anyone
from Houston? No, okay. Just wondering. So it's important to note that this brown, muddy water
is what we're going to be looking to identify. And then also note that we have these clouds here.
These white specks are clouds. Clouds are basically the bane of people who work with imagery like us,
like our existence. We hate clouds. Especially on top of snow. Yes. What's cloud? What is snow?
What's water? We have no idea. So this is part of the reason that I bring this up, is because
these clouds might be identified as water when we get into our NDWI calculations. So just something
to keep in mind. Ideally, if you can get imagery without clouds, that would be perfect. I know
that's not always possible. There are sometimes techniques you can use to remove clouds. I know
Planet has a data product that's a usable data mask where it'll just mask over the areas that
are clouds or not usable. So if you have that kind of thing available, that's also good to use.
All right. Moving right along. Let's go back here and we're going to open up number three.
Notebook number three, compute NDWI.
And again, go ahead and run this first cell to get the data.
So here we're going to talk about what NDWI is. We're going to calculate it for our image.
And then we're going to visualize this data and then create a mask, a land mask and a water mask
from this NDWI. Okay. So import packages, get our data. So here we're going to calculate NDWI.
NDWI stands for Normalized Difference Water Index. And this index is related to plant water content
and it helps identify areas of water on the ground. So to calculate the NDWI, you can take
the green band, subtract the near infrared band and then divide that by the green band plus the
near infrared band. So the first thing we're going to do here is we're going to allow division by zero.
This is because our image might have sections of the image that are clipped or masked already or
have values of zero. And when we do this division, the denominator can also be zero. And if that
happens, we don't want our code to just completely stop working. So here we're just allowing division
by zero. Then we can extract the bands we're going to need for the NDWI. So in this case,
you'll notice we're using a four-band image instead of a three-band image.
So we have our blue, green, red and the near infrared band.
And then once we have these bands, we can go ahead and calculate our NDWI
with that same calculation, green minus NIR plus over green plus NIR. So now this NDWI object
will show us NDWI values that we can use for further analysis. So we can look at what this looks like.
So here's our NDWI. We see that the darker blue areas are the areas that are identified as water
and have the higher NDWI values. And the lower values, the lighter blue lower NDWI values are
the areas that are maybe not classified as water. So generally, NDWI values range from negative one
to positive one, anything around. There's different literature on this, of course, but generally 0.3
and up will be NDWI values associated with being water. And then NDWI values lower than 0.3 are
less likely to be associated with being water. So with this threshold, we could use 0.3, as I
just mentioned, but because we know that we're working with murky water, it's flood water, so
the boundary between water and land is not as clear as maybe like a coastline or a lake or something
where it's more clearly defined. We're gonna relax our threshold a bit. So we're gonna say
that actually I think I'm jumping ahead of myself. I think this is in the next notebook.
All right, so here we're creating masks, but we will visualize these very soon.
So let's go back here. And we're gonna go to number four, masks and filters.
All right, so same thing here. Do all the usual things.
Okay.
All right, so the first part of this notebook is just a kind of repeat of what we just did. So
we're gonna do the NDWI calc again, import our packages, get our imagery, allow division by zero,
get our bands, NDWI calc, and generate a mask.
So we can take a look at this here. This is showing according to our NDWI that we just calculated.
Our water masks, so areas of water, those are the purple areas. And then down here, if you run this
next code cell, you can see areas identified as land according to our threshold. So you'll notice
it's pretty fragmented. We know according to our eyes when we saw the previous image, this area in
the top right of the image, a lot more of that was probably water. For some reason, it's not identifying
it that way, but we know that it is water. And then same with this land. There's a lot of gaps
here, and we can probably tell that some of these gaps are land, but they're not being classified
as being land currently. So to kind of help this, we are going to apply filters to our mask.
So this is where that OpenCV library comes in. So we're going to be using morphological filters,
using OpenCV to kind of help us improve this land versus water segmentation. So the first thing we're
going to do, we're going to be doing two different types of operations, closing and an opening filter.
These are both, these honestly, I am frequently confused by these because they just seem confusing,
and you'll see why in a second. So the opening operation is basically removing false positives.
So you're taking empty pixels outside of a mask, outside of the mask. And then the closing operation
is removing false negatives. So that's for filled pixels inside of the mask. I find it a lot easier
to look at this. So this is the OpenCV documentation. So this opening filter, so you're taking these white
specks outside of the main image, you're getting rid of those. And then the closing, you're taking
the sort of dark filled specks inside the image and getting rid of them. The reason this is so
personally confusing for me is because I feel like the names should be switched. So if you are also
confused, just think of them switched. That's what I do. If that's confusing you more, ignore what I just said.
All right, so what this is doing is this is taking a kernel, like a box, with the size that we have defined.
So these sizes, by the way, the 40 and the 15, those are kind of arbitrary. Ideally, if you're doing
this for a project where you want to be a little more nuanced about how you approach this, you could
do something like a grid search maybe where you try out all different values of opening and closing
kernel sizes and then you can see what, say if you have a ground truth image that you're comparing
against, what combination of sizes gives you the best sort of final outcome. This is just
a bit arbitrary right now, so these numbers don't sort of hang on to them too tightly. They can change.
But that kernel will go over the image and then depending on what we decided, it'll open and close
those holes accordingly. So in this cell, we're applying the closing filter and then to that resulting image,
we're applying the opening filter and that will give us our final filtered image.
And then we can see this image.
And here we go. So the dark purple areas are areas of water. You'll notice this looks a lot more filled in than the previous
image that we saw before we applied these. Of course, you can definitely continue to refine these as you wish.
You'll also notice here on the left side of the image, these specs are probably that those are the clouds.
That's why we hate clouds. Clouds are good. So we're going to go ahead and do some refining.
We hate clouds. Clouds are great, but not today.
Yeah, so just know that these are probably showing up here because of those clouds, but the
area identified on the right is going to be water.
All right, almost there. Last notebook, number five, plotting a histogram.
And this, we are just kind of doing this. This will make a lot more sense when Kevin leads us through the full
coastal erosion example in a bit, but we're looking at the sort of distribution of the pixel values
for each of the bands to kind of see where they fall.
All right.
All right, so here we're just going to see how we can plot our bands and their values
in a histogram. So we're going to grab our image like we did before and get our three bands.
We're using a four-band planet scope image here, so we're using blue, green, red, and IR,
but for the purposes of this, we're just going to look at the BRG, blue, green, red for the histogram.
And here we are plotting our histogram, so we're establishing title, labels,
colors, bins, all these things.
All right, so here we go. On the x-axis, we see the pixel values in our image for each of the three bands,
and then on the y-axis, we see the number of pixels at those values.
So you might notice here if we're looking at the blue band that the blue band pixel values,
there are the most number of pixels in the blue band, which might make sense because we have a lot
of water. This image is flooded and we have clouds, so that might make sense. And you'll see the values
are around 8,000. Oh, sorry, wrong axis right here, 7,000. The pixel values where it peaks
right here is around 7,000. So this, you might be wondering why this is or maybe curious about it.
I went into, let's see if I can pull this up on this.
There we go. So I went into QGIS because I was curious about this, and I noticed that this is just
filtering for the blue band, so you can see the blue band. But clicking around at different values,
this, the areas where it's blue here, the blue band tends to be around that 7,000 mark.
So that might be one of the reasons why we see this peak happening at the 7,000 mark is because
so much of this image is flooded and that flood water is around those pixel values. So this will
make a lot more sense in context when Kevin talks about this in the context of the coastal erosion
example. But I just wanted to introduce this concept of pixel values in histograms.
Any questions? I know this was a lot.
We'll have time for questions at the end too. Yes?
I'm not totally sure what pixel values you're referring to.
Yeah, that's like, so let's see if I go back here.
This slide, so if you think about like each of the colors or each of the different things
represented in imagery having different values just because of how they're represented
in the array, that's what that's talking about.
Oh yeah.
Okay, something like that.
Cool. So all of this, hope that you all have a better understanding of how to work with
geospatial imagery using NumPy, REST stereo, all these things. So I think we'll take a few minute
break, maybe like a 15 minute break now just so you all can stretch and all the things. Please
feel free to get more of the swag if you haven't already. And then when we come back, Kevin will
take us through an example looking at coastal erosion, kind of bringing all this stuff together
in a full real world example. Oh, 220, so 235, 15 minutes.
All right, everyone. Is everyone good to go? Cool. All right, thumbs up.
All right, so we're going to move on to the next section, well, the last section,
which is the hands-on example, well, everything's really been hands-on, but
the next hands-on example, which is where we analyze coastal erosion in a specific area.
Let me move this mouse out of the way. There we go. Cool. So Monza did a really great job of
explaining everything earlier of how do you get your data in, how you analyze geospatial data,
how you create image processing pipelines and how you create masks and all these things. Now we're
going to put that to the test for real world. I mean, the other stuff was also real world, but
more real world data. So this was inspired by a recent paper where they were looking at a severe
example of coastal erosion in Bangladesh. And before I go any further, because the wi-fi is slow,
I'm just going to have you download the data. So let's go back to the notebooks repo
and then go to the coastal analysis Jupyter notebook at the very bottom.
And then I'll go back and talk about a little bit. Then open up in Colab
and then just run the first cell to install REST Serial and then also download the data.
And then just run the first cell to install REST Serial and then also get the data.
Because instead of this being like one image, this is
great. Oh yeah, right. Okay. So some of you might see this screen. This is basically just saying
you have a lot of stuff open. So just go ahead and close them. I'll just go to many other sessions.
Yeah, cool. I think go ahead and download that data. So instead of this being one image,
this is 12 or so images. So it's a lot of data. I'll go back to my slide quickly.
So in this example, we're going to look at a coastal erosion example from this area in Bangladesh.
This was inspired by this paper I put on the bottom. I'll just show you a quick little snippet
from the paper. Here's the real world, wow, this is kind of small, the real world
version of where we're going to look on the ground. They've been trying to put sea walls up to try and
reduce coastal erosion, but for many reasons it hasn't worked. And the area of interest or the AOI
I'll be referring to it, is just a small, small section of the actual area that they've been
analyzing. This is the small section here, by the way. So our end goal is to get this filled out
area. This is like the little chunk of land that's just been receded away into the ocean.
Let's go check on our data. Okay, worked for me. Does everyone else have the data?
Does everyone else have the data?
Is anyone from here? Why is it so dry?
Okay, okay. I don't know if anyone else feels this, but like my face is just shrinking.
Yeah, I'm from like Vancouver, like Pacific Northwest, where it's just like tropical,
but cold, cold tropics. Yeah, the opposite. Yeah, pardon me. Oh, that's great. Thank you.
All right, cool. Well, let's get these packages in. Well, maybe I'll talk a bit about this stuff.
Well, I sort of already did. I'll talk about it anyway. So we're going to do the same thing
that Manzi did earlier in the five notebooks, but in one notebook. So we're going to get the
data that we're going to look at. So we're going to look at both visual data, which is like the
red, green, blue data that you can combine to one pretty picture, and the analytic data,
which is like the data that you can analyze the bands and make like the normalized difference
water index image out of. And then we're going to create that index image, so the NDWI image.
And then from that, we're going to look at the pixels and how we can identify water and land,
and then try and measure the recession over time. Okay, cool. And just from like a geographical
perspective, this is like a Google Maps capture of where this area of interest or AOI is. So that's
Bangladesh. That's the southern part of Bangladesh, and it's just a small little polygon. In reality,
it's much, much larger where the recession is happening, as I mentioned earlier, but
it would be so much data to do. And I don't know if our instances can handle it, to be honest.
So we imported data. Didn't miss anything. Very good. Okay. So the first thing we're going to do
is we're going to just like get pointers to where this data is, and then we're going to sort it by
date. So we have data from 2017 up until 2023, so six years of data. As Monti mentioned earlier,
you can do this all on your local computer. You can grab this data, do it on your local computer.
The only thing that won't work is this part here, where I import the files. I have like a backslash
or a forward slash. This works for Ubuntu and Linux and whatever,
Macs, but it doesn't work for Windows. You'll have to reverse that slash and maybe more things. Yeah.
Date. Yeah.
That's a really good question. I named them 2017 underscore or year underscore visual or analytic.
So we would sort them 2017 through 2023. Yeah. There's better ways of doing it using metadata
to be more robust, but in this case, I just did the easy way. But that's a good question. I could
really be wrong if I wasn't careful. Okay. So now we have two different lists of data.
The analytic images are again, are the images that aren't the pretty images. They're the ones that
we're going to be using for our science purposes. And then the visual images are just going to be
the pretty images. So we're going to create a function. I'm assuming, has everyone here
created functions in Python before? Yeah. Cool. So it's nothing new. So creating a function here,
a pretty simple function. It's what we've done earlier for extracting the bands using Rasterio,
but we're going to call it multiple times. So I'm just going to throw it into a function.
And we're specifically going to be using green and near infrared as Manzi mentioned earlier.
That's all we really care about for the NDWI. So I'm just going to run that to save that.
Cool. Cool. Okay. So I'm going to run through the whole example using just the 2023 image.
And then at the end, we'll kind of combine it all with the whole thing. So
the only thing that doesn't index by one is, or sorry, everything indexes from zero to negative
one for your last one. So negative one in this case is going to refer to the last image in our
list of images, in this case, 2023. And we're going to extract the spectral bands for
the 2023 image. So here we have green and NIR for near infrared. And then, well, let's just visualize
it, right? So here's the green image, right? Not really much to see. A lot of green.
This little part here is a sandy section, which comes up as really green. Kind of interesting.
I'm not really sure why. Some of you might just say, no, why? Sand looks really good. No,
I don't really know. Okay, cool. And then the next section is the, look at that, typo. I plot
the red image. Nope. Near infrared. So we're going to plot the near infrared. And so does anyone here
know why the near infrared looks really bright in land and not bright for water? So near infrared is
a proxy for temperature in a lot of cases. So the water temperature is going to be much cooler than
the land temperature. So the land looks really bright compared to the water. That's what's
happening here. And then here we're going to create another function to compose a scene. So
as we've done earlier with the visual imagery, we can just stack the blue, the green, and the red
to create a visual or an array for a visual imagery or a visual image. Then let's go ahead
and run that for the 2023 image. And boom. Here we go. This is what the visual image looks like for
2023. This was taken in like April. This is April. This was taken recently.
Cool. Yeah. I'll mention this here. There's a little thing here. I'm still not really sure what it is,
but it appears like every year in the spring. And you'll see in the masks later, it kind of pops up
as land. So I'm going to guess this is either like a really shallow part of water or murky or maybe
a little island. I don't know. Doesn't matter. We're going to mask it out. So the next part we're
going to compute our NDWI. So green minus red over the sum of them. And we're going to, like
Monty said earlier, ignore zero. Kind of scary if you're in the math world, but let's just pretend
it's okay. The main reason, actually, I'll just show you visually why we're doing that.
These black parts here are zero. So when you divide by zero, this would explode and so would that.
So we're just letting it still be zero. Okay. Let's compute the NDWI for 2023. Let's take a look at it.
Cool. Okay. So you see that little island thing I was talking about? Yeah. We're going to do that
Yeah. We're just going to pretend that's water. So we're going to mask that out later. But in general,
we have ocean, land. This is not really important, but a little river in here that
kind of messes with our stuff later. So sorry about that. And as we mentioned earlier, the zero
point is what we're going to be taking for what is and isn't water. Or maybe I do 0.3. Oh, I do
zero. It'll be zero. So basically anything less than zero, we're going to say is land. Anything more, water.
Okay. So another function, let's define how to find water and land. So it's going to take in the NDWI
image or array. And then it's going to throw out two different masks, the water mask and the land
mask. Just as I mentioned earlier, if the NDWI pixel is more than zero, water. If it's less,
land. And do I say equal to? Yeah. So if it's more than or equal to, we'll just say it's water.
Okay. So what we're doing here is we're creating images that will say if the value is one, it's equal to,
let's just say the water mask. If the value is one, the pixel is associated with water. If it's zero,
it's associated with not water. And the same goes for the land mask. So if it's one, it's land, not one,
it's not land. The word mask is kind of a funny word, but it really just means like
ones are the things that you're associating with and zero or things are not.
Here we're just going to compute them. Here's what the NumPy array looks like for, in this case,
a land mask. I'll just scroll up quickly to the NDWI image. You can see there's water and then
there's land. So you expect there to be ones down here and not ones here. And that's what we got.
And I will correct myself. Earlier I said zeros and ones. In this case, it'll be ones and then Nams.
I did do zeros in a previous iteration of this notebook, but it kind of messed with some
other things later. So I said it was Nan. And then let's just visualize what these water and land
masks look like. So water mask with that pesky island in the way. And land mask,
it all kind of adds up, right? You have that little river in here. Does this make sense, everyone?
Yeah?
Shouldn't the water and land mask be exact negatives?
I don't think they would be based on the mask because they give up.
Uh-huh. Yeah. Do they not look like exact negatives?
Well, like, so one has an island and one doesn't.
Oh, oh.
They're exact opposite.
Gotcha. Well, let me take a look. Why don't they look like that?
This is the beauty of live programming.
Ha-ha. Yes. Thank you. That's why.
So wouldn't that still fully encompass all the values?
Oh.
You're right. And then you might expect there to be a river over here.
And I'm just confused now.
Um, yeah. Should we change it?
You guys up for it?
Let's just say equal. I don't know. We'll see.
Yeah. Of course.
This is my second time put coding.
Okay. Let's see.
Um, here.
No.
Well, let's just pretend like you didn't bring up that really good point.
And I'll.
Yeah. Uh-huh.
Yeah.
Yeah. It's a good point.
But, um.
But.
Like, um.
I fear your name.
Oliver mentioned.
They should be the exact opposite because.
One's just exactly greater than or equal to the threshold.
And then the other one is exactly less than.
So they should be just negatives.
And now I don't know why.
Well.
I mean, this, this looks like pretty distinct from this.
So I don't know.
Should we just change it for fun?
Let's just say 0.3.
Yeah. I mean.
The thing is.
Again, they're not exactly the same.
They're not exactly the same.
The thing is.
Again, they're not exact opposites.
So.
Let's just ignore that.
No, it's a really good question.
I don't know.
Hey, do you know what you can do?
Do you want to file a little GitHub issue?
And then we can figure that out together.
Yeah.
Good question.
I don't know.
Does anyone else know?
Pretend like it's OK.
Yeah.
It's probably a map upload issue.
In fact, you should just file your ticket there.
OK. Yeah. I don't know.
But it doesn't really matter because we'll just mask it away.
But it's a really good question.
Now I'm really bugged by it.
OK. So we have our land and water masks.
Kind of.
And like you mentioned, there's this little island.
There's a little river.
And we want to measure the recession over time.
And we don't want little artifacts like that getting in our way.
So we're just going to mask away these things.
We're going to mask away this little island.
We're going to mask away this little river.
And throughout the years, there's different things that pop up too.
There's only one year's worth of data.
And so you can might imagine we're going to do some opening and closing filters.
Like we've got this little river.
And we're going to do this little river.
And we're going to do some opening and closing filters like we did earlier.
If you take a look at this open CV thing, right?
So you can imagine this is like, we'll see.
Does Monty have the zoom thing?
So this could be like the little island.
And we're going to open it.
And this is like the little river.
And we're going to close it.
Oops.
There we go.
So we're going to do this little river.
And we're going to close it.
Oops.
There we go.
So our function looks pretty much like the one earlier.
So we have a closing element.
A closing kernel.
And then a mask.
This is kind of a lot to just like take in.
But it's exactly what we did in the fourth notebook.
Just like parameterized instead of with numbers in it.
So we have a closing mask.
An opening mask.
We combine them.
And we have mask closed and opened.
And then we have a closing mask.
And then mask closed and opened.
And then let's do this with some real numbers.
So earlier we were talking about how like these numbers are kind of pulled out of thin air.
And they kind of are because I just want them to work for this example.
But you can also think about it as like each pixel is about 3 meters.
In this case they're actually 3.7 meters per pixel.
It all depends on the data processing pipeline.
And you can find this out in the metadata.
But let's just say it's 3.7 meters per pixel.
So in this case our closing element will have like 29 pixels.
Which is, let's see, what's 29 times 3.7.
So like about 690 meters.
So you can like picture it that way.
So you can say like this item is about 3.7 meters per pixel.
So you can say like this island is about this big by this big in meters.
That's like how much you're going to want to close.
So you can run that there.
And then let's run it for the year.
Let's see what it looks like.
So it got rid of that island.
And it got rid of the river.
Look at that.
So now we have distinct masks.
This one's land.
This is where water is.
We know where the two lie.
And we can measure now how they're going to change over time.
So let's just do this for each year.
So 2023 through 2021.
You'll see this plus one because we want to include the year 2021.
So basically what we're doing here is we're going to extract the spectral bands.
We're going to get a visual image.
We're not actually using this visual image.
But this is here in case you want to visualize what's happening over time.
You can just do a quick plot of that image for each year.
Creating water and land masks.
We're going to filter them.
And then we're going to add them to a list.
That's all running for me.
Did that run for everyone?
It's going to take us up to water.
Okay.
So now let's see what this looks like over time.
So we're going to measure how the land has changed over the time period, over the time frame.
And in this case, we can actually report out in physical units.
So we know, like I mentioned earlier, the resolution is 3.7 meters per pixel.
Hard code to this. Again, you can take this out of the metadata like Manci showed earlier.
But kind of lazy.
So the total land lost over this time is 13 square kilometers.
That's massive.
Over the past seven years.
Well, it's kind of hard to visualize.
So let's just go ahead and do that ourselves.
So this is a plot of the land lost over seven years.
So this is land lost over seven years.
As it kind of says, yeah, cumulative land loss.
So let's just go back up here to take a look.
So here's our...
I'll just go all the way back up to the real image.
I'll just do this one.
So this is the NDWI.
So this is where the water was, the land was.
And scroll all the way down here.
And then this yellow stuff here is the total land mass that was lost in those seven years.
Okay, cool. So let's continue.
So I'm going to throw time into an array from 2017 to 2023.
I'm going to throw in the land masks.
And the land mass loss.
And then we can plot that over time.
We can see just how much land was lost over time.
Just in a plot like this is kind of helpful.
So you can see in the first little bit, it was like accelerating.
Like it's incredibly fast land loss.
And over the last little bit, maybe it's slowing down.
Let's take a look.
So we can measure that through just simple like first year physics kind of stuff.
Math.
Velocity.
We can do math.
So let's just go ahead and do that.
Velocity.
We can do math.
Anyway.
So, someone's tired.
Yeah, cool.
This is my first session.
Like I shouldn't be tired.
Okay.
So let's measure the velocity.
So that's just, yeah.
Total land mass loss over time.
So this is like the speed of how fast.
Speed of how fast.
This is how fast the land has been receding over time.
So you can see, like we mentioned earlier, like it's speeding up, speeding up, speeding up.
Then over the last year, it's kind of slowed down.
Which is a good thing.
But not such a good thing for the first six years.
And then we can do the same thing for acceleration.
So it's just the derivative of velocity.
And then you can see over the first six years, it was accelerating.
Like it's getting really bad.
And then the past year, it's getting better.
It's like decelerating.
Or accelerating negatively.
Which is good.
But let's just like visualize this a little bit easier.
Easier.
A little bit easier.
Hi.
Help me.
I have a question about the change in the last year.
Does that mean that it's getting much bad?
Is it still getting bad?
The flow of the water?
The flow is lower?
Exactly.
It's not getting good.
But it's getting less bad.
So like if the velocity was zero, then there would be no landmass loss between 2022 and 2023.
But the velocity is still above zero.
So that means there's still landmass loss between the two years.
But it's slowing down compared to the first year.
Which is a good thing.
The reason why I asked is because for a moment I thought it had to be better.
Oh, that would be really good.
The place where I threw up, it will spread down.
The bees are watered.
And it jumps the sand on the bees.
It will spread the bees to the floor.
Cool.
Is it cool?
Is that good?
I don't know.
I mean it saves the floor.
That's what you're looking for.
I guess that's one way of doing it.
I know in this region specifically they were creating sea walls.
I don't know if you guys are familiar with sea walls.
But basically they're like walls put in the sea.
That's exactly what it sounds like.
It's a good name.
And it helps slow down coastal erosion.
But not so much in this case.
What's the difference for the bees and the water bees as a result of the
local mining sector wanting to handle the coastal erosion?
Either the bees are not interested in the break or what?
Yeah, well I'm not sure if it's taking a break.
But it's a really good question.
I'm not really sure why it's slowing down.
I haven't taken too much, I haven't looked into it.
This paper was actually from 2020.
So all the analysis after is just kind of like we know that it's happening.
We're just not really sure why.
In fact this area of interest like I mentioned earlier is a really small
section of the land that is being lost.
Let me take a pose back up.
So like this little polygon here is fairly small compared to this entire
coastline here.
This section here is just one tiny chunk of it.
And in fact it might be accelerating.
It might be actually getting a lot worse over the entire coastline.
I don't really know.
It's just a small chunk of land.
You mentioned some amount of coastal erosion is expected.
Is there a way to compare this philosophy to what that kind of expected
philosophy or measure the given impact?
That's a really good question.
I don't know what is expected in this case.
But if you do compare to other beachy regions, I was trying to find an
example in the U.S. for instance because this kind of hits home for people.
And sections of coasts that I can find that had data for like 10 years were
nowhere near this bad.
And those sections were like non-human contribute.
Those are by Earth, Mother Nature.
And it's just so much more dramatic.
But I don't know what the actual answer is for what we would expect over time.
That's a good question.
Yeah.
How can we do these pairs?
How can we do the FTOs?
Right.
Okay.
That's a really complicated question.
And I tried to do this by...
Okay.
So for those who didn't hear.
Maybe also let me know if this isn't what you're saying.
Are you asking if we're not accounting for the elevation of the water?
Right.
So sorry, of the land?
Of the land.
Oh.
Oh, I see.
I didn't account for that.
But this section is a very...
Well, again, I'm cherry picking.
But this section is a very flat section.
The way you can measure height is not through our satellites.
You need something like LIDAR which can tell you the height of the land.
We don't have that.
I don't even have access to that data.
I just know from the paper that this is a really flat section of land.
But yeah, you're right.
It could appear as though like coastal erosion is slowing down because,
like you mentioned, the land is becoming higher.
Yeah.
That's a good question.
But I did try to reduce some variables.
Like this section, this part of Bangladesh gets monsoon seasons.
And so you can get really high water levels.
Which if you look at different times, it can look like there's a false sense of
coastal erosion, but it's just the water level is really high.
So I chose the same month each year, so April of each year,
during their dry season to try and reduce those extra variables.
I know that's not what you're asking, but just another point.
Yeah.
That's a good point.
I don't know about the elevation of this land.
I just know it's pretty flat.
Any more questions before I get on to our stuff?
Okay.
So the next section.
Let me see where we left off.
Right.
We were looking at acceleration.
Okay.
Now we're going to look at land recession.
Now we're going to measure actually how fast the land is moving inward.
Or the water is moving inward in this case.
So to do that, we are going to try and find that water land that's
going to be moving.
So we're going to try and find that water land border.
Lots of ways of doing this.
What I'm doing is I'm going to use an edge detection algorithm from
OpenCV.
It's called the CanE edge detection.
I won't go into how it works really, but in general, what it does,
it looks for a spike or a slope in like intensity of pixels.
So it will look for where there's edges.
Edges, I guess.
I don't really know how else to say it.
And in this case, there's a pretty sharp edge, right?
Where the water meets the land.
So I'm going to use, in this case, the land difference mask.
So this, where there's an obvious edge, right?
So I'm going to try and detect this edge here.
And this edge here.
So this edge is where the land started.
Or yeah, where the land started in 2017.
And now this edge here is where the land starts in 2023.
And if you can measure the distance between the two,
you can measure how much land was lost or how much coastline was receded.
And you can measure how fast they receded.
So let me scroll down.
So we're going to take that land difference mask,
throw it into, it was a float earlier,
so I'm going to turn it into some integers,
and then we'll detect all the edges.
Zero being one threshold, one being the other,
because it's a mask.
And then let's just take a look at what that looks like.
So the Kani edge detection did a good job of detecting edges.
Like I mentioned earlier,
2017 land or coastline on the left,
2023 coastline on the right.
And then, well, we'll do a histogram.
So what we're going to do here is we're going to try and
automatically detect, like not just by pointing and clicking,
but just like getting the computer to just detect where the
coastline was in 2023 and in 2017.
So I'm just going to bin up all the pixels vertically.
And where I'm just going to try and say,
where all the pixels binned up on the left and all the pixels
binned up on the right are on average,
are going to be the two coasts.
There's lots of ways of doing this.
You can already imagine this won't work for an image where
the coast is horizontal.
And in this case, the coast on the 2023 side is already kind
of sloped just from how it's been receding.
So it's going to be kind of like not so good,
but it'll be okay.
So let's bin them up.
And then I'm going to use a SciPy algorithm called
Find Peaks to find the peaks.
I'll show you in a second what this means.
Here's my histogram.
So here are where all of the pixels are binned up vertically
on the left side of the image and on the right side of the
image.
And I'm going to find the, I found the peaks of the two
histograms.
And these are supposed to be where the coastlines are.
Let me just plot that on top of the landmass difference.
Okay.
So you can see, well, it's kind of hard with this light here,
but this is where all of the pixels were binned up.
And it does a pretty good job of like saying roughly on
average this is where the coastline was in 2017.
And, you know, we started this tutorial in 2022 for a SciPy
presentation.
And back then this coastline wasn't so eroded,
wasn't as eroded, and did a pretty good job of capturing
this section here.
But it's gotten, as I said, it's gotten worse.
And so with this new data, it's kind of capturing over here
because the river's getting wider,
which is a whole separate issue.
But in general, kind of, this is where the 2023 coastline resides
for the bottom part.
You can picture that as the bottom part of the image.
And then let's measure it.
So the land has receded basically 2.5 kilometers over
the past seven years, which averages out to like 356 meters
per year, which is pretty dramatic.
I don't know miles, so you can just kind of divide by 1.6
and put it into miles.
Yeah, and that's our coastline analysis.
Do I have any other questions?
If not, I'll just throw it back to this.
Uh-huh, yeah.
Well, we can just have fun in Python.
But I mean, something we could do is we could relay this
information to the government.
So something like that a lot of government agencies do is they
task satellite data or they get plant data like this,
and then they do this analysis themselves to just try and see
where, in this case, where coastline is receding most.
And then they can begin to be like, oh, shoot, like,
up here, we don't need to do anything about it.
Like, nothing to worry about up here.
No seawalls need to be put in.
Down here, though, it's getting pretty bad.
We have to start to implement something, right?
And maybe they have, but maybe that's why it's getting
a little bit better.
And so that's just, or another thing they can do is let's say
they have people who live here.
I mean, this is such a zoomed out picture you can't really see,
but maybe there are people who live here who live here.
So they can do that.
They can zoom that picture you can't really see,
but maybe there are people who live here or there's farms
or other important infrastructure.
They can begin to warn them, be like, look, it's moving at a rate
of 300-ish meters per year.
You're next.
You know, you need to move.
And that's actually something that's happened in the UK.
There was another example I was going to use maybe,
but I didn't use this one.
It was more dramatic, where they had to move an entire city,
you know, a few kilometers inland because the coast was just
so dramatically receding.
Yeah.
Just further on that, we're talking about pollution,
what H.U.R.A. is, right?
Yeah.
It's huge.
Would that be the result of this incremental erosion
or would you be monitoring this?
Yeah.
There's so many ways of doing this.
Of course, the year mark is like the most dramatic way
of doing it.
It's like the most smooth data.
You can definitely do a temporal resolution of every day.
The problem with, there's a few problems with that,
but an issue with that is like seasonal changes.
So like this region has monsoon season.
So it's like the most dramatic way of doing it.
So you can see the difference between the two.
So the region has monsoon season.
So like there's a, I can't say this for certain,
but there's a good chance that a lot of the erosion happens
during that monsoon season
where there's a lot of wind and a lot of waves
and probably deteriorates a lot of that soft land.
But yeah, I mean, pulling this down to like quarterly
or monthly, bi-weekly or even daily could be interesting.
You probably see a lot of noise,
but you probably see, you pull a pretty decent powder
out of it over a week.
So it's like the most dramatic way of doing it.
So yeah, I mean, there's a lot of wind and a lot of waves
and probably deteriorates a lot of that soft land.
But the question
is how can you go about reducing it from,
and last year the
potentially look at that as well I think.
It's almost like your question was planted. Yeah so I do think it's
valuable to talk about what we can do. I think the first is just to build
awareness here in Salt Lake City where landlocked we don't have a body of water
unless you count the Great Salt Lake which is also drying up. So I guess maybe
that doesn't count either. But just like learning about coastal erosion and how
it could impact your community if you live in an area that's by the water that
in itself helps a lot connecting with your communities in a lot of places
there's like local government organizations, community organizations,
nonprofits, things like that who are already working to understand the local
impacts and effects of coastal erosion. And then finally because this is PyCon I
think this is important, data plays a huge role in this especially I think now
we have greater availability of satellite imagery and just environmental
data in general. So I think that also helps just being more informed and then
using these skills that you now have to kind of dig into things a little further
wherever you can find data. And Planet luckily makes this easier to do so I
wanted to share with you all some resources that we have at Planet that
might be of interest to you if you're interested in poking around at this use
case or other use cases. The first is this Planet gallery. So here you can see
I know the internet is really slow. So this isn't all of our imagery but they
are highlights of images that Planet takes and you can filter these images
based on whatever agriculture, civil government, there's all different kinds
of categories and so these are just sort of they're really cool images like
little case studies of different areas if you're interested in playing around
this is free and available to use on the Planet website. It's the Planet gallery.
We also have this disaster data sets sort of area on our website that is made
available. So this I don't know when is the last one they sent out actually but
for big natural disasters natural and man-made we collect imagery and then
make it available to people so that you can look at it. I know one of the things
we have under this umbrella is Ukraine data. We have a lot of Ukraine data that
people have used to kind of help efforts there as part of this disaster data
thing. So you can sign up for email alerts and things when new data sets are
available here. We also have the NICFE program. So I'm actually blanking on what
NICFE stands for. Oh right here. Norway's International Climate and Forests
Initiative Satellite Data Program. So what this is this makes planet data
available as an open good to anyone working to reduce or reverse the loss
of tropical forests. So there's tons of tropical forest data here. I think there's
a map here somewhere. Yeah right here. So in all of these regions across the globe
this data is free and available to use if you're looking into forestry
issues. There's also the Planet DevTrial program. This is something that is on
our team. We're on the developer relations team. This comes through to us
where if you're someone interested in using planet data maybe you want to just
test it out as a developer and see what you can do with it. Our DevTrial program
is a way you can do that. I'll come back to this hopefully when it's oh there it
is. Yep so DevTrial program and then you can sign up there. We also have our ENR
program which stands for education and research. This through this program
let's see through this program all researchers funded by any US federal
agency and or the National Science Foundation you have access to planets
archive of satellite imagery. So if you have an EDU email address or something
like that associated with one of these agencies you can get data through this
program for free. And last one this is a link to planet publications. So this is
one use case that we showed that we kind of turned into a analysis using planet
data but if you're interested in how have other people use planet data what
kind of applications and analyses have been done we have this whole thing a
whole collection of different publications where people have used
planet data and done like written papers or analyses or released code or things
like that. So all of that is available here. Feel free to take a picture of this
slide or anything if you would like to. Also oh that's a good point so if you if
you all could email one of us either me or Kevin we can send you the presentation.
And yeah finally we just wanted to give you our contact information. This
is developers at planet.com and then also the developer center developers dot
planet.com. This is where if you're interested in planet imagery using it or
learning more about it you can find everything you need to know there. Also I
highly encourage you all to take one of these flyers up here the dev rel
because the notebooks and everything all the materials we used for the
presentation today it's part of this larger effort that our team maintains
we have tons of Jupiter notebooks with different examples and analyses and not
just with planet data but how to do things with geospatial data in general.
So if you're interested in any of that we would love your feedback you can file
issues or do anything any of that stuff here. So yeah with that thank you all so
much for coming really enjoyed it.