So this is 10.9 o'clock.
Is everyone okay to start now?
Yeah. Okay.
Cool. Am I ready to start now?
That's a question.
Oh, no. Are people still coming?
Right. Okay.
I think we are going to start as soon
as this person walks through the door.
Sorry. Don't turn and look at them.
Sorry.
Okay. I think we are going to start now.
Wave.
Okay. Hi, everyone.
So welcome to PyCon US 23.
I mean, unless you were here yesterday,
in which case you already know what we're doing here.
So just so you know, you're in the right room.
This is the Exploring Ecotopics with Python.
So that's me.
You can call me Chin.
I mean, like this.
Okay.
You can still hear me? Great.
Okay. So hopefully you've got, like, all the files,
as I have already been stressing.
Hopefully you've got all the software and files.
There is a lot. I'll talk about that in a second.
So we're just going to go through a couple of sort of
ancillary things.
The main bits are this, this, and this.
I'm going to try and take 10 minutes breaks in between.
But I'll sort of consult with you.
We'll decide as a group how you want to use the time,
because this is your time.
So if you want to have more of a break or less of a break,
we can figure it out.
And then a wrap up, just if we have time.
It may literally just be like the last line of code
and then off to lunch.
Okay. We'll see.
I'll introduce myself in a second,
but I just want to, like, set the expectations.
So this tutorial is about you adding some of the Python skills
that can help you find out what's happening to our planet.
And when I say you, because also there is a recording,
as you know, I'm sort of saying you as a potential scientist,
scientist, researcher, policymaker,
people whose livelihood depend on natural resources,
people concerned, citizens concerned about the next generation.
So, yeah, for the wider audience who hopefully will be watching this,
this is to kind of help everyone.
And then when we say Python skills, when I said Python skills,
I was thinking of Python skills from the scientific Python ecosystem.
So things like those.
And then what's happening to our planet, I'm thinking,
particularly what's happening to the planet,
which is our fault as humans.
So more of the anthropogenic impacts that we are having.
So there we go, some little emojis,
which will signpost where we're going.
So at this point, as a data scientist, question mark.
I just wanted to, if you are willing to share,
can I understand a little bit more about yourselves?
Like, it's going to just be like a hands up.
Anyone, people who are scientists?
Oh, yeah, okay, a couple, cool.
They're working through all these like systematic, but yeah.
Educators? No? Yeah, a little bit.
Anyone want to volunteer who you are, what you are?
It doesn't have to be like a long soliloquy,
just concerned citizens, interested Pythonistas.
Okay, that's cool. Yeah.
Yeah, because it just kind of helps me shape, again,
how we use the tutorial, so depending on your experience.
So I guess the other thing I need to ask is,
your experience with scientific Python.
Are people familiar with these?
You have experience with them before?
So previous experience, yeah.
I don't want to out people like first time newbies
with scientific Python.
Okay, cool.
Oh, this is going to be easier.
Then I can run through more of the tutorial faster.
No, I'm joking.
Okay, great.
So who am I?
You probably want to know.
Oh, collage.
Right, so obviously my name is Chin.
I said that.
I am basically a data science entrepreneur from London,
specializing in open source outreach.
I'd say people probably know, if you like Duck Duck Gomi,
you will see a lot of my community work.
So originally in 2016, sort of starting Our Lady's London,
which then became Our Lady's Global.
Then more recently, some of the work I do with my startup
around outreach to disadvantaged young people,
working in schools, mainly through sports, actually, analytics.
So a lot of those references come up if you look at me,
and you'll be like, oh, what does Chin got to do with eco stuff?
So actually, what isn't publicly known
is when I was head of data science at the Foreign Office
in the UK government, I actually worked, and that was in 2017,
I worked on a lot of these issues.
So actually, illegal wildlife trade,
some sort of energy sustainability, earth observation.
I can't tell you too much because that was a security classified role.
And unlike some people, some US Air Force National Guard,
I keep official secret secrets.
So we won't go too much into what I actually did,
but just know that I did do stuff.
Now, whilst that was six years ago,
actually recently the past couple of years,
two worlds have sort of emerged,
and actually a lot of the schools and young people I work with
have actually started, they're like, okay, Chin, the sports is great,
but actually we kind of want to know about the disaster
happening to the planet.
So I've actually started doing more of that kind of ESG,
ESG work, culminating in today.
Okay, so I don't know if you've seen those four.
I find this a really useful diagram,
but anyway, as you already have experience with scientific Python,
a lot of people, it'll just be useful, like a bit of a roadmap,
a learning roadmap where we're going.
So your tools, I'm kind of like, if you really know scientific Python,
I don't know what, am I going to help you learn something?
Okay, never mind, we'll find out.
So as you know, obviously starting with Python
as a basis of everything we're doing today,
Jupyter, which hopefully you have some experience with,
and then obviously everything stems from NumPy,
although obviously they would say that from this article being about NumPy.
So we are going to do a lot of NumPy, mainly under the hood rather than exposed,
a lot of mapplotlib for plots.
Sorry, I don't know if you can see this.
So a good amount of pandas, some network X,
but also some stuff which is off-diagram.
So extending pandas with GeoPandas,
which is the geographic extension for pandas,
and then using some of the other JavaScript functionality,
just a little bit via folium, and then a tiny little bit.
We're using X-Ray and rear X-Ray,
so X-Ray which is basically labeled multi-dimensional arrays,
and then rear X-Ray which is the geographic extension of X-Ray.
I'll just set your expectations now.
We're not doing a lot, if you've looked at the test files,
we're not delving really deep into the internals,
and actually really internals of any of these.
This is very much about using these tools, rather than behind the scenes,
all that kind of stuff.
But yeah, specifically X-Ray, rear X-Ray,
to work with the satellite image data.
Oh yeah, question mark.
So people, you're kind of familiar with some of these things?
Can people tell me your experience with your console with NumPy?
You've worked with pandas. What have people done before?
Nothing, anything? Yeah?
Okay, so people know what they are,
so I don't have to be like, this is an array.
Okay, cool.
I guess the other thing is, obviously,
I'm assuming that you've worked with Jupyter,
then people are comfortable with Jupyter.
Oh yes, don't have to spend so much time on that.
Sorry, this isn't like, let me take shortcuts.
But it's just, yeah.
You never know what kind of experience people have in the room,
and obviously you want to make it as inclusive as possible.
Okay, so let's preview the exploration outputs.
Welcome.
Can I get out of this?
Come on, PowerPoint won't work with me.
Okay, so, excuse me.
Right, where are we going?
So we are starting with the wildlife trade exploration.
We'll start with society's data,
and then you end up with a network graph.
So this is for Pangolin specifically.
And then we go to, in the second session, or second hour, hopefully,
EPA, so Environmental Protection Agency.
Sorry, I don't want to teach you the suck eggs,
but I don't know what you know, what you don't know,
so I'll probably try and do more or less,
using some of the data from the greenhouse gas program,
greenhouse gas emissions reporting program, GHGRP.
So you go from that.
So we'll go to universities, particularly this sector here,
so that you can also use other stuff.
And then we'll go, the flashy bits are actually the least Python bits,
but never mind, use what is.
So we go to fun interactive maps, and also boring maps as well.
And then kind of more, I guess, traditional statistical graphs,
but again, useful and stuff like this.
And then the last section, we start with the Landsat data.
Well, as in the data, we're not doing the whole workflow,
so as you know, you've read all the data sets which are prepared,
and then we end up with a pixel-based image classification,
so land cover, thematic map, at the Brazil-Bolivian border.
Okay, so that's where we're aiming.
I'm not entirely sure if we're going to get through all of it, but we'll see.
Now, okay, let's start.
I have to find my actual Jupyter notebook.
So I think with that, okay, over to the coding,
because that's why we're here.
So can you please open up your Jupyter notebook
and whatever kind of IDE, or I am mostly using JupyterLab.
In the browser.
I know you said people were generally okay with Jupyter.
Do people need any, as in, can we just start going,
or do people need a bit of a run-through of some of the functionality?
I'm going to take that as a note.
It should be quite intuitive, but okay, I'll just read it quickly.
So you've got the notebooks which are prepared,
so you shouldn't really need to do much.
Okay, if you are new, you might end up double-clicking stuff like that.
Don't worry about that. Just run it.
When I say run, use that, or do a shift-enter,
because that kind of gets boring having to go back and forth.
If you need to add more cells, it's like that.
Delete is like that. You've also got, hello?
I'm sorry? Oh, bigger, yeah, sure, of course.
Pugrande. Yeah, sorry, I should have done that.
So 150. Is that a bigger? Yeah, sure.
Yeah? Okay, perfect.
So yeah, that's adding cells.
You've got, what do you call these, controls here, delete.
Other fun things, so tab, controls, so import.
So tab is great for autocomplete,
and then shift-tab for docstrings.
Okay, whatever. So shift-tab, we'll use that a lot as well,
so we're already done with that.
Okay, so with that in mind, oh, I should also just double-check.
So can you set it, if you're in Jupyter like this,
we'll see however you're using it, please have the tutorial,
you've got the materials designed so that it's like,
you're just basically dumped in the same directory,
so you've got your three notebooks,
you've got your data's all, I know, free and easy out here,
and then you've got the subfolder, this is for, obviously, the deforestation,
this has got your for-rester data files,
and then that is the shape file which was downloaded from US Census.
But obviously, if you are, because this is not a beginner's tutorial,
if you, I presume you kind of know how to access, you know, local.
We don't have access to this right now.
No, no, sorry, this is just like how it's sort of set up,
as in how, like, in the notebooks,
when I'm calling things like the file path,
we'll be assuming that things are local like that,
but obviously depending on where you've put stuff,
like maybe in downloads, but yeah, we can sort of run through that.
I think also just before we start, oh, 14 minutes, not bad.
As you can see, I have no TA.
It's quite lucky that I can even sort of be here,
given the crisis which is happening in the UK in terms of clustering.
So if people have issues, as a room, like I believe in democracies,
I, you just let me know how we want to kind of proceed.
So if someone has an issue, like, do you want me to stop, and then I help them,
or like, you know, yeah, stuff like, you know,
I think we're just going to have to figure it out as we go along.
But to be honest, this is an easier crowd, because like I said,
normally I'm just dumped into, I just go into schools
with teenage kids who really have no interest in anything.
So you are, honestly, this is like an absolute holiday.
You're not trying to sneak out and have a fag, you know, behind the bike sheds.
You're actually paid to be here.
I'm kind of hoping this is, that's why I was like,
okay, maybe we can get through a lot more than actually than normal.
So we're just going to go, okay, and we'll see how we go.
Whew!
Okay, so if you're going to open up your eco-tutorial,
Wildlife Trade Exploration Notebook.
Oh, I should probably start at the beginning.
Okay, so a bit of a blurb.
I'm sorry, I also use a lot of slang.
Are people okay, I was going to say, with the level,
the pace of English that I'm using?
Yeah, okay, sorry, just want to make sure that's inclusive.
I really try not to use slang, but I can't help it.
Okay, right, I'll read off here.
So what example of wildlife trade are we examining?
Trade from 1975 to 2022 of all eight species of pangolins.
People know what pangolins are, right?
There's like artichoke, okay, cool, which became illegal
for commercial purposes in early 2017, having been uplisted to societies.
Anyway, scientific approaches.
We're taking our graph theoretic and network science approaches.
What outputs will we develop?
Network graph, data structure, and visualizations of this.
What will our outputs tell us?
They'll support identification of the country's most involved
in the illegal pangolin trade to date
and the main international trading partnerships.
Beyond the well-known eco-impacts of wildlife trade,
sorry, biodiversity loss, what makes this example significant?
So pangolins are currently the world's most trafficked wild mammal,
despite the 2017 global commercial trade ban.
In fact, many sources report that illegal pangolin trade
has actually grown post-ban with the expansions of criminal networks.
So tackling their illegal trade is therefore an urgent conservation priority
and being able to identify the countries who are known to be
most active in the legal pangolin trade, which is the aim of this example,
is likely to have some predictive power in terms of tracing
the apparently thriving black market.
Okay.
I know that also seems a bit school-y that I'm just kind of reading stuff up,
but I have also designed the notebooks so that it's basically all the material
so then you can use it as a resource like after.
So, stuff on the data, so if you want to learn to print it, okay.
Okay, section A.
I should also just bring to your attention the table of contents.
So, I mean, anyway, you can read that, that's fine,
but just so you know where we're going.
So A to F is where we are going, hopefully by 10 o'clock.
Okay, A, set up cheaper notebook and pangolin trade data.
Step A, zero, import the third-party packages,
NumPyPanda, NetworkX, and the MatplotlibPyPlot submodule
with conventional aliases.
So, I've designed this so that we obviously type in together
like an interactive lab, but obviously feel free just to like copy and paste.
We may do that if we start running out of time.
Or when the code doesn't really have a lot of pedagogical value
for you to type it.
I have not done that right.
That's also not right.
Ah, cold fingers.
My set of words. Okay, A1.
Excuse me. For auto-completion or if it's not working,
try running this magic command.
I'm just going to copy and paste because this is, again, not particularly exciting.
A2, read in the pangolin trade data, wildlife trade data CSV,
and assign to raw data. So, pd read CSV.
Then you can do this however you want.
This is just kind of how I tend to demonstrate.
So I kind of go with the right-hand side first to be like,
this is what we're actually loading.
And then this is where we're assigning it.
Phew, that worked. That would be awkward if it didn't.
A3, make a copy of raw data called df prep.
This will be the data frame we will prep and ultimately construct our network graph from.
So raw data, auto-complete, copy.
I really didn't need to bring that up because I knew that.
So again, we'll do that basically every, what is it called, notebook.
Okay, section B, inspect the data.
Excuse me.
Have a look at the prep data frame using head method to display the first five rows.
So, df prep.
Okay, so as you can see, there is a lot of data in there.
So as you can see, there is whatever, various columns.
We're actually not using most of these.
The thing really to note is, as I said in the comments, this is a Pandas data frame.
So as you already know this right, two-dimensional.
So rows, columns, labeled.
Show the label.
So there.
So that's the row label.
Seriously.
And then column labels.
So, oh yeah, columns are potentially different types.
Do you sort of know this already?
Yes, okay, great.
But okay, if you don't, I'll just quickly say.
So yeah, what's interesting about Pandas data frames, as opposed to, for example, an array,
you don't have to have a mod just data type.
So here, for example, you've got obviously string object data, but also here, there's also numeric.
So that's really handy.
Okay.
Panic.
The other thing to note is that not all the transactions have data for every column.
So this has been marked with nans, which that's one last number.
So, b1.
Let's just have a look at the number of rows and columns.
So the interpretation of that is that the data set records 1,689 transactions where pangolin commodities were traded,
which date between 1975 and 2022.
So let's now look at the actual data types.
Oh, sorry, I should say.
See what type of data Pandas inferred was in each column when it originally went into CSV.
Ignoring my own notes.
So the object data type, as you see here, is one way that Pandas stores string data.
There is another, I can't remember the name.
Anyway, when you see object in our data sets, that basically means string data.
Okay, section C. So I'll just give you a quick overview.
So now we're preparing the data for exploring illegal wildlife trade,
and then we've still got a couple of more data wrangly things to do.
So the context for this.
The original data request from CITES deliberately did not filter trade based on any recorded purposes.
Let's review CITES purpose codes as per the database documentation.
So these are all the codes. This is not obviously just for the pangolin data.
This is within the trade database, the CITES trade database as a whole.
Obviously, not all the transactions have complete data.
So this is where they got a purpose.
This is what they categorize it into, but obviously not all of them have a purpose.
So C0 access the subset of DF prep containing just the transactions driven by the types of demand
that could be more likely to persist after a ban, i.e. hunting for a free personal,
circus or traveling exhibition or commercial purposes,
as well as where this data is missing and reassign DF prep to points to the copied subset.
So just some intuition.
Again, if you actually did this, I guess for research purposes, you could do this in a more,
I don't know, more whatever way depending on your purposes.
But it was really more just like if there was a ban,
I'm assuming the scientific community wouldn't just go underground, right?
So I was like, which of these things might continue?
But again, there isn't necessarily, this is only like partial data.
It's just illustrative. Sorry. Yes, great.
So, okay.
So for people who haven't used Pandas, seen Pandas before, so okay, sorry.
So data frame indexing operator, we're giving it a label, a column label in this instance.
That would pull out the column like that.
That won't work.
So you can't see basically, is it in this list of stuff?
Again, you can see this in the code detail, which I'm not going to talk through.
It's again, just for your reference.
But I apologize that it's a little bit busy on the slide, but you know, more information is less, right?
So basically, let's bring out a Boolean for where the values are in one of these strings,
which are the purpose codes and then NANDs as well, which there are lots.
So there we go. There's your Boolean array or series.
And that's how we're going to cut the data prep.
So now we should only have the rows where that term, what was it?
Purpose even. Without purpose.
So there you go, NANDs, TPs.
That's kind of what I want to see. Great.
And then let's copy that. Copy even.
Excuse me. So C1, let's sense check.
So we should have less rows, right? So 1396. Great.
Okay. And of course, the same number of columns, because we didn't do anything to that.
C2, we need to be able to quantitatively compare transactions in the data set in terms of the volume of wild pangolin specimens lost.
So let's compute a quick histogram, such frequency table, of the term column values to see the different pangolin commodities traded.
So data frame, we're indexing again by column label.
The column label is term, which of course breaks up that.
Value counts, which if you haven't used patterns before is like the best.
I am in love with this method. It's like my favorite thing ever.
I use it far too much. So just so you know, the default is that the drop not equals true.
So we're just going to override that. Although actually in this case it doesn't actually matter.
But just, you know, illustrative. So you can see in this data set, again, this is just the number of trades which traded this type of product, right?
This is not the number of products. There's no kind of proportionality in terms of the scale of like, was it like 428 transactions skins with one skin each versus like a thousand.
Anyway, you get the idea. So this is just so you see what's in it and also a bit of the sample size.
So unsurprisingly, we're also going to filter rows.
I'm getting ahead of myself. I'll just walk through C3.
As a necessary but imperfect approach to standardizing the trade, subset Df prep for the transactions involving commodities where each unit is more likely to represent one pangolin animal taken from the wild rather than a constituent part, i.e. skins, live bodies, excuse me, trophies and specimens.
Be aware our remaining data will significantly undercount relevant traded pangolin numbers.
So does that make sense intuitively? You understand what we're doing that we can't like you can't compare like a skin scrap to medicine to a scale like we just don't know.
And obviously, if you were doing this properly, you could use, you know, you create some sort of algorithm to figure out how you estimate a whole pangolin from some of these other things.
But we're not. Okay, so again, we're going to pull out the term column, which is still that, is in.
So pass it a list of the values skins live bodies sorry it's a little bit gruesome.
But you know that's that's what humans are doing. You know my people as well, or anyway, we'll talk about the country things later.
So that gives you a billion.
And that's what you of course index the data frame on, which then, maybe you can see here will give you less rows.
So that looks sensible copy.
Okay, so now let's properly look at the shape again. Sorry, see for check that DF prep now has even fewer first than before.
I don't know why I write things that when I don't actually read it.
So now we have 612 rows.
See for comment, we have cut the number of pangolin transactions in our data set from 1689 originally to 1396 to now 612.
Whilst the steps taken in the section to clean the original data that have undoubtedly dropped relevant as well as retained less relevant data.
These remaining 612 trade records are still a useful subset for demonstrating a Python enabled graph theoretic approach and being able to derive limited but interpretable outputs related to real world illegal wildlife trade.
Okay, so so don't like give me feedback. We like, oh, that's certainly why did you do bodies? Why did you? Why did you not do? It's like, I know, I know.
This is not how you do it properly, but you can always refine this, you know, method if you need to.
So section D just show you quickly. So now we're going to prepare for graph, graph construction.
So finally, we're moving towards the you know, the fun exciting part.
D zero intro. As previewed, we are preparing to turn our pangolin trade data into a network graph with a nodes vertices represent the country's importing and exporting pangolin commodities and the edges connected them represent trade from an exporting country to an importing country.
Have people worked with networks before? Okay, cool. Yay. Tell you something.
So I mean, it's again, it's intuitive, right? Okay, we'll go through that.
There are multiple graph types. Please ask questions, by the way, I mean, not kind of like an hour long lengthy questions, but you know, if you need to.
You're just not like disruptive teenagers. This is just very weird. There are multiple graph types. We will construct a multi digraph, which is a directed graph with self loops and parallel edges.
And I will just bring this up because it is useful if you have not worked on network access. I mean networks are great. Sorry, I'm just like.
So this is just give you a little bit of context. So a graph. Okay, so undirected basically it's like, so you know, think.
Okay, like as they are a sponsor. Okay, so think matter. So Facebook, right? So Facebook friend your your friends, right? It's not well, hopefully it's not just one.
You need to direct your friendship because that would be like creepy and stalkery. But okay, anyway, so that should be a friendship should be undirected, right? That'd be friend friend.
Edge.
Diagram. Okay, maybe I don't want to talk about stalkers.
Then you could have knowns obviously which could be directed. It's like, you know, there is a direction. So I don't know maybe it's like a friend request right so someone sent a request to someone else like a LinkedIn connection something like that say, then multi
Then multi-diagram. So parallel edges. So, okay, yeah, so it's like LinkedIn. So maybe someone sent that person like multiple. I know you can't do that bit. Let's say like whatever they send them multiple requests on different platforms or something.
So you've got multiple edges from a node to another.
Excuse me node and then multi-diagram.
So again, that was our power edges. It's basically everything right so it's directed.
It's got parallel edges. So it could be like that way, that way. And then also you can like for the other ones you can also have self loops, but we don't have that in the trade because you
So it's, I guess in our example, because we wouldn't have it but it's like let's say the, let's say Japan sold pangolins to itself.
You see what I mean? So like it would loop back but obviously that doesn't happen in our situation but yeah.
Sorry, I can't remember. This first is a better example. Does that answer? Okay, great.
Thank you for the question. Right, where were we here? For each directed edge we designate the country who exported, sold the goods, export country as a source node and the country who imported the, bought the goods as the target node.
So, sorry, sorry, sorry. I'm trying to give you directions. So you sold it to this person. Yeah. Source node, target node.
Hours are drawn from the source node, seller to the buyer. Parallel edges of our multi-diagraph will reflect a pair of countries who have made pangolin trades where one was the buyer and the other the seller and vice versa.
So, because actually in this instance, as you will see, excuse me, okay let's say Japan and Singapore.
So, you know, obviously Japan can sell to Singapore and Singapore can also sell to Japan, right? So that's your parallel edges between two nodes.
Okay, D0. We can only construct a pangolin trade graph data structure from transactions with both defined source nodes and target nodes or else it's just like source node to nothing.
Our visualization also requires quantity data for each transaction which we'll address after. First check if any NAND values exist in either the importer or exporter columns because then we cannot use them.
So, we're indexing again, this time because we are indexing on multiple columns, we need to pass it a list with those column labels.
So importer, exporter.
That's not gonna work, sorry.
It's gonna sound really weird on the recording. Isna.
Okay, sorry, I should do this in steps.
Right, so pulls out the columns, great. Isna.
Yes, no, true, false.
Values turns into an array.
And then any, which is, I think this is definitely a non-play function, basically says
are there any trues in that array, right? This is where your boolean logic goes.
Are there any trues in this array, true or false? So we want it to be false.
And it is false, thankfully. You can also run this step, D1, I'll give you another way which basically pull out the rows where both importers and exporters are NANDs, but we won't go through that.
D2, now turning to the availability of quantity data for each transaction, try randomly sampling rows of the data set, say 10 at a time and maybe a couple of times,
just because I actually, I don't want you to see some of my particular data.
I can't remember the default, oh here we go, doc string, shift tab. So the default is one.
Which is, I mean, cool.
Okay, so I'm going to, I'm trying to demonstrate something. Okay, so these are the columns that we are interested in in this instance, right?
Because we need to have a quantity value for each transaction. So you can see you've got NANDs, you can see sometimes you have the same data, which is really helpful if it's corroborating.
I'm trying to find, okay, this is a really poor example, but here you do have two values, but they're not the same, right? There are some worse examples.
Like this, okay, this is a good one, isn't it? This is five times the size. So, you know, like, again, things you need to think about, how do we handle that?
And D3, how are we handling that? Oh, okay, we'll do that next time. D3, find any transaction rows which are missing both importer reported quantity and exporter reported quantity data.
So basically like, at this point we're like, well, even if you give us two values, that's still something to work with, but we can't work with no values, right?
So let's see where we have neither of these values because we cannot use that importer. Tab, yes. Thank you.
That's not going to work.
So I'm going to do this cheat way. So one condition, another condition. I'm just going to, that will work, right?
And then I am, excuse me, indexing on those multiple conditions. Oh, no.
Sorry. Oh, poor, poor, poor. Yep. Live debugging. Who doesn't love it? Okay, so you probably got there faster than I did.
So thankfully there are no transactions where there is neither of these data. So that's great, I guess. D4, construct new quantity data for every transaction where the value is greater, the value is the greater of the reported quantities or the only reported quantity.
Okay, so my method to deal with this is basically like, whoever said there was more quantities, because I'm assuming people don't want to like be like, yay, I like took loads of pangolins out of like the world.
I'm going to assume that the one who said more is probably more correct, right? The other one was like, oh, it's just not that many. Don't worry, nothing to see here.
So that is what we are doing in this code. So how did I start this? Okay, so we're creating a new column in D of prep.
So think of this as like, if you haven't used this for this, like, you know, creating any dictionary key value pair.
Creating a new column called quantity.
That quantity, excuse me, is going to be calculated by applying a function to D of prep that particular function, which will use a lambda function is basically going to be a non max, which basically means take the max of these values and ignore the non's if there are any.
So really great function. Thank you. Numpy. Love you.
Importer.
So tempted really just to copy my own code.
That's probably not good practice.
Max writes those columns.
And then you have to specify access equals column so basically tell
tell the method to look in the look in the columns for those labels, because they're not in the rows.
I do not feel confident about that.
Okay, I'm sorry. I'm just going to copy my because I don't want to create.
I don't want to create a double.
I don't want to create a quantity column twice.
That is not what I prepared for.
Okay.
Right, so quantity. So sense check. Yes, yes, yes, yes. I mean we could, you know, maybe we should look at some other things just in case.
Is there anything.
Okay, well anyway, I can't find that example of like where there's two but it works.
Okay, section E. So here we go. We're really getting more into the network stuff.
I know. Sorry. It's that data sciencey thing where it's like 80% is the wrangling isn't it before you can actually get to the good things which take literally five seconds.
Construct edge lists. So E intro and edge list is a data structure used to represent a network graph and as a listing of adjacent nodes.
Our edge lists will differentiate between the source and target nodes, which is a necessary distinction for directed graphs.
We will also include the new quantity data for each edge in our edge list. So quantity which will basically use to like change the width.
As I said there, this edge actually we used as weights.
Easier. Construct an initial edge list called edge list raw by copying the subset of DF prep with just the importer exporter and quantity columns.
So DF prep.
So we are just why are you there.
We're going to pull out those column labels importer.
Exporter.
Quantity.
So there we go. Those are three columns.
Oops.
Make a copy.
Edge list raw.
And then we can have a quick peek at that.
So cool.
Okay. Things I'm about to point out in the next section.
So you can see not surprisingly you do have like multiple transactions between the same exporter and importer.
So E1 context.
Whilst we could construct and draw a multi-diagram from this edge list raw as is the visualization would obscure significant edge detail.
So repeated directed edges. So like those ones.
Between a pair of nodes such as the two transactions from the Netherlands to Great Britain.
When both drawn with the same default line drawing in the same position it will look indistinguishable from a single default line representing a single directed edge.
And then even if the line bits could be drawn with varying widths in the case of multiple edges only the widest width would be visible dwarfing thinner lines.
Does that sort of make sense? That's a really lengthy description.
I don't know how it's been any faster.
So yeah. We will therefore create another edge list with just the unique pairs of source and target nodes.
So I just one reference of NLGP for example.
USG.
Well no there's not a double. Anyway. Good idea.
Create another edge list with just the pairs of source and target nodes i.e. particular exporter importer with an aggregate quantity metric.
Namely the totals of the quantities recorded in all the trades made between each particular exporter importer.
This is why it's so it's like writing stuff is so painful.
E1. Create edge list unique a data frame produced by performing a group by operation on edge list raw which groups rows by unique exporter and importer combo sums the row quantity values within each group and then also renames the quantity column as weight.
I swear all these things are just like so much easier like to actually just demo but anyway.
For learning purposes. Okay. So oops group by this is our first group by.
If you don't use group by you should it's really cool.
So this is not going to give us much because you have to like give it a kind of like action on it.
So in this case we're going to do some.
But again if this is the only thing group before you could also do all sorts of things like count.
Which is telling you the number. I mean it's not particularly relevant in this case. I'm just showing that there are other things.
Minimum Max etc etc.
Actually give you a Max. Oh well anyway.
Anyway.
So we're summing it.
I'll just do this before I forget because I forgot this in one of my practice runs.
So you can see here it has the group by operation has automatically shifted export and import into the index or basically created a multi index.
But we do not want that.
Please do not have that because that messes up your code later.
So bus as index equals false.
So now when you do that now it's just not normal which is great.
Sort now I want sort the rise because as you can see there is the sorting is by alphabetical by I guess exporter which is not particularly useful for us.
So no values.
By quantity.
The default is ascending equals true.
Which is never what I want.
Maybe it's what you want. I hope I don't know. I hope it works better for you than for me.
So ascending equals false.
And then finally in this like massive chaining operations which I guess is my laziness.
Rename the quantity column.
Quantity as weight.
Please tell me that's the end.
Oh no it's not. I haven't assigned this.
Unique.
Please be right.
Okay.
And then have a look at it.
Great.
Okay.
So long and complicated.
Anyway so now as you can see now we don't have duplicate edges.
I mean not duplicate obviously because they're different transactions but you get the idea.
I'm going to comment.
The road I mentioned of this resulting edge list tells that there are 138 unique Pangolin trading relationships in this network.
And then obviously you can sum this to see how many.
Like basically what that adds up to.
But I won't do it.
But anyway just so you get a sense.
And then remember that's also under counting.
Okay section F.
So here we go.
We're really finally getting into the drawingy bit.
Construct and draw multi-diagraph.
F intro.
And then at this point onwards we start to use map plot live in the tutorial.
Be aware that there are a variety of styles slash APIs available for accessing map plot live functionality and this is reflected in the tutorial.
There are some cheat sheets.
Sorry I have opinions on map plot live but I shouldn't share them.
Do people use map plot live?
Yeah.
Sorry.
I really should say that.
Again grateful that we have it.
F0.
Create a multi-diagraph object using the network X function from pandas edge list.
Okay.
I'm going to break this into steps.
From pandas.
So thank you network X.
So they've made that really easy for us.
Okay so then you need to pass.
Passing required inputs from the edge list unique data frame as well as optionally specifying the weight column data as an attribute of the edges and the graph type to be multi-diagraph.
So this is the data.
The data frame we're using is obviously edge list unique.
We're saying the source nodes are the export column.
The target nodes are the importer column.
And the edge we're giving it a edge attribute.
Obviously not all of this is how are we doing for time?
Oh pretty good.
We're going to pass that weight.
And then we're going to say create using the multi-diagraph.
Okay.
Create using that.
So F1.
Finally we can do some visualizations.
Use network X's basic map plot lib drawing functionality to try a minimal visualization of our Pangolin trade network G.
So this is where you discover if you created this correctly.
I'm not entirely sure.
So this is literally your absolute MVP, you know, minimum viable product.
It's like all the defaults.
And it's going to look ugly.
Although you know that if you did the test notebook.
So we're giving it.
Oh here we go.
So node positions.
There are no positioning algorithms.
You can obviously you could set them yourself.
You could set them yourself.
You know, be like this node is here, here, here, here.
I do that a lot actually in sports analytics.
You know, like a formation.
But in this instance we're just going to be like the spring layout can just decide for us.
But of course that means that it will be different every time unless you set a seed.
So I'm not sending a seed here.
So you'll see how that runs.
Okay.
So there we go.
Ugly basic graph.
But I mean fast, right?
Like if you had data in edge list, that would be really quick.
Okay.
So K equals 20.
So this is you can basically adjust this to let's do like five.
So you can make that smaller.
You can actually just play around.
It's more mushy.
There's less like force or like 50.
So then things will be more further apart like that.
So you play around.
And then if you want to set a seed, which we'll do actually in the next section.
So we like, okay, I should not do one.
So actually I still keep wanting the same.
I want the same positioning.
So it'll just keep giving me that.
Okay.
So you get the idea.
That's ugly.
We want to do some more fun stuff.
So you're literally at the last section here.
G intro.
FYI, NetworkX is not a plotting library.
So as for the docs in the future, graph visualization functionality may be removed from NetworkX
or only available as an add-on package.
And they highly recommend that people visualize their graphs with tools dedicated to that task.
So like not matplotlib.
So therefore, because constructing matplotlib drawn NetworkX graphs has low transferability,
I'm just going to use, we're going to use this section just to demonstrate ideas for fine tuning network visualizations.
So not recommending specific inventations.
So does that sort of make sense?
Because obviously if you were doing this, you might use Geffi.
You might use, I was like, Pi.
I don't know.
There's like, oh, in fact, there's lots of things which I referenced here.
So yeah, this kind of stuff graph is, I mean, Pi dot.
That was it.
So there are other ways you do it.
So yeah, I'm just going to show you ideas and then how you implement that in different packages would be totally different.
So G0, don't bother typing this.
Just literally just copy and paste.
It's just producing two arrays, which will just, they're just like helper arrays, which will help change.
Here we go.
They'll be used to draw the edges of our multi-diagraph with varying widths and colors proportional to their weight, i.e. quantity.
So don't worry too much about that.
But you can always deep dive.
I think it is intuitive enough to understand.
G1, draw a customized map plot live visualization of our Pangolin trade network with a plotting routine that exploits more of the available options, i.e. functions to draw just nodes or just node labels, et cetera, rather than just that kind of like draw networks.
Okay.
So obviously do this how you want, but I'm going to just sort of do it in a kind of absolute build up from nothing.
So you do need a pause layout.
Because then that feeds in, you can see it feeds into these draw, draw, draw calls.
So I'm going to give a, what did I say?
Okay.
40.
I won't do a seed.
Okay.
So now I've got a pause.
So you can draw nodes.
The absolute basic is the graph and the positions.
Those nodes literally do not have actually any labels.
So you need to give that labels, which is node labels.
Also needs G and pause.
Then you can draw some edges or else you're just a bunch of floating nodes with labels.
G, pause.
Is that, what was the last one?
Oh, okay.
So that should work.
So, okay.
So there we go.
So now you're basically at the last thing we just did in the last section.
Okay.
So we're going to work up from here and make it better.
So, okay.
First of all, I'm going to need to make this the fig size bigger because or else you just cannot see anything because the nerves are all like lumped over each other.
So let's increase the fig size.
Let's give the, okay.
So we'll start with the edges because this is where we use that thing that I just made you create and didn't tell you anything about, which is really good practice.
So this is where we're going to specify the widths now to actually the edge widths to vary.
And then we're also going to change the edge colors again to vary.
Color, custom, edges.
So that should work.
So there.
So now you can see instead of just all those lines being exactly the same, they now, they don't necessarily look like they vary that much, but that's actually mainly because everything was sort of the same size apart from basically this bad boy here, which was massive.
So, yeah.
So this is on a scale of like greens to yellows to reds, but actually a lot of things were basically not a lot.
So green and then a couple of just the one thing was like red.
So that's where those two arrays I just told you to make without looking at are useful.
And then I mean other things.
I mean, I'm not going to type this because again, this is not particularly interesting for you to watch.
But yeah, then you can change nodes.
Again, no actual labels.
Well, actually, no, sorry.
There are labels, but the label default color is black.
So you can't see them.
So change the font.
So now you can actually see.
Sorry, I'm going to make this just small so you can actually see.
What else?
Anything else? Oh, arrows.
Yeah.
And then stuff like this.
So because actually that's not directed at the moment, your edges are just, you know, your like friendship edges are friends.
But, you know, this actually needs a direction.
The min target margin.
So what I've said is the target node.
So the person who bought the country, you bought the pangolins.
I'm giving you like a bit of a boundary so you can see the arrows and also it sort of differentiates the bar from the cell.
So there we go.
That's that margin there.
I love map.lib.
I really do.
Plat axis.
I'm going to turn that off so you don't get that box.
So there.
So yeah.
And like I said, stuff like that you can play around.
That's just an idea of the different things you can do.
You can also save that as well.
But I won't because I have about a thousand copies of it.
I guess we could probably talk about some.
We should like interpret it, I guess.
This is a really ugly layout.
I'm going to try another one.
Okay, slightly better.
So yeah, interpretation.
Okay. So again, I know we couldn't be constrained.
Our analysis cut lots of things.
We made a lot of assumptions.
Like I said, I knew that we were going to get some kind of
change in the data that we could actually look at.
That's why I did a lot of research with xyz.
But within the framework of what we have,
the data that we end up with.
I thought this is really interesting.
I didn't actually know this.
I assumed when we were going to look at pangolins,
I thought it was going to just be Asia.
And all the normal sort of, you know,
not stereotype, but you know,
Things that people think about when they think about, yeah.
People eating exotic animals and making medicine.
So yes, Singapore, Japan, Malaysia, they obviously are still involved, so selling and buying.
But actually what I thought was really interesting and I did not, like I said, plan it at all.
But actually, the US bought a lot of pangolin commodities.
They bought a lot of pangolin commodities from Japan, but also from lots of other places
in the world.
Yeah, and there's also, okay, you can't see that well, but yeah, Great Britain also pretty
complicit, France, quite a lot of things happening there.
Mexico actually, yeah, was more than I thought sort of surprising.
Well, I don't know, surprising to me, but this is not my field, so I'm more than an expert.
However, of course, while saying that, some caveats, again, the interpretation.
A few of the further caveats and considerations redrawing inferences from our pangolin trade
network graph include possible range in the quality of trade monitoring and record keeping
by country, as well as influential geopolitical factors.
For example, not all countries are parties to the convention.
I don't actually have data on their trade or have been at all times.
Plus there were changes to country boundaries existence between 1975 and 2022.
For example, if you are my generation, so check the checklist of Vakia is now the Czech
Republic and Slovakia.
So things like that.
And then obviously maybe the US has more data on their trade rather than another country
where they don't monitor so well, so on and so forth.
There is the section H. Okay, we'll do it really quickly in two minutes.
Yes.
So I, it's not necessarily what I would be suggesting, but I think there is probably
the countries who have better data quality probably are going to look worse in analysis
like this because they have, you know, the they have actually recorded those trades.
They've kind of been transparent about their transactions.
Whereas you know, there are other countries.
Oh, this is all recording.
But you know, there are other countries.
I mean, in Asia, for example, where I'm 100% sure they are not, you know, they're not going
to be recording the data and or providing that data to like, siteys like to the UN.
You know, so yeah, is that the answer?
Did you have a position on?
Yeah, yeah.
So I think yeah, I think it's as you said, I had my preconceptions and then this kind
of was like, oh, I totally did not expect the US to be so mean, I can kind of see obviously
from the data going through it.
But yeah, I didn't expect to be so dominant.
But then obviously, then you also have to count that and be like, but actually, maybe
there is more data collection and so on.
So it's a balance, I would say.
But yeah, I would definitely if someone like worked on this, it'd be really interesting
to see what other insight people had.
Okay, we're really quickly just going to work through H just to show you that it's not just
visualization.
There's actually actual maths stuff.
Okay, H0.
I'm just going to whack this.
So you can obviously just get out lots of metrics.
There's like edges and you know, so obviously, if you just do G and then you can just do
H and then dots and then look at stuff, you know, there's other things.
H1.
Okay, so I'm not going to read this through.
I'm just going to tell you there are things like centrality functionalities.
So that kind of gives you a sense of which nodes are important.
But based just on like in this case, just based on like how many different people are
they connected to not the volume of their transactions.
Like I said, it is just to show you that there are things, things you can do and then okay,
this one I'll just really quickly show you.
So if you sort that list and just take the top 10.
So this is just about the degree centrality, which means that the US in this case has traded,
like I said, traded any trade number of trades in paranglans with the most other countries.
So in this instance, 91% of the 55 countries in this network, which is 49 countries.
But yeah, the other thing which I sort of mentioned here you'd want to look at is community
detecting algorithms could be a good next step because you'd be like, actually there
was, you know, there are, you know, obviously smaller communities within this.
So US, Japan, Singapore maybe, can't remember what GQ is, not a magazine.
XX is like the unknown.
So you know, there's a portion there.
But yeah, there could be sort of smaller kind of little regional relationships.
So communities you want to look at.
Okay, that is your first exploration, break time.
I think, do you want 10 minutes?
Yeah, okay.
All right, I'll see you in 10 plus 10.
Are we okay to start like now?
Yeah.
Okay, look.
Okay, so I say that like, I've been waiting for you rather than you've been waiting for me.
I hope this microphone wasn't on when I went to the toilet.
That'd be really weird.
Anyway, sorry.
That's a cyber security background, government background coming into play.
Okay, so if you want to load up the carbon fleet exploration notebook, which hopefully you have.
Honestly, I can't believe you all had the stuff.
This is so smooth.
You're so much better than like teenagers.
Sorry, that's like damning with frame praise, isn't it?
We probably do need to check.
So we've got a little bit more data.
So you should have, unsurprisingly, my verbose labeling.
So you've got this CSV.
But you also need to have the, well, this is the shapefile.
Yeah, that's like, there's nothing more I can tell you about that.
So yeah, please make sure you have that somewhere you can access because that's going to help us make pretty maps.
Okay.
Someone's not here.
Okay, anyway, I think we're going to start.
Okay, so welcome to part two.
I think we're going to try and do this by 11 and then have a break just to set your expectations.
So carbon polluters exploration with Python.
Note that you need internet access for section E, which is the interactive JavaScripty map.
So which sample of carbon polluters are we examining?
So it is the university, the US university facilities with large greenhouse gas emissions,
which, according to the EPA, is over 25,000 metric tons of carbon dioxide equivalent per year.
And so that those studies are in our sample if they reach that threshold in any year between 2011 and 2021.
So 2011 is because that's when the GHGRP, Greenhouse Gas Reporting Program was launched in 2021, as I said, the latest reporting year.
Have people heard of the GHGRP?
Because I was going to say I hadn't.
I should also say, even though I work for the UK government supporting foreign policy, I'm actually a US citizen.
So this will come up actually in this tutorial.
Yeah, this is a surprise to me.
I didn't know about the GHGRP, but anyway, lots of really good data.
So I really hope this will incentivize you to look further.
What scientific approaches are we taking?
So we are doing statistical and geospatial approaches.
What outputs will we develop?
Oh, sorry, make this bigger.
Statistical graphs and interactive maths with historical and or regional dimensions.
What will our outputs tell us?
Who and where are the significant US sources of carbon pollution within the higher education sector,
a facility and state level, both recent and since 2011?
Beyond the well-known eco impacts of carbon polluters, climate change.
What makes this sample significant?
So to me, it's the fact that this sector has or individual universities are large fossil fuel burners.
So that might be a surprise seeing the out of sync with any green credentials and reputation they have garnered,
especially relating to clean energy.
And so I also want to point out,
so yeah, after I had sort of done this or proposed this and developed it, I discovered this Reuters article.
Again, I don't know if you're as excited about this as I am, because I was like, this is just really,
I was like, these universities are naughty.
But it turns out that Reuters actually came up, they used different data from a different source,
but they were also, it's like the sentiment is the same.
They're like, oh, look, these universities talk really, they have very secret.
And also I just want to point out this is dated after I like proposed this tutorial.
So I did not take this, but it does corroborate a lot of the things which I thought were interesting.
So I really urge you to have a look because then they do a much more sort of in-depth analysis because they're Reuters.
So they had, you know, resources.
But I also want to point out, this is my personal link to the story.
So I don't know if people know, but I was there.
So this is Boston.
This is a facility, the Cambridge Olsen Blackstone power plant, which Deferred Harvard only bought, acquired in 2005,
I think, was really interesting.
And I guess, so I don't want to dwell on the sentimentality of it.
But what I find really interesting is that doing this tutorial, preparing this tutorial,
I discovered that I actually grew up as a toddler.
I grew up two blocks here from where this photo was taken.
And I did not realize that I grew up under so near a excessive carbon polluter.
So we'll talk about that later.
But that just kind of gives you like, you know, there are real, obviously, I hope you know, there are real world impacts or real world, you know,
factors behind a lot of this data.
It's not just, you know, abstract.
So, yeah, I'm like, great. I breathed lots of fumes.
That's cool. Maybe that explains a lot of things.
Data source. So there's some background stuff if you want to know more about it.
But, you know, it's all mainly like government data.
And that shapefile is from the US Census Bureau. Blah, blah, blah.
I shouldn't say that in my own tutorial.
Sorry.
Why is this?
OK, sorry. I just I wasn't sure why this was already there.
OK, cool. So I'll just go over the table of contents.
So a bit shorter.
Yeah. But like different.
There's a much more variety, I'd say, in this one than the last one.
So A, set up Gif notebook, university, emitters, data set and US state shapefile.
So easier import the required packages and submodules.
But their conventional aliases.
It's important as MP format.
So I thought.
No. Try again.
Again, take this. So if you are new to Jupiter,
I know this seems tedious, but every time every computational notebook
is, you know, you kind of have to set up your environment all over again.
So that's why they seem to be boring, but that's a A to we are going to set
a panda's display option, show all columns, not truncate the display.
So because if you've got lots of columns,
pandas will automatically like cut out some of them
just so you can fit more on the screen and like ellipses,
which may not be what you want.
A3 reading the university emitters, data set, column,
suitors, data and assigned to raw data.
So PD raw CSP.
Carbon polluters, data.
All data.
And then again, a four.
If you create that prep data frame,
although I just want you to be creating a lot of data frames
in this tutorial for reasons.
And a five, just the other nagging reminder to please make sure
that you have that shapefile as a subfolder somewhere you can access.
I don't know if people have people work with shapefiles before.
Yeah. OK, cool. Some people. Yeah.
So if you haven't, I mean, I'm not an expert.
I, you know, I just use it for.
I know enough about it to like do the things which I need to do.
But yeah, if you actually open up, it's got other files in it.
But that's apparently that is the shapefile.
So anyway.
It works. That's the most important thing.
So it should be inspect the university emitters data set.
So these are have a look at the data set of large carbon polluting
university, U.S. university facilities.
So you have prep.
Also notes that instead of returning a default number of rows,
you can start specifying the end argument.
OK, so comments like the original Pangolin trade data.
There is missing data we need to handle like this.
However, unlike the Pangolin trade data, the data requested from the EPA
flight data source is the exact sample of interest.
So namely, all the facilities in the U.S.
university sector with large emissions in any reported year
between 2011 and 2021.
So every row is therefore relevant,
which is not like the case in the previous exploration.
The required data prep, also called cleaning, munging, rambling,
is therefore needed to modify the columns,
not the rows, which is the focus of the next section.
OK, so B1 find the dimensions of DF prep.
So shake again.
So there are 118 U.S.
university facilities, which are large carbon polluters
in at least one of the years between 2011 and 2021.
Did people know, like, I presume, you know, some of you all are studying in the U.S.
Did you know that they have these big power plants burning?
What? No, OK. I was going to say, like, unless you're like, yeah, obviously.
This is like because it really was a surprise to me.
I don't I think in the UK,
I don't think, you know, the idea of universities
having a power plant is really unusual.
So I didn't know that was just.
Yeah, where I live, my experiences.
Anyway, section C, prepare the university and missus data sets.
So C zero, some of the columns are definitely not needed.
So let's prepare to drop them.
And with some efficiency, instead of manually counting,
let's programmatically find out the index positions of each column.
So you've got the columns attribute.
From the FRAP. So that's the list of labels.
There is obviously a lot.
And we don't need them all.
So this is just a really quick way to.
Find out. The index position of each one.
So. C1.
Perform a job operation that moves four particular columns from DF rep in place.
So subparts change in emissions,
that one change in emissions and then sectors.
And review the modification.
So we're going to do a DF.
Prep drop methods, we're going to drop.
Columns and the columns that we are going to drop.
Have these index.
Positions, so 10, 22, 23 and 24.
And then we're going to drop that in place.
And then we are going to see if they have gone.
Nope, that's not going to work.
OK, great.
And I guess another point to stress,
as with, I guess, everything in Python is there are lots of different ways to do things.
This is just a way.
And I probably also should point out that the index parameter
is accepted by several Panda methods is used in this tutorial
where possible for brevity, but its existence is controversial and currently in flux.
So that's just to say that it's not considered best practice.
So, yeah, I'm not endorsing it, but it just makes things a lot faster.
OK, so C2, see what data type Panda's inferred was in each column
when it originally read in the current polluters data.
So DF, D types.
OK, so the comment, Panda's inferences are only partially correct.
The columns that are essential to correct are the 11 years of reported emissions data.
These are all currently object D type.
So basically string data, not numeric as required.
You can also see here these other ones are not, I mean, like
what's this one? Yeah, like an ID.
This is not I mean, it's really a category or something better.
There's other stuff which is not correct, but we're not going to worry about it
because we don't need to.
C3, before we start modifying the 11 reported emissions data columns,
let's shorten their long cumbersome labels to just the reporting year reference.
So we're basically taking out that stuff.
Excuse me. And then review the modification.
OK, so DFPrep, we're going to rename.
We're going to rename the columns.
Um, to basically itself,
but without this long cumbersome string.
If it's in there.
So take out, oops, no, jumps ahead of myself.
So replace that with nothing.
And then do that in place.
OK, so I'm just slightly not confident that I've done that correct.
So I'm just going to do that again.
OK, and then let's see what that happens after that.
Excuse me. String be gone. There we go.
Much easier. OK, C4.
Now start the process towards converting these 11 columns to a numeric data type.
Remove the comma characters from the source data.
Remove the comma characters from the string data in these 11 columns,
but not anywhere else in DFPrep, e.g. reported address.
And then review the modification.
OK, so does that make sense? So there's these commas which are,
I mean, I know that it looks nice and readable, but is a pain.
But we can't just take all the commas because there are actually commas here
which are useful or relevant.
Although we're not using that data, but we don't want to touch it.
So we are going to use the lock operator.
To do some multi-dimensional indexing.
So we're going to take all the rows.
OK, so that would be all the rows and all the columns.
Right? Just in case people haven't done indexing with the lock operator before.
Because we're using lock as opposed to ilock,
we can, well, we have to use labels.
So we're going to use this label.
And if I leave it like that, that will slice everything from 2011 onwards.
Perfect.
So that's how I'm selecting these 11 missions data columns.
OK, so now that I've selected them, what do I want to do with it?
I want to apply apply map.
So basically take out the commas or replace the values with itself,
but without the commas.
So lambda x, x.
This is not lambda.
Apply map is not before anyone says, that's really slow.
It is really slow because it goes through every element.
But in this instance, it's, you know, we don't need like the fastest thing.
By itself.
So that would take away your commas and then reassign to its override.
OK, and now let's see if that worked.
Please have worked.
Great.
OK, so OK, C4 comments.
So this is just to tell you that these are just other ways that you could have done
a site to those columns.
And there are obviously more beyond that.
C5, the last string cleanup step is to deal with the dash, dash, dash instances
in the 11 columns that we assume is EPA notation for nan.
Sorry, not applicable.
We will replace these string values in place with nan and then review the modification.
So this one is easier.
Just take out those weird dashes.
You could also do some like fancy regex solutions.
But, you know, that's not really necessary here.
So you take out that.
And take a look.
Great.
C6.
Now convert the 11 columns to a numeric data type and then review the modification by I.
So we're going to use that lock method of selecting columns.
So all the rows and then all the columns from 2011 onwards.
Just that.
And now we can apply the Panda function to numeric.
To numeric.
It's funny.
It's only when you're like live coding data wrangling, when you realize it doesn't,
it's very difficult to make it fun.
But anyway, it's necessary.
And I obviously as your adults, you sort of know that.
And I don't have to tell it to you because you're, again, like I said, not disruptive children.
Okay, so.
There we go.
There's a deprecation warning.
Like if you wanted to read it more closely.
It's actually helpful.
It's basically saying, I think in future you don't have to reassign it.
It will just do it.
Anyway, so it sounds good.
Whatever it's saying.
But yeah, currently this is how we're doing it.
And this works.
So there we go.
By I, this looks good because it looks like it's a float.
It's a float.
But obviously C7, we should double check that that is actually a numeric data type.
And there we go.
It is a float.
Just perfect.
So C8.
Now we've got the columns with the 11 years of reported emissions data.
Now that they are a numeric data type, let's compute some quick summary statistics.
So describe.
Use the describe method.
So as I said, although we do have some columns which shouldn't be numeric, but we could have
tidied that.
You could obviously do that.
We should have more time.
What is interesting here, I guess, just things to note.
So count, for example.
So this is like the number of US university facilities, which met the threshold of being
considered large.
In fact, the carbon polluters.
So 104, 103.
It kind of went up.
I mean, again, this is not anything kind of world breaking, but just interesting things.
It went down.
But there's no sort of obvious pattern of dipping like 90s, 80s.
So that's kind of interesting.
Other things, I guess.
I guess the mean you could look at.
Again, you'd be hoping to see these kind of on a downward trend.
So kind of a little bit, 81,000, 80,077.
But then starts going back up again.
Again, I'm not saying this is particularly, it's not statistically significant, but it's
not the direction you're hoping, right?
Okay.
Anyway, we'll look at that in a bit more detail.
C9, the subset of 11 emissions columns is time series data.
Generate a quick map plot, lib, line plot.
So we're going to select columns by a different way now.
Select from minus 11 position, index position.
So index df prep, excuse me, by that, which gives you those time series data.
To do a line plot easily, you need to transpose.
So you want to have your, each row is the year.
And then obviously along, this is each university facility that way.
And then you can easily plot.
Oh, yeah.
That's why I said legend equals false.
So there, again, just a really quick plot just so you can see.
So yeah, again, like, you know, Reuters and me, like, I think there's something, I don't
know, this is just surprising that, hey, there's so many, this is the threshold 25,000, we're
assuming, but yeah, there's just a lot.
This is really a lot.
That's actually MSU.
Even though it's coming down, but it's like, I don't know.
It was just interesting because I was like, you know, they're all like, oh yeah, look
at, come in, you know, sign up for our masters on, you know, environmental, and I'm like,
look at you, you know.
Anyway, sorry.
Not like I'm like the perfect, you know, perfect green activist.
Okay, C9.
So there we go.
But I, oh, okay, I said this, didn't I?
Fine.
C10.
Okay.
You could optionally check, you could check whether all those values are in fact above
25,000 or nan.
So you can do it in your own time.
C11.
Final task for section C. Create a new cumulative column with the sum of each facility's reported
emissions data over the 11 years.
Review the modification.
Okay.
So we're making a new column.
So remember, just like creating a key value pair for a dictionary, give it a label, and
then we're basically summing those columns.
So access those columns again, as the same way with the block operator, sum, tell it
to sum across the columns access as opposed to the rows.
Seems to be correct.
Let's find out if that has worked as expected.
Oh, phew.
Okay.
Yay.
So you should have a cumulative column, excuse me, here, and then you could also see some
of that if you want to just see how much total carbon pollution these facilities have been
responsible for creating.
Oh, in fact, I figured it out for you.
So C12, 11, Jesus, no.
118 university, US university facilities are responsible for approximately 96 million tons
of carbon pollution from 2011 to 2021.
Now, I don't know if that's, you know, I can't give you any context for that, but that seems
like a lot.
Okay.
Now, the main wrangling cleaning is over.
We can actually do stuff.
Phew.
I'll also just show you where we're going.
So some basic mapping, then some interactive mapping, and then we do the kind of pandas
statistical graphs, which I know are less fancy, but probably more informative.
So D intro, for this mapping section D and E, we use the geographic pandas extension,
GeoPandas, to create a GeoDataFrame object.
So a GeoDataFrame is a pandas data frame that has a column with geometry and extends pandas
functionality in order to make basic maps.
Some people use GeoPandas, a little bit, yeah, okay.
Okay, so some people have heard about it.
That's helpful.
I'm like, it's really a shame because it's like, it's basically all the JavaScript, like,
productivity stuff, which really, that's the best way to engage people, like kids with
Python, not the actual Python, which is the problem.
Anyway, D0, import GeoPandas with its conventional alias, which is GPD.
Create a GeoPand, brain.
D1, create a GeoDataFrame called GeoDF using DF prep, repeat the new object.
So GPD, Geo, excuse me, DataFrame.
Okay, so you pass it the prep DataFrame, and then we need to make some geometry.
In this case, using the longitude and latitude columns in that DataFrame, the previous DataFrame.
Okay, so this column, longitude.
So, and also remember, so points from XY.
So, everyone says like lat long, right?
Actually, longitude is actually the X axis, and latitude is actually the Y.
So if you're doing geospatial things, obviously for people who really do it, then I don't want to tell you stuff you already know,
but for people who it's new, just be aware that you're passing the right thing to the right axis,
and that will really, you'll get some like weird US plot kind of, not on the right dimensions.
DF prep, and then give it latitude.
I'm like, snacks? Yay, thank you.
Oh, that's service.
Sorry, anyway.
Okay, so actually, I'll just run that just to see what, make sure.
So I haven't assigned that yet, but yeah.
So there we go.
You would get the geometry.
It doesn't look like much because it's just the lat and long, or long and then lat.
But yeah, the stuff you can do that once you've got that is really cool.
Geo, heads.
So there we go.
Okay, perfect.
So there we are, points.
And then now you've got the points.
So D2, generate a default plot of this new Geo DataFrame, GeoDF,
then try a customized plot where the color of the points is based on their cumulative column values.
Okay, sorry, I'll do this.
So we'll do this in order.
GFDF, GeoDF plot.
So this is your kind of quick and, I don't want to say dirty, but quick plot.
So as you can see, those points just are just like a, you know, 2D, Cartesian space.
But it does look like in the shape of the US, as it should.
Then if you actually want those points, for example, to relate to an actual column, you can pass that column.
So now it varies, but we haven't chosen the colors and they are not very interpretable.
So then you can pass your own color map.
Cool.
So yeah, stuff like that.
So D3.
Okay, so evidently GeoDF plot needs a base map to contextualize the points.
Load one of GeoPanda's available datasets, natural earth low res, assign to base map, then plot.
So, this is really the basic, you know, you're kind of just using pre-existing sort of toy datasets.
And then the next session we'll kind of do something more customized.
But base map.
But yeah, the point is also to kind of show you that it's like, I'm not saying this is obviously the coolest stuff in the world,
but, you know, it doesn't take a lot of code.
You didn't need a lot of resources and you can create something which is, you know, usable.
So there we go.
That's your base map.
And then optionally, just to get a sense of what the geometry data represents and enables.
Okay, I'm not.
Actually, okay, I'll let you do that step.
But this is just to kind of show you, like, you know, those kind of geometries.
When you look at the, there's me trying to be clever and skip things.
So when you look at geometry and there's like polygons, multipolygons, that's what those polygons are, right?
Like they're shapes.
It's kind of the easiest way I can explain to you.
But I'm sure there's, you know, geospatial experts who can tell you more.
Okay, so there's also a CRS thing, which if you were doing more of this, you probably want to look at, but we'll skip that.
So D6.
Use mapplotlib to construct a basic map which plots geodf and base map together,
Featured the location of the 118 large university emitters and the relative size of their cumulative emissions over 2011 and 2021.
So as you can imagine, we're basically just taking those points and then putting it on that base map.
And then it actually looks like something meaningful.
Oh, my favorite.
Sorry.
I have to stop having attitude.
Okay, so let's do set up sort of base bare bones.
Base mapplot.
It does need to be on axis though, or else it's not going to show.
Then so that's your background thing.
Then your points.
Then you plot those on top.
And then so that would work, right?
Now you'd be like, oh, it really hasn't worked.
But actually, it has actually plotted those points, but because they're on the same default blue, like the west coast just looks kind of bulgy, right?
So hence why you need to start doing some customization.
So as before, column equals cumulative.
Let's give it a different seam up.
This is nicer colors.
What else did I do? Oh, is that it?
No.
Sorry.
Deep plugging.
Oh, sorry.
I put it in the wrong call.
See, why didn't someone.
I'm joking.
Your fault.
No, I'm joking.
Cool.
Nothing better than live debugging on a recording.
Autumn equals R.
That's not going to work.
So there, you know, it's not going to set the world alight, but yeah.
Okay, I should just I'll just make this bigger just to show that is actually usable.
So yeah.
So like I said, it's not beautiful, but you didn't have to do a lot of work to get there and does tell you stuff.
Right.
Okay.
So section E, this is where we basically do fancier version.
Because of JavaScript.
But you shouldn't say that at a conference.
So actually, Matt, data set for regional trends.
And this is the interaction version.
So he intro in this section, we extend our Gia pandas extension of pandas with folium and optional Gia pandas dependency, which provides interactive mapping from the open source leaflet JS library via panda.
Python interface.
So easier and portfolio.
E one test out the extended Gia pandas functionality that folium now enables so called explore on base map.
So right.
This is the same base map as before.
Right.
But now you've got folium.
Now.
Now it's interactive.
I mean, that's basically the same data.
Right.
But it's just like.
Flashy.
And does stuff.
Okay.
So, etu, rather than using a world map as a base layer to plot to us only data, let's prepare a regional map.
Read in the US census states shape file we double checked in section a creating another geo data frame and assign it to us state boundaries.
Okay, so this is where I've been like, make sure you've got the shape file.
Because then this will not work if you don't.
So passing the file path to that shp extension file.
Like you know I never really understand why this works but it did you know it does it's some sort of magic.
So, again, thank you jio pandas people.
Developers.
So you could run that again you could see what those boundaries.
You know look like interactively, but you know, as you imagine they are.
Shapes of the US states.
So, he for three a plotting routine harnessing folium extended capabilities of jio pandas via jio DF and US state boundaries construct an improved version of our D six basic map, namely an interactive map that visualizes the location of the
of the 118 large university emitters and the relative size of their cumulative emissions over 2011 and 2021.
Okay, so we'll do this again, just like bare minimum steps right so base layer equals us state boundaries, explore so it's that census data, like fancier.
That's your absolute minimum.
So then you take the geo DF, you know, which has got our points, the actual data we want to plot.
And then, explore, explore.
So basically calling explore.
But we're saying, m equals base labor. So basically, like, put this on an existing map instance, which is that base layer that you just created the line before.
And then actually that's it, then you can just call base layer.
I think, as your absolute minimum right. So again default blues.
So that gives you all the data.
But yeah, so that does work, but obviously, you know you want to customize that and that's where all these other things are. So I'm not going to go through all them because they are pretty intuitive.
So if you do that, that kind of like customize as the base layer so that's where you, you know, I've just changed colors, made things like, with your.
This stuff here.
These options here for the geo DF explore.
Or just to make the points more interesting, relevant, less irrelevant.
So there are so kind of colors things, and then only gives you particular information, not everything.
No, and then you'll also you can save it as an HTML. Okay, so I'll just take this quick more point to point out.
So, whilst doing this through doing this tutorial.
I discovered.
So here we go so Boston, you've got four university facilities which are large polluters or these you know within this 2011 to 2021 period.
Which are actually you can't see it right you can't click very well actually if you zoom in too far but they are basically Boston University MIT.
This is that Harvard facility. There's northeast and I think whatever you get the idea. So as a transpires.
I discovered that.
Okay, so
See the learning through doing so.
However, so this is that now owned by Harvard, Cambridge Austin Blackstone power plant which featured in that royalties article I showed you.
So, I grew up as a toddler here in Pima de Terris.
So, whilst my parents, my dad was a poor grad student, I shouldn't say that recording but yeah so and he couldn't. I should also say that.
But this is a cheap.
This is the cheap grad accommodation for Harvard. And this is the expensive apparently accommodation for it.
Which I don't know I mean obviously it's still within the boundaries of three miles and I say three miles because that's what the EPA.
So here we go.
So three miles which is 4828 meters approximately, which is this. I use this radius here because that's what the EPA reference in terms of the impact of looking at the impact of facilities on surrounding communities.
So I lived.
I was breathing in that sweet sweet air as a child.
So we did move out.
We moved out to Belmont for like, which you know is outside the three miles but you know it's still, you know, there's, there's a lot of cumulative smoke and stuff there which is fun.
So, yeah, that just kind of.
It kind of makes this like more real but also like, you know, what about the people who still live there, you know, under this fossil fuel behemoth.
Anyway, okay, so enough of the sentimentality sentimentality.
Excuse me, E5.
So this is that heat map I showed you earlier it looks really pretty.
It's probably the most impactful but probably the kind of least, the least kind of scientific Python aspect of this. So that's why I said it was optional but again this is just another tool for your toolkit, you know, especially, I shouldn't be mean.
So non technical stakeholders they love this.
You know this always really gets them engaged, and then you can like show them like actual science.
Sorry, I shouldn't be mean.
So yeah, so you can go through that it's pretty self explanatory you just need points, just sort of a list of points.
Okay, so section F, how are we doing for time.
Not bad.
Okay.
So data for statistical trends.
So,
F0, copy df prep and assign to df trends which we will prep for developing statistical graphs and have a look at the new data frame. So, copy df.
Create the trends data frame.
It's exactly what you expect but you know, just
for best practice. So yeah, but you can see here.
There's a geometry column.
I'm not going to be truly transparent. It's kind of weird. I don't know why this, this kind of has been added to this that df prep.
There might be some sort of hang up so but you do need to.
Excuse me, do you need to delete that.
If anyone can tell me why
geometry was added to a different
a different object in memory, then please tell me.
So now you delete that F2, the statistical graphs we're developing plot each facility separately, and also separately within state subsets. It's now useful for the row labels to be meaningful, rather than the integer index created by default by the original pandas read CSV call.
Set the index of df trends using the existing columns facility and state, making the change in place. Okay, so, I mean this makes more sense if I just show you.
So, basically now we want those two columns facility and state to be the index, we can then, you know, call rows by their name, as opposed to by like 512 118.
So set the index to be these two columns facility state
in place equals true.
So now, you should see that.
So there. Now that's multi index.
I mean, each of those facilities is unique. So, but then obviously you've got the state, and then that kind of tuple, you know, is a unique combo.
Okay, so, F3 the statistical graphs we're developing only need the columns with stats data. Now the essential non stats data is in the, excuse me, is now the row label.
Drop the slice of columns from g, h, g, r, p to parent companies.
So, df trends drop. Again, sorry, this is not exciting data wrangling, but you know, the end result I think is quite interesting. So, you know, worth it.
So drop that slice of columns, all the rows. So, excuse me, by labels, gh, g, r, p, id, id equals even to parent companies, which is inclusive.
As you'll see, axis equals one. So remember, it's like, look at the columns, because you're not going to find it in the rows in place equals true.
Df trends, please have worked. Yep. I couldn't remember what I was supposed to, I couldn't remember what we were supposed to be doing. Yeah, so basically now, that's great. We just now have the stats data.
Okay, F4, generate one of the target statistical graphs, namely a horizontal stacked bar chart of each facility is reported, year emissions ordering the facilities by their cumulative value.
That description is really like doesn't really tell you, as it lots of descriptions of code, it doesn't really tell you what you're actually doing.
But yeah, hopefully this will be more intuitive. So, okay, you're storing these by this cumulative column, which is why we kept it in, but we're not going to plot it.
So as I said, remember, it's always going to do ascending equals true. So there we go. See, Howard is that, you know, only hit the threshold once and never again.
She's a little sus to me, but anyway.
Okay, so, but we actually only want to plot the stats, the time series data. So use the local operator again.
You just want these columns and only to 2021, not to the end. Right. So then that will just select that.
Then you can plot tell that you want a stacked bar, a horizontal. Sorry, this is bar H is horizontal bar stacked equals true.
Is that a stacked horizontal bar? You could run that, but try and put everything in one because this does take a while to render because it is computationally meaty.
Give us fixed size, take out the legend, make the font size small because you're trying to fit 118 rows.
So, again, that's not obviously how, you know, like this is not massively readable.
You would do other things to make that. Oops. See, and that doesn't really work either.
But yeah, obviously it is interesting. I'll read this for you more. You can see on your own.
So, yeah, as I said, that was MSU, unfortunately, loads of loads of emissions every year.
So, yeah, you know, from a statistical perspective, you say it's sort of a, you know, they serve these heavy, really heavy, heavy polluters.
And then, I don't know, maybe like a actually, you know, like half of the is that half?
But a lot of the data said actually not not that much.
Some of them, you know, are every year. Some of them only a few years. So like, who's that? Missouri.
There's only four years, you know, so there's there's going to be some interesting stuff if you delved into that.
Anyway, just show you stuff you can do. OK, F5. OK, we're on the final track for the last graph.
And then we'll have another 10 minute break. F5, prepare for generating the final graph,
visualizing the time series of each facility, but in subplots by state and only for the 12 states with the worst aggregate cumulative emissions.
So compute the state level aggregate cumulative emissions.
So regroup by the states.
Just know an index so that I don't think does anything. Yeah.
Pull out the cumulative column, cumulative column, cumulative,
which is also doesn't give you anything. I always forget what you can see and what doesn't.
But yeah, then you can sum it and then you've got, you know, that's like all the facilities in each state rolled up to the state level.
Again, that is alphabetical by default, which, you know, maybe it's sometimes what you want.
It's not what we want. So F6, reuse the code from F5.
But this time, sort the default alphabetical output from worst to best, i.e. from large, excuse me, from big to small,
and access just the first 12 indices and then assign this expression to worst 12 states.
So what was I doing here?
It's weird. Okay, sorry. The format is just weird.
Sort values. So let's now sort the values ascending equals false,
which is in that. So no surprise Michigan, because it's got MSU and other things.
Perdu, I think. But then now we just want the 12.
We just want the index and we just want 12 of these.
So index 12, which gives you that and then save that down.
Worst 12 states. Okay. And then you can see that again.
I mean, you really need to. Okay. F7, assign a copy of DFTrends without the cumulative column to a variable DFTimeSeries.
So, yeah, sorry. I know this is a very faffy, but, you know, it will all come together in the final graph.
So we want to drop cumulative. You can just drop it by label because it's just one of them. Copy DFTimeSeries.
So double check, because this is what we're going to make generate all the plots from.
So, yeah, perfect. Okay. F8, we're going to test how to select a cross section of DFTimeSeries using the multi index we set in F2,
specifically returning all the facilities in the state of Pennsylvania and then transpose for the line graphs.
So, I mean, you can try any, you know, you don't have to do PA. You could try something else.
But this is just to give you a sense because we're going to use that again in the final plotting routine.
So I'm just trying to show you the components. So the final result looks less weird. I mean, I'm not understandable.
So you select. So, yeah, so this obviously is just selected all the facilities in Pennsylvania.
And then transpose. I mean, obviously, this could be Utah, which is that.
Okay, so there is a bit of a prep here around how the axes work. You can read that if you need to.
But we'll just go straight to F now and make the final statistical graph. Yay.
Use Matplotlib to set up and generate state level time series subplots,
sharing the 2011 to 2021 emissions for each facility in the 12 states with the worst aggregate cumulative emissions.
I swear all these titles sound so much lengthier than, you know, it's so much more intuitive just to see it.
But okay, so subplots. Here we go. Let's do the absolute basic. I mean, that would be nothing in it.
But okay, let's show you. So remember, we've taken 12 states.
We're going to arrange that in 12 plots in a four by three effect fee arrangement.
So n rows equals four. Do I spell that right? Yes. n calls equals three.
So there we go. So your axes are just your plots. I mean, if you've worked with Matplotlib, you already know this.
But yeah, so four rows, three columns, and then that loop is going to generate the relevant time series.
Okay, so this loop state acts in zip.
So there's 12 more states and the axes, which we flattened as per the note above.
Flattened. And then we're basically going to loop through. We're going to go df time series, cut it by that state, which is in that.
That's where you access it in the index. Transpose, plot and plot it on that specific axis.
What does it look like? It's not defined.
So that's not very useful for you to see. So I'm going to, that's why I set the fixed size.
Okay, so that now you should effectively see is close to the end result.
So, you know, 12 more states, the time series for each facility in each state, and then the rest is just, you know, aesthetics.
So share why is just to make sure you can actually, you know, those, this actually slides up because obviously, you know, that is not the same as that.
Even though it looks like it's on the same level because of the scale. So this is just adjustment.
So share why equals true. Hence why I'm not going to type it. What else is here? So here we go.
These are just, you know, given a title. So format-y formatting-y things.
So that kind of just makes it look more, you know, readable. So there we go. Now you've got labels and bits.
And this is just, this is basically just for the x axis. So that looks kind of presentable or is presentable.
Oh, it's not going to be presentable there.
Ta-da, ta-da, ta-da. So, yeah, that's just like I said, just adjust the labels.
And so F9. So final bit of this session. So comment.
Different approaches to carbon reporting. This is your, you know, real world interpretation.
Different approaches to carbon reporting and accountability could reveal different insights.
Instead of the EPA's GHGRP requiring individual facilities, exceeding the 25,000 carbon dioxide equivalent metric tons threshold to report their position,
there may be more interesting trends if this requirement was at parent level.
So I'll just tell you what I was thinking here. This is your sort of boring accountability thing. Accounting even.
So for example here, like, you know, like Yale, this is the green and the orange. Sorry if anyone's colorblind.
But yeah, so they both beat the threshold, but they're obviously individual. They're still reported.
But, you know, obviously if that was at Yale level, it'd be at least the sum of the two.
Then, of course, you've got all the other things. There could be other facilities that Yale manage, which don't meet the threshold.
You know, so then you're not seeing that full picture. And maybe that could be like even higher, you know.
But it's not going to be lower than some of these two. So that's why I'm saying that, you know, I would bet that there's some sort of accounting, you know,
nuances which don't necessarily make the full impact of university.
I mean, not just US university facilities like any facilities. Reporting at this level, I think, could hide a lot of trends, which could be pretty interesting.
Hello. What was your name again? Jackie, sorry.
Is the threshold for the data or the threshold not available?
No, correct. Exactly. So they're literally, you're only, it's, so the reporting requirement from 2011 was that, yeah, you meet the threshold.
You have to mandatory report. And then the threshold is not going to be developed from the rest of the data.
Yeah, exactly. So there's no, yeah.
And I guess the other thing I should mention, which is interesting, within that data on the EPA, you can actually see the, excuse me, you can see like more details.
What are the kind of chemical stuff, which is not my background, but you can actually see that the majority of these facilities, sorry, this isn't necessarily your question, but this is, you can see that these are all through stationary combustion.
So fossil fueling, you can see the fuel types. So it's basically all natural gas, gas and oil.
Someone, I think it's North, do I mean North Carolina?
One of these is coal, really heavy burning coal. Where is Carolina? No, where is Carolina?
I can't remember. One of these is burning.
Oh, oh yeah, sorry. Yes, that's it. NC Chapel Hill.
Sorry. Yes, exactly. Thank you. So this one.
So yeah, so that's coal.
That's kind of, you can see other articles online. Someone is burning tires, actually.
So, you know, there's just, there's stuff. There's like a whole stuff. So, you know, I really hope someone kind of does more reporting and like more insight onto this because, you know, like I said, Reuters and I both found it really fascinating.
I'm sure Reuters will be pleased to know I thought so. But yeah, anyway, sorry. That is, that's the end of the carbon pollution exploration.
And if you would like to take 10 minutes, then we will return and do deforestation.
I explore deforestation. We're not going to do deforestation. That would be very counterintuitive.
Please make sure you have, I mean, obviously you can manage your files, I'm sure. But yeah, you need to have, or this tutorial is set up, assuming that there is a subfolder called deforestation exp data, which has
TIFFs in it. So, there's four TIFFs, which hopefully you downloaded. This is the point where, did anyone, sorry, faffing with, okay, that's fine.
Did people manage to download or install VierX Array?
Or I guess, did anyone not manage to download VierX Array? Wow, yes. Okay, sorry. I thought that might be. So yes.
But don't worry, this is not a sort of shame moment. Just because, sorry.
Because I'll just tell you the issues with VierX Array. So VierX Array, which seems to be where the geospatial community are going in terms of raster import and export.
So it's kind of, instead of using raster IO, which people might have heard of.
But it does use, VierX Array does use raster IO. Raster IO requires GDAL, which is a C++ package.
And that does not work very well with Windows, basically. So to that extent, if you don't have VierX Array, which is fine.
I just need to tell you now, explain, and also for everyone else.
So I've set the tutorial, or I've developed the tutorial, so you've basically got like the VierX Array, I think I said this in the message.
You've got the VierX Array like workflow, which is just your normal stuff.
But then this is the, there's an alternative, basically as you can say, which doesn't need VierX Array.
And just effectively a kind of pill, numpy version.
So for people who are doing the alternative, there is steps, sort of parallel steps for the majority of the workflow, not the last section, which is optional anyway.
The difference mainly in the outputs is that because you're basically using, you're just basically plotting an array of numbers, there's no geospatial dimensions to it.
So there's no axes. But hopefully the idea is that, you know, at some point, you know, in the future, you might be able to figure out how to get VierX Array.
There's some non-official wheels that you can download.
So anyway, just so people know, so the way I'm going to run through is, I'm not going to go through the sort of numpy version.
It is there. So what I'll do is, I'll just kind of hide it, right?
And then people who need to do the alternative, obviously use the alternative.
Does that make sense? Okay.
So assuming that you do have this data, then, okay, we'll get started.
We are actually doing really well on time. Well, I say that now, and then we'll rush at the end.
So I was going to set the scene. So first of all, do people use spectral data?
Okay, yeah, great. So one person, this is going to be really boring for you.
Remote sensing stuff. If it's new, that's kind of great because then I can play you this video and it's kind of worthwhile.
So instead of me explaining it to you, because I actually am an economics grad,
I thought I would let the National Ecological Observatory Network explain a little bit of the space in which we're operating.
So we'll just go.
So.
CZ is there.
Sorry, we'll just do it again.
If you've ever used a camera, then you know something about spectral remote sensing.
Spectral related to the electromagnetic spectrum, which includes light that is both visible and invisible to human eyes.
And remote sensing, which involves measuring the properties of objects without directly touching them.
The typical camera that you use measures and records visible light that objects like trees and rock reflect.
This light might come from the sun, but it also might come from other sources like light bulbs.
While we often use cameras to take selfies and silly pictures of our furry friends,
scientists use high powered cameras called imaging spectrometers to measure changes in things that impact our environment,
like water quality or vegetation cover and health.
Imaging spectrometers mounted on airplanes and satellites help us create maps, like this vegetation cover map for the entire United States.
But how exactly do scientists measure changes to our environment using reflected light energy?
To answer this question, let's have a look at the electromagnetic spectrum, which is composed of thousands of wavelengths of energy.
Visible light, what we see with our eyes, is contained in the blue, green and red portions of the spectrum.
The rest of the spectrum is not visible to human eyes, but can be detected and recorded by sophisticated camera-like sensors called imaging spectrometers.
Now, there are thousands of wavelengths to record in the electromagnetic spectrum.
To deal with all these wavelengths, imaging spectrometers divide the spectrum into groups of wavelengths called bands.
For example, a band in the near-infrared region of the spectrum could include energy from 800 to 850 nanometers.
This band is useful to map healthy vegetation.
The width and number of bands is what we call the spectral resolution of an image.
Higher spectral resolution means more bands that are spectrally more narrow.
Lower spectral resolution means fewer bands, each of which covers more of the spectrum.
Now, imaging spectrometers measure reflected light energy.
You see, different objects reflect, absorb and transmit light differently, depending on their chemical and structural characteristics.
For example, plant leaves are green because they reflect more green light than blue or red light.
On the other hand, Fido the dog reflects more light in the red portion of the spectrum because of the chemical and structural makeup of his fur.
If Fido's chemical and structural makeup was the same as a plant's, then he would look green.
Now, when you point your camera towards your favorite canine doing something silly,
the camera records the amount of light reflected from the dog and its surroundings in the visible,
or red, green and blue, bands of the electromagnetic spectrum.
The camera creates what's called an RGB image, which is composed of millions of pixels.
Each pixel in the image contains a value representing the amount of red, green and blue light reflected.
We can break the image out into its red, green and blue bands too.
Here's the red band on its own.
Brighter pixels mean that more light was reflected by objects in the image
and recorded by the camera in the red part of the electromagnetic spectrum.
The darker parts are areas where less light was recorded.
When we combine the red, green and blue bands together, we get an image that looks similar to what we see through the camera lens.
We can plot the amount of red, green and blue light recorded in each pixel to create what's called a spectral signature.
In this signature, the amount of energy reflected in a particular wavelength is shown in the y-axis
and the full range of wavelengths that were measured by the camera.
In this case, blue, green and red is on the x-axis.
The spectral signature for phyto is quite different from the spectral signature for a plant.
This makes them appear visually different to our eyes too.
Differences in spectral signatures can help scientists identify different types of surfaces and objects within images.
Most cameras record light in the visible, or red, green and blue bands.
However, plants, dogs and other objects on the earth also reflect light that we can't see with our eyes.
For example, plants reflect up to 60% more light in the near-infrared portion of the electromagnetic spectrum
than they do in the green portion of the spectrum.
This is why differences in reflected light in the near-infrared portion of the spectrum
are important for mapping vegetation on the ground.
To measure these differences in the non-visible portion of the spectrum, we use imaging spectrometers,
which record light in both the visible and non-visible parts of the spectrum.
Imaging spectrometers produce what are called multi- and hyperspectral remote sensing data.
Multi, meaning many bands, more than three, and hyper, meaning up to hundreds of bands,
collected at very high spectral resolution.
We use these multi- and hyperspectral remote sensing datasets to measure light energy reflected from objects on the earth's surface
and to estimate many physical and chemical properties of objects that we wouldn't see with our own eyes.
We then use those measurements to classify what's on the ground.
For example, pixels that have a spectral signature with a lot of near-infrared light energy are often vegetation.
To review, different objects reflect, absorb and transmit both visible light and light energy that we can't see differently.
Imaging spectrometers record the amount of light that these objects reflect.
The amount of light energy reflected by an object throughout the electromagnetic spectrum is called its spectral signature,
which is driven by the physical structure and chemical makeup of the object.
We can use that signature to identify different objects in both the photograph and across the earth's surface.
And that, my friends, is how we use reflected light energy to both map what's on the ground
and measure changes in our environment.
Amazing. Okay, so sorry for the person who presumably already knows that, or other people.
I should probably say that I think that person who made that Lea Blaster, I think they are actually here at the conference doing a maintainers thing, which is really cool.
So I'm going to go and like fan person them.
Anyway, so that's kind of, we're using a lot of those concepts, not obviously all that, you know, like multi-structural hypostructure, like not all of them.
But if that kind of gives you a good sense of good context for what we're actually going to be doing.
So at this point, I should probably also show you that we...
Oh yeah, there. I knew I set it up.
Okay, so I'm just going to give you a sense of where the data came from.
So I know I showed you this earlier. Has anyone used like Landsat Look? Access TOS? I mean, apart from that person, I'm not sure.
So I took the data. That data is literally from this portal.
It's one of these scenes. And then I clipped it just so you know, because these are big images.
And you'll see they already take quite a while actually to load, even the clipped versions, which are like a fifth of the size of the original ones.
So let me give you some of the context.
Okay, so which example of deforestation are we examining?
So the change from 1984 to 2022 in a 60 square kilometer region of interest, an ROI,
originally covered mainly by tropical dry forests at the Brazil-Bolivia border within the Amazon River Basin.
So there's more context here.
So again, haphly, I'm so proud of myself. So, you know, I came up with the region myself. Sorry, this is a bit of a, hey, yay me.
And then it turns out that NASA had actually also examined the same region.
I mean, okay, our region is slightly smaller, is here, like here, but it's that portion.
But yeah, so, you know, this is obviously a relevant area.
Okay, what scientific approaches are we taking? So satellite image processing and classification.
So this is not your, you know, deep learning, you know, fancy bougie hype stuff.
This is just, you know, handcrafted and experimental, just like I said, as a more like a prototype to show you how what's possible.
And then for your purposes, you can, you know, scale up as needed.
So what outputs will we develop? Spectral vegetation indices, but specifically NDVI and thematic maps, specifically land cover or estimated.
What will our outputs tell us? So they will help quantitatively detect and measure land cover and land use, LCLU.
Change in this ROI, particularly the clearance of original tropical dry forests since 1984.
Beyond the well-known eco impacts of deforestation.
So yeah, the no whatever carbon stores or whatever.
But what makes this example significant exemplifies the contrasting historical LCLU change in a biome as a consequence of country boundaries and local differences.
So EG enforced governance, stewardship, et cetera.
So you can also read that secondary issue, which is just interesting, but not obviously totally relevant.
But yeah, what I wanted to show you was this.
Now, of course, I don't know if this is real or not before, you know, caveat, caveat, caveat.
But I just thought this was really interesting.
This is this. I'm pretty sure I could identify where this is on our map.
But yeah, so the dry tropical forest, it seems to be might be called like Sahado, something experts would tell you.
But yeah, this is the Bolivia side, Bolivian side.
This is the Brazil side. This is in the state of Hondonia.
I'm sorry if I pronounce that really badly.
I pronounce everything like French and Italian.
So, yeah, and you can see again if this is real and the the river, the Rio.
Co-opore, what's it? Co-opore is like the delineation of the country.
And yeah, so if that is real, you know, that is just really interesting to see how, you know, exactly the same biome.
I mean, basically, you know, how it survives or doesn't survive or, you know, is managed or not managed, you know,
can really depend on geopolitical differences.
So anyway, hopefully that gives you a sense of what the region is, not just, you know, pixels.
OK, so this is the data source. You can look into a bit more and some extra things on remote sensing.
Because like I said, that is not my background. I'm just telling you enough to be able to do the tutorial.
OK, A, oh, I should do the table of competence. So this is where we're kind of going.
Set up Jupyter Notebook and satellite data. So remember, if you are, you've got X-ray and Rio X-ray.
We use that. If you don't use the alternative. So import glob, globe, glob, I don't know.
Import NumPy as NP, import X-ray as XR, import Rio X-ray as RXR, import mapplot, libpyplot as PLT.
Please work. Or else this could, yes, thank you.
OK, again, just your normal jig, the auto-completion.
So A2, reading the four tutorial files in the deforestation subfolder, also creating global variables with the same name as their corresponding file name.
So how you would do your I.O. would be totally up to you.
So I would not stress about the specifics of how I've done this, but just know that it's basically creating now variables with the same name as the file, just about the extension.
For the people who are doing the alternative, please note you have to change the extension from TIFF to TIFF for PIL.
I do not know why, but it works.
OK, section B, let's inspect satellite data. So B-intro.
RASTA data is one of two main types of geospatial data.
The other is vector data. So the points and polygons we handled in the mapping section of the carbon polluters exploration are examples of this.
So data stored in RASTA format are typically in grid matrix structure, and they render as pixels, picture elements.
For geospatial RASTA data, each pixel relates to some area on Earth, and each pixel value is a measurement of some real-world phenomenon.
The four tutorial files are geospatial RASTA datasets, and the pixel values they contain are satellite measurements of amounts of light reflected from a single band of the electromagnetic spectrum.
So spectral reflectance values, so brightness, so more light, as you saw on that scale.
Less light, more light. Less red light, more red light.
OK, quick caveat. I won't read that because it's detailed, but basically because we're using effectively an older satellite or an older sensor and then a new one, so that you have maximum temporal difference.
So the Landsat 5TM captured a different wavelength to the Landsat, or different wavelengths for the red band and the near-infrared bands compared to the newer.
I would assume, again, if someone was from NASA, that'd be great if they could tell me.
I assume this basically was more, you know, the fact that they basically made the bands, I presume, more defined, so it's kind of more accurate, which probably means that this is less accurate.
But anyway, it's just things to know. They're not exactly like-for-like, but they're still useful for general purposes.
So B0. So let's check the dimensions of any of the four tutorial RASTAs. I'm going to check the 1984 red band.
So you know how those variables, because they were created in that load step, so the shape.
So we basically reduced it down to a two-dimensional 2001 pixels by 2001 pixel.
In fact, you're in a way. So B1, check the data type of any of the tutorial RASTAs.
So again, I'm just using the 1984 red band.
And so that should be in the float, but just be aware that the original data is in, is in from the Landsat Look Portal, is in UINT 16.
And then there's more about digital numbers and how the raw data was collected, which is way out of scope for this tutorial.
B2, try rendering the red band reflectance values of the ROI in 1984 using plot, which, of course, uses map.lib.
So I'll just do this first. RRI plot. OK, now, pass reds, underscore R, so reversed reds as the optional CMAP argument,
and adjust the size and aspect of the plot to be smaller than the default, so as to be faster to load.
Because like I said, these are really heavy. You already see these, those data sets are massive.
Aspect equals 1.3, size equals 4. So again, you could customize that, but just to give you a starting point.
So, oh, comment, there we go. I'll just load up for it.
So yeah, so I know it doesn't look like very much we could adjust the scale, but so remember less light, lower reading, darker in this instance.
More light, so more reflectance, like less red. OK, so just to be clear.
So that's as that is forest, that should have lower values as it does have low values because spatial signatures,
the vegetation should have absorbed the chlorophyll should have absorbed more of the red light.
Then there is firing patterns here. So I'll just show you really quickly that link.
This is a really interesting NASA resource just to show you different sort of agricultural patterns from space.
So yeah, I think one here, the one in Hondoa in Brazil looks a lot like the fish bone.
But again, I'm not an expert, but I'm sure you could find someone who is.
So B3, there is a range of spatial mass data embedded in our rasters.
Use rear X-rays bounds method to check the spatial extent of any of the rasters.
So, you know, basically like the dimensions of of what we're looking at.
So RIs, rear bounds.
And there's just a note here that I actually clipped it specifically for these values and they are different.
Anyone who is not a geospatial expert, I want to have a guess why they may not be exactly the same.
Why can they not cut exactly how I asked them to?
This is not the exciting question. So it's because they're like the pixels.
So maybe like it has to cut on a bound, right?
Unlike where exactly a pixel is and where I asked for clearly is not exactly where the pixels, the pixel boundary were.
So these, I presume, are the nearest pixel boundaries.
So just a little note.
B4, have a look at some actual reflections values. Extract a sample at the top left corner.
So from your so here, top left corner of the ROI 1984 red band 3 raster as a numpy subarray, specifically the first five rows and columns.
So ROI, red band values, which then turns it into a numpy array.
So multi-dimensional indexing, first five rows, first five columns.
So the rest are, you know, it's just numbers in a grid format.
Those are reflections values. Why do I always anticipate myself?
Okay, so each value, there we go. So it's a specific 30 by 30 meter area at the Brazil-Bolivia border.
And this one is these are the readings that lands at 5 T.M. measured on August 13th, 1984.
Be precise. 30 meters represents the spatial resolution of our restors, a metric indicating the ground surface area that forms a single pixel.
Satellite sensors can have higher or lower spatial resolution. So for example, MODIS, which is another NASA, I think, sensor, isn't it?
So yeah, that's a higher spatial. So I mean that higher, lower, higher, lower.
Anyway, there is a larger area covered by each pixel, so it has, you know, less granularity.
So 30 meters is pretty good, it seems. So B5, try rendering this numpy subarray of red band reflectance values using matplotlib's matshow function.
So remember, at this point, it's literally just an array of numbers.
So you can plot those, render those with colors.
So yeah, which is not massively exciting, but it just shows you that, you know, your image, if you don't do any sort of this kind of digital signal processing stuff, you know, images are just numbers.
Okay, optionally, this is just again to kind of give you more of a sense of what the data is.
If you run that, I've just plotted that really quickly so you can, you know, again, I'm just reinforcing the concept that brighter colors are higher spectral reflectance values, and then lower is darker.
B7, okay. Don't worry, it does get more interesting, I think, but I just kind of need to like give you some sort of basic concepts.
As the area of the ROI in 1984 covered by the pixels in the top left corner is not overly interesting, let's have a look at the top right corner instead.
So, we'll do this again, values.
So this time, top right corner, we're going to look at minus five to the end, CMAP again is reds are.
Okay, so there's that. Now, as I said, start by visualizing a five by five matrix and then keep increasing the size up to 500 by 500 because, you know, because I've tested it and it looks fun.
So now you've got 50 by 50, you know, and you can start to see again remember each of these is 30 square meters on the ground.
And then if you start getting just kind of zooming out. So this is where you can really start to see some of the, remember this is 1984 already.
So, these are those, I'm going to presume, you know, agricultural driven deforestation, sort of rectangular plots, and that's a fishman pattern.
And then, you know, you can just, you can move out a little bit more.
So yeah, again, like I said, we're just, just trying to show you that you know the relationship. Oh, hello.
Try.
Oh, I see. Yeah, sorry. So you want to try a different color map. Yeah, of course.
Underscore Earth, like that.
Oh, yeah, the gist. Yep.
That.
Yeah. So yeah, you could definitely. Yeah.
Honestly, I was like, Oh, I really want to like, you know, do a sort of kids visualizations or, you know, satellite image art sort of knock off from this because I think there's some really interesting things.
But yeah, sorry. Anyway, we'll move on. So F7.
Did I do this agricultural patterns.
Okay.
Okay. Yes.
Yes. Yeah, exactly. So the spectrum, I'll tell you what, actually, I'll just go to the next section because I think that will help reinforce your point.
But yeah, sorry, I was trying to stress it because it can be confusing.
So, section C, prepare to calculate a spectral vegetation index. So C, intro, a spectral index or ratio is an indicator of some phenomenon.
Phenomena, such as biophysical or biochemical properties calculated using the different reflectance properties of different objects.
So to this person's point, Landsat data products like burn ratios and moisture index are example of spectral indices.
One type of spectral indices relevant to deforestation are vegetation indices, VI, the most common of which is the normalized difference vegetation index NDVI used to quantify vegetation greenness.
So NDVI utilizes certain reflectance properties of plants. So chlorophyll strongly absorbs red light.
So lots of forest means lots of red light is absorbed. So not so much.
Whilst leaves slash plant structures strongly reflects near infrared light.
And so that's the spectral signature.
So the formula to calculate NDVI therefore requires the reflectance values in the red and the near infrared bands.
So there.
Yeah, that's I hope that's kind of fairly intuitive there.
So, or is intuitive. Okay, maybe we should talk about.
Okay, so.
So if it's plants, right, if there's like more green, if the surface that 30 by 30 meters just like thick, dense, totally green stuff.
So it means that it will have the plants because plants and leaves structure strongly reflects near infrared light.
This will be really high.
And then if there's plants, the chlorophyll strongly absorbs red light.
So this should be high. That should be low.
So there should be, you know, that minus that should be large.
And then that over that plus that obviously normalizes it.
And then if it's like, like water or concrete, I think stuff like that, then I think basically they're about the same.
So then you don't really get a difference.
So then your reading is much lower than if it was plants.
But hopefully that will make more sense when we actually do it.
So by design NDVI values therefore range from minus one to one.
Negative values to zero indicate no green leaves.
Whilst values approaching one indicate highest density of green leaves.
And there's some like NASA, NASA NDVI training.
I mean, there's lots of NASA training, but yeah, that's one which I think is more accessible.
In section D, we will calculate NDVI values for ROI to help detect how the existing tropical dry forest cover in 1984 had changed by 2022 as likely deforestation.
And then just to note that you can get this pre-calculated, but you know, it's better that you do yourself because you understand it more.
So C0 in advance of calculating NDVI values using the above raster math formula, render the red and near infrared rasters of the ROI from 2022 as subplots.
So.
So we're basically plotting the two rasters from 2022.
Side by side.
Just so you can get a sense of what the data looks like before we calculate the NDVI.
So red band, we'll do red band on the left.
So plot.
Then we'll do the near infrared band on the right.
Plot.
Okay, and I'm just going to copy this because there's no value and you're watching me type that.
So.
Lose, lose.
That also needs to be on that axis and then plot show.
Show.
No, subplots.
There we go.
Schnal, Schnal, Schnal.
There.
Like I said, it really does take a long time.
So yeah, so this is 2022, right?
So the one you showed you saw earlier was 1984.
So, I mean, you can see even from the red band, like, I mean,
I mean, you know, even as like a non-scientist like me, I mean, it's pretty clear this, you know,
again, this is the Brazil side.
This is the Bolivia side.
I'm pretty sure that that photo I showed you, I think it's somewhere possibly here.
These kind of tributaries.
So, yeah, it's, yeah, not a lot of trees left on that side, clearly.
And then, okay, the near infrared, this will not be particularly interesting itself.
It's like, as we said, the culmination of the two.
But let's start actually calculating some NDVI.
And I'll just tell you, so we're going, so we're calculating this.
We're going to make some maps.
Then we're going to do some thematic maps.
And then there's some optional kind of relation to the real world thing at the end if we have time.
So D0, calculate NDVI values for the ROI in 1984 by performing the required RASTA math with ROI 1984 near band 4,
then ROI 1984, red band 3, and assigned to NDVI 1984.
So the kind of most important bit I'd say is actually the easiest because of the power of NumPy and vectorized operations.
This is a piece of cake.
And I say that now, and I hope that this doesn't fail.
I haven't jinxed it.
So the near infrared band minus the red band over the near infrared band plus the red band, which I'm literally just going to copy that.
Oh, I'm doing the wrong, I'm doing the wrong date.
1984, 1984, 1984.
Okay.
I knew I said it was the easiest, but I totally jinxed it.
And then I messed it up.
Okay. So you've now got NDVI 1984.
So let's sense check that by looking at a couple of values.
NDVI values, turn it into a NumPy array.
Let's just look at some 2x2.
Just a sense check.
So yeah, so in that particular corner, that top left corner,
you're looking at sort of, you know, 0.3, 5, 0.4.
So that, we'll talk about that later, but that is sort of like some veg, sparse veg, not like super dense, but veg.
D2.
So calculate the NDVI values for the ROI in 2022 by performing the required RAS math with the ROI 2022 nearby band and ROI 2022 red band and assigned to NDVI 2022.
So basically the same thing, but for the other time period.
So near infrared minus red over near infrared.
Plus red, that's right.
Yes. Good.
D3. So also sense check that.
2x2.
So, I mean, just by coincidence, or maybe usefully.
So these values are lower, you know, which, I mean, I wouldn't draw a massive point about it, but you know, you would basically say that that could indicate that where in 1984, there was more veg, maybe in 2022 in the same spot.
There looks like there's less veg in these 30 square meter areas on the ground.
D4. This is just so you know that you can save stuff.
You can export stuff so you can do that. I already have 5,000 copies of these so I'm not going to.
Okay, section E. So now let's just make some maps from that data.
E0.
The NDVI datasets are still geospatial rasters, i.e. grids of pixels, and still each linked to 30 square meters on Earth. However, the value of these pixels indicate the density of green leaves covering that place on Earth on a scale of minus one to one.
So not just measurements of light, as before. So let's therefore render both NDVI rasters to help discover how dense vegetation was in our ROI in 1984 compared to 2022.
So this is your classic before and after.
Which, I shouldn't ruin this part. It may not be quite what you expect and that's where I'm going to say this is possibly down to the change in band coverage of the different, of the older and the newer sensors.
However, you know, I mean that's science right like you don't always get the results you're hoping for and if you're ethical you're not going to jig them just to make it show you what you want.
So plot, plot, plot show.
Yeah, plot show even.
So this again is just the same CMAPs, putting on the axis but here I'm just specifying. So instead of actually having one to minus one to one as the scale.
I'm okay I am jigging a little bit just so the colors stretch a little better.
Because that is, that's the sort of range of the values in these two rasters, NDVI rasters.
So,
Okay.
So, you know this is real data so you know it's, yeah, obviously I would have liked this to be like really really, you know, really green and that would be really, I don't know, not, but again, you know you're using different data so not like for like
a whole bunch of data collection, but you know there's still things that you can see. So, what can you see.
I mean here you can obviously see. So, you know, this is going to be lower NDVI values because this is presumably like earth roads that are created to in order to create the farming plots and then then they've obviously kind of really gone to town
with more clearing of the forest, but also you know plotting, plotting, growing crops, that's why I meant crops, which are also green so then you know if you want to do more sophisticated analysis, you would, you know, want to try and figure out the difference between, you know, crops,
green is from like crops and green is from like forest. So I'm sure someone, an expert could tell you that. I think something for me, what I thought was interesting actually was that there does seem to be, so you know it's not just like, you know, you're clearing the forest and you know carbon sinks and stuff like that but also when you don't have trees, then you get more runoff and you know there's more sedimentation, goes into rivers.
You know, I'm just guessing by eye, like these rivers, they kind of look a lot kind of weaker here. Some of them kind of like the loops are kind of cut off, that would sort of make more sense to me that there's more kind of silt, like affecting river pollution.
So anyway, things. There are things you can do, things you can see.
Here we go. This is the caveat reminder, but the thing which we can use is, I'll just read it. So, this is about the NDVI values of what surfaces or what materials have what kind of NDVI values.
So, areas of barren rock, sand or snow usually show very low NDVI values. Sparse vegetation such as shrubs and grasslands or senescent crops may result in moderate NDVI values.
High NDVI values correspond to dense vegetation such as that's found in temperate and tropical forests or crops at their peak growth stage.
Anyway, and then the other interesting things.
Are there sciencey things? Okay, so E1. So, so far in this exploration we've been handling continuous raster data. However, in preparation for developing a thematic land cover map next section, let's start to consider how we could meaningfully group or bin pixels into NDVI ranges associated with specific land cover.
So check the distribution of both sets of NDVI values through quick histogram plotting.
So, let's literally just look at those values on top of each other.
So, you can just pull that straight away. That's not super useful. Let's give it some colors.
Colors and then also we're going to give the 2022 plot some transparency with the alpha value just so you can actually see stuff and then the semicolon is just to suppress this weird stuff.
I mean, great stuff. Thank you, Matplotlib. So, again, I mean, this is, I guess what I was hoping to see when I designed or, you know, came up with this. I was like, oh, hopefully in 1984, you know, these values would be like way over here.
And then in 2022, they'll like be way over here. And it's not quite like that. You know, I don't know. There's also things on the day, the angles of the satellite, all that kind of stuff.
But I mean, you can see though, this is a lot, there's a lot more here in this area than there was. I mean, in this NDVI, this range of data than there was in 1984.
So I'm like, this feels like agricultural bits.
Okay, so now let's do the classification, the classifying land cover using NDVI and make thematic map.
Okay, so, this is like a caveat. So this section is designed to introduce the idea of pixel based image classification of land cover using satellite imagery in order to create thematic maps and does not represent best practice.
Check out more NASA training material. There's lots of it. Although I would like to say though, the NASA training material, so they actually use QGIS mainly.
So I would like to say this is kind of more, you know, more kind of pythony. Although QGIS is great, I'm sure.
We will be executing an experimental process trying to develop a meaningful thematic land cover map of our ROI in 2022, leveraging known NDVI values of certain land cover and the distribution of empirical NDVI values.
So, sorry. Central to this process is performing pixel based classification. We will have a go at producing a map that describes four land cover types by implementing the below experimental classification scheme, whereby every pixel will be assigned to a class based on its NDVI value.
So like I said, this is really just, you know, just an idea of how you could do it. You could obviously design the classes differently, you know, call them different things.
But, you know, it's just to give you a sense that actually sometimes simplifying the information. So from continuous to, you know, discrete is actually more useful for being able to interpret things.
So F0. Find out the official type of the NDVI 2022 object, because we have actually been using X-ray data arrays, but I have not been sort of emphasizing that because we're not going into it because it is a bit confusing if you're just starting out with scientific computing.
But just know that it's a data array. F1. So we're going to make a copy called LCLU NDVI, which is what we are going to basically bin the pixels.
F2. Our approach to implementing the pixel classification involves manually binning the subset of pixels that belong in each class, so the process is more transparent. Try calling X-rays where function in order to test replacing the NDVI values in LCLU, which are under 0.3 with 99.
Okay, so this is just to show you like the method that we're going to use in order to do the binning. There are much more like, there are other ways to do this, but this is kind of a really transparent way.
So here we're basically saying the NDVI values, which are under 0.3, replace it with 99. I mean, just arbitrary, just, you know, because you want to see. And if it's not under 0.3, just leave it as is.
Okay, so here you go. This is a data array, which I have not showed you because I didn't want to because it's got things called coordinates, which are not actually like, they're confusing.
But just so you know, that is what you're working with. And they're very 2,000 by 1 by 2,000, 1 pixel size. So here, actually, it does turn out that actually those values in that top left corner do mainly see as being under 0.3.
So that's why you get 99. So anyway, once you've tried that, you know how that functionality works. Now we're going to replace, we're going to bin all the pixel values.
So F3, build the final data array output, LCLU4, through creating a series of incrementally updated data arrays that replace the pixel values assigned to each class with 100, 200, 300, and 400 respectively.
I wouldn't type this out manually for you, because like I said, the way you might do this is differently. I mean, really, you would probably use NP digitize and then a ufunk, just FYI.
But this works. And you can see you're basically, you've replaced here the values under 0.15 and then values under 0.25, 4, and so on and so forth.
So that works. So F4, let's review the fully classified raster LCLU4 representing our land, cover, map by generating a quick plot.
So now you've literally just got four values, 100, 200, 300, and 400. They're not meaningful. They're not supposed to be. It's just so that you can separate them out and color them.
And then color them like this. So again, that's, yeah, it's not actually a continuous color. So don't worry about that. But like I said, it's just a quick, dirty plot.
So you've got the four colors. This is the default. So this is your higher. Yeah, that's right. So this is, so remember, this is like your low NDVI, your highest.
So that should be your most green, least green. So most green, most green, which is correct because this is like the null comp, the conservation project.
So there should be forests. Or they're doing a very bad job at conservation. This is actually rock. So that should be low. And then these are like crops.
So that kind of looks sensible. Not perfect. But like I said, this is just to show you how it could be done. And then you can tweak it yourself.
F5. So I'll just tell you what we're doing now is we're going to create our own color map and just sort of make a kind of more usable version.
So F5, let's prepare to construct an upgraded version of this land cover map. Import the listed color map class from mapplotlibcolors.
So mapplotlibcolors. Colors, colors, import listed color map.
F6. Create a custom color map consisting of four appropriate named colors called LCLUCMAP. So LCLUCMAP.
So yeah, so this is like literally the color maps that you've been using, like someone else has actually gone, oh, it's going to be like red, orange, yellow.
So this is you just making your own, which is a useful skill anyway.
You could also choose your own selection. This is just, you know, things which seem to look good or appropriate for screen.
Yep. And then you can make the upgraded land cover map of the ROI from 2020 using the LCLUCMAP and other mapplotlib options to find you.
Okay, so let's build this up again from basics. FIGX is subplots. FIG size. Just make them all like that.
8 by 6. So your absolute basic LCLU is you need that final classified raster and UVI.
We're going to give it that CMAP we just customized. So this would be your absolute, I mean, this will work.
This will be your classified land cover map with those colors, specified colors.
And then the rest is just tweaking because, you know, like we don't, like I said, that 100 to 400 were just random values. It could have been anything.
So this is where the tweaking happens. So I'm not going to type that because it's not very exciting.
And you might do it differently if you are using a different visualization package.
So that just gives you some actual labels. And I think that's yeah, you can get ready to, you know, export that as per the other things.
Yeah. Okay. So in the, we actually can do this last bit. I think this is actually interesting.
So this is the last section, section G. Transform coordinates from different map projections.
So I was like, should I read this? Okay. I guess basically the point is it's like, so this is cool. We can do stuff within this.
So like, if you want to kind of basically like cross references with something actually in the world, you know, so you've got coordinates of this area from some other map, but they're in a different map projection.
You're like, how do they, you know, how do I, what's the relationship between these coordinates?
So I'll just kind of show you the, like this is optional, so I'm just going to show you kind of the bare bones of this.
So what I did was I went to this map biomass.
This is the Brazilian annual land use and land cover mapping project and basically identified.
I have to remind my Portuguese. I think it's this one.
So this, I basically was looking to see what someone knew about this area so that we could then translate it into our analysis and then annotate our land cover map.
This is really slow.
But yeah, I mean, if you are looking at this particular area, this is quite interesting.
And maybe it's a nice change not to look at Jupiter notebook for a second. State.
Hondoa.
Just do that.
Which yeah, I was going to say, this is a really interesting tool that I stumbled on. I remind myself what I need to do. Oh yeah, okay.
Pasture. I won't go through all that because you've got the steps. But yeah, this is really interesting because it can show you, you know, obviously people who actually research this can tell you what these things are.
Sorry, let me just remind myself click natural and anthropic use. Deselect anthropic use.
Okay.
Okay, that's right. So this is as of 2021.
So this is where this project said there is forest.
And this is according to them, which is obviously much better source and you know, me who knows nothing. Oh, hello.
Oh, well, okay, that's supposed to come up with something.
I can't see it.
Okay, anyway, so there's an instruction I can show you. Yeah, in the Jupiter notebook you can see. But yeah, the point was using these maps.
I identified a point. I think it's here.
30. I'll just show you here.
30, 55, 13, 55 and 61.
30, 55 and 61.
There was a somewhere here where you could actually see from 2018 to 2021. It looked like it was new pasture. Oh, here. Finally. Seriously, like I'm doing a live coding demo.
So yeah, so here in 2018, this is it.
So okay, you can really see like there's bits of. So this is pasture, I'll just tell you. Yeah, there's bits of the forest being cleared for pasture, pasture gem.
You can actually change it to English. I probably should have done that.
And then actually as you slice it out long, you know, you can start to see more yellow, more yellow, more yellow.
So, you know, so anyway, so this coordinate, this is at minus 13, 55 and minus 61. So you're like, okay, well, how does that relate to, you know, this map projection we've been using here?
Like there is no 13, you know, there's no 13, 55, 61 because it's on a different coordinate system. So this is just really quick steps.
I won't talk through them because they're not particularly exciting on their own, but this is just to show you, give you a process of how you can convert if you've got coordinates.
So these coordinates, which are in the very, the standard map projection, which is EPSG 434343436.
So is it 43204326? I was close.
So most things are in that. The satellite data isn't.
So in fact, the satellite data is in this EPSG 32620, which again, you don't particularly need to know, but you just need to know that they are different.
So it covers this area of land, which is, you know, that Brazil border.
So this point of interest, pure eye, those are the coordinates.
So I'll just let you work with it just to show you. This is a method that you could just replace it with whatever other coordinates you're interested in.
You need to do some sort of transform thing.
You need to apply the transform thing.
And then you've actually got your transform coordinates. So there is coordinates minus 13, 55.
Minus 13, 55 and the 61. I think this is the 61 and then this is the minus 13, 55.
Right. So remember XY, because this, I'm going to stress it again.
This is not in XY. This is Y and that is X.
So you have to remember which way around. Anyway, then just to show you at that coordinate, let's see what the NDVI value is.
So 0.38. So actually it's quite high. That's surprising because it's pasture.
But OK, well, it is what it is. And then G8. So you can copy the F7 plotting routine.
OK, I will do that just to show you how we're annotating because I said we're annotating.
So the F7 plotting routine.
There. And I'll just change the size, just make it bigger.
But literally all we're doing is this annotation here. I mean, you could put it anywhere, but I guess I said I'd put it there.
So annotate, annotate, annotate. New.
Deforestation for pasture.
And then at this XY. And then, yeah, the rest is just kind of like, you know, arrows and bits.
So I'm not going to. I'm not going to put you through that. I mean, to see that. But yeah.
Obviously, the point is that you generated the XY coordinates. So now you know where that is.
Invalid syntax, because it does not have a coding parent.
Please work. Thank you.
So, yeah.
So that is how you can annotate, you know, a way of translating something from, you know, a different map, for example, or a different projection.
But you want to annotate your satellite data derived output with, you know, a thing.
And that is, thankfully for me, that is the end of the coding of the tutorial.
And I think, yeah, so we've got six minutes for wrap up, which I didn't really prepare because I wasn't expecting actually to be able to do wrapping up.
So, yeah, I guess we should just do questions.
That's probably more useful than me just like.
Trying to come up with something interesting.
Anything.
Any comments, something, I don't know.
No.
Yes.
So, if you're dealing with two different sets of satellite image data, and you worry that there might be discrepancy with the technology that was used or the quality of the camera or whatever,
would you consider normalizing dataset one off of dataset two, given an area that you know hasn't changed or something like that?
Like, would you consider it to be using pre-processing on one, or is that getting a little bit dangerous?
When you said, so do you mean not using two different satellites?
Using the two, but let's say you're noticing on one that the colors are coming out a little bit lighter, like there's just kind of across the board, you're not getting the data you would have expected.
Would you consider comparing an area that you know has a change with satellite image two and be like, okay, so across the board on this one, we should lower values by six or whatever because they seem to be a little bit lighter in this one?
Oh, I see, yeah. So you're sort of saying like, would that be a valid?
Yeah, that would be a good research step.
Yeah, I was going to say, I think there did seem to be a lot of, I mean, obviously, Kevin's tutorial, and I did see there was a lot of people referencing adjustments, so the corrections, and I think that would, it sounds like, often is just going to be on that case by case basis,
you say like a region that you know, and it's like, actually, maybe we can make that own sort of manual adjustment of, you know, so like, for example, I mean, you could even see that the difference in the wavelengths, so with like the red band, you can see it was like tighter this way, so you know, maybe you could adjust the data and be like, actually, we know the values, you know, maybe some of these values, based on the things we know about the surfaces on the earth, maybe we know that that's kind of over, you know, like over reading, and like, because it's like rock versus plant design.
So yeah, so yeah, sorry. The end was like, yes, I think so. It seems like that's how people do it. So yeah, I hope that's helpful. Question.
So,
another question. Okay. No, that's fine if you don't have.
Because it's been a long session for me. Anyway, yeah, thank you for coming. I hope that was useful.
Like if you want to, I don't know if you want to ask me stuff about it. I mean, I, yeah, I'm all over the internet in a professional way.
So yeah, just feel free to like reach out.
Yeah, thanks so much for coming and have a great rest of conference.