Does this work?
Okay.
All right.
Hi, everyone.
Sorry for the small delay.
My name is Guillaume De Ken, and today I'm going to talk about fixing legacy codes one
pull request at a time.
So sorry.
Before I start, a few words about myself.
So my name is Guillaume.
I come from Belgium, and for the last four years I've been working for Sonar in Geneva,
where our goal is to enable developers to write clean code, and we do that through the
use of static analysis tools that we develop.
And as for myself, I've been working on our static analyzer for Python, which, by the
way, is free and open source.
So today I'm going to explain a bit the methodology that we promote when dealing not only with
legacy code but also with all code projects in general.
And I will show a small demo of this using one of our tools, which is Sonar Cloud, and
for that I will take an existing Flask application and pretend to develop a new feature for it.
This part can be followed interactively if you want, but of course you don't have to.
So a few words about what we offer at Sonar.
We have three products.
The first one is called Sonar Cube, and it's a self-managed static analysis platform to
analyze and monitor the health of your code base.
It's meant to be self-managed, and it's free and open source with additional page features
available.
We also have Sonar Cloud, which is essentially a cloud-based version of Sonar Cube, and this
one is entirely managed by Sonar Source.
It is not open source, but it's still free for open source projects.
And because it's operated by Sonar Source, it's easier to set up in your CI-CD workflow
for continuous analysis and inspection of your delivery.
This is what I will show in this presentation.
And finally we have Sonar Lint, which is an IDEA extension that you can use in PyCharm
or VS Code to have a similar analysis as the one we provide on the platform.
So a quick agenda for me today.
So first I will explain the problem that we're trying to solve and explain a bit the methodology
that we promote.
And then I will be using Sonar Cloud to set up the analysis for our small Flask application.
I will use what we call automatic analysis, which is that we don't need to integrate
the analysis on the CI.
Sonar Cloud will do it itself.
I will show that this has some limitations and present a more advanced setup where we
do the analysis as part of the CI itself.
And finally I will quickly show how you can set up Sonar Lint in the IDE for the same
analysis so that you raise the issues and fix them before you commit them and push them.
If you want to follow along when I'm doing the demo, the only prerequisite really is
to have an account on GitHub and be logged in.
I will be using some GitHub actions.
You don't really need to know about them.
If you do, it's better, of course.
And the project that I'm going to use lives in the Sonar's first organization.
It's called PyCon-Sonar-Workshop.
And I will fork this demo project with all the branches.
So if you want to go ahead, feel free.
I will come back to this anyway.
So quick reminder on CI-CD since I talk about CI-CD workflows.
CI-CD is continuous inspection, continuous delivery, or deployment.
It's meant to help deliver incremental features in your code base and to deploy them systematically.
Of course, one important part of this is to make sure that the code actually works.
So we have tests that are running in the CI workflow.
We can also have a step to have static analysis running so that you can catch some issues
that before any manual review or anything.
Now what do I mean by static analysis?
Quick reminder as well.
I'm talking about analyzing code without executing it.
So really looking at the code, finding issues in a systematic way.
And the goal of that is to help developers to write clean code.
And what we mean by clean code is code that is fit for development and fit for production.
So you want it to be fit for development so that it's maintainable, it adheres to standards,
you can understand what the code is doing and change it if you need.
And fit for production, of course, means that you want the code to behave as you expect
with no bugs.
It's reliable and it cannot be exploited by malicious actors in any way.
So this is what we mean.
A small example of this is a, here is a small snippet.
Here what we have is a list, a call to list.extend that is assigned to a value.
However, list.extend doesn't return anything.
It only mutates the list, the receiving list.
So this is an obvious mistake that can easily be caught by static analysis.
Maybe a reviewer would need some knowledge of the API to catch that.
So if you can do it automatically, it's of course better.
Now the problem is when dealing with legacy projects is that if you decide to analyze
for the first time, if you decide to have static analysis on the first time,
you are drawn with a lot of issues.
It's supposed to be an image that doesn't load, but there's basically someone
drowning.
And if you analyze for the first time, you will see a lot of issues in your code
and it will be really difficult to deal with it and to fix them all at once.
And the main problem, the main question that people will ask from a manager's
perspective is of course, where do I find a budget for this?
Where do I find the money to actually fix all those issues for this legacy project?
Knowing that there is of course a risk of functional regression and bugs that you
can introduce so you can break stuff.
From a developer point of view, we don't also want to fix all those issues that
are caught because we don't have the ownership of that code.
It's an old code that we didn't write.
And there are a lot of issues and it's frankly quite boring to do.
So nobody really wants to fix all the issues that you would find in a legacy
project.
And yet everybody suffers from the situation.
Developments will cost more.
Developers will be unhappy to work in a legacy code base.
And even if you do manage to fix all the issues that you have, it will be quite
difficult to raise the quality standards of your project.
So let's imagine you reduce the number of issues caught by the analyzer down to zero.
Then you want to enable a new rule or be more strict about code coverage or
whatever.
You don't want to spend months to fix issues.
So the conclusion to that is that fixing all issues without a methodology is not
really scalable.
You will have too much to do all at once and too much of an upfront investment to
do and it's too difficult to keep up with this.
Now what we do promote instead is what we call the clean as you code approach.
And it's based on two main principle.
One is that we do have ownership of the code that we write today and
we understand it way better than old code.
And if you can guarantee that this new code that we write today is respects a high
quality standard, then we will eventually clean our application just by working on
it and it will eventually let's say clean itself with no upfront investment.
To illustrate that, let's imagine that we have a code base today that has fully
legacy code and we assume that only new codes will be added.
Of course, adding new code also means removing old codes.
It means renewing and refactoring the code.
And if after one year we assume that we've renewed 20% of the code base and
everything that we added is clean, of course we have 20% clean code.
Again, after five years, if we assume that we've rewritten 50% of the application,
that's 50% clean code and that's how we will lean towards a more clean
code base with no upfront investment.
Okay, now I will illustrate this with my small demo.
Again, if you want to follow along,
the prerequisite is simply to be logged in on a GitHub account.
And I will work with this project that is here,
so our source by con sonar workshop and I will fork it in a minute.
Quick presentation of the application.
It's basically a small Pokedex Flask application.
So it has only two routes.
One will list all the existing Pokemons available.
So those small monsters, it doesn't matter if you don't know them.
And the second route is subscription route so
that users can subscribe to a newsletter, for example.
And this is stored in a SQLite database, so very, very simple CRUD-like application.
There are problems with some of the display.
There's an image here, I will skip it.
But this is basically how the applications look like.
Again, it doesn't matter too much.
I will not actually play with it.
But basically the goal here will be to pretend that we want to add a new
feature to our application and it's a new route.
It's a get basically so that when you click on one of those
Pokemons you get brought to a new page with a detailed description.
So this is the new feature that we want to add and
we'll see how we can check for the quality of this.
So now I will move to GitHub where I have my repository that I want to work with.
So back into our workshop, I will fork it now.
I will fork it in my personal organization.
And it's important to not only take the main branch but
to take all existing branches because I will play with the existing branches as well.
So let me create this fork.
It takes a couple of seconds.
And here I have it.
So I do have a GitHub workflow already in the application.
I can show it quickly.
It's basically the default GitHub action workflow.
It will set up Python 3.10, install some dependencies.
It will actually run flakate and py tests by default.
So this is what we start with.
And because it's a forked repository, this GitHub action is not enabled by default.
So I need to go to action and I need to enable the GitHub actions to run.
So that when I will open my pull request, it will actually run.
And now what I will do is to open a pull request from my feature branch to
my main branch.
So I go to pull request and I will open a new pull request.
Here I need to target my fork, not the upstream.
By default it's targeting the upstream.
You don't want that.
And I will take the add feature branch and
I will create a pull request for my main branch.
So let me create this.
I will go through the changes really quickly here.
So what I have is basically a new route for
my Flask application which takes a pass parameter and will return a new page.
I'm making some changes in a helper that will retrieve the information from
the database so it will perform a call to my SQLite database.
I have a small helper method to orchestrate that.
Some ginger templates, some tests.
So it's a fairly straightforward pull request for a new feature.
You can pretend it's any new features you want.
And here I see, okay, my CI has passed.
I could merge it.
Of course I will not do that yet.
And instead what I will do is to enable Sonar Cloud to analyze this pull request
so that we see the issues that we can find in it and
how we can apply this clean as you code methodology on it.
Because by default if you're using a linter like this,
it will analyze the whole code base and maybe that's not what you want.
So for this I will go to Sonar Cloud.
And there is in the read me the link in first analysis on Sonar Cloud,
there is this link, SonarCloud.io sessions new.
So I will follow that link and I will onboard my project on Sonar Cloud.
So I will be using my GitHub account, of course, and
I need to give some permission to the application to set it up.
And I will be prompted to analyze a new project.
I think if you've never logged in on to Sonar Cloud,
you will be asked to create a new organization first.
But I will do that in a second, so
might have the screens in the different order.
So I will import an organization directly from GitHub.
I will use my personal account, so you need to install Sonar Cloud for
this on your personal account, which I will do.
And we need to give visibility for the repositories that we want.
You can give to all repositories if you want.
I will only give for this workshop project.
And I will install Sonar Cloud.
Now I'm creating an organization into Sonar Cloud.
It already read my information from my GitHub profile, so
it prefilled the name, the key of the organization.
I can choose my plan.
I can choose a free plan since I have an open source project.
And I can create my organization like that.
And then I can import a project from this organization.
So I only gave visibility to the workshop one.
This is the one I will select and I will set this up.
I know what will happen.
So we didn't change anything in our CI, of course.
And what will happen is that Sonar Cloud, by default,
will automatically analyze the main branch of the project and
also all pull requests of that project.
And it will compute metrics to make sure that everything works well.
So maybe a small recap of what I did so far.
Again, this is not displaying very well.
So just meant to say that, okay, I forked the project,
enabled my GitHub action, opened the pull request.
And then I went to Sonar Cloud, imported my organization,
analyzed the new project.
You cannot see the images, so I will basically skip this.
And here I am on the overview of my project where I can see the history
of the quality of my project.
Of course, there's no history to speak of since I just onboarded this project
into Sonar Cloud.
I want to still quickly show you what it looks like on a more mature project.
So I will open another just to show what we can see and
how this clean as you could thing work in real life for us.
So this is a project for one of our analyzers for .NET code, actually.
And here I can see the full history of this and
I can see a graph of the number of issues.
And what I want to highlight here is that this is exactly what I was talking about
with this clean as you code and this raising quality standards.
Which is that here we have the number of issues over time and
we can see all those big bumps into the number of issues.
Which actually represent moments in time where the team decided to change
the quality profile to enable more rules.
And basically what they say is that they don't really care about the number of
issues that they find.
So here we go from, I don't know, 150 to 1,600 issues.
And what matters is that over time this number tends to decrease until the next
big spike which generally comes from enabling new rules.
But generally the tendency is to basically go down with time,
one pull request at a time.
This is a real project, so of course it's a bit messy here.
We have a lot of stuff where the team played with configuration, but
still the overall thing remains the same.
That issue number tends to decrease over time thanks to this approach.
Now coming back to my dashboard here, I have several things that I can see.
The first thing is that I can see the quality of my main branch with all the
issues that are found on the main branch of the project.
I can also see the issues on the new code since the last version if I set up
a new code definition which I haven't done here.
And what's interesting is that I can go to pull requests and
I can go directly to my pull request here that has been analyzed automatically.
And here I see the dashboard that relates to this pull request.
And this is where we will enforce that only the new code that we add is clean
through the concept of what we call a quality gate, which is basically a set of
metrics and a set of conditions that we will look at the code for.
And if the conditions are satisfied, then the quality gate will be passed.
And the pull request can be merged from a quality standpoint.
And of course if it's failed, then there are issues to fix.
And this is divided into several categories.
I will go through them quickly.
So first we have the reliability category which relates to bugs.
Here of course we don't want bugs, so
this category will be failed as soon as there is one bug that is detected.
Now let's see an example of those bugs.
So we can click on the number to get the filtered view of the bugs that we have.
You have the issues that are here.
And if we click on them, I can see in context what the issue is.
So here it's a fairly simple and straightforward bug.
We're trying to raise a string.
In Python we should raise exceptions, not string.
Otherwise we get the type error.
So this is fairly straightforward.
You get to interact with the issues if you want.
You can actually change the status or report it as a false positive.
If you think it doesn't make sense or just say okay, I won't fix this.
I intended to do this, which maybe is not the case for a bug, but let's pretend.
You can also get a detailed description of the issue so
that you understand it a bit better if you don't for
more complex issues that might make sense.
And yeah.
So this is a simple issue that we can find.
Now let me move on to another issue here,
which involves multiple locations.
So in this case, we're calling a function that is called
isPikachu with one argument.
But in fact, this function is defined to receive two parameters.
So of course there's a mismatch.
It's again a fairly straightforward issue, but
this is just to show that you get this information of issue locations.
So that you get the issue in context and the context is provided as well.
Now let me move back to the summary to talk a bit more about
the security issues that we can find as well in the code.
So in this case, what Santa Cloud is doing is called taint analysis.
So it's trying to look for
data flow between the entry points of the application and
the sensitive actions that you could perform.
So in this case, for example, reading into a database.
And what it's looking for is whether information provided by the user,
which is tainted, can actually reach the sensitive points of the application
without being sanitized or validated.
So let's see an example of this.
Here we have two issues.
I will select the first one.
And it says, change this code to not to construct
SQL queries from user controlled data.
So here we have the issue that we are executing this SQL statement.
And of course, if you're just looking at this line,
it might not be clear why there is an issue.
So the data flow is actually represented.
And we can track it.
So we can look at the source here, which is actually the pass parameter that is
indeed user controlled and provided by the user.
And we can basically track the flow of data from this to the helper method
that's, sorry, the helper method that is called here.
And then this is the fetch Pokemon method that receives the Pokemon ID as
a parameter we call our connection wrapper gets single Pokemon with this value.
And here we see that it's again received as a parameter.
It's used to construct the statement and execute it directly.
So at no point in time have we sanitized the value or
checked what data can actually contain.
And this is why our cloud will raise a vulnerability issue because in this case
you can actually change the SQL statement that will be executed.
And this is of course something you don't want to happen.
Now the second issue that has been detected here is very similar.
I will go through it quickly.
So again, we have the same source,
the same Pokemon ID that is provided as a parameter.
It is sent to this render template method and
here it's actually passed in the dictionary for that template.
And we see that in the HTML we don't have auto escaping enabled for this example.
And because of that we are sensitive to reflected XSS vulnerability.
So this is the kind of vulnerabilities that you can find in the code using
Summer Cloud.
And now finally another category which is maintainability issues.
Here it's more about good practice, bad practices, readability, etc.
So it might be a bit more opinionated sometimes.
Let's see a couple of examples.
Here we have a bare except.
Generally using bare except is not very recommended in Python.
You will catch exceptions that you might not want to catch.
So it's better to be explicit.
This is one issue.
There is another kind of issues which more relates to type checking.
So in this case we have a comparison for
equality against an integer for this value which has a type int of string.
This comparison will never be true if the type int is respected.
Here, Summer Cloud is being a bit conservative knowing that type ints are
not enforced.
So it will raise a code smell for the inconsistency but not a bug.
Okay.
So sometimes code smells can still be bugs in fact.
And finally we have another one which is more stylistic where you can
merge two if statements to make code more concise.
This is again something that might be a bit more opinionated and
in this case saying that you don't want to fix the issues or
disabling the role depending on your use case might be interesting.
Finally another type of issues that we have is security hotspots.
In this case this is about code that is sensitive from a security perspective.
But there might not be an actual issue to speak of so
it needs to be reviewed and it's more context dependent.
So we don't have one.
The pull request, there is one in the main branch that I can show,
there are two actually I want to show.
This one, so for example here we're using a regular expression
that is vulnerable to catastrophic backtracking.
In this case we're using it with user inputs in our Flask application directly.
So it might actually be vulnerable for a denial of service.
In some context this might be an acceptable,
maybe this regex is not acceptable but
a polynomial runtime for regular expression might be acceptable in some cases.
So in this case our cloud is again being a bit conservative by saying that this is
a hotspot and not a vulnerability or a bug.
The same thing goes for
using anything that relates to cryptography for example.
In some context it's sensitive, in some it's not.
So this is what security hotspots are for.
Coming back to my pull request,
there is something that is missing right now which is coverage information.
So as I said, right now the only thing that happened is that
Summer Cloud read the data from this GitHub repository and analyzed the code.
And this is static analysis, so there is no code execution at all, or
at least not the user code.
And so it cannot compute things like code coverage information.
And for that, actually what you need to do is to compute it yourself and
to provide it to the Summer Cloud scan.
And this can currently only be done if the Summer Cloud scan happens as part of
a CI workflow.
And so for that we need to enable a CI based analysis.
So this is what I will do now.
And for that I need to go to administration and
I need to go to analysis methods.
And I will need to change my analysis method.
So right now we've been using automatic analysis,
which is enabled by default, I need to disable this.
And what I will do is I will follow the tutorial for
GitHub actions because I have a GitHub action already set up, so it's easier.
You can use other CI if you want, of course.
But I will follow the tutorial for a GitHub action.
I need to create a secret to authenticate to Summer Cloud.
So I need to do that in my GitHub repository.
So I will follow this link here.
And I will need to copy and paste those two values.
So I'll already copy this one.
So I need to go, so I'm in the secrets of my repository.
I create a new repository secret.
I am pasting the name of the variable.
Copy pasting the value here.
And I'm adding my secret.
So, oops.
Back to Summer Cloud.
Now what I need to do is to change my build file to integrate the Summer Cloud scan.
So there are easy way to do it if you're using a build system like Maven, Gradle,
etc.
Here for Python, we're not using a specific build system.
So I go with the generic tutorial.
And what I will have to do is to integrate the Summer Cloud scan to my GitHub workflow.
So this is basically this part here.
I've already prepared the changes in a pull request that can be used.
So I will not actually do it.
But this is basically what I need to do to integrate this Summer Cloud scan.
The other thing I need to do to enable the CI-based analysis is to create a Sonar project
properties file that will contain the properties for the analysis for the code.
Since now it happens in the CI, the properties needs to be defined there as well.
On automatic analysis, you can do it in the web UI instead.
And I will need to copy those informations.
They're not in my pull request yet, so I will already copy this.
And now I will go back to my repository to make those changes.
So for that, I will go back to pull requests again.
And here I will cut a few corners because, of course, it would be annoying otherwise.
So we'll create a new pull request, again targeting my FORT repository.
And I will target my add feature branch so that I change the workflow for my add feature
branch.
And I see the result of this.
Of course, if you want to do it cleanly, you probably want to change the main and then
rebase.
But I will cut a few corners.
So I have my enable CI analysis that I'm looking to.
And let's see the changes that this brings.
So what I'm doing is I'm creating a new coverage RC file.
So that's a configuration for my code coverage tool where I give the source of the code is.
I enable branch coverage as well.
And I set the relative files flag to true to avoid any mismatch in the file path with
SonarCloud.
And I'm changing a bit my GitHub action here.
So now I'm not running just simply PyTest.
I'm running PyTest.gov to compute the coverage information for which I create an XML report.
And I use the configuration that is already defined here.
And I add this SonarCloud scan after I've computed the coverage.
The secret, the GitHub token will be provided automatically.
The Sonar token is the one we've created just now.
And here I have my project properties that are here with the placeholders.
If you want to do this yourself, you need to replace this with your project key and
organization key.
I pasted mine.
I copied mine already.
So I will change it here.
So I create my pull requests.
And I will change it directly from the GitHub UI to make things a bit simpler.
So I will just edit this and paste my project information.
I can commit this directly and merge this pull request so that my changes are taken
into account.
All right.
So now let me see if you see a bit a small recap of what I did.
So I went to administration, analysis method, disabled automatic analysis, created my secret
in my GitHub repository.
Here we don't see the images again, but I created the coverage RC file, updated the
GitHub action, and created the project properties file.
And I actually merged the enable CI analysis branch from this.
What I can see, so the CI is, of course, running.
One thing I can see also that I did not mention is that SoundCloud will also provide a small
summary of the issues it found in the pull request itself so that when you open a pull
You don't have to go to the web UI.
If you don't have issues, you can go directly to the pull request, see the comment and see
the issues that you have so that it can be a bit quicker.
So this should be running.
This is still running.
It should not take so long.
But now we can see that the SoundCloud scan is part of my CI before it was really done
by SoundCloud on its server.
Now it's really part of the CI and we really have a bit more control on the analysis.
So right now what I'm doing is importing code coverage information.
You can import other things like MyPy reports, FlakeH reports, any other linter information
that will also be able to import.
So if I go back here, so I don't need this anymore, I can go to my pull requests again.
Now I see the coverage information that has been computed.
What SoundCloud did here is not just take the coverage information and put it here,
it actually recomputes it respective to the new code that you wrote.
So all the issues that we see here are issues on the new code.
And similarly, the value of the coverage that we see here is the coverage on the new code
that has been added.
So the overall code coverage is estimated here to be 74%, but we see that the coverage
on the new code is lower.
So that you can really have quite a high threshold on your code coverage thanks to this, because
it will not impact the old existing code.
So that can help as well if you have a project with very low coverage and you want to get
higher coverage but you don't want to spend six months writing tests for it.
Again, we can see some details here.
If you follow the links, you can see all the information that you would see in a coverage
tool.
So you see the covered code, what is the new code.
You also see coverage on the old code if you're interested in that.
And because we have enabled brand coverage, we see what is not covered.
So we see here we have quite a few issues, but it's not covered by tests.
So we could have expected that and written some tests.
So this is all that we can see on the Summer Cloud UI.
Now the question is, of course, can we fix those issues a bit faster?
Some of those issues are quite simple, actually.
We shouldn't probably commit code with them.
And this is where Summer Lint comes into place, because the analysis that Summer Cloud performs
can also be performed in Summer Lint.
You don't get all the issues, like the vulnerabilities that are found will not be found in Summer
Lint because they're more complex and require a full analysis to be found.
But most issues that can be found can also be found directly in the IDE.
So I already prepared my project, or at least a copy of this project, to show how this would
work.
So here I'm on the main branch, actually.
And I can go to Plugins and install Summer Lint.
In this case, I already installed it, so I will just enable it.
But of course, we can install it.
I need to restart my IDE.
I'm doing this with PyCharm.
Of course, it's basically exactly the same thing in VS Code.
And here what I see is that I have this new panel that is from Summer Lint with a recap
of the issues that are found in my file.
For the issues, I have the description that is available as well, similar to what you
can find in Summer Cloud.
So you have the description as well if you want more explanation on the issues.
Of course, the issues are highlighted.
And for some issues, you can also, like in IDEs, have quickfix that are offered.
So in this case, we have an exception that is created, but it's not raised.
I can trigger a quickfix to just raise it.
So this is one of the things that you can do.
So yeah.
Now let's pretend for a second here I have a pass statement that is flagged as unneeded,
of course.
Let's pretend for a second that I don't actually want to have an issue here.
Maybe you like this pass statement for whatever reason and you just want to silence an issue,
basically.
There are several ways to do that.
One of them is to add a small pragma comment, which is no sonar.
It will disable inspection for that line and you will not see the issue.
So this is one option.
I don't like pragma comments so much myself, so maybe you don't as well.
Maybe it's not a very good solution for you to have all those pragma comments in the issues
that you don't want to see.
Another option would be, of course, to disable the rule directly into sonar lint.
But then if you're synchronizing with other people working on the same project, you don't
want to have to do this manually.
And this is where we have something that is called connected mode between sonar lint and
sonar cloud, where you can synchronize issues and quality profiles and issue status between
sonar cloud and sonar lint.
It also has the added benefit that for some issues that cannot be found in sonar lint,
you can still display them in a limited way.
This is still rather new, but it's something that we've been working on so that you can
still see vulnerabilities in the IDE.
And for that, let me go to my other projects that I prepared.
And let's pretend I want to silence my past statements here.
So I go to my maintainability issues.
I go to the issue I want.
And I will flag it as won't fix.
I'm asked for a comment to why I won't fix this issue.
I can put whatever here.
Now my issue is silenced from this setup.
And now what I can do is connect my sonar lint to my sonar cloud.
I can do that by going through this toolbox here and select bind project to sonar cube
or sonar cloud.
And here I will be asked to configure a connection, which I will do.
I will add a new connection.
I will call it workshop.
And I'm asked for a token again to authenticate with sonar cloud.
So I can just follow this to create one.
I will create my token here.
I will copy it.
I will paste it.
And now I'm authenticated with sonar cloud.
I will select my organization.
In this case, it's not on my personal organization.
So I select the one that is relevant.
And now the connection should be good to go.
So I can select it.
I need to also choose the project on which I'm synchronizing.
So I select the project.
And here what it will do also is synchronize the analyzer version between the two, between
sonar lint and sonar cloud, because they might not be the same analyzers running.
And now I see that this pass statement is not flagged anymore.
It's still here.
I think I need to just reload the...
Okay.
Here I see that it's completely disappeared.
So my pass statement that I wanted to keep, I get to keep it.
And this is how you can silence issues that you don't want or synchronize the rules that
are enabled to have a consistent experience between your IDE workflow and your code review
process.
All right.
So this is all that I wanted to share today.
So a few words to conclude.
So today I presented this clean as you could approach that I believe will help to clean
legacy project in a systematic way with no upfront investment and no compromise on quality
standards so that you can really have high quality standards on your project.
And I think this principle holds even outside of what we do at sonar and what our products
are doing.
So I think it's a very important mindset in my opinion.
And then I showed sonar cloud how you can implement this clean as you could methodology
using sonar tools.
With sonar cloud as a central place to monitor the health of your code base, automatic analysis,
CI based analysis so you can have a better, more complete analysis.
And finally, we've seen also how to set up sonar lines.
So that's all for me.
And I'm open to questions if you have any.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Yes.
You guys ever thought about like with that coverage report they called that which line
in the new code using like an AI to test it?
No, by the way, I think there's a microphone is it meant for the questions so that they're
recorded?
Can I ask you to repeat the question?
the question there so that it's a...
All right. Is this working? Okay. So my question is with like a coverage report like that that
has the specific lines, you know, maybe they're called out for branch coverage or maybe it's
just line coverage. Now we have an AI that will suggest a test case for us and write
some code, you know, maybe it will be wrong, but you could feed that to some type of prompt
and just get suggested tests. Have you guys thought about doing that?
That's a great idea. To be honest, I don't think we have considered that idea. So in
fact, code coverage is at the border of what we do because we don't compute the coverage
ourselves. It's computed by external tools and we import it. Now it's true that there's...
There must be a way we can do that. For now, with what relates to AI and machine learning,
what we're looking at the most is how to filter out false positives and issues for
rules that depends on heuristics a bit more. We're not into generating code ourselves.
So this is not something we plan to do. Any other question? Yeah.
Just a short question. You demonstrated a little bit earlier silencing some of the issues
that Sonar Cloud detected on a particular PR. So if you have like a very high traffic
area of your code, is there an easy way to silence that like for all future PRs in that
same area or is it a per PR thing? So it is per PR that you will silence the
issues. Okay. I'm not sure I understood properly the question. I will answer and you will let
me know if I understood well. So what happens when you silence an issue in a pull request
and it gets merged? That issue is actually still existing for Sonar Cloud. So it's still recorded
as a silenced issue so that it will not be raised on a second pull request that triggers
the same rule again. That was my question. Thank you. I want to build on that question.
So typically when we run static analysis on big code bases like legacy code bases,
we'll get like hundreds or thousands of issues. Like how do we prioritize? Because when you see
just thousands of issues, like developers just throw the ball, whatever, and we just silence the tool.
Yeah, exactly. So this is the core of the idea behind this clean ASU code is that the number
of issues you should see should be proportional to the size of your pull request because the issues
that you will see are only the issues on code that is modified by the pull request. So if you
have a legacy project with thousands of issues and you create a small pull request on it,
you will only see the issues for that small pull request and you will not see the thousands
of issues. It will still be there. It will be still on your main code dashboard. And
if you want to look for things like vulnerabilities or things that are really critical, you really
want to find, you can do that. But on a daily basis, what we say is that you should not
focus on that. You should focus on the new code and on making sure the new code is clean.
Thank you. You're welcome.
For private repositories, what kind of data does Sonar Cloud keep during the analysis and after
the analysis in the paid tier?
Okay. So I'm not the best person to answer that question with precision, to be honest,
because I'm developing the analyzer. I'm not in the data team. I know that one of the data that
we can, if asked, look at is when your flag issues are false positives so that they can be
investigated. But even that is not available to developers most of the time. So as for the data
that is actually collected, I'm sorry that I don't have a precise answer. If you want to know a bit
more, maybe you should reach out to the better people to answer this. If you are concerned about
this, this is what SonarCube is also about, because SonarCube is free and open source. And even
with paid versions, it's on premise, so we have access to zero information.
Okay. Thank you very much.
All right. If there's no other questions, thank you very much. And one thing I did not mention is
that we are sponsoring the event, so we will have a booth in the expo later today and in the next
few days. So if you want to know more, feel free to drop by, and we'll be happy to help you there.
Thank you.