And I think that's a very important point.
I think that's a very important point.
In the last few, the ages 70s and 70s into the last few years,
the kids were mostly  Cynthia Mr.
The kids were mostly ach Cynthia Mr.
Because of some of the things that come out in the kids
It was the age cut that they picked up that.
So the spring of 2010
was actually the moment of change of culture forcue.
It was the moment of change of culture forcue.
It was the slower matters of culture forcue.
the Prime Minister and he is wonderful.
Of course, interesting in a way.
De moment, he says so obviously,
but he is a great and very special person.
it is also not one of us to face this danger that feels like workplace despair.
In our field we do not raise chili to  troop.
Put it this way, lately the effects of that disease have spread
all over the place.
And we have to go deep and look for answers.
I'm not a fool.