Okay, we're going to go ahead and get started with our first talk of the afternoon block,
Getting Around the Guild, Paralyzing Python for Better Performance with Ali Faridzadeh.
Thanks, guys. Hi, everyone. Thank you for being here today. My name is Ali, and I am the Director
of Solution Engineering and Platform at Bluebelt AI, the high-performance computing platform for
Python and SQL. A little bit about me. I live in Houston, Texas, in my right-hand
computer room. I started coding about 20 years ago, same time as PyCon's first. Then 10 years
ago, I wrote my first team fellow world with Python, and today I'm presenting at a 20th
Python conference coincidentally right on my birthday. So thank you. So I want to take a
selfie with you all. I'm not supposed to be taking my birthday with you. So if you don't mind.
So I have to get the lights out somehow, but anyway. One, two, three. Thank you. Okay. So
here, I'm going to take all of this. I'm going to take this picture. This about me is in
the next thing in this two-hour flow of career, journey and education and et cetera. Today I'm
going to talk about various ways to get around the GIL, the global interpreter lock, which
prevents Python from running on multiple CPUs, as you know. It is okay to take pictures if you
like in the slide. You have a lot of the special stuff that I do, like jumping to the
verizenda. I will talk a little bit about what is the GIL, a little bit deep. And then solutions
to get around the GIL. Some examples. I get some questions. If not, I'm going to stay around
for more questions. So there have been a couple of sessions about the GIL in this conference.
So by now you probably know about the global interpreter lock. And it is a mechanism using
C-Python implementation of Python Texture that only one thread can execute Python bytecode at
a time. This means that even in a multi-predic application, only one thread can execute Python
code at any given moment. But it would likely take advantage of all CPUs in our machines, right?
To accelerate the execution, I would use a compute class. So let's talk about the real world
use case. For a small data unit, not a lot. Because here I need to text maybe less than a minute
to finish the job. But for larger data, which is not the case in enterprises and even
mid-sized, small-sized companies, it's my character that I like. So let's talk about one use case.
Let's say you have an application. It requires 500 TB RAM. You will take an R524H storage in the
memory optimization between a Samsung and AWS for about $6 per hour. It provides you with
760 TB RAM and it also gives you 48 physical cores or CPUs. Let's say this job takes about one hour
on Python to run. And the frequency of the job is just one time per day. If you do the math,
this job alone is about $1. And the frequency of the job is just one time per day.
The frequency of the job is just one time per day. If you do the math, this job alone will cost you
around $200 per year. And normally in companies, there is not just one job, there are thousands of jobs
running. So that's why companies are spending millions of dollars on just AWS. AWS is happy,
but maybe not your CFO. Is there any CFO in this room? Anyone in charge of finances in this room?
Okay, I'm glad. So yeah, I'm not too happy with this waste of money. But really, it would be nice
if you can reduce the cost to just $45 per month. I'm taking advantage of all the 48 CPUs that
this instance gives you. Of course it would be nice. So let's get a little bit deeper. Why this
happens actually? Why this happens in Python? In order to understand why Python behaves this way,
we need to understand how Python manages its memory. It's all about memory. Obviously whenever you
create a variable in Python, Python needs to create it in the computer's memory. As with all
memory-managed languages, Python needs to know when the variable is not needed anymore so it can
remove it from the memory. Python achieves this by a method called reference counting. What is it?
Basically for every variable that Python stores in memory, it also stores a tally of how many
objects are referencing that variable. As long as the reference count for any variable is greater
than zero, fine, Python will keep that variable around. When that number hits zero, that means no more
objects need that variable. The garbage collector removes the object from memory automatically.
That's why people say you may not need to explicitly call for library PC to call the collector because
Python does it for you anyway. Let's see what happens if threads could modify the reference count
simultaneously at the same exact moment. Suppose we have two threads, two Python threads running, thread
one and thread two. If both reference the variable v, the variable v could be a large data frame.
The reference count for v would be then two because both threads are referencing that, the reference
count will be two. Then of course both threads simultaneously remove their reference to v. Well, have you
just guessed it right? At the time they both remove their variable, this reference count is two, right?
If each thread reads the reference count simultaneously, each thread would get an initial
reference count of two for variable v. Each thread would then increment the reference count value of
two for one. The final reference count would be then one. Unfortunately the actual reference counts
would be zero since both threads remove their reference to v. Now imagine hundreds of variables
are staying in the memory and soon he will run out of memory. Imagine you have multiple threads on the
same time. A lot of variables. Okay, so in order to remedy this problem, you could make sure that both
thread one and thread two cannot modify the reference count simultaneously. That means we achieve this
by locking the reference count such that thread two waits while thread one reads and increment the
reference count and only then we allow thread two to increment the reference count in turn. This
implementation was actually tried out in Python in the early days. However, locking the reference
count for every increment or fiximent for every object over every thread supposed to be
extremely slow. The fastest solution is to just lock the entire Python interface and let's only
one thread run on the interface at any given time. Hence the global interface lock. The deal is
definitely faster than any visual reference count lock but it only allows a single thread to execute.
There hasn't been a lot of work actually to improve the way in which Python is scheduled threads and
there is a definite improvement in Python 3 over Python 2 in that regard. I'm already talking about
how we can actually get around all the included deal that has been in Python 3.12. However, two
parallels on the approach has not yet been achieved completely. That can only happen by removing the
deal altogether. It may take a few more years to see that deal be completely removed but there are
ultimately back-outlets. The only way to do that is to have a single thread run on the interface.
It may take a few more years to see that deal be completely removed but there are ultimately back-outlets
to improve the performance of Python applications. This really needs a big amount of explore.
Before getting to available tools we need to understand the differences between concurrency and parallelism
because there is a lot of confusion in the computer science literature about that.
Concurrency is about multiple tasks which start, run and complete in overlapping time periods in no specific order.
Parallelism is about multiple tasks or sub-tasks of the same task that literally run at the same time on a hardware
with multiple compute resources like multi-core processors. Imagine that, next to 10, one step on the left
is stopping the salad while occasionally stirring the soup on the stove. He has to stop chopping,
shake the stove top and then stop chopping again and repeat this process until everything is done.
As you can see we only have one processing resource here, the chef, and his concurrency is mostly related to
logistics. Without concurrency the chef has to wait until the soup is on the stove and then stop chopping.
So, the chef is focused on the stove's grid and he starts chopping the salad.
Let's see now on the right side we have two chefs, one who can do the stirring and one who can chop the salad.
We have divided the work by adding another processing resource in other steps. Parallelism is literally
the simultaneous physical execution of tasks at the runtime and it requires hardware with multiple computation resources.
This is the hardware layer. As Rob Pike said in 2013, concurrency is about dealing with lots of things at once.
Parallelism is about doing lots of things at once. In a single course of computer you can have concurrency
but no parallelism, but both go beyond the traditional sequential model in which things happen one at a time.
So, there is a key difference between all task-based or some people call it scheduled-based engines versus two parallel engines.
So, let's map our kitchen async and cook example to reality.
So, this is how the scheduled or task-based computation engine life affects this work to look like.
There is a driver, some people call it leader, master driver, master node, who is scheduled and monitors the task.
And the computer node who executes the task.
The computers often need to wait for the next task to come causing some overhead and lots of computer resources
due to being idle. But at least there is some parallelism here. You see some many cores are working at the same time.
They are not at their full capacity. There is some idle time, but still there is some parallelism.
That's why some people call it partially parallel architecture.
On the other hand, in a two-part execution, you expect the cores to know their task end-to-end
and this causes running down without major delays resulting in a faster performance.
Basically, you get more bandwidth for your books. Is it bad?
Definitely, it's good. You'll like it. You'll like it if you're running at 100% because you're paying for it.
So, in a picture, on the left you see there is a driver node which coordinates tasks and assigns them to the computer node.
There is also communicated to the driver node. The users wait for the next task.
But on the right side, all the nodes are worker nodes. They are not tracing one node just for a scheduling task.
No, get that node for work.
So, all of them on the right side are imaginary colleges that are basically making all the work for nodes.
And all the nodes know what to do from the beginning to the end because there is some compilation process at the beginning.
So, there are a handful of libraries trying to help us achieve parallelism in PyCon.
I would classify existing libraries into two categories. Those which are what I'm calling partially parallel versus truly parallel.
Most existing data analytics libraries are based on the principle of distributing the data and parallelizing tasks to get performance benefits.
Parallelization is a very difficult problem to solve in general, but it can be done quite effectively for data analytics.
True parallelism is achieved when there is no driver-accessible bottleneck.
As I showed in the couple of slides earlier, the partially parallel libraries can be further explained through building Python libraries and executing task-based computation engines.
So, here on the left, we have a grading, which is good for IO data tests, multiprocessing, mainly for security data tests,
subprocessing, which we saw a few sessions about in this conference. They all run on a single machine typically.
In the middle, we have PySpark, GAS, Ray, Modin, and Unidisk, which can run on a cluster of nodes.
And Numba, which basically runs on a single node for now. And on the right, we have Bodo and MPI for Py.
Among these, Bodo and Numba also use just-in-time compilers.
One way to speed up Python in general is to compile it to native code.
Most general-purpose compilers use by converting between native sequential code.
However, for data analysis domain, Bodo has built an auto-parallelizing, we call it inferential, compiler.
It can detect data types from the data source automatically, compile the program, and then generate a truly parallel implementation, which uses NTI, and can be deployed on any slice cluster so that
the way we get around any slice cluster. So the way we really get around the deal is by not trying to get around the deal at all.
Instead, we run multiple Python processes, each with their own deal, in a truly parallel SPMD fashion.
SPMD means we are saying that program multiple data fashion.
So, I was looking for a company that landed with all these libraries, how they compare with each other.
I pulled this from the blog, and added Bodo based on some feedback from our customers.
But I wouldn't rely on this kind of parts a lot, because many of them are subjective.
For example, ease of adoption, what do they mean exactly by ease of adoption?
But the other one, like scalability, it's really easy to reference the background, like 1 terabyte of data, 100 graphics, etc.
Which is very 1 terabyte. And Bodo has been more than 10 terabytes of data.
So I wouldn't spend much time on this kind of comparison, because to be honest, each one of these libraries is used for one purpose.
And you have to find a purpose. I will talk about that in a second.
So, let's talk about a few examples. So, with multi-processing.
Now I'm going to talk about some data, simple data technologies, data transformation.
A group by an aggregation, like grouping by a column, and then doing a sum.
I don't expect you to read this because it's super small, but if you use multi-processing library for a group by,
you need to get the keys and data frames and append them to a list of data frames via a for loop.
And then apply the function locally on each process using a tool of math.
And then finally you concatenate all of these small data frames in your list and make it the original data frame.
So, if you want to use NPI for Pi library, you need to do a little bit more than that.
It's about 50 mb of code to do a simple group by dot sum, which is a one line in pandas.
But if you use this library to initialize NPI, load data on root process,
discrete data among processes, apply the group by function locally on each process,
gather the output from all processes, concatenate all local data to get the final output.
So, yeah, it's a lot of just word group by operation.
And imagine you have a simple application of a data frame of 3,000 mb of code to 5,000 mb of code.
So, it won't be for every single one like data to be hard.
Not just group by, you have other operations like merge and filtering and all of that.
So, there are simpler alternatives we can do to parallelize your code,
as long as you're working with simple data transformation like pandas operations,
with photo, modeling and that.
As you see, with all these libraries, you just need to write about 10 lines of code.
This is basically one line for group by.
There is no difference between pandas and these libraries.
Not much difference.
Bordel is just the same, but you have to add a GIF compiler,
a decorator on top of your function.
It's not even unique to just call a modim.pandas.
And Dask has its own data frame.
The data frame is called Dask's data frame.
We call it as dd, and then just call that.
Then you're reading the package files.
So, using this library is a bit easier to scale your code for thousands of data frame operations.
It's easier to maintain when your code is smaller.
And it saves a lot of engineering time for code review and all of that when you stop into your PR.
Save on cloud cost, compute resources, because you parallelize your code through these libraries.
And you can scale with large data simply from your java.local frame,
which is like a simple data engine,
at most 100-millibit of data you're working with,
you just java.local and repeat.
And then once you want to put it through production,
yeah, it's a simple migration.
So, now you may wonder, okay, which one is better?
Ali, you talked to me about a bunch of libraries,
and how can I know which one is best for me to use?
This question typically drives us into checking some benchmarks.
But, to be honest, let's not get into the benchmark game.
In fact, every vendor uses benchmarks to show that the product is better than others.
For example, while modern claims to outperform Pandas on DAS,
others, like in the middle, I read in an independent blog about that,
and in the middle you see a picture that they showed,
actually modern performance makes it fairer,
in fact, larger data, and they just use two different ways of data for that data operation.
So, and also there's another blog that compers all of these things,
Bodo, Array, Pyres, Spark, DAS, and a workflow that is derived from TPCA on AWS.
But again, you know, like some of these libraries are fit for compute-heavy operations,
some are not fair-backed, some are beyond the IO-heavy,
so you really need to try out yourself.
Don't rely on some benchmarks and don't just go with this.
I was like back in 2018, I was using multi-processing libraries,
and I saw that even for my operation, even in this lower-down,
higher-down itself, I'm sorry, the lower-down, Pandas itself,
so I wondered why even I should use it, it's just a bit busy.
So, I used it, Pandas had a large node on AWS,
and no one cared that much about cost of the time, so I just let it run.
I didn't use all of the CPUs, but yeah, I didn't know about all these libraries at the time.
So, what are the steps for boosting your performance?
First, you need to profile your application, meaning timing, timing for a function.
It's very basic, that is wrong for a long time.
Identify where the button next is, assuming there is no for loop,
you are using vectorization, there is no group by apply,
which is typically a various operation in Pandas,
and you have found other work-trounds for that, so no option exists.
And then, okay, save every input into that function,
and package some of these packages, good formats, compressed, columnar,
it's easy to read with Pandas, and then work exclusively on that function.
You need one of the libraries that I've shown before,
I'm going to show you in the next slide,
the base on-front-force-decast, it's kind of a rule of thumb,
and it's not vital, but it helps us navigate to which library we want to run.
So, let me get into this decision tree.
So, as I mentioned earlier, if your gameplay is very small,
you may not care a lot, you know, it's running fine, no one is picking on me for this.
So, if your gameplay is small, so what's the problem?
Why are you even thinking about optimizing?
You're not missing your SLAs, you're still like a mess,
unless then you have to run it for one minute and it's run for two minutes.
If yes, you're missing your SLAs, then life is good,
but if you're not missing your SLAs, you know what, to be honest,
many of these libraries are not really good, then you're dealing with very small run times,
like 10 seconds, 5 seconds, because you have your own other,
some have to compile and it does not.
But if you're not missing your SLAs, you can use other approaches,
like divide and conquer.
You divide your data from a category that is independent,
like a field that is independent, which can be stored with no dependencies,
so then run multiple jobs at the same time, so that would definitely reduce your SLA.
What is your thing when data is big?
Then I would ask you, what do you mean by big?
Does it fit on a single machine or not?
You're dealing with a huge cluster.
If it fits on a single node, then what is it that you want to achieve?
Do you want to reduce your costs and SLA?
No, you don't even care about your SLAs or costs,
so then, as is, there's no problem, just make sure your node has enough memory,
so it doesn't run out of memory,
because every reach your data from your data warehouse is going to grow,
it's not going to reduce, so after maybe one year,
or maybe even six months, your application may not work,
just make sure that you're watching for memory utilization.
But if you want to reduce the cost, maybe you want to store it your SLAs,
or get the RAIDs, and then, yeah, so let's talk.
Then you have to decide if it is a single data frame operation,
because many of these things I haven't told you are designed for data analytics
and data frame operation.
If no, it is not data frame operation,
I'm just basically having a problem on training my machine learning model,
for example.
Data frame operation is fine, if you don't get to the machine learning frame,
then it's going to take a long time.
Then you can try using RAID.
But if you're using NumPy, then you would try Numba,
because this has a trust and time compiler,
it's going to run in parallel, so for a NumPy operation, Numba is great.
But if you are doing Pondos operations, right,
then you have multiple pressures on a single machine,
you can use Bodo, Python, multi-tasking,
just be careful with that, as I told you,
that scan model, because if it is IO heavy,
multi-tasking may not be able to help you,
you have to use training instead.
Then let's talk about the real deal,
which is, no, my data really did equal the fitness in general,
I needed cluster to run it.
Then you have to ask yourself,
do you have the budget for the engineering bandwidth
to convert your code to one of these mature libraries like PySpark?
Then you say, yeah, we have three months allocated
by the engineering budget approved by our director of engineering
to convert the code from Python to PySpark,
then yes, we can go to this line,
it says, yes, I have time,
then again, are you using data-friendly operations?
Yes, then okay, convert it to PySpark or Dask.
That's good.
If no, again, machine learning is tough,
some kind of other, maybe Python,
or other stuff that you're doing not much in,
your bottleneck is not in data-friendly operations,
then consider Ray or PySpark.
And then if you don't have time,
or you don't have your budget to convert your code,
and you want your condos put as is to run,
just putting some gist decoration on top of your function
with a little bit of manipulation on data type stability,
then you can try Bodo or Modem.
Modem is really a laughter around Dask, Ray,
it's just kind of a condos, we use a condos API.
And Bodo is just in kind of a compiler using an API.
So let me get you to a simple example.
The rule of live demos is that in all of the live demos,
there is an AI agent sitting there to make sure it doesn't work.
So let me see if it's a sleeping or not a sleeping.
So yeah, this is a multi-color simulation,
and I'm going to try Bodo with this one,
so I already spun up my cluster,
and let's try without Bodo, it's just simple Python operation.
It's calculating the pipe, the 2.14.
I put 100 million data points for this estimation,
so it ran about 2.85 seconds.
If I run the same thing, and I just add this chip,
plus sometimes I put it on top of it,
and I run it the same,
it took about 0.13, so 0.13 runs to 2.8,
I have an 8 core, so if you do the math,
2.85 divided by 8, it should take about 0.35.
But why is running even faster than 0.35?
It's because when it does a compiler,
then it does some optimization on how to run this code
versus how Python runs it,
and even if I had run it in one single node with this compiler,
it would speed it almost faster than 2.8 seconds,
it may run it one second.
So that lets me to actually run this even much larger data,
lets me increase the data by 100 times on my machine.
Here's a simple example, think of about this,
it probably might raise from 100 megabytes to 1 kilobyte of data,
and if I run this,
so 100 times larger data will take around,
if Python will take around 200 seconds,
it took about 14 seconds.
So you see with the parallelism,
oh, one thing I forgot to show you,
and I want to show you the CPUs, that's the front part.
I had this 100 for the H-talk to be able to have some time
showing me the responses on the CPUs.
You see, the CPUs are 8 of them,
are working almost at 100% capacity,
running this and knocking in the parallel fashion,
when it comes to the real two parallel fashion.
So they are working very hard,
and yet, when I'm still done,
they go back to normal life.
So thank you so much, my name is Ali,
and I'm glad to be here with you,
so I can take some questions. Thank you so much.
Okay, we have about two minutes for questions.
If anyone wants to step up in the center and ask a question,
if not, you can catch Ali outside,
and he'll happily answer all of your questions
until it reaches 10 o'clock.
Okay, thanks, everyone.
We said there's no questions?
Oh, yeah.
Okay, we're just going to have it?
There's no question?
Yes.
Just one question.
What about PyPort, another machine that I use a lot?
Yes.
PyPort and TensorFlowflow and all of these libraries
are very particular for GPU systems.
A lot are discussed today, they're mostly on CPU systems,
except Numba that's had on on CPUs as well.
But at this point,
we're not really talking about the CPUs,
we're talking about the CPUs,
but at this point, for example,
Bodo does not support PyPort or TensorFlowflow.
It's a very small support you have for TensorFlowflow,
but not for PyPort or Chalk this moment.
I have also a question.
You mentioned data frames.
Did you mean Tomlats data frames here?
Yes.
Yes, okay.
Yep.
And what makes them so special compared to, for example,
Nampa array?
So in data science field,
you usually have tables that have column headers
and indexes and all of that.
In Nampa, you don't have the column headers,
so it's easier to communicate with the business person
of the company through like for the data,
like this is my price, this is my task,
how much I pay for this, and all of these have a name.
So for that reason, like that's one of the reasons.
But the really kind of thing is built on top of Nampa,
the same thing, added an index thing
and the column headers on top.
So it's the same.
Bodo also suffers Nampa, same way.
Okay, that was all the time we have for this.
If you have any more questions for Ali,
catch them out in the hallway.
You have 15 minutes before the next talk,
the second to last one of the day.
And the next talk in this room will be supercharging pipeline efficiency
with demo performance prediction.