Thank you so much, Deb, and congratulations to all the award recipients.
For this next section, it's our final special guest who probably needs no introduction.
It's Guido van Rassen, the creator of Python, and who will be speaking about his retrospective
of Python, basically.
So please welcome on stage Guido.
I need a dongle.
Let me play with a mic to see if this works.
OK.
Oh my gosh, they gave me way more time than I needed.
That's OK.
Slideshow.
Yeah, I do this every day, as you see.
OK, I think.
Ha.
Sorry, folks.
Hello.
So there's been a slight change of topic.
At the very last moment, I decided that I'd much rather talk about what everybody would
much rather talk about, feeding CPython to chat GPT or large language models in general.
Can we actually use AI to make Python faster?
Actually, that might have been a cool talk, but I have nothing on that.
I'm just trying to give Mariada a heart attack.
Really sorry, Mariada.
Or maybe really sorry to everyone who believed that for a moment.
This is a PyCon retrospective, not a Python retrospective that would take weeks.
Actually, the way I'm envisioning this is a talk in the style of,
Grandpa, please tell us some stories from when you were young.
I'm a lot older than Carol Welling, and you could have figured out how old she is.
Usually, when confronted with a question like that, I tell stories like from the time before
Python had classes, or how we got along without decorators and descriptors, and things like
context managers.
But this is really about PyCon, because I was asked for memories about PyCon, and I
have a head full of memories that I want to share.
I did apply a little bit of scope creep, and I'll also talk about pre-PyCon conferences
and also about the PSF, its history, and sort of aspirational predecessors for the PSF.
This is all very personal.
The moral of the story is definitely going to be, if at first you don't succeed, try and try again,
because there were a few goof-ups.
So, earliest Python meetings, there were definitely Python meetings before we called them PyCon.
In particular, in 1994, we had the first Python workshop.
It was organized by Mike McLee in Maryland, and there were about 20 or 30 people.
It was a very small event, but it was a big success, at least we all had a little bit of a
big success, at least all 30 of us who attended thought it was a big success.
And we wanted to do more of that, and we quickly escalated from the Nth Python workshop to the Nth Plus First
International Python Conference.
I have more about that.
There were also early Python organizations long before the PSF.
Or at least, well, I don't know if there were actually Python organizations, there were attempts at organizing.
And this was separate from organizing events, because the event organization was in the end pretty successful
right from the start.
But the organization creation was a little bit challenging, and actually I have a story about how the PSF itself
almost suffocated in the cradle.
Oh, yeah.
This talk is not about the Python Secret Underground, because the Python Secret Underground does not exist.
Any rumors about its existence are false.
In fact, you never saw this slide, or I would have to kill you all.
Be warned.
So, yeah, the first Python workshop.
That was also the advent of, as far as I'm aware, the first Python T-shirt, and that is a long and venerable tradition.
The very first Python T-shirt, that's the logo on the front, there was something else on the back.
Made by Steve Majewski, who stayed with the community a really long time.
It's really cool that we still have those T-shirts.
So here is actually the program of that first Python workshop.
You don't have to read all that, look at the things highlighted in yellow, and notice the Monty Python references,
which we also decided to work into the documentation.
But if you Google this, you can just ask Bing for first Python workshop 1994.
It's very important to put the year in, otherwise you get lots of other Python workshops that were held last week.
But really count how many current language features were proposed during that workshop or discussed.
And that's quite a few.
I don't want to go into them because it would become a Python retrospective again.
But based on the success of that workshop, we wanted to do more workshops.
And in fact, we did, six months later we did another one, organized by Jim Fulton of the United Geological Survey.
And we did a very interesting workshop, which was a very interesting one.
And six months after that, he ran another one.
And then we realized every six months, what are we thinking? How can we keep up with this?
People can't get travel budget every six months to travel to a Python workshop because their managers have never even heard of Python.
So we came to our census and we went annual. And it turns out annual is stressful enough.
So these events were organized initially by single individuals.
And these were individuals who had some clout with their organization to host small events.
And really all you needed was a meeting room for maybe 50 people at most.
Because small events are easy to organize.
We went to the cafeteria or to a nearby restaurant for lunch.
And the only visible expense was to make coffee appear during the breaks.
And then we transitioned to international Python conferences.
So this was really the fourth Python workshop organized by Paul Dubois at Lawrence Livermore National Laboratories in Livermore, California.
Now imagine the security implications of by then maybe 100 computer programmers swarming around on the facilities that were also used for the United States government's most secret nuclear research.
I don't know that we would be welcome there in today's climate.
But somehow in 97 or so we were, 96, they did ask for a copy of my passport several months in advance because I'm not even a U.S. citizen.
And Paul actually introduced a bunch of innovations that are still with us.
Not only did he rename it from workshop to conference, he invented, well introduced pre-conference tutorials.
Which we still have.
He was the first to announce that there was a dedicated hotel for the conference.
Although it was not exactly on the premises.
And so we changed the name to International Python Conference.
But we kept the numbering because we thought it would be more impressive if it was the fourth international Python conference.
And there had probably been one or two international guests to previous Python workshops.
Oh, like me.
So anyway, I actually, I have very personal memory from that conference that I can't really explain.
I'll just name the title.
The memory is titled, can you sproing the bunny?
And you've got to sort of track me down in the hallways to explain that one.
So after that, now I'm going to take a brief sip for my drink.
After the fourth international Python workshop, we realized that organizing these conferences was really a lot of work.
And even very high caliber volunteer like Paul Dubois couldn't quite cut it.
So in 97, the organization moved to a small for-profit company, Fortek Seminars.
And they were actually a subsidiary of CNRI, which was a nonprofit research lab that was my employer at the time.
Fortek had some considerable experience organizing conferences because they organized the IETF meetings,
which are like gigantic meetings of the size of current PyCon, three times a year, I believe.
And they also ran the first few worldwide web conferences.
So we thought they knew what they were doing.
As a result, the prices for registration went up a bit.
The quality of the facilities also went up.
And sadly, as far as I know, Fortek never actually made a profit.
They were really hard to pin down on that, though.
So I'm not sure, but I don't think that they ever actually were successful.
So yay, PSF for being successful at making a little bit of money on these conferences.
The hotels did all right, of course.
So one of my best memories of any of the Fortek conferences was being snowed in in Washington, D.C.
We were at a hotel that no longer exists.
I think it was literally torn down.
It was the Key Bridge Marriott.
It had quite a bit of fame at the time.
And I lived pretty nearby.
So I actually tried to drive to the conference in the Marriott, and I was there.
I tried to drive to the conference in the morning, but the weather was kind of snowy and my car got stuck.
So it turns out I ran into a neighbor who said, oh, I'll give you a ride.
I work right next to the Key Bridge Marriott.
So he gave me a ride.
I arrived at the conference thinking that in the evening I'd catch a bus home or something.
Nah.
There was no way I could get back home.
And I was not prepared.
I had literally just sort of planned to drive there and drive back home.
I was offered this ride.
I had grabbed my bag and got on my neighbor's car.
So here I was snowed in for the next three days with no underwear.
Well, no fresh underwear.
Fortunately, it turns out hotel gift shops do sell a small amount of that stuff.
And of course, it was a Python conference, so there was not a shortage of T-shirts.
So anyway, going back a little bit, there were also attempts at creating a Python organization.
But while meetings flourished, the organizations mostly fumbled.
In 95, there was a group of people in Washington, D.C.,
quite a bit of overlap with the people attending or being involved in the organization of the first workshop,
who said, we want to create an official Python nonprofit.
And they had a name ready for it, the Python Software Association.
It's a pretty good name.
But that's as far as they got.
But the next thing they did was start a mailing list discussion about what exactly should be in the bylaws of the Python Software Association.
And that kind of topic just doesn't converge.
Fortunately, to help us out, my employer, which was itself a nonprofit, offered a way out.
They would sort of host whatever that means.
The Python Software activity was not an association because association implies independence,
and activity apparently implies nothing in particular, but it was still the PSA.
It would not be an independent organization.
And in the end, it was just a mailing list that charged $50 for membership.
And you'd think, who would pay $50 for membership of a mailing list?
Well, somehow a lot of people were looking for Python friends, and it was not as easy to find Python friends at the time.
So we had a lot of people.
I think we had 300 members or so at the high point of the Python Software activity.
And actually, when I was doing research for this talk, I even found that there were actually membership benefits besides being on the mailing list.
You got a registration discount to the fourth Python International Python Workshop.
That was the one at L&L.
So maybe that's why we got so many members, because they basically got their membership back in discount to the conference.
So another thing that we tried, somewhat more ambitiously, was a Python consortium.
And CNRI was familiar with the people who had started the World Wide Web Consortium and the X Windows Consortium, both of which, as far as I know, were run by MIT at the time.
And the idea was there would be members, which would be large corporations, who would pay a hefty sponsorship fine for a seat at the table.
And exactly what was being discussed at that table, or whether it was a dinner table or a dining philosopher's table, I don't know.
Presumably, the idea was that they would have a say in language design.
And that had worked for the X Windows Consortium and again for the World Wide Web.
So why would it not work for Python?
Who wouldn't want to pay for a say in Python's design?
Well, at the time, in around 1997 or so, Python was apparently unimportant enough that we couldn't get anyone to sign up as the first member of this consortium.
We got some nibbles from Hewlett-Packard.
They were trying to launch a big Python-based product, which was actually pretty amazing at the time.
But in the end, even that was not really enough to get the Python Consortium started.
And none of the other big names in software were at all interested.
So scratch that.
Now, I have a blank slide because I want to sort of protect the innocence.
But around 2000, I left CNRI and I did something unforgivable.
And I didn't realize at the time how unforgivable it was because I convinced like four coworkers to leave with me.
And we went in a startup adventure.
And the idea was that we wanted to do something that was a little bit more interesting.
We went in a startup adventure and the adventure was a terrible disaster and we had to be rescued by another startup.
But anyway, because of the way we left, it was kind of awkward to have CNRI in charge of any Python-related things like the Python software activity or the international Python conferences.
If you want to understand more about why we decided to left apart from dot com fever, look at the license file for CPython in our GitHub repo.
Anyway, what were we to do organization wise?
Fortunately, one of the active core devs at the time was Greg Stein, who came up with a brilliant tactic to avoid getting stuck in the bylaws quagmire again.
He happened to be a board member of the Apache Software Foundation and Apache had already solved all these problems.
They had working bylaws for an open source software organization foundation.
And so Greg's proposal was that we take the Apache Software Foundation's fish license, I mean bylaws, cross out Apache and write in Python in Crayon.
So that's what we decided to do and there really wasn't much more to it.
We did have a false start in 2000, but in 2001 we did actually get incorporated and by 2003 Python was, the PSF was feeling quite real.
We did have a bank account, we had a post office box, we even had a part-time admin I believe.
Oh, let me say a bit more about that false start.
We were all gung-ho about getting the PSF started in 2000 and yet if you look up the official paperwork on python.org, if you know how to do your Bing searches, you'll see that it was incorporated in 2001.
Well, the way I remember the story was there was like somewhere in 2000 was a conference, it must have been still one of the IPCs, and about 20 people got together who were the founding members of the PSF.
It was mostly early days core devs and there were a few small companies with big plans and big hearts.
But of course, a number of practical things had to be done like getting the legal paperwork filed, opening a bank account, setting up a PO box maybe even hiring a part-time admin and such.
But we were a bunch of computer pilots and we had to do everything in our power to make it work.
So fortunately, one of us was already a successful businessman.
He was not a core dev, he was one of these small companies with a big heart.
But he was already successful and he knew how to do stuff.
And so he volunteered to be a part-time admin and he was a part-time engineer.
And he was a part-time engineer at the time.
And then a year passed and at the next and final international Python conference in 2001, I think it was the last one, nothing had happened.
It turns out that if you're a really successful business person, you're not going to be able to do anything.
And so we had to do something.
But it was so, so nice to be dedicated,
or so kind, to get a job in the back of a bank account.
Fortunately, my new employers, Paul Everett, he is here, and Rob Pike of Zoab Corporation
offered the help of their corporate attorney to get it done, and it was done.
And we did do it using Apache bylaws with Python written in in Crayon.
So at last, okay, according to my notes, the last IPC was actually in 2002, so the chronology
is a bit murky, I think, because conferences are planned so far in advance, it was difficult
for Fortek to stop organizing Python conferences without losing even more money on commitments.
But what we were going to do for 2003, now O'Reilly, bless their hearts, offered us a
track at the open source conference, OSCON, but informally we still mostly thought of
that as the Pearl Conference.
So even though the Python community accepted a track at OSCON as sort of a consolation
prize for losing our own international Python conference, we weren't all that much into
it.
Also, I think OSCON is even more expensive than IPC ever was.
So the PSF having been freshly incorporated and by 2003 actually having been set up completely
and even having a little bit of money in that bank account, and this is an important part,
we got a stroke of luck.
I got a phone call.
Late 2002, I got a phone call from, guess what, a Pearl community organizer who had
a venue where he had planned to hold a Pearl community conference which for some reason
had to be canceled.
Maybe there was a glut of Pearl community conferences that year.
And so he asked if I was interested in using that venue and that particular week that he
had reserved it for a Python community conference.
And I said, sure.
I don't know where we came up with the name PyCon, but that was not an entirely sort of
random name.
I think many people probably could have come up with that name for the Python conference.
And really the rest is history and I don't even have that many more stories to tell except,
oh yeah.
One thing because the venue came through me and I was I think the president of the PSF
at the time and I sort of was an important connection point and so I ended up being the
main organizer.
So I had to negotiate with the venue over money and catering and so here's the refrain.
Being a computer programmer, I had no skills in this area.
And so for one example, I ended up ordering exactly the same menu of sandwiches for three
days in a row.
And I'm sure it was the cheapest option three days in a row because I was terrified finally
seeing the prices they charge for sandwiches.
And I think the larger the conference, the larger the higher the price per sandwich.
Anyway, there were complaints and I turned that into my advantage.
I decided to delegate and the next year someone else was handling the catering and the negotiations.
And we had a total of three fantastic conferences at George Washington University.
After that I think we grew too much and we sort of wouldn't fit and we looked for different venues.
So conference registration is also incredibly stressful.
So this was our first conference.
So for that first Python workshop, I personally sent emails to everyone I wanted to show up
there and they all said yes, I'll be there.
So that was easy.
For PyCon 1, we advertised on Python.org and on the mailing list and we had a little bit
of registration automation and then we were looking at registrations trickle in.
And you said like a month before the conference or so there's an early birth registration
deadline and a few days before the deadline we had a few dozen registrations.
And this caused considerable stress because we already had pretty much committed to paying
for all those sandwiches.
So then fortunately it turns out that procrastination is universal human nature and on the afternoon
of the final day that you could register at the early birth rate, hundreds, well at least
a hundred registrations came in and everything was fine.
And then again like one or two days before the final deadline of the conference, like
one or two days before the actual conference, we got a lot more registrations from people
who didn't care about the early birth discount but who also were procrastinating on whether
they would actually come or not.
Anyway, this seems to be universal.
But we were saved and it was a big success.
So fast forward to what happened in 2008.
You might remember that in 2008 the world and PyCon were hit by the financial crisis.
This was pretty stressful.
People were worried about their jobs.
People lost their jobs.
Big name software conferences were being canceled left and right.
We didn't know what to do.
Shall we still have the conference and hope that enough people show up or shall we cancel
it and forfeit a huge deposit to the hotels.
In the end we decided to do it because otherwise we'd be definitely in the hole for a huge
amount of money, probably several times the cost of the first PyCon by then.
So we stuck with it.
We did run at a loss but the PSF had been prudently saving up for bad times and so this
was one of the bad times.
And we made it.
The PSF did not go bankrupt as a result and years after that the world and PyCon recovered
from the crisis.
And I was very happy that the PSF by then had financial staff who were careful with
money management.
I see that I'm out of time.
I have one more stressful memory.
There was a year that I procrastinated on my keynote so badly that I was almost in tears.
It was like I was at the conference and of course when I'm at the conference I have no
time for anything.
I had no slides.
I had no story I wanted to tell.
I didn't know what to do and I confess that to one of the conference organizers who alerted
Steve Holden.
I don't recall if Steve was at the time conference chair or if he had he definitely had been
conference chair in years past.
I knew him well.
He said let's go to dinner.
He fed me dinner, calmed me down and proposed a super simple solution.
He said let's have a fireside chat.
That means we put two comfy chairs on stage and Steve interviews me.
No preparation required.
I'm sure Steve had to prepare a bit because he had to come up with some questions.
Knowing me he probably knew that all he needed to do was prepare the first question and the
rest would happen without his intervention.
Anyway it worked fantastically.
We repeated that format later.
I very much still procrastinate.
That's why I'm talking last today.
Speaking of conference chairs, that is genuinely one of the most stressful jobs I know of.
I know several past PyCon chairs personally who burned out as a direct result of being
conference chair.
Fortunately nowadays the PyCon staff and the PS staff are providing a tremendous amount
of support.
In the beginning we all had to figure it out by ourselves.
Nevertheless, boy am I glad I was not Emily in 2020 when she had to decide to cancel PyCon
because of the pandemic.
Anyway thanks to all the conference chairs past.
And let me hand it back to the conference chair current Mariada and her team.
Thank you all.