Good afternoon, everyone. Our speaker for this session will talk about how to keep a secret.
Let us all welcome Glyph, the prophet.
Hi, everybody. I'm Glyph, and today I'm going to be talking about how you can keep secrets in your Python code.
Hello?
On?
Yeah.
We'll try that again.
Hi, everybody. I'm Glyph, and today I'm going to be talking about how you can keep secrets in your Python code and beyond.
Secret management is a huge topic, and we've only got 30 minutes here, so before I get started, I want to lay out my specific goal.
I will talk about how to store sensitive information on your computer.
Mostly, I want to talk about how to do this as the author of software that expects to be dealing with secrets.
However, in order to talk about that, I also need to talk about how users are going to behave in order to get the most out of the thought you put into that process.
I think it's also useful to talk about what areas of security I'm not going to be talking about.
I'm not going to be talking about secure messaging apps. This is not about how to share a secret with another human, a secret that you don't share.
I'm not going to talk about HTTPS or certificates. You might be able to use these techniques that I'm talking about today to store your secret keys a little bit better, but that's good to know.
So the kind of secret that I want to focus on is one that is not meaningful to a human being.
Things like passwords or cryptographic keys. They're short, and therefore they don't require significant storage.
I'm not talking about encrypting large amounts of data. In order to do that, you need somewhere to store the key that is doing the encryption, so you need to know what to do with these short secrets anyway.
Talking about security properties on that are, in terms, to be a little bit dry.
A narrative with characters and motivations to raise the level of interest.
A little easier to keep track of what's going on. So I'm going to introduce a character to you.
Say hello to Dletro. Dletro is the main character of our story today.
However, since this is an educational story, it's more like a modern fable.
And historical fables use talking to the primordial animals to teach their lessons.
But modern fables that need to have their main character in a grim lesson about the world instead incorporate a familiar plot point, the time loop.
In all of their time loop stories, the moral may be somewhat obscure at first, but its true nature will be revealed as our protagonist struggles to understand their situation.
They will be released from its relentless repetition only when they have learned the lesson.
So, okay, if you saw the words content warning come up on the slide and suddenly got a little nervous, don't worry, there's nothing offensive coming up.
But I do want to point out something about this story that applies to all in-depth information security work.
You might legitimately make you anxious. You might hear things that you're doing and then some horrible kind of breach or consequence for the users or company that could follow from that.
Thinking about that over and over again can really start to take a toll on your mental health.
To some extent, being a security engineer involves being a professional catastrophist.
You have to keep thinking of the same worst possible thing that could ever happen in detail over and over again.
So it's important to note and to emphasize that the attacks and errors I'm describing are rare and in many cases would require quite extreme effort and resources on the part of the attacker.
There are also lots of people who are out working to defend you against these attacks.
Your operating system vendor, open source packaging containers, the PIPI admins, they're all constantly trying to help defend you.
There are attacks across a whole range of vulnerabilities and Secret Storage is really one of them.
For one example, I'm going to talk about type of swapping, the practice of attackers registering malicious packages on PIPI.
Such attacks are possible and they do happen regularly, but even if you're completely careless with your pick and stalls, the PIPI admins are routinely being notified of such packages and actively moving them.
And that's just one defense among several against this unfortunate attack vector.
Now they're perfect, but they're all helping.
So with that caution out of the way, hopefully we're all too done.
There's the calm and everything to happy place.
Time for the nightmare of you whole Rx.
Jethro has an idea for a billion dollar company.
Blue4U is an API that can compute a unique blue that nobody else is using yet for their company or project randomly.
The idea here is that it's maybe an open core offering.
Blue4U is open source.
You can self-host it if you want, but the enterprise version, purples for professionals, can also generate purples.
That's the value of that.
Also, as a brief aside, speaking of combinations of worn cool colors, some of our fellow trans-biparties, this might have had difficulty attending this year due to unfortunate recent political developments in our venue.
Those developments affect those who live here even more.
I don't know if I should have to say more, but I'm going to be mentioning the first hundred dollars worth of donations to a local Utah LGBTQ plus charity.
Encircle together, find me after the talk, or send your receipts to encircle at Wolfson IM and let me know if you'd like to donate some to me.
Back to the topic.
What I'm going to do here is call threat modeling in the international security industry.
We will be enumerating threats and compromises.
Each time we will try to confront a set of threats and defend against them.
So let's begin.
It is the morning of February 2nd.
Jector wakes up.
Jector frees a different phone.
The Excel website starts testing it.
It's great.
Processing all kinds of requests for new kinds of blue on his laptop.
He's getting votes from the press.
He's on the Python podcast.
This is in your revolution in the open source blue community.
But of course, there's no use for his planned paywall professional purples if it's just sitting on his laptop.
So he makes an account at his side provider.
Jector's a busy guy.
He doesn't have time to memorize some complicated new password.
And so he just uses the same email and password that he used for his LinkedIn account.
Now, with the benefit of the narrator's eye view of this story that Jester doesn't have,
I suspect many of you can already see where this is going.
Attractors hear about Jester's cool new website, cross-reference it with a few password dumps from past data breaches,
and well off, they take them over his entire cloud account.
A boot of million servers, they mine cryptocurrency, blue for you is instantly bankrupt, all his blue is lost, like tears in the rain.
And now, it's the morning of February 2nd.
Jester wakes up.
If you don't already have a password manager, you need to get one right now.
There is often a tradeoff between convenience and security, but in the case of a password manager, you actually get both.
I highly recommend one password, which is free to anyone working on an open source project,
but there's probably one built into your web browser, too, and that's fine.
So Jester does that. Gets a password manager, generates a new, good, highly secure random password.
Jenny immediately forgets that password and loses access to everything.
She goes to reset it, and is unpleasantly surprised to learn that the inability to reset that one password is where the rest of the security comes from.
So it's impossible. He loses access, blue for you is now bankrupt again.
It's the morning of February 2nd. Jester wakes up.
Now, storing secrets isn't just about being a super spy using cool encryption tech.
It's also about backups and reliability.
So now, I'd like to talk about something called the CIA Triad.
I realize many of you may already have a strong association with the acronym CIA in the context of security,
but no, it is not about the Culinary Institute of America's Practices in Safeguarding of Traskees.
What the letters actually stand for in this case are confidentiality, integrity, and availability.
Confidentiality is the fun part, where you keep stuff secret with encryption and firewalls and stuff,
but the other two letters are important, and if you don't have them, you don't actually have security.
The I for integrity refers to the fact that you can't let attackers change your data.
This isn't super relevant to this talk because modifying a random piece of data like a password or an API key is insanely misleading it.
So that leads to the one that is important, which is availability.
Your system is available if you can use it.
In the case of your secret management system, that means it's unavailable if you forget the master password,
so make careful plans to remember it.
I've actually got a little tool that can help you generate and remember those core passwords
that you've actually got to remember in your brain with your phone pin and your master password called PinPanel.
It's a little rough. It's command line only at this point, but you might want to check it out.
So it's February 2nd once again.
Jethro is more careful to memorize his master password this time.
He puts all his website passwords into it.
Great.
After he's set up that cloud chat, he gets an email explaining that he can do a security check.
So he clicks the link and tries to log in.
Now for some reason, his shown new password manager isn't on his phone like he expected to.
He figures it's a bug.
Once again, the benefit of the narrator's RU, being outside of Jethro's universe, you can probably see where this is going,
but he doesn't. He opens up his password manager app, copies the user's new password manually,
and pastes it into the website.
It's the morning of February 2nd.
Jethro wakes up.
The most exciting question was, in fact, not his cloud provider's security website.
It was a question of time.
Now, a million security websites will get to this point with their narrative and tell you that you should never click on links or emails.
This is terrible advice. It's 2023.
All our jobs are like 75% clicking on links or emails.
The other 25% are just like idling on Zoom.
So we just hope we don't get hacked, right?
Password managers actually have a really neat feature that can help you here.
They will only autofill your password on the correct site.
So don't override autofill.
If you ever find yourself in a Jethro situation where the password's not autofilling,
which can often happen, many companies have many different domain names,
and you might need to use the same password on all 47 of Microsoft's login sites,
what you should do is open up the password manager, find the entry for the password in question,
and manually type the URL of the correct site you're trying to log into.
You can either copy it, as the attacker's URL might be quite convincing.
Just type it into the website field by hand, and if it still doesn't match,
then maybe consider getting some help or some friends to look at the mail to make sure it's legit.
Even better than a password manager, alone is a hard token that uses web auth numbers,
which are respectively physically impossible to use with the wrong website.
There are a few other cool things you could do with these keys.
That's for shadowing.
So Jethro learned his lesson. He gets a password manager.
He generates and memorizes its own log password.
Jethro is ready. Time for code.
He gets his read-through setup, starts hacking on some code,
gets the development kit from his cloud provider, and tries to boot the server with the Python API.
But the cloud SDK can't read his web browser's mind, so they can't authenticate.
He looks in the docs for authentication, and the examples from his provider
all just show the secret being pasted into the code.
So he logs onto the site, grabs the API key off the security page,
sticks it into his code, and takes it down.
Okay, now it's time to start coding.
Bootless server works. Pushing the code up there is a breeze.
The site's live. Bleed for you is in business.
Great. Time to push that code.
Wait a sec. The secret's just still sitting there in a source file.
And this read-through goes open source. This is an open core project.
Jethro realizes his mistake only a minute later, but as he's struggling to figure out
the right series of our keen git commands to rewrite history and purge a dinner repository,
automated script is already half the key, the cryptocurrency miners are out for the races.
It's the morning of the 22nd.
Jethro wakes up. Some of you might be staying on the topic list.
I know we're suspending disbelief here, thanks to the poignant emotional narrative you're supposed to be skillfully leaving.
Thank you, by the way. I'm happy to say.
But that's just silly. I've made a server on AWS.
I know there are no tips on how to put your API into your source code.
And you're half right, dear reader listener. It is very silly.
But unfortunately, it's actually quite common.
Now, I don't want to pick on these providers specifically because this is pervasive,
but just to show that big, serious companies with very good security in general do this,
it's a pretty tall of show.
Stripe Python SDK gives an example where they literally just show some Python code,
the API key pasted in the middle of it without any caution this might be an issue.
DigitalOcean's API documentation shows an export command.
It implies you should be putting your API key into your shell startup.
Again, no caution.
Unless the Python showed this, think that it's just a Ruby thing,
the Python documentation's a good example of this thing.
The officially recommended Python API for Zemdesk gives an example that features every type of credential.
Well, it's also your password in there, too, is not its word.
Put it into a source code.
So, a little bit of a personal digression here.
I have a five-year-old kid, and they got to come see me give another talk
at a different Python conference a little while ago.
They didn't get a ton out of the talk itself, given it was about MyPy
and how to use high-level features to make modeling dynamic code more type-checkable.
However, one slide slipped out, and it specifically asked me to include it in this talk,
because it was, in their words, the funniest joke.
This is a good spot to use that slide to express how I feel about docs that set up beginners
to use secrets in source files.
So, you know, this one's for you.
This is why I was motivated to give this talk in the first place.
If you were interested enough to attend this talk, you probably already know better than this,
but for developers starting out, they are going to see and copy the examples.
Authenticating to your service is literally the first thing that you will ever do with it.
They, by definition, do not have other experience to rely on.
This is why, if you're going to write documentation like that, this talk is for you.
At the end of this talk, if you're bored because you already knew all the technical content,
great, your users don't. They're going to follow your directions.
Don't tell users to paste APIs into their code.
So, okay, hopefully I've convinced you, but what should you do instead?
Well, we're in the middle of a fable, and typically you find the lesson at the end of the fable,
so let's rejoin our story.
Where were we?
Oh, right.
Go to your second.
Jacker wakes up.
So, Jethro knows he needs to try some different stuff.
Let's see what he does.
He sticks secret into his Dropbox folder instead, but then he's fat fingers and pastes a share link
in a blog post one day, and now it's public.
It's very disheartening.
He tries to put in his code again, but what he did ignore this time is some special file that doesn't get shipped in.
Later, he, like, accidentally gets enter while his editor has the get-ignore file focused,
but before tapping over to another file, another git commit-a and pushes it.
That's very very exciting.
Then, he tries using his dash RC in an environment variable and reads it from rs.environment.
Unfortunately, in the process of submitting a bug report for an open source library,
a put your logs in a gist tool dumps the output at the end command to build public gist.
It's very exciting.
Okay, so this is the story more carefully this time.
Later on, after they have the thing about the source code,
they suggest putting in an image dedicated to config file.
So he does.
To be honest, you might be able to get away with this.
Private files on your personal hard disk are, after all, somewhat private.
If you can't trust that a little bit, then you're going to have a hard time doing anything private.
But we can do a little bit better.
More importantly, Jethro, unlike us, lives in a universe ruled by a capricious god
who is intent on him learning only one very specific lesson.
So bad things are going to keep happening to Jethro.
For example, Jethro uses a backup service to backup his laptop.
And his backup provider gets breached.
Since the file's playing text, these hackers grab it out of the backup.
Jethro wakes up. It's February 2nd.
Jethro tries to put his backups on the hard disk instead, but then the hard disk gets stolen.
The hackers read it. Jethro wakes up.
This time, Jethro decides he doesn't need any backups, but he chains the laptop to his wrist.
But remember availability? There's a power surge. His laptop's disk fails.
Attackers don't get their cryptocurrency, but he still loses everything.
It's February 2nd. Jethro wakes up.
So Jethro enables full disk encryption in his OS.
He encrypts the backup drives, too. So he's back up.
Now he's got backups, and they're encrypted, and his disk is encrypted.
It's good stuff.
He's really starting to get serious now.
He looks into the best way to actually store his secrets on purpose,
and he starts using the key ring function to write them.
Jethro uses macro-esq development.
Jethro goes into this custom keychain, which is encrypted and secure.
Here, right. I should really emphasize this.
If you learn anything from this talk, it's really just use the key ring module.
Key ring's straightforward.
We will be exploring more of Jethro's mistakes in a moment,
and that will give us the opportunity to explore the advanced features,
but in code that just uses secrets, this is really all you need to do.
Call set password to save something. Call get password to get it back.
Any application that's done this is instantly more secure.
Gives you a couple things by default.
Key ring defaults to using the operating system's credential store,
which means that you get all the collective wisdom of your operating system's vendors,
ideas about what threats are salient, what you're standing against,
and what the best ways to deal with those threats are.
Even if it doesn't actually provide that better security for your case,
it also means that when either you or your users go to review
what sensitive information is available on their computer,
they can use standard interfaces for this stuff on their operating system.
Key ring supports multiple backends, which means that users with different needs
can configure applications using key ring to pull secrets
from more secure places if they do need that.
Just use key ring is the 80 in the 80-20 of this talk,
but as you may recall, Jethro's life is ruled by him a level of course
whose only interest is better information security,
so he's going to have to contend with some slightly more esoteric tricks.
This next one is something you might want to think about,
but keep in mind that we're starting to get into more advanced security.
Everything we've done so far assumes that Jethro's computer itself
is following his instructions, but what happens when some evil software
wants to steal his secrets and it's already running on his computer?
Now, Jethro's not going to any evil dark web hacker websites,
but he does install two new IPI packages every so often.
And actually, IPI, our software that runs on your computer as your user,
would access all of your files.
IPI does not have any way of scanning every single new piece of software
from malicious code automatically, so you have to be careful about what you install.
One day, Jethro tries to pip install pandas,
but instead he accidentally does pip install pandas instead.
And unfortunately in Jethro's universe, IPI's administers are a little bit less quick
to remove malware in response to reports,
so this actually belongs to their target there.
It's the morning of February 2nd. Jethro wakes up.
On every platform, by default, Turing grants access secrets automatically,
because that's what the platform production stores do.
You can request stuff in the background without you noticing.
This time, Jethro reads Turing's documentation very carefully
and sees that there's a security note about macros
where you can get prompted every time a specific secret is used.
When the Tegro's plotting mistake inevitably happens again,
Jethro's ready, and he gets a cross-center as long as possible.
He realizes what's happening, he hits the nine, deletes the bad package.
Unfortunately, if you recognize this case, it's a D.
On every other platform, Turing grants access to pretty much any software
that's running on your computer, because widgets and Linux don't have
meaningful entry user security brackets.
And Jethro's co-founder uses Windows, so same story again.
Jethro wakes up.
At this point, Jethro writes a case of software to try to address this problem.
Turing supports custom backends, which can be specified by users
even if the applications don't know about them specifically.
So Jethro can control what happens when secure background code gets for a secret.
Specifically, Jethro's new backend will prevent secrets from being accessed
even by malware without his knowledge.
WebAuthn has a specific terminology for this.
It's called a user presence check.
It's why, if you use a token authenticator, you need to both plug it in
and physically touch it to log in.
And that's why Jethro wants to raise extra sense of the secrets here.
As I mentioned earlier, this sort of hard token that you can use to perform
WebAuthn authentication on the website is a great security option,
so Jethro already had one of those password packages.
Number four, Shepard.
You wouldn't necessarily want to use this for every kind of secret,
but some secrets are more powerful than others and should be protected more aggressively.
Some secrets can do stuff like sync your email in the background,
and you need them to have easy access because you wouldn't want to have to touch your hardware key every two minutes.
If you're doing it constantly, you won't notice when something unexpected happens
because the touch prompt would always be accepted.
So Jethro writes a piece of software, a custom keyring backend
that uses a part of the hard token protocol to encrypt each secret as a Frenet token,
making it impossible for his secrets to be discovered unless his token is plugged in and he touches it.
When Jethro writes a keyring of tokens, he calls it token-writ.
Sorry, Zoobards, that's a joke for you old people who don't know what a token is.
If not copyrighted, Frenet Honey, it comes from a parallel universe,
so I grabbed this software from this iteration of the time loop before Jethro got reset back to the beginning.
And since I've spent so much time doing the fickle god version of someone else's life,
I didn't want to give the demo gods the opportunity to do this thing for me,
so this isn't a live demo, but it is from a couple hours ago.
After steering Jethro's code and resetting his universe,
I'm going to do a quick recording of me releasing it on PyPI this morning.
Note that I'm using token ring to release token ring,
and in just a second, we should see...
Maybe I think that's a bit of a mistake, so long.
So when the package finishes building, I use coin,
which is the standard outbuilder for PyPI packages,
and it drops for a touch because it's using that keyring backend.
So if you have some high security application that you'd like to secure above and beyond your concert manager,
you can just install token ring and feel free to use that solution.
Now, Jethro's in a pretty good place at this point.
This is an extremely difficult to approach to secrets management.
The most sensitive secrets he's storing on his laptop are incredibly secure,
only accessible when his hardware is used plugged in,
every access requires easier management.
But Jethro's attackers are no longer attackers.
They have access to advanced alien technology.
They now deploy a zero-click zero day against his laptop.
They wait until he catches a UVQ to steal his secret out of memory.
It's the morning of favorite seconds.
That's our website.
At this point, he loses it.
He is going to protect his secrets at any cost.
He raises $100 million in venture funding.
He hires a team of 1,000 security engineers.
They comb over every aspect of the possible uses of secrets that you might ever have.
They airgap all of their systems.
Unfortunately, in all this endless security hardening,
he forgets to ever actually create an application.
Remember the application?
They run out of money and the company shuts down,
never having generated even a single blue,
let alone a purple, for a question.
It's the morning of February 2nd.
Did you think the lesson was just about being infinitely careful about your secrets?
Jethro wakes up and thinks long and hard about what he's been doing.
He realizes that he's just been reacting to each new attack,
always fighting the last one.
There's no way that he can out-resource these attackers.
They appear to be almost demonic in their power and influence.
So instead, he makes a list in a budget.
He reviews the basics of his black.
He uses a password manager.
He encrypts his disk.
He encrypts the backups.
He uses the keyway module.
He can figure a back end appropriate to the sensitivity of the data.
He makes a plan for all these attacks.
He writes it down.
He tells his co-founder about it.
He trains any new employees or contributors that need to interact with these secret agents.
He knows the interactivity secrets as well.
When the attackers break in again, who knows how,
Jethro contacts his provider and shows them his documented security procedures.
They agree to discount above and beyond.
They restore his servers and give him the response.
The attackers knew his machine was ransomware, but he's got up-to-date backup.
It steals his laptop, but it's encrypted.
It's the morning of April 22nd.
Jethro wakes up.
The attackers have given up on the secret.
How? Jethro's at PyCon.
He's got a boost at Startup Row.
He's got a new and purposeful pros website.
It's online generating colors and movement.
And he lives completely alone.
In this talk, which as you've seen is already long enough that it barely fits into this time slot,
I've only been able to review how Jethro secures his secrets on one computer, head-to-head.
You also need to deal with secrets in the cloud.
Another important rule that I didn't have time to cover is that you should limit the power, scope, and lifetime of your secrets.
Make them less powerful if you can.
You still eventually need to store them somewhere.
You still will always have some power for secret, but it doesn't have to be all root access all the time.
There are quite a few tools that you can use to create short-lived API tokens.
They're inherently specific in service you're using them, which is why it's hard to give a talk about the general concept.
Several issues for AWS, though, which is certainly one of the higher-privileged things that you're likely to deal with.
Two popular ones you can check out are GimmieAWSCreds and AWS Vault.
You'll also need to put secrets into your CI systems and cloud servers.
The providers have APIs for this, and in particular you probably want to know about GitHub Actions' dedicated secrets management tools.
There's also a Python library called DTVAC, which is sort of a queuing for the cloud.
It's a client for the HashiCorp Vault service, which will extract all of the backend secret sharing services that various clouds have collected.
Note also that if your application is already using queuing, then when you start integrating with tools like this,
you can change your queuing backend on different deployment scenarios that you're using.
So for basic secrets access, you only need to change your configuration, not your code.
Thank you very much for coming to my talk, and happy Secret Keeper!
So I'm Glyph. You can find me on the internet by typing Glyph into various places.
We only have a couple minutes left. You might have time for one question,
but I think most of the questions are going to be in the hall outside if you'd like to join me there.
So, thanks again!