Okay, so good morning everybody.
So what I'll do is first show you some of the reasons why we created Type-I,
where we come from and all of this,
and how different we are from all those new packages that come into existence on a daily basis.
Then I will show you some code about Type-I, some demos.
I'll show you also how it works in different environments.
That's one of the rare tools that works basically as Python scripts,
and you will see some graphics on some backend work,
but it also works very well in notebooks.
So you can have a full blown interface within a notebook environment.
I'll show you that on local Jupyter notebooks.
You can use this also on platforms where you redirect using things like ng-rock,
use colab, data breaks, or some of the other platforms.
Okay, so let's get started.
So I come from a background of large companies.
I work for a company called Allog, which was acquired by IBM.
I spent my life basically developing AI projects for a long time for large companies.
All of this was developed in C++ initially, and Java, JavaScript, all this stuff.
A few years back we were tired of all these things.
I remember having software.
Installing them was taking like a minimum of three hours.
So I said, let's do everything on Python.
And we tried, and we tried on real projects.
Also, when I say a project, it's not an AI project, it's the whole software.
It's the integration, the graphics, and usually you have end users also on the other side.
And we discovered that Python is great, because we love Python to develop all these things,
but there were some issues with the product, hence the creation of Type-I.
So Type-I has been created with a wide, maybe it was a bit too ambitious,
but we really wanted to do anything from dashboarding in Python,
you want to have nice dashboards and things, all the way to complex applications,
multi-user, that could be AI simulation, optimization, mathematical optimization,
a whole range of different types of applications.
One thing that's often missing in all the discussion I'm seeing in the data science environment
is really the role of AI.
We see very often people are really, really focusing on the algorithm,
exposing very smart algorithms, all these things,
but end users, it's not only the data scientists, it's also the end users that interact with the algorithm.
So this is also a very important thing that led us, you will see,
to really make sure that Type-I was managing what we call scenarios.
So scenarios are a little bit like experiments for the end user,
but it's also experiments for the data scientists, but you have the same need for end users.
Okay?
One thing we noticed also in the world of Python is this amazing failure rate,
if we can call it failure.
We see about 85% of Python pilots basically staying pilots,
sometimes for good reasons, for instance, the ROI wasn't there,
but sometimes it's because it's too complicated, so you may need to rewrite everything.
So you've got the data science department develops in Python,
you need to hand over to an IT department that redevelops everything,
instead of having a couple of guys who end up with an army of IT guys
that redevelop in JavaScript, in Java, and all this stuff.
And that has a cost, and a lot of companies are also short of IT skills.
So unlike what most companies do with startups, especially in the open source,
Type-I had to be designed with large companies.
So we didn't start from the community side.
When we started the product recently, a year and a half ago,
we developed it with McDonald's, with a large retailer in Europe,
with a company called Tal, which is one of the largest cloth manufacturers in the world,
companies like Samsung, and so on and so forth.
That's the result of what can be achieved for a large retailer called Groupe Les Mousquetaires.
So what they did, Intermarché, the largest retailer in France,
they had the choice of outsourcing a very large cash flow prediction model for all the companies,
which is about 18 flows to be predicted.
And they had the choice of doing that with an external company
that quoted 600k for people for about 8 months.
And they did that, and they basically competed against their own IT,
which did it with Type-I for 60k, 1.5 people, about 2 months,
but basically a 10 times reduction in cost here.
And they chose also the end user, the CFO, who is the end user,
and the treasurer of the company chose the Type-I solution.
So it was not inferior in quality or anything like that.
So that's the kind of thing why we created Type-I.
So you will see that we both, we really wanted to target the front end and the back end,
so you will have these two components.
I will tell you a little bit of the roadmap,
but we will produce also a conversion of these two packages.
At the moment, they are like two independent packages.
When you do pip install Type-I, you will get both the graphical side,
the front end, and the back end package.
So one of the things when we were studying about what's there in the Python world,
we looked at really two families of graphical interface when we were looking at the GUI side.
On one side, you've got all these widget libraries, which are extremely nice,
but that doesn't make a full-blown interface, highly interactive, multi-page, and all these things.
You have tools above, I'm sure you know about Streamlit,
but for real applications, we felt we were using Streamlit,
the event management mechanism was really inefficient.
It wasn't working on notebooks, that's something that we wanted to have,
and we wanted to have also a lot of capabilities for managing big data graphically, and so on and so forth.
The alternative, of course, is to have a dedicated GUI specialist that develops with Plutly,
or in TKinter, or all these graphical software.
But our intent, again, was to make the tool easy to learn.
That's something I didn't mention.
A quick learning curve, the ability to develop quickly for almost any Python developer.
On the backend side, it was a little bit of a different story.
We looked at different products, and none of them had all the features we wanted.
Some of them were really complex, too complex for the audience.
For the audience, we were targeting.
A tool like Airflow, for instance, is really a steep learning curve.
The functionality we wanted were all the tasks, all the orchestration, basically the pipeline orchestration stuff.
Caching, simple caching where you need to model data.
We didn't think some of these packages were not modeling data sufficiently enough or not at all.
Scenario management, that's something I really insist.
That's this capability to do what-if analysis with your pipelines.
Versioning, so I'm not talking about versioning of your MLflow with your registry for your data model,
nor am I talking about the versioning of code here.
I'm talking about versioning of the pipeline itself.
When you change, the pipeline evolves over time.
You may have a new data source and this kind of thing.
You need to version it.
We didn't find any tool that could do that.
Cycle, so that's more of an option, but many of the customers we deal with, they have cycles in their business.
McDonald's, when they do prediction of sales for their stores, they do it once a week for every single store.
So the scenario management, basically you need to be able to create scenarios per time bucket every week.
One of these scenarios could become the official scenario, the one you are going to publish,
the one that is going to be the official one.
So all these capabilities are built in inside Type-I.
Again, there are situations, I don't know, like fraud detection where you don't have cycles.
But a lot of companies in the business world do have cycles, whether it's daily, monthly, weekly.
So let's start now with a little bit of code.
So I'll show you some code.
So let's start.
A bit of code on the green side.
So I'll start with something simple so I get rid of...
So...
Okay, let me get rid of this.
This is here.
Okay, so let's start with the simplest program that you can have with Type-I.
Okay.
Okay, so in fact you will see that Type-I is in fact an augmented markdown.
Okay, so what you see here, once you have done your PIP install, you import the GUI,
and you start having your first markdown, the page.
I'll move that here, it might be easier.
Yeah, the page that you defined is just markdown. That's markdown, no Type-I.
And you start having your first Type-I object.
So Type-I objects are basically defined with these symbols here.
I will go into this a little bit later.
You can see here a Python object that is an integer, value 10.
And everything Python always has these curly brackets around it.
Okay, so that's how you see whether it's a data frame, a dictionary.
Here it's an integer. And it's a text here. By default, it's a text.
And we're going to basically run this.
And you can see that I'm passing the page, which is a markdown page, to this.
Okay, so let's execute this.
Okay.
So it's going to spin off a web server.
And you will see a thing appearing here. Maybe I'll try to do this.
And you can see the code side by side here.
So you can see you've got the markdown demo, which is in, this demo is in italic,
so that's just markdown stuff. And you have your value 20, which appears here.
Okay, so let's try to make it a little bit more complex.
So what I'll do here, I will add an object.
So here, beside providing a Python object, the next field is actually the actual widget,
a graphical widget you would like to use. So here it's a slider.
You will have charts, you will have menus, bar, different kinds of objects.
At the moment, most of the objects are coming from Plutly, built on top of Plutly,
but you have also an API to bring any graphical objects that you want.
So here we have a slider. And here that's also some parameter, we call it property.
After you define properties, so you have all the properties you can find for charts.
Here it's a property associated with a slider, which gives you how quickly you want your graphical object to react.
If you have a remote platform, for instance, you may want to have a kind of slow response time,
whereas if you are running locally, then you will be able to react very quickly to the typing of your code here.
And next, I'm going to plot a chart, which here I'm using the data.
So you will see the slider is basically connected with an initial value, which is the same Python value.
And next, I have a chart object, so it's a new object. By default, it will be a line chart.
Sorry, yes?
Sorry, I don't know if I'm doing all that. Can you zoom in, please?
Sure.
Can I zoom? If I do that? Yes, but I'm not sure it will.
Is it better? I don't want to zoom too much. Is it better?
One more? Yeah.
Sorry.
Okay.
So you will see there are a lot of parameters, in fact, that you can use.
For instance, again, most of the tool like Streamlit, if you have a long run, for instance, you are launching a function.
When you click on a button, you are stuck.
Okay, here you have parameters also to decide whether you want to go asynchronously or synchronously, whether you wait or you want not to wait, for instance.
So you got a lot of things here which are about really fine-tuning the way you interact with your software.
So here what I'm doing, I'm creating basically a sine curve. It's a function here that returns a list.
You can see that this is a list that we are building. So it's a decaying sine curve.
And I put this as a list. It returns a list. So when I compute that, I get a list and I put that list in the chart.
Okay, so that's what I'm doing here.
So I'm going to run this again. So never forget to stop your previous run because you are going to use the same port otherwise.
And let's run this again.
In fact, I'll show you next time. But here I'm running again the server. You could have saved and just update your page.
So here you have your graphics. Okay. And you have the trigger.
So what you are seeing is two things. So first, I didn't do anything to connect value here with the slider.
Except if you remember in the code, you have this simply disconnection here value with the slider.
Okay, so if I change the slider, I change the value.
What I've done here is also connect so that different ways. So I'm showing you here what is called a callback,
which is basically saying whenever you change, it's a global callback, whenever you change, sorry, it's here.
Whenever you change this particular value and this Python variable called value, then recompute your chart.
Okay, so this is what you see here when you run the software.
Hold on. Yep. So you see this connection occur here.
Okay, so there are different ways of doing that. First, you don't have to do it. That's another method.
Do not use any callback. Okay, so in this case, what you do, you just do that.
Okay, and you pass directly the function call here. So you just put compute data of value directly in there.
Okay, so if I can do that, sorry.
And you put your value and that will do the job. So it's like a Python F string that you can put directly in there.
So if I do control S, okay, I save that. If I update my page, sorry, if I update the page,
you should have the same behavior. Oh, sorry. What is going on? Maybe I didn't stop.
Let me run. Oh, yes, I still had this running. So let me run again.
So you see you still have the same connection. So there are different ways to do that.
I'll just show you one without a callback and one with callbacks. Okay.
What else can I say? So there are a lot of objects available. You can go to the website. Yep.
Yep.
No, you don't. Absolutely not. No, you can remove it. Absolutely. That was for the previous case. You wouldn't need it. Yep.
So basically, there are reasons for using certain callbacks versus doing F string call directly inside the...
Obviously, if you have like three or four objects that relate to your computer data value, you don't want to call the function three times.
So it's more efficient to have a global callback on this. We also have local callbacks and things to optimize.
It's all about optimizing the reaction and the interaction you have with the software.
For those of you who are not used to callbacks, we do have tips and videos and things like that to introduce you slowly with very simple articles on how to tune this.
But this is very important when you build a full application. It's multi-user.
I will show you also how it works on notebooks. It's exactly the same thing.
It will spin a web thing on a notebook. I'll show it to you right now.
Before that, I want to show you something we did, which is what we call Decimator.
We have customers who really want to show big data or large data, I should say, graphically.
Of course, some people use the different shaders and things like that, but very often you need to keep the shape of certain things.
What you will see here is a specific object. We use a chart which has many points.
We just add a property to that chart, which is Decimator.
Let me run this demo first for you.
Here we'll just take a particular...
You will see that over here.
No, that's not the one here. Why? Because it's using this.
We need to use this, this.
Let's start again.
It's using the other...
Okay.
Here we have to assume...
We choose a particular time series here.
Let's assume it's a very large one. It could be an IoT thing. You may have a lot of points.
Of course, if you show that in Python, it's likely to crash if you have too many points.
The first curve is the kind of curve that would crash, but I have to show you a curve where you have many points and how that curve evolves if you make it a decimator.
When you use a decimator, you say, I want to use 500 points, and it will remove all the points that least modify the shape of the curve.
You can see here, for instance, that the shape is respected. If I do some zooming, it will add points. It will still be 500 points.
The more you zoom, you maintain that capability. It works also very well with clusters to respect the shape of your clusters and things like that.
It's extremely useful for some of our customers.
That's just one of the algorithms that we have used as part of Type-I.
One thing I want to show you also before we move to the next Type-I core is...
That's basically the fact that it works on notebooks.
Here I have some colab stuff. I've got a notebook thing here. I'm going to use the Jupyter notebook here.
I'm running Jupyter locally.
It's a small sentiment analysis with some neural network involved here.
Let's assume everything has been installed.
Here we just get your transformer engine loaded.
Down here you will see I'm creating a series of pages with Type-I. I don't want to go into it.
It's the first page that we create. The second page is here. After that, I'm going to run this.
Basically, from your notebook, you will see this application like what you would do outside of notebooks.
Hopefully.
That should be coming. It's supposed to be a sentiment analysis.
I think there are two pages. Maybe we can have a look a little bit at the code.
I don't know why it takes so long.
Not sure what's going on here.
That's not...
Okay, running.
That should work.
Let me try another time again. Was there any other notebook?
Okay, nothing is running here.
Let me start again.
I think there must be some port issue here. Let me see if that works better if I use colab.
This should work.
I need to install that as well. This hasn't been installed. This will take a while. I think if I do it, it will take too long.
That's quite fine.
It's just reinstalling everything here.
While it's doing it, it's quite interesting to maybe have a look at how we combine the pages. We have two pages. This is page one.
We just specified the page, the markdown basically object. We have one for page one and another one for page two. These have been defined above.
We connect them as a dictionary of pages and you just pass this to your GUI here.
How is this going? Okay, we are fine. This has been loaded correctly. Let's move to here.
After that should be fine.
This is page one. This is page two.
This is the thing we will be getting. We go back to this here.
I think I need to rerun the whole thing. Basically it works on notebooks.
We have a booth where I can show you later if you want. I think there are some port issues on that front.
That was for the graphical side. If you want, you can go to the website. You've got a step-by-step thing. You've got some tips.
You've got some resources, demos that you can run with the code. You've got the documentation.
You can see some of the graphics that exist inside Type-I GUI. The different visual elements that you have in there.
You have quite a few of these objects here.
Let's go back now to the Type-I Core. Type-I Core is a different object. Here on the visual code, I'll be showing you the editor for our pipelines.
Here you will see that you can create graphically on the visual code your own pipelines very easily.
In blue, the blue box are all data nodes. The red boxes are tasks. The pipelines are actually the tasks that you associate with them.
The data node is a larger concept than you may think. It's not only about external data that you fetch, whether it's a CSV, a parquet, or some other format.
It can be also a parameter. Here, for instance, the day is a date. It's a Python date object. That's also a data node.
It could be an in-memory object that you define here. That's interactive. That's an extension, a visual code extension that you install.
By the way, on the visual code also, for the GUI, you have the code completion to help you with the syntax and everything.
Here, for instance, we can check the different parameters that we have created. This particular initial dataset is a data node.
The premise is that it has zoomed a lot. You've got all the properties. We know it's a CSV type.
You can have a wide range of data node types, but you can create your own very easily.
There's no limitation here. You define the path, the property, and you can define also the kind of data, Python object, you want to use.
For instance, if you are dealing with tabular type of data, you can say, okay, that will end up...
The passing, basically, of the result of this can be a data frame, could be an MPI array, it could be a dictionary. That's your decision.
You can modify it here with a property if you want to.
The task, in fact, that's a Python function.
You link that particular object to... Here you have the directory. It's a relative path.
You've got the name, algo.pipe, and that's the function inside this config, this data.
You will have... Sorry, that's not the inside algo, sorry.
You've got this config function, which is clean data.
You've got clean data that you have defined inside your algo here. It's a pure Python function.
Okay?
Of course, it's an editor, so you can create your new data node. It will appear, and you can connect it.
It's basically a graphical editor for you to do that. It saves as a .toml file.
All of what I'm doing here can also be done programmatically.
If you want to do it programmatically, the very same thing that we have here under your eyes can be programmed like this.
You create... That's because of the zooming here.
You can see the different things. I create data nodes with a function and so on and so forth to create the tasks.
One thing I wanted to show you also... Sorry, that's not what I want to do here.
Okay.
I lost it.
Okay. One thing that we have in the configuration... If you go to .toml...
I lost it. I don't know how to get it back.
One thing that exists inside the task is the concept of caching. You can see it here. You can do it also graphically.
One particular task here, we associate the properties skippable.
It's skippable basically if none of the input of the task has changed from the previous run.
There's no reason why you would rerun this task again. If you assign it skippable, then it will skip it.
You can attach also a time period. You may say, I want that to be skippable only for a day.
You've got different parameters that you can play with.
At the end of the day, what you end up with is really your main file.
If you have created a .toml file, you just need to load that config. It's a configuration file.
You can start creating pipelines and scenarios and execute them.
I'm going to run here a scenario. You remember this date parameter.
It's actually the date from which you want to start the prediction for this very simple pipeline.
We are going to iterate the date from the 25th of January 2021 and add a day and call this function.
It's really just a creation of the scenario and the submission of the scenario as a job.
Let's run this.
Here, there is no fancy stuff really going on.
You will see basically the jobs. I think there are about 10 jobs that will get executed.
10 scenarios.
That's what you get here.
I'm waiting for this to happen.
One thing you will notice, each scenario is actually made of three tasks.
There are three continuous tasks that occur here.
I've launched a little bit of graphics at the end of it.
What I want to show you is the fact that one of these tasks was actually skippable.
You can see that when I run the first time, that's the first time it runs.
On the second time, you can see that...
Completed, completed.
Two, two, two.
You will see...
Zooming, that's not that easy.
Two, two, two, two.
We run the three tasks several times.
No results.
One of the tasks is supposed to be skipped.
Let me start from the start.
That's the first run. This is the first prediction I'm running.
This is done.
It has never been written.
Again, this doesn't seem to be skipped for some reason.
I cannot check on the diagram.
Here it's not being skipped, but normally it should be.
I don't know why.
That's the objective of the skippable.
What you have also here is the possibility to...
Of course, you have all the orchestration, so the running in parallel of your tasks.
The capability also to keep some intermediate data.
One thing that we do provide is the versioning.
For instance, one thing that we have here...
When you run, for instance, Python, you get some first list of your version with the minus H option here.
That tells you what are the different options for versioning your scenario and your execution.
One other thing you can do is list what are the different versions that you have.
There are three different levels of versioning.
Development, experiment, and production.
If you want to create a new thing, you just do minus experiment.
You give it a name.
It will run the whole thing again.
There are just ten different scenarios with different predictions that are being run.
Here we execute it.
Let's go back to the thing here.
If we want to look now at my list of versions, I have actually this test one that has been recorded as a new version.
Once you have done that, you can create several of your development versions.
You can move one of these into production.
The difference between experiment and production is development, experiment, and production.
Each time you run, it will erase all the intermediate data that it keeps, metadata for each of the runs and scenarios.
Eventually, one of the experiments will actually become into production.
If you modify your pipeline and you run it again with the same version, it will complain.
It will tell you you have modified something.
Here, this is where we provide some tools to help you migrate your code so that it can work within the same version of your pipeline.
Typically, if you change a little attribute from CSV file, for instance, the file that we are reading, which is a CSV file, you move it into an Excel file or something else, it will notice it.
If you add a new source, it will tell you there is a delta with a previous run, so your code needs to be ported.
We provide this capability because you have a lot of customers that work on a particular pipeline over time, and they want to keep and reuse the existing scenario.
If you change your pipeline, it's difficult to make that still useful.
We provide this kind of migration path when you have this kind of work across versions.
That's it on the Type I Core side.
Let me give you a little bit of background on the roadmap now.
Let's see what we do.
On the Graphic Core side, we are going to have a GUI preview in June.
While you are coding your graphics, you will see the layout of what you are coding appear while you are coding.
That will help you see really well without having to run or execute your code.
We provide enhanced tables.
Available are already quite nice.
They are editable and all these things.
You can enter data inside.
We provide more capabilities in some of the double indexes and pivoting and all these things.
It's basically going to be built on AG Grid stuff.
We will provide some cascading style sheets.
It's actually already available.
We released it this week.
We have a style sheet that is provided.
It helps you with something quite nice and easily modifiable for those of you who are not into CSS.
That is really useful.
On Type I Core, we will provide some graphical objects that will actually provide graphics on top of the Type I Core object.
We will have a scenario selector.
Cycles.
Your scenario will be sorted per cycle.
You will be able to visualize data nodes.
You will be able also to query with natural language.
These objects will be predefined and ready to use.
You can see Type I Core and Type I GUI basically being combined.
We are launching Type I Cloud next week.
That's an open source.
It's free.
Sorry, it's not open source.
It's free for our community users.
We are open source.
I don't know if I mentioned this.
It will be a very easy way for you to deploy your app.
The application will request to define the machine with some basic parameters.
You will upload your zip file and you will be able to admin your different machines and execute them also there.
We will provide a decent machine, not a huge machine at this stage, but something that's quite useful for you to deploy in your application.
I think I've covered most of the things I wanted to cover here.
I'm open for questions.
I want to apologize also for I'm not the one who's supposed to present.
That's why it was a bit of a hiccup with some things I wanted to show you.
All of this is basically being used in large applications again.
That's something that the software has been used in very large organizations, has been tested even though it's fairly recent.
The idea is really to be able to cover the whole spectrum of application building.
Any questions?
Oh yes, of course I always forget.
Please contribute, at least give some stars to our repo, Aviga.
I have two questions.
One is you mentioned that you are using Fontium backend.
Is there a plan to use it on the library?
The second question is, is there some logic around why you decided to use enhanced markdown as a forward layer and fallback layer?
Okay, the first question.
First of all, I mentioned that we have an API, which is fairly easy to use.
It connects with any JavaScript library.
That can be part of the contribution.
We'll be working with some guys, I don't know if you know Vizu.
We'll work with those guys to have these dynamic graphs.
We'll be working progressively on Matplotlib stuff.
Plotly also, we're looking at what they're doing to provide.
We have very specific graphics.
For instance, we have some guys who really, some of our users really want an ICN chart.
It's a specialized library.
We have a contribution.
We are at that stage where we really want to build the community around contribution here.
We are really open to this kind of stuff.
On the second, why markdown?
Markdown provides you already a network, a framework, sorry, for a lot of the which the loop can fill.
It's a documentation kind of language, if you want.
We had to benefit from this.
We had to design, of course, the syntax for embedding this.
We have done testing also.
We had different ideas at the beginning.
We look at three or four different options.
That's the one that seemed to be adopted by our customers.
You don't need to know markdown.
Markdown is very easy to use in general.
In terms of learning curve, we measured how long it takes for somebody who is using the markdown approach.
We had another approach at the very start of the product.
We noticed that better productivity using the markdown stuff.
We didn't want to do something like streamlit because we were really heavy users of streamlit.
We decided to stop.
We didn't want to do something like this.
It came as a natural choice.
If you want more explanation, I have to get my R&D guys involved.
That's the gist of it.
It's also something where you don't see it here, but it's extremely efficient.
A lot of the work has been spent on having a very efficient interface here in terms of interactions
instead of dealing with different size of data, multi-user, not being locked when you do a long run.
You want to be able to move, but you need to decide.
You can decide that when you work on remote platform.
There's this refresh rate as a parameter.
It could be as complex as you want.
You have this level of customization that we didn't want to give away.
That's why I'm not very keen to say our marketing guys want to say we are low-code,
but I'm very careful with that.
First, as a Python developer, I don't like to use low-code in general.
Low-code means a lot of different things.
Very, very low-code stuff.
We are not really low-code, but we program very quickly.
We understand you need customization.
We need very high-level.
We kept that in mind to try to build something which is efficient and can build a complete application,
not only pilot.
Of course, you can use it for pilot.
But at the same time, maintain a high level of customization.
To avoid a mistake that we have seen, it's not really a mistake.
I think the tool extremely at the start was really developed for pilot, not for real application.
Since we are seeing also a lot of CIOs, we have really two types of customers and prospects.
We have an enterprise version, by the way, which is only providing support on the LDAP connection security stuff.
But then feature-wise, it's the same.
But when we talk to our prospects, we have really two types of customers.
We have customers who are absolutely, they know everything about the Python ecosystem.
Most, for instance, in finance, not surprisingly, they know absolutely everything.
And you have to fit Type I within their ecosystem.
And you have to be very technical, go very deeply to see how it fits.
And you've got beginners.
It could be a big company with CIO, and they just start on Python.
And this is a platform also to gently make them easily develop full application.
So we cater for both.
It's a big gap.
Any other questions?
So thank you for your patience.
And again, apologies for being late and not being able to show you everything here.
Thank you.