All right, guys, welcome to PyCon 23, your first open telemetry tutorial.
So before we start, I just want to thank everyone who's working here and volunteering and help
make this thing possible.
You're all doing an amazing job.
So thank you all very much.
So let's jump right in.
Welcome to how to monitor and troubleshoot applications in production using open telemetry.
So this, I believe, is the number one most comprehensive tutorial for open telemetry
that exists.
I wish I had this when I was starting out because this would have saved me a lot of
time.
So that's what I hope to do here today for you.
And I hope to cut you a lot of time and cut you little corners.
And maybe we can all learn really fast today.
So does anyone here know what open telemetry is?
Is anyone familiar?
Please raise your hand.
Okay, a good amount.
And everyone who doesn't know what open telemetry is, please raise your hand.
Wow, most of the class.
All right.
Well, welcome.
So we'll get right into it.
But there's a lot of backstory and a lot we need to know before going into it.
We need to define observability at first.
And the way that I would define observability, and this is really the standard now, is measuring
the internal state of a system and how well you understand what's happening inside given
only the external outputs.
Okay?
So you're watching something change from the outside.
And you kind of have a smarter and smarter and educated guess as to what's really happening
inside.
And so we can start with a few examples.
We can see, for example, a person aging here.
And can anyone raise their hand and tell me what's happening to this person as they're
aging and getting older in order?
No one knows?
Exactly.
So you summarize basically in a couple words.
He's losing hair, he's growing whiter and whiter hair, and just a few small changes
outside.
And same with this star that's burning.
Right?
We're basically summarizing what we're seeing in a few words, but these don't really capture
what's really happening.
There's a lot happening behind the scenes for both of these events.
There's millions and millions of tiny events happening inside that we don't know.
And every year we're just learning more and more and making smarter and smarter guesses
as to what's happening.
So that's exactly what we're trying to do here.
We're trying to observe, but not a person that's aging or a star that's burning.
We're trying to observe modern day applications.
Right?
Applications for the cloud, cloud native, in distributed environments, and so on.
And so we need some data basically.
Just like we have microscopes and lenses and we're able to see the sun and we're able to
smarter and smarter and educated guesses, we need some information on the application
side as well to figure out exactly what's happening.
So observability for modern applications are built on top of three main pillars.
Metrics, logs, and traces.
Okay?
Metrics.
Can anyone raise their hand and explain what metrics is in their own words?
Do they have an idea of what it could be?
Yes, please.
Exactly.
It's a series of numbers that add up and really they just measure activity and you can display
them on the graph and you can have all sorts of fun with them.
And traces as well.
Traces are a bit more abstract.
They're really the, I guess the cooler part of observability.
They're a document based metadata really that contain all the information of one microscopic
atomic event.
Okay?
So when we see here this image of a trace, what we're really looking at is spans coming
together.
Feel free guys, come in.
Don't be shy.
It's okay.
Welcome, welcome.
And so what we're really seeing here is a collection of spans.
A trace, you should think of it as a big, big family.
Okay?
And each one of these little circles that you see here, this is what we call the root
span, the first one.
And each one is a span we see here.
So this would be the root span.
Each circle span you see here would be a child to this parent span.
And I guess each circle span, you can think of it as a sibling.
Okay?
Is that a question?
Oh, okay.
Yeah, don't sit there.
Okay.
Are there any questions so far on metrics or traces?
And logs.
We've never heard of this, right?
Just kidding.
This logs is your normal standard output, standard error streaming.
It's what you see when you do print Hello World.
It's exactly that.
So logs as well.
Together these come and they form a stack of telemetry data that we call melt.
Logs, traces, logs.
Right?
So when you have only one of these, it becomes really, really hard to monitor and debug your
application.
When you have two, it becomes slightly better, depending which two.
And when you have all three come together in a concise and consolidated place in a single
plane of glass, it becomes very, very easy to quickly debug, monitor your applications,
and stay on top of everything.
Any questions so far up till now?
Okay.
Amazing.
Class full of geniuses.
So welcome.
Next, we'll get into what open telemetry is.
So open telemetry, you should think of it as, I guess, you can think of it as a collection
of tools and APIs and SDKs.
Okay?
And they do four main things.
I'm not exaggerating when I list out all these words here.
They instrument, they generate, they collect, and then finally they export telemetry data.
This is all that open telemetry does.
It does these four main things, and we'll get really, really deep into all of those.
Okay?
But what you should really think of it as, open telemetry is just one protocol just to
extract telemetry data out of your application and to be able to do something with it later
on.
Okay?
Any questions on this?
Okay, excellent.
So we're going to look at it at a high level, what really happens.
So on the left side, on the blue, you have your demo client, demo server.
Ignore those.
Those are just your applications that you wrote in Python.
You wrote a hello world in Python.
Okay?
That's the blue.
From there, open telemetry does what we call instrumentation, and it's able to extract
telemetry data from your application and export it somewhere else.
So your application, it exports it to an OTL collector, an open telemetry collector.
Okay?
A collector should think of it as a queue or a sort of bridge or a bus or a highway.
That's just an intermediate stop for your telemetry data before it reaches really its
final destination.
Your data will never live in an OTL collector.
It'll just stop by there for a little bit before advancing on and moving on somewhere
else.
Okay?
And finally, we're going to export it today to three main places, and these are really
your telemetry backends.
This is the final stop and the final place for it to end.
Okay?
It's an open source tool for distributed tracing.
Zipkin, also for distributed tracing, and Prometheus for metrics.
Has anybody heard of Jaeger?
Please raise your hand.
Okay, good amount.
Zipkin?
Less?
And Prometheus?
Everyone.
Amazing.
So I'm sure you heard of Prometheus at work.
I've definitely heard it many, many times before I really found out what it was.
And that's exactly what we're going to be doing today.
We're going to be creating your application, sending it to an open telemetry collector,
and then finally exporting it to these three main places.
Okay?
Keep in mind, you can send it to a lot more places.
These are just vendor neutral places.
They're open source telemetry backends that you could send it to.
But for commercial options, you have many, many, many options out there.
Any questions on the high level architecture?
Okay.
Anyone not understand anything?
Okay, let's move on.
So let's go a bit more in depth now.
What it really means.
This is exactly the same thing as this diagram.
Just much more in depth behind the scenes.
So let's start with your platform in the blue.
Your platform, you should think of it as any place where Python 3 can run.
Say an AWS EC2, a Lambda function, it doesn't matter.
Your computer, it's all the same.
Open telemetry sits in between your libraries and your application.
It sits in between.
Can anyone guess why?
Nobody has an idea.
Exactly.
It's able to intercept your libraries and it gives you, let's say you have requests,
the request library.
You don't really access your request library exactly as it is.
You access an open telemetry instrumented version of your request library.
Because it's able to intercept all of your third party libraries before you even access
them.
Any questions on the interception instrumentation?
No, it does it on the spot, on demand, right before you run your code.
So yeah, it becomes very, very easy.
That's the cool thing about Python, that it's interpreted, everything just happens on the
fly last second.
And it's scary but cool.
Go ahead.
Good question.
I guess we'll find out.
But you're right.
It's now my favorite idea that it intercepts your packages at runtime and it's able to
maybe possibly mess up and give you a dangerous version of your application.
So this is the idea of monkey patching.
And so we're making it safer and safer and we're adopting community standards to make
it as safe as possible.
Any other questions?
Both.
It's your application.
You'll do it soon.
Pretty much.
Yeah.
You'll do it on your computer locally.
So the application is any piece of Python code that runs.
It's just a very generic thing.
And yes, a question in the back?
The overhead?
A bit less today but we can go into that if you want at the end.
Definitely.
Okay.
So any questions on the interception and instrumentation?
Perfectly.
So it's able to instrument.
So what happens when you do, for example, request.get, Google.com or Bing.com or anything?
What happens is the API and SDK work together first.
And the blue and the green here, they are able to do what's called generating the trace.
And what it is is essentially a big JSON or a dictionary in Python that contains all of
the metadata about the operation or event.
And from there it's sent on to a processor.
The processor, you should think of it as simply a sort of a queue that just handles it before
it's being sent out.
From there, when it leaves this queue, it goes to an exporter which is another sort
of queue but when it leaves the exporter, it's sent out through the internet to anywhere
you want it to go.
Okay.
Usually the first stop from your application is an open telemetry collector.
You don't have to use the collector.
We'll get into it.
But the collector is sort of optional because as you see the collector also has an exporter.
So you could send it directly from your applications exporter to the telemetry backend and the
collector is optional.
But this is part of the overhead question that it reduces a lot of stress from your
application when you send it directly to the collector as local and as close as possible,
just send it out quickly.
And then all the overhead is on the collector really to do all of this.
Any questions on the application side?
Go ahead.
It's your choice.
You could configure sampling.
Go ahead.
Does it block the call?
It got you.
I'm sure there's a way to configure it, but by default, no.
It doesn't block anything.
It does it all kind of at the same time.
Anything else?
Okay.
Let's move on.
And so we'll move on to what the open telemetry collector is.
The collector is really just a place to offload really stress from your application and put
it all in the collector.
It's a different piece of architecture.
It could be, I guess, for example, its own EC2 or it could be anything else.
And it's just this tiny little thing that's able to receive traces and send it back out
to somewhere else.
So what it is is almost the exact same thing as what we see on the left.
Although instead of creating it, creating the traces and spans with the API and SDK,
we're just receiving it.
We're listening, we're listening, we're listening, and oh, we've got a trace coming from this
exporter.
From there, it's sent on to the processor, just a small queue, and there to the exporter.
And finally, it's sent to a telemetry backend, someplace that can store your data and then
also hopefully visualize it as well.
Because having just data in a database doesn't really help much.
You need a way to also see it and interact with it somehow.
So any questions at all about the architecture, high depth and low depth as well?
Okay, great.
So let's move on.
And hopefully everyone has...
Yeah, go ahead.
I've seen...
In enterprise situations, I haven't had much...
I haven't seen many problems of the collector handling stress.
I've seen in enterprise applications where they just have a really big EC2 or something
like that, and it's able to hold everything, and it does it very well.
Yeah, in the back.
Could you repeat that?
I couldn't hear.
Usually it's separate, right?
Because we want to offload as much as we can.
Today, we're going to co-host.
We're going to have the application and the collector and the backend all running on your
computer today.
Okay?
So we're able to see how it's all possible, but you could easily split it up.
And so I hope everyone here has Python 3 and Docker installed.
Does anyone not have these installed right now?
Okay.
So just make sure you have...
Are you able to run Docker Compose?
Okay.
I recommend you have Docker Desktop, but good luck if you have an alternative.
So if everyone's here on my repo...
Is anyone not on my repo right now?
Okay, perfect.
So just go to GitHub, and it's basically this.
This is the username, and this is the repo over here.
Awesome.
So this is it today.
It's basically...
Like, you could think of it as a big tutorial, a big blog post, but it's basically just 17
small steps.
We're going to do them all together.
Hopefully, stay with me for the first couple of four or five steps, and from there, you
could go at your own speed.
You can go as fast as you want.
And I think if you go fast, you could do this in around 20 or 30 minutes, and you're free
to go.
I mean, you don't have to hold you here for a couple of hours.
But you can go with me at my slow pace, and we can have a good time.
So perfect.
Let's start with prerequisites.
Number one, I want you to git clone this repository and have this locally.
Why?
Because it has a few YAMLs that are going to help you to run everything, and you don't
have to copy paste a lot of boilerplate, basically.
So just clone this, and give me a thumbs up when you're done.
Okay, awesome.
Most of the class.
We're going to take a couple seconds so we can move on.
And while we wait, I want to ask you a couple more questions about your experience in Python,
Flask, global telemetry, I guess, in general.
Who here is in their first year of learning Python?
Wow, nobody.
That's amazing.
Who here is five years or less?
Raise your hand.
Okay, small number.
And who here is 10 years or less?
Okay.
Is anyone here over 10 years?
Wow, veterans.
Thank you so much for coming.
I really appreciate it.
I have a lot to learn from you, so I'm going to ask you a couple more questions at the
end.
And who here has used Flask before?
Either at work or at home?
Okay, almost the entire class.
Amazing.
Does anyone here not know what Flask is?
Okay.
And open telemetry and observability, has anyone worked with these or is familiar with
these before they came in today?
Yes.
Did you guys just talk one sentence, I guess, about your experience?
That's amazing.
Yes?
Oh, wow.
Wow, okay.
So this is a bit more in the future, I guess.
And anyone on this side?
Yeah, definitely.
Okay.
Anyone else want to share?
Okay, perfect.
So let's jump right in.
Step one, just go into this directory, collect your demo, CD into it.
On Windows, I'm not sure, so I'm going to be using only Mac and Linux commands, okay?
I'm sorry, guys.
And step two, I want us, because we're going to be writing some really, really good code
today, to be able to write good code, you have to read good code.
So we're going to be reading some code just a tiny bit, just to understand exactly what
we're doing here.
And then from there, we're going to go on to writing, okay?
So let's start with Docker Compose.yaml.
And I have it right here.
And if we can close this.
Basically, Docker Compose.
Does anyone here not familiar with Docker or Docker Compose?
Okay.
So the entire class is familiar with Docker.
Yeah?
You're unfamiliar?
Does anyone want to explain it in a couple words, just maybe four or five words?
Okay.
So essentially, you could think of it as a tiny little VM that runs inside your computer.
And you're able to run almost any operating system or any little, I guess, base, they're
called images.
That's what the word we're going to be using.
Oh, okay, perfect.
So that's exactly what it is.
That's what Docker is.
And Docker Compose is just a way of running a bunch of images all at once on your computer.
That's all it is.
So perfect.
We're going to be running a few images together.
The first one is Jaeger.
This one is for distributed traces.
And we're going to be using Jaeger tracing slash all in one at the latest version.
And we're going to be using at these ports.
This port is the port for the UI.
When you go to your browser and you're going to be looking at it, you're going to go to
this port, 16686.
The following two ports are only for accepting traces.
So it's going to set up a little server on your computer.
It's going to be listening for traces on these two ports.
Okay?
We'll come back to these later.
Any questions on this?
Go ahead.
These two are the default, but it has a lot more default.
It has also 4317, 4318, and it has a couple.
You can configure it however you'd like.
You can also reroute it to any other port you like.
Anything else?
Okay.
That's nice.
So, Zipkin, also for distributed traces.
We're going to be using this image, openzipkin slash zipkin at the latest.
Okay?
And zipkin runs only on one port.
This is the same port for listening for spans and everything else, as well as the UI.
You're going to access it at this port, 9411.
Any questions on zipkin?
And the next is OpenTelemetryCollector.
Okay?
So this is the exact same collector that we saw over here, the exact same one, as we saw.
And the collector is...
So what we're going to be doing here is notice that the volume...
Does anyone here not know what a volume is?
Okay?
Perfect.
So we're going to be setting our local file, otelcollectorconfig.yml, and we're going to
be throwing it inside of this container at this path, slash UTC slash otelcollectorconfig.yml.
Okay?
And from there, we're going to say, hey, when you run my container, please set the config
equal to this exact same file that I just threw in the container.
Okay?
So it's our easy way of saying, my custom configuration, I want this inside of the container.
Is anyone confused about this part?
Okay, moving on.
And we've got a bunch of ports open.
Don't worry about most of these, but the one you should know is 4317.
This is where the collector is going to be listening for income expands and traces.
Okay?
4317.
And we're going to be using this port a lot today, actually.
It depends on Jaeger and zipkin to be running.
So first, those are going to be up and running, and then the collector will go up.
And then finally, Prometheus for metrics.
Okay?
We're going to be running this image from Prometheus, Prometheus at the latest version,
and we're doing the exact same thing with our volumes.
We're going to be saying, my local file, Prometheus.yml, I want it to be thrown inside of this container
at this path, slash UTC slash Prometheus slash Prometheus.yml.
Okay?
And same port.
This port is for accessing the UI, and we're going to access it pretty soon.
Any questions at all about Docker and Compose?
Go ahead.
It's why it's under the collector asking?
And it's a good question, because we'll get into actually in a minute or two.
And I just want to go over the...
So any other questions about it?
Okay.
So I want to get into the OTL collector config that we're talking about.
And this actually took me a bit to learn, and I kind of didn't understand that at first
why it was the way it was.
But when you look at the architecture, it actually makes a lot of sense.
It's comprised of three things, the receiver, the processor, and the exporter.
That's all it is.
It's only three things.
And you have to clearly explicitly define all of those in your OTL collector config.
So we're going to say, I want to receive spans by this protocol.
OTLP means Open Telemetry Protocol.
It's a standard open telemetry.
And I wanted gRPC.
gRPC is a Google protocol for compressing requests before they're being sent out.
Any questions on the receiver?
Perfect.
The processor, very simple.
We're going to use the standard batch one.
For almost everything you're going to do, you're going to use the standard batch one.
You could have some configurations if you'd like, but we're not going to do anything crazy.
And then for your exporters, we're going to have to explicitly say exactly where we want
to export it to.
The first one is Zipkin at this endpoint.
So go to the Zipkin container.
Go to this port, 9411, where it's listening.
And at this path, it's going to be listening for spans, slash API, slash V2, slash spans.
Almost every single telemetry backend will have some slash V1, slash V2, slash something
path at the end of it.
Any questions on Zipkin?
Perfect.
For Jaeger, same thing.
We're going to be saying send it to this endpoint, the Jaeger all-in-one container at port 14250.
And the TLS insecure true just means that even if there's no SSL and there's no encryption,
it's okay.
Just make the connection happen and just make it work.
And finally, Prometheus, we're going to be sending it to this endpoint, 000, which is
just localhost at 8889.
Any questions on Prometheus?
Okay, perfectly.
And finally, we're going to be using the built-in logging one.
So this just means that the collector itself is going to be logging everything that comes
in.
Okay?
Extensions, we shouldn't worry about them today, but ideally, if you're running your
own application, you're starting from tomorrow when I'm not here, you should use the health
check one.
It's pretty good.
But all of this, when you write your file, it's kind of useless if you don't define it
in your service.
The service is really what's going to be run at the very end.
So in the service, you define whatever extensions you like.
You can run...
We could remove the extensions here and it wouldn't have a major effect on us.
But you have to say within the service, I want this pipeline for traces and for metrics.
So I want...
For traces, I want to receive them with my open telemetry protocol.
I want to process them with batching.
And then I want to export it to these three places, logging, zipkin, and jaeger.
Okay?
And for metrics, almost the same thing.
I want to receive it with OTP.
I want to process it with batching.
But I'm going to export it to these two places, logging and Prometheus.
Okay?
So zipkin and jaeger for tracing, Prometheus for metrics.
Any question?
Okay.
Perfect.
So we can move on to Prometheus.yml.
This is the last one.
So Prometheus works a bit differently.
It's going to...
Instead of pushing to Prometheus, which we're going to do also, but it's also going to pull
from the collector.
So that's why we're going to basically be scraping with Prometheus.
Okay?
So we're going to say, go to this container, OTA collector, and every 10 seconds, I want
you to scrape these two static targets.
OTA collector at port 8889 and OTA collector at port 8888.
Okay?
Does that answer your question?
Because Prometheus is going to be pulling instead of pushing.
So any questions at all about these three files we just went over?
Because each one has a slightly different reason to be.
Basically we can see over here, this one is Prometheus metrics exposed by the collector.
And this is Prometheus exported itself metrics.
They're slightly different, but we can read up on more of that later.
It doesn't really have a major effect.
Anything else?
Okay.
Perfect.
So back to the readme we go.
And I have just one question for the class.
Over here, this side note.
So the main difference from the computer's perspective, not from our perspective.
Even you were the computer.
The main difference between Jaeger and Zipkin is that Zipkin runs as one process.
This includes the collector that's listening for spans, the storage of them, the querying
service, the UI, and they also did even list a few amongst others.
Okay?
All of this runs in one single process.
Jaeger is a bit newer than Zipkin.
It came out more recently.
And they introduced this concept of saying, no, we're not going to do it all in one process.
Each one is going to be a different process.
One being the collector, another being the UI, another one is the query service, and
so on.
And we can even see it over here in our files when we say in Docker Compose, for Zipkin,
we just run the Zipkin image.
But for Jaeger, we have to say we want specifically the all in one.
Every single process, I want them all together.
Can anyone guess or tell me why that is?
Why did Jaeger split it up?
Go ahead.
Scaling.
Perfect.
It's built more for distributed systems.
That's exactly it.
You can have each single process running on a different computer.
That's exactly the right reason.
Good job.
So any other questions so far?
Awesome.
You can skip this one.
And when you enter, you should be inside of the directory already, collector demo.
Just run Docker Compose up and raise all of the images together.
I'll do that with you.
So pretty viewable.
And Docker Compose up.
And cannot connect to Docker daemon.
Does anyone know what you're doing here?
Nobody?
Then I'll tell the class.
Start Docker.
Exactly.
So we have it up and running.
It's starting.
Okay.
Perfect.
How's this up?
Let's delete it.
Okay.
Perfect.
So let's run that again.
Docker Compose up.
And we should see the logs for everything come in.
This is Zipkin.
This is the collector.
We have Jaeger over here.
And so on.
And we should see Prometheus.
Prometheus as well.
Perfect.
So our logs are ready.
That means the collector is up and running along with Jaeger and Zipkin and Prometheus.
They're all up and running.
They're just listening and waiting for spans to come in.
So at this point, you can go at your own pace.
You can go as fast or as slow as you want.
But I'm here for everyone.
I'll go at the slowest pace possible.
So good luck to everyone if you're going fast.
Yes?
I did a lawyer this morning and it took about eight minutes to download everything.
For me, so it's probably just a little more.
You finished everything?
Oh, it's downloaded, yeah, but it took eight minutes.
What's downloading?
For all the images.
Oh, wow.
Just the images?
Yeah.
Okay, okay.
I'll wait for the images to be downloaded.
You have a what?
Config file, not readable.
You want me to take a look?
Okay.
Sure, just give me a thumbs up when everything's up and running and you have all the images.
So a couple.
I'll wait for everyone else.
Thanks for your patience, guys.
It turns out that the link 0, 0, 0 at the port of the telemetry backend, it might not
work if you're on Windows.
You might have to put localhost instead or 127, 0, 0, 0, 1 yourself.
So sorry about that, guys.
Sorry about the inconvenience.
So once everything's working with Docker Compose, you should be able to access it here.
I can actually push the changes locally and push it up.
I mean, as long as you have the tab open once, you can just keep it open.
Downloading, we can move on because the next steps don't require this.
So move on to step six and let me know if I can slow down and help anyone else.
So step six is our base case.
This will be our normal Python application with no instrumentation with nothing else.
We're just going to create this file once and we're not going to edit it or touch it
again.
Okay?
So we're going to create a Python file by this name.
So just to make sure I'm not mistyping, I'm just going to copy paste here.
And I'm going to do command D to split the screen.
And I'm going to be doing this a couple more times because it's very, very helpful and
useful.
So in our directory, I'm going to be creating this file with touch.
And then over here, just cleaning up a little bit.
So we're going to be repeating this step.
We're going to create our file with touch.
Once we have that file, we'll go in.
We'll just copy exactly as it is.
Does anyone not understand what this file does?
Can someone please raise your hand and explain?
You don't even have to raise your hand.
Just explain to me exactly what this file does.
Yeah, exactly.
Exactly.
I couldn't have said it better myself.
It sets up an API with two endpoints, slash and slash error.
That's all it does.
For slash, it will return hello world from our plain Flask app.
In slash error, we'll do some arithmetic that's a bit hard for the computer to do.
And we're going to be running this locally at port 5000.
I'm not sure about Windows.
If you have to change this to localhost or 127.001, then please feel free to do so.
But on Mac and Unix and Linux, it should work.
Okay, I understand.
So we'll do that when we get there.
We'll change it for the Windows users.
We'll change it to the right thing.
So in our file, I'm just going to be dumping this all in.
And that's it.
And let's install our dependencies.
The only thing we have is Flask.
So let's clear this.
I'm going to be using a virtual environment.
You don't have to.
If you don't know what it is, it's okay.
You don't have to worry about it.
Just install it normally as you would.
So I'm installing Flask, our only requirement up till now.
And it's installed.
And let's go back and do this exactly as it says.
Open two terminals.
So make sure you have two empty terminals.
You have your collector here and one more.
So I have top and bottom.
You could have it side to side.
You could have it diagonal and swirly and whatever you like.
So on one of them, we're going to be running our Flask base.
And I have to do allow to accept incoming connections.
And we're up and running.
Of course, this will make the collector a bit smaller.
We don't really need to look at it.
It'll just be for fun.
And we see that we have exactly this.
On localhost port 5000, we have these two endpoints.
So we could curled localhost.
But what it really is, is has anyone near not used curled before
and not know what it is?
Okay, perfect.
So we'll just do as it is.
We're calling localhost at port 5000.
Slash.
And we'll return our string, hello world.
You could do with that the slash as well.
It's the exact same thing.
Hello world.
We're able to see over here that two connections came in,
a get from this address, and they returned the 200 for both of them.
When we reach an endpoint we don't know, for example, unknown,
we'll get this weird HTML.
And that's because it's...
Can anyone tell me why it returns HTML?
Why does it not just return an error message?
That's default function.
Again?
That's default function for my class right there.
Exactly.
But why is it HTML?
Why is it not just a string that says, hey, here's your error
with the stack trace?
It's currently default to say that it's not a track trace.
Oh, okay, okay.
So I think it could change it.
So I don't know.
I didn't know they could change it.
But from what I understood, it's really because it's meant to be opened
in the browser, and now it makes sense that it's HTML.
Oh, it's not found, it's nice and readable,
and it makes much more sense.
So when we reach something we don't know, we get a 404,
and we don't really know why it's known or unknown,
and then when we reach something that we know will cause an error
and the computer will struggle with this one,
we get a big error message, 500 internal server error.
We get a big error stack trace over here.
But let's say, for example, we're looking only at this screen
because you're the user, right, and you reach some website
and you get this 500 internal server error.
I want you to answer a couple questions for me, okay?
One, I want you to tell me what happened.
You're the client, okay?
You only have access to this little pane right here
that we're looking at.
This is all you see.
You know what?
Let's do it even on Chrome.
So we'll go to localhost.port 5000.
It works, and then when we reach here, look at this.
So tell me a few things.
One, what happened?
Two, why did the request fail?
Can anyone tell me?
Just from looking at this, why did the request fail?
Or, so there's no definite answer.
We don't know.
Nobody knows.
I want you to tell me, did the server crash, yes or no?
No?
But it looks like it did.
Internal server error.
It looks like there's an error in the server.
But if you look at the same URL again,
it's still running.
Would you know without retrying?
Without retrying again.
Would you be able to tell me?
But even if it came back correctly,
you wouldn't know if it subsequently crashed either.
True.
You're right.
That's a fair point.
So next question.
Is the server still up and running?
Because it just returned a big server.
You just told me it's overloaded.
You're telling me now it's up and running?
So what is it?
Is it up and running or is it down and crashed?
So nobody knows.
Is my application still working or do I need to restart it now?
Do we need to restart Flask in order for it to work now?
No?
How do you know?
Unknown.
Exactly.
We kind of have no idea.
Nobody knows.
Even when you work over here and you work in the company
and you're able to see the logs,
you also still don't really know.
And it's really not enough.
You only get maybe 20% of the painting
and even that's a bit blurry.
So this way we need open telemetry.
We win this firsthand that we need some observability
to help us debug and figure out exactly what's happening here.
So we'll move on to the manual instrumentation case.
If you see over here in our directory over here,
in our table of contents, we have a few cases.
We started with the base case and this we finished already.
This is just by having a Flask app.
Sometimes it works, sometimes it doesn't work
and we don't really know why.
We're going to go over three main instrumentation cases.
The first one is manual.
This is by hand we're going to be doing it.
The second one is contrib.
The contrib contains all of our favorite extensions
and libraries and support and automatically instruments
all of them for us.
And the last one is the coolest,
the no code instrumentation case.
Okay, so we're going to be jumping straight into the manual
and let's figure out what it means.
So as I said, it's the hardest with the safest
and you have the most control over exactly
what's happening to your application.
So I want you to create this file just by copying
the Flask base into this file.
So we kind of have Flask base in a new file now.
You can do by hand, you can copy all the contents over.
So I'm going to do Ctrl C to end this and get out of it
and running that command.
Is anyone confused about this part?
We're just creating a new file with the same contents.
And we're installing our dependencies.
Just like we talked about earlier,
we're installing directly the API, the SDK
and the exporter that we want.
We want the OTL P exporter.
So we can copy this directly.
PIP to install.
Just three small little things.
Bless you.
It will take a second, but eventually it will finish.
And this is why the manual one is so hard.
Because while they don't call it boilerplate,
I'll call it boilerplate because it's a lot of code
you're just going to have to copy over and over every time.
So we'll do this once and we'll see just how fun it is.
It's not so fun.
Imagine you were typing all of this by hand.
Which I've actually done several many times.
So for the manual, we're going to be closing Flask base.
And I want to go into the manual.
And I'm going to basically just drop all of this at the very top.
And I don't like the disemboll to the bottom.
So I'm kind of moving the import at the top.
That's it.
And that's it.
I have a bunch of imports for OpenTelemetry and Flask.
I've defined exactly what I'm going to send it to.
So, gentlemen in the back, you said that you need to change this 00
on Windows to localhost, correct?
Okay, awesome.
Thank you.
So everyone on Windows, sorry you have to change this by yourself
to localhost for it to work.
But on Linux and Mac it should work.
So we send it to 4317.
Can anyone tell me what's at 4317?
That's the?
The collector, exactly.
Our collector is listening for spans at 4317.
It's waiting for something to come in.
And then it's going to send it back out.
So every service you can define a name, and if you don't say
it's going to be unknown service, we're going to call it
MyFlaskAppInProductionManual.
Okay, so every single case we're going to be doing is going to
have a different service name, and that way we're going to be
able to differentiate at the end.
So you first have to create the resource.
Then you have to create a trace provider with the same resource.
You have to define exactly where you want to export it to.
So I'm going to create it, and the exporter is tied to the processor as well.
So we're going to create one batch span processor that's going to
export it to the console.
This is our standard output.
And we're going to add that processor to our trace provider.
We're going to do the exact same thing for the OTL collector,
although instead of the exporter to the console, we're going to use
OTL-P span exporter.
This is the exporter for native OpenTelemetry protocol spans at
this endpoint that we've just defined, localhost at port 4317.
We add that one as well to the provider.
We set the trace provider.
We finally create the tracer.
And so I would definitely define this as boilerplate, and this is
definitely not so easy, but you have as much control as you want
over the application, and you have choice to do whatever you'd like.
So no, we're not repeating anything, actually.
So in the configuration file, you're referring to the OTL
collector configuration, right?
This is before it even reaches.
This is to make sure it reaches the collector.
You do all of this to just instrument and generate the spans,
and we send it to the collector.
From there, it's going to be processing and exporting to our backends.
Does that make sense?
Yeah, but in this case, what we're setting up, you're right.
It's exactly the case.
You have to know exactly what the collector is waiting for, and you
have to send that exact same thing.
If you send a mismatch, you're going to get an error message.
It's going to be some hidden message that you're going to get
back to the collector.
And then you can send it to the operator.
So this is the same thing that we're sending to the operator.
So we're sending the error message to the collector.
It's going to be some hidden, mysterious message, and only then
you're going to figure out, oh, I'm sending the wrong protocol in.
It's not accepting, and it's rejecting my spans.
That's a great question, actually.
Anything else?
Okay, perfect.
So over there, we create the tracer, and we create the app.
And you think, okay, that was a lot of code.
Are we at least done?
No.
We still haven't even created the spans ourselves yet, because
we're still in the manual way.
We have to create the spans.
So this entire hello world, I'm going to be replacing our
function at the bottom with this.
And we'll go over it exactly what it does.
We're going to be saying, at this path, I want to define this
function hello.
And what it does is, immediately we're going to be creating a
span root, and we use the with one to make sure that we don't
have to open and close it.
Everything inside of it is just automatically inside of the
span.
So we're going to be doing the same thing for the other
message.
We're just going to be creating a file and so on.
So we create a current span, and we give it a name root,
because every span has a name.
And you can add an event if you'd like.
I can just call it root event.
You can add anything you'd like there.
And finally, you have hello world from our manually
instrumented Flask app.
And does anyone have any questions with this so far?
What does it mean to create our own span, the name, anything
else?
So it's the exact same thing for the other message.
We're just going to be creating our span and adding an event
and so on.
So step nine, we're going to test it and run it.
I'm going to run this file, the instrumentation manual file.
And it's up.
And here I'm going to curl my local host at a port 5000.
And we should see a few things here.
One is we got a response.
Two, because we sent the exporter in our application to
print the logging and to send it to the collector, we see
inner logs over here.
Can anyone guess and tell me what this big JSON is, this big
document?
Does anybody know?
Exactly.
This is the span.
This is what we're looking at.
We're looking at the span.
So we're going to run this file.
And we're going to run this file.
And this is the span.
This is what we're looking at.
We're looking at the span that just happened.
And that's the name root, exactly what we did.
And it's got a context.
So the context is very important to worry about.
Because this can be very, very hard when you're doing things
manually.
Basically, every span, like I said, belongs to a bigger
family, which is called a trace.
He could be alone in the family.
He could have siblings.
He could have parents and so on.
So he has a trace ID, which is almost like the span's last
name.
And he's got his own unique span ID.
This is the span's first name, essentially.
It's unique within the trace.
OK?
So if he has, for example, children's span and so on,
they'll have the same exact trace ID, but different and
unique span IDs.
Our kind, for example, and so on, our span kind is internal.
This is when you don't set your kind.
It'll default to internal.
So this is kind of mysterious as to what exactly does this
mean?
And it's because when you do do it, you should set the span
and you should define everything as well.
And that's the problem with doing things manually.
Sometimes you don't know exactly 100% what to do and how
to fix everything.
And that's why sometimes it's best to leave it up to the
contrib in the later versions we'll see.
Our parent ID is no, meaning there are no parent spans to
this span.
And this is the first span in the trace, if there is no
parent ID.
We've got a start time and end time.
Our status code is unset, even though we did return 200, the
span does not know anything about it.
And the span says that our status code is unset and
unknown, basically.
Our attributes are empty.
And we've got one event, a root event that we created, and at
least we got the timestamp of when we did it.
And we've got no links, but at least we're able to capture the
service name of my flask app in production manual.
The same thing happened over here on this side of the
collector.
It said, hey, I got an image of my flask app in production
manual.
And we got the same thing over here on this side of the
collector.
It said, hey, I got an incoming span, I got a trace that was
exported to me, and the number of spans that I received was
one.
So if we bring this back, and for example, we just send a
bunch of spans, we now see over here the number of spans that
came in was six, and the number of spans that came in was seven.
And so this is by the batching.
It sends in as fast as it can, it sends it out, and it just
hopes to not overload the collector with too many.
So the collector will, and the same with the application as
well, the application doesn't want to hold too many spans in
its queues.
It wants to just get rid of it as fast as it can.
So it'll get rid of it, the collector will try to get rid
of it as fast as it can, and finally it'll send it to the
telemetry backend.
So we've got this, and we're able to curl, and it works.
But what happens if we curl an unknown endpoint?
Unknown.
Well, we've got this.
We've got the 404 here.
But do we at least see the span for the 404?
That's something I don't know, and we'll have to find out.
And what about if I do the error?
Will we at least see the error in the span?
And so we can come back here.
And so we got our successful response with 500.
We got an unsuccessful response with 500 slash error.
And it's time to look at the spans.
We can open over here, and we can see the error.
We can actually see the error.
So we can come back here.
And we can look at the spans.
We can open over here.
By the way, for Windows users, you have to change this to
localhost manually, because I put the link in at 000.
And it won't work for you, so sorry.
You have to go to localhost.
So we've got Jaeger over here.
And Jaeger looks like this.
It's got a cute little animal.
And we can define by the service, since we know exactly
the name, myflaskapp and production manual, we can find
errors only for that service.
And we can say some have errors.
We see that.
And some don't have errors, and some won't work.
So let's look at ones that didn't have errors.
Let's see what we can see.
Okay, we've got proto.
Our library name is main.
And our span kind is internal.
I don't know.
Not a lot of information.
At least we got some logs.
Okay, we can see the root event.
But does anyone know what just happened in the application?
Can anyone tell me?
I'm kind of lost, too.
There's not much information here at all.
And that's because it's up to you, when you're doing it
manually, to add all this information.
And imagine it would take a lot more time to make sure that
you're capturing every event, every error, you're tagging it,
and everything else coming in.
And let's look at the ones with errors.
So okay, at least we captured a few more tags.
We got that error is true.
And we at least captured the error message that it was
zero division error, division by zero.
It didn't really tell us where, when, or why.
But at least we got some logs.
And okay, at least it was able to capture our traceback for us.
And we can say, okay, it's probably on line 44 we got this error.
And is that the case?
It is.
So we got something, right?
But we don't know everything about the request coming in.
We're kind of left in the dark.
And we don't really know much.
Are there any questions about this, about the manual?
Okay, so we got some logs.
And we can see the error message.
Are there any questions about this, about the manual?
Or are we looking at the spans here?
Okay.
So as we saw, there's not much information here at all.
It's kind of, kind of looking in the dark, I guess.
So that's Yeager.
We can look at Zipkin.
And we can say, you can add by this red thing,
you can say, my service name, I want to look at only for spans
with my Flask app and production manual.
And we can just search for those to begin with.
We can see a bunch came in with errors.
And, oh no, sorry, is that even?
Yep, it is.
So we see over here, this is our timeline.
It's kind of hard to look at.
And over here, at least we captured the error.
We can say, exception escaped false.
And at least we got some sort of traceback,
even though it's very, very hard to read.
Does it even say the line?
Line 44, if you look very, very closely,
it's kind of hard to understand what's happening here.
At least we got the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the,
the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the,
at least we got the, the, the, the status code
and at least the status description,
but it's not much at all.
And on the Prometheus side,
Can you, how did you put in the service name so quickly?
The service name?
In Zipkin here.
I had to refresh it.
Yeah, I thought I would refresh it exactly beyond that.
So you might need to do that.
You might need to refresh.
I clicked the red and I went to service name
and yeah, is this what happened to you guys?
It auto-completed this?
Okay.
Does it work after a refresh?
Awesome.
So good job, good job everyone else.
Good job here.
Any questions on Jaeger or Zipkin about the traces?
Yeah.
Yeah, I would say, I would say they're both not the best in the world,
but I would say Jaeger is definitely much better than Zipkin at least.
It's also newer and I think people are still working on it.
Anything else?
Okay.
And on the Prometheus side, if you don't know any Prometheus expressions,
you can click this globe over here and you can ask all sorts of questions.
For example, and this is mainly about the physical infrastructure
it's going to be related.
So we're not too worried about right now,
but for example, the collector process uptime we can say,
and I want to graph that.
And so you get this big, big request,
but you're able to graph it and you see that since time is linear,
okay, at least it works.
But we can ask questions about the CPU and all sorts of things.
So any questions on the manual case?
Okay.
On a scale of 1 to 10, can you rate how much fun the manual case was?
No.
Not fun, thumbs down, I would say maybe like a 2 out of 10 at the very best.
So thank you, thank you.
The manual case is very, very hard.
A lot of boilerplate, not much fun.
And we're about to see what fun is.
Step two, we're going to go on to the contrib instrumentation case.
And we're kind of doing the exact same thing.
I want you to take your base
and I want you just to copy it over to this contrib file.
So we're kind of just building on top of the same code we know.
And so I'll do this.
And so I'll copy the file over.
I'll pip install only this one thing.
And this is the instrumentation for the contrib.
Open telemetry instrumentation flask.
So all of your favorite third party tools and libraries,
they all have instrumentations in the contrib repository
and you just install them and it works just like magic.
So let's paste that in.
And I'm sorry about the boilerplate in this one.
I guess it is possible with environment variables
but it is better to do it this way, just one time.
So I'm going to go ahead and paste that in.
And I'm going to go ahead and paste that in.
And I'm going to go ahead and paste that in just one time.
So, oh, and also for Windows users,
this is a place to watch out and change this to localhost.
So I'll close our manual.
And I'll go to the contrib.
And I'll add the boilerplate at the top again.
And but what it's doing is it's saying
I want to import the same exact things
but additionally the flask instrumenter, just one class.
And then I'm going to set these two environment variables
equal to essentially true in a way you can think of it
but it's regex so we'll get into that.
So what it says is for my OTA instrumentation,
for every HTTP call,
I want you to capture the headers of the server request
and the server response.
And it's going to be set true to whatever matches
with the regex.
And so we say dot star,
it captures everything.
And then I'm going to set the same thing
dot star, it captures everything.
Any questions on this?
Okay.
Perfect. We're going to say on the endpoint
we're going to be sending it to the collector again,
4317, but this time with a different service name.
MyFlaskAppInProductionContrib
so that way we have differentiated
and we're able to see which spans are better and worse.
Same exact thing, we're going to be sending it
to standard output as well as the collector over here.
Right? Nothing new.
And then you say,
okay, what else is there?
Only one line.
After you create your application,
you go into the Flask Instrumentation,
you say, take this application
and instrument it for me.
So you go over here
and boom, this is all the work.
We don't touch anything else, your code remains the same.
So imagine
you can write your code and you can just
even have the boilerplate on a different file
and you can just import everything else and it will work.
So let's test it out.
By the way, any questions so far on this
and what we did over here?
An ID? Okay, perfect.
So let's run our contrib file.
We're running the contrib
and we can curl our localhost
at 5000.
Now I want this to print
over here as well as over here
and look at this, this is a much bigger span
than what we just did.
It's even captured the exact path that we just did.
So it captured the path.
It's captured the fact that it's a server as well.
It was able to
well it didn't set the status code yet
but it did capture everything else about the request.
It got the get, it got the fact that
we went to 000,
it got the fact that it was HTTP, it got the port
and it got pretty much everything else
as well as the headers, would you believe it?
It even captured the status code.
So why was it able to get it?
I learned it was a proper way to
instantify it
but you barely went down that one step.
Why wasn't that there?
At the top here? I'm actually not sure.
We can get into that. That's interesting.
That's a good one.
But as you see it was captured over here.
So I'm sure there's a way that we could do that.
And they got our service name as well.
And over here we say that we got
one span coming into the collector
and so on.
So we can do the same thing.
We can ping an unknown endpoint.
We can do it a bunch.
Just be careful not to do that on your computer.
And from there we go
we'll do the error
and I want to spam it with errors as well.
And we see
six spans came in, ten spans came in
thirteen and so on.
And we can go back over here.
We did a successful, we did an unsuccessful
and it's time
to check what happened.
We'll go back into Jaeger
and same thing over here as you experienced here.
We do need to refresh in some cases.
And boom we got a new service coming in.
And we now have two services.
The manual and the contrib.
So let's check out the contrib one.
And we'll find traces.
And you'll see you can even change it by operation
you can check.
You can check by the traces that came into slash
the traces that came into error
and again we made as well.
So let's see what it looks like
without an error.
And this is again, let's see.
Interesting.
So that's good.
Okay, okay.
So even now I'm learning something on the spot now.
So whatever we made to slash was sent to slash
and it returned a successful response.
Okay, and we're able to see everything that came in.
We got the fact that it was in a get
to localhost 5000.
We got all of our headers, the accept, host, user agent, everything else.
We got the status code and so on.
We're even able to see the fact that
it's open telemetry with this flask instrumentation
at this exact version and so on.
And everything that came in
to slash error
was an error but at least the trace was sent
to the collector and we got the trace.
And it captures a little bit more information.
It tells us the fact that it was an error.
The same exact things about the request and the response.
We got at least the error message.
But here in our logs if we go
we didn't get the full trace back as well.
So we got the full trace back for there.
We got all of the headers as well.
And I think body is something that's coming up soon.
In fact we're able to also collect the entire body.
And yeah go ahead.
Can I ask you now,
another thing that's on the top of the presentation.
How does this work when you're running a full on app
where you can go in and basically come up with a
new message and then you can actually
go in and actually send it to the user.
So that's a really cool thing.
So I think that's a really cool thing.
It should look pretty much the same.
But we can feel free to test it in
I think from Unicorn.
Whatever is instrumented.
Whatever the instrumentation is
is where it's going to send
is exactly what's going to send it to the collector.
And from there it will be sent over here.
So I just want to pause for a second.
And I want to see if anyone has any questions.
Anything else?
But else I'm going to go ahead and ask you
anything else.
But I also want us to appreciate the fact that
we just did all of this.
You guys did it, not me. You guys did it yourselves.
You guys ran all of this.
You co-hosted it on your own computer.
And good job everyone. It's not easy.
And you did an amazing thing. This is much more than you guys realize.
And it's a big deal.
So,
good job everyone.
And so we just got a few spans over here.
And so we looked at slash.
We looked at slash, we looked at slash error.
And everything that came in
that wasn't a defined endpoint
is just defined as HTTP GET by default.
And we can look at that.
And so these are the 404s that we did to slash unknown.
We see the fact that
it went to slash unknown.
It was a 404.
So we can't say exactly what target it was because it's an unknown target.
We don't know what slash unknown is.
It's just a GET we'll call it.
But it captures everything else the same.
Okay, on a scale of 1 to 10,
how much fun was the contrib instrumentation?
Slightly better.
Okay, maybe a 5.
Yeah?
So this is an interpreting class
if you're running like
two blocks away or something.
Database queries and that kind of thing.
Do you have to do those separately or will
the whole thing fall?
I'm assuming it.
For the contrib version?
Yeah, what was that?
So how are they related together with your instrument?
Yeah, it works very well together.
This is the purpose.
Not to disrupt anything.
So the whole point of monkey patching
and wrapping all your code is that
if anything breaks down, it's open telemetry
that's breaking down.
We don't want to break your application.
We want everything to run as smoothly and as possible as it can.
And so if something's going to fail,
it's going to be open telemetry and at least
maybe you won't get a trace,
but it's open telemetry that's breaking down.
So if you want to do, for example,
we'll be over here with Flask Instrumenter.
And say for example, you're using also Mongo
and Redis and all these databases
and anything else. Same exact thing.
It's one line to import
and then only one line just to instrument
for the contrib way.
For the contrib way, you do have to import
and also initialize the class.
Yeah?
So I don't have to instrument
one thing or the other,
but something that calls
for a term that's not appropriate.
When I get child's band
based on
Flask app,
do you get information about my
service model? Exactly.
This is the whole point of distributive trace.
That's an amazing question. We won't get too deep
into that just yet. Maybe if we have time at the end
we can go into that. But that's an amazing question.
That's the whole point. Is that every service
should ideally be requested, should be instrumented.
And that way you can see the distributive trace
and start from here, start from your
application, go to Redis,
go to Flask, go to anything else, and so on.
So yeah, that's exactly it.
This is the whole point, is that
you can use eBPF if everything's
running on the same computer, but it's a bit harder
once everything is in a distributed environment.
Any other questions?
Yeah?
Is there
a recommendation on
the non-save users
that have like
one great, like one
parent that has
5,000 fans
at the same time?
So, great question.
It's ideally as many fans
as you can get, right? If you can have
3,000, yeah, why not? But
I've actually seen a few, even commercial limitations,
where it's just too big,
the request coming in is way too big to handle.
And so, yeah,
we do need to do better work to keep up on that.
So, I was actually at a
different commercial offering
for something like this, and we actually told the customer
like, way too many spans for the trace,
like, it's just impossible to keep up with.
So, but yeah, ideally as many
as you can, you can have, because
really, it's just a story of how a request
propagates through your system.
And if your system is huge and it has all these components,
you wouldn't want to be missing a piece, right?
Yeah?
So, what do you mean by
in-flight request?
So, if you have a request
for an API that takes like
an hour for a return on a clock,
that's probably why.
Do you get information about
in-flight requests
or does it only
cost us to monitor
on returns, nowhere?
What do you mean in-flight requests?
Let's say for some reason, you have
data and download all of these
and delete it, and that's how it applies.
Can you see how many of those
are in-flight while they're in-flight?
Do you have to wait until the failure
to do the show-down
with the return
ground? I haven't tried it, but
I think, currently for open telemetry, you have
to wait for something to finish, and then you'll see it.
I think that
is the case. It has to wait for the failure to succeed
and then. Which was then?
Yeah.
Would I explain with this
the spans are sent
by each service
and they're combined by the
collectors so you would see
the in-flight of and if you
can't refresh more data, they're showing up?
That's exactly the case.
That's the whole point. Since each one is
distributed, that's exactly what you said
over here. So say you have an application
that
pings this one
with requests. This one goes to request, this is
the flask, and then it goes even up to
Redis for example. Each one would send
a different span to the collector and it's up to the
collector to piece all of it together and to put
it into a unified trace.
Exactly.
True. True. Exactly.
So also the case
is that it's kind of a race condition. If you
check, for example, the hotel collector
or your telemetry backend, when this one's
finished but this one hasn't
or vice versa, then you could see
an incomplete trace, of course.
Because the span just hasn't
come in yet.
These are excellent questions.
Anymore?
Yeah?
Oh, definitely. We can do this with Yeager.
And we could say, for example, max
duration, min duration as well.
We can do this also with Zipkin as well.
And we could say for this service
I want to see things with max duration
or min duration as well.
Right.
I would want to be alert
to some number of
requests of
X number of packets.
And I don't think Yeager is doing that.
So we have the full
metrics in the
full alert. Is there any way to set
those metrics
to the time series database?
Yeah. Well, everything
is sent to Prometheus as well.
Which is a time series database. But
I don't know if what you're saying about having
an alert and things like that. I don't know if it's possible with these
vendor neutral options. You might have to go to a commercial option.
Yeah?
OpenHolinger is designed to send to a lot of
commercial options too. So you can
basically send it to Elastic Surgery wherever you
are in the shop and most of the places
to support it.
That's an option too. You don't have to use Yeager.
You can use Elastic Surgery to
swap other things. Exactly.
Yeah?
Question about the automatic
instrumentation for
streaming responses
over your government regenerative responses
and your government's response to the
authority for getting file uploads and
streaming up. How does that
go with the
data?
You were also coding it yourself.
That's an excellent question.
So these are excellent questions, guys.
I've actually never even tested downloading
something huge and having a trace with open telemetry.
We can test it at the very end if we have time.
That sounds excellent.
Both.
I'm sure there's a way. I'm sure there's a way to do it.
It's designed to be as flexible as you want.
So we can get into that.
That's very, very interesting.
Anything else?
Okay.
On that point,
the question that I would have is
with the automated
communication
how would you get access
to generate
shout spans?
To generate shout spans?
You still have all the flexibility
of the manual way.
We still have the trace provider. We can create the tracer.
And we can still do create span here inside.
So, yeah,
the Flask instrument, although it makes things easier,
we didn't give up anything to be able to use it.
We can use everything
in parallel and have both.
Does that make sense?
Yeah?
Exactly.
It's not giving you?
That's an excellent question.
So we still have the trace provider, right?
We have to keep this in mind.
Basically, when a request comes in,
its entry point will be this hello function.
Do you agree?
And so everything inside of here will be inside of the Flask instrumentation.
But from here, if we say, for example,
it won't be exactly this,
but it'll be like tracer.startspan.
And then we do like with, for example.
And we do whatever code we want in here.
This code will be inside of this new span.
You can call this, for example, Redis.
By the way, there is a Redis instrumenter
and everything else, and also AWS and everything else.
But let's say there's something that we don't have an instrumenter for.
We could create a span inside here.
But it's important to keep in mind,
this is a brand new span
with this brand new information.
It's completely blank.
But it is a child span of this span over here.
The hello and this slash.
So this is the hierarchy.
It wouldn't be a parallel.
One is clearly the parent of another.
Yeah, amazing question, guys.
Any more?
Okay, amazing.
We're actually nearing the end, guys.
And I'm guessing this table over here
is pretty much finished, right?
I would like to see Prometheus.
What's the latest thing?
You showed something briefly before.
I don't know if it's perfect or bad.
Yeah.
Only because Prometheus, it wouldn't capture everything much
than about the trace, per se.
We could convert the traces to metrics.
But that would take quite a bit of effort here.
So what it really contains
is mostly about
the physical architecture
and the physical infrastructure
of the ultracollector.
So for example, we have
we can look at the queue size and queue capacity.
We can look at how many spans were sent.
We can look at, yeah?
I'm sorry.
How do you pull those down?
How do you get those?
Oh, so over here
I have my bar.
And so it's the globe here on the right side.
And so you can look at
you can look very deep into the physical architecture
that's running the collector.
For our purposes, it's not so exciting
because we're mostly interested about traces, right?
Yeah, exactly.
You could do just that
and then send them in.
So that's the whole point.
You could do just that
and then send them into Prometheus.
I've seen that happen before, yeah?
Of course, the request contains everything
about the start time and end time
and the creation itself.
So of course, you don't have to pull everything at once.
You could group it however you'd like it.
Does that answer your question?
Okay.
Anything else?
Do you guys want me to go more into Prometheus?
I mean, this is pretty much it.
Okay.
We can see exactly
some pretty cool things.
For example, the collector.
The process has been up.
We can execute that one.
And we can see it's been up
for
over 3000 seconds.
So good job, guys.
So
because it's time series,
just monotonically...
Yeah, exactly.
But as we have it right now,
there's not so much interesting information here.
That's the only issue.
What's the most interesting
thing about the matrix
that are related to the application rather than
the
With Omotelemetry?
In Prometheus, of course.
Oh, so we can look at it...
I think now we can look at it.
The response time?
Yeah, we can look at that soon.
But the exporter,
QCapacity, QSize,
so sense bands.
For example, we can look at...
empty, I guess.
Oh.
And so we see we've sent
58 spans, for example.
We can see how many failed
by failed spans
or failed requests.
And if we execute this one, we have...
It says zero, but I don't know about that.
So, if you were to convert the path
of the application and
give it the ground of the QLQS
for the class here...
Yeah, of course.
I just don't believe that the path
was sent in over here.
Yeah, it wasn't.
But once the path, for example, we send the trace,
we convert the trace to a metric and do that,
of course we could do that.
And this is the query language.
This is PromQL here at the bottom.
Whoever doesn't know it.
But I want this specific instance.
I want you to look at this specific job
and this service instance ID.
For example, this service...
So that's the only thing.
We've pointed Prometheus only at the collector,
not at the application.
Yeah?
Q. Converting the trace to the metric,
is that all automated anywhere
or is that all at-hoc
currently by the application itself?
A. Yeah.
I'm not sure about the details, but I think
it's all automated.
I just haven't seen it firsthand.
Yeah?
Q. So at the beginning, someone asked
whether or not OpenTelemetry
supported sampling as opposed to
just all the tracing every request.
How do you configure that?
A. Yeah.
I mean, let's see. I did see that it was released
pretty recently, the head tail sampling.
So let's see. We have
OpenTelemetry. We're going to Google it together, guys.
And we're going to see what's new.
Because things come out every day.
This is the cool thing. This was released
in March of 2020.
So...
Let's see.
And over here.
I don't know.
Let's see, guys.
Let's see.
It doesn't say here.
But let's continue at the end.
Yeah?
Q. So what's the process
of the process coming?
Is that some sort of
feature that's happening between the collector
and the Prometheus?
What's
up side?
A. It's just how long the process has been up
and how long it's been running.
Q. So that's the last process of the process?
A. No. This is what's important.
The collector. Because if you look over here
in our collector demo,
Prometheus YAML, we've pointed
Prometheus only at the collector.
So...
Q. So that doesn't necessarily mean the app is up for that?
It goes to the collector?
A. Correct. We'd have to point this to the application.
But for now it's pointed only at the collector,
so we're looking only at the collector for metrics.
Q. So in response to your
question right at the start,
like how do I tell if my app is
broken, needs to be restarted?
What would your go-to
metrics be, or your go-to
app, given the tools
that you've shown us and that we've implemented?
How do you answer that question?
A. Yeah. That's exactly it.
I would send the
metrics to the collector as well.
Just a bit more, sorry.
Q. So given everything that's set up, how do you answer the question
what's wrong? You've got an error page.
You've got all these metrics
announced. Which one do you look at?
A. My go-to is always traces,
number one. I jump to Jaeger, but
that's the thing. That if Jaeger says
there hasn't been any traces for the last hour,
then I would go to, I would resort to this.
That's why it's kind of more of a backup. But traces are really number one.
That's true, but sometimes traces are generated
without you getting a response back.
It could be that one's working and one's not.
So it's not a definite yes or no.
Exactly.
At least you'll get something. You'll be able to see, oh, it's an error right there.
Even if the user sees
page destroyed,
there's no application, you'll probably still get traces.
But yeah, traces
number one, and then metrics as a resort,
and then logs
finally, if there's nothing.
If everything looks healthy apart from slash error,
which looks sick, then I would be in the
confused, like, isn't this healthy?
Isn't this? Exactly. Yeah.
Yeah, that's exactly what we do.
We'll go over here, and
yeah.
It looks a bit hard to do in these.
Oh, over here. I'll do area equals true.
Sorry guys, I'm not too familiar with these. I'm more familiar with a few commercial options,
so I've tried to remain
vendor neutral today and stay open source.
But over here we do area equals true.
You would look at what came up, and let's say
it was a couple minutes ago, you say, oh, I got a trace
right there. And what's the error?
At least you have an idea now of what happened.
And then also, if you're also capturing user data,
you could see, you would have, for example,
user.email, for example, or user.username.
Oh, this is exactly the user that was affected
by this error and this and that.
And so at least you have some context as to
not just, oh, it broke, but it broke for this
user when you clicked this button.
Oh, yeah. So.
Over here in tags, I just
said area equal to true.
And let's see how helpful this question mark is.
Yeah, so we can do a few things.
And I saw a question over here.
We'll start with the one on the right.
Yeah, right now. Sorry, sorry.
We just got a bit distracted.
Sure, yeah, let's do that.
Let's do that right now.
Let's actually do it in the no-code.
That would be pretty fun.
Okay, so any more questions
before the no-code?
Okay, perfect.
So the first one, the
manual way that was not so much fun.
It was a one or a two out of ten at most, right?
By your definition, not by mine.
And the contrib was a bit better.
At least it was at least four or five.
At least we got some more information.
But it was still defined, still needed some boilerplate.
And so let's go over here.
We'll come back.
And we're ready for step 14.
The no-code instrumentation.
Now this could be a bit heavy on your computer.
It could take some time to download everything.
But you kind of need to pip install this
OpenTelemetryDistro package.
We've installed it.
And then we just need to run this command.
What this does, OpenTelemetryDistro,
when you install it, it installs a CLI command
called OpenTelemetry Bootstrap.
And when you run it with install,
I believe minus A means all, to install all of them.
And this could take a few
seconds or maybe even a minute on your computer.
And it'll install all of the
contrib instrumentations manually.
Or automatically meaning.
So urlib3,
we got request earlier,
we got everything else.
So OpenTelemetry instrumentation request.
So exactly. So we'll do this in the no-code.
We'll get the waterfall.
And yeah, an excellent question by the way
about the waterfall.
We've got gfpc.
Is everyone here, is anyone waiting for this to finish?
Okay, perfect. Let's move on.
Step 15.
And so we got this long, long, long command.
And so when you install this bootstrap and you do install,
I believe also when you,
I believe it's here actually at this stage.
When you do pip install OpenTelemetryDistro,
it installs two main CLI tools.
One is OpenTelemetry Bootstrap.
And what is OpenTelemetry Instrument?
OpenTelemetry Instrument is for Python,
you can basically wrap your
Python command with OpenTelemetry Instrument
and have the benefits of the contrib
but without touching anything in the source code.
So what we're doing here is
we're doing OpenTelemetry Instrument
and we're defining our trace exporter.
I want to send it exactly like we did earlier.
I want to send it to Othelpy
and I want to send it to my console as well
and print it out.
I'm going to define my service name
and I want it to be MyFlaskInProductionAuto.
So this is a new one.
So we can see a brand new service
and you're going to define exactly where
we're going to send it to for my
Othelpy endpoint and that's going to be
localhost 4317.
I believe this is
already suitable for Windows users because
it's already localhost.
And then we also attach it to the base.
So we're not running Python 3 separately.
This is part of the same command.
And this is the command that I used
to run Python.
And this is the file that I'm going to be running.
So it's part of the exact same command.
So our trace is exporter,
my service name,
my exporter
Othelpy endpoint,
and Python 3
FlaskBase.py.
So we'll first run it
normally and then we'll add like
requests or something. We'll make a request and we can see the waterfall.
So basically copy this whole thing.
Does anyone have any questions about anything here
about the big command?
You agree it's kind of the same as what we just did?
We just defined exactly where to send it to,
what we want to send. Yeah?
This open for the
you ran it with other than Python.
That's a good question.
It's like another program that you can use.
That's actually a great question.
I had the exact same one until I realized
that, oh, it's by pip3 install.
So there could be,
but not for, because
it's for pip install that will contain only the Python relevant stuff.
And we'll start with the
Can you use environment variables instead of
like dash dash stuff? Of course, yeah.
You can use environment. So it could be even more
simpler, even simpler.
And sorry, we'll just leave the one in the back first.
I thought it would be part of this bootstrap and this distro, but if it's not, okay, then I'm sorry.
But you should already have it from when we did it over here.
Okay.
So good to hear it worked. Good job.
And over here in the front?
Yeah.
Okay.
So I'm going to use the
I'm going to use the
And over here in the front?
If your Python app
is not using Python app
instead of importing it and launching it in process
does it follow that
or can you use subprocess to launch
full-fledged JavaScript properties
or does it follow that?
You're saying if you're doing open telemetry
instrument on a Python file
and this file internally calls subprocess
and it runs Python 3,
run this file?
I believe you would have to change the subprocess command inside.
You'd have to say open telemetry instrument Python 3.
I don't believe it wraps.
It wraps that call.
Oh, okay.
That's amazing. I might come and ask you.
That's pretty cool.
If you want to know how it works, you can come ask me afterwards.
I've been playing around with this for our last six months
and it's pretty cool stuff.
That's amazing. I might come and ask you.
Or I can come out after.
Anything else?
Anyone else?
Okay.
Guys, you're asking some amazing questions.
I'm really, really proud.
Okay.
So we have this big, big command.
We'll copy this command
and we'll put it into a file named
Flask Instrumentation NoCode.sh
So I'm going to just copy this
because I'd like to create
files with touch, just to make sure it's there.
So I'll touch and I'll create this
NoCode file.
I'll place this big command in there.
And over here.
So we'll go over here to NoCode.sh
and we print it.
So you could do it like this
just to make it more readable.
Maybe this is a better idea.
But we'll just leave it as is for now.
So,
oh, I like to do Chmod. Does anyone not know what Chmod is?
Okay, amazing.
Can anyone tell me what Chmod is
if you're also knowledgeable about this?
Okay.
What does this line do?
Okay, you got it. Good job.
Okay.
And then we're just going to run this file
as an executable, like you guys said.
And so what we did is
we're running our Flask
Base.py.
We're running this exact same file
that we looked at earlier
that has no instrumentation.
It's just basically a program
It's just basically a print hello world.
It could be anything else.
But the fact that we're using Flask
and this has instrumentation
for Flask, then
we should see something cool out of it.
Now over here, if I curl localhost 5000,
then I want to see a print here because I am printing
the console and I got it.
And I want to see the span come in as well.
And we got it.
So now if we span this a little bit
and we do error as well.
So now if I come back to Jaeger
and you see
it doesn't show up here. I do need to refresh.
So I'll refresh
and now the auto does show up.
So now we have our three main ways
of instrumenting. The manual, the
intrib and the no code or the auto way.
So I'm going to look for traces
and okay we still have error equals true
that doesn't affect us in any way.
So we'll look at this one with an error.
And now we can see we've actually captured
a little bit of information. That's pretty good.
We've captured the fact that it's an
HTTP call to this.
We didn't capture the headers
but this is the environment variable.
We could just set that one.
Let's actually take this from the contrib.
So let's take this one.
And so if I put it in front of this
this equals dot star
and can anyone tell me
how do you do multiple? You can just do space
and just do the same thing again?
Okay awesome.
So I'll do this one as well.
So capture the request and capture the
response equals dot star.
And then our command.
Right?
Any quotes?
Makes sense.
And let's run it.
We'll get the error one.
And let's see.
So I want to see in Flask
this exact same thing
but with also
everything about the headers in the request
and the response.
So we'll find more traces.
When did this one come in?
A few seconds ago is good enough.
And boom we got it.
So this is quite a few
bits of information.
It's not bad. It's more than nothing
would you agree?
We can think something about the process.
So this might seem trivial to you
that we collected today but back in
OpenTracing and OpenSense and a few
older protocols before OpenTelemetry
this wasn't always collected and it became
quite a pain to figure out exactly which
version the user was using
and what language exactly. And so now it's
just sent in the trace and just
make things easier.
Is that a question in the back?
Okay. And we collect also in the
log as well everything about the exception.
Everything you'd see in Python
as if you were on the computer itself.
And
yeah. Any question about this?
Go ahead.
Does Auto wait for the
production?
You would do something like Auto, yeah.
So when I
do production I have
something that really works.
So if you want to start
a new project
I have to do
how would that work with the
automatic production?
Let's see. I actually have no experience with Unicorn personally.
I haven't used it.
A thread or eight processes?
Okay.
So let's see.
OpenTelemetry Unicorn.
And working with four processes.
So this is something they've actually
taken care of. It is possible.
But personally I've never
worked with Unicorn before.
So that would not be auto-aimed on the other side?
Oh, if we think for the
contrib way, let's see.
I have a question. Do you have to do a
string-based version or do you have to do a
top-based version?
I would just wonder if
you call a nine-row or a ten-row.
It should be.
Yeah. Contrib and auto are the same thing.
Pretty much.
Alright.
This is kind of like a modified
contrib.
And
okay. So let's do what you guys said.
Let's do our requests.
So I'm going to make sure.
I'm going to pip to reinstall
requests.
Now that we have requests, I'm going to be
So I want you guys to tell me.
If I do over here
request.get
Who's the parent span? Flask
or request?
Flask. Of course. Because it enters
Flask. And then inside of that
you have the request. So the request I
expect it to be the child span.
So we're going to make a request to
Google. And
we can do that and
we can print the status code.
Okay.
Let's do this.
So I run the no-code way.
And
because it's only in this
one, so we'll do without the error. We'll do this.
It didn't print. Oh, it should print over here,
right? So let's see.
And so we see two spans here.
This is the Flask that finished.
And this is the request.
This is the
request that we made from the
client.
Yep, 200. So exactly
what you said. Because the Flask is kind of
wrapping around it, it's before and after
the request, the HTTP
request that we made to Google finished first,
printed first, and then
only when this one finished, the outside,
basically the parent of it, then we get to see
this.
But usually it's not like that. Usually in
a case of a distributed environment, let's say
for example, it's a bunch of ECS tasks
or a bunch of lambdas, when the
first one finishes and he invokes
this one, he'll just send the span out. He's not always
waiting for a response. It could be an asynchronous
push. So it could
be that you'll see the parent come in first and then the child.
But in our case, it's the opposite. We'll
see in the time that it comes in the collector,
it's first the child comes in and then
the parent comes in.
Yeah, it's just like a race condition.
So let's see.
I expect to see over here. Let's take
out there as true.
And that's exactly it. We have our waterfall, exactly as you
wanted it. And we have
over here. So basically this is the parent span.
Someone made a request
to our server.
We returned the 200.
And it was Flask.
And then if we close this one,
our child span inside.
And you can clearly see the hierarchy as
you know, it can collapse this
and this is inside.
And let's see what we did.
We made a request to Google.com
with our auto instrumentation for requests.
It returned the 200.
And we're a client.
Any questions on this?
Another general question.
Suppose
you have everything
instrumented
but you don't have
a speaker to pick your trigger on.
Like you run your application
and it
wants to connect but it's obviously not successful.
Your application still doesn't work
or is it going to hang?
You're saying if your application
is trying to send spans somewhere
this person is not willing to accept it.
There's just no one to talk to.
The collector basically.
So like I said earlier, your application will work
of course. Because OpenTelemetry
and every single instrumentation framework
out there, their number one goal is not to touch
and mess up your code.
Because this could be a real production thing.
There could be billions of dollars at stake.
We don't want to touch and ruin anything.
Worst case scenario, your code is still
running but you might not have a span to look at it.
But we want to keep
your code running and ideally also have a span to look at.
So I've done it before.
You would get eventually
maybe like a warning log or something like that
at the worst case. But that's it.
It wouldn't hang and it wouldn't destroy anything in your application.
I was saying that I acted that way earlier.
I gave it a bunch of retries.
It did about a fifth retry
to the test between the two.
So it's taking a few places to do that.
But otherwise, yeah, it was a lot.
That's right.
I'll just take the right version of that.
You've mis-configured your barter wall
and the tracers
and the collectors are just
straight up dropped.
It should be a fun to see.
You know, there's actually a lot
that's never been done before.
It's pacing
or it's run it down.
You know, the logic
is too quick.
There's a lot of things out there.
That's what I'm saying.
Yeah.
These are excellent questions, guys.
This is amazing.
But essentially, if you do have a firewall
you do need to make sure that connections are allowed
to go in and out and make everything work.
And yes, question in the back.
So when we did the boot driver
earlier with the DAPA install
I noticed that it didn't install
everything in the barter wall.
It didn't get people off the game.
It didn't look at the packages
and the virtual environment
and all that.
So it looked at the package
and it installed
the implementation of the algorithm.
Oh, really? I didn't know that.
Is that the case?
I mean, it obviously had requests
because you didn't have to run it again.
So it didn't install everything
but it must be looking at something
because that installs
last for you or whatever.
But like, yeah.
So it could be the case.
But in case it doesn't work
and it doesn't install what you want
like I said earlier, the no-code
is just really a more advanced
and basically contrib way.
So you could just install
whatever instrumentation package you need.
For example, you could install this
and the no-code would work. Yes, question?
What would be your recommended way
to distribute people across
the microservice architecture
in the past?
How would you do that?
Well, that's an excellent question.
It depends actually very specifically
about which microservice you're using.
That's a thing.
So for example, I've seen for Kubernetes,
OpenTelemetry,
you could do a sidecar,
you could do an operator,
and you have a lot of really cool ways.
You could do it straight with Kubernetes,
you could do it through Envoy,
you could do it with a C++,
you could do it through Kubernetes,
you could do it through Envoy,
that they create the spans for you,
but let's say you're on Kubernetes,
you'll have automatically generated spans,
you just define exactly where to send it to,
send it to this collector, and so on.
For example, for Lambda,
AWS actually has their own distribution
of OpenTelemetry.
You just add it as a layer to your Lambda,
and it'll automatically make sure that spans
are sent out to the collector, and so on.
Let's say it's a containerized application,
you can just determine all our applications,
and then everything that you're writing in the top image
that's all your custom code,
then it's automatically instrumented already.
Yeah?
So like that request thing.
Yeah, for which microservice?
Oh, yeah, yeah.
If you're doing it manually with the width,
then you really have to worry about,
so let's say OpenTelemetry,
let's say Python, manual,
you have to worry about something that's called
the context and the baggage,
and so yeah, this gets really, really complicated.
This is why I hate using the manual way,
and pretty much everyone else does.
I want to say a good example of context,
but let's see.
Yeah, I was wondering about security.
Is there a way to set up a shared secret
between the source and the destination
to make sure that you go in and you're really connected
to the raw collector?
Yeah, I believe you could use any secrets manager,
any vault manager for something like that.
I think OpenTelemetry is trying to stay out of something like that.
Something like that.
I was wondering if you had a question
about the way you set up OpenTelemetry
or something you were talking to them about.
I've talked about that in the academic department
or a situation where we would have
multiple different students all in the same post,
and we also have multiple students having their websites,
but they don't seem to see the combined logs
because it's very, very open.
I was imagining one of the students
wanted to set up OpenTelemetry
to see the results of their website,
but then they turned it off or forgot about it,
and somebody else came along and used the same port number
now, the wrong websites get looked at
into OpenTelemetry.
I was wondering if there was a way
to set up a shared secret or something
so that you couldn't set it from the wrong one to the wrong one.
Oh, actually, yeah, definitely.
Sorry.
There are definitely things like that,
so we use actually, at my company,
we use something very similar called an OAuth2 extension,
an extension for the OpenTelemetry collector.
Sorry, my spelling's terrible,
but essentially you have to combine,
you have to say a few secrets,
you have the client ID and the client secret,
and you have to have some token URL and things like that.
So for example, in our production environment,
you have to set up the collector,
and for the exporter, you have to set it on both for it to work,
and so only this person can send it,
these exact spans to this location.
And so I can show you the name,
but it's really the OAuth2 client.
Yeah?
Is that one?
I've never heard of this.
What is GPDR?
Oh.
Oh, I'm sorry.
I'm sorry.
Oh.
You have to click all the things.
I don't care about the key.
So most of these,
I don't know,
so we have a few clients at Elastic as well,
and we really work hard on playing GPDR.
It's just going to play high-end.
That's why you have to do the header thing, right?
It doesn't play header.
Because that might be GPDR.
Yeah.
Thank you. Thank you so much.
I know nothing about GPDR.
Yeah.
You don't want to end your
in your Yager thing anyway, right?
So, like,
if I'm doing the user data,
it's going to be a pain in the oil.
Yeah.
Anything else?
Okay. Does this make sense?
There are two clients?
I think so.
Where is the one here?
Oh, so I'm over here
on the Collector Contrib.
And so, yeah, it's defined as an extension
in the Collector.
So basically, there's the Collector,
and then there's the Collector Contrib version as well.
And this contains the same exact thing as what we just talked about,
all of the extensions and everything else.
And so the Collector Contrib contains
much more than the Collector itself.
And there should be a table here.
I remember seeing a table, but it was somewhere.
And...
Not sure.
But yeah, if you go over here to extension,
you get the full list of all your extensions.
Oh, so over here.
So Yager remote sampling you could do
for whatever asks about sampling.
You have your OAuth 2 client extension as well.
But you do have a couple other.
You have basic auth token, bare token.
And so you don't have to use the OAuth 2. That's a bit more complicated.
You could use a couple of simpler ones.
Such as these two over here.
You could use ASAP auth extension.
But yeah, I would use probably something similar.
Probably something easier
if the students are doing it themselves.
Yeah?
Do you have any suggestions or recommendations
for deciding on your sampling?
I wouldn't do something too high.
I would say you would want most of your traces.
But I would say maybe
you could cut out...
You could do something like, I want to keep only 5%
of my traces or something.
But the main, main thing
that I would focus on is
if there is an error in this trace, don't sample it.
I want this trace.
So that's the main thing to keep in mind.
And so when you're doing sampling, and I'm not too familiar with the sampling
because it's pretty new.
But this is the main thing to keep in mind. If there's an error, you don't want it sampled.
You want it there.
And then from there you can pick your own. You could say 10 or 20%.
But I think ideally
you would have all of your traces.
Because each one tells a different story and you don't know how it might
come up in the future that you might need it.
So that's a way to age off traces.
To age off traces.
So, a funny story.
Yeah, exactly.
At my previous company
we had just too many traces in our database.
It was just too much. Everything was going crazy.
So we decided to have a policy that after seven days
your trace would be gone.
And we would delete it.
And you could pay for extra if you wanted.
But every seven days, or after seven days
the trace would disappear.
Because obviously the issue is not relevant anymore.
But it also became a nice premium enterprise feature.
Question in the back.
I think there's both now.
There's head-tail and tail-based.
There's head-based, sorry.
And tail-based sampling as well.
So you could do an application side.
And I think now they just added on the collector side.
Or vice versa.
You could do it on both.
And anything else?
Okay.
We're nearing the end guys.
I don't want to hold you too long.
We are going to go soon.
We're going to go soon.
Maybe we'll finish even before the break.
And I'll let you out for the second half.
You could stay as long as you'd like.
But I want you guys to now answer a few questions from me.
And so we'll scroll here all the way to the bottom.
Step 16, we're done.
Right?
And I want you to answer me.
I want someone to tell me here, what is observability?
What is it?
Nobody knows?
Almost.
These are the three pillars of observability.
That was good.
Can someone give me a, okay, that's actually great.
But can someone give me a generic and a very basic definition?
Exactly.
You're watching something from the outside.
And you're able to, just with a tiny bit of information,
become smarter and smarter and make better and educated guesses
about what's happening inside.
Okay?
Can anyone tell me what is open telemetry?
Feel free to shout it out.
It's okay.
Yeah.
Yeah, pretty much.
It's a protocol that creates bands and sends them
and eventually stores them somewhere.
And can anyone tell me what app observability tools exist?
Three main ones that we've used today.
Okay.
So, I'm going to ask you a question.
Amazing.
Good job, guys.
And can someone tell me what methods can I use
to instrument my app with applications,
with open telemetry?
And?
Awesome. Good job.
But when should you use each?
What's the advantages of using each one?
For example, the manual one.
Why would I ever use that one?
Yeah.
Exactly.
Both answers are correct.
Good job, guys.
And so, why would you then use the contrib one
or the auto one?
Is there a difference?
Yeah.
Yeah. Awesome.
That's it. Good job.
And what is the open telemetry collector?
What is it?
Why do you need it?
Why do you need it and what does it do?
I want to.
You can answer only one of them.
It's the buffer.
But why?
Then why would you use the buffer?
Because it's the same as the other one.
Yeah. Exactly.
Both are correct.
Raise your hand if you learned something here today.
Wow. Wow. Amazing, guys.
Thank you.
Okay. You're free to go, guys. Have a great day.
And thank you so much.
Applause.
So what is it
going to do?
Oh. So is it still recording?
I don't know if I can show this.
So I
worked at this
other company
called Epscom.com.
We were purchased by Cisco about a year and a half ago.
So this website is almost down, but for example,
I think I can show you the demo still.
So this is a commercial product, Epsilon.
Within Cisco now, we do have also AppDynamics.
Let's see, maybe there's a demo.
There is also Teletrace.
This is a vendor neutral one that's open source,
but it's very, very new.
The Epsilon demo.
So this is what Epsilon's really famous for.
When you go to traces over here and you click on it,
this is basically a table full of your spans,
and you can have a very sophisticated span search
that we're able to show spans like I've never seen before.
And so you really get, like forget even the waterfall.
The waterfall is like a secondary one,
like this timeline, right, that we see in Yeager.
So for me, this is really, really cool.
And they're able to see, you know, from here,
and we also collect also everything that happens.
So for example, in the Lambda,
we're able to not just get, you know, basic metadata stuff.
We can see also, and let's see if I can see it, and no.
But for example, in this HTTP call,
we see not just the headers very easily.
We see also automatically the body and everything else.
And also in the response, the headers and body.
And yeah, it just works amazing.
We can see for kinesis, everything,
and yeah, for the database as well.
So I would say this is even a sort of boring trace
if we can find some pretty interesting traces out there.
And for example, even in the database,
when you make a request and you make an insert,
we can see the exact SQL statement as well.
You could obfuscate it as well.
You don't have to include it.
But if you'd like to see it in there, we do have it.
And this really, really helps in debugging.
You can see, oh, this isn't the table I want to send it to.
And this isn't the exact value I want it to send in.
I wanted something kind of different.
So this is great for finding bugs that you did
even realize were there.
And maybe they even made it to production.
And now you realize, okay, this is the issue, exactly.
Does that answer your question?
Would you use something like this?
Just curious.
You use AppDynamics.
That's cool.
So use AppDynamics, which one?
The hotel one or the non-hotel one?
So we don't use those.
We use both of their, well, they may use it
under the other things, both of their,
okay.
Okay.
Phrase synchronous?
Oh, I'm not sure.
Yeah, I do know that AppDynamics is moving
towards open telemetry as well with AppDynamics Cloud.
And yeah, these are the ones I would recommend, definitely.
Epsilon, AppDynamics, Teletrace, I think those are good ones.
Okay, you're free to go, guys.
Thank you very much.