Hello, everyone, and thank you for coming.
Welcome to our tutorial on property-based testing.
My name is Zach Hatfield-Dodds, and over here, my colleague Brian Siklasky.
We're both maintainers of the property-based testing library hypothesis, and pretty excited
to share more about how you can use it with you today.
So the plan is we're going to go through four parts of this tutorial, and we've got exercises
for parts two, three, and four.
In the first, we're going to talk about basic property-based testing, starting with, for
example, what is property-based testing?
Hands up who already has a good idea about that?
No?
Okay, this will be an important section then.
Once we talk about what property-based testing is, we'll start talking about how to describe
the data that you want to test with, common tactics for using property-based testing,
and then we'll finish with a section on putting it into practice, which is the kind of tips
that take you from the exercises that you're going to be doing today to actually applying
it at work or in open source projects or in a larger kind of realistic context.
So property-based testing at kind of a 101 level.
I'm just going to start with the testing part of this.
My favorite definition of testing is that it's the art and science of running your code
and then checking that it did the right thing.
So there are a lot of cool ways to make sure that your code does the right thing that are
not testing by this definition.
Things like putting assertions in the main code, using a type checker or linters like
Flakate, getting one of your colleagues to review your code, drinking coffee or perhaps
getting a little more sleep the night before.
All of these are great ways to improve the quality of your code or find bugs, but they're
not testing.
So that's the last you'll hear of them from me today.
And there are a lot of different kinds of tests that we might use.
One of my friends Hillel wrote a big list, and some of them include things like unit
tests, integration tests, snapshot tests, where you record the output of your code and
then can later check that it didn't change when you changed your code.
You can parameterize tests.
Hands up who's used PyTest before?
Keep them up if you've used a PyTest parameterize.
Okay, about half the room.
You can have fuzz tests, and fuzz tests basically throw random data into your function or your
code to try to make it crash.
You can have property-based tests, which is what we're talking about today, and then stateful
model-based tests, which are like a fancier form of property-based testing that we will
not be discussing in depth.
So to start off with, I want to talk briefly about examples.
Our friend David says every time someone uses reversing a list twice, which should give
you the original list, every time someone uses this to demonstrate property testing,
he takes a drink.
It's not a drinking game.
He just doesn't like this example very much.
Let's make the most common example in blog posts a non-generalizable property of a function
that's almost impossible to get wrong.
Who here has ever had to implement code to reverse a list?
No one?
Yeah, so maybe one.
It doesn't come up very often, and honestly, it's not why we think property-based testing
is important.
So let's talk about sorting instead, which hands up who's implemented a sorting function
ever.
Okay, quite a few more people than reversing.
So this is a real-world kind of problem that we might have, but it's also a good demo.
So traditionally, in tests, we might write a couple of tests that our sorting function
gets the right answer.
If we sort 1, 2, 3, we should get 1, 2, 3.
Yeah?
Okay, good.
If we sort 3, 2, 1 as floats, we should get 1, 2, 3, but this time the output of floats.
Still with me?
And it's not just numbers.
We can also sort strings.
Anything we can compare, we can sort a list of.
Right?
Does this look like a good test suite?
It's not a bad test suite, but it's not exactly comprehensive, right?
So you might just want to make this a little simpler to maintain and go, that's too much
code, so let's use PyTest.
We'll use this parameterized decorator and just be able to write out a table of the inputs
and outputs.
And this has a big advantage.
It's much easier to add new test cases to this one compared to writing a whole test
again.
Admittedly, there's not that much setup code for these tests, but in realistic cases, parameterize
can often be a big improvement.
But there's still a bit of a catch, right?
We have to manually work out what are good input values and then manually work out what's
the corresponding expected output value.
And we could get that just by running our code and seeing what it does, but then we're
kind of testing that our code does what our code does, which sometimes that's the best
option available, but sometimes we can do better.
For example, if we have a trusted sort function, which for some reason is not Python's built-in
sort function, we could just come up with the inputs and then assert that our sorting
function gets the same result as a trusted sorting function.
Can anyone think of a case where you might have this kind of pattern in practice?
Whoever refactors code?
So you have the old version and the new version.
Or you might have multithreading code, and you can run it with one thread or with many
threads.
So this pattern of being able to check your results against a trusted implementation,
it doesn't have to be a completely independent implementation.
It can be last week's version, the single-threaded version, sometimes a really slow and stupid
version, which you're confident is correct, but it's too slow for production.
So that's a pretty useful pattern, but you still have to come up with the inputs yourself,
right?
And how do you know that you've covered all the edge cases?
Kind of by definition, you're unlikely to discover an edge case that you didn't think
of by running this kind of test.
And so if we don't have a trusted implementation, we can still check some things about the outcome,
right?
We can sort our argument, and then we can check that if we look at each pair of elements
in the output, that they should be in non-decreasing order, right?
This test should pass for every valid sorting function, right?
Is it a complete test?
Any problems with it?
Yep?
Indeed, this test would pass if sorted returned to the empty list for every input, which is
maybe not quite what we wanted.
So we could add an extra couple of checks.
We could check that we have the same number of elements in the input and the output, and
that the set of elements is the same.
Is this a complete test?
No?
What's the problem this time?
Yeah.
So you could go from 1, 1, 2 to 1, 2, 2, and that would not be a valid sorting function,
but it would pass this test.
Okay.
So what about this one?
So we have the same ordering check as before, but then we say that the result has to be
a permutation of the input.
Is this a good test?
Maybe?
It's a bad test?
Why is it a bad test, Ryan?
First of all, that permutation might get real expensive.
Yeah, this could be incredibly slow.
So I guess it's a fine test to fill lists of, like, of length up to four, but in production,
it's not going to work very well.
So if we import collections.counter, we can say we have the same number of each distinct
element in the input and the output.
What do we think of this test?
You've all become terribly cynical and untrusting in the short time that we've known each other.
You could be modifying the inputs.
Yeah, so if you have mutable inputs or mutable elements in the input, that could be a problem
still.
But if you don't, I think this test is actually pretty good.
This is how I would write a property-based test for the sorted built-in.
So we've just written two properties, and that's the properties in property-based testing.
The first property is that the output has to be in order, and the second property is
that you have the same elements in the input and the output.
So this is what we call a complete specification.
These two properties are sufficient to identify a correct sorting function.
But partial specifications, even if we only checked one or the other, there are still
many bugs that we would have found.
Even that earlier test where we just checked that we had the same length and the same set,
this would find most plausible bugs.
If someone is not trying to sneak an evil sorting function past you, this test is pretty
good.
So the generalization is, Hypothesis is a library to help you come up with the inputs
to this kind of test to discover the edge cases that you hadn't previously thought of.
And so in this case, we can say instead of writing out that list of integers and floats
and strings, we can say that given an argument which is one of either lists of some mixture
of integers and floats, right?
So it's OK to sort a list that combines integers and floats, but you can't combine integers
and floats and strings.
So we'll say it's a list of either numbers or of strings.
And then we have the same checks.
This test actually turns up an edge case that we hadn't thought of, because floating point
not a number compares unequal to anything else.
If you compare Nan to any other number, is it greater than x?
False.
Is it less than x?
Also false.
Is it equal to x?
Still false.
And so the behavior of sorting a list which contains not a number gets remarkably more
difficult to specify than you would have thought.
So I like property-based testing partly because it teaches me about the language and the libraries
that I'm using by checking my guesses about how they behave.
In this case, though, we're just going to tell Hypothesis, look, I just don't want to
hear about Nan.
That's too complicated for a tutorial example.
I'm not going to put that on a slide for you.
So just exclude those examples for me.
I only want the well-defined comparable numbers.
So to summarize, we've looked at property-based testing.
It helps us generate input data that we wouldn't have previously thought of.
And the key idea is that we can check that the result is not incorrect.
Even if we don't know how to calculate what the results should be, just checking that
we didn't get the result that we can tell is wrong in some way is enough to find an
awful lot of bugs.
And those bugs can often be in our, or at least my, understanding of the code I'm using,
the code I've written, the language, the libraries I use.
And in some cases, though, I didn't show this, you don't even need an assertion in your test.
I like putting lots of assertions in my code to check that something I think is impossible
hasn't actually happened.
And then generating weird input data and feeding it into your test can often trigger those
assertions or just a plain error in your code somewhere where you hadn't handled an empty
string or an empty list or an infinite element, for example.
So with that, we're at the end of the first of four sections.
We're going to take five minutes now to go to this link, rsockels slash testing tutorial,
and get that set up.
You can either install all the dependencies locally and run things on your own laptop
environment, or we have clickable MyBinder links which will open a notebook in the browser
for you if installing things becomes difficult for some reason.
In five minutes, then, we'll come back and go through part two of the talk on describing
data.
So can I see a quick show of hands?
Who has Hypothesis installed locally?
Okay.
Who would like a minute more to install Hypothesis?
I will trust that you can install while I'm talking then.
So let's jump into part two of four.
So I think I actually missed describing the mass structure.
We've got four parts.
We're going to run through the first part, which we've just done, and install things,
which we've just done.
Part two, we'll give a short talk and then have some media exercises using the tools
you've just installed.
Then we'll take a quick bio break for people who like things like coffee or bathrooms or
stretching your legs.
We'll come back and have another pair of short talk and exercises, short talk and exercises,
and through all of the exercises, Ryan and I will be around to answer any questions you
have about the exercises or about Hypothesis generally.
So the second part, now that we know what property-based testing is, is talking about
how to describe the specific data that you might want to generate using Hypothesis.
There are a number of different kinds of what we call strategies.
These are those things like the lists and the floats that I showed you, which describe
what the data should be.
Hypothesis comes with built-in strategies for things like scalar values, the various
numbers or strings that you might want to generate, for collections, where you can say,
I want lists where the elements are drawn from some other strategy, or I want sets or
tuples or dictionaries.
You can modify strategies with the map and filter thing, and there are a variety of special
cases that we'll walk through with specific slides.
Exercises at the end of this part, we're going to be focusing on generating data rather than
asserting particular properties of your code at this point.
So for scalar values, scalars are like individual elements.
Hypothesis has built-in strategies for none.
That one's very simple.
It just generates none.
The Boolean strategy can generate true or false, so we're getting more complicated.
And then once you get into numbers, we have integers, there are floats where you can specify
the range, whether or not to allow infinite numbers, whether or not to allow none.
For floats, you can also specify bit width, so whether you want 64 or 32 or 16-bit floats.
You can generate strings, whether individual Unicode characters or the string type or bytes,
dates, times, time zones, and very many other things.
I believe it is literally the case that if you can name it in Python, you can generate
with hypothesis.
So let's look at a short example.
This is one of those simple patterns that I talked about earlier.
We're going to look at the binary or not library, which is on the Python package index.
It has an isBinaryString function.
And so what we're going to do is say, given any binary string, this generates instances
of the bytes type, we're just going to call isBinaryString on that.
And if it crashes, then we'll know we have a bug.
What do we think is going to happen?
It'll work perfectly?
Well, it would be nice if that was the case.
But in this case, not even asserting and just calling things can be sufficient to find bugs.
So this one has since been fixed, in fairness.
But what happened was that binary or not internally used the charDep library, which tries to detect
character encodings.
And charDep looked at the first few characters of a randomly generated binary string and
said, oh, this looks like it's UTF-8, or whatever the encoding was.
And so based on that, it returned a 100% confidence rating.
But as documented, there was no implication that a 100% confidence meant that this was
actually a valid string for that encoding.
It may be a little confusing, but it was documented.
And so what we found here was a bug where the authors of the binary or not library had
misunderstood the return value from this other library that they were using.
And that could cause a crash on some particular weird inputs.
Let's look at something a little different.
Who's heard of the Mercurial project?
One person?
It's a version control thing which competed with Git for a while, implemented in Python.
And so it has these two functions, from UTF-8b and to UTF-8b, which encode bytes in Unicode.
And so the test that we're writing here is, given any binary string, if we convert it
to UTF-8b and then from UTF-8b, we should get the original string back.
Seem reasonable?
Can anyone think of a case where you might apply this to your own code?
Some of us?
You'll see more of this soon.
Unfortunately, we find another bug here.
Again, this was found using hypothesis, reported upstream, and fixed quite promptly, where
it turned out that this particular weird sequence of bytes would lead to a crash.
Okay, so what about date parsing?
Who here loves working with times and dates?
No?
I can tell from the laughter that some of you have had to before.
So what we're going to do here is we're saying, give me an arbitrary date time.
I will format it using the ISO format method, which gives you the nice four-digit year dash
two-digit month and so on.
And then what we're going to do is we'll check that our formatted string is the same as parsing
the formatted string and then formatting the date time that we get from that.
So we're comparing things as strings rather than date times here, just to avoid any particular
weirdness.
That's not really necessary.
And what we find is this completely bizarre bug that brought joy to the lives of several
maintainers a few years back, where it turns out that this failed if the year and the month...
It would swap the year and the month in the parser if and only if the year was between
the year zero and the year nine and equal to the number of seconds in the date time.
Do you think it would have caught this without hypothesis?
Because I'm going to admit, I'm kind of surprised when we caught it at all, ever.
But here we are.
Okay, so that's what we can do just generating individual elements, scalar values.
If we're generating collections, this gives us the ability to do more complex data sets.
We can have lists of any particular thing.
And for lists, you can say what the minimum and the maximum size should be and whether
you want it to be a unique list or unique by some key function or group of key functions.
You can have tuples where you say, I want a tuple where each element is drawn from the
corresponding strategy.
Or you can have dictionaries where you say, give me a dictionary where each key has a
value drawn from the corresponding strategy.
So this is pretty useful as well.
To look at that, we might test, given some list of floats, which is non-empty, we're
going to test that the mean is between the minimum and the maximum, inclusive.
We have to specify min size equals one because the minimum function will just raise an error
on an empty list.
So what do we expect to happen here?
Nan could be an issue.
Yep.
But in this case, what we're going to see here is if we have two very large values,
it seems like mean is probably implemented by adding them together and then dividing
by the length of the list.
And what we've found is if we pick two very large floating point numbers and add them
together, we get infinity.
And then when you divide infinity by two, you've still got infinity.
And so the mean is now larger than the maximum.
It turns out there is an entire field of research on numerically stable floating point algorithms,
which do not fit on one slide.
So mean is harder than we would think, and the standard library mean function turns out
not to be stable in this way.
So much for collections.
The next two things which you'll probably use all the time if you start using hypothesis
is the map and filter methods on strategies.
So what map does is it draws an example from that strategy, and it applies the function
that you provide.
So for example, if you have integers.map.str, this will generate an integer, then call string
on it, and generate the strategy with the map will generate strings that were created
by calling string on those integers.
And filter, conversely, lets you reject kind of weird or bad inputs.
The idea is you can provide a function which returns false or a falsy value if the example
that was drawn is one that you don't want to test.
So for example, you might say I want integers but not zero because I'm testing division.
You write integers.filter lambda x, x not equal to zero.
And that would give you random examples, but rejecting those that didn't match.
So here, for example, we might want a pair of integers which is in ascending order.
And there are two ways we could do this, right?
We could do it with the filter, saying if we have this lambda, we want x, y such that
the zeroth element of x, y is less than or equal to the second element.
And that will work, but it will work by rejecting about half of the examples, right?
So we'll draw random examples, and some of them will be in the wrong order, and we'll
throw those out and try again.
This works pretty well in practice, but it's more efficient if we just map sorted, which
just swaps them if they're out of order.
And then in this case, because sorted returns a list, we can map tuple to turn it back into
a tuple afterwards.
Does this make sense to people?
Cool.
I'm getting some nods.
A couple of special strategies.
I realize I'm just kind of info-dumping on you.
That's why we have the exercises.
A few special strategies.
Just is when you have a value but you need a strategy for the API.
So for example, the datetimes strategy has a time zone argument, but the time zone value
that you pass has to be a strategy.
So if you always wanted your time zone to be in UTC, you could pass time zones equals
just UTC.
And the just strategy pretty much does what it sounds like.
It just generates the value that you fed it.
Sampled from is great if you have a couple of different alternatives.
Say you wanted your join to be either an inner join or an outer join.
Well sampled from will generate random selections from that list for you.
This also works well with the nums.
So if you have something like permissions, it will also generate combinations of those
values if you have a num flags type.
When you want to combine strategies, one of is just the union of those strategies.
So we saw this way back at the start where we wanted to generate integers or floats or
lists of integers or floats or lists of strings.
That was using the one of strategy.
And then nothing is kind of special here.
Nothing is a strategy that can never generate anything at all.
You might think what is the point of having a strategy that can never generate anything
at all?
It's pretty useful when you have for some reason an API where you have to return a strategy
which you're going to use one of with.
And basically we'll just skip over that because we know there are no elements in it.
So one of integers and nothing is just the same thing as integers.
Unfortunately, you can't take the intersection of two strategies.
You can't say only give me values that either of these strategies could generate because
that would require us to understand whatever map or filter functions that you put on it.
And you can't generally subtract them.
So give me everything from this strategy unless it could be generated from that strategy.
It's just not feasible in general.
Okay.
Are you following so far?
Raise your left hand.
Okay.
So most of you are still awake.
The builds function is the next useful kind of strategy.
Who here ever defines their own classes?
This will be useful for all of you then.
Builds is how you tell hypothesis how to make an instance of some arbitrary class or function
or other callable.
So you could think of it as basically error handling and some syntax sugar over the map
function where you could generate instances of your class by generating a tuple or dictionary
of all the arguments you need and then mapping with the constructor of your class.
But builds is a little more ergonomic.
You just pass it the thing that you want to build and then positional and keyword arguments
which are strategies and then we build you instances of those things by generating values
from those strategies and passing them as the corresponding positional and keyword arguments.
Builds will also do type inference for you.
So if you have type annotations on your code and you don't pass a strategy for a required
argument, hypothesis will just look at the type annotations and work out how to make
one for you.
Ryan's a fan.
It is remarkably convenient.
You can just say give me instances of foo and it will look at foo and if foo takes a bar
it will work out how to make a bar and then pass that to the foo for you.
Who here has ever dealt with recursive data?
So trees for example.
At least two of us.
Maybe more.
Okay.
This is a little more tricky to express.
So there are a couple of different ways that hypothesis gives you for describing recursive
data because each of them will be more natural in different contexts.
The first is that we have this recursive strategy and then you give it a strategy as the base
case and then a function which takes an object and returns a strategy based on that.
This is like your base case and then your extension.
So for things like JSON this is remarkably nice.
This is by the way a complete definition of a hypothesis strategy that can generate any
value representable as JSON.
Which is pretty nice.
Or we have the deferred strategy which lets you define mutually recursive functions.
My rule of thumb is use that whenever you get a name error.
When you're trying to refer to something that hasn't been defined yet.
The last nice thing here, or not the last nice thing, another nice thing is that hypothesis
can often infer strategies for you because writing things out by hand is kind of tedious
and I feel like against the spirit of Python.
So from type I mentioned is built into the builds strategy.
So if you have a type annotation it can just automatically work out what to call there.
You can also call it on a particular class or type for yourself.
And so inference is designed to be a time saver.
It will almost always pretty quickly work out something reasonable for you.
But sometimes that will permit more possible values than you actually intended.
And in those cases you can write a strategy by hand.
Even just specifying the particular bits that you want to be different and inferring the
rest.
We also have this register type strategy function.
This one is so that you can customize.
So if you have a particular class you can customize what hypothesis will generate as
a strategy for it when asked.
This is pretty useful if you use a type all over the place.
Once you register it once you can then infer it everywhere else and the constrained strategy
you define will be used.
And we can infer from other things like if you have a regular expression that you use
for validation, hypothesis can generate strings that match the regex for you.
Who here uses NumPy?
We can also generate things based on data types or shape signatures.
Who uses Django?
Okay, if you have a field or a model hypothesis will also automatically generate things that
can be stored in those models for you.
And in fact stash them in database.
So inferring these strategies is a really nice pattern to save some time and generally
make your testing more ergonomic.
If you're implementing your own inference, which you probably will do once you've used
hypothesis for a little while, try to err on the side of inferring the most general
strategy that could generate the widest range of possible inputs.
Because in my view the worst kind of problem with tests is the missed alarms.
The tests that just didn't check the edge case that turned out to be a bug in production.
So I'd much rather spend a little more time when I'm writing my test to make sure that
I'm actually covering all of the edge cases that I can think of.
And then the last tip which we've tried to follow here is to make sure that there's a
really smooth path from just letting you say hypothesis work it all out for me to then
saying like hypothesis work it all out for me except the bar argument to a baz needs
to be non-negative.
Yep.
So does each strategy generate all possible permutations or outputs?
So we do a sort of heuristically guided random sample from that space.
The exact distribution is remarkably complicated because we keep tuning it based on research,
based on feedback from users, based on measurements of what your code is actually doing as we
execute those tests.
In practice the search space is usually too big to enumerate all the possibilities.
In many of them it will just be infinitely large.
So hypothesis by default will generate about 100 random samples.
But if you want to you can turn that up to a million and leave it running overnight.
Here's an example using Django.
This is a more complex test.
Right?
So this is sort of business logicky and it still works.
So running through it.
We say we have given.
This is our standard decorator that describes what kind of outputs you expect.
We say from model.
So we want instances of our project where the collaborator limit is between zero and
20.
And we want lists of things generated from a user model of at most 20 users.
With me so far?
Awesome.
So we then have a test with a descriptive name which takes a project and our collaborator's
list.
Then we go for seeing collaborators.
If we're at the collaboration limit of the project, assert that adding that user raises
a limit reached exception.
And then check that our project team does not contain that user.
Right?
Or if we're not at the collaboration limit, add the user and assert that the user is in
the team.
Simple enough?
It's not rocket surgery.
What we actually see if we run this is that hypothesis will generate a list containing
two identical users.
And then our assertion will fail.
Because if you try to add a user who is already in the project when you're at the collaboration
limit, then you'll raise the limit reached exception.
But the user will still be in that thing.
So the solution in this case is that we needed to make our lists unique as well.
And if we'd done that, then this test would pass.
So I think these are the last strategies that we're going to talk about before we
jump into exercises for a while.
Sometimes you have data which has internal dependencies.
By that I mean one part of it has to have a particular relationship with another part.
For example, you need two numbers, but they have to be equal.
Or you need a project and a user, but the user has to be a member of the project.
For these cases, there are a couple of ways to do it.
The most elegant is usually the at composite decorator.
This lets you generate functions which define custom strategies.
So you put the decorator on.
You provide a first argument called draw by convention.
And then you can take whatever other arguments you like, whether they're strategies, other
values.
It's fully customizable.
So you can write anything that you can write in Python.
And then the draw argument is a function which you can pass the strategy and it will return
a value from that strategy.
This is like a little bit of the hypothesis internal is ready for you.
So in this case, we want widgets.
And so we're saying, well, we'll pick a random factory from the locations strategy that was
passed.
We'll pick a random power setting, I guess, between zero and the maximum voltage or whatever
it is.
And then we'll return a widget constructed using that power thing made in the factory
and with a given key.
Flat map is similar, but it's a sort of function composition style for people who like functional
languages.
And data is another thing again.
In this case, we didn't actually need to do this validation every single time, right?
We're going to pass our arguments in, but then each time we generate a value, we don't
need to repeat the validation logic.
So I often find this kind of a useful pattern where I put the composite on an inner function.
So that's doing the minimum possible amount of work each time.
When you have expensive validation, this is a nice performance tip.
In this case, though, we didn't actually need composite.
You can just have functions which return strategies, right?
So in this case, we take our arguments and then we return builds.
So we say, build me a widget where the power is drawn from this float strategy and it's
made in locations and the key is just the valid key.
Does that make sense to people?
All three of these do the same thing, right?
Where we have our original composite.
This is a pretty enigmatic use of composite, but we have that validation.
We pull the validation out to save a bit of performance and then we realize that we don't
actually need composite at all.
In this case, we can just use builds.
And having custom functions which return strategies is just a great ergonomic tip, right?
I really like having a file full of help utilities for my test suite.
The data is exactly the same as composite except it works inside your test function.
So the decisions about what data to draw, how to interact with those strategies can
be made based on partial results from your test.
The upside is that this is the most flexible and powerful possible way to do it.
The downside is that it is the most flexible and powerful possible way to do it.
And that means that the error reporting, for example, is slightly more complicated because
we have to show you the order in which you drew things instead of just the arguments
which we generated for you.
My summary there is use data if you need it and then look at the test you've written and
check whether you could think of a way to do it without using data.
All right.
That's the strategies that we have available built into Hypothesis.
Where do you look for these?
For core strategies where there are no dependencies beyond the standard library, Hypothesis.strategies.
It should be easy to remember as long as you remember that they're called strategies
and they live in Hypothesis.
For things which have external dependencies like NumPy or Pandas or Django, those are
in Hypothesis.extra.whatever that library is named.
So if you want to generate NumPy arrays, you will import Hypothesis.extra.NumPy.
And then there are also a range of third-party extensions you can find in the documentation
where people, much like yourselves, have written their own packages which provide
Hypothesis plugins for things like generating NetworkX graphs or pretty much anything else
you can imagine.
I will note just because we list them in the documentation doesn't mean we endorse them.
It just means we know they exist and we think our users may also want them to know they
exist.
All right.
Before we jump into the exercises for this part, I'd be happy to take any questions.
Is it guaranteed to be deterministic?
Great question.
Slightly complicated answer.
We'll get into this more in section four.
It's not deterministic by default, but there is a determinism setting you can enable.
And we do guarantee that if we find a failure, we will cache that and replay it on subsequent
runs.
So you should never have the problem where it's flaky in that running it once fails and
running it again with no changes, passes.
Any other questions?
Yep.
Do we have more shared examples of how to write things?
Yeah.
So some of those should be the materials, including in the exercises that we're about
to do.
So we have the master branch where we have all of the questions for the problem sets.
There's also the instructor branch where we have our solutions to each of these.
So I'd encourage you to try them for yourselves first, but if you get stuck, feel free to
ask us or if you're doing them later, you can look at those solutions as well.
All right.
So we're going to spend the next 25 minutes or so on these exercises and then take a 10-minute
break.
Let's get to it.
So for some context, what we're going to be doing is going into the notebooks.
So notebook zero taxonomy of testing.
Microphone.
I'm pretty loud to begin with.
It's going to be notebook zero taxonomy of testing.
So this is going to rewind way, way back to the most basic test.
We're going to have a couple of basic functions, counting vowels and merging dictionaries.
What we're going to do is write some by hand tests for them.
Then we're going to write some pytest parameterized tests for them.
And then we're going to use some of those hypothesis strategies that Zach just introduced.
So that was a rapid fire tour through everything in hypothesis.
This is going to go back and babysit all the way up to using the most basic strategies.
So one thing to keep in mind is as you're going through the notebook, it will ask you
to actually write tests in the repo's test suite so that you can run it with pytest.
So that is to say the notebooks are not fully self-contained.
The notebook will ask you to go and write code in the repo.
And as Zach mentioned, you can always toggle over to the instructor's branch if you want
to peek at the answers.
Although I recommend doing that in your browser so you don't lose your changes locally.
Before we start with our next section, I wanted to make a couple of comments.
I think first, someone brought up the fact that when they saw their test pass,
they asked themselves, well, is it even possible for my test to fail?
And that is a very wise thing to check.
If you write a test and you've never seen the test fail, you should assume
that there might be something wrong with your test.
I am very embarrassed to say that I've had like an hour of writing increasingly
sophisticated tests that always pass.
I'm like, I'm the best.
My code is perfect.
And then I realized I never actually called my function in the test.
And once I called it, the most basic example failed.
Just like tears streamed down my face.
So a very good strategy is just switch that equals equals to a not equals
and see the test fail and say, okay, I can move forward.
More sophisticated is when you parameterize a pi test test,
you can intentionally include a parameter that should fail your test
and then mark it with pi test as an X fail parameter.
In that case, pi test, the test will pass
if that example causes your test to fail.
And the test will fail if it causes your test to pass.
Sorry for the confusing.
But this is a, it's more advanced, but it's really nice
because this helps you stay confident that you didn't do anything
to break the test itself, which would be very nefarious.
Second thing is if you have.
Hypothesis has similar support where we have this at example decorator
where you can provide explicit examples.
We'll show those in a few minutes as a way of reproducing previous failures.
But that also has a dot X fail method on it.
So similarly, you can write a property based test and say,
but here's an example input which should make the test fail.
Right, yeah, maybe you wrote a hypothesis test
where you generated positive integers as an input.
You could add at example negative two, but with an X fail saying,
this one should make my test fail.
If it doesn't, there's something wrong with my test.
This is really powerful.
The other thing is if you are still working on the first part
of the tutorial, feel free to move at your own pace.
The GitHub repo has all of the solutions with it.
So don't feel the need to skip ahead if you feel
like you're getting meaningful information out of continuing
to work on the first part.
So just wanted to put that out there.
Yep. All right.
So we're about halfway through our time together.
And so it is time for me to attempt a live demo.
Please think calmly of me when this breaks.
Because it's going to break.
Okay. So the thing I want
to demonstrate is what we call the hypothesis ghostwriter.
This was inspired by my experience at PyCon a few years ago
where I came and I was really excited.
I taught a tutorial much like this one.
And I would bump into people on the hallway track.
And they would say, oh, hypothesis.
I've heard of that.
It sounded kind of cool.
I'm like, awesome.
What do you use it for?
And they would say, well, I don't.
I'm not sure how to apply it to my code.
And after hearing this about 20 times over the course
of three days, I decided that like all software engineers believe
deep down, this was a social problem
that had a technical solution.
Where I could fix this problem in front of me just
by writing a bunch of code.
And so the code that I wrote uses hypothesis
to write tests for you.
Although in this case, we may need to, yeah.
Apparently my environment has broken, which may be relatable.
Wow, that's impressive.
Yeah.
I don't know.
So let's try using my shell session here instead.
I think I've now appeased the gods of live demos.
That was what we call hubris.
Okay. So there we are.
It's just very slow today for some unknown reason.
So the hypothesis write command writes property-based tests
for you.
You point it to the module that you want to test or the function
within the module, and it goes off and produces those tests.
In this case, we tried to write a function,
a test for the sort function, which doesn't actually exist.
So hypothesis helpfully told us
that the built-ins module does not have a sort attribute.
Try sorted or perhaps format.
Well, we didn't want format.
So here instead is a test for the sorted function.
Let me zoom this a little more.
So hypothesis sets up the imports.
It writes our given spec.
And it has three arguments.
There's the iterables, which is one of either integers or text.
Does this seem familiar from the previous section?
So one difference is we've said, this is what I get
for attempting a live demo, I guess.
So we've got iterables instead of lists.
So it could be any kind of iterable thing,
including an iterator.
But we also have these key and reverse arguments,
which I didn't show in the earlier demo,
because Python's sorted built-in does take a Boolean
and reverse flag optionally, and potentially a key function.
And this just tests that if you call sorted iterable key
reverse, then you don't get a crash.
Seems pretty reasonable.
So it doesn't have particular knowledge of the sorted built-in.
You can also request this in unit test style.
So this gives us a unit test test case class,
and the decorator goes on a test method,
which is otherwise the same.
Who here prefers unit test to PyTest?
Okay. You're in for a treat, then, because it all just works.
Hypothesis is perfectly happy
to help you write those methods instead of test functions.
We can also tell hypothesis that sorted is idempotent.
Idempotent meaning if you call sorted on the output
from a call to sorted, it shouldn't make any further changes.
And hypothesis, well, my laptop seems
to be really slow right now.
Yeah. There we are.
It will eventually write a test that sorting is idempotent.
So if we get our result by calling that, and then we repeat
by calling on the result, then our result is equal
to the repeat thing.
Make sense?
This is a pretty general property, right?
So you can test many functions that are idempotent,
or could be idempotent in some cases, and you can test those
with hypothesis without even having
to write the test code for yourself.
So here we see another kind of test, which is pretty common.
We say that the AST literal eval function is equivalent
to the eval built in, right?
So that is if you call the two functions with the same input,
they should give you the same output.
And so we set up all of our various inputs.
We call the two functions, and then we assert
that they're equal.
But here we actually see a problem.
One takes a node or string argument.
So we're passing literal eval, the node or string,
and we're passing source to our eval function.
So we would actually want to edit this a little.
The Ghostwriter is designed to give you a starting point,
but it's not always complete.
If we want to test for the addition operator,
hypothesis can write the sort of standard tests for addition.
The addition should be associative.
So if we add A to B plus C, or we add A plus B to C,
we should get the same results either way.
That's associativity.
Commutativity, A plus B equals B plus A.
And the identity operator is just that there should be some value
such that adding it to A gives you A.
And with integers, that's zero.
Right? Next form of tests that we can write is if we just say,
I want to test for gzip compression.
I don't know what the properties should be.
Just like work it out, hypothesis, please.
And so here it will actually give us a round trip test.
So it will say, hmm, well, you asked for compress,
and I happen to see that there's a decompress function
in the same module.
I bet if I call compress, and then I call decompress
on the output from compress,
that it should give me the original thing back.
Does this seem reasonable?
Yeah. It's done with a classic AI technique known as a big list
of regular expressions and a couple of statements.
And this works remarkably well.
Again, this is actually a template.
It's not quite complete,
because the data strategy here is just nothing.
That's the empty strategy that I talked about before.
So if you try to run this, hypothesis will actually say,
you haven't told me what data should be.
And in this case, we can look it up in the documentation
and see that data should be a byte string.
And if we put in binary, then this test will run as well.
Okay.
Does this make sense so far?
Can you imagine applying this to your own code
and checking the results?
You can even run it on whole modules.
I'm not showing that here
because you end up having to scroll a lot.
But if you apply it to your entire module
and just pipe that into a test file,
you get a pretty good starting point for some tests.
This is what you get if you check whether JSON round trips.
It turns out that the standard library JSON loads function
has a lot of arguments.
Like a lot of arguments.
So one thing here is,
we're just gonna cut this down a bit.
We don't actually care about all of them,
so I've edited this.
And for the object, I've put in that recursive definition
of JSON that I showed you earlier.
So the definition of JSON, according to the standard,
is that it's none, a Boolean, a number, or a string,
or a list of JSON things, or a dictionary,
which JavaScript people call an object,
where the keys are strings
and the values are any valid JSON thing.
Make sense?
So what does this test actually do when we run it?
This is gonna take long enough.
I can take guesses from the audience.
Any guesses as to what this will do?
Can you outperform my laptop?
Yep.
This particular test will eventually...
I don't know.
It was fine this morning.
Yeah, never do a live demo.
They're just cursed.
Yeah, we're not gonna wait for the result here.
What you would see if my laptop was faster
is that if obj is nan, then of course,
the object and loaded are not equal to each other
because they're nan.
You can also go, only give me objects
which are equal to themselves,
and then you get a list containing nan.
It turns out that Python's list comparison
has a special case where it just checks
if the other list is the same object as this list,
and if so, it returns that they're equal,
even though some of the elements don't compare equal
because they're nan.
Fun times.
Okay.
The ghostwriter should be faster on your laptops
because you won't be doing live demos.
So part three of four for this talk,
and our first of two before the end,
we're gonna be talking about common test tactics.
So these are ways to apply properties to your code
and common kinds of properties
that will often be relevant for you.
I kind of divide these into properties
which are applicable to most code.
Almost all code bases will have many cases
where you can have this fuzzing property
where you just call your code
and check that it didn't raise an exception.
Roundtrip pairs or equivalent functions tend,
like most functions are not roundtrips
or equivalent to another function,
but most code bases will include some that are.
For example, most of us, I would imagine,
read data and then save data.
Well, try saving data, reading it back,
and asserting that you got the same data again.
Metamorphic properties are also common,
but we'll talk about them in detail later.
And then there are situational properties
where just checking that your output is okay,
checking things like the binary operator properties
or stateful model-based tests are also pretty useful.
So again, I wanna emphasize,
literally just calling your code
with the weird inputs that hypothesis will come up with
is embarrassingly effective on my code.
It finds a lot of bugs.
For roundtrips, we saw those with the gzip example
and with JSON.
If you have save and load, encode or decode,
send or receive, if you ever convert between data formats
or do logically inverse things,
these tend to be present in almost every code base,
and they also tend to be really important.
If it turns out that saving something to the database
and then bringing it back gives you a different object,
that is a really important bug to find out about,
even if it's a rare edge case.
So the fact that they're critical to our code,
they also tend to be logically complicated enough,
and those logic bugs tend to be silent failures.
Instead of a crash, you'll just get a silent wrong result.
And that, I think, makes it particularly ripe
for property-based testing.
So if you take one thing away from this tutorial,
use hypothesis on all of your roundtrip functions.
That's probably the highest priority thing.
For equivalent functions, I talked about this before.
If you have the single-threaded
versus the many-threaded version,
the old version or the new version,
or sometimes things like the order
in which you call functions shouldn't matter,
and you can test that, in fact, it doesn't matter.
You can also have functions
which are equivalent only for some inputs.
For example, functions which take any range of numbers,
but if the two functions are both fed only positive numbers,
then they should have the same output.
You can test those kinds of things as well.
Or sometimes functions are like special cases
of another function.
In that case, you can check that they're equivalent
for those special cases.
I always feel silly writing these kind of validations,
but I find them really valuable as well.
And I prefer to write them as assertions in my code.
I just calculated probability.
Is that probability between zero and one?
Just assert.
Zero less than or equal to probability less than equal one.
Is my string non-empty?
Is the thing the type I expected?
These give me really fast feedback
when I try an ambitious refactoring
and turn out to break a lot of things.
Property-based testing was originally developed in Haskell,
which is the first time I've mentioned that.
And it's named for algebraic properties.
They're pretty rare in Python code,
but if they come up, they're worth testing.
There's this lovely blog post from Atlassian,
Programming with Algebra,
which actually finds that these kind of properties
are really useful for things like merging streams of events
as part of their data infrastructure.
So again, if you're working with that kind of code,
which is doing principled data transforms,
these kind of things can be useful.
Now look them up then.
And then model-based or stateful testing
I've alluded to a few times.
It would be a full tutorial of its own
to go through it in depth.
But the basic idea is that instead of hypothesis
giving you inputs to a test function,
you have it choose which of a range of possible actions
to take as well as the inputs to each action.
So this basically gives you a state machine API.
State machines are very powerful.
Very flexible, and they're particularly good for APIs
which are stateful.
So for example, I use this with my friend Dimitri
to build schema thesis,
which is a tool for automatically testing
REST or GraphQL or OpenAPI web APIs.
You just point the tool at your schema
and it uses stateful model-based testing
to work out what sequence of calls the API should I make
to try to uncover errors.
Metamorphic relations are probably the most complicated
kind of property I'm going to talk about.
The idea is that for cases where we don't know
what the relationship between the input
and the output should be,
we might still be able to look at the relationship
between two input-output pairs.
For example, we might be able to say,
even if we don't know what the code should do,
if we can get coverage information,
we'll be able to say if we change any uncovered code,
that shouldn't change the result.
This turns out to be really powerful in compiler testing
because often the uncovered code
triggers different compiler optimizations.
And you don't need to know what the code does
to know that changing code which didn't get executed
should never change the result of the code that did.
If it does, you have a compiler bug.
You might know for some numerical code
that if you double all of your inputs,
the output should also be doubled,
even if you don't know
what that relationship should be in detail.
You might be able to say that negating every element
of a list and then sorting it
should be the same as sorting it
and then reversing the list and then negating the elements.
So in fact, the government of France has a similar thing
where they used formal methods to prove that
their tax code was such that
any time you would increase your pre-tax income,
your post-tax income should never decrease.
Right, this is actually a pretty common problem
where there are so many tricky interacting laws
about benefits and tax rates and so on,
that in many cases, earning more money
leaves you with less money.
And they decided to use software testing techniques
to make sure that that would no longer be the case.
So metamorphic relations tend to be
quite specific to your domain,
but this idea of thinking about
what do I know about the relationship
between two different runs of my function
if I know something about the relationship
between the inputs or between the outputs
can be quite powerful.
But the bottom line here, right,
is just put assertions in your code,
then run your code just on random inputs.
Be careful to cover all of the edge cases with hypothesis.
And then test any round trips that you have.
Those ones are super valuable and often quite easy.
After that, just relax, right?
You have 80-20 to it.
You have got, I think, a majority of the value
you can get from fancy testing
with a tiny fraction of the possible work.
Of course, the further work to get the next bit
can also be very valuable.
But if you're wondering, just write your assertions,
fuzz your code, test your round trips, and then relax.
Any questions?
So, in American traditional testing,
is there anything you can do to apply it
to the other methods of what we do in the unit test?
Is there anything that hypothesis doesn't do
that we should still use traditional unit tests for?
Absolutely.
Hypothesis doesn't test that you got
exactly the right answer.
So, I tend to think most projects should have
some amount of property-based tests.
Typically, I think between 20 and 80%
is usually a good fraction.
So, I have projects at both ends of the scale.
I've also seen projects like Black, for example,
the autoformatter, just has one property-based test,
which says, given arbitrary Python source code
generated by hypothesis, Black should not crash.
And Black should be idempotent when you reformat.
That should not make any further changes.
And so, that single test has given them a lot of value.
It's found dozens of bugs by now.
But they decided that it wasn't worth trying
to write much more specific tests.
So, they use snapshot testing instead
for that kind of thing.
In general, I would tend to think, like,
a lot of this is kind of experience.
You get a sense for your particular project
and for property testing.
So, my serious advice is something like,
start by just getting every round trip
that you can think of tested.
And then, think for a little bit about,
are there properties that you think might catch bugs?
And if so, test those.
But don't feel that you have to replace
all of your existing tests.
Unit tests are great.
They're really fast.
They tend to be stable.
Hypothesis is a great complement to them,
but I don't think it's a substitute.
Yeah, so this is, can you control the number of permutations
from each strategy?
We'll cover that in the final section
on practicalities of property-based testing.
But we have quite good support for settings
which allow you to control things like run time,
the per test case deadline, and so on.
Last question on this section,
and then we'll jump back into exercises for a while.
All right then.
Let's do some exercises.
In this case, I think we're moving on to,
it's notebook two.
Actually, I'm curious.
Did any of you already go through notebook one?
Or was everyone working on just notebook zero last time?
Thumbs up if you worked on notebook zero.
Great.
Thumbs up if you worked on notebook one.
All right, we're doing notebook one.
Yeah.
Great.
So yeah, this will give you hands-on experience
with hypothesis, different strategies,
map, filter, and some of the other patterns
that Zach went over in the first part of the talk.
Yeah.
And it will also discuss more deeply
what we mean by identifying properties
to do property-based testing to complement your manual tests.
So last time you wrote by hand,
this string has three vowels.
That is a manual test.
Now, can you add to that,
what are properties of my count vowel problem or function
that I can write a hypothesis-driven test for?
That's something that you'll do in this exercise.
Cool.
Thank you.
Give this one about 20 minutes.
Maybe take any questions about this
and then we'll move on to notebook two
at the end of that time for people who want to.
So I'm glad to see so many of you are still with us,
still awake, no one's run away screaming just yet.
It's always a good sign.
So we've got about 40 minutes left of this tutorial.
That's just enough time for part four
on putting it into practice.
So like each of the other parts, we'll have a short talk,
time for some questions,
and then continuing exercises at the end,
whether you want to keep going with the exercises
you've been working on for the last few minutes
or jump into the exercises specifically for part four.
So you've learned the kind of principles
of property-based testing.
You learned what it is,
how to describe the data that you'll use,
and how to recognize and apply common patterns
in your own code.
Beyond that, I want to talk about some of the practical tips
for applying this to kind of production workloads.
It always feels kind of weird to try to work out,
how do I describe the tests
for the systems that I use at work?
They're not exactly production because they're the tests,
but they're not exactly examples or toy things either.
So we'll talk about settings and settings profiles.
We'll talk about the way that Hypothesis saves examples
to replay and how you can store and manage that.
And we'll talk a bit about fuzzing
and also the release cadence.
So one important point,
which we got to in the questions earlier,
is that I see property-based testing
as part of a more general test plan.
It's not all you should do.
And the last thing I want you to believe
is come away saying like,
Zach says we should only write property-based tests.
Not at all.
I think you should write at least some property-based tests,
but probably not literally all of your tests
should be property-based.
I see sort of 10 to 90% as being a pretty good ratio
for most projects.
And where in that depends on what kind of project it is.
One neat tip is design custom strategies
for your particular project.
They're great as a single source of truth
for what kind of weird edge cases
does this data structure need to handle?
What does our user model actually allow?
What kind of thing could be in this file format?
And updating your tests and your strategies independently
means that you have sort of additive work
rather than multiplicative work, right?
If you have those shared helper functions somewhere
rather than writing them out each time,
when you expand one or when you refactor it,
it gets picked up by your whole test suite immediately.
And that can be a really nice way to test a refactoring,
for example, if you generalized something.
A couple of patterns for that.
One which we've seen here is just write a function
which returns a strategy.
Those may or may not use the composite decorator
that we saw.
One underrated strategy is literally just write
some global variables.
Write out the strategies in detail
and just assign them to a global variable
that you can use later or import from other test modules.
And register type strategy for custom types.
Who here has ever indulged in print debugging?
Who here likes it more than debuggers?
At least sometimes, yeah.
If you're doing print debugging with Hypothesis,
you might have noticed that it prints every single example.
And this gets pretty verbose.
So there's two improvements.
The first is the note function.
Hypothesis.note is basically print,
but only during the final example.
So this means that you just only see the prints
associated with the input that Hypothesis displays for you.
Nice little sanity saving maneuver.
And the other one is the event function.
This is a little different.
In the statistics, when you show statistics,
the event function will give you the fraction of test runs
that had each distinct value you passed to event.
So this can be great to get a sense
of what the distribution is.
I usually recommend against paying too much attention
to distributions, but if it's like 99 to one or something,
that's worth looking at.
If it's just 10 to one, I probably wouldn't worry.
Statistics looks something like this.
Who saw statistics during the exercises?
One person.
So if you pass dash dash hypothesis shows statistics,
you will get something like this.
It will show you during the generate phase
or the shrink phase, how long each test tended to take,
how many passing and failing and invalid examples it tried.
The invalid ones, for example,
when a filter rejected too many times.
We'll just throw out the whole example and start over
and call that one invalid.
How many failures did we find?
And then these events.
So in this case, 40% of the time the length of LS was one
and 60% it was length two.
And we split that out during each phase separately
so that you can get a decent sense of what was going on.
Settings are a separate thing.
They're kind of useful.
So a number of people ask things like,
how many examples does hypothesis run?
The answer by default is 100 random examples for each test.
But that's configurable.
You can decide how many you want and just pass that either
as a decorator on the test function or you can set
up settings profiles where you can determine, for example,
am I in CI or not?
If I'm in CI, I want a longer, more rigorous one.
If I'm locally, I want a quicker run, for example,
for local development.
And you can select the profile
from the PyTest command line as well, as well as setting certain
settings from the command line.
So the two settings to look at for performance.
There's a per test case deadline.
By default, that's 200 milliseconds.
So most tests, if they're taking longer than that,
it's because something unexpected has gone wrong.
But sometimes, particularly if you're writing tests
that use NumPy or PANAS or Django,
it might be totally normal for your test cases
to take longer than that.
So if this triggers, I recommend, like, remembering,
it's just a warning, right?
If you decide that you're comfortable with it taking
that long, you know better than a hypothesis
about your test suite.
And you can adjust that.
You can increase it to a larger value or turn it off entirely.
And the other one is the max example setting.
How many passing examples should hypothesis find before it decides
that it's done with your test?
By default, that's 100.
This one is a really easy way to make your tests more
or less rigorous at the cost of taking less or more runtime.
Right? If you turn that up to 10,000,
you'll be more likely to find bugs.
And it will take about 100 times longer to run.
So 100, we found, it tends
to be a pretty good default for most people.
It's rigorous enough that it will find common bugs pretty quickly,
while also not taking forever.
I've also been asked,
you guys are well ahead of the curve here, about determinism.
Is hypothesis deterministic?
And the answer there is no.
It's not deterministic.
Hypothesis is deliberately randomized
because we have the database to make sure
that if we discover any failures, we'll save them
and then replay them before doing random generation the next time
you run.
That means that if you find a bug and your test fails
and you run your test again and it passes, you can be confident
that it's because you fixed the bug rather
than because hypothesis didn't find the same bug again.
If you do want determinism, though, there is a de-randomize setting
and you can also set the hypothesis random seed
from the command line.
In both of these cases, I tend to think it can be useful to run
in deterministic mode, but you want
to separately have a non-deterministic road
to discover new bugs.
Question?
Periodically.
So this is, if you're running a hypothesis regularly over,
for example, several months of development, do you want
to re-randomize that to change the set
of examples it's looking for?
Great question.
So this is basically my argument against the de-randomize setting.
We have it in there for people who really value determinism,
but I think that being able to discover new bugs tends
to be pretty useful.
The other one there is we'll talk in a moment about, sorry, go ahead.
Okay. Yeah.
So if you find a bug early on in development,
should you continue replaying that forever?
Hypothesis will evict database entries if they turn
out no longer to trigger a bug.
So if you discover a bug and then fix it,
hypothesis will replay that for a little while and be like, okay,
I guess that was fixed.
Let me throw that one out.
It can make sense to blow away the database occasionally,
but it should automatically manage itself just fine.
We'll talk more about databases in a moment.
This blog post from my colleague Nelson Elhage is really good on two kinds
of testing, sort of distinctions between people who use tests
as a tool to find bugs, which is in some ways
like the natural mode for hypothesis, and people who use tests as a way
of checking for regressions during team development.
And in that case, you really want a very fast,
quite deterministic workload, so you can be confident
that your CI system will only ever fail
if a bug has been newly introduced rather than just newly discovered.
And in that case, it's really important to complement
that with a separate system for finding new bugs over time.
Hypothesis is designed so that you can configure it
to run in either of those modes.
Who here uses the random module?
Yeah. Randomness is great, but it is also kind of a curse
for reproducible tests.
So hypothesis has a couple of tricks to deal with this.
The first is just there's a strategy for instances
of the random.random class.
I would recommend passing one of these around.
It's a good practice to make sure that you isolate the state
of various parts of your program.
But there is also the random module strategy,
which will just seed the global random module for if you're using code
or calling code that does that.
And there is a register random function
so that you can add more known instances of the random class
that need to be seeded and then reset after each test.
This is useful for libraries
which maintain their own separate copy, for example.
If it is a popular library that's doing this,
hypothesis just has native integration with many of these
to manage them automatically.
So my general advice is like you don't need to think
about libraries unless you notice a problem.
And if you notice a problem, please open an issue on hypothesis
and we'll fix it.
So reproducing failures.
I've been talking about the database.
One option is just rerun your test
and the database will take care of it.
And that works great on your laptop locally.
Another option is to add an explicit at example decorator.
So these ones, they take the same arguments as given,
but instead of strategies, you pass the values.
And so this is a great way to write regression tests
or as Ryan was mentioning earlier, you can write at example,
blah, blah, blah, dot x fail for an example
which should cause your property based test to fail.
If those fail, we also have a print blob setting.
So this is true for CI systems.
And we'll print this kind of base 64 blob
so that you can add the reproduce failure decorator and ensure
that you can pretty much always reproduce a failure
that you had in CI locally.
It's kind of awkward, but we are willing to put
up with a little bit of awkwardness to guarantee
that you never have this problem
where your CI system found a failure
and you just can't reproduce it locally.
That used to happen and it was really annoying.
So it's temporary, but pretty useful.
The database by default just lives in a local directory.
You might have noticed this dot hypothesis directory showing
up on your local file system.
But if you're, who here often writes code as part of a team?
As many as 10 of us.
So if you're working with others, you might want
to share your hypothesis database with them.
So that if anyone's run or a CI run finds a bug,
that starts showing up in everyone's tests.
And there are a couple of ways to do this.
The default is the local directory based example database.
But we also have options like the Redis example database
for if you have a Redis server around or a GitHub actions cache.
So these are systems where you can set up, for example,
a profile where on CI you use the shared database.
And in local development, you use your read,
write local database and your read only view
of the shared database.
The result here is that if CI finds a failure and then anyone
on your team can reproduce that failure just
by running your test locally.
It's a remarkably nice workflow.
Any questions about the database before I start running
through more useful tips?
Nope. Okay.
Let's keep going.
So far you've been using hypothesis in sort
of random exploration mode.
And this is pretty useful.
But sometimes targeted or guided search can be more effective.
And so the target function does pretty much that.
You give, you call hypothesis.target in your test function
and you give it a score that it will try to maximize
and optionally a label.
If you want to call it on multiple different things,
you need to give it several calls
with different labels each time.
And then hypothesis will do a sort of hill climbing search to try
to find examples that have the largest possible scores.
This can be pretty useful for things
like target the absolute value of some numerical error
from a simulation or a calculation.
Or try to maximize the number of tasks in this queue
that haven't been executed yet.
Or try to maximize the run time of this function.
Or minimize the compression ratio.
Or even sometimes just balancing, you can pass one
if it was valid or zero if it was invalid.
This can be a good way to avoid filtering only to valid input
if you want to test both valid and invalid while still biasing it
somewhat in that direction.
If you don't know what you're targeting,
then coverage guided fuzzing can be a great technique.
The idea here is that we start by running random examples.
And then each time we find an example that executes a line
of code that we haven't seen tested before, we add that example
to our pool of known inputs.
And as we go on, we start to produce new inputs
by trying variations on that pool of existing inputs.
And the idea is this lets us get through sort
of multi-step criteria much more often than you would expect
by chance, right?
You have sort of exponential difficulty to make it
through multiple conditions.
But if you can sort of evolve your way through
by local variations, that can be much easier.
So, atheris is a library from Google.
It's a wrapper for the well-known libfuzzer for Python.
It's designed to run a single function for something
like hours or even days, sometimes weeks.
It's particularly good for C extensions or native code
because it can use coverage of native machine code.
But hypothesis integrates really well with this.
So, this here is in fact a complete integration
where we define our little property-based test
in the usual way.
We call our atheris setup function,
and then we call atheris fuzz.
And that will just sit there until you control C
or otherwise kill the program,
trying out new variations over and over again,
trying to evolve inputs which do something unexpected.
There's also hypo-fuzz.
This is one of my side projects.
It's designed, instead of fuzzing one test,
to fuzz a whole test suite.
So, it will use PyTest to find all
of your property-based tests, collect them up,
divide them between all the cores on your machine,
and then do coverage-guided fuzzing
of all of them simultaneously.
So, interleave execution, it will prioritize them dynamically
in a variety of ways.
And in both cases, both for hypo-fuzz and also atheris.
As soon as a failure is found, it just gets saved
to the database in the usual way.
So, in order to reproduce a failure found by the fuzzer,
you just run your test.
So, if you're planning to leave your tests running overnight
to find bugs, I would recommend leaving them running
under hypo-fuzz, or maybe another fuzzer,
rather than just using hypothesis itself.
That's basically just because there are some design decisions
you can put into a long-running fuzzer, which just take, like,
a couple of minutes to really pay off,
but then pay off increasingly much
over subsequent minutes and hours.
Last thing here, I think,
is you've all pip installed hypothesis today.
Hypothesis releases pretty regularly.
So, every pull request to the library is automatically released
on PyPI as soon as CI finishes running,
because continuous deployment is great.
That means we think you should probably just update
on a schedule that works for you.
That might be weekly or monthly,
to make sure that you get any new features
or performance improvements or improved error messages
that we've put in.
Hypothesis takes stability and semantic versioning
extremely seriously, and it may not surprise you to hear
that hypothesis is very rigorously tested.
But you should still probably pin all your transitive dependencies,
just as a good practice.
So, that's the end of this section of the talk.
Going to take some questions now, and then after questions,
our remaining time till 5 p.m. will be, you're welcome to hang
around and work on further exercises,
including for this section, or leave early if you wish.
So, thanks very much for coming, everyone,
and thanks for sticking with us.
All right.
Any questions about this section?
Seems like we answered them.
Yep.
Yep. So, for the recording, I'll try to repeat this
and to make sure I understand you.
If you have a library which defines a lot
of its own custom types, so for subsets of possible values
or custom data structures,
does that make property-based testing particularly valuable?
Is that right?
I think that maybe makes property-based testing easier
in some ways, because you just say, build the instances
of this type, and you can register a strategy
for that custom type and get it exactly generated each time.
So, it maybe makes it more ergonomic,
but I think property-based testing can be equally useful,
even if you don't have that, if you're using built-in data types
or messier data structures.
For example, I mentioned earlier,
Black, the autoformatter, has gotten a lot of value
out of just saying, give me strings
which are syntactically valid Python source code, and I'll check
that if I format them twice, it's the same as format
in the months, and I don't crash.
That's a relatively simple test, conceptually.
It was kind of a pain in the butt to engineer the strategy
to generate arbitrary syntactically valid Python
source code, but if you have those custom data types,
it will often be more obvious what the properties might be.
You know, round trips between them, you can just look
at the types and see whether that might be a round trip.
So, this is a little bit tangential, but I hope related.
One thing that is interesting about the testing process is
oftentimes when you're writing tests for your code,
it's the first time you're really using your code.
Right, like, writing code is not using code.
Once you're actually writing tests and you're like, man,
writing tests for this is awful.
Guess what?
Using the code is probably awful.
Like, if your code is very hard to test,
there's a good chance that your code is hard to use
and hard to read.
So, it's actually kind of like your first chance
to get feedback on your own design.
So, kind of along those lines in terms of if you have
a lot of data types or a lot of stateful code
that you wish was pure functional,
and you're just clobbering yourself with these tests,
that might be a good signal to iterate on simplifying things.
Yeah, I've actually been very surprised by how informative
it is to go through the testing process
to improve my design process.
Yeah.
So, where are the failed cases cached?
Hypothesis generates the examples it uses by sort of parsing,
making random choices with a random number generator,
which you can think of as parsing a stream of random bits.
So, the thing that we need to save is like
the underlying byte string, and we stash that
in the database.
By default, those live in files under the .hypothesis
directory in your local working directory.
But, let's see.
You can also store them in Redis
or a number of other places.
One nice pattern is if you're using something
like GitHub Actions, you can cache that database.
So, subsequent CI runs will also replay from the cache.
And then, one of the databases we have
will automatically download the zip file
from GitHub Actions and replay any examples
that were found by CI.
But yeah, by default, they're stored
just on your local file system.
Okay.
You didn't mention the file.
I'm sorry.
Sorry.
The notion of random assertions,
there are some adjustments.
Is there any kind of change to do that
with the calendar for the running function,
either performing files or taking out a file
and then doing the same thing?
Great question.
So, I've recommended a few times
putting the assertions in your code, not just your tests.
Is there any penalty for that?
So, the first is just a logical thing.
There will be some assertions which only apply
to a subset of inputs.
So, it's not correct to put those in your code.
You have to put them in a test
where you know you'll only generate those inputs.
But more generally, performance is a potential concern.
If your assertion is very slow,
then you put it in your production code,
then you get a slowdown.
Python does have a dash O mode
or the Python optimized environment variable,
which will skip running assertions.
That's why many security linters will say,
you should not use assertions
because they're thinking of beginners
who will often use them to like,
assert user is authorized,
assert user is logged in.
And then if you run in Python optimized mode in production,
you no longer check those things.
So, that can be a security risk, right?
You've got to make sure that your assertions
don't change the behavior of your program,
that they only check what your program is doing
in some way.
But given that, my preference is usually to
write assertions pretty liberally
and then if they turn out to be a performance issue,
run with Python optimized mode in production.
If that becomes complicated,
you could also do a similar thing
where you have an environment variable
that you set during testing and say like,
if I am in testing mode,
assert all these things.
Yeah, so if you want to check that your code
raises a particular exception type,
I tend to think that that's not really a concern
for hypothesis itself,
but for example, there's the
PyTest.Raisers context manager.
You can try whatever, accept my exception,
else assert I expected, whatever.
Yeah, so the way I tend to think about this is
PyTest is a bundle of two different things.
There's the test runner,
which lets you select tests, execute tests,
find all the tests to be executed and so on.
Hypothesis doesn't do that at all.
PyTest also bundles in some things like the raises,
context manager, the warns, context manager,
fixtures and so on,
which help you write more expressive test functions.
And hypothesis is pretty much purely on that side of things.
So hypothesis will work with PyTest,
but it will also work with unit tests.
So you could use like self dot,
I think assert raises or assert warns,
depending on the style you prefer.
All right.
Yeah.
Would there be a clash between PyTest settings
and hypothesis settings?
We try pretty hard,
like mostly no because they're configuring
different libraries.
So, yeah, so I usually use PyTest
to run my hypothesis tests.
In fact, I'm a core dev of both.
So from that perspective,
I say we, but partly just I try to make sure
that they play nicely together
because I know a lot of people use them together.
Hypothesis actually ships with the PyTest plugin
that improves the integration in a few ways.
Hypothesis settings are configurable
only through Python code.
We decided that it was just simpler to say like,
no, we're not going to read config files.
We're not going to look at environment variables.
So our PyTest plugin will actually read things
like from the command line for you
to let you select the profile and so on.
But my preferred way of configuring a hypothesis
is by having a PyTest, conftest.py
and just calling the hypothesis code
in that setup file.
Great questions.
If that's all of them though,
thanks again everyone for coming.
Ryan and I will be around here until five
if we want to keep going through exercises
or keep asking you questions.
But that's a wrap.
Thanks so much.
Thank you.