All right. Welcome to PyCon. This is your first tutorial. It must be because this is
the first tutorial at PyCon. So I got to chat with some of you before we got started here.
We have some very mixed backgrounds today, which is always the case with a tutorial like
this. Some of you have done Python before. Some of you have written code before, but
never done Python. Some of you have not written code at all. Now, this tutorial was originally
intended for folks who have never written a line of code, never even seen a line of
code. For many of you, that means it's going to be a little bit slow at times. Also, for
those of you who are brand new to coding, you are in the right place. This will be a
little fast sometimes, partly because many people in this room have written some code
before. So there's no way we can please everyone at all moments. If you're a little intimidated,
if it's a little slow, it's just going to be the way things are sometimes this morning.
So this place that I'm in, does anyone know what this is called? I'm actually typing code
right here. Yeah. Yep. Python interpreter. That is a name for it. Anyone ever heard another
name for this? The REPL. That is another name for it. Anyone heard another name? Terminal.
That, ooh, yes. I am in a terminal in the Python REPL and in the Python interpreter,
which is sometimes also called the Python interactive interpreter. Anyone heard another
name? IDE. This one isn't technically an IDE, though I like that one, because it is something
you see embedded in IDEs. And in fact, later on, you might wonder whether I'm using an
IDE. Python prompt is another one I sometimes hear. Python shell. Code editor. Ooh, this
isn't a code editor yet, but we will see a code editor. I like that one. And the reason
is it's funny because we're not at our system prompt. I'm going to exit Python here. I'm
now at my system prompt. My system prompt, if I open up terminal on Linux or Mac, if
I open up command prompt on Windows, this is my system command prompt. I can do things
like change directories, go up one directory, change into this directory. Apparently, I
have something from PyCon last year. I can list this directory. There's nothing in this
directory, so it's empty here. This is my system command prompt. When I type Python
or Python 3, either one works on my machine. On Windows, sometimes you have to type just
different things on different machines. I'm now in the Python repel, Python interactive
interpreter, the Python prompt, the Python shell. There are far too many names for this
place that I am at. Melanie in the back of the room there at some point said that these
three little greater than signs look kind of like the back of an alligator, I think,
which is a reptile. I think alligators are reptiles. Yes, they are reptiles. Alligators
are reptiles. This is the Python rep tile. There you go. The Python repel. The Python
repel, that's the way you can remember those three little greater than signs. If you see
those, that's where you're typing code. This is basically an interactive sandbox. We're
able to type Python code, immediately see results. It's not a code editor only because
it does more than, well, it actually doesn't edit code. It allows you to write code. You
can't really change it. I can hit the up arrow and I can run code again, but I can't change
code I've already written. It's very, very interactive. It's a little sandbox. We're
writing our code, seeing results. Anyone want to guess or maybe you think you know what
R-E-P-L stands for? Ripple. Yes. People either tend to know all four of the letters or they
know none of them because most of us, we don't need to know what repel means. You just know
it's called the repel. It actually describes what it does. Python is currently reading.
It's reading what I type here. It's evaluating or executing what I've written. I'll say
either one was fine, though. And then it'll print whatever the result of that thing is,
that line of code I've typed, and then it loops, meaning it just does the same thing
over and over. Go back to step one, in a sense, there. Step one, read, evaluate, print, and
then loop. All right. This is going to be very interactive today. Who thinks they know
the answer to this when I hit enter? Error. Great guess. There are no wrong guesses, by
the way. We don't know what we're doing. Error is a perfectly good one. Two. Two, two. Ooh,
that's a good guess. Four. That's the correct answer in this case. I wasn't tricking you
this time, though. I like those ideas. I am going to be tricking you. Two plus two equals
four. Python, you know, it obviously can do math. It is a programming language. It can
As we type here, it's reading. When I hit enter, that's what makes it finally evaluate
what I've written there. It prints out a result, and then it loops, meaning it waits for more.
Anyone know or want to take a guess what this thing does? What might it do? Yep. Yeah, this
is exponentiation. It's raising something to a power different from this. What's this?
Yeah, for those of you who've done maybe Matlab or you've used a calculator on your computer
or, you know, graphing calculator maybe, it's just multiplying. Star, star, raising something
to a power, multiplying two by itself ten times. What about this? What's your guess?
What might we see when I hit enter? What are the options? Possibilities. Could be a valuer.
That's going to be a very big number, right? Two by two by two. I mean, we all learned,
if we hadn't before, what exponential growth is like during the pandemic. This is exponential.
This is a very, very, very big number. So it could be an error. It isn't. Python can
represent a number as large as we'd like. It has something called big integers. This
is two to the 10,000th power. I don't know how big this number actually is, but it's
scrolled off my screen as you can see. They get bigger and bigger as they need to get
bigger, which is interesting. They just take up more memory as needed. So we're in the
Python REPL here. I'd like you to play with the REPL. We're going to take a very quick
break now. I know we're only a few minutes in, but I want you to get practice with this.
The reason I want you to write code yourself right now is you do not learn by putting information
into your head. Anyone know how you learn? Yeah, there's a phrase everyone says, you
learn by doing, right? The reason doing is important, it's not actually the doing that's
the important part. It's the memory retrieval. Active retrieval is the important part. The
fact that we're trying to take something that might be in our head and take it out of our
head. So it's important that we actually write some code to learn some things. So I'd like
you to bring up the Python REPL on your machine. The way you can do that is open up Terminal
or Command Prompt and type Python 3. And after you've done that, I'd like you to try out
some exercises. These exercises are on a website that we're working on today. I am not on the
Wi-Fi, even though I put up the Wi-Fi password. I'm just going to type the URL for the website
and hope it works. So that URL there, you can go to the website, click on the very first
one, pycon2023.pym.dev, and then click on the REPL over in that section. And then you
can see the sidebar there. Click on the REPL. And that website will stay up online afterwards,
so if you're watching the recording later, it should still hopefully exist on the internet.
I am now going to wander around the room along with Melanie, who's in the back of the room.
And oh, what I'd like you to do, I'm going to give you a few minutes here. Just a few
minutes to play around in the REPL. I want you to try to type 4 plus 7 in the REPL, see
what it does. And then try to do the other things that are at the very bottom of that
page, just a couple ideas for playing in the REPL. If you get done with all the things
in this first section here, actually no, if you manage to even open up the REPL, type
something and see a result, please put a green sticky, a green sticky note on the top of
your computer. Excellent. Some of you have already done that. If you're having trouble,
please put up a red sticky. All right, I'll be wandering around here.
All right. For the folks on the recording, I want to note a problem that multiple folks
are having here that I forgot to mention. I'm also going to increase my font size here.
That didn't quite work. Increase the font size over here. There we go. If you were on
Windows and you say, I know I installed Python, but when I type Python or Python 3, it opens
up the Microsoft store. What's going on? When you install Python, there is a checkbox that
says do you want to add Python or Python 3 to your path? This is on Windows when you
install Python from Python.org. You probably didn't check the checkbox. That's okay. I
didn't tell you to. What you can do instead of typing Python or Python 3 is on Windows,
you can type py. It's short. It doesn't work on Mac or Linux, although it does for me because
I have a special alias installed there. Type py and it will launch Python. Every time I
type Python or Python 3 today, if you're on Windows, type py instead. If Python or Python
3 works even though you're on Windows, excellent. That's great too. The reason is the Microsoft
store has their own Python that you can install. It competes with the Python.org. Sometimes
the two don't realize the other one's installed. All right. I see a lot of green stickies,
which is excellent. I want to ask you why are we using the red stickies? You want to
take a guess. I'll ask a different question, actually. When you have a question you need
help, what do you usually do? Yeah, what you were just doing. You raise your hand. What
is it difficult to do while you're raising your hand? Type. Right. I want you to be able
to type even if you have a question and no one's able to answer it at the moment. The
red stickies are to passively indicate I have a question. No rush, but come help me when
you have a moment. I'll be wandering back around. For those of you who have red stickies
up, I'll get to you in just a second. We'll get back to talking about the REPL and playing
with Python in just a moment. All right. So I would like to move on here. I want to ask
you oh, you can put down your green stickies, by the way, and your red stickies. When I'm
up here, I'm talking to you, feel free you don't need to stick up a stickie to ask a
question, by the way. Feel free to raise your hand or even just shout something out maybe
when it seems appropriate. What do you think will happen when I hit enter? Error. Yeah,
maybe unless it's a variable. So that's something we're going to talk about in just a moment
here. By the way, my name's Trey. It's nice to meet you. I'll be typing my name a lot
because it's fun to use your own name when you were learning coding. Yeah, we get an
error, a name error. There is not a variable called Trey. We're going to work in variables
with just in just a moment. But the thing I'm trying to do is represent characters.
Anyone know how I can do that if you've done programming before? There's a type of thing
that we often use. There's numbers. And there's the other thing, the two most common things
you see in programming. Strings, yeah. We need a string. So you can put double quotes
around something to make a string. Do you think I could put single quotes? What's your
answer? Do you think there's a difference between double quotes and single quotes? Maybe.
In some programming languages there aren't and some there are. I'll just tell you the
short answer in Python is there isn't. There isn't, except if you want to represent single
quotes inside your string. So if I wanted to say I don't know, what do you think will
happen here? Yeah, Python might not know where's the end of the string. We get an error in
invalid syntax. I could fix it by using double quotes. Anyone know another way to fix it?
Yeah, you can use a backslash before a quote to say I'm escaping this. Typically though,
since we have both single quotes and double quotes, it's pretty rare to have strings that
have both of them. So you just switch the quote you're using. If you prefer one, you
need a single quote or a double quote, you switch to the other. Another question I want
to ask is what are the possibilities? What might happen when I hit enter here? What are
the options? We might see an error, always an option, always a possible option we hit
enter. We might see an error. What else might happen? Yeah, we smoosh the stuff together
somehow. Maybe we'll get PyCon and 2023. So we get back a string of PyCon 2023. What other
type of thing could we get back? A number. We could get back 2023 or zero or something
else. We could get a number. We could get a string. We've seen numbers and strings at
this point. We could also get an error. In Python, in most programming languages, you
get this concatenation thing. You're taking two strings, adding them together. You smoosh
them together. In Python, you actually do get an error, which is unusual. It's one of
the few programming languages where a string plus a number is an error. You have to explicitly
convert that number to a string. There's a str function. We'll talk about functions later.
Or if you're just writing it out yourself, you do this. Now, this is a little bit silly
because we could also just write the string out ourselves. Notice there's no space here.
We'd have to put the space in ourselves if we wanted a space to be there. So we're going
to play with strings just a little bit at the REPL again, just a few minutes here. This
will actually be just a few minutes this time. I know it took us a little while to
get up the REPL before. Play with strings. So on the website, we are under strings. At
the very bottom of the page, string exercises. Try strings out in the REPL for just a few
minutes here. I'll be wandering around. If you have a question on anything, stick up
a red sticky. Oh, and once you've tried anything with strings in the REPL, put up a green sticky.
All right. So a couple folks asked about the timer that I'm using here. Yes, this is written
in Python. Countdown. If you have ever installed a Python package, I'm guessing most of you
haven't since you're brand new to Python. Python 3-M pip install countdown CLI. It'll
be on the recording. You can write it down if you'd like. You don't need to do that right
now. It will globally install on your machine that little countdown script if you ever need
a countdown timer for some reason. It's great for teaching. Who found something interesting
out? Yeah, what did you discover?
Yeah, I wonder if there was a typo involved there because it shouldn't be an error. So
you said double quote plus double quote. Comes out as 23. Yeah, so it might have been a typo
there. But this is interesting on its own, the fact that there's no numbers involved
here. We're just concatenating strings. Anyone else find another interesting thing? Yep.
Right. Yeah, a couple folks found this one. What does this do? What do we get? Right.
This is called self-concatenation. So in Python, you can multiply a string by a number. You
get that string that many times. Now, it doesn't have to be a single digit. Anyone try something
bigger? Or maybe you can take any string you'd like and concatenate it to itself lots of
times. Now, this seems really silly, right? But it is actually sometimes useful. When
might this come in handy? Sometimes you want one character in a string over and over, for
example. You want a string that has, for example, something I've done often when teaching,
I want 80 zeros on my screen to see whether my font size is big enough. It's an easy way
to check if the projector's in the right mode. Yep? Right. This is a great question. So some
programming languages, Perl is one example. Concatenation and adding numbers are two totally
different things. Because in Python, we've seen plus. What does plus do? There's two
different things we've seen it do. What does it do with numbers? Adds them. What does it
do with strings? It smushes them together. It concatenates them is the fancy word for
that. It's really just a fancy word for smushes together or gluing things together, I guess.
Plus does both, depending on what objects it works. Now, this is something you'll see
a lot, not just in Python, but other languages, that plus often does both things. Perl, you
need to use a period to concatenate. You need to use a plus to add. Two totally different
things. So they've actually decided those shouldn't be the same symbol. In Python in
particular, it's actually pretty common to see one symbol overloaded for multiple different
purposes. For example, multiplication. We've seen multiplication for two different things.
You can multiply numbers. Can you multiply strings? Anyone try this? What's your guess?
When I hit enter, what do you think we'll see? What could we see? Could always be an
error, right? Could be an error. Could be two 10 times. Could be something else. Turns
out it's an error. But you can multiply a string by a number, right? We just saw that.
So string times a number, that does a different thing than number times a number. So it's
very common in Python to have one symbol do different things depending on the types
of those objects. And those objects can usually control what happens there. So when I typed
tray before and we said it didn't work, somebody said, but if it was a variable, it might work.
How do you think you make a variable? If I wanted to say I have a variable X and its
value is four. X equals four. So who's done algebra before? Who liked algebra? A different
set of hands. I actually liked algebra. It was one of my favorite mathy things. And I
think it's because I got exposure to programming around the time I got exposure to algebra,
just a little bit of programming. And I liked the fact that they felt similar. But felt
similar in ways I couldn't quite say how are they different, how are they similar. I just
knew they were similar in some way. One very big way is they both have variables. So X
equals four. We're assigning the value of X to four. Now this is different from in math
where we say, well, we have some expression we need to solve for X. X equals X plus three.
This doesn't solve. There's no solving for X here. What does this do? Yeah, this assigns
X again to what value do you think? Whatever X was, which was four, plus three. So it should
be seven. So because I'm in the REPL here, I type an expression, I hit enter, I get the
result of that expression. Notice when there's an equal sign there, I'm doing an assignment,
there isn't a result. It's just empty. That's one of the expressions in Python where Python
doesn't see this as having a result. So if I'm maybe packing for PyCon, I've got two
pairs of socks isn't quite enough at PyCon. I mean, the sponsors are generous at their
booths. Socks are not so readily available. Shirts, you could come to Python. PyCon with
one shirt. There are lots of shirts here. You probably do not want shorts this year.
Something to wear. This here, socks equals, there's nothing after it. The REPL's not printing
anything out. There's no result of this. But if I say socks plus shirts plus pants and
I hit enter here, what am I going to see? Yeah, add two plus one plus three, we get
six. So assignment from the REPL's perspective doesn't have a result. Pretty much any other
expression you see it printed out there. All right. Again, we're just going to take
a couple minutes here. We're going to try out some variables in the REPL. So just two
minutes this time. And then we will finally be making a Python program after this. I promise
we'll actually make a working Python script. Got questions during these couple minutes
here? Stick up a red sticky. If you create a variable from the REPL, stick up a green
sticky on your machine. All right. I know that was very quick. Some interesting
things that we found. So if you make a variable, let's say it's x is two. I hit enter here.
We see that x is two. If I say x plus two and I hit enter, I see four. What is x? Yeah,
it's not a trick question. There will be trick questions. It's still two. How do I change
x if I want it to become the result of that? Yeah, I need to say x equals. So this is a
very common thing you'll see in Python, not just with plus, but with lots of operations.
Lots of operations in Python give you a new thing back, but they don't change the object.
We have two types of change in Python. There's changing a variable and then changing the
value that variable happens to be pointing to. We're not going to get into the fact that
in Python variables and objects are two distinct things, but they are. I'll link you to an
article on that later. It's a big and scary topic. You mostly don't have to know about
your first couple years of using Python because Python typically pushes you in the right direction
of reassigning variables when you need to reassign them. All right. We're going to be
making our own Python programs here. So what I'm going to do here, by the way, what you're
seeing with this split screen situation I have going on, which you probably don't have
on your machine, I'm using something called TMUX, Terminal Multiplexer. It allows me to
have up one terminal and in the same window, physical window on my machine, another terminal.
I happen to use a text editor. It is a very confusing text editor. Anyone want to guess
what it's called? Vim, Emacs. I like these confusing text. There are multiple confusing
text editors. The one I'm using is Vim. So I'm using Vim. I do not want you to use Vim.
Something nice about Vim, though, is that I can show it on the screen easily at the
same time as my code editor. So when you see something that looks like this, where it says
greetings.py, it may be complaining about something, there's some line numbers, this
is my text editor. You might have Visual Studio Code, you might have Notepad++, you might
have Sublime Text. Who has a different editor installed? Edit? Oh, G-Edit, yep, or B-Edit,
or there's a lot of them with that name, yep. Emacs. It's also PyCharm is another one. That's
kind of an ID, that's a bigger one. So I'm using Vim here. It doesn't matter where you
write this code, though. You're going to make a file called, ooh, I misspelled that. There
will be a lot of misspellings today. Greetings.py is how I'm going to make this. And I'm going
to type in here a string, hello world, and I'm going to save this file. Now, right now,
from the Python REPL, if I type Python 3 greetings.py, anyone want to guess what might happen?
We haven't tried this before. We get hello world, that's one option. What's another option?
We get an error, always an option. What's another option? Nothing. We see nothing. Any
other options? So when I hit enter, I get an error. It says invalid syntax. Why? Anyone
want to take a guess? That's a good guess. In the wrong directory, yep. Yeah. So this
is a very common problem. The answer here is that there are two places you can run code.
There's the Python REPL. There's your system terminal, your system command prompt, your
system shell, your system prompt, whatever you want to call that thing. I'm in the Python
REPL. I can tell that within those three greater than signs here. I can exit the Python REPL.
There's a function called exit. You put two parentheses after it. Hit enter. I'm back
at my system command prompt. Depending on how you launch Python, you might exit my...
It might close the window. If you bring up on Windows your command prompt or on Mac and
Linux your terminal, this is where I want to be. Now, I see a dollar sign. That means
I'm in my system command prompt. But I'm on Linux. Mac, you see a dollar sign typically
as well. Windows, you typically see C colon backslash greater than. Some kind of greater
than sign with something before it. This is my directory name. So greater than sign, dollar
sign, whatever it is, it's at the beginning there. I can type Python3 greetings.py. Now,
I want you to guess now. This is actually how you run a Python program or Python script.
It's Python file name. We have to do it from our system command prompt, not from within
the Python REPL. What do you think might happen now when I hit enter? It's your guess. Nothing
again. Always an option. Could also be an error. Could print hello world. Yeah. Nothing.
Why did nothing happen? Yeah, we didn't print anything, but I wasn't printing before. I
mean, if I type... Let's go into the Python REPL and I type hello world. Why do I see
hello world? Yep. Nothing's being outputted. Yes, it's not the full answer there, but you're
absolutely right. Up here, nothing's being outputted to standard out. Something is here.
Why? I didn't ask it to do that.
Yeah, so the REPL, read, evaluate, print, and loop, it is printing out the result of
this expression. Now, it's printing out the programmer readable representation. If I use
the print function, it's built in the Python. We'll talk about functions in just a moment.
Print open parenthesis, something, close parenthesis. There's no quotes. So, this is showing the
user readable, the human readable representation. Not that programmers aren't humans, but we
want to see things that other humans might not want to see, like those quotes there.
We need to do that in our program. So, at the Python REPL, there's P in the name. It's
printing the result of every single evaluation. In a Python program, nothing gets printed
unless you ask it to print explicitly, or unless you run a function that's going to
ask it to print. So, we need to tell it or ask it here to print out hello world. All
right. So, we're in our Python program. Now, when we run it, got to run it with Python
3 greetings.py, hit enter, it prints hello world. So, it took us a little while, but
we finally made hello world. It's just one line of code in Python, but we've got our
first Python program here. So, I would like you now to try to make your first Python program.
It can be hello world. I actually have two other recommendations on the website. Each
of them involves downloading a file called rand.py. I'll show you what rand.py has in
it real quick here as you download it on the website there. I'll put up here where we are
on the website. Again, that's pycon2023.py.dev under scripts. And we'll go ahead and download
it. We are at script exercises, very bottom of the page there. So, that rand.py file,
it looks like this. It's got in there import random. We haven't talked about import yet.
Random.randint, 1 in 100. What could I do if I wanted to see the value of x here? That's
your guess. Yeah, print x. Let's see what x is. So, we'll run python3 rand.py. And we
see x printed out. It's 60. Who thinks it's going to be 60 again? Yeah, it seems like
there's randomness going on. So, you can play with this, see if you can figure out what
it does, and see if you can figure out how to make a six-sided die roll. So, make your
own program called die or dice, whatever you'd like to call it. On the website there
are some instructions. There's another exercise after that for a meditative breathing exercise
that involves figuring out how to stop doing something for a couple seconds and start doing
it again. When you work through the first exercise, you make a random roll of a dice,
put up a green sticky. If you need some help, put up a red sticky if you have a question
or anything at all. So, not done quite yet, but a couple notes for folks at home, some
of the issues we're having here. When you were running your code, you're trying to launch
your program. If you're in the Python REPL, to get back to your system command prompt,
you can usually type exit, exit, open, close parenthesis. Also, you might sometimes be
in a different directory or folder. So, wherever you saved that file, you need to get into
that directory. So, you can use the CD command to change directories. There's also a shortcut
on Windows, which unfortunately I can't demonstrate here because I'm not on Windows. In Windows
Explorer, you can go up to the top location or URL bar, click on it and type cmd and hit
enter. It launches the command prompt in that directory there. What did you learn? Anyone
find anything unexpected? I know there were some glitches and unexpected things, in particular,
editors or IDEs or some folks who were in the browser found interesting things. Yep?
Yeah, this is an interesting one. So, what was said there was instead of Python 3 rand,
that didn't work. You have to put rand.py to actually get it to run, which is interesting
because on Windows, sometimes you can also just type rand or rand.py and it will run.
But if you put the Python 3 before it, it doesn't. So, depends on your operating system,
but whenever you're typing it this way, you've got to put the full file name. That's a good
thing. So, let's do this first one together. The meditative breathing one I know is a little
bit bigger. We may take a look at that one together later. This first one here, rolling
a die, what did you do to modify this to make it like a dice roll? Yeah, change the number.
So this first number 1 is a good one. Yeah, change 100 to 6 there. So, I called this rand.py
here. Let me rename this file to, actually I'll copy this file I guess to die.py because
we're rolling a single die. So, if we need a dice roll, we've got a dice roll. Rolls
a random number from 1 to 6 there. So, this is a nice one. So, this is a nice one. So,
so far when we've been using Python here, we've been doing things entirely within the
Python process. We haven't looked at any files. We haven't asked the user any questions. We've
only been outputting things. For those of you, I know at least a couple of you have
taken a Python tutorial at some point before. How can you prompt a user to ask them a question?
Anyone know? There's a function in Python that's built in. I know a couple of you have
probably seen. Yeah, so this function, it's not called prompt, though that would be a
nice name for it, to prompt the user. Instead, we're asking the user for input. And actually
before I talk about that, I want to talk about what functions are real briefly here. I'm
going to start up a new Python rebel. So, we've already used a function. What function
have we used besides input? Yeah, print. We've been printing things. So, print takes one
argument or you can even give it multiple arguments. An argument is these things that
go in the parentheses. So, a function has a name. After it, you put parentheses. What
happens if you don't put parentheses? Anyone ever tried this before? What's your guess?
What might happen? Yeah, we could get an error. Always a possibility. What else might happen?
See nothing at all. Maybe it'll print nothing. Yep. Get a description of the print function.
That's an odd guess. I feel like maybe you've done this before. We do. We get a description
of the print function. The reason is in Python, everything is an object. We've got a name.
That's a variable. Functions aren't any different from variables we make. Now, they're different
in the sense that there's a function object. Functions do a thing. A string doesn't do
a thing. It stores things. It's got some characters. Function does a thing. The way we use this,
the way we use a number, maybe we add the number, maybe we multiply the number, lots
of ways to use it. There's one way to use a function. What's the way to use a function?
There was a verb I used a moment ago. What was the verb? Call. You call a function. Now,
it's not the only verb, but it's just one thing you can do. You can call a function,
evaluate a function, execute a function. We call it with parentheses. Put print, parentheses.
You give it whatever you'd like to give it. Now, if I put nothing in those parentheses,
your guess is right. It does nothing. Well, sort of. It prints out a new line, because
print always puts a new line at the end. There's also a function called help. We can pass print
to help to ask for help on the print function, which is a little weird. So help in parentheses
print. We're giving it the print function. And it tells us print takes any number of
arguments. That's what that little star thing means there, which we haven't explained and
I won't explain. That's just a special syntax in Python. There's an optional sep, an end,
and file, and flush. We mostly don't care about these. But we could actually make it
not print a new line if we wanted to. Then it really does nothing. So arguments in Python,
there's two types of arguments. We'll mostly be working with one type. There's positional
arguments and keyword arguments, or named arguments. That's where you've got something
equals. We've been using positional arguments. Print name. Or print, we give it two arguments,
hello, comma name. It prints out hello, puts a space in between, which we can also customize
if we wanted, and then my name. What other functions have you seen in Python? I know
I've seen a couple of you call functions in your terminal there, your REPL.
The comma, yeah, well actually comma doesn't make the position argument. Comma makes an
argument. You've got argument, another argument. If it's just a comma, positional arguments.
But if it's a keyword argument, what do we put? What's the symbol you see with a keyword
or named argument? An equal sign. If I wanted to change the separator between these, instead
of being space, hello, space tray, it's dash. You make it a dash. Or maybe comma space.
We're going to put a bunch of things here. You put comma space between each of them.
You can also change the end there. Instead of new line, maybe we can make it two new
lines. That backslash in represents a new line character. The reason is, what happens
if I make a new line? What's the key I hit on my keyboard to make a new line character?
Yeah, enter. What does enter do? It runs the code. So we need something to represent in
a new line character. Backslash in. That was a weird one that I just did there. Let's type
that again. So if I do hello name, I change end. Its default is backslash in. If I make
it nothing, what happened? Yeah, it stuck three greater than signs after my name. Sort
of. It didn't stick those there. It always puts three greater than signs. There was no
new line. And so two lines are just kind of smooshed on top of each other. So now I'm
typing Python code right after the end of what kind of looks like a prompt. Because
it just didn't print a new line. We asked it not to. So other functions that I know
a couple of you have seen, how can you take a string and turn it into a number? Yeah,
turn it into an integer like this. There's two kinds of numbers in Python, though. What's
the other kind of number? Yeah, I haven't talked about this. If you have a decimal point
in a number, it's a floating point number. It actually works in a different way than
an integer does. So two types of numbers. So there's also a built-in float function
for turning into a floating point number. What if I have a number and I wanted to turn
it into a string? Yeah, maybe there's a string function. Right, some of you have done a Python
tutorial before. STR is how we spell string in Python. We like it short for some reason.
It turns it into a string. So lots of built-in functions. There are I think 72, 71, somewhere
in there are built-in functions. There's only a dozen or a couple dozen that are probably
going to be practically useful for you in day-to-day coding. There's stir, there's
int, there's float. There's a number of these things. We've also got print. We also have
other functions that can live in other places. We can define our own functions, but there's
also functions that can live in modules. So math is a module that's included with Python.
This is called the Python standard library. It has a function in it called squirt. Square
root. Yeah, that's what it's actually called, but it's spelled squirt. So if I give it a
number, it gives us the square root of that number. So there's lots of modules in the
Python standard library. There's third-party libraries as well. I have their own modules.
There's functions in them, and we can call those functions the same way we use any function.
What if I don't put parentheses after it and I hit enter? What do you think it might do?
Yeah, kind of something similar to what print did. It doesn't do anything useful. It tells
us this is a function object you're working with here. Same if you type a variable, you
hit enter. It shows you what's in that variable. There's another type of function in Python.
If I have a string, and I want to make that string lowercase, we don't have a lower function.
There is a way to do this, though. I'm sure a couple of you might have seen this. Anyone
remember, for those of you who've taken an intro to Python class before, what that is?
Yep. It's a dot, right? Yeah, not lower.name, name.lower. So we're still calling a function
here. We're still calling a function, but it's a function that lives on the name object.
Name is a string, and every string has this lower thing on it, this lower function. Anyone
know the name that a lot of programming languages really like this name, this distinction between
this type of function and the other type of function? In Python, we do have this distinction,
though we don't care about it as much. There's a word for this. Yep. Methods. Yeah. Something
dot something. If there's parentheses after that second something, it's a method. So lower
is a method that lives on the string type or the string class. You really don't need
to care about that all that much. You can think of it as a function that lives on all
strings. So it's just four strings. If I have x equals four and I say x.lower, what's your
guess that might happen? So it worked on name. It might work on x. What type is x? Yeah,
there's actually a built-in type function in Python. You can pass to it name, see that
it's class str. You can pass to it x, see it's an integer. Pass 3.5 to it, see that
it's a float. I said strings have a lower method. So you can say name.lower. X isn't
currently a string. It's an integer. So if I call lower on it, we do get an error. There's
no lower method on integers. So each type of object has its own methods. Eventually
we talk about lists. You'll see there's an append method on lists. If you have your own
custom class, you can have methods that are just for that class. It's a function that's
attached to that type of object, only works on objects of that type. Yep? I like this
question. There isn't, though anyone want to guess how we could get the first letter
of a string? Yeah, does it start with something? There is actually a starts with method. So
we can say does it start with p? Oh, it doesn't give us the first letter. We have to guess
the first letter at that point. What else can we try to do? I like that name.fl. Doesn't
work though. It's a good guess. Ooh, index. We haven't talked about that. Yeah. What does
the index look like? What's the syntax for this? Yeah, a lot of programming languages
have this. Not all of them. Name, open square bracket, zero, close square bracket, gives
us p. Now strings aren't the only thing you can index. You can also index lists and anything
that is a sequence, which is a fancy word for something you can index basically in Python.
It has a length you can loop over. We'll talk about loops later and it can be indexed. So
I haven't shown you all the things you can do with even strings, which are one of the
most basic data types. But you absolutely can do things besides call methods. Indexing,
concatenating, looping over them are mostly the things we haven't seen. Questions? Yep?
Maybe. It depends on the function. So what type does the print function... This is a
great question. So the question is a general function, not a method, a function that maybe
lives at the top level of our code, not something dot something, just the function. Does it
work with any type of object? We've been passing into print strings. Could I pass in a number
to print? What's your guess? Maybe. It seems to work. Could I pass a print into print?
No, this feels wrong, right? It seems like this shouldn't work. It works. It says built-in
print function print. That's what happens when we type print and hit enter. So every
object in Python can be converted to a string, even a function. Now, string representation
is funny. It's not actually very useful. Every object can be converted to a string. So to
answer your question, some functions accept any type of object. Stir is one of them. Print
is also one of them, but not all of them. If I ask int to convert three, the string
three to an integer, it says three. If I ask it to convert tray to an integer, what do
you think it'll do? Could give us zero. Could give us the number of letters, maybe four.
What else could it do? Yes, every letter in programming land is represented by a number.
It's numeric. Called ASCII, or it was called ASCII. Now it's called Unicode because we
have things besides just English characters, emoji and all foreign language characters,
and many characters that are not languages of any sort in Unicode. So there might be
some kind of adding up or using of those numbers that are under the hood that represent each
of these. We get an error. So strings that aren't anything numeric, we actually get an
error. So it's not even just the type. You can pass strings to int, but not all strings.
But you can also pass some other things to int. You can pass 3.5 to turn it into an integer.
It just lops off the .5. What about, could I pass int to int? I could pass print to print.
It doesn't seem like you could convert a function to an integer, so no you can't. So to answer
your question, sometimes yes, sometimes no. Some functions accept any type of object.
Most of them don't. In fact, some of them don't even accept all objects of the same
type. You can't always pass a string to int. Some of them just give you an error. Great
questions. Other questions?
What was that?
Good question. So if I say 3 plus 2.5. 5.5 is what we hope for. Who thinks 5.5? That's
your guess that Python's going to give us. Who thinks an error? Who thinks something
else? I want to know what you think.
5 or 6. It'll round it for us. Maybe it'll give us an integer. Maybe because the integer
was first. If we flip them around, maybe it'll give us a float. I'm glad that Python doesn't
work that way. We get 5.5. So yes, integer and float, you can always add together. It
doesn't matter the order of them. You can always add them together. So the Python core
developers actually had to do something special, some special magic to say, integers actually
do not know how to add themselves to floats. Floats know how to add themselves to integers.
However, an integer knows how to say, I don't know how to add myself to a float. Then Python
goes over to the float and asks it if it knows how to add itself to the integer. It says,
yes. All this happens under the hood and we can be grateful that it works. You can take
a look at this yourself if you really wanted to. All objects have these things called Dunder
methods, double underscore methods. This says not implemented. Integers do not know how
to add themselves to floats. But there is a right-hand addition, which is the same as
left-hand addition. You can do it in either direction, does the same thing. Floats know
how to add themselves to integers. That's actually what's going on under the hood whenever
you use the plus symbol in Python. Now, I'm showing you this not because you need to know
it, but because we can be grateful that we don't have to know this. These are the nitty-gritty
details of what's going on under the hood. In fact, you might see those sometimes. If
you ask for help on an integer and you scroll down, if you go to the Python documentation,
you'll see these same things. All these scary-looking double underscore methods, these are all implementing
all the various operators in Python. Plus, equals, equals, equals to ask if two things
are equal, which we haven't really talked about or seen yet there. All those are implemented
and you can actually see them and control them on your own objects in Python.
So back to the input function, the input function in Python. We can prompt a user for input,
which I didn't actually show you. Someone shout out, what's your favorite color? I heard
three. Green, okay. I was going to say three is an odd favorite color. Green. Although
we could have typed three, Python wouldn't have cared. Color is a variable. We said color
equals input and then it printed out what's your favorite color. I then typed green. What
do you think color is right now? What type do you think it is? Yeah, it's a string. What's
your favorite number? I don't have one. Anyone have one? 42. It's a classic favorite number
there. 42, we hit enter. What type do you think number is? Right. We're torn here. Is
it an integer or a string? We typed in an integer, it seems like. It's a string. The
reason is input, it doesn't make any assumption about what we're typing. Everything you get
from user input starts as a string. Now, what could we do if we wanted to turn it into an
integer? Yeah, we pass it to the int function. What is number now? I tricked you. It's a
string still. Why is it still a string? Right, we're at the Python REPL. Tricky things are
going on here. Int, the int function, we pass number to it, it gave us back an integer.
What did I not do with that thing it gave us? I didn't store it anywhere. We see the
result printed out. If I wanted to save, what could I do? Yeah, assignment. Number equals
if I want to use the same variable or make a new variable if I wanted to. It doesn't
really matter. It's up to us how we want to do this. Now it's actually an integer. You'll
sometimes see people do this. We use input. You can actually take the result of input
and pass that to a function. I'll show you what I mean by that. Int and then in parentheses
input. How does Python run this? What do you think it does first? Does it run int first
or input? It has to run input first. It actually has to go from the inside out here. Because
in order for us to know what to even turn into an integer, input has to run. So first
we'll prompt the user for input. Then they'll type in a number and then it turns it into
an integer. So you can nest function calls, but it does run them from the inside out as
it would have to if you're taking the result and passing it to another function. Questions
or thoughts? Yep?
Yeah, so I'll try to repeat the question here. So there's a thing called type coercion
that some programming languages have. The notion where you've got an operation. It happens
on different types. Then the programming language magically figures out how to convert one type
to another for the purpose of the operation actually working. It's automatic type conversion
or type coercion. We don't really have that in Python, but this still seemed to work.
So it is true we don't have this automatic type conversion in Python. You know, when
we said three, a string plus a number, what happened? Yeah, it loudly failed. It didn't
work because we don't have this thing, this automatic type coercion that other languages
have. Now, how could we have fixed this if we have n equals two? That doesn't work. What
could I do here though? How could I? Because I can add two strings together. How could
I turn n into a string? Yeah, pass it to the str function. So you're right that we do have
to go out of our way quite frequently to explicitly convert from one type to another, but not
always. And the reason is some types know, like floats, for example. Floats, it's very,
very common to add an integer to a float. So common that the float type in Python has
decided, if you give me an integer, I know how to work with it. And so it's possible
for a type of object to take it upon itself to not do automatic type coercion so much
as say, I know how to work with objects besides just myself. In fact, we've seen this. A number
multiplied by what? What was the thing? It wasn't a string. It was a string multiplied
by not a floating point number. It had to be an integer. So in this case, strings know
how to work with an integer with multiplication, but not with even strings. So it's sometimes
the case they know how to work with multiple types, sometimes only the same type, sometimes
only a different type. It's up to the object, though. So you're right, it does seem like
it kind of goes against that idea of we don't have automatic type conversion, but it doesn't
fully go against the idea. Yeah, good question. A little bit of an in the weeds question,
but it's something you'll see happen often in Python is that idea of we've got to convert
between types quite a bit. So I'm going to make a program here called add.pos. And I'm
going to add the...the graded funding to this program, so there goes this gaura number in
our example. i AND IP FUCKING NONE. Not even a faulty exact number. And here in the
terrible idea of we start to, like, look at an example of an index, and as people see,
a series of actual numbers appears.
strings. So this is another problem in Python, plus works on multiple types of things. If
they both happen to be strings, Python's happy. It's not going to complain. If they both have
any numbers, Python's happy. If one's a number and one's a string, it's unhappy. How do we
fix this in our case? Yeah, we can convert them. Ooh, I like that. We could put it up
here or we could put it down here. Which is the right way to do it? It's a true question.
There isn't a right way to do it. We can do it either way. So let's do it down here. Just
because we did do it at the top before, doesn't really matter where we do it. As long as at
the point where that plus operation is happening, we end up with two numbers. We'll do 7 and
13 again. And it works this time. We get 20. All right. I would like you to try to make
another Python program here. I'm going to give you too long for this one. And does anyone
know when the break is? 1230. No, not that break. I will figure out when the break is
during this break here. Because what happened in a past year, we decided to take a break
a little bit later and all the food was gone. I would rather take a break on time because
we want food. Yeah, food or drinks there. All right. So I'll give you seven minutes
to try this out. On the website where we're at is input. We're on input doing input exercises
at PyCon 2023.pym.dev there. So any questions at all? Put up a red sticky. If you get through
the first exercise, which is printing out the number of things you need for a party
based on the number of guests that you have and different numbers of things in packages,
if you get through that first exercise, put up a green sticky on your machine. We have
two minutes left. But I'm going to change things up here. I want you to stop what you're
doing entirely. You're in the middle of something. I'm forcing you to stop whatever you're doing.
And we're instead going to take a break to go eat because there is food and drink out
there right now. And then afterward we will come back and you'll continue what we're doing.
How long is the break meant to be? I like how everyone who thinks that everyone who
should know how long the break is, we don't know how long the break is. Last year. I thought
it was 15 minutes. I couldn't remember if it was 15 or 30. 30 felt too long. We're going
to do a 15 minute break. This is not an exercise break though. I actually do want you to get
up away from your machine. Even if you're not getting food and drink, walk around to
the room. Take a stretch. You need to let your brain not think about Python for a minute
or so maybe. So we've got a 15 minute stretch break. And then we will get back to it with
a few minutes writing some code. If you've got questions in the meantime, feel free to
ask.
So we're done with our break break, but we're still in an exercise break. So I'm going to
give you a few more minutes here to keep working with input, keep working with the programs
you're working on there. I did want to note there are more exercises in each section than
I expect you to possibly get through. So don't feel like you need to get through every exercise.
Try out the first one. If you get done with it, try out the next one. As many as you can
get through there. But you're always welcome to try them again later. If you have questions,
stick up a red sticky. If you get done with the first exercise, you end up prompting the
user for input, put up a green sticky. We'll get back to it in a few minutes here.
All right. We are going to get back to it. We're doing pretty well on time here. A little
bit more behind than I expected, but that's all right. Always the case. So I want to mention
real quick, there will be resources linked on the website. They are not linked now, so
as not to distract you. And also because I keep thinking of more resources I want to
link as you are asking great questions on Python. One I want to link you to right now,
though, because it might actually be helpful for some of the exercises. Tray.io slash built-ins,
all one word. That will redirect you to a blog post I wrote a long time ago. Well, actually
not so long ago. I've updated it recently. On the built-in functions in Python, which
ones to learn first, which ones to learn next. It's about 25 I recommend committing to memory
at the point where you actually write in Python code frequently. Or don't commit them to memory,
just open up that blog post every time you need to use Python. And again, there are about
70 built-in functions in Python. You don't need to memorize them. You don't need to know
most of them. Most working Python programmers only know two or three dozen of them. It will
get you many years of happy Python programming just knowing a couple dozen Python built-ins.
So we've got some input from the user so far. We've printed things out to the screen. What
if we had not done that would be an interesting thing to do with a program? The possibilities
we might take our coding skills to next. We haven't done number crunching really outside
of just basic math. We haven't talked about any data structures yet. But what about things
getting stuff from outside of our program or putting things outside of our program?
Passing arguments to our program, that might be something we could do to control it. What
about if we have lots of data? How could we get the data into our program? Yeah. Right,
a database. Yeah. Or we could go to the Internet, do an HTTP request and say I want to go to
this website and download this thing. So we're going to talk about files. Now usually when
people talk about files in Python, I want to note that there is a function that's built-in
called open. We're not going to talk about that. The reason we're not going to talk about
that is open involves opening a file. Then you have to worry about do I need to close
the file? How do I get things into the file or out of the file? Do I want to read it?
Do I want to write it? Instead, I'm going to show you a few lines of code that will
seem a little bit magical but they're a little bit easier to get started with. The first
one we're importing a type of object called path. Like a string, like an integer, like
a float. It's a type of object, a class is what it's called, called path with a capital
P from Python's path lib module. So this line we type first, that's our magical incantation
to get access to path. Now I have a file, well I don't actually have it, I'm going to
download it right now, called declaration of independence.txt, which has the declaration
of independence in it. It has the text of this document in this file. Now it's a TXT
file, it's not a Word document. If I wanted to open up a Word document, I'm going to have
a little bit of trouble because Word documents have, they're actually binary files, it's
not just plain text. Each type of file needs a separate mechanism for handling that file
type. An Excel file, a docx file, a TXT file, a CSV file, a JSON file, whatever that file
type is, you need to handle it in a different way, it's a different format. Text files are
by far the easiest, it's kind of the non-format format file, kind of like the non-copyrighted
copyright. You can take a work and say my license is it doesn't have a license. This
is saying I don't even have a type to this file, it's just raw text. So we're going to
open up this file here by using not the built-in open function, which is what you'll usually
see in Python tutorials, but we're going to make instead a path object. So this object
here, it's a POSIX path, anyone know what POSIX means? Anyone who's done some system
administration stuff in the past might have seen POSIX before. There's NT path and POSIX
path. NT path you'll see on Windows, Windows NT, which no one talks about anymore, but
we still have that verbiage. POSIX path is anything but Windows basically, Linux path,
Mac path, it's Unix, Unix or Linux. So I see a POSIX path on Windows, it'll just say NT
path, same thing, that would say path object. So to get stuff out of this, to get the entire
file as a string, I can say dot, read text, what is that called again when I say something
dot and then there's parentheses? Yeah, method, which is just a function that lives on that
path object. Since it's a function, I have to call it. If I don't have the parentheses,
I instead see this bound method thing. I don't want that, I want those parentheses. So I've
got our path object dot read text. Now what I get back, its type is str. It's actually
a string that represents everything in this file. If I were to print it, I see the entire
file printed out there. So I'm going to type all that again, show you what I did there.
Three lines. The first line you only have to do once. So I already did it, doesn't need
to be done again. Second line is getting a reference to that path and then the third
line is taking that path, storing it as a string. The entire file is now a string. Now
we don't know how to work with files or we haven't up to now, but we know how to work
with strings. We've used them a little bit. Now that we have a string, we can work with
that string just like we've been working with them before. What if I wanted to write some
text to a file? So I'm going to say let's make a file called PyCon 2023.txt. Call this
our PyCon path. And I want to say this file here, it should have the text, yay PyCon in
it. How can I do that, do you think? What's your guess?
Maybe the write text method? Yeah, so this doesn't work. There's lots of aspirational
thinking I could do here. I could say maybe plus works, maybe there's another symbol that
works. Read text worked before, let's try write text. PyCon path dot, instead of read
text, we'll say write text and we'll give it this string here. Yay PyCon. Nine. And
why did we get nine? Yeah, there's nine characters in this string. So Python thought it would
helpfully tell us nine. Sometimes you get really weird results from functions. This
is sometimes useful if you want to know how many things you wrote to a file. This is pretty
much there for historical reasons. The notion of writing back in the C world often, how
many bytes did I write out to this file is a thing you sometimes want to know. We're
just going to ignore that nine, we don't care about it. The thing we care about is
in my text editor, I can now see this file. If I list my directory, my folder here, I'll
see this PyCon2023.txt file. So we just wrote it out. So the two things you can do with
pathlib there, read files and write files. There was a question earlier. Or anyone have
a question, maybe I answered it already.
So two things. Here's reading from the file. And then if we wanted to write something different
to the file. Yep.
Great question. Yeah, this is implicitly in our current working directory. So that means
when you run any program on your computer, doesn't matter if it's Python or another program,
there's a directory or a folder that it thinks it's inside of. You can change that directory
it thinks it's inside of. Sometimes you do, sometimes you don't. But if we had a file
that was in a different directory, what could we do, do you think? We've got to tell it
where it is. Yeah, we could give it an absolute path. I could say, for example, well, actually
this is in home tray. It's in a different directory. Or maybe it's in the root directory
on my computer or something. So I could give it a different directory there and instead
write to that directory in that path. Or I could use dot dot, which means the directory
above me, or some A slash B that would be the A directory, the file B below me. So yes,
implicitly it's the current directory. Other questions?
All right, well, you're going to play with pathlib a little bit here with reading and
writing from files and working with strings that are stored in files. Where's our read
text here? By the way, what do you think will happen when we write text to a file that already
exists? It's your guess, it might happen. It could overwrite it entirely, it could add
to the end, let's see. So right now, this file has yay PyCon in it. If I write PyCon
exclamation exclamation, and I go and I refresh it, that's what we see. So yes, it did and
completely overwrite it. If you wanted to add to the end, there isn't an append text.
There could be, but they haven't made one. What could you do if you wanted to add to
the end of a file? Right, read the file, concatenate something to that string to make a new string
that's got the stuff at the end, write it back out to the file. You can always manually
add stuff to the end of a file that way. And in fact, that's what you will want to do for
the very first exercise in this section. It's called jot. So under files, file exercises,
this is, as you'd expect, the most challenging exercise we've done so far. There is a little
bit of a helper you can copy paste there. It involves taking the current date, printing
that to a file. We're also prompting the user and asking them, it's basically like a daily
journal. You type out a thought that you have and it sticks to the end of the file, the
current date, and the thought that you have there. And I'm going to give you at least
ten minutes on these exercises here to try this first one out. There are a couple other
exercises after it, but I'm guessing jot will probably take you a little while. If you get
through jot, if you get most of the way through it, stick up a green sticky on your machine.
So take down those green stickies because I know you haven't got through it yet. If
you need some help, you find yourself stuck, put up a red sticky. We'll come by and help
you out. And I'm guessing more of you than before will need help on this one, so please
don't hesitate to put up a red sticky if you get yourself stuck for 30 seconds or so.
So I know the website's a little confusing the way it explains this. I gave you a starting
script that doesn't do what you want yet. It prints out the current date. It does prompt
the user. It doesn't write to a file. Not only that, it doesn't print anything useful
yet. It doesn't print anything out that's useful yet. It doesn't write to the end of
a file, certainly. You now need to figure out how can you take that working code that
does kind of the wrong thing but something in the right direction and make it read from
a file, write to a file, stick the current date in there. So again, when you find yourself
stuck, which is probably going to happen at some point here, put up a red sticky. And
I'm going to give you a few more minutes as well. When you finish this, stick up a green
sticky. All right. I know I didn't give you a lot of time, but we're going to do this
together. So very few green stickies up. That means most of us are still working on this,
and that is okay. We're going to use our collective knowledge to see what we've learned so far.
For those of you who have green stickies up or you're most of the way through or you finished
it and forgot to put the green sticky up, maybe don't answer my questions right now
because you already know some of the answers. Those of you who haven't quite got all the
way through it, maybe you'll have some complementary knowledge. Some of you figured out different
things probably here. I know some of you did as I was wandering around. So we're going
to make a new file, jot.py. We're going to copy paste into it these three lines that
were on the website. Now, they don't do what we want yet. We know they don't do what we
want, but it's a starting point. It does prompt us. Now, it's a funny prompt. It just shows
greater than we're expected to know now that this is a prompt. You can type, it's the first
day of PyCon, and I'm teaching. If I hit enter, just like when we used input before, the result
of input, where does that go? Yeah, it actually goes in that variable user message. What are
we doing with user message? Nothing right now, so let's print it out. We are printing
something though. It happens to be today's date, so let's do that again. I'll say at
PyCon. Ah, so now we see at PyCon and today's date. We've got a variable. The variable does
seem to work. It got the input from the user, and we got the current date. How do we make
a string that has the date colon the message? We're not working with a file yet, but we're
supposed to stick that at the end of a file. How can I make a string like that? I'll call
this the line, the line that we stick in the file. Well, we're not going to work with a
path yet, but how could I get the current date in here, do you think? We're printing
the current date. What do I need to do to this line to make it useful for storing in
a variable? Yeah, so could I say line equals this thing? What's your guess? Yeah, maybe
remove the print. Do you think it'll work with the print? Maybe. So it's prompting us.
I'll type A. That's interesting. It printed, the first thing we printed, we asked it to
print the current date in the same line as this line thing here. Then we got none. We
haven't talked about none yet. There's a default return value for every function in Python.
Typically functions return something useful. Print doesn't return anything. It does something.
Functions tend to either do a thing or return a thing. Print does a thing. It shows something
to the screen. So it doesn't return anything. So we get none, and then it shows A. So let's
remove that print as was suggested there. Try that again. Type B. So we see the date
and B. B is our user message. Let's remove that. So we do see the date. Okay, so we want
it to look like this though. Date, colon, and then our message. So how do we do that?
What are we going to type on this line here? Plus, we want to concatenate. What do we want
to do with? Colon, space, and then user input. Oh yeah, what's missing? Right. So if we run
this right now, we get a syntax error. We need quotes there to make this into a string.
Does that work? It didn't do anything because I didn't print anything. Let's try it again.
Ah, user message. Right, wait. And also it said user input. Why didn't it actually show
what I typed? If I type tray or I type type, it says user message instead. Right, user
message is inside the quote. Okay, so we got colon, space in our quote. Concatenate again.
So you can concatenate just like if you say two plus three plus four, you can add three
numbers together. You can concatenate three strings together. There is a way to do it.
I'm going to show you how to do it. I'm not expecting you to memorize it, but it is called
an F string. It looks like this. An F string is basically flipping string concatenation
on its head. So string concatenation, I described, what did I describe it as? String concatenation.
Right, this. It's this. It's smushing things together. This is called string interpolation.
It's not smushing together. It's more of sticking inside of. We're saying we've got a big string
we're building up. We want to inject into it a couple things. Those things in the curly
braces are the little bits of code that give us the thing to stick in there. You notice
we don't have to convert these things to a string. That's optional. It will convert them
to a string for us. So we'll do it this way. That's for the fun of it just because we've
seen this. All right, we've got our line in the right format. How do we get it in our
file? Yeah, we need to write to the file. We need to write to the file. So we need to
import. So can I say jot dot txt dot write text line? Read pathlib from pathlib import
path. We'll put that line. So this is called an import. You tend to see these at the very
top of a file. All the things you're importing come first. Kind of like you're declaring,
here are all the things I need. Okay, now let's use those things. So we've got this
path thing we can use just as we have this date thing that we're using. So if I say path
jot dot txt, will this work here? Path equals this thing. We'll call this a jot path. What
method did we have on these path objects for writing to them? Yeah, write text. So let's
try to give it our line. So instead of printing it out, we'll try to write to the file. Oh,
do we not need quotes? Well, what's your guess? When I hit enter, what do you think might
happen? Sounds like your guess is you think it'll be an error. It wasn't an error. Oh,
it was an error. So a problem in Python, or in Python, I guess in Python as well, sometimes
Python's running your code and it's fine, and then suddenly it's not fine, and the error
blows up later. You can't always tell if your program starts that it is in fact correct.
Now it didn't loudly complain here until we got to jot dot txt. This is actually valid
Python syntax. What is it interpreting this as? Yeah, variable. It thinks, oh, jot's a
variable. It must have an attribute called txt. An attribute is something dot something.
If there's parentheses, it's a method. It's a function attached to something. We haven't
talked about attributes, but they do exist in Python. Something dot something. So we
need to put quotes around here for Python to see that as a string. It's not supposed
to be a variable lookup. It did something. What should it have done? How do we know whether
it worked? Right. Do we have a file called jot dot txt? We do. Let's open it up, see
what's in it. It says we're a PyCon. When we run it again, what is it supposed to do?
What is it meant to do again? Yeah, it's supposed to add to the end. So if I say we're at PyCon,
we're going to eat lunch. It didn't add to the end. It completely overwrote the file.
How can I get it to add to the end? What could we try to do here maybe? Yep?
Right. So read the file. We're not giving anything to it. It will get back, though,
the contents of the file. Say contents, and you're saying concatenate here the contents
with our line and then write it out. Maybe like that. See if it works. At PyCon still.
And then we'll look at our jot dot txt file. Well, that was weird. What happened there?
It didn't put it on a new line. What else happened? It's the same message twice. At
PyCon still, at PyCon still. Okay. So let's look at our code here. We've got our path.
We're writing to the file. We read from it, but we just wrote to it. So we overwrote our
file. So that might be where our problem is here. Instead of making guesses, though, I
want to show you a function called breakpoint. Usually folks don't show new programmers breakpoint.
I think new programmers should probably know about breakpoint, even though a warning here,
this is going to be scary, because we're going to enter the Python debugger. So you've got
your code editor, the Python repel, your system command prompt, and now there's a fourth
thing we have to worry about, the Python debugger. The Python debugger, it acts kind of like
the Python repel, though it's not quite the same. We're going to type at PyCon. What seems
to happen here? What do we see? It's different than before. We see a path here. Home tray
PyCon 2023, jot.py. What else? There's a number nine. Jot path equals, this looks like Python
code. Yeah, this is the next line in the file after breakpoint. We're actually stepping
through our Python program here. So in the Python debugger, you can do things like this.
Kind of like at the repel, for example, I can say jot path. Just like at the repel,
it shows me, it would show me what's in that variable, except I don't have a jot path variable
yet, because that's defined on the next line of code. It's defined right here. It hasn't
been defined yet. However, I do have a line variable. That's the line. To go to the next
line of code, we can type n. We just ran this line of code, which means we should have a
jot path variable, and we do. So we're actually interactively running our program. Kind of
like how at the Python repel, we're interactively working with Python, typing lines of code
and seeing results. We've basically injected ourselves into this program. We put the program
on pause and said we want to run the next line of code. We're going to poke around.
Don't run the next line of code yet until we ask you to. So right now, our path, we've
got our path defined. If we say read text, this is what's in that file. This is what
was there before. If I run the next line of code, the line that ran was this write text
line. We're now just about to run the read text line. So we've now written to the file.
If we read text, this is what's now in the file. We just overwrote the whole file. So
we're going to run the next line of code. So I want to mention the Python debugger break
point, even though it is scary, because at some point, you may find that using print
to debug your code isn't quite enough. It's kind of confusing sometimes to figure out
what you even need to print. Sometimes you just wish you could drop into a Python repel.
And in fact, this scary land here, we can make it slightly less scary by typing interact.
Where are we now, do you think? What does this usually symbolize? Yeah, we're in the
Python repel. Those three greater than signs mean we're actually in a real Python repel.
In fact, there's a function called dir, tells you all your currently defined variables,
all these ones that have underscores we just ignore. There's line, there's jot path, there's
user message, there's date. So we can poke around and see those. If I type exit, it does
actually, in fact, exit my whole program, which is unfortunate. I thought I was going
to go back to the Python debugger, but we'll just ignore that fact. Anyways, break point
is the way to start the Python debugger. The way to fix this program, has anyone seen it
yet, the way we can fix this? We do need to read the file, we do need to write from it.
We're writing twice, though. We're overwriting the file first. We need to read from it and
then stick on the end and then write. Someone noted we're sticking a line of code on the
same line as another line. How do we fix that? Yeah, we need a new line. So we need a little
bit extra concatenation. What's the symbol we use for a new line? Backslash n. So the
current contents of the file, let's stick a line at the end and then we'll put another
line there. Oops. Let's run this code again. I'm going to remove break point.
We have a problem. Leading zero in decimal. Not permitted. Oh, it's because I tried to
run jot.txt, which is not a Python program. You can give files that are not py files to
Python, it'll just try to run them as programs. Maybe it worked. Let's go look at jot.txt.
At PyCon. At PyCon. All right, let's try it again. At lunch at PyCon. It worked. Now
there is a possible problem in this program. If the file doesn't exist yet, what do you
think might happen? Yeah, when we try to read from it, we could get an empty string back.
It might also give us an error. Let's try it out. So we don't have an error yet. We
do get an error. So I didn't show you how to fix this, but also the way to fix this
is to make the file exist. And then your program magically works. Sometimes a workaround
is a decent solution. One thing you could do, though, is you could look up on path objects
in Python. How do you ask whether a path exists? There is actually a way to do that. So if
jot path dot exists, there's also an is file. Is file versus is directory. Either one is
a perfectly good way to do this. If it doesn't exist, set the contents to an empty string.
I just used something we've never seen before. What is that? If else. Yeah. Let's talk about
if else before we do, though. Any questions? Yep. Yep. Uh-huh. Good question. So the question
is os.path is a thing you'll see on stack overflow results. You'll see it if you're
looking at Python code that works with file paths. Pathlib is this newer thing. That's
what you've heard. Is os.path going away? Is it being replaced by pathlib? What's going
on there? The answer is os.path will probably never go away because lots of code uses it.
It's just a lot of old code floating around. And there's no reason to make it suddenly
disappear because it would just break things for no particularly good reason. Pathlib is
very well supported by everything at this point, though. It's newer in the sense that
it is much newer than os.path. It's not actually very new at this point, though. It's just
not 20 years old. Well, os.path's even older than that, in fact. Also, pathlib is slower.
If you are traversing your file tree and you're looking at thousands of files on your system,
you'll notice that it's in different paths. Pathlib takes a little bit more time to make
the path object because it's got some fancy methods attached. Os.path is all strings.
Strings are fast, even though strings can be messy. So I would recommend pathlib over
that os.path thing when you see it. They both work, though. A little bit of an in the weeds
question, but I like those. You see stuff online, you want to know what the answer is.
So I want to note here something I don't think I mentioned at the beginning. We're not going
to learn all of Python today. You probably guessed this, but in three hours you can't
possibly learn all of Python. Doesn't matter how advanced you are already in programming
or in Python. We're only getting a taste for Python, which means we will see if and else
in a moment. We'll see loops. We'll see lists. That's about where we'll end. Beyond that,
there's functions, there's the standard library, there's modules, there's list comprehension,
there's tuple unpacking, there's indexing, there's slicing. There are so many other
features that exist in Python. They're all built pretty much on these features we're
talking about today, though, for the most part. So we're going to talk now about if
else. We're going to do it by using if else. So I just used if else to ask does a file
exist. Before I talk about if else, I want to ask you, some of you have done some programming
before, what do you think will happen when I hit enter? False. It's a funny guess if
you've never done programming before. Zero equals equals one, false. But it is false
with a capital F. We have in Python a variable false and a variable true. It's capital F
false, capital T true. We don't have the lowercase ones. This is asking is zero equal to one?
So, for those of you who knew this syntax, the answer is obvious. Zero is not equal to
one. Equals equals is the way we say this. Why not equals? Yeah, this assigns something.
Now, we can't assign to zero. So, in fact, in this case, it wouldn't be ambiguous. But
if I said name equals tray and I wanted to ask, well, is name equal to tray? I can't
do it this way. That's an assignment. Got to use equals equals. So you can use equals
to ask is a string equal to another string? Is a number equal to a number? Could I ask
is a string equal to a number? What's your guess? So you think the answer will be true
or false? False. Yeah, it's not an error. In fact, equals equals shouldn't ever give
you an error. Objects in general, just as all of them are supposed to have a good string
representation of some sort, all of them should give you an answer with equality. Question?
Ah, good question. So the reason there's quotes around my name, not around the number,
there are two types of things. So I'm going to do it a different way. X equals zero, Y
equals zero. Both of those worked. What's the type of Y? It's a number, specifically
an integer. This is kind of the weird one. What's the type of X? Str, string. So this
in Python, this is a problem you will run into a lot. Even after you've been doing
Python for a while, it's hard to internalize the fact that there's really three things.
There's variables, which are when we have something like X, right? X is a variable.
It doesn't have quotes around it, but it has some characters in it. It represents a
pointer to something. And then there's a string that's got quotes around it. You can think
of it as literal characters. It's like the things you'd write on a piece of paper. When
we don't have quotes around it, that's something special. It's either a number, or it's a variable,
or it is a special syntax. This here, this is a string. This is not a string. It's called
a list. The square brackets mean something. So whenever something's in quotes, you're
making a string object, just literal characters. If it's not in quotes, something else special
is going on. In our case, we're working with a number. Yeah, great question, which means
X is zero, Y is zero. Is X equal to Y, do you think? False. They're both zero, but one
is zero the string, one zero the number. Now, int of X, is that equal to Y? It is, and X
equals equals str of Y, and it's also true. Converting them to the same type, then they're
actually equal. So we don't just have equality in Python, we also have inequality. Anyone
want to guess what inequality looks like? Yeah, so there's a few different ways that
languages do this. Python doesn't do it this way. This is something different. This is
division, actually. Division and assignment at the same time. That's confusing. Some languages
also do this. In fact, Python 2 used to support this. It's kind of a SQL way of doing things.
This is the way we do it in Python. Exclamation mark equals. It doesn't equal. We also have,
as you'd hope, greater than is one greater than zero. We have greater than or equal to,
less than or equal to. What about this? What's your guess? Could we ask is a string less
than a string? Lots of yeses. What do you think it's going to do? Alphabetical, maybe?
So you think it'll be true here? The size of the string, maybe. I don't know. It's true.
So A comes before B in the alphabet. Okay, let's try it this way. We'll say A less than
B. True or false or error? False. It is false. What about A less than lowercase b? Now we're
confused. It's true. So it's true for a strange reason. All the capital A's in the alphabet
capital letters come before all the lowercase letters. So if you're comparing two strings,
you want to make sure that you're comparing them with the same case. Now I'm talking about
strings. We're using just characters here. What about a string with multiple characters?
Is this possible, do you think? What do you think it does? It kind of seems like it'd
be like when you went through these old books we used to have. You'd flip through them.
They had words and then they were called dictionaries. Now we go to dictionary.com, right? We don't
care about alphabetical ordering on dictionary.com. You care about them in a dictionary. In alphabetical
order, Apple doesn't come before animal. L-M-N-O-P. Animal comes before Apple. But case does matter.
So even though the A is the same, it goes to the next letter and sees which one is less
than the other one. What about special characters? Yeah, what about the number zero? Is that
less than the letter A? We should probably ask ourselves, why are we asking this question?
We're going to get a weird answer, right? It is going to be either true or false. Turns
out it's true. That one's true as well. I believe zero is 48 on the ASCII table. It
really comes, where does it come in the ASCII table? If it's an emoji character, it's usually
at the end. If it's a digit, it's at the beginning. If it's a linguistic character, it's a non-English
linguistic character. It's somewhere in the middle. So you want to be careful about what
it is you're comparing when you're ordering your strings.
All right. We're about to get to if statements. One more operator I'd like to show you. We
talked about equals equals, not equals, comparing things with less than and greater than. If
I want to ask whether my name has a Y in it, whether it contains a Y, what's your guess
that I could do? Now, I want you to just guess, complete guess of what I could type in here.
For those who don't know the answer, there could be a method, name dot, what would the
method maybe be called? Contains? That's a good guess. Does it contain the string Y?
There is no contains method. That's a good guess, though. Name dot in. Invalid syntax,
that should signify something. There is a find method, which is interesting. It gives
us an index. There's actually an operator in Python for doing this. What's the operator?
I know some of you know this. Yeah, in. Most programming languages don't have this. Y in
the name. Is Y in the name? It is in the name. Is Z in the name? That's false. This
is case sensitive. Is T in the name? That's false because it's a lowercase t. Capital
T is in there. We have in. What's the opposite of in? Out. Yeah. T out name. That didn't
work. Yeah, not in. Wait, is there an operator with a space inside? Is that valid? Yeah,
it is. Python core developers decided not space in is a valid operator. They went out
of their way to make that work. All right. So let's finally use if statements. So we
have the answer to a question. We get true or false. These are yes, no questions. In
Python, it's very, very common to ask a question that has a yes or a no, and based on the result
of that, you do something or you don't do something. So we can say the year is 1999.
If the year is equal to 1999, is there syntax for an if statement in Python, colon, and
then I hit enter, something weird happens. What happened that's kind of unusual? Yeah,
we see three dots. We don't see three greater than signs. Python knows that there is more
to come. That means there is a block of code. So who knows that Python indentation is somehow
important in some way? This is something that people often complain about. Even if you've
never used Python, you might hear people complain about the fact that indentation matters in
Python. This is where we finally see that indentation matters. At the Python repl here,
we could hit tab, space a few times, typically four spaces, although the tab key in your
text editor will insert four spaces. We now can write some code. It could be one line
or multiple lines. Let's write it's 1999. That's a bigger year. So we should party quite
a bit. And then if we hit enter again, we still see three dots. What do we do? I mean,
we could type more code, but what if we actually wanted to end? What's your guess? Yeah, for
the few of you who've used the Python repl with multiple lines of code already, you have
to hit enter again. So the reason for this, it's something specific to the Python repl.
It doesn't know when we're done. What if some other programming language is used to say,
here's a block of code and here's a start and the end? Yeah, a curly brace. So C, Java,
JavaScript, some of these languages say if curly brace, then you're going. And then finally
there's a closed curly brace. We don't have those in Python. It's all about indentation.
The problem is with indentation, we don't know if our indentation is done until we've
out dented our line of code. There is no out dent at the Python repl. So you've got to
hit enter twice. So this is specific to the Python repl. You've got to hit enter twice
to end your block of code when you're writing an if statement. So we don't just have if
in Python. This is if something's true, we run some code. If it's not true, if it's 2000
and we run this same bit of code again, it's not going to print anything because it's not
true. What do we do if we want it to do a different thing if it's not true? Else, yeah.
So we can say if the year is 1999, we do those same things as before. Right after that, else
and then a colon. There's no condition with an else. There is actually a way to add a
condition though optionally. You don't want to guess what the way to add an optional to
chain conditions is. Elif. Some languages call this else if or else if. None of them
call it elf for some strange reason. Some language should call it elf. We call it elif
for characters just like else. Elif, the year is less than 1999. I don't know what we type
here. It's still the 90s. Not quite time to party right. Otherwise, the party's over.
So it says the party's over because year right now is 2000. So this is pretty much
the, not the biggest elf, elf, the biggest if statement you'll see, but this is the biggest
style. This is all the things you can possibly throw in. There's if, there's elif, there's
else. If has to, or else has to have if before it. How many else's do you think you can have
on an if? Just one. How many elifs do you think you can have? Yeah, zero worked. You
don't have to have an elif just like you don't have to have an else. You can have lots of
them though. Elif, elif, elif. It has to come before the else though and in between the
if. So you always start with the if, end with the else if there is one, and you sandwich
elif in the middle if there are any elifs there. It does not, only elif. There is no
else if in Python. Now you could say else, indent, do another if, and indent further.
But you're going to have to indent even more if you did that. So technically yeah, you
could get something like else if. You can't do it on one line though. Like you couldn't
say C or Java or some other languages. Yep, I've been hitting four spaces here, but yeah,
you typically hit tab. Basically every text editor knows if you have a file open and ends
with .py, it should use four spaces. Four spaces is typically what we use in Python
to indent. You can technically use anything. If you really want to upset people, use three
spaces. Not quite right, but not wrong enough to notice easily. But four spaces is what
typically happens when you hit the tab key. Five spaces is also equally bad. So if you
want to do that, you can use the if statement. So we're now going to write some if statements.
I'd like you to, even if you don't write it at the REPL, you can write it in a text editor
and copy paste it in. I do want you to try copy pasting it into the REPL because it's
going to be frustrating. I don't want you to be frustrated, but I do want you to understand
that the REPL works a little differently than your text editor does. It's a little pickier
about whether there's, you've hit enter twice for example. Your indentation is going to
matter in both your text editor and the REPL. But when you find yourself making a mistake,
it's frustrating in the REPL because you have to start over. You have to type all the code
again. So type it in your text editor. Maybe copy paste it into the REPL so you don't get
too frustrated there. But try running it from the Python REPL. So try out some if statements.
We're on the website under conditionals. Conditional exercises. We have about a half an hour left
here. I think 12.15, I think is the time I should be stopping here because lunch is at
12.30. And we took a 15 minute break. Is my reasoning right there? Anyone want to correct
me? Calendar says to 12.30. Okay. The video may be a little bit longer. I'm fine going
until 12.30. Everyone fine with 12.30? Excellent. We'll go to 12.30 then. We might want to stop
like a couple minutes before just so we get a head start on lunch. But yeah, 12.30 basically
is when we'll stop. Oh, and if you find yourself stuck while you're writing an if statement,
probably it's a syntax error, but I want you to put up a red sticky and we'll try to help
you out. So put up a red sticky when you find yourself stuck. If you end up writing an if,
if statement or if statement rather successfully, put up a green sticky. So if you're trying
to take and ask two questions at the same time in Python, for example, is the year less
than 1999 or is the year greater than 1999? In other programming languages, suppose you've
done them before, how do you do or? Right, yeah, like this. This way, whatever that symbol
is. Nobody knows the name of that thing. This thing, it's called a pipe symbol. Year, or,
year. This doesn't work in Python. Anyone found out what this is, what we have to do instead?
Yeah, it's deceptively like English. Or. We have or and we have and. So if you find yourself
wanting to ask two questions at once, we've got or and we've got and. All right. I know
that wasn't long. But we are going to move on because we don't have too much time left.
We're going to move on to talk about finally our first data structure in Python. Anyone
want to guess what our first data structure is going to do? If those of you who've done
some programming, what is a data structure? I want to try to explain that. I'll give you
a hint. It's a structure and there's data involved. Yes, it stores data. A data structure
stores data. It's kind of boring. Data structure is really just a way of saying we've got some
stuff. It's not a string. It's not a number. Something more than that. Something more sophisticated.
And there's a common way we tend to want to work with it. The first data structure you
typically see in Python, the very most common one, is this. What do other programming languages
sometimes call this thing where you've got multiple things stored together in a particular
order? Yeah, an array or a list. In Python we call it a list. Some languages call it
an array, an array of things, a list of things. I kind of like list because it sounds like
a shopping list, a grocery list, a list of things. I might list things out. It's also
kind of a verb. This list, and we can check its type using the built-in type function
and confirm it is in fact a new type, class list. If we want to get the first thing in
this list, what could we try to do? I'll give you a hint. It's similar to when we got the
first character in a string. Yeah, square bracket. And then what do we put in there?
Yeah, why not one? We're programmers, so we start counting at zero for some strange reason.
There are good reasons for this, but we start counting at zero. That's the thing to internalize
to remember there. What if I put in 10? What's your guess? Could be an error. Could be nothing.
Yeah, what's the thing that represents nothing in Python? None. Turns out it is an error.
Sometimes we get none back, though getting an index of 10 on a list that doesn't have
10 things, that is an error. How could we find out how many things are in this list,
do you think? Yeah, somehow get its length. A lot of languages have this notion of you
take a list, you access a length attribute. A.B. is an attribute lookup. We don't have
a length attribute in Python. Right, we have len, but it's not a method. It's actually
a built-in function. So to get the len of something or the length of something, you
pass PyCon feelings to the length function. Kind of weird that it's a built-in function.
It doesn't live on the object. Why is that, do you think? What else might have a length?
Right, it might work with anything that you could count the number of. If it has a length
that's kind of a property, could be a generic property, we can index strings and lists.
It's not a method we use. We use square brackets as a special syntax. Kind of similar. We use
a special built-in function just as you can convert multiple things to an integer or a
You can get the length of multiple things. So if I say length of a string, we get the
length of the string. Now, the length of everything in Python is not four. Let's do something
that's not four. Length of an empty string is zero. Length of a list with, by the way,
you can have mixed things in a list. We have strings, we've got numbers. You can even mix
up your strings and numbers. Python really doesn't care about types all that much. We
practice something called, if I can find this here, this. You probably can't see it on the
recording. What is this little thing I'm holding up? A rubber ducky, which is also useful for
debugging your code, by the way. You can look up rubber duck debugging on Wikipedia. It
is a real thing. If you find yourself stuck and you're not in a room of myself and Melanie
and other people to ask questions to, talk to your rubber duck. It's not going to respond.
I mean, hopefully it won't respond. You've got other problems if it responds. Or you've
got maybe a talking, maybe it's good if it responds. It depends on the type of duck.
Talk to your rubber duck and just verbalizing the question will sometimes help you figure
out a possible landscape of answers. Anyways, in Python we both have rubber duck debugging,
but we also have duck typing, which is the idea that if it looks like a duck and it quacks
like a duck, it's a duck. So if I'm asking, do these objects work with plus? I don't check
them and say, well, are they plusable objects? I just try out the plus operator and if it
works, it works. That happens a lot. The built-in len function is another example of that. I
could pass x to it. I don't know what x is. If it works with the built-in len function,
we'll get a length. If it doesn't, it won't. Now, what was x? Oh, it was zero, apparently
in a string. Let's make y four. What do you think the length of the number four might
be? Could be zero. Could be one. Could be four. Oh, that was the length of x. It is
an error. You can't get the length of an integer. So practicing duck typing, we try
it out. If it works, it works. If it doesn't, it doesn't. But multiple things can work
with the built-in len function. Lists are one of them, strings are another. Okay, so
we've made a list. We made a list of PyCon feelings here. How could we change a list?
Typically with a list of things, the most common thing to do with lists in Python is
to stick something on the end or to remove something from the end. After that, it's common
to change a particular value. So we know that if we wanted to get amazing from this list,
how could we do that? We'd have to know its position. What is its position in the list?
Remember, we start counting at zero. Yeah, zero, one, two. So position two. I can assign
to PyCon feelings position two to change this feeling. What feelings should we put in here?
Super amazing. We really like PyCon. And it's changed it to super amazing. If I want to
add to the end, what's your guess? There's a method we can use. What verb do you think
we might use? Could be append. You already knew the answer. What's another verb we could
use? One that's not quite right. Yeah, add is the one I often would guess first. We do
have an add in Python. It doesn't exist on list. It does exist on sets. Instead, we have
append. What's another feeling? Anything. Lacking Bs is a valid feeling. You can put
anything here. What's a feeling you have? Hungry. Yeah, I also have that feeling. So
append. What's the opposite of append, do you think? Remove. Confusingly, we do have
a remove method on lists. It doesn't remove the last thing. It's not the opposite of append.
You have to give it a thing to remove, and if that thing is in that list, it removes
it. To remove from the end, we pop. So this is a computer sciencey term. If you have a
stack, like a stack of plates, you can pop something from the top of the stack. Anyone
know what the opposite of pop is in computer science land? You push something onto the
stack. We don't have push in Python. Perl has a push and a pop. Python has an append
and a pop. I'm not sure how that mishap happened, but that's the way things are. I actually
like append better than push, but it's a little bit unfortunate that we have pop, even though
the opposite of pop is push. So to add to the end of a list, you can append, and to
remove from the end, you can pop. Let's make sure it's actually in the list first. Yep,
it did add to the end. Now, notice pop gives us back the thing that it's popping, and it
changes the list. That's a little bit unusual. Most functions in Python either do a thing
or they return a thing. Pop does both. It gives us the thing back, and it changed the
list. Some functions do both do a thing and return a thing. It is unusual, though, in
Python. Questions on lists, thoughts on lists. We're going to get some practice with lists
in a moment here. Question for you. How could I find out if I had a list of things that
I'm scared of? Weather. Scared is one of the things in this list. Yeah. We had an in operator
that works on strings. It works on lists, too. It's a very common theme you'll see in Python.
If you know how to do something with one type of object, similar objects often work with
that same operation, kind of in the same vein of duck typing, that lots of things have the
notion of containment. Does in work with them? They have a length. Does len work with them?
They can be indexed with those square brackets or the indexable. We have some exercises here.
We actually have two sets of exercises. You can pick which one you'd like to do. The first
one is lists, list exercises. That one does not involve changing lists at all, only asking
questions of lists. The other one, if you've done a little bit of programming before, you
might find a little bit more interesting. It's in more lists, more list exercises at
the bottom of the page there. The first one there is a random vacation planner. It's a
picking random locations, random amounts of time, and random destinations to go on a vacation.
Not the greatest Python program, but kind of a funny one. After that, there's a state
capital guesser, which is kind of fun because you start with the U.S. states and capitals,
and then you have to make a program that prompts the user and tells them whether they guessed
correctly there. That first one is a guest list and a couple other exercises and list
exercises there. I'm going to give you a little bit of time on these here. After this, we'll
talk about iteration in Python. I'd like to answer your questions. If you have a question,
you've had questions, try to write them down because we will have a little bit of time
at the end to answer questions before lunch. Any questions right now as you're going through
these, put up a red sticky. If you get through an exercise, it doesn't matter which exercise
it is. If you get through an exercise right now, stick up a green sticky, and I'll be
floating around the room here. I have a question for you as you're working on this. Who has
found a way to get a random thing from a list in Python? What was it? There's something in
the random module. There's actually a couple things you might be able to use. Yeah, there's
a couple things. That's what I would recommend using. If you have, say, a random list of
colors here, you can say random.choice and give it your list. It will give you a random
thing from that list. I would recommend if you're doing that random vacation planner,
you might want to check out random.choice. Reminder, if you find yourself stuck, put
up a red sticky, even if you just want a rubber duck to chat with.
All right. We're going to solve one of these together real quick. I started with this states
and capitals.py file. Missing white space. Oh, I've got some funny... There we go. Hit
that. This is a very big list of lists. You can see this list has lots of lists in it.
Each has two things in it, a state and a capital. We're meant to ask the user, what is the capital
of a state? Which means we need to get a random state and capital. How could we do that? We've
got the random module. What could we use with this states and capitals list? Yeah, if we
need to get a random... What's the way that I just showed you to get a random item? Yeah,
random.choice. So random.choice, let's just print that out just to see if it even works.
This is a good way to write your code is not do everything at once. Don't try to be
super ambitious. Just try to see if the very basic thing works. Can we get a random state
and capital? We got Hawaii, Honolulu. We got a different one. That's good enough for me.
It looks random. Okay. So this is our state and capital. We now want to ask the user,
what is the capital of a state, of a particular state? How do we get access to the state?
Yeah, it's in that state and capital list, which is a two item list. How do you get the
first thing in a two item list? Zero. So plus state and capital index zero. Okay. So we
need a question mark at the end now. So question mark and a space to make this look a little
bit nicer. And it's supposed to prompt them. I'm using print. How do we prompt a user?
Write input. So input will both print and get a response. So we'll say guess equals
this thing. Our code's a little bit long. I'm actually going to break this up over multiple
lines. This is something you're allowed to do in Python. Normally when you hit enter
in the middle of a line of code, Python complains. It doesn't care here. Anyone want to guess
why? Yeah, that open parenthesis lets Python know there is more to come. So it's okay with
us writing that over multiple lines of code. Anyone guess what the capital of Pennsylvania
is? I have no idea whether it was right. It didn't tell us. So now we need to do something
with that guess. What question do we ask? We've got an if. So if index one, which should
be the correct capital, if it is equal to our guess, then we'll print out yay, great
job. Otherwise we'll print out, maybe we should say what the actual capital is. So if index
one is incorrect, the capital is actually, now we need to say state and capital one.
Virginia. Sacramento. Oh, interesting. It wasn't Sacramento. So we'll print out, oh,
Sacramento. It was apparently Charleston. It seems like it works. Let's do one that's
actually valid. New Mexico. Yay, great job. We made a working program. Questions or thoughts
in our last 10 minutes here. So one more thing I want to show you before we wrap up. Yep.
This is a great question. So the question is, if you said I'm good and you've got a
list of things, there's good in there, but I'm good isn't in good. And you'd have to
somehow maybe loop over your list and say, well, is good and I'm good, or is part of
what I have in that thing. So we're about to talk about loops. You could loop over your
list and say, instead of is my item here within the list, ask the opposite. Is each
of the items in the list or any of these in what I'm working with here is good and I'm
good. The other way is a scary thing that is often used in text processing in many programming
languages. Anyone know what I'm about to say? Parsing, even scarier than that. It's called
regular expressions. It's a programming language inside of a programming language where everything
is on one line of code, there's no white space in comments, and every symbol is actually
a line of code. It sounds awful. And it is a little bit awful, although it's also very
powerful. Regular expressions are one way to maybe do some pattern matching. We're not
going to do regular expressions, though. I do have a tutorial online, that website. We'll
take you to a PyCon tutorial on that, though. So what I'd like to do now is take a list
of items and do something for every single item in the list. What can I use for this
in Python? A for loop. Yeah, a lot of programming languages have a notion of a for loop. Many
of them look like this. For i equals zero, i is less than the length of fruits, and then
i plus equals one. We don't have this in Python. We're thinking in terms of indexes here. Python
doesn't have that at all. Instead, we say for fruit in fruits. No index. We just get
each item. If you look up in Wikipedia, for each, all one word, a for each loop, that's
what we have. We call it for in. We're typically just for, because that's our only for loop
in Python, is a for in loop. It gets each item in the list.
Right. How could we do something four times, like meditative breathing, for example? Great
question. Ideas. Ooh, I like that. That's a thing that's a little bit more advanced,
but we can take a look at that. What other ideas?
We would need a wild one. We could do something like that.
If you want to manually add things, you have a condition, and you've got something you're
incrementing maybe. If you need a loop with a condition, that's called a while loop. So
while, say, x is greater than ten, something like that, and you're decrementing x. We have
that. We don't tend to use them often. The reason is we tend to try to model everything
in Python from the perspective of an iterable that is something you were able to iterate
over. So a list is an iterable. If you can write a for loop to loop over it, it's an
iterable. Can I loop over a string, do you think? Yeah. In fact, before I loop over a
string, how does Python know the singular of fruits? It doesn't. That's a variable name.
I can call that whatever I want. I'm essentially assigning, I'm defining a variable there.
X is under our control. So I could say, let's take a string like my name. For x in name,
what do you think this will print? It's kind of like when we index, right? Every character,
every character in the string. Anything you can loop over is an iterable. So there is
an iterable in Python called a range that you can get from calling the range function.
Range of ten gives you this thing that if you loop over it, will count upward from zero
to just before ten. You see this a lot in Python, either a built-in function or some
kind of utility for making an iterable when you didn't have an iterable because you need
to loop. We really love our for loops in Python. Not that we don't use while loops, but we
like modeling things from the perspective of a for loop. Now, if you didn't know about
range, how could you make a string that has ten zeros in it? Yeah, zero. How could you
make that ten? We could loop over a string to get the same thing there, or we learned
about how strings and lists are similar in many ways. That works on lists too. You can
actually also use plus on lists. You can concatenate strings, you can concatenate lists. You can
also multiply lists by themselves, self-concatenation. Now, range would probably be the right way
to do this, though, the easy way to do it. Other questions on loops? Yep. Right, yeah,
you can't do that. It's kind of funny because in, we've seen in, it was for containment
checking, is x in y. This is a different in. For x in name, this doesn't work because it's
actually not the in operator. It's a different in. It's actually part of the for loop syntax.
Kind of confusing. You see this a lot in Python, in fact. Else isn't just for if else. There's
try else. There's even a for else. I think there's a while else. You hopefully won't
see those because they're weird. Try else you might see. If else, you'll almost certainly
see. So sometimes the same keyword is used in different ways in Python, which is kind
of confusing, but it's just the way things are. It would be for x in range for, yep.
You don't have to print x. You do something else. You'd probably ignore x. In fact, if
you want to ignore a variable and you want to make it clear you don't care what it is,
sometimes people use underscore. Underscore is a valid variable name. It's a throw away
variable saying I don't care what the value is. We wouldn't usually use underscore there.
We'd say print hello. We'd print hello four times. Of course, you can call it whatever
you want for x in, for y in, for count in. So we don't have too much time for you to
do exercises individually. What I'd like to do instead is in our last few minutes together,
that breathe.py that some of you worked on earlier where we used time.sleep to sleep
for a few seconds. And we would say breathe in and then breathe out. You were supposed
to do this over and over for two minutes. How can we do this over and over? Right. You
could have copy pasted before, but now that we know about range, let's say for x in range,
now how many times do we want to do it? So we were supposed to do this for two minutes,
and we wanted it to be, I think it was, was it six times a minute? Once every six seconds.
So I guess seconds equals six. Once every six seconds there. So how many times we would
do it would be, what's our math involved? Two times 60 is the number of seconds total,
divided by six, is that right? Let's see if it works. Oop, float object cannot be interpreted
as an integer. Ah, what's going on here? On this line of code, by the way, this is called
a trace back. Who's seen a trace back before? Everyone should be raising their hands. You've
all seen this even though you didn't know it. Whenever you see an error in Python, you
see this printed out. The last one, the last line there is the line you read first. That
tells you the type of error and hopefully a helpful message. Honestly, it's not helpful
some of the time though. That's the thing you would copy paste into Google and hope
for an answer. If that doesn't work, go to chat GPT and hope that it gives you an answer.
If that doesn't work, ask a friend. I don't know what you do. But it's in the context
of the code. Just up from that, that's your actual code. The deepest line in your code
where you are. Python programs when they run, they use something called a stack and a stack
frame. A function can call a function that calls a function. We can go as deep as we
want. This is the deepest line in our code. If there were more lines above it, it would
be going up the call stack there. So you read from the bottom up, the last line is the most
important. It's saying on line seven, this is a float. It's supposed to be an integer.
How do we fix that? Yeah, we can wrap it in int. So range, it actually can't use floating
point numbers. There's another way to solve this, though. In Python, there's a slash slash
operator. I'm only going to show it off here because it exists. But you could just use
It does integer division. That would have been another way to solve it. So we're breathing
in, we're breathing out. Hopefully it's only six seconds. Oh, it's funny. It's printing
things in groups, right? So we maybe should have done three second pause and then a three
second pause. Oh, is it six each time? Okay, then I probably should have divided this a
little differently. I think I would have needed to do a divide by two there. You can play
with this on your own. Something you might want to try if you do end up playing with
this program, you could do something in between. You could say, let's print, for example, period,
and then we'll sleep for one second. And then we'll print out period twice and kind of make
a little line that gets bigger and smaller as you go. I'll show it here real quick with
a slightly smaller line. You know, to signify you're breathing in, you're breathing out,
you can make this whatever you'd like here. We are about to eat lunch in two minutes,
so I want to let you go so that you can actually eat. So I'm going to wrap things up. It has
been a pleasure. If you have questions, I will stick around afterward as we eat. Feel
free to ask. If this is your first PyCon, as I know it is for most of you, the newcomers
orientation tomorrow night, I will be on stage along with some other folks. I recommend going
there because you want to orient yourself to this conference that will be even scarier
tomorrow as more and more people show up. If you would like stickers for a Python exercise
service that I run where I do screencasts and exercises for Python morsels, I have them
somewhere. I'll pass them out in the back of the room in a moment here. Have a great
PyCon.