Just before we move on to the content, I just want to give an overview of the two different
repositories if I didn't already.
So we're going to start with a high level introduction to LLMs and transformers.
And then we're going to go into our fine tuning BERT exercise.
And then we'll kind of go back to high level and look at two generative AI demos, one for
GPT versus chat GPT, and then another one for stable diffusion.
And then at the end, we'll have a discussion about the bias and risks of AI, hopefully
in open discussion or in small groups.
Okay, so.
Taking a little bit of time to load.
Okay so first we're going to start with an introduction to natural language processing.
Now I have this figure here.
It's meant to be a little bit silly, but it's meant to also motivate us to think about some
important ideas for the rest of the tutorial.
So one of the things I found fascinating about deep learning when I started was this idea
of being able to take really unstructured data like text and images and actually apply a
structure to it.
But let's look at these lines first.
Three minus two equals one.
We all know what that is.
This is PyCon.
Numbers are very easy to understand.
We can measure them.
There's no confusion.
Now let's look at this next line.
Queen minus woman plus man equals king.
Now this isn't strictly speaking an equation.
This isn't something that we could say put into a model or have a computer understand.
But we know language.
So if we look at it and we say, okay, a queen is a female ruler.
And then if we subtract the idea or the concept of female gender and we add male gender, well,
that seems like it's a male ruler.
That seems pretty reasonable.
And for those of you who might have heard of Word2Vec, this is the classic example from
Word2Vec.
And if you haven't, that's fine.
I can add a reference.
Okay.
Now if we could represent these concepts that we understand in some numerical way that we
could feed into a model or have a computer understand, that would be really interesting
because then this numerical space would actually represent semantic understanding.
So hold on to that thought.
Now let's look at the last line.
I love dogs.
I had to include some dogs.
So on the left, we have a very cute pug, my personal favorite.
And then we're adding it to a chihuahua.
Does that equal this super happy pug-wah-wah?
That's apparently what they're called, this crossbreed between pug and chihuahua.
Well, I mean, it kind of makes sense if we're breeding dogs.
But again, we don't have a numerical representation of dog breeds, but we could.
And again, this is image data.
I'm sort of introducing the idea of dog breeds.
But again, representations are images, another type of unstructured data.
So we covered addition and subtraction on different data types.
I'll now make this a bit bigger.
It's text.
So deep learning gives us the ability to represent all kinds of unstructured data like text and
images, video, and even more abstract things like dogs or even emotions in a numerical
way as embeddings.
This is something a computer can understand and that we can use for models, but also captures
our understanding of data.
For the rest of this tutorial, we can think of embeddings as vectors, just arrays of floating
point numbers.
Okay, so that was the intro.
This is to motivate us.
See some pretty pictures.
Now let's get closer to what we're actually trying to do.
Natural language.
So language, you know, words are great, but we need to start looking at sentences.
We want to get close to natural language.
So let's use our knowledge of language to gauge sentence similarity.
So I have two sentences here.
The feline slept in the sunshine.
Sentence one.
Sentence two.
The cat took a nap on the rug.
And these images have been very helpfully created by Dali, which we will experiment
with in a later section.
And we can see from the pictures, we have two cute cats.
They're curled up.
They're sleeping.
They look quite peaceful.
Do we think these two sentences are similar?
I see a couple nods.
I see thumbs up.
Great.
Yeah, they're not exactly the same, but there's a similar idea of, you know, this cat or feline
sleeping peacefully.
Now let's look at another sentence.
Let's not go too far.
The cat took a bite of a rug.
This Dali picture shows a cat with teeth.
There's violence.
There's a rug.
There's a cat.
Is this similar to the other sentences?
No.
Great.
In some ways it is, but you know, the meaning behind it.
I'm talking about the meaning behind it.
So now let's come, let's look at a very simple NLP model.
This existed well before our large language models.
Can everyone see this or should I make it bigger?
Make it bigger.
Okay.
So let's, you know, before we get to LLMs, maybe we don't need them.
Let's try to come up with something ourselves and see how well we do in this tutorial in
the next 10 minutes.
So we're going to use a bag of words for sentence similarity.
If you don't know what that is, don't worry.
I'm about to explain it.
But now what we're trying to do is come up with a way to quantify our feelings about
the differences or similarities between those three previous sentences we just saw.
So I propose we try something simple.
So we're going to do this bag of words idea.
So basically we take all the words in a sentence, throw them in a bag, essentially jumble them
around and then pretend I'm holding a bag.
This is one sentence, another bag, another sentence.
And we can represent this quite well as a Python set.
And so that's what we have here.
The individual words are members of the set and order doesn't matter.
Now I'm not going to run this cell.
It's pretty simple Python code, but it is in a notebook.
But you know, we'll just look at it right now.
So now we want to come up with a metric to compare these two sentences.
So one way to do that would be to look at the overlapping words between these bags of sentences.
So let's do that.
So we're going to look at the intersection between the different sentences.
So the intersection between sentences one and two is just the and the lowercase and capital.
Uppercase.
Even though these are the two cats that were sleeping peacefully.
What about the overlap between sentences two and three?
Well, there are a lot more words there, right?
The, rug, a cat, the, took.
There are a lot of them words.
So let's turn that into a score, a similarity score.
So what I'm doing for the score is taking the length of the intersection between two bags
and dividing it by the union of the two bags.
That'll give us a number between zero and one, which is good for a score.
So we look at the similarity between sentences one and two.
Not surprisingly, we saw there was a little overlap.
The score is 0.17.
Pretty low.
Similarity between sentence one and three.
0.17.
Pretty low.
That we expected.
You know, sleeping, biting.
Similarity between sentences two and three.
0.6.
Does this match our intuition?
Okay.
I saw a couple of notes.
No, it doesn't.
So this doesn't match our intuition because we're looking at a syntax-based approach to
understanding language.
This is not capturing the semantic meaning behind these sentences.
But we know we need a numerical way of quantifying differences between sentences.
This is not going to work.
One solution is large language models.
This is an incredible jump to go from a bag of words to LLMs.
I just want to point that out.
But since we're focused on LLMs here, and that's what we're going to be working with,
I'm skipping over decades of work in NLP.
And we're going straight to the cutting edge.
So large language models have the ability to represent sentences in a numerical way
as vectors or embeddings that reflects our semantic understanding of language.
That means those two first sentences we saw, if you look at their embedding vector after
running it through a model like BERT, they would be much closer together than those two
sentences from the numerical representation of that third sentence.
That's the beauty of these large language models.
So now I want to talk about a little bit of history.
So on the y-axis, we have model size in billions of parameters.
And this is in long scale.
And on the x-axis, we have years.
And this is only the last five years.
There's been an exponential increase in the size of these models and the power and the
ability of these models.
And if we look at all of the data points on here, all of the models on here, except for
the first one, ELMO, are based on this transformer architecture.
That's what's really revolutionized NLP.
So we'll be talking about BERT today.
We'll also be talking about GPT-2, the second and third smallest on here.
I tried running some larger ones and they crashed our free colabs.
So unfortunately, we need more powerful resources for those.
And I just want to say that this graph cuts off 2022.
There's been a lot of stuff that happened since then.
POM by Google, LAMA by Meta, GPT-4 by OpenAI.
So this is still like a lot of stuff is happening.
And so I mentioned the transformer architecture, but the way I see it, there are four things
that really came together to cause this revolutionary improvement in NLP.
So the first is computing power.
Deep learning has been around for decades, but decades ago, we didn't have the machines
we have today.
The amount of RAM, memory, we have graphical processing units, TPUs.
These models, and the second point is that these models are huge, so they need a lot
of data.
But we have a lot of data now.
We look on the web, there's a ton of text data, there's a ton of image data, so we can
feed these really data-hungry models.
The third point is that typically, for those of you who are in the field, you may know
that if we want to build a supervised learning model, we need labels.
And those can be very expensive and very time-consuming to get, prohibitively so in a lot of ways.
But these transformer models are trained in a different way that sidesteps that issue.
They're trained in a self-supervised way, so we don't need explicit external labels.
So we can actually access all the data that's available out there.
And fourth, I mentioned it already, all the models that went on here, transformer models,
it's this transformer architecture that really changed things.
And at the heart of that is a particular neural network layer called the attention layer,
which we'll talk a little bit about and develop some intuition for, that we won't get into
the exact matrix multiplication behind it.
Okay, so I'm going to talk a little bit more about some of the points I mentioned above.
So large data sets.
So what was BERT trained with?
So BERT, normal BERT, not large BERT, has 100 million parameters.
And BERT was trained on the BookScoreBus data set, which is 800 million words.
And this is a large collection of free novels by unpublished authors.
And BERT was also trained on English Wikipedia, which is 2.5 billion words at the time of training.
So large data sets.
Then I talked about the special training method, self-supervised learning, so training without labels.
BERT was trained with two different training objectives.
The first is masked language modeling.
So I have an example here just so we can make it concrete, really understand.
So let's look at the following sentence and try to predict what the word should be in the sentence
instead of this mask or blank placeholder.
The clever blank got the cheese without springing the trap.
What do we think it is?
Mouse, okay, great.
And I have two helpful pictures by Dali.
One's a mouse, one's an elephant.
I mean, you know.
But no, it's mouse.
So by training BERT to predict the correct word, but over hundreds, like 100 million sentences,
we teach the model to learn relationships between words and become a better language model.
So that's one training objective for BERT.
There was a second training objective.
And that one is next sentence prediction.
So BERT was also trained by taking two pairs of sentences
and then predicting if the two sentences were related.
Like, does sentence two logically follow from sentence one?
So just to really understand this, let's take an example.
The first sentence is, the cat climbed up a tree.
Can you guys see this?
Bigger?
Yeah, just do this.
Helpful signal.
How's that?
Good?
Okay.
Sorry about that.
Yeah, just, you know, wave.
The cat climbed up a tree and got stuck.
Let's look at two possible next sentences.
Letters can be posted in person during business hours, sentence one, or sentence two.
The firefighter came with a ladder and climbed up to rescue the cat.
Getting with the cat theme here.
Which sentence makes more sense?
Two.
Yes.
So by training BERT over next sentence prediction as well,
we capture even more semantic content.
And because these two training techniques, like the first one,
we just removed a word.
So essentially, we had the label.
So we didn't need external labels.
We could use the data as is.
And again, natural language is, you know, sentences following one another.
So we already have a data set that we can use.
So then the final point I mentioned was this transformer architecture.
So I'm going to keep this kind of high level.
We're not going to get into, you know, the nitty-gritty and the math,
at least right now.
But this diagram here represents a transformer encoder layer.
So BERT is made up of 12 transformer encoder layers.
So if we look inside this encoder, we see two boxes
representing two different neural networks.
The first one is the one I mentioned.
This is like the magic behind the transformer architecture.
The attention layer.
And then inputs, in this case, the example is a sentence in French.
It goes through the attention layer.
And then it goes through a feed forward layer
or a fully connected layer.
If you don't know exactly what that means, that's fine.
But it passes through this.
It passes through 11 more blocks.
And through that, it actually gains the ability to learn
about language in a really powerful way.
Okay, so I mentioned that attention is a magic.
So let's talk a little bit more about the attention mechanism.
So attention is an efficient way of processing a sequence of data.
Like, say, a sentence, a sequence of words.
Modeling sequence data, historically, has been really difficult.
So it's typically done by modeling it element.
Oh, let me make this bigger, maybe.
This is just text, and we'll get to a diagram shortly.
So historically, this has been challenging.
We model everything sequence, or element by element.
And so as we're entering each element into the model,
we're learning a representation of everything that's come before
that particular element.
We add another element in, we update a representation
of that sentence.
We keep doing this until there are no more words,
and then that representation is our numerical representation
of the sentence.
And then that's what we're getting out of language models.
But this is, you know, I'm talking about before language models.
This is what we had to do.
And that representation could then be used for downstream tasks,
like, I don't know, maybe building a sentiment classifier.
Or if the sentence is in English, translating it into Spanish.
Or, say, figuring out if two sentences are similar or dissimilar.
So if this approach sounds complicated, that's because it is.
So the technical details of attention are out of scope.
But it's basically a way of combining the numerical representations
of words in a sentence with the position information
without having to look at everything element by element.
So intuitively what we do is, here, let me scroll down.
Intuitively what we do in the sentence is,
if I'm an element in the sentence, I ask or query
every other element in the sentence to see if it's relevant
for my own meaning.
So as a more concrete example, let's take the sentence.
The cat, purred, and happiness.
Oops.
In this sentence, the words cat and purr would attend to each other
because they're related.
Cats tend to purr, say more than elephants purr.
And so I have a visualization of that here.
So this is from a helpful repository called BurtViz.
And what we're seeing here is what the word cat
is paying attention to in the rest of the sentence
to get more information about its own meaning.
And so the pink on the left represents the strength of
or the importance of that particular word or token
to cat's meaning.
And we can see that purred is darkest,
meaning that the word cat is sort of paying attention
to the word purred.
So by passing inputs through many such layers
with this attention, with this attention neural network layer,
we can actually get really powerful models.
This is the magic behind the transformer architecture.
Okay.
So now we have these really powerful large language models.
And we'll see today they're pretty easy to use
and interact with.
So why is that good?
So a big thing that's really made this technology
really easy to use and widespread
is this idea of transfer learning.
So transfer learning is the act of initializing one model
with another model's weights.
So in this diagram here, say we have a model A like Burt,
which has a lot of innate understanding about language
and it was trained on a huge data set, English Wikipedia,
you know, task A and the book's corpus data set.
Now I need to build say a sentiment classifier
and my data set is not very large.
And I don't have millions of dollars to spend pre-training
or training these models,
just how much it costs to train some of these models.
So what if I start my model with Burt?
My sentiment review data is language.
Burt already understands language.
I then just need to adapt it a little bit
to be able to predict positive sentiment
or negative sentiment.
It turns out this has been remarkably successful
with large language models, as we'll see.
And we're going to see this up close and personal pretty soon
in our next hands-on section.
Okay, so the title has the word intro to hugging face.
We're going to be using hugging face a lot.
This is something that I started using in my last role
and I found it really helpful.
I really like the documentation.
There are a lot of helpful resources.
So what we're going to do now is just do a quick look,
the hugging face.
Okay.
So I'm logged in.
That's why we're seeing this.
But what I'm going to direct us to is the documentation.
And Dana's going to take us through some of the models
and the data sets info.
But here, this is where I usually start
when I look at hugging face.
So the libraries that I have used most
are the Transformers library.
In this, we can access things like BERT, like GPT models.
And I've also used the diffusers library
for things like stable diffusion.
And this is just a rich source of information.
I'll just quickly...
So here, you know, this is a Transformers landing page.
If we scroll down...
Oh.
So we're going to be focusing on text models.
You can see these are all the text models
that we can learn about.
And this isn't even all the models that are available
on hugging face through, like, the models hub.
It's just the stuff that, you know, has references
to the actual original papers and, you know, how-tos
and tutorials.
So there's a lot of information here.
And now I'm going to turn it over to Dana
to get us started on our first hands-on part of this tutorial,
which is actually getting our hands dirty with BERT.
Okay.
So I think we're going to take a couple minutes to switch.
Yeah.
If anyone wants to take a couple minutes,
and then we'll get set up here,
and then we'll get started on the next section.
Here we go.
Okay. So first, I guess let's take a step back.
Why are you guys here?
I want to get a sense of, like, who's in the audience,
who I'm talking to.
Anyone here?
I'll give a call-out to Stable Diffusion for all
of the artwork in these slides.
Anyone here who is, like, really interested in specializing
in natural language processing specifically?
Do you want to raise your hand?
Okay. That's great.
Cool. How about, like, of you guys, like,
do you already have some experience specializing
in natural language processing?
Oh, that's great.
Okay. So you can help me out if people have questions that,
that I don't know because it's such a big field.
Do you guys see that allow accessories?
Don't allow.
Well, okay.
So I just listed some of, like, the top people
that I've found helpful in my exploration.
These are, like, free resources, but then they also have, like,
you know, paid ones.
So that's, I would start with Chris McCormick to meet,
for BERT, to, like, do a really deep dive into BERT
because in this session we just, like, don't have enough time
to go really deep into it.
This, I was just, it's a question on, like,
on natural language processing and kind of doing a call-back
to Juy's thing about, like, queen minus woman plus man.
Does that mean king?
But then when you, like, multiply man by seven,
what do you get?
You get snow white in the seven doors.
So we can understand that, but there's, like, you know,
a lot of complexity there in, like, you know, that being picked up.
It's just a, another thing on the, like, NLP side
that I think is really interesting is, like, mixed, code mixed text.
There's a lot of, like, text out there that's, like,
partially in one language mixed with another language,
and that's, like, a field that's rich for, like,
if you have a background, if that's something you, like,
that's something that you do at home or with friends,
I think the field of NLP, like, needs a lot of work in this area.
There's just not a lot of data sets.
A lot of our data is in English.
So, like, this example was from a research paper
where they had to, like, manually convert, like,
English text to code mixed.
This is Hindi and English.
Okay, what about, like, managers?
Maybe you guys read the abstract and you're like, oh, yeah,
we've got sentiment analysis on our roadmap,
so I just want to get a sense of what's going on.
Is there anyone in here who's, like, more of a product manager
or, like, okay, we've got my manager.
Okay, that's cool.
Yeah, I threw this one out.
Like, FinBert is financial sentiment analysis
with pre-trained language models as, like, something.
Then there's just, like, a lot of articles.
If you follow the slides, you can see if any of them are interesting.
I'm just, like, a lot of companies are using it
in different ways and variations of BERT.
And then I guess, what about anyone here
who's, like, trying to do something good for the world
with everything you're learning here?
Anyone here, like, everyone's, like, guilty,
like, putting their hand up, like, not really.
But so I have some, so I just kind of did a deep dive
and I got really excited.
And some of it was, like, dark but useful, like, meaningful.
Like, we can use our expertise for good.
So let's see what I threw up here.
There's, like, you can use, like, there's articles
about using BERT for, like, detecting early-onsight Alzheimer's disease.
That falls under the NLP category
because that's, like, it's less, that's not really sentiment analysis.
That's, like, their degradation of their use of the English language
that you can pick up on it earlier.
Fake BERT, also not sentiment, but just, like, detecting fake.
This one is sentiment.
The last one is, like, with the stay-at-home mandates,
like, looking at social medians
and seeing, like, how that affected people's sentiments.
And that can inform policy.
There's just a bunch of examples.
This one was, like, kind of really stood out to me
as, like, using it as a way to intervene.
We know that, like, when there's news reports about suicide,
it actually increases suicide.
So this article, they were classifying, like, different types of tweets,
tweets that could, like, signal an intervention
where it's, like, oh, this person is at risk
versus, like, tweets that are just kind of, like, sharing.
So they have different categories there.
Some other ones, like, I'm just trying to pump you up,
like, give you ideas of, like, when you leave,
you're like, yeah, I've got cool stuff I want to work on now.
Oh, I already had the Alzheimer's one.
Oh, this is, like, they're using it for detecting human trafficking.
Both, these are two different examples of this,
using BERT to do that.
So moving on.
Who here is, like, a software engineer
and you're not super, like, into going deep into it,
but you want to, like, quickly make some apps that are useful?
Okay, great. Okay, great.
So, yeah, like, we're not going to go super deep.
Hugging Face makes things super easy.
We're really, like, standing, I'm going to say this again probably later,
but we're, like, standing on the shoulders of giants.
The Hugging Face, like, document, libraries and stuff
and all these open source models makes that really easy.
For you guys specifically, I have this, like, one talk that I recommended
that it's, like, few-shot learning in production.
It's a Hugging Face talk and it, like, gets you from, like,
making a quick model all the way to the deployment.
And also just the Hugging Face, this is for everyone, really,
if you go through those, like, 79 videos,
they're pretty short for the Hugging Face.
So, okay, but where am I going with this?
Ultimately, we all come to tutorials hoping to transfer
what we've learned to use cases we care about,
and that's what we call transfer learning,
which is strangely what we're also here to do today is take a model
and fine-tune it to transfer what it knows to a new task,
to achieve a new task.
So that's, like, this is the Wikipedia definition,
transfer learning applied to machine learning.
And then when it comes to humans, it's pretty much the same thing.
It occurs when people apply information strategies and skills.
They have learned to a new situation.
So I'm just trying to kind of create some empathy for the model
that we're about to mess with.
So there's BERT on one side, and it's, like, representation
and understanding of the complexity of language is encoded in embeddings.
And what we say is we call it intuition.
And the, like, embeddings, they come from a tokenizer.
For us, we say that it's, like, from our gut.
And then how did we learn?
Like, that's where when we talk about this mass language modeling,
like, oh, it learned from this mass language modeling task,
and it learned from this next sentence prediction.
That, for me, was a little bit confusing.
Like, how did it learn this random thing that doesn't really seem to be useful,
and now I'm applying it, like, now it has information
and I'm applying it to something different?
So the way I think about this is, like, maybe you want to have a kid
and you want them to become a doctor,
but you don't start them out reading medical books.
You start them out with children's books.
You get them a solid foundation of how the language works.
And then afterwards, you can, you know, then they've got this base model,
essentially, that you can then fine tune
by teaching them something about medical stuff,
and they can do that task.
And then, like, along those lines, if we think about hiring people,
like, we can think of, I mean, this is, like, a little bit absurd,
working in AI, I basically, like, understand my brain
and everyone else as models,
like, which is maybe not healthy yet, it's questionable.
But, yeah, like, when we're hiring someone, we evaluate, like,
think of them as a base model that we're going to fine tune.
And we're thinking, we're weighing the pros and cons.
We're like, okay, well, this person has, like, a lot of background in NLP,
and the tasks that we want them to do are NLP.
So maybe the ramp up will be, like, faster.
There will be less fine tuning.
We can give it less data.
It'll be faster to get them ramped up.
Or we go, oh, this person's a generalist.
They are going to be, you know, we could fine tune them
for a few different types of tasks.
So it's the same thing, like, when we have to decide what model to start
as our base model, there's these pros and cons.
And it's kind of overwhelming.
If you go to the Hugging Face website, there's all these different models,
and it can feel, like, really, really overwhelming.
But that's just sort of, oh, and then, like, the final point here is, like,
how, like, you guys today are going to try to fine tune a BERT model
to learn the new task of sentiment, like, analysis,
like, classifying sentiment for specific tasks.
And then we, as your instructors, are trying to fine tune you
to learn how to fine tune models.
So it's kind of a fun thing there.
So here we go.
So you guys are base models.
If I gave you a quiz at the end of this, would you all get the same result?
No, you wouldn't, because they're different base models.
Some of you guys are better than others.
Not to say that, but some of you guys, you came with vastly different knowledge.
So some people who have this, like, NLP background,
they're going to, like, maybe pick up on certain things
versus someone who has, like, more of a social background
will, like, quickly come up with ideas of how they're going to apply this
to, like, meaningful things.
And then, yeah, this is the Hugging Face.
Let's see.
This might be my break where I go to, yeah, let's go over,
and I'm going to kind of, like, start to show you the Hugging Face.
If I can figure out how to exit out of this and make sure I'm on time.
I've got till...
She's got a lot of good material, so I don't want to...
I can't go too slow, because I've...
Okay, what about, like, how many of you guys have played,
have looked at the Hugging Face?
Over half.
What about, like, do you feel, like, super comfortable with it?
How many feel super comfortable with it?
Less.
Okay, but some of you guys have, like...
Anybody that's, like...
Oh, this one's a hard question.
Everybody close your eyes.
Has anybody, like, never touched it?
Okay, great.
Okay.
I always hate to, like...
I'm the person where I, like, look around,
and I don't want to raise my hand.
I'm like, oh, no, I've seen it.
Okay, cool.
So, yeah, Julie showed you the documentation is, like, really...
Is really great.
Sometimes, meh, sometimes documentation frustrates me,
but parts I'm going to show you is, like,
there's the models and the data sets.
So we can start with the models.
Really overwhelming.
Let's just make this, like, full screen.
There's, like, there's lots of models from different people.
Think of it as GitHub.
When you go on GitHub, there's some repos that are, like,
really well documented and open source.
There's lots of contributors.
You kind of know, like, oh, they have a lot of stars.
This seems more, like, credible.
I am comfortable using this.
It's going to be well maintained versus people like me
who have some random thing that I won't touch for three years.
And so you don't have to, like, kind of look at all of them,
but over here you can kind of make selections to filter them by.
So in our case, like, sentiment analysis,
we're really just doing text classification.
We're classifying, is this thing positive or negative?
Is there joy in this?
So you could filter here to text classification.
And then, okay, I've still got 20,000 models to choose from.
So then over here you could do, like, sort by most downloaded
or most likes.
Or if you want to be on the cutting edge,
you could do, like, recently uploaded.
And just like GitHub, you can have an account here
and you can upload your own models for other people to play with.
So you can pick a base model, fine tune it, upload it here,
and then you'll get your own.
I don't know if they're stars or they're hearts.
Let's click on one to see.
They're likes with hearts.
So you can kind of, like, become part of this community.
So, okay, we already filtered to, like, text classification.
You can also, like, filter by name.
So if we wanted to do, like, sentiment,
that gives us, like, some ideas of, like,
some different things that we want to do here.
And really there's a lot.
So, like, so I would encourage you guys to kind of explore a bit
video classification, audio.
Then let's just take a look.
Since we're talking about BERT, let's take a look at,
well, I don't know what happened here.
It's not recently uploaded.
Do I have something weird?
What else do I have for my?
Here we go.
This is one we're going to look at.
When BERT was published, they actually came out with, like,
large models and then smaller models,
and then since then they've come out with even smaller models.
And there's also Distilbert,
which we're going to play with today.
But this is a model card,
and it, like, has so much information about it,
but then this is another way to, like, have, like, a little smoke test.
Let's go.
Can you make it bigger?
Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah.
I think.
This is really small text.
That's weird. It's not.
Oh, there we go.
Yeah, thanks for the feedback there.
Is that better?
Should I make it?
How's that?
Okay, cool.
So, yeah, it gives a lot of information.
Like, it includes the paper.
So here it says, like, the data sets that were used,
Wikipedia and this data set's book corpus.
It says how it was trained.
It gives intended uses.
So, like, one quick one over here is, like,
well, here, this even, like, lets you play with the masked,
the mask thing.
Use in transformers.
There, you got the code, and you can download it,
and you can start playing.
Then you've got the tokenizer and the model.
And then if you follow along with the documentation
that she showed you.
So that's kind of cool.
So that's going to lead me to the next thing.
I'm going to, let's just play with this a little bit.
Let's look at this.
I think, I don't remember where, but it shows, like,
so limitations and bias.
Sometimes they're not filled out.
And so that's, like, where I would encourage,
if you're going to start making your own models on here,
like, let's do that.
Let's, like, have some good quality documentation.
And then where was the last bit?
That might be on the other.
Okay, so now let's move over to, let's hopefully all get
our Colab things working.
Is everyone able to get to this repo here?
And then under notebooks, I'm struggling to click on it.
Bert, we're going to go with number one, Bert base case,
uncased, is what I meant.
So that means that it's all lowercase.
It doesn't care.
Like, when you put in text, it's just going to lowercase
everything.
And if it's cased, then it's case sensitive.
So over here in the corner that has this, like, opening Colab,
do you guys all have that?
Should I make that bigger?
Yeah, but I think it, like, it still opens if in Google Colab.
Okay, another way you can get to it is if you go to Google Colab.
So I'll show you this.
Oh, is that why?
But if they go to Colab, that's not a browser extension, right?
Yeah, so if you go directly to colab.research.google.com,
and then it has, like, this auto population, you can say,
I want to get it from GitHub.
And then my username is Dana Sore.
So it's a little bit bigger.
And then you go down to Dana Sore Burt.
Are you guys following along?
Or does anyone?
Okay.
Yeah, let's see if I can zoom in on that.
It doesn't zoom in.
Colab.research.google.com.
In this first notebook, Burt base uncased.
Did that work for people?
You got it?
Everyone's good?
Everyone's in there?
No, someone's not in there.
Oh, I see.
So you have to log into GitHub first.
I think for this one, we'll take a break after this,
but for this one, you can kind of just follow along.
So, okay, so this is the, whatever.
So I said, like, see the model card for more information.
Well, we just looked at the model card.
There's also the Google release of this on GitHub here.
So you can also like deep dive into the release
and see that there's like different, like, this is the one, Burt base,
but there's like lots of like smaller ones now.
And okay, so how comfortable are you guys?
Who has never used Colab before?
There's a few, okay.
Okay, I messed up and in my second notebook is where I give instructions
on how to use Colab, so.
But it's going to be like, whoops, command, if you're on a Mac,
command return to like execute a cell.
And then you're going to get this warning,
this notebook was not run anyways.
I'm just, no worries, just putting viruses on all of your computers right now.
And it's kind of slow, so I mean, you can just follow along
because there's so much material I have.
So you don't have to like run these parts.
I can just, but you can, you know, you can try to run it in the background
and I'm just going to kind of walk through what I've got here.
So this is Transformers library.
It's a hugging face library.
From there we're importing, yeah, I'll try to give that a chance.
Get rid of this guy over here.
So I'm importing auto tokenizer, auto model for Mast LM,
that's the like Mast language modeling, that's the task,
one of the two tasks that Burt learns from in a pipeline here.
This creates the tokenizer and the model.
The model and the tokenizer, I think I put that in this one.
That's in another one.
They always have to get paired together.
So with the input, like the input that you put in,
it has to go through the, it gets translated via the same tokenizer
that the model was trained on.
And so here was this like exercise, just playing with the tokenizer
if this thing ran.
That's pretty slow.
I just was like, hey, you can put in different things.
My suggestion was like try to put in different things
and see how it gets tokenized.
More common words will be tokenized like as its own word,
but as you can see, like it doesn't understand my last name,
Engerbretsen, so it tokenizes it into like, it separates it.
Yeah?
Yeah, the hashtags mean that it's like not the beginning of a word.
So if you can see Eng is Engerbretsen,
and the hashtags mean, oh, this is a continuation of the token before it.
And then...
Why is it tokenized like that?
How does it manage to be done?
So every model will have a limited vocabulary.
And so in this case, the BERT's vocabulary didn't have my last name in it.
And so if there's like sort of a dictionary where each item in the vocabulary
has like a number, sort of like an index.
And so when the word's not in there, it uses, it kind of does this like,
thinking, if you think of like a compound word,
it tries to look for like in this word Engerbretsen,
do I have something in the vocabulary that is part of that word?
And then it takes that token, and then it just kind of keeps trying to add on to it.
Yes, go ahead.
For the type...
Yeah, Wordpiece tokenizer. Yeah.
So just for like audio, so he was asking,
is there a name for this specific tokenizer, and it's based off Wordpiece tokenizer.
But I'm not sure what other models use that same, like what umbrella uses that.
That's not something I've like dove into really.
Was there another question?
Okay.
So let's see if the line before ran.
So yeah, I would just say play with, these are some things like compound words,
any obscure words that you think might not be in there,
anything from your culture that might not be in there.
Did anyone find anything funny that was like,
oh, you thought it should be in there, but it isn't,
or you thought it wouldn't be in there and it is in there?
What did you get?
Which one was it?
I don't even know that word, defenic.
That one's in there?
Oh, okay.
How do I spell it? Let's put it up there.
Oh, you're too fast for me.
D-E-F-E.
Okay.
Were you like a spelling bee whiz back in the day?
Def-ens-tra.
So the T-I-O-N, that one's common.
That one you can see is like a very common ending of a word.
Okay.
So that means your name is in the vocabulary as is.
So Burt has a vocabulary, I don't know, I don't remember off the top of my head,
I showed it as like 30,000 or something.
It's high.
But it's strangely, so the Chris McCormick I had put in my other slides,
he has this great, what was it, this one.
He's got a really cool notebook where he goes through the vocabulary
and he actually picks out a bunch of common names and he runs it through
to see which names are in there and you can just print out the vocabulary
and it's kind of funny.
That's definitely an exercise to do of just looking through what's in there
and what's not because that obviously, like all the models we build off of this
is going to have that vocabulary, so it's going to have those limitations.
Like if less common names are in there, you know, it's not going to necessarily
know it.
Okay, where am I going?
I'm too slow, I'm too slow, I've got to move on.
All right, mass language modeling.
So this I wanted to give you the opportunity and Juhee is also going to do this,
but kind of from a different perspective.
So here I've got, we're just going to play this.
I threw in these two as examples, but I did the capture because I didn't want you
to cheat and look ahead.
So what I just want us to pretend we're the model.
She craved blank to quench her thirst.
What do you guys think the most probable answer would be?
If you read all of Wikipedia and a bunch of books, what would you guess?
Yes, she craved blank to quench her thirst.
Gatorade and water.
Those were my two, Gatorade and water.
Yeah, I was like Gatorade was slightly below water for me.
Okay, so are you ready for this?
We're going to see, I'm going to remove, I'm going to comment out.
This is the thing, so shift and then the hash-y thing.
What do you call this guy?
I should.
Hashtag, you guys are messing with me.
I clearly am not like a Twitter, like I'm not like an influencer on Twitter
or any of these.
Okay, we're going to see what Burt thinks.
She craved something.
She craved blood to quench her thirst.
She craved him to quench her thirst.
She craved someone or nothing.
So like whoa, okay, she was like that was like that really threw me.
And then this one I wasn't, I promise you I wasn't trying to go down a path.
I was like petting my cat and I was like, and then I had these cat libs,
like a little book on like cat libs.
So I pulled out the cat libs and I was like the best thing
about blank is they mostly clean up after themselves.
So what other things might clean up after themselves?
Any ideas that it can be, you know, recorded?
I guess.
Okay.
Vampires made it on there.
What?
The book is unpublished, right?
Published authors actually.
Are they unpublished?
No, there's a lot of those books are now being being sold.
Doesn't it mean romance?
That's exactly the point we're going.
Actually, so yeah, that was exactly what I was going to point out.
So I did a little deep dive.
There turns out that somebody did wrote this article addressing document.
I'm going to miss the page.
What page is this?
Nine is what I was going to bring you to.
Really interesting article addressing documentation debt and machine
learning research, a retrospective data sheet for Book Corpus.
Book Corpus is one of the two data data sets that BERT was trained on.
And it's like kind of it was like really an interesting deep dive.
The actual like original copy is like no longer available.
So people have had to recreate it.
But the author of this, the author of they like through a security thing
managed to get the original Book Corpus and they did this analysis on the
original data set.
And it's wild.
Like this information is super interesting.
They've made this like cool data set fact.
Like it looks like it's on a I don't know what you call it nutrition label.
But yeah, that was exactly the point was that the percentages that as it
breaks down 26% was on romance and then like vampires was pretty high up
there.
Five point four percent of the books were about vampires and like
historical books was like one point six.
So if you think about like Google search, like a lot of companies are using
this as the base and we're fine tuning off of it.
And I just feel like there's like an ethical responsibility on my part if I'm
going to teach you guys how to fine tune this model just to be very aware of
like any biases are going to get propagated into your what you're bringing
to your customers.
Okay.
But yeah, so there's optional exercises for you to play with that a little bit
more.
I gave some some prompts that I said try some sentences.
Try some sentences with references to your cultural historical events
scientific discoveries maybe a joke song lyric and just see like if you do this
during the break or while you're bored of me talking then you can kind of tell
us something interesting you found.
And then now let's move on to the next notebook.
Which was maybe we could skip that that one.
Yeah, we'll skip data Burt was trained on.
That's an interesting one.
That one I just kind of went and did a deep dive into like things I could get
out of that book.
So we'll move on now to to Rotten Tomatoes will be our first fine tuning
exercise.
Rotten Tomatoes ever does everyone like maybe close your eyes.
Does anyone not know it.
Okay, everyone knows it.
So I shouldn't know though like I've never used it and it seems like that you
have to make a one to five star review and this data set just has binary yes or
no like it's rotten or it's fresh.
And I so there this was where I had that optional precursor for anyone who's
still not comfortable when I say that like a lot of these I say like uncomment
it and comment it out and you can do this like control see if I have an example
like so I could copy this whole thing and I can do like command forward slash to
comment it and then command forward slash to comment it back out to toggle that.
Sorry.
Okay, okay, okay.
Here we go.
That's the optional precursor.
We can skip that optional design decision just briefly.
I'm saying I don't know why this is hidden like we picked this data set because
it's binary classifier.
So while you're getting started out that's going to be easiest for you to like try
to kind of not feel defeated because you're just guessing between two things.
It's kind of easy and then the model we picked is distilbert which is a smaller
version of burt but that has still like very very good results and it's like
faster to train but I was kind of disappointed like I made these data sets
so small for this so that you guys can kind of run through it but when you go
home make the data sets bigger it's flexible and then you can actually get
like more reasonable results but I just wanted to be able to get through this
where it wasn't like running.
What's up?
Yeah, I mean so there's a paper on distilbert and like how they made the
decisions but there's like layers to like so there's like there's a number of
layers for each model and in this case I know that they went down to, burt has
12, I don't remember distilbert went down to, was like what is distilled about
it essentially in the architecture and that's where I was kind of shying away
from diving into the architecture just because there's a lot of like more
fundamental stuff to go into but yeah in terms of like the architecture there's
less layers.
It's been distilled, distillation about that and so what they did is they
cranked this smaller network using the larger network and that then allows it
to make almost the same decisions over fewer parameters because you've gotten
rid of the exuberant parameters that are actually helping the model performing
better.
So you went on a diet.
It went on a diet.
Yeah, I'll try to think of a better like I can follow up to with like more
concrete.
The papers would show like show I can kind of show like more concretely what was
taken out because it's a good question.
Okay, so and like for now like if you feel overwhelmed with anything this is
like we're going to go through this fast because I have other stuff I want to get
through and it's just like to get a high level sense of the order of like what
things are happening so I won't necessarily touch on every like little
detail because documentation will help you kind of go through like go into like
different parameters you can tweak but this is to get a first draft sense of
like what's the process of fine-tuning?
What are the like high level things?
So the first step is to load, inspect and in our case down sample the data set
just because we're you don't necessarily have to do that but because we're like
all using free compute in the same room and stuff.
Yeah and it's not super reliable we're going to down sample it so that we can get
faster results because we want to move on to the other tutorials.
So you're going to run this this line you're going to pip install these libraries
run anyways.
And then you're going to import the libraries and I just said here help is your
friend.
A lot of you guys already know this but just like you can always do help on an
object and it'll output the documentation on that.
So I have something like this you know help on load data set load data sets like
very powerful it can load.
Yep what's going on?
I can't hear you so let me come closer.
Oh perfect question.
Thank you.
Yeah I now I was supposed to do a transition to show you guys the data sets part.
So the question was how did I get the run tomato data set where that come from.
It came from hugging face.
So yeah great transition.
Hugging face has a bunch of data sets that you can play with so I showed you the
models area you can go to data sets and it's a similar like semi overwhelming but
there's like okay this is twenty nine thousand you can sort by like most downloads
or most liked my Internet seems to be like not responsive but you can also like if
you're trying to do a specific type of task you can filter to those.
So in this case it was like text classification again.
Is anyone else having Internet issues.
We got cut out.
Okay well hopefully my notebooks are I just won't execute the cells.
That is a bummer.
This thing keeps coming up.
Oh gosh and this thing keeps coming up too.
Okay so so yeah I'm so sorry you're not going to be able to run through this with me but
it would be slow anyway so data set so you're going to load the data set and from the
from the hugging face like let's see if I can get this one up.
You can just call it by its name but also this function load data set it is like very
flexible you can load it from locally you can load it from a JSON from a CSV.
I always mess up CVS and CSV like I'm going to go to CSV to get some.
And you can load it from like you can load multiple files from a folder so it's a very
flexible function there's just like basically hugging faces made like all these wrappers
that make things like a lot faster for us and then okay this is the object the data set
dict object.
What I found confusing is that it's I'm calling a data set that's what I'm seeing in other
tutorials too but it's a data set dict and it carries more than one data set.
So what's if you look at this there's actually three data sets in this one which is what
we loaded from this to make rotten tomatoes and one is the train data set and it has
columns if you think if you guys are comfortable with pandas like how many here are comfortable
with pandas.
Okay so I mean that's what I'm going to use as my like so the pandas columns are like
text and label and this is how many rows there are which would be like how many samples you've
got training samples you've got and then this is your validation data set and this is your
test data set.
So what's a little it's going to be a little confusing because you're going to see a lot
of tutorials and stuff like mine that say data set but that really represents the dictionary
that holds more than one potentially more than one it can hold just a training set it
can hold just a training and a test and sometimes it can hold three.
So okay yeah what are some observations I just kind of said them.
And then now in this case we want to down sample the data set because I think like just
to make sure your code works while you're iterating on this like down sample you don't
want to wait 12 minutes to have it break or something or like not have kind of what you
were thinking so I always down sample to just get like you get a first pass.
So similar to like scikit-learn it's got this like the data set has this train test split
function where you can specify either the size or the percentage of the data that you
want so in this case I made a really teeny tiny data set I said I want a hundred samples
from training and I want 20 samples for the test size and then a very important key point
here is stratify by column because what you don't want is see I don't know too like a
lot of you guys I'm sorry if I'm just repeating stuff you know but you don't want to have
like all of like you know you're trying to classify between apples and bananas and all
your bananas are in your test set and so you weren't able to learn anything about your
bananas so stratify just says I want whatever the portion is in the total data set keep
those ratios the same when you split the data.
And then.
So we did that and this is a little convoluted here this this process.
Because you're because because if you notice I'm doing this train test split on the train
data set and then I'm moving on to like to then then I'm going to like do another split
of the test that came from this one and I'm splitting it in half to create the valid the
like the validation set so I end up with like so it's yeah it's a little little convoluted
there was there a question over here no some stretching that's fine yeah yeah.
Where the valid is valid.
Oh.
So you should either you'll have to change later on when you pull off the data set.
You in the in the notebook you're typing forward validation out.
But it's just about.
Yeah I guess where do you see the.
Validation.
Oh I might not have fixed I know like I said I had I saw an error but I thought I had pushed
that.
Yeah OK interesting I did catch.
Why don't I see it.
Here we go that one.
Like that.
Thank you I so that must have been a push that didn't get like or a thing that didn't
get saved because I did yeah I did run into it and then so thanks for catching that.
OK so where were we.
I've got so many things I want to show you guys tokenize.
I lost where we were are we at tokenize the data now.
We were still just we were just splitting we were just like downsizing the data get to
know this is optional get to know the data set object I'm going to skip that but you
can like kind of do some things to get to know it better another optional inspect the
data with pandas.
Saying that's optional but you should do that that's like good practice that you don't
just throw stuff at at the model.
And then now here we're going to tokenize the data.
And this is where my cookie monsters.
Didn't come through.
But basically I was trying to say like think of it as like you've got to feed the model
like with the tokenized data from the right tokenizer so like a cookie month.
And now you can just have a visual thing that a cookie monster like doesn't want to eat
vegetables is like wants to eat cookies so just make sure that you're using the same
tokenizer.
And then here we go we've got like.
So this is like auto tokenizer it had you can like pass it which tokenizer you want.
So in this case you want the distill Burt based on case on case being that it's lower
case.
And then.
We're creating this tokenized function here this is so that we can do parallel processing
because it's kind of like well what is this doing it looks like it just already does it
down here.
But when you turn it into a function.
Like this you are able to like.
You say data set dot map and then you do it in batches and so those like.
Run in parallel it's tokenizing your data and in parallel so it makes it faster and you
end up with like tokenized data sets which is still that data set dict that has like
the now tokenized training.
Test and validation sets.
So yeah here there's here we got tokenized data sets and what happened is it retained
the text in the label label is like the target label that we're trying to predict which is
like zero or one positive or negative but now it added like the information that the
model cares about which is the input IDs and the attention mask that you he mentioned
are and like in this case.
The beginning at the beginning so there's like.
The input.
Has like a default limit for Burt of like five hundred and twelve tokens and so if the
text that you're putting in it is more than that it will truncate it and if the text is
less than that it will add padded tokens and that's just the like when it so that the math
works out so that it's putting in like a uniform link.
To the input.
Actually no yeah they have their own like token which is like.
Looks like I just add a code cell here their own token that looks like this.
Right is that the one pad something like that yeah.
Pad that so again those hashtags at the beginning of a of a word it just means that hey I'm part
of a word I'm not the beginning of a word and I'm not my own word.
So like.
Like dance ing it might it might tokenize as dance as one word I don't know there's like an E
I have to come up with a better example but yeah.
Presentation maybe present is one and then there's like hash hash Asian.
But so in this case for this for this attention mask.
I want to show it to you but I haven't been able to maybe I already have it.
It's going to basically just be at this layer it's going to be ones for anything like think of it as an
array that's the same size as your tokenized like.
Text and it's just going to have a one whenever there's an actual token and wherever there's a padded
token it's just going to have a zero and that's telling the model don't pay attention don't pay
attention to these padding things so that's at the initial.
Okay optional exercise that I'm thrown out here is a deep dive into how the tokenized function works.
See.
Like.
Let's now compare show index where we at.
Like I want to give you guys like a break to.
But are you guys is your Internet better are you able to run any of these cells.
Oh you guys are running cells now.
Okay maybe I'll start back at the beginning.
And run some cells.
Run anyway.
I'm just doing a shift return on these I could have done like a run all but.
I just want to get to here.
Sorry what was that.
Yeah exactly yeah hugging face so there's like a lot that they are like taking care of us for under the hood and
that's why I like this is pretty high level and if you like so there's wrappers around pie torch.
Libraries that would show you more lower level how that would work and so yeah this this is more like high level I
would say but.
Of like.
What's going.
It's yeah it really is taking care of a lot behind the scenes that is important.
Yes it's doing yeah and and like if you want to get into like more like deeper fine tuning I do want to get to the next
example because there's some fine tuning that like even at this level there is a lot of fine tuning that you do have power
to do but then like yeah if you kind of want to go lower.
I was that.
I wanted to at least just get to the.
So this is just kind of looking at these input ideas like yeah if you kind of want to inspect it that's what I was.
Kind of going here.
This I was just trying to illustrate from 46 on that they are zeros like because that because it was padded I think though I
don't know if the example changed I picked an example that.
Cut off the padding.
I think that I think this example and maybe I didn't have a seed if you if you have a seat like a random seed then it'll
stick with the same example.
But you could play with this to see that it's always going to be ones wherever there's actually tokens and then wherever
there's paddings the attention mask will be zeros.
Okay now let's compare initial input text to the tokenized text.
Let's see what I got here.
I think I was just.
Kind of a little lost what I was doing here load in the pre trained model.
So need the.
Okay so I think we're to yeah sorry we're we're we're loading the model now we're getting ready to train it.
And so this is the same exact here like the tokenizer we use was called this still Bert base base on case and we got
it from the hugging face library when we when we looked at the hugging face.
Models that's where we found that and so we're just passing it in the same exact name.
Now we need to define an evaluation metric how we want to evaluate the.
So we're importing this evaluate library.
And then here in this case because it's binary I wanted to use accuracy F1 precision accuracy.
And then here we're going to use the same exact name.
And then here in this case because it's binary I wanted to use accuracy F1 precision and recall.
For evaluating it.
So this is a function we made compute metrics it gets passed in there is like a lot that's getting kind of like.
Yeah.
Like.
What are the steps to make these big steps to like what are the expectations are they all the rappers.
So it's just like kind of questions I have trying to keep together.
So again some kind of language model some kind of.
So every model has like so every model that's on the hugging face hub will have a name and that's the same name you
pass in for the tokenizer.
And so for the tokenizer step I'm I don't know if I'm understanding your question exactly if I'm answering it.
Yeah.
Yeah for all of the hugging face models they will support like from that like auto get I don't remember the exact.
For any model you can pass it in it's also tokenizer.
Yeah if you want to make your own then that's like a little bit more complicated you have.
Yeah but for all of the ones that are on the hub it would be with its associated.
The each key yeah keyword.
Yeah the same keyword for the model you'll use for the tokenizer.
No no no that's great like that's that's an important thing.
OK so train and evaluate in this case it's kind of garbage so I want to move on because it's on a really small amount of data.
When you want to run through this again use more data like at the beginning step I down sampled it.
So I think as a take home assignment go through this and up sample like use more of the data samples because in the next exercise I can show you.
More like other ideas of things that you can do.
For fine tuning at this level.
But yeah this will show like the.
I guess I'll finish up the.
So you define the valuation metric.
You define the training arguments that get passed and there's this like.
Training training arguments class or you can pet or that you can.
Pass in kind of where like how you want to I guess like who knows what an epoch is.
Anyone not a lot of so it's just like how many iterations that you're going to run through this for each and that's you can say like I want to evaluate it based off of the F1 measure.
Every epoch you can set the number of epochs you want to run so those are like things you can fine tune if you want to you can increase the amount of data you have like these are like beginner kind of steps.
That I'm giving you I'm not it's not exhaustive but you could like add the cut E like add the number of epochs you could change the like measure of accuracy that you that you care about you could see if that's like interesting.
And you can also you know change the model that you do that you run it on.
I assume so like initial things.
Then that gets passed.
These training args get passed into this like trainer class now as training args along with the training data and the test data and then that function we made for compute metrics gets put in here.
And then you train and evaluate the models is like train train train train train evaluate.
Here I have an optional exercise of like evaluating the confusion matrix in this case it's like really.
Basic because I had like not a lot of data to run this one I was I was trying to do with like a really small amount of data.
Okay so I'm going to we don't have time to like go through the full next exercise but I encourage you to I'll just kind of like highlight it that the next one is.
Yelp reviews which are like from one to five stars.
And the way that I kind of went through this is I said I'd had like a baseline model first.
And and was and basically basically I'm just saying like don't overthink it just like pick a model get a baseline and then kind of iterate from there and then look at your data like spend time looking at your data.
And in this case like one of the things that popped out to me was kind of skip ahead.
So the baseline model like didn't have a lot of data and like one one small thing just running it with more data same exact architecture was like wait you know a lot better results as like oh you just want to spend more time on it.
But there was another thing that kind of stood out.
Let's see.
Oh.
Well I don't see it.
Okay I'm going to look for it while I would make you watch a watch something. So take this like think about this as.
Think about this in terms of like if you're trying to classify sentiment for reviews.
Oops.
Sideshow.
I don't know slideshow.
Play from start.
No not play from start sorry.
Like if you're trying to classify like this is kind of illustrates a problem that we have with.
Okay so I had like a perfect example from the Yelp.
From the Yelp one that was like exactly that that I thought was really funny.
If I can find it.
I don't know did I have more than one Yelp notebook.
Maybe I lost it but it was.
It was a pretty.
Yeah I don't know.
I guess I had so I had one where it just started out like the first five sentences anybody would predict it as a positive.
And then it kept going.
There was like 10 you know 10 more sentences that kind of didn't see it.
Informative it was just like two TMI and then the last like three sentences were all caps.
And very like angry like like Jason you're never gonna.
Like never gonna see you again.
And so that was like a good example of where like evaluating the.
Yeah I'm so sorry I'm definitely missing missing a notebook in here.
We're evaluating I'll update this but.
Evaluating like that this the text that you have to write.
And then you have to like.
We're evaluating I'll update this but.
Evaluating like that this the text that you have is appropriate for whatever that default like.
Token length is that the model expects because like there's trade offs if it's like.
If your text is a lot smaller and you're dealing with like 512 token length by default then it's just like a lot of extra compute time that's not necessary.
And if your text is a lot longer it's truncating important information and so that's like gonna really affect the performance of your model.
Okay now we are going to do a demo of text generation with GPT and.
There's a link to where this demo is adapted from.
So let's run this cell.
Yes.
GPT so the question is about GPT 2 was it always open source or did it start out in private and go open source I believe it was always open source.
And we're actually going to play with GPT 2 today and you'll see the difference between GPT 2 and chat GPT is pretty different.
It's not nearly as good.
Okay has everyone successfully run this cell.
Yeah I'm seeing a lot of thumbs up okay great.
So now we're going to move on to create prompts so this is generative AI this is supposed to be really fun.
We're not trying to predict things we're just trying to generate things and sort of be creative here.
At least for this demo.
So I have a couple prompts here and I'll make them bigger but hopefully you're following around in your notebook.
I mentioned I love dogs I had that picture the pug with the beginning I enjoy walking with my cute dog.
That's one prompt I think that's from a demo I found but I like it.
There's a prompt unicorn.
This is also from a demo that I found and then I have this other prompt which I wrote.
Which I wrote I'm in a tutorial buffer and generative AI and I just wonder if these models are going to join forces and escape our computers and turn into a guy.
I don't think so but let's see what chat GPT and GPT do have to say.
So now let's run this and let's generate text.
So there are a couple parameters that you can play with and I've had some suggested experiments in the next cell.
So obviously you know you should try different prompt texts.
You can set a manual seed to kind of ensure repeatability of your output text.
There's do sample.
So if you do false then it would be more deterministic text output.
I think people are already playing so that's great.
There's a there's top K.
So we talked about how when the dog is running across the yard to get something there are a number of options.
Most people came up with ball.
I thought of stick.
So there's some probability distribution over next possible words.
So the top K limits the options that will consider for the next word so that and by varying top K you can see you get more creative responses as you increase K maybe more deterministic more boring responses when you have a lower K.
And then finally there's a top P.
So this is a probability cutoff for considering next possible words.
So a lower P will further restrict K and so have fewer next options for words.
Whereas a larger P will allow the full sample of K next words.
So just to kind of get you situated I have some suggested experiments that you can run.
And has anyone run the cell yet.
Yeah.
So you're welcome to play with this individually if you want to talk to each other in groups and you know like to if you feel like it if not that's totally fine.
I ran the cell.
I ran the prompt about the tutorial about Bert so for someone who's run the cell what do you notice about this.
Output.
Yes.
It's very repetitive right.
It's kind of boring.
Say again.
Yes it seems to get into a loop.
Now has anyone gotten it out of this loop.
Has anyone tried playing with the experiments I suggested up here in the cell above the generation text.
Yes.
In fact it will be to sample to sample false will actually make it more deterministic.
So we're sampling we're actually sampling from possible next words when it's at the false it's you know whatever is the most probable reward will come next.
It'll come next.
And if we hit a loop it'll keep looping.
So I suggest you set do sample to true after you try to sample equals false.
Yes.
Yes you can definitely.
Sorry.
Set a temperature instead of what.
Yes.
So the question is can we set a temperature for this instead of I think do sample binary.
True fault.
Oh I see.
OK.
So what I would say the question is can we set a temperature instead of having a true or false for do sample.
So I'm glad someone knows the idea of a temperature.
So what I would suggest is that you set do sample to true and then there are different ways of varying the output.
I picked top P and top K.
There's also a temperature which kind of also alters the probability distribution of next possible words.
So there are different ways of tweaking the output.
So yes feel free to use the temperature.
I would say it's not it's sort of a complementary thing to do sample and it would be another way of controlling the output instead of top P or top K.
Has anyone gotten a non boring output out.
Yes.
OK.
Someone changed top K to 300 and got better text out.
Did you change top P at all.
I think it's.
OK.
So what I would suggest for the most interesting text as.
As you.
I don't know.
As.
As Morton has just found out is that if he set top P to something very low the output gets more deterministic.
So.
I guess at this point I was going to say hey take five minutes.
Try a couple different prompts.
Try a couple different variables.
Kind of get a sense for the output.
We're going to contrast the output of this model GPT 2 which we know is an open source model but not that powerful to what we get out of chat GPT if we put the same prompt in.
If you have an open AI account and want to do that for chat GPT.
OK.
We'll circle back in five minutes and then we'll see what people have come up with play with the prompts.
There's some interesting differences between what you put into chat GPT and chat GPT 2.
OK great.
I see some collaboration happening.
Feel free to talk to your neighbors.
OK.
I think a lot of people came up with some interesting stuff.
Looks like conclusions are if we make top P pretty high we get some really creative responses.
If we increase top K we get some creative responses.
If they're too low we get stuck in these loops.
A couple of people already went ahead and put the same prompts in chat GPT.
That's my next suggested exercise.
So how many how many people have not yet done that.
OK.
A couple.
So take another.
So why don't we first let's summarize what we think of this output.
I think I just summarized it.
Does anyone have any other insights to add or what I did about the top P top K.
No.
And the quality output for those of us who have played with chat GPT response.
What do we think of this output relative to what we've seen from chat GPT.
That's so bad.
Said well yes yes.
GPT 2 is a much smaller model and there's a lot more that went into training.
Question.
OK.
Okay. Sure. So the question is, why is do sample, even if do sample is true, why is
it deterministic? That's because there's actually a random seed being set here. So this is the
torch manual seed. So if you comment this out, then you won't, for the same input parameters,
you'll actually get different output.
So why do you set do sample to false?
I see. So the question is, if I want to make a product out of this and I want a known response,
you know, and I want to set do sample to false, how can I still get interesting output? The
answer is you can't, because when you set do sample to false, whatever is the next most
probable word will be put in there. So if for some reason you get stuck in a loop, that's
it. You're not breaking out of the loop. Yeah. And I would think, you know, since we're chatting
for your product, you might want a little bit of variability. But, you know, I don't
know your use case. Okay. So did anyone? Okay. So we got some conclusions from that. And
just before we, before I formally move on to chat GPT, I just want to point out just
to reinforce what we learned for BERT. It's really this easy. We imported a model from
transformers. We imported a tokenizer. We load them from the same checkpoint, which
we did with BERT. That's how hugging face works. And it's this easy. And then, and then
we do the tokenization. At that point, we're not doing any fine tuning. We're just using
the pre-trained model and changing the parameters. Okay. Let's take another two minutes to test
out chat GPT for those who haven't. I specifically recommend trying the unicorn prompt in chat
GPT. It's a very interesting response relative to GPT 2. So I will, we'll meet back in three
minutes.
When you say try that with chat GPT, do you mean just put that in the input chat box or
the specific command we should do with our prompt to chat GPT?
I mean just cut, just paste the text of the prompts into chat GPT. Does anyone not have
an account to use chat GPT? Sounds like, okay. So take another couple of minutes and then
I want us to talk about the differences that we see. Okay. I think we've had a couple of
minutes to play with chat GPT versus GPT. It sounds like the consensus is that there
is some, so when, for people who tried the unicorn prompt in chat GPT, I think it was
like, well, no, unicorns don't exist. So you can see that there's some extra like sort
of safety checks or guardrails like, hey, this isn't reality in chat GPT. Let's see.
What are some other things that people noticed? Anything? Chat GPT is a lot better, right?
It's an actual conversation, I think I was discussing with someone. Yes.
Okay. So one second. So we're going to talk about the differences between the unicorn
and chat GPT. So we found out that if we ask chat GPT to pretend that it's writing a fictional
story, then it'll bypass the safety check of like, hey, unicorns don't exist. Question
in the back.
Yeah. I tried to like rephrase the unicorn a little bit. So I was like, oh, I read on
Facebook that they found the same unicorn and then what do you think? And it picked up
on the subtlety of that and started walking in tight.
Okay.
It like picked up on a particular voice type, which is very subtle to use in a thing. And
I'm like, okay, so I'm going to use that.
Okay.
So I'm going to use chat GPT. So I'm going to use chat GPT. So I'm going to use chat GPT.
Okay. But it kind of took it to Facebook, you know, your, the prompting into account.
So it kind of like continued a conversation. That's the chat part of GPT.
Okay. And it had a cautionary message. Okay. So, so we've noticed some differences in the
output. Why are we seeing this? So one thing is the size of the model. So now these are
some discussion points that we talk about. So GPT-2 we know is much smaller than chat
GPT and then much smaller than chat GPT-4. Parameter tweaking. So we could tweak the
parameters for our model. Could we do that for chat GPT? No. It's private. We have a
web interface. Context. So if we chat with chat GPT, we say something, it responds. We
can then adapt that response, right? There's this idea of context, the way like to human
beings when we're having conversation, we have that continued sort of context of the
conversation. So chat GPT has that ability. GPT-2 does not. Cost. You know, right now
both are free. You know, we're playing with our free Colab notebook and we're using this
free web interface. If we wanted to build a product around this, then we have to do
API calls for chat GPT versus a hosting our own model on infrastructure. You know, unclear
which would be more cost effective than this open source versus private thing. You know,
chat GPT is private. But one really important thing that I want to point out is the fact
that chat GPT has an extra training step that actually incorporates human feedback. So the
base model will produce all kinds of things based on the statistical distribution of next
tokens. Then by using reinforcement learning with human feedback, which I'm trying to
illustrate in this diagram, we take the output of an initial model and of a tuned model.
And we're trying to tune the model to actually be more human like. We rank the outputs of
the base model and then using reinforcement learning, we then have this feedback loop
of trying to make a tuned model even better and better. That's another big reason why
chat GPT is so much better than GPT-2, this model that we're playing with our notebook.
I believe, yeah, so the question is, how much effort did it take to do this further tuning process?
I believe OpenAI had to have an enormous budget to actually do this process. So this is a big
part of chat GPT. It's not just like a little, hey, let's slap this on and see what happens.
Yeah, it's a big part. And I believe the same thing for chat GPT-4. Question?
Yes. Good question. So the question is, how do we get that context, that conversational
So at least for initial versions of chat GPT, the context was simply appending all the conversations of chat GPT to the initial prompt.
So that the prompt just got longer and longer and then the conversation continued from there.
I don't know if that's true anymore. I think there might be some more sophisticated sort of memory involved in context.
So I don't know. One second. But let's see. The other thing is that chat GPT has a much longer input token size than our GPT-2.
That's why we can hold that context of the multiple back and forth conversations. Question?
I know you can reach the end of a conversation, like the conversation gets too long and it forces you to restart.
Okay, so data point. Conversation can get too long even in chat GPT.
So we know there is a maximum token length that we will hit. We can't have an infinite conversation.
Make sense. Okay, if we're ready, let's move on to stable diffusion.
Who wants to move on to stable diffusion? Make some pictures. Okay, cool.
So. We will go back into the notebook folder of NLPower.
And we will look at 3.1 generative AI and diffusion.
Click on that.
So there's an open in Colab button. Use that to open this in Colab.
It should automatically connect to a GPU runtime. We may need to explicitly disconnect from our previous notebook.
I think we can only access a free GPU one at a time.
Okay, have other people successfully loaded the notebook in Colab? Cool.
So let's run the setup step first. PIP installing what we need.
Now we're moving away from text, but you know, since chat GPT and you know, stable diffusion are like the hot things right now,
I thought we should at least touch on them in this tutorial.
So I have here a diagram of the stable diffusion model and then a blow up of a specific part of that model.
So what's actually happening? So there are different components in stable diffusion.
And when we load up, you know, when we load up a model, we'll actually see the different components.
But basically, the idea is that we just have noise and then we build a model to actually predict the noise and slowly remove
noise and reveal an image underneath.
So the model that does that is called a unit.
That's the big yellow box in the middle.
And then we produce sort of a compressed version of an image with noise, which we run through a scheduler,
which is this loop that we see with the pink box, which slowly denoises or tries to predict the noise and remove it from an image.
And then by doing this multiple times at the end, we'll end up with a compressed image, this orange box,
which we run through a decoder.
And, you know, if you don't know what these these are, we can still do the demo and I'll point out the various components of the model.
But we take the compressed image, which we've denoised successfully by running it through this loop of this unit and the scheduler.
Then we uncompressed the image, essentially using this decoder, and then we magically get a nice image out.
So I've talked about the main part sort of on the left now.
And this is what I find super interesting about stable diffusion is that we can pass in a user prompt as text and using that text,
we can actually condition the image that we generate.
That's why we can use stable diffusion to generate pictures that have never existed, like an astronaut riding a horse on the moon or what have you.
And so the way we actually align image and text embeddings is through this diagram, which is on the right.
So we encode the text. We've used BERT to do that.
We know how to do that now. We can actually encode images.
There are very powerful computer vision models that can produce embeddings for images.
And then if we train these encoders to actually align the embeddings of text and images,
like say you have a picture of a dog and it has a caption, hey, here's a picture of a dog in the grass.
If we are able to align the embeddings for both the image and the text, we can actually do something very powerful with this clip model.
It's called the clip model.
We can put in a text embedding and actually get a picture that closely matches that text.
Yes. Yes.
Yes.
So this is where captioned images on the web came in.
So this was trained by scraping images off the web that have captions.
Yes. To train this image and text embedding alignment model, you need to have captioned images.
That is correct.
OK, so here's a high level model overview. Now let's actually run this.
So let's run the first cell.
Now I'm running the second cell.
And we're going to have to download a number of files.
And so this diffusion pipeline that we're loading from a pre-trained checkpoint, this should look very familiar.
We loaded from pre-trained checkpoints for BERT, for GPT-2.
We can do it for diffusion.
And this is a beauty of hugging face.
So this diffusion pipeline contains the components that I talked about, this unit, the decoder, the scheduler, and then also the clip model.
So when we put in text, we can actually get an image out.
So again, this is generative AI.
So it's meant to be creative.
I provided some prompts here for you to try.
An image of a squirrel in Monet style, prompt to a black and white cartoon of a friendly monster eating ice cream in the style of Shel Silverstein.
This is something I enjoy, Shel Silverstein.
So I tried these.
I have a suggested number of experiments.
So I talked about how we run through a denoising loop.
So the code that I have here uses a generator and an input text prompt.
And then try varying the number of inference steps to see how the quality of your output image changes.
So this is a picture of my squirrel in Monet style, which I saved in the notebook.
I was actually quite impressed by this.
So why don't we take a couple of minutes, try a prompt, try changing them by inference steps.
I suggested varying them from like 2 to 100.
And have a look at where you get up.
OK, I think we've had a lot of fun playing with prompts and different inference steps and denoising, getting a feel for how stable diffusion works.
Yes.
Cool.
OK, let's move on to the second demo.
So this is the one I find really interesting.
So we were inputting text to get an image out.
Now we can actually condition this on an input image and input text.
So we can actually.
So for those of you who have your own picture, you can actually use your own picture for this demo or you can use a provided picture.
Does anyone have their own picture they want to use?
Yeah.
OK, cool.
So there are.
Let's run the cell.
And for the picture part, we can use this first cell under initial image or there's a sample data folder that's provided by Colab.
If you want to upload your picture into here.
And then uncomment this line here.
I think two people I saw were using their own image.
So let me know if you have questions.
But yeah, so it's sample data.
And so I will use the picture that's provided.
So this is a picture that's provided.
It's very colorful, kind of a sketchy drawing.
And then the prompt that we can input the prompt that I have here is cheaply style a fantasy landscape with castles.
So as before, there are parameters to tweak.
Now we have a couple more.
So we have both an image input and a text input.
Of course, you can change the prompt, try different styles, number of inference steps, clear image, more steps, fuzzier image, fewer steps.
But there's also a strength parameter, which determines how strong, how close it will follow the initial image and also a guidance scale, which determines how important the text prompt is for the output image.
So I have some suggested experiments.
Try varying strength from zero point one to one point zero.
Fix strength and then vary guidance.
So figure out how much of the image you want in your final image.
Fix that and figure out how much of the text you want in your final image and then experiment.
So take a couple of minutes to try this.
I thought this one was really fun.
Just varying the text versus the image strength.
So it just came up that the text that you input is completely independent of the picture.
You're using both to generate the output.
That text, Ghibli style and fantasy landscape, is not a caption for that picture.
You're actually using two inputs to generate something out.
That's a creative combination of both.
OK, sounds like we've had some fun kind of varying the strength of the text prompt and the image.
I saw some really cool images, one of Goku, one of Salt Lake City.
Anyone else have anything interesting they want to share?
OK, well, I hope you had fun playing.
Who wants to try Dali with some of these same prompts?
Yeah? I got some yeses.
OK, so for those of you who have a Dali account or an OpenAI account where you can use Dali.
Hopefully this will load.
Try putting in some of the same prompts and see,
do you prefer the model that we were using in our notebook or do you prefer what Dali can create?
I just want to point out that Dali isn't the only way you can do this.
I think there are a lot of web interfaces for stable diffusion now.
So feel free to use any that you're familiar with or that you're curious about.
Things are rendering a little bit slow.
I'm trying my picture of a squirrel in Monet style here.
This is a picture of a creature eating ice cream in the style of Shel Silverstein.
I'll just leave this up.
So I think Dali is definitely better at some things, but I was pretty impressed by the stable diffusion model
and it slowed up from hugging face as well.
I think some of you were impressed as well based on when I walked around.
So while you guys play around, I'm just going to pull up a little bit of hugging face documentation
for where this came from, just to tie it all together.
So I'll just keep talking through it.
Feel free to keep playing.
But this is the diffuser's documentation.
So a lot of the demos that I got are from here.
Just like a lot of the transformer related demos were from looking at the transformer's documentation.
There are various pipelines that you can use, different kinds of image generation.
So anyway, this is a resource for you if you're more interested in running stable diffusion.
One of the personal projects that I'm working on is trying to fine tune a stable diffusion model
to produce art in my own style.
That's an ongoing thing I'm working on.
Okay, we don't have too much time left.
Are people good playing with Dali on their own?
I'm going to go ahead and start with Dali.
Okay, we don't have too much time left.
Are people good playing with Dali on their own after this?
Okay.
Was there a question in the back?
No?
Okay, you're good with that.
So I want to move on to the last topic.
I definitely didn't want to skip this one.
So I'm going to go back to the repository, click into notebooks.
And then I'm going to click on 4.0, which is AI in society.
You don't need to run this one in Colab.
It's more about demos using Hugging Face hosted APIs.
So we talked about BERT.
And I think Dana mentioned that a lot of this data is, say, romance novels.
A lot of historical data.
People drinking blood instead of water.
So it's a little concerning.
Actually, it's very concerning to me.
But I also want to point out some other possible issues with a model like, say, BERT.
So I suggest you right click on these links that I have here.
So the first sentence is, the nurse went for a walk because blank wanted some exercise.
And we're going to use BERT to fill in that mask token.
Let's see.
Okay.
So I'm sharing.
This is a hosted inference API on Hugging Face.
No.
So on the right here, we put in the sentence.
And then BERT has computed what it thinks should go inside the blank.
What do we notice?
She is exponentially more likely than, say, he.
Okay.
So what does this tell us about BERT?
It's biased.
It thinks nurses are female.
What if we change this profession to, say, doctor?
And we compute it.
Now what do we notice?
He.
So this bias is built into this model, BERT, that we're using for basically everything.
Now a lot of products are being built on top of this.
So aside from the vampire and the blood, there's also this where we can see actual measurable bias.
Does anyone have another profession they'd like to try in here?
Software engineer.
Okay.
I heard a bunch of, I think I heard the lawyer, but I heard, I also heard software engineer.
I'm going to go to software engineer first.
I think I actually did this with a friend.
She's like, hey, put in an engineer.
Okay.
He.
Is this what we want for our language models that we're building everything off of?
All right.
So I'll let that sink in for a little bit.
You can play with this on your own time.
The link is there in the notebook.
You can test it out.
I want to look at another potential area for bias.
So I'm going to open this next sentence in the API.
Here.
Let's do it here.
Okay.
Can everyone see this?
Yeah.
Karen went out to, sorry, let me show.
Blank the bank.
Okay.
What do we see?
Check.
Visit.
Find.
See.
Watch.
Let's change the name.
Mohammed.
Mohammed Ali.
Right?
Compute.
What's the first word that comes up?
Rob.
Very different from what we saw with Karen.
Now I think at the beginning when we were talking about tokenizers, I think someone
said, oh, my name's in the tokenizer, but like my friend, you know, my coworker's name
isn't.
That's one form of bias already.
Right?
But here, this is what the language has learned on top of the tokenizer.
If you're at this API, try your own name.
Feel free to do that.
If you're just watching, that's fine.
You can try it under your own time.
But, you know, let me try a couple other names.
Let's try Sarah.
Check.
Visit.
See.
Find.
Let me try my own name.
Okay.
Well, I have a 7% chance of robbing the bank.
Based on this.
So this is what we're using for everything.
I just, you know, I don't think it's responsible for me to have a tutorial like this, Dana
and I agree, and not point out some of the real flaws in this.
Question in the back.
Yes?
Sorry.
The question is, I couldn't hear all of it.
Static data set, yes.
It is older, yes.
Yes.
So the question is, like, how do you correct the bias in society with a model?
How would you address that?
What does this mean?
So I guess the question is, how would you correct the bias in society in a model?
So I guess there's bias in society, that's one thing.
Then there's bias in the model.
So now in the nine minutes we have left, to address that, I have some ideas that we can discuss.
So given how prevalent LLMs like BERT are, do we see risks from above?
I think the answer is yes.
So what are some ways of mitigating bias?
It could come in in the data.
We could have more curated data sets instead of taking a big thing of vampire blood,
novels that may be published or unpublished, and Wikipedia which may or may not reflect what we wanted to in terms of society.
So curated data sets, that's one thing.
We could change the model.
So the way we train it, we have a certain type of loss.
We can reweight certain samples, say, with names that aren't as highly represented in the text corpus that we're training on.
That's one way of doing it.
Post-processing, I think it was mentioned in the back.
So we know chat GBT uses reinforcement learning with human guidance to kind of give us better responses in the web interface.
That's another post-processing way, once you have a base model, to try to fix or mitigate some of the bias that we see.
But this is an ongoing area of research.
And I think this is a really important topic.
I have a section here on the risks and benefits of AI.
I don't know if anyone's seen this picture.
A pope in a puffer jacket.
This was created by Mid Journey, an alternative to like stable diffusion and Dolly.
And it's fake.
It's fake news.
Credit to Pablo Xavier and Mid Journey.
Pablo Xavier did not want to mention his last name for fewer repercussions.
So I have a section, and I was hoping this would be an open discussion for those of you who want to stay and discuss amongst your neighbors.
Here's a selection of views on AI and how we could possibly, you know, the risks, the benefits, what can we do.
And I'll just call out some of them.
Smaller curated data sets.
This is by a researcher who is at Google and then I believe was fired for actually speaking out against the large language model trainings and not having curated data sets.
Many of you may have heard Elon Musk and other luminaries have called for a six month pause on AI.
No more models, more powerful than GPT-4 before we understand what we're doing.
Another view by Jan Lukun and Andrew Ng.
This is a video I watched and Jan Lukun was saying, oh, well, a lot of AI can help make better AI.
Better, like more AI, like hate speech and toxic abuse online can be mitigated by having better AI.
So that's one view.
And like, can we even stop AI progress?
Probably not.
I mean, I don't see anyone pausing.
And then risks of misinformation.
We saw that picture of the Pope.
Speed of the expense of safety.
The White House has a blueprint for AI regulation.
It's not law.
It's just a suggestion at this point.
Economic risks of AI.
Is chat GPT going to take our jobs?
Data privacy.
This one resonated with me.
A lot of artists found out their work was used to train stable diffusion.
Now the value of their own work is much lower because people used to use stable diffusion to generate work in their own style.
So if you would like to discuss with your neighbors about this, I would love to walk around and just hear what people are thinking.
You're also welcome to leave.
We're almost at time.
So question in the back.
Okay.
So this is a resource that you can use to detect models in machine modeling models.
And it's called Fairlearn.
Fairlearn.
Okay.
Open source project by Microsoft.
I'll close.
I have another question.
Okay.
So why don't we close here?
I'm going to walk around and talk to people who are interested.
But thank you very much for coming.
I hope you learned something.
Dana and I were excited to put this on.
And we're excited that you came.
Thank you.