Okay, hey, I have sound.
Perfect.
Hi, everyone.
I'm Geir Aniela, and this is a tutorial about decorators.
So first of all, thank you all for coming.
It's great to see so many here.
And just to tell you a little bit about the plan today, I guess is that we'll talk about
decorators.
And the first part, I'll kind of be a little bit teetery and just stand here and talk and
show you some examples.
And then we'll kind of move into more of an interactive session quite soon, where you'll
be sort of like giving exercises, and then you'll have to play with them a little bit.
And then we'll kind of discuss a little bit of solutions afterwards and move on to different
exercises.
So before I start, just to sort of like get an overview, how many of you have written
your own decorators before?
So a few of you.
Okay.
How many of you have consciously used a decorator?
Cool.
How many of you do not know what a decorator is?
Perfect.
Then we have a nice diversity here, and I'm sure that at the end of this, you'll all have
written decorators yourself and hopefully have some good ideas about how you can use
them.
Okay.
So my plan is to do this very interactively.
So it looks like I have slides, but those are just the exercises.
The rest, everything will kind of happen live.
And also afterwards, I'll put everything up on my GitHub, so I'll share the GitHub link
with you.
So you can find all the code I write afterwards.
But the idea is that you'll be typing yourself as well.
And then let me just see if we can get these things looking decently here.
So we have, essentially I'll just be using an editor to kind of have some code displayed
up there.
And then I also want to have, let's see if we can make that work.
Come there.
Sort of like a screen like this.
So here on the right-hand side, I'm running IPython.
Let's see if we can make this there.
I'm running IPython, which is an interactive Python REPL.
If you don't have IPython installed, feel free to just type Python and use the REPL
you have there.
IPython brings a few niceties, like it's easier to find your history and move around and things
like this.
But everything we'll do is very much basic Python, so we can just use our REPL like this.
In terms of colors, I guess I'll try to make everything, let's see, we don't need that
background.
So just to make sure everything is readable.
Let's see.
Turn off the transparency.
And I guess I can also toggle this one.
Okay, are the fonts big enough?
Can you see them from the back?
Perfect.
Yep.
Goodie goodie.
The end should be almost ready at least.
Okay.
So to start off, I kind of just want to give you a brief overview of what is a decorator.
And then we'll kind of look a little bit about, it's really about how do you call and define
functions.
So we'll kind of talk a little bit about what are functions, how can you deal with functions
in Python.
So this will kind of just be a small overview like that.
And then as I said afterwards, we'll kind of look into how do we actually define these
things ourselves and so on.
So first let me just show you some examples of which decorators are kind of out there.
And I'm going to at least in the beginning we'll be using a lot of sort of like toy examples.
So it may seem like decorators are for doing silly examples, but they are actually quite
powerful and you can use them for real stuff as well.
But bear with me with some of the toy examples in the beginning I guess.
The idea is that I've chosen them more for their explainability, so to speak, than their
usefulness, at least the first ones.
Okay, so I'll start off just by importing the time library, mainly because I just want
to show off something that's slow.
And instead of creating a function that takes a long time to run, we'll just do the easy
thing and do a time sleep in our function.
And for this one, I want to just define a function that I'll call a slow square.
So it'll take in a number and then it will square that number.
But it will do so very slowly.
So not very useful necessarily, but it can show us some of the things that we'll use.
So let's see.
Let's start off at least by saying that we'll be sleeping for a given number of seconds.
So yeah, just to be clear, this is an F string.
I'll make this one slightly wider for now and then we'll put it back in again.
So just to let people know that something is happening, and then let's actually sleep.
So I'll just sleep for some given number of seconds.
And then we'll actually do the job of squaring the number.
So this slow square function, it just squares a number, but very slowly.
So for instance, we can square the number 3 and after 3 seconds, we'll get the number
9 out.
I don't want to really go on square very big numbers because that will take a really long
time, but you can see here every time I call this, it takes some time.
Now think of this more as you're doing some operation, you're doing some function that
actually takes time for normal reasons.
So you may want to avoid doing that operation over and over again.
And Python comes with one of the standard library decorators, which is called cache.
So this one you can use to cache results, which essentially means we've already calculated
this.
So just recall the result from previous.
And one way we can use this is that I can define a cached square, which I'll just define
by applying this decorator function to my slow square function.
So for now, we don't really know what this cache is doing unless we go read in the docs
or something like this.
So it may not be clear that this cache can be applied to a function like this, but for
now let's just trust that this works.
So you can see here what actually has happened instead of I applied cache to slow square.
Let's see the result of this.
So if we now call cache square with three, then we can notice that again it sleeps for
three seconds.
So it again takes a little bit of time.
But now if I call this a second time, you can see I get an immediate result.
And it's not printing out the sleeping for three seconds at all.
So what it has actually done is just completely skipped the second invocation of my function
because it knows the return value is nine when it calls it like this.
Now if I change the parameter here, so I'll do watch the square of two instead, then we'll
see that again it goes back to sleeping because now I have different parameters sending in
and then sleeps for two seconds and then we get four back.
But then now this is also cached.
So if I call cache square, I get this immediately.
And it has some memories.
If I go back and call in cache square three, that's also immediate.
So all of this last stuff is not really about the decorator.
The decorator part is just cache is a decorator.
So what can decorators do?
They can kind of change functions from the outside.
So right here I didn't do anything to my slow square function, but I changed how the slow
square function works, right?
Instead of being slow at every call, now it suddenly caches the results and I could
do this without going in and changing the function itself.
So that is typically what we use decorators for.
We can apply some behavior or something to different functions.
So different examples of this would be, for instance, if you have setting up some website,
you can kind of say that some of the routes you're going to, you need to be logged in
and some you don't.
You can kind of put the log in logic in the decorator, which makes it really easy to just
say these are private pages, these are public pages, for instance.
Or maybe you need to time certain functions.
You can have a timer decorator that can just time things.
One example we'll play with a little bit later is that maybe you have some function that
sometimes fails, so you just want to retry.
So then you can kind of retry until it succeeds and so on.
Different ways where you can just add some behavior outside.
A very powerful one, I guess, from the numerical analysis thing is that you can say that I
want to apply just-in-time compilation to a function so that it can run faster.
That's also something you can do just with a decorator.
Okay.
I'll also now very briefly just show you the typical syntax for using decorators.
Because if you've seen decorators, they usually don't look like the one in number six there.
That's one way to decorate your functions, but usually you do it when you define the
function itself.
So we can also define the cache square.
Let's see, we can do this on top here.
With this at symbol.
So at symbol cache means that now I'm applying a decorator.
And then I can just type out my function here.
So previously we called it slow square, now I'll call it cache square like this.
And then I can again, I'll kind of just repeat the same code like this.
And now we should have exactly the same behaviors earlier.
So if I call cache square with three, it sleeps for three seconds, but the second invocation
is immediate.
So this is kind of the typical way that we'll use decorators.
Okay.
I guess I didn't say this when I started, but feel very free to shake your hands in
the air and ask questions.
I'll try, so for video purposes, either I'll have to repeat the question or there is a
microphone up there as well.
So if you want to get, stretch your legs, you can also go up to the microphone.
Yeah, do stop me if there's any questions.
And I guess when you're talking logistics, there should be a break in about one hour
and 18 minutes.
So we'll have a half hour break.
So it's like in the middle of the tutorial.
Yes?
So you're asking, well, previously imported cache from Functools?
Yeah.
Right, yeah.
Yes, exactly.
So let's see if I find that one.
So here I had this, and then the first thing we did was this, right?
Yeah, so first I imported cache and I used it there, and then what happened when I did
number 12 up there is that I overwrote that function.
So I kind of just redefined it with the exact same behavior.
So it's kind of...
Right.
Right, now you can see, I guess here I renamed the slow square to this cache square.
So then I...
Yeah, so they are kind of different, but the end result is the same.
Yeah.
What's the cost of essentially doing the creative thing?
You could potentially just add cache to every function you ever wrote and call it twice.
Exactly.
Yeah, I guess there's two questions hiding there.
So one is what's the cost of applying decorators essentially, and those I believe they're not
very much optimized.
So essentially it is an extra function call, and function calls take time in Python.
So there is some penalty to using decorators in general.
In particular in terms of the cache, why don't we just cache everything?
And that may be a good idea if you know that all your functions don't have side effects.
For instance, if you could see the print statement disappear there.
So if you kind of need all your function calls to have some side effect, then caching won't
really work.
And yeah, caching can lead to very subtle bugs, and you'll really have control on them
being pure, I guess.
Okay.
So now we've seen decorators.
Then now I kind of want to take a step back and start talking about what's a function,
and how can we play with functions.
And I guess, yeah, the question is not so much what's a function.
I'm kind of assuming that you're familiar with doing your def something with parameters.
But what can we then do with these things?
So typically at least when we define a function, let's just do something like a double there,
and then let's just return x times 2.
So here I've defined a new function that just returns the double of whatever is passed in.
And what I guess at least not always true in all programming languages is that in Python
a function is again just an object that has a name reference to it.
So for instance, if I just type out the name, you can see here that it kind of references
this function object that's there.
And then we can see that there is a difference if we have if we just type the name and if
we type the name with parentheses.
So if you just have the name, this will kind of be important for the rest of the tutorial.
So if we have the name like this, that's just a reference.
But if we add parentheses, then we're calling the function.
And what we get back is then the result, the return value from that function.
So you can see here in number 17, I'm getting the function.
In 18, I'm getting the number.
That's the return value from there.
But since these things are kind of just named references in this sense, it means that we
can also redefine things and so on.
So for instance, I can do something weird like this where I'm saying that skrivut equals
print.
So skrivut is Norwegian for print.
So this is me starting to translate Python into Norwegian.
And we can see now this skrivut here, if I ask it just what you are, it is the print
function.
And I can use it to say something like, hi, Python.
And it prints this out for me.
So that's kind of one thing we can do with functions.
We can give them different names if we want to.
And this is kind of now just both print and skrivut are both functions that kind of just
reference the same function objects.
So they are identical, how you call them.
Of course, this is probably not a good idea if you kind of want to have your code been
read by others and so on.
It's also then, we can kind of do the opposite, which is probably also bad.
But I can reuse print as a statement like this.
And we can see now this has become the number 3.
And I can't really call, let's see, 2 plus 3 or something.
We can see now that this is actually a number, so I can't really call it like this.
So it kind of just lives in the same namespace as regular variables.
So you can kind of need to take care that your variables and functions have different
names and so on.
But if I delete my variable, then I get back the built in here.
So we can, I guess, play with it.
OK.
So we've seen that functions behave very much like variables, objects, those kind of things.
And we can also then use functions as arguments to other functions.
And now we're getting close to the whole decorator thing.
Like you saw earlier, we did the cache of a function and returned a new function.
So let's play with this a little bit more before we go to the decorator world.
So let's say that we have a greet function.
And this function takes in, yeah, let's keep it like this, a name and a greeter function.
And then it just does, I'll do something like this.
So I'll call the greeter function.
And you can see here that this greeter function is passed in.
So it's one of the parameters.
And then it just calls that function with the text hi name.
So how can we use this?
Well, I could then say something like hi, PyCon, I guess.
I can greet PyCon and say that I want to use the print function as my greeter function.
And then you can see it prints out stuff.
So what happened here is that we're taking print over there, it's passed in there.
So this greeter of something is actually just calling print.
And since we also gave print a different name, I can also use the screen greeter for it.
So there's really no difference whether you pass a regular object like a text or a number
or a function.
And yeah, to kind of play a little bit more with it and try to see the nuances of what's
happening, let's also define a new function I'll call nerp.
And anyone want to guess what the nerp function should do?
Print backwards, there we go.
Perfect.
So it will just print our text reversed like this.
So if I, for instance, say nerp hi there, I'll get out eretve or something like this.
Now of course we can use our greet function.
And instead of using PyCon like this, I can just use the nerp function.
And we can see that it then prints out hi PyCon backwards.
So we can see that we're kind of passing through the function there.
Okay.
So let's see.
So far we've kind of figured out we can pass these functions around.
It means we can actually also define functions dynamically.
So so far we've just defined functions kind of with our def statement, but it's possible
to define a function that defines another function.
So it's not like a function factory.
So as an example of this, I'll define, I'll call it a prefix factory.
And the way that we define these dynamical functions is that we'll just sort of like
add in a new function in the middle of this.
So in nest functions we often call them inner functions.
We define an inner function.
Inside of the prefix factory here, I'll just define a prefix printer, I guess I call it.
And with this one, I'll then just print out the prefix and the text.
So untangle the syntax there in a little bit.
And then what I also want to do here now is that my prefix factory returns this inner
function.
So if you've never seen these inner functions, it may look kind of weird that, okay, I have
a function, then I have another function within there, and then what I'm actually doing at
the end there, so my factory function returns the inner function.
And first of all, let's just have a look at this.
So prefix printer seems to be a defined function now, but I can't call it.
So it's defined within that other function, and in some sense it's not really defined
here at all, it's kind of just living inside the function.
So we see we can't get to the prefix printer function there.
But I can.
Let's see.
Get to, let's say that we create the prefix here that I'll use for debug.
So if I just call this, we can see the return value of this is now some function that has
a fairly weird name over there, but if we stare at this for a while, we can see that,
okay, it belongs to prefix factory, it's sort of like the locals of there, and then it's
this prefix printer function comes back out.
So that means that I can use my factory to define new functions.
So if I do this, I have now defined a function and I've given it a name so I can reference
it, and then I can say something like debug, well, let's say high pi conference.
And you can see now the result of this is that it prints out our debug prefix in front
and then the text we pass in.
So now let's see, okay, so we lost the text up there.
I'll go slightly back there.
Do you maybe want to make it full-frame?
Yeah, how, no.
I'll soon start using that side.
Yeah, so the prefix factory, if we look a little bit at this, see if we can figure out
what happened here, is that our prefix factory, oh no, so the prefix printer function is only
defined each time you call the prefix factory.
And each time we call the prefix factory, we create a new function from this.
And then one thing that might be weird is that this prefix variable comes from the outer
function, well, the text comes from the inner one.
So what we really do there is that we kind of enclose the value, so we kind of have,
yeah, I guess it's called a closure, where your prefix value is stored so that the debug
function that we create down here knows that for this function, prefix is always debug,
while the text can change for every notification.
So we saw here that we did high PyCon, but I can also say something, well, I can say
something else, and it will kind of print out that.
So the prefix is fixed, but something else changes.
And similarly, I can create a warning function, and then our warning function will again then
have these changing texts, but a fixed prefix that is different from the other prefix.
So in some respect, the debug and warning function, they're the same function in the
sense that they're both this prefix printer function, really, but their behavior is slightly
different.
Okay.
Let's see.
So now I guess we can also just check out, since we have a new function, we can pass
it to greet, and we can see that, okay, our greeter debug also works with this, so we
can pass in kind of any function where we can do these things.
And let's see.
So now we had a factory that could create new functions, but we can also play with this
and create a different factory that kind of takes in functions.
So let me just look up my notes for this.
So we can also create a different type of factory where instead of just having the prefix
factory have this fixed text there, but that can also be a function.
So we can kind of have a function that depends on a function in a sense.
So let's see how that would look.
And I'll define a reverse factory, but here you can see instead of just taking in a text,
I'll take in a function.
And what I want this thing to do is that it will kind of just reverse.
So it's similar to that NURP idea we had, that it can kind of just reverse whatever
you give to it.
So my inner function here I'll call a reverse caller, and this will then just call a function
like this.
So the factory creates a function that can kind of call things with the parameter reversed.
And then we need to do the same thing since we don't really have access to reverse caller,
we need to actually return that back out of the function.
So let's just check out this work then.
So first of all we could do something like reverse factory.
And if I then pass in the print function for instance, then we see that okay I get out
this inner function thingy.
And this is a function, so I could directly call it like this.
And you can see that it has actually, it calls print but with stuff reversed.
But again to kind of keep this more or less traceable what we're doing, I'll give a name
to this.
And then a reverse print function, we can call this and we'll see that it reverses the
arguments that we have.
I could similarly apply this to some of the other functions we have defined.
So for instance I can do a reverse nerp.
And let's see what would the result of this be?
Hi-Picon, yeah.
So we're reversing the reverse so we get back to this one.
Okay so now let's see, I want to, let's see.
Yeah I should, let me actually briefly just copy a few of these.
So this is a reverse color and I also want the prefix factor I guess.
Then we'll see if we can fit stuff on screen.
Okay, because now I want to do a reverse debug which will be reverse factory of debug.
And then we'll call this.
So anyone wants to take a stab at guessing what result of this last call, line 14 will
be?
And it's okay if you can't pronounce it I guess.
So let's.
Right okay, yeah so debug will be forwards and then Hi-Picon should be reversed.
Let's have a look.
I'll do this.
Okay.
So debug Hi-Picon.
That was not what we wanted, we wanted a reverse debug.
And actually did I, yeah apparently I fooled both myself and everyone else there.
There we go.
So yeah, debug for some reason is not reversed while Hi-Picon is reversed.
This is of course when you start sending, applying functions to functions to functions,
keeping track of which happens is which order is not trivial.
So but if we trace this I guess let's see if we can put stuff on the same screen there.
What happens when you call reverse debug Hi-Picon here, let's see.
So this becomes the parameter that goes into the text there.
So Hi-Picon is reversed over here and then that calls the function which came from somewhere,
that's the prefix printer function that then sends the reversed Hi-Picon part in.
But debug is not reversed since that was already a part of that function.
So that's kind of the story there.
Okay.
So now we're kind of gone sort of like off the deep end a little bit with functions and
calling functions and stuff like this.
So now let's wrap this back up together and see what it has to do with decorators.
And in a sense we're kind of already there because this reverse factory is a decorator.
And then what is a decorator?
So let me see, so I have it over here.
A decorator is just a function that accepts a function as a parameter and returns back a function.
So it kind of has the power to transform a function essentially.
So you can see here with the reverse factory it takes a function coming in there and this
reverse caller thing is a function so it returns another function.
And then you have a decorator.
So now we have created our first decorator.
That means that we can use this.
So let's see if that actually works.
So first I'll kind of define a simpler version of greet that I'll just say hi and it just
says hi like this.
So now we kind of, oh yeah, I got the wrong, we need our F string in there.
So when we're calling this, this is kind of what we've seen a bunch of times already.
So we print out hi PyCon.
And now I can essentially apply the decorator similar to what we did with cache in the beginning.
So I could say something like hi equals just this reverse factory of hi.
And then here we kind of see the same effect that we had with debug that it reverses the
parameter that we're sending in here.
So we get hi null slip.
So this we talked about, this was kind of the syntax for decorating, which it really
tells you all you need to know about the decorator if you kind of know this.
But then we have this nice syntactic sugar where I could instead just spell it out like
this.
So let's see, print hi like this.
And now if I do hi PyCon, we have the same result.
Just to show you that this actually is, since I get the exact same result, right?
So let me also just do a hello instead just to show that it does the work.
And we need a colon.
So this function should say hello.
Something like this.
If I say hello PyCon, we can see that it still applies to reverse factory there.
So in a sense, you know everything that I'll teach you about decorators now.
That's kind of, that this is kind of how you apply decorators, but the effect of it is
really just that it's doing this.
So whenever you're kind of wondering what's the effect of doing in the decorator, you
can try to unravel it into this.
And then that kind of is easier to figure out what's happening.
Well, this is kind of the nicer syntax for it in a sense.
So let's get to the place where you also get to do some work.
And I'll, let me think.
Yeah, I'll first just say two words about decorators and then we'll show some exercises.
Yes.
Right.
Yeah, so the question is just about essentially here it seems like we're doing it as part
of the definition, while if we do it like this, we're doing after the function is defined.
And yeah, that's completely true.
The two things are kind of, they're equivalent except for the fact that you kind of have
this intermediate step where you have the function, this temporary function so to speak
defined.
So that's not defined in this case.
So we'll play a little bit more afterwards with seeing how sort of like this at reverse
factory really happens at defining defined time, compile time more or less, versus at
runtime which it more or less seems like we're doing it 65.
But let's see decorators were introduced in Python 2.4 and before then there were actually
a few decorators introduced.
You may have seen if you've done some object-oriented programming, there is a static method and
class method decorators.
So those were actually defined as decorator functions in Python before decorator syntax
existed.
So when you used these statements in say Python 2.3, then you would have to kind of do what
we did at the end there.
And that was kind of observed as kind of being some frustration, some friction with kind
of using this is that you first define your function or your method and then afterwards
you need this weird step of adding that this is a static method.
And one thing I guess we can at least to some extent see out of this as well is that if
we're doing, yeah, let me type it out completely.
So if we're doing the hello there and there and then we're doing this thing afterwards,
then to define a function like this, I have to repeat the name three times, which feels
very wasteful in a sense as well.
So this was really the motivation.
We need a nicer way of doing this.
So as you can see, even without the decorator syntax, Python already had support for functions
as first-class objects and things like this.
So you could kind of, we could kind of always do this.
But then adding the special syntax was kind of what happened then in 2.4 and when kind
of the, I guess decorators were more popularized in a sense.
This happened with the PEP 3.18.
So I don't know if all of you know the PEP process, the Python enhancement proposals,
but this is sort of like a formalized way of introducing new features to the language.
And it typically happens with a lot of discussion online.
And it's somewhat fun to be reading these PEPs and look at what were discussions about
how to do the syntax.
And it seemed like everybody was in agreement there about, yeah, we definitely need a nicer
syntax for this.
And then of course, everyone in total disagreement about what kind of syntax should we use.
So some of the suggestions for this was that, or I guess the argument against the syntax
they ended up with is that this is the first and possibly still the only syntax where
one of these lines directly applies to the line below it instead of kind of, I guess
we have things like, okay, we start a block and stuff like this.
But here we just have a weird line of code that kind of floats by itself and then it
has a very significant effect on the line below it.
So there were some attempts at, okay, let's try to put this decorator syntax in the middle
there.
So I think one suggestion was let's write something like reverse factory hello.
But the syntax would be something like this, which potentially could have worked as well,
right?
It's kind of we just need to make some choice.
This will of course not work now.
So I guess, yeah, it starts yelling at me at some point.
And I think there were also some discussions, should we use the at symbol, which were not
used in Python before, or should we reuse some of the others and so on.
But at least in the end we found a syntax and then I guess at least we've gotten used
to it.
Since the decorators were introduced in Python 2.4, there was very little change to it.
It's kind of just been a syntax that works.
One slightly weird thing maybe when they defined the decorator syntax was that they somewhat
artificially limited what you could do.
So what we've seen so far is that here we're just spelling out this function.
In theory this could have been say a class method or something like this as well.
That was kind of explicitly disallowed in the beginning.
So in Python 3.9 I think they just lifted all of these weird limitations and said that
anything that's callable more or less you could put in there.
So now I guess it's theoretically possible at least to use a lambda or something there
as well.
In general this is still the way that you typically will use them.
So now you've seen a little bit of what decorators are.
We'll definitely return to this much more.
But I think we can try to give you a small exercise.
Let's see if we can make this work.
And let me see if I'm able to do a couple of things at once.
So the exercise, and I'll kind of give you some time for this, is that you'll write your
own decorator and it will not do anything very spectacular, but it will print out before
calling the function and it will print out after calling it.
So you should name it before and after and to test if it works you can kind of just implement
this test and see if you get this result.
I have also, and let's see if I'm able to show this.
See what happens here.
And this, yeah, feel free to do this if you like it and feel free to ignore it if you
don't.
Let's see.
Why is this not working?
I have created, okay, let's see.
There we go.
So this is probably the simplest Google form ever.
But if you want to kind of share your code, feel free to just drop it into here.
And fortunately links to these Google forms are not always trivial.
So you'll get a little bit more extra effort as well that you need to figure out how to
type in those letters.
Sorry.
But yeah, the important thing, have fun with the decorator.
Just a quick note if you don't want to type in the link stuff there, you can also find
my GitHub.
It's GA Gjelle.
And then just maneuver to decorator's tutorial 2023 and the link is there as well.
Cool.
I'm seeing quite a few responses already.
I guess at least a good portion of you have gotten this to work.
So I guess we'll pick it up from here.
If you're still not finished, just feel free to play with it and then we'll discuss the
answer here as well.
So let's see what would one of these decorators look like.
And I see most of you have kind of come up with the same answers.
Let's see.
I'll get this thing back on the screen here.
So exercise one.
So what we need to do was to create this before and after decorator.
Before and after.
What we talked about is that a decorator is a function that takes a function in and returns
some other function or some function, I guess.
Doesn't need to be another one.
So I'll just call that funk here.
And then what we've kind of seen a little bit in our example so far is that this inner
function, it's not really exposed, I guess, to the end user in the sense that they don't
need to know the name of what to call it, but it kind of leaks through a little bit
here and there.
So sometimes it's okay to have some kind of nice name for it.
We'll soon see how that we can avoid leaking the name of these things as well.
So what I tend to do is just end up calling this thing a wrapper, but you can kind of
give it some name that makes sense.
But yeah, I'll do a wrapper here.
And then in our example, let's see, or our exercise, we want this before and after to
then be able to print before and then run on this high PyCon thing and then print afterwards.
In the example, we used this high function that we've been seeing.
So we kind of come down to a question, what should the argument to wrapper be?
And if we're really designing it just for the high, what will end up coming in here
is this name parameter.
I'll pretend to be slightly more generic by writing text there, but that's just a name,
so it's really not more generic.
And we'll discuss some of the issues with this soon and then see how we can make this
even better.
But let's stick with this one for now.
And what kind of will happen is that this wrapper function is the one that kind of replaces
the high function, right?
So this is where we need to do the print before and print after.
So the first thing we'll do inside of this wrapper is that I'll just print out before
like this.
The last thing I'll do is that I'll print out after.
The thing I'll do in the middle is to actually call the function.
So we can call this and then I'd name this text in this example.
And then I need to have my decorator, so that's the before and after thing, then return this
wrapper function.
So if we kind of end up with some code like this.
Part of the reason I kind of wanted to show this still fairly basic and completely useless
example is that it kind of shows you the typical template for your decorators.
Typically you want to use a decorator to either do something before you call a function or
after, so you kind of end up with something that in principle looks like this.
So you kind of do your stuff before you call your function, you do something afterwards.
Yeah, I see most of you kind of come up with something that looks like this.
Many of you have found something that's even better, so we'll continue to improve on this
soon.
But let's check that this is actually something that works.
So I'll copy this code.
Let's see.
There we are.
So if I have this, and then our test was that we wanted to apply this to a hi function.
Not the hello function.
So now if I do hi PyCon, we can see that it does what we wanted it to do.
You get the before, you get hi PyCon, you get after.
Yeah.
Okay.
Yes.
Perfect.
I like that.
So Glenn here tells me that he added a default value to name.
So let's see what happened then.
So if we do before and after, and then we have a default value here.
So I'll have this one greet myself by default.
And now I guess our hi PyCon still works.
But if I just do this, then we can see we get something wrong happened.
So what is that wrong thing that happened?
So we can see if we kind of stare at this error message here, it says that before and
after wrapper is missing one required positional argument.
So our wrapper, let's see.
So this wrapper function requires one parameter.
And when we send in, when we call hi with no parameters, we're really calling wrapper
with no parameters.
Because wrapper has replaced our hi function.
So that's kind of the decoration.
So the error message comes because this one doesn't have a default value.
But it also kind of points to the fact that our decorator is not very flexible.
And to kind of show you a different example of this, I mentioned earlier, I guess, that
decorators are these things which you can apply to any function and then you can change
the behavior of it.
So for instance, we had, I mentioned, I guess, this JIT compiler thing that can compile any
function, maybe we can time any function and so on.
But here in our decorator, we hard coded that this has one parameter that we named
text.
And that kind of causes some issues for us.
So just to show you a different example of this, let's do this fairly silly example.
Because we have a plus operator in Python, so we really don't need to do this.
But again, it kind of just shows us that we can say add two numbers like this.
But now if I decorate this with my before and after, I'll have the exact same issues
that we had earlier.
So let's see if we do before and after.
And then I'll do the same thing here.
And now I call this.
Again, I get this error message thrown at me.
And again, it's kind of because this wrapper takes only one argument.
In this case, I gave it two.
So what can we do with our decorator to make this one work better?
So what it comes down to is that we really want to have this thing work independently
of how many parameters are passed into it.
To do that, we'll use, I guess, the star and star star operators, which are often just
called args and quarks, which are just weird noises we're making.
But if you...
Yeah, so let's have a look at what those do first, and then we'll figure out how to use
them in here.
So we can define a function and then just use this for our parameters.
And the important part here is actually the stars.
The names are not important, but they kind of...
Unless we have better names, then we typically end up with calling them args and kw-args.
So the args there are just the arguments that you're passing in without the name, and then
kw, that's a keyword argument.
And just to show these things, I can...
Let's see.
I'll add a few f-strings, which also gives me the opportunity to show off...
I don't know if everyone's familiar with this f-string syntax, but it's kind of neat.
So we'll play with that.
So these two lines of f-strings, when I throw in an equal sign there, it will print both
parameter name and its value.
It works on Python 3.8 and later.
But if I now call this function and let's say...
Stick with my high PyCon thing.
You can see here that in this case, args here is a tuple with one element that is my first
argument there.
And if I would give this a name, so maybe I'll say greeting there, then you can see
that what comes in here is instead passed in in this kw-args.
And the kw-args is a dictionary where your parameter name or keyword is the key in the
dictionary and then the other thing is the value.
And then we can have a mix of these.
So I could, for instance, have 3.14 there.
And maybe I can have things like this.
Just for fun, let's...
I guess I can do this.
And e equals 2.7128.
So as we're kind of passing in more and more of these arguments, you can see they're collected
either in args or kw-args, depending on whether you use the keyword arguments like I did for
the last two ones or just pass them in as values, as positional arguments.
So this is typically how you then can create functions that take either a variable number
arguments or things like this.
And that's really what we need for our decorators.
To show you just quickly, I guess a more practical example of this, I'll also do a new version
of my adder function.
So I want my adder function to be able to add up any number of numbers.
And in this case, we could potentially just say that I want everything in as a list.
But if I do this thing here, now I'm saying that I want at least one number and then from
zero to infinitely, I guess, in some version of infinite, numbers, which will then come
in as this args thing.
And here also you can see that it's the star that is the syntax, not the name args.
But whatever I put there comes in as this similar tuple.
And what I can do now is to say that, okay, if I'm not getting any numbers, so that means
I'm only getting one number, really, then this is empty.
Then the sum of the number is just a number.
So I can just return number.
And else, let's see, I can return number plus the sum of these numbers.
Something like this.
So this now, it's not really anything about decorators, just to show off the star syntax.
But here you can see that I can now add one number.
That's just a number itself.
I can add two numbers.
I can add, I don't know, three numbers and so on and so on.
So this is how you can kind of create these more flexible function arguments.
So let's see, how can we use this now in our decorator?
Any questions about this, by the way?
No?
Okay.
Then I'll jump back to our before and after function.
And what we saw was that we got issues with wrapper being insistent on only taking in
one argument.
So this one we can now replace with our args and quarks.
So the way we'll do this is that we'll just throw in args and quarks like this.
And then when we're calling the function, we also need to do the same, pass them back
out again, essentially.
So with this definition now, before and after, we should be able to make the previous examples
work.
So let's try it.
Let's see.
So then we had our before and after with the default value for high.
And let's see this one.
Something like this.
So we've already seen that it will work if we kind of just use PyCon.
But now we should also be able to get it to work with the default value.
So what happens here, and let's see if we can pass this through, is that high, when
I'm calling high there, I'm really calling wrapper.
So wrapper up there, if I call high like this, the args will be empty, the quarks will be
empty, and it means that it prints out before, and then it calls this function without any
arguments.
So that means that at that point, the default value triggers.
And then it's able to print out, get on and on there.
And now we can also do the before and after on this adder function.
Before and.
Yeah.
Right.
Okay.
Yeah.
Good point.
So the question was essentially what if I have more arguments to high, right?
So high, if we throw in something like this.
Yeah.
This will not work, and that's kind of the same as because, let's see, our high function
can't take two arguments.
So the decorator can't magically make a function suddenly do other things like that.
What's actually possible, I don't know if we'll get to that, is that you could kind
of have your decorator eat up some arguments.
So typically what you want to do is essentially follow this template where you just take in
the arguments and pass them back out again.
But it is definitely possible to say that here I'll eat up an argument and not pass
it on.
So for instance, I could say that I'm eating up the name argument and not passing it into
this function.
So it's possible to do weird stuff like that, but it's seldom useful at least.
And let's see.
Yeah.
I guess we can also check now that our adder function, let's see the previous adder, the
simple adder.
So number one, this one.
So now we have two arguments, but now this should actually work.
Yes.
You can see it prints out before and after.
It didn't print out the answer, and it didn't return an answer.
So that's actually another thing that we haven't really fixed yet, because let's have a look
at what happens to the return value.
Let's see.
There's a wrapper.
Yeah.
So what we've done so far with the high function is that we printed out stuff.
So we've seen the print stuff.
What you typically do when you're passing stuff around is to return values.
And if we look at this wrapper function, it doesn't return anything, which means that
implicitly it returns none.
So we're actually killing off whatever return value we got from this one.
So that means that we're still not done in that sense.
We have something that kind of destroys our functions.
So let's see if we can add that as one more improvement.
So what we actually need to do is to also collect up the return value of this.
Not value, but value.
So if I store the value there, and then I can return it here.
So since I need to do something after my function call, I need to save the return value, and
then I'll explicitly return it down there.
So let's see how this behaves.
So I'll go back to this one.
And then let's try to define our adder one more time.
So now we can see that I get the output at the end there.
So we preserved the value.
I guess the return value from a function always comes at the end, even if we've kind of decorated
like this, at least as long as we're keeping stuff synchronous.
So we can see here that before, after, the actual adding calculation happens between
before and after, and then it kind of returns the value after it's kind of done cleaning
up or whatever the after operation is.
So what we have on the top there now, that is really, well, that would be one more improvement,
but it's essentially the template that you'll kind of end up using for most of your, at
least basic decorators.
So if you can kind of just define, okay, there's something I should do before calling the function,
something I should do afterwards, and then just put it in where we have the print statements
right now.
Let's see.
Yeah, we have 15 minutes until the break, so I guess that's a good point to do another
exercise.
So let's see what we have.
So in this one, we're going to, you can kind of reuse the template that we've created now,
but see if you can write the decorator that runs this decorated function twice.
So if we, for instance, had this high function, it should then say high PyCon, high PyCon.
And then now we kind of got to know that we need to care about these return values, and
when you run a function twice, it's not clear what should be the return value of this, so
somewhat arbitrarily, I'll say that you should return a two-tuple with both return values.
So if we implement a random roll dice function, then rolling this with the do twice, you should
get back two numbers.
And again, feel free to share the code in the same Google form that you played with
earlier, then I can kind of see what comes in.
Cool, yeah, so I'm starting to see some responses again, so I guess we can start looking a little
bit at this.
And yeah, we're still at these decorators that are kind of silly.
I don't know if there's a very good use of this do twice thing, but let's see if we can
figure out how to implement it at least.
And in this case, we'll kind of have a look at the template that we kind of came up with
for before and after, but we can see that we can kind of cut away several things for
it.
So I'll start with the typical my do twice and it takes in a function, and then I know
I'll have a wrapper thing inside of here.
And as we discussed, these wrappers will typically always have the args and quarks just to be
flexible enough to be applied to anything.
And now our task was that we wanted to call func twice and return the result as a tuple.
So we could kind of be fairly clever with this and just do, let's see, I'll return args
and quarks, and then I'll add in a comma and call it one more time.
And then I just need to remember to return this wrapper function.
So this is kind of the maybe too clever version of this.
So here I'm calling func and then I'm calling it one more time and I'm just returning the
results as a tuple.
So let me see, I can start by just proving that it works and then we can see, we can
write it more readable afterwards.
But let's see, I want to import random since our test was this random function.
This is my do twice wrapper.
And then let's see, the task was to apply this to, let's see, roll dice.
So roll dice is a very simple function, doesn't take in any arguments and it just returns
a random number.
Like this.
So now if I roll dice and actually call it, we can see that I get at least what looks
like random numbers like this.
And you can see that even though here I'm returning one number, I'm getting two back
there.
So the do twice thing does something.
Let's see, let's just spell out kind of what we're doing here.
I could also then say that I'll store these as temporary variables.
So I could call them first and second, for instance.
Like this and then return.
First and second.
This might be a more readable way of implementing things.
Just to show that that still does the job.
You can see that we still get our two results back.
Any questions about this?
Was it okay to implement?
You can kind of see the things that works.
Yeah.
Yeah, what's the limit in decorating decorators?
Was that kind of the question?
Now, there can be turtles all the way down essentially.
So you can decorate a decorator if you want.
Yeah, let's actually do that right now.
We can even have stack, sorry, we can stack decorators on top of each other.
So in this example here, I could for instance do a before and after like this.
And now if I do my roll dice, you can see that it's calling before and after for each
of these functions.
And the way this works is that you just have nested function calls.
So what we have up there in the sort of like the middle of the screen now would be more
or less equivalent to doing before and after and then if we just define roll dice as a
regular function and then we do apply before and after to roll dice and then we apply do
twice to that again.
So in this case you see that the before and after decorator is also then executed twice.
If we kind of do the same as there but we flip the order, then we'll see a slightly
different result.
So I can do before and after, do twice, and then this.
And now if we call it, you can see that the dice rolling is done twice but the before
and after is now only done once because the do twice is only applied to this one.
But yeah, it's possible to kind of stack decorators like this in some sense as much as you would
want.
It does depend then that these are actual decorators that return functions since we're
kind of transforming functions all the way.
Okay, any other questions?
All right, so the question is whether should decorators be very generic so they can be
applied to anything or kind of be specially designed to things.
And in general you want to, I guess, make them as generic as possible but not more generic
than that.
So for instance, say I think in the Flask framework there is sort of like this login
decorator that you can use to check is the user logged in.
And that's of course designed to be put on some of these Flask routes so it's kind of
designed to work inside of this framework and it won't really work if we just throw
it on some magic function here.
So yeah, it's kind of like function in that sense that, yeah, you want to be fairly generic
with them but not too generic as well.
They need to do their task.
Oh yeah, if you have several do-twices.
Yeah, so I guess the idea was what happens if you do twice several times.
And let's just check this.
So it's something like this, right?
And now if I roll my dice you can see that I get two pairs essentially now.
And then if I keep doing this I'll get, I guess, next iteration I'll get two of these
pairs of pairs and it kind of just explode out.
So I'll do twice, three times will give me eight numbers and so on.
Can you use a decorator from a different class?
Yes, if you can kind of name it then you should be able to call it essentially.
Right, so let's see.
We'll have some example later where we use a class as a decorator but yeah, it's kind
of just a namespacing thing so as long as you're able to reference something that works
as a decorator you can use it.
Good, good.
Then I'll guess it's time for a coffee break.
So we'll continue in half an hour.
And if anyone has any questions I'll be here.
Okay, yeah.
Right, so any good rules of thumb for when you want to use decorators and perhaps when
you want.
So one typical use case at least that I find is that you have the same functionality that
you want to implement all over your code base kind of thing.
So I guess one fairly basic example of this would be that you have several pieces of code
where you want to say time your function or something like this.
So I want to figure out how long is the run time of this part of the code, how long is
this part, how long is this part.
And then one way to do it would be that you just add in this, what do you use, something
time dot time minus previous kind of thing all over your code.
And when you kind of start to recognize that okay, I have the same pattern that I kind
of have spread out in many places, then you can start thinking is this something that
I can do with the decorator instead and just create your time decorator and add timer here
and there.
I guess similarly with this login functionality we talked about previous with the flask and
so on or what they did with this compiler thing that it kind of...
So when you start to see that I'm doing the same thing but in very different areas of
my code, then maybe that behavior thing is something I can pull out and use the decorator
for.
So that's kind of the...
It's still somewhat abstract, but one way to recognize it.
Other questions?
No.
So the plan now for the second half is essentially to keep doing what we have been doing, exploring
the decorators and kind of grow now from...
We kind of figured out how to write our basic decorators, so now how can we do different
types of decorators.
And the first thing we'll look at is looking at decorators that only do stuff at defined
time.
So we'll look at the decorator in a function.
That may sometimes be useful and we'll kind of see how that changes the pattern.
And then we'll dive into how can you have decorators that have parameters on them.
So we'll see some examples of how to add that to things.
And then it may sometimes be helpful to have a decorator that can somehow keep state.
So hopefully we'll have a chance to look at those as well.
So that's kind of more or less the plan going forward.
But yeah, we'll keep doing this sort of like with the same fashion.
So you get some exercises, then we'll kind of talk about things afterwards.
Okay.
So I think we kind of left it after we did this do twice decorator.
And what I kind of want to go back a little bit at is just make sure that we understand
when is kind of the decorator...
When is it kind of running?
When does stuff happen when you decorate?
And we talked about this a little bit in sort of like looking at the syntax, our add syntax
versus this high equals something of high kind of syntax.
And let's see.
If we go back to...
I guess I have over here.
So I'll just use our old and trusted before and after decorator.
And if I add in a line, very much on the top, so before the wrapper there.
And I'll just say here something like decorating.
And then double underscore name.
So this attribute...
So I don't know if you've seen this double underscore attribute.
There's something called stunder names or special names.
So these are typically Python's.
They research Python, so that's why they have the underscores to kind of mark them.
And they can often give you a lot of information about say the whole data model of Python.
So for instance, when you define a function, it has at least some idea what its name is
that you can pull out of this stunder name attribute.
So this print statement is now something that I want to call not inside of the wrapper,
but outside.
So I'll just see what happens then.
So I'll take this, copy this, and let's see.
So now I have the before and after.
And let's just use this on our good old high thing.
I guess we can do a simple high.
Something like this.
And yeah, let me just call this so we see everything immediately.
That was the simple high without the string.
Okay.
We'll leave that.
So what we can notice here, though, is that the decorating high came already when I defined
high.
And this line is what's printed on the top there.
So that's the print that's already at the top there.
So what we can kind of read out of this is that before and after, if you think of this
as a function, that function is executed when we define this.
And what happens then is that everything that's not inside the inner function there is executed.
So the print statement comes here immediately.
And then when we're actually running the decorated function, what we're really doing is executing
this inner function.
And since that print statement is not part of the inner function, we don't see anything
about decorating here.
Here we just see the before and after that kind of is in between there.
So that's kind of just something to, I guess, keep track of, keep in mind.
And it means that if we have a decorator where we only want to do something at defined time,
so we actually don't want to change the function, we just want to do something when a function
is defined, then we don't actually need that inner stuff.
So for a very basic example of this, I can pull out, yeah, let's call it define or something.
I can pull out this functionality that we just had now with the print statement.
So I'll say that this define thing just prints out, oops, what did you do now?
The same print statement that we had earlier.
And then I'll just return the original function.
So what this does then is that I can use define there, and then I'll define the high, and
then that should print.
Let's see if we get this correct.
Like this.
So what I've done here is that I'm able to do something, ideally more interesting than
just printing, but I can do something whenever a function is defined, but I'm now not changing
that function at all, right?
So here I'm returning the exact same object.
So if I do high PyCon here, we can see that it runs just like this.
And if I look at this function, I can see here that this is the high name function that
I just defined.
For this latter thing, let's have a look at if I go back to the before and after, and
let me decorate the hello function instead just so that we keep both of them.
So this was the version of before and after where we added the print, so we can see here
that that print is run there.
But then if I now look at what is this function object, we can see here that high is exactly
the high function, but hello has become this before and after wrapper function, because
that's what we kind of sent back there.
Yeah?
So primarily we can say that it's kind of the same function as the text, or the round
of the text, but it seems like you could also use it to implement functionality, call text
functions, logging, something like that, just every time a function is dead, you could have
it.
Yes, exactly.
Yeah, so the comment is that so far we've kind of just been doing the stomach examples
for printing out stuff, but the real use case for this would be that you can implement some
functionality whenever something is called.
Maybe you want to do some logging, which is a great example.
You can do some call stack manipulation, but we'll come back to some of these.
You can do some validation, which hopefully we'll have time for an example at the end
and so on.
So yeah, you can do all kinds of stuff with this.
One thing that we can see here is that here there's clear proof that we have done something,
and it is actually a completely different function object than this thing.
And what's kind of happened here is that we have this kind of closure thing where we're
saving a reference to the original function, but what we get back in hello here is actually
this wrapper function.
But then that wrapper function calls this thing here that we don't have direct access
to anymore actually.
Okay.
And what we're actually seeing kind of leak through here is that this decoration kills
a little bit the names that we have for things.
And let me just point out that here we see that the function kind of knows its own name,
and we can see this if I do, I can do the thunder name that we talked about, or that's
printed in the REPL when I do this.
And we can do the same with say print.
You can see this knows it's the function print.
I can do the name for this.
It knows its name is print.
But now if you remember I had scrivut, which was just equal to print.
And if I do scrivut like this, you can see it still knows it's print.
It's not become scrivut somehow.
And if I ask it here for its name, that's still print.
So the name of a function as it kind of knows itself may be different from the name that
we're using to refer to it.
So those are kind of two separate things.
Let's see.
Yeah.
So we saw here that when I had this hello thing there, it messed with the name, which
may be an issue.
If you're kind of using this name for anything, then this will be terrible.
For instance, if you're logging that I'm not calling this function and then suddenly you
get this usually not useful information that it's this inner thing.
So there is actually a decorator that already exists in Python that can help us kind of
keep track of metadata or make sure the metadata here are more well behaved.
So let's go back one more time to before and after.
And I'll remove this decorating thing again.
That was kind of just to show you.
But then I can apply a decorator now to the wrapper function, to the inner function.
And let's first of all import functools.
So this is one of the standard libraries.
And inside of functools there is something called reps.
And if you just look at the help text for this, you can see that this is what they call
the decorator factory.
Think of it almost like a decorator.
We'll soon come back to exactly what it is.
But this one can then essentially, this is fairly technical, but it's okay.
This is too technical for now.
What it does is that it changes name and so on so that the decorated function looks like
the original function.
So let's have a look at it.
If I do functools.reps up there and then I actually need to pass in the original function
as functor.
And I see that VS Code is yelling at me because I haven't imported functools.
Okay.
So now let's have a look at what happens if I use this one.
So I once again redefined my before and after decorator.
And now we can use this again on the, well, let's use it on high.
Before and after, high.
Print.
Hi.
Because now remember hello is kind of still the old one.
So it has this weird name.
But now hi, even though it has been decorated right here, it looks like it's just a plain
function.
It's logical name, so to speak.
So that's, yeah, on the very top there you see this functools.reps.
Its task is essentially just to keep the metadata or pass on really, copy the metadata from
the func that's passed in to the inner function.
So that it's usually at least a good idea whenever you have a decorated wrapper like
this to just throw the functools.reps on top of it.
That kind of makes things play nicely together.
Yeah, I think essentially the only thing is if you don't have an inner function, so you
don't change the func.
But yeah, I think, yeah, always do it.
And yeah, if there's an exception, you'll probably figure it out.
Okay.
So I think that brings us to a new exercise.
And this one might seem like yet another of these dummy examples.
But this one is one, it's probably the decorator I've used the most myself.
And it's actually a fairly powerful mechanism for doing sort of like plug-ins where you
can kind of inject code and things like this.
So what we want here is to write the decorator that stores references to decorated functions.
So we don't want to change the decorated function at all.
So it's similar to what we did with define.
But we want to just keep references to them.
So in this case, our test is that we'll just, okay, let's create a global dictionary.
And then whenever I define a function that is sort of like has this register, the decorator
on top, it adds a reference to the function in this function's dictionary.
So yeah.
Have fun with this one.
And then we'll talk about it more in five, ten minutes.
Okay.
So we're starting to have at least some implementations.
Oster, did this work out fine for you?
I guess we'll discuss a little bit now, so we'll see.
So the idea here was that we will, let's see, I get the question again.
So I want to define this register decorator that doesn't really touch the function at all.
It just makes note that this function exists, essentially.
So that means that we only need to do something at define time, so we don't need to change the function.
So we don't actually need to use that wrapper that we have been using so far.
So this will turn out fairly similar to this define decorator we did.
So let's see.
I can then do something define register.
And then what I wanted to do now was to just make a note in this functions thing.
And here we can use the thunder thing.
So I'm just saying that, okay, I'll use the name as the key, and then I'll pass in a reference to the function.
So make sure we're not calling the function, right, we're just storing reference to it.
And then I should here also return the function itself.
So this is kind of the decorator that we're looking for.
I should also, yeah, we'll run it afterwards without returning func just so you can see what happens then.
And let's see, before I can actually use this, I also need to define functions.
So I'll just let that start as a global dictionary here.
And let's see what's the dice rolling example again we did.
So if we do register, dice roll, and then we return random random int like this.
So what has happened now is since this is define time, right, so we're not need to call anything.
So when we did register there, then this functions thing should have been populated.
So let's have a look.
You can see now it's no longer empty, but it has a reference now to the dice roll function.
And since this is a function reference, we can start playing with it.
So I can't pick it out here.
So there's my function reference.
And then I can call it.
And I can see that I get some random dice rolls here.
So this is really, let's see, where are we?
If we're just doing something at define time, then this is enough.
We don't need to wrap anything because we're not changing the function.
So it just stays the same.
So if I look at the dice roll function, we can see that it has its nice name here.
Let's see.
So yeah, first, if I wouldn't, let's see.
So if I do def register and I do this, but I don't return anything, what do you think
will happen then?
Anyone want to guess?
The function will register, but I can't, what did you say?
But I can't use it, essentially.
So let's try that.
So okay.
I'll have, I'll redefine functions as the empty dictionary.
Just to see it's empty.
And then I use this bad register with my dice roll.
Like this.
So you can see now functions has the dice roll implemented there.
So that's beautiful.
And we can even call it.
So we have the reference there.
But now if I look at dice roll itself, you can see, well, nothing seems to be there.
And if I check slightly more closely, we can see that it has been replaced by none since
we're not returning anything.
So when we do a decorator like this, it is really replacing the function we're decorating
with whatever is the return value of our decorated function thing.
So since we didn't return anything, Python implicitly returns none, so we get none back
there.
So this I guess might be a feature because it means I can't call it like this.
It kind of forces me to use the functions thing there.
So maybe that's a feature.
Maybe it's a bug.
Then just lastly, I claim that this is a very helpful decorator.
It may not seem like it immediately, and I don't want to kind of dive too far away from
the decorator stuff.
But what we can kind of do with this is that we can then dynamically call functions without
having to kind of specify it beforehand.
So for sort of like a still a fairly silly example.
But I could then do something like this.
Which function do you want to call?
And then here I can say dice roll, and then essentially we do something like functions
name call.
So here I kind of somewhat interactively define which function I want to call, and then if
you have several defined, you can kind of use this.
For maybe a better example of this, say that you have different file formats that you want
to read, and then you can kind of define a handler for say CSV format, another one for
JSON, and if you just register each of them and then you can kind of call them indirectly
using something like this, then it makes it very easy to then later just patch on another
file format for you.
Then you can anywhere else you can kind of register a handler for YAML or something like
this.
So it kind of allows for, yeah, very flexible ways of structuring your programs.
Okay.
That's not what we wanted.
Let's see.
Then we talked about those.
Yeah.
So one thing I guess I'll also now just point out.
Let's see.
The high function, I should have pointed this out earlier.
I just want to show it to you, and then we'll look at this more closely later.
But the high function was one of those where we used this wrapper.
It's actually possible to access Thunder wrapped like this.
This is one of these before and after.
So if I do high PyCon, we do the before, high PyCon after.
This wrapped thing, you can see it seems to also be the same function, but it's actually
then the inner function.
So that's another bonus with using this wrapper is that you can actually access the original
function quite easily as well.
So if we have used Functool wraps, then using diving in through wrapped, then you can get
access to the original undecorated function.
Okay.
I think we can then move on to the next exercise.
Are there other questions, comments?
Yeah.
Yeah, what would be a use case for accessing the wrapped thing?
Well, usually you have, I guess, wrapped things for a reason.
You kind of decorated them because you want to use it.
So typically it's not something that you'll use.
But it could be a way, say, that you can sneak through the, well, in a log in example, if
you just want to test something.
So don't do it in production, I guess.
You could then sneak through the log in stuff by going beneath it, or if you don't want
to time something that has the timer on it.
Yeah.
In general, it's more know it exists kind of thing.
Okay.
So I guess in keeping with somewhat silly test functions, I've here changed the rollDice
function so that it creates an error if you roll less than five.
And then what we want to try to do is to create a decorator that just retries a function
call if the function call fails.
So in this case, when we run this thing, we should get either five or six.
We should not get the error message.
And then, yeah, this is a silly example.
Look at slightly better examples once we have the retry decorator.
So, yeah, have some fun with this one.
Okay.
I guess we can start to have a look at this.
So this one will again be sort of like a regular decorator where we're kind of needing to do
something.
But now I guess, well, we can think of this as doing something more or less after calling
the function where we're catching an exception and then potentially running it again.
So let's see.
One way to solve this would be that I can, let's see if I move this up a little bit.
So I'll define the retry thing.
And then as we kind of learn, we can add a wrapster.
And then we can define a wrapper.
So I'm kind of just throwing in the template more or less we have by now.
And then here we'll do something and then we'll return a wrapper.
So this is kind of just the template part.
And then what did we say we want to do here?
Essentially I want to call the function repeatedly until it doesn't return an exception essentially.
So in this case I guess I can just throw myself into a while true loop.
So I'll just run forever.
And then I'll try to call the function.
Something like this.
And here I just return immediately the value.
So I don't need to do anything else with it.
So the only problem is if this thing now raises an exception when it's called.
But that's something we can catch with an accept clause.
So I'll just accept the exception.
And then if we get an exception I just really want to keep moving.
So for now I'll just do a pass statement there I guess.
So I think this is probably the most basic thing we can do with the retry.
And then we'll add in a little bit more functionality to this after a while.
But let's see if it works.
So I'll put this into our REPL.
And then our test was to see if we could keep rolling and only get five and six in this.
I guess I called it only roll highs.
But it's really just our dice roll thing in hiding.
So we'll have some number that's a random.
And then I said if number is less than five then we'll raise a value error.
Value error.
Let's see.
Were we more offensive with this?
No.
And then I'll just return this number.
So now if I run this only roll highs.
We can see that okay I got six, I got six, five, six, five, six.
So I'm not getting the one, two, three, fours that should be there.
So now everything kind of happens so quickly that it's kind of hard to really see what's going on here.
So let's change this a little bit, just add a little bit of visibility into it.
So when I get the exception here I'll also print out that something bad happened.
So retrying.
I guess we can be talkative and say funk name.
Because of E or something like this.
So now if I run this one.
And then I'll just do, no this is easier.
So now I redefine my only roll highs.
And then if I run this you can see now that we see some traces of it actually re-rolling the lower things.
Now of course this is a completely silly example because I could just have my random number generator give me five and six directly.
So just to show you an example where something like this might be useful.
And I think just to kind of be a little bit nice to the system I'll also add in a small delay.
So we can do something like time sleep say for a tenth of a second or something.
So if we use this.
And then let's see.
I'll do the only roll highs.
So now you can see it just takes a little bit of time in there.
So now this is something that we could for instance use to poll for resources maybe that we know are coming.
But they may not still be there or things like this.
So to do a small example of that.
Yes please.
I think the second one is running wrapper again.
Okay so the example Martin is showing here is that he essentially calls things recursively I guess.
So instead of doing the while true loop.
So instead of using a while true loop here it just calls the wrapper itself in the except block.
And that also works except that I guess Python has this recursion limit.
So I guess it will fail after 3000 attempts or something like this.
But yeah in general it's possible I guess in Python again function calls takes a little bit longer.
So doing a while loop is probably better but it definitely works.
Okay then the example I want to move into was to try to use this for some kind of system polling.
Just to see a slightly nicer use of this retry thing.
So let me see.
I'll use an example where I'm just trying to get the file from a disk.
So I'll do a path lib operation.
Let me see then I can retry.
Something like.
Well let's say.
Well let's call it process file.
It sounds like we're doing something interesting.
So we're getting a path.
And then let's just print out the content of this file.
So I'll do something like path read text.
And now I could then do something like process file.
And then I'll throw in a path there.
So path lib path.
And I'll give it the PyCon text file.
Now this file doesn't exist right.
So it just tells me here that I'm trying to read this file but I can't find it.
What I can do now.
Let's see if we're able to do this.
I'll do this in the black so we kind of see the background there.
And I think.
I think this is the retry I made.
So let's see if we.
Yeah.
So I'll add some text just into a file here.
Hi everyone.
PyCon.
Okay.
So this is just on Linux.
I'm just creating a text file that I just for now called text.
And it has this content.
So now if I change the name of this file into PyCon.text.
Then the process that's kind of running in the white screen should be able to pick that up when it becomes available.
So let's see.
So rename text into PyCon.text.
And hopefully I'm in the right place.
There we go.
Yeah.
So this is kind of one way to kind of you can kind of poll for resources that ideally you know are coming.
And this could be then on a local directory or out on the web or stuff like this.
But when doing this it's nice to have these leaps in between so you're not completely overpowering your system.
I guess a similar thing we could try is this becomes kind of somewhat too simple maybe validation.
But I could have some function where I'm trying to get some information from the user.
So say that I just want to read say a number, age or something like this.
And then my or actually before doing this let me actually do this example without the okay.
So I'll do get age.
And I'll say that this just returns int input.
How old are you?
Something like this.
So now if I do this, so I guess PyCon is 20 years, right?
So we can say 20 and it returns 20.
But if we do something like 20, you can see here that I get an error because I'm doing this int conversion up there.
I'm converting this to a number because I want to use the number.
So one way to kind of avoid this is that I can define the get age with the retry.
Like this.
And now if I do get age and I claim to be 20, it says that okay, I'm retrying get age because I got this bad thing there.
So now I'll behave properly.
So there are some uses at least where you can play with this.
Okay.
And now for the fun part.
First.
Perfect.
You were five seconds ahead of me.
Yeah.
The pathlib?
So did we use pathlib?
So I imported pathlib and did I use it?
So I very briefly used it here.
So here I passed in .path.
And then when I define this process file function, let's see.
Let's just look at it here.
So there, this read text method that I use is a pathlib path method.
Okay.
And then yeah, for the fun part.
Sometimes we want to add parameters to our decorators.
It's also not the functions we're decorating because we may want to have some different behaviors.
So let's see.
I'm.
I have two versions of this.
Let's actually just jump directly to the one that Glenn wants to solve.
So we want to adapt retry so that it only tries a maximum number of times.
So then if we do apply this on our only roll highs function, then we could get five, six, or we could actually get the error if we don't get the number within the max number of retries.
This exercise, I'll give you a few minutes to ponder it, but there's I guess a few things I have told you, but I haven't really told you in how to actually make this work.
But think back to what we did early with the function factories and those kind of things.
Because what we really need to use here is that this retry becomes a decorator factory.
So something that returns decorators for us.
So for each parameter, essentially a max retry will have a different decorator.
This kind of this ends up being.
So yeah, try it out and then look at it together afterwards.
Yes.
So how's it going?
This one is definitely the hardest exercise so far.
So.
Let's have a look at see what we can do with this and we're kind of yeah, there's sort of like a new idea that we haven't really talked about.
It's kind of was just mentioned.
So let me find my editor.
So essentially what we what we kind of know how to do now is this.
OK, we can run this for everything, but I want to add in some kind of parameters somewhere that I can use to kind of say I only want to run this and times or something like this.
I have maximum number of retries.
And.
Let's see, so that means that I want to be able to send a parameter to retry itself.
So somehow it should say Max entries there, right?
My three tries. Thank you.
Retrace that's how I spell it.
So that's kind of what I know I want this to look at, and that means that when I run it or when I use it, I should be able to do.
Max retries.
Equals three or something like this and then we'll have our function beneath here.
But.
How does this then if we look at so what we kind of.
Said so far is that typically when we have a decorator, it should look like.
This so we have fun tools.
The traps.
Func and then I'll have my rapper thing here, so this is me just kind of filling out the template that we kind of found so far.
And do something and return.
Rapper.
So now I want to do this, but I also want to do that, so I kind of need to put those together somehow.
And what I said was that this new retry decorator here becomes like a decorator factory, which is similar to what we did with these function factories in the beginning.
So if you remember.
All the way up here we kind of had this prefix factory that dynamically created a new function for us or reverse factory, which kind of did the same thing.
So that's kind of the idea that will use here as well.
And what that means is, let's see, where are we here we are.
That I still want this to be.
Decorator, but this is actually the thing that will be dynamically created, so this retry that I have there.
Will be the retry decorator, so I'll just rename it and call it decorator like this.
And this will be inner and inner function thing, so it will be part of this retry.
And then.
At the very end here, I'll actually then do a return decorator.
So this is definitely when our brains get somewhat overloaded and things like this, because now I not only have an inner function, but I have an inner inner function.
So kind of keeping track of this is not trivial, right?
But what this means.
Is that where we earlier just had retry like this.
Now this full expression.
Retry max retries.
Is what.
Let's see, that returns the decorator func and that decorator func returns the wrapper.
So we're kind of back to where we started.
So if we want to have decorators with parameters, then typically what we'll do is that will kind of push in a template and have this factory outside of it.
OK, so when we have this setup ready, then actually implementing this is very similar to what we did earlier, except for now, instead of having this while true loop.
I can just do for say I in range.
Max retries.
And then I realize I'm never going to use this I, so I just call it underscore instead.
And then I'll try to return.
So this is the same code that we had earlier.
Try to return func.
And if that fails.
I'll print that it failed.
Let's see what was the text we used retrying.
Retrying.
Func name.
And then let's throw in the error message there as well.
So then I have exception.
And let's see.
Yeah, this is close to something that works at least.
So let's try it out.
So if we now copy this.
And then I can use retry.
But I'll only do OK, let's max two of them, for instance, and then we'll do the only roll highs.
And let's see that was number.
And if that number is small, then we'll raise the value error.
Otherwise we'll return the number.
Like this.
So now I have this function that rolls the dice but raises an error for smaller numbers.
But now we say that only when we retry this twice.
So let's see what happens.
Yeah, so you could see that the first three times I ran it, it tried twice because I won one and three, four.
One challenge here is that it doesn't actually raise the error.
The error is kind of eaten up, which I guess may or may not be a good thing.
So we could potentially just change our function so that the last time we call it, I guess, we don't protect the error.
So I could do something like, OK, I'll do this max retry minus one there.
And then I'll just add in a, at the end there, I'll return.
So my last retry, I don't protect it with the try block.
So then if it fails that last time, then we see the error itself as well.
So just to demo that.
Yeah, since maybe that error is nice to get, I guess.
So let's see now if we only roll highs.
There we got the five in the second roll, six.
And there you see it. Now I get the error after retrying a few times.
So that may or may not be a good thing, I guess.
The previous example just returned none at the end.
Yeah.
Right. So can we do something like an else after the for loop to get to the same thing potentially?
So here I have my for loop.
So the else statement, I don't know if everyone's familiar with else in for loops, but it's possible to do an else here.
So kind of lining up with the for.
And that else loop, let's see, that kicks in if you go through the loop without breaking out of it.
Since we're now just returning from there, I guess, yeah, let's see.
So if we, instead of returning this, yeah, so let me actually copy this so I don't mess up the previous example.
Let's see. So this one didn't have an else.
Yeah, so if we have the else there and then we could just say print.
Next.
Retries.
Max retries done or something like this.
And then we go back there.
This should look nice as well, right?
And I guess technically we probably don't even need the else there since we're returning and not breaking.
So that would look like this.
And then let's throw in this one.
So are we able to break it? There we go.
I forgot my f string.
So but yeah, this would be another alternative of kind of alerting someone that we're done.
Cool.
Yeah, so this is then the principle, essentially.
If you want to have a decorator that takes an argument, then essentially just add another layer of stuff on top of it, which then becomes this decorator factory.
And now I guess I can show you.
I claim that, which was it, functools for apps, that this one wasn't, it was a bit too technical, but here you can see that this is actually a decorator factory.
And we see that it takes an argument, right? It takes the func and so on.
OK, we're running close to the end, so we have like 17 minutes left.
So I think for the last exercise we'll do.
Let's see, we'll, I know, let's maybe just do this one.
So can we make retry have state, essentially?
So instead of just saying for each function call, it can only do three of these.
Can we, and in this case, I guess, max retries may not really make sense, but can we make it just count how many times it has retried across all kind of different function calls?
So that would mean that somehow we need to keep state.
And there are kind of a few ways to do this.
So one would be to have some kind of global variable that kind of does it.
That's typically not a great idea.
A better idea would be to use some attributes on your function where you just store that state.
And then the other third example would be to actually create a class.
And I'll definitely, I don't know if I have time to demonstrate this, but I'll definitely leave some notes about how to use classes for decorators.
Because so far I've claimed that the decorator is a function that returns, well, takes in a function, returns a function.
But it's really enough that it's a callable and you can have class instances that you can kind of call.
So you can use classes as decorators as well.
So in some of the notes I'll share links with you afterwards. You can see how to do that.
But now, yeah, for sort of like the final example, can we just put a counter on the retries that will then globally count how many retries we made?
So we can adapt the code that we already wrote. So it's just a few more lines, I guess.
So I'll leave this since we're almost out of time, but I'll leave you with two, three minutes to play with it and then we can look at that.
Okay, I guess then to finish on time, I'll just start working on this.
So I'll show you the solution where we put this as an attribute on our decorator.
And let's have a look at this. So we have our retry.
So we won't change this function a lot, let's see.
But what we can do, which maybe looks a little bit weird, is that it's possible to add attributes.
And we have actually seen this briefly, if you remember, this functool wraps, adds this thunder wrapped attribute.
So for instance, let's see, if we had the only roll highs, we should be able to do, to look at this, right?
So somewhere this attribute has been added.
So we can do something similar here by, after defining the wrapper function, we can say something like number of retries, retruse, is zero.
So now I define an attribute on this wrapper function.
And for now, I'm not using it, so this is not, we're not done with implementation, but let's just have a look at what happens.
So I'll move this over to my REPL, and then we'll implement the only roll highs again.
And now if I look at only roll highs dot numretries.
Have I messed up something? Sorry?
Max retries.
Ooh, I copied the wrong thing.
Impressive. Thank you. Okay, let's try again.
Now it's there.
And then let's see.
Then I have this and this. Yes. Okay, there it is.
So this retry decorator, because of this line up there, adds the numretries attribute.
So that means that we're kind of storing this state on the function itself, instead of kind of polluting the space.
So then our next task done is to actually use this.
And let's see, what did I actually want to do with this?
Well, I could now, let's be slightly advanced then and say that I want to do max retries, but then subtract the number of retries I've already done.
So I can do numretries there.
And then I need to actually count these things, so then I'll say wrapper dot numretries plus equals one there.
And then retry func name.
Yeah, I'll just throw it in here at the beginning so that we can see it.
Wrapper numretries.
Yeah, so this becomes a little bit of a long line, so let's see.
Okay, I'll leave it like that for now.
So now if we copy this, so now there you can see I added, let's see, in the for loop, now I'm just doing max retries minus the number I've already done.
And then in the exception, I'm printing out this number and then I'm adding one, so I'm counting them.
So then if we do the decorating, and now let's add this number a little bit higher so we can do 10 retries.
Okay, and then I say I only want to roll highs.
And call this, and now I got a six, and there you can see it's kind of doing some of the retries.
I guess I should have added before printing the number, but something like this.
And now we can see that it has stayed, right, because it continued counting at two.
And if I look here, you can see that I now have done three retries.
And if I now do this a few more times, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine, ten, then I can see now I get the 10 retries done.
So we kind of have kept the state across several invocations, even without using a class.
Yeah, let's look at the code for this. So now we actually managed to more or less fill our screen.
So I guess the somewhat magical line is here where we can add in our attributes, and then I'm using that attribute a few times here and there.
Okay, any questions? I'm sure there probably are.
But if you, yeah, they don't pop up now. Feel free to stop me if you see me at the rest of the conference, or send me an email later, or something like this.
As I said in the very beginning, I'll put all the code on my GitHub.
So let's see. Let's switch this to the resources.
So yeah, on github.com slash g-a-y-l-e, you should be able to find these things.
I've given a similar course when PyCon was online, so there are some of these video courses that's also there, and then I'll add the code from this course onto there.
I guess I didn't say this at the beginning, but on my day job I work for RealPython, which is a web page website where you can learn a lot of different Python stuff,
including then we have an article about decorators that I wrote a few years ago where you'll find lots of the same material there.
And within the paywall, you can also find a video course that goes through a lot of the same things.
Then there are some other nice places online, of course.
If you really want to look at the technical details, you can have a look at the PEP 318, which is kind of spelling out some of the history why they wanted to do the decorators and how they work.
That's also, I think, the fun part there is probably reading some of the stuff that wasn't accepted.
And there's an awesome list for decorators. That's also on GitHub.
So yeah, there's still lots of things to explore.
But I think that kind of takes us to the end.
Any questions?
Sorry?
Yeah, so I'll put the exercise slides there as well. Yes, exactly.
And no. Well then, thank you everyone for your participation. It was really great. Thank you all of you for uploading your solutions as well.
Yeah, it was really nice to at least get some sense of the activity. So thank you. Thanks.