Hello, my name is Jonas, I'm the session chair for the upcoming session of three talks.
The first speaker I want to introduce to you is Victor Sinner, who will be talking to us about introducing incompatible changes in Python.
Take it away.
Hi everybody, I'm here to talk about how to introduce incompatible changes in Python,
and especially how to reduce the number of affected people and reduce the number of grumpy people.
My name is Victor Sinner, I'm coming from France, and I'm paid by Red Hat to maintain Python downstream and upstream.
Downstream is to maintain Python in the Fedora and Red Hat operating system, and upstream is Python.org, so the main pattern.
I'm a code developer since 2010, and since 2010 I went through many incompatible changes,
and my work at Red Hat is mostly about incompatible changes and how to deal with them, so I would like to talk about that.
I'm a happy Fedora and Red Hat user, and you can find me on Twitter.
First I would like to travel in the past and see the previous approach regarding incompatible changes, which is called the D-Day approach.
You may notice on the picture that everything is out of the way, and you will understand why.
So if you travel in time, for about 14 years ago, before the Python 3, a long time ago, in a galaxy far, far away, there was Python 3.
So maybe some of you used Python tools, and one of the big things with Python tools was to handle text, especially what is called the Unicode Errors,
because everything was biased and it was causing a lot of problems.
And in the Python tool era, Django started to become a real critical of the PHP framework and Ruby on Rails.
But one of the common issues in Django was to handle Unicode text, especially non-nasty characters.
And as a French person, I can say that we are very aware of Unicode Errors, because even in the first time, we can get non-nasty characters,
and this was just enough to close the big description on our world web browser.
And just in Python 2 in general, handling Unicode Errors was a frequently asked question.
So for the rule, we didn't choose Python 2.
You have to know that just a string, LBC, this is a byte string.
This is not a string made of characters, but of bytes.
And if you try to concatenate a byte string and a unicode string in Python 2, you get an Unicode Error.
If one of them is non-nasty, and that's not something very obvious, because if all of your content is made of asked characters, you're fine.
But as soon as a French person starts to draw and give you his name, you get into trouble.
And getting Unicode correctly was very complicated in Python 2.
So what was decided to work around this issue is to fix what you call the root issue of this problem.
The root issue of this problem is to make the Unicode type a first-itizen class.
For Scrapper, first-itizen, sorry.
And for example, to combat this infamous LBC string, now this string is a Unicode string,
which means that each part of the string is a real character and not a byte.
And this is the major difference between Python 2 and Python 3.
Sadly, the big deal with that is if you come from the Python 2 world and want to embrace the beautiful Python 3 world,
you have to go through all of this Unicode issue at once.
And this is really painful, because in Python 2, if you only have asked characters, you're good.
But as soon as you have non-nasty characters, you get into trouble.
In the Python 2 world, it's very different, because you get zero as soon as you start your operation.
And you have to fix all issues at once to be able to integrate Python 3.
And in the old era of Python 2, we also started to introduce new concepts.
For example, what is called the iterator, the type 234, that was introduced in Python 2.2.
And also a new concept called the numerators, and that was a long time ago.
That's the type 255.
And because it was a new theme in Python 2.2, things like a built-in function, mark, and zip were still written and used.
And this is fine for most of the cases, when you are manipulating biometric data,
because you have to add a little bit too much memory, because you have to complete all values at once.
And that's not the most efficient way to process a file or process it from a data in your application.
So to switch to the new fancy world of iterator and generator, you have to opt-in for something called the iterator's module,
and to use imap and izip, which this one returned a generator.
And another example of that is that for the built-in type dictionary, you can iterate on pairs of key and values using the items method.
But if you call this one again, you get a list.
And if you wanted to use a more efficient generator, you have to opt-in for the iter items.
So again, Python 3 decided to make the language consistent and to fix that issue by changing the map and zip built-in functions.
So now this one returns an iterator.
You don't have to opt-in for the iterator's module, it's just the default.
And the same for the dictionary method, they also return generators.
And if you really want to get a list, you have to explicitly cast the generator to a list, and that's it.
So the Python language evolved as Python 3, that has same default module,
because we want the users to have the most efficient and the best method by default, and not ask for help to use something uncommon.
So the default module is now to use Unicard to create generators, and to make the whole language consistent again.
The big deal with all of these changes is that, from the Python 2 world, when you migrate Python 3, all of these changes are backward in the compiler.
So, the next question is, why did we decide to break up everything and to change the default and to bring a lot of change to all of our users?
I think that one of the reasons can be found in the Zen of Python, SuperPonty,
which shows that there should be one, preferably only one obvious way to do it.
What it means is that when you write Python operation, Python module, we are trying to get consistent coding style,
Python language should be easy to teach, and also easy to review.
So when you read the code, it should be very obvious, and you should not have to think about,
oh, is it the correct way, or should I use the other way to do it?
So, it's a deciding approach for the migration to Python 3.
Honestly, it was very simple.
The rule was that everybody has to run an application called 2-3 to migrate their code base,
and the idea was everybody has to do it on the same day, and suddenly everybody becomes compatible with Python 3.
Well, it didn't work as expected, because we did not expect that we got something called Jogos,
and in fact we had many, many users, way more than expected,
and something that was not really prepared is that when you have a large application with dependencies,
and one of them is not compatible with Python 3, you are blocked by this single dependency.
So first, you have to migrate this dependency to Python 3, just to be able to start coding your code to Python 3.
So it's a long process of connecting all dependencies, and also dependencies of dependencies, so you can have a long chain.
And the other issue is that this wonderful program called 2-3 is a one-way tool.
So you go to Python 3, but you cannot go back out.
It means that when you run the application, you drop support support into,
and that was not something that we wanted as a maintainer of our project,
because Python 2 was simply the most commonly used version of Python.
Python 3 was a new thing. It was full of bugs, it was slower.
So we had to find a way to support both.
And the last problem is that the migration by itself took over 10 years, which is quite long.
So to explain to you this problem of the D-Day, I found another example in the history of the Sundown County.
So they decided that on one day, on the 3rd September of 1967,
they switched from driving on the left-hand side of the road to the right-hand side of the road.
It's called the D-Day, or D-Day in Swedish.
And they took four years to prepare the city for this migration,
because it would impact the world, people of the country.
For example, to give you an idea of the cost of the migration,
they had to change more than 350,000 signs to remove them or to replace them.
And just in the city of Stockholm, they had to change 20,000 signs.
So it's not only about the signs, it's also about the bus with the door on the one side,
it's about the bus stop, about the tram and many, many other things.
So to advertise this change, they even created their logo.
And the logo is quite straightforward. You move from the left to the right with the date below.
So they created underwear and socks.
And I think it's quite a good idea to advertise the change and prepare everybody for this big day.
And T.V. Channel also decided to organize a contest of the dance song.
And this is the winner, keep to the right, Svenson.
It's a song to advertise the migration.
Okay, so we talked about the Python language Excel.
But on my side, I care about what is called CIPI.
For people who don't know that, the CIPI is used to expand the Python language
because Python has already many modules as part of the standard memory.
But sometimes you want things which are not supported by default.
So you want to expand the language by writing three extensions.
And for that, you need a way to connect the three codes to the Python.
And thanks to the CIPI, we have great modules.
And this is really part of the success of the Python language as a whole community.
And without the CIPI, there is no Python, there is no non-Python,
so there is no scientific community.
You cut large parts of the Python's success.
And now drivers for data analysis, etc.
This is an example of recent changes in the CIPI.
There is a huge and growing work for Microsoft to optimize Python.
And by the way, you should be required to Python 3.11.
It's a big system which uses less memory, which is quite impressive.
But to achieve this goal, we have to make some deep changes in the internals of Python,
in the code which executes the bytecode.
And to make these changes, we have to modify what we call the structures of the language,
like the code object, the frame object, and also the thread state.
The problem with these changes is that sadly, some people rely on the exact structures,
on the exact behavior, and there is no abstraction.
So people access their thing to the structures, and as soon as one of the members changes,
that becomes an irreparable change.
So for example, when you access your thing to the funderscore code member of the code object,
it doesn't work anymore.
Now you have to call a function for that,
pyncode underscore getCode,
and you have to make some changes for the frame and for the thread state.
And the new problem with that is that these functions are new in Python 3.11,
and you cannot get access to these functions in Python 3.10, because these functions are new.
So to make your code compatible with Python 3.11,
one of the ways is to have what you call if-dev, to have conditional code depending on the version of Python,
or you can simply decide that everybody has to move to Python 3.11,
and you give up on supporting old Python.
Okay, so that was a long introduction of what was done in the past.
Now let me introduce what is done in QL Clinic,
and what we learned on how we are making things differently on Edge.
So first of all, I think this was one of the technical solutions to a major issue
in the transition from Python 2 to Python 4.
Benjamin Peterson created a module called 6,
and this module allows you to write code working on Python 2 and Python 3 using a single code base.
So depending on the version of Python, the implementation will be different,
but the code is always the same on the 2 version of Python.
This is really something very important for the migration,
because this is really a very different approach for the migration to Python 3.
Instead of running 2 to 3 and drop support for Python 2, something that nobody wants,
the new approach is to add support for Python 3.
So you don't use support for the old version, you add support for the new version.
And this is way better, because nobody will lose anything,
you just add support for new users, and this is way better.
So the new approach is to port infinitely the code,
so you don't have to port everything at once.
So for example, if you have 10 files, you can go one by one,
and this is way easier to migrate on an application.
So we just say that as we do play the approach using 2 to 3,
the new approach just abandons, because it doesn't work in practice.
So I would like to say that we learned that that was not a good approach,
and we can do it differently.
About incompatible changes, what I said previously is that
to make some optimization, to add new features, to keep the language consistent,
we have to introduce incompatible changes,
but there are some ongoing discussions to say that,
okay, maybe we can have a different timeline for these changes,
because we don't have to make them right now,
maybe sometimes we need more time to migrate everybody.
So in the engagement cycle of Python 3.11,
we identified that the two changes were causing a lot of troubles,
and the problem is that a lot of Python commissioners in the world
still wanted to support Python 2.7,
and the support for Python 2.7 just ended up clean,
because it was three years ago,
and dropping Python 2.7 right now was not an option,
so we decided just to revert some changes,
just to give people more time to embrace Python 3,
and slowly drop the support for Python 2,
but don't require people to drop it right now.
I think this is something new in the Python community,
and we learned from our mistakes,
and we are trying to learn from the feedback of the community,
and to make things smoother for everybody.
So the two reverted changes are one flag when you open a file,
it was a flag which was ignored on Python 3 for 10 years,
we just decided to keep it for one more release,
and the other one are aliases for collection abstract,
there is classes,
these aliases are just kept for one more collection,
but again we remove them in the next Python 3.11.
So again, in the recently released Python 3.11,
we also noticed that a bunch of changes were causing too many troubles to 20 projects,
so we identified that unique test aliases removal,
the deprecated conflict parser functions removal,
and the removal of the wall,
I think our model was causing too much trouble,
and we decided to keep them for one more release,
and to remove them in the next Python 3.12.
Because again, it affected too many packages,
and the idea is to give one more year to everybody to embrace this change.
About the policy, we have a PEP called the Backward Compatibility Policy,
the PEP 387,
and this one describes how we deprecate something in Python,
and how this theory is written for.
Previously, we could remove in a single version,
deprecate in one version,
and remove in the next version.
So in two versions, you could remove from one version,
and it was fine because we got a Python release every 18 months,
but since the release of Python is exactly once per year,
so the development cycle is shorter,
and the deprecation period was shorter,
and a little bit too short,
so after our discussion, we decided to give the last version,
so after our discussion, we decided to give two years to everybody
to notice the deprecation and adapt the project for the studio's removal.
For example, if you want to remove a function in Python 3.11,
it has to remain deprecated in 3.12,
and you can only remove it in 3.13.
So overall, it takes three years.
By the way, about the deprecation running,
we decided to hide the deprecation running by default,
because we noticed that this running was causing too many troubles to users,
because most of the users of Python are actually teams of users,
and not really developers.
So the best is to fit the use case of the majority of users,
which is to hide the warnings,
and to suggest to the developers to opt in to show these warnings.
In Python 3.37, we made a private challenge,
which is that for scripts, for the main module,
these warnings are shown again by default.
So if your developer wants to see these warnings,
there are different ways,
and one of them is to use the command line option uppercase W.
With the value default, you display this warning once,
and if you pass er, you treat all warnings as enough.
And if need, you can go into the documentation
and see how to filter warnings per module or per file,
and there are many ways to control the warnings.
And I also added something called the Python development mode,
which shows the warning by default,
that it also enables other kinds of helpers for developers to detect bugs earlier.
And if you want to enable the development mode,
you can add the option dash uppercase x.
So what I would propose for smooth deprecation of a function in Python,
so how to have a smooth integration for incompatible changes,
is to follow this step.
So first of all, what you can do is to add the new API,
because adding an API has no impact, this is just fine for everybody.
Slowly, you can duplicate as an old way in the documentation,
but only in the documentation.
Afterwards, you can start to edit a warning at runtime,
so when you actually use a function.
And what is really important in my opinion,
is to explain how to update the code to the new way,
and it provides a solution to run a single code base
working for the old way and the new way.
Because this is the only acceptable solution to have an integration,
otherwise people just get empty and will abandon Python and switch to something else.
And the explanation is the documentation and providing a concrete solution to our single code base.
I think this is something new in Python,
and I think that we should do that even more.
When you did all of the steps, in that case, okay, you can remove the old way,
you can remove the old API.
So as part of my job, what I did is to use code charge.
So when I noticed that one of the challenges can cause incompatible change,
what you can do is to first download the source code of the most popular API project.
For example, with the script, you download the source code of 5,000 projects.
And once you have everything locally, you can use a tool to charge using a regular expression.
And this way, you can identify which projects are affected,
how many projects are affected,
and then you can also look how the API is used,
so to think about how to update the code and how you can explain to people how to migrate to the new one.
So overall, for me, the ideal integration would be to add an API,
document the challenge, and also provide coding to help the integration,
and then you can automate most of the steps even better.
Identify projects which are affected by your change, and if possible, update this affected project.
And the most difficult part is the next part, is to wait until you get your release,
because fixing an issue in the code is easy,
but if you don't have the release included in the code, people are still affected in practice,
because they just use a different style of something, and they are still getting the old version with the issue.
So in an ideal integration, you should wait for release of all affected projects,
then you can think about duplicating the API, and then remove the API.
So this plan takes between three and five years, depending on how many projects are affected.
Okay, now there is a new category of projects, which is causing more trouble than the other one.
It's projects which are only maintained by the single person, and this person is unable to wait about.
And the problem with that is that if there are core dependency scores,
means that they are very common, so you cannot hold them, and you are really blocked by these dependencies.
So why a maintainer can be busy? In fact, there are different reasons.
People can be busy with their work, with life duties, they can be bored by the project and move to something else,
they can move to a different programming language, they can move to a different job,
they can get someone sick in their family, in their friends, they can just change their life for the higher-level.
I don't like what we call the birth factor, or saying that the only way to deal with a project is a good maintainer or not,
it's depending on how many people maintain the project, because if they are hit by a bus, they can die.
I don't like this comparison, because the death is something uncommon.
But moving to a new job or being bored is something very common, and it's becoming a big issue in the open source community.
So now the question is how can you update this project when the maintainer doesn't reply?
Honestly, I don't know, because sometimes the maintainer decides to come back, sometimes there is no reply and you are blocked.
One way is to force the project and create a new one.
Maybe you can use authorities and they'll cover the project, but this is really an easy issue.
You may be aware of that, but this is also the issue of funding, because maintaining a package which is very popular can take a lot of time,
a lot of energy, and usually could allow the pay for that.
So if you consider that the dependency is very important for your project, please think about funding and help these people not get in trouble.
Another problem with this project is maintaining a project which is very popular, which I think has won't work,
because it's very uncommon to get a thank you email.
Most communication that you get from users only comprises one and they get the request that we need, the request that we need to do this, and then they say that,
oh, my boss asked me to do that and you have to do it for me.
The other category of projects is what I call the hidden project.
There are projects which are developed behind closed doors.
You can think about the resource groups or giant applications made of millions of lines of code.
A different way to describe them is a closed source project.
The issue with this one is if you think about a new compatible challenge, you don't have access to this project.
So you cannot estimate how many of these projects are affected.
You cannot help them to migrate.
How you can do is to expect that some people will be affected, but you don't know how many.
Usually this category of projects is a very old code base.
It's no longer maintained.
And as a result, Turnover is a development team.
So the people who created this project usually moved to a different new, higher project.
And the new team who is supposed to maintain this project doesn't understand anything about the code.
So it's very difficult to reduce the technical depth and to upgrade it to the new API.
One solution for that is to use a script called the ParryUpgrade.
ParryUpgrade identifies some code patterns and tries to use a new way in Python, which is compatible with the newer Python.
For example, when there is a new API or a new syntax.
So you should give a try to this tool.
And for the C API, I wrote a project called Upgrade.CAPI.
So this project takes your C extension and adds support for the new Python without losing support for the old Python, which is very important.
Obviously, if you cannot use this tool, if you don't know how to update your code, there is always the last resort option.
Just keep the old Python.
It will continue to work forever.
Just be aware that you will be in a lot of security issues and many vulnerabilities in Python.
So if your application is isolated from the rest of the world, it's fine.
If it's connected to the Internet, be prepared for attacks.
To come back to the C API, I wrote a project called the Bikest API compatibility.
So the idea is that when there are new functions, for example in Python 3.11, I provide an implementation of this function for old Python version.
And so you can modify your C extensions to use a new way and you are still compatible with your old Python version.
So three years ago, I created the project, which is quick to update your C extensions automatically.
The year after, I added support for Python 2.7, which is quite old, but it was needed to be able to use it on Markerio.
Last year, I added a bunch of new functions for Python 3.11.
So if you want to use these functions, they are already implemented for Python 3.10 and others.
For example, 10 projects decided to switch to this compatibility layer to support Python 3.10 and 3.11.
So the idea of the script is that you take your C extension, you run the script, and they use the new functions.
And thanks to the compatibility header file, you get access to the new functions on all the Python versions.
And then I'm trying to keep support for the very old Python 2.7 because of material and other projects which still want to support the old Python.
But the nice part is that you should not have to do this often. You should have to do it only once.
Once you convert your extensions to the new one, there is no need to update it on a frequency basis. It's one step, actually.
To make the CLP more future-proof, we designed some guidelines to try to avoid the mistakes that we did in the past.
For example, when in Python we add new C functions, we require that you don't return a borrowed response, but a strong response.
It means that the result that you have, you control the lifecycle of this object, and you know that the object remains valid until your benefit.
New functions must not steal responses, which is a little bit similar to borrowed responses, but a different kind of issue.
We also require to well define the ownership of the object and the memory, and also the lifetime of arguments and structure menus.
The idea of all of these guidelines is that the CLP should be easier to implement on Python implementation or the other 3 Python.
Because there is also PyPy, REST Python, IWRM Python, JARLTN, and some others.
By the way, we are trying to fix this CLPI by grouping the CLPI in 3 different categories.
For now, you have the EliminatedCLPI, which is linked to what I call the stable API.
You have the Public CLPI, which is wider, so it contains more functions.
And the last category is the Internal API, which should only be used by C Python itself.
To come back to my work at Reddit, what my team is doing is that as soon as there is the first alpha release of our new Python version,
we grab this version, we put it in the Fedora project, and we try to rebuild it all Python packages, which is quite big.
It's about more than 5,000 packages.
And we try to identify... we check for failures, and if there are failures, we try to identify the root cause of a failure.
Because sometimes if one dependency is broken, it can cause the failure of 50 packages.
So it takes a lot of time to go through all the logs of the big failures.
And once we identify an issue, either we report the issue to upstream, or sometimes we even propose a fix.
And the idea of our team is to detect issues as soon as possible.
This is something very important because detecting bugs earlier gives more time to fix them.
And we try to collaborate with upstream projects to get the fix image as soon as possible.
So to summarize what we did in the last years in the Python to make the situation better,
we are trying to check in a proactive way for affected projects using Pro Church or other means.
We are trying to document how to migrate user code without losing support for the old Python.
We are trying to help affected projects to update them and prepare them for the new Python.
My team working on the Fedora is providing feedback quite early on,
so we have more time to think about solutions or maybe sometimes continue to revert some changes.
And there is this new project, the Python C API Compatibility Linear, for the specific issues of the C API.
So what can we do tomorrow for the API to avoid incompatible changes?
First of all, you have to know that for C extensions, there is something called a stable API.
The idea is that you compile your C extensions on your walls, and the binary is compatible with all Python versions.
So you can distribute a single binary, which is way better than one binary per condition.
And in Python 3.10, now we have better test-free products, we have better documentation,
so we keep track of all this limited API and the stable API to make sure that we don't introduce regression.
And also for Twilio, there is a CI which is checking the wall API to make sure that one Python is released,
so the API doesn't change anymore.
And just for two examples, the cryptography and Python project are using the stable API.
I really care about the CI care, so I want to introduce you to a new project.
So the problem with the C API is that fixing issues one by one will take a long time,
and it will take further to fix the root design issues of the C API.
So Go for Feedback is able to create a new, brand new C API, we can the correct way from scratch,
so it's rather good at design, and also to have an API which is stable and provide a stable API.
So there is a brand new project called Hpy, it's getting more and more ready to be used,
and by the way there is an ongoing integration of the new Python project to Hpy, so that's getting serious.
And the main advantage of Hpy compared to the existing CI API is that if you take care of Python,
you can expect a huge speed up, because I ported the micro-gson module,
and just by switching to Hpy it became three times faster on Python.
I also would like to ask you something today,
is that I'm a Python developer, and as a developer we need your feedback,
so please test the isolation of Python, or at least the deterioration of Python,
and provide feedback as soon as possible.
Testing manually is one way, but the best way is to put it in a serial and test what we call the 90 bits of Python,
for example in GitHub you can get access to it very easily.
And if you find any kind of issue, please report our update to Python upstream,
and we will help you figure it out if it's on the Python side or on your side or both.
And the idea is that if you report issues as soon as possible,
we will have more time to design a fix and to help you to get it fixed.
So thank you for your attention, and if you have any questions, there are two mics over there.
Thank you.
We started a few minutes late, so we have time for one or two questions if you would come to this microphone.
I think one of the biggest hidden problems that you mentioned,
is that I'm the one who wants to make it easier for people in the future to maintain it on my account or I move on.
So what did you have for making my code easier to maintain or more friendly to do this for other people?
This is a hard question.
So, first we want to expect what we think are the most important changes in Python.
What you can do is to test the development action of the next Python, select 3.12,
and try to get the issue to be aware of the issue as soon as possible,
because there is basically one year until the next release,
so having one year is way better than having Python released and the emergency to get it fixed as soon as possible.
So, thank you.
Looks like no more questions, so thank you, Victor.
Thank you.