All right, welcome everyone.
I'm Jeff Hale and I'm here with Pam Gerlach.
And Pam is going to be talking about iteration toward transformation of the Python documentation.
Let's give Pam a round of applause.
All right, everybody.
Thanks, Jeff.
Really appreciate it.
And thanks to the patients, everybody started to relax.
All this starting at 1.45, I miscalculated.
Sorry about that.
But I guess we have a just-in-time presentation here.
So, yeah.
Today I'm going to be talking about how we're iterating to transform the Python documentation
in order to better serve readers' needs.
Because Python documentation has got a lot of docs.
There are a lot of people who put a lot of effort into it, but there's a lot of things you can do to help make it more forth.
You should make it, and essentially make it easier for readers of all different levels to be able to use that
and do some awesome stuff with Python.
So, let's go.
So, first of all, about me.
I'm Tim.
Just as of the language summit, I was officially promoted to a Python Core Dev.
Can't believe it.
But, yeah, that's that.
I'm also a tech manager.
I'm on the docs team.
I work on patching stuff.
Some of the second-semester in the patching summit, if you're interested in that.
I'm also a core dev provider, which is a scientific Python development environment.
And I'm in team a number of other free and open source projects, like QtPy, Pyroma, Docker, and a number of others.
And my background is actually not a programmer.
I'm actually not a real programmer.
I'm just probably one on the internet.
In real life, I'm actually a grad student and a lightning researcher at University of Alabama Huntsville in Huntsville, Alabama.
And, but I am looking to, once I graduate and get my master's, I'm looking to actually, originally I was going to go PhD,
but decided to actually, thanks to my experience with how welcoming the open source community is,
and particularly the Python community, all of you guys,
I'm looking to transition into being a full-time open source developer.
So hopefully that works out.
And that's me with my kitty cat, one of my kitty cats.
And I do love my kitty cats very much.
So yeah, and now also, I'm also contributing to this presentation is,
hopefully I can get his name right, Alain de Ofrance.
He just taught me the correct pronunciation.
And he's also a Python core developer.
And he's a member of the docs team.
He's contributed a lot as well.
He's actually the main senior of the SQLite 3 module, which we'll talk about in a minute.
And me and Alain actually work a lot together on helping transform that in particular,
following the DICACS's principles and other improvements.
And I'll go over a little bit of a case study of that later in the talk.
He's a senior software developer at Inventos in Norway.
So quite a bit of a geographical influence this day.
But of course, most importantly, this is talking just for me.
This is on behalf of the entire Python docs community who made all this stuff possible.
And a lot of this stuff we talked about wasn't even done by either of us.
It was done by all the great members of our community.
In particular, of course, we all know Mariana, as well as Peter, SGO, Prachun, Ned,
who is here today.
Thank you.
And then Adam Per, Daniela from DICACS, and of course, Joanna from RealPython.
And everyone in the Python docs community is just very valuable.
So I really want to thank them.
Let me get rid of that audio there.
So let's take a quick look ahead at what we're going to talk about.
So first, I'll give you a quick look inside the docs community.
What's it all about?
What sort of things do we do?
And then we can take a look back at the past year or so and go over some of the incremental
transformations we've made to the Python documentation.
Roll credits.
And then we'll zoom in a little bit, take a little closer look at
the, particularly the stuff that Alon, SGO, and I have done on the SQLX3 documentation
that followed the DICACS principles.
And more importantly, the kind of stuff we've learned throughout that.
Then let's take a quick look at the features.
They give you a sneak peek at what's next for Python docs for next year.
And if you're interested in helping out and being part of that, I'll let you know how
you can do that.
So let's go.
So first, let's take a look inside what is this whole docs community thing?
I mean, we've had a lot of questions.
Well, the depending on the situation is a decentralized collective of Python developers,
contributors, and documentarians, interested in improving the quality of Python documentation.
So that's a lot of big words.
But in other words, we're really just a bunch of people working at Python docs, which could
include all of you too if you want to help contribute.
So you can definitely be a part of us.
And so what sort of things do we do?
Well, we collaborate together on projects large and small from DICACS to much smaller
improvements.
We share our tips, advice, and feedback and help each other out on things like that.
We help onboard and mentor new contributors to the Python documentation, which we're always
meeting new folks and we always want to get more.
And we also discuss more larger issues of concern to Python docs.
We build consensus on how to move forward and how to make Python docs as best as they
can be.
So what sort of platforms do you use for that?
Well, where does this all happen?
Well, ideally, we'd drive around in person.
But of course, we're located all around the world.
So one of the primary places, of course, is on this Python, the dev guide and other
repos that are iffy, faster, simple requests, just like everyone else.
And all of our resources are public and anyone can join them.
It's all designed in a very transparent process.
It's not some private team somewhere like making decisions behind closed doors.
So this is our primary location where we collaborate.
But of course, we also have the docs community website, which has some kind of meta guidance
on the Python documentation and the repository there where we have issues that span not just
the C Python docs or the dev guide or the PEPs, but all of them, and kind of address
some of the larger cross-cutting issues.
We also have the docs documentation category on the Python discourse, the discuss.python.org,
not infused with Discord, very different thing.
And that's where we kind of discuss with the community the source of more of our term
history and see how should we change all this specification, how can we make the docs better
to improve.
And also community members will say, oh, look, we found this issue that's confusing.
Can you help improve that?
And we'll often help them or we'll help improve ourselves to address those things.
So if you guys have any concerns, questions, feedback into the Python docs, if it's a broader
kind of topic, more so than a mission, the documentation category might be the place
for that.
So finally, of course, we have the docs community Discord server, which is kind of for real-time
communications, you know, quick questions, feedback, back and forth.
And it's also public and you can find the link on our docs community site.
So everyone is welcome to join that as well.
Because we all can be docs materials.
I mean, when I joined the first, oops, I accidentally hit the wrong button.
And oh, and one thing we also have that I really have a graphic for was our monthly docs
community meetings where we get together and kind of discuss the things we've been working
on and we ask questions and we kind of raise ideas with the group, oh, should we do this?
Should we do that?
And we kind of have a real-time discussion of that.
And again, everyone is welcome to those.
And when I went to the first one, I had hardly been shooting anything to the C5 end docs.
I was like a real newbie.
But Mariana and Peter were like, oh, you know, it would be helpful to have some feedback
from someone outside that.
So we definitely welcome you to join that as well.
So let's take a quick look back on the sort of things that this has also been for the past
year, the sort of things you've been improving on the CPython documentation, the Dev Guide,
the PEPs, and the R.
So first, on the CPython docs, the big ticket item that I will be talking more about later
today is the Diataxis, applying the Diataxis framework and guidelines to CPython docs,
which is a whole bunch of different guidelines and how to ensure that the docs not only fix
in the different categories and is organized well, easy to navigate, but also the docs
themselves best serve readers in order to help give them the information they need to
navigate Python and to be a better Python programmer.
So you can see kind of here's an example of one of those cases which visits from the SQLite 3
documentation, and I'll talk about more in detail about this a little bit later in the talk.
And this is what Aland, Xeo, and I worked on through quite a long process, which again,
I'll get into in just a bit.
And of course, what you also probably noticed is a little bit of a difference where we have a new
docs theme for the CPython documentation.
Now it's not going to be blasting your eyes out every time you navigate to it.
Of course, that's optional based on your system theme settings, so you can of course still have
the light theme or the dark theme, and that was of course thanks to Hugo who put a lot of work
into doing that.
And that also applied to anything else using the Python docs theme, state theme as well,
so others can benefit from that too.
Of course, we also are exploring for especially some of the very, some of the longer functions
and methods that have lots of parameters and can be really hard to navigate.
Here's kind of a moderate length example.
We've actually used this thing, the structured parameter list format in to make it not only easier
to navigate, but also provide a lot of key information, like the data types, the defaults,
and other things like that to make it easier to navigate in the reference unless you want to say
okay, what does this parameter do?
You know if you read through paragraph after paragraph to try to find the areas there,
you can jump right to it.
And of course, the formatting is perfect.
We're still working on that.
It doesn't look quite as good as we want, but we're definitely working on that as well.
This is just a moderate example that also thanks to Adam's work, Adam Turner, who's now become,
thanks to his work on the PEPs, has actually become a space and a docuCells maintainer,
is one of the lead maintainers there now.
He's actually helped contribute a lot of improvements there that help the Python docs.
Here's just one example.
In our search previously, you can see that previously due to some issues and things,
it wasn't actually picking up the list built in class.
So if people searched for list, it wouldn't show the Python list.
It would show lots of other lists, but not the actual list in Python.
So now you can see it shows up there and it also has a Gloucester entry that shows there.
So you can jump right to the explanations of common terms.
So that kind of covers some of the improvements we made in the C-Python application base.
We launched a little stuff.
But we've also focused a lot on the dev guide, the developer guide.
And that's essentially what provides some meta guidance,
on how to develop Python, how to contribute to it,
and how to improve the documentation too.
So we focused on improving that, making that easier and more accessible for new contributors.
Probably the biggest thing is that Adam worked on in collaboration with the rest of us,
is reorganizing them.
So I unfortunately don't have the screen to show that,
but previously the dev guide was this one long list of dozens and dozens and dozens
of different documents, you know, all in not any particular order,
describing all different parts of Python.
And now you can see we've actually organized it in different categories.
So you're getting started for new folks.
We have documentation for documentarians.
We have information for criators in its own category, information for core devs.
And we've also tried to reorganize the different types of documents,
some of the longer documents and the smaller ones, so they're easier to navigate.
And you can kind of see the example, kind of see the result of that here.
And then we've also worked on some pretty good things.
Peter and Hugo in particular worked on this new Python release cycle chart.
That kind of gives a graphical representation of kind of the life cycle of each Python release
and what the status is.
So you can get at a glance, see what Python versions are supported,
which ones are still in development, and which ones are on the life.
So that also integrates with several APIs that ingest these data, thanks to SVO's work,
which makes it easier to programmatically integrate with other services,
like in Validate and Audit software to make sure that your Python is up to date.
So and then we've also, thanks to SVO's work as well, we've also had a new special face role
that makes quick links to the C Python source code.
So you can easily link directly to a file that shows, if you use the actual source code,
when we're explaining something in the docs, in the dev guide, you know,
here's how this was implemented, we can link right to the file with just C Python and the name of the file.
We don't have to type in a long URL and maybe it breaks or something changes.
And you can see kind of the result of that there.
Also do with the right formatting.
So that's been an improvement.
We also have a quick reference for, now here's the stuff for folks who are working in the docs.
You know, since restructured text can be really hard to navigate, really hard to remember where all the syntax for this and for that,
well, at CIO also we're kind of collaborating with the rest of us to work out a kind of quick reference.
So, you know, sometimes even experienced folks can forget, oh, how do I format this in this particular level?
Here we have a quick reference that kind of shows examples and the syntax for each of the common kind of constructs
that you're likely to use and the links to where in the docs can get more information.
Now you don't have to go forward and Google and try to find how to do this stuff.
It's all right there on a quick little table.
So, one thing I worked on is I improved the kind of guide for how to build the docs,
how to get started with building and setting up your development environment for the Python docs.
And I overhauled that.
Previously it was kind of a long paragraph of description and now it's kind of a step by step,
here's this command, this command, this command, and then they also are much clearer for what you do on Windows
versus what you do on other platforms and your other options there.
So we've really over, we've really revamped that a lot.
So finally, now one of the biggest things that Adam Turner worked on was basically completely overhauling how we're doing the tests.
So previously the Python tests, which are Python enhancement proposals,
which are kind of the specifications and the case proposals for the Python language, for caching and for other things,
previously there was a custom built, like huge build slip that would build from REST files into HTML
and was incredibly hacky and different.
It was literally unchanged for a lot of it from 20 years ago, which was a really cool time machine,
but not so maintainable nowadays.
And also involved parts of manually copying things to the Python.org website.
There was lots of different parts of it and it was really hard to maintain, hard for people to build,
hard for people to work with.
So we replaced all that with a custom syncs extension that builds it with standard syncs
and it can also use all the modern syncs contrast.
This brings us to you could only use the basic RBSC stuff.
Now you can use all the modern syncs kind of ways of doing things.
So you kind of see, and we also have a brand new theme, which has a dark theme, light theme,
and it's shorter and more concise, easier to read.
I'm going to see an example of that there.
We also made some minor improvements, smaller improvements.
We now have indices for each type of text.
Release text, patching text, typing text, governance text.
You can kind of scroll through the whole list trying to find the type you're looking for.
You click this on the index link and boom, you've got just the text that you're interested in.
And we also have a lot of new metadata and links in the descriptions.
Now you can click the link to go right to the thread.
It'll tell you what type, it'll tell you the date, it'll tell you the resolution links,
and sort of long dirty URLs that may or may not be there.
I always find it really hard to navigate to where is the latest discussion in this PEP?
What's the status? What is it approved?
And what are these status and type? What does all this stuff mean?
Well now you can hover over that or you can click the link and it will tell you exactly,
it'll take you right to that information.
So it's also much shorter in case of less space as well.
And we also have a new thanks to Hugo.
We have a new PEP API, which is basically a base on file that you can read in easily.
That kind of gives all the basic information about PEPs.
You can say, oh I want just the rejected PEPs or the accepted PEPs for Python 3.12
and it'll get you all those PEPs.
Or the packaging PEPs for say by say, by June or whoever you want.
And it will get you all those PEPs or between certain dates.
You can do all that with the PEP API.
Hugo will actually use that and build something called Pepatron that you can
just mail on interface that you can do PEP number and it'll take you right to that PEP.
Or say you can fuzzy search PEPs.
You can jump to governing PEPs.
You can jump to PEPs for a certain Python release.
It's a really handy tool to quickly navigate especially if you do
and you work a lot with PEPs or with Python specifications
or you want to see what's new with Python.
And we also have expanded a lot of help for PEP authors.
We have new documentation, new reading, new consuming guide.
We've updated PEP 1 and PEP 12.
Make it easier for authors and give more guidance and information.
And update some things that are out of date and answer some common questions.
So for authors, we try to make things a lot easier.
Of course, there's still some things we gotta work through.
But we have made some improvements on that front as well.
So and we also have some new CI checks to catch common syntax errors.
A lot of them would just pass finally and then they wouldn't render correctly
and look all funny and not show the way the author intended in the actual end of output.
Well, now we have a lot of text to back and help PEPs be more consistent
and display in the way the author wants.
So yeah, and again, we're working on that to make that more user-friendly for authors too
because sometimes it can be a little too nippy and we're definitely working on that.
So and we have a bunch of cross-cutting fixes.
Hugo in particular made a lot of search engine optimization fixes.
So the Python docs actually show up pretty high on the list of Google search
or however you search for them.
And we'll also have a built-in preview across Discord or social media sites.
And also a big thing for authors and contributors if you want to contribute
across we're not only PEPs, the Dev Guide, the C Python itself.
You don't have to set up your own dev environment anymore locally.
All those now have built in support for rendering previews of the documentation
or the PEPs or the Dev Guide right on the PR.
So you just make the changes, submit a PR and boom,
it'll still link to the preview, rendered preview of all those changes.
You don't have to set up the whole build environment just to see,
just to kind of see how your changes look.
And it's also helpful for reviewers.
I don't have to go download the PR, build it locally, look at the files.
I can just click a link and boom, I'm right to the,
right to how that, right to the rendered version of that PR.
So I can easily check to make sure everything looks good.
So that helps reviewers and helps authors.
We also put on, thanks to Mariana and with Ned who's here,
we also put on die-taxis workshops for the core team by Daniella,
who's the creator of the die-taxis framework for documentation.
And that kind of helped give a lot of guidance and advice
not only on how to make docs better,
but also to help make the workflow for docs contributors easier and smoother
and flow better as well.
And I'm sure there's a lot more stuff I'm forgetting.
So I don't want to go too much over time.
So let's take a brief closer look at some of the insights we gained from Alain and Efti and I,
taking a look at the SuperLite documentation and proving it to better serve readers,
following die-taxis and these other principles that we have.
So first, die-taxis.
I keep bringing this up.
What type is it?
I mean, I'm really not explaining it.
So die-taxis is kind of a grand unified theory of documentation.
It's kind of a meta strategy for doing documentation that serves readers' needs,
is easy to navigate, is accessible, and ultimately communicates effectively.
More concretely, it kind of laid out a framework for doing documentation.
And it's very specific, but general and outside-?
I'm going to talk some more on that now.
Advice that kind of applies to any kind of documentation that serves a particular purpose
says here's how you use language, here's how you use structure,
here's how you use other writing tools to make it effective and make it communicate well.
And it kind of focused on four main categories of documentation,
which relate to the four main purposes that documentation serves.
So tutorials, which help readers learn how to use, which explain exactly how to do something.
Explanations, which kind of give background and abstract information about concepts.
And reference, which kind of gives concrete specifics, say the API parameters of a function
and that sort of thing.
But, I mean, the key to die-taxis kind of does emphasize these four different purposes.
What we learned, and we'll talk about this in a second,
it's not really about sticking dots into four different bins and leaving them there.
It's really more about thinking about what purpose or purposes does your dot serve?
How can you ensure that readers who are looking for that find them?
And then how can you ensure that that language and the structure of that documentation
serves that purpose really, really well?
And this has become very popular in a number of other projects, like NumPy,
QIAtas.
A number of other scientific community projects and other projects as well have been following
die-taxis and seeing a lot of improvements in their documentation.
But it also takes some learning process to really get used to it.
Again, just going over the kind of four categories, we have tutorials, which are learning oriented.
So more aimed at kind of teaching some concept as opposed to just doing something.
How can you guys just say how to do something specific?
So say how to do, like say, how to handle a sequel injection attack.
For example, in SQLite.
We have references again as being kind of information oriented.
Kind of the structure of the code right here, the functions here, the methods, here's how
you call them, here's all the specific details.
And finally, we have explanations.
Trying to give that background for why something was the way it is.
What is the conceptual model that this code operates on?
So with that out of the way, what we essentially focused our initial efforts on was on the
SQLite, I'm sorry, I'm not sure how to pronounce it, SQLite 3 module in Python, which is essentially
a wrapper for the SQLite database engine.
So it's widely used by a lot of folks who work on databases.
I'm a scientist, so I don't have any more background on that.
But that not really did anything really well because the module hadn't really had any
change until Alain stepped up very recently.
So he wanted to improve me.
So there were some things they did well, but a lot of areas where they could really be
improved.
And also would be a great opportunity for hands-on learning to apply data tasks and
kind of get some real experience using that and learn more about how to apply it to other
things.
So Alain actually recruited me to help with him because, because I was a beginner, I didn't
know anything about SQLite or even SQL in general.
I was a real noob, like scientists apparently are like officially banned from learning database
stuff to business fees.
So I really had almost no background in it, but that ended up being exactly what Alain
was looking for because I would be someone coming into it for some time and I would be
trying to figure it out just from the dots.
And I could say, okay, here's where I can see this, here's where this is confusing.
And so, and actually also was one of our main folks who works in the Python documentation.
He came as well to give some more feedback and a lot of great expertise as well.
So this whole process actually took a number of months and kind of was spread out in iterative
chunks and we'll kind of go through that.
So let's just take a look at what these SQLites or the SQLite 3 documentation looked like
previously.
Well, it's not looking too bad, but so we have the main types of objects here, that's
kind of a reference.
We have some suggestions on how to use it efficiently.
We have some guidance and controlling transactions and that's kind of it.
It's not clear if I have some say I want to, how to, where do I find that information
guidance?
I'm looking at the sections of the sort of objects that it's related to or, you know,
or where's the tutorial?
I don't see anything listed here for the tutorial.
Well, it's kind of embedded into the introduction, but it's not quite doing the job as well as
it could.
So, and you can kind of see in some examples in the tutorial, you can see that it kind
of has some long paragraphs going in great detail about certain things and not really
showing perfect examples of both breaking up into smaller step-by-step chunks and we
have a big long code block with a lot of stuff going on without a lot as much explanation
for users.
So, you know, it's not bad, but it could definitely be improved to be clearer and more
step-by-step and also providing more helpful guidance for a new user.
So, how do we approach this?
Well, the most important thing was making sure the key functions, the key methods, the
key behaviors were documented and not only documented, but documented clearly in the
way that is accessible and understandable for new users like myself and that's why I
helped review a lot of those parts.
So, first of all, we wanted to make sure are the key points being got across before we
did any kind of pre-answered diatasis stuff and then we wanted to make sure that the reference
was complete and was accurate and was up to date with the current API in the module, that
we documented everything documented because there was some stuff that wasn't documented,
so we upped it with that and then we were like, okay, how do we organize this into four
diatasis categories?
Well, at first we tried just splitting everything just in one big PR, but that didn't work
out really well and along close that we decided to try and go incrementally.
First we tried to see, okay, which things are which and then we did PRs to move things
around and then we looked at each category and said how can we make that category better
serve that specific need whether it's tutorial or how-to, etc.
And then we took a look at tutorial which according to diatasis is the hardest part
and it really was.
It took us several tries to actually get it, you know, several big PRs and long discussions
to really get it to a place where we're happy, but one thing we also did, we added some fun.
The previous tutorial was kind of boring and we injected some classic Python fun there
with making it among the Monty Python movies and the ZVDM's Monty Python movies.
And so and then we also from there we can sort of how to make the how-tos and explanations
better serve their purposes as well.
So let's take a look at how that ended up.
Well, you can see this is something's the same, but we can see we have right here right at
the top we have a list of the four main types of documentation, the four main purposes and
directly links to them so readers can jump right to the tutorial, to the reference,
to the how-to guide, the fast and the sort of type of docs that they're looking for.
We also have more structured on the index, we also have a more kind of structured area.
If you're looking for say the reference on how to, you know, just how to use one function
you want to use, you jump to the reference.
If you're looking for a how-to guide on something, we have a list of those.
If you're looking for the tutorial, you can jump right to that, etc.
And you can see kind of an example from the same section of the tutorial I showed earlier,
before it was this big, this huge paragraph with very dense explanations, very dense
descriptions and then a big huge block of code where we kind of split it up and made that
into a much more incremental step-by-step guidance that also focused on kind of teaching
the reader some key things to know about the module, as opposed to just saying,
okay, here's how you do this, here's how you do that, that's it.
And of course we also need to see the example of Multiplica, where we should make it a little less
a little less dodgy and boring.
So, the key thing here for you guys, what sort of things did we learn from this?
We learned, I mean this was really more than anything a learning process because we got a
lot of stops to start, a lot of things we weren't sure about with Dietaxis, a lot of things we
actually kind of had wrong in the beginning that we learned through experience, here's what we
actually need to do.
So the key thing is, which Daniela will tell you, is to start small, to focus on one novel or even
one section of one part of your code at a time and of your documentation and work on that and
then incrementally try to improve it in as small steps as you can.
And that was something that we definitely, we tried it a lot and tried to do too much at once and it
just really didn't work.
Instead we focused on here's smaller incremental improvement.
Some of that is going to be really overwhelming to improve, especially the Dax for large programs.
And just like the Dietaxis framework says, tutorials are the hardest part.
They take a lot of work to really do a good job teaching the sorts of lessons that they're trying
to teach and also keeping them up to date and keeping them relevant for a wide variety of readers.
We had to do several iterations on that, like I said.
Also a big thing that Alon figured out earlier on and got me involved was having reviewers with
different ranges of experience with the modules.
Some like average users, some absolute beginners like me and some much more experienced folks like
Alon who know the background and all the nitty-gritty details and having those different
perspectives was super valuable in making Dax that actually addressed those different readers of all
those different levels.
Because otherwise, especially the readers with Dax that are most likely to serve, the beginners,
are likely to be confused because honestly, something I learned, every single expert at something,
it can be really hard to see where those gaps are, where those assumptions are, where those
points of lack of clarity are.
Because if you learn something a lot, you know your brain decisions automatically, but that was
super helpful and something Alon told me to really stress here.
Also, the key thing was we kind of got too caught up in the organization, how to put things in those
little boxes with Dax.
So that's what kind of jumped out at you first.
That's kind of what the most obvious and easy thing to do is.
But in reality, what also, I mean, both Alon and I, and actually all kind of learned and really
wanted to stress is that it's not just putting things in the boxes.
The language and how you present things in the structure, particularly kind of the words you use
in there, the clarity of expression in phrases and ambiguity is so critical to making Dax that are
clear to even understand and make readers feel like they have a good grasp of the material,
supposed to be unsure and doubt that they get to understand it correctly.
So, and because the key thing is you've got to focus on how you serve readers best as opposed to
how are we going to make it stay in these boxes, right?
And that was the key insight from Dax that really took a lot of real practice and reading and
trying things and discussion to really internalize that, which really is what it's all about.
It's hands on work.
You know, take it and try it and iterate.
That's really what kind of the meta framework of Dax is all about.
So let's just take a quick look at some of the things we're planning for the future for the
Python Dax.
So first of all, of course, we're going to continue with the Dicatse work, the Dicatse
transformation.
That's something that's definitely going to be a years long project, module by module, and it's
going more slowly than we'd like, but hopefully, hopefully will have more folks to help out because
it's a big project and it's something that we try to make a big plan for.
It can be very overwhelming, but we're trying to focus on step by step, module by module,
section by section.
That's kind of the big ticket item.
Another big thing is we're continuing to modernize the theme, make it easier and more flexible for
readers, and we're actually considering a new theme named Lutra by Per Jun, who's one of our
members.
He's also the author of the Firo theme that you've probably seen everywhere on different docs
sites.
And Lutra is specifically designed for the needs of the Python, the Python org site and also the
Python docs and also the Python programming guide because they're much larger sites that have
different needs than, you know, say a smaller progress documentation.
So it's specifically focused on the needs of this site as a proposed next step for the Python D,
for the Python docs.
We also have a new member of our group, Joanna, who might be making some improvements to the
tutorial, which is really a critical area for Python that's kind of been neglected over the
years and could really use some further improvements.
So we're really excited to see that, but it's also one of the hardest parts.
I'm also building a tool that's almost done that can actually sync up kind of the change logs and
what's new and other old and new docs and make sure that the new docs have all the information
from the old docs and the old ones have the new ones, making things easier for release managers
and other folks like that.
We're also, since we're moving through the round a lot with the iTasks, it helps readers be,
make it easier for readers to find things.
The key thing is we definitely do not want to break the links, especially the links down to
individual sections that we have for the old docs.
That's something, you know, there's a lot of those out there and that would be a lot of breakages
if we did that.
So I'm actually also working in a tool and a workflow that will at least automatically help
preserve those links to make sure that if you put the link down to a certain section, you know,
automatically know exactly what page and what section to redirect it to or what function,
what method.
So I'm working on a lot of tooling around that and also kind of an extension of that,
some tooling that can extract more structure data out of that application in terms of looking at
what functions are deprecated, which functions are new, what audit events, what other, you know,
what platforms certain functions are available on then and that can actually be, and to transform
that into a machine readable form that will allow, that can be used by linkers and by testers and
other tools to see, you know, if you specify, do you want your code to be sorted by Python 3.7
to 3.12? Well, does it use any functions that are deprecated in those versions? Does it use any
functions that are added new in those versions? Are they, you know, are you using parameters that
are new? And potentially they build a semi-automated tool at least to help upgrade the new Python
versions to reduce the impact of compatibility changes, which is something that a number of
developers like Victor have been really looking for.
So that's kind of a big project and more of a long-term thing. Hopefully I'll have more in the
next year, but that's something that we're also excited to do. So just a quick look at Lutra.
So this is the theme that Projunce has been working on. It's kind of a theme for larger docs
types like Python and like the Python Caching Guide to make them easier to navigate and easier
to find what you're looking for and also more useful when compatible with kind of modern UI and
UX constraints. You can kind of see that's the home page there and this is what the SQLite
re-documentation as a reminder looks like right now. And then under the current theme and then
that's how it looks under Lutra. You can see on the left you have a list of a kind of, I know one
thing I also get confused in the Python docs is where am I? Like what other modules are nearby or
what sections are nearby? There's not necessarily a great list of that right now. And we have that on
the left and then on the right we have an indicator of where you are in the docs and you're
left to show what section you're in because I'm used to having to track where exactly I'm
controlled to if it's a long documentation that I'll show you and make navigation a lot easier.
There's also lots of other improvements I can't get into but again just as a reminder this is
the, you know, this is still in alpha. It's still being worked on. It's still a proposal. It's not
necessarily for certain features of Python docs thing. There still needs to be a lot of feedback
out of the session but if you do want feedback just search Lutra and you can definitely add
feedback there and let everyone know what's good, what might need some improvement. So definitely we
have a full working demo of the CPython docs there which is what this is from. You can browse
that and see what looks good, see what looks better, see what might need some improvement and give you
your feedback as well. So Purdue is definitely looking for that. So yeah, so if you are looking
to help in other ways, well there's plenty of ways to do that. So of course you can join us on Discord
and Discord and our discourse, Discord, two different things, and our community calls. Those are
where we can, those are all the different platforms that we test things and of course the Asia
Strap as well where we discuss, you know, and you can give your feedback on what you think of the Python
docs as well, what doesn't, what sort of things we should do. If you want suggestions on how to,
what products to help to start with or what things to help with, or if you have your own idea, you can
definitely compose that there. We'll give you our feedback and then we also appreciate your feedback
as well because everyone is different. You need perspectives. We work in different areas. We have
different levels. We have work in different modules. We have different, you know, we all
ask them the icons on the scientific domain. Several other, a lot of other developers come from
the web domain or somebody scripting or someone from the core Python. So having all these different
perspectives are really useful in making docs that are accessible to everyone. Of course you can simply
fix the improvement. We're always happy to review those and tag us and get a review and get feedback.
And you know, we're also happy to review and mentor new contributors, but if you're in,
you're experienced in documentation, you've already worked on other docs, and you know,
we always need more mentors and more reviewers for other people's documentation. So we're happy
to have that as well. Now, but if you think you're not experienced enough, well,
honestly, that means you're perfect to help us out. And that's exactly what Alon and I and
actually all learned with the SQLite application. You know, it's good to have somebody who's an
expert, good to have somebody who has a good understanding of something, but it's also really
good to have a beginner, have that beginner's mind who can take a look at the docs for the first time
and see all the gaps, see the places that are, you know, if you're actually trying to use something
for the first time from docs, you know, it can be super challenging because they can use stuff that
maintainer would never have thought of that might be unclear or might be ambiguous or might not have
enough explanation on something. So your input is super valuable. So even if you've never looked at
a certain module or even tried to help the documentation before, you need a perfect person to help us out.
So just getting feedback is super valuable and something that we really, really appreciate. So we
hope to see somebody do there. So again, one more time, I want to thank everyone in the docs
community for helping with this. I mean, it's been a huge community effort. I've just been a little
part of it. I'm just kind of the messenger, but it's been a really community effort. We're a
decentralized collective, but we all pitch in and help out. It's a great, great community. I mean,
honestly, as of course Brett Cannon famously said, you know, you come to the language, but you stay
for the community. And that's something that I'm incredibly thankful for everyone here. And so,
again, I want to thank you all for being part of the community. Thanks to Python docs community.
And thank you for your time.
I don't believe it is.
Okay. Oh, now it is. Awesome. Thank you, Pam. Really appreciate all your work. And this is going
to help an awful lot of people in the future. We have just a couple of minutes here for questions
if anyone has those, or perhaps you can catch Pam in the follow up if you want to talk to her.
Anyone have a question for right now? Yeah.
I, of course, have another question by comment. The value of new members is really
effective in tackling normalized deviance. That was a term that was created after the
China was explosion. So thank you for reinforcing that. Thank you.