So, next we have our next keynote speakers who will be setting up right now.
So, James Powell, who is when I was starting to just becoming starting to in my journey
in the Python community being involved with other Python community members, volunteering,
speaking.
I was impressed seeing James Powell's talk at PyCon Canada many years ago.
And when he talked about how to engage with volunteers and how to align goals of volunteers
who have personal passions and the bigger goal of the community.
And I always found that his talks are super engaging, very unique style.
He's a great educator and very entertaining.
So I really so exciting to introduce James Powell to you all.
Go ahead.
Good morning, everybody.
This is I don't want to be a Python expert.
We are at PyCon US number 20 in Salt Lake City.
It's Saturday, April 22nd, 2023.
I am of course James Powell.
If you want to follow me on social media, on social media, I'm always basically don't
use this code.
This should also serve as a disclaimer for everything that you're about to see.
So I used to give a lot of really crazy talks about doing things like live patching the
Python interpreter to swap out the C eval, pi eval frame x loop.
And people would come up to me after the talk and say, hey, I want to be a Python expert
too.
And my answer to them would be, why bother?
What does this really add to your life?
And I tried to think a little bit more about this.
What does this expertise really add to our lives?
Now, I also gave a talk at Pydata Seattle in 2017 called so you want to be a Python
expert.
Because enough people have been asking me about this.
What does it take to be a Python expert?
And this talk ended up being very popular.
Here's something that's quite interesting.
I gave the exact same talk one week earlier at Pydata Berlin and it was titled advanced
metaphors encoding with Python.
Almost nobody on YouTube have seen that talk.
The clickbait title really works.
And if you think about it, it probably makes sense because that word expert is a very loaded
term.
It means a lot of things to a lot of people and to an audience like this for whom we are
often valuing ourselves in terms of being thought of as being smart or being thought
of as being experts.
This term expertise really has a lot of implicit meaning.
Oftentimes in my own actual work, I'll see a rejection of this idea of expertise.
And it's a very valid rejection.
That is to say I'll work with a scientist or a data scientist or a quantitative modeler
who will say I don't want to be a Python expert.
In fact, I don't really even want to be a Python programmer.
I just want to be somebody who uses Python to get things done.
And I'm extraordinarily sympathetic to that perspective because in the end, what is the
value of the expertise itself?
The value is what you're able to accomplish with that expertise.
And so let's not talk that much about expertise.
In fact, let's start with something very simple.
Let's start with something quite elementary in this presentation today.
We'll even start with something that you might have covered in your elementary education.
Let's start with Newton's method.
And for those of you who do not remember what Newton's method is, it is an iterative approach
for solving or finding the roots of a real valued function.
We often use this to find the roots of a polynomial where there isn't an easy closed form solution
like a quadratic formula.
And even though we're going to talk about things like Newton's method, what we're going
to talk about here is actually broadly relevant to any case where the code that you're writing
is a solver, a simulator, an agent model, even things that might look like back testers
or even things that might look like machine learning training mechanisms.
Well in Python, making use of something like Newton's method is quite easy.
We go into SciPy and we say from SciPy.optimize import Newton.
We give it a function.
We optionally give it the derivative of that function.
And it'll go and it'll find the roots of this polynomial.
And so in this case, it'll find the roots negative two and four.
And it'll tell us that's where that polynomial intersects with the x-axis.
Now this is SciPy and so NumPy and DRA should show up somewhere along the way.
Well in fact it does.
You can provide not just the one guess, not the one initial point, but all of the initial
points.
So if you bracket those two initial points around the two edges of the parabola, you'll
be able to find both of the roots simultaneously.
But that's about as far as the use of the NumPy and DRA really gets into this.
And so when you think about this, the implementation of SciPy.optimize.Newton probably is very
similar to the most naive approach that you might take.
It probably looks something like this.
A simple for loop where you're looping and then applying that iterative step.
And in the case of Newton's method, the iterative step is quite simple.
All you're doing is evaluating whatever your guess is in the function and dividing that
by what the derivative is and then subtracting that until you get close enough to zero.
Of course, when you look at this code, you might say, I'm not that happy with it because
why do I need 50 iterations?
For the polynomial that we just looked at, you don't need 50 iterations to find the roots
of that thing.
You probably only need three or four.
And so we'll parameterize this.
And this is in fact what the API for SciPy.optimize.Newton looks like.
You have a max iter and you can give it the maximum number of iterations that you want
to run for.
But you can think, well, how do I know what the iterations are ahead of time?
Maybe I want to give it a tolerance.
When you get close enough to zero, then you're done.
And if we're going to write this in pure Python, we might make use of the math module.
And here we can implement an absolute tolerance.
But the moment you see is close, abs tall, you think, well, if there's an absolute tolerance,
what about a relative tolerance?
And the keyword arguments start to grow.
Because now we have three keyword arguments, max iter, tolerance, and rtolerance, to implement
this.
And we are now matching very closely to the API of SciPy.optimize.Newton.
If you think about any sort of iterative approach, you might say keep working until there's no
additional improvement.
Don't keep doing work.
Don't burn through my cycles if you're not getting anywhere.
And so we might add yet another keyword argument, one which SciPy.optimize.Newton doesn't have,
which just matches for the previous step to the current step, what is the actual improvement
here?
And we might say if we're going to do the absolute improvement, we should also look
at the relative improvement.
And this thing is beginning to spiral out of control.
Now there is one saving grace for this, which is we were able to write a function which
has a keyword argument titled RIMP for relative improvement.
And I don't know about you, but that just feels very SciPy circa 2007 to me, a keyword
argument called RIMP.
But if you're not convinced that this is beginning to spiral out of control, really think about
this.
In our first iteration from the first variation of the function to the second variation of
we added a keyword argument to match to what SciPy.optimize.Newton was doing.
And if anywhere in the world the very last line of code that you see here where somebody
passing those max iterations as a positional argument, not as a keyword argument, exists,
the moment you made this change to this code, you broke their workflow.
These people don't want to be Python programmers.
They just want to use Python to get things done.
They will get on social media and they will abuse you for breaking their code.
You did something wrong.
you probably should have used keyword-only arguments to save yourself from this debacle.
But there's another hard lesson learned.
If you think about this a little bit, when we look at all the places where somebody might
use this code in the wild, somewhere in the wild one of your users is passing in multiple
modalities, both the maximum number of iterations and the tolerance.
Is this well-defined?
What does this do?
If you change the underlying code, are you going to break their code?
Are you going to get on social media and hurl abuse at you?
You don't know.
It would be a good idea to document what happens when all the interactions of these
keyword arguments occur.
Which you probably won't do.
If you think about the documentation tool we have, we're very encouraged to document
keyword arguments individually and not the interactions of them.
That fits into a block at the end of the thing.
Very likely you're going to preclude this entirely, which I don't think is the right
choice because sometimes you want to run from maximum iterations or until another criteria
is met.
If you really want to be diligent, you need to specify how this works in the form of tests.
You might write a unit test or a property test where you say these are all the different
ways this can be called and I'm going to specify that and that way if I make a change to the
underlying code, my test will break and we'll see not in documentation but in the form of
a test how to specify the way in which this works.
Except the problem here is for five modalities that we have, we need the Cartesian product
of either choosing or not choosing that modality, so we need 32 tests.
And if we had one additional modality, we need to double the number of tests.
This expands geometrically.
This will genuinely spiral out of control.
And we are obligated to do this because what might appear to be an innocuous change to
the way in which this code is written will break user code and practice if we look at
this code and say if they didn't pass in the imp or the rimp, great keyword argument name
if I must say so myself, arguments, we're repeatedly checking in this type inner loop
whether that's set to none or not.
Let's see if we can factor that out of the loop.
But the moment you do that, you've broken people's code and you need that unit test
in place.
And so note that this is already spiraled out of control and we haven't really tested
limits of our imagination because if we can consider all of these ways to do something
as simple and elementary as Newton's method, well, somebody can come to us and say, well,
could you run this for a fixed amount of time like a soft real time limitation, run Newton's
method for two seconds and see how far you get?
Or maybe we could look at the ratio of adjacent terms and we could see if those converge to
something.
A lot of integer sequences converge to particular values.
If you think about something like Fibonacci, adjacent terms of the Fibonacci sequence converge
to the golden mean.
So you could run this until the convergence reaches some particular threshold.
Rat tall I don't think is as good as rimp but we're still on the right track for 2007
to ask sci-pi keyword argument names.
Having said that, if you really think about this, I've given the game away.
The moment I said Fibonacci, half of you out there are thinking this probably should have
been a generator from the beginning.
And you're right.
We should have implemented this Newton's method as just an infinite sequence of steps and
then when somebody says, oh, I want to run this for 50 steps, you say, here's the intertools
module, import iSlices, iSlices 50 steps.
Or when they say, well, I don't want all of the incremental steps, I just want the end,
you say, well, here's the collections module, use collections.deck and throw away everything
except the very last value.
When they say I want this for up until I reach a particular absolute tolerance, that's just
intertools.takewhile.
If you want this for a relative tolerance, that's just intertools.takewhile with a different
lambda.
If you want this for some relative improvement or some absolute improvement, that's just
takewhile on an N-wise where an N-wise is a generalization of the idea of getting overlapping
windows of some particular size of some data which is basically just when you take the
intertools module and you enumerate T, a bunch of iterables, and then you iSlices them
and do them together, of course, for those of you who have seen a talk like this before,
that's just fan service.
You're welcome, Jeff.
In fact, these days you just do an intertools.pairwise.
But whatever the case may be, we're going to sit in a code review somewhere along the
way and we're going to have to either litigate or adjudicate, is this code actually better
than what we started with?
We know it's spiraling out of control, but is the other version any better?
Well, we already know the answer to this because all code reviews are all the same.
We all know what good code is and what bad code is.
Good code is code I wrote and bad code is code you wrote.
But we still have blocked out 30 minutes for the code review session.
We probably should take a couple of notes along the way and let's see if we can litigate
this a little bit more deeply.
Well, if you think about it, the very first version is just adding keyword arguments,
so you do all of the things you want to do with Newton's method in just one line of code.
Whereas the second version, you have to have two lines of code and you have to have an
import.
And if you're a data scientist, you're thinking, you know, why write two lines of code when
I have to write one line of code?
I'm very sympathetic to that attitude, but definitely data scientists who know who you
are.
Additionally, in order to even understand how all of this works, you need to know what
a generator is.
You need to know what the intertools module is.
A set of colleagues of mine have created a framework for data acquisition and data management
around X-ray beam lines.
And the dominating concept for that framework is PEP380 delegation to a subgenerator.
If you think a scientist will complain when you show them a generator and yield, see what
happens when you show them yield from.
There's a bar that you have to meet to be able to use this code.
And the question might be, is it worthwhile for us to inflict those requirements upon
our users?
But on the other side, you might be able to mitigate a little bit of that by creating
a convenience layer.
So the core layer looks one way using all of these advanced functionalities, and there's
And when we look at a lot of projects in the in the pie data ecosystem, you see this pattern
of the core and the convenience layer.
Matplotlib and pyplot are very good examples of that.
And maybe that allows you to write tests a little bit better.
The convenience tests can be a little bit more superficial, and the core tests can be
a little bit more exhaustive.
So there might be some benefit there.
But I think one thing that hasn't come up at all in our code review is the design of
or specifically the absence of design.
That is to say, if we are to clumsily define the word design in a way that we don't typically
define it to be any decisions that we make to address questions whose answers are unknowable
or unverifiable, anything that we make, which we say, this is a judgment call.
I think this is how this is going to be used.
I think this is what our users want.
I think this is what people want to do with this.
Well, there's a lot of these calls and there's no right or wrong answer.
Even if you think about the temporal dimension, it may be the case that the right answer today
is the wrong answer tomorrow.
Design is not necessarily timeless.
It's oftentimes very idiosyncratic or very specified to a particular period of time.
Well, of course that makes sense, because if we think about design, we're thinking about,
especially when we talk about APIs, the accommodation to the human requirements.
How is a human being going to use this?
And this necessarily means accommodation to the infinite profundity of the human experience.
So design doesn't really have a right or a wrong answer.
It's just what seems to work and what you can get away with.
And you're always trapped in this puzzle of, well, did I get it right?
Did I get it wrong?
Do I know if I got it right?
Do I know if I got it wrong?
Well, if we're willing to accept the clumsy definition of design, maybe we're willing
to accept a clumsy dichotomy between the idea of design and effort.
Where if design is trying to approach these unknowable questions, effort might be the
processes that we take to do things to solve problems that are knowable and that are verifiable,
where we just know it's just a matter of number of lines of code that we have to write.
And so if we think about this, the core convenience layer dichotomy, I actually don't like that
very much.
Because you're just trading the design at one level for the design at another level.
You're still making a decision for what somebody wants to have available to them, what they
want to see, what modalities they care about, what modalities they don't care about.
And you've narrowed the problem only very slightly.
In fact, I actually think the preferred solution here is to make the scientists use generators.
And to teach them generators and to teach them about the intertools module and to avoid
the design problem entirely.
Don't presume that you know the modalities that they care about.
Just give them a generator and let them supply whatever they want to do.
But this does necessarily introduce some complexity.
And we can take this complexity to the extreme.
Because honestly, I have written this in real code before.
Some of you are looking at this, you have no idea what this is all about.
I am a very strong believer in the idea of pre-pumped generator co-routines.
I have to remind you one more time, don't use this code, folks.
But if we think about this dichotomy that we've set up, clumsy as it is, between design
and effort, we can think that what makes us better at design is judgment.
And what makes us better at effort is expertise.
That is to say, by understanding these complex mechanisms that we have, we can lever our
expertise to turn problems that have an unknowable aspect to them into problems that have a
knowable aspect to them.
And to be honest, I am very skeptical about my own judgment.
After all, look at how I'm dressed.
But I'm much more confident about my ability to leverage expertise because largely the
expertise that we're talking about here, the expertise of using parts of Python that
are considered to be more advanced or considered to be more esoteric, it's largely about a
conceptual expertise that can be very obvious, in fact, and can be methodically constructed
and most importantly can be methodically instructed.
I'll give you an example.
We talk about generator co-routines and we put this in front of a scientist.
They have no idea what you're talking about.
They've never seen this before.
Their familiarity is with mechanisms that they've learned when they first learned programming
using MATLAB or C or maybe even C++.
But you can share with them a very simple idea.
We can represent data in multiple different ways.
We can represent the exact same data, the three entities, A, B, and C, as a string or
as a list.
But beyond the superficialities, whether it's a list or a string, we can see that there's
something a little bit deeper here.
In other words, one of these is an in-band encoding and the other is an out-of-band encoding.
One of these uses a single channel for representing the metadata and the data or the structuring,
and the other one uses distinct channels.
The string conflates the commas which are delineating the data with the actual values
themselves and the list has an out-of-band encoding where there's no way for you to
mistake is this a comma that's part of the data or not.
And we know in-band encodings are fundamentally ambiguous.
And so we run into these problems where is this A, B, C, D, four entities or A, B, C,
comma, D where the comma is part of the entity, three entities.
The out-of-band encodings are fundamentally unambiguous.
Well, in a very similar sense, we can think when we want to disambiguate these in-band
encodings, we have a set of techniques.
And the techniques are almost always the same, partitioning, quoting, escaping.
When you think about partitioning, you think about taking the input data space and designating
certain input values as being only metadata.
So an example of that would be the bit patterns that are NANDs and payload NANDs and IEEE
754 double precision floating point.
You have quoting or escaping.
Of course, CSV is very famous for this.
You have mechanisms like prefixing, which don't show up that much in our programmatic
mechanisms, but if you look at how Git objects are represented, there's a prefixing mechanism
where it says the next number of bytes are the underlying payload itself.
And you see these in network protocols.
And when you think about some of the things that we as data scientists have to deal with
in contemporary versions of tools like Pandas, things like the D type with a capital I in
64, well, this is actually an out-of-band encoding very similar to the NumPy masked
array to represent missing values in the absence of an unambiguous partitioning of integer
data.
Largely, despite all of the verbiage behind this, many of these things are quite obvious.
And oftentimes when you see these core concepts, which are very easy to point out to somebody,
you can't unsee them.
I'll give you an example.
Some of you out there are users of a very, very high quality, very nice package called
X-Array that combines the ideas of NumPy and Pandas together.
And for those of you who aren't that familiar with X-Array, I'll give you a very brief
refresher.
NumPy is all about representing multidimensional data with broadcasting.
Pandas is all about representing index aligned one-dimensional data.
And X-Array is about doing coordinate aligned multidimensional data.
I must and I'm obligated for a very brief aside.
Number one, the Pandas data frame is not two-dimensional.
The Pandas documentation says it is.
The Pandas documentation is wrong.
Pandas data frames are like indexed one-dimensional data.
You heard it here.
I will take that to my grave.
Number two, for those of you who are complaining about Pandas, Gilad, I know you're out there,
the API of Pandas is guaranteed.
It is absolutely very inconsistent.
It sometimes swap underscore levels or drop level with no underscore.
It's very inconsistent, but the core concept behind the tool is incredibly coherent.
And three, the only thing you ever really have to know to be really good at Pandas is
index alignment.
They once asked me to write a book on Pandas.
They asked me for the chapter outline, and I said chapter one, index alignment, chapter
two, everything else, and then the Apple log.
There's only index alignment and nothing else.
That's the only interesting thing about Pandas and the only thing you have to know.
But back to X-Array.
When we talk about X-Array, we're representing multi-dimensional data with some dimension.
So you have maybe a volume metric data and you have an X, a Y, and a Z dimension.
And you can select a slice of this down the X axis or down the Y axis or a combination
of these.
You can even interpolate this if you have missing values.
And because this is a wrapper on top of tools like NumPy, Pandas, and SciPy, you can even
pass an interpolation method.
You can use SciPy interpolation methods, linear or cubic or whatnot, in order to choose how
that interpolation works.
But what if your dimension is called method?
This is fundamentally ambiguous because it's an in-band encoding where you're conflating
the single channel, the keyword arguments you have, to either represent one, the modality
of how you do the interpolation, or two, the data that you're interpolating on.
There is no resolution for this.
This is a flaw in the API and it's as obvious as you cannot unsee it once you see it.
And the solutions are largely quite routine.
You want to find an unambiguous encoding, partitioning, quoting, prefixing.
None of those will work in this approach.
So what you'll do is you'll use an out-of-band encoding.
You'll have two layers of a function, but nobody likes that.
Or you'll do something like pandas.lock and .ilock where you'll create one more layer
using the descriptor protocol or using some other protocols in Python.
And so you might do something like this to say this is a linear interpolation for these
particular axes.
Or you might realize that this is just the problem of a nominal decomposition of a bounded
modality.
In other words, there's only a set number of possible interpolations that you have.
SciPy only supports less than a dozen of these.
You can put a name on each of those.
This is basically the idea behind class method that we do all the time.
You could just have a bunch of methods linear underscore interp and you would have solved
this problem entirely.
Now, once you see the problem, you can't unsee it.
I'm certain that you're going to begin to see these problems in the actual code that
you have.
When you think about this difference between the in-band encoding and the out-of-band encoding,
that's basically what a generator is all about.
The core concepts here are actually quite simple and quite present there.
They're obvious and they're in front of you and they can be methodically thought through.
Because if we have some function that does a bunch of different things, we might as a
human being put step numbering on these.
A function that loads some data, cleans some data, removes outliers and processes some data
contains three steps.
Step one, step two A, step two B, step three, or maybe four steps corresponding to the lines
of code that we have.
But in truth, this is an ambiguous in-band encoding for the structuring of the underlying
computation.
And all a generator is, is an unambiguous out-of-band encoding for the structuring of
It unambiguously delineates this is where the first step is, this is where the second
step is, this is where the third step is, and this is where the fourth step is.
And the moment you have an out-of-band encoding for the structuring of this function, you
can do things like unambiguously delineate the steps.
Which means you can then create mechanisms for controlling how many steps you run through,
which is the core problem that we had when we were using our various implementations
of scipy.optimized.newton.
We were constantly having to add additional keyword arguments to control the number of
steps of the iterative method that we go through.
Well, we can devolve that entirely with just a very simple conceptual idea.
We can devolve those modalities such that instead of presuming that we know we're going
to run for a maximum number of iterations or into a relative tolerance or an absolute
tolerance, we just say we'll run forever, but we'll structure the computation so that
you can choose how you want to do this.
And we can empower the end users to do things which are not capable with the scipy.optimized.newton
implementation that we have today, which of course I don't want to criticize too much
because there's a lot of historical baggage to these tools and many reasons why they're
written the way they are.
But we can devolve those modalities to allow things like complex combinations of these
stopping conditions that are otherwise impossible to easily represent in the form of just keyword
arguments.
From this perspective, we can actually come to an answer for why bother with the expertise
in the first place.
If we reframe the idea of expertise as the methodical approach to devolving design into
effort, to taking questions which cannot be answered because they are fundamentally a
consequence of adapting to some human requirement where we have to make assumptions about, well,
are they going to use it this way?
Are they going to use it that way?
Are they going to want to do this?
Are they going to want to do that?
And we discover through the advanced mechanisms that are available in a programming language
like Python, mechanisms like generators or context managers or meta classes or even some
of the more esoteric mechanisms that are available when you start digging deeper like import
hooks and whatnot, we can oftentimes devolve that design into effort.
And we can remove the unknowable quantity of design.
We can then just implement some mechanism that allows us to not have to guess, are we
going to get this right or wrong and not have to risk spiraling into this unknowable,
uncontrollable future.
Because if you really ask me, I don't want to be a Python expert.
I don't even want to be a Python programmer.
I don't even want to be a programmer at all.
I do want to be somebody who uses programming to get something done.
But the answer of expertise and the motivation for this is really, can I be more effective
in the work that I do via a deliberate methodical approach to developing expertise?
And I think I've made a compelling case for why that may be.
This has been I don't want to be a Python expert.
I'm James Powell.
Thank you all.
Applause.