Are you ready?
Woo! That was a strange howl I made for you all.
Everyone, welcome to day two,
afternoon lightning talks.
How's everyone's day two been so far?
Wow. I can tell you've had a really good day today.
Yes. I have so much fun.
I went to the mental spring,
I juggled a little bit,
and then I went to the PSF lunch.
The members lunch, that was great.
Some really exciting things
the Python Software Foundation is up to.
If you have not yet registered as a member,
you can register as a basic member, which is free.
We also have a lot of other members options,
and you can find any board of director member,
any staff member, former people.
I'm happy to answer those questions.
We'll be happy to talk to you more about the PSF.
Also, as a reminder,
there are still open spaces going on.
Can you tell us about an interesting open space
we heard about earlier that's going to happen tomorrow?
Yes. Did you submit the lightning talk and did it get selected?
Do you feel disappointed that you have these slides
that you have prepared and you didn't get the chance to show?
Don't worry, because tomorrow there's an open space
that you can submit your...
I guess you don't have to submit, you just show your lightning talk.
What is that section called again?
Yeah. It's called Lightning Talks They Didn't Want You to Hear.
I don't know if that's better or fun.
We're not going to take it as too better.
I think it's all in good fun.
That's at noon tomorrow in room 250 AB.
By the way, conference convention halls
have the weirdest numbering system, so I don't know.
250 AB, enjoy that.
And let's see, any other...
Oh, any other announcements that we would like to share
for people about lightning talks, for example, tomorrow?
Yes. So tomorrow we have a very special lightning talk
because there will be people who are around the world,
they have communities and they have events
that want to tell us about.
So if you organise any Python conference locally
or Python events locally or community events locally,
then it's your last chance, send Lorena a slide or a picture,
I guess, then you can show up tomorrow
to give a very, very short promotion.
Yes, so that is...
You can use my email, lorena at python.org.
It's also floating around on the Python Discord, on Twitter.
I don't know, I spammed a lot of places with that info.
So that pretty much does it.
So let's go ahead and get kicked off
with our first lightning talk.
And speaking of amazing events around the world,
we're going to be hearing about some really exciting things
happening over with PyCon Korea.
Let's take it away.
Hi, I wanted to go my 10 years of PyCon Korea.
My 10 years, yeah, it's because I bought the domain 10 years ago.
Yeah, but it's not.
It's not 10 years.
It's actually 9 years of PyCon Korea.
Yeah, I'm going from South Korea.
In the beginning, there were PySans.
I started with PySans since 2000 with 1.6.
It was time of the open source and the Linux.
Many people teach each other's.
So I learned from some prox.
PySans supported my bills and housing.
So I decided to give back to the people about what I learned.
So I started in 2012.
After that, I started.
So I got some prox to make PySans visible to the prox of Korea.
Made a Facebook group, PySans Korea, for Korean users.
Many prox joins.
I bought the domain at that time and started PyCon.
But yeah, after that, I got failure.
Too many schedules and too many words, do something here,
do something here.
And actually, at that time, I didn't get a job.
There's many consulting out of time.
So I paid to launch PyCon at that time.
And the love begins.
I got the job.
I got the job because that job, I can success PyCon.
It's a Japan-based company.
So I went to Japan for the company trip sometimes.
It happens because working on a Japan-based company.
But yeah, but again, too much work, too much trouble.
I have no time to work at PyCon Korea.
And yeah, I visited PyCon Japan.
Yeah, actually, that's me.
Yeah, there were PyCon APEC sessions.
So I joined and talked about the people.
There was three reasons.
PyCon JP, Singapore, Taiwan.
They had one to help me.
So I got contacts and they encouraged me.
After that, good luck again.
I got the whole new, new purpose to learn PyCon Korea.
What should I do?
Yeah, I need to get some experience about PyCon.
Yeah, PyCon US.
I should go.
Well, I should run.
But yeah, I got a second son.
Yeah, schedule canceled.
It's long flight.
Yeah, my family needed.
Okay, let's go to Taiwan.
Short flight, short schedule.
I can go at weekend.
Yeah, that was PyCon APEC.
But tickets sold out.
Wait, there is group check-in for three persons?
Okay, I can fly.
So I have two free tickets.
What should I do?
Invite two people from the plus Korea,
the Far Ladies and John Craig Niles join.
If I didn't invite them, it didn't work.
Both folks went to Taiwan.
I got advice from Taiwan.
Start from small core teams.
And at PyCon APEC panel discussion, yeah, like this.
I said, we will have PyCon Korea at the end of August.
Actually, I didn't ask folks about it.
Yeah, I just did it.
Why August?
I have second son in September.
I made announcements by myself.
If I don't do that, I get some brain.
Actually, at this time, I think they don't blame me.
But yeah, at that time, the announcements works for me.
Tell me two people resigned their day job.
I don't know why.
And devote to PyCon Korea.
We got the venues and website, not a big venue,
but start at small.
Okay, we need keynote speaker.
Ask some PMS people about keynote.
I got a little bit of a loss.
Yeah, they rejected because of schedule.
Two times schedule, I was getting mad.
I got advice again, start small.
It means we can go without keynote.
Okay, open registration, sold 400 tickets in one day,
all sold out, yeah.
But in these days, out of time, yeah.
So anyway, many people talked, I want ticket.
Look again, Chang Hyesik, the PSP,
one of the committee of Python, give me a phone call.
Can I get a ticket?
Yes, you can do the keynote.
We ask you speakers, it's kind of loud.
If I do more details, it cannot happen.
And the 90 years of PyCon Korea, we got something like this.
Of space, charter, dragons.
And yeah, this, we have 1,000, yeah, about 2,000 people.
Yeah, like this.
And we did it.
Also you can do it, that's important.
The countries have PyCon, ask me.
Also we have a space.
Need people, more digital speakers to PyCon regions.
We more connect.
Yeah, like this schedule, you can ask me.
And thanks for the PSP, your money,
and help, I put memories of our cars.
And after 10 years, this became this.
They start to learn Python.
Thank you.
It's a very, very touching lightning talk.
Thank you so much.
And we have actually ordered lightning talk,
a very different topic.
And the next one actually is about typing.
So another talk, and we have our speaker here, Reddy.
So thank you so much.
Hi, I'm Cass Stor, and I'm with Unified,
which is a social network that supports activists.
And I'm gonna talk to you about workflows with typing.
So what is a workflow orchestration engine?
Actually I should say, this talk was gonna be 10 tips
for using temporal to orchestrate your workflow.
But I have to be totally honest with you,
I don't think I have 10 tips to offer.
So this is like less than or equal to 10 tips.
So what is a workflow orchestration engine?
Most of you are probably familiar with it.
It's anything that runs batch jobs,
and now pipelines, user triggered async events,
that kind of thing.
We've used a lot of them, airflow,
we've used cron jobs on a scheduler, lambda functions.
They all have their headaches.
I was here last year talking to a bunch of people about it.
People had solutions and work around,
they had workarounds, but not really solutions, right?
So we came across something called temporal,
one of my colleagues did,
and it's really made running workflows a lot easier,
primarily because we get to type the inputs and the outputs.
So I'm not gonna go into temporal too much,
they have a booth, go talk to them.
This is what it looks like, there's a server,
a bunch of workers, and a web UI.
You can scale the workers like you would
any container on your deployment.
This is the web UI, right?
You can see I have two workflows here,
one that completed, one that failed.
When you go into it, you can see a little more detail
and including the payloads.
So let's look at some code.
This is a basic sample workflow.
I'm not gonna go into detail,
but one thing you notice here, there's a model.
And that model uses object IDs,
which you'll note are not JSON serializable.
We define an activity, it prints those IDs,
and a workflow that runs them.
At the bottom of this workflow,
we also define the activities.
We've configured it so we can just define
all of our workflows with YAML files,
which really makes deployment so easy.
And then we run a little code to deploy them to the worker.
So typing, we use PyDantic.
I bet a lot of you do.
Within PyDantic, we customized it to do
JSON serialization of our object IDs.
So all we had to do was write a data converter for PyDantic,
and we used that as our data converter,
and now we're just passing around
PyDantic models between tasks.
Also, it's pretty Pythonic.
You can use normal Python code.
So one of the things with workflows
is you wanna see when they fail,
and you don't wanna have to write that code
over and over and over again for every workflow.
So I just wrote a base workflow class.
It has three methods.
It logs when a workflow starts, when it completes,
and it raises a critical error when it fails.
And then you can see here, to run that, it's pretty easy.
I just have my workflow as per usual,
and right here you see if the failure error is caught,
then I just run this method, and it logs it,
and then I get a Slack alert.
So that's typing with workflows using Temporal.
We found it really easy.
We can use PyDantic, and it makes life so much easier
to debug and test our workflows.
If you have questions, let me know.
I wanna thank my team at Unified,
Jack Lecha and Brian Vanderhoof who stood this up,
the community at Temporal, and obviously PyCon
for letting us share our little learnings along the way.
Thank you.
Thank you so much for that.
Next we have Paul, who in talking with them
about being an employee at Indeed,
who is one of our sponsors, I had a really fun moment
when I was like, yes, Indeed, I will make sure
to reference that.
My own silly humor.
But anyways, let's pass it over to Paul to take it away.
Okay, great, thank you.
So last year or so I was involved with going through
sort of a survey of significant Python changes,
code changes by version as part of some upgrade projects
and as part of some book writing.
So I'll go through one of the things that we found
as part of this survey was this change in the stir function.
So common function that we use a lot,
all strip and Rstrip typically for removing white space.
But if used, it can actually maybe remove a little more
than you would want.
So if we look at this line of code,
who knows what this is going to print?
Yes, L.com, yes.
You would think that it's going to return shell.com,
but this is not the string to remove,
but this is the list of characters
that Lstrip is going to remove.
And all of these characters are in that set.
In version 3.9, we got the new features,
remove prefix, remove suffix.
And so this would be more properly written this way.
So what we found when talking to our different networks
of people using Python, companies were looking
at their code bases and they found that they were using
Lstrip and Rstrip perhaps in some,
it uncovered some latent bugs in their code.
And so this is something that you might want to do
as an item when you head home.
Look at the Lstrip and Rstrip that you have.
Calls that take the no argument form, not a problem,
but it's those that take a quoted string of some sort.
Might want to review and make sure that it's doing
what you really want.
So this was actually done as part of the work
on the latest edition of Python in a nutshell.
It covers latest versions of 3.7 up through 3.11.
And so as part of that work,
I was talking with the other authors
and really wanted to have a good catalog
by version of what were the different changes in there.
So people could plan their Python upgrades and so forth.
And also we added an appendix with detailed information.
So this is one page from the appendix
and you can see that by version we have
the different changes, whether they're additions, removals,
whether it's a breaking change or not.
And here's the remove for 3.9,
remove prefix and remove suffix.
So it turns out that even if you don't buy the book,
this information is available at a website
that we have open so that you can just go to,
and this is the QR code for that website,
if you care to record that.
And then I'm going to try the live demo.
Try the live demo.
So here if I put in the stir,
what are all the changes related to the stir class?
And then we can see, okay, well,
there's is asking was added in 3.7,
there's remove profits.
Oh, why not?
Windows B.
All right, that's not what I wanted.
Here we go.
Yes, so okay, thank you.
So I'll go back and I wasted some of my precious time too.
Okay, so if I put in stir,
now I can see these are the results that we get.
And for you, for those of you doing the challenge,
you have some points now, there's some 3.11 features.
You can put in other things.
You can put in a version as well,
so I could put in 3.11,
and those are all the changes that were new.
So this is an open website for you to do
release planning or upgrade planning
for your own install base.
And that's my talk.
Thank you.
And yeah, it's very scary when you are giving a lightning talk
and you're having technical difficulties.
So I guess if you kind of, you know,
unfortunately running out of time,
you can give your talk again tomorrow at the open space.
And our next speaker, David, is going to,
so his talk is definitely not written by Chatchi BT,
so enjoy.
Yeah, sorry, my talk doesn't have any Chatchi BT.
Instead, I'm gonna tell you about my experience
submitting Crozetta to Pi OpenSci.
I'm David Nicholson.
You can find me at all those places.
Who am I?
I'm a high school dropout.
I'm a failed rock star.
Later I got a PhD in neuroscience studying songbirds.
I'll tell you about that later.
I now think of myself as a research software engineer.
I'm active in US RSE,
and I also happen to be the current editor-in-chief
of Pi OpenSci.
So long story short,
I would say I have a very non-traditional background.
So from personal experience,
I really know why we need to work on inclusivity
in science and software.
And that's a big part of the Pi OpenSci mission,
which is why I'm really proud to be part of the organization.
I'm also somebody who just submitted a package there.
I guess you could call that dog fooding,
but that word is gross, so I'm not gonna use it.
So Crozetta is a Python tool to work with any format
for annotating animal vocalizations and bioacoustics data.
So basically there's two ways you can annotate animal sounds.
You can make a bunch of lines,
or you can make a bunch of rectangles.
Sometimes you make a bunch of dots.
There's like a thousand different tools for doing this,
and it wasn't easy to work with all their annotation formats in Python
and not easy to share that in a simple flat file format
like a CSV or JSON.
And so this is part of a research software community
for people that study animal communication.
So basically how an actually intelligent being
would actually communicate instead of a stochastic parrot
that just randomly regurgitates the internet.
So there is actually a chat GPT reference in my talk.
Thank you. You can laugh at that joke.
Or cry.
So when you submit to PyOpenSci, it will go through me
or a board of editors-in-chief that replaces me,
but I instead had to go to the executive director, Lea Wasser.
If you want to find out everything about PyOpenSci,
you should watch her maintainer summit talk,
should read our blog post, check out our guides.
I went to her and I said, hey, if I was the editor for my own submission,
would that be a conflict of interest?
And she said, yes, you should not do that.
So she found an editor, Chiara Marmo,
who's way too smart for me to fit into a lightning talk,
but for our purposes what matters is that she's been a project manager,
contributor to Scikit-learn, AstroPy, many core scientific Python packages.
She started the review by doing some initial checks
and then by finding two reviewers.
The first of which was Tessa Reinhardt,
who's a very awesome grad student in the KitSys lab.
They also have a poster here you should see tomorrow.
And she has this bioacoustic software resource on GitHub.
If you want to see some of the 1,000 tools that are out there
that give you these annotation formats,
sure, she's a perfect person to tell me,
is Crozetta going to help her work with those formats in Python?
And during her review, she helped me fix up issues with her tutorials.
She gave me feedback on how easy it was for another human being
to set up a development environment
and pointed out that I needed a linting session.
So already that leveled me up.
Sylvain Halper, who's the other reviewer, he developed Scikit-M.A.D.
He's one of the developers.
This is for working with soundscapes in Python.
And he contributed an initial implementation of a class
for working with the format from Raven.
This is an application out of the lab of ornithology in Cornell
and also spotted a bunch of issues with the test and documentation.
Then we brought in a technical expert, Yannick Yadul.
He develops ParcelMath.
It's a wrapper for a prot, which is a tool for doing phonetics.
And he basically helped me parse the prot format text grids.
So thank you, Yannick.
And he also contributed in many other ways
I don't have time to talk about.
Then because PyOpenSci partners with Joss,
the Journal of Open Source Software,
we had an expedited review with them.
Olivia Guest was the editor.
And in this case, she basically just had to check off some boxes.
If you want to read some really clear, incisive writing
on computational cognitive science and AI,
you should check out her papers.
That's an aside.
So Crozetta is now officially a PyOpenSci package.
PyOpenSci review in review, I'm going to borrow an analogy from the SciPy
maintainer's track this year.
It's about tending the open source scientific software garden.
So there is an idea from philosophy of science
that science is actually just people working together, just community.
Maybe we've heard some of that here this year.
This becomes obvious in scientific software.
So if I can paraphrase Brett Cannon, I came to PyOpenSci
for the science and programming language.
And I've stayed to help tend the community garden.
I hope maybe some of you will as well.
Thanks.
Thank you.
Pretty cool to see the Journal of Open Source Software up there.
I know we have some folks in this community who are editors.
I've actually collaborated with them as an editor.
So if anyone is curious about that, I'd
be happy to talk to you about it.
That being said, I'm going to go ahead and pass it over to Mario.
And I'm just going to let you take it away.
OK.
Because I move a lot.
Hello, PyCon.
Are you ready for a lot of slides and a live demo in five minutes?
So yeah, yeah, get excited.
So everyone loves f-strings, right?
And I'm here to show you what you already know, which is like f-strings.
You can put the string.
You put some placeholders.
And you can get some nice content out of them.
But there is a lot more on f-strings than that, hopefully, you know about.
If you go and read the documentation, something I love to do whenever
you're using any Python feature, I really encourage you to go and read about it.
Because I'm sure we are rewriting a lot.
That's already part of the standard library.
You'll find that there is the specification of what you can do with f-strings.
And the first part is the f-expression.
And that basically means that you can put whatever you want as far as it's
an expression within an f-string.
So here you can see that, for example, we don't need to pre-compute this variable.
We can just show it as part of the f-string.
And that works.
You can also find some other cool things, like, for example,
this conversion part of the grammar.
What this allows you to do is you can pass the exclamation mark r.
And that's going to show you the wrapper of the variable that you put in the f-string.
You think, OK, like, here for a string, it will just show you the name within quotes.
Not that useful.
But if you print exceptions, this is extremely useful.
Because it's going to show you the exception time.
How many times have you seen a log that it includes an exception.
It's just the key of the key error.
It's horrible, right?
Use the wrapper for it.
It's amazing.
And what else can you do?
We can also use the format space, something that, again, I find really useful.
How can you use this out?
There is another section in the documentation.
I will tell you everything that you can do with it.
Read about it.
And some cool examples is that we saw that before we had the float,
and it was showing 375.0.
You can just use the format to just say, like, I don't want any decimals.
And then you don't need to convert that to an integer before printing it, right?
All of us have done that.
What else can we find in the documentation?
You can find that you can align and pad the variable that you're printing.
How is this useful?
Here, for example, you might think that it's not so useful.
But here in Madrid, there are spaces around it.
With this upper arrow and 10, you're saying that you want at least 10
characters to be printed when you're formatting that string.
What's doing is basically padding it with spaces.
But what's really cool is that you can choose what you want to use for padding.
You can use some modges if you want, and you can get this kind of cool strings.
But if you want something useful, I'm sure that you have printed sometimes
a file of the output of a subprocess, and you have manually crafted this.
You don't need to do that.
Like, the FString format already has this for you.
Also, don't forget about the backstrings.
You can just put a W, and it's going to print as well the name of the variable.
And if you want to go crazy, you can have a custom class that defines
that Dunder format, and you can pass whatever you want to it.
You can have a really cool Boolean that's able to format the Booleans as emojis or
whatever you want.
And I'm going to show you that as part of the demo.
So in case you don't trust me, here is, not this one.
So here is the same code that I showed you before.
And I run it, and you can see that it's true.
And the happy emoji face and the sparklings, right?
And the sparklings don't appear.
What is going on?
Oh no, this is a lightning talk.
If I now want to debug this, maybe I add a lot of print statements, or
they run PDB, or maybe I have to run GDB and then attach.
Like, what could I do to figure out what's going on?
Oh, PyStack.
Oh, amazing.
Yeah, have you heard about this new cool tool?
You can just run PyStack remote, pass the PID or something, and
you see the Python stack of the program that you're running.
But you might say, yeah, but is this really useful?
I want to see the variables inside.
You can do that.
You can just pass dash dash locals, and it will show you as well the locals that
this in the function that it's running.
So useful, right?
And I know, Mario, this is really helpful, but I work doing C extensions.
Don't worry, we got you covered.
You can also pass dash dash native, and it's going to show you as well
the C native code of the function that you're running.
So useful, I have this tool at hand, right?
And where I was presenting?
Yeah, so this talk was totally about F strings.
It was not about PyStack.
So please, if you are ever using any Python feature that you find
interesting and you find yourself writing code around it, I would really
recommend that you go and read the docs, because many times, a lot of the code
that you write is already written.
And I still have 10 seconds.
Look, this is a function you probably didn't know about.
The string, the F string code is going to get rewritten.
Check out that.
We have PyStack pancakes.
Three seconds.
This is my home city.
You can go visit it.
It's amazing.
Thank you.
I feel like I've just watched a whole variety show in five minutes.
Yeah, that's actually Mario getting his talk in, because he kind of sneakily
put Lorena's name in the talk title.
That's why, you know.
So next year, you can try to be smarter than maybe you would get selected.
So our next talk is by Jessica, talking about malware donation pipelines.
Yeah, let's get dangerous.
So hello, my name is Jessica.
I'm a senior data engineer at Elastic.
I like to call myself the lady of the data lake.
I'm also an emoji enthusiast.
Here are some of my faves.
And I'm also devoted cat mom to Rupert and Xander.
Come ask me about them later.
We'll have a hallway track about our cats.
But also, I want to talk about what I do at Elastic.
So I work on the protection services teams.
We're a group of cats and dogs who build cloud services and data systems
that enable our internal threat research team.
So what does that actually mean?
So we sit around and we talk about how well is Elastic Security defending
against real world or emerging threats?
And this is very difficult, because what you have to do
is you need to blow up the malware in order
to know if we're catching the alerts, if we're detecting on our agent.
And if you want to do this manually, it takes a lot of effort.
You have to get a VM, make sure it doesn't spread that malware
to the rest of your team.
You have to make sure it's connected to Elastic,
set up some infrastructure, all these other things.
So for the past two years, we've been building a service called Detonate.
Started my coworker Joe Desimone and maintained by myself
and mostly Sergey Polzanov, who's been amazing.
This runs malware and other malicious or potentially malicious software
in a controlled environment.
We have the full suite of Elastic Security available.
I promise this is not a vendor plug or anything,
but we want to make sure we're defending against all threats
against our own product.
And we use this as security researchers to make sure we can measure
the efficacy of our solution in an automated fashion.
Oh, sorry. We need to protect the net.
That's a hockey joke.
So this is a terrifying diagram that we're going to go through
in the next few slides.
But what I wanted to kind of show is sort of where our Python
and friends kind of start.
We're going to go into this in a lot more detail.
So hold on to your horses.
So the first thing that we do is we prepare our task data.
And the way that we set up Detonate is to basically start
with an API server.
We use fast API with Pydantic for type verification
and making sure everything's well structured.
And then we dump things in basically from queue to worker to queue.
And we go kind of through this cycle.
And each worker is very easily extensible.
All it requires you to have is a name of the incoming,
potentially outbound queue, as well as kind of what the worker
is supposed to do so we can build out more workers if we need.
But this first one is basically going to prepare our task data.
We want to be able to get this malicious file from a third party
source. We use virus total or malware.
Bizarre here.
And we post kind of the files, including the malware
and some startup scripts for our virtual machines into a bucket.
Then we go on to our next worker,
which will start the virtual machine.
We make sure we have enough resources and then we do our
infrastructure setup.
In this case, we're using GCP for Windows and Linux
or AWS for Mac OS on top of Anka.
We get all the files from GCS.
We get our startup scripts set up.
We also register this VM with our elastic age with the elastic
cluster. And then we wait until it's done.
This takes about two to five minutes or we do time out if it fails.
Tear down all the infrastructure, post some logs to the bucket,
put our alerts in the right cluster.
And then we make a human readable summary.
This will grab that job.
We'll basically go look at the alerts in the stack.
We're going to take a lot of that information and make it
a little bit more readable for our threat intelligence researchers.
The raw JSON can be quite verbose,
has a lot of maybe unnecessary information.
So this allows us to pare it down a little bit.
And that's the end of the pipeline.
But you may have noticed on top,
I didn't talk about that little task updates queue.
Every time we move between workers,
we're able to index an update to another elastic cluster.
So we can gather all this and then look at what workers are running,
how long did it take, et cetera.
So we can go do some debugging.
But also we get to use our awesome CLI tool.
So here's Python.
We haven't gotten to friends quite yet,
but this is using Click and Rich.
So we can use our CLI to put that in there.
And then we can see all the steps as they output,
which is very awesome.
But we also have a website that we have internally called
Protections Portal.
This is built on the elastic UI and TypeScript.
You can enter in a hash for detonation,
and you can see all these awesome results here.
If you want to demo that tomorrow, I can show you.
But really, this talk is about Python and friends.
So while Python is at the core of what we do,
we have a lot of various other pieces of technology
that support this, everything from cloud infrastructure
to Docker containers and Terraform
to using the elastic stack itself.
But even within Python, we have a lot of very good friends.
This is just a very small subset of the kinds of libraries
that we're using, all of which we love.
We talked about PyTest love earlier.
Hi.
But all these different things help us make detonate.
So thank you very much.
If you want to grab me for a hallway track
to learn more about protecting against threats using Python,
you can come find me tomorrow.
We have a blog series about detonate,
the one in the in-depth Python stuff should come out this month.
Again, big shout out to Sergey, who did all this work.
Thank you to the Canadian Internet Registration Authority
for these great stock photos, and find me on the internet.
Thank you so much.
As a fellow lady of the lake and a very big cat enthusiast,
I am very plus one about a cat hallway track.
So sign me up.
So now for our next talk, we're going to have Eric take us away
talking about isolating extension modules.
All right.
So my name is Eric Snow.
I'm a Python core developer, and I gave a talk yesterday
about per interpreter GIL.
So today we're going to talk about one
of the things I didn't talk about yesterday,
which is how this relates to extension modules.
So extension modules have to be isolated from each other
because they're per interpreter.
And so they have to be isolated
from each other in the same way.
Before I get into that, I want to say pretty much all the stuff
I'll talk about right now is made possible by the effort
of Peter Victor and another one of our core developers.
And just I want to applaud his effort.
I also want to say thanks to the captioners because as just
like last year, they've been doing a great job.
OK. So who does this relate to?
People who create or maintain extension modules.
Not everybody, but it's quite a few people.
What does it relate to?
Your extension modules.
When should you worry about this?
Now, if you want to.
This, a lot of these APIs have been around since Python 3.5,
but it's really going to matter starting in 3.12
and increasingly so.
So start thinking about it at least.
Where do you want to work on it?
You know. So why does this matter?
There are lots of reasons, but the main one,
like I was saying, it helps.
If you want to support multiple interpreters,
you need to do this stuff, which is the multi-phase init.
And pep 630 defined exactly what people need to do.
It got turned into a how-to document.
So you can go look at that.
It's really clear.
What do you got to do?
There are kind of four things really you got to do.
That last one is support for a per interpreter gill.
So for the actual supporting multiple interpreters themselves
without the per interpreter gill, you need the first three.
The first one, you got to convert static types to heap types.
And so it involves these steps more or less.
You got to take your static types and turn them,
make a new array of high type slots
and these different things.
So that how-to kind of walks through this stuff.
I have some slides here.
I'm going to skip them.
So the next thing, you got to take any global variables you
got and move them into what's called module state.
It's pretty straightforward.
May take a little work.
Depends on how you're using your global variables,
how many you got.
Again, that how-to document spells it out pretty well.
And then for multi-phase init, once you
got those other two things done,
you implement multi-phase init.
It's actually really straightforward.
And there's not much more to it.
Depending on how big your extension is,
it doesn't really matter.
There's just you take the init function you got
and you convert it over into your exec function.
You set up module slots.
And the how-to document explains it really well.
And then the last thing with the external global state.
So when you have a library that you're
relying on that has external state,
you can't do a whole lot about that.
You got to figure out how to manage that.
Mostly you got to figure out if you have that sort of dependency.
And if you do, you got to figure out
how to make sure it's thread safe.
Maybe throw some locks around how you access it.
You got to make sure that your different instances
of your extension are handling that properly.
It shouldn't be that common, but it's something to be aware of.
If you want to help with this, give us feedback.
We've already got lots of feedback,
and Peter's been able to turn that
into a lot of really useful API.
We also have documentation that documentation can always
use some help.
And anything else you can help with, just let us know.
So again, it's kind of these three and then fourth step.
And that's it.
RO
Sorry I was organizing something.
Thank you so much.
And next, we have something about A Solomon.
Presented by Felipe.
Thank you.
Hi, so today they're going to talk about A Solomon
and how we are doing black activity with technology in Brazil.
So first I will start with me.
I'm called Felipe Demoraj, but you find me on the internet
by Felipe Python.
And some people ask me if that's how my mom called me.
That's true.
My mom called me Felipe Python.
I'm a software engineer.
I'm also the co-founder of AfroPython.
I'm a Jiu-Jitsu blue belt.
If you like Jiu-Jitsu, like come talk to me.
I also speak four languages.
I have been to ten countries so far, four continents.
And I try to be healthy.
I'm also a dog father, so I'll show a picture of my dog here.
That's Pasoca.
A little message here.
And she is my second adoption.
Actually, I am the second adoption of hers.
Because at the first adoption she was mistreated,
and she was given back to the place that she was born.
And I adopted her.
And since then she is very scared because she was beaten
when she was pooping in the wrong place.
So if I'm going to take a pet, it can be a cat, a dog,
please take care of Van very well, please.
Okay. Going back to AfroPython, that's how we started.
And actually we came from a lot of women in IT events,
especially jungle girls.
And we understood that there was no incentive for black people
in IT as we have for women in IT.
So we decided to start an event that started as a workshop.
This is our first meeting.
And it started to grow.
We had our first event that was a workshop in south of Brazil.
And more and more people get interested in AfroPython
and Python itself.
And as the time passed, we have more conferences and more time.
And this was one of the biggest conference that we,
biggest workshop that we have done.
And after that we made a conference.
It was 2019.
And we realized that there was company willing to sponsor us
and gave us support.
And we wanted to give, to bring this change
for more people as well.
So we decided to make a company out of AfroPython
that would be especially a boot camp where people are going
to come for free, the students.
But the company is going to be sponsoring
so we can hire the people.
And we start to make this change that we want to make
to bring more black people to IT in a scaled way.
This is our last event in person.
Before that actually we had an online conference as well
that went pretty well.
But we don't have as many photos
as we have for the in-person events.
And after that we decided that we want
to have a second conference that will be held in Salvador,
the same city where this happened.
I recall the pre-conference.
Actually part of this is in Portuguese.
If you want to learn a language, that's your chance.
So we're going to have a conference in the middle
of this year, 22 of July.
If you want to come, if you're interested in,
or maybe next year, come talk to me.
And I'm going to do something different this year.
I will call for an open space for black people in IT.
Especially at PyCon we want to take a picture and see how many
of us we are and how we can connect to each other.
And if you want to come, please come and we're going to chat.
That's what I have to talk.
That's Tafra Python and I am Felipe de Morais.
Thank you.
Fantastic.
Thank you so much.
I love all these open spaces.
It's always a really fun range of ones we hear,
be it if we're slightly being teased
about your lightning talk being selected
or really great empowerment of all the people in our community.
So now next up we're going to have Ross to take us away
on our next lightning talk.
Hello, I'm Ross Bryant.
I just clicked that slide too soon.
I lead Phyland's research team.
Thank you to the organizers for giving me the opportunity.
This is my first PyCon and I'm learning a lot
about lightning talks and open spaces and overloaded acronyms.
This invitation grabbed my attention yesterday
and I bounded up the escalators brimming with excitement
to talk with fellow security researchers.
But the group that was leaving said they needed
to make way for the sysadmins.
So I leaned over and asked,
isn't this for software reverse engineers?
Never even heard of that term.
This is for site reliability engineering.
Well, farewell and good luck with your nines.
I have to go now.
So I want to talk to you about code obfuscation,
specifically PyPI packages that contain obfuscated code
that is itself malware or is malicious code
that ends up putting malware on your machine.
Nearly daily our automated platform detects obfuscated
packages such as these and we report these
to the PyPI security team and they're fantastic by the way.
Both of these are easy to deobfuscate
and what you find underneath is that each starts
with an import statement and ends with malware dropped
on your machine just as soon as you pip installed either of them.
But for this talk they serve as minimal examples
of what any obfuscation really intends.
And that is, it's hard, it increases the difficulty
for someone to reason about the code,
including the original author.
More about that in a moment.
But this is typical of what we find in report.
Pretty standard stuff.
Lots of things there that we see across many obfuscated packages.
This one was particularly nasty
in that it dropped a remote access tool
on your machine written in Golang.
We have a blog post about that one.
Next slide.
This one was part of a massive typo squatting campaign
that dropped a crypto wallet stealer.
We have an entire blog post about a postmortem for this attack.
It was about 900 packages typo squatting, about 40
of the most popular packages across a wide variety of interests.
So if you typed Matt Pult lib like I've typed so many times
in my life and pip installed that, you got malware.
And even though there's identifiers in this file
that use non-ASCII, the Unicode abuse that this talk focuses
on comes from this sample.
So at first glance we see a number of the usual tricks.
Dunder import, B64, B64 decode, Zlib decompress.
But what, in fact this ended up being just a Discord token stealer
but a Discord token stealer today is an SSH key stealer tomorrow.
And these are in vogue right now.
But this caught my eye and I said this can't possibly work.
Like we see malware that gets published
and the guys don't even test it and it doesn't even work.
To me I thought, no this doesn't work.
It can't possibly work.
None of those self-identifiers are the same string.
Like this just can't be true.
Right? I mean self does not equal self.
Even though maybe if you're at the back you can't see,
if you look at the Unicode code points or the names,
they're just two different strings altogether.
And so I began reading the Python language reference
and in chapter two I discovered that this is a design feature.
The parser and the Python interpreter normalizes Unicode
in some identifiers.
And so this means that though two source code files could be
different while being visually similar,
the Python interpreter sees them as the same.
And this is the advantage of this obfuscation.
It's still readable.
Self still looks like self.
But any string matching or regex is looking
for the canonical ASCII self, they're going to be blind to this.
And so this raised my curiosity because I'm a mathematician.
How many different ways can you do this?
How many different variants are there of self?
There's 19 S's where S like characters that normalize
down to lowercase S. Thank you Ned
for telling me what lowercase means now.
And so there's about 122,000 ways you can write self.
And that's not a terribly exciting identifier
to look for when you're looking for malicious code.
But these are, you can see there's a lot
of digits in those numbers.
They're big.
Dunder import, subprocess, crypt, unprotect data.
And so what's the takeaway here?
The takeaway is that many of the state of the art obfuscation
detectors count many things, including function calls.
But if they're not normalizing these prior to counting,
all the counts are going to be wrong.
Moreover, the string, the regex
and string matching will be blind
to all the Unicode variants.
I hear you.
Even though this technique is noteworthy,
it allows this guy to hide in plain sight.
We can reason about the code and so can he.
So it's a strange obfuscation scheme.
This is the link to our research blog
where you'll find all the details that I suppressed here
at our Discord channel.
And I'm happy to talk about anyone later about this.
Thank you so much.
And then we have, next we'll have Juliana talking
about something that I found very scary personally is ETL.
Okay, I need the, there you go.
Can you hear me?
No? Okay, can you hear me now?
Wait. Can you hear me?
Now I got it.
What about this?
This one is fine too.
I don't think I need it.
Sorry. Hi. My name is Juliana.
I'm a software engineer and my talk today is called ETL,
Extract Transform Load, AKA life of a data engineer.
That's my mastodon.
So what is a data engineer?
It's a person who works in a variety of settings
to build systems that collect, manage, and convert raw data
into usable information for many different people in a company
like data scientists, business analysts, and so on.
So the goal of a data engineer is to make data accessible
so the organizations can use this data to evaluate
and optimize the performance or improve business.
The most common method used
in data engineer is the ETL, which stands for,
oh, it's a bit, sorry.
Sure. So ETL stands for extract, transform, load.
So let's go each of them.
Extract, it's when we extract the relevant data
from the source database, transform the data
so it's better suited for analytics and load the data
into a target database.
So I'm going to give an example of a recent project I work,
where I work.
So I work at this company called Remix, which is a software
that urban planners use to plan the cities.
And we usually bring data to Remix
so the urban planners can use this data to make better plans.
And one of the data we usually bring is the census data.
So what I did this year was bringing the Canadian census
data to Remix.
So you can see in this diagram, it's pretty simple,
but we have the Canadian census website.
We have the local database and the production database,
which will be the end goal.
So let's go for each of the process separately.
Extract, look at those guys.
They are moving data from one place to another.
And that's exactly what we do, like using Python scripts.
So we extract the data from the original source and load it
to a temporary database.
In Canadian census example, we extracted the data
from the Canadian census website to my local machine.
Transform, magic, that's where the magic happens.
Some ways we can transform data.
We can clean data, fit standards so we can use the data,
join different kinds of data, deduplicate data,
convert data into a consistent format.
And in the Canadian census example,
we join the census data with geographical information
because we needed to visualize that in Remix,
which is a map-based software.
So transformation is usually made using SQL, joining data,
creating and populating tables, creating the necessary indices.
Load. There are the guys again moving data from place to another.
So we just move the data from the temporary database
to a permanent place, usually a database that lives in production.
In Canadian census, we move the final table from a local database
to Remix production database.
After that, we can then create the data sets and layers,
which is what our customers will use in the Remix platform.
So the final result, let me see if that loads.
So, okay, this is the Remix platform.
This is the Canada map.
So here we have the data layers.
Population was one of the layers that we created.
And if you go for each block,
you can see the population amount for each block.
And that's the final result of this project.
That was my talk. Thanks for listening. Thank you.
APPLAUSE
Thank you so much for that talk.
And now for our last lightning talk of day two, afternoon talks.
We have Tyler who's going to go ahead and take it away.
Cool. Thank you, everyone.
I wanted to say thank you. This is my first time being at any conference
related to any sort of open source software.
I have been in the community for years,
but this is my first time actually meeting people in person.
And you all are so wonderful. So thank you so much.
APPLAUSE
So my name is Tyler Menezes. Here's a photo of me,
very embarrassing photo of me from when I was younger.
And I work for a non-profit.
You may have seen us over in the community spaces.
And we work helping get community college students
into open source software contributions.
So you may be thinking, community colleges, why community colleges?
Did you know that community colleges can give out bachelor's degrees now?
In most states.
Did you know that community colleges cost like $5,000 a year in tuition?
Which for those of you international, that may sound like a lot.
For those of you in the US, that's not very much.
So because of this, a lot of the students who go to these schools
are lower income. They work for service industry jobs, et cetera.
Really interesting backgrounds.
And recruiters don't come to community colleges, right?
That no one is, no companies are going to community colleges
and trying to get these students into tech jobs.
So we found that if we can get students some open source experience,
they're about twice as likely to get a job.
They're more confident. It's great.
So I'm here to talk to you today about how you can help students like this
get into open source software.
This talk is focused for maintainers.
How many people here consider yourself a maintainer?
OK, how many people here have at least one GitHub repo
that has like maybe a hundred lines of code or more?
OK, everyone here is a maintainer.
This is all we need because a lot of these students just need really,
really simple, easy things to get started with.
So this talk is for everyone here.
So what are the things we can do to help make open source software,
even small repositories, more accessible to beginner contributions?
First one, contributing .md file, right?
This is table stakes.
Every repository who wants to be friendly to beginners
needs a contributing .md file.
Resources, what should people look into?
What are the coding conventions and the code styles?
Is there a code of conduct? Things like that.
That should go into the contributing file.
Second thing, development environment.
This should probably also be in the contributing file,
but I want to call this out specifically.
There are a lot of very large open source projects
that if you follow their instructions,
the development environment that you will set up does not actually work
and you will spend an hour trying to troubleshoot it.
If you're a student who is new to open source software, that sucks.
It's going to take you a week. It's awful.
So check it regularly.
Make sure your development environment instructions
in your contributing file are actually working.
Should work for Linux and Mac and also ideally Windows.
A lot of lower income students who want to start contributing to this
don't have money for a Mac and maybe haven't learned that much about Linux.
Even if it just says to install WSL so you can run Linux on Windows,
call it out.
Third thing, continuous integration with linting and tests.
When someone opens a pull request, it's really helpful
if they get feedback right away instead of having to wait a month
because they're probably going to be pretty demoralized
if they waited a month and their pull request gets rejected
because they didn't use the right coding conventions.
So to help students avoid easy pitfalls.
Fourth thing, architecture.md.
This is how the pieces of your project fit together
and how information flows between the different files and modules.
If you want to create one of these for your project
and you don't know what to do, search for architecture.md
just on Google. There's some really, really great resources out there
that will help you put together a really good one for your project.
And the fifth one is having good first issue tasks.
Speaking of which, okay, so here's my sort of sub points.
A good first issue, what does it mean to be a good first issue
for a beginner? It should be self-contained, right?
Something that's solved in one file or maybe a couple of files
but it shouldn't be that hard to follow the flow through the thing.
You have some initial idea of probably how likely this is.
It should be clear. There should be enough data in the issue itself
that they don't have to ask you for clarification
because beginners are terrified of you.
They think you all are so cool.
I think you all are so cool too, by the way.
But the beginners especially think you're so cool
that they don't want to bother you with their stupid questions.
So it should be clear. It should be decided.
You shouldn't have to have a discussion with the maintainer
about what needs to be done.
And lastly, it should be recent.
It's not obvious to students if issues that are six months old
are still valid and if they spend like a week or two
getting their development environment set up,
that kind of sucks if it turns out they couldn't do anything.
Okay, so five seconds if you want to take a screenshot.
If you want to take a picture, there's your cheat sheet.
So if you are a maintainer, try to have your project do these things.
It's really helpful.
Last thing I wanted to call out, we are a nonprofit.
I'm not going to pitch you too much, but we are a nonprofit.
We're looking for mentors.
So if you're interested in mentoring students
a couple hours a week, visit that first link.
And if you're an open source project
that wants to help contribute issues
that these students can work on, visit that second link right there
and we'll actually help you write those good first issues even.
So thank you all so much. You've been wonderful.
And I hope to see you at the next PyCon.
Well, thank you so much everyone for participating
in the day two afternoon lightning talks.
We are now going to go run to the PyLadies auction.
So if you do have questions for us, find us later, not right now.
But again, we are still collecting those slides.
Again, we're both visible on Twitter.
If you are a mastodon, we're also there as well.
Or we are in the staff room.
So feel free to find us and have a great rest of your evening.
Thank you.
Bye.