Good morning everybody.
I told you I would sing.
That's a lot of singing.
I want to just say a huge thank you
because this is actually your first year helping running
Lightning Talks and you've been a fantastic co-MC.
So just a round of applause for all of our volunteers here.
Thank you so much.
And also I thank you for like taking care of me
because you handle a lot of logistics and stuff
which I found it very confusing
because my brain is not working very well.
As you can tell, we have not sleep a lot during the conference.
Indeed, indeed.
So welcome to day three.
So what's on the agenda for today?
Well today, so it's kick off with a very amazing session
is the Lightning Talks session
but it's a very special session
because we will start off with not just your normal
Lightning Talks but with a community announcement
which you will see how it works.
It's like super quick, a lot of conference,
your mind will be blown by the end of it
because there's so many events.
Fantastic.
And then I also heard that there is a,
oh again, there's, if you did apply to do a Lightning Talk
and for some reason it didn't get selected,
today at noon there is an open source space.
I believe it's called the Lightning Talks
they didn't want you to hear.
So you can go check that out
or you could just go and listen to people talk
and trying to think about any other housekeeping items.
Oh, what about the sprints?
Yes, so please stay after the keynote today
at the last keynote today because at 5 p.m. at this room
because for those of you who have never been to the sprints
please come because there will be orientation
tell you what is a sprint, what project you can sprint on.
But those of you who have been to the sprint
also come here because then you will know
what project you can work on tomorrow.
Fantastic.
Well I think with that,
do you wanna go ahead and kick it off?
Yeah, sure.
So like I said, the first will be community announcements
so our first community speaker is here already
so they all only got like 30 seconds for each slide
so you have to be really paying attention
because they will be quick, okay?
So let's start now.
Hi, so my name is Felipe, my mom called me Felipe Aitan
and we're gonna host a conference in Brazil
and a conference focused on black people in IT
and if you wanna join, that's the date, 22 of July
and we also are gonna having a open space today at 2 p.m.
at room 250C for black people at PyCon
and you are welcome to come to Brazil.
Bye bye, thank you.
Thank you so much.
And I'm here to talk about Python Brazil as well.
Python Brazil is the biggest Python conference in Brazil.
We get together all the local communities in Brazil
and go to this big PyCon that we have called
Python Brazil every year.
This year is gonna take place in Caxias do Sul
which is kind of like in the south.
We're a huge, warm, loving, welcoming community
of Python developers and we would like to invite you all
to attend and see it for yourself.
We're also looking for sponsors
so if your company is interested,
just like hit me up and yeah.
Hello, North Bay Python is the San Francisco Bay Area's
one track Python conference.
This year we're back after a three year break
returning to Petaluma, California,
just 35 miles north of San Francisco.
It'll be on July the 29th and 30th
before the Californian summer gets too harsh.
This year our venue is a barn on a 600 acre ranch.
There are cows and horses and friendly venue cats.
Our call for proposals is now open
and closes on Friday, May the 19th.
I'm also here to invite you to the southern most
Python conference in the world, Kiwi PyCon,
which is taking place this year in Waihupai in Vicargo
in Aotearoa, New Zealand.
It's at the far south of New Zealand
but you can make it there with just one connection
from San Francisco, Los Angeles, Chicago,
Houston or New York, so super convenient.
The conference this year is on the 15th to 17th of September
which is the beginning of spring in the southern hemisphere.
If you want to take part, the call for proposals
is open from today until May the 19th
and if I've convinced you to come along,
there is a discount code right there on the slide.
So see you in Vicargo.
Hello, I'm Michael, I'm the organizer
of the Orlando Python Meetup.
There is a vibrant tech scene in Orlando,
it's more than just the theme parks.
So if you find yourself on vacation
and want to give a talk, we are always looking for speakers.
We will make a date work for you.
We'll create a meeting and we have a lot of our talks online.
You can reach me at pyorl.org and a lot of our past talks
can be found on YouTube at watch.pyorl.org.
Sorry, that's actually PyCon UK, so I'm representing them.
So PyCon UK is going back to the beautiful Cardiff City Hall
is actually like a historical building.
So if you have never been to a British historical
like Victorian style building, so this is your chance.
And it's in September 22nd.
So all the announcements, please check out their website.
I don't know when the CFP is open.
So next one also in the UK is,
but this time it's in other country technically
because it's in Scotland instead of in Wales.
So PyCon UK was the other one is in Wales.
This one, JungleCon is in Scotland,
is in 29th of May to 2nd of June is in Edinburgh.
Again, Edinburgh got a lot of beautiful castle.
So if you love beautiful country, beautiful castle,
beautiful things to do and drink a lot of whiskey,
then please come to JungleCon.
Next one.
Good morning.
I would like to invite you to a US IPI.
This is a European Conference for Python and Science.
It will be in the nice city of Basel in Switzerland.
We had this in the same place last year.
It's a very, very nice city.
It will be August 14 to 18.
We do have tutorials.
We have talks and we do have sprints.
We also have posters.
So the call for proposals is open to the end of the month.
So if you would like, you can still propose a talk,
a poster or a tutorial session.
See you in Basel.
Good morning.
After a brief absence, PyCon Australia is back this year
in Tandania, Adelaide, in the Adelaide Convention Center
on the banks of the Karawari Piri.
It is a multi-day conference,
a first day of specialist tracks,
incorporating an education track,
JungleCon Australia, all things data
and our connected universe.
Two days of regular tracks, including a PyCon fair,
and then two days of sprints.
Our call for papers is open right now
until the 14th of May.
For more details, PyCon.org.au.
Thank you.
Yeah, we love you.
Oh, sorry.
So this is PyGotham.
Also, I'm representing them.
So it's an online conference, so you don't have to travel.
You can see it from there.
You know, the domain is PyGotham.tv.
So they are very like a theme.
Then it's very cool.
So it's October 6 to 7, 2023.
So also, I think the CFP is open because there's a link there.
So check them out.
Next one.
So hello. We are Javi and Christian,
two of the organizers of this year's PyCon in Spain.
That takes place in the island.
If you are not aware of Tenerife in particular,
it's one of the most beautiful islands in the entire Europe.
We have beautiful beaches, a lot of nature to see and enjoy.
So yeah, this is a great opportunity.
As you see there, we will have an English talk as well.
So like here, we give space for people to speak Spanish.
There, we give space to people who speak in English.
So if you have any questions, please let us know.
That's the website.
And the call for paper ends in June 23rd.
All right.
I'm here for PyCon Taiwan.
So we timed it exactly right.
So it's too late for you to submit a proposal.
And it's too early for you to buy a ticket yet.
So what I want you to do now is just book this date
onto your schedule and just come.
And if the only problem stopping you is financialary
and not the long flights,
we do have financial aid programs that you can apply.
And we have everything you expect, good food, beer,
and occasionally conference talks.
And also something that you might not expect
that very exotic souvenirs and like live band performance
and things like that.
So yeah, we'll come with that.
Good morning.
My name is Lisa.
And I'm one of the organizers for Pyjamas,
the laziest conference on earth.
It is now in its fourth year.
And it's a 24-hour online conference
for all ranges of Python users.
It is free to attend.
But we encourage small donations
with all proceeds going to the PSF.
We're always looking for more volunteers
and organizers, more diversity.
So if you're looking for a conference you can watch
in your pajamas, go to our website, Pyjamas.live.
We're also on Twitter, LinkedIn, Instagram, and look
out for our call for proposals soon.
Thank you.
Okay, so this is me again, EuroPython.
So this year, EuroPython will be in Prague,
a very beautiful city.
I really love castles and like churches.
So that's why I can tell you I've been there in the castle
and churches there are amazing.
A lot of art.
And also it's in July, so weather will be nice, 17 to 23.
So check out the website.
And next one is PyCon Uganda.
So we have a new PyCon in Africa.
So for those of you who may not know,
there are actually PyCons in Africa, in different countries.
So this is a new one.
So if you go there, it could be your first PyCon in Africa.
So you know, it is their first as well.
So call for paper is now open.
Check out their website.
And PyBay Area Python Association.
So this slide also sent in by the organizers.
So these are the amazing, you know, user group
or communities that you can join.
So there are a few of them.
If you live around the area, please check them out
and join the events.
PyTexas.
Hello, my name is Mason, and I'm the organizer for PyTexas.
You just missed PyTexas.
It was three weeks ago.
But we already have next year's date, so we're good for that.
It's April 20th and 21st, 2024.
It'll be at the Austin Central Library in Austin, Texas.
Our CFP will be opening in Q4 of this year.
So keep an eye out for it.
And if you want to keep in contact with what's going on,
please follow us on all the socials
or join our mailing list,
and that's how we'll get the information to you.
Thank you.
Good morning.
I'm Rina Kataeo, the chairperson of PyCon APOC 2023 in Japan.
This year, the Japan team is organizing a conference
as PyCon APOC.
The dates are October 27th to 29th, Tokyo, Japan.
Now call for proper now open.
This will be given in English and in Japanese, of course.
I hope that it is about half in English and half in Japanese.
Our team would like to make this conference more
international than last year.
Please take this opportunity to visit the Pacific
and to please come to Japan.
Thank you.
Hi, I'm Ben.
I'm the chair, one of the co-chairs of PyCascades,
which is a regional conference in the Cascade region.
We are back in Seattle in 2024.
You may notice a lack of detail on this slide,
but you might have questions like what are the dates,
what's the venue, when's the CFP open,
and when do ticket sales open?
The answer to all of those questions and more
is to be determined, but you can help.
We are currently looking for organizers.
If you would like to help, you can email us
at organizers at PyCascades.com.
We're on all the socials as PyCascades,
and we are on mastodon at PyCascades at fostodon.org.
Thanks.
You shouldn't miss PyCascades.
Highly recommend it, but I'm going to tell you about another conference
that you shouldn't miss either.
It's the PyCon Latam.
My name is Andres.
She's Denny, and we are part of the PyCon Latam organizers.
This year, PyCon Latam is going to Monterey on August 24th, 26th.
There are four keynotes, two conference days, two tracks,
one in Spanish, one in English, a whole weekend
with all the PyCon enthusiasts.
But who's PyCon Latam?
Basically, we are the ones bringing PyCon awesomeness
to the Latin America communities.
And we have a big surprise for you.
We have a super early bird ticket available in this QR code.
Please go and enjoy.
Thank you.
And that is all the community announcements.
Fantastic.
So I've been to some of these conferences,
and they're really, really amazing.
I actually used to run a few years ago lightning talks at PyCascades.
So it's a slippery slope.
If you love volunteering, you can start at a regional conference
and then wind up up here one day.
So choose your own adventure.
But to kick off our lightning talk section now, we're going to go ahead
and kick it over to Greg, who's going to be talking to us a little bit
about Python and education.
Good morning.
That's all right.
I'm Greg Dante, and I'm here to talk about education, and in particular,
PCBL, which is personal competency-based learning.
I'll explain a little bit more about that.
First off, I'm from Kansas City, so clap if you're a Kansas City fan.
I knew it.
That's everyone.
Just a quick background on myself.
This is the little dance that I did for about 20 years plus of my career.
And then in terms of kind of just a quick personal view, this is some
of the roles that I play in life.
And then some of my hobbies, and as I look at this, I don't actually live
into any of these, so these are more aspirations, but I'm working on it.
And what am I doing now?
I'm a first-year educator, so I went from industry into education,
and I teach at a STEM school that focuses on prepping students
for the real world and real world learning.
So this is a sample of them at Summit Technology Academy,
where I work with a number of other teachers.
And we have 36 of them that came out to this conference,
and they're high school juniors and seniors.
So if you see anyone wearing the sort of STA polo, please introduce yourself.
So my big sort of when all you have is a hammer, everything's a nail moment,
is that courses are just projects in my mind when I take a look at them.
So as a first-year teacher, I just mapped everything
from what I was doing to education.
So when I see objectives and learnings, I just think of tickets and requirements
that go through a workflow, and especially one in, say, like a Kanban-type board
and visualization, and they're sized and estimated,
and you can work them in different priorities.
I see sprints, two-week sprints and iterations and percent completes
and deliverability of items otherwise called units in education,
but they kind of map into the same sort of concepts for projects for me, milestones.
And then the idea of visualizing how much is done, how much is left,
and just being able to see what's in the backlog and to prioritize backlogs.
So conveniently, all of these things were in GitHub, and GitHub also conveniently is
in the list of approved items that we can use as educators.
So why first PCBI said personal competency-based learning,
and it's a little bit more of a forward-thinking view into education,
so it's nontraditional, but big surprise, it's personalized.
And what that means is that it's individual to the student, and they can sort of self-pace
and grapple with the material in the way that's meaningful to them
and also align to their identity.
And then the focus of it is more on competency, not on grades,
and about sort of assessing that.
So in my classes, I have students that are really experienced and students
that are brand new, and to force them through kind of a sequenced curriculum
at the same pace just doesn't make sense.
And then why GitHub?
Well, because so many people use it.
Everything I've seen here, it's just everyone's sharing GitHub,
so why shouldn't students work in GitHub?
And the other nice thing is that with GitHub projects, I can orchestrate the classroom
as well as code and tie those things together to produce evidence of learning and competency.
And then students get to invest in their own portfolio, their own repos,
and then also build activity that they can showcase to employers in the future.
And why Python?
I just learned Python probably in the last three, four months,
so I'm brand new to it.
I'm mostly .NET and Java and PHP based.
But I've loved it so far.
I love it so much that it basically is my go-to now for programming.
It's expressive and it has a lot of the libraries that were necessary to build this,
and it's loved universally by students and teachers.
So it's working for me right now.
And then why Google Sheets?
As I moved from developer to manager, my IDE became Excel.
And I know that's not cool, but it actually is super powerful,
really helpful and easy for filtering data, for being able to kind of write formulas.
And it's my database.
And for this prototype, it worked really, really well.
So this is just like one type of view where I can actually go and look and
filter by students.
And you can see down at the bottom, there's courses, course sprints,
course units, course objectives, and those are all sort of just the database tables
of sorts that end up being recreated and modeled into GitHub.
And I can go in and check things as assessed, and
it moves tickets to done, closes tickets, and so on.
So there's a number of libraries, Google API, Python library,
PyGitHub for the REST API of Git, and then the GraphQL for GitHub is critical too.
So then we get these beautiful sort of aggregate views of student performance.
And as you can see, along these lines, students are underperforming,
but that's just because we just launched it.
And again, this is our group, 36 students, say hello.
Thank you.
It's a very long runway, sorry about that.
I'm sprinting now.
Talk about sprints, remember to stay for the sprint orientation today.
So our next talk, we'll have Adam,
who is the first time attending PyCon and he's now giving a lightning talk.
Thank you so much.
Hi everyone.
Hello, my name is Adam Silke.
I'm an empathetic leader and technologist.
First time PyCon and I've got a lovely new tie thanks to Pi ladies, so
yay Pi ladies.
This is a photo of me winning an ugly sweater contest.
And yes, I know what some of you are thinking, that's not a sweater.
Don't worry, the year after that, they explicitly called out only sweaters.
You know, explicit is better than implicit.
Anyway, this is leadership and the zen of Python.
There's a thesis to my five minutes up here, it's this.
Be present and lead with empathy.
It's that wonderful quote by Maya Angelou, people will forget what you said,
people will forget what you did, but people will never forget how you made
them feel.
I, like many others, was recently caught up in the ongoing layoffs that are
affecting our industry.
And a senior leader who I rarely interacted with reached out and said, hey,
checking in, I'd like to set up some time to talk.
And I said, yeah, yeah, that'd be great.
And four weeks later, I walked out of the workplace on my last day, never having
had that conversation.
People will never forget how you made them feel.
More than ever, we need leadership in our industry.
And I truly believe that Pythonistas make for perfect leaders.
After all, we have the zen of Python.
Beautiful is better than ugly, explicit is better than implicit, simple is
better than complex, complex is better than complicated, and so on.
But the problem with humans is that we're complicated, and
our thoughts are implicit, and our emotions are messy and sometimes even ugly.
So what can you do as a leader?
Be present and lead with empathy.
Beautiful is better than ugly, but messy happens, so learn to love it.
Dig into the messiness of people, and I promise you'll discover beauty there that
you never expected to find, and it will make all your relationships better.
Explicit is better than implicit, but people are 90% implicit at least.
It's that old conversation, hey, how are you doing?
Fine.
They're not fine.
So your goal as a leader is to learn to read the implicit, to listen and
lead with empathy, and give your people the space to be explicit with what they
want, and how they feel, and who they are, because explicit is better than implicit.
And people may be complicated, yes, but as Ned so
eloquently pointed out on Friday, so are you.
Understanding starts with you.
There was this one time that one of my employees gave me a call, and he said, hey,
man, I need to take the day, and I could tell immediately that there was something
wrong, and what's more, I remember being in his spot before where managers
interrogating me saying, well, what's going on?
And I didn't want to be that person, so I said, you got it, man, you take care of you,
take as much time as you need, and I'll take care of everything.
He told me two days later that the reason he needed time was because his dog had
suddenly gotten ill and passed away.
And the day that I found out that I had been let go, he gave me a call and said,
man, the reason I've stayed all these years is because of you.
People will never forget how you made them feel.
Let me give you one more story.
It was the middle of a major production issue, not my fault, but I was responsible
for helping to fix it.
And I'd been on site for 20 hours, and one of my leaders, the one who actually
introduced Python to me, had been there the whole time.
And he was doing the typical leader thing, not a whole lot except reading emails and
going to meetings and having really important phone calls.
And I told him, hey, man, you've been here a long time, just go home.
And I will never forget what he said.
You're here, so I'm here.
So be there.
Thank you.
Thank you so much, Adam.
Speaking of the Pilates auction, I think we raised over $36,000.
Amazing, right?
So there was things like ties.
People decided collectively to bid on pens, just like random pens we had.
There was Python set, fine China for a set of six and Dev Proof, which was a loan
kit. There was a lot of really cool stuff.
So if you haven't been to the Pilates auction in the past, please, please, please
consider it if you're going to be coming in the future to PyCon US.
It's a really good time.
But anyways, our next Lightning Talk speaker, Mariano, is going to be talking
about some work that I'm really, really excited about.
I've been reading about what this community has been up to for a while.
So why don't you go ahead and take it away?
Welcome. I'm Mariano from Python Argentina.
And we're talking about some project that we have there.
The first one is a course to teach Python to all kinds of students from high
school to adults.
And it's a remake of our original course of Brazil.
This course was just videos and exercises that you have to download and run in your
local computer.
And what we do is to create an online course using Ronstone.
That is a Python platform where teachers can out-or-the-work the lessons.
So this runs completely in the browser.
You don't have to install Python.
You can run it in a tablet, in a cell phone, even offline with no internet
connection or with high latency.
And also this has zero cost for hosting because you don't need a server to run the
exercises. Here is the online version if you want to try.
You have simple exercises to start Hello World programs.
And also some quizzes that have unit tests.
So you will give immediate feedback if your exercise is correct or you need to fix it.
And you also have visualization of the program step by step.
This is for students that want to learn how the program is run.
You have more traditional activities.
And what we do is also adding a new interpreter that is called Brighton.
That is Python in JavaScript.
And this supports a lot of features.
We work in, for example, SQLite wrapper to run databases and Pygame.
So you can run games directly in the browser.
This is an example of the queries you can do with the SQLite.
And it's regular Python.
Also you can do web UI with bots and dialogues so the student can have a vision of everything.
And this is the last challenge that is writing a game with Pygame.
So the student also can try to practice and edit the game and just press run.
And this will run in the browser without installation.
And the only difference with a traditional Pygame is this line that we need to do for JavaScript
that you cannot block the browser and so on.
But anyway, we have another project in Argentina.
This is a web service for the government library.
And all of this project participated in the Google Summer of Code.
That is a grant program of Google that pays students and students to work in open source projects.
So if any one of you are interested to start to collaborate and learn how open source is developed and so on,
you can try to join and make a proposal.
We are working under the Python Software Foundation umbrella.
Here's the link.
And you can also join to our Telegram group for this that has the information.
We do the announcements and news.
And these are some students.
I was a student of the Google Summer of Code program a lot of years ago.
Then we have Nicolás also was a student and now he's a mentor and active collaborator of our community.
And we have a lot of students from Argentina and other countries.
And here are the links.
If you want to talk about this, I will be on the screen the next day.
So you can learn.
We need better tests and so on.
So thank you for your time.
Why is it so far away?
Okay.
Thank you so much for the talk about the game, right?
I think, sorry, I wasn't made of it.
I haven't slept enough.
Okay.
So the next talk is Ali will be presenting about.
Oh, I can't read that.
Can you explain please?
Thank you.
The stage is yours.
Cool.
Thank you.
Yeah, my name is Alastair, aka Ali.
And I just want to talk about something cool that I've been doing the last few days.
I think it's cool at least.
Started on Friday morning when I was trying to think of topics for a lightning talk and saw this logo pop up.
On a slide.
It was kind of.
It had this nice kind of mirror symmetry to it.
I was thinking, oh, could you write some Python code that had the same mirror image symmetry?
And I realized I'm talking about palindromes.
So can you write Python code that is a palindrome?
Yeah, it's very difficult to search for this.
So I have no idea if anyone's done it before.
Just spits out Python palindrome checker algorithms.
So by Friday afternoon, I gave up on that and decided I'm just going to try and do it myself.
So I'm going to show you what I came up with.
Yeah, my second example is a bit more interesting than that.
Slightly more interesting.
Yeah, this one still doesn't do anything, but at least illustrates the point that for our case,
palindromes are going to be ignoring white space.
Otherwise, it's really difficult.
So what about a program that actually does something?
Can this be made palindromic?
Yeah, of course.
Obviously, this one's cheating a bit.
So I'm going to say we're also going to ignore comments.
And well done if you noticed that is actually not a palindrome.
Because the brackets don't match.
We're matching an open bracket with a closed bracket.
And just because they're mirror images doesn't mean it's a palindrome.
So we need to flip those around.
Now it's a palindrome.
But also expose as a problem with brackets we're going to have going forward.
If we have code that has any brackets in it at all, the first one is going to be an open bracket,
which means the last one also has to be an open bracket and that's not going to fly.
So bye bye brackets, I guess.
So let's take it all the way back.
The simplest sort of operations we can think of, variable assignment.
Can we do them?
This is problematic because when we flip it around,
we're going to end up with something like this on the other end
and we can't have an integer on the left side of the assignment.
Same with strings and that sort of thing.
But complex numbers to the rescue.
1j is square root of minus 1, j1 is just a variable name
that happens to equal square root of minus 1 here.
Yeah.
We can do lambdas.
They don't need brackets.
But unfortunately, if you try and do anything useful or interesting with them at all,
you run into cases where you need to use brackets and it kind of falls apart.
So maybe class declarations work.
We can put in some type hints.
That's fine.
But all of these are parts of ideas and not really coming together
into something useful as a code.
So I cleared my head on Saturday morning in the mountains
with these wonderful people and came back and wrote that thing.
So ignore the actual function declaration at the top, the line at the top,
but the rest of it from lines to onwards is a palindrome.
And it's fine if it's not clear what it does at first.
But those are the actually useful bits.
The rest is just sort of filling to make it palindromic.
And just show you quickly what it outputs.
If you print the first couple of things from the generator.
Technically Fibonacci.
Admittedly, the outputs formatted a bit unusually.
I could clean up and get rid of those zero J complex number bits,
but I stopped there.
I had my sights on something bigger.
Can I write a palindromic palindrome checker?
And even without making a palindrome,
trying to do this without using brackets to index into a string
or a reverse function is kind of tricky.
It's not obvious at first how you would do it.
But you can.
And once again, I'll highlight the actual useful bit of that for you.
Feel free to have a look.
I've got stuff on GitHub afterwards.
And I think I've created something that's even harder to search
than what I initially had, which was quite nice.
The next stage is creating a palindrome Turing machine
implementation in Python.
So if you want to help me with that, please get in touch.
Okay, I'll admit when I was looking at some of that, I'm like,
I know it's early, but what am I looking at?
So fantastic, fantastic talk.
Thank you so much for that.
Our next lightning talk speaker is JR,
and they're going to go ahead and take it away.
Thank you very much.
Good morning, PyCon US.
So I'm JR Rickerson.
I've been doing Python for a while, and for around the last 10 years or so,
I've also been teaching Python in various capacities,
like professionally and as a volunteer sometimes.
And teaching Python has taught me a lot about Python, right?
You actually learn quite a bit when you're teaching.
I don't have any slides, thank you.
And so I'm going to talk to you a little bit about what I've learned
and what I've learned about learning.
So I don't have any slides for you.
I don't have any live code.
I just have ideas.
So we'll talk about a few of those,
and hopefully I can provide some perspective on things.
So I'm going to talk a little bit about playing games.
That is something that hopefully you have done before, right?
Who here has never been a child?
Right? Probably nobody.
And who here has never played any sort of a game?
Right? Pretend, sports games, board games, whatever.
It's a universal kind of thing.
Everybody plays games.
And it's one of the few things we can kind of all agree on.
It doesn't matter where you come from, your financial situation,
kids play games, right?
And we play games for a reason.
One of those reasons is to learn things,
to mimic adults that we see,
and try to figure out how to be bigger humans, essentially.
So why do children play games?
Well, it's kind of wired into our brains, I think, right?
It's one of those things that you just don't have to be really taught.
Even babies start playing games
to learn how to physically move around, right?
How to control their arms and legs and so forth.
And then as we go on, we learn things like rules.
We learn things like social interactions.
And we learn how to control our emotions, right?
Winning is joyous sometimes.
Losing is maybe not so much joyous in a game.
So we learn to kind of deal with that sort of thing.
And it's an effective form of learning for us
because it is tied into emotions, right?
We remember things that have strong emotions associated with them.
We remember the good times.
We remember the especially bad times.
And so games can kind of provide that for us.
Playing can kind of provide that for us.
And they're just fun, right?
There's some motivation there.
If we enjoy a game, if we have goals and rewards,
short cycles of things, it's fun,
and it keeps us motivated to keep doing that same thing.
Excuse me.
So as we get to be adults,
I think we start to forget how to play, right?
We become a little more inflexible in our learning,
in the way we do things.
We don't have time to play, right?
The 12 hours a day I used to play NES or something
has turned into 30 minutes once a month, something like that.
And so we just kind of forget.
We fall out of that pattern.
And we turn to serious business.
So what I'm here to say is, during my teaching of Python,
I've tried to encourage that, playing, right?
I've tried to use games as a way to learn, right?
Even something as simple for someone
who's never programmed before,
something as simple as guessing the number game, right?
Pick a number between zero and 100 and guess what it is.
Everybody can kind of understand that right off the bat,
and you can use that to teach coding concepts, right?
You can teach conditionals, you can teach rules,
you can teach types and that sort of thing.
And then you can kind of expand on that idea.
So I've tried to encourage that in my students,
and I think it's been a pretty effective way to learn
that we kind of naturally have built into us,
but we tend to forget as we get older.
So this is a Python conference, obviously.
What should you do with this information, right?
Well, you probably came here
with maybe a goal to learn something or meet someone.
Maybe you learned something new while you've been here
that you're now interested in learning.
So instead of resorting to serious business
and going and digging into it,
go find a way to play with it, right?
And go find people to play with it, right?
So enjoy.
OK, this time I start running early,
but I'm still a bit late to start early.
OK, so thank you for the talk.
And the next talk is actually something that I think is,
well, it's fun at the beginning and then it's very frustrating.
It's about web scraping.
So thank you and please take us away.
All righty. Hey, everyone.
My name is Lubo, and I'd like to tell you
about my first web scraping project,
my web scraping woe and the workaround that I found.
The goal of my project was to scrape information
from a website after being logged in.
This was a website that I cared about.
I wanted to keep my account,
so I wanted to play it as safe as possible.
The tool that I ended up choosing was PyAutoGUI,
a Python module by Al Swigert.
It allows us to control the mouse and keyboard programmatically.
And so we can, with Python, move the mouse,
click the keyboard and interact with the browser,
just like a real user.
This is a demo of the workflow that I came up with.
I'm combining PyAutoGUI with Beautiful Soup,
another Python package.
We're importing our packages, alt-tabbing over
so that the browser's in focus.
We click control-S as a hotkey so we can save the file locally.
Here we're interacting with the operating system GUI.
We open up the file, pass it into Beautiful Soup,
which parses our HTML,
and then we can extract whatever we want
from that local copy of the website.
Great for most of the pages that I came across
until I came across this one.
At first it doesn't look too bad.
We have a table.
Some of the rows are always visible,
and clicking on the visible row
toggles the visibility of the row beneath it.
The problem becomes apparent when we look at the HTML, though.
Here we're looking at the first question and answer pair.
Favorite color is present,
but this is when the page is first loaded.
The answer isn't present.
It's only after we click it that the answer gets populated,
and then it stays in the web page after that.
The workflow that I showed earlier does not work.
If we save the web page locally,
the information I want is not going to be there.
What made this more challenging as well
is that this table is part of a larger web page.
I didn't want all of the rows.
I didn't know how many rows there would be
when I first loaded it anyway.
Those were all things that made this tricky.
Here's the workaround that I came up with.
The first step is to use our existing method
to download the page and extract the text from the links.
Since I don't want all of the rows,
this allows me to know, from the link text,
I can tell which rows I want and which I don't.
The next step is to take a screenshot of the table.
This is using another Python package,
mss, or multiple screenshot.
I need that screenshot so that I can pass it
into an optical character recognition package,
easy OCR.
This takes that image and tries to identify each word.
It tells us what it thinks the string is,
how confident it is from zero to one,
and crucially, where it is in the image.
So it gives us coordinates of the bounding box.
Here it's per word, but I wanted per row
so we can join up those bounding boxes.
Now we have the text that the OCR package
thinks is in the links.
Notice it's mostly the same,
except the question marks are now the number two.
Now, in the example that I gave,
the OCR text is pretty close.
The font is quite large.
There aren't a ton of special characters,
but sometimes the output of the OCR is less than ideal.
So I need a way to match the rows that I want from step one
with the bounding boxes from step three.
And for this, I used another Python package
called the fuzz.
It implements Levenstein string distance,
which sounds fancy, but it's one metric of many to compute,
give a number to, how similar or dissimilar
two strings are from each other.
And I'd like to show you an example.
So here we're comparing the stuff from step one
through step three, favorite color versus the OCR version,
and we get a score of 93 out of 100.
Okay, if we compare it against the other one,
against favorite food, we get a lower score, 76.
If we compare it against nonsense,
we get 17.
And I'll note that you have to be empirical about this.
There's no one number.
So in my case, I had to play around with the strings
a little bit and find a number that allowed me
to separate matches from not matches.
And once we've done that, we can match the stuff extracted
from steps one and three, take those bounding boxes,
compute the center, click each of those,
and from there, our normal method works beautifully.
We save the web page locally and pass it into beautiful soup.
Big thanks to all the people who maintain these packages.
It would not have been possible without them.
And thank you for your time.
APPLAUSE
Excellent.
Thank you so much for that talk.
And our final lightning talk of PyCon 2023
will be telling us a little bit about simplifying pandas.
Take it away.
All right.
Hi, my name is Hao Sun.
Very happy to be here.
If you see me in the hallway, please say hi.
So today I'll be talking about simplifying pandas.
This is for all your data science people out there
and anybody who's trying to learn
getting into data science, data analysis.
And what I like to call this is data agnostic data analysis.
So the question is why?
Because life could be so much easier.
So I'm going to present to you an idea
that's going to change your life and how you view data analysis.
Once you see this, you can never unsee it like one of those memes.
But right now there's no open source code that you can play with.
But you can dream about it at night or at work
when you're crunching away at data analysis.
So what does it mean by data agnostic?
So basically I want to separate the logic from the data.
So basically when the logic is not changing,
when the data changes.
So what is logic? What is data?
It depends. It's a little bit subjective.
Something that changes could be considered data.
If it's across different iterations of your building,
your feature, different features, different projects, different teams,
or even different data storage medium.
So this is a little prelude to later.
And it's a little bit subjective.
But with the next two examples, I hope you'll get a better idea.
So consider the following scenario.
You want to get into stock trading
and you want to calculate the seven day average price for a stock, stock A.
OK, so looks innocuous enough.
You jump into penless and start calculating this.
But let's go back a step.
So can we separate this into data and logic, right?
So here the data is highlighted in blue and logic is highlighted in green.
So really the only logic you have is average.
Everything else is pretty much data that can change.
For example, you might not want a seven day average.
You might want a one month average.
Maybe you don't want an average price.
You want to average volume.
Or you don't want to calculate for stock A.
You want to calculate for stock B.
Or you want to do all of that at the same time.
Imagine how many times you have to change your code
if you go through that iteratively, right?
And then in the second example, it's a little bit more complex example.
So here you want to calculate the max average min of the length of streaks of zeros.
In a column of ones and zeros.
I know it's a mouthful.
But actually this is a very good interview questions
for all your recruiters out there.
Especially for PySpark because stack overflow and chat GPT
doesn't give a workable answer, but it's very complex even to understand.
But after seeing this talk, you'll be able to know
what are the three or four steps that you need to calculate this.
Anybody who doesn't know that, meaning they haven't seen this talk, don't hire them.
So yeah, it could be streaks of zeros or streaks of ones.
So right now here, the zero and one, I consider them to be logic.
As you will see in a bit, but just to illustrate how easy you can extend this.
So the goal I want is the separation of data and logic.
And also I want the logic to be modular and reusable so I can plug and play.
Then into different pipelines to build more complex logic.
And I want to distill the essence of desired subset of pendants.
I don't want to recreate all the pendants.
I'm not Brett.
So, but if there's need, then people can build it.
So here is an example of what you can do for the first scenario I showed.
So you calculate the 7 day sum average of stock A's price.
So you can see the top part is the logic and the bottom part is the data.
So they're pretty much separate.
Right?
And then you might think, OK, this doesn't look like pendants.
These are just JSON configs.
Right?
Yeah, I know it's a little bit prerogative.
But if you can write JSON configs and have the backend work out the pendant logic,
why not?
Right?
And then if I just want to change this to a 7 day, one month sum average of stock A
and B's price and volume, if you look closely, I'm going to do it again.
OK?
You just change the data part.
You just add two strings, three strings.
And then you don't need to change the logic part.
So this is what I mean by separation of logic and data.
So this basically distills everything that you need to do this computation.
So pendants is basically an implementation, maybe an implementation detail that you
don't need to know.
And then for the second example here, the more complex thing about calculating the
streaks.
So you can see these are the four steps.
So, yep.
And this last quote, best code is no code at all.
Thank you.
You really do have like a full ramp you have to sprint up on that side.
Yeah, I feel like I already did the sprint.
So I already one day ahead of everybody.
So we're just going to close up with a few reminders about some events and
activities and things to pay attention to as the lightning talks now are officially over.
So first things first.
Oh, but.
But all the lightning talk is officially over.
But if you kind of not get selected or now you just come up with a new
lightning talk, you can go to the open space.
There is an unofficial lightning talk there.
Correct.
Which is again, so lovingly titled lightning talks.
They didn't want you to hear at 12 p.m.
in room 250 AB.
And we will not take that title too personally.
So another thing about the sprint is that today at 5 p.m.
back here, we'll have a sprint orientation.
So for the first timer who don't know, oh, what is a sprint?
But you have a few days, you know, you're still around the city.
Then please come to the orientation and see what you can do in the sprints.
So for people who are not the first timer and then you already plan to stay for the
sprint, please also come and see what projects you can sprint on on Monday.
Fantastic.
And as one last reminder, if you did not buy your conference t-shirt at 11 p.m.
or 11 p.m.
11 a.m.
If you're here at 11 p.m.
That's confusing.
11 a.m.
There's t-shirt sales, suggestion donation of $20.
One other thing I did want to plug, if you were interested in the Python
Software Foundation specifically, we have an election coming up for directors.
I'm a previous chairperson and director.
I would be super happy to answer your questions as well as many other people
that are at the PSF booth, our staff, volunteers.
They can help answer any questions you may have if you're a little bit
interested in that.
But I think that's about all of our announcements.
So we're going to go ahead and conclude.
This is the end of lightning talks for 2023.
Thank you so much, PyCon.
You all have been amazing.
All right.
The irony is that took longer than my talk is going to take.
My name is Tom Calloway.
Everybody calls me Spot.
I'm an open source evangelist strategist at AWS.
I'm here today to talk a little bit about PyPy.
If I can get this thing to work, go for it.
Okay.
So PyPy and AWS have been partners since 2018 when PyPy was fully rewritten in
order to scale a little bit better.
Part of that work was to overhaul the back end and rewrite PyPy to run on top
of AWS.
Today, PyPy has been able to scale and meet the growing needs of the Python
ecosystem.
Many, many kudos to E and the infrastructure team who support PyPy along with all of
the volunteers and release managers for Python.
Currently, PyPy is averaging 425 requests per second to the back ends on AWS for a
total of 257 million requests per week.
You all are hitting that thing a lot.
At Amazon, one of our principles is that success and scale bring broad
responsibility.
And as part of our commitment to this principle, we're investing in open source
projects that are critical to our customers, our builders, and the rest of
the world.
We're proud to provide AWS credits to cover all of the AWS costs for PyPy, which is
something that we've done for five years now.
Python is a critical component for AWS and its customers, and we recognize the
responsibility that we have to give back to the open source communities that we
rely on.
Today, there's a new challenge for PyPy and open source.
Supply chain security is an industry-wide issue, so I'm not trying to sort of say,
well, this is the only place that's having this problem.
But PyPy is facing threats like typo-squatting, malware, dependency
confusion, support ticket backlogs.
AWS in particular has been a very notable target of a lot of these things.
And right now, we have one volunteer, Dustin Ingram, I don't know if they're
here, but if they are, my hat is seriously off to you, for taking down 88% of the
malware on PyPy alone.
That's fantastic, but it really doesn't scale very well.
And so we are proud today to announce that we are becoming the first official
security sponsor of the Python Software Foundation.
We're increasing our commitment to securing critical open source software and
providing additional funding, which will allow the PSF to hire a full-time safety
and security engineer to work on PyPy.
I'm going to briefly deviate from my notes here to say that when they asked if I
would give this talk, the one condition I had was that it had to have a really
sweet cartoon snake to go with it, and this is what I got.
Obviously, the Python Package Index is critical to countless companies and other
users, and we feel strongly that this new position will help alleviate the
bottleneck of support issues, remove malware faster, and keep PyPy secure for
the benefit of all of its users.
Basically, we want to help put armor on Python so that developers and users can
continue to feel safe using PyPy.
So we set out some goals together with the PSF for this new role, things like
creating a standardized way to report malware to PyPy via API, not via human
ticket, streamlining the malware review process, lowering the average PyPy
response time for malware takedown from the seven days where it's at currently
to three days after report, developing a security plan with improvement
milestones, enabling proper security audit of all new PyPy features before
they launch, decreasing the average time for all of the security support
requests, and most importantly, freeing up the PyPy maintainers to focus on
adding new features without feeling like they're having to sacrifice the
security concerns.
Thank you all so much for everything that you do for the Python community.
We're proud to be able to support you.
I need those pictures.
I want to make stickers today.
All right.
Thank you, Spot.
So that job is live right now at jobs.python.org, and you can come work with
me and the others at the PSF.
I am E.
I'm the director of infrastructure at the Python Software Foundation, and I'm
very...
Oh.
I'm very glad you're here, whether you're in this room or online.
And let's just from my heart.
Five years ago today, approximately, at PyCon, we were celebrating PyPy
relaunching as warehouse on AWS as a full new rewrite.
And one of the things that we were most excited about in this was not just the
maintainability of the code, but the ability to deliver new things more
easily and more safely.
We've done a lot of that.
Focus has primarily been around security, and it will continue to be with the
ever-growing threats.
But in addition to that, we've also delivered features that are just usability
or purposeful.
So today, we're rolling out a step that goes beyond just a feature and works
towards the sustainability and financial support of PyPI, while also giving our
users one of the most requested features, organizations.
So I'm not going to sort of make this sound like it's more than it is.
The truthful feature, the truth of it all is that organizations are just ways to
organize your projects, organize your teams, and organize your permissions.
It's a first step in what we hope will be a long road of features that basically
provide a lot of good value out of PyPI for not just us as a community, but for
corporate users as well.
So we're making organizations available for community projects for free forever.
And I just want that to be clear.
We're never going to get me in the business of doing things just to extract money
from the people who need it to do their work in the open.
And for corporate projects, these features will be available at a small fee.
In the last year, PyPI served 235 billion downloads for the 550,000 projects that
are hosted there.
This means that since the previous period, we saw 57% annual growth.
And I was a little shocked because I was just sort of updating some canned notes
and noticed that it was 57% of four.
If you've learned anything about the way that curves grow recently, you'll know
that if you have the same growth rate period over period, it's exponential growth.
So having more people using and contributing to Python every year is a fantastic
problem to have.
But it's one that we have to increase organizational capacity through
sponsorships like AWS and our...
I'm blanking.
I should add that.
I know it's other sponsors as well who help pay to put employees onto projects.
And so by charging for these organization features for corporate uses, it increases
the ability for PyPI to become a staff platform that can respond to all manner of
support requests, not just security, in a timely fashion for everyone.
So again, we want to be very clear that these new features are completely optional
and completely free if you're a community project.
If features that are required for larger teams and larger projects don't sound
appetizing to you, don't worry.
You don't have to use these things.
But it may be something that could be useful for larger teams and larger projects.
There's no obligation to create an organization and absolutely nothing about
PyPI.
Nothing about using PyPI will change if you don't opt in.
And this is only the basis for future work.
We look forward to discussing what other features PyPI users would like to see
tackled next.
We know there are a lot of ideas out there around safety, security, and
usability.
And we're looking forward to having a way to connect directly with people who we
know are using the features, which currently is difficult.
Versus coming through an organization we know who to talk to.
And in the spirit of open source, we always want to welcome that feedback at
github.pypi.warehouse.
So these are available today.
Maybe even right now?
I don't know.
Probably.
So we're flipping a feature flag.
It's going to be instantaneous.
And you...
What's that?
Cool.
So they're there now.
So...
Both community projects as well as corporate teams can sign up today to request
their name.
We're going to be validating and verifying these.
So it may take some time before your organization is brought online.
For community projects, that may start happening over the next week or two.
For corporate teams, we'll be finalizing the legal and accounting things necessary.
And you can expect to see some of those details in May.
The most important part for me anyway about this is the shout outs and thank yous.
Organization feature development was approved by the packaging working group and
funded through the Python Software Foundation sponsorship program.
Thanks to our sponsors for making this work possible.
We especially want to thank Bloomberg for funding our packaging project manager,
Shamika Mohana, who oversaw this work.
And as always, a shout out to the companies that donate services in kind to
run PyPI.
We're also grateful for the many PyPI users who shared their perspectives with
Shamika during user studies and laid the foundation for these new features.
And lastly, I want to thank our beta testers, including the brand new
organizations on PyPI, the Python Cryptographic Authority, the Palettes
Project, and Certify.
That's all I got.
Thank you.
All right.
Well, yes, thank you so much, Eve, for those updates.
It's amazing news.
And right now we have the job fair and the posters are happening.
There will be talks after lunch break.
So go ahead.
Thank you.