Good morning, everyone, and welcome again to Python.
Our next speaker is Natalie, and she's going to be talking about source code management
and using the Python Open Policy region to ensure governance and security in your development process.
Please welcome her to the stage.
Good morning, everyone. I hope everyone is enjoying Python's research. Nice to see you.
So my name is Natalie, and today we're going to talk about source code management, development, and compliance,
a little bit about security and a little bit about Python.
So a little bit about myself. I'm currently working as a scratch card engineer.
My task is to use students who work in companies like Solante,
who are rather happy to work mostly working on different infrastructure-related tasks,
and enjoy conditions including my work using a lot of Python.
And there's my Twitter handle, so I'm just going to put it in your hand.
So today what I'm going to cover is basically source code management type.
This is a big part of our development process.
What kind of challenges some of us may face during the compliance procedures is probably happening.
At some point, everyone's...
Once companies are growing those and what does open policy use it,
why do they want to use it, or how do they start using it, what is policies as a code,
as well as how we can use policies to achieve source code management
for other compliance-related tasks in our development process.
So basically, source code management is just...
I assume a lot of people know about it because most likely it's a big target group process
that everyone is going through within the company when you develop your code.
And it helps us to collaborate between our teams, right?
It spores all the information, important information where we all can access it,
we all can collaborate as well as it makes our jewelry with the product much faster.
So it's different procedures.
And these days, I think, source code management is not just storage of your code.
A lot of extra features are added like CI, CD, Sparse, like secret management,
and many more things can be added using some tooling for games and things like that.
So just giving you an example of the code I'm talking about is like GitHub,
GitHub, there's a few examples as well from Atlassian, there's Azure Reinforce, and many more.
Most of this old one is based on GitHub these days.
And so the reason I am bringing this up is I don't know if you're following or not,
but these days, they're kind of like, last couple of years, they're recruiting and
target packs related to the source code and related to the code, like code codes,
or SolarWinds effects.
I'm not sure if you want to know about it, but a lot of things were leaked right outside.
And there's also those practices where people build in the code and are not always aware
of the policies, what it says, or like how to post the news when you do a report.
So because of that, I decided this talk might be useful, or let's say if, I know when you're
working as an engineer as a developer, you're not always going to work in certain things
right, and if there were compliance and security for some people in some cases,
maybe not the most interesting part.
And in some cases, it's just easier to automate that, so everyone just follows this rule
without actually reading the rules and reading the laws and understanding where things are going.
So why there's challenges.
Source code management exists for so many years, and there's still challenges because,
and I mentioned, there is a lot of different practices that are also changing because of
change changing and the speed of doing it and self-courage changing.
So also the way we work, right, the agile works more full, agile is more faster,
now they've got continuous delivery, and people try to work more quickly from the main bank,
and the deploy friend is going to run sometimes, get posts, and also like around those
security-wide different rates.
So because this part is a physical part, and all of us are doing things like this,
sometimes it's kind of hard to make sure that everyone follows the exact same practice, right.
Sometimes we have fuck fixes, or sometimes we have weird, how do you say,
merge conflict rate, it ends up to be a bug or some other security issue.
As well as like usually in the company people trade, people have access to free and to do different things,
right, and we're free to create and reinforce, and now everyone always knows what kind of
project is going to be created, how to make the project is now public, do they actually need to do that,
or are all of those projects to be public, right.
And it's hard to assure that everyone actually goes through the same practice and understanding
all the reasons behind a trade when you just quickly turn into what you're doing.
There are very interesting things that I always want to talk about specifically because I imagine
that in this case it's information, and it's like a known inferior, it's always happening,
but there are so many ways that it's still a big problem.
So it's a big challenge where people just in the rough ways not condition their advocacy
because there is a big rotation policy within their practices, but also let's say if something happens
there's not always an mechanism to prevent this, or fix what happens because of this kind of
So as I mentioned there are different accesses, there are different roles within the company,
different people that have different access that can create, do, commit different things,
so this is a choice as well since someone who manages all of that and is doing what can access
everyone who can, and what can actually they do in order to make sure that they're doing the right
thing. So this is the basic functions when you're going to the compliance or security
you want your first-person management to think about your first-person management and the most
possible effective and effective way to do it.
So I'm going to talk about the first-person management.
So when you think about your first-person management and the most possible effective areas.
And here's this slide. So what does this slide represent? Basically, I don't know if anyone
on the ranking complies with a mid-company or the other file, but basically when you're doing
compliance, how is it treated? Right? First of all you decide on the type of the compliance or
security norm that your company has to go to, and they decide on the area of, for example,
structure, right? And what it represents is that there will be different, different policy
teams that have different, different things, and everyone within the company needs to make sure
that this proposal is followed, right? To give you an example, let's say someone came into the
repository and they need to make sure that this repository is public or private, it depends, but
that everyone can commit to doing so, but probably not to the main branch. So there's a different
branch protection establishment as well as it could be something that people are, they say not,
they should not commit those secrets, right? Or if that happened, it should probably first be
how the speaker should be repeated, how does the sector, let's say, database was affected, and
how to immediately back incident in that area, I think. So basically policy are kind of like
actually explaining to you to understand what happened, when you think there's an accident,
and then you can follow it through the development process. So these days this is kind of called
a quick site, you have some stats, which also like you have those possible control issues, and then
you create things like Sederland, and then you know if a test is affected by that test, and on our
right side there is a column called mitigated by security controls, so those are the polls that
you're writing in order to make sure that everything is secure and confirmed within our
organization. And we talk about code, as I sort of mentioned in traffic, this is an example of
seeing like something was leaked, let's say someone copied part of the code on their laptop, and
then they were able to do it, and then they were able to do it again, and then they were able to
copy part of the code on their laptop, and then it's made of that code, as you can see, the
long-time key, so the code was leaked, right, and what kind of actions are going to take in order to
fix that. So there's a map that we kind of have like stuff of those tools, which I mentioned before,
and we call them control objectives and control restrictions, but this is kind of like a paper,
what's going to happen, and what's going to, how we're going to control it. So if you look at that,
this is kind of old and I would say security and compliance, security and compliance in some cases
is kind of, in my opinion, like it's a big part of subculture development, but I feel like it's a
big part of subculture development, but I feel like it's a big subculture development that we tend to have.
So in the past, like this would be a, not the people work, but the culture framework's relevant,
because it's going to look like, and not everyone understands it, there's lots of specific people,
we call them auditors, right, who can read those files, who can understand it, who can take the
auditors and see if you're complying with it. So basically what we just saw is kind of the policy, right?
So how can it work? Basically, it can create some policies as a code, right? If this is just,
just that, where there's some kind of, it could be a YAML or some kind of a do-sense, right, why we can
just quote a file and make sure that it has some similar parameters that everyone can just use.
So with creating these policies as a code, is the main focus of my talk, and there are different tools in the market
that can adopt those tools, and this is what I'm going to cover. So why do we want to consider policy as a code?
So as I said, there's a combination of every one of our highlights. There's direct tool, it's going to be
written in my useful, written in my company, because I'm going to be in the paper, I'm going to be in a real work
studio. Also there's recognition, right? I did not experience the importance of recognition these days.
The mere force is not something we enjoy, it's not something we can receive, and there are so many benefits.
As long as we're working together, when we see what happens, when we see how it goes, there's still a record of that,
which is important for our compliance. So going back to the Open Policy Event, I think if you read that quote
by Cedar, of Open Policy Event, that everything can be a policy, right? If you put it in a specific data structure
and we can run some things, we can run some things in order to detect them, we need to read them, and what is that?
So why not just to build something as a component, as a code, right? So combined as a code should be about some
tools that we can build in-house, or some of them exist, but are pretty costly from experience. So I say if we can
probably afford the things in production, but if you just want to follow the process and run it in a later environment or
less important environment, so probably want to think about something in-house building my book, as well as, for example,
you don't want to comply all your repositories, maybe e-house, in your company, something like, many production or code
base, as well as the latest Internet porting. So you still want to comply with my specific practices for security purposes,
but you probably don't want to run this expensive search trade unless you just get that in your case.
So what is, how do you work with policy in the code, right? These things, there is an interesting Open Source policy agent,
which is an Open Source, basically, it unifies the policy enforcement around the sentence. So I'm going to talk about how we can
build them policies ourselves, how we can discuss them, how we can process them, right, using code. But Open
Policy Agent also complies with the sentence platform. If you use Kubernetes, there is a way to use that agent with a lot of
the sentences on security and compliance around Docker and other, like, there is different libraries that you can use to
build code using Open Posts. And that basically is just declare to find which, and it likes to specify every policy as a code,
and use simple API to propose a decision making from your sub-credit. Open Posts can be used to enforce policies,
and you can set the micro-genesis, write security guidelines, the libraries, and the networking tools, and much more.
So here is, let's say, a basic example. If I want to build a compliance service, and this should be something basically that I want to
start with, it should look like this. It should be able to create input for my Open Policy Agent. It should be able to create
open post solution against the policies we built, right? And the rules should be simple. So the policies should be,
should be five things, and open algorithms should be returned allow or deny based on the policies. So it should be small,
it could be many of them, it's usually this way. If I think about architecture of this application, I would think something like
policy input and credit, I would think something like offer evaluator, and then I would think on action, which is like,
excuse me, allow or deny. So here is an example. This is the image from the offer side, and we can use, and basically on this slide,
how do we view the fact that we never used Open Policy Agent, and they tried to understand why we were trying to define here.
So if we have a service, right, in this example is an application like the service, which simply receives a request,
it could be running, or denied, anything else, and for the service, we want to decide how to handle this request, right?
And then the service should be able to receive a response people with our slogan, so how do we do it? What is the next step?
So the service would send a specific call to the Open Policy Agent, right, and the policy will contain an experience
through conduct, which Open Policy Agent cannot take, compared to the list of policy created, and then detects things like
a few things on that, so basically allow or deny this user to allow you. That's it. That's as simple as that.
So let's say if we want to build a tool, we want to use Probe and Probe, and we want to build a simple,
basic compliant tool for our resource probe management tool. There is open source library or client.
It's pretty much maintained, maintained by the OPA. It's currently, like, latest in use versus recently happening.
There is a nice recommendation to it, and it's hosted on IPY. So based on this theory, if you think about what kind of service
you want to implement and what they just said about resource management, how is it all going to look like?
So all this, those are kind of some things that may have some paper-like policy or we can put them in some case
and some map, and we have this tool called Open Policy Agent, which we might know or might not know much about.
We just know that it takes some input to process something, and it returns changes, actually.
And we know that in-house, I have this kick-off organization, for example, where I want to manage the rules of my post
without manually checking my 1,000 emails without manually checking what my management plans are doing.
So if I think about service like this, but I'll tell you quickly, where do I start?
So let's say in my company, I want to create one simple policy where users can just take the email,
and I want to make sure when I'm really going to create it, it has a name brand and it has branching protections.
So I know that GitHub or Google Apple gives back a drill how that works, based on the events that users create, right?
So when someone creates a default, it creates a direct hook.
So coming from infrastructure background, I think I probably can use some random rate to create a direct hook,
which is just a serverless application. I could use it in Python because I'm just a first Python, and I can use that as my service.
So what will service will do? It will detect my policies, right? It should be in the same group,
or it could distort this one back, basically, because I want to manage. It should trigger my open agent.
So the next step is to push the question, right, like, if this people has branching protection in the book, yes or no, right?
And then based on the code, my linebacker can just take that as yes.
Or, for example, if I'm asking to a user if it's a security person who watches all this components and security policies,
they are followed within the company. So here's an example of the policy.
So open policy isn't users' random language to write the policy. It's the, it needs some time to talk to the line,
but based on the way that the playground, when you can try a different policy, you can add your own policy,
you can find a lot of open source policies. And here's an example of the policy, which I would use for branch protection,
for example, with UCLan. This is branch protection simply describing what is happening.
So my user goes to UCLan, creates a repo that suggests to me, this is where my work is with open,
this one resource, which in the end will be basically my compliance service.
And this is the open agent which makes policy decisions and depends on results.
And then my service would take this result and make the decision on what users are allowed to do or not,
whether they're going to create or maybe to be built. Or maybe my service can just adjust their source by itself
and it's a commission question. So user doesn't even know what's happening. But we're still controlling this company.
So here's an example where say if I want to build my own language and then I want to connect to the open policy agent,
as you can see it's basically super simple. You just call the library and so you first create the appliance
and connect to the open agent and then you just make the connection. There is a different way how you can
identify, you can put it in the local forest and the documentation is pretty good. And then as I said,
when you design in this way, there are different ways how you can design in this part of your architecture.
So it could be on the service. It could be a different open service or microservice if you run in the broker,
for example, it's got all this work. It could be trigger by Red Hook or it could be a specific application
like a lower GitHub. There is also an easy GitHub app to do that. And again, we can do it with type
and we don't have to go into buying an expensive software to do this in my community, it's an easy thing.
And there is also interesting approaches how you can do it within your CI-CD pipelines. So basically,
if I think about how to get to an app like this, I would not create a trigger, I would create maybe a job
which calls every day, runs all my reports and connects them or deletes them or maybe disables them
or applies them based on the action I would put on the page. And within that, my service would just need
to have a couple of things, which is connecting to the open agent and receiving the result.
So this is basically an example of the action where I want to update my policy. Let's say you create the policy,
something has changed and in this architecture, let's say you could possibly have policies
policies called mapping to talk for somewhere in this database site. And everything also expenders
for this to manage the policy itself. Or we could have something in the code repo which would limit the database
and in my service, this is an FGRI 12 using the passing client to talk for their specific storage of my policies,
and then you can have a database or anything else. So this is how you connect. This is how you update.
You can delete. You can delete. There are so many things with this URL called the writing.
So basically, someone is, let's say someone is getting hosted by this appalk and they want to try how easy it is
to start using open policy agents within your company. It is not a fight. You just need to decide how do you want to run the agent.
Number two is you need to write the policies. This is where sometimes we'll be spent.
For now, I know there are more tools coming out how to generate these policies. I'm sure a certain
system probably can help with that. We just need to validate that whatever version we have is correct.
And then that's what the learning curve is. And then I would say if you're really interested in working in compliance
with security and managing the policy and there's something for all your company that's effective, there's also a learning curve.
And then just managing those two is something that would take some time. But once you run through this practice,
everything else is kind of super easy. And you can just start building some policies. You can open source them, which is pretty cool.
Let's say there is a very cool project where you can sign a lot of policies for GitHub. But my company countries using GitHub, right?
And there is not many policies there. So we have our internal deposit policy where we run to create these policies for different cases.
And my one goal is to run some source for my work on projects like this, I think. And basically, this is the end of my talk.
Thank you so much. Everyone, welcome in.
Thank you very much.
Thank you, Natalie. Thanks for the question. I know software and compliance is probably not the most exciting thing,
but policy as code is definitely a way to send that to our fellow developers. Thank you. And we all learned a lot.
Let's give another round of applause for Natalie.