Thank you, Marietta.
We appreciate you.
And when you come back, make sure to give me a high five so I can get one point.
Hello, everyone.
And welcome to PyCon US.
My name is Itamar.
I'm a software engineer on Meta's internal Python platform team.
And I'm thrilled to be here today to help kick off PyCon US and hopefully not waste
too much of your time before our first keynote speaker.
So first I wanted to begin by expressing how proud we are to be a visionary sponsor of the
Python Software Foundation.
We are also excited to announce that we have extended our support for the amazing and influential
developer in residence position for one more year.
And specifically, we are very glad that it is Woukash that we love very much and we are
enabling him to stick around for a while more.
We are honored to contribute to the growth and development of the Python community and
are thrilled to be part of such a vibrant community.
Python and the Python ecosystem is incredibly important to us at Meta.
With CPython itself and some other implementations and thousands and thousands of open source
libraries and packages, we rely on all of those to power services like Instagram, a
wide range of AI and ML systems and thousands of tools, scripts, automations that tie everything
together.
And we appreciate everyone who contributes to it, all the open source maintainers, core
developers, CPython contributors and everyone that helps enabling that.
Thank you everyone.
We believe in the power of open source to drive innovation and we have open sourced
numerous libraries and frameworks ourselves, which you are all welcome to check up on GitHub.
Even contribute, we welcome contributions.
So yeah, thank you all for joining us today and we can't wait to hear from the keynote
speaker.
Thank you.
Mariana.
All right.
So thank you again, Meta, Itamar, for sharing your message.
So, when I was tasked with choosing keynote speaker, I thought about who do I want to
invite, who do I want you all to hear from?
And I know that I talk about the first timers and I reminisce about my own self, what it
was like when I was new.
And I think about who are the people who have been helping me, who are the people who I
look up to, who are the people who have been supporting me throughout my journey in Python.
So I really want to just introduce you to people who are really influential to me.
And that probably didn't know this, but on the day before my first ever made talk at
a local meetup, I was freaking out.
I was so scared.
I was ready to pull the plug.
I was going to call in sick and cancel.
And then I asked for help.
I think all I needed was someone to encourage me.
And Net was there.
I think all he did, all he said was just, this is a good talk.
That's all.
And I think if Net wasn't there, none of the ice cream selfies probably will not happen.
So thank you, Net.
And really I just want you all to know about Net Bachelor.
So Net, welcome on stage.
I think now I have to start with, you're not crying, I'm crying.
I did not know that, Marietta.
Thank you very much.
And also, by the way, I feel like I am cool because I am on the stage where the lightning
talks will be rather than the other way around.
So thank you, Marietta and the PSF and everyone else for inviting me here.
It's an honor to be here on stage at the 20th anniversary of PyCon.
I saw a lot of people in those pictures that I know.
I saw myself in a few of those pictures.
And I'm reminded again of the energy here at PyCon.
So before I start, I have a question.
Are you excited for PyCon?
All right.
All right, good.
There were some pictures up there before.
When I mentioned that I was doing this talk to my friend Antonio, I told him that I wasn't
at the first PyCon in 2003.
He said that he was.
And he sent me a picture.
Here's Antonio on the right with another conference attendee.
And I think the cool thing about PyCon is that some things haven't changed over 20 years.
My first PyCon actually was in 2007 in Dallas.
And Gito did the keynote there where he talked about the plans for this thing coming up called Python 3.0.
During his keynote, he momentarily forgot the word annotations and said, you know, the things that aren't
type declarations.
So some things have changed over 20 years, I guess.
But when I thought about doing this talk, I thought, well, what should I talk about?
I thought about the various ways I've been part of the Python community, things that
I've done.
I thought about, you know, what should my keynote be about?
So my day job, I work at edX, which is a 2U company working on the Open edX project, which
is a large Python and Django application that powers edX.org and thousands of other online
sites around the world.
So I thought I could talk about online education or million line monoliths or building large
open source projects within a for-profit company.
I've been maintaining coverage.py for a long time.
This is Sleepy Snake.
Thank you.
This is Sleepy Snake, the mascot of coverage.py.
He's covered and he's resting easy because he knows his tests work.
And notice that he's in the shape of a C for coverage.
So I could talk about what is it like to maintain a project that's widely used by many people
in the community.
I also maintain smaller projects that may not go anywhere but sometimes do, so I could
have talked about that.
I am an organizer for Boston Python, which is a local meetup.
So I thought maybe we could talk about, you know, how that sort of dynamic works.
What did we do during the pandemic to keep things going?
Boston Python is actually doing really well.
We have three new organizers since the pandemic started, one of whom I only met in person
yesterday at the reception.
We have three new kinds of events that we've been running during the pandemic virtually.
So it's actually going really well.
I've been running a blog for a long time, actually since before PyCon, the first PyCon.
So I thought I could talk about what is it like to put ill-formed opinions out on the
internet for abuse.
I hang out in online arenas like IRC or Slack or Discord.
So I could talk about what is it like to help beginners or how are these environments the
same and different.
For instance, in Discord, I'm hanging out with people a quarter of my age who often
ask me is that really you in the profile picture because they think that if a gray hair guy
is in a picture, it's probably a meme rather than really a person.
But then I thought, well, let's step back.
What do all of these things have in common?
I wanted to talk about something bigger, right?
It's a keynote.
It should be big, right?
So I decided that I would talk about high uncertainty components in complex systems.
All right.
That's not really the title of the keynote.
I do want to talk about things that are less certain to us and how we interact with them.
But there's a much simpler way to describe what those things are than this fancy high-tech
jargon that I put here just to entice you all to keep listening to me.
The simpler way to describe what I'm going to talk about is people.
And what I mean by that is that we as engineers interact with people, of course, but as engineers,
we might approach those people as if they were technical components.
We may think less of the work we have to put into interacting with those people, and as
a result, the interactions might not go as well as they might.
But as engineers, we can use the skills we have to learn how to do complex things with
computers and software and electronics and apply those skills to our interactions with
people and make those interactions go better.
And often we think of those things as soft skills.
We call them soft skills.
And some people don't like the term soft skills because it sounds like we're lowering it,
right?
We've got the hard skills.
Those are important.
We've got the soft skills.
There's the hard skills and soft skills.
I don't think of it that way.
I think that the reason people think soft skills are less is because as quantitative,
technical, engineering-type people, we value the hard edges of the hard skills.
There's numbers attached to it, and you can design processes, and you can automate them,
and you can do all that sort of stuff.
And we like that.
And then dealing with people, the soft skills, it's all squishy and subjective, and there's
no linters that you can apply to your Slack conversations or whatever to figure it out.
There's no coverage.py that can tell you whether you're getting along with that person or something.
Right?
So it's all squishy and soft, and that's exactly what makes it difficult.
If you like, you can think of soft skills as emotional intelligence.
At least it's got that cool word intelligence in it, right?
So that's maybe that will appeal to us a little bit more.
But honestly, if you think about it, people are terrible, pretty much.
But only if you think of them as components.
If you approach people as an engineer and think, I don't have to worry about this, then
yes, people will be terrible.
But they don't have to be terrible, because if you take their interaction seriously and
then they won't be terrible.
Let's look at some of the engineering qualities that we value and how people stack up on those
criteria.
So this clicker's a little weird.
First thing, people are nonstandard.
They're all different, right?
We got this guy on the right.
He's trying to figure out the people on the left.
They're all different.
They're all weird.
You know, what he says to that first guy, he's probably not going to work if he says
it to the second guy.
They're all different in different ways, big ways, little ways.
There's no way to know.
And because they're all different, you meet a new person.
There's no documentation, right?
This poor guy, he's just met this pointy-headed person and he's scrambling through all these
books and there's no explanation.
And because there's no explanation, people can be really unpredictable.
Oh, this is going to go great.
I know exactly what's going to happen.
He's going to talk about a stellated dodecahedron.
Nope, didn't do that.
He didn't do what you thought he was going to do.
Sorry.
And because they're unpredictable, I mean, they're unpredictable partly because they've
got all this hidden state, right?
When we write our Python programs, one of the big no-nos is mutable global variables,
right?
People's heads are full of mutable globals, right?
When you come and talk to me, I may still be thinking about that rotten breakfast I
had at the hotel this morning.
You'll say something to me and you don't know that I'm thinking about that or my shoes are
too tight or I'm worried about my kid back home or something, right?
And all of that is hidden from you, right?
Oh, and by the way, this guy, one of the things he's thinking about is Sleepy Snake.
So he's got Coverage.py in his mind so I can relate to that guy.
And because of all that hidden state, you've got these nonlinear responses, right?
You say a little thing to a guy and suddenly it blows up in your face, right?
For engineering components, we'd like to have a little bit more input, give us a little
bit more output, and that is not the way people work.
And when things go badly, you might try to find out what's happening and they say, nothing.
You know, nothing.
That's a terrible error message, right?
In our systems, we like to provide feedback to the user about what went wrong and people
are not always good at that.
And it might be because they don't want to tell you that they're worried about their
kid or they think they're in a space where they're not allowed to be that vulnerable
or they really don't want to get into it.
There's just all sorts of reasons why that happens.
As engineers, we have to understand these kinds of dynamics and take them into accounts
as we deal with people so that things can go well.
So, you might be thinking to yourself now, okay, so these components, you know, I could
use a Raspberry Pi or I could talk to this person.
Why would I choose the person?
They're terrible.
Well, you don't really have a choice, right?
No matter how introverted you are, no matter how much time you spend in the quiet room,
you are going to be dealing with people, right?
You've got a boss, you've got coworkers, you've got collaborators.
Whatever you're building, someone's going to end up using it.
You're going to have to deal with people, right?
This is a part of your life and a part of your job and it's too easy sometimes for engineers
to simply overlook that aspect of what they do and therefore have it come out badly when
if you focus on it as a skill that you can build, it can go better.
And let's face it, people are fantastic, right?
I mean, they are flexible.
They can do things that other people can't, right?
If Marietta had said to a bunch of Raspberry Pis, can you help me organize this conference,
it would not be a good conference.
Instead, she can say to people, can you help me organize this conference and they are flexible
and will adapt and do great things, right?
Some of that unpredictability comes out as creativity.
I asked you to do a thing, I had an idea about how it would go and you did something beyond
my expectations.
That's amazing, that's great.
And they can reflect that energy back to us, right?
If I put some energy into you, you give some energy back to me.
And lastly, like I said, they are kind of the reason we are doing any of this, right?
Whatever it is you are doing, it's probably because there is a person somewhere that you
are doing it for.
At least I hope.
So I want to talk about how to talk to people, but again, you are a technical audience.
I don't, rather than try to convince you that you want to talk to people, let's just look
at it as people, the API user's guide.
The first, so let me just explain something before I get into that.
Let me just say, I am not a psychologist.
I am an engineer.
This model of the people, the user's guide, API user's guide, this is based on my own
experiences, debugging a bunch of interactions, reverse engineering a lot of people, reading
the trace backs from a lot of discussions that didn't go that great, and thinking about
how they could have gone better.
I am seeing some nods in the audience.
People know what I am talking about.
It's a little tricky.
Okay.
The way I think about interaction with a person is, when I talk to you, and by talking I could
mean talking, I could mean typing, I could mean sending an email, I could mean commenting
on a pull request, any way that I am sending words to you.
Every message consists of two parts.
There is information, which is the thing I mean to say, this, you know, you shouldn't
use Len of range over there, or I need you to do this task, or whatever it is I am saying
to you, there is facts involved, but there is also always sentiment.
Every message has both information and sentiment.
That's just the way people work.
When I talk to you, you are thinking about how I feel about you.
You know those programs that like read every tweet and do sentiment analysis to figure
out whether people like Nike sneakers or whatever brand, you know, people do sentiment analysis
all the time.
Every time I speak to you, you are trying to figure out how I feel about you.
You may not realize you are doing it, but you are analyzing every message that way.
That's because you want to feel good about yourself and you are a social emotional creature
that gets that feedback from around you and integrates it into your own self worth, essentially.
I know that sounds a little extreme in some ways.
It might just be a tiny amount, but it is happening all the time.
When I say sentiment, it comes down to sort of what those sentiment analysis programs
do, which is it is either a yes or a no.
I think of every message as being either a yes or a no.
The words in the message can either welcome you in or they can push you away.
Sometimes in just tiny ways, sometimes in really big ways.
But I think essentially every message can be categorized on one side or the other of
that boundary.
And the goal is to try to make every message be a yes.
The problem with information and sentiment is that people will find a sentiment even
if you didn't put it in there.
And they will default it in a few different ways.
The first way is they will think about their history with you.
Right?
Marietta just explained her history with me.
I can say things to Marietta and for the most part, it will be on a yes, if only because
Marietta has had a lot of positive experiences with me in the past.
Right?
If I walk up to someone with whom I've had a lot of conflict, a lot of those messages
will be considered negative because of our history.
The second place, the default sentiment will come from is similarity.
I've never met you before, but you seem kind of like me.
So probably it's positive.
And what do I mean by similarity?
It could be anything.
It could be you have the same stickers on your laptop as I do.
It could be that you're at PyCon with me.
In this building, if I say something to someone, it will probably strike that person better
Then if we happen to bump into each other with no identification out on the street because
they're like, oh, you're at PyCon, I'm at PyCon.
When my kid was little on the beach, he would just walk up to another kid who was like the
same age as him.
He's like, you're a kid, I'm a kid, let's just play together.
That similarity just works for people.
And if there's no history and you don't feel a similarity, then you can just, I don't like
these clickers.
I don't like these clickers.
If you can't find the similarity, then you can pretty much assume that the sentiment
is bad.
It's going to be on the no side.
Right?
And by the way, as I'm explaining this to you, let me just be clear.
I am not only am I not a psychologist, I'm not perfect at this.
I know for sure that I have had conflicts with people in this room.
I mean, first of all, my wife is sitting in the front row.
But second of all, I mean, I know I've had conflicts with people in this room that were
based on nothing more than I was careless and I said something too fast in a way that
wasn't thoughtful enough and it struck that person wrong and we had to unravel that.
And I know it's going to happen again in the future because I'm human and we're busy and
that's okay.
Standing in a programming conference, the goal isn't to never write a bug.
The goal is to be good at recognizing the bugs and fixing the bugs when they happen.
And that's the same thing that we can expect from interactions with each other.
So the defaulted sentiment, history, similarity, and bad.
And fourth, there's going to be some, I have to kind of get this moved down.
The defaulted sentiment is going to be that hidden state, right?
Everything's going to be colored by the bad breakfast you had or your too tight shoes
or you're worried about your kid, whatever it was.
Right, so all that sentiment gets defaulted if it isn't present.
And just because it's, and by the way, so the yes and the no's, the reason you want
to avoid the no's is that people will defend themselves and probably won't listen to you
if they're hearing no's from you.
Right?
So you're going to have someone yell at them and expect them to stay in contact with you.
And just to make this very concrete, let's look at some code.
Now, just to be clear, this is pseudo code.
It's not the real code.
But very simply, yeah, so when someone receives a message, they knew who the sender is, they've
got the info, but the sentiment might be missing.
If it's missing, they're going to try to find history with the sender.
If they still don't have any sentiment, they're going to try to calculate a similarity.
And if it's missing still, then the sentiment is bad.
And then they apply all that hidden state, get all those mutable globals in the mix just
to complicate things.
They'll record that history, by the way.
So whatever they defaulted, that's now part of your history with that person.
That's not your fault, but that happens.
And if the sentiment is negative, then they're just going to throw away the information.
And otherwise, they're going to use the information.
That's it.
People like to think they're complicated.
It's pretty simple in some ways.
At some level, it's kind of simple.
And you might also be thinking, like, okay, come on, we're all grownups, we're all adults
here as we say in the Python community.
Can't we just stick to the facts?
And the answer is no.
I know this is 2023, so AI, yeah, yeah, yeah, but we're still talking to people.
For the time being, at least, we are still talking to people.
We're not going to be talking to robots.
And this is the way people work.
And by the way, I don't mean to shock anyone, but everyone here, you are also one of these
people that is doing this sentiment analysis.
So at the same time that this poor guy on the right was trying to figure out all those
four people on the left, they were all trying to figure out him.
So it's a two-way street, right?
And you don't realize that you're doing sentiment analysis to other people.
I know you all love me right now because I'm amazing, but in the future, you might be having
a negative interaction with me, and that's just bound to happen.
So you're doing the sentiment analysis at the same time that people are doing it to
you.
It's a two-way interaction.
So what can we do here?
To improve your chances of not having defaulted sentiment that ruins an interaction, first
thing is to say yes.
I'll get into these more.
Second, use more words.
Third, choose your words carefully.
Four, be humble.
And five, be explicit.
Let's talk about the Meech intern.
And what I'm going to show here, I'm going to show interactions.
I'm showing it in sort of a chat format because that works visually.
And mostly what we've got is kind of newbies on the left asking questions from helpers
on the right because I've got a lot of experience from IRC and Slack and Discord, which are
kind of intense crucibles of these kinds of interactions, but the principles apply
the same across.
It's just easier to have these little quick little interactions as demonstrations.
So first thing, I said say yes, but let's look at it as don't say no.
So the newbie asks, how do I get the length of this array?
And the helper says, that's not an array.
Now that's clearly a no statement, right?
It's got not in it, right?
And let's be honest.
The guy on the right is correct.
Like he's absolutely correct.
In terms of information, absolutely correct.
Totally unhelpful, right?
He's just immediately turned off this guy on the left who now has concluded that he
must be stupid, right?
That's a bad interaction.
Instead, when they say how do I get the length of this array, he could have said the length
of that list is and given the answer, right?
He's sneakily snuck in the information the newbie needed, which is that he used the wrong
word and gave him a yes.
He gave him the answer he needed and the newbie has learned something and is happy and has
had a positive interaction, right?
So say yes.
Make your statements be yeses.
Sometimes we don't use enough words, right?
I need help with thing.
Why are you using thing?
Now this is a mistake I make all the time.
I am genuinely interested to know why are you using it?
What's going on?
What's the big story?
But simply asking why are you using thing can make a person think I knew I was doing
it wrong.
It can sound like you shouldn't have been using thing.
If you use more words, thing can be tricky.
Good, it's not just me.
I had trouble with it when I started using it.
We're similar.
I'm not weird.
If you tell us more about how you're using thing, we can make it work.
They will help me, right?
So those are a lot of words, right?
In some ways the information content between the short version and the long version was
the same but the sentiment was completely different.
And using more words helps with that.
And by using more words, I don't mean add more technical detail.
I mean put in words that are explicitly there just to add the sentiment that you mean to
express.
And choose your words carefully.
My program says one plus two is four.
That's wrong.
Yeah, that's wrong.
That's why he's asking because he knows it's wrong, right?
But instead if you had said, hmm, that doesn't sound right, you've opened up a possibility,
right?
That's wrong is kind of closing a door.
It feels like something is shut.
Hmm, that doesn't sound right.
And I've put hmm in there on purpose.
That adds a little bit of uncertainty.
It puts the person on the right in an uncertain situation too.
It makes them more similar.
It levels the power balance between the two so that they can have a conversation.
And it's part of being humble.
This guy says my if loop only returns once.
Now let's just be clear.
I have no idea what that means.
That's complete nonsense.
Like I can see through the lines sometimes of questions that don't make sense.
When he asked about an array, I knew he meant list.
I have no idea what that means.
But if you say you aren't being clear, that's an accusation, right?
There's actually a negative in it.
And that's an accusation, right?
The helper has accused the asker of something.
If the helper instead says I don't understand yet, now they're taking some of the responsibility
for the interaction.
Instead of you haven't been clear, I don't understand yet, right?
That's a type of humility, right?
It's opening the possibility that there really is something going on that can be understood,
but it just doesn't understand it yet, right?
Being humble is something that experts often have difficulty with because we've worked
hard to know a lot of stuff and we're really proud of all the stuff we know and we're very
certain of a lot of things that we know.
And sometimes we're even in a situation where we are certain about a thing and we are actually
right about the thing, but that certainty will prevent further discussion.
I don't want to get into gender stereotypes, but one good way to be humble is whatever
the opposite of mansplaining is, do that.
And lastly, a simple way to not default sentiment is to be really explicit.
Someone says what do you think of my project?
Even doing this, it's not working.
Okay.
It's really good work, right?
That's a positive statement.
It's a yes.
It gives them encouragement.
It's really good work.
Now there are some things to fix, but I can help you.
So what we've done there was we've given them a yes and a little bit of a no and then a
yes.
And that's kind of a sandwich.
You give a positive and negative and a positive and that makes for a good interaction.
And a lot of this might sound like, well, this is just kindergarten stuff, right?
This is stuff we learned in kindergarten.
Ned, all you're saying is be nice and think of the other person.
Yeah, that's what I'm saying.
Be nice and think of the other person.
Right?
I'm standing up here now telling you this, right?
But this guy, that's me at about one-tenth my current age.
That guy could have probably told you this too because he learned it in kindergarten.
It's just that as we get older, we tend to focus more on the technical stuff and we think
everyone's going to take care of themselves, but they need help.
Everyone needs help.
We're all just people trying to understand this chaotic world around us.
We're surrounded by 2,000 people.
Do they like us?
I don't know.
Let's try to figure it out.
The more you can give the messages, the better it's going to go.
All right.
We've talked a lot about sentiment.
Let's talk about some information.
Let's get some technical content.
We'll talk about some technology.
In the mid-1400s, Gutenberg developed a process for producing printed pages for movable type.
I know that's not the technology you thought I was going to talk about.
This will go quick.
Don't worry.
It's an interest of mine.
There's a point at the end.
You'll see.
Stick with me.
Developed a process producing pages from movable type.
If you wanted to make a page like this, you arranged little chunks of metal in a press
like this.
You put ink on top.
You put paper on top.
You pressed it.
That's why we still call the journalists the press, by the way.
A piece of type was a little chunk of metal that looked like this.
It had to have the image of the letter on the top.
One of the challenges was making these chunks of type uniform enough that you could get
an even impression with a consistent design.
One of Gutenberg's innovations was he developed a process for doing that.
It would start with a chunk, a bar of steel called a punch into which the end would be
carved a reversed letter at actual size.
The punch would be driven into a little chunk of brass which would produce an indentation
called a matrix.
The matrix would be put at the bottom of a mold into which you could pour molten metal
over and over again which would produce all the pieces of type.
This process of making a punch was called punch cutting.
It was a very involved process because you had to work at actual size on a chunk of steel.
It was very hard to assess how the process was going because you didn't want to take
the punch to make a matrix, to put it in the mold, to make the type, to put the type in
the press, to put ink on the type and then make a piece of paper.
Even back then it was an ordeal to get your work into production.
So instead what the punch cutter would do is that they would simply put the punch into
the flame of a candle to coat it with soot and press that onto a piece of paper which
gave them a really nice black forward reading image of the letter they were working on that
was really easy to clean off.
The word they used for that process was the same as the word we use today for a quick
assessment of our work in progress.
It's a smoke test.
I know there are other etymologies of the term.
I think this is the right one.
Fight me.
Okay.
So now once the punch cutters done their work and they've made all the type, what happens
is that a person called a typesetter would stand at a wooden tray full of type.
They'd make lines of type starting from the bottom moving up, upside down, and reading
backwards to produce all the letters, the text that had to go into the press.
They would stand at a workstation that looked kind of like this with these wooden trays
full of chunks of metal.
Let's look at how that's laid out.
So the little letters were at the bottom tray and the capital letters were at the top
tray except they didn't call them trays, they called them cases.
This was the upper case and that was the lower case and that's why you call them that today.
So remember a case insensitive regex is one which doesn't care whether the chunks of metal
come out of the bottom wooden tray or the top wooden tray.
Let's look at the layout of the lower case.
So the lower case had an ergonomic layout where the most common letters were at the
center of the tray in large compartments with less and less common letters in smaller
compartments headed out towards the edges so that the typesetter's movements would be
very, everything would be right where they needed to be.
If you look at the layout of the upper case, it goes from A to Z but with J and U at the
end.
Now, I want you to stop and think for a moment.
How are you feeling right now?
I just did something, here's the reason why I'm talking about Gutenberg.
I wanted to talk about some technology that I think most of you would have been unfamiliar
with.
I wanted you to all be newbies in this technology and I wanted to throw a lot of information
at you really fast.
I wanted to throw in some weird digressions where you weren't sure, is this important
smoke test?
Do I need to remember that?
Is this going to be on the test?
I don't know what I need to pay attention to here.
And we'd end up getting to a point where we see something so odd that it seems like it
must have been done intentionally to annoy us.
Why are J and U at the end?
Why not put them, it can't be based on the common, how common the letters are.
J is way more common than an X or a Q in capital letters, right?
And the reason I'm talking about this is that we talked a bunch about sentiment but even
the information in our messages to people can be difficult and we have to take that
into account.
And I'll talk a little bit more about that just to close the loop.
The reason J and U are at the end in the uppercase is that J and U were not considered
distinct letters in the English language until the mid 1600s, which meant that the layout
of the uppercase had been in use for 200 years by the time that J and U had to be added to
it and rather than disturb centuries of tradition, they were just added at the end.
And they remain there to this day.
If you visit a letterpress shop today, the uppercase is still laid out like this.
So the next time you want to whine about your legacy systems and backwards compatibility,
go and talk to these guys.
Okay.
But Python is also strange.
I last year's keynote, Ruka Ashlanga said, if you don't say something controversial in
a keynote, are you really living your best life?
I don't know.
Is this controversial?
Lambda is a terrible keyword.
It has no mnemonic value.
There's a historical reason, but it doesn't really come up that often and it doesn't help
people remember what's going on.
And I'm saying this not to say that Python is bad.
Python is technology.
Technology gets weird over time.
It starts weird and it gets weirder.
And that's just the way technology is.
And that's something that we deal with.
When we're talking to people, we're talking about technology and that weirdness can interfere
with our ability to communicate well with people and we need to take that into account.
We love to show people this XKCD cartoon because it's all about how Python is really great.
We're not so fond of showing them this cartoon because it's about how Python can be confusing.
And I'm not showing this cartoon to talk about packaging or installation mechanisms or to
say that Python is bad.
Python is technology.
And technology starts weird and gets weirder.
And that's just the way it is.
Right?
We talk about how Python is easy and it is compared but only compared to other programming
languages.
It's still a programming language.
It's still weird.
You may know what some of these words on the left-hand column mean.
I know what most of them mean.
You may know what some of the ones in the middle mean.
I know what most of those mean.
I have no idea what any of the words in this right-hand column mean.
Right?
Python has been hugely successful, which means that two experts in Python can have very little
terminology in common about the things they're actually dealing with day to day.
And that can also interfere with our ability to communicate.
So we need to provide context.
We need to understand that those difficulties are going to arise.
And we need to help smooth over those differences.
And it's not just Python.
I didn't think that was going to be the biggest joke in the talk.
But there it is.
All technology is weird.
It's all weird.
And we can't get away from it.
We can try to smooth off some of it, but we'll never get rid of all of it.
We have to deal with how we talk about it.
So, for example, someone might say Python is hard.
And we as Python advocates and lovers of Python, and we want to help this person, we want to
be enthusiastic and optimistic, we might say no, it's easy.
This sentence literally starts with no.
This helper is contradicting the questioner who will now decide I am stupid.
I am having difficulty with a thing that is famously easy.
Therefore I am stupid.
Even if you say it's one of the easier languages, I'm still stupid.
Right?
I didn't understand.
I can't do one of the easier languages.
Instead, you should listen to what they're saying.
Because this person's got a sentence, the subject of which is Python, but that's not
really what they're saying.
What they're saying is I am struggling.
And if you know that what they're saying is that they're struggling, then you can help
them.
It can be hard at first.
Yeah, it can be hard at first, but we can help.
It goes better.
And experts have this problem too.
So, right, I've been talking about these examples with a newbie and a helper, but the same is
true of experts.
Right?
If I start work at Metta and have to jump into their monolith, I'm a newbie.
And the first thing I'm going to think is I don't get it.
And my imposter syndrome is going to kick in, and I'm going to feel like, okay, this
was a huge mistake, and someone's going to have to help me, and we're going to be talking
about the same things as Python is hard, but with much bigger words and much longer sentences
and much longer conversations.
As we like to say in Boston Python, we are all beginners.
It's just that some of us have more practice.
One of the characteristics of being an expert is that when you get to that stumbling block,
you know you've been there many times before, and you probably have some skills to get yourself
past it, but everyone's a beginner at something.
Python is big.
Python is changing.
I don't know how to use pep669 that's coming out.
There's going to be peps after that.
I'm going to have to be the beginner at that again.
We all have to do it all the time, and we have to feel okay about our interactions.
We have to help each other.
It doesn't help that the world now looks like this.
We're all sitting at our screens.
Things are flying by.
I know there are days where I'm at home working remotely, and I feel like an air traffic controller
just trying to make sure that none of the planes crash.
Stuff's just flying around.
It's really easy in those moments to think there are a lot of notifications when really
what's happening is there are a lot of people.
Every one of those notifications is a person talking to you, and you might want to just
quick respond to something, and that's the exact opposite of use more words.
I literally have keyboard macros to help me insert softening phrases into my responses.
I can type four keystrokes and have a sentence that starts with, if you don't mind me asking,
comma, which puts me, it levels the playing field, it gives a little bit of humility,
it gives the other person that asks permission to ask my question, and that just helps the
conversation go.
Lastly, one engineering technique that we have, we all know how sprints work.
You make some goals, you do a bunch of work, and then you assess how it went, you consider
what went well, what could have been done better, and then you repeat.
You can do the same thing with your messages.
This guy says, my singleton is hard to test.
You're doing it wrong.
I did mention IRC before, right?
Okay.
I'll ask someone else.
This angry person probably genuinely felt like they want to help people, but it didn't
work.
The technique they used to help that person did not help that person.
It made that person leave.
And a little bit of reflection, what was I trying to accomplish?
How did I try to accomplish it?
Did it work?
I don't mean like every Slack message you're going to stop and have a little retro with
a wiki page or something, but having that sort of attention to how things are going,
treating this as an interaction that is valuable and you wanted to go well and how could it
go better next time is an engineering skill that you can apply to your people interactions
so that they'll be better.
It all comes down to this.
People are important.
Our interactions with people are important.
Whatever we do technically, like you might be able to write the best program ever and
debug the hardest problems, if you can't actually work with the person sitting next to you or
hear what your customer needs or figure out how to please your boss so that you get that
raise, it doesn't amount to much.
And by the way, I've had only a short time here.
We've really only just scratched the surface.
There are tons of more complex factors that come into all this.
What if it's not two people talking?
What if it's ten people in a meeting room?
What if there's an actual power imbalance because I'm your boss?
What if I'm talking to someone and it's not going well and it is not going to get better?
How do I decide how to end that?
How do I fix a conflict that I had with a person?
There's lots, lots, and lots more.
Just like every talk at this conference is only going to be able to give you an introduction
to the topic and then there's a whole PhD thesis after that to become an expert, the
same is true of interactions with people.
By the way, I mentioned that I've been writing a blog since before PyCon started.
After my first PyCon in 2007, I wrote a post, and I didn't even go and read this post until
talk, but my advice then was talk to people at PyCon, which is just what Marietta said.
The people who are here, and by the way, this whole keynote, this might be the wrong place
to do it.
You've all traveled a long way at great expense to be face-to-face with people.
You're probably exactly the experts who don't need to hear this message.
There are people that you interact with who stayed home because they don't see the point
of being face-to-face with people.
We're the ones who need to hear this keynote, but I'm hoping you can take this message and
spread it widely.
My advice for the next few days, the same as Marietta said, talk to people.
We are here because we want to talk to you.
I want to talk to you.
If you see me in the hallway, come and talk to me.
One last note.
The writer Kurt Vonnegut asked his son Mark, who's also a writer, the really big existential
question, what are we here for?
I don't mean Python developers at PyCon.
I mean people on earth.
What are we here for?
His son Mark did a very clever thing.
He both answered and avoided the question by saying, we are here to help each other
get through this thing, whatever it is.
That's my advice to you.
Help each other.
Talk to each other.
Listen to each other.
And help each other.
That's it.
Thank you.
Thank you for your attention.
I am at NedBat.
I'm on Mastodon.
And thank you to my illustrators.
Enjoy PyCon.