Okay, so all doors closed, so I assume that we can all start.
So thank you for coming for the workshop
or tutorial, whatever you call it.
So this workshop, we'll have, first of all,
we'll have a break in the middle.
It will be around 30 minutes.
I will try to be, stick to the schedule, have a break
around like 10, 30, but it really depends on the pace
of like how people are feeling and so.
So if you would need a break or anything, you don't have
to wait for the break, you can just like go get a coffee
or use the bathroom if you have to, don't worry about that.
Another thing, because I think I've already sent a message
about where you can find all these material
and slides beforehand, but if you haven't got the time
to check it, don't worry.
This is the link.
So it's on GitHub, so it's, you know, on my account
and it's called using Numba.
So if you go to that repo, you can clone it,
you'll have all the Jupyter Notebook that you need
and also there will be a link to the slide deck as well.
So, yes, that's the kind of what I want to say beforehand.
Also, I'm Chirk, I work for Alaconda.
That's why I work with the Numba team, you know, I don't match
with them like physically, but I do talk to them regularly.
So kind of, you know, if you have any questions,
I would try to answer, if not, I would direct you to them,
direct the question to them for answering.
I love open source, that's why I have been, you know,
getting involved in lots of open source projects
for a few years and also I organize events.
So I don't want to, you know, tell you
about all these different events you can go to
because you have now just started at a very amazing one.
So, yeah, you can enjoy if I can do this first.
So I want to know like what's people's background a little bit
first, so who is actually considered themselves data
scientists and handling data and doing analysis of data?
One, two, three, some of you?
So what do other people do?
Are you a developer that just write code and you are curious
about Numba and what does it do?
Okay, so maybe you have, we all have the same problem
that like we think our code are too slow
and we want it to be faster.
So for today I'm going to, you know, mainly explain Numba.
So Numba is actually designed to use, I can show you later.
So yeah, Numba actually is designed to use
with a lot of data science work, but if, you know, if you're
like curious, there's other things that also do similar things
that can compile code, I can tell you a little bit more later
about Numba, if you found that, you know,
the exercise today is not very applicable to your work
because you don't work with data, it's fine.
I can also give you other recommendation to other tools
that you may try out.
So for those of you who are mainly doing
like statistical analysis, doing like data science work,
it may be a little bit new to you, like what is profiling,
what is compiling, like why do we care about that?
Because I just, you know, day to day you load in some data
through maybe pandas, your CSV files, and then you load it in,
and you do some data kind of manipulation,
maybe you deploy some scikit-learn algorithm,
and you know, you get your results
and then create a beautiful dashboard or story to tell
to your teammate or, you know, your boss, then well, we are happy.
Why do we care about this?
So if your code is too slow, a lot of times you may wonder,
why is it slow, right?
Why it got stuck?
So profiling, I know some of you who are like,
maybe you're a software developer, if you come from a,
you know, computer science, academic background, this is,
you know, all trivial to you, but I'm just going
to get everybody in the same place.
So profiling is actually we are investigating what our code is
doing, right?
We call that dynamic analysis because, you know,
there are different ways you can analyze your code,
but how profiling do is actually some kind of tool that is
like running along with your program and then kind
of inspect what it is doing when it's got executed.
So, you know, those are called profilers.
They're different type of profilers.
I have also, you know, a few days ago I was in PyCon DE
and I give a talk about profile, memory profiling,
which is another type of profiling.
Today we care more about the speed.
So, you know, there are tools that do that and we want to investigate
because we want to know which part is slow.
Maybe we can improve that part that's actually slow.
So compiling is another tool, kind of things you could do
to improve the speed of your code.
So for those of you who is like maybe from a science background,
from another background that is not computer science, then, you know,
you may heard about the term compiling a lot,
but you don't actually know what it does.
So for some programming languages,
compiling is required to execute your code.
For Python doesn't work that way, but there are other programming
languages that work that way.
So compiling is actually because your computer actually, you know,
they're dealing with zero and ones, right?
So they can only understand things that are low level,
which is for example machine code.
They are basically numbers.
They are zero and ones.
So your machine can understand.
But that's, you know, nobody want to write code in machine code
because it's so difficult.
So that's why we want to write in a programming language
that can be compiled into a model level code that kind of, you know,
is like a translator who translate a piece of article
like a Google translate from a foreign language
to a language that you understand.
So compiling is translating that from a human understandable one
to the machine understandable one.
So before doing that, like I said,
Python works slightly differently
before other programming language, for example C, C++.
The program needs to be executed before it can be,
the programming to be compiled before it can be executed.
So sometimes you make actually, I heard people talk about that
for beginners actually, you know, C and C++ is very,
you know, a little bit difficult to learn comparing to Python
because every time you make some changes,
you have to compile the code before it can get executed again.
So if you have a huge chunk of code, as I remember my time
in university that like, you know, the C++ course,
they teach a C++ for the first programming language, scary.
And then you have a lot of different files, you know,
if the program is big, then you have to compile all of them
and then run it super slow to kind of test things out.
So, but there is a good thing about compiling is
that once you compile the code, it's actually because, you know,
it's already in a form that the machine understands.
So actually it can be very fast.
But Python doesn't do it like that.
So again, like, you know, we are here.
We want to make our code faster, especially during data science work.
So this is the strategy that we're going to deploy today.
We'll analyze what make the code very slow.
So at the beginning of this workshop, you know,
unfortunately there's a lot of concept, a lot of things
like how to use NumPy or this.
I need to clarify first through the first few exercises.
And after you get a chance to get your hands on to a final big project
that you're trying to improve the code.
So this is your strategy, right?
You can analyze it and then you see which part is slow.
You try to make the slow code faster.
Sometimes compiling is not needed.
For example, NumPy, because it's already have a lot
of optimization of itself.
Then what it does is that, you know, for example,
if you have used NumPy, you know that avoid element-wise operation.
Try to use matrix operation because NumPy is optimized for that.
So that would make your code faster without using NumPy
or any other things to compile your code.
But sometimes, you know, even you try to avoid all the slow code,
sometimes it's not avoidable.
Then compiling may actually help you.
But how? Then I will go into the detail later.
So number, number is a JIT compiler.
So again, at the first half of the workshop,
a lot of concept need to be clear, right?
What is a JIT compiler?
Scratch your head.
What is JIT?
But what we can get from this definition, which I copy
from the documentation, is that we know that it's worth for NumPy.
So it's very good for a lot of numerical code because a lot
of numerical code actually use NumPy.
So it's kind of designed for that.
It translates a set of Python codes.
So translating code, something to do with compiling.
Well, compiler already told you that it's doing some compiling.
That's why it does.
And so your code will be, you know,
a chunk of your code will become low-level code, which is faster.
So, but what makes it different from the compiling
that I explained earlier?
What is the difference from, for example, C or C++
that you compile the whole program?
Is that, is a JIT compiler.
It's not just a compiler.
But JIT, JIT, stands for just in time.
So I found this term very funny.
And once I know what it means that I use it in my daily life,
I'll be like, oh, just in time finishing a presentation,
you know, that kind of thing.
Which means that it basically finish it last minute
when it does compiling.
So, hmm, it's getting more questions than answer right now.
Because how Python work is
that Python does not compile the program.
Like I said before, you don't have to, you know,
write all your Python code and then run some command
to compile all your Python code, which is maybe something.py,
into a low-level code.
So, so Python doesn't work that way.
Python is actually an interpreter.
So for those of you who have not thought about that before,
Python, that is on your machine.
It could be, for example, you download it from PyPI,
or maybe you get it from Alaconda,
there's a Python inside.
So that, well, Python itself, we all know,
is a programming language.
But that thing that's in your machine,
that is actually an executable file.
So it's actually a small program in your computer
that interprets your Python code into code
that the machine understands.
So, for example, C Python is actually interprets Python
into C, and then C, of course, is, you know, can be compiled
into lower-level code so your machine will understand
those C code and it will understand your Python code.
So it takes time.
So Python, that's why you have heard a lot
of people say Python is slow, right?
Because, you know, every time you have to go through these steps
of like, you know, when you see Python, you know,
if you use Windows, actually, it's Python.exe,
so it's executable file, it will see your code,
and then it will, like, pass it to the C APIs, and it will, like,
and then it starts to work.
It's slow.
It's not like your, for example, you write a program purely in C
that before you run it, it's already compiled.
So every time you run it, you run that compiled form,
so it's super fast.
So what, how can we, how can we,
how can this compiler kind of modify the, you know,
the behavior and to make things faster for ourselves?
Is that when you can, you'll see the code later,
well, you can define this part, I want it to be applied
to be compiled, and every time the number
or other JIT compiler see that bit, and then, okay,
if you're going to, you know, the first time you saw it,
for example, in your definition, it's not going
to do anything yet, but until that part,
that function is called, then it knows that, oh,
you're not writing things for nothing.
You're actually using it.
Okay, I'll compile it for you.
So next time you use it, it will be faster.
So that's the magic, right?
So remember one thing, when the JIT compiler sees your code
that want to get executed for the first time,
it will compile it.
Okay, so what does that mean?
It means that if you just use that function
for the first time, you will go through the step
of the compiler will compile your code
and it got executed, right?
But the first, the second time,
when you record that function again,
it won't compile the code again because the same thing,
you haven't changed the definition of your function.
It's going to be just the same thing.
So it got to look for the already compiled code
and execute that one.
So it means that the first time and the second time,
when you call that compiled function,
the speed will be different, okay?
So bear that in mind because that will be useful
in our exercise later.
And that's also explain why a lot of times, you know,
people just use a JIT compiler and stuff
and it may not speed up your code,
but if you have a loop that you actually do the same thing
again and again and again, then that would actually help you.
So be smart, don't use the JIT compiler
for things that are not looping
because then that may actually be slower.
So, well, numbers, a number is designed for NumPy.
Like I said, it's designed for scientific kind of coding.
There's another thing you may have heard about called Cython.
Cython, again, is, you know, is a JIT compiler.
It will compile your code.
That is more kind of, you say, I would say more general.
And actually a lot of your, the thing that you use,
for example, Panda, actually under the hood,
it uses a lot of NumPy because it will help, you know,
type Pandas to be faster.
And for example, Cycular also uses a lot of Cython.
It kind of helped the algorithm to be faster.
So, yeah, so this, the NumPy or Cython, they are all
like JIT compiler and they have been used in other libraries
without you kind of knowing.
So it's actually there everywhere.
And so a number, again, like I said, because it's a JIT compiler,
it kind of, for the things that are loops, is where it shines.
So if it's, again, be smart.
Think about when you use it, where you use it.
So in a number, there are different modes that you could use.
So ideally, you want everything to be no Python mode
because I think now you may already understand Python is slow.
So we want to avoid Python.
So using no Python mode means that everything that is defined
in that, all the code that you include
into no Python mode should be compiled into something
that is slow level, that is, you know, it doesn't go
through the Python CAPI, which is the interpreter that I talk about.
You know, it will see your Python code
and it tells the CAPI to do stuff.
So we want to bypass that.
We want to directly compile that bit of the code
and then it will get called directly in like very fast speed
because it's low level code.
Its performance is very good.
If you can make all the things no Python mode,
then you would probably have a very fast time with, you know,
if you don't count the compiling time.
But it's not always the case, right, because, you know,
a lot of number things, a lot of, you know, simple calculation,
you can use no Python mode.
But we all have been there, right?
We have, you know, used different Python objects
to do different things.
So those Python objects, if you are using it,
then you can't use no Python mode because they are Python object
and Numbar doesn't understand.
So you have to use something called object mode, which is kind of,
it can still have some capability of handling Python object,
but for the base that it sees
that actually you can bypass it, it will bypass it.
So it's kind of a middle ground between not doing anything
and using no Python mode.
So, you know, it sometimes kind of make your life easier,
but then you have no control of what is actually being done.
So this is, you'll see the syntax very soon when we go
to the Jupyter Notebook.
So to use Numbar, we just call in the decorators.
So there are two decorators, you know, JIT and NJIT.
So NJIT means no Python mode.
JIT means by default it's object mode, but you can also,
like here, see that actually you can also change JIT
into no Python mode.
But sometimes if you use everything no Python mode,
instead of typing so many things, you can just call in NJIT.
So, yeah, I've already covered this.
You know, ideally you want everything to be no Python mode,
to be optimum performance, but a lot of times, you know,
you may accidentally or in under the hood is using some Python
object that you can't avoid that.
Then maybe to make things work, you just switch to object mode.
So there are other things that actually Numbar would be very
useful as well.
For those of you, for example, you all work with a cluster,
you work with the CUDA GPUs or you have a CUDA GPU at home,
then you may wonder, okay, you know, does Numbar help me?
Because Numbar does support CUDA GPU, but I'm not going
to cover it today because not everybody is using a GPU,
CUDA GPU especially.
So, but there's talk that actually talk about that in detail.
If you, those of you who use it
and you wonder how you can use it to get a number,
that is the place that you could look into.
So I think I talked too much and so we better look
at the notebook and do it together.
Like I said, there's a lot of things that at the beginning,
there's a lot of concept when you clear a bar.
So unfortunately, you have to hear me talk a lot,
but after that, there will be chance for you to kind of code
and then, you know, try to, you know, in a similar kind of setting
of when you're working and stuff.
So get the Red Bull and then, oh, by the way,
the Wi-Fi is already there.
I hope you already discovered it before I start talking.
So let's, oh, I, you know, always have the documentation ready.
It's very useful.
If you have an error, you don't know what it work, why it's
like this and you don't understand how it works or how to,
you know, even the syntax, just refer
to the documentation, it's fine.
So in the notebook, you have a few things.
Ignore the others, but maybe have a look at readme
if you just downloaded it.
But otherwise, other things, you know, you just need
to worry about the notebook.
So I hope you already have the capacity
of opening a Jupyter notebook.
There are a lot of ways to set it up.
For me, I just, because this is my personal computer, I just,
you know, set up myself, install Jupyter notebook
and install these things by pip install.
But if you don't want to, you know, set up yourself,
you are already, you know, using Alaconda.
Alaconda will have all of them included as well.
So let's open the first notebook.
We will do it together and then we will read the code together
to try to understand what's going on here.
Oh, so far any questions?
I talk too much.
So any questions I want you to talk?
No? Yes, no?
Okay, all good?
Following? Good.
So, you know, this is the exclamation mark magic.
It just means that you can execute some kind of command
on the, like, command prompt.
So if you haven't got, like, number and unpy install,
you run this out.
But if you have installed it, this is useless for you.
So don't do anything.
I'm just skipping it.
So this is kind of like demonstrating how number works.
So like I said before, there's JIT and NJIT.
They are decorators that you could import from number.
So the decorator would decorate the function
and then just basically is marking that number,
understand that bit that we want to compile.
So, yeah, so you have to, so first thing I think, like,
people asked me before, they're like, oh,
what if I have just a bunch of code?
Well, you have to wrap it in a function.
Otherwise, I don't know, like, can you just, like,
kind of turn it on and off?
Maybe, but the most, you know, official way to do it is
to use the decorator.
You have to wrap your process, your calculation,
whatever, in the function.
So we are also doing some timing here just to check,
like, comparing the time with or without the compiling.
So this is doing something very simple, right?
You just have a huge NumPy array
and then we would just do some kind of calculation with it.
And so these two functions are basically the same.
The only difference is that one of them, we would modify
that function by applying a decorator,
which is the JIT decorator.
And we are using no Python mode, so, you know,
you can actually change it.
If you want, you can change it to NJIT.
And then you can change it to NJIT and then delete this.
This will be the same.
All right?
You can try both, but I would just stick
to the original one for now.
They are basically the same, like I said before.
So that's why this is an experiment,
so there's not much we can do, but we can look at the result
and try to make sense out of it.
So which one is the fastest?
Which one?
It's quite obvious.
Or you can look at your machine.
Your machine may be different,
but it should give the same result.
Who get the without compilation the fastest?
Let me know.
You have the without compilation the fastest.
Yeah, so you can see it's very interesting here.
It's like with compilation, and then after compilation,
why there's like two different things, right?
We are comparing the one with the JIT, one without the JIT,
but why there's two here?
So if you look at the comments, it's already trying
to explain it.
So without compilation is your baseline, so it's
like what you do, normally do, with like Python doing Python thing,
you don't interrupt it, you just let Python be Python.
So this is the without compilation time.
So you can see they are at the different amount,
so be careful when we do this kind of experiment.
Be careful of like what scale are you looking at.
So you can see the first one and the last one.
Actually they are comparable,
but the last one is actually kind of one-third of the time
that you take, maybe half.
Let's say it's like half the time, which is like double the speed.
But the one in the middle is the puzzle that we have, right?
Like why this one is so slow?
It's like in order of like five, it's like slower.
It takes like, how could it be like one to the power,
ten to the power of five times slower?
Well, actually ten to the power of four times slower,
but it's very, very slow, the one in the middle.
So what happened?
What happened is that if you re-look at the code, right?
So this is without compiling, this is Python, okay fine.
So this is the one that we are using GoFast,
which is the one we add the JIT here.
So this one is supposed to go fast.
Why is this so slow?
The reason being, like the opening, I already planned the seat
in your head that compiling is slow.
And because it's a JIT compiler, it doesn't compile this bit
of code beforehand, right?
When you execute it, so Python is reading, you know,
it's like okay, I'm trying to talk to CAPI,
try to get your thing done, until here.
It's like oh, now the number come in and say like wait a second,
that is the JIT, so that's like me doing my thing,
now I will compile it.
So okay, Python said fine, okay, Numbah compiled it,
but compilation takes time.
So this one, that's why it takes so long,
because it's compiling.
So for example, if you only call GoFast once,
so what would you do is actually have a slower program
than the original one, than the normal one.
So this is not a good thing.
However, if you call GoFast a second time,
since it's already compiled, so again, you know,
Python read all the code and then go here and then Numbah jump
in again and say hold on a minute,
this one I have already compiled,
just grab that already compiled things,
don't need to talk to the CAPI anymore.
It's like okay, so execute that super fast, all right.
Yes?
So if this is compiled in like a certain scope,
does it apply to the outside of that scope?
Use the function again or it's only that?
No, it's only that bit.
So that's why you have to wrap the bit that you want to speed
up in a function and then apply a decorator to it.
So for those of you who are maybe new to decorator,
this add thing is actually would take what it decorates,
which is a function, and then modify it, right.
So well, normally you can write a decorator
and modify it using Python code, but this time, of course,
Numbah is doing the Numbah magic, right.
It will come in and modify it and make it into another blob
of things, which is the compiled code
and then it will get referenced.
So next time when Python see it, it won't talk to the CAPI
to try to do what it normally do, but that will try to call
that already compiled bit or if it's the first time, compile it.
So yes, questions?
Yes?
Okay.
You mean comparing?
So, if you're asking what's the difference between the GOFAST calling first time
and the GOFAST calling the second time?
Ah, so if you put in a different X, you mean?
You are very ahead of our time because, no, no, no, it's a very good question
because you have very good thinking.
That's why you already see the problem that we may encounter in the future, right?
So, you will see later when we go to Chapter 2,
sometimes we would come into some problem.
Is that because Python do dynamic typing, right?
So, in Python code, this input can be anything.
It could be integer, it could be floating point, it could be imaginary number even.
But for NGIT or the JIT no Python mode, it doesn't work that way.
You need to have a defined type.
So, that's why if you like the scenario, you suggest that, oh,
what if I put another X in GOFAST the second time?
What if it's a floating point this time?
Hmm, well, it won't happen because we can't compile it if that's the case.
If we don't know the type of the input, then it can't be compiled.
We will see that problem later, then it will make more sense.
But it's very good that you raised this question because all
of us will have this question later, okay?
It's very good.
So, now we have the basic understanding.
So, this example is just to explain that what it's actually doing
and the first time actually is slower.
So, we have to remember that is the main thing that people got confused
when they start using number.
And that's why they think, oh, it's not really helping me.
So, it may be one of the reason why.
So, now we are learning something about not just number,
about NumPy as well.
So, like I said before, NumPy is designed for numerical calculation,
especially for matrix calculation, right?
So, we are now, so in this experiment or example,
we are creating a NumPy array that's quite big, okay?
So, we are doing some calculation with it.
So, this is something with sine and cosine there.
I don't like the name of this, like, it's some trickle-o-machy thing,
right, like, you know, like the triangle, you calculate that,
the tangent, whatever, the bit.
So, I'm not going to explain the math.
But there are multiple ways of doing this calculation.
So, for example, the first one, I'm using a NumPy operation,
which is basically, you know, for example,
if x is a NumPy array, I would just use the NumPy method,
the sine and cosine there, and do the thing, do the calculation,
instead of the second one here.
So, I would run this, I know this is out of order,
but I will run this code because I'm explaining this one.
So, this one, I'm doing a loop.
I'm doing element-wise operation.
So, the difference is that this one, because this np.cosine
and np.sine, they are NumPy methods that is built
to handle NumPy array.
So, you don't have to worry about each element in this array.
It will just handle it by itself.
We don't know what it does.
Actually, we know, but I'm not going to show it yet.
So, this is if you don't understand NumPy, if you think
about it in a more kind of more, you know, deep dive way,
it's like, wait a second, I have to, you know,
calculate one by one, right?
Because it's a matrix, you know, and it's very complicated.
I want to do it one by one, so just so that, you know,
I am in control.
I know what's going on.
Okay. So, if you compare these two, so,
oh, you already see the warning.
It means that this one's quite slow.
So, I'm going to explain a little bit about what's going on.
Why this one is way quicker than this one,
because in NumPy, it uses not just Python, right?
So, if you do this inside NumPy,
it won't do what you think it's doing.
So, you may think, oh, NumPy is calculating it element-wise,
you know, it's just a shortcut for us to use this,
make our code cleaner.
No, it's more than that.
NumPy will have some already compiled component.
They are low-level code.
They are not written in Python,
and it will just make this calculation way faster.
So, that's why in NumPy, a lot of times,
people tell you do matrix operation,
don't do element-wide operation, because they are super slow.
You see, it's still running.
It's slow, because if you do this,
it's just purely using Python to do this element-wise operation,
and Python is very slow, and you are looping it a lot,
because this one is one to the power of seven,
so it's actually a lot of numbers that we are looping,
doing it one by one.
It's very, very slow, and you want to avoid it.
But why do I talk about that?
Why do I talk about, like, element-wise operation?
It is because sometimes, you know,
so this one, we already have a very nice NumPy built-in method
that can handle it for us, so we don't have to worry about it.
Just do the NumPy way, and we will get it done.
But sometimes, you want to do something
that is maybe a little bit specific,
that it doesn't have a NumPy operation that has to do that for you.
You have to do it element-wise.
I can't think of a very good example on the top of my head,
but sometimes, for example, because there's always a way
that you could do some smart thing with NumPy and get away with it.
But for example, you do very, very strange things
that you compare to array, and then you do a Fibolochi number,
whatever, that is like, nobody do that except you.
Then it won't be in NumPy.
You have to do it element-wise.
You have to do it yourself.
So you have to write it like this yourself.
So, oh, no, this time, you see this is like 10 times slower.
This is millisecond, right?
This is second, so it's like already 3-0 slower.
So it's very, very slow.
But sometimes, you kind of avoid,
because you're doing some very, very specific things,
and I need to do it element-wise.
But I don't want to have a program that basically runs overnight,
because every time I run an experiment, I change something
that would cost me a day to run, which is bad,
especially for data scientists.
Because sometimes we have project that you have to have result
within a week, within a month, oh, no, can't, don't have that time.
So, what should I do?
So you see that now we're using NGIT.
Basically, it's the same thing like we do before,
no Python mode, okay?
Just to show it can be done differently.
If you want, you can again change it into no Python mode
if you want to try it yourself.
So this is element-wise operation.
It's stuff that, oh, this is not error, okay, sorry,
confused a little bit.
The element-wise operation is here, down there, loops.
There's those element-wise.
So let's try to use number to see if it will help us to be faster,
right, because every time things are slow,
it's like, oh, I would use number.
You see that?
We try to run it first, because again,
if we time it the first time, you can actually try it.
You can try not executing this, and you have
to restart your kernel, but you can try.
If you haven't done it, you haven't run it,
you can try running this one first, and then run,
and then you can like do it again, or run it two times.
It will say that, because the result, if you forget
to run this one and run this one, the result will tell you
that, oh, actually the result is a bit strange.
The first one is super slow, but the mean won't be correct
because the first one is slower than the rest.
So it gives you a hint that, oh, I haven't compiled it yet.
But this is the speed when it has been compiled.
So it's quite an improvement, one to four compared to 200.
So it's a slight improvement, but it's an improvement.
Good. We love it.
We love seeing improvement.
But this element-wise thing, right, this thing that you try
to avoid very, very hard, but sometimes you can't avoid,
now NumBot is going to be a Superman and come and save you.
So let's compare this to the one before.
This one, this cell, I give you a warning
that it takes a long time to run.
But this one is still running, but already, yes, it's fast.
It's already done.
And this one is actually even faster
than the original NumPy.
So, wow, what happened here?
Yes, it's crazy, right?
Like we, this is, you know, everybody use NumPy as a scale
of these element-wise operations.
We know it's going to take forever.
And now using NumPy is super fast, because again,
the magic is the reason why it's so slow is
that because it loops for a lot of time, right?
Remember how big it is.
The bigger your array, if you do element-wise,
it's each one of them.
So this one got one to the power of, you know, 10 to the power of seven.
So if you do it one by one, it's very slow.
It adds up, you know, even if it's not, you know,
even if one of them is not super slow, but it all adds up, right?
So if one of them is improved by, let's say, half the time,
it's already saved you a lot of time,
because it has got compiled and it's super fast, right?
So it's a good thing.
It's a good thing.
And next time, if you're stuck, right, if you're, oh my God,
I have to do element-wise operation in NumPy, like I have to loop,
or even, you know, you have to loop a lot of things, right?
So if you're like, for example, calculating a, for example,
you're calling the, with the Fibolochi or whatever that, like,
you know, you have to call a lot of the function,
a lot of time, then this is here to help you.
So the rest of this notebook is going to tell you all these,
like, kind of smaller things.
So those two that I talked to you about, the main key takeaway.
These are the small things
that you can improve a little bit more.
Yes?
It will help you when you write the loop yourself,
but it won't help much if you don't write the loop.
It will still help.
If you compare these two, it will have a slight improvement.
It won't go slower, but it, well, unless you have
to compile it the first time, then it's slower.
But you will still get, generally,
like after compilation, you'll get an improvement.
But if it's not a loop, then, you know, you have to compile it,
and you may as well not do it.
So yeah, like, loop is where it shines the most.
So try to improve it when you have to loop.
Or, yes?
Yeah, so.
So.
So I think there's multiple scenario
that we're encountering here.
So, for example, let me clarify, because now we are learning,
right, that's why we will compile it first and then run it.
But in a practical scenario, you won't write it separately.
You would just like, for example, you have a loop.
You would just call it, because, you know, you don't, we don't,
how can I say, we don't actually comparing the actual compiled
and the non-compiled version.
This is, you know, in a teaching setting that we do that.
But if you, for example, oh, I have this piece of code,
and it's in my project, and I have to make it faster.
You just apply this engine and then run it.
You won't be, you know, oh, I have to write it first
and then write it second time.
You won't, you just, for example, you won't even write time it,
because you just want it to be fast.
And then you already, maybe you already tried before,
but in production, you won't write time it.
So you just run it once.
For your question, that, oh, if I'm reading, for example,
I'm reading a lot of things, I'm processing all this data,
then how can I be faster?
Well, so again, you can think of this
as the case of element-wide operation.
For example, each row is an element.
Then you could actually, you know, compile handling each row.
And then every time, it would be like very fast.
But we have to be careful, because, again,
number is designed for numpy.
So it's not designed to handle io,
which is reading the data, those kind of things.
It really can't, because io is a thing
that number is not going to be speed up,
because that is a Python object.
And those things, like, it's not what number is designed for.
So, and also, a lot of times, io is more complicated.
It's not just how your, you know, your code work and stuff.
It's also about, like, how your computer files system
or this more complicated stuff.
So it was, we are trying to speed up the internal part,
but not the reading and, you know, and output the data part.
So, yeah, so there's multiple things.
I know it's very complicated, and you're thinking, oh,
if I work, how can I use it?
So hopefully by the end, when we try to use it,
then it's getting more clear.
So these are small things that you could use together
with what we just explained and make it go fast.
So, oh, what is fast map?
What is this swing?
Scratch your head.
This is kind of the case that I would see
that it's not being used a lot, because a lot of times, it may,
it's a very, very minor thing,
that kind of smoothing the edge or something like that.
Now, what happened is that for these computer, this chip,
and how they handle mathematical calculation,
there is a compliance that they follow.
Reason being that, you know, because your computer
or this memory and stuff, they are finite, right?
So if it's not handled correctly,
you may accidentally get wrong results
because the digits are overflowing, all these things,
that I'm not going to explain it again.
Like, you can read it yourself if you want,
but it's a very complicated thing
that someone has a PhD published, so I'm not that smart.
But so what happened is that if you use fast map with NGIT,
it means that we'll relax this compliance,
meaning that we are not following this, but why do we do that, right?
Because sometimes following the compliance to make sure
that all the precision, you know, sometimes, you know,
a flow number can have a lot of precision, right?
Sometimes we don't need all those digits, right?
At the end, for example, when you report your result,
you're truncated anyway, so all these digits,
at the end, you don't really care.
So what you can do is to use fast map,
you release that compliance.
It may introduce, in a very unfortunate case,
it may introduce some small error at those digits
that you don't care, but you don't care anyway, so it's fine.
But by releasing this compliance, then we don't have
to follow the rules of, for example, doing this operation first
and then do this, then you won't have the precision error.
But fast map kind of, you know, we sacrifice the decision
but to increase speed because we don't have
to really follow the order.
We just do whatever order is the fastest
for the computer to handle.
So this is a small demonstration about how it can be faster.
But again, for me, I see it as more like a kind of last speech
of things you can do because, you know, it does improve
but it's not the major improve like, for example,
the looping things that we showed earlier that can do.
So, yes, this comparing using fast map and not using fast map.
So they're both using NGIT.
They are supposed to also do the sum very fast.
But if we relax the compliance, which is using fast map,
then it's slightly faster.
So you can see that it's like five-mini-second faster.
Like, again, it's not a huge, it's not like, oh,
multiple improvement.
It's a slight improvement for, if you, again, looping and doing a lot
of agromatical calculation, then your computer, if they don't have
to follow the compliance, they can just do it as fast as they can.
It will be slightly faster.
But this is the last bit of improvement that you want to do.
For example, you, you know, you have nothing else to optimize, right?
You have already done a good job.
You want to just go through the finish line,
do it a little bit better than you can maybe think
about whether you can use fast map.
Another thing that you could improve is to use multiple cores.
For example, my computer, now, you know, nowadays,
you can easily get a computer that has multiple core.
If you do something on your cloud service,
you can also use multiple cores.
So it could be fast.
When I write this tutorial,
I was still using a very old dual core thing.
So it's, but you can still see some improvements.
So if I run it now with this new computer, it should be quite good.
So.
Before it's 130 something, right?
Yeah. So this one is the same thing, cosine sine.
Remember this thing?
So if we use, so my new computer is eight cores.
So if you compare one to four, this is without the multiple core.
This is with, so it's kind of like one-third of the time saved.
So, so yeah, it's kind of three times faster, right?
So, you know, Python, Python by default is not multi-core.
It's not multi-thread.
Python by default is single thread.
So by using this, we would also, I don't know what it does.
Maybe remove the GIL.
I don't know.
Then, yeah, it would be using the power of multiple cores faster.
What if you do not want to use parallel?
It seems like it does.
I would say sometimes there were, you may come,
and I can't think of a good example again.
Like, but some algorithms
that multi-thread actually can damage the result.
Yeah, because it's kind of similar to the concept, right?
Like, fast math, it has to follow certain order
to make the precision.
But for some other algorithms, for example,
like parallel would actually mess things up.
And sometimes, you know, the scary bit is
that it will mess things up, and then you don't actually know
that it got messed up.
So you get the wrong result, and then you thought it's right.
So yeah, for this thing, like, you know, this is demonstration,
and we all know how it works, and that's fine, but be careful.
Yeah.
You mean like this one, or?
Yeah. Yeah.
So if, actually, I can quickly do an experiment, if you allow me.
So I can restart the kernel, okay, restart.
So it, go back to original state, and then we try to quickly want
to run some of the thing that I need, for example,
I need to import whatever things here.
Oh, I need this, probably.
And then, okay, so yeah, I think I have the njt and jit, right?
I'll run a few of these.
Oh, yeah, njt's not defined, so I'll run off these.
So, okay, now let's go back to here.
I think it should be fine.
So I have these, right, parallel ones, so I created this.
And I don't run, I don't compile it this time.
I jump directly to this one.
If I run it, yeah, you will see that.
What happened is that here is, actually it's not, maybe it's strange
because, yeah, it doesn't show.
But anyway, like, what this does is that it will compile,
so maybe I have some previous memory of this, say, if you have
to go back to maybe, like, restart this, or whatever.
So yeah, what I want to show is that, like,
if I run it after I've compiled it,
because the first one is always slower, right?
Like, for example, this, go back to this example.
You see that this is doing the same thing, go fast, right?
So the first time is always lower.
So when I want to compare the results, it depends.
You know, sometimes you may be like, oh, I want to see, actually,
right, actually when I want to code, how much it improved.
Then you may want to include the first one,
because the compilation time should be taken into account.
But if you just want to do a pure comparison, how fast it is,
by compiling it, then that's why in this notebook,
we always run it second time,
because the first time we want to exclude that, right?
But yeah, I don't know why it's not showing,
but like, if you don't run this cell,
if you directly run it, it should show you that, oh,
the result is a bit strange, because, you know,
the first one is actually slower.
They will tell you that, you know, the deviation is very big
because of the first one, very slow, something like that.
But yeah, mess around with the notebook.
You may be able to see that, strange things yourself.
So yes?
I know this is probably only for the second time,
but have you tested within this OL,
if you can put out, like in every,
the second would be something, something for the book.
I would think probably with the file mode,
you have like, reading from outside,
like, you might be able to do faster than that.
Yeah, that's something that I think is worth trying.
I haven't tried myself, again, like,
I don't know if numbers are gonna work in that scenario,
because probably if you, anything involve IO,
you can't use NGIT mode, you have to use the object mode,
which is just the JIT.
But yeah, like, multi-fretting, practically,
is supposed to be faster, right?
But for example, IO, that kind of things,
then you also have to use a tool
that is also be thread safe,
because especially when you're accessing the same object
with different thread, and it could, weird thing can happen.
So I would say that, yeah, you can look at Numbah,
but also maybe look at Siphon,
maybe they know how to handle it.
I haven't looked, I haven't used Siphon for ages,
but I've just talked to the commenting,
like a few days ago in Germany.
So yeah, if you encounter him in a conference,
then you can ask him, like, oh, is it thread safe?
But yeah, I think, you know, but also,
so my talk tomorrow, we talk about, like,
sometimes scientific programming,
do we get the improvement of using multi-fret?
It depends.
So yeah, so come to my talk tomorrow,
if you want to talk more about multi-fretting,
JIT and other stuff.
So yeah, so that's the first notebook.
Any other questions?
Do you want a coffee?
Do you want a break?
Yes, I can see some nothing.
So originally, the plan is 1030, we have a 30-minute break.
How about now we have a 15-minute break,
and then we would maybe have another break later?
Okay, good.
So we will come back at 1015.
Okay, so we are about to start.
Before we move on, actually, I have a question as a survey.
So I want to know what environment people are using normally
for work or for example, this,
I know that we're all using juvenile notebook,
but so what would you use, for example, do you prefer,
who do you use PIP to install your things?
PIP? PIP.
Who use Conda?
So a few of them, okay.
Okay, so who use, so this is very tricky.
Who use Pi Env to manage your environment?
Okay, how many use Conda?
Okay, oh, actually it's quite even.
Okay, Poetry?
Oh, Poetry is getting more popular.
Okay, who is using others that I haven't asked?
Okay, I don't know that one.
Any others?
Okay, good.
I just want to know what people are using.
So thank you for participating.
Okay, let's go back to Numba.
So, okay, so there are, so I think some
of you already kind of very smart, right?
You already have questions about, oh, you know,
why do we have JIT and NJIT?
When do we use it?
And what if it doesn't work?
And all those things.
We now going to debugging or problem solving territory
that like when you start using Numba,
you may come across some of these.
Again, Numba is, you know, so some of you ask me like, oh,
so when will I use it because, you know,
a lot of mathematical library already optimized.
I would say that for most of you,
you may actually be using Numba without you thinking
about Numba because it's written in some of your libraries.
So I would say that the maintainers, they use it the most.
So but for those of you who, you know, doesn't have plan
to contribute to that project or become a maintainer,
then maybe one day there's an edge case that like, for example,
you have a thing that no library is providing that for you.
You have to write it yourself.
And so you also have to do some optimization yourself.
Then this is the time that, you know,
you suddenly remember this and maybe you look
at this Jibudana book again.
So yeah, so it's not a very,
that's why it's not a very popular tool.
A lot of people don't know about it,
but actually they're using it without knowing.
Okay, so that's why sometimes it's difficult
when you come across, encounter a problem.
For example, remember when you learn pandas, you know,
you have some error message or how do I do this?
You can Google and a lot of answers will be provided, right,
because the user base is very big.
For number, it's a bit tricky because a lot of times, you know,
you can't find exactly what you want the answer easily.
So, but I hope that by this notebook it can solve some
of the very more common problems that beginners may came across.
So it already saves some of your time to troubleshoot.
So now we are doing something that someone already mentioned.
Oh, what if I compile the function and it's designed for integer
and then I now put in a float?
So what happened?
So this is the problem that is caused by the type.
So, you know, in Python, types are very dynamic.
You can put in anything.
You can change the type or, you know, but for program
that need compiling doesn't work like that, right?
If you have learned other programming languages, for example,
against C or C++, those you have to define the type
of the variable.
It's not dynamic like Python.
So those are actually, you know, designed to be compiled, right?
So it's not like Python.
Python is like I said, it's interpret bit by bit.
So it's kind of figured out as it goes.
But for compiled program, you need to know beforehand
because the code needs to be translated into something
that a machine understand.
And if you can't just suddenly decide a type
because it has been translated
and the machine is not very smart.
It's very rigid.
You need to know the type beforehand.
So now, so let's look at this.
This again, it was reminding that like NGIT is like,
it's the no Python mode.
So we are compiling this for sure.
And we're adding two numbers.
And this is something that you may do in Python, right?
X and Y, there may be a naughty user putting something
that is not integer.
Or if it got passed in from another function
and then it may come in as a string.
For example, if you're running your Python code
and then having the, you know, when you're typing the command,
Python my code.py and then one and two.
So those one and two actually come in as a string.
So this is what you would do.
Oh, I'll convert into integer and then it will be fine, right?
So it's fine in Python, but it's not always fine.
So this is no Python mode.
So this is, you know, again, the more rigid mode.
I can't handle Python object.
So this is kind of working fine, you know,
because both of them are integer.
It know what to do because these two are supposed
to be integer, right?
So everything is fine.
But like I said before, if this one, this is what it will come
in through your arguments from the command line.
It is a string.
It's not an integer.
Then you will have a scary error.
You have a type error.
So it doesn't work.
But then you will scratch your head, right,
in normally because, well, I have already done this in Python.
Why it doesn't work?
Well, because this is a compiled code.
It works in Python, but it doesn't work if it's compiled.
So another thing you can do is to use, so this is what's going
on here.
So I suggest like, oh, you want to be very fast.
You use njit, very, you know, optimistic, very ambitious.
And then, oh, no, this does not work.
I don't know what happened.
Okay. The quickest fix is to remove the n.
So I will just use jit instead of njit.
Then instead of getting an error saying that, no, no, no, no,
I can't do that.
Number can't do this.
Number will say that.
Okay. It's not recommended, but number will handle it for you.
This is what happened.
But again, you know, this tradeoff is
that the code won't be, you know, as fast as you want.
So, yeah. So this is another case that we may come
into the similar problem is that for some of the return type.
So this is the problem that we have with a type
that the input type is not what we are expecting.
We're expecting integer, and now it's not an integer.
This is the other side of the problem is that what
about the return type is not defined, right?
For this one, what is the return type of this function?
What's the return type?
It's an object.
It's a very, very good answer.
You apply to everything.
So for those of you who like love typing, you'll be like, oh,
you would maybe mark it as union, string,
and integer, something like that.
But again, it doesn't, you know, njit doesn't like it.
It can't be both.
It needs to be one.
So this can't be done.
So yeah. So we have to use a proper decorator for that.
So this is your time to shine.
Can you fix that for me, please?
But if you have the notebook open, go to this cell,
you may be able to find it using the to do.
Can you fix this?
I will give you maybe three minutes to fix it.
It should be quite straightforward.
Yeah.
Yeah, scary warning.
I don't like it.
Yeah. It doesn't mean a lot of things as well.
It's like I would scratch my head.
What's going on?
And can't find a lot of answers on Stack Overflow either.
It's not as easy to find as other things.
For example, if you use pure Python,
a lot of people use Python, they would answer your question
with Numba.
You have to be very lucky to find someone
who you expect to use Numba and answer your question.
Or you can split into two functions.
For example, you sacrifice one value and then
that value is an error value and then you have another function
to mark it up or something.
Yeah. There's always a way to rewrite the code.
It's just that, does it work the effort?
Do you want to do it?
Yeah.
Yeah, you can always break it into two parts,
but yeah, this is a very oversimplified example.
A lot of things are not that straightforward.
They're very tangled.
There's a lot of loops and stuff.
You will see later when we look into the scary bits.
So one more minute.
Who already, I see some of you already stopped,
so I guess you have done it.
So who still need more time?
Let me know.
No? No one responds.
So I assume people already guessed the result is
to remove the end and use JIT.
So yeah, so if you do like JIT, I think I've imported before.
It should be fine.
And then run it, then like, you know.
Then yeah, I get a scary warning,
but it's not a scary error.
So again, like this, if you don't want to see them,
you can change your setting in your Python or Jupyter notebook
and get rid of them and as if everything is fine, you know.
But some, yeah.
It's telling you that you could add them without a force object
and then it doesn't give you the warning, right?
No, it's basically telling you that it's not optimized.
Mine has like a, there's a deprecation warning.
You have a deprecation warning?
Oh.
Right there.
Well, you have to add force object equals true.
I think that's what it's saying.
Yeah, it's, yeah, there's number one as well.
That one again was compiled in object.
Yeah.
That parameter to the decorator, the warning was wrong.
Maybe. There's the multiple problem here.
You can see like, oh, you already compiled it before and stuff.
So without force object, it was true.
If you add that force object to the decorator,
it'll just pass without your warning.
Yeah, I think like now it's saying that like, well,
you're kind of like forcing it.
Do you really want to force it?
And then you said, yes, I want to force it.
Then it won't warn you because you already know what you're doing.
Yeah, it's just in case like if you, you know,
if you're kind of a beginner, you don't know like, you know,
your thought is this what the best you can do
and then it would just tell you a bunch of things.
But if you are very, you know, because it's ambiguous.
So Numba doesn't know whether that's something
that you want just to make sure you can always, you know,
get rid of it if you want.
So, ooh, extra task.
I love extra task.
So profile this tool and compare.
I will give you some time to run it yourself before I run it
and everybody see it.
Then you can have a thought about why is it different.
And yeah, what's going on there?
So let's, okay, so I guess you already seen the result.
I'll run it.
It took quite a while.
Right. Oh, actually I got a warning.
Oh my God.
Or is it still doing?
No. It's still running.
Yeah, it's very slow, this one.
Because it is a string.
Because it is 1.93.
So yeah. Ooh.
Oh, maybe because no.
This is nanosecond.
Okay, so it's like an order of magnitude difference.
Yeah. So yeah, you can see that it's slower
and it's, you know, have the conversion of the type.
Because, you know, again, it's, even if you use JIT, right,
so JIT will still try its best to help you.
So when JIT see that, oh, actually you are just passing integer
in and it should be, you know, NJIT instead of JIT.
Okay, I'll automatically do NJIT for you
so you will have it faster.
But then like if it's something that can't be NJIT,
that need to use object mode, can't be no Python,
then it will be slower.
So even though there are lots of scary warnings,
so sometimes it could be an easy fix because, you know,
if, even if you're using object mode, if it can be optimized,
it will be optimized.
So it's kind of, you know, nobody's trying its best
to be smart and try to help you.
So yeah, sometimes it's not a bad thing to use JIT
if you're really struggling.
It's just that some people may want to have full control
to make sure that nobody break this, it must be compiled
and NJIT will safeguard that for you.
So another thing is, okay, it's empty list.
So this one is showing the normal thing.
This is not an empty list.
So everything should be fine, right?
Everything's fine.
I can compile it.
No scary warning.
I can use NJIT, no scary warning, everything is good.
But if we do the empty list, as you can guess,
this will give you a scary warning, right?
Can you guess why it is the case?
Anybody already know what's going on here?
You don't know what type it is?
Yes, this is what Numbot doesn't like is to,
so this is even worse than this, right?
So you can say like this, for example, this, right?
It's like only two, kind of when, you know,
guess or something, but this really can be anything, right?
It's empty list.
You can put anything in it.
You can even put your self-defined
like a Python object.
You can put a magic mark, you know, you can put anything in it.
So Numbot really don't like it.
So this is a very, very, very difficult question,
but how can you create an empty list,
but you can still tell Numbot what type it is,
for example, integer.
Yeah, this is a fun kind of exercise.
Don't worry if you can't
because I already have the answer somewhere.
You can load it and check it yourself,
but I would give you maybe like five minutes to try it first.
It's really something that, you know, you would get an aha
when you see the answer, but give it a try.
See if your idea will work.
You'll give you five minutes to try it.
Who has confidence that they have got it?
Ooh. It's fine.
You can look it up because, you know,
we all look up things when we work, so it's fine.
So, but anyway, this is the answer that I have written before
or actually is actually in the documentation.
So if you're paying attention, then you will find it.
So this is, well, it's creating a list of integer, obviously,
but the funny bit is like it's in a range of zero,
so basically it's creating an empty list of integer.
I don't know if Python can do that.
Okay, range zero, I don't know, and I don't know
that like it actually registers an integer
because technically there's nothing in it,
so it's mind blowing.
Yeah?
You can do that as well, that maybe actually, yeah.
Yeah, the typing.
Yeah, so I have actually, I've talked to the maintainer saying
like oh, now everybody loves typing, right?
How about number can understand typing?
And then he said like that's a good suggestion,
but we don't have that in the near future,
so please be patient.
Or you can start contributing if you want
to solve that problem.
So yeah, so now actually other people's already having break,
so let's have a break until 1130 when, no, sorry, sorry, sorry,
sorry, wrong, 11 where everybody finished their break
and you also come back at 11.
It's like okay, good, yeah, okay, so.
Though you can meet up with your friend in another tutorial,
they may be having coffee outside, you know,
some cookie, I don't know what they have outside,
but come back at 11 and then we will finish the second part
of the tutorial.
Okay, it's about time we come back to the zone.
So before I started, again, I want to do a survey,
but this survey is irrelevant this time.
It's who has done this tutorial actually?
This tutorial, by the way, is actually
from the NumPy documentation.
It's about how to build a newer network from scratch
to distinguish the MNIST data set,
which is the handwritten digits.
Who has done this before?
One person.
Oh my God, you would be very fast ahead of us,
but who have actually maybe seen this but haven't really go
into detail about this before?
A few of you, okay.
So since the majority of people hasn't done this before,
I think what I'm going to do is I'm going to give you how much time,
maybe 20 minutes to go through this,
and then I will spend some time just like speed run this, you know,
so that we can make sure everybody's on the same page.
But I'm sorry for people who already have done it before,
already know you can already, like maybe you can read it again just
to like refresh your memory, and then you can move on to 3.2.
But otherwise, for the majority of people,
I will give you 20 minutes to go through this tutorial.
It's very good explanation there.
Just like I think understanding what's going
on will help you in the next exercise.
That's why I think it's worth spending some time to do it,
especially also loading the data as well.
So yeah, spend some time on this, and then I would do a sum
up and explanation right after.
But I will let you try it yourself first.
Okay? So it's about time.
So I know that people are at different places,
but unfortunately we have to finish the workshop.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to go through this quickly.
I will point out a few things that we have to take note,
but I won't explain all the detail of the mathematic and how,
you know, back, you know, the forward propagation back.
I won't explain that because that will take a course
to understand the neural network.
So yeah, for those of you who are really interested
but you don't have the time to finish,
you can always come back to do this.
I think this is really good and very good explanation.
And even though like maybe you haven't heard
about machine learning and like, you know, network,
neural network and want to learn more, there's also online courses
that you can do as well.
So this graph explains how it works.
So it would be, you know, there's a hidden layer
which is just matrix, and then there would be like, you know,
there's a loop, so because every time you would calculate how much,
like how far off the prediction is and then we try to improve
itself by doing this forward and backward propagation thing,
which is some mathematic steps, which I won't go into the detail.
So this also, I hope you already have the library
so it's not a problem.
And then the NS data set, like I said, is a head-wintered digit
so they're back and white images or grayscale images.
So how an image works is basically, you know,
if you see it on the screen, it's a picture, but actually,
if you, you know, look inside how big they are, you know,
you pixelated, you know, because each pixel is actually a value.
So for grayscale image, actually, it's just showing
that how dark maybe like, you know, 0, 0, 0 is black and then
if it's like 2, 5, it's white.
So it's just how dark that pixel is.
So that's how we interpret the image.
So they are all like kind of, you can download them online
and stuff so it's using requests
to grab them somewhere on the internet.
So if you don't have good connection,
it will take you a while.
So yeah, it's just all this technical stuff and then
after that, then you have that image.
So if you draw it on the screen, it's kind of like that,
it's pixelated again, like each value kind
of represent how dark this pixel is.
So these are all zeros and this one probably 255,
something like that.
So all of them are actually like pictures,
they're handwritten image.
So the goal is to see if we can build a new network,
which is kind of very basic form of AI,
to see if we can determine this is a 3, this is an 8,
we can do it perfectly, right, as a human,
but can a computer see this?
So this is again just showing the image
and because image is just again,
just a matrix of numbers like this.
So yeah, it's just a bunch of values.
At this stage, this is integer so that you can see
that now we do some processing,
which like convert the integer into float.
So this is a point that you have to maybe put a mental note
in your mind that oh, all these will be floating numbers
so we know the data type, right, so it may help you
when you try to use compiling.
So now they are kind of, we call them normalized,
which is like from, because originally it's 0 to 255,
now it's divided by 255, so it becomes 0 to 1,
so we kind of compress the range
and they become floating point numbers.
So similar thing happened with the results.
So the result we do one-hot encoding,
which means that it will be a vector.
So if it's 1 and then all 0,
then it's representing the digit on the picture is 0,
if it's 0, 0, 0 and the last one is 1,
meaning that is number 9 represented the picture.
So this is called one-hot encoding, so which one it is.
So basically like if you imagine it's a checkbox,
which one is check, okay?
So that's like that.
It's like you see 0 and 1, all of them,
that's because they are one-hot encoded,
but because the data type need to match again,
they become float for some reason.
So you can see there's a dot there,
which means that they're floating point numbers.
So yeah, so this is the basics of what happened.
Now this is the scary bit, which is the neural network bit,
which again, if you're very interested,
look at this math,
it is neural network only have like three layers,
0, 1 and 2.
And I think that number 2 is the result
and you compare that with the one-hot encoding
and something like that.
I may be wrong though, you can look into the details.
There's also the weight that is for propagation
and things like that.
Again, we'll skip the detail for now.
These two actually are the functions
that is used quite a lot in machine learning.
So you will see this rather function in the spoiler,
you will see this rather function soon.
So pay attention to this.
This is quite an important function.
It's using backward propagation.
If you draw it on a graph, it's kind of like,
when it's positive, it's like this and then negative,
so it's like, so when it's negative,
it's like this, zero and then positive,
just like a diagonal line.
There's another function similar to ReLU,
but it's just like one and zero like this.
Yeah, so basically this is useful,
I think it's useful kind of seeing how wrong
or how correct you are,
it's useful to give feedback to your neural network
to correct itself, that's why it's needed.
So yeah, these two functions are quite tricky
because they are not your normal function.
If you know math, they are not smooth, right?
They are like, so, funny, funny.
And then we have this, these are hyperparameters.
You can change them when you do machine learning,
you can fine tune your model to make it better
and change it, but we won't change them,
we just leave it at this.
The wage, so this is the starting point
of where you start to train,
so this is just an initialization.
And then these are the steps that's doing your propagation,
your training the neural network.
So when you train a neural network, there will be loops,
there will be, because every time you will have a result
and then see, compare the results to the correct answer
and then you correct itself, so it's a looping thing.
So loops, then ah, take a mental note,
this may be the part that we could improve with number.
So yeah, and then, so originally they will print out
the result every single time,
you will see that I kind of muted it
when we go to the part, but I will explain more later.
So yeah, and then this is just plotting the progress
of the training, so not related to what we are trying
to achieve today, but if you're interested, they're there.
Again, this is, I'll just skip them,
it's for the other tutorial.
So basically that's that, so how are we gonna improve that?
So if you really want, you can change this one,
but I have make a simpler version for you in 3.2,
so I copy some of the code from the original tutorial
and I have put them, just delete all the explanation
because you have it in the other notebook already.
And so this is basically the same thing,
so first step, loading the data,
there's nothing much we're going to do that,
it's just input, output and things,
so we won't use number on it,
we just let it be whatever it is.
One-hot encoding, we're also not touching it this time,
so we'll just run it.
And it should be downloading something
on my computer right now, let's check.
Is it doing anything?
Oh, it's on the, because it's on a,
it's on a further dot dot slasher, you won't see it here.
It's somewhere, it's downloaded, I just trust it, I hope.
And then build and train a small neural network.
So this is the bit that is doing the training,
so this looks familiar but it's different.
So, oh, also I forgot to mention one thing here.
One second, let me find that, that's quite important,
but I forgot where I put that.
Oh yeah, so the original tutorial there,
if you have go through them already,
then they are using only a thousand examples
in their training.
Actually this one is very fast when you go through them
because they only use a small sample size.
So practically, a lot of times,
when you train a more sophisticated neural network,
you will want to use more pictures and more images.
So to make it more challenging for us,
to basically making the algorithm not run too fast
so we can't improve it, I have put more data in it,
I think I put 5,000 somewhere here,
you can change it if it's too slow for you,
yeah, here, 5,000.
So if you want to just give it a try first,
you don't want to make it too slow,
you can change it back to 1,000,
but I will start with 5,000 for now.
So yeah, just the sample size of the front.
Here, this is where the machine learning thing works
and I'm not touching this, I'm just copying them
and then making it into a new function.
So you can see this code is different from the tutorial,
I have made a new class and then I have put all these
forward propagation as a separate method,
backward propagation as a separate method,
you will see why very soon.
It's kind of because, well, I will just explain myself,
because you see that this process is just in a loop, right?
It's not in a function.
If it's not in a function, we can't apply the JIT
and ENGIN decorator, we can't apply it to a for loop.
So we have to write it into a function.
And just for the ease of passing all these layers
and variables, these need to be passed
between these various functions,
so I create a class for it.
So this weight and all these like layers,
very of the layers, they need to preserve
during the training, so I put them in as a class.
That's the main reason why it's written like that.
They're doing the same thing, trust me,
I've tracked the result, cross-tracked the result before.
So if you encounter anything weird, let me know.
So they are all kind of structure,
it's a very good start for you,
if you want to use JIT and ENGIN, it's already done for you,
so you can start attacking them right away.
But before we attack them, we want to do profiling.
There's another name in the title, right?
So now we are doing some profiling.
So how we do profiling, we use the very basic C profile
to do that, like I said, there's a lot of profiler
available out there, if you have another favorite,
then please don't be shy and use it,
but I'm just using what comes with CPython.
So here we are trying to do some profiling.
Have I run the code before?
I think I haven't run the code before, let me run this.
Okay, so it will take some time,
again, because I've upped the size of the sample.
So this is kind of standard how you do it,
but notice that, so okay, a few things to notice here.
So when profile.enable, it will start profiling.
Profile.disable, so basically it's that
and end of the profiling process.
So between these two is what I want to profile,
so this one is, you know, how I, you know, the training.
So I want to see all these different things going on
in the training.
And you are also, by looking at this,
you will also see why I put them into different methods
or functions like before.
I will show you in a bit.
But you will see that the statistic,
how we display them, you can change it a little bit
to play around, but what I do is I would sort them
according to accumulated time.
They are different things you can sort them with.
You can sort them with how many times they're called,
how many total times they are, they have been spent
to execute all these like different things you can use,
but I would use accumulated time.
Feel free to change it.
It's yours now.
It's your experiment.
You can play around with it.
So this looks a bit scary.
It's just because, you know, all this code are stored
in a very funny place because of how iPython, you know,
Jupyter notebook work, but what I would do normally
is just look at the end of it.
Usually it would just like have the name of the function,
for example, a module is just module, but train.
So train is the biggest one, right?
So of course it's taking the most time
because it's the matter of everything.
So everything run inside it.
So it's taking the most time.
But if you look at this, you can see the back propagation,
actually it's here, forward propagation is here.
So if you compare accumulated time of the backward
and forward propagation, you will see that backward
actually costs more, even though they are run at,
oh, actually this one, oh no, yeah.
They are both run how many times?
It's a bit difficult to see.
So yeah, this is the time they have been called.
So they have been called at the equivalent.
So number of times, this is like how many,
it's like a hundred thousand times,
both back and forward prop,
but the backward prop costs a little bit more time
because of the process costs a little bit more time.
There are also, of course, these have built in things
that you can't really do much about it,
but try to look for these ones that you name
and define yourself, then you'll have a better idea.
You can compare them to see which one get called more times,
which one is taking more time and all these things.
If you want, you can also break this up more.
This is, again, like I said, a starting point for you to compare
and try to break things down to investigate
which one actually costs the most time and where to attack it
to reduce the time that it took.
So yeah, so if you want, you can also like, oh,
maybe break down these steps a little bit more
so you can maybe see better or maybe later when you use JIT
or NJIT, then you can have a more detailed control
of what you are compiling.
So this is how it works and how you interpret it, right?
So it's just a very, you know, cover the basic of profiling.
Again, it looks a bit scary, but look for the ones that you define
and look for the time, which one costs more time,
then maybe that one you should worry more about.
So after that is your time.
So now I have add to do here,
which means that I haven't done anything yet,
so it's your time to do things.
I created another class just to, so they don't overlap each other.
So within that, again, you can change stuff.
You can decide which one you want to use the decoration.
You can choose JIT or NJIT.
Well, if you, I would say that try NJIT and see which doesn't work,
then you can use JIT, but then I would challenge all of you
to try to just use NJIT.
Maybe it will take you a week or a month, but you don't have
to do it today, you just get a taste.
Try to try your best to see how much you can improve
and then we'll profile it again.
Then you can compare the process,
like how much improvement you got compared to the first one
when you profile, or does it really, you know,
worth the effort to rewrite it and make it faster,
how fast you can go.
So yeah, all of them are open questions,
so it's now your time to try it.
At the end, I put the rest of the code in one cell
so you can compare the result with the previous one.
You can see that the neural network is not very good
if you use a huge amount of sample.
You know, the original tutorial have optimized everything,
but yeah, you can change the sample size for your liking
and just to see which one can make it faster.
So to have a better result, so you may wonder, like, oh,
how can I get better results with more samples?
You may have to change the hyperparameters,
so that bit I won't go into detail because we are here
to make it faster, not to make it more accurate.
Well, ideally you want to make it more accurate as well,
but then you have to put another effort
to change the hyperparameters.
So yeah, so now is a free time to try and do stuff,
ask questions if you want, if you already kind of talk
to your neighbor, you have make friends,
then you can work together maybe.
So now how much time we have?
We have around, so slightly shined, then an hour,
so you have plenty of time.
Try to challenge yourself.
This is your hands-on exercise bit and ask questions.
So we have around 15 minutes until the end of the tutorial.
You, of course, feel free to stay and then work
to the very, very end.
Or if you have questions,
this is your last chance, ask me questions.
But if you, for example, have questions in the future,
my DM on Twitter is open or you can find me on LinkedIn
and drop me a message and I would genuinely,
if I can help, I will help you.
But sometimes, you know, I may have to direct your questions
or if you can have a very clear question,
then I can just put it directly to someone who can help you.
So, you know, here's my contact and also the other thing I want
to tell you is EuroPython, which is, again, maybe not as big
as PyCon US, but also quite big conference in Europe.
There will be other maintainer, other developers there
that you can meet.
If you are based in Europe or if you are, you know,
want an excuse to go to Europe, this is your chance.
It's going to be somewhere in Prague.
It's going to be a very nice place to be.
You know, it's beautiful.
So I think that's it from me.
Also, one last thing, since you know I work for Alaconda,
we'll have a booth.
The opening will be later today, so please stay around and,
you know, come to our booth.
We'll have demonstration.
We'll have Pyscript people there.
We'll have Condor people there.
We'll have people who also show you how
to do your data science work on the cloud and things like that.
So please come and have a look.
I may be there as well.
So I hope you enjoy the rest of the conference.
And it's not the end.
You can still ask me questions.
I'm just going to announce it in case some people want
to leave earlier.
Thank you so much for coming.
Oh, by the way, they may also ask you a questionnaire
to give me feedback.
So all the feedback are very welcome.
But if you don't like anything,
could you please maybe mention a small thing that you like?
So it's not just like last year the questionnaire was quite,
you know, people are very honest.
So yeah, I welcome feedback, but if you, you know,
think that's something I have to improve,
maybe mention a small thing that you like first
to make me feel better, that would make me feel happier.
But anyway, thank you so much for coming.
And I'll be here answering your questions till the very end.
So thank you.
Thank you.