All right, then.
It's 9 a.m. already, so we'll officially begin the tutorial now.
So, hello.
Good morning to all of you.
My name is Mahe, and I am a software engineer at Anaconda.
I live in Berlin, and this is my first time being in the States, my first PyCon US, and
I am very happy to be here with all of you.
And I want to thank you for joining us today for this tutorial, which is titled Publishing
Your Python Package, The Condo Way.
And I am very excited to co-present this with my colleagues, Bianca, Dave, and Valerio.
We also have Yanis, Ken, and Steve at the back, who were kind enough to offer their
help and support during the tutorial.
I will briefly go through the structure of the tutorial.
So, we will start with an overview of some basic packaging concepts.
Some of you might already be familiar with them, but I think it's important to lay out
some background before we get to the actual hands-on, and it's also important to ensure
that everyone is on the same page.
The overview will be presented by myself and Bianca.
Then we'll move on to the hands-on, which will involve Valerio taking you through the
process of writing a Python package from scratch, building it with CondoBuild, and publishing
it on Condom.
Then we'll have Dave talking about Condor governance, the Condor CoC, and more.
This will then be followed by a Q&A session where you can ask us questions about the tutorial,
about Condor, Anaconda, and more.
And there will be breaks throughout the session, because, you know, we all need our four cups
of coffee in the morning.
All right, so let us begin from the beginning.
What is even a software package?
A software package is a piece of software that someone wrote and published for other
people to install and use.
Now, to ensure that this piece of software that this guy wrote works on other people's
machine, the package, the software needs to go through the process of packaging.
The process of packaging involves taking into account dependencies and OS requirements to
make sure that the software works on each individual's machine.
Now, you may install different kinds of packages on your machine, but sometimes they will not
work out so nicely with each other.
And it gets difficult to take care of all these dependencies and OS requirements.
This is where Condor comes in.
Condor is a package manager.
It's open source, and it runs on Windows, Linux, and Mac OS.
Condor is language-agnostic, which means you can package software written in any language
using Condor and not just Python.
Condor is also an environment manager, which means it lets users create, load, and switch
between different environments.
A Condor environment can contain specific interpreters and libraries that are separate
from other environments and that are then separate from the libraries installed at system
level.
The benefit of Condor being a package manager as well as an environment manager is that
it does all the tedious and difficult work of making sure that different packages work
well together on your system.
By the way, Condor is not the same as Anaconda.
Anaconda is a Python and R data science distribution that contains Condor along with more than
250 packages.
Mini Condor is a bootstrap version of Anaconda that contains just Condor and Python and the
packages that these two depend on.
All right.
Now you know what a package is, what packaging is, what is package management.
You know Condor, Anaconda, and Mini Condor.
The question is, where do I put my package for the world to see?
Well, the answer is channels, but I am done speaking for now.
Now Bianca will come over and talk about channels and more.
Thank you.
Hello.
My name is Bianca Henderson.
I am a software developer at Anaconda.
So yeah, channels.
Depending on the packaging technology that you're using, the online location where these
packages are made available will receive a different name.
So typically users will know about hosting packages on PyPI.
In the Condor world, however, packages are hosted on channels.
Channels are like warehouses for packages.
The default Anaconda channel for Condor packages is the default channel.
A Condor package creator can also create an Anaconda cloud account in order to host packages
on their own channels.
So in addition to the default channel, there are several community-owned channels such
as CondorForge and Bioconda.
The most wide-reaching community-maintained channel is CondorForge because it hosts many
packages over, I think at current count it's over 21,000.
Common standards are enforced to ensure that all packages have compatible versions and
many of the packages are kept up to date by multiple maintainers.
In Python packaging, specifically, there are certain files which contain the project metadata
that are required in order for the application to be packaged properly.
You may have heard of the setup.py and setup.cfg files, which used to be the standard for distributing
Python modules.
They're artifacts of the setup tools module which is designed to help with the packaging
process.
The more current way to package Python applications is via the use of a PyProject.toml file, which
was introduced in PEP 5.18 in 2016 as a way of separating configuration of the build system
from setup tools and also enabling setup tools to install itself without it needing to be
installed before the packaging process.
All right.
Packaging, something specifically for a conda channel, requires something called a recipe.
Each recipe minimally contains a meta.yml file which contains metadata such as the package
name and version, its dependencies and how to build it.
Recipes also require a build script in the form of either a build.sh file for Unix systems
or build.bat for Windows.
Alternatively, conda build will look for the build script in line inside of the meta.yml
file.
When you submit a recipe to the staged recipes repo on conda forge, it is reviewed by the
conda forge community members.
Once approved, an automated conda forge process then generates the package based on the recipe
and then something called a feed stock becomes available on conda forge.
The word feed stock typically refers to the mixture of raw materials used for industrial
processes or blacksmithing, which is why conda forge adopted this term.
It's kind of a cool back story there.
Writing recipes manually can be very time consuming and tedious.
So this is where greyskull comes in.
Greyskull automatically generates conda recipes for PyPI packages, GitHub repos or cram packages.
GitHub.py and pyproject.toml were mentioned earlier.
Greyskull takes the metadata provided by those files and generates a recipe using that information.
This recipe can then be used to build a conda package.
So now that we have the knowledge about how the process works, we'll start this tutorial
and hand over the mic to Valerio.
Before we start, any questions on any of the topics that we covered?
Or no?
We can just start.
Nice.
Okay.
This should be working.
I think at this point I would need to attach my HDMI cable.
Nice.
So for this part, I will try to do an hands-on with you.
Just move a little bit so I can see all of you here.
In case you have any question, feel free to interrupt me at any time.
It's very fine to have questions during the hands-on and we would love to have as much
interaction as we can get during the whole tutorial.
So I think that the idea of the project we decided to come up with was to create a project
which we called a D&D Roller.
I think the idea is to make an application that would make you able to revolve some dice
for Dungeons and Dragons games.
I don't know how many Dungeons and Dragons players we have in this room.
Oh, okay.
Not that many.
Anyway, so likely I actually brought my dice so you can physically see them, sort of.
So we do have, in Dungeons and Dragons you do need to have seven dice, different.
So you have different faces for the dice.
You're very welcome to see them later if you want.
And essentially these dice are particular because you need them for different things.
And you have the classic six-size dice, but you also have the four dice, so D4, then you
have D10, D8, D12, D20, and D100.
So essentially you need all of them to play.
And you only have these particular dice.
So from a perspective of a software, we need this application to handle this specific set
of dice.
And we also had an extra requirement, which is, since this is going to work in the terminal,
we might want to have numbers printed in emojis, so Unicode characters.
Last but not least, we also have this project to make a report.
Because sometimes when you play D&D, what you have to do is to roll many times multiple
dice and so you have to have an overview, a tabular overview of everything that has
happened with your rolling.
So these are the two main requirements we want to develop together.
All right?
So the first and foremost thing we want to do is to create a repository because we will
be working as this is a real project we want to pack and to deliver and distribute for
everyone.
So the first thing we do is to go on GitHub, and I hope everybody here has a GitHub account.
You can create a repository which presumably will be named D&D Roller.
I assume it will be named this way.
You can name it as you like.
And I can do that with you now.
Is everything okay?
Yeah, okay.
Sure.
So just to be clear, do you have the document open in front of you?
Your HackMD document?
If you need the link, no worries, we can send you.
Or I think that has been sent around so you should probably have an email with all the
links and references.
But please if that's not the case, please let us know.
It's very, very fine.
Okay?
We're here to help.
And again, we hope we could make this as interactive as possible.
Nice.
So by the way, my plan for this hands-on is to work on...
So you'll be seeing the browser.
So I'll scroll down the document on this side.
And probably what I can do is to hide this one because I don't need it.
And then grab some space.
I want this this way.
Then I have an editor.
I will be using Visual Studio Code, but you can do any editor you like.
It's very much the same.
And I will also be using a command line shell.
So, and at this point, if the font size won't be bigger enough in the back, you'll let me
know and I'll properly manage.
Okay.
So what I want to do now is to go and create this repository.
We'll be moving this window on this side.
So I'll go on GitHub on my username page.
And I will be clicking on plus new repository.
If you're not familiar with this, please let me know.
I will be slowing down.
But essentially, I set up the name, dndroller.
I'll put some description.
I think the description could be something like simple Python app, as it's here.
Simple Python app to roll dice for D&D.
Now the important bit.
We should have to, we should select the visibility of the project.
It's going to be public.
We want to initialize the repository with readme file.
That's generally a good practice.
And also, it's very important when you create that, although you can do that later, but
generally, you should have an idea when you create a project what is the license you want
to pick for your distribution.
We're going to select MIT license, which is the most open source license you can have.
So you can essentially reuse everything, no problem.
And the git ignore, that could come handy.
It's to have a Python template.
So essentially, what GitHub is going to do with this is it's going to create a .gitignore
file for our own repository with the list of the most common ignored resources and files
when you have a Python project.
Nice.
We click on create repository, and we're good to go.
So at this point, you should have something similar to this.
If not, please let me know.
And what we need now is to make a clone of this repository.
So I'm going to copy the URL, clicking on code, and I'm going to move it on something
in a folder that I want.
I don't know, let's say, let's make a conda tutorial.
And then I git clone.
Is the font of this shell big enough?
Larger?
Better?
Nice.
Thank you.
Okay.
So what this is doing is creating a new folder, which is going to be called dndroller as a
repository because I didn't specify differently.
And cloning.
Nice.
So at this point, oopsie.
At this point, I don't see anything.
We should have a dnd folder.
I'm using zish in this particular case as a shell with a bit of gimmicks.
So there's some plugins in the shell that tells me that it's a GitHub repository, I'm
the main branch, and the base is my default conda python environment I'm using currently.
So, sure, definitely.
No, no.
Please, please interrupt me at any time.
It's very fine.
And this also is for you.
So just like need from you a bit of feedback as much as we go through the things because
I don't know how familiar with things.
And it's very fine if you don't know things.
I'm actually here to tell you what I know.
So this doesn't necessarily guarantee that I know the answer, but I might try.
Anyway, so I think we've done this already.
So we did the repository, we created the folder.
I call it python.tutorial.
I call it differently.
It doesn't really matter.
And we cloned the repository.
So we're done at this point here.
Okay?
Yes, sorry.
We were thinking that this is the general case.
It doesn't have to be.
If you want to have a different setup.
Hopefully, you can have a local package.
We can touch that.
But that's a very good point, actually.
This will be relevant when we get to creating the package.
So so far, we're actually doing a standard python development.
So the plan for this step and for the break, I guess, is we get to develop this package
from scratch.
Hopefully, this project would be entertaining for you enough to make it fun.
But it's like we're building what it's going to be the target of our packaging in the second
part.
All right?
And this package, this project being the DND roller we've been talking about.
So at this point, I would move myself to using...
I can close this one.
Well, I'll leave it there.
I will be moving on to the editor.
And we'll open this folder.
Or maybe I do it a smart way, which is opening directly from terminal.
So like code.
You should open a new window.
I'll be using Studio Code.
I can close this one.
And at this point, I may make it bigger.
Is this big enough in the back?
We have an empty folder so far.
And we have exactly what is it in the repository.
We have readme, which is also empty right now.
Well, it's not empty.
So now we have to create our own actual package.
So we can create a new folder.
In the instructions here, you see the commands to do that in the shell.
So I will be doing the same.
You can do the way you prefer.
I am the folder, so I will be making a new DND underscore roller folder.
Then I create a new folder called tests.
This is how now the structure of the project looks like.
Let me show you in the shell here.
Sorry.
LS.
So this is, sorry.
Let me do this properly.
I'm going to do this in vertical so you can read it better.
LS minus 1.
Nice.
So this is starting to be the classical project structure when
you're creating the Python project.
So you have the DND roller, which is where we're going to presumably put
the code, the Python code, and tests, where we're going to presumably
put the test code in Python code.
And the rest of it is essentially what you can see here.
OK?
So any question so far?
Nothing?
Fine?
Boring?
Yes?
No?
Nice.
The first thing we do is to create our first module, dice.py module.
And this will go within the DND underscore roller.
So it's the first file of our own package.
So within the DND roller, we create a new file.
It's called dice.py.
There you go.
OK.
Close this one.
In case you're using, I just remembered that I skipped creating the
environment, the conda environment.
I don't know if you have done this already, but we can do that
together now.
So in the beginning, on top here, in the preparation step, you
should have created the conda environment, which is the
environment we'll be using during the hands-on.
So that we work on an environment which is specifically
created for the hands-on.
And also, it's very useful because you're not polluting
whatever environment you have on your computer.
So it's going to be the sandbox of our own project, our own work.
Do you have created the packaging environment as
the instructions?
OK.
If not, you can do that with me.
Yes, please.
Sorry, I didn't get that.
Sure.
Is that better?
I can go even further with that.
OK.
So again, in the terminal window, I'm going to clear
so I have a better view myself.
So what we do here is conda.
We do the classic command line instructions by creating a new
conda environment.
So we do conda create minus n, which is the name of the
environment we want to create.
We call it packaging.
Then we say minus y because we don't want to hit down yes in
confirmation.
We assume everything is fine.
Then we have Python 3.10 installed and PyTest.
These are the only two packages we're going to install there.
All right?
So we run it.
And you should be seeing something like that executing on
your own.
When this is done, we should have a new packaging
environment ready to be activated.
So the last step is to activate our new packaging
environment.
So we do conda, activate.
I would probably do this now.
Probably move, sorry, shrink the window a little bit so my
last line in the terminal is going to end up in the middle
of the screen.
And still it's very difficult for me.
OK.
Nice.
Let's do this.
OK.
Packaging.
So now, if you're using zish, you might probably be seeing
that I am on the packaging conda environment.
If not, it's essentially you can test.
I don't know how to do that on Windows, though, if you're
Windows.
But if you're on a Linux slash Unix machine, you can
actually check which Python you're using and essentially
points you to the path of the Python command in your shell.
And that should be something like that.
So on a conda installation folder or minicond installation
folder, slash m, slash name of the environment, slash
mean, slash Python.
That's the path.
And essentially this is telling you you're using the
Python interpreter of the environment called packaging.
OK.
So everything we'll be doing now, from now on, in this
session of the terminal, will be within the
packaging environment.
That sounds good?
Is that OK for you so far?
Or is it like to common knowledge?
You know this already?
OK.
Good.
As soon as there is anyone interested here, I'm very
happy to explain things.
There's no problem at all.
So just to make crystal clear what's going on, we're
creating a conda environment so that everything, so imagine
that you have your own Python interpreter on your computer.
And now we are saying, and this could be available via an
interpreter.
We suggested to install miniconda because miniconda,
as Mahe and Bianca said already in the first part, you
can have Python and conda altogether.
So you have conda now on your computer.
A command you can run.
And afterwards, we're creating, within this
environment, we're creating some space where we're going
to install all the packages we need without interfering
with the rest of the installations.
And you can have a list of as many environments as you like
on your computer.
In case you're wondering and you want to check what are the
environments on your computer, you can run a conda info,
minus minus m's.
And this gives you the list of all the
environments you have.
In this particular case, I have this list.
And the star indicates the one that you're currently using.
This is another way to check, by the way.
This is probably a platform-independent way to
check, using directly conda, to check what is the
environment you're currently using.
And in fact, I'm using packaging.
So whichever package I'm going to install from now on, in
this terminal session, is not going to interfere with any
other environment here.
So I'm pretty sure I'm installing everything there.
And any other package that is not in that environment will
not be accessible or available.
So we are now going to work on the dice module.
Let me go back to the code.
Well, the first thing is we need a
function to roll a dice.
And probably the main and only requirement of this function
is that we just have a limited set of dice we can choose.
So this could be one of the seven allowed in D&D. So it
could be a D4, 6, 8, 10, 12, 100.
There's actually a catch in this, if you're not familiar
with D&D.
So the D100, this is one, is essentially a probability
die, which means that you get numbers in decimals.
So like you have 10, 20, 30, 40, up to 100.
You don't have numbers in the middle.
And so that's the little catch we want to
implement in the function.
So it means that you essentially roll a D10 and
you multiply by 10.
This is the 100 that you need.
So let's write down now the roll function, which is the
main building block of everything we're going to do
from now on.
This is the pretty simple requirement I was expecting.
So you have a function roll.
You pass the parameter D, which is the number of sides
of the dice you want, or the die you want.
And then you return a number in 1 for included.
So if you're using, at least when I wrote this one, I was
assuming that using square brackets means the interval
with the two ends included, as in the mathematical
notation.
If you have a call like roll D equal 10, you return a
number in 1 and 10, both included.
D5, you have an exception, because D5 doesn't exist in
DND.
And the catch about the D100 is essentially roll D10
multiplied by 10, as I told you already.
So that's good.
So let's write it down.
Well, the implementation is going to be quite
straightforward.
So I'm going to copy now and then comment over the code, if
that's OK with you.
I'm going to copy and paste.
I'm not expecting you to do differently.
You're very welcome to copy and paste as well.
The point at this point in this tutorial is not to write
Python, it's just to have something to work with.
So it's very fine.
What this function is actually doing is we have a tuple of
supported dice here.
We have a function roll parameter D of type expected of
type int, returning an integer.
We have random dot run int to generate the random numbers.
And we rely on that.
Probably the only thing to mention here, if you're
interested in this particular flavors of Python programming,
is instead of checking, so we have to make sure that D is an
integer.
So instead of actually checking that D is directly if D is an
integer, we assume D is an integer, or we try to cast it.
And then if that's not going to work, an
exception will be raised.
And so we handle the error accordingly.
Otherwise, everything works.
This particular pattern of programming is called EAFB,
easier ask for permission than forgiveness.
So it's a way to program idiomatic Python.
The alternative would have been if closes.
But in the Pythonic solution, or idiomatic Python if you
want, better to ask for permission than forgiveness is
a better approach.
So you're essentially forced to cast to an integer if for any
reason this is not going to work, because for example, it's
a string, which is an alphabetical string, not a
number, a numerical string, which is going to work, by the
way.
It raises an exception.
And if everything works at this point, so if we reach the else
branch, which happens when no exception is raised during the
try block, again we check that D is in the supported dice.
If it's not, we raise a value error.
And if it's not, so everything is fine, we use randint.
And unless we have D100, if that's the case, we change the
way in which we call D.
Essentially, we make a recursive colon D10 times 10.
Does that make sense?
So assuming this is pretty much it and quite straightforward
for you, and the few comments I made already, before moving on
to the second bit, which is normally what you would
normally do when you develop that, is OK, I'm done with the
code, I need some tests to make sure that the implementation
is actually doing what I'm expecting it does.
And so we're moving on to testing.
To make this a proper Python package, we should be creating
another file within the dnd folder, which is
called dunder init.
I'm going to tell you exactly what dunder is in a minute.
Just for now, assume that we're using double underscore
init, is that bit again up again?
Double underscore init double underscore again dot py.
So the double underscore in Python terminology is
generally referred to as dunder, as a short for
double underscore.
And the dunder init file is what is actually making the
dnd roller folder a Python package.
And just to clarify a little bit of clashing in
terminology at this point, we're calling package, using
package to refer to two different things.
So the dnd roller is a Python package.
The whole project we're going to build in the end is a
Python package as well, but actually is a package.
Let's call it package, not Python package.
So to make distinction between the Python package from the
perspective of the name resolution and the namespace of
your programming, and the software package you're
building and distributing on the repository to be installed.
So let's call it Python package, this one, and software
package, the ultimate target of this hands-on.
So the dnd file is particularly useful in a
package because it essentially defines the public
API of your package.
So whatever is, and I'm very happy to explain how that
works in case you're interested later on, or maybe
during the break, or you have any question later on.
But let's assume for now you're familiar with how this
works, and believe me when I tell you that the dnd init
file is essentially making the public API of your package.
So whichever name we're writing and we're defining into
the init file is going to be the public API of the package
as well from the import perspective.
So for example, if we do something like from .dice
import role, we're essentially making the role function
available in the dice module a public function of the dnd
roller package, Python package, with just this line.
OK?
And if you don't believe me, as you should, because it's
always good to test it, what we can do is to run a Python
interpreter.
And so interactively, if we run Python, OK?
I'm going slow down because I'm really improvising at this
point, what we can do is we can import.
So we know that the role function is in the dice module
here within the dnd roller package.
OK?
So for sure, we can do from dnd underscore roller dot dice
import role.
Is that clear?
Good.
And this should be working.
It does work.
But with this instruction here in the dnd init file, what
also works is from dnd underscore roller import role
directly without using the dot dice module.
There you go.
So essentially, we have promoted the role function as
an important function for the package because we want this to
be imported by our own users using the dnd roller Python
package.
So from a programmatic perspective, what you're doing
is telling within the many, many functions you have in your
package, these are the important ones.
The other ones, if you want to use them, you have to import
them following the full path within the Python package.
Does that make sense?
OK.
Brilliant.
So now onto the second bit, which is testing.
We need to test the code before moving on to developing
another feature.
We might be creating a new file here, which is called
PyTest.ini.
It's the configuration file PyTest needs to have name
resolution.
So we just move on and create a new file.
I'm going to use the editor directly.
You can use the command line of the editor as well.
That's very fine.
And this has to be created in the main root folder.
So here, not this level.
I think the other one.
I will be moving later.
It's not working with me.
PyTest.ini.
And this should live into the main root folder.
There you go.
This contains just a PyTest directive.
And the PyTest.ini is, if you're not familiar with
PyTest, is a configuration file where you put some
configurations.
And I think there is a link in the document of where to find
a specific configuration for PyTest.
In general, here is the link, by the way.
It's in the comment of the code.
Essentially, this configuration is sometimes
used for reporting or to specify extra dependencies.
Or if you want to set up some logging with your tests,
things like this.
OK, now we're done with this.
And we can move on creating a new testing module.
It's standard practice to create a testing module for a
specific function or a specific module.
It really depends on the granularity of the test you
want.
At this point, we're developing one function at a
time, so presumably we want to develop a module for a single
function at a time.
And so we're going to create a new file here within the
tests folder, which is called test-roll.py.
Again, I'm going to do as I did before.
So I'm going to copy everything here, and then I
make comments on the different testing.
How many of you here are familiar with PyTest and how
that works?
Fantastic.
So PyTest is the testing package we're using.
And just for your information, the standard library, in the
many, many things already containing, there's also a
unit test package doing sort of the same thing.
So when you say Python is a battery included language, it's
because the standard library has essentially everything.
And just a shameful plug for the talk I'm going to do
tomorrow, it's somewhat related.
Because I will be talking about some of the gems you have in
the standard library, but also everything I will be doing and
showcasing is done essentially just using standard library,
no extra dependency package.
This is just to let you know that the standard library is
an amazing piece of software we have with Python directly.
So it's not just the language, it's also all the extra bits
the Python package is bringing with it.
PyTest is actually a unit test.
So testing is historically following the tradition of being
the standard testing package for every language.
JUnit for Java was the most popular one.
And unit test is resembling sort of that structure.
PyTest is like a more Pythonic testing package and also helps
you to make things very easily.
So the default configuration, this is, for example, another
thing you can configure in your PyTest.ini.
The standard configuration for PyTest is whichever function is
going to start with test underscore, PyTest is going to
think that's a testing function automatically for you.
If you want a different naming, you can set it up.
But it's not going to be the point nor the case.
And in addition to that, oh yeah, just by the way, if you're
using Visual Studio Code as I'm doing, this is complaining
because it says PyTest is not in your environment.
What's going on?
I cannot import this package.
And this is because I haven't set up my editor with the
right environment.
So for this particular case, as you can see, I hope you can
see, but it's pointing to a Python which is not within the
packaging environment.
So I'm going to switch interpreter,
choosing for packaging.
If it's not, we should, there you go.
A bit of refresh always helps.
Now I switch to this one.
And in a matter of a second, now PyTest is not an error
anymore because it can resolve the name.
Because if you remember, we just installed Python 3.10 and
PyTest, nothing else.
We actually have been installing extra things that we
didn't specify explicitly.
But those were dependencies of the previous two packages.
So we just have an environment with anything we need to just
run Python and PyTest, nothing more.
And this is what we need so far.
So far so good.
Yes, so the function we've been testing is role.
And since it's a function that essentially gets an integer,
we have to make sure that end also just is restricted to
specific integer values like d, four, six, seven, eight,
and whatever.
The first test is make sure that the actual function
returns a valid number.
So this is the test in which, OK, everything works.
No, no, no black magic.
And the only automation PyTest is providing here, for those
of you not familiar, is instead of writing every
single test or every function call with all the possible
values, in this case with the sides of the dice supported,
PyTest is making a parameterized test.
So we say, call this function with all the supported dice we
have here, from supported dice.
So it's going to make, out of this function, automatically
one test for each value we want.
And so it's essentially the same test changes only the
input of the test.
Then we test roll d 100, because it's the specific
case, and so in particular we just test that the number is
within the range, but also is a module 10 is equal to 0, which
means there's a number, is a power of 10.
It's a multiple of 10, sorry.
Now we test the conditions, so generating errors, something
like string which are not numbers, weird testing.
Oh, by the way, this is another thing that's probably useful
for you.
So Valerio warned us that we need to take breaks.
Oh, yeah.
And he never thinks of that.
No.
You have to shoot me.
And in this country could be a problem.
No, please don't.
No.
Sorry.
So in the spirit of whatever we're doing, taking a
frequent short break, let's take a 10 minute break.
Let's be back here at 10 o'clock.
If you have questions, now's a great time to ask.
Yeah, I'm here for you.
No thanks.
Thank you.
Yeah, I warned you.
OK, I'm back.
Nice.
Good.
Where was I?
Yeah, no, I was going through the test.
I think there's nothing particularly interesting to
say here, but maybe highlights how you could test for a
positive case, a negative case, in particular for the
cases when you're expecting exceptions in your code,
you're essentially testing that the code is indeed
raising the exception you're expecting.
And in this case, PyTest offers you a context manager
called raises.
So essentially, you wrap the function call within the
context manager offered by PyTest.
And if the exception is being raised, the accession
essentially passes.
So the test passes.
Otherwise, it fails, because it doesn't raise the
exception we're expecting.
Probably the last and perhaps the most important thing to
tell you, apart from the specific case as a takeaway
message, as a person.
Oh, something I wanted to do here is like getting rid of
this, because it's making me headaches.
OK, so I can see everybody here.
Is whenever you're dealing with test code, my general
advice is test functions are not going to be production
function.
And by that, I mean this test function won't be called by
other functions, but PyTest itself for testing purposes.
And so whenever you're naming testing function, please make
sure that they're actually giving you an immediate
message, as in what this test is about.
And they can be as long as you want.
It doesn't really matter.
To me, in my personal experience, the clear and the
easy to remember, and even for your future self, those names
are the better.
Something like test roll with unsupported dice will rise
exception.
You immediately know what this test is doing.
Or test roll with negative or float, no will rise exception
will not, actually, rise exception.
No stands for number, sorry.
Negative or float number will raise exception.
Nice.
So at this point, I think we just need to run PyTest to make
sure that everything works.
To do that, I'm going to run this command, which is
Python minus M. PyTest.
Python minus M is essentially importing the PyTest module.
And then minus V is the option for PyTest to have verbose
output.
So we run this.
We have, yeah, in this particular case, we have lots
of passes.
And you might notice this or not, but essentially, the
number of passes you have in the output is way more than
the number of test functions you've actually developed.
And this is thanks to the parameterized test I was
explaining before.
So PyTest is automatically generating new test functions
with different input here.
So we have the test roll die return a valid number with an
input of 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, 20.
And PyTest has done all this job for us.
So we have all green.
We can move on.
Any questions so far?
OK.
I will be going a little bit quicker on this part just
because we're sort of building what we want to.
So it's not the main attention here.
I guess the last requirement we have is that we really want to
have this roll function to be fancy in the terminal because
we want to bring numbers using emoji.
And we do not reinvent.
We're lucky somebody has already developed a package
which is called NoEmoji, as in emoji number.
And this package does exactly what we want.
Very happy to show you the code later on.
It's really, really silly.
And just to clarify, the process I went through to make
this package available is exactly what we're doing right
now.
So I essentially did the very same thing but with a
different project called NoEmoji.
And now this package is, to my shame, available on PyPy and on
my own channel, on Conda.
So you can install this package using my own channel.
And this is just an excuse, really, to let you know something
I was discussing in the break with one of you is you can
indeed have public channels for yourself, for your own
publishing, for your own package on anaconda.org.
At the end of the tutorial, they will guide you through the
process of how CondaForge works because CondaForge is the big
repository available for anyone with lots and lots of
different packages.
And as you might guess, because the importance of this
CondaForge is for the community, you might expect that
this CondaForge is not hosting every single package everybody
is going to submit.
So there is a review process for that.
And they will tell you later about it.
But in the meantime, you can add on anaconda.org your own
channel, and that is yours.
So you can use that to upload any package you want.
Incidentally, I realized that my own package was dated back
to 2016 for some reason.
And I wasn't an anaconda yet at the time.
And Lerio Maggi is my username, so I'm going to use that.
Just to show you what I was showing you earlier, so if you
go to anaconda.org slash your username, this is the page of
your channel.
And you see NoMergy has been updated and uploaded to my
channels here.
Other packages are just like here.
They're quite old ones, actually, so don't count them.
But this is an official channel.
And as soon as you have a channel, you can install from
it using Conda.
The way in which you can use specific, a different or
particular channel for your installation is using the
minus C option in the command line.
So if you do conda install minus C, the name of the
channel, in this case, Lerio Maggi is my username, and the
name of the package you want to install, you get it.
So this is what I'm going to do.
And you should do the same.
Conda install minus C, Lerio Maggi, NoMergy.
Installing a package tells you, you want to install this?
Yes.
There you go.
So I installed a custom package from a
specific channel now.
Alternatively, you can install it directly from
PyPy using pip.
And this is also another excuse to let you know that
within a conda environment, you can install packages both
from PyPy or from conda channels.
So conda channels are the standard of preferred ways.
But if at any time any specific package is not
available in any channel, not even CondaForge, which I
hardly think is the case nowadays, but if that is the
case, like NoMergy, for example, I promise you, is not
a CondaForge, it will never be, you can
install it via PyP.
And another important feature to remind you of having
environments in conda is that you can mix conda package and
pip package within the same environment, and they will
work seamlessly together.
Yes.
Good question.
When you're creating a conda environment, you're actually
installing pip within the environment.
And so you can install whichever version of pip you
want, because pip is a package in the end.
So yes, the answer is yes.
You can do that.
Does that answer your question?
Sorry, I have this.
No.
When you create the package, I did the minus y option
before, so I didn't show you what it was telling me to
install, but let's say I'm going to create a new package,
a new environment here.
Let's say, oops, sorry.
Just give it a second.
This is a new one that doesn't remember.
So create conda create, find this hand, test them.
And I just want Python here.
So he's doing his job, and blah, blah, blah.
Then it tells me what's going to be installed.
And within this, there will be Python and setup tools.
And also pip.
So pip will be installed already.
And when I do that, let me enter there, it's going to take
a second, because this package will be presumably already
downloaded, so it just has to install it.
So this means that, by the way, whenever you're creating
an environment, conda is actually caching on your own
computer the package it downloads.
And whenever you're creating another environment, if this
package is already there on your computer, it's not going
to be downloaded again, unless the version will be
different, the platform will be different, the whole thing.
But if you're there, already there.
And I'll also tell you a trick to remove this cache if you
want to make some space out of it in a second.
So if I conda activate test-end, sorry, let me clear
the shell now so you can see.
Conda activate test-end.
And then I do which pip.
It's within the test-end environment.
OK.
Back to the trick I promised you.
I deactivate the environment first.
And so I'm using, again, this gimmick in Cish telling me the
environment, if I deactivate it, I go back to base.
And now I want to remove the environment, conda remove,
minus n, the name of the environment, test-end, or
minus minus all, minus minus yes.
This is removing everything in the environment.
But the package will still be there.
So now the test-end doesn't exist anymore.
And to double check that, you do, again, conda
info minus minus ends.
And test-ends is not in the list anymore.
That's what we wanted.
But the packages are still there.
And so to do that, you do conda clean, minus minus all,
minus minus yes.
So now it's removing everything is locally installed.
So from now on, whichever package I'm going to install
will be downloaded again.
It tells you also the number of packages and the space it's
saving afterwards.
OK?
Yes, please.
Correct.
You can probably specify the minus n option there.
I'm not entirely sure.
You can probably try that and let me know.
When you do conda clean, minus n and the name of the
environment you want to clean up.
I presume that worked.
No, both.
There is a mini-conda cache.
And the package is installed and created within the
environment as well.
Yeah, both of them.
It's actually taking its time here.
That's fine.
I don't know what it's doing here.
OK.
Where we are.
I do have a, no, let's try this way.
Switch window here.
So now we do have NoMoji installed.
And we have to modify the code so that we can use this.
Essentially, what this code is doing is adding a verbose
option in the role function so that when it's fault by
default and when this happens, essentially we print using the
emojize function, which is available in NoMoji.
So the only modification you have to make to the previous
code is just like, so going back to the role function, we
have to add the input line, NoMoji, the parameter, verbose,
type bool, default false.
And if this happens, I just copy and paste here.
It's really not worth it.
We can print and then we return.
So this has to go into a variable.
And then adjusting tabulation.
And that's it.
So if we are verbose, we print game die and then we roll it.
So if we want to try it, we can move into a Python
interpreter.
And then we can do something like from D and D roller,
import role, and do role at D or for with verbose equal true.
And that's it.
Does that make sense so far?
All good?
Nice.
This is something I'm particularly curious about,
actually, because we had a bit of testing in the preparation
of this controller.
But I personally have no specific clue about it.
Do you have any problem with emojis on your end?
You do?
OK.
And you're running on Windows.
So if you can't see them, it probably means that the font
you're using in the shell is not supporting Unicode characters.
So don't worry about it.
It was just a silly, stupid thing to let you know about the
channels and to let you know about the PIP packages within
the con environment.
OK?
It was just a stupid excuse for that.
There was no extra reason about it.
But thank you for telling me that.
That's very useful to me.
We are probably updating that with this particular disclaimer
or warning.
And the second is there are fonts that you can set up your
shell with specifically supporting Unicode characters.
All right.
Let's give it a go again.
Let's roll a D of what dial you want me to roll now?
100.
Let's go for 100.
70.
Well, that's pretty cool.
Yeah.
In D&D, there's D20 especially.
And sometimes you can hit 1 or 20, and that's the critical
ones.
And that happens generally is a very good bit.
So if you roll a D20, let's see what we got.
17.
Yeah, could be good actually.
Really good.
I think that I had too much fun working with this stupid and
silly project.
It gave me the opportunity to include in the explanations of
what's going on here.
A bit of these and that relating to also random number
generations and how you test with random number
generations.
So I think this is generally particularly.
Oh, I actually rolled 18 in my previous test.
So that generally is a good bit.
Oh, by the way, Dave who tested the part of a window
actually got critical here.
You got 1.
Where is Dave?
That's actually pretty good.
Very well, Dave.
Well done.
OK, so the second step here to work on is dice roll.
And dice roll is a simple function essentially
generalizing the roll function with multiple times with a
single die.
So dice roll is really, really simple.
Essentially, we specify how many times you want to roll a
single die.
And we call roll that number of times.
And we report the list of numbers we got in the rolling.
Remember that roll has the verbose parameter default.
So whenever we call this roll within dice, we're making sure
the verbose is going to be used so we don't have any print out
during the generation of the rollings here.
So we go back to the dice.py file and we add this new
function, dice roll.
There's a bit of docstrings there.
Rolls a single die with given sites and throws a number of
times, just to explain a little bit what's going on.
If you're not familiar with this expression, this is
called list comprehension in Python.
So we're actually creating a list on the fly using this
syntax.
It's really no different from using a folder explicitly and
doing it and accumulating the results into a list
explicitly.
Nice.
So we have our dice roll function now.
I think what we have left is to have some tests with it.
The takeaway here is we can reuse the same strategy we used
with roll by using, again, parameterize to generate a few
test inputs.
And by the way, the test inputs in testing terminology,
in particular in PyTest terminology, they're called
fixtures.
And so I think this is what I'm going to do soon.
I'm creating fixtures in PyTest.
And then the parameterize is going to be used with the same
strategy for testing is going to be the same.
So we can specify a list of die we want to roll and a list of
times we want to roll.
So that would be the values for the true parameters, and we
can parameterize them.
And then I think the other excuses of talking a bit about
other things not specifically related to conda building
packages is about mocks in tests.
So for example, in this particular function, if you had
to test it, you have to test two things.
Because you have to test that the function is actually doing
what you're expecting.
So it's returning the numbers you wanted, and it's raising
the errors you're expecting.
But also, you have to make sure that you don't have
duplicate code.
And so one of the things you want to test at some point is
is this function really calling roll function?
Or is it actually re-implementing the wheel
and re-implementing the same piece of code which is
already in roll?
And so one way to do this in a unit testing fashion, and the
unit testing function as just one rule, you have to test
everything in isolation, you want to patch the roll function
just for the purpose to make sure that you're actually
testing that that particular patch is being called.
You don't really need to know anything more than that,
because the rest of it will be tested with normal testing,
checking the output of the function dice roll.
In this particular case, you're interested in
understanding that the roll function has been called, and
in particular, a certain number of times that function
has been called.
You can do that using mock object.
And this doesn't require any extra packages installed.
This is Thunder library again, unit test of mock.
You can import patch.
And in our test function here, we're just patching the roll
function with a mock object.
And this mock object has particular features.
One is that you can assert that this mock object has been
called during the dice roll.
So the dice roll function is being recorded.
There's a check there that the roll function has been called.
And you can also assert that the function has been called
with a specific input.
In particular, we say we want to roll a die of four, and so
we're expecting the roll function one to be called and
to be called with the parameter d equal to four.
This is what we're testing here.
This is just a takeaway message for you in case you've
never been working with mock object before.
So what I'm going to do now is creating a new testing module,
which is written on the top of the snippets here,
testdiceroll.py.
And again, the practice I'm using is creating a testing
file for each of the function on testing.
Test dice roll.
And also, the naming is important because the name is
reflecting the name of the function on the test.
Nice.
I add this within the test folder.
And now when I run again, PyTest, PyTest is actually
looking for the test folder by default and is gathering all
the test function from all the modules you can find.
And it's running everything in a single battery.
So again, Python minus M, PyTest minus V for the verbose.
And now it's running everything.
So you can see it's running tests from testdiceroll.py
and from the testroll.py we had before.
100% passed.
We can move on.
Another thing, in case you're not familiar with testing
and unit testing, unit testing has to run fast.
And that's why you don't want to have dependencies,
specifically, mock object.
So you're using mock object also, for example,
to avoid communicating with the IO,
communicating with the databases,
because you have unit tests to run fast on everything
in isolation again.
So no dependencies again.
But I'm diverging here.
Nice.
So far so good?
OK, move on to the last bit.
Any question?
Good.
So the last, but by no means least, function we're
developing is called sequenceRoles.
And sequenceRoles is a function that essentially is
expecting a pattern of dice rolls in a form of string.
And you have to slightly have a bit of a logic
here to pass the sequence in some way.
And the sequence is specified here.
And the pattern is done in this way, essentially.
I thought I had written the pattern somewhere
in the document.
I'm just realizing it's not where I needed.
I think it was in the beginning on the very top.
So sorry for scrolling up again in the document.
But in the very, very beginning when I was developing,
yes, there you go.
So in the very, very beginning, so
at the beginning of the dice module section,
I said that we need a function that is
I said that we need a function that would receive a sequence
of dice rolls in this format.
So you have 2d4, 3d6, 1d10, 6d12.
And we'll generate a tabular report of the outcomes.
So in essence, this sequenceRoles function
has to do two things.
Getting the string, pass the string,
and then translates all of this sequence of rolls
into dice rolls invocations.
Does that make sense?
So this will mean that we need to call diceRoll function
with thrown parameters of 2 and a d parameter of sides
parameter of 4, and so on and so forth.
So we want to roll two times a d4 die,
and then three times a d6, and so on and so forth.
So going back to the sequenceRoles function, it's here.
This is a sequence function.
I'm just adding this extra function in the dice module.
And here, so I go to the dice.py file.
I just close this one, paste it.
So the first thing this function does is to pass the input.
And the way it does is, OK, I appreciate
this might be convoluted and not immediately understandable.
But again, that was a shameless plug for my talk tomorrow.
So bear with me a little bit.
So essentially, what this is doing
is passing the string in input using
a bit of a functional approach, as in functions calling
functions calling all the function.
If you're not entirely familiar with what's going on,
essentially, you have a map function.
And this map function is calling the street function
from strings on every single element of the sequence.split,
which is going to be a list.
And then for each of those, we're
essentially calling again.
We're splitting on the d to get the side of the dice
we wanted, and then we're converting them as integer.
And then we plug everything together,
and we call diceRoles.
And by the way, this is also done
within the dictionary expression, dictionary
comprehension.
So essentially, we're also creating a dictionary out
of it on the spot.
So in three lines of Python, we're essentially
doing lots of things.
It's very condensed, very convoluted.
If you're interested and you want
to know more a little bit about this flavors of programming
in Python, I have a talk tomorrow.
I'll be more than happy to let you know more about it.
And if you're scared by it, let me know.
I will change my talk immediately.
And I think that the last bit that remains here
is the tabulation part, because we
want to have a sequence of roles,
and then we want to print them automatically
using a tabular report.
We don't have to reinvent the wheel.
There is a package for you, and that's actually
a package I discovered working on this project, which
is generally available.
It's called a tabulate, and it's really, really useful
to do exactly what we're doing, like creating tables
and printing them in different formats.
So what we're going to do now is to install tabulate
in our environment using Conda directly.
We're not adding any channel here,
which means we're using the default channel from Conda,
so the Anaconda default channel.
So we do first off, we do Conda install tabulate.
And by the way, in the meantime, this
is a good opportunity for me to remind you
that when I'm installing external packages
for this particular project development,
these packages will become the dependencies we
need when we have to package.
In other words, so imagine that someone
want to use your software, in this particular case,
this stupid D&D roller.
If you want to run the code, you need
to have Noemoji installed in your environment
and tabulate now in your environment.
So given this piece of information,
you have to remember that these two packages will
become the dependency of our project,
or our soon-to-be package, the software package.
So takeaway message, we're going to use Noemoji and tabulate
as the dependencies of the software we're going to pack
into Conda package.
OK?
So that's done.
And I guess that the rest of the code here
is like adding tabulate here and making it working.
So let me do that super quickly.
I go back in the dice.py file.
I add the tabulate dependency.
There's a tabulate file.
I also define the header for the table I want to create.
So we have a first colon, which is dice.
The second rolls.
The third, sum.
And that's header.
I've also added this screwed up there.
OK?
And the last bit is adding the verbose parameter.
This time, it's true by default, because Sequence Source really
wants to have tabulation.
I type bool equals to true.
And that's the code we need to copy.
So this code, let me show you properly,
is actually using tabulate.
So we have our dictionary of rolls in Sequence.
This dictionary is essentially indexed
on the sides of the rolls.
So we have default and other dice.
Actually, I realize now that that's not a very good idea.
Oh, no, sorry.
Rolls is what you put in the table.
Rolls is what you get from the input.
So that should be fine.
Well, if you have clashing, the software
is not handling the clashing properly.
So I'm just realizing that.
So that was not a smart idea.
We should probably fix that later.
Or maybe we should have a test to it
to see that this won't be working as expected.
But anyway, we're using tabulate function,
passing on the table, the headers, and that's it.
So I just want to show you how easy
is to use tabulate in case you might be needing that.
Let's say we're approaching the break.
Yeah.
So yeah, I think we're going to go 10 minutes early.
10 minutes early?
OK.
Sounds good.
Let me just print out the output so I can.
And I think this is perfect timing.
I was hoping to find the.
Yeah, let's use this one.
So I have a sequence in my terminal.
So let me clear this.
I run the Python interpreter here.
So let me create this sequence I want to import from DND roller.
And by the way, I haven't added neither dice roller nor
sequence rolls into the init file.
So I need to have the full input in this particular case.
Dice import sequence roll.
Or maybe let me show you that the other way doesn't work.
Import sequence.
What's the name of the function exactly?
Sequence rolls.
As I told you, it doesn't work because it could not
be finding the data in it package.
But if you look into the dice module, it could be fine.
And so there you go.
And then you can do print sequence rolls of sequence.
There you go.
This is how tabulate works.
It's pretty convenient.
And that's it.
So I think the last thing I want to tell you before going into
the packaging, unless you're not entirely interested, and then
I will skip that part, is essentially how do we test
these things?
And in particular, how do we test having random numbers
generations?
So we have to make tests a little bit unfair in order to
be consistent in our tests.
All right.
So the very last thing I promised I wanted to tell you
about the software before moving to the package,
finally, you might say at that point, is an extra excuse to
tell you about how do you test with random numbers.
I think it's something that might be, I'd say might,
because it really depends on what you're doing.
But it might be useful to you to know.
And that's also something I had fun playing with while
preparing the material.
So moving on to the last sequence of tests for sequence
rolls, I'll just go and copy all the code I have here into a
new file, and then I will make some comments about it.
So again, we have a third test module called test
underscore sequence underscore rolls dot five.
And this is just containing the test for the sequence
rolls function.
So again, it's a matter of how you decide to do things.
But at the level we decided to do with this project,
essentially, the corresponding is one function, one Python
module, which seems quite a lot in terms of granularity,
because it's really different.
But in the end, every single Python module is really
self-contained.
And again, if the takeaway message is to do tests in
isolations, you want to test every single functionality,
regardless of what's happening with the rest of your own
software, that's perhaps a good development pattern or best
practice.
So the first thing we do here in the first test is very
similar to what we've been doing in the previous test for
dice roll.
So we patch this time dice roll, and we make sure that
when we call sequence rolls, the dice roll mock object is
being called so that we are absolutely sure we're not
reinventing the wheel.
And by the way, this idea of reinventing the wheel is, I'd
say, particularly close to me because of what I've been
doing in my previous life, doing my PhD in particular.
And I was working on a problem which was called clone
detection, so methods to identify duplications in big
softwares.
And even if this seems very niche to you, just think of
the refactoring functionality you might have in code
editors or advanced ID.
This piece of code, by the way, is very similar to
something you've already written here.
Duplications in code are not always a good idea, and so you
really want to get rid of them.
And so this idea of making sure that you're not
reinventing the wheel is essentially testing both.
So it's testing that you're reusing the piece of software
you already have.
And so you did have a dependency by your testing
this dependency in isolation.
And the second bit is I'm not duplicating code in my code
base, which generally is also a good bit.
But that's for the first test.
So again, I'm using patch from unit test, standard library.
Here, there's not PyTest involved at all.
It's just like unit test.
The other thing now is what would you do if you have to
make sure that since a sequence roles is going to be
calling dice roles, and dice roles by effect is what is
calling role, and ultimately the round end from Python, you
have the randomness there.
And when you're testing with random, there's no way you can
actually be consistent, you might think, because they're
random.
Well, indeed there is a way.
And you have to remember that this is not real random.
This is pseudo random number generators.
And so there is indeed a way to control the randomness in
your code.
And this is obtained by random seed.
So the random seed is that piece of information that you
can set.
And whenever you rerun the code with the same test of
input multiple times, you're absolutely guaranteed that the
output will be the same.
So essentially, I called it unfair dice in the sense that
you're essentially generating an unfair sequence of numbers
which are totally controlled.
It would mean that you're essentially playing with a die
you can control.
I don't know how to say that in English.
You're cheating.
Sorry?
Loaded dice.
Thank you very much.
I was missing that.
Thank you.
You were playing with loaded dice.
So you know exactly what's going on.
And the way you do this is using seed on a specific
number.
And what we will be doing is we're generating sequence with
unfair dice.
And then reusing in the test the same exact random seed in
our test, we're absolutely guaranteed.
In this case, it's like 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7.
Which, by the way, is also a very good seed because of the
binary representation of it.
But that would open an entire new chapter which I'm not
going to go into.
And then essentially we absolutely guarantee that when
we do this, we're using the same random seed.
And so any random number we generate is
absolutely repeatable.
This is what this test is doing.
So I'm fixing a seed.
I'm generating some rolling here in this unfair dice
function.
And so I'm calling run the end here.
And then refixing the seed again.
So the first fixing has been done internally in unfair dice.
I'm doing this in the test code.
And then I call the roll function.
And so again, run the end.
I'm calling run the end again.
And you'll be absolutely guaranteed that you're
generating again the same number because you're
restarting from the same starting point.
So this is just to take away another piece of extra, an
extra piece of information relating to testing with
random numbers.
And the rest of it is just testing that this is actually
going to happen.
So to finalize this bit, we run Python minus M, PyTest
minus V. And we're all done.
We have 26 tests passed.
And testSequencers.py has been run as well.
So we're absolutely sure that according to the test we
developed, everything works fine.
Nice.
So we're fun done with the code development.
And so what we have achieved so far, and we can go back to
the code terminal maybe, code editor, we have, let me close
a little bit this files.
We don't need them anymore.
Nice.
So this is our project structure.
This is what it might look like on your end, too.
So we have a dnd underscore roller, which is the Python
package we've been developing.
This is the test folder, which is containing all the test
modules.
And the rest of it is just like the previous thing relating
to the GitHub repository.
So what we're missing now is we have to make this folder an
actual software package.
And to do that, we just need a couple of things more.
Nothing particularly.
The first thing we're going to do, and we move on to the
third section of the document, so time to pack, is creating a
special file, which is called setup.py.
So let's move on in creating the setup.pile.
And with this setup.py, we'll be using
setupTools.setup function.
So we create within the main folder here.
Before we do here, there you go.
It's setup.py.
So from setupTools, we import setup and findPackage, which
is packages, which is the function we'll be using.
So the setup function is a function that will be called
whenever we want to install a package.
And by the way, this is general Python packaging
information.
This is how you do.
And actually, in the document, the reference you're going to
find is pointing directly to the main official Python
documentation.
So we're not talking Conda yet.
We're not talking Peep specifically yet.
We're just talking general Python packaging.
Python, as a language, is offering you a framework to
prepare your software to be packaged.
The next bit for ourselves will be, let's use a tool that
generates recipes that will be useful to install these
packages on many, many different platforms.
OK, let me just copy this for the sake of time in the
setup.file.
You can do that as well if you want.
And then we can comment what's going on.
But it's pretty much straightforward.
So I hope, at least.
And if it's not, please let me know.
So well, the setup file is taking a series of metadata.
And this is very important, because we'll be using this in
a second.
We specify a name and a version.
And those are the main two things you
immediately specify.
The name corresponds to how you want the package to be
named when you pack everything.
And the version is the version number.
I'm not going to have the time to go into the how do you
version your software.
But there are documentations there.
And if you look at the general official documentation of
Python packaging, there are references for you to expand on
this particular topic.
Let's say that so far we have version 0.0.1.
So we have a minor version.
Actually, we have a patch of a minor version in this
particular case.
But it is where it is.
It's fine.
We can set our initial number as we like.
I go for 0.0.1.
Then you specify who are the authors or the single author.
It's really up to you.
It could be the name and then author email.
This will be all package metadata that if you've
published packages on PyPy during your work days, or you
have experience with working with PyPy packages, these
information will be published on the main page on PyPy directly.
So these very information go there on PyPy.
But they're also part of the metadata of the software
package we're going to develop.
Then we have a description.
And that's a simple description.
In this case, it's just a sentence, Python package
draw DND dice in the terminal.
And you can also have a long description.
In this case, we're doing something which is a standard
practice when you have to code into GitHub repository.
We're reusing the readme file.
So on the top of this file, what I've done is essentially
loading the readme file into a long description Python
variable.
So I'm reading the file.
I'm specifying in the metadata of setup that the long
description content type is marked down, because readme is
generally written in markdown.
Actually, it's a markdown file.
So that is the format you're expecting.
And then you specify the URL of your project.
So what is the home page of this project?
Generally, this corresponds also to the GitHub repository
where you're publishing the code.
In this case, let me fix this.
It's going to be my username slash DND roller, as we've been
creating in the very beginning of the workshop.
What else?
That's my email.
That's actually a mail not existing.
I think I made a mistake there.
But that's fine.
I will be fixing that now.
It's anaconda.com.
And then, yes, names could be and all of you, because we've
been working with this all together.
And we include package data true.
Well, this is actually true, but we're not using it.
This include package data is, yes, we have a question.
Yeah.
Well, that answer I don't know.
But the thing is, let me show you what I've been doing with
the emoji thing.
The Noemoji package pipeline.
Pipeline.
The classifier actually is something I was going to talk
about in a second.
So let me keep this page here open.
The pipeline.
Because actually, something I don't remind, I don't
remember off the top of my head right now, and I'm
checking with you, is, sorry, there's no Noemoji here.
No emoji.
There you go.
So if you go here, yeah, you do have an email here.
That's the mail to link.
Yeah.
It's pushed there, directly on there.
You can use specific email for project if you're
worried about spam.
Yeah.
That's actually a very good point.
No, no, no.
That's a very good point.
And to be honest, a point I've never thought about before.
So thank you very much for your contribution.
It's a very good point.
There are ways in which, as far as I know, and you can
correct me if I'm mistaken, you have sort of an alias
can specify for your emails.
So you can actually, Apple, as a service developed
specifically for that, it's called Hi My Email, is doing
exactly that, isn't it?
So it's creating alias for your emails so that your email
has never showed up in clear.
And you can about that.
Yeah.
That's a very good point.
All you can do, as I was doing, like putting fake emails,
that's never going to work.
But I'm kidding.
What I was going to say earlier was, we have an
include package data here.
And this include package data is specifically necessary when
you have dependencies in your package that are not specific
source files.
So for example, I happen to have packaged something that
had HTML, CSS dependencies, were not Python dependencies.
So you can include all of them into the package as
resources of your package.
This instruction here is necessary to instruct the set
up function to look at your folder structure and in case
exclude specific folders.
You don't want to make part of the software package you're
building.
And last but by no means least, the dependencies of
your package.
So in this particular case, we do require NoMoji, that
particular version, for example.
We can drop the version specification if that's not
necessary.
And Tabulate, as we're doing for Tabulate, for example.
We say we need NoMoji and Tabulate.
That should be fine as well.
Good.
Sure.
I wouldn't.
Because tests are there.
And when you install it, you want to have tests in your
Python package.
Unless you have a very specific reason not to.
But I cannot think of one at the moment.
Oh yes, please.
At this particular step, we're not using Conda yet.
And what we'll be doing, using Grayscale in a second, is
actually leveraging on these information here to generate
the recipe for you.
So it's the opposite of what you're asking, if I
understood correctly.
So you specify your dependency for a package that presumably
we go on PyPy.
And instead, we will make it a Conda package out of it.
So it goes on a different place, because on Conda Forge,
on Conda repositories.
And Grayscale is essentially doing the job for you in
writing all this thing manually.
It's like reading the metadata from your specifications
there and preparing the recipe for you.
Yeah.
Yes.
Sure.
That's a very good question.
When we will be about to build the package,
there will be default packages including the environment,
which are the very same defaults that you get when
you create a new environment.
So you don't have to specify them as the paper
package you were mentioning.
That would be part of the dependency for you already.
What happens?
Oh, sorry.
Condo-exclusive dependencies, you mean packages that would
be downloaded from condo rather than from PyPy?
Yes, there is.
That was actually a part which is not in the tutorial,
but in the break I actually thought it could have been
a good addition, and so I will be doing right now,
so bear with me.
One of the things that you can do in condo environment,
and this is probably one of the most important things,
one of the main reasons at least to my experience,
why you want to use condo environment over other ways
of creating environments, is that you can easily replicate
and reproduce environment on different platforms.
And this is one of the benefits of condo.
So I'm going to show you now in a new shell.
So let me increase the font here.
So let go back into the condo info minus minus m's.
So I have a list of environment.
I want to export this packaging environment.
The way to do this is to do condo m export.
This will create, you have to name the environment you want,
and that's going to be packaging.
This is going to create a YAML file,
which is similar to the PIP requirements you generate.
So I'm going to show you now what's going on.
This is the output, but most likely you
want to save it into a file.
So you do condo m export.
So let me clear shell here so you can see.
Condo m export minus n packaging.
And then you redirect the output to an environment.yaml file.
There are other options you might want to add,
and this also brings me to another point.
I don't remember exactly all the things.
So let me go with help.
Otherwise I go, yes.
So you can specify the channels you want.
Otherwise they will be automatically inferred.
You can avoid putting the number of builds.
And this is generally useful when
you want to have portability between different platforms.
Because build numbers might be very operating system
specifics, because especially when
you have scientific packages dependencies like NumPy,
this has always been my experience.
If you go with build on Linux, it's
not going to work on Mac, because the build number
is different.
So you want to get rid of that if you really don't need them.
And you might also say ignore channels,
so that it goes by default by the channels you've set up
as default on your environment.
Otherwise it goes into the packages you have.
And in fact, we're going to avoid that.
So we're going to avoid the number of builds here.
You can also specify the file you
want to write the export to without using
the redirection there using the minus f option.
So let me just do that.
Conda no builds.
That was the option I couldn't remember.
So clear conda export minus minus no builds on environment
dot channel.
So if we open this file now.
Oh, sorry.
You're right.
Let me do that again.
I forgot the name of the environment I wanted.
It goes on the current environment by default.
Thank you.
I didn't see that.
OK.
So this YAML file is the file you
need to recreate exactly the environment you had.
As you can see immediately on the top,
you can see my channel, because that is where one dependency is
being taken.
And how the channels actually work in Conda
is you have a list of channels.
You can specify as many as you like.
And you can specify the number of channels
that you want to have.
So you can specify the number of channels
you can specify as many as you like.
And any package will be taken using a name resolution order.
So if one package can be found in one channel,
like Lerio Maggio, that is the channel that will be used.
Otherwise, it goes to the next in the list and go on
on until that package cannot be found anywhere.
And the same applies if you're using Conda Forge, for example.
Or if you happen to be working with PyTorch, which
is my experience, for example, you always
want to install PyTorch.
Well, not always, because now you can use default channels.
But in the past, you wanted to specify the minus PyTorch,
sorry, the PyTorch channel to install things.
And so PyTorch was the top of the list.
And PyTorch was installed from there.
The rest of it was installed from Conda Forge or Anaconda
default packages, packet channels.
Yes.
Yes, yes.
That's why Conda Forge actually exists.
And we've been discussing this in the break.
Actually, you can do much more than that.
You can actually force any specific package
to be in a channel at a specific checksum.
So even when you're installing packages,
you want to check that you're actually,
this is one of the extra bits provided by Conda,
to be honest.
Something like when you're getting packages from defaults
in Anaconda channels, you're absolutely guaranteed
that you're not getting rubbish.
Because this is one of the things
we do on maintaining the default channel.
And the Conda Forge is a similar effort,
but it's a community effort.
And that's why they will tell you later,
and I already spoil it a little bit,
that Conda Forge, being this important,
and this community-centered repositories
for other packages, that there is an approval process
to have packages on Conda Forge for exactly the same reason
you were mentioning.
Because you never know what you can get in from the internet,
specifically from PyPy.
That there's been lots of examples.
In my experience, because this is what my radar
is going closer to, is in PyTorch specifically,
if you're looking for packages, you have plenty
of other similar-named packages, malicious packages.
And it was at some point, and there was actually a news,
a piece of news which was particularly useful.
The nightly build of PyTorch on PyPy was tampered.
And in fact, if you were installing it from Conda,
you didn't have any problem.
But if you install it from PyPy,
you were installing malicious code.
And that was quite an issue.
Anyway, sorry for going away with things.
Well, as you can see now, what the expert has been done
is just telling me the package I had in my environment
and the version, not the build version.
So it's like fixing the version.
At this point, to my experience,
and this is what I normally do, is like,
if I have to share this file, do I really need to have
a list of everything in my environment?
If you share this file, you're absolutely guaranteed
this will work, and I promise you it will.
But if you really want to tell to someone
what are the dependencies to your project,
you can get rid of some of them,
because some of these packages will be installed anyway
because they are dependency of the Conda environment.
So what I would normally do is like, okay,
I've never installed any package called this or like this,
so I just, an emoji, yes, I do, and I keep this.
So packaging, no.
Pip, yes, pip is really necessary
because I might need to install things from pip.
So let's install pip.
PyTest, I've installed, yes.
Python, sure.
Setup tools, it's default, let's keep it.
Tabulate, yes.
The rest of it, I didn't.
You can get rid of the prefix here because you can.
This prefix is used to say what is gonna be the path
of your environment.
You can get rid of that, it's not necessary.
And that's it, so this is your environment.
Once you have this file, you can push it on the repository
as it will be doing, and you can recreate
on your own computer using directly Conda,
the same environment using this specific version
of the package.
And the same rules apply similar
to the pip requirements file.
So if you don't want to have this to be a strict dependency
but at least a minimum dependency,
you can say instead of no emoji equal to no point no point five,
you can say greater than or equal to no point no point five.
Same, it works the same way.
Just a reminder that in pip, you use the double equal,
in Conda you use a single equal.
That's the only difference.
And in this particular case,
we don't have any pip installed packages,
but if you were, you would have add an extra section here
that is called pip, and then you have the list of packages
installed from pip in this sub list.
And the result will be that when you recreate the environment,
Conda packages will be installed first
and pip dependencies later.
And that's it, yes please.
Sorry.
Sure.
No, no, if you had pip dependencies,
Conda and the export would have added them.
I can, for example, show you this very quickly
on a different environment, like let me see.
PPML-SIFT has a pip dependency for sure because I know that.
So I'm going to export this one.
PPML-SIFT, and let me just print it.
I don't save it.
There you go.
You have an extra section pip, and this list of packages
that will be following the requirements.file standard.
So the double equal there.
And the mxport has gotten them directly from the environment.
Okay?
No worries.
That being said, okay.
Okay, we have the environment there.
That's been said.
We need to finish the packaging, yeah.
Yeah, so we write some description to the project.
I just copy here to make it super quick.
So I'm going to copy this into the readme file
so we have a proper longer description.
So I replace the content here to this one.
And if you're wondering, you can see preview
of what we've been doing.
This is how it looks like.
Maybe tabulation is bad, but it should be good on GitHub.
And this is what will be the longer description
for our project, this mark down here.
Last but not least, we have some configuration file to set up.
This is, again, standard Python packaging.
So we go for the setup.cfg and the pyproject.toml.
Some of these could have been used.
I decided to share both of them because some of these
you can actually use directly pyproject.toml
in case you don't want to.
I just decided to show both because standard practice
to have either one or both is the same thing.
There's no particular rule there that applies,
at least to my knowledge.
So you create a new file, setup.cfg, and you copy them.
The only thing I want to mention, I think, here
is you can specify the license file, which is generally
a good important bit because you want to license your software.
And then you have a classifiers.
And this is the extra metadata for package retrieval,
specifically on PyPI.
This is very useful.
And the pyproject.toml is essentially
replicating a few environments.
The last thing in this is what we need, pyproject.toml.
Sorry, I missed the name.
Toml here.
Toml is this format that we'll be using here.
It's a metadata.
It's a markup formatting here where you have,
we were specifying the same classifiers,
the same instructions, sort of replicating
the same information in a different format.
We're also replicating dependencies.
Again, an emoji and tabulate.
The reason why we're doing this is
because both Conda, Build, and Grayscale
will be reading from different bits.
That's why I'm doing this.
But I will be showing you in a second.
Nice.
So at this point, this is how your project might look like.
And feel free to tell me any questions in the meantime
if you have them.
So we've been doing this.
This is the project we have.
We have the code, the tests, the metadata, and the set.
Tab.py.
We're actually ready to pack.
So the last bit we need is to add everything on GitHub.
So I will be doing something that I would normally never do,
as in doing a git commit with everything in it.
But just because I don't know what is your practice,
I would be more than happy to know what you do.
My general way of controlling things in git repositories
is having very clear git commit messages.
And in particular, they should be semantically related.
So whenever you push something on a repository,
you don't want to see something like,
I've done this, this, this, and that in many different files
from many different things.
I do one commit at a time.
Because you don't pay commits, it's fine.
And it's always good for you to track things back.
And when you have to roll back changes,
you can go very neat peeking the thing you need.
But that's up to actually the practice
you prefer to embark, I would say.
But at this point, I git add everything.
And then I git commit, say, release ready to be packed.
Good point.
I actually would like to add it to the repository.
Because this is something you can automate your things with.
In this particular case of packaging,
it doesn't really make any difference.
But if you're sharing your code with somebody
and just want to say, OK, my project is actually
on that repository with this code,
and you want to have instructions
to replicate your environment.
Or if you're working on open source projects,
you have presumably a section how to contribute.
And the first thing you do in contributing
is setting up the environment.
And that's how you do it.
So you make that file living, environment.yml.
So my general practice is I do both.
I do environment.yml and requirements.txt,
depending if Conda is urgently necessary or not.
So if I support both, it's up to you, whichever you prefer.
And these things are actually taken into account
with automated systems.
So I'm working a lot with Jupyter Notebooks.
So like having tutorials in Jupyter Notebooks
for data science.
And if you go with projects like,
I don't know if you ever used it, but MyBinder, for example,
which is a sort of a Docker generating a Jupyter
server for you, it reads from the repository.
And if it finds a file which is called environment.yml,
it understands that second environment.
It sets up everything for you.
Otherwise, it goes for requirements.file.
If you couldn't find any of those,
it goes for default environment.
And if you have dependencies, it's not going to work.
OK?
But yeah, I should probably, I have no idea where that file is.
Is it here?
Yes, it's here.
So let's move this file into this one.
Let me cut environment to make sure it's the right one.
Yes.
So I git add everything, and I git commit minus m,
ready to pack.
OK?
Everything is my environment.
By the way, this is git ignore at its best.
As you can see here, we have PyTest cache.
But this is not part of the git commit,
likely, because that has been ignored by git ignore.
And this is the reason why you want to use templates,
because this is standard things you don't
want to have on your repository.
That's it, I guess.
We have to git push.
So you push on your repository now.
That has been done.
Go back here, refresh.
Wrong window.
We should refresh this one.
And there you go.
What would we have everything?
Nice.
So before actually doing the package,
we want to create a release.
And this release will be automatically
used by the graceful conda recipe generator.
So to do a release is actually pretty easy.
So you go and releases here, create a new release
of your software.
You want to use a tag.
And when you specify a tag, you want to use a version,
because this is what will be visualized directly into,
what did I say here to do?
I say this after telling you what graceful is.
So let me just not jump to conclusion.
Let me follow the same mind path I had.
Well, I don't know how many of you recognize this picture.
How many?
I love you guys.
Essentially, the reason why this is called graceful
is because it's an open source re-implementation
of a previous system, which was called Conda Skeleton.
And so they come up with graceful.
I think it was genius.
Anyway, graceful is an open source project
that you can use to automatically generate for you
a conda recipe, starting either for a GitHub repository, which
is hosting your project, and in particular, a package version,
a release of your project, or starting from a tarp archive
you can have of your local folder.
So we've been demonstrating, and this
is to answer a question I got in the very beginning.
I can't remember from whom.
Asking, we just need to have necessarily GitHub?
The answer was no.
In alternative, you can pack everything in a tar.gz file,
and you can use that as a reference for graceful.
I'm not going to do that, but that's for your information.
You can just use a local package instead
of using a URL from GitHub.
It's going to be the same thing.
Anyway, so before that, we have to have graceful
installed on our machine.
To do this, we just add graceful,
which lives in Conda Forge.
So this time we do have an extra dependency,
but it's not going to be a dependency for our package.
It's a dependency for our building system, which
is two different things.
But we're still installing everything
within the same package we don't care at this point.
So we go Conda install.
Sorry, let me just clear the thing so you can see on top.
Conda install minus C, Conda Forge.
So we're installing everything from Conda Forge, Graceful,
and send our disk specific version.
The reason why we're specifying also this
is because an incompatible version was installed.
So I just wanted to make sure that everything
is ready for us to work.
So we install Graceful first.
It takes, should be taking.
Yes, just in the meantime, I think I know what's going on.
What's going to happen is essentially now
making resolutions for the names and things.
And what this will require, since we're
switching to installing packages from Conda Forge,
will require to update some certificates package.
And this is the exact package containing
the checksums of all the packages
that you have in the channels, which will be referenced
when you have to check that you're installing actually
genuine package from there.
By the way, this is downloading everything.
That's why it's taking so long.
Because if you remember, I've done something
that wasn't actually in the path, which
was Conda clean my cache.
So it's actually downloading everything now.
And on our conference Wi-Fi, probably that
wasn't a good idea.
But fingers crossed, it will be working pretty soon.
Yes, so you're essentially seeing
the effect of cleaning the cache.
So you have to install everything from scratch.
OK, everything has been done.
Installing.
And that's it.
Yay.
So now we are creating the release for our software.
So I go back to where I was.
So I just go back again to show you what I've been doing.
I click on Create New Release after having pushed everything.
So just make sure that everything is on the repository
now.
You create a new release.
You create a new tag, which has the name of the version
you want, because this will be the version that Grayscale will
think your software will have.
Let's say, sorry, create a new tag.
Target main, so the main branch we're taking as reference.
DND roller, 0.0.1.
Description, DND, nice roller, the 0.0.1.
Nice.
We publish it, and that's it.
So the effect of doing this is GitHub is creating for us
these two archives.
And so these archives are exactly plus some metadata
here on a specific GitHub commit.
Checksum and versioning.
So at this point, what we want to do
is using Grayscale to generate a new recipe.
So we move away from the first thing
that the tutorial is telling you to do
is to move away from the root folder
because Grayscale will create a recipe that
is called Azure package that shouldn't
be living in the root folder of your project.
So we just have to get away from there.
And in particular, we're telling you
move away in the parent folder if you like,
and then create a new Grayscale folder.
It can be any folder you like.
It doesn't have to be Grayscale.
And we're moving into this folder as well.
So this is where we're living now.
Something, something, something slash Grayscale.
OK?
And now we create the recipe.
To do that, we just copy this one and then adjust it.
So this is going to be my repository.
Yes, so Grayscale, PyPy, and the URL of GitHub repository.
This is going on the GitHub repository,
checking the release, getting the latest one,
and generating with all the metadata and the source code
found in the archive a file which
will be named meta.yaml, which is going
to be the actual recipe for our Cunda project.
As you can see, it's downloading the dependency.
Tabulate has been found.
It's been reading the PyProject.toml.
Everything is fine.
NoMoji has a red missing dependency
because of this maintainer.
OK.
Something I want to try now is to see whether I could perhaps,
I don't know, let me check that.
The help here of Grayscale.
Grayscale essentially, as Mahe was telling you
in the beginning, is able to generate recipe either
for Python packages or R packages.
And so this is the meaning of passing PyPy in the beginning.
If you were going to create package for R,
you would have said crun, because that's
the reference package provider.
And that's the only options you have here on Grayscale.
So there is no way you can specify
at this point in Grayscale.
That was my guess, actually, but I just wanted to be sure.
Grayscale has generated a recipe for us.
So if we look at what's inside this folder,
there's a DND roller folder.
Within this folder, we have meta.tml, which is the recipe.
Let's have a look at this.
Nice.
So this is the actual recipe that CondaBuild
will read and use to install your package.
The reason why we're using Grayscale
is because we don't have to write this manually.
Otherwise, you're very welcome to write it manually.
Or similarly, you're very welcome to update it manually
if Grayscale has something missing into that.
So we might quickly understand the format here.
You're setting the name of the version of this package.
And so this variable will be used later on.
In particular, in the package section,
you have a name of the version.
Then you have a source.
And this source is pointing to a specific tag,
which is, by the way, the version.
That's why we call it the no.no.1 on GitHub
and with a specific checksum here.
So we're absolutely sure we're getting that one.
There's a section specifying
what are the instructions to build it.
In this particular case,
we have no specific architecture for a package.
So it's going to be no arc,
which means every single platform we're going to do.
The command to run to build is Python.
So the Python that you have in your environment,
minus m pip install dot,
which is the current folder, minus minus v,
to have some verbosity.
And then you have requirements.
So you have Python, setup tools, and pip.
And all the external dependencies like Noemoji and Tabulate.
And then you have tests as well.
And this test will be run and used
to make sure everything works.
Okay, so you have the import test in the nd roller.
You have the pip check test and the requires requirement test.
Metadata, the about section will be taken from this URL,
the URL, the license.
License file is here within the package.
And recipe maintainer is this one, this guy here,
because there's that dependency on the channel we had.
Nice.
So at this point, we have the recipe.
We just have to build the package using this recipe.
To do that, we can first of install conda build
in our own environment, because we need conda build.
Conda build.
Fingers crossed this will be quick.
Yes.
I need to download a bit of packages.
Okay.
It was quite quick.
There you go.
And now we can build our package.
In this case, we are trying to specify the channel we need
for the extra dependency, because we're building
this package with that channel dependency.
Pardon, I'm in the wrong folder.
I need to be in the grayscale folder,
because it was actually looking for a folder
named as the name of the package,
and that's why grayscale is calling that folder in that way.
So you have to be, let me clear this one.
You have to be in this, da da da da, grayscale folder,
and within this folder, you have the dnd roller package,
sorry, folder, containing the metadata,
pardon, meta.yml recipe.
So we do conda build again.
This time should be working.
I think you do, but I'm not entirely sure,
to be totally fair.
If you do, you shouldn't be doing any harm, but...
When I tested this, the YAML wasn't there,
so I'm not sure.
It might be not necessary now, but I'm not sure.
So what is doing that right now is actually building a package.
So it's gonna be local,
and it will be telling you where that package lives in a second.
As soon as this is done.
But essentially, it's telling you already now here.
So, okay, let it finish.
Nice.
Successfully installed.
Now it's running testing.
Make sure that everything is done.
So the package has been built.
Test is being run now.
Import check, paper check, no broken requirements found.
That was good.
We have the package.
There we go.
We have the package done.
And the package is actually living in this folder.
So yadadada slash minikonda, whatever,
slash konda dash BLD.
It should be similar to on your end.
And within that, there's a subfolder,
depending on the architecture you were building for.
In this case, we have no arc.
And then you have a tar.bz2 file,
and that's the package we've just built
from using konda build.
This is a local package,
and if you scroll down there, it tells you,
by the way, to have konda build upload
to anaconda.org automatically,
use konda config mother-of-man set anaconda upload, yes.
Or you just do anaconda upload and the package that you want.
Okay?
So if I now do this, and you can do that if you like,
on your end, so I copy this path,
I do anaconda upload,
entrusting myself remembering the password,
which might be really not the case.
So this is what it's doing.
So I'm actually trying to upload.
I'm actually not gonna do that
because I'm pretty sure I don't remember the password.
I probably do.
No, that's bye-bye.
No, I don't remember the password.
That's fine.
Anyway, this is the command you want to run
to upload on your own channel, the package.
So if I do that, I will be uploading that
on my Ledium module channel as well.
And so there will be a DND roller packet there
that you can install from.
If you want to do that live right now,
you're very welcome to do so.
So if everything goes well,
a DND roller dot tar dot BZ, actually BZ2, not GZ,
GZ here, should be created into
conda prefix slash conda build, no arc, blah blah blah.
And this is the Windows version.
And now I think it's time for Dave to get the stage
and telling you a little bit more about CondaForge.
In the meantime, do you have any question
as soon as Dave is getting ready for his part?
Yes, please.
We have two.
Can you go, please?
That's a very good question.
So the conda environment is a Python virtual environment,
meaning it's a collection of packages
living in a sandbox together.
I'm sorry if I'm messing the setup up.
The conda package is actually a single package
that you can have within a virtual environment.
Virtual environment could be conda environment
if you're using conda to prepare everything,
or they can be virtual M virtual environments,
pyM virtual environments, we have all the alternatives.
We've been seeing conda virtual environments.
That's a conda package, the whole thing.
But what I put on GitHub as environment.yml
was the file you can use to recreate the same environment,
sorry, same conda environment I was having
while I was developing the project.
Meaning, if you're willing to contribute
to this fantastic DND roller project,
you might want to set up my own environment
so that you're absolutely sure that you're working
with the same version of packages I was working
to make everything working on the project.
And at the same time, you're not polluting
any thing you have on your computer
because you're just making everything
living in their own sandbox,
and that's just for the purpose of working with DND roller.
No worries, thank you.
We have another one.
Pardon?
Yes, astu, yeah.
I think it must be public because otherwise
I don't think there is any way for you
to provide credentials there.
At least to the best of my knowledge.
But exactly, if you don't want to have that at all,
you just bypass GitHub completely
and you pack your project as a tar.gz file
and you do conduct, if we do grayscale, pi, pi,
your package.tar.gz, same thing.
Essentially, the GitHub bits is just
to automatically download these packages.
Oh, sorry, you're not seeing that anymore,
but it's just to download the packages
from GitHub automatically.
That's it.
Yes.
That's a good question.
To my experience, no.
Well, yes, but the location of this environment
doesn't live within the source code,
unless you really want to, because you can do that.
You can specify the path of your conda environment.
So the default one is conda prefix slash ems,
and they all live there.
So in fact, if you, I'm not showing,
but if you do conda info management as ems,
you will see that the prefix of everything
is always the same.
It's always conda prefix slash ems slash whatever.
Yes.
To my experience, that's the case, yes, yes.
I just want to tell you that something
that we've been working on, and that would be game changer,
is we'll be working that for the Anaconda notebook
we've been having.
I don't know if you know that,
but Anaconda has a notebook online service you can use.
We've been working on, it's still ongoing,
but we've been working on having dependencies
within environments, so that you can have
child environments from the parent environments,
which means that some packages may be reused
from other environments, so you don't have to install them.
And the reason why we're doing this is to save space,
because as you've seen, when you download lots of packages,
it's a good bit that you have isolations,
and so you have your own version with the same thing,
but when the versions are exactly the same,
you're not deloaning the packages multiple times,
but you're having Python packages replicated,
the same Python packages replicated multiple times,
and when you are limited in space,
in cloud storage space, for example,
you don't want to do that.
And so we're trying to see if there's any way to do that.
Can we proceed?
I think I've told you everything I know.
I don't know any more than that.
That's true.
Thank you.
Stephen, I'm going to be using this mic, so.
OK.
So we have 24 minutes left, OK?
And I want to discuss a couple things,
and since we have 24 minutes left,
I'm going to discuss them in a particular way.
First, I'm going to talk about how you can publish your package
now that you have it created, kind of compatible package.
And then secondly, I'm going to talk about the Conda ecosystem
and community, OK?
And then if we have time, we'll throw it open to questions
and answers.
Hey, I'm live.
We also have several other people
in the room who are savvy on Conda, so.
OK, so if you look at the HackMD,
there are two sections at the end.
One is submitting to CondaForge, time allowing,
and the other is publishing in your own channel, time allowing.
OK.
Now, Valerio talked about this a little bit, the second option
here.
Both of these are slightly different from what
we've covered before.
So the tutorial above this covers a lot of things
that were out there on the net, but not in a necessarily
coherent form.
This, excuse me, these two sections
are based on documentation that's out there
that's in a coherent form, and it's pretty good actually.
So today, I'm not going to step you through these hands on,
because the documentation that's out there is pretty good, OK?
I do recommend you take a look at this.
I've added some comments to the tutorial,
but yes, we're not going to do a step by step.
But I'm going to talk about it at a high level.
Anybody objecting?
OK, you people have the power.
Remember that.
OK.
So yeah, CondaForge is step by step instruction.
So CondaForge is the largest public channel out there.
It has over 20,000 packages on it.
It has over 3 billion, that's with a B,
package downloads per year.
OK.
CondaForge is widely used and wildly popular.
So if your goal is to have your package become
visible and easily installable to the world,
you want to publish on CondaForge.
And there's a process from their website, again,
fairly well described.
And here's how you would use it for our particular example
today.
And you basically make a copy of the Stage Recipes repo.
You then add your recipe, which we just created.
Excuse me, then add that to your copy of that repo.
And then you submit a pull request.
And a couple other things.
You probably want to change your GitHub ID there if you haven't.
OK, great.
And thanks to the magic of Grayskull,
we already have a SHA-256.
And thanks to the magic of Valerio,
we already have test cases.
OK.
So they do have standards at CondaForge.
And they want you to conform to them.
So it then has a checklist after you've
done their step-by-step instructions.
It tells you, OK, what do we need here?
And it says, OK, make sure you've got a license valid.
OK, I looked at the SPDX.
We're using MIT, which is actually in that list.
So we're good there.
Ensure that you have included a license file in your license.
If your license requires one, most do.
I have no idea.
OK.
If MIT requires us to recopy the license at the top level.
So I went looking in CondaForge, and I found this recent thing
that was merged.
And it was an MIT license, and it didn't
recreate the license file.
So you don't have to if it's an MIT license.
But I don't know where to find this information.
I just want to be clear on that.
Maybe others in the room do.
It's about having to duplicate your license, which sounds bad.
Because as Valerio mentioned, duplicating things
is not how you want to do it.
OK.
A bunch of things are already done,
because we use Grayskull.
And we're good.
OK, and then you commit.
You push, and you file a request.
When you submit the pull request,
because you have forked this from CondaForge,
you're submitting a pull request to the Stage Recipes repo.
There is a long template here about what it involves.
And the top part is about notifying the Python team
for us, that hey, can you take a look at this?
And there are directions on how to do that.
It's a little bit complicated because of how GitHub works.
So if this is your first submission,
you have to do one thing.
Whereas if it's your second submission,
you do a second thing.
It's much easier.
We apologize for that.
And then there's a checklist.
And you want to walk through this checklist
and make sure, yeah, OK, this is all good.
No, we're not including any static libraries, for instance.
All sorts of things.
So you want to actually check these things,
x them off as you go.
And then you want to create pull requests.
So you're going to submit it.
So you've got your package.
You put it into your copy of Stage Recipes.
You then submitted a pull request
to the CondaForge organization.
Now, CondaForge is an entirely voluntary organization.
And they are busy because CondaForge is the place to be.
So you, as a package submitter, you want it right now
because you just did this really cool thing about rolling D&D
dice.
You want it out there for the world to see.
But CondaForge is swimming in requests.
And so it's going to take them a while.
And so you now enter this dance where you think, OK,
have I waited long enough to ping them again?
Because sometimes you do have to ping them again.
Sometimes they don't get to it unless you ping them again.
And so my personal recommendation is wait a week.
Try and wait seven days.
If you haven't got stuff in seven days,
you can ping them in GitHub.
You can also ping them on their Matrix channel and say,
hey, I submitted this a week ago.
Can somebody look at it?
Do your best to be as polite as possible.
Absolutely as polite as possible.
Again, these are all volunteers.
They do this because they want to help the community actually
do stuff and share stuff.
So that's my advice for CondaForge.
Yeah, and Valerio mentioned some of this.
Here's what happens once it actually
gets published in CondaForge.
Yeah, and so they'll use an internal tool
called CondaSmithy.
And that's that.
OK, any questions about publishing in CondaForge?
Yes.
You said there's a schedule that you kind of have to meet.
What would be the thing that would be difficult
if you wanted to have a license?
I mean, sure, the testing is not that hard.
Yes.
Yeah, so people will often submit things without a license.
That's not difficult. It's just tedious.
Testing, I don't know if testing counts as difficult,
but it certainly is tedious.
Let's see.
I don't know.
The CondaForge.
So does anybody in the back row have an idea
on what CondaForge usually throws back on feedback?
Because they often do.
Anybody know?
None of us work on CondaForge.
So we're not the volunteers helping the world.
OK, yes.
Do No In the World and New York sugar harvest
Okay. Thank you. I'm sorry I can't answer. Thank you for answering. Okay. We're good.
Thank you, Stephen. Yeah. I'll try and repeat the question. Okay. So the second thing is
publishing in your own channel. So if your goal is not to make it visible to the world,
if your goal is to make it visible to a certain number of people and maybe make it public
and maybe make it private, okay, but you want your coworkers in Australia to be able to
use it, you can create your own Conda channel on anaconda.org and it's dead easy. Okay.
I did this last night. I've done it twice now. I have two channels. I don't know. I
was going to do it today and I have three. It's really easy to do. And then you have
to install the Anaconda client. Yeah, the Anaconda client and then you just push it.
And then lo and behold you have a channel and people can see it and they can use it.
It's minus C, you know, Larry Omagio. Sorry for your last name. I pronounced it wrong.
Okay. Yeah. So this is really easy. And once you have created the channel, you can say,
I want this to be private, which means it's restricted use. Or you can say it's public,
which is the default. Okay. There are lots of other channels out there. CondaForge again
is the big one. There's also Bioconda if you work in life sciences. Bioconda has about
8,000 packages on it. NVIDIA has its own. I think IBM has its own. I think Intel has
its own. There's a bunch of channels out there. So, okay. Okay. Good. So I'm going to stop
there and I'm going to go to the presentation. You're not supposed to see the thanks yet.
I'm going to ignore that. Nobody saw that. Okay. Good. And let's present. Let's see
what happens here. Okay. No smoke. Good. Okay. So my role in Conda is I'm the community manager.
Although you don't manage the Conda community. There's 35 million people. Okay. 35 million
users. So keep that in mind when you publish to CondaForge. You're potentially reaching
35 million people. You're making it easy for them to install stuff. Okay. So I'm the
community manager and in that role I've taken on a bunch of stuff. A bunch of stuff happened
before I started. Okay. This is an indication of what's going on in Conda. Let's see in
the big picture. Okay. So in 2021, so I've only been there 16 months. So keep that in
mind. But in 2021, the Conda, the core Conda engine became open source in practice as well
as in name. So it's been open source in name the whole time. It's 10 years old, whole time.
But say four or five years ago if you submitted a poll request, we might act on it, we might
not. And now if you submit a poll request, we know it's there and we are acting on it.
Okay. And that changed as of two years ago. Second thing that happened, code of conduct
last year was formalized. This is not, yeah, so this may not seem a big thing, but it's
actually huge. You can't have a functioning community without a prominent code of conduct
and one that gets enforced. And this sounds really weird, but we were really proud we
got our first case last year. Why are we proud? It means people care. Okay. If you're in a
community that doesn't care, you can have all the code of conduct stuff you want. It
doesn't help. But in Conda, people actually care. So we are trying to establish this open,
friendly, welcoming community. Okay. In 2022, the governance was changed and it now encourages,
well, it always encouraged participation from individuals, but it now encourages community
and corporate contributions. Okay. So a thing with open source is how do you get companies
to contribute without just taking? Okay. And so we have re-implemented our governance policies
so that we actually encourage corporate community contributions. So you have a voice at the
table. Okay. So equally important, we have limited the impact of corporate contributions.
So even if you're Anaconda, which is where I work, you have a limited impact now. It's
in the governance. So yeah, so Anaconda has a limited impact on decision making within
the Conda community now. And that's hard coded in the governance. Before that wasn't true
and Anaconda made most of the decisions. Okay. So big changes in the Conda community. These
are driven in part by Anaconda. I mean, I was hired by Anaconda to make this happen.
So we're really, really committed to the open source ethos. Last thing on this slide,
this year we became a non-focused, fiscally sponsored project, which means we had to actually
prove all this stuff. Okay. And so we are now officially an open source project with
non-focus, which is a great organization. I recommend looking at it for your open source
projects. Okay. Second thing from the community, there are lots of places to gather. So after
we leave this room in 10 minutes, well, we're all here, first of all, but there are a number
of places that you can actually get help and you can get information. So we launched a
discourse Q&A forum last year at Conda.discourse.group. We consolidated chat. We had chat everywhere,
everywhere. And now we have it in one place on Matrix. Okay. And it's the second URL,
which is really heinous. I apologize for that. And then 2023, this is almost here. We thought
it would be here by PyCon, but it's not quite there. We're going to have the Conda.org community
website. And so if you want community news, what are releases? There's a ton of products
in the Conda ecosystem. Just a ton. Okay. Not just the Conda core engine that we talked
about today. There's also Grayskull, which came from the community. There is Mamba. There's
just a bunch of stuff out there. Okay. So our goal is to have that be the place to go
for information. It's the hub. Okay. And what else? Conda is also at PyCon. So here's a
couple more things that are happening. If you're going to the packaging summit, there's
a talk by Yanis, who was here earlier, about Conda and PyPA. And then Bianca has a talk
on Saturday about Pluggy and using Pluggy in mature products like Conda. We have an
open space meetup. So if you want to talk about Conda, we'll have an open space meetup
on Saturday after Bianca's talk. That'll last for an hour, although you don't have to stay
there for the whole hour. And then on Monday and Tuesday, we're here for two days of sprints.
Okay. So I know there will be at least several people from Anaconda at that. So that's where
we are. And then many thanks to Valerio. So Valerio started his day yesterday in Europe
at PyCon DE, where he presented as well. And today he's here. He was here bright and early.
Amen. Yes. Really impressive. So Mahe and Bianca, who prepared the opening, Ken, sorry,
I'm stuttering. I stutter and I'm hard of hearing. I'm really good at my job. Okay.
Ken and Yanis and Steve, who are all in, well, yeah, Yanis is left, but they're all in the
back row. They came to help and answer questions, which they have been. So thank you so much.
I'd like to thank Amr. Are you still here? Okay. He's the one who made sure that you're
in the right room. Okay. Steven, are you a big person in back? Thank you so much, Steven.
Amen. Yeah. So nothing went wrong. And you don't, yeah, it's great. Okay. And finally,
you guys, because it's 12 22 and you're still here. Okay. And almost all of you are still
here, which is really impressive for a hands-on tutorial. So kudos to you. Okay. And I think
that's it. Yeah, that's it. One last thing. If this tutorial changed your life, okay.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, exactly. There's a conference about packaging and it's not just about the
Python packaging ecosystem. It's about everything. So on Linux, it's about all languages. It's
about language independence. So it's in Berlin in October. It's two days of conference and
one day of sprints. Think about attending this. And that's it for me. We have seven
minutes for questions generally. And keep in mind, we have four experts back there and
one here. Yes. Oh, you, oh my God, you have a question.
You're welcome. Yeah. Okay. Six minutes for questions. Anything. Shoot.
It comes in from a sort of known walled garden of conda, not conda forge, conda specifically.
And it gives me magical dependency resolution. Yes. And that's the bit that I'm actually
most interested in. So in the example I've just got, say I'm a dungeon master. I built
my own stuff. I decide that I'm going to use this DND roller. I locally have, what was
the name of this? No emoji 0.0.6. We've got a conflict. I can't use this because the requirements
are it has to be exactly five. This is a really simple example, but the environment we've
got has got flipped in hundreds of requirements and you get dependency conflicts so easily.
What do I do? Does anybody want to take that? I mean I could, but I'd be bold. Bianca.
Sorry, what was the first part of the question? You're not going to answer it? You can make
it up. I didn't know what the question was. Okay. Do you want to repeat the first part
of the question? Okay. So conda's magic to me because it gives me trusted versioning
from conda, not conda forge, where as working for a big company I can say I trust this stuff.
I'll let people have it. I'll build it into my own distributions and it gives me dependency
resolution magic that I don't quite understand that lets me build increasingly complicated
projects with dependencies that mostly work. But the dependency, like I've spent days
of hell on this when dependencies don't work out. So as a really, really simple example,
the roller class uses NoMoji 0.0.5 exactly. No flexibility whatsoever. Say I locally use
NoMoji 0.0.6. I try and use this project. I've got a conflict. Like in that scenario specifically
and then more broadly for dependency resolution, what do I do?
She does have the answer. I do. You did, Bianca.
I don't know if this is specifically going to answer your question, but this is something
that happens a lot when everybody or when you install everything into your base environment.
It gets more and more and more complicated the more things that you install. So that's
why you have a separate environment where you have just NoMoji, you know, the specific
version that you need and then everything should work. I don't know if that answers
your question, but like so you're saying that you can't have that version at all on your
computer anywhere.
So I'm going to tell you something you already know, which is this is a really hard problem.
Because when you write the recipe, you could either say, okay, I'm going to make a prediction
about the future, which I have no idea. Right. Maybe it won't. And so you're faced with,
you know, I can state this fact, which I know is true, or I can say anything greater than
or equal to what this is. Valerio, you have it. Okay. He's stretching. Yes. You've earned
it.
Yeah.
Yes.
I don't know that there's a great solution.
I have a, sorry.
You're at the mercy of the other community.
So Steve is one of the packagers at Anaconda. So listen to whatever Steve says.
It's reassuring that it's all the time.
It's just, it's a waiting game sometimes. Yeah.
I've had that issue.
So we have one minute left. Does anyone, yes, you have another intractable question. That's excellent. Okay.
Just to first say, like, Anaconda and the Konda product is really good. You know, that's an example.
I'm using it for an enterprise client. And how could I get enterprise support? You know,
I don't want to depend on the community support, like pushing on the forum. Because like, if
something is down for some reason, we need somebody. Like, if you take any other products,
like, you get an enterprise support. Is there any timeline or like anything on the roadmap
getting us that enterprise support as well?
So KP, if I understand the question, I think you should talk to the booth. Okay. So another,
no, it's not intractable at all. I think it's very tractable. But if you want enterprise
support, you're going to need to pay for it. Yeah. Okay. Yeah. So talk to the people at the booth,
which will be sort of me at some point. But okay. And we are officially out of time.
However, the rest of us are here all week for the rest of the week, you know. So find us.
Think about it. Thanks to the row, Bianca, Valerio, and thanks to you all. Okay.