So, my name is Moises Arca.
My website is coverdisi.com where you can find everything about community and also humankind.
And today I want to tell you about Spike ProjectOMO, packaging, and how you're going to fit into
that picture.
I am from a southern and northern country.
I live in Belmont in the San Francisco Bay Area Peninsula, which is the ancestral homeland
of the Ramaytush or Loni people.
I also want to say that I'm going to be smashing donations up to a total of $100 to a circle.
It's an LGBTQ plus charity in Utah.
Okay, so before we dive into Spike ProjectOMO, let's talk a little bit about the total format.
It's an interesting format.
We want to talk about what's good about it and what you need to know.
So, as far as semantics goes, you can more or less imagine that it's the JSON format,
plus supports for dates.
So, you don't have to figure out how to represent date or string or whatever.
It has a native support for date.
And also, as far as numeric types, while JSON makes flows to the integer and things,
TOMO will tell you what's the flows and what's the integer.
So, this is a good way to easily remember what is the semantics.
What kind of stuff can you represent in TOMO at all?
As far as syntax goes, it's more editable than JSON.
If anyone has ever tried to manually edit in JSON, you know that it's a lot.
Very easy to make mistakes, like fading formats and all kinds of things.
We are going to do inedible formats.
So, if you have a project, TOMO ends up being a pretty editable format, which is good,
because you're going to be editing your project TOMO.
If you can actually use some tools to update it, but often in the case you want to edit it using your editor,
it's much, much easier to parse than YAML.
So, first it's much easier to parse face-only,
because you have weird options or weird extensions that often bring YAML down.
And also, really important, it's not supported in the previous version of Python in the library.
Again, that's a reflection of it, but it's much easier to parse,
so the core developers felt more confident putting a parser built in.
So, this is good, because we'll be talking a lot about parsing in generation TOMO.
And, just an example.
So, the first thing you'll see, that's TOMO support comments.
It's really useful, again, that's one of the things that makes it more editable than JSON if you actually want to explain
why you did something in the file.
You know, this detail thing is right there, so work around for bug XSS, and you just put it there.
This is not exactly how things might look in your project tunnel.
This is just to represent TOMO in a quantity that's something that will remind you of what's in a project.
So, what logic itself is what we call a table in TOMO,
and when you parse this table, it gets a form of addition,
which means name and author are going to be queues in that dish name.
The author is a list, well, in TOMO terms it's an array.
When you parse it, it will transform into a list.
And, TOMO has a special syntax for something that's called key value pairs.
When you parse it, key value pairs will also become a dish name.
So, it means you can't really tell from what you just parsed back what was the original TOMO,
but you usually don't need to and you don't care much.
And that's the person who's writing it sometimes.
They do things a bit differently if they need a bit more room to maneuver.
So, what happens when you do parse it?
I'm using TOMLY because I want it to be compatible with Python 3.10.
3.11 has TOMOLED that's built into Python, so there's no reason to take it from TOMLY.
We have exactly the same API, but we're very compatible, so you can just
run the definitions back and forth.
And I'm doing something a bit weird, but I hope that you understand why.
I think the easiest way to display what data structure looks like in Python,
is to just dump it into your DIMP.
It's the easiest thing that you can easily display without using a wiki module,
which sometimes has to be a bit of a problem.
So, if we load the things that you just saw, that's what we get.
So, at the top level it's a dictionary, marking the table name for the table content.
At the top level the table is still in the dictionary.
The name just maps to all the tags, there's a simple value.
The author will map to a list, because remember when we said an array transforms into a list.
And in that list is one item, and that one item is a dictionary,
because the key value always refers to a dictionary.
You see that the dictionary is kind of the default thing that you get out of it.
And that's how you parse it.
This is really important because we'll talk about, like,
cases where you actually want to parse it yourself, or all kinds of reasons.
So, okay, fine, we have the sum of the tomolays, we know how to write it, we know how to parse it.
Why is PyProject only good for us?
Well, originally it was designed to configure our build system.
The system that takes our source code from a dictionary, from a directory,
and makes it really out of it.
Why do we want it in a file that's static and also something in SetupUI?
Because SetupUI already consumes SetupTools.
It can't even tell you what version of SetupTools it needs,
because by the time SetupTools reads that file, it's kind of already a bit too late.
So, again, we have a file, this will allow us to experiment with the parameters to SetupTools.
The parameters to SetupTools is expressed by extensions, right?
Again, you might want to use SetupTools right here before you start even reading the file, the logic.
So, SetupTools per views, and again, being able to specify versions for that, for example, and so on.
Now, everything seems to be the original goal here, you know, a little bit ambitious maybe,
but it's not a very specific reason, why just to configure the build system.
However, the name was just too seductive, and the format was also too seductive,
and the combination of both meant that people were like,
I can use it to configure my Python project.
That's awesome, why do I need a configuration file?
So, what is still used for that, and we're talking about that, right, we talk about packaging,
is also going to be the place to put build system and logic metadata,
like name and version that any build system would need.
It's a place to configure ecosystem tools, that I thought I'll give examples later, and so on.
So, in the build system section, one of the fields is required.
This field is similar to the dependency field anywhere else.
It says be the dependencies for running the build.
Running the process, that takes us from a directory to a wheel.
Not the dependencies, you need to install it.
It might be more, it might be less.
You don't necessarily need set up tools to install, you probably need set up tools to build.
And you probably don't need, like, your YAML parser to install,
but you probably need it when you're at Ranta.
Almost always, these little tools are led to something like else,
like Patchery or Portsy or one of your separate systems.
This can, of course, also include greater or equal to or other version parameters.
And the other thing that we have in the build system section is the build backend.
Now, assuming you've already installed everything in your dependencies,
this is a path to a module that is a build system.
Why does it need a specific contract?
Why does it need for a module to be a build system?
And this will be the path to it.
So the next thing you want to put is using the author.
That's under the project.
So you see that this is the section inside project that is authored.
And you have name and email.
If you're interested in doing this with set up tools, you'll notice that it's slightly nicer syntax.
The description is what in set up tools you would call the source description.
This is one line.
It just says it's a specific project.
And after we took the description and authored out of the project,
usually we have name, version, and you're using what's written.
There are several ways to configure your long description in a PyQuad or Thermal.
This is usually the best one.
Going to your readme file, put the long description.
Your readme file, anyway you usually should have the same content.
It will figure out from the extension whether you want markdown or rest.
And you should not use anything other than markdown or rest.
So very simple.
Clearly you want version because everything should have version and name because your wheel should have a name.
So the requirements for the build system is just that it should be prompted.
Again, using the 2D set up tool, you might want to have set up tools plugged in.
And if you're using an accounting build system, you use that instead.
And the back end is a module.
And the specific contract, as I said, what needs to be a build back end is to have the right methods.
What do we mean by having the right methods?
Well, so we're getting to that later.
So in the project section, you have to have a name and a version.
It will literally not allow you to put in something you've authored.
You can give the project section entirely, but you can't have a project section without name and version.
More on that later.
But I highly recommend that you probably want to have show description, usually inline.
Long description, you want to get from a file you use as a readme field.
And a license.
Whether you put the license in a file or inline is your choice.
In kind of recent times, I've decided I want to put it inline, because when that makes the file project
so much easier to be hardware, it means that when people look at my top level files,
there's no license file there, which is kind of useless and annoying, and it just sort of takes up
very limited real estate in your top level stuff.
You want to put the URL.
Specifically the URL that you would name home page, specifically like that, with uppercase H.
That would be the link that if you upload that realtor file API, it will interpret it as home page.
Any other links you have, API will still put, but if you put like whatever string you put,
home page can be special, so you can put in your special home page section of the link.
See, you want to have that, but you can have arbitrary links to issues, documentation, pull requests, whatever.
The tool section is just saying that anything that has tool.something is the name of a configuration section
that projects tools.
Usually for tools that are reasonably popular in the Python ecosystem.
So in this example, we're configuring black.
We don't need to write a custom file to configure in black.
We want to include all files that have .py yi.
It's really shouldn't have a dollar in spite of it, but I'm not trying to basically configure black.
I'm trying to figure out how you would configure black.
So this is not a good black configuration, but it is a black configuration.
So it's great.
I also have to include some time from site declaration files, so black and one and one, two.
I can configure coverage.
So basically, this is a famous way to configure coverage with set up.cfg, except with also the pull doc prefix.
So for example, if you want to configure your coverage to actually do branch coverage, which is not interesting for our situation,
but if you want that, then you have that, and coverage you automatically read it.
So most modern Python tooling, not all of them, are starting to read from PyPojectToma,
which is nice, again, reducing the files you have.
Another example, if you want to configure source, you can configure source to offer you to collect paths under case.
So that's nice and useful.
So project section, the things that we talked about so far, like an MA, version, and description,
don't change what the wheel does, if you already installed it.
We also have semantics that will change what the wheel actually does.
Most popularly dependency, because that will get skipped to install view dependency.
Again, this is equivalent to what you so require in set up.py.
You have a list of dependencies.
As usual, all the caveats about putting dependencies in set up.py apply.
Why not to over-team them, because this will impact every user of the library, and so on.
And again, set up.py also has a git.
We have an option for optional dependencies.
We have case dependencies or doc dependencies.
That will be installed if people install the wheel with graphics, test, or docs, respectively.
So it's useful, right?
You know how to build a wheel from that.
Call from scripts.
Again, if that's what your wheel does, that means that when your wheel will be installed,
a binary of also commands will be generated, and it will call my package.name.
That's how you specify it under the code in the script.
For the people who have used the set up tool for longer, you might remember that script used to be a subsection of the entry point.
But we do an entry point for general things.
So, let's say that you have used the page.appfactory.
The entry point is how you do it.
This is kind of an interesting, syntactical thing.
As you notice, I put a string over there in page.appfactory, and that means that page.appfactory will be the name of the entry point.
This is important because the name of the class of the entry point is something that is part of the code practice we use.
So, you need to have a specific name of the entry point, and if it includes docs or anything else that someone would interpret, you need to protect it.
So, let's go back to how you use set up tools specifically as a build system.
Obviously, every single build system is different, but a default system that you probably have been using until now is set up tools.
So, if you're migrating to set up your eyes, this is how you do apple to apple.
So, the required is the usual dependency rules.
You can include minimal, and no key quality version and specific version have a bug.
And the build system, specific context in 5.17.
And I said methods earlier, and it's kind of like, I think completely right because of other optional methods.
But they're not interesting.
But you can assume it's a kind of lie.
And the only really interesting method is build wheel.
So, didn't want to go too far in.
Set up tools back end, this has a function called build wheel.
This build wheel will get from the builder, the builder front end, right?
Because it's a builder back end, as you can imagine.
Therefore, there has to be a builder front end.
We'll talk a little bit about the front end in a second.
It will get from the builder front end the build directory, and it can change settings that you got,
and which directory to put the metadata in, and it will do the same.
So, let's talk about packaging in Python.
This is an example of some Python that has been packaged.
Almost always, you use Python-bytes and builds.
If you've written your Python project formal carefully enough,
but without any specific settings, like the names, the versions, the dependencies,
then it will get worked.
You want Python-bytes and builds, you wait a few seconds because it does stuff,
but this will get front end, and when it's done doing stuff, you will have a wheel.
Here's a great.
What happens when it doesn't work?
Most of it doesn't work.
It means that it will work better if you use what you call the FSC structure.
You can see that the new partners and arguably the best practices,
which is to put all your Python code on the sub-directory of your top level under FSC.
That makes it much clearer which parts need to be packaged as Python code.
Like, you know, the solution is from the test, the solution is from the docs,
if you have other directories, that's fine.
So, if it doesn't just work, probably consider not already configuring your Python project formal,
but just using the FSC structure.
Sometimes, either this doesn't help or you can't do that.
So, the option you have is data in application with an exclamation mark.
So, I hope that it's clear, that it's clear what I'm recommending right now.
If the FSC structure doesn't work in Python management,
then it doesn't work in a better solution.
It's not formally supported, it's been reasonably stable,
and I've been doing this in my old stuff,
I feel reasonably comfortable recommending music.
Basically, this is how we configure every other thing in our build environment.
We have tools.something.configuration.
Setup tools will be configured via tools.setup.
So, you put the...
And you can do it in the documentation for setup tools to see what something needs to be for you to configure it.
But this gives you the ability to specify data files and stuff like that,
in a way that's possible to consume.
Those are set up tools for specific fields.
Everything I've said so far was built in some of the most advanced tools.
And people install.
This has been changed as a version of when I was a prox.
Back then, I could have pretty much done my own E work,
which your package is only using PyProject.
You use an empty setup.cfg.
That was 3,000 years ago.
So, we don't need it anymore.
Now, you can support an editable install,
which is like you're riding your hand.
It will change if you change the code.
So, without setup.cfg, it gets work, again, most of the time.
I lied earlier.
I said you have to have versions.
It's only a small lie because if you just don't have versions,
it will fail.
It will kind of get at you very loudly.
However, if you want another, say, a setup tool for games,
or maybe a different build system,
to set up your version,
what you have is you specify, because,
essentially, the version is dynamic.
That means I'm not going to specify a version,
and that's okay.
I know I have not specified a version.
Some other tools will fit it in.
If the different tool does not come into your page,
it will be 0.0.0.
But, again, you can make sure that some tools,
again, setup tools, SEM is the most popular setup tool,
particularly on games I hope are pretty nice.
So, that's how you use setup tool SEM.
You add it to the requirements,
you change version dynamics,
and if you need setup tool SEM to figure it out,
how to target, and if you target,
you might want to add some, again,
you can configure setup tool SEM specifically in your,
you know, file project,
so that's setup tool SEM documentation.
So, let's kind of recap what I've been talking about.
File project normal.
Main use and best use is for packaging.
And you should use that,
and just stop using setup tool.ui
and setup tool.ui and setup tool.csd.
There is no benefit to using them.
Again, more after this, technically,
the setup, if you actually use a lot of setup configuration,
setup tool.csd is not better.
And using it in the setup, in your file project,
so make it beta.
I feel this is a reasonable tradeoff to make.
Anyway, usually you don't want too much configuration,
so that's fine.
Again, in many, many projects,
I've not been looking for a lot of configuration,
especially if you use this source structure.
But open your book for everything else.
Right, again, everything in the book is big,
because there are still tools that are not suitable
for your file project.
But you see that almost all tools are like this.
If you haven't done it already,
you have a plan to kind of support it.
So, this is great.
And if you write your own tool, right,
let's say you want your own version plugin
that does something,
and you need to configure it a bit,
don't bother adding a new file for your thing, right?
Anyway, I really, if you write your own thing,
then it doesn't need too much configuration,
as you put some sources on the default.
So maybe it is a line of two configuration.
You don't want to make people write a new file
for a new line of two.
So just support another tool,
a new tool, a new tool,
by project owner.
You don't need to keep people,
like, a new file, like, where it should be placed.
And you see that, right, just put it there,
and everybody has reasonable expectations.
So, project field, right, like, name,
has to be their version,
has to be their asset.
The system, license, read me.
So, if you don't have them,
your package will basically look bad
if you don't have them.
You know, like, it makes sense, right?
When you upload it to PyPI,
it will just look weird,
right, that the page in PyPI will look weird.
Depends even on some depends,
again, if you have them,
which most packages do,
that's where you put it in.
Scripts, again, you still need them,
depending on what you're well done.
So, that's the point.
For set up tools,
default will carry you 90% of the way.
The other kind of 5% of the way
is using the proceed structure,
and that's basically what people
would call convention over configuration,
and where you must configure as lightly as you can.
And this boosts you against using Python management build,
and what I mean by that is that
if you set your CI tools or whatever,
like, you know, kind of slowly using two Python management builds,
you don't have to worry, right?
If later you want to move to, like,
Hatchery or Corpore tree or any of those systems
to build your stuff,
nobody else has to know about it, right?
You'll just change your PyProject.com mode,
and Python management build will still work.
Python management build can take any of this, right?
So, this is important to know.
So, a few last week announcements.
I have an open space that you're supposed to be
right after this talk.
It's called author PyProject.com mode.
Right now, in after the talk, in 2.58.
I will be giving away some books, if you come.
And that's pretty much it.
So, I do have almost five minutes
for a bit of Q&A, and I'm very happy.
Please remember to cheat your questions
in the formal questions,
ideally with the question mark again.
Thank you, Moshe.
If you have a question, please come to my microphone
so everyone can hear.
All right, so my question to you is,
are there limitations that you've identified
in the current use, the current community use
of Python for Python and along with the other ones?
What are you looking forward to
in the development of this space?
I guess one of the biggest things I would say
is that you're going to be able to
build your own Python management build,
in the current use of this space.
I guess the biggest thing that I would say
is missing from PyProject.com right now
is that the set of tools support is still in beta,
which makes it slightly harder for me to just
endorse whole hardware, just throw away all your old stuff
and make it new in PyProject.
I think it will stabilize pretty soon,
but this is what I'm going to track you into today
and how it's going.
So you can implement tool configurations,
so it's LAP and LAP and other tools inside of it
in PyProject.com, but you're also able to have
your own Python files for configuration.
I'm curious if you consider it best practice
to put everything inside of your class project
or break out into individual configuration files.
Yeah, that's a good question.
So here is kind of like my intake,
which is kind of a bit bigger than whether it should be
a separate Tomo file or not.
In general, when you build a tool like that,
if the tool doesn't work without any configuration,
then you usually want to think a little bit about
how does your tool work with your configuration, right?
Like, again, single tools that you use in your own life,
like Vegas, Python, right?
Some of them work very well, some of them really badly.
I would say if you're working on building a tool,
you want to think carefully about making it work well
with like zero configuration.
The reason I kind of went on this weird tangent
before answering the question is because this means
that the typical use, you know, if people do it
to configure it, it should be very light configuration.
And because of that, I usually recommend support PyProject
Tomo only because then otherwise,
you'll get like one file with like one line in it.
And again, you also should have some sort of
limited view of your own importance, right?
What if everybody does that?
Then like, you know, if every tool will have its own file,
then eventually we have tons of files
that will develop the actually, it's going to get annoying.
So with the combination of why to not ask for an auto configuration
and try to assume that people will be using an auto tooling,
I would recommend default to putting it in PyProject Tomo.
Of course, you can always fall back to like, you know,
oh, if there is a tool named after,
if there is a file named after my tool, I'll do that.
Again, if you feel you really need to do that,
think about why people need to configure a tool that much.
Hopefully that answers the question.
All right.
Let's continue the conversation in Q50A.
Thank you, Mase.
Thank you.