Hi everyone, good afternoon. For this session, our speaker will talk about Pysch group and
the magic of Python and the browser. Let us all welcome Fabio Plyer.
Thank you so much and thank you for coming after lunch, which is always very hard. So
I really appreciate it. Because of that, I tried to put my, you know, the rising pace
headshot in the speaker. So this was clearly a mistake. I usually use the hipster one,
which is better. So a little bit about me. I'm software architect at Anaconda, creator
of Python scripts and been in the Python community for many, many years. I'm a Python
dev and Python fellow, mainly for the work with organizing EuroPython. I was chairman
of EuroPython Society for five years and organized, I think, EuroPython across Europe. I also
co-founded a Python EOE and the Python EOE conference as well.
So I want to first, actually, let's comment about this slide first. This is very experimental,
very alpha. But I was a little disappointed about my colleagues not demoing most of their
demos with Python scripts or creating their slides with Python scripts. So I took it to
the next level. This is definitely a whole slideshow. Is it a test to the demo guys?
So things really mind break, keep that in mind. In fact, this whole presentation is
written by scripts only. There's almost no JavaScript besides the highlighter.
So it isn't pretty much about me working on this talk, trying to make things work in a
way that I thought about putting my irony here, but a lot of the young generation wouldn't
understand. But it's pretty much holding together with the data.
Before I start, I really want to thank the amazing people behind Python scripts. It's
been an amazing year. A lot of this is the work from the community, trying to build a
healthy and sustainable community where we can welcome different types of people, not
all developers. We want to learn a lot about education, about students, about people. We
want to welcome people that have talent in writing documentation or socializing a project
and things like this. So please, if you think Python script is cool or you like the NEL
or you think it's promising or interesting and kind of involved in this project, we are
always looking for you to make the NELs and you hope to collaborate with.
So a little bit about the agenda. I'm going to start with a little refresher about what
happened last year. I'll talk about the Python script today, the state of it. I will finally
be able to show the vision, the real vision that we had to try to run Python scripts.
Last year, I downloaded the first version, doing Python last year, and while it was very
innovative and got a lot of attention, I think it wasn't enough to capture the full vision.
I think this is going to hint a little more. Also, I really wanted to have an interactive
demo because how can you do a good talk about Python scripts after the amazing keynote last
year or the amazing talks that we had this year? So I thought it would be great.
The other bad aspect is also that while I was writing the slides that I was doing demos,
the team kept creating new things and kept making advancements, so I had to change the
slides and include new demos until 30 minutes ago. So keep that in mind.
So what is PyScript? I'll be very fast on this one. You can check on the slides. I actually
will be running a little at the beginning because I think most of those things are available
online. So PyScript is really a framework, a platform that enables Python on the browser.
So you might ask, how does it compare to other frameworks that enable Python on the browser
via the Idle, micro Python, et cetera? It's actually a platform on top of these and allowing
trying to create easy and blog-able interfaces for us to extend the things that you can do
with Python. And just a little bit more about it.
So why PyScript? Why not PyScript? Right? But there are actually very good reasons why
we should be working on PyScript. So first of all, Python is the most popular language
in the world. And it's super weird, honestly, that it doesn't really have a great story
for Python on the most popular hardware in the world, which is mobiles and tablets. I
think it's extremely hard to have Python built. It also doesn't have a good story for running
the first software operating system in the world, which is your browser. So it's really
weird that Python is the most popular language, and we want to fix this. Also, there were
many thoughts about this in the past around as a community, we are enjoying the success
of Python, but we need to look ahead where our society is going in data science and everything
and look forward. I think it's crucial for us to invest in web technology, technology
that can be used in new generations to use Python in a funny and nice way.
So also, distributing Python applications is hard, not only on those two platforms,
but everywhere. Since I started Python, we created a bunch of tools where I have my application,
I just want to ship something to someone else's computer, and it's been incredibly hard.
We have Python 2.xc or Python installer and other things trying to bundle Python applications,
but no real good solution for that. Also, if you ask students and professors, people
in education, I think they all will tell you that it's extremely hard to install Python
and get that machine with Python running in very short time. So it's a considerable learning
curve. So real quick, how many here don't know what
PyScript is? Awesome. So if you haven't heard of PyScript, it was super popular last year
to do Python. And this is a mean that Jess Haverman, our first person running on the
Chrome education, she made it after the crowd at the booth today. Everybody's excited about
PyScript, and I think because people see the excitement.
It was actually the highlight of my career year last year when my daughter came to me
before dinner, and said, Dad, I finally know what you do. I saw a post on TikTok about
PyScript, and you're trending and everything, so I can retire now, and I'm happy.
So this is the star's history of PyScript since last year. As you can see, a very, very
popular, a huge interest from the community, which is amazing. We want to keep that growing,
and we want to make sure that we carry the community with us as we talk more about that
in the big. So this is a piece of the docs, a part of the docs on getting started with
PyScript. You can see how to set up your development environment or how to install PyScript,
which you don't need to install anything, really. You just need to link your PyScript
JS file in your HTML. You don't really even need to do this one, the CSS, but it's better.
And then you can just use PyScript tags to insert Python in your browser.
There are better ways than this. In fact, we'll talk about it later in the documentation.
You can use the Python state to configure your packages and your dependencies and things like
this, basically creating your environment, and then you're ready to go.
So, by the way, if you didn't notice, this is an iframe inside the presentation itself, and you'll
see a lot of things like this. It'll make it fun.
Well, if you look at it after a year, it's not that impressive, I agree. You know, it might feel
like we didn't make a lot of progress in that sense. Well, surprise, we have a lot of progress.
We made a lot of progress in the platform itself and surrounding tools, and that's what I want to
show you today. So, let me talk about stability first. As soon as we started, we released. I said
something like, well, I expect that you'll be breaking your code every release and very often for
some time. It's not quite true. Calm down. That is true for any piece of software, by the way.
If you're developing something, your code might break very easily in Python if you're not managing
your dependencies correctly. So, I want to correct that statement a little. PyScript is way more
stable today. Way, way more stable. It has a, well, I'll talk more about it in a bit. But also, just some
advice, have the best practice as a software developer. Always pin your versions if you don't want
your code to break in your versions, because if you don't, they will change on the end of the day,
and your code might break. Pin your dependencies. Same thing. Right, in the first
version, I mean, give you PyScript versions. Second, pin your dependencies versions, and then
write tests. That's the only way you can make sure that your code is as safe as possible.
Now, I'll go through these real quick, and then I'll show you some things about them. So, PyScript
now has versions. When we released, it didn't have any version. And we chose to, a specific version
pattern, because I think it captures the nature of the project. We killed PyM, which is a Python
object, it's a PyM. We killed PyM and made PyCon think, which is more expressive and supports way
more things. We improved Python handlers, event handlers, we improved escaping and I.O. We made
the lifecycle way more predictable. We improved logging, warnings, errors. We introduced a new
global level function called display. And I'll talk about this in a bit. We improved the Python API,
which is unique, need a lot of work, but it's way improved compared to what we launched. We redesigned
the concept of interpreter so that we can enable other interpreters and I'll talk about that as
well. We have a new nice plugin interface, better documentation, better tiles, blah, blah, blah,
blah. So, we'll see a little bit more. So, this is the PyScript application running inside another
PyScript application to demo some of those features. So, as I said, PyScript now has a version.
And then also we replaced Python with PyConfig, as you can see. This is, for instance, installing
those packages and basically fetching this file and this file. PyEvents way improved. They're a little
more familiar. We're going to change that in the next release as well to make it safer. But I don't
know how long it will take. I spent too much time on that. I've stayed in the idea of data. I want to spend some time
on the display because I think it's important. So, Python on the browser brings a lot of new things to
think about. The browser is not your traditional operating system. So, things like print. Well, what do you
want to do with print? Do you want to print a debug statement or printing is actually a display or
a notification on the browser? So, because that is very confusing, we decided to make it very explicit. So, anytime you want to
display something in the browser, you can just display. And it will display right under where you are running
display. Now, my colleague Antonio will be like, it's horrible because you cannot really predict where you are in the
browser. So, we decided to make it that way. We also made a few changes where you can decide if you want to append to your
debug or you want to replace the contents of the debug. This is a clear disk. And whenever you want to make sure that you are
printing where you are supposed to, you can have a target. So, I can say this target is a debug right here.
If I display here, I'm going to display right on the top. And this is how print behaves. It will print on the terminal,
which is a plugin. So, as I mentioned, we also have better warnings, better errors. Now, there's an error by default.
It will show a red window on the page. So, we make it explicit, blah, blah, blah, blah. But let me go ahead and talk a little bit
about plugins. So, we like to make sure that, to centralize that Pusk it is a platform more than a framework. The
difference here for us, as we're using the difference in the terms that we're using is that a framework enables users to create
applications, a platform enables users to create frameworks and applications. So, we want to make sure that we allow users to
create things on top of Prescript because we will never guess correctly what each one of you want to do. So, we want to make sure
that we have a healthy plugin system that you can hook into and create new things. Just to show real quick a plugin, I will open
Trap real quick on the examples page on Prescript. And as you can see, there's this little thing here with Vue Code. That is the plugin.
It's the PyTutor tag. And that if you place in your code, it will basically inspect the code for you and show what is the code behind
this application. Both the configuration and the coding page. If you have files and things like this, it will show the files, the Python files
of Square and issue the link of Java. Also, you don't know, but right in this page, there's another plugin that is the PyMarkdown plugin.
And in fact, I'm going to write the slides in HTML, but not all of them. This is Markdown and it's being translated in real time to HTML to render the slides.
Also, a lot of work on performance. So, Prescript is not alone. Actually, we really want to promote the idea that Prescript is just an accelerator for the Python
meaning to plan on whether. And it's also a point of, it's like the market square of different projects where we can make them collaborate.
We can work together to make things better. So, in that sense, PyLite is the interpreter, the default interpreter for Prescript.
It's the most impressive today, but it was the one year ago. PyScript is faster as well. It's also smaller. Also, we have a lot of exciting news on the development
around performance that I will be demoing a bit. So, let's keep those. Also, we are working on support for Microsoft Python, which makes loading times faster on the page.
And we are also working on Web Workers allowing blocking calls for free. Who did here thanks AsyncAdobe's breaks.
Okay, not the most. How many of you think AsyncAdobe is easy? None.
And it's important to note that the browser by itself is Async. It expects things to be Async for very good reasons. We don't want to freeze the browser.
Python expects the default Python is synchronous. You expect things to just run in a sequential way. Otherwise, it is async and good luck.
But we want to make sure that PyScript is as easy as it can be. So, with Web Workers, we want to try and make it easy for people to write AsyncApollic instances for free.
It also will allow us to support debugger and other debugger patterns that are really useful. Also, this work also relates to another generic app I find that we want to develop.
So, that's right now you can use. So, FFI stands for Foreign Function Interface. It's what allows us to use JavaScript libraries inside PyScript.
We want to try and make a generic one or a higher level one that can be used for PyDog or for MicroPython or C-Python and so on.
And so, the whole ecosystem can benefit because, well, we are better together. And this is actually a gift of the team.
This is Antonio and myself in the middle. After we argue, because we argue all the time, and Nicholas trying to hug us as well.
But, look, I want to be serious on this because it's really important. PyScript, the whole idea is that we are seeing on the work, amazing work of others, and we want to make sure that we are supporting their work and we are enabling others to join this community and make things better.
So, we are effectively supporting Python and Wezm. We just had the Wezm Summit here at Python on Thursday. And it was an incredible chat with core developers, the different projects, and I think we all want to go in the same direction, which is very exciting.
We are currently supporting PyDyde by both funding and with many initiatives as well. We're supporting MicroPython as well. And we are thankful for Hood and all the core creators, core maintainers of PyDyde and being here for MicroPython.
And we joined the bike for the likes as well to try and make a difference, better in support of Wezm. We are actively trying to push the conversation about Python packaging on Wezm because, hey, we're having an opportunity to do it right this time.
We're ahead of time. So let's do it. And also, as I mentioned, it's going to make a boring function into the face. Now, enough of this. Let's talk about the future. And finally, it's exciting that I can show the vision.
Let's hope it works. So first thing I want to show is PySquip.com, which is not an open source project. It is a free platform that we created. And I kind of created two support PySquip and to allow users to just connect to a web page from their computer, from their phone, from their tablet, and start developing PySquip apps right away.
So you can visit PySquip.com and hopefully connect to Wi-Fi. The COFAS Wi-Fi is going to work. So this is my dashboard where all these apps that I created, I can go there and just create a new project. It will start a new project for me, create the files that I need to start my project.
So I can take my name, I can call it Client, save it, and then I can say Hello, Michael. And if I save and run, this is going to run in the browser right away. And if I want to share with you the application, all I need to do is open a new tab or actually go to the end of the page.
This is a URL that I can share. And I also have the option to go and share. Copy the link, share on Twitter, and things like that.
If you noticed on the deployed app, there's a small section on the bottom right where I can actually use the code. And if I share with someone else, they can use the code as well. They can clone the project and start hiding away using the code that I started and created.
Cool. Now, I want to talk about another project called HyperCard. Who here ever heard of HyperCard? Cool. I thought it would be even less. So I would say 5%. So HyperCard is based on another project that was called HyperCard that rotates around the concept of cards and a stack of cards.
This card represents a state and is a card on your screen and allows you to go from one state to another and define variables in that state. And as you change variables, you can change states and what not.
So this is the link to the project to people.
People.
You can see it's public. If you go check it out, I know this person is here.
How's that? It's alpha. It's super alpha.
Exactly. So it's in alpha. But you should go try it, break it, give us feedback, and we want to learn about how you want to use it. I'm using it to run this presentation.
This presentation was actually done with HyperCard and I've learned some other tools that I've never used before.
So it's a quick and easy to use Python to create software with modern interface. It's deliberately constrained, naturally powerful. Actually, I should change my voice.
Deliberately constrained, naturally powerful.
So it's easy to learn and that's really important. I really care about the 99% SPP critical put last year.
I think that part of the reason that I'm showing is this is the right path in that direction. So one of them is hypercard, so it won't make it very easy.
And it's also super easy to deploy in Chef. So let me demo it. This is the GitHub page of the project inside this presentation.
And actually one of the cool things is that I can run the test suite from here. So we can go there, run the test suite, and see if anyone drops a code.
There you go. My test in the browser.
Now, I want to show some applications as well. Temperature is a cool one.
It has the concept of three cards. One card to input your temperature, another one to show the results, and another one to handle errors.
So for instance, if I have a 35 Celsius or what translates to Fahrenheit. There you go. If I go back here, it goes back to my input card.
But if I click Celsius, I get my error card. Now, let's see how this code works, the code behind this.
Isn't it cool that you can just open the resource in this Chef resource site? I love it.
So this is the template for the cards. First card is the input card. Second card is the result card. And the third card is the error card.
This is the...
So this is the whole code for the whole application. There's no code that regards a state. There's no code that regards an interface.
Everything is... But the whole interface is injected from the image.
And all I need to do here is just define my app, say I have those three cards, and I want to handle transitions between one card with the others with those functions.
It's a nice transition decorator that tells me I want to go from this input card... I'm sorry. Every time the user clicks on this button to see in the card input card, execute this card.
And those transitions, functions, all they need to do is just return to the next state. So for me, the next state, if there's no error, is the result card. Otherwise, the error card.
Same thing goes for the other, uh, translated function. Same thing goes for when I go back to a card or I reset the cards.
Alright. So this basically is telling me, hey, the application starts from here. But that's not all.
And we go back here. Actually, I will go back and open a view. So hopefully you see the overalls for here. The audio.
This is a different type of application where it uses an audio file to transition between cards. So it's a different type of application. It doesn't require a lot of these things. It's just a showcase of things and stuff.
But the cool thing about it is that we are using a sound and we are using a timer to progress between the card.
I'm not going to show the code because it's basically the same. But, I'll show it back there. If we go to that, if we, I write it to the end without breaking anything, I'll just show something else.
Alright. Ready for more? This is just the beginning. This is a platform that will enable new applications. But, well, how do you create those interfaces?
Welcome to VisualPyScript. Basically, it is in 3D alpha, so we didn't open the window yet. But it's a framework that allows you to visually create your applications with PyScript.
So in this case, actually, this slideshow was created with VisualPyScript. I didn't write much of the HTML under this presentation. I used VisualPyScript.
The first type of app that we want to support is HyperCard apps. And as I mentioned, the concept of cards. So let's read a presentation right now inside my presentation.
So, I have the concept of a layout. When I create a new card, I can say I want just one element on this page to be my title. So we can do text and say, my meta, my company card.
And this is large. I can also define other things, but this will do for now. I can go here and add a new card. This card is going to be a little more complicated. I want to know more about you all.
So you want to do a card with a header. And you will have three elements. One header, one input, and one button. I really want to spend 30 seconds on this one, which is an experiment that we're doing to see how can we create interfaces in a very fast way.
It's very hard to create, to adjust your web pages with CSS and things like this. So we try to simplify the problem as much as possible. And trying to see your interface as a grid seems like a good option.
But we would love to hear more feedback on those things. Actually, let me ask you another thing. Tell me to tell you another thing. In Dookinfield, it's on purpose. It's not because it's free of work. The 80s are back. So stranger things and all of that. So it's pretty much like the 19s web interface.
So I'm joking. I'm going to make it better. So header here. Hi. Let's see your name. And you're going to be there. And then here, I want to put an input. We just add you here. And you're going to call it this little hole.
And then we're going to add the value domain username. And then we can, well, that's the last thing there. That's perfect. Text is perfect. And I'm going to add a button here. That is user. I didn't know what the button is, but I think it's a button for user. Oops.
You would never know if it was on purpose or not. OK, actions. And I want to, as you can see on the bottom, I have the preview of the card. It's looking somehow OK. I want to add a new card. And then this card, I want to say, hi. Excuse me.
And the concept here is that we can template the variables that we have in the Card app and use those to inject variables. Now, it's not going to work fully because this is just the interface and we don't have five or five connected to it.
But if I come here back and I put that the next state for this button is card three, and I go to here and say, actually, it's an email. I think it's a Python. And I click on add user if I go to the state that I expect.
So we're trying to make things reactive and observable in a way that's why we develop things you can track your application when the main states are built to that. It also has, I'm not going to spend too much time, but we're also supporting the sound, what's the next card, and how can we progress to the next card with a time-based workflow.
Now, you can also save.
And it has HTML or JSON. And as JSON, it will basically hold the state of this app. So if you want to save your work here and then go back later, you can just load it JSON. Now, because of time, I should be re-run. And I will show you a new thing that we have in Python.com, which is the Python.com Assistant.
And, it's not your physical one. So your physical one, which one do you think is your physical one? Actually, which one would you like to be your physical one? Right or left? Left. I hear left. Oh my gosh. I'm telling you.
Okay. Last one or this new one.
So, Gratitz and Zonzo who made the, the, the, the, I already knew it. It was going to be the latest.
Oops.
Let me go back to the,
the, the, sorry. If I close the, I'm going to go back here and I want to show you the Assistant.
All right. Click on new project.
And, it's unloaded.
By the meantime, I can connect to the Py script on our.com Assistant and ask, for instance, what is Py script?
And I have an answer. Sorry. I don't know what's the difference between, for instance, Py script and Jupyter notebooks.
Cool. So I can ask, for instance, who are the Py script main games that are not affiliated with Amazon?
Cool. That's a little creepy, but that's cool. But more important, I can ask, how do I use Py, comma, say,
Py script?
How do I use Py, comma, say, to add appendices to my position?
There you go. In this case, it's wrong, actually. So.
I'll put that down. It's super new and we are training and we are learning with it. So, yeah, we need to be patient.
But it's pretty good in a lot of things. So, for instance, how do I write me people that actually understand?
Add an integer parameter, too? I'm not sure. It's a return to function. We can copy it, reuse it.
The whole idea here is that we want to help users create things faster and use it to their advantage.
But I already have running really behind. So, go ahead and show more.
So, we also added, we're working with the MicroPython folks to have a blazing fast MicroPython support.
In effect, we have a demo of a MicroPython app running on a Piper card. Sorry, Piper card running on a MicroPython app.
And it uses the app and as you see, it loads basically, spontaneously. I'm actually reloading the page.
But more important is that if I open my phone and I click on the app and I reload it, it loads it spontaneously.
And I can actually, in a matter of seconds. And this is the type of thing that we want to help everyone achieve with their password applications.
Cool. As I mentioned, we are working on Web Workers and I have higher level FFI.
What this will allow is to do all those things in a very fast way and allow R2D1 on a Web Worker and not on a MiniTrend.
But I want to close with the last demo, which is I want to really thank Chris, a friend of the team who reached out and said,
Oh, we love what you guys are doing. We're actually using PyScript in education and helping our students to run, to run, to use PyScript to control their number of robots.
So that's what I want to show. And I have a robot here, which is, I don't know if you can see, but I will show you how to do it.
So I'll explain this one first. I don't know if you can see, but this is an egg. This is the wheel.
This is the
Is that the phone? No.
Piping packaging, eggs on wheels. Anyway, it also has a egg roll, so I can control it manually.
But if it attacks to the computer and I load control it with PyScript and it doesn't attack the demo, it's already attached to the, I will destroy it first.
So this is the first. This is the drawer of the phone.
So that's all you see. Open a serial port. I don't know if you can see the text list.
Connect. Connect to the page.
Nice.
Cool. Should be connected.
So that's the port. Right here. It opens the number half.
Or, to help everybody see, I'll add the camera here.
And I'll just do this way. I'll go back and in fact, if I run more, you can see it's going from PyScript.
So I can stop them in order. One cool thing that Chris did is actually he connected PyScript to his, I don't know, an API of his solar system.
And I can actually help get the data from his solar panels and I can spin the data.
You see it spins with the same acceleration of the panels.
There you go.
So let me go and take the edge bar out.
Sorry because it's extra cool. Actually just one.
I think I need to reload the page but I don't know. So, this is five.
Yeah, it's cool. So this one has a cool story actually. It was great.
Same little robot that was used at the White House. I think for the Easter events where the kids could color their heads.
If I click here again, I'm next.
And I'm going to do this fast because I'm running out of time.
If I do one, it's very fast looking head.
I'll just stop the camera.
There you go. That's it. That's how easy it is without installing anything on the computer.
All right, so let's stop this thing.
Let's put it here.
And let's go ahead and close.
First, reminding you, if you wanted to check all the PyScript sessions, sorry, I'm sorry.
I'm going to show you a little bit of the code.
And I'm going to close with first reminding you, if you wanted to check all the PyScript sessions, sorry, this is the last one.
The other one, which were way better, you missed them.
Go check the videos online.
But you still have an opportunity to engage with us to help us grow the project and our own things.
So you can go to PyScript Open Space tomorrow at 11.
And then there's a title that at the end basically we're going to be here for the students.
So just come hack with us.
And with this, I really want to thank you all for coming and for the interest in the project.
And I also want to thank Anaconda for supporting the project.
We are investing a lot of money on the teams and all the technology because we believe it's going to help everyone democratize our community and to assign us.
So we really want to thank the Corman Daners, Piadai, MicroPython, the CPython folks, and last but not least, special thanks to Brett.
Also the Red Assembly community, the UF folks have been amazing to talk with.
Well, Tim for inventing the Internet and many more.
And that's it. Thank you so much.
Thank you.
And with that, please back to the support line.