Good morning again, everyone.
So now we have Neeraj Pandey with us.
So he's going to deliver a talk on
Python meets UX
and enhancing user experience with code.
What do you think?
Thank you so much. Good morning, guys.
So this talk is about the intersection of
AI and the user experience.
So we're going to be discovering how we can use
Python, which is like a very powerful tool in the AI landscape,
and use it to enhance a user experience.
So throughout the presentation, we will be discussing
the importance of user experience in the digital landscape
of any product, be it any online space
or the offsite or offline space.
So later on, we'll see how Python can be
incorporated on those aspects,
including data mining and automation
to personalization for any product.
So to begin with, we see
the importance of UX, because UX
is very crucial to understand any user
needs and to satisfy the end user goals.
So it not only helps in making the product
more personalized, but also increases the
revenue for the organization, for the companies,
and also helps them retain the users.
So to begin with, we need to understand
the process, a typical process that a UX designer
works with in its everyday life.
So we start with our discover process, where
all the information is being gathered from different
multiple sources, be it a data engineering task or something.
And then once we have a lot of data with us,
we can define the problems for any businesses.
So we have a concrete example now that
we need this kind of problem to solve, we need to find a solution
for this issue now. So then we go to the
ideation phase, which is a more experimental
phase where the UX designer is continuously
brainstorming over different kinds of iterations for the product.
And then it creates some sort of designs,
be it a digital product or some sort of
prototype with its own normal product.
And then they test it with the real users
or the test users and reiterate accordingly.
So if we go deeper in the AI and UX space,
we'll see there is a common train between
the AI and UX, both goes with
gathering the information and then finding their insights.
And if you see more than 70% of the
devices we use has some sort of AI services being built in.
And when you see
if a typical UX person is going to do all these
in-depth processes for the product,
for gathering information and finding insights,
all these AI models can just do those things
in like a fraction of minutes and so.
So with this intersection, we can make more user-friendly products
and help them make personalized for every specific user.
So to begin with or to understand
this intersection, we will be starting with
data processing. And we see like data is
code, we always hear this term, that data is code. Similarly for the UX
processes, data is very crucial because it
helps identify the insights about a specific
user and how they are behaving to the product
and their feedbacks. And then we can use those feedbacks
to create new metrics and make
decisions which are not just based on presumptions, they are like data-driven
decisions. And the second thing we see
is like traditionally when you see UX designers need to like spend
hours to analyze some processes and
gain insights. So Python can be utilized to analyze these
kind of data from multiple resources, be it in
forms or historical data like e-commerce,
purchase history or buying
studio. And then we can find insights
which are more useful for the users.
And the third thing is the patterns,
the UX patterns, like every single user
or every single pool of users have a similar pattern.
So we can use those similar user behaviors
to filter out those patterns
and then make decisions without arguing data-driven.
And a good example would be clickstream data, which helps us finding
the navigation patterns of a user.
This can be used to get the knowledge of
how the user is behaving to your product
and then we can make some decisions on like how
and where the bottlenecks are and how we can like sufficiently
efficiently fix those issues.
So, and yes, so we can also like,
you know, whenever there is a UX designer involved,
it's not just one UX designer, there are a couple of people
involved in a UX experience process and those processes
get way too tedious, especially when
the end has to be done by an engineer
and all the workload has been like thrown up to the engineer
and those lead to very increased latency and all.
So these kind of specific tasks like collection of data,
creating user personas, pain points, can be directly utilized
and created by Python and the AI models.
And in conclusion, we can say like
AI can help you ease your work and then make
products which are more user friendly.
The second thing before we go directly to examples,
like real life examples, we can say like if we look at the user's behavior,
no one wants to go with a genetic kind of experience,
they are all looking for something that is more personalized to them.
And things like
AI can offer these personalized
experiences to the designers and make
their work more accessible and efficient, which can be
used to create like an art personalized experience
using lots of auto data. So a good example would be like
normal user streaming apps, you can use normally every single day
and based on your listening performance
the user, the system just like gives you
the recommendations on what to listen for that.
You don't lose customers and you are just the team of people
who are just like listening to some specific kind of music.
The second thing is behavioral data analysis.
So AI can help you identify these patterns in user's behavior
and make predictions about it.
So for instance, we will be using this use case
in the slides, the presentation.
So on the customer's website, we can use those purchasing
purchase history and their buying history
to create some sort of
recommendations on how we can associate items together,
like alt text sets, and make the best use of the data we have.
So that we, as an organization, I can improve
and increase my users
and everything.
The third thing is like, again, the predictive analytics.
We can say like the quick stream data, which we already discussed
in the A-B test, could be a great help here to find
the predictions about a specific user set.
And the last thing is the real-time data targeting, which is like
we can based on locations and diversity,
we can make some necessary immediate changes for the users
and which again enhances the user experience.
So to conclude, this extension does not only
enhance the user experience, but also provide personalized
content to the UX designers
so that they can make those predictions
for the users and streamline the process.
And the last thing we want to discuss before
going to the example is like the automating tasks.
Traditionally, UX designers are known to use
these kind of manual tasks to
complete their processes.
And this is first of all, very time consuming.
It's very tool-as-efficient and also leads to like
engineering delays.
And with the automated AI to this
systems, we can at least not fully automate
and at least we can do semi-automate these kind of processes,
which again enhances the accuracy.
And processes like A-B testing,
wide framing can be completely changed
when your unit has a data driven decision to make.
And we also have to save our costs
and engineering failures so we can also find
early design failures into the process so that like
the country is not losing money while not losing
while returning the users.
So let's put this learning into an actual case study.
So we have something like a problem set, which is like
enhancing user experience for a hybrid e-commerce platform.
And here we assume a few challenges like
we need to make this platform more personalized for the user
and we need to understand the user behavior.
And we also take into account that we don't want to just like, you know,
make the UX better for the online visual space.
We can also take care of the offline store experience.
So let's say we have, we just opened up
a store called Pashions for all the Pashions staff there.
So we try to solve these issues. We already just
assumed using a data driven strategy.
And we also see like how this intersection can be most useful in this.
Because this will help us find the bottlenecks
and fix them in real time, which will be much more
accurate than the normal traditional UX processes.
So just to give you a little insight,
like we don't know what data mining is,
it's like a process of finding digital insights
on the larger data sets. And when we have to
put it up into the UX perspective, we can say like
we want to find some crucial insights about the user's behavior.
And specifically in our case, it's going to be
a purchasing history of the user, and then
thereby we'll be able to cater the users in a better way.
And some specific things we're going to look at,
it's going to be user segmentation, where we're going to include those
specific users based on their purchasing
history or browsing experience.
And we're also going to analyze the feedback, which is a very crucial thing
when you're working with the e-commerce kind of a domain,
because the use affects a lot of things, specifically
to find the pinpoints for a UX person
in order to identify some details in the next iteration.
And again, there's one more thing, which is
the clickstream, which is a very crucial thing throughout
the processes for the UX to understand how the users
actually behave into the product.
So if you see the user segmentation, we can like
provide some personalized experience so that we can cater different
user pools with their needs. Here we can
make use of something like a cluster, k-means
clustering, which is a very novel unsupervised
learning algorithm. And then we're going to segment users
based on their purchasing history and browsing
history, which is basically, we'll be getting this data
from the transaction history of a digital e-commerce
system. And then we're going to segment those users
into specific clusters based on their
vector and feature similarity,
like the browsing history, as we already discussed.
And for example, here we are just simply
creating whole clusters for users based on the transaction
history and putting them to have a feature
similarity. So with this, we can say
we're going to get some personalized content
created for every single user. And even
the early training thing is like getting some
promotions to some specific pool of users, because we don't
want something that has been selling super fast.
We don't want to get like most discounts on to those products,
but we want to get something, we want to sell,
we want to make the things without being in the
inventory for a long time, we want to sell off those products by
getting some sort of promotions. And the second
thing is we're going to, you know, UX designers
usually take into account the feedback or the reviews on
their website, which helps them identify the
recurring beliefs about the problems and the bottlenecks which people
are usually facing. And it also helps like
gain, you know, like the valuable insights about some sort of product.
And the most important thing here is
per user pain points, because this is something
UX designers are used to make, like
by getting some information manually and then making them one by one,
and then creating, putting them into a pain point prioritizer, and then
finding some specific pain points, and
then using those to ideate into the next process.
So here we can simply use something like very basic
sentimental analysis to understand the sentiments of the
reviews that users are getting onto this platform.
And it could be positive, negative, or neutral,
and therefore they can help them create a pain point so that
it can streamline the process for the ideation phase.
And in this example, if you see like, we just like simply
calculating the polarity score of the
text we're getting of the reviews.
And if you see like, for example, if you think that a large number of
reviews has a mention called like
floor shipping, and they have a negative sentiment, so we can
consider like, it's a clear indication that the shipping needs to be better.
So instead of just like going through a tedious process, we simply do that
for the UX designers so that they can simply
ideate this thing, this step into the next iteration.
And the clickstream analysis for navigation patterns,
so as we said, it's a very powerful thing to understand
for the navigation patterns of a user onto a platform.
And it gives you insights and bottlenecks
for losing customers, and it also detects
potential pain points, which
tells them the areas of confusion where the user is actually
getting stuck are the bottlenecks, and
thereby using this information, we can fix the needs of the user,
which we'll be seeing later in the A.V. testing with this thing,
like how we can automate those tests.
And one thing which we discussed earlier is like,
the store is not going to be an online database, based on like,
it's going to be in the offline setting as well. So it's a new,
we just made the store open up into the offline setting,
and we have a lot of issues now. We don't know what the user
experience will be, but we're going to be able to do that.
We have a lot of issues now. We don't know what the user experience will be,
how the arguments will be placed, and
there will be stock outs which we need to figure out
so that our utility doesn't go down. And we also want to
cater the users by providing some specific
promotions during discounts on some specific products,
thereby increasing everybody's utility. So we'll make use of
the online store insights which we gathered in the
previous slides, and put them in use
into the local setting. So we basically make use of the data
mining algorithms here. So mostly we have
four which are the most used in the e-commerce space.
One is the market basket analysis.
So it basically analyzes the transactions,
and helps you find the frequently bought items
together so that you can play those items together
to increase the revenue. For example, if you go to a
supermarket and you see like milk and milk bread and butter
all together, so you're more likely to buy all these three items together
instead of just like being put up into different sections
of the supermarket. So the second thing, as we already discussed,
is the customer segmentation, where we can
just like segment them on the basis of some specific
user behavior. And optimizing store layout.
This is a very important thing which you must have seen in stores
like IKEA, that some specific items
are always put up next to each other.
So it basically helps you navigate to the store
and helps you increase the revenue because you are
most likely to purchase those products because you're getting those
historical data based on the previous transactions of the users.
And the last thing is the inventory management.
Again, we use the historical data here
and we figure out what the trends are, specifically
in some seasonal events like if it's Christmas,
we know some specific items will be sold out
much sooner than the others. So we make sure like
we can improve the inventory accordingly so that we don't go into
stockouts because, for example, if you are more tend to buy
milk and butter, and if you go to a store you find
milk only and if you want butter and bread as well,
and if you don't find that in the store, you're more likely
to go to another store where you can find all these three items together.
So reducing stockouts is another aspect of data mining.
So if you see this example,
we are trying to find the more purchased items together,
the item sets.
So what you're doing is we are pre-processing the data
with one-hot encoding, which is basically
we create in binary columns for each unique item,
one being the items being present in the data set.
And then we complete the frequent item sets
by using the A-priori algorithm, which is
a very common algorithm in the data set.
We are using the A-priori algorithm, which is
a very old algorithm, but we're not using it from scratch.
We're just using the email exchange things, and we just like calling the algorithm,
which creates a set of items that are bought together.
And we also provide a minimum support to this function,
which is at least
this x percent of the items should appear together.
So that's the first step in creating the high-frequency item sets.
Then we generate the associative rules,
which is basically how these item sets
are frequent to each other, and we discuss some sort of
rules for likelihood of these items being purchased.
So while the rules,
as we said, these are the likelihood, and the confidence
which we are also passing, is representing
the probability of the rule being leased, like it's been true or not.
Then we simply filter the rules
based on the lift and confidence, which we already discussed,
and create the item sets with the higher lift.
If you see in the next slide, that
these are the items, and if you see the lift,
these are the items with the highest lift, and these are the items which are more
likely to be purchased together. So as a store owner,
I'll place those items more closely into the store,
so that it's as a user behavior, they are more likely to purchase those
items into the store.
And another aspect is like,
we use Python to automate tests, and this can include
something like web scraping, scraping the data
from different sources, because for example,
on a website, you're just getting this
information about the reviews on a website, but there are so many
different third party websites, which are also, people are just putting
their reviews about our company or our product, so we can scrape
their data from these different sources, and we can also
automate multiple tools, like human efforts.
For example, if you are a subletting company, like a broker kind of thing,
you have so many tedious processes, like you have to go to
some exchange kind of thing, you have to put the email first of a user,
who's just going to be coming to your house,
and you have to go to some messaging platform, like a text matcher,
you put the phone number of the user, and so on.
So you can always use Python to automate
these processes, so that you can streamline the process, and
reduce the human efforts and human errors.
So, in this example of the case study, we are saying,
we want to automate external review analysis,
as we already discussed, as I said,
instead of just the reviews coming on onto a platform from
our own comments and reviews, there must be
third party websites where these reviews are being put up by the users.
And for example, we say we have a couple of reviews,
customer reviews over here, and what we're going to do is
we simply can scrape the reviews
and what we're going to do is we simply can scrape,
as useful as the web scraping thing from multiple websites,
anything can be used, like we did with Soup,
here we used Excelanium, and we can use that information
to get more data insights, we do
sentiment analysis or the common trends using NLP,
and once we have the keyed-nosed data
from some text website, from a third party website,
we can then synthesize that data into a single
data warehouse or a data lake so that we can just
now start working on it. So as a typical
user experience designer, we're going to
create some sort of affinity time-gaming, which is
gathering those similar groups all together, and we can make
use of something like another user segmentation
like K-Rings Clustering to do so, so that we don't have to
go through this tedious process of affinity time-gaming.
And this
helps us, again, finding the pinpoints, because pinpoints
are always important for the user at every single step of the
user journey, and we will find the required things,
also positively used. We can then visualize
these results and draw the conclusions.
Second last thing is the user
testing, user analytics and A-B testing.
So A-B testing is basically a method of comparing
two or more different variations, and so
for example, we have to figure out which design pattern
performs better. So we can make use of
different A-B tests, and how this
typically works is like we can use some sort of an analytics service
like Google Analytics and the Python API. We can gather
information. It could be page clicks, time spent on the
website, and you can see a simple
example where we are just like, we have two groups of data,
the control groups A and B, with the conversion rates for each
group represented by an array of data. Maybe, for example,
we can say there are five pages altogether. Then we perform
a test, and we use the TTTest underscore IUD
functions of the site library, which helps you
calculate the T statistic and the T value
for the given samples. And we have
put up alpha value as 0.05, which says like
if we have the T value less than
0.05, then there is definitely a significant
change in the T value, which is not by chance, and it is happening
because of some specific reason. To understand this
more comfortably, we can go for something like a button
color test. For example, we have two buttons on the website,
like the CTA call to action buttons, and one is red, one is
blue. So we can provide
a basic picture of it, just two buttons,
for instance. And what we are doing is like
we are taking two groups again. One is
clicks, and the second one is the non-clicks happening
on the website, on the specific page. And then
we are creating a contingency table, which is basically
the interrelation between those two or more variables
on the groups here, like group A and group B.
Then we are going with the car square test,
which is a statistical method used to determine
whether there is a significant association between
those two categorical values.
And once we are done with this, we are going to be finding
the T values. If you don't know, I think I can explain in the last slide.
T values and statistics is basically
the evidence of the null hypothesis. And in our
example, if you see, the null hypothesis
is basically the difference between the conversion
rates by clicking those buttons and like
non-clicks. And if we just like try
to print out the values, the significance
values, we'll see the group A has a CTR of 10 percent,
while the group B, which is the green button,
is having a CTR of 12 percent, and there is a
relative increase in the CTR by 20 percent,
and the P3 value is 0.268, which is
greater than 0.05, which shows that there is a significant
change, which is not by chance and due to some different
user's behavior. Similarly, we can also
go with something like a navigation mini test, which
helps you consider like reordering of the
libraries. Does they have any effect on the user's behavior
or the kinds they are spending on your website?
And we can make use of an algorithm, a test
basically, a map mini test, which determines
like whether the two groups are
coming from the same population or not. And in our
perspective, if you see, we have two groups A and B, which
has the page view, the bounce rate, and the average
from one page. And we're going to check like whether the differences
between the average size spent on the page is
happening because of a chance or they are statistically
significant. And if you see, what we're doing is like
we just like simply calling the man with the
geofunctions from the game recycle library, which is just
giving us the P value and the T values of the use statistics.
And if you see the use statistics, the more the
use statistics is, we can consider like this is not
because of, this is more likely to happen because of chance, but
if the use statistics vary too less, then we can conclude
that this is not happening because of a chance and has
statistically significant values associated with it.
And the last thing I want to discuss is like
developing the personalized user experience. So we can
use some algorithms like user-based collaborative filtering
or the content-based collaborative filtering
to provide personalized user product suggestions
or recommendations to the user. We can also provide
some user experiences like data promotions to a specific
set of users and which again, will start to help those
conversion rates more.
And what we're doing here is like we are just like
going to the user-based collaborative filtering, which is
what we're doing is like we're creating a sample data
space for the users, ratings for various products
represented as dictionary. And then we basically
pivoting the data frame to create a user product matrix
that is also representing the users in the column
which represent the product and the values are the corresponding
ratings of those products. We then simply compute the cosine
similarity between those two vectors in a space.
And then we find the target user, which is two in our case,
and we find the most similar user by using the NG ArcMaps
on the user similarity matrix.
And then we find the target user, which is two in our case,
and we find the most similar user by using the NG ArcMaps
on the user similarity matrix, which is going to give us
back a value and that you can send those values back
to the, to identify the product rated by the most similar
user on the group. And once we are done, we can just like
find the difference between the sets of the rated products
for both the users. And if we just like run this
and if you are about to look for the outcome for the most
recommended product for the user two, will be our BNC.
And similarly, we can also make use of the TTF-IDF
vectorizer for the quantum based
collaborative filtering, where we basically convert
the object and transform the descriptions into a TTF-IDF
matrix. And then this matrix holds the importance of
all the input, which is there in the descriptions of the disk.
which is there in the descriptions of the disk.
If you see the object has a product and a description,
and then we take into account the frequency of the object
and then we take into account the frequency of the words in the description.
And again, we do the same thing.
We compute the cosine similarity, but now
we are not using the, the functions we used earlier.
We are using the linear kernel, which takes into TTF-IDF
matrix. And then this matrix basically
represents the similarity between all pairs of
clues based on their descriptions.
And then we simply define a recognition function,
which is the most common one, and it takes the product index
and the similarity matrix, which returns the most similar products.
And in our case, if you go with the
product A, which is the linear cache-based clues,
the products, the most similar products
with the cosine similarity are the stickers and the format keys.
And all together,
we can create the user personas.
More recently, when we
consider the large learning models, creating user personas is much more simpler,
especially when we have all those information from
the previous information we had,
like the information we gathered from
the user segmentations and all.
And here we can say, like, there is a user, say, Jared Thompson.
He's 28 years old. His occupation is a software engineer,
and he is in the specific, like, the Inca range.
And he's a tech savvy,
and he prefers to shop online, and he has a specific personality.
And he has some goals and needs,
which we have figured out from the previous examples.
And he has some frustrations, which we again figured out from the reviews
and feedback. And then these are the solutions,
which us as a UX designer has provided,
which are data-driven. We can provide them more personalized
communication based on the browsing and the process industry,
and we can also make use of the AI-powered A-B testing,
which might lead to the better user experience
and so on. And yes, that's pretty much it.
Thank you so much for joining,
and if you have any questions, please let me know.