All right, I hope everyone settled on.
Our speaker for this session will talk about
how secure security and security slopes
help to elevate an entire ecosystem at scale.
Let us welcome Dustin Ingram.
Thank you.
Yeah, so I'm Dustin.
I'm on the Google Open Source Security Team.
So the mission of that team is to make open source software
software that Google and everyone else uses more secure.
Also on the Python Software Foundation Board of Directors
where I help ensure the long-term success
of one very big open source Python project
you've probably heard of, Python.
I'm also one of the Python package maintainers
where I help ensure the long-term success
of hundreds of thousands of teeny tiny Python projects,
many of which you've never heard of.
And also I'm on the Technical Advisory Committee
for the Open Software Security Foundation,
which is new, where I help guide the success
of the next generation of open source security technologies.
So this talk is about ecosystem security.
My focus at Google is to kind of think about
how to increase adoption of security improvements
across many open source ecosystems,
including Python but not just Python.
And as a maintainer of PyGI,
I also really deeply care about making sure
that the Python ecosystem is safe and secure
for all our users.
So I definitely care about how one would go
about elevating the security of an entire ecosystem
at scale, but you probably don't have
those same responsibilities.
You probably don't have that job either.
That's fine.
But why do I think you should care about this?
So here's what I want to get from this talk.
First, why is this hard?
I want you to understand what are the actual challenges
that make this hard to do.
Second, I want you to understand why some turn is necessary.
And I was playing with what I mean by turn,
why I think it's necessary,
and how I think we should deal with it.
Also, I want you to understand how security
can increase sustainability.
So there's more of a relationship between these two things
than you might actually expect.
And finally, I want you to understand how you can help.
And this isn't just, let's pitch in on some
of the projects together.
There are actual ways for you to help when you think about security.
Overall, I want to give you an insight into how these things
change, how we think about security in our ecosystem,
and all the trade-offs that exist at each point.
Because everything is a trade-off, right?
There are trade-offs in every decision.
There is never just one best move.
They're always balancing between the two choices.
So part one, why is this hard?
Security is hard enough on a small scale.
So some of you might be familiar with implementing
or adopting security changes, procedures, practices
on your teams or maybe in your organizations.
And my guess is that those were
pretty somewhat challenging.
If you were implementing those changes,
maybe you had to articulate the problem,
get the sign-off, that's what I will make a claim on,
check it twice, get everyone on board,
and bring forward all the holdouts,
announce it, roll it out,
then you can clean the holdouts.
It's not easy, right?
If you were the person adopting the change,
you probably had to deal with a really confusing change
that nobody told you about
and probably wrote something that you're responsible for.
So these things are hard on a small scale.
These things are extremely hard on a large scale,
especially on the ecosystem scale.
Why is that?
So one reason is that users don't ask for security.
They need a student.
So, for example, GitHub is requiring all developers
who contribute code on github.com
to enable one or more forms of two-factor authentication
by the end of this year, by the end of 2023.
The number of people I've seen
asking, cleaning GitHub to make this change
is basically zero, no one's asking for this.
However, the number of people that are assuming
that all code pushed to GitHub
is pushed by the actual owners of the accounts
that push it is basically everywhere, right?
That's like the basis of your GitHub.
So, so many times I've seen this lack of user requests
held up, or lack of user requests for a security feature
held up as a reason for why it's just not worth doing.
The lack of requests is because users assume
that corrective security is just happening behind the scenes,
that they don't need to ask for it.
Additionally, for those users,
it's hard to work towards hypotheticals.
So, I think that security as a field
generally is an exercise in professional anxiety
and care and learning.
It's preemptive work to mitigate some potential outcome
of varying levels of bad
that has some varying level likelihood of happening.
And users are reactive.
The reason they don't ask for security features
is because a bad outcome is of sufficient impact
hasn't happened to them yet.
So, we can sort of think of this as a quadrant, right?
The range from low likelihood to high likelihood,
low impact to high impact.
So, low impact, low likelihood,
these things are nothing to worry about.
Low impact, high likelihood,
this might be something like password reuse,
credential stuff, a decision.
So, something where like, you know,
it's very likely it's gonna happen.
You're just gonna stick your password somewhere
that doesn't belong.
But usually there's enough of a blast
where you just have a single person
that it's not the end of the world.
There's some things like high impact,
high likelihood stuff like leading us
to a bucket world readable.
That happens all the time.
You can lose a lot of information,
like secrets, leaks, and the like,
taking you to the east of your kingdom.
These are extremely high impact,
but also very incredibly frequent.
And in the last quadrant is stuff
that's just like getting hacked by an agent state, right?
For the same reason that some of these
are harder to address than others,
they're also harder to load.
It's not really just the users though.
Here's a refrain I see from time to time from maintainers.
But we haven't made any mistakes yet.
Where the ask is to adopt some security tool or feature.
Like, I haven't been phished yet.
I haven't leaked any API tokens yet.
I haven't included things I shouldn't
and released yet.
I haven't unknownly created a vulnerability yet.
Here's a real paraphrase quote
that I got from a maintainer,
and this is in response to a request to automate
the build and release process for a library.
They said, I've made more than 200 releases to date,
and I've never made a mistake.
So first of all, who knows this may take a look.
That is actually impressive.
I have not done it myself.
I break Prykion all the time.
But is this actually a good mindset to have
as an open source maintainer?
Like, what are they actually saying?
They're saying that they don't want to change their behavior
and that even if the risk is high enough,
an impact is reasonably unlikely.
And they're probably also a little offended
that we don't consider that a foul word
that they might make a mistake.
This also kind of fails to consider
because really often our problems
are not directly caused by us,
but we don't work in decades.
A lot of things are caused by other people
or other systems.
Other things around us that are
entirely out of our control perhaps,
that can also go wrong.
High uncertainty components in complex systems.
This is another reason why this is hard.
Security often requires changing
high uncertainty components in complex systems.
Who is it that's key to that question?
Do you know what I mean by that?
People.
It means changing people's behavior,
especially their behavior, in security.
There's really, I think,
two ways to interpret
how to handle a technical problem.
One is that the problem is easy
because people can just do X, right?
We can build a technical solution to our problem,
and that solution might work perfectly,
and then people can just use that system.
The other interpretation is that
the problem is actually incredibly hard
because it requires people to do X.
So often that the hardest part
of solving the technical problem
is not the technical problem itself,
but changing the behavior of people
around that technical problem.
So, for example,
I still use Code Editor
that I first used almost 20 years ago,
which itself was first released
almost 50 years ago.
And to be fair, Code Editors are
incredibly personal tools.
But for me, all of the benefit
of a modern IDE
has still not outweighed
across the meaning changing our behavior.
I'm extremely resistant to it.
So, there is
a third thing that happens sometimes.
Sometimes it's very easy.
It doesn't require people at all.
This almost never happens.
Improvements that don't need humans
to change their behavior are so
few and far between.
Even still, when we have the opportunity
to make such an improvement
that might not require humans to change their behavior,
it often doesn't happen
because it ends up
being technically more talented.
And so we fail to take into account
the cost of changing human behavior
and adding that up all the time
that it goes into a change.
So there's almost always a requirement
that people do X.
The need to change human behavior is basically
inevitable for almost
every technical problem.
And I think this is especially true
for software security because
let's be real.
Most software in security
comes from those best in humans.
This is called
churn. This is the part where we
require humans to change and make a change.
Meaning any work that you
have to do that isn't directly
related to your outcome.
So an example of churn would be
adopting a convention updating tool
on your ProBit and merging version
bumps in your releases.
Or adopting a vulnerability scanner to run
across all your dependencies and a lot of your vulnerabilities
when they happen.
Or maybe churn is like
a change on your keyboard for just a second
to pop a little address in your
toggle window.
Okay, so part two. Why is some churn
necessary? So we've established that
churn exists, but let's figure out
why it's necessary.
So sometimes security
can happen by default.
So one example
of this might be like auto-revoking
credentials from a token leak.
So right now if you put your
IPI or API token
inside of a PID and you push out
to GitHub, GitHub would
immediately detect it,
alert IPI, and PID would immediately
revert back to the control. Probably within
milliseconds of you pushing that PID.
And this requires zero
change to human behavior.
To get this increased security,
humans can and do
continue to happily share in those
handshakes, secrets, and so on, but they're protected.
There's just significantly
less fallout to deal with and so
they don't have to do anything to get that benefit.
But usually security
does require some change. Usually you gotta
do something to give something in return.
So yeah, okay, if churn is inevitable,
what should we do about it?
So first, here's some things that I don't
think we should do.
So one of these things I think
we should do is assume we can just
magically give people to do things that are
impossible.
We can't just like wave our hand and get humans
to act. So maybe
an example here is PGP in a
anatomical sense, okay, maybe it's a decent solution
to the problem. In a practical sense,
I think it's kind of absolutely nonsense.
In order to use
this project, you get a bunch of humans
in a room and have them show each other their drivers licenses
and special random characters
to verify their identities. And then also
those humans can never lose those stuff of random
things or characters, ever.
Like, god.
Everything we shouldn't do is
shift the complexity on the
people. And I'm talking about stuff that's not
strictly possible for humans to do,
but it's not always the most
ideal thing for humans to do.
So, for example,
reading CDE does for vulnerabilities.
And trying to determine if
they're effective. So
I have defined the vulnerability
in some computer thing, and
then the way to fix it is that I write
as humans some long document,
and then I have to have other humans
read that long document, and then
they have to try to figure out if they're trying to find their own computer
changes. That's madness, right?
We should cut out the middle bit of that.
There's better ways to do that.
The other thing we
shouldn't do is nothing.
We could all just give up and become
farmers, but we shouldn't do that.
So one
thing maybe we could do
is force a change. The other thing.
So, I work at Google,
which I often describe as having
like this black key upside down,
which is a universe of software tools.
And in this ecosystem,
adoption is not owned by
many little small ones that can get
some individuals. Because if you
can just convince a couple people,
very special people, you can just
demand that everybody does the same thing.
So overnight your software
pool can go from like zero users to
9,000 users just by hand.
And this works for Google, because
there is authority
for anybody to change. So
it's possible that could work for your
organization as well, but it might
not work because it's also really
expensive, right? It requires
paying people money to beat the cost
of adoption to do all the turn.
And I think usually this
doesn't work in open source ecosystems.
Usually because there isn't
a central authority. So in this context,
something like the Python steering
capsule or core dev team, right?
They have some authority to
make changes, but they have very little authority
to make users use those changes
to adopt their changes, right?
It works for using M197.
But also, because of
the expense, right? If those
mandatings are not the ones who are
paying the expensive curve
of mandates,
that becomes problematic, and I'll talk more about that
in a second. And that's
the other thing that I do think there are times when
mandates are necessary, and I'll talk more
about that in a second.
Alright, so turn is inevitable.
What should we do?
First, as much as possible,
we should minimize. This means
putting the hard work in to shift
as much complexity
from people into
the technology to pull the
solution. And there's a few types of
minimizations that are possible here.
So one, we can minimize human
effort through local automation. So like,
these are like the bots that
vary. The dependencies for new engines.
Humans don't have to be there.
Humans don't have to make the PRs, the bots do that too.
All the maintainer has to do is click work.
It's still a little churn there, but we've really
minimized it. Another
one is minimizing the costs
through efficiency and simplification. I'm not
talking about like cost to cost of life,
I'm talking about people's time.
As long as we can use
these to minimize the effort necessary
to adopt some new thing or to change,
that counts.
The other thing is minimizing
human time through education. If
the human already has a base level
of understanding about why a change
is necessary, that's not just coming out of the blue.
There's a lot less context that
you need to build in your mind
to adopt a change.
I'll highlight a specific example
on this if you don't want to get
clued by the foreign firms thinking. So
we just launched trusted publishers for
API application. So this is
a new way for maintainers to publish
to API
from GitHub Actions that does
not require long-lived passwords or
API tokens.
So this is something that requires
maintainers to make a change,
but we put a lot of effort into
minimizing how much churn is necessary
to adopt this.
So, the first thing we do is
we minimize effort through automation.
So this requires a new authentication
that involves a somewhat complex
token exchange. You can't use it
because it might see your eyes, nose, and nose
already. Don't worry. It's all
really nicely abstracted away
from the user if you use
the IP address GitHub Actions. You don't have to think about it.
We also minimize the cost of adoption
significantly. To adopt this,
all you need to do is really change
the different lines that you're going to have work with.
And one of those is to comment
two over windows such as building an entire
house or building a building.
And the other thing we did
is we educated. I
just told you everything you need
to know about this. So you should now
feel empowered to go and adopt it.
You'll be accepted.
Okay, getting back to the ways that we can
minimize churn.
Another thing I can do,
another thing you can do is a regular response.
So what I mean by this is
is to develop a change that is so compelling
in a way that it always
makes sense to adopt a
buy or a novelty.
And an example here that I like to have
is Sixer. I think Sixer is a really
good example of this. So full disclosure,
I am very biased because I work on
this project. I created
the Python client for Sixer. Sixer was
support and I spent on the
technical committee that
is the whole of Sixer.
But the reason I decided
to do all these things is because I found
Sixer to be such a novel
compelling solution to the problem of code
signing, which solves many
existing problems in our ecosystem.
So I'm not going to go into full detail
about what really compelling
reasons are and how Sixer works.
If you want that you can watch one of my videos
to talk ergonomic code signing
for Python, especially with Sixer.
He goes into a very deep dive about this.
But suffice it to say that Sixer
is a brand new way to sign
and verify just without any
help. But this comes at a really high
price point. You need to adopt an entirely new
set of tools first time and verify.
Or about the set of
tools in the first place.
So in this case I would say that
Sixer is revolutionary because
the cost is worth it and
continuing to invest in this as a solution
is still worth it.
And if all else fails we can't
accept the lies. So one, maybe
this solution is really expensive
to adopt or maybe it's not
particularly revolutionary
or maybe it may need
fields related to it. So
instead we can sort of put our finger
on the scale in various ways.
So sometimes this comes naturally
like with trusted publishers
the presence of this feature unlocks
many other things that we could do like
we'll be able to show
and verify a link between a Python
project and the GitHub repository that created it.
It's not something we could verify before.
But this will only be possible
to projects that have adopted this feature.
So in that way it sort of helps
to incentivize our adoption.
Sometimes we can add
other related benefits.
Like for example the PyQ 2.0
giveaway and
security key giveaway.
Sometimes this works, sometimes it doesn't.
I know there is some drama
about the security key giveaway.
I know. But in this example
I think it worked because
we gave away
thousands of keys
and
more than 35,000
users now have two factor enable a giveaway.
So with the example of
two factor authentication
why would we even do that?
What's the point?
It's perfectly how security
increases sustainability.
I think a lot of it already means
four security improvements usually
amount to because hackers.
It's preventative care to make sure
that bad things don't happen
someday or bad things are like
compromised execution or whatever.
There's also
common criticism for this though that security
is like a slippery slope. Especially
things like security decades.
The idea is that if we keep increasing
security requirements we'll end up
in some pit of maximum security where
innovation is completely stifled
and those maintainers and consumers
just can't do anything.
Ultimately I think
our goal is increasing
the sustainability of security. There is a cost
to the life of security.
We just don't pay it when we choose
not to adopt. We pay it months
and years later when things happen
and we pay it with interest.
So here's an example.
Think about what has to happen
when just one maintainer on a pipe
attic gets fished and their project
gets compromised and now it gets published.
So it's up to
to create reports, that can do investigation,
that can do public communications,
get down to malware,
do a top cover for the maintainer,
talk to the press, talk to
other folks. Like it gets really complicated.
It eats up a lot of time. So
at the expense of maybe one person
not taking a few seconds to be used
to fact-count a login, this seems like
hours of maintainer time that
could be used for other things. And also
potentially downstream users who use
this up their time as well.
So in this case we want PyPy to be
secure and useful for
all users. The goal isn't to make
PyPy impossible to use. That would be
kind of a two-bit thing.
But if these are the kind of things we have to
spend all our time on, PyPy will
become impossible to use. Like if I spend
my entire day responding to
malware, then responding to
people getting fished and their
accounts compromised, I don't have time to build
cool features.
I don't disagree that software security
is a slippery slope, but
I think the slope is actually upwards,
not downwards. Like really
deep, honey, upwards.
And it's because people, like people, all
people, they're resistant to change.
And because this upfront
investment in security is really
hard to show impact for
when the result is something that doesn't
happen. The effect
of all of this is that it's
often really hard to adopt
insecure features.
Here's another example. So maybe you've heard
about the 3CX
blockchain attack. So this just happened last month.
What happened was
attackers exploited a bug in the way
that when those executables are signed,
it compromises a communications company
called 3CX.
So this bug allows an attacker to modify
any sign of an executable
to include malware.
And for verification to frame,
to still claim that it's
originally inside.
This bug was known for 10 years.
And yeah, it sounds like a pretty big
deal. It was fixed, actually,
but then it was only fixed as
an opt-in.
Why was it opted?
Because many people were shipping
Windows executables
using this bug as a feature.
So, for example, Google Chrome,
the installer for Google Chrome,
using this bug to provide
a slightly modified binary if you opted
into sending you statistics
and crash reports to Google.
So when you downloaded Chrome, and when the executable
was installed, it uses
this bug to determine if diagnostic
reports should be enabled.
It wasn't just Chrome. Lots of people were using this.
So because fixing this
bug would break so many
workflows, it didn't happen.
For 10 years, it was opt-in.
Engines made things worse.
When you upgrade to any version
of Windows, it reverts the opt-in.
So remember, users
don't ask for security. No one was petitioning
Microsoft to fix this.
And sometimes users tend to take
it to pregnancy. No one asked for security.
Okay. That's enough writing for me.
Let me get to my point.
So I hope that you now have an understanding about
why this is hard,
about why some turn is necessary,
about how security
increases the system in building.
What do I want you to do?
First, please don't depend
on others.
This may be a rare case, but don't take
dependencies on the presence of bugs,
especially security bugs.
While we're at it, don't take dependencies on
internal APIs that way.
When you're breaking changes, it's a difficult
program. The users should be able
to ship bug fixes,
ship security fixes, and improvements,
and have them happen by default,
especially when they address security
vulnerabilities.
I think what I'd like you to do is
look for opportunities to proactively
invest in security.
So weigh the cost of adoption
with the cost of if things
go well. So for example,
with trusted publishers,
what would you rather do? A few minutes
to change your developer
for now, or a dental clapper bias
if your long-term security
can't be there for some reason.
Maybe take a couple minutes to pay the check.
Last thing is I want you to support
sustainability.
Be willing to accept a little
turn when it's reasonable,
and when the end result is
a better overall ecosystem.
Maybe also trust
the maintainers of your ecosystem to make
decisions that have your overall
long-term best interests
in mind, even if they might
fail to still learn the inconvenience.
Okay, let me make some quick shout-outs and
acknowledgements. First, I want
to thank William Woodruff and the Team
Control Bits. We've done a lot of work on
podcast specifically around trusted publishers
and quality of good work on how
it was doing. I want to thank
Stas Los-Sitarenko, who's the maintainer
of the podcast publisher,
She Had Action, for also doing a lot of good
work and making it very easy to use
and adopt. I want to shout-out
to everyone who enabled two-factor authentication
on PyGI. Thank you.
Again, go ahead.
I want to shout-out to the
Google
Social Security, who funded much of this work,
funded this creative giveaway, funded their trusted publishers' work.
And finally,
I want to give a huge thank you to
podcast staff and everyone else
as usual. They really deserve their thanks as well.
So please look forward to and appreciate
what they're doing. I thank you to all of you
as well. Thanks.
Thank you.
Thank you so much
for being so thoughtful. In the same sense,
we still have a couple of minutes
left. If you have any questions, you can come up here
and we can go next to you.
Let's do a...I'm going to cut it off now and we can do
a follow-up track. And then also, I should say
there is an open space at
4 o'clock downstairs
on Black Sheep Security for maintainers.
If you're using my archive,
I'm going to take this as well and show what we talked about
along the way and stuff. So please
go check it out. Count with me. Nothing
less for all I have. Go see the stickers
if you want to. It's all down in the sticker.
Thanks.