Hello everyone. Welcome to the next session.
Now it's after lunch, so you are still a bit sleepy, but I'm pretty sure that this topic will be really interesting.
So we have people like the microcontrollers and machine learnings here.
I guess that this is a really cool talk to be in.
So without further ado, let's welcome our speaker, Maria Jose Marina Contreras.
Thank you. I'm so excited to be here talking about this topic because I'm super excited and I love it.
Just to let you know, this talk is going to be, I hope not intense, but it will be with a lot of information.
Just be aware of that. But I hope that you enjoy as well as I am going to be.
And of course, if you have questions or something, we can always clarify everything.
Let's start. My name is Maria Jose. My background is in plant molecular biology.
I work as a data scientist in a company for indoor farming called InFarm in Germany.
And I mainly work with central data.
Also, in my free time, I enjoy work with embedded systems and of course, data science.
This is the last process that I have been doing in the last years.
This was high and fun. Some weathering systems here, here.
Some kind of machine learning detection. You know if my plant works, think or not.
Maybe it was not necessary in these days, but you know. In other cases, it was necessary.
Also, I have been doing some very basic beginner-scale robotics.
Just to have fun, just to play around and share with the community.
To motivate other people to start playing with microcontrollers.
And my next project was focusing on air quality in indoors.
And it was in that moment when I realized that I could do things a bit different.
Let's say, this system is working very well.
Our child is having here. We have here is two sensors.
This is for particles. This is for fuel. And here we have a rasterized.
And then we have a second rasterized here where I was displaying the monitoring and also the carry this system.
But only for kids, what if I can have this system for the doors.
And then at some point I say, okay, well, but I cannot go for anything in my daily life with two rasterized sensors.
As normal, imagine. As beautiful when I arrive running.
And it was in that moment I said, look, I'm going to start to find a solution to that.
Maybe there is some way that I can have this machine learning, capital data science in microcontrollers.
And this is how I start into finding an air.
Let's start from the beginning. I am going to show that there are going to be different levels of everything.
And as we are going to cover a lot of topics, I'm going to go really fast.
No worries. But just to be sure that everyone is on the same page.
Well, in here I'm going to not say a lot, just to be sure that everyone is on the same page.
That machine learning is a fulfill of AI.
And also deep learning is a fulfill of machine learning.
Specifically, we are going to talk about some neural networks, but more than two layers.
Just to give you a point where we are.
Well, machine learning is everywhere.
And it's in recommendation systems, identification of objects,
classification, forecasting, NLP, and of course, what's above, chat boards.
Lately, the tiny little hotchpotch, in the console, it's everywhere.
And it will be more and more in our lives.
But what is then worth tiny machine learning?
Tiny machine learning is in between data science and electronics.
It's in the intersection between these two worlds.
We are going to go into that. And why?
We can't know. Well, we can't have this machine learning autonomous in our system.
We can't pull a process and have the art in our devices.
This is going to increase our data privacy.
We are going to have lower energy consumption because the microcontroller doesn't consume a lot of power.
Let's go on that later.
Low latency. And also connectivity.
How many of you are working with IoT data, central data, daily business?
Okay. And do you have some connectivity issues?
Yeah, I have them.
I can tell you that for me it was an issue.
I'm not trying to hear in my workplace.
And I realized that this could be also very good alternative.
What about the tiny amount of use cases that we have?
We have in the field, kinetic maintenance.
And kinetic maintenance is what we are going to go later on about because we are going to go into a sample where we are going to talk quite not deeply, but kind of specifically.
We have healthcare devices.
For instance, in this publication, it was very cool because they were giving a very low cost for that just for blood pressure.
Also, there are the sound recognition.
Maybe some of you know about those devices that you say some keyword and say, hey, can you reproduce music?
And you reproduce the music or other things, right?
This is also tiny amount.
We have also smart spaces.
There are some companies that need to detect if there is people inside or not before to have the alarm, drop the light.
This is also happening currently with tiny amount.
We have the whole conservation project in here.
This is very cool.
Our is the program of conservation where they are tracking the elephants to know if there are furtive around and try to monitor them to avoid to kill the elephant.
It is super nice application.
And also we have agriculture.
And maybe some of you are going to think, do you cook here?
Because there are some places, some countries that the internet access to internet is limited or is costly or doesn't arrive.
The application in your mobile without internet, this could help a lot of farmers.
Well, let's read back again about this intersection of the tools.
Because of course, this is a surprise.
When we talk about machine learning, we usually are doing our training, our elections in classes, CPUs in our computers.
Of course, we have limitations of RAMs, of course.
But it is not a big deal, right?
You can manage and educate.
When we talk about embedded systems, we have them.
And this is a topic that we are going to need to talk about.
Of course, one of the features of our program is that you can have some bags, a bracelet, some euros, some cents.
And also it can take for a long time.
And also we have the low latency, but this implies that we'll be faster.
Well, this is a tool that I found very interesting from this website.
Be aware that these numbers, of course, could be different.
But for me, it was kind of, I like it to see of which magnitude we were talking, right?
When we are comparing to about microprocessors, let's say, finding devices to see how different it is.
And especially it will be key for memory and storage.
This is super, super important that we have really to do.
Well, what about the state of art of machine learning for microcontrollers running languages?
Let's start with, in these days we have a project called 50-Python.
There we're generating text with the type DPP, CO3-8-Python.
There are not a lot of projects outside of 50-Python and HANY now.
It's a time for you.
For micro-Python, I found these two tutorials quite interesting, both of them.
One, this first is focused more on things videos and this is a neural network.
And then we have in here on the bottom a library, a Python library called EverywhereNL,
where you could have the full Python using this library.
I didn't try, to be honest, let me be honest here, but I thought it could be very interesting.
That's what about other programming language.
Of course, we have programming language.
This book of HANYML with Arduino, if you are familiar, of course, with Python, but also with Arduino,
you're going to find very interesting examples, but I truly recommend at least to take a look
at the series, super well explained and very nice.
But also we have C, C++, Java.
There are other options.
And the pen.
You're going to listen a lot of depends in this talk.
Don't be afraid that depends on the situation of the project and the goal.
You're going to need to evaluate what is the best for your project.
Which kind of boards options do we have?
This is just an example.
We pull up so many more boards.
But I wanted to plug some of them.
On the bottom, we have some with scanners.
Why?
It's because maybe I am doing some other development.
In the meanwhile, I am doing this talk.
And maybe soon there are going to be some problems with some images things.
I think it's a small spoiler.
But in here, but also you can add your cameras in the other devices.
And of course, you can use other devices.
Close to this.
In C2, S2, and this kind.
I'm going to focus on this one.
By the way, for the next slide.
Because this is the one that I am taking out of place.
I am working with it because it has some of the very interesting things.
First, it has Wi-Fi and Bluetooth.
Of course, for this project, it will not be necessary because we were talking about that.
But for other projects, it will be.
And also, you have the parents here.
You have the pins headers.
And you can connect directly the wires.
And it's a development board.
And it's very easy.
Just arrive and work with.
What do you need for do the setup?
Do you need the board?
Do you need the cables?
And just a computer that runs Windows, Linux, or Mac OS.
Just be careful and check your cables.
Because let's be honest here, now that no one is listening to us.
But I've had a lot of issues with that cable because I was not using it right.
It's not the same the cable for closing the data, but for closing the names.
But now we can continue.
But no one is listening.
Yeah, this was one of my mistakes when I was starting.
The fact that the same cable for USB, right?
It's okay.
But it works now.
I'm sorry for this advice.
It's a lot of information, but I only want to explain all the data, all the steps that you will have for the initial hardware setup.
Just to let you know that only in five steps, only in some minutes, you can have your setup of the board working.
And now we can have the install.
You only need to install the operating system.
You need to build the application, set up the tools, set up the environment, and then you can start with the firewall.
And you can have a better explanation here in the official documentation.
But this again is like six, seven command lines.
It's like if you don't have any problems in minutes, you are ready.
But for all the boards the same, no.
It's four and a half.
The incident protocol, you're going to take the different setup.
But well, this is one of the most exciting things that we have new challenge with each board.
This is how it looks like at Hello World.
Also, I just wanted to share it to give you a little review of how easy could be to start Hello World on that.
Step one, you prepare your code.
Step two, you connect your board to the computer.
Step three, you configure your project.
Then appear this Google screen.
That's for a Hello World distribution enter.
And then you just need to build the project and slash it to the device.
In this case, it will not be Python code.
You're going to need to be aware of that.
But of course, you can do it if you want.
In this case, it was just to take a look at the board was okay.
The keyboard was working.
Everything was working.
And this is what you're going to get.
And it's quite difficult to see.
It's just to show you what you're going to see in your terminal.
I'm going to show that you can read it.
It's just what you're going to see.
Well, let's go now for the machine learning path.
Because we were covering the microcontroller.
Let's go for the machine learning path.
Okay.
How many data people do we have in the room?
Can you write some plans?
Okay.
Like, 60, 65 at least.
Don't kill me for write this workflow linear.
I just wanted to simplify it for this talk.
But all the data people knows that this is not linear.
Data science is a creative process that we need to collect data,
process the data, check the teaser, it's okay.
Do that again because we don't have enough data,
wait for everything, but it's not okay.
Let's design the model now that it's okay.
Wait, we need more data.
And we are in this loop with the model.
I wait, but not enough data.
Let's be back.
And again and again and again.
But as I just wanted to simplify, I just write it in this horizontal way.
If your overwhelming at this point worries that there are some platforms,
this is one of the temple platform that you can have your whole pipeline.
What you need to take a look is which devices are compatible.
And also once you do the deployment in which programming language,
you can do the deployment in case that you want to drag the chain forward.
Just be aware.
It's very, very important for this kind of project to be conscious of everything
that I mean this decision that you're going to make.
Because you're going to see that we have a lot of limitations.
Anyway.
I tried and it was quite interesting.
However, I decided to go do it by my own.
Because I wanted to play with the architecture and play around the path of machine learning.
To be honest.
Okay.
Now, let's wait for a bit.
And let's start with the most hypothetical, pure, real use case.
Let's imagine that you are walking around and you find your friend.
This is him.
This is me.
Hi, how are you?
How is everything going?
Oh, very good.
I went to the platform you were talking about.
I learned about my community.
I learned everything is awesome.
I know about political campaigns.
Oh, what is that?
Can you share a bit about it?
Yes.
You can do a kind of like happening.
A training team.
Little different maintenance.
Let's say we have relative maintenance.
That is the one that something breaks and then you fix it.
You have the relative maintenance that if you maintain your bloodline before breaks,
like a car for instance.
Okay.
You have the option to predict what and when you're going to break.
And then the school helps to make decisions or order new power or just manage a bit better things.
And then you continue talking with your friend.
And you say, yes, and then I can predict now anomalies.
And you can say, well, I have a thought.
I think because I was starting the business and I got a freak which is not new.
It's second hand.
I would love to have that because it's very important to me to have fresh products.
And I need to be sure that these freaks are going to be always running perfectly.
And if I can prevent the damage, I need it.
Well, no problem.
Let's start implementing the assistance.
First point, data collection to prepare the data.
You need to share this with your friends as well.
We need to think about the sensors, how we are going to connect.
And your friends understand perfectly.
But no worries because the serious owner of the fix gives me data ready.
I have the data for you.
I'm sorry, this is not coming back on the internet.
But just let me know.
And then your friend gives you all this data.
Be aware that these are public data sets that are not mine.
In case you do it, please just refer to the author or the people, the owner of the data set.
Well, you have all these parameters.
And you are very happy because it's like, OK, well, then let's start analyzing the data.
Let's start understanding what has outliers because for anomaly detection,
we need to understand what's an outlier and what is an anomaly.
Well, outliers don't data the data points that are not in the inflected anomaly view.
An anomaly is a specific type of outlier.
This means that anomaly is always an outlier, but not outliers are always an anomaly.
And this is very, very important.
And of course, when we are here in this great example,
it's very obvious that you have here something, and here maybe you have something else.
And we need to understand if this is real or not because humans can detect some patterns
that then algorithms sometimes think that this is not a real pattern,
and this is very important, and sometimes we don't see patterns, and the algorithms can see them.
And this is what we are very interested in.
Then, let's go to define a model and train the model.
There are different modeling approaches for anomalies detection.
You can start with statistical techniques.
You can go for classical machine learning or go for deep learning.
And definitely OK.
If you ask what is the best, it depends on the case, it depends on the business case,
it depends on what is your experience, it depends on how much time do you have,
how many interests you are going to have, and now it depends also on your board and your hardware
because now we are going to need to deploy it in an embedded system, and this is a new challenge.
In this case, I decided to go for a deep learning approach.
Let's start with that.
OK, don't be scared about this table, but I love it because in this table summarize all the things
that we need to be aware to be sure that the system is going to work.
We need to know what are the training libraries for the model,
but also that are compatible with the platforms and also with the frameworks.
OK, then you can see in here, for instance, that we have neural network,
which has a new problem, I think it's almost everywhere,
but then if you want, for instance, go for SDM, for instance, or some progress with scikit-learn,
you can also have it.
You don't need to run always deep learning.
This is very, very important.
But always, you are going to need to check all this information before making decisions.
In this case, we are going to go for LSTM, which is a code approach.
It will be auto encoded, to be honest.
I'm not going to go into a lot of details about the architecture.
I just want to show mindset that LSTM is an artificial neural network designed to detect patterns
during the time, sorry, like time series.
Let's go here, some very interesting resources, and let's go for auto encoded.
What about auto encoded and how it works?
Imagine that you have a cake, which you love it, and you decide to say,
OK, I'm going to reproduce this cake.
I know that there are flowers, flowers, eggs, chocolates.
And at the end, oh, you do.
I guess you already know what it is.
And at the end, you can end up with different situations.
In one, you have a cake that is almost the same as the beginning,
but as the input, which will be the normal data.
But then, you can also end up with the same map, with the same ingredients, with a cookie.
In this case, it will be an anomaly.
And then, there is a tricky case that is this one, this is the pie, the between 10 million points.
That is the most, it will be the most tricky part, because there will be some that could be here,
but also could be here.
For this data, we are going to need to establish a threshold.
And the threshold is going to be based on how important are the false positives,
the false negatives for you, for your case, and see how this affects your knowledge.
Well, if you need more information, take a look to this link.
That is super good.
For setting this model, we are going to use normal data.
This means that if you know that the base background, that there was a problem with the fit,
this data problem needs to be out, because the model needs to learn what is normality
to detect the pattern for anomaly.
And this is the result.
In this case, we have two classes, right?
We are going to have normal data, but in this case, it is the blue,
and then a normal data, but it is the orange.
And this line shows kind of the threshold.
With them, you see some points here that are kind of false positives.
And this is going to need some work and adjustment.
Okay, well, then we have TensorFlow and TensorFlow Lite for different points of the process,
like both the workflows.
I am not going to go into all of the details, because I don't have a lot of time,
but just an important information.
TensorFlow Lite, it is an optimization of TensorFlow.
It is a simplification and also an optimization of that.
Take a look to the guide, TensorFlow, because it is very, very well explained
and it is super useful to understand it.
But this is not enough, because now we need to evaluate and optimize this model.
Imagine that we decided that our model was perfect, the one that I showed you,
we can detect it, everyone is happy, our metrics, everything is okay.
And we need to plan off our transits to put it inside the natural control.
There are different methodologies.
I am going to just focus in quantization, but there are also kernels and other systems.
In this case, what is the goal is a conversion that reduces the model size
in a way that you have a range of values and you fit all these values into one number.
And then what you are doing is converting your model of 30 to 16 or 32,
but also you are going to need to check your board to be sure that it is compatible.
More resources.
And if you are wondering, okay, but where would you work in all this time?
Of course, in my case, I was working in the
As a last point from the model deployment, one of the recommendations of TensorFlow Lite is a good example.
It's a business summary.
Generate a small TensorFlow that you can fit in your target device.
The important, always check that it's called fit.
Convert your model to TensorFlow Lite using the converter.
This is two lines of code.
Convert fit to fit and flash it to the microcontroller.
And then run the inference using the C++ and process the results.
This is one of the options, but it's not the only one.
This is what we were mentioning.
You are going to need to take a look to your business case and your business system.
With that, I'm going to finish.
Thank you so much.
Here is my information.
If you want to be in contact, I will be very happy.
Thank you so much.
We don't have enough time for questions, so we'll have the next session in 15 minutes.
But I guess if you want to report to Cedar later or something in the conference, you can do.
Thank you very much, Miriam.
Thank you.