Okay, we are in this time now to start our second to last talk of Python 2023.
The talk will be Supercharging Pipeline Efficiency with ML Performance Prediction with Boaz Wisner
and Geren Maron and they will be taking questions after the talk.
So if your questions after the presentation is over, please line up at the microphone
right here in the center and ask your questions.
So please join me in giving a warm round of applause to our speakers.
Thank you very much.
Okay, so hi everyone.
I'm sure all of you out there have some dear Python at work, right, and you've been busy these days
and I'm sure most of you have also experienced heavy loads and high queues in your system.
Well, today we're going to talk about how we supercharge our pipeline's efficiency
using machine learning performance prediction.
So my name is Karen Lavon.
I'm a software engineer at Cingular.
I live in San Antonio and I just got married just a month ago.
Thank you.
And I'm Boaz Wisner.
I'm a DevOps engineer at Cingular and also as an employee.
Thank you for doing life events.
I had a first born daughter three months ago.
Thank you.
I'm so glad.
Okay, so in order to understand what we're going to talk about today,
I just want to tell you what Cingular does and just the fun things.
So our clients are companies with marketing teams.
We need to pull their marketing data from over a dozen of ad networks
and combine that all into one big table in order to view and analyze their marketing data.
So at Cingular we do just that.
We pull ad campaign insights from over a thousand of ad networks,
process it through a pipeline which does things such as interpolation and combining of data.
And then all this in order to show our clients full knowledge of their marketing efforts
and their return on investment all in one.
So each server in our data pipeline consists of dedicated workers
which run tasks which are logically grouped.
So for example, all tasks pulling or pushing data for our Snowflake database are labeled Snowflake.
And then our workers are salary workers.
And for those of you who are not familiar with salary, salary is a task to implementation
which is used to execute tasks as an assignment.
And this we have now as right to the notice which is a containerized application
which is used for automating management, deployment, and scaling of containerized execution.
So it's important to note that our clients rely on their data from us on a timely matter
so they come to work at eight in the morning and they need to view their marketing data on Cingular
in order to make decisions on their current campaigns which they're writing.
So that means that all the tasks if you're running in our pipeline need to be finished on time
and they can't really be buried.
If there is, if there are any queues in our system, then at eight in the morning they won't have their data.
So what was our problem and what are we here to talk about in the first place anyways?
Well, we did experience queues in our system and when we investigated those queues, we saw something interesting.
We noticed that 90% of our tasks are light tasks in terms of duration and required memory,
and only 10% are heavy tasks.
This means that story tasks were getting stuck in the queue behind the longer tasks
and then smaller tasks were being affected by bigger tasks because their tasks wouldn't otherwise
finish on time and they wouldn't have had a data jury.
So we started thinking how we would solve this issue and the first thing we did actually
was humanly scale our workers.
The problem with that is that it's very expensive and it increases our cost and it's really not a scalable
and sustainable solution because we'd have to have our engineers scale the workers up and down all the time
because we don't really want to have an infinite amount of workers all the time.
So it really is not a big long-term solution.
The next thing we found was putting our tasks into smaller tasks which is a great design for this one,
but also here we realized that some of our tasks are already pretty small in terms of what we can do.
For example, if we have a task pulling data from a facelift API, first one is time-based,
then we're already pulling some one-day data from the minimum amount allowed,
and then one thing with more information.
So we finally realized what we really need to do and what would help us is have better resource management.
We need to be able to split up our tasks between the light tasks and the heavy tasks
in order to then better optimize each one of these groups according to their properties.
So for example, one of the things we could do is auto-scan and we'll talk more about that later on.
Okay, but how will we do this? So how will we differentiate between the light tasks and the heavy tasks?
Well, you could tell me what's the problem. Let's just create some static function which,
given some tasks, will tag it as light or heavy, and then obviously the tasks will have some input parameters.
So we can take those into account, take some pieces into account.
Well, that's not so simple because obviously we can have a very long list of parameters,
making it quite hard, but also some of these parameters have very high cardinality and variance,
meaning that a lot of possible values which could go in,
making that decision to be very, very impossible to do.
Another thing which makes this kind of hard to do is that we came together as tasks
so that the tasks are running together and the output of one task will be the input to the next task.
So that means that something which only happens during runtime,
and we can't possibly know how to statically know that ahead of time.
And obviously, not obviously, but the input to the task will have very significant effect on how long it's running for.
So then how will we solve this classification problem after all?
Well, we did decide to use machine learning.
So we played around with different models to see which one gave us the best results.
And in fact, it was a fairly simple model.
We used the support vector regression, SVL, model,
which is a supervised learning algorithm which is used to predict discrete values.
And what it does is try to find the helpful line in an n-dimensional space
which matches the necessary number of data points.
So the pros of the SVL are that it's robust to outliers, it's very effective in high dimension,
it's very easy to implement, and this is very important since we're trying to actually
productionize the model and not just only using the research.
On the other hand, the cons of the SVL are that it's not very suitable for large data sets
because it has fairly high training time and it doesn't perform well with noise.
So noise, in our case, would be, for example, a bug in the code,
which obviously is something which we should not have very often
and when it does happen, not exist for a very long time.
So that's why we're okay with noise.
Here you can see how we set up our model configuration.
So this is one test, for example.
We set this up for each task which we want to be able to differentiate
between the red and the heavy task.
So this is a straight supplement test which pulls data from third party networks.
And you can see we set up the parameters for this task,
the parameter feed down on epsilon which we played around featuring it while training our model.
The features, which are number of days and number of accounts.
And a deep parameter name, which is custom ID.
So this means that we train the model per customer.
Now we did start out trying to train one big model for all the customers together,
but that gave us not so good results because you can see how each customer's data
is very different from each other.
And then getting the series of values do not get good results.
And therefore we set up the model per customer.
So how did we choose our model, our features?
Well, we started out with the longest possible parameters for the task.
And here's an example of some of them.
And then played around with different combinations, feeding them to our model,
training them to see if they were the best results.
And we could get the number of days and number of accounts.
And since we're pulling data of customers, then you can see how that would have an immediate effect
in the amount of data pulled and how much time we take to process it.
So we did productionize the model, trained it for some time, and then use it in our pipeline.
Then after a while we were starting to see not so good results,
and we had to investigate what was happening, what did we forget?
And we found out that we did forget about something called an account.
So sort of an account, really big clients have a lot of apps,
so what they do is they split up the apps between accounts.
So each account is responsible for a certain number of apps.
And then at the end of the day we do something similar.
Instead of pulling data of the clients' data on one task, we pull data for a certain number of accounts.
So not only will the number of accounts change from task,
which is why we have the feature of the number of accounts,
but also the combination of accounts will change.
And some accounts can be really big, but some can be really small.
So that is why if we just take into account the number of accounts,
then if it's two accounts that sometimes are big, sometimes they're small,
we're not going to get good results.
So we were thinking, okay, how will we use the actual account as a feature to our model
and not only the number of accounts?
The first thing we found doing was leaving all permutations of the account empty.
The problem with this is that the account is a number, but it has no numerical significance.
So if you're using a number, the model will probably keep it as a number.
Therefore, getting really, you know, not so good results.
So next we tried to do something smarter.
We tried to take into account the total size of an account,
meaning how much friends is allocated to this account by the client.
The problem with this is that we can have one row of data with a total spend of $1,000,
or we could also have a thousand rows of data with a total spend of $10.
And if we're doing operations such as aggregations and several other data,
then it's taking more time to process this value of data.
So finally, we realized what we really need to do is know the expected row count,
which we're going to pull for the account.
So if we're pulling from third-party networks, we can't really know how much data we're going to pull.
I mean, if you're a fortune teller, that might work, but we're not.
So what we did is look into our database and see how much data we pulled for those accounts into these studies.
And then we used that as a feature to our model.
And we did do that, and we were getting kind of a model and we were getting good results.
So that was great.
So now Buzz will tell us a bit more about how we product-trived our data.
And then we'll talk a little bit more about how we product-trived the model,
and then how did we actually use this differentiation to lie in heavy tests in order to improve our 5 times efficiency.
Cool.
Hey, everyone.
That's Buzz, the proud guy here.
And so the first thing that's most important, product-triving the model,
is that we can't have the model's decision capability on your laptop time at all.
Because in that case, we're just slowing down all of our tests.
So we're going to have to do a lot of training architecture, and infrastructure has to happen, you know,
de-task or asygnomacy from data-saving process.
And it looks at it like this.
I hope it's not too scary of a graph, but we're going to break it down step by step.
So the first thing that happens at the end of every celery task, we have something called a task info collector.
And it's just some custom code that we wrote that collects the relevant metadata for each task.
Things like the duration or memory, which is what we actually want to use this anyway.
It then takes that metadata and puts it into S3, which is AWS's object storage.
AWS also has a neat tool called Asena, which allows you to use SQL queries and run SQL queries over data settings in S3.
And we'll utilize that actually right now in kind of a meat and potatoes of this whole infrastructure,
the performance predictors train runner.
This is a celery task that we run periodically, once a day, for each customer.
And it is responsible for actually creating and recreating the model.
And the way that it works is as such.
First, it queries S3 using Asena, gathers the data for the past day, and builds a data set out of it.
It then takes the existing model and takes the new data and trains and retrains the model to have all the updated information.
So in this way, if something changes or something would become heavier instead of light,
then it would pick up on this, since we run this task periodically.
Now, finally, once a performance predictor train runner is done, it saves the entire model into a Redis database.
Now, since the model is per customer, then the serialized model can be pretty small and actually fit into the value of a Redis.
So we just have the key being the customer ID and the value just being the entire serialized model.
Now, the last piece of the puzzle is the celery router.
The celery router is the bit of celery code that runs every time that a new task is received,
and it tries to decide to which queue to send the celery task.
And we wrote some custom code there that all it does is it gets the task, it takes the customer ID from the task,
gets the model from Redis, and runs the task parameters to the model and makes the decision based on the output of the model,
should it be a classified as light or heavy, and then sends it to the light queue or the heavy queue,
which have dedicated workers consuming from them.
Now, finally, for all this to take, we need to monitor our model predictions and make sure they stay accurate.
So we compare the predicted duration of memory with the actual duration of memory using RNSE, or Root Mean Square Error.
This error level gets too high, but we're alerted and we dive in to investigate.
So, I mean, it works, right? We have split our tasks into light and heavy queues.
We have dedicated celery workers for each type of queue, and in that way we solve a problem,
no balling task load up, and data delay for our customers.
So that's great. And we decided to start looking a bit more into the future and start talking maybe a bit about auto scaling.
So auto scaling in general is the ability to increase and decrease capacity based on real-time parameters.
So, an example of classical auto scaling is that a bunch of web servers behind a load balancer,
and my web server is running hot and will run to load, then auto scaling would just automatically spin up a few more web servers to handle the load, and that would be that.
In celery, we need to scale the number of workers up and down,
since those are the things that are actually consuming from the queue and doing the actual work.
Now, how do you even bother with auto scaling?
Well, if I put the fact that I'm upside down, just saying the word auto scaling makes my heart happy.
It has actual legit reasons.
So, first of all, it reduces queues in times of heavy load, and the queues go up,
then it will automatically scale and bring up more workers to bring the queues down quicker.
Additionally, it has increased multi-tenancy resource utilization,
so I can take two jobs and run them on the same underlying infrastructure,
and I can set one job to start working really hard at one point while the other one isn't,
and then vice versa, the other one will work really hard while the first one isn't,
but they could both run on the same underlying infrastructure without bothering each other.
Auto scaling lets you do that really efficiently.
And finally, there's no manual intervention necessary.
I mean, we've all been there, middle of the night, if you get paid, you wake up at 3am,
and you click the plus button, terrible, auto scaling solves it, and then everyone's happier.
Happy engineers can have your fun.
Okay, so auto scaling in celery is a little bit different than classical auto scaling.
First of all, we have to scale based on the queue length metric.
That's what determines the load of our system, not necessarily the CPU or memory of the underlying infrastructure.
Secondly, it's only cost effective for short tasks.
Now in our data pipeline, we have an axiom that we don't want to interrupt long-running tasks.
If a task takes one, two, or three hours to run, then you wouldn't want to kill it in order to scale down,
because then you lose those two or three hours of work, and now it's done.
So auto scaling only would work for short tasks.
But since we now split into light and heavy tasks, and 90% of our pipeline is light,
then hey, we can like auto scale 90% of our pipeline, which is pretty awesome.
Now let's take a quick look at the architecture needed to auto scale celery on Kubernetes.
Now the most important component is the horizontal pod auto scaler,
which is responsible for automatically adding and removing pods.
In our environment, one pod, or container, is one celery worker, which is consuming tasks from the queue.
And as I mentioned, we want to scale based on queue length.
The queue length of all of our metrics is stored in Datadog, a fast, monolayer solution.
They provide the Datadog transfer agent, which sections the queue length from Datadog
and exposes it to Kubernetes through the Datadog metric CRD, or custom resource definition.
CRDs are the Kubernetes way to expose external data through the Kubernetes API.
Now then all you have to do is attach the horizontal pod auto scaler to that CRD,
and it will begin auto scaling based on queue length metric.
The last piece of the puzzle is the cluster auto scaler.
If the horizontal pod auto scaler adds too many pods, and there is not enough underlying capacity to run them,
the cluster auto scaler catches this and scales up a new AWS instance to run on.
And just like that, everything works.
This is the actual metric used by auto scaler.
Those who are a sharper buy will notice that it's a moving roll up.
This is because queue lengths tend to be very spiky, and they go up and down a lot,
and that would make the auto scaler go up and down a lot and kind of work a bit unpredictably.
So moving things out with like a rolling average window makes everything work more predictably.
And at the bottom you see the number of running pods.
There's a very clear correlation here, right?
The number, the queue goes up, the number of running pods goes up, queue goes down, number of running pods goes down.
Another really interesting thing to note here is that the queue has to go up first before the number of running pods goes up.
This is, it means it's like it's inherently reactive, and it's kind of a constraint of that split end to scaling based on queue length,
but it does work, and it's pretty effective.
And last, but definitely not least for maybe some of the people in the crowd here, cost optimization.
So AWS actually has some useful spot instances which are essentially spare compute capacity that they offer at a fraction of the cost,
which is one added caveat that they can interrupt your instance within a three or four minute notice.
But now, since we split our tasks into light and heavy, and they are short jobs that are running on auto scaling servers
and they'll spell healing, then we don't care if the underlying instance dies because our infrastructure will just handle it.
So you can utilize spot instances and really cut down on applied costs.
So we've kind of been through a lot today, so let's take a look at the top and sum up this quickly.
We had queues and resource contention causing racism production.
We had heavy tasks that were holding up light tasks and causing data delays for our customers.
I used machine learning to predict the task performance and then send the task to dedicated workers based on
if it is expected to be a light task or a heavy task.
And finally, we were able to auto scale our light tasks with Kubernetes,
thus auto scaling about 90% of our pipeline and just making everything work more efficiently,
federal resource utilization, web waking up at night and all the wonderful things.
So what does the future hold?
Well, one thing that we could do is we could implement some kind of auto scaling predictor based on
few length patterns or a few time to follow patterns throughout the day, and so that holds true for many people.
And we could solve that problem of reactivity I mentioned earlier by knowing to predict when the spikes are
and then scaling in advance.
So implementing that could help with that. It was pretty cool.
So that's it. Thank you so much for listening.
Our mails are up there if you're too shy to ask any questions, but we're here and we're going to answer any questions you have.
So again, thank you so much.
Thank you.
This is a kind of clarifying question about your usage of spell instances.
You said you've got a few-to-four-minute notification that you're going to lose that instance.
Are your jobs usually shorter than that?
So you expect them to compute?
Or are they so short that it doesn't matter if they're killed and have to spend over?
Yeah, they're so short and then we just don't care.
It's really not the case.
We do also make sure, we do have alerts on if something goes wrong, then we'll see if our tasks are taking,
if our tasks are taking too long but are running on our spot instances, then we'll see and we'll notice and we'll fix things.
Right?
They're usually too short.
Are you using platform or other infrastructure as code to create these?
So we use CoP, which is a Kubernetes operator, like we place Kubernetes using configuration.
That's what we use to build this infrastructure mostly.
It allows you to just pass parameters saying, just see your spot instances, you see spot instances,
run them like this and all the other, you know, sort of things.
A question about the spot open, do we update the classification in mobile?
Do we update in our failure or like...
Yeah.
So the training we actually do like once a day, we run and we train the model on the failure task,
which has run now on the previous day and then like we run it in all the tasks that have run on the previous day.
And then the routing is done for each task.
So a task is created and then if anything, once it reaches the router, which we have implemented routers before,
we still have other, we still have other routers for routing it.
So then on that router, we will actually use the model for each single task and then dedicate it for the queue,
which is supposed to be a queue.
Hi.
As we were developing this, did you have issues with things like when you have the spot instances, if they go down,
how do you check to make sure you haven't run something through your queue twice or is it okay if something gets rerun
and how did you kind of deal with like any errors that happen in this pipeline along the way?
Yeah.
So the tasks which we have in this specific pipeline, it is okay that if they're running more than once,
we have a recovery system and dedications, which makes sure that it's okay and that's why we don't care if a task is killed.
It's okay if it's run again.
So you mentioned that you're monitoring in place to kind of like monitor some models or like drifting or something.
So, how often have you been notified about a wait and how often have you had to kind of like adjust something
since you've done like this?
Yeah, so usually, so the answer is almost not at all.
It all works pretty automatically.
And that's because since we reach frame, since we reach frame the model every day, then we expect it to,
if something really does start to skew, then the model will get that metadata, reach frame the existing model
with that new metadata and then it will already just start splitting it correctly.
So it doesn't really happen.
Yeah, and mostly when we do these tasks, if we run out on to our solo time, because we don't have all of our tasks using the model,
we like add each one at a time and we think that it needs the optimization.
So then at first, obviously, the error is silent and then we have like two things like, for example,
with the account or the next frame.
And once we sort that out, then it just ends.
Yeah, we have like a pre-train period where we just train the model and don't split.
Like we don't send it to split.
We have a new task and we want to just train and gather data.
So we just do that first.
We train the model without actually sending it to separate queues.
And then we can like enable it, like the feature files and okay, now it actually starts splitting the new task.
Good question.
Okay, so thank you again.
I want to send it.
Thank you.