Can you hear me? Hello? Great. Hello everyone. Welcome to the afternoon sessions for the talks.
So our next speaker is Dan Craig. He's worked in aerospace and web development.
And so his title of this next talk is called Testing Spacecraft at the PI-COP.
So if you can give him a round of applause and welcome him.
Thanks everyone. Good afternoon. It's a real pleasure to be here.
My name is Dan Craig. I'm a software engineer at Vardo Space Industries.
We are building the world's first on orbit industrial park.
Our goal is to be able to leverage microgravity for manufacturing materials for use here on Earth.
This is our first spacecraft, the Winnebago 1. It consists of two parts.
The first part is a reentry capsule on the top that contains the manufacturing apparatus.
Made into a Rocket Lab photon satellite bus on the bottom.
That's the gold part, which is the satellite or the solar panels there.
That provides the power, propulsion, communications and guidance.
Winnebago scheduled to launch this June on a Falcon 9 ride share.
It will stay on orbit for a month or more.
It will perform a pharmaceutical manufacturing operation.
The capsule will separate and parachute back to Earth, landing out in the desert here in Utah.
Now obviously we are doing our best to make sure that this mission is successful.
Naturally that involves a lot of testing.
For those of us on the software team, that involves a lot of software testing.
We're fortunate that we have tremendous access to tools available to us to make this possible.
Python and PyTest are two big ones that we take advantage of.
I'll talk about that later in the talk.
But it's important for us to keep in mind that a lot of the discourse around software testing
over the last 20 years has been dominated by web services.
And web services are great, but we need to be considerate of the differences and similarities
between testing a web service and testing a spacecraft.
Now you might not think there are any similarities between testing a web service
and testing a spacecraft, but you'd be surprised.
Both tend to be remote from the user.
Your web server is off in a data center or in a cloud.
Your spacecraft is off above the clouds.
Both tend to work on a request-response interface.
And spacecraft, of course, defend screens with telemetry,
not unlike a modern, well-instrumented web service.
There are big differences though.
Consistency of network connectivity is one of them.
A spacecraft really only has a consistent network connection when it's over a ground station.
And depending on your orbit, that might only be a few times a day.
You also generally have no physical access to your spacecraft,
assuming it's an unfroened spacecraft like a satellite.
So there's nobody who can go in and push the reset button if you're really in a pinch.
And lastly, the impact that a single occurrence or a single defect can have on your spacecraft
is very different from what it can have on a web service.
And I like to think about this as like putting it on an axis here about the volume and criticality.
Volume here being the number of requests or operations that your software is performing.
Compared to the criticality of any one of those requests or operations having or failing
because of a defect.
The most web services operate down here on the bottom.
They're high volume, low criticality.
So take for example a social media API or something where you might have thousands or millions of users
making millions of requests to your API.
And if you introduce a bug in the production that starts to cause some of those to fail,
like you know, it might be a bummer for some of those users.
Like maybe they don't get to make their posts or their feed doesn't refresh.
But that's not really the end of the world.
And because you're just such high volume, most of your users may not even know that the bug ever happened.
Because spacecraft are sort of on the opposite side of that.
There's low volume, high criticality.
You might only have one spacecraft that you're working with and you're performing one operation,
like a rocket launch or a reentry capsule during the reentry sequence.
You're only going to do that one time.
And it has to work that very one time that it counts.
Otherwise the results could be disastrous.
For example, June 1st, or 4th, 1996 was the maiden launch of the RAN-5 rocket.
37 seconds into flight, this happened.
So what happened here?
Well, the RAN-5 borrowed a lot from the RAN-4, its predecessor, including its initial measurement unit.
In the IMU software was an fast alignment routine that could be used to do a quick recycle of a launch countdown after an abort.
RAN-5 didn't need this capability, but the software was left in for commonality reasons,
and besides it was well tested and had flight heritage on RAN-4.
Initial alignment routine was a type conversion of a horizontal bias value from a float 64 to a science-based 16.
On the RAN-4, that bias value was small.
On the larger, faster RAN-5, it was bigger, resulting in an overflow exception.
And the software had been designed conservatively to detect that the IMU would shut down in the event of an unhandled exception,
which it did, leaving the rocket flying blind.
So, the RAN-5 was a very fast alignment routine, not knowing which way it was pointed, the engines dimpled hard over, and aerodynamic forces tore it apart.
Now you might wonder, like, wasn't there a backup? IMU on board? How come that didn't save it?
Well, there was a backup IMU on board, but it was running the same software, experiencing the same physics, and it shut down at exactly the same time.
So what can we learn from this?
Well, this has become a classic example of how software defects can be very different from hardware defects.
So, we know that there was a random failure of some parts that broke because it didn't meet specifications.
The software performed exactly as it was specified.
The problem was that the specifications were wrong.
Now, it would be a whole other topic, several PSV systems, about how you can prove that your specifications are correct,
and I'm not going to get into that here, but there's another lecture that we can take away for our purposes here,
and that's that the operating environment that your software is running in is just as important as the code itself for its successful execution.
So if your operating environment is different from what you tested and analyzed,
it might be irrelevant or misleading, and it will lead you into a false sense of confidence, as it did for the R1.5 developers.
You have to test your software in the environment that it will be used when it actually is running in production.
Example number two.
The Planetary Society's Lightsail 1 launched May 20, 2015.
This is a cube stat that was designed to demonstrate the deployment of a solar sail,
a thin, mylar sheet that can harness the momentum of the solar wind for its propulsion.
Six days into its flight, it went silent.
Well, what happened?
Well, Lightsail 1 was every 15 seconds would send a telemetry beacon message,
and it beautifully logged that message to a CSV file.
The problem was that nothing was rotating that file, so it grew unbounded until it filled up the 32 megabytes of disk on the flight computer.
Once that happened, the spacecraft became unresponsive, including unresponsive to the reboot commands being sent from the ground.
So the operators put their last hope in a radiation hit, triggering a reboot, which is not unusual in spaceflight.
And eight agonizing days later, it finally rebooted,
and they were able to reestablish contacts and schedule additional reboots before the disk showed backup,
and then they could deploy a fifth, and ultimately they went on to have a successful mission.
So what can we learn here?
Well, one is that software defects can be accumulated over time.
So if you have a really fast test suite, which I hope all of you do, and you can't have test cases run in seconds,
you might never notice that your disk is going to fill up over the course of six days.
The other lesson we can take here is a positive one, which is that having the ability to deploy a filth to your bug
can make the difference between success and failure.
Example number three, Boeing Starliner's global flight class, December 20, 2019.
Starliner was on its maiden voyage untrue, here a straight down flight, before sending crew to the International Space Station.
While it was on the CAD, it synchronized its mission-alapsed time clock with its Atlas V booster.
The problem was that it synchronized it too early, before the actual T-zero time had been set,
resulting in Starliner and Atlas thinking that they were 11 hours apart on the mission timeline.
At separation, the spacecraft thought it was in the wrong place seemingly at the wrong time,
and the navigation system tried its best to put it back into the right place,
by spending enough propellant to rule out a safe rendezvous to the International Space Station.
So how did this happen?
Well, it seems that there was never any integrated testing between Starliner and the Atlas V under a launch scenario.
So the lesson we can take away from this is that we can't just test to an interface.
We must test across interfaces, because different teams may have different understandings of that same interface.
And that there's just no substitute for integrated hardware and the loop testing.
And what matters to you is, for a successful mission, is the end-to-end performance of your system.
So you should be testing to the extent possible end-to-end.
And if you can't do that, then you need to have overlapping integrated tests.
And really, a good example here, like you're testing for systems A and B and B and C,
the tests have to overlap, otherwise you have a gap if you're not testing across every interface.
So now it's easy to pick on these projects, and there have been many other software failures in spaceflight before.
It's easy to pick on them in retrospect, because we know how they failed,
and we can go figure out from the data what the causal change of events was that it ultimately caused it.
And as Nancy Leveson pointed out, the cause of any accident is kind of by definition the thing you didn't test for.
So, yeah, it's easy to look at that in retrospect.
But in advance, which was marked here, there's a lot of different ways that your system might fail.
And so ultimately, you're asking the question of, will it succeed when it actually runs in production?
And this is a prediction, and your verification process is a prediction,
and specifically your prediction or answering the question here,
when running in a production environment under production load, will it perform as intended?
There's three acceptable answers to this.
No, maybe, and probably.
Yes is not an acceptable answer to this question, because our prediction is what the philosopher Karl Popper would call
a defiable hypothesis, that it can be disproven, but it can never really be proven.
Like we may collect corroborating evidence out of fruit passing test cases,
or we may know that the software doesn't even compile, so there's no way it would ever run in production.
But we can never be sure how it's going to perform in production until we put it into production.
So what we're left with is having confidence in our predictions.
And hopefully we are somewhere along this continuum here between, you know,
no, it's definitely not going to work, or probably almost certainly it's going to work there.
And we can move ourselves along that and gain confidence through the more corroborating evidence we have
and the more lack of refuting evidence that we have, despite rigorous attempts to gain it,
the more confidence that we have before we release this into production.
So now we have to ask, how much confidence do we really need?
And now you might think, well, why not go fulfill confidence?
The problem is that gaining confidence costs effort and time, and that costs money.
And if it doesn't really matter if you get it wrong, why would you waste all that time and effort
trying to make sure that you're 99% right that it's going to succeed?
So I'm going to offer the following questions, kind of as a rubric, to think about how much confidence do we need.
And I'm going to deliberately avoid being quantitative about it.
I think you can mislead yourself with false precision.
But for these questions, the kind of answer to dry this through.
Do you need more confidence or do you need not so much confidence here?
So we'll start with the basics.
Can your software kill or injure someone?
And can it cause property damage?
If it's so, you need more confidence before you release this into production.
Can it cause large financial loss?
And are the damages that it could cause, are they irreversible here?
If so, then you need more confidence.
How critical is it that it works the very first time in production?
This kind of goes back to the criticality volume part from earlier that for a rocket,
the first time it's in production under production load is when it's lifting off from the cloud, flying into space.
Everything else is just changing.
So you need it to work that one and only one time.
For a lot of web services, we can take a lot of steps to reduce the criticality
if it's running the first time into production.
And there's been a kind of good produce that have been developed over the years.
So we have rolling deployments, feature flags, deploying to production before you release.
All of those techniques are really good.
And what they accomplish is reducing the criticality of that very first time it operates in production.
How closely can you test environment match production?
In our space, we talk about this a lot, about tests as you fly and flies as you test.
But it can be really hard for satellites in particular because we are operating in vacuum
and microgravity in a high radiation environment and thermal extremes.
And you can simulate some of that on the ground, but it's really hard to get it right
and to get it to test the complete package.
And so we need a lot more confidence going into it because we don't know exactly how it will behave in that environment.
How frequently does the software run in production?
This is on the volume side of that.
So it's not like if the software runs the same operation over and over and over,
you can gain confidence through each one of those operations over time.
But if it only does one, it operates one time, on that one time the rocket is launching,
or during the reentry sequence of the reentry vehicle, it's got to get it right that one time.
And so you need more confidence going in before you limit.
But how easy is it to roll out a change that made the difference for the light cell phones?
And it's something that should be really easy in the web software world, but it's unfortunately not.
And a lot of people do get stuck in that business cycle of their deployments are slow and painful,
so you do them less often.
You need higher confidence before you can deploy, spreading out your time, and it's a cycle on and on and on.
And when you're developing spacecraft, it can be very easy to de-scope on-orbit software update
because it's not a trivial thing to implement.
But in my opinion, it's one of the most valuable features that you can have on your spacecraft software.
How embarrassing is it if you need to roll out a fix?
So even if you have the fastest, easiest deployment cycle at all,
if you're, say, a financial institution or a password manager or provider,
having a bug in production can be devastatingly embarrassing to you.
And lastly, who do you need to convince that your software will be successful?
For most of us, that's just our teammates or our managers or others in our company.
But when you're dealing with safety-critical software, there's often regulatory oversight involved.
And remember, the regulator's job is not to help you be successful.
The regulator's charge is to protect the general public from you and from your potential failure.
And they do this by asking that you follow good engineering practices,
that you follow through on testing your software and your system to show that it will be safe.
And so they need to be able to see that you did what you said you were going to do,
and that involves leaving an audit file, so leaving evidence behind of your testing, of your review, of your analysis.
All right. So how do we at VARTA take approach to gaining confidence here?
Well, we've defined the follow-on lightweight process for our team.
We have two sets of eyes on every change, three if it's a high-impact change.
We put our emphasis on hardware-on-the-loop testing for all of our ranks for record.
We do have unit tests, and those are useful for kind of supplemental confidence.
So HIDL is really where it's at for the actual value of providing full confidence.
We run our full suite of hardware-on-the-loop tests regularly,
and we try as much as possible to avoid spending an effort trying to justify not running a test
because it's time consuming, right?
Now, we do have regular soak tests that have a long duration that cover well beyond the time
from when we would power up the satellite to when we would be able to perform a software test.
We have the ability to perform a software update.
And we have the philosophy of never doing anything for the first time on the vehicle.
Always do it in one of our test environments first.
All right. So what would our – how do we get to a hardware-on-the-loop test environment for our vehicle?
So I mentioned before that our spacecraft assistants have two pieces.
There's the capsule and the bus.
And so if we were going to design a hardware-on-the-loop test rig for the capsule,
we would start here looking at the actual satellite.
And then we would start designing interfaces between the capsule and the bus.
There's the data for commanding its telemetry between the capsule and the bus.
And then the bus provides power to the capsule to charge up the batteries
and to run in its normal operation while made.
Now, inside our capsule is what we call the capsule controller,
and that's supposed to be our main electronics board.
And it has two different separate computers on it,
which we refer to as either nodes or strings coming in interchangeably, so node A and node B.
And both of those computers can be wired up to different peripheral devices like a GPS or an IMU.
They can both fire the pyros to deploy the parachute.
And they can both run on the batteries on the capsule once the capsule is separated from the bus during the re-entry sequence.
To turn this into a hardware-on-the-loop test bed,
we would take all the components of our capsule and lay them out on the table.
So we would have our controller and we would have our GPS and our IMU also wired up on the table.
We'll substitute the pyro's spin for the actual pyro so that we can just see electrically where they were fired.
And then we have a test draft that can provide the data and power interfaces
through just a test server with the serial of course,
and then some commandable power supplies and switches to act as the simulated bus and battery power.
And this is what the table looks like in practice.
You see the rack there on the right, the table here, the sticker boards on the front of the table are the pyro spins,
and the controller is behind the gray panel right on the center of the screen.
So we want to run these regularly, and that means automatically.
And so an auto-hiddle, the kind of sequence of events that we would want to achieve in an auto-hiddle, looks something like this.
We're going to power up the controller.
We're going to flash the new version of the software and the test on to it.
We're going to start out some of our helper software, like our ground software for commanding.
We're going to run a series of test cases where these have their own specific setup and tear down steps.
Then we'll stop the ground software, power off the controller, and generate a report.
Now if this kind of sounds like a good use case for your PyTest picture, you are exactly right.
We make extensive use of, we implement a different PyTest to make extensive use of PyTest pictures.
Now if you're not familiar with PyTest pictures, they're a way of defining setup and tear down steps for your test cases.
And you define a function, and you can run setup steps up to a point where it either returns or it yields.
You can return or yield an object that the consumer of the fixture can then operate on later.
And if you have a yield statement in, then your function executes up to the yield, then your test case runs,
and then after your test case is completed, it comes back and runs the steps after the yield to perform a tear down step.
And so this is an example of one of our fixtures.
This is the one that starts by telemetry a decoder, and it's just alternating with the decoder, starting and it's on thread,
and then yielding it so that other fixtures and tests can work on it, and then afterwards stopping the thread and waiting for it to complete.
And another great part of PyTest is the execution order of these fixtures.
You define fixtures can depend on other fixtures, and test cases can depend on test cases or on other fixtures.
And so the execution order of all of them is determined by the dependency graph of these fixtures and tests.
So another aspect of PyTest fixtures that we make cutting use of is the scoping of fixtures.
So you can scope things so that they run either like once per session per run of PyTest.
And so we do that for flashing the controller.
We don't want to do that for every single test function.
We can run things at the module level, like when we want to switch a configuration,
so we put the capsule on battery power and run a series of tests that are in that file.
We can run it at the cost level, if you want to do a one-time fixture set up and then run a group of parameterized tests,
we'll all use that same fixture.
And we'd probably make plenty of use of the function level fixtures as well.
Here's another example of one of our fixtures.
This is the flash board fixture, and it demonstrates a couple of new features of PyTest.
One is that we can put in a command line flag and put PyTest, a custom flag, and tell it to not flash the board,
which is really useful if we're trying to iterate on tests and we don't want to spend the time re-flashing the controller every time we run the test.
And then you'll notice that all the rest of these fixtures that are being tested are being called as functions.
And this is another PyTest feature called factory fixtures that we make a lot of use of.
Now factory fixture is when your fixture returns a function that then the caller or the dependent on that fixture can then call at their will.
And a really nice feature of this is that now your fixture can depend on other fixtures.
So this one on the top, this one is the powering on the screen and the fixture on our capsule.
So it needs the switch relay session object to be able to connect a certain relay to power it on.
But the consumer of that, this kind of bus powering that calls those two, the power on for the two different strings,
it doesn't need to know that. It doesn't need to know the power on the screen depends on the real assistant.
It doesn't take any arguments. It just does what it's told.
And there's a really nice side benefit of that, which is that you can override fixtures to accomplish things like running on different test beds.
So the usefulness here is that we want to run the same test case on different test beds with different configurations.
We already talked about the capsule huddle where we have real capsule hardware, where we have a simulated bus and simulated power.
And then we can turn on power to the capsule by commanding these switches and power supplies.
You have a different test bed that's an integrated capsule and bus hardware in the loop that has real bus hardware going together.
Now a bus does respond to commands, but it's very different. It's not commanding a switch on a relay.
It's a different way of implementing the same request to power on the screen.
Or we have our developer boards that we have at our desk, which is kind of like huddle and it involves a simulated bus.
But we don't have the fancy commandable power supplies and switches. We just have a little hand operated switch.
So we can implement this by defining three different folders under our test cases.
One's for huddle, one for flat size, what we call the integrated capsule and bus environment, and our desk folder here.
We can define our test case once in one of those folders and then just import it into the other folders.
And then this is where the magic happens, where we define that same fixture three different times.
So the one on the top is the fixture for how we're running in our capsule huddle environment, where we want to turn on the switch to close that relay.
In the middle is how we would do it in the integrated software environment, where we need to send the command to the bus.
And on the bottom we just prompt the user to flip the switch.
And so now it makes it very easy for us to test the runnings test on these different environments.
Another feature of PyTest that we make the most sense of is parameterizing the test.
And the use case here is that our pyro systems have a lot of layers of redundancy.
So we have two controller nodes, I've already mentioned, different computers that both can fire the pyros.
They can both do it at the same time or they can individually do it if the other one is done.
And each of those nodes is also looking at a majority vote of three different separation computers.
So there's a lot of combinations of ways that we could either correctly fire or not fire the pyros that we want to test.
The solution for this is to parameterize those tests across all of those different combinations of inputs.
And we can do this like these tests here, where we can have different tests for running the full pyros,
like just a single string one or two out of three separations.
And we can implement all of that multiplication of it by just having different groups of inputs here to these same tests.
So it can really do a good job of decreasing the verbosity and repetition of each test sheet.
But sometimes that's not enough. Sometimes we need to still be true verbose there.
And this is where parameterized chips here can come into play.
So here we have, I guess we have two different computers on the Casper controller.
And so we end up wanting to run a lot the same tests on both of those nodes together.
And so does that mean I have to parameterize my entire, you know, every single test in my test suite?
No, I can parameterize one fixture and have the rest of my tests depend on that.
So here's an example of this one where we have this test loop that's here that runs, you know, depends on the node.
And then we have a node one that is a parameterized fixture that does cap A and cap B, the two different nodes over four.
And the nice part about this is that my test course now doesn't really have to know or care that it's actually depending on a parameterized fixture.
It just does it depending on a node. And as long as you pass in that string, it's happy.
Right. Moving out of some process, so one common pattern that a lot of our test pictures or test results have is that they send a command
and take some action and then wait for that action to take its effect and be observable in Client Tree.
And unlike say an HTTP request, there's no like blocking the response that we get.
So we send the command and we just have to wait until the frame of Client Tree changes.
And we don't want to wait and kind of fix them at all time.
We kind of like to see the Client Tree coming. We like to await the change.
And so we implemented this in a context manager that we called Client Tree Becker.
But when it enters the context, it starts accumulating the Client Tree that's being collected by a Client Tree processor running in a separate thread.
And now we can provide a generator that can yield all this collected Client Tree points and any future points as they arrive.
And we can wrap that with some things to help filter down to just the points that we care about.
And we further wrap that with some test assertion helpers that can say assert when we receive an acknowledgement message
or assert that a particular channel eventually equals a certain value.
And the code for this is really small. This part here is just a setup of the context manager here.
We're sending a deck because that's a thread phase list that we can attend to.
And then this generator that iterates over the points, this is this.
We're iterating over the deck and then once we hit the end, we'll sweep for a little bit and check in again to see if any points have been attended
until we run to our timeout.
And now we can just start using some of the magic of Python. So like make another generator that filters that down
to just the points that we want. We can call next on that to get the first matching point there.
And now our assertion helpers can just call the first and say if you want to check once you get an awk,
look for the first matching point that matches the acknowledgement.
And this makes for a really clean and simple API for a test office.
So you can instantiate the telemetry buffer, the context manager, execute your commands,
and just assert all your telemetry values coming back.
We use some PyTest extensions here. We use PyTest HTML for generating reports.
We've customized it a little bit with some links. I'll create Grafana here.
We can use other cool things with Grafana passwords here by putting some annotations about our test values here
that can actually give you the test value message.
And we do this through the magic of PyTest Hooks.
And specifically here, there are expectant interactions, our interactive hook that can make that annotation
and send it out to the telegraph.
Okay. So this is kind of where our current test suite is at right now.
And we've been using this for about a year and we've been very happy with it.
We have plenty of future improvements that we could make.
One, I'd like to start adding some more leveraging these annotations more.
And so we could start with testing test assertions and annotations as well.
We actually experimented with that just a little bit.
And the problem was we had a really high rate of assertions sometimes that could overwhelm the telegraph
and just do it better. So we'll figure out how to solve that one day.
I'd like to add a log handler to create the Grafana annotations from log statements
so that people who are reviewing data can follow along the sequence of events
by looking at the timeline.
I see data review fixtures or decorators is something we're very interested in.
And this is for not just asserting on the specific condition that the test goes to use,
but for checking other health studies as well, like do we reboot accidentally or generally middle of a test
or did our CPU spike or something like that, just not specific to the particular test.
And we might end up implementing that as some form of a fixture or decorator.
By the way, I'd love to start collecting code coverage on our actual capsule software while it's running in Hittles.
We already collect code coverage on our ground software because that's all written in Python.
And coverage.py is awesome.
We'll probably do some custom HTML reports at some point.
I'd love to start embeddings linked to Grafana directly in the test output.
And then lastly, our test suite has been growing.
It takes a lot longer to run.
And so we want to know where is that time going, you know, the ways we could maybe shorten it or optimize some of our tests.
And recently started experimenting a week ago with PyTest Open telemetry that can produce a nice expand part here
of a bigger UI telling us where the time of our test cases are going.
So that is probably something that we'll be looking at much closer this summer.
And I think I am exactly on the time here.
So thank you for coming. I hope this was interesting.
So I'll be around in the hall if anybody wants to ask questions or talk more.
So happy to do so. Thanks.