Okay. It's 9 o'clock. Let's get started. Good morning, everybody. Welcome to PyCon 2023
from my side. My name is Mike Moller and I will be your tutorial instructor for this
morning. So we're going to look at object-oriented programming in Python, how we do it and why
we do it. First, I would like to start with a short introduction from my side that you
already know who's talking here for three hours. And then I'm going to get a little bit of
overview over your Python skills and expectations. So I've been a dedicated Python user since
1999. So I can always claim since the last millennium. So I started with version 1.52.
I still remember. Yeah, that was my first book in April 1999. I don't have it anymore.
I lent it to somebody and didn't get it back. I don't remember to whom. But this would be
like a historical document because I started. And then I programmed pretty much on a daily basis.
And it happened that in 2004, I gave my first training. So of course, I gave some lectures at
university already, some other stuff. And so I kind of said, okay, why not give a Python training?
And I gave a Python training. So the thing developed. 2006, I founded Python Academy,
which is the logo here. And since 2010, I do this full-time. And currently, we have quite a
few other trainers in Python Academy. So we are a team of trainers training Python. And we
specialize in Python. And we do some tutorials like this, but also introduction to Python,
advanced Python, a lot of scientific and data science topics, SQL, testing is a big topic,
database programming in general, size and programming, high-performance programming,
this Python and so on. Okay, that's about me. I would like to get a short overview about the
people in the room. I just asked you how long you use Python, which is not a really good measure,
but better than nothing. So please raise your hand if you program Python less than one year.
Oh, that's like 20% or so between one and three years. So if you use Python on a more regular
basis, yeah, that's more between three and five. Also more than five. And that's my minority. Okay,
so kind of distribution more people that don't use Python extensively long, which is kind of
expected. Good. Let's go. I have a few slides. And then I explain a little bit how we're going to do
it. I talk a little bit about the objectives. So the objective is here to learn the basics of
object-oriented programming. And so we look at how to create a class. We look at a concept of
inheritance, which is an important concept in object-oriented programming. We look at operator
overloading or the special methods. So operator overloading is actually a little bit too narrow,
we will see, but very often used this term. And the way we do it, we start with a procedural code.
So I will give you a short procedural code, short procedural code, which is working already. And then
we step-by-step convert it to a more object-oriented solution, see if it's getting better anyway. So if
it's worth it to do or how we do it, and then see how much it gets better or if you like it better,
if it feels better, works better, whatever you think is better. So we learn about advantages and
also maybe disadvantages. A few years ago here at PyCon, the talks like don't write classes,
which is like the direct opposite of what I'm doing here. So at disclaimer, I also teach a full
day of functional programming in Python. So Python has some functional features and I like them,
and they are useful and it very much depends on the task at hand. So Python supports multiple
paradigms, some functional, pretty full selection of object-oriented features, and you can use them
and you can combine them. And you learn some basic techniques of object-oriented design, how to
design the program. So we only have three hours for the whole thing, including some exercises,
so that cannot be like a multi-week design course, obviously. But I give you some basic things to
understand that might be useful to design programs. Good. So we start with an example code. I will go
to the, show you pretty soon. It works already. So we go through this example code, a few minutes
that you understand. Hopefully it's not too difficult, not just the hell of a world, yeah,
that's too simple, but not a very complex thing. We spend three hours just trying to understand
what a thing is doing. That's not going to work either. So we have to have some in between. It's
still a toy example to some degree, but you will see you could make it way more complex very easily.
Yeah, so in the real world things tend to become more complex. Then we convert it into object-oriented
code and we apply these principles when we do this. And hopefully this is useful and you see how this
works. A few words about this programming paradigms. If you go to Wikipedia, you find more like 70 or
so different paradigms. There are different kind of hierarchies and structures and stuff, and there
are different names. These are the main names you might see. So we have these big groups, imperative
programming and declarative programming. By far the most people do more or less imperative programming.
Procedural programming, that's rewrite your function, you call your functions in the procedures,
or object-oriented programming, but you look now. Declarative programming, the main example of
declarative programming is functional programming. The others are very rare, so logical programming
is only prologue around and I never used it, I have to say. And the other ones I have also not much
idea, so they are also in this category, but they're even more rarer than the other paradigms.
So some people say it's all rubbish to do all these paradigms. I don't think so. It helps to a certain
degree if you don't take it as a religion, say that has to be this paradigm. You can always combine
it, but sometimes it helps to have some terminology to communicate what you want. So now Python's
generally pretty pragmatic, you want to get the thing done, and how you call it doesn't matter
too much, but sometimes words and those definitions can be useful. Okay, object-oriented programming,
there are different ways how you express it. My background is numerical modeling, as well as
modeling. So what is modeling? Modeling is having a simplified representation of the real world.
You do modeling all the time. Most of the sentences, if you count something, one, two, three, four,
that's a kind of modeling, where you represent something as a number, but there's no number out
there, it's just three chairs, but you say it's just three, which is kind of if you want to,
say it's modeling already. So it's simplified. And the important thing, we have an objective.
A lot of people don't really start with it, but you say, okay, what do you want to achieve as a
model? And then they have to simplify the model as much as possible to still achieve the objective,
but they'll make it simpler. So you need to specify, and you also need to specify your
assumptions. So if you say, okay, we here on Earth, we can have the assumption we have Earth's gravity,
which is usually a good assumption. If you take this model to a space station, then it doesn't work
anymore. But very few people ever go to space station. For the big majority, the Earth's surface
is fine, and assuming gravity is a good assumption most of the time. But still, you have to write down
your assumptions. The same goes for software, but are my assumptions. And very often when you write them
down, the problem becomes clearer already. So let's go to the example. I have an example driving electric
cars. So one and a half years ago, I switched from a combustion engine to electric car, and that's why I have
this example driving an electric car. And driving an electric car is a bit different as an assumption
already. It's a bit different. So typically when you have a gas car, you go to the gas station, you fill up,
and then you go. It takes a few minutes. You pay, and you go. When you have an electric car, a big thing is
the charging. So you need to charge your electric car to go from A to B. And this charging typically takes time.
Depending on the type of the charger, you can get away with a few minutes, so like 20 minutes, you can get a decent
charge if you have a fast charger. But it might also take multiple hours if you have a slow charger. So if you do
just your home outlet, it might take several days. It's just the weakest one. So there's a big range there.
So this is the example here I would like to introduce. And these are the assumptions. So I wrote them down.
And I wrote just around a few, and then after a while I looked at it, and I did something. I said, I have more
assumptions. And I added more and more. There's probably more you can add here. So it's always assumptions.
It's a good thing to have this assumption table there, because this is your world. Of course, we represent the real
world in one way or the other in software, and then you write down your assumptions. So those cars just to keep going.
There are no other stops. They just stop for charging. They drive at a constant speed. So in real world, it's not
realistic, obviously, but to make it simple, it's a constant speed. You can always make it more difficult later to have
to accelerate and brake and stuff like this. So the energy usage does not depend on the speed. It's just even more
unrealistic. Of course, if you drive faster, you need more. If you accelerate more, you need more. We take this out.
It's just a constant rate. So and then every car always starts with exact 80% battery capacity. So we have the battery
capacity. So you charge up to 80% when you start there. And then as soon as you reach 20%, you stop for charging and you
charge to 80%. So typically, you don't want to unload, totally discharge your battery. You know this from this deep discharge.
It's not good for laptop, not good for the car battery, because they're kind of similar. So I'm not a battery expert, but in
broad terms. And very often, you also don't want to charge to 100% all the time. So that's good to 80%. That's usually
the implementation. Also, this is usually the area where charging is faster. Outside this area, it usually gets slower a bit.
It slows down. It's not always there. So that's the assumption. And then the charging rate depends on the charging station you
have, how much you can get out of here. Depends on your car, how much your car supplies. I talked to a guy here, the old car,
said, I cannot use the station. My car can only do 40 kilowatts. That's it. Yeah. The 150 kilowatts station is not useful for me.
Yeah. And I have my car. I put it at 150 kilowatts. It does about 100, 110. It's the maximum you get out of it. So I guess if
it connected to 300 kilowatts, it doesn't change a thing, because it's a limiting factor. So there's some extra driving.
Typically, when you go to a charging station, you might have to leave your route and go a few kilometers or miles somewhere and
charge. We don't consider this one. And there are probably many, many more assumptions here. So that's a problem.
So this is how it looks like. There's actually a result already of my run, but this gives you an assumption. This is one pattern
for one car. We use example data for cars. I pre-computed them to make them a bit easier. And this is
one of them. And it happens to a Volkswagen, but it could be any Tesla or any kind of electric car. And you see here,
this is the travel time. And this is the distance. So we go 1,000 kilometers. So everything is metric here.
So we go 1,000 kilometers. And we have a travel time in hours. And you see how the distance is increasing. And this is,
I'm driving with a constant speed of 80 kilometers an hour. It's about 50 miles. So I go at a constant speed. And then I stop
charging. The distance doesn't change anymore. But the time progresses and I charge. And between these two red lines, I have the
charging. That's what happens, charging time. You see? And there's always charging from 20 to 80 percent. All of them are the same
This one is thinner because here I don't charge to 80 percent. I only charge as much as I need to reach my end, my destination.
And I still have 20 percent left. So this one has to be calculated backwards. Typically, by the car, it's always predicting when you drive.
It tells you when you reach your destination, you have so many percent left. It's changing a bit always because it's not constant.
But they have a prediction in there. They take account of your driving style and your last, I don't know how many trips you did on something like this.
So they have some kind of prediction which is more sophisticated. And this one, this is just everything is linear which makes it easy.
Okay, this is an example. So now I switch to Jupiter notebook. So this is material. You have it already. I'm going to use Jupiter notebook.
Who of you is using Jupiter lab, Jupiter notebook, something like this. So if you know how to use it, you can use it. If not, you don't have to.
These examples work anywhere where Python works. You can just work from the terminal, no problem. You don't have to do anything special.
They will work. But the notebook is great to demonstrate something. That's why I usually work with notebooks.
Okay, let's look at the example. First, we have, maybe I make this
bigger. Can you read this in the back in the room? It's big enough? A little bit bigger? Okay.
Yeah, this screen is compared to the room, not the biggest. So I'm creating new notebooks and the notebooks have a bunch where I can write text.
And I can put the figures in and I can load my code in here. So when you download this stuff, you will have this two PDFs and then you have the directory eCars
which has all these different versions of my program, different incarnations. And you have the data here. This is the data. These are not the original data.
I have a long explanation where the data come from. So you can read through it, but it's not of interest here. So I used them and modified them a little bit and took something out to make it easier to use.
So the data is like this. That's how it looks like. You see this is not good because it's a...
Yeah, this is my. So I have to open it. I say it's CSV, but that's not a good opening. So this is the data.
Actually, I can load the data from the notebook. I do make a new notebook. I start with new notebooks. So you're encouraged to, if you can type along or work along or just listen, we will do exercises.
If you have an exercise where you do something yourself, I will be here. You can ask me questions, but it's important that you actually kind of more or less active. If I'm just always talking here and giving a long presentation, that's not too helpful.
So the data first. So look at the data.
So if I CD into this...
I CD into the ECOS directory.
No, I'm there already. I'm there already. So I started there because I put the data there, so which is not good, but yeah.
Maybe...
Closes.
There it was. It's not good to have the mix up there, so I cut it out. Mix up, put it into... I want to put all the notebooks there.
Okay.
So now I can say...
S and I say CD, ECARS.
ECARS and then you can look at the...
Percent less.
I've gotten over there. The name is ECARS.CV.
Less.
ECARS.CV.
These are the data I changed a bit and you see in the top, we do have a short JSON thing with units. So I don't know if it's a good format, but at least we see the units.
So this is our table. So if we have a brand, yeah, Tesla or whatever, a model as one or X or something like this, then kilowatt hours per 100 kilometers, which is usage.
The battery size in kilowatt hours and the charging rate the car supplies.
And then here we do have the data and these are the data of what we're going to use. So in the end we can really make instances of... That's real data.
Three years old, so it's not the most current one, but it doesn't really matter too much. So you can just put in new data. I modified them a little bit. If you want to, I have appendix where I go in great detail how to do this, but let's stick with it.
So let's look at a procedure solution. I will go over...
So you know already that the problem is not that difficult mathematically, hopefully. So I wrote a solution that produces this picture.
We look at it a few minutes so you understand the problem. You need to understand the domain to a certain degree, otherwise it's getting difficult to do this.
So let's look at the procedural solution. And for this one I can make a new notebook.
And I save it. It asked me to change it. Procedural.
Okay, procedural solution.
And the first thing, if I go to the... Again to the ECAR subdirectory, I'm using a config file where I put the config option. So if I can load this here to execute it.
config.py. So my configuration is very simple, Python dictionary. So if you want to get more fancy you could have different input format, but for simplicity I just use the Python dictionary.
Here I specify my world data, my model parameters if you want. The chance of using supplies a maximum rate of 100 kWh per hour. That's the rate.
I don't want this new line here.
Doing there?
Oh, just jumped in.
Then there's the 20% and 80% thing, yeah, we talked, and then the speed, 80 kilometers per hour.
It influences the time. The speed doesn't influence the usage of the energy, which is not realistic as we said, but this is our configuration.
Since we use them all the time, we just import it and then everybody imports this one, we get the same configuration so we can compare our modeling thing.
Good. So this is the data. And then let's look at the first one, calc travel times.
This is calc travel times without anything. This is a procedural solution and I have a bunch of functions that do things. I need a bunch of imports.
And now we have different things. We have driving and charging. So driving is actually when I cover distance, when I drive somewhere.
So this is the first thing I implemented in the function and I do charge. We can look at this.
Then we can also calculate the charging amount, which is constant.
And then we have something called the travel. The whole thing is a travel, which includes driving and charging.
That's the terminology I use here. It might be a different terminology, but that's what I'm using here. It's important otherwise.
When you talk with people and somebody says travel, others say driving, what is what?
So driving is actually the thing. Moving the car with a speed of 80 kmph where travel is the whole travel from A to B.
Good. So that's what I do here. So we start here calculating travel time.
So I do import my config. So if it's not given here, I make it optional.
Otherwise the config is given and I just extract exactly the same thing for my config file.
This is the data we just saw. And we calculate this thing.
So now we translate this 20% and 80% multiplied by the battery capacity to get the absolute number of this battery.
So this is 20% and 80%. And this is this here. And here I divide it by 100 because I want it for 1 km.
So it's easier to calculate. So the maximum charging amount is 80 minus 20%.
We don't have any distance traveled. The remaining distance is the target distance, 1000 km.
The travel time is 0. The current charging amount is 80%. That's our assumption.
And then what's the effective charging rate? It's the minimum of the charging rate of the car and the maximum rate of the charging station, which is provided here.
So if the charger provides only 22 kW, then we can only use 22 kW. That's typical.
That's 32 or 11 kW, typical sizes at least. At least in Europe. I'm not here, but maybe similar.
And then I do the driving. So this is a loop where I do the driving.
This is a little bit algorithmic. So I do the drives. Here I drive and I call the function drive.
And I provide this parameter. The function drive does nothing else.
But here you see this is I get the target distance, which are still 1000 km in the beginning.
And then the available battery by the km per hour.
If I'm at the end, this target distance will be shorter and shorter as long as I travel.
And if I only have 10 km to drive, I don't have to charge to 80% because it will be less.
That's what it is. And then of course the drive time is the distance divided by the speed.
And then return the distance and the drive time.
And then the charging is also very easy. You get the charging, how much you want to charge.
The charging rate and then the charging time is just the amount, the rate.
So a little bit of mathematics. So this is a little bit algorithmic.
If you don't understand all the details, it doesn't matter if you have a solution
that works and we have these components. So we have this travel.
And then you have to be a little bit careful if you compare to something that you round a little bit.
Otherwise you might get into the one is not equal to 0.999999 or things like this.
You want to avoid these kinds of things. It's something like this.
And if you reach your destination, then you stop.
The thing is done. I'm finished. Otherwise I calculate the charge amount here.
I give it how much I need to drive for remaining distance and the amount,
min charge, kilometers hour. Do my computations.
The charge amount is this one here. Okay, how much do I need?
The minimum charge plus this one.
But I so the minimum charge has to stay there 20%.
And then the remaining distance by the kilometers, how much I need.
And if it's more than 80%, then I charge to 80% if less I charge to this thing.
So that's why I take the minimum of this and this.
This is everything you need to make this picture.
And I put it into functions.
And then I return this time.
And then I drive my all my cars.
So I read in the data. Actually, we haven't looked at the data section.
We also have actually here. I've forgotten how to read the data. Very easy.
Just for completeness sake.
Read data. Yeah.
So we ignore the CSV totally.
The JSON parts totally and just read the CSV.
And we don't do anything special. We just read the file in with encoding UTF-8.
We start at the data.
We split by hand.
The easiest thing that we can do, you can use Orkind if you know pandas.
It's much easier now.
But just do it by hand and go through and split the arrows.
I do some conversion.
So everything that can be converted to an integer will be converted to integer.
Otherwise, I try float. If not, I keep it as a string.
So very easy. Good enough for our purposes.
If you need a more fancier reader, use any kind of reader.
So it's not about data processing.
Reading data in.
This is just a thing.
Here on the data is a list of lists.
As you can see here, every entry goes in there and then you have it.
Yeah. Good.
So this is our solution.
And in the end, you can drive.
And report travel times just prints out the travel times.
And I want to have the guy who is the fastest first.
And that's why I sort all my cars.
And to do this, I would like to use the travel time here.
And I use the item getter, which is a function.
That's this that I import up here from the operator module.
So this one is essentially going into my dictionary and extracts the keys.
The key here, it's a function and this function can be used by key.
Who knows how this sorting with the key function works?
Just a few people.
So I need to explain.
So if I have, I think I have an example here.
I can use it.
I don't have to reinvent a new one.
Yeah. So if I have a dictionary, if I have a dictionary,
a dictionary with entries, A is 10 and B is 2.
And C is 24.
I would like to, and we have to make colon here.
And I would like to sort my dictionary and say, okay,
I want to have the B as a first because this is smallest number.
Then I could go on and write my own function.
Get value if you want.
So I put my dictionary in.
Yeah. So actually I don't have a dictionary.
I have a list of these dictionaries here.
So I have to make my thing more complex.
So that's why it doesn't make sense.
So I have a list of these dictionaries.
And this one has this one.
I copy this whole thing.
And now I want to sort it by one of these things.
Yeah. So now I just use the value of B.
And here I say this is 25 and this is 8.
Now I would like to sort by B.
So now I see I get my dictionary and I just return my dictionary value B here.
Yeah. This is a function.
And now I can say sorted of my dictionary, of my list.
Actually this is called, this has to, I call it a list.
It's a better name.
And this function is okay.
I put in my, here I say key function is my sorting function.
Yeah. Get value function.
And now when I sort this now, you see this is the first,
this is the second to the third because what happens,
so if you add a print here you see what Python is doing.
So we add a print.
And then you see when I call my function,
my function, Python hands in every element of my list
which happens to be a dictionary to this helper function get value.
And I retrieve the value for B which will be used for sorting.
So I create my search criteria, my search key.
So if you, you can think of this is a function that creates a yellow sticky note
where you write what you want to use for sorting.
So if you say we want to sort by first name,
everybody writes a first name on a sticky note, puts it here.
I sort you and when you're done,
I take the sticky note available and you want to write order.
Yeah. Because I certainly can remember all your first names
but if I have a sticky note or name tag in this case,
that would be useful.
Yeah. I know the alphabet usually so I can sort.
So the same thing here, you write a helper function
and the item getters doing exactly this.
This is not unimportant because we want to use the sorting as an example
for potential advantages of technical programming.
You can make your objects easier sortable.
It's easier to sort them.
You don't have to write this helper function here.
So that's what I'm doing here.
And then I have a main function that reads the data
that takes drives or cars.
So drive or cars just goes through all the cars, a list of cars
and then calculates the travel time of all of them.
Yeah. So if I take this out because now this wouldn't work.
So if I take this out and I load my file, now I have my main function.
Actually it's easy to put it there otherwise it's difficult.
My main function and now I just give it my e-cars file
and then it prints out this car.
So the Tesla Roadster here in this case is the one
that needs 13 hours for the thousand kilometers, 13.7.
The next one, 30.78 and so on.
So this is one of the shortest travel time with my assumptions.
If you have different assumptions, yeah,
then you might have different result.
You see this battery capacity is very big,
about 200 compared to the other ones.
This is much smaller but here this guy takes only 10,
200 kilometers and there it takes 20 which is really more realistic.
Yeah, so it's always a combination how much you use,
how big the battery is and how fast you can charge all this thing.
And then you can investigate.
Yeah, so this is a procedural program.
It works and I can find out which car arrives first according
to these simplified assumptions.
Good. Any questions about it?
So if you have questions, I'm supposed to repeat it
because it's recorded or if you would like you can go to the microphone
and talk to the microphone and then we have direct.
Any question?
Everything clear what we're doing so far?
Good. It's supposed to be, it shouldn't be too difficult.
So if it would be a lot of questions then it would be too difficult
because we assume we know our solution and it's a procedural solution
and we do something.
So let's go and do something with objects.
So we do something with objects by the way.
So we have 10.30 we will have a coffee break, 20 minutes or so,
something like this so you can get coffee outside and then we continue.
So let's go and do our first object on a solution.
So.
And for this one we now take our existing solution
and we don't really implement any new logic you will see.
We use this, we don't do any new mathematics or anything.
The end result is the same.
Only the way we express things is different.
That's important.
That's one I'm going to show you.
So if you don't want to you can get away for a very long time
without writing classes in Python.
There's only a few cases where I need to write the class.
So if you want to create your own exception
you have to inherit from exception write the class.
Yeah and some libraries might make you to inherit from a class
and write the class otherwise you can most of the time get away
with just writing functions but writing your own classes can be useful
and that's why we want to look at here.
Good.
So typically a class so you could have a class.
So if you before we go there you can have a class car.
In our case we will see it would be electric the car
and we have the class statement and then we define a function
and the function inside the class is usually called a method
and then we have a self and we have value
and then I can say self value equals value.
So this is a very typical pattern if you want for writing a class
very often we have this init.
This init is a special method.
We will have a deeper look at special methods.
They all have these patterns two underscores name two underscores
very often called Dunder methods because you say two underscore
what up two underscore you say Dunder.
It's called a Dunder method and officially there are special methods
some people call the magic matches which is not actually correct
because I know that magic special methods that do something
and this is one you very often have most of the classes will have in it.
You can write classes without in it it's possible
but very often you want it because you want to initialize something
and here I could say def a method and then have myself
and then I increment something here and then I say return self value plus increment.
So it's not very useful but shows the thing what you can do here increment
and then I can make an instance of my car and give it a value
yeah so this is the first thing you can do with your car
and then you can say car dot increment and you get
so you can access the value attribute and then you can say car dot increment
you know car dot method and give it an increment this way around 100
and you get something like this back good.
This is the basic thing and if you see now we look at my electric car
which is a bit more complex but exactly the same exactly the same thing.
Okay let's go to the directory eCars and import our file
reload our file
and then we can say file calculate our travel times
calculate travel times object on the way.
So now you will see a lot of things I took pretty much all the mathematics we have
there are not much changes but I rearranged things so the imports are the same
and I have my eCar and you see typically per convention class names are capitalized
and here have multiple nouns here this electric it's not a noun it's an adjective but we take it
as a noun and I shorten it to e which is everybody understands what the eCars usually so that's good
enough and eCar that's why the e is capitalized and c is capitalized for the car.
We have electric car we always use the most important thing for functions in classes the
doc string so write a good doc string so we have a doc string now you see I can get this
configuration options if you compare with our other solution we see very often we move the
same data around many times here we can use this one and the unders anybody knows what the underscore
means yeah it's internal usage it's a pure convention but the underscore means this is only
as supposed for internal use in in this case internal use from inside the class you can access
it but you're not supposed to do then you write a test for your own class then accessing is
totally fine then you use the library from somebody else you shouldn't do this because
these things can change without notice if you have other method or attribute they cannot just
change it they have to have to have some procedure like a deprecation warning or something and there
has to be a documentation about this and these things can also be undocumented more or less
because they are for internal use you see now I just take my configuration data these numbers
from here and store them here inside the class and this can be useful because now can you reuse
them so if you need data in many places when you do it in a good function style you always
a function should never change the outside world you only get data in and get data out
if you do this and you can be pretty repetitive if you need the same information at three functions
you have to hand it in as parameters yeah or arguments when you call it again and again
here in the class you have something like a global scope so when you write Python you should never
use the global statement so if you use pyLint it will warn you never use a global statement
here this is something this is a global statement you can use so to speak and this is called the
glass variable and this will be available over the whole class you see now my init is doing quite
a few things in the setting all this information so there's a lot of setting I said my brand my
model kilometers and all those kind of things and I can pre-compute the things like this is my 20
percent my 80 percent all this computation we have done before in one of these functions yeah
there's nothing new here so the travel time doesn't exist yet I could introduce a travel time
later but it's a good style here to set the travel time to none so the travel time is there
as a name but doesn't have the value yet I didn't travel you could set it to zero it's possible
none is also possible so this is a design decision so it hasn't traveled yet or
maybe you could say if it's zero maybe it's sort of is charging I'm not sure so something like this
no doubt that would be zero anymore so it could be the same thing I decided for none but zero would
here potentially also a choice yeah and you see I have my drive in charge functions now moved inside
the method they do exactly the same I can reuse it the only thing I hand in the self and we look
at the self and we see what happens here good so
and there's a few more things charged charging amount it's the same mathematics here nothing
new and the travel is also the same but it's a bit shorter so if you compare this travel function
this is a travel function and you see the travel function needs to do all these things in the
beginning and this is what we do in the class on the top so now we can better divide these things
for this example it's not always the case maybe but for this example so I do all this static kind
of getting things out here and now my travel functions which essentially is exactly the same
becomes shorter and fits on a screen rule of thumb a function should always fit on the screen
if it doesn't fit in the screens potentially too long it doesn't mean you should use six font and a
42 inch screen that's not what I mean but just a normal size font and string should a screen should
fit on there so this is the same mathematics we do here and then we have this
um in there I'm reusing this function this I've I this one I use in function I don't write classes
for these so in Python always allows to combine classes and functions and you should always do
this and these things are potentially better than these functions I don't didn't turn into class
if you want you can you can always turn everything into classes but maybe it's not a good idea in
this case have it here not just travel so if you look at this in in a moment so I'm taking this out
here otherwise everything will be executed so I'm executing this now everything in here it's now
in my notebook and I can call all these functions because they're all executed so um the first one
I have I can read the data yeah so read data I can put in the file and then I can read data and
then I can have the data so and then we don't have to type anything in we can use data data
is read data and we did this
so I can access data zero so now how do I work with this with a with a class the class is a
blueprint for a new data type so if you look at my other type of this e-car if you look at the
type of this e-car you will see this is a type type and if you look at the type of int
if you look at the type of this e-car you will see this is a type type and if you look at the type
of int this is also a type and if you look at the type of list this is also a type so int and lists
are classes so very often when I start with my beginners class I say okay I can use a function
int to convert a string to an int that's not correct it's not a function
it's a class I instantiate but it's a callable so very often when you say function Python you
mean a callable that's an important thing and instantiating class and calling a function looks
exactly the same and in practice you don't really care what it what kind of type you're using there
you care about the result so very often Python doesn't really care about types it cares about
behavior and that makes a lot of things much easier because it doesn't really matter
what type this callable is as long as it's callable so as long as I can use this
on the parentheses it's giving me something back I'm happy yeah so that's why very often you don't
know even if you use a class a lot of beginners when I type in a one I use the class because this
is a literal one makes the instance of the class int this object on the programming so typing a one
is object on a program if you want so of course you make instance of a class good so now we have
our car now we can instantiate our car and you see I can look at my ecar and I can look at
the question mark at the help so this is the same thing if you're a normal person type help
parentheses putting in car you see the help and this help is obviously the
signature of this init file yeah so of course the class itself doesn't have anything but this is
these parameters here you want to put in and I'm going to feed it with arguments so if I have my
tesla this is my tesla here this is data zero
my tesla is my data zero yeah and now you see I can feed them in I can say now I make a new tesla
car there's an instance and I say it's my ecar and I can say brand
brand brand equals tesla brand so you can do something like this so you can write this out
and you can type it in tesla brand you see they'll have to type a bit model equals tesla model and
so on so I use the same names for some reason so this also implies you can make it have a faster
way of doing it and then I say kilometers
per hour equals so now getting pretty long so this is one way of formatting it putting every
argument on one line there are different styles of doing this but this is a
something that works and now I can I don't need to retype this I can copy it
yeah so I can t and instantiate my car and I do the same thing here
battery size battery size equals this you see if you do it like this we use the same name there's
a shorter way of doing it I can show you in a second but I'll show you the
the long tedious way first charging rate equals equals t charging rate yeah so now I copy this
and now I have my
what's wrong brand a mistyped brand yeah so I didn't copy it and now I have my tesla which
looks like this this is a this is a standard representation this can be nice so we will do
this we will make give our classes nicer representations but now I can access my tesla
and I can look at the brand and I should say tesla yeah so you can look at all these properties
anybody knows how I could make this thing a bit shorter
so now you can use two stars for this so if you want to say let's say I make my tesla 2
just it's the same thing I say tesla 2 equals e-car and I can say double star
double star my t up here and this tesla you should write tesla tesla then it's doing the
same thing so this this one line is equivalent this whole thing that's what it's actually doing
this one unpacks the dictionary and feeds all the content in there you if you if you have a
different string and they're not going to work so the names these names and these names have to be
exactly the same otherwise it doesn't work but this makes things easier so we can instantiate
it so if you can guarantee this and you want these names anyway then you don't have to and if
another two parameters it doesn't matter as long as they have the same name you
when they are in the dictionary it would work yeah so this is
what they do now we have our e-car and we can do something with the e-car let's look at our tesla
so our tesla now has a bunch of properties tesla and if I say dot tab here then I do get
some suggestions and you see that you see that's the the type i is an instance and f is a function
or method so we technically all these methods are functions there's no difference yeah but usually
you call the methods when they're inside the class and if they're standalone they're called a function
but there's no technical difference and now I can access all these
yeah max charging amount is it's so all these kind of the things I computed in between I can access
and I can do this this is an instance and since I made a tesla obviously I can make as many instances
as I like but I can also look inside the test and I look look and use another dando but not this is
not a dando method but then the attribute if you want and this is a dictionary this is how an instance
stores the data so this standard dictionary is interesting to look at when you program it you
might not want to modify it by hand because there might be some strange effects very often works but
there are a few things that like pyson supports properties they just look like attributes but
they're not sort of dictionaries because they have a different technology to work with so you might
it might not be exactly what you want to be careful but looking at is very interesting you see now
pyson stores all this information all this instance variables in in this dictionary good message if
you know dictionaries you know how to how this works you know how this works and you can access
all these things okay but I can also say tesla if I really like to I can access these underscore things
these underscore things and they are not stored in this dictionary but still there so usually
when you say tesla dot then pyson looks in this dictionary and looks for this string
and if it finds it it gives you back the value yeah if I say tesla dot brand it gives me back the string tesla
if I say dundum underscore max charge then it cannot find it here and what that what does it do it goes
further and goes to the car and I say car dot underscore dict and the car itself also has
a dictionary which looks a bit different it doesn't say dictionary says mapping proxy
because this is read only you cannot directly write to it you can directly modify the dict of
an instance this is something you have to think twice if you really want to do it
I wouldn't recommend modifying the dict of dictionary unless you have a good reason to do so
like if you debug something and you want to introduce something to get a better output
so that's totally fine so for debugging you can do pretty much everything if you say okay
I write some help us to get some better information and throw it away otherwise you might not want to
do it here you cannot because it's a mapping proxy otherwise it's a dictionary and you see all
these things are here in the dictionary so then you say instance dot python looks in the instance
first and if you kind of find it it goes further to the class yeah this has advantage that I need to
to store this information here only once in the class so this number is stored only once
in all instances share the same number when you read then you access the same number and you don't
have to store the same number 100 000 times if you have 100 000 calls yeah this is important
saves a bit memory but also don't repeat yourself if the information should be exactly the same
then it's probably better to have this information only to one place not in 100 000 places
that might change independently good so that's how it works so you have attributes
and this objects instance and the class and you can work with these attributes and they're stored
in here good so now let's look at our car and do some traveling so we can do some traveling so if
I have our tesla car here and I say travel time then it gives me a none which is not shown here
there's no travel time it's not defined yet it could be zero maybe you can change it to zero
would be I think totally fine and now I can say I drive
I travel I travel my thousand kilometers to stay with our example
then it's doing the you don't see any output here and then if you look at the
travel time now the travel time increased to the 13.8 hours should be exactly the same as
the other example hopefully so this is
yeah this is not it's not sorted this is just I haven't sorted the cars yet I just have one car
that I read in that's why it's not exact it's not the same tesla as we have then they sorted it
good
so
okay and now the result is exactly the same we have no new output but the program is different
everything is organized in a class and not only in functions but we reused quite a bit of our
functions and made them methods of our class this is a totally me fine approach and you can
do something like this so if you want you can also do a plot so I have this plotting here so if I have
this this this I can say from travel times this this graph here I import a different class
this is a graph car yeah graph car and now I make my graph car I'm lazy just one and I use the same
thing my t yeah I have my graph car and I can say travel a thousand kilometers
and then this one now supports plotting and if I say plot so if I have
met putlip so if you want to use a plot actually you need met putlip sorry I didn't
specify this one and to it to suppress this output here in the cynical now this would be the plot
so but the plot is not essential for the understanding object rotation it's just you see
this this is output you see that this tesla for instance stops only three times for charging
because there's a bit bigger battery compared to this volkswagen which stopped five times or
something yeah so this is something you can visualize directly now you can explore these
objects step by step so this is a different car we don't we don't need to look into plotting how
plotting works you can look at the code I gave it to you this is met putlip if it on met putlip
it's not of interest because it doesn't really it's not concerned with our object on it
problem good so now this is our pro program and here you also have a helper function show dix
and and also the sorting I can do the sorting the same you see this I can also sort by travel times
and I just put in and also I can use my get my attribute getter function which is exactly the
same as a function I wrote it's just generating the function for me and I can sort my cars to
have the car this is shortest travel time first so very similar to our solution before but we
have it in the class any questions everything clear
yeah so so far the advantages don't seem to be the big we can reorganize things a bit nicer
so we can have things that are in the class the class attributes and we can have
things that are in the instance yeah and then therefore our travel function came a bit shorter
because we could move something to a different place and this is one advantage at least for
this application good let's come to the next topic which would be inheritance so we just
can make new notebooks here so then we have for each topic a new notebook and we stop inheritance
inheritance is one one technology if you want or one technique one technique in object on
programming that can make your life easier
okay let's have an example so far we said okay as soon as we reach 20 percent charging starts and
when we're done you keep driving that's not how it works typically you have to if you go there
you have to stop get out you have to take your cable put your cable in then you have to take
either a plastic card or some app and then the app doesn't work and they work around them it might
take a while to get connected this time is not it's not in here this time is not in here and we
want to change our problem a little bit to include this time so we want the most of it what we have
anyway so the driving everything should be the same only this little bit extra time to connect
the disconnect from the charger should be included so as example you have something and you want to
modify it a little bit and for this type of problem inheritance can be a good tool
the term inheritance comes from biology so we will use the term parent and child because they
use this analogy of parent and child and typically the child is very similar to the parent
in this case you can have one parent here biologically it's probably not so easy but here
you can have one parent and in python also allows to have two parents or three or four
which is very uncommon but possible i wouldn't recommend to use it in python but you can and so
you have this this analogy of course you say the child is very similar to the parent but not exactly
the same it's a little bit different it's not a clone which would be 100 the same but it's a bit
different and this this principle can be used for inheritance so let's look at our example that we
that we consider this
consider this charging connection disconnection time and
the import the load the file i have to put the file name there this must be the
yeah i don't start from the beginning so i have to check myself how to find this name
sometimes so it's here yeah connection time so pretty long name so load
so we import
travel travel time connection time so and we need pretty much everything from our car therefore we
import our e-car here that's what we just wrote and now we do inheritance and we write the parent
so the e-car is the parent and this charger connection time e-car which is a pretty long name
yeah you see this the so-called camel case this is a camel case because you always write the first
letter of each noun you capitalize them it looks like a camel in nature they only have two but here
you can have as many pumps as you like see and then here i introduced the charge connection time
there are many ways how to do this i use a class variable here again so put something the classes
will be available and let's say okay it takes about six minutes to do the whole thing yeah
and i've lumped both of them together connecting disconnecting which is kind of reasonable because
you have to find your app and then you have you have different charging providers and you have
the wrong app and so on yeah so then you have this extra and now you see i don't implement anything
i do get everything for my parents so the child gets everything from the parent for free
and then i override the charge yeah this charge match i re-implement the charge method
and now the this this class the child class charge is a little bit different than the parent class
and the difference is very small it still wants to do the same thing as the parent and that's why
you use super what does super mean
yeah so there's another analogy we sometimes the the parent would be super and the child would be
sub so it is a different terminology so and this means please bring me my parent in this case this
is very obvious it can can only be e-car there might be more complicated cases if when you have
a deeper inheritance hierarchy here we only have parent-child relationship but i could be
a parent and a grandparent and a great-grandparent and so on and there could be even
python supports multiple inheritance there could be two classes in there which is not
the common but possible and then you would have your ancestors from the mother side and from the
father side and then it can be pretty complicated and sometimes strange things happen to do and
anticipate and the super is doing the right thing in this case it just brings e-car and i call
charge battery from the e-car so if you go back to this solution this would be so we call this
charge it's not much so i could easily copy these lines this is just one line essentially
this is just one line but still it's just one line if you copy this line and don't change it
then you might think do i have to do this is this maybe they sound easier way because if you find
the problem here and you fix this problem here then you have to go to this other e-car also and
fix it also yeah and then you find the solution and you have to go to this other e-car also and
fix in three places forget place number four that's not going to work for long don't repeat
yourself just try to do it in one place whenever possible yeah question so in terms of the
grandparents would you layer the super method or the question was a parameter layer what does it mean layer layer the parameters
like we're not comparing from the parent or from the grandparent
yeah so this one we look at this is this is what's called the method resolution what we look at in
second i make an instance i'll show you how this works typically you you inherit from the parent
if you want to skip the parent go to the grandparent it gets a bit more difficult
because you have to know who the grandparent is but very often if you very often the parent
uses the super from the grandparent this is a very common thing that you have multiple supers and
the supers always goes up this doesn't have to be like this but is very very common yeah you can also
override the method and don't use super if you don't need any function if you do something totally
different that's also fine yeah so let's look how the super comes about how this works so again i make
in this case i take this i take this out here you can run this also from the command line so i make
a new car so for this i need to duplicate a bit of code because i made a new notebook so i have to
i have to copy something like this yeah of course i need to get my data in
yeah so i read my data and the data is not defined
so
good so i have my data and now i make my my uh my charge to the connection car which i give this
great name see here and then i say okay make this this car and i can now feed in again
uh star data zero which would be my tesla
yeah so i have this this car and now um
this is would be an instance but the main thing actually is if you look at the mro
what's the mro so if you don't know what it is just look at help so of course if you just
uh if you use this say help so in the notebook i use a question mark but the python help is also
same so if you look at it the return types method method resolution order so the method
resolution order then you say instance dot something then it looks in the instance and then
then goes to the class and if it can't find in the class it goes to the next in line and next in line
is the one in the method resolution order and you can see here our charger connection time
inherits from ecar which inherits from object everything always inherits from object yeah that's
the same my sentence i don't know how many thousand times i said everything is an object in python
because i repeated many times in each training and this is the proof you see the object is always a
and it's a stuff everything everything inherits from object
and so if you say instance object it always works
that's no no problem there so you always have an object instance here and the super does nothing
else but uses this one and goes along this method resolution order until it finds a method so if the
parent doesn't have maybe a question if the parent doesn't have it done the charge it will go to the
grandparent because it looks in the parent and the parent doesn't provide it that goes to the next
and in the very end they will ask object for something yeah this is also the reason that
by this by this this output is this is called representation looks like this this representation
comes from object if you look later on how we can make our own representation
so object brings quite a few standard things with it if you don't implement it we get the standard
ones so this you see now this is a very short class that's exactly the same as ecar and does
a little bit different and this makes is it's nice because now you can go step by step and explain
for me because i can pretty much focus on what changes i don't have to copy the whole code or
change all these functions yeah if you do this with a charge function you would need to
write a new function that could call the file you could do the same thing but here you have a kind
of a standardized way that's inheritance when everybody expects that something like this happens
when you write functions you have to make it really clear that this function is going the other
function and so on so but inheritance is a concept that exists in python in objectable
programming and of course also in python for quite a while and you can do a few things with it good
any questions about this everything clear good so let's continue
let's come to operator overloading so i make a new notebook
and i call this
overloading operator overloading so as an example
if i have two lists
i have two simple lists and now i can say list one plus list two and this works typically the plus
is something for for mathematics for numbers but in python you can use a plus for lists you can
use a plus for strings so how does it work when you use a plus actually in the background python
is using the add function here this is add this special method this dunder add this dunder add
and i throw in this l2 put in the l2 and i get the same same effect in fact if you have a number
the same thing happens so you say number plus five i do get this one and i can say number add
plus five and i could do get the 15 the same thing as adding it here so whenever you use the plus
python is looking for this dunder add in your class if it doesn't have it it goes to the parent
class if it exists and searches for it if you it's not there by default so object doesn't have an
ad so that's why this one would fail this object doesn't support the ad so if you want to know more
about it you can go to the python help so this this help opens just the norm exactly the same
to come python documentation and if i type in add which i did before obviously then it jumps
to object add and then you will see there's many many more you see this is a section emulating
emulating numeric types and this one provides pretty much all numeric operations add sub minus
multiplication so the signs are explained here not there but you can read them up so everything you
can do with numbers you have an ad and there's more this are it so if the left partner doesn't
have an ad it goes to the right part of the second partner looks for the ad for this partner and then
there's an i add which would be plus equals yeah plus equals minus equals and so on and a bunch of
more like a a negative sign in front of the number could turn something you can turn something in a
complex in the float number which doesn't make a lot of sense with the car but you can do it with
numbers yeah so it does put you be very useful you can implement your own rounding and this is not
connected to an operator like plus minus and so on but to a built-in function so the operator
overloading is a little bit too narrow it's a special message to a bit more and because also
this same here these are complex in the float are not operators but you type in complex in the float
and when you type this function in or this name in then pyson is looking for this dunder method
of this object and applies it same goes for length so there's many of these so if you want to you can
look through there's more of these once this contains would be the in so whenever you say
x in list then if your object has a contains it uses contains you will see if it doesn't
contains there are some other fallbacks that is also doing using for the same same purpose
yeah they're reversed which would return iterator so you have to read up a little bit how this works
and you can override a lot of these things get item set item things a lot of different syntax
here you see this would be the
and set item get item things this x-ray you have to read through if you want to implement some of
them you can also make your instance callable for instance so we learned that classes are callable
and functions are callable and you can make your own instances also callable by implementing this
dunder call method the most interesting ones actually are
to go up a little bit um they are top here the comparison ones so
you can make your you can say here my calls true or false what does mean
i don't you could implement something like this but the interesting ones are the six
these are the comparisons ones yeah less than less equal equal not equal greater than greater equal
and then you can make your cause comparable and that's what you want to do now so that's what
you want to do now and i'm probably need to close some of those tabs otherwise i can't see anymore
which one is which so close inheritance tab so
so i have an example where we do this so we improve the this comparing so we don't need to
specify this key function anymore by improving our class a little bit so i load this
um
comparable call so we can compare it
so and again i use the concept of inheritance you don't have to combine them but it makes it
easier because i want to focus on it so you see i'm i inherit from e-car already we did this just
now and then i override this lt function less than and this is enough to make them comparable
the documentation says you might want to also have the equal implemented but just for to sort them
for sorting this this lesson is good enough and here we provide the same information that we would
have used this is special key function so we take the travel time so the car this is this is shorter
travel time will come first that's what it says and now i move this comparison from an helper function
that i have to apply from outside into the object so the object is active to some degree it can do
something so always the object doesn't do anything but you you can think about the object is doing
something and this energy makes makes sense and now my sorting is easier you see the sorted now
doesn't need this key parameter anymore i can sort it directly and have the same output so if i i can
run this here which tells me this is not there because i changed the directory and then you see
now this is exactly the same output as before but i don't have to specify a special key function here
because and move the same conception into the same thing into the object itself so the object
knows what to do i don't have to tell from outside what to do with the object so if everything goes
right this would be an advantage that the object knows what to do and you just do something it
behaves and accordingly and you don't have to tell from outside there's a function how to do it
and now if you make it comparable and you could override many many more of the special methods
if they make sense yeah if it makes sense you can override them and you can improve your car
good and that's what we want to do now because if you look at this
e-car so if you have our our tesla here if i type in tesla
you get this this output this is a representation so python has two bit and functions representation
this looks like this and there's str which for many objects gives you the same output not all of them
yeah so this is exactly the same if i say representation representation of a string
representation of a string then it looks like this where if you say string from a string
then it looks a bit different so there's a slight difference here
how things look like because the string is just a string and this is just a string that represents
the strings a double string that's why you have this double and single quotes here
and the thing is if you run this through the this is just the same source code if i if i run this
representation through a vowel which takes a piece of string and involve a value as a python code
then you should get back a string that's the whole thing about it yeah that's the whole thing
if it's possible it's not always possible but if it's possible then the representation should
so if you do this with this car it doesn't work yeah well here it just shows you this is a standard
representation of a class that gives you the class name which lives in name which is my notebook and
this is an id this is a hexadecimally a decimally formed number of when you use id yeah so if i
if i say id from tesla
id from tesla and i convert it into a hexadecimally formed then it should
this does work so it should be giving me the same yeah so if you look at the number that's the same
number yeah that's actually what this puts in the id is unique yeah that's the whole purpose of an
id and then you can distinguish your instance of the class okay ids can be reused it's like you have
a license plate from car if you if the car doesn't exist anymore then somebody else can get the same
license plate later on similar here so it can happen it's not very common but it's totally
possible but this one you can you can do so make our car representable then so i load my represental
the car and
calc
why doesn't it load so typically it should give me okay copy it in so
so
sometimes it doesn't like me so and now i override these representation function and now i can give
it a richer a richer representation and this is up to me what i'm doing you see i have to return
the string here and that's what i'm doing just how you come up with a string is up to you but
this should look nice and that's what i'm doing here and i'm just using an f string to return a
string so now you have to give it a little bit more thought to make it
reusable so i could just say okay i take this name represent the car and return to so let's
let's run this one so i can now yeah if i run the whole thing i get an error message because
i have the wrong directory so if i run the whole thing you see now
it doesn't look nice because i would need to i have to put a print what did i do here
so
let's just use a print yeah just choose a print don't use a pretty print so i have to change this
that looks better so now you see i have a representable car and this car looks like this
so this looks exactly this one if you type this in you will get instance of the car so now this is
a bit more involved to get there you see i use the f string which generates a string and then i
do a little bit here and i make it just list all this because i have so many attributes i have a
list of the attributes i like and i use some formatting here to format them one of the other
i don't write it out by hand i just format it okay visit go here have a new line the indent which is
four spaces so add a four space and join these things here and i go
and in this attribute as you use get attribute self attribute name so automatically
into the instance and retrieve the attribute names here and
and yeah get get these attributes for all these names here and i can put them in automatically
for this one gives me the value because if i print this out you see this is a this is the names i
provide but this value is an instance the information which i need to get out and this
get attribute does it automatically and this get attribute does the same thing itself but
attribute and then i use here the representation of the object yeah and the produce so that's a
bit more involved obviously and then i also need to anybody knows why i do this long thing here
what does it mean self class self name so this is representable cause if you this this produces
this representable call so i could have just copied in represent the call
why is not idea a good idea to copy in represent the car as a string here
any idea
yeah
no this this one in this case just gives this one just copies this this thing as a string directly
in there yeah yeah when you change the name of the class later or when you do inheritance
so if you inherit from this class and you don't specify a representation then python say okay i
don't have a representation i take it from my parent going up the method resolution order and
then it takes a rip this one from the from the parent and then all of a sudden my class with
a different name says it's a representative of the car which is not the case it's lying about it
this can happen yeah and this might this might not be obvious if you don't test for this you don't
see it yeah so this if you use inheritance you should think about making your code inheritance
proof and this is not that easy you have to think a little bit ahead what could happen so if i write
the class and give my module with a class to somebody else somebody else can inherit from my
class i cannot really prevent it i'm not aware that as i say i don't want to be inherited from
then they can do all kind of things and then you should actually you need to more or less factor
in this this use case that somebody's inherited from you and what's going to happen if this is a
child class one of my own class still doesn't work the same way i like it to work yeah so this is
this could be a problem and so this representation thing is a bit more involved i want to show you
you can do this and then you get a nice representation here and if you do this in
in the notebook you can get even a little bit more so if i say now
do i have my data here yeah so if i say my representative of the car over the time or is it
represented the car or is a representative of the car my data
ever star data zero which is my first car i'm reading in so i have my my car and if i do this
here you see now this looks different this is colorful this is colorful which i produced
because it's just a string but if you're in a notebook you can add another not so special
method but notebook special method which just has two one underscore on the beginning end is
representation html and you can generate html which can be useful so if you work in notebook
and you use pandas then you always get this nice html table yeah and here you can do it yourself
and this one it's i don't do the work myself i just use pigments which is a pile of modules so
if you want to run this then you need pigments but it's not essential for the object annotation
and then i just this is just this is plain pigments so this is uh if you go to the help page
on the very first page this is plain pigment thing how to format make everything nice colorful
syntax highlighting so there's nothing special i don't have to write any single new line and now
i can have have syntax highlighting if you want you can make your own html by hand and generate
html with css whatever you like yeah could be useful and this happens in the notebook
if you do this in command line you see this text without anything yeah if you do it in
so if i say print r which now this print r would use a representation and that's the same thing
but you don't see the syntax highlighting there's no colors in this case yeah can be useful making
your object representable because this representation is used when you debug when you
do when you see error message you see the representation and if if you just see this is
one instance of this car this id maybe it's not the best information if you say this is this type
of car with all this information maybe it's much more useful because it's yeah yeah okay this value
is zero it could be the problem this is what you can do you can make can make your
car representable
good
any questions about these special methods
python offers many of them if you go to the help it's like 150 you never ever need all of them
there's many of them very special very deep some of them are very common like this add one for the
plus the comparison operators the representation yeah there's a second one is called the str which
you could also implement if the str is not implemented it will fall back to representation
so if i since i don't have a str here bundle str it will fall back to the representation and uses
this information from the representation now we make our object more expressible and we move some
functionality we had to supply from outside like for the sorting inside the object so the object
can do more if i move it inside the object this can be advantage if you create objects
yeah
okay if i know what i said it's just see faces i don't know if if you don't understand we have
break feel free to ask me in the break if there's anything so it's 10 30 is one minute so let's say
20 minutes this is okay yeah so 20 minutes so we continue here
so we have a second here
break
till
it's 10 30 10 50 10 30 now 10 50 and then we continue
this our travel into object on land
okay we have one more minute i don't have seconds here but about one more minute so please come back
in if you're outside if you can hear me we would like to continue so we have a lot of ground to
cover that's why you don't want to lose time so it's 50 now so at first i would like to address
a few questions during the break a few people approached me for instance about the notebook so
all these notebooks are developed i will share with you because they have something they have
questions answers in there so i will take everything i have notebooks i also do have a solutions
document the pdf and i put everything into the zip file and upload again so you can download the
same zip file and that includes all the stuff so there's no new link give me now also to do this
if i forget just give me an email if you forgotten to do this then i sent you the network that just
uploaded yeah a few other questions about these these notebooks people might not be familiar with
the notebook so last year i gave a whole tutorial about the notebooks you can do way more than i
show you so these are kind of you just mentioned the term prototyping this good it's good for
prototyping for trying things out as soon as they get more serious move it to the file so because
they have also disadvantages if you don't mind to implement the classes now all my classes are on
files i just import them i just show them to you here but when you do something more serious use
your ability studio code pycharm all these nice tools you have you can always combine it there
are some limited to reload options so when you change the source code imported function will be
really automatically there are some caveats it's not always working but to most degrees it works
and you can combine so notebooks are a great tool but that is always you have to use the right tool
for the right purpose people complain this doesn't work this is because you use users in the wrong way
then it doesn't work yeah so you have to be aware of the disadvantages or the shortcomings or
assumptions as we stated them then things become clear a few more other things about inheritance
there was a question about inheritance and composition so there's different approaches
i don't recover composition here which i could but the time is limited so inheritance is usually
is a relationship so a e-car is a car so if i would have a car i could inherit my e-car from
the car because it's still a car the composition is more has a relationship so like a car has wheels
the wheel shouldn't inherit from car a wheel belongs to a car so that's a simple example but
these things are there also in python you can actually do a different approach is called wrapping
but called wrapping so instead of in her do inheritance you have a class that uses the instance
of author class as a proxy you always delegate them to broke to this class because when you do
inheritance you always get everything from your parents you don't have a choice you either get
everything or nothing you can adjust i just want this method or this method if you don't want you
have to override the methods you implement the method when you raise a not implemented error
that's what i call blacklisting so if if you do inheritance you get everything if you don't want
to you have to actually say i don't like this i don't like this i don't like this
yeah and you have to be inclusive like this not cannot can be difficult because you might not
know but you get everything if you're not on the way out then you get all these methods for some
reason because you get everything from all your ancestors there so if you do gui programming so
this is also a good example if you write a graphical user interface all the modern ones have
classes hundreds of classes in each class has hundreds of methods because they have very deep
inheritance hierarchy with a lot of when you get a lot of methods from a lot of widgets in this case
most of the time it is designed like this but it's kind of difficult if you're classed with 350
methods how you're going to work with it yeah so this could be a little bit overwhelming it is
so big and this is wrapping you can do white listing you can explicitly just say i want this
and this and this and everything else won't work so white listing can be easier this is a different
approach is but you can can do more things in python inheritance can be great a prime example
of inheritance is exceptions so if you go to the python help when you type in so this also
let's keep this open i make another help because i want to show this also there was also a question
so if you go to the python reference when you say something like zero division exception or some kind
of exception you will go to the exception page so if you go to exception page and the very bottom of
the exception page that's a help page about exceptions in the python standard library or
python standard help then you have an exception hierarchy and this is the prime example for
inheritance because all exceptions do exactly the same you don't want this exception to this
and this it should be exactly the same the only difference is the cause why the exception is
raised and the cause is is shown in the name of the of the of the class class names camel case
yeah this is a good example because all exceptions do exactly the same they generate a trace back
information all the things only why they are raised or why they happen is different yeah
inheritance makes a lot of sense then you can write down your problem you have nice boxes and
arrows and they assemble in a nice hierarchy that indicates that then inheritance can be a good
solution if all the boxes and arrows go like this and you tell them they don't form a nice hierarchy
then inheritance might not be the best solution yeah all those technologies can work against you
if you apply them in the wrong way because then they do a lot of things you don't want then you
might hold the term you work against the framework the framework gives you very nice tools to do
solve a certain type of problem but if you have a different problem and it's different
enough on the framework then you work against the framework and the same thing this programming so
if your problem doesn't lend itself to the thing then maybe not use inheritance yeah this is
something that might might not be so clear at the beginning it turns out when you've broken it that
over time I realized oh maybe not the best thing okay about this there's this less than so here
the the fight the func tool func tool modules in in python has a class decorator called total
ordering so we don't cover cluster greater here but this is thing you put there and then it happens
so that's all you need to know here and here you only implement equal and less than and this total
ordering decorator implements the other four six of these comparison functions you don't have to
implement them with some rules yeah less than the opposite is greater than that it's easy yeah so
just just this around and then you don't have to do this and you would have all of these four
methods working if you want to use your objects with those operators so typing in these operators
as an operator then it would work yeah so there's quite a few helpers here and there which some of
them I mentioned the pdf but I probably have mentioned it here good let's continue one more thing about
so I call this second constructor even though it's not a constructor
so um
python has something called class methods anybody knows what the class method is
now so if you have a class a then you have a normal method and then you have a normal method
you have the self as the first argument what's what does the self mean what's the self put for
what's the self
yeah the self is a placeholder for the instance because these are functions in the first argument
instance I can explain this um so I don't or just say return 42 so it's like and then I have
a class method and to have I have a class method in order to have a class method I need to have
a decorator so I need to decorate this one with a class method so decorator is doing something
this method changes the method you can implement decorators yourself but this would take another
three hours to explain all the things so we don't do this that's why I have this um
so let's assume we have an init
so
something like this yeah so and now I have a very often called from from from um from a
quote from me and then here I get cls so in cls this is just these these names self and cls are
just conventions they're not fixed they're turned into blue syntax because they have a very special
meaning but they're not fixed you can use any kind of work there but this is very strong convention
use self and cls stands for class back in the day some people spell class with a k or something
like this but that's not common anymore so now I have this um this one and I just say I return a new
I return a new instance of this of this class by using class and supplying this um
this other a instance a when I say a dot value so this makes a class from the other class that's a
very common typical application of a class method so a normal method takes the instance as an
attribute so if I make an instance of my class a yeah then I can say which I have to provide the
value and yeah and I mistype the value so I can always fix it here go back in history so a is this
now I can say a method and a method returns a 10 if I say capital s a method then it tells me
oh no you're missing something there's one you forgot the self you forgot the self and the self
has to be a special kind of argument it has to be instance of the class if I put the instance in
now this is doing exactly the same as this yeah because the a method is a function
just a normal function nothing special just a function that happened to be inside the class
and the first argument is the self and here this method is a bound method so it is bound it's bound
to what it's bound to the instance therefore you you cannot because the a is in front of the
a dot method then the a is consumed the lowercase a is consumed already then you don't supply this
argument anymore that's the whole thing the method bounding is complex complex using descriptors and
so on but we don't we don't have to be concerned about how it actually works we just know that it
works yeah so so if you want to you can say the class in first it's just a collection of functions
that belong together somehow and I have a bit more structured way to put them together that's
one approach if you want to yeah and they then they have a global namespace and this global namespace
is handled over itself so the globals you don't want when you write functions you use all the time
when you write classes so if you if you have some information that needs to survive multiple
function calls somehow as a global then probably a class is a good approach actually I would
recommend you as a class instead of global now the global keyword you should never ever use a
global keyword and if you don't do this there probably you would need if you want to do the
same thing you would need to use classes yeah so this is a second constructor now we have this
example here and this one is a
um
what's the name from class flexible yeah flexible I call it flexible so usually I have this
method
yeah so I have a class method when you see now this follows the same pattern as the class method
first is the class and now I instantiate the class and this is the in this case of course is
explicit flexible call here which I can
which I can create with this if somebody inherits from this from this class this handed in class
will be the current class not this class but the child that's inheriting yeah so now it just
make an instance of of this class which is handed in and I now say okay brand is the instance dot
print model as an instance and so on I don't have to write this out I can make it it's kind of a copy
a bit more or less yeah and from something is very common now anybody used pandas pandas you can make
a data frame from a dictionary from what kind of stuff very similar so this is a typical name from
something and then you have a class method and this would be explicit so I specify everything by
hand but if you're too lazy you can go a little bit deeper into introspection and I use introspection
module and instead of writing this out I use introspect up there yeah and the inspect gives me
the signature of the init and then I can get the parameters out and I remove the self and I do the
same thing this one took me a while to get there yeah so that's you don't write this just in a half
a minute it takes a bit but this is exactly the same but if now the class gets three more
attributes in the init or more parameters it would be automatically there so this and this in this
case is equivalent this goes automatically and all this everything just inspects the init of the class
and gets all these these are the parameters of the init yeah from my parent class of course
and then I just have the massage system after takes itself out because I don't want to provide
the self and then I can do the same thing now I have the option to create a class from from existing
class so this would be a second constructor if you want them you will see this quite a bit
it's typically called from and this is one example where I can use a class method which can be useful
remove the self yeah because no no because the if when you when you write an instance I don't put
in self you see this is here when I make an instance when I make an instance in my first
instance I made by hand um this one yeah so I don't say self if I put self here as a first
argument I get an exception because this I call it on the init the init has a self already at the
the init is not the constructor that the new is a constructor there's a dundo new which you
I never ever remember implementing a new it's very rare that you need a new the new is a real
instructor constructor that returns something the self never ever should return anything
because the init just initializes very often it's called the constructor which is technically not
correct because new constructors making the instance the new makes the instance the init
fills up this initial values and 99.9 percent of time you just want to fill up these initial values
the new is used for the only thing is like if you have the singleton pattern anybody knows a
singleton is then the new is the good thing but this is the only application I know of that you
need a new there might be some others which I don't so and then the self the self is part of
the signature but when I use it here I get an exception say it doesn't take a parameter self
that's why I have to do strip the self out yeah so this is something you don't I got an exception
that the self is not allowed to move otherwise yeah you don't think about it usually but very
easy in Python because always get an exception that explains what's going wrong another question
depends depends so if if if you have an init then it will use this one if not it the init is
not special in this case the inheritance works the same it goes up the method resolution order
if my class doesn't have the init it goes to the parent class and takes it from there and
then depends what you want for all our samples we didn't override the init because we didn't do
anything different but he can also use super tip that's typically what you do you get something
you do something in addition then you typically use super called the parent in it and then do
whatever extra you want so you can only do extra you cannot do less because then equal
the function is one thing you cannot take things out of the function but you can do something before
after the init if you want to yeah like you could check values and say okay the value that comes in
should be in the limit and I can if it would like it erase exception then I just hand develop the
init and don't do the work for instance yeah so in it is exactly the same if it's a normal method
or in it in terms of inheritance exactly the same behavior good okay let's do a short exercise I
hope it works so I haven't really rehearsed the exercise because I don't know how to rehearse an
exercise actually I haven't rehearsed anything it is pretty new tutorial here but so far we are kind
of in my anticipated time plan let's do an exercise so if you go to the pdf there's a description of
the exercise so if you turn on the table of content then you can go to the
object on a solution exercise here and we have an example of
so this is so we do this it's called height so we have this here do we have it I hope I have it
otherwise I need to upload it and we do the exercise later
so
do we have this
height
but it should be in there so the height the
person's there yeah so we have a person and we have this heights file
they have a read data and a card and I don't have it here so I need to quickly upload this one so
that this works so give me a minute to do this so I can see the data and I can see the
I need to quickly upload this one so that this works so give me a second so we want to do exercise
now exercise now you can read through already so be following the thing situations I need to
upload this quickly and then I give you this thing it'll take me a minute
so if you have an existing solution
and we want to modify this and I was just now nothing nothing works when I when I'm here
and we want to modify it and I have a very simple one they have a CSV file we read in and I would like to
if we implement this procedural solution with
this
object on solution so we just read in the CSV file which I gave you but for some reason the
code didn't end up but it should because I referenced it and my automatic somehow didn't
didn't do it but I can
do it
exercises okay
okay I found it so we have this this existing solution and we would like to
modify it and turn it into an object on solution and this is a bit smaller example but very
similar and now you should you should try to do this and work on it and so
for that I need to concentrate on uploading okay so something always goes wrong but now we have it
okay
a
need to download this zip file again.
And I copied over into my tutorial.
So I didn't even realize that's not there.
Something always goes wrong when you do something like this.
And for some reason, this doesn't show up.
Good.
So if
you
download
the whole thing.
Yeah, if you
re-download this file,
then you should have the directories
data and this height in there. So this is application.
So if you re-download, you should find this height.
Yeah. And here we have a read data, which is a very simple one that
reads a CSV file, nothing special. And we have a calculation. And this calculation does
not have a very simple calculation. So calculates the mean, calculates the shortest person,
and the tallest person from this data. It's a very, very simple.
It's a very, very simple application that exists. So it's a module here that you can
use. Yeah. And this one,
so everything is included into PDF, but I didn't give you the source, which is
a very simple application. So it's a very simple application.
So this is a given one.
And I quickly go through and show you the source code.
This is a CSV file we read in. This is a person with a height.
This is in centimeters, by the way. Yeah, so no meters and feet.
Just one number is easier. And then you read it in,
and then you can use this one, and you can
display the people here. And then you have this great functions, the mean,
which exists already in Python as a statistic mean. You can calculate the mean.
You have to show this person's the tallest person, and so on. So this is
the given task, the given source code.
And then the task now is to rewrite this one
with the following steps. Create a class person. So I gave you already a person. So make a
class person that has a person, has a name and a height, so instead of the functions.
Then make some instances. So everything is just a few lines. It's just a person's very short.
Create a class with the height, make instances of this for all data.
Write a function that computes the mean value, the heights of persons, and create a
child class of person that is comparable. We did this comparable thing.
And then create instances, and
then find out which person is the smallest. So the mathematics is
the same as the functions already. Just move everything into the class. See if it works.
I haven't tried it out on real people how fast you can do this.
Anybody has a question about the content of this
function?
That's instructions of the PDF. That's a PDF, and if you go to exercises, then you find it.
So PDF, this is a section here,
page 31 down here. This is the 31 in the document, which
translates to 38 here. If you go to the here and go object oriented solution
exercises, then you find these instructions.
And before, here is the explanation of these files. I'm not sure why they are not there,
because I'm, yeah, because they are under exercises.
Okay.
So I can show you quickly how to
use this.
So big.
I think I have to make it a bit smaller.
So see anything useful. So let's go to the
exercise, make a new notebook exercises.
So
now if you have this
directory height there, then if I say
so the tree only works on Unix, if you have Windows it doesn't work.
So tree height, then you see this is my great package.
And I do have the data, and I can say
from height import
from height dot read data import read data.
And then I can say my data,
and then I can say my
data.
And then I can say my data
read data lists, okay, it's a different name.
And then I can say my data equals read data
lists, read data lists, and I say
my data has a check data called persons.
.csv
and then I have my data that looks like this.
Displayed now this pretty printer, you have the names and
if you don't like the pretty print, by the way,
you can turn off the pretty print and then it looks like this.
So this is one of these magic to get the display differently.
And then you can say from height import
calculations, and then you can say calculations dot
mean, and you can say
data one should be the
second entry
and then you get the mean value.
So this would be the second entry in my data, you have the mean value. So not very difficult in terms of what it's doing.
And you can also have the shortest person
and you have to put in the
names and the
values which would be the
data zero, data one, which you can
choose.
Yeah.
This would be
data zero and data one should work.
Which could be short cut too.
So if you don't want to write this out, then we can use our
star thing.
This would be the shortest person and this would be
the tallest person.
That's what it's doing and now
the output should be the same, that has no new logic, so you can reuse the logic,
and then you can sample them using a class. Of course the obvious class would be a person,
because we work with persons, so please try to implement
the person and methods.
I will go through and if you have questions I can try to help you. There's quite a few people though.
Yeah?
So this would be equivalent to...
We don't need that, but we can make it shorter. So instead of
writing this, here in this case the star is exactly the same as
this. The star unpacks the sequence because the data is a list.
One tuple is two entries and the first is the name, the second one,
and I can write it like this. If I use this one, so if it would have data
0, data 1, data 2, data 3, data 4, data 7, this would be the same. It would take
everything, it iterates over it. Very often, like if you say print,
so if I have a list,
then when I say print list, it just prints the list. If I want to have the single arguments,
print,
list, first entry, list,
second entry, list, third entry and so on.
But I can say print and then I just say
star, L, L, and I'm doing the same thing.
In fact, you don't even need a list. You can say print, star, range 10,
and now I feed all the numbers from 0 to 9 separately to the print.
This always works. This one takes this iterable object apart
and feeds all these things you would get when you iterate over it as single arguments to the function.
Pretty long sentence for this little star.
If you're lazy programmers, if you can reduce the work and you still know what you're doing,
then do it. If you end up with a poor code, then you
overdo it a bit, shortening the code.
I will come around. I turn off the mic so I don't disturb you.
After a few minutes, you see how it's going.
Let's continue. This is a solution. I'll show you my solution. This is a PDF.
This is a solution. You will get this PDF. I will edit it as a zip file.
The first thing, write the class person. That should be pretty straightforward. The class person.
You have to have the unit and you have the name and the height. Very typically, you say self, name equals name,
self, height equals height. That would be the first thing.
I put options here, I think. That's pretty much how it should look like.
Create instances. You see there's a solution with
list comprehension. You can also write the loop if you don't like list comprehension.
This is the shortest one. You create a person with name and height and you get name and height
by zipping name and height. This is just how you read in name and height. If you have data, you just say data star.
You can write here, explicitly, the first column is name, the other one is height.
We have persons. Write a function, it becomes a mean. This is still a function
outside the mean. Inside one class, it doesn't make sense. You need multiple instances.
Then you see a mean and you say, okay, now you access person.height for person
and persons provided the persons is a list of the persons.
You can always combine functions with classes. It doesn't mean you have to always
everything has to be a class. If a simple function is doing it, use a simple function.
If you need more, write a class. Then you can just apply it and you get your mean.
You get the same result. Then make it comparable. For this one, you need the less than.
It doesn't implement the equal or even more. The less than on here,
the thing is this is the criteria you want to use. The height of the person is what you want to compare.
You could also compare persons by name.
Then you use just the name with string comparison.
Right here we use the heights and then when you do this, you make comparable persons here.
Then you can have this mean.
You can use built-in mean function which works the same.
Sort and mean use the same principle with the key functions. It works exactly the same.
If you have a less than, you have a mean.
The user doesn't need to know anything. You know they use mean and you throw in your object
and it gives all your objects a list of your objects or a collection of your objects.
Then it gives it the same thing.
Then representable. That's a bit more involved.
For this one, you have to have the wrapper. Here it's up to you to create a nice string.
This one is a bit more work.
This exclamation mark R means use the representation of these objects.
It adds the extra quotes for strings. You don't have to fill it around in this one.
You say, okay, give me the representation of these attributes. These are objects already.
Built-in, Python, whatever. Fill them in.
Here again I use the class name so I get the class name.
Then when you see this, now a person looks like this. If you have your list
in a notebook printed out, something like this comes out.
Second constructor, maybe you haven't done this yet. Here you have the class manager.
You just put in the class and the person. Then you make a new class and you say person.name, person.heights
and take those things and fit it into the init.
This might be a small exercise but it gives you some feeling of what you can do.
In the real world things get more complex and more lines.
But the essence should be the same.
Hopefully. Good.
Any questions? Anything didn't work? Any unexpected?
Usually when I do training we do this together in a Jupiter Hub and then we can
change the solutions. Usually we also have more time for exercises.
But here we will stay with it. Good.
This concludes the first part. When we have this procedural solution we move step-by-step
into more object-oriented solution. Now we would like to
go to a different thing. I have to make this bigger.
The next one is
you do object-oriented analysis. Instead of
starting from an existing solution
you start from the problem and you start object-oriented from the beginning on.
There are many different ways of doing this and you have to analyze your problem and come up with
a solution. So starting from scratch.
Here I have
one approach. There might be different approaches. This is one approach
how to do this. Actually you don't start programming right away.
You start writing down things first. Defining the problem is always a good thing.
You shouldn't overdo it. You shouldn't specify for months. But writing down a little bit is not too bad.
Write down your problem with sentences
in a way that somebody else who knows something about the domain can understand.
This somebody else can be yourself six weeks, six months down the road.
Then you totally forgot what you meant. You send us and state your assumptions.
Then we analyze the text.
Our analyzer is like grammar fourth grade, third grade.
We just go through and find nouns and verbs and maybe adjectives.
Then out of these we identify potential classes.
Then we try to implement some prototype classes and then refactor our code.
There can be a lot of details. But typically if a simple solution
works then use a simple solution. So now I have my story.
The whole thing we just talked about all the time, the electric car thing.
An electric car travels a distance with constant speed. It has a battery of a certain size in kilowatt hours.
The car starts to travel with 80% charged battery.
These are the same assumptions.
They are from the same file. They include the same file in this place.
Write down a narrative, use full sentences and formulate in a way
that if you give somebody else, somebody else will understand what you mean.
Then it makes a lot of sense because it makes you think. When you have to formulate it, it makes you think about it.
This is what I did.
I have these assumptions here, which are our assumptions so far.
Then we do the analysis.
I just go through and now I collect all my
nouns. Then I have the verbs that I use. The verb is two here.
I have a car or electric car here in this case. This car travels.
There's a start and there's a charge. That's what I took from the text. There's a lot of other nouns.
Distance, speed, battery, battery size, travel and so on.
There are a lot of nouns here. Not all nouns should become classes
typically. Not all of them. Only the ones you are interested in.
We do have an objective with our modeling and only these
most important nouns that are in the center of our objective will become classes.
The other ones are sustainable attributes, just numbers, strings, lists or something like this.
Battery charge. You reach a battery charge. You have a start
charging station. If you haven't looked at a charging station at all, you might have a different objective.
You want to plan charging stations. You want to have the best distribution of charging stations
to minimize travel time and charging time. Then you might
want to have a charging station as a class. Here the charging station doesn't
matter. We just take them as given, as provided. We don't read them as a charging station. We just drive.
Charging rate, travel time and so on. A lot of these words come here.
Most of them won't become classes typically.
But this can be helpful. This is technically
not very difficult. Writing a good text that is readable.
Going through, identifying. If you want you can write a script for nouns.
Go through and sort them a little bit.
There might be more sophisticated techniques. Simple is good.
As long as it works. Of course the nouns are candidates for
classes and the verbs are candidates for methods. Nouns are something.
Methods do something. There might be the exception to the rule. Very often
in English you can use the same word for verb and a noun. Like some can be the some or to some.
It doesn't work in every language by the way. But very often it can be
two things at the same time. And then we have this modeling
analogy. I talked about this modeling. Modeling is the representation
of the word. And now I look for a quote. Most of the people say
Einstein is a sorcerer. Everything should be made as simple as possible but not simpler.
If you make it too simple it's wrong.
I go to modeling conferences and there was one theme.
All models are wrong, some are useful. It's not totally correct.
But it's good enough for our purpose. If you look in your column
you measure the speed. You don't measure the speed with 20 digits after the period.
You don't need this. Why? It's roughly good enough.
Even that doesn't have any definite places.
And it's good enough for our purposes. Same here. Don't make it too complicated but also not simple.
This is something that's easier said than done because very often you don't know
how this works. Here we state our objective.
Find the travel time of an electric car considering battery charging.
These objectives might change over time.
And then you need to revisit them if your assumptions change.
And then I do something
still I want to have my thing kind of future proof which is not easy.
This can lead to over engineering
if you put in a lot of possibilities that are never going to happen.
But sometimes it might make sense to prepare
for some future changes that are very likely.
You might notice you end up with needed things.
You might add a lot of things you're never going to use later on.
You have to somehow predict what's going to happen.
It's not very expensive to design it in a way that you can still do it later.
I don't hardwire the gravity as 9.81
to be able to just give it an mg and then I can put the value
of my equation because I make it a variable.
That's not very expensive to make it a variable.
If I ever use this model at Mars I don't know but maybe even better to have the number in a different place than in the code.
This would be a pretty easy decision. Sometimes it's not so easy.
This is a little bit thinking. It has nothing to do with programming. It's just general problem solving.
If the problem is big you don't do it in one day.
I wake up in the morning and I have a thinking heart and nothing came out.
This is something you need to do.
Consider the aging of the battery.
Nowadays batteries age. You might have also from your laptop in the beginning after a few years
and you might not last that long anymore. These types of batteries have some effect.
Memory effect and what kind of thing.
They lose some capacity over time and then say maybe we would like to
take this into consideration. Maybe in 10 years there will be no batteries.
There's no issue anymore. Who knows?
This is what we want.
Now we have to do a little bit more about the battery. Why not make the battery
your own class? Before we just had a car and the battery was a part of the car.
Now we can make the battery your own class.
This would be a little bit different here.
If it doesn't hurt it's okay. It doesn't make it more complicated.
It doesn't produce a lot more work. If you don't need this thing
it doesn't hurt too much.
Other things.
Keep the time and distance information.
For instance you could class it as stores those information so you can check what happened.
Actually we need it for the printing.
That's where I changed it.
Now we design our class.
This is a decision now.
We are not unbiased. We implemented it before.
We don't get under refresh. We have a battery.
The battery will also become a class.
Here I have the other nouns become attributes of this class.
It's pretty much written in text. Of course the model brand is all attributes of the e-car.
The verbs to drive, to get to, to reach. Maybe not all the verbs will become methods.
But drive and we had already.
The charge is gone. The charge went to the battery.
When you say you charge a car it's actually not correct. You charge the battery of the car if you want.
Then we have the battery. The battery has attributes of size.
We have the verb here.
We use charge as a noun.
This is a process and this is the current state.
Then to charge several times.
Then the nouns we have no use.
Travel time we used before.
They are left over.
This is some thinking. Depending how complex your problem is.
This could also be a tool if you need to talk to other people that are from the domain but not programmers.
That's a good thing because they can write text and they can sort nouns and things.
They can identify what's important.
There's not a single line of piles involved yet.
Now we have the battery. Let's look at these things.
I make a new notebook as always.
We call this analysis.
We analyze everything here.
Again I CD it into my Ecos thing.
I need to check.
I call this object first.
Here I'm reusing the code that I created.
I made it similar to the other one.
We have this prior experience.
I have the E-car and I have a battery.
The battery is new.
Everything that has to do with charging moves to the battery.
That's my new thing.
Otherwise the functionality is exactly the same as before.
The layout is different.
I have two classes.
The battery has
some new features.
It has a size, a current charge, a charging rate, and the effective charging rate.
I can provide that here.
The size is given.
Here the effective charging rate can be none.
Here is the charging rate.
New.
The charging rate is the charging rate that the producer
writes down.
After two years the charging rate is
5%.
The effective charging rate needs to be smaller
than the charging rate.
An error check.
That's my definition.
The charging rate can only be 100%.
Now the charge moved here.
This is the same calculation
we did before.
This is a state.
I can always ask the current charge.
We didn't have this before.
Now we have this information.
I have this current charge to keep track of it.
This is something new.
I don't check theoretically.
I don't check that I have enough.
I can discharge to minus 20%.
You can only discharge to zero.
You get a warning if you discharge below 20% or 10%.
That's something you can do.
When you execute the whole thing,
it will give you the same output as before.
We distributed our content over multiple classes.
We made a battery our own thing.
That's a new element of electric cars.
If you have a good battery, you should have a good car.
It makes sense to have the battery.
This is a result of our design.
We identified the objects that are important.
This is a new design.
Otherwise, if you look at the content of the mathematics,
it's not much new.
Everything that concerns charging went to the battery.
We didn't look at the engine at all.
We didn't even mention it.
For our purpose, we don't have to make it our own class.
If you design electric engines, it might be very different.
Fortunately, electric engines are much simpler than combustion engines.
You don't have all these moving parts.
This is a difference.
If you look at this one, it looks very similar.
I have one small change.
Something moved to the batteries.
If you go back here,
you see here we have the battery size.
The battery size was the property of the car.
Now we have a battery that has a property size.
I want to use the same interface.
I did a small trick.
That must be it.
Did I close the wrong one?
Analyzes.
The battery size.
I still put the battery size in.
The battery size is not stored here, but I give the battery size to battery.
I would like to have a property battery size of the car also.
I want to store the information size only once.
To do this, I use this thing.
Anybody knows what this thing is?
It makes two of what?
You cannot set it.
That's a side effect.
A property is sometimes called a computed attribute.
Let's look at a property.
The typical example of a property is a class square.
Then you have an init.
You get a side.
Square is a rectangle where both sides have the same side.
I define a property
and I call this area.
Define area.
Then I just return
self-side squared.
Now I can make a square instance.
I can say,
okay, this is now the side of five.
Now I can access area and this gives me back.
This is not a method anymore.
You have to put the parentheses.
You can use the process.
It returns this return value of this area.
This can be useful if you start out with a constant value
and you use it and then later on you decide it has to be a method to compute this value because it's not constant anymore.
Then you can use a property.
The API, the outside view of this attribute looks the same.
If somebody accesses this attribute as a constant value, you can use access same.
There's no difference, but in the background something else happens.
You can keep the interface from outside.
That's what I did here.
You can use the property battery size, but actually it just delegates to the battery and gets the size from the battery.
That means the size is only stored inside the battery
and the car asks the battery what's your size instead of storing this value.
You store the value twice and you change it and you have two different battery sizes.
This can work. Of course this generates a coupling between the car and the battery,
but there's a coupling anyway because the battery is only inside the car.
You're only concerned about car batteries.
If you recycle things you might use car batteries later for something else, but that's not our concern here.
The battery is only inside the car, so the coupling is kind of okay.
Those things you can think about if it's always the case and so on.
Now this property from outside looks exactly the same.
I can use the same functions to work with my car, but inside I have a class battery
which now later I could have an algorithm say okay introduce a time
and the battery is aging over time.
The time is still missing.
This is how often is the battery charged and discharged to what degree
because this also influences the lifetime of the battery.
If you discharge very low all the time then probably you reduce the battery capacity very quickly.
You might notice if you don't take care of the battery and just do it then this is very similar.
It depends very much on technology. Soon there will be new technologies that use different kinds of physics
then there might not be that much more.
This is a pretty good code, but this is just a translation.
The main thing goes into analysis first. What I want to achieve, what classes do I need,
how could it develop in the future.
This can lead to a lot of things you implement you're never ever going to need.
In this case it's not so much more complicated.
It's doing the same thing only that I moved something into the class.
Battery here that takes over a few of these things I'm doing.
Good.
Okay.
This is my take on analyzing your problem coming up as a solution.
Do you have any questions about this kind of strategy here?
Yeah.
I didn't understand the question.
Can you repeat?
Yeah.
Good.
Any more questions?
Okay.
This would be the exercise.
Maybe you can get started.
I have a big appendix where I explain how, by the way,
where I get the data from and then how to make the graph.
If you're interested in the graph, I have a long thing about the graph, but just not so important.
This would be the exercise.
Here maybe you can choose a small problem from your domain, then go about, write your user story,
state your assumptions, and then
do this.
The following would be I have an example here about computers, virtual machines, and something like this.
If you don't have an example, this should be still general
enough for programmers that you know what a virtual machine is and you can go to the cloud
and spin up some machines without a lot of details and use a docker
and it's just, if you don't use docker, this is just the thing where you can
install everything with one thing so it will speak and everything runs immediately.
Then there are some assumptions here. You see a long list of assumptions
that we have. This is the given task. Alternatively, come up with your own task
and analyze your own task.
Then go through
the solutions
shouldn't appear here, but the solution is not shown. Explicitly write down
what the program should do, identify classes, methods, and attributes. So no implementation yet
actually. You can implementations, but you can just use stubs.
The methods don't do anything. You just give method names. You come up with class names
and method names, but don't put any implementation. That would be difficult anyway.
The solution is still
sticking here. This would be the exercise
we should do, but let's go back to my presentation.
Advantages.
I wrap up the presentation, then we do the exercise because it's a little bit open-ended.
Advantages of this object under programming. If you want, you can have a higher level
of abstraction because now you can use
better boards from your domain. Those class names, method names might be better than
the class names.
You can use analogy of modeling of real world objects with object representations,
real world things. Inheritance can be good for
code reuse. We've seen this here for those examples.
It's established. Object orientation originates from the 70s, 80s,
and that was the first one. It's not a very new thing. It's been around for a while.
There's also a lot of criticism about object orientation.
The answer on Python is you can always combine object orientation.
You can only do part of your program in this way and the rest the other way. Totally fine.
You can have more extensible design if you do it in the correct way.
Good. Disadvantages. Inheritance creates dependencies.
I told you when you inherit, you get everything from your parent. You have to turn something off.
If you don't want to, you have to turn it off explicitly.
It might lead to a little bit of this over-engineering thing where you add more things.
I still remember I took part in one of those small programming competitions to take a piece of text
and get some references out. I was inspired by the Python solution.
The Python solution was eight lines or so finished. This guy came with a Java solution, 250 lines.
He had the interface here, an interface there, something there.
He solved a lot of problems they didn't ask for.
This could be useful, potentially, but there's a lot of extra work that may not be needed later on.
If you do it wrong, it can make things more complex.
You have all kinds of connections between objects you don't want.
In Python, you have PyLint, PyReverse inside, so you can take your classes and it creates a class diagram.
UML.classDiagram. Usually it's the other way around.
There's a lot of tools.
You can model your objects graphically and then from this they generate code stops.
In Python, you can program your classes and then generate these files.
Then you see who's inherited from whom and how it looks graphically.
That can be useful if everything is connected.
This might be too much. You want to have a clean hierarchy.
You can visualize things and maybe they can be useful not to make your program too complicated.
PyLint.
I think the command is PyReverse.
When you install PyLint and it creates a .file, you need to install this graph to visualize the .file.
There might be other tools. That's a tool I know.
What to do from my perspective in Python you can always use multiple programming paradigms.
We just write functions, use classes, use functional programming.
The list comprehension we did is you might put them into the box functional programming.
Iterators might belong to the box functional programming.
If this is enough and it's small, write functions.
You don't have to always say I have to write a class.
No need.
The important thing is a function gets input arguments and returns an output and shouldn't change the world outside.
If you need to change the world outside, then you should consider a class.
You put everything into a class and you have the self.
You can use the method to change the world.
That's my recommendation.
Use functional features if you like.
You move to the next, you move to the next, you move to the next.
This is something you can use functional features in a better way.
You can combine them in your way.
This is a pretty broad thing, but that's my experience.
We see here this electric car has a state that everything changes, so it makes sense.
It makes sense because something changes over time and you want to keep track of what's going on.
A lot of things are connected. Then having an object is pretty good.
If you just process something and it's really a pipeline, then maybe a functional approach would be better.
Good.
Any more questions?
The exercise is still outstanding, but this is a kind of open-ended exercise.
I gave you some idea.
I have a solution for this exercise I wrote you.
I will add the solution to the zip file, also my notebooks.
Then you have everything in the zip file.
If you feel like you can start now with the exercise, I will stick around.
I will be around through the sprint, so if you can catch me somewhere on the hallway,
then you can always talk to me about these things.
I will stay here for a little bit longer for questions if you want to come.
Otherwise, thank you very much for your being here.
You can start the exercises now or go have lunch or come to me and ask questions.
Thank you very much.