Alright, good afternoon everyone.
Right on the dot.
Thank you all very much for coming to my presentation.
Today I've lured you into talking or attending a talk about Pokemon.
But yeah, the project I'll be talking about is how to transform a Juketrainer notebook into a root-reducible ML pipeline.
Just to give you a bit of an idea of myself, my name is Rob.
I'm from Juketrax in the Netherlands.
I used to be a developer advocate for InternetShip, although I was part of the layout a little while back.
And important for this talk, I may want to talk about Pokemon training.
So a while back in IJuild, where I was part of NetfieData, there I presented projects to create a machine learning model to classify Pokemon.
And that's nothing to become the very best like no one ever was.
And from there on, I wanted to figure out, okay, we've done this, can we do some other Pokemon related stuff?
That's a fun step project that will also help showcase some cool technologies.
And that's what I'll be talking about today.
So you'll probably have heard that StableDiffusion and other text-to-image models are quite huge nowadays.
So my idea was to create a pipeline with which I could create new Pokemon artwork and create some concept art for Pokemon for upcoming games.
So that was the goal of the project.
The approach would be to do a StableDiffusion or use that as a base model, one for Pokemon to be precise, and frame a Laura to adapt the model into actually generating real proper Pokemon projects.
So for those of you who don't know, Laura is an appreciation for low-ranked adoption.
And it's the current beta in trying to get your text-to-image models to produce the best possible output.
And the great thing about this is that you can frame a relatively cheap and quick model that you just put on top of the base model.
And that's something that you can do from your laptop, make the entire pipeline work on my local machine because it's cheap and because it's convenient.
So the implementation, as I think many of you will do here, the first thing I do when I cut a beta-type project is to start working on the Jupyter Notebook because they're great for prototyping.
And if we move over here, I'll quickly take you through the Notebook.
So it's pretty straightforward.
We do our imports and parameters.
This is some housekeeping behind the project rules.
We set some of the model parameters.
So here I'm interested in starting all Pokemon types, like it also changes to water or grass or dragon.
And here we've got some model parameters.
So the max frame stats or the max inference stats for the model is going a little bit, I think it's 5,000 or something.
And that's some stuff for generation.
So text-to-image works with text as an input.
And this is where the prompt comes in.
And as you can see here, we're using the LoRa beta-type trained in the pipeline.
So then we need the diffusers repository from the handling phase.
We need to install the requirements and run a beta prompt text.
These are all stuff you need to do once.
Then I straight the Pokemon images from the Pokemon website.
So one Bulbasaur and an Ice-Taur and a Heem-Taur.
And those are the official concept art images.
Actually, I think that the story goes right here.
If you take a look at our journal data, then these are the kind of images that we're interested in generating.
Having done that, we can get a subset of the relevant Pokemon.
So way of the bath fire is to say how you can set it to only do one of five Pokemon.
So now we'll just do each and every Pokemon.
We need to resize the images.
And then we get the extra font bar, which is training the LoRa.
So this is a beta command.
And these are the settings.
And as you can see here, I'm importing the parameters as we use them in the rest of the notebook.
From there, I just straight forward to set up the pipeline.
So we take the base model, which is set to Fusion 1.5, and we then load the LoRa on top of the model.
And then we can use it to generate images.
So that's something I've already done here.
And we can display those images.
So this is the first result of creating a Pokemon that doesn't exist based on Pokemon that do exist.
Is it any good? I'll let you be the judge of that.
But to be honest, I'm quite happy that at least the art style is fairly similar to what we're getting from the actual Pokemon engine.
So if we then take a look at this implementation.
So these are the results for the same font and exactly the same settings if I only use the base model, set it to Fusion.
And these are the results we get when using the LoRa.
So again, you can be the judge of whether these Pokemon are in use.
But especially the first one, I think it looks like an excellent, but it does reflect Pokemon in effect.
And this is how powerful LoRa can be.
Because with about 20 minutes of training on my own laptop, I get really different and really targeted results.
I'm quite happy with these, I think, in initial experiments.
So then moving on, what I started in from here was experiments to find the best settings to generate the best Pokemon.
And in general, this is something you'll see time and time again in machine learning projects.
Where you just keep experimenting, you keep tweaking some parameters to get to the best Pokemon.
Or to get to the best predictions.
Or more generally, to get to the best or the most performant model.
And there's probably a few data scientists in the room today.
This is what you will be doing as a data scientist.
You're tweaking parameters, you're changing data sets, pushing back and forth to see if we can improve our models.
Because you rarely get the opportunity to just produce a model and keep it in production.
We have to experiment all the time.
Even when we get a performant model and we put it into production, there can still be changes to the business requirements.
We may need to change the context of our model, there may be some data derailment, we just want to keep optimizing.
There are plenty of reasons for us to keep experimenting.
But experimenting gets real messy if we don't keep proper track of what's going on.
So for the Pokemon images I showed you earlier, I can't recreate those right now.
Because I don't know which precise settings I use when generating these images.
And that's not particularly a problem for creating Pokemon sprites or Pokemon artwork.
But it can be an issue when you're doing actually high-stakes model development.
So maybe a quick show of hands.
Who here has been guilty of keeping track of parameters and results in NFL speeds or maybe even a physical note set?
I sure have. That's mostly the room, right?
Because that's easy. You just go back to the form and you tweak some stuff and you write it down.
But it's messier. It gets even messier when you need to work together with your colleagues or your teammates on these projects.
So a while back I was in Berlin and I talked to someone, I think it was roughly similar to this one.
And they actually told me that a while back he was the head of a engineering team for a bank.
And they put a model into prediction about four years ago.
And someone from IRS came up to him and said, hey, you know that model that we had back then?
It makes some funny predictions and we're in a bit of trouble.
So we need to reconstruct what precisely went into that model.
So which data were used to train the model, what parameters, which choices were made.
And the entire team had to spend about two weeks of their time trying to reconstruct that model.
Which is not something you want to do.
And the more models you keep in production, the more difficult it gets to keep track of.
So that's why we need reproducibility.
And it's not enough to just track the model and track the results because then you know what the outcomes of your experiments are.
It's not reproducibility of the experiment.
And just like in science and data science, reproducibility is very important.
So what do we need to do to get to full reproducibility?
If we want to get there, my pitch to you is that we should define an experiment as a specific combination of data, code and parameters.
Because if you have the data, code and parameters, then you can rerun your pipeline, you can rerun your model training, you can rerun your predictions and get the same deterministic outcome.
Or at least that's what we're aiming for.
But this is quite difficult to do.
Or at least for some of the parts, it's difficult to do.
Because for code, this is very much a small problem.
If we look towards data sharing or more broadly software engineering, then of course we'll have Git to keep track of our code.
And Git works really well.
You get it free.
But it only works really well if your file size is relatively small.
So it's great to keep track of changes to a stack.
But maybe less so when you're trying to version your beta test.
So it could be something that's Git for data and that defines the 50 and the size limit in Git.
So some of you may now think, oh, you could use Git LFS for that.
And that's true.
But Git LFS requires a separate server.
And I'm here to give you a product that doesn't require that, which is VPC.
So remember how I told you that I used to work for the greatest VPC of it.
Take that into account.
That's my full disclosure to you.
The good thing is VPC is free of the stores.
So you can give it a go.
And they let me off, so I'll be giving an honest opinion here.
VPC, its main take is data version control.
But there's a little more than that.
Its main features boil down to three components.
So you've got data version control, pipelines and experiments.
And I'll now go through those three components and then show you an implementation of a pipeline made in VPC.
So first, the data version control.
This is a Git repo, as you may recognize it.
So we've got our list of commits.
And in a given commit, we have a data status code form.
So you receive fancy and laptops and catapults.
And those are part of a Git project.
Or sorry, a virtual resource garden.
Now those images, we don't really want to drag in Git itself.
So if we start using VPC, we run vpmit.
And we replace the physical images with a metadata file.
And the metadata file, the data.vp, contains a hash for the images, the size and some other information, the number of files.
And it points towards the VPC cache.
And the VPC cache is where the physical images are actually stored on your password.
And as you can see, the images have moved to the VPC cache.
Their names have completely scrambled up because they're not hashed.
And we don't want to keep track of that manually anyway.
So the VPC cache may look a little odd if you actually dive into the file system.
But you can see it handles the translation between the metadata file in your Git repo and the files in your VPC cache.
And now the beauty of this is that if we create a new commit, so here you can see that the device has changed.
So we've got a new dataset that points towards a different specification in the VPC cache.
So here we removed the bottom Pokemon and we added Ampharos because for now we're currently in Generation 2 of Pokemon.
And the others in Pokemon are still part of the new commit.
So Kenshi and Lepros are part of both commits.
But they don't get duplicated in the cache, which saves you a lot of time, storage and also money.
And then we have this cache, which lives on our local system, in my case, my MacBook.
And we can mirror that to a remote storage, which can be an S3 bucket, a Google Drive, an SSTP server, anything you'd like to do.
So once we mirror that and we apply the same basic principles of versioning our data as we do for code, we can start using that in some more interesting contexts.
So we can just do data versioning, but you can also automate that based on Python.
So this is the setup I showed you earlier in the notebook.
Roughly, we've got cohesive sets of codes.
So first we set up the user, then we download the Pokemon stats, we straight the images, we resize those images, then we train Laura and we generate the set data.
And if we go from top to bottom, much like you would in your notebook, then you get the results of that.
But each and every one of those stages produce an output or multiple outputs.
So here we see, for example, that the resize Pokemon in a stage creates new Pokemon styles of a new size.
And if we specify those outputs, we can also use them as dependencies for downstream stages in each stage.
So if we then tell the train Laura stage that the process Pokemon directly is a dependency, then we can make sure that the train Laura stage only triggers once the images have been resized and placed in the process directory.
And what's great about this is that oftentimes you won't change all of the stages at once.
So for example, if I change the train Laura stage, then that doesn't affect all of your buff stages.
And we don't need to rerun those, and you can cache the outcome of it and just feed it to our model train.
So we can then restructure this as a DAG, where each of the stages is dependent on the outcome of the stages that are treated.
So that's the pipeline. And then we can start using that pipeline to run experiments.
So this is our pipeline where we do some stuff, or we do some inputs and outputs.
So the input is the code, the data, and the parameters, and the outputs can be the model itself, but maybe also some plots, some metrics, anything that's the result of our model train.
And as we discussed, we want to version each and every one of those components with either this or this.
So as we've written some small files, we versioned in Git, and the larger files, which is the images, are in the mobile cell tree version with these keys.
And if we do all of that together, then we can consider one pipeline run as an experiment, or more technically speaking, as a Git commit.
And now if we want to go back through our history to find our pre-hint experiments, we can simply do a Git checkout.
So here we see that parameters changed for one of the previous experiments.
The other stuff stays the same, but because the parameters changed, we've got an effect that models plots metrics.
And with Git checkout and then the Git checkout, we can quickly pull out those results.
So, implementation number two.
And this is where we get to the fun part, the code.
So I will pull up the code.
Is this big enough for all of you to see?
Good.
So let's take a look here.
We are in our first four environments.
And the first thing I did, so we have the notebook still here.
I could remove it at this point, but I split this up into separate files from my list.
So if we go to SST, for example, we've got the straight-flow font initiative.
This has got precisely the same content roughly as the notebook, but with some more boilerplate so that we can run this module from our command line.
So if we then use that command, we can use that command in a DSTMF file.
So these are the pages, as we showed them earlier.
And of course, without having to use users, we can create Pokemon images.
Let's put a little bit down.
So for example, the Resized Pokemon image is here.
It simply runs this command.
So it's a Python pre-thread.
It runs Resized Pokemon images for five.
And it passes the parameters from the grounds that Yamal has.
And in DST, we can also specify our dependencies.
So that's the existence of the Python module.
But also the existence of these files so that we don't get almost high data.
And it's got a number of outputs that are the result of this page.
And then we pass the parameters, which are passed in some grounds by Yamal.
So here we have our overview.
We can change the seeds.
We can change the learning rate.
We can change the maximum set.
And then with these two combined, we can run the DeepFight line from our command file.
So for example, let's change the seed of our int generation.
So we're a Python 25.3.
So let's change it to that.
I think we'll be fine just generating maybe three Pokemon right now.
Let's go with this one.
I will speed it up a little by doing fewer and fewer.
Yeah.
OK.
Cool.
Thanks.
So if we now do DeepFight repro, which stands for reproduce, we can...
Oh, hey, there we go.
We can now use DeepFight repro to reproduce our Python.
And you see, as you will see, it has passed the underlying stages, so it's kicking up.
And then taking it up where we generate our test data.
And we can see the images come in in our output folder.
It will take a little while.
So two steps.
I shouldn't forget to put the mic on as well.
There we go.
And this one returns an entirely black image because apparently state diffusion thinks that this is not suitable for work content.
If you've been around the Internet in the past few months, then you will have seen that state diffusion and our test image models are gradually being used to generate much suitable for work content.
They are trying to comb that.
But yeah, you also get some false positives.
So this is the first result.
I don't know what type of Pokemon we're looking at.
Maybe teal, maybe dark.
Could be ice.
I don't know.
But yeah, fairly happy with at least our style.
This one's quite good.
It's got ice.
It's got an appropriate amount of lint.
I think this might be flying grass if anyone wants to pitch them in for the concept Pokemon hitting up after the show.
So we've got our free image generated.
And now we could do a git gist.
There we go.
Git commit.
Oh, sorry.
I should have said git after for us.
That's for the audience.
Git commit.
And generate Pokemon with 25, 32.
There we go.
And then we could reach out to our remote.
And now if we take a look at our git log, we can see our different commits that we generated.
So we ran a few of these experiments before coming here.
So right now you'll see that first of all, rams.yml has the speeds that we specified and the images are there.
Now if we go back to one of the experiments that I ran earlier.
So for example, the speed with, let's take this on speeds 1500.
So quick.
And then git checkout.
And on hash.
Then we can see that rams.yml has been updated.
And we now have the speeds from the previous experiment.
Now I can see that the output still hasn't changed.
And that's because those are checked by the EC, so we also need to run these speed checkout.
And if you like, you can automate this.
Whenever you run git checkout, git speed checkout gets run as well.
So to do these speed checkout, we retrieved the images from the cache.
And hash comes out the Pokemon that we created earlier.
Also just found one here.
Let's see if there's anything else I would like to show.
I think that's the most important part.
I could quickly show the dbc cache.
So here we've got the cache.
And as you see, it's split up in nonsensical directories where we've got files based on the hash.
Which you can see here.
Then if you're a user of VS Code, you may also be interested in the dbc extension for VS Code.
It's not the most useful here because our results are in the system, our outputs, and the difficulty ratios.
So we don't get an automatic score to see how each experiment performs.
But if you do, so for example, if your target is an Apple 1-4, then you can specify that as a metric.
And we can compare those experiments in our experiment table.
So for example, we can see what parameters we changed and then which metrics are the results.
And from here we can also have done new experiments for example.
So yeah, that's a more visual approach to what you can also do on the command line.
So much for the implementation.
Then the recap and takeaways.
I hope this has been somewhat insightful.
The takeaways I'd like you to take home is in data science we experiment constantly.
And so we rarely get to just put a model into production and leave it there.
To do proper experimenting, we need free-to-use ability because otherwise we're just messing around.
Much like science, we need to be able to reproduce the results for them to have any value.
And Jutri notebooks are great for prototyping but not so much for read-to-use ability.
I don't think I actually highlight this, but let me just, I've got a little bit of time.
Why Jutri notebooks aren't great for read-to-use ability.
First of all, whenever you run them, their metadata changes.
So you'll get a completely new file in your GIF repository.
And there are ways to mitigate that, but it's not a nice way of working.
Also, you can jump back and forth arbitrarily between cells, which makes it non-deterministic.
Yeah, and the file size thing gets quite large in notebooks.
Again, I'm really not basking you for this. I think you're a great tool.
But once you get to the point where you have a working prototype or you have something that you're happy with
and you want to quickly run some test experiments,
my suggestion would be to move over to a pipeline,
which we can run with a single command rather than getting through this process.
So that's all we've been doing. We can achieve this combination on GIF and VPC.
And then we can track the data, the code, and the parameters.
VPC is then used for the data version control and the pipeline and the experience management.
That concludes my talk. Thank you very much for attending and for your effort and attention.
I hope you take something away from this.
As I mentioned, I'm open to work, so if you have an exciting opportunity, this is all about that.
I've got a few further resources.
So the easiest one is to go to roplinit.nl, my personal website, and the slides are there,
so you can take a look at the further resources.
The other one, dbc.org for the docs, and dbc.org for the Discord community.
They actually do the community part really well, and it's easy.
We can help if you're starting out.
And you will also find the links in the slides of our Discord, so I use the created project.
Thank you very much.