Hello, welcome everyone to our second talk today.
So our next speaker is Chitin Ho.
She will be giving a talk on kind of
trying to deal with scientific programming.
So please welcome her to the stage.
Thank you.
My computer is leaking so I have to wait.
Right.
Hello everyone.
So thank you so much for coming to my talk.
I know it's the last talk of today,
excluding the last talk.
You may be very tired.
But I feel that if you are here,
then you must have some questions in your mind
that you want to clear up.
And maybe scientific programming is your thing.
That's why you're interested in it.
Or maybe you want to understand more about GIL.
That's why you're here.
Or GIL or GIL.
I don't know how you pronounce it.
GIL.
You prefer GIL?
Okay.
So I usually would say the first slide
is usually the most important slide of the whole slide deck.
Because you have the link to the slide deck.
So once you have this slide,
you have the rest of the slide deck.
So let's talk about GIL.
So you know,
that's why it's so difficult to pronounce it
because it's actually the first letter of a term.
So who knows what this term is?
Ooh, a lot of you.
I feel like I don't have to explain so much.
But can you shout out to me?
Yes, it's a GoPro interpreter lock.
But before that, I'm going to tell you about me first.
I'm Hyt.
I work for Alaconda.
And I love open source projects.
In the past, I was involved in different open source projects.
And I love community.
I love conferences.
That's why I'm always trying to be there
and connect with you all.
And I also help organize some of them as well.
So GIL.
Talk about GIL.
Global interpreter lock.
So D-I-L.
That's why I, again, like sometimes
I don't know how to pronounce it.
So, well, it's in English.
It's global interpreter lock.
But it doesn't explain a lot of things.
So people who may hear this term the first time,
like for example, like the first time I heard about it,
I was like, can someone explain it to me please?
So I know some of you is already like maybe you're an expert
in the field or something.
But for the people who are not, I will be trying to maybe
give you some information.
So the thing about Python, Python is very interesting.
So Python is very user friendly, you know,
very good for beginners and stuff.
And also Python is very, very secure.
One thing about Python that is Python is interpreted
in a way that is not, just by default,
is not doing multi-threading.
So what does that mean?
So because Python, by default, has this global interpreter
lock in it, so this lock is locking that so that only one
thread can actually access an object at a time.
So it means that, you know, all these like kind of very
fancy things and like, you know how many call your laptop
has?
Probably more than four right now.
So, you know, because of Python's nature of having
the global interpreter lock, no matter how many calls
your computer has, it will be the only one that can access
your Python object at a time.
So what's the good thing about it is not that we are talking
about like, oh, we want to get rid of it, of course,
we will get to that part.
But before that is that why Python was defined this way
there are actually some advantages.
One of them is being that multi-threading is something
that's quite tricky because if we look deep down into
things, right, look deep down into each kind of moment how
Python, when Python is running, what's going on,
it makes it seem like if Python doesn't have the global
interpreter lock and two threads trying to access the same
object at the same time, it's not a good thing.
The computer doesn't work that way.
So, you know, you can imagine what's going on, right?
Imagine there's a car and there's two persons sitting,
you know, usually one is driving, one is sitting next to
the driver, but now if two threads, actually the same object
is kind of like two persons is fighting over the steering wheel.
One friend is trying to do something, turn left,
and the other friend is trying to turn right,
and it is like the fact that it's going to happen.
So, that's why this global interpreter lock is a very
simple way to solve this problem is that, you know,
we are driving from point A to point B and we only have one
best-amidst driver.
We won't be doing anything fancy except because we have
only one driver, it won't be someone who other than the
driver touching the steering wheel.
But of course, this is not where everything works and how
Python works is the, you know, someone started this problem
by using the global interpreter lock which is
simplified things.
But, for example, there are other programs that maybe
support multi-threading.
What they do is that they would actually change the driver
in the middle of the trip.
So, imagine you have a long trip and you sometimes, you know,
go to service station and then there's this driver,
that can happen, you know, I mean that is not, you know,
it's impossible, you can only have one driver, it can happen,
but the interpreter will be much more complicated.
So, Python decided to, you know, release the GIL instead of
changing driver.
So, what is no-GIL Python?
So, especially for this version that I talked about is a
clone of Python 3.9.
So, you may already feel that, well, 3.9 is ancient history.
Now we are at which Python version?
3.11?
Yes.
You know, some talk is even talking about 3.12 already.
So, yeah, like this one I just feel like history is true.
But, actually, you use UI and, you know, as we talk about this,
because it's the latest attempt to remove the GIL.
In the past, there's actually like four attempts to do that,
right?
We have all these very smart people, smart Python experts,
you know, we have attempts to remove the Python GIL before.
So, I hope that doesn't surprise you.
Otherwise, like, oh, yeah, yeah, oh, it's true that I can't see
you.
I'm so sorry.
But I will talk to you after this book.
So, you know, they have tried many times.
You can see like every few years someone will give it a go,
you know, but then maybe, you know, the discussion doesn't
carry on.
Then, you know, someone else try again.
And this is the latest attempt by Sam Gross.
I heard about it actually last year in your question because
he was giving me keynote.
So, a lot of this information is that I'm giving it before I show
you my experiment results.
So, this talk actually, let me, you know, give you some
overview.
I'm going to give you this information that is like, you
know, that I digest about like what I know about GIL Python,
and then I'll show you the experiment results that I've
done.
So, but you may, so let's go back to the topic, right?
Like, but why we want to give Python, well, I think, I hope
the analysis already kind of, you know, about driving will
give you the idea that if we have only one driver, then even
if you, for example, you go on a trip, right, you have multiple
drivers available.
Everybody got a driving license.
They're all very good drivers, you know, very good
behavior.
They're not drunk.
But for some reason, right, we have like, you know, we do a
lucky draw and someone who was destined to be a driver,
I'm so sorry, the trip is 10 hours and you have to go, you
know, you are the best driver and you have to drive all the
way for 10 hours.
This is not interesting, right?
For example, my computer got eight cores.
I have eight drivers, but it would be better if I can fully
utilize, right?
Everybody, you know, then, you know, they can, you know,
switch.
So maybe if with one driver, they would get exhausted, then
they may be good slower just to be more safe.
But if you have, you know, everybody took a turn, then
maybe, you know, we can go very efficiently.
So before we call, we can actually, you know, in theory,
things will be more efficient and we can trust that we can use
all resources from the computer.
So, but there's, like I said, a very simple way of finding the
gil and there's a reason why, right?
Because this challenges, if you want to remove the gil to make
sure that we don't have a disaster where this happens.
So first of all, if, for example, imagine we suddenly let
the, well, it's not happening, but imagine in a hypothetical
scenario, 3.12 suddenly we, no gil, yay.
Then what if, you know, someone who want to do things
efficiently, they can go further things, then it will be very
slow for them because it's not designed for them, it's only
designed for others rather than the result, which I think
the community won't be happy about it.
So before, you know, if one day Python takes a decision to do
it, then we, of course, need to specify all the uses that
everybody got in a CIFT, not just create some pit of users,
right?
And also, all these are technical difficulties, you know,
reference counting, you know, because before we have one driver,
we have one person who knows the map, who knows, like, when to
turn and stuff, all the information won't be lost because
it's very organized.
Imagine, like, everybody, you know, one person, they just pick
one to drive his car and then, you know, some people are like,
oh, you want to make sure you turn left and turn right, you know,
and then what?
Can you say that again?
So when they are, like, multi-thread, sometimes, like, when
they, you know, reference objects, so what Python is doing now is
that, like, we would always have, you know, counting how many
references are to an object.
When there's no reference to this object, that means that we don't
need it and then it's heading to, you know, kind of do some magic
things, to do some garbage collection, to free up the memory,
all this stuff.
But if this reference counting got messed up, like, you know, all
this information on the map got messed up, then we won't get to
the destination and things will go wrong.
So there are actually some tricks that this version of Python is
deploying to, you know, solve this problem.
For example, some commonly used object, if you have to kind of do
reference counting and, you know, all these different threads have to
share some information that's too complicated, how about we just make
them immortal because, you know, they just stay there forever until
we end the program and we free the memory.
So there's no use to reference count, but because those are commonly
used objects, right, so we won't lose out, almost because they need to
be referenced a lot of times anyway.
Or sometimes, like, there's a technique that was used, it's called,
like, the third reference counting, so it's actually when doing the
garbage collection, then some reference count will be adding back, so
kind of, you know, we kind of, you know, after drinking and eating and
then we kind of look at the bill and then we kind of decide, like, okay,
how much we take, right, and at the end we kind of, you know, do the
calculation correctly.
So also, you know, Python objects, right, a lot of them are mutable.
So, for example, the object that we all love, you know, it's not really
they are actually mutable objects, so, you know, it's not a good thing
when you have multiple threads, because, you know, again, two threads can
change something at the same time, it's going to be very, very weird.
So instead of having a global encoder lock to lock everything to only one
driver, we would have a small lock, which means that, for example, the
piece of the station on the highway, we won't take driver, right, that's
dangerous, because, you know, you're going, like, 18 miles an hour, and
you're going to have to use it only to train drivers at the service station.
So here, so we use smaller lock, we lock that journey, right, being between
service stations, we are not changing drivers, but these are smaller locks.
So instead of the whole journey, one lock, locking one driver, it's a big
question, we have the best way to drive it, but we can change it.
So then it means that we have to have some change of define for key Python.
We have to write some new Python API to, you know, increment this small lock,
so there's the new functionality that needs to be added.
And also, Python uses built-in memory-allocated time-alog, so for those of
you who know, you already know I don't have to explain, but for those of you
who doesn't know, Python has allocate memory by, you know, blocks for small
operations and they bundle them together, this is like second boxes.
So that works for Python right now because we have to do.
But without it too, there's these things that need to be implemented.
So, instead of any scheme, I have this new now lock, so it's a different kind of
mechanism, I won't go into detail because, you know, it's very complicated.
So all these internal stuff needs to be changed.
And also, sometimes, you know, you have to stop the world from garbage collection
because, you know, what if I need that and then you thought I don't need it
because the other spread said that, oh, oh, oh, oh, okay, that's better.
I want to lower memory, I hope it's fine.
So yeah, you have to, sometimes, you know, because you thought I don't need that object
to be the other spread, especially using it, the communication is wrong, so you have
to stop the world and again, like, it's really, we don't need it, okay, we can get rid of it.
So, so all these are actually how, you know, Node.Gil Python is actually, that's why,
it's only get tried, even though it's very useful, so I've noticed, I think that it's
kind of a holy grail of very fast Python, but it's only been a 24 times, it's just,
you know, you can see the complications and then now it's up to a fee fee.
Actually, this is something that's kind of like a picture and you have, you know,
to change the design of Python.
But what about scientific programming?
Because we all know scientific calculation is a very time consuming thing,
especially for data scientists or scientists who handle a lot of data.
So that would actually be very time consuming and also like resources consuming process.
So those are the things, like you may have heard about NumPy, you know,
how to learn audit from a civic library.
They are designed to be, to handle all these mathematical calculations relatively efficiently.
With a lot of different help, for example, if you look at the source code of NumPy,
you will see it, instead of like all the code, all the source code is .py, there's like some .cpy,
those things. So those are the external kind of things that help to speed up all these calculations.
Sometimes they would maybe use a different color, NumPy, I just gave her a tutorial yesterday.
So it's something that can be so strict to speed up your calculations.
Also, Cython is also a thing that compiles on Python code in the C before hand and it can be faster.
So, by applying Node-Drop Python, because we are trying to achieve the same thing, right?
With Node-Drop Python, how further of these libraries to have their speed up?
So we already are kind of, you know, the maintainer of the NumPy second-hand library.
They already apply a lot of tricks to speed up the process.
We'll apply Node-Drop Python even further to speed it up.
Or, well, it's the price of that it doesn't work, or even worse in some cases,
because it's not designed for that, it's some hiccup there.
So I want to test it. I'm very curious about it.
And also, you know, I'm from a data science background, I'm really curious that whether we find a new tool,
or even tool that like can help us to have faster work, we don't have to wait for the whole day
for the experiment to finish, right?
So, I've designed something to test it, so it's, you know, it's not a research paper that I spent years
to write a paper and publish it in some scientific journals,
or it's not going to be super high-file scientific to bear with me.
So, in my mind, what I want to test is, first of all, I want to try something with Pure Python.
Because when I kind of start looking at mobile Python, I remember that there is some kind of
speed comparison, I've seen that it's the original, which is 3.9, and then there's like speed equaled one,
if I remember correctly, it's a 40 frames, something like that.
So I want to try it myself to see if I use Pure Python, whether I thought it's 3.2.
Then, so that's the baseline, right?
So that's the baseline, right? That's supposed to be input, because someone already did the experiment
and just to make sure that everything works.
And then I'm going to try it on some algorithms that we use a lot in Pricular, those kind of
the codec machines, those kind of things, NumPy, because again, it's a very huge matrix of numbers
and because it works well together, and since I'm trying to do it, I end up don't do too much
of the Python calculation because, you know, I focus on such and I'm in NumPy.
So, also I want to do something about Neural Network, because Neural Network, for my part,
the students usually takes a long time because of the training, of the loop, so I want to try something
about that as well.
So, in this experiment, I will of course compare the Node-Bio version and original 3.9 version,
but since now we have the sadly 3.11 version, which is supposed to be also maybe sometimes
20% faster than 3.9, so I want to compare it, like, allowed to be in the race.
So, the code I tested on GitHub, so the GitHub, if you find the link, I have this, so one thing
that I have improved ever, because this is not the first time I do this experiment,
I thought that before I only run it on my local machine, it's super not scientific, which is,
you know, don't do it like I did, but I won't be reproducible without, that's why I put everything
in this code report, and so what I did is that I would have a lot of tests, so I would run,
so I write some Python and also bash grid to execute the code.
Inside the code, there would be some timing function to calculate the time, and all the result
will be exported to 2.0 BIOS, which output the full file outage that I also do some
view profiling, as well just for feel free if I want to investigate more about which part actually
maybe takes long time or which part has the best improvement, I think, look more into detail.
So, this is, as you can see, is run on a use-github action, so it's reproducible.
If you want to do it yourself, if you pull this ripple, change whatever you want to change,
so every time you make some changes and push it back, the GitHub action will be triggered.
So as you can see here, I have run a lot of experiments in the past, so once the experiment is done,
so we get a green tick, and then it will push a new branch, so it just kind of number it,
because this is different time, so I have a few attempts here, this is a special attempt,
and then you would get this output of tests and then profile out text, so this is the output file
that is run by a experiment. So it's not very neat, the report, but like I said before,
it runs on three different versions, and then all the results are recorded, all of them,
because of accuracy, you know, some kind of strategic programming and stuff, you know,
they may have some discrepancies, so I loop them and then I trace them out, so this is the result.
Basically, you can see what's going on here, so I've put them into practice life.
So, so first of all, this is the baseline, it's usually two Python to generate velocity numbers,
we all have seen those on the textbook, we don't have to look at the code, and I hope you already know how to do it.
So I've generated 25 numbers in the RedBlood series, and compared their performance,
so as you can see, as promised, no good Python is super fast, it's like ticking only half the time,
but this is, remember, this is GitHub Action, right? GitHub Action, because I didn't pay for extra resources,
GitHub Action only gave me two calls on this Ubuntu-based image, which is Ubuntu.
So this is, so this becomes the factor, if you look at 3.11, 3.11 is actually not slow,
but in still, it can't beat no good Python, so you can see all the claims that we have heard before by the different developers,
it's correct, no good faster than 3.9, and 3.11 is faster than 3.9 because there's inclusion in 3.11.
So, but this is, what I really want to see, right, this is the scientific one, this is, you know,
there's a whole support vector machine, we want to, so this is the very typical example you can find on the NumPy documentation,
and it's recognized, I hand-written the case, so I use the support vector machine,
and then you can see that actually there's no significant difference, you can kind of, you know,
if you run the theorem a long time, you know, one can be faster than the other, you know, the other way around,
because there's no significant difference in the, in the graph, so, you know, it's not a good thought.
Then I prepare more experiments, so this is clustering, so what this does is that, again,
they're kind of with the digits, but if they're using different methods, it costs a death,
again, note the difference, some of the results actually note that it's worse than the others,
so that is something that, you know, oh maybe because we already have to speed up,
and look at how much to sign for it, you know, maybe it isn't, you know, the scientific result,
something's wrong, this is the thing though, this is the thing, the logo is still faster,
I don't know why, I still have to investigate more, so if you want to, you can help me out,
you can, you know, pro-clone the code and have a look at the profile and maybe you can figure out why and what we know of this.
So, 80 algebra, I highlighted the fastest one, so again, you know, even this, you know,
3.11 is not fixing 3.9, so, you know, it's not easy, especially on scientific programming, right?
Again, it makes me think that, you know, very fast, I don't know why, I actually have a theory,
I'll tell you at the end, so, and I think that finally there's something that 3.11 is, you know,
get the first price, it's the fastest, it's kind of similar performance to 3.9, but Nokia is significantly slower.
I am kind of disappointed because at the beginning I thought that I found a new core,
I can speed up my work and I can tell everybody, see, this Nokia Python is amazing.
And it's, you know, we need to look at what happened.
So, why we don't see much difference in a lot of results, I think my speculation may be correct
because in a lot of those mathematics scientific libraries, we, the things that have already,
have a lot of external packing to speed up, right?
They already optimize the best they can and a lot of times the optimization is taking things
out of Python to get taken care of.
So, pure Python is a significantly smaller role in that.
Also, this kind of communication, you know, the extensions and Python itself,
it's actually, you know, from the development of the class, right, for example, if you compare them
to like even 3.9 to 3.11, sometimes 3.9 is faster than 3.11, it may be when this extension,
when this speed up was defined, it has been developed over time and it's been, you know,
it has been developed over time and it's not the native 3.11, it's something new that's trying to be very fast.
And then, you know, it's out of expectation, so maybe the communication between the extensions
and the Python part is not as what is expected.
So, in the future, if this, you know, if we come here, the essential removing the gifts,
of course, like compatibility needs to be taken care of.
And so, but, but not all hope is lost.
I'm only comparing the results, I only run on a free version of GitHub engine, it's only dual call.
So, maybe, because, you know, we have multiple call, multiple thread, you know, if you have more call,
of course, like if there is any speed up, the difference may be more significant.
So, maybe because I'm running on dual call machine, the difference is not big enough to show in every style,
because, again, it's always on discrepancy, so maybe it's already got hidden,
because it's not, the difference is not big enough.
So, this, Node.Github is still working process, Sam is amazing, amazing maintainer,
every time I was like, you know, I want this library to provide that for me, he would provide for me,
like I say, which is amazing. So, he's still working on it.
So, what do we learn, what do we learn, like, you know, they've been sitting here for like almost half an hour.
So, first of all, Python is very versatile, when, you know, Python started, it's, you know,
it's for ease of use, so it's very easy to jump on and get started.
But then, when we do more kind of sophisticated things, like data science and all that stuff,
then all this stuff cannot edit. So, it may be a good thing that we have four different tools for different jobs,
so Python is kind of like a Swiss army knife, it can handle a lot of different things, so it's a good thing.
But then, it makes that, creating a general strategy to make things faster for everybody is almost impossible,
because, you know, it may be faster for pure Python people, but then, like for people who are using mathematical calculation,
then it's a different game. So, I want to get this opportunity to thank all of those open source maintainers,
core developers, and Simon and Phil, that is an amazing work, a lot of effort to try to improve the tool that we use every day,
so thank you very much for them. And it comes to the end of my talk, so I hope that you get these flybacks,
because they are very good, you know, you can watch the Sanxinok right here at EuroPython, you know,
also last year there was some discussion in the Language Summit, and Lucas Rafferty proposed about it,
so you can also check that out. So, EuroPython, right, so maybe this year we will also have amazing keynote at EuroPython,
so maybe you'll consider going, so take a look at that. And the last thing, please check out the Colors Group,
you know, we have a lot of demonstrations that may be interesting to you, and also, we are building a community,
so we are looking for community leaders in the beta client, so if you're interested,
this Q&A talk will bring you into the forum, and if you just tell us that, like, you know, introduce yourself,
and you're interested, then we will talk to you later. So, I think I'm running out of time for questions,
thank you so much for coming here, next will be a live speech talk in the main hall, so I hope you have a nice conference.