Welcome to the final talk of Python 2023.
You have made it. Congratulations.
Yeah, that's better. A round of applause.
Yeah. Okay.
So our final presentation today will be using Python to help the unhoused by Josh Weisbach and Sheila Flood.
They just asked that we do a Q&A for them after the session to catch them outside in the hallway.
This is going to run pretty close to the end of the time here.
So without any further ado, please join me in giving a round of applause to our two speakers for the final talk for Python 2023.
Good afternoon, everyone. Thanks for joining us for your last talk here at Python.
So yeah, a favor to talk about how to use Python to support an NGO to help the unhoused in Victoria, BC.
Quick introductions. I'm Josh Weisbach. I've been using Python since you had a six.
I'm currently living in Ottawa, Ontario, Canada. I'm actually from Victoria, so this is a hit post to home for me.
Right now I work within the Canadian Federal Government doing data science.
I also have a PhD this fall at Cross University in data science.
And with me on my team, or for this team for this project, is my shield, Sheila Flood.
Hi everyone. My name is Sheila Flood. I'm a data scientist and sort of cross-medialist.
I have a master's in cross statistics and a background in risk analytics and strategy.
Let's see. Let's get into it.
So currently there are over 1,500 people experiencing homelessness in Victoria, BC.
To kick our perspective, that is the largest percent of population anywhere in Canada.
The second and third largest cities are Vancouver, who have twice the many people experiencing homelessness,
with a population seven times larger, and Toronto with a population 30 few times larger,
but seven times as many people as three times less.
So this is a big issue within the city of Victoria, BC.
So those of you who aren't familiar with where Victoria is, it's the capital of British Columbia from the west coast of Canada.
It's on the southern tip of Vancouver Island, which we're going to stick with now,
which is the main city of Vancouver.
And for this talk, we need to reference Victoria. We're talking about the capital region district,
which is actually 13 different cities in the southern tip of Vancouver Island.
The city of Victoria, plus 12 other cities, such as New Toson, Duke, Esquimalt, Langford.
But when we say Victoria, we're talking about all of them combined into one area.
So trying to help the people experiencing homelessness in Victoria is an NGO called the Greater Victoria Coalition on Homelessness.
This is what they're known plus for, this project.
They actually just presented themselves to the Alliance to End Homelessness in the capital region.
They were paid back in 2007, when the mayor of the day started a task force to address funding solutions
to help people experience homelessness in the community.
This evolved into what became the NGO, and there's a group of people in the community trying to find a cage of institutions
to help people who need it the most.
It comprises of social workers, healthcare workers, government, businesses, religious organizations,
people who are experiencing homelessness who have a sense of homelessness,
thinking that anyone in the community who has some integral piece to the solution
are working together to try to find a solution.
Now, part of the NGO is they would often go online and look on Twitter, they would look on Reddit,
they would look at the CDC and the news articles, and try and figure out what the current sense is about people
experiencing homelessness in the community, and also to know where it would be if they had any problems
or a problem area, or a street problem area.
They could then use this information to know where to direct them in their resources to try and help the community.
It's taken a lot of people hours, so they decided they needed a tool to help do it.
So with that, they went to statistics and web borders in order to come up with a tool to help monitor
the sense of homelessness within the community.
Yep, so this is how we got involved with the project, which is Fixed Without Borders.
SWB is a volunteer outreach group that's part of the American Statistical Association,
and they provide poor borders with the support of data science services to NGOs and different global organizations
specifically who wouldn't have access to such resources.
So GBC and EH reached out to SWB with their project proposal.
SWB reviewed it, it was accepted, and then together they formed the State and the Work,
which as Josh was mentioning, involves reporting on online social media posts by citizens
that are related to homelessness in the Greater Victoria area.
So in January 2022, we each got this email.
This is about people calling for volunteers, and this is pretty standard for SWB if anyone is interested in looking to get involved.
Just go onto the specific website where you spoke to them, you fill out an online form of information,
you're getting an email super quick.
And then I say that if you decide to come times a year, you'll get an email such as this form calling for volunteers.
If you're interested, all you have to do is respond, especially if you're interested in the project, you can get such a resume,
explain your credentials, and then if you're supposed to keep up with the project,
there will usually be an interview step or otherwise you'll get an email saying that enough volunteers have already been called
and the call is being closed.
So our team consisted of seven individuals from five different countries.
We had a three team mates and then four of us were given different components of the application.
There was the integration, the modeling, the dashboard, and the spacing component.
And then we also met by twice a month over the past year to work on this project.
We used free communication tools such as Slack, Google to meet and communicate with women.
And then the special guests were really awesome.
Yeah, so the team leads were from SWED and the NGO came together and ultimately came up with a statement of work to help define what we needed to do.
The very first step was that was creating, was a 27th analysis on tweets about the subject of people's trans and homelessness in Victoria.
So the team lead and the NGO put these together.
So they gave us a key to finally list the keywords they wanted us to start looking at to help identify the relevant tweets.
As a team, on the more technical side, we put our heads together and decided we would come up with just a straightforward pipeline.
We're going to do it all in Python and we're going to do it all free.
The NGO is going to continue to run it at whatever cost it may involve, additional resources.
It's a pipeline, pretty straightforward, exactly what we expect.
We're going to build a scraper, collecting information.
We're going to put the collected data to a sentiment model, which will apply the sentiment on the tweets.
And then we have a dashboard for the non-technical users to be able to actually look at the collected data, come up with their own analysis of the subject, and be able to make their own decisions within the NGO.
And underline all that, we had an integration layout which helped connect the different pieces so they could talk to each other.
So right away, we started working on the scraper.
Scraper was my team.
As we said, the statement of work gave us a predefined list of keywords to collect relevant tweets,
to help identify which tweets are actually relevant to the subject of people, students, and home staff, and in the region of the target audience.
These are the capital of the region of the scraper.
From a Python perspective, we just used TPUs, a simple package that wraps the query API.
These panels help collect the most data.
We collected additional metadata on the tweets that were collected, so it's like we're developing a Lights 3T quote tweet.
We tried looking at geodata on tweets to actually identify tweets that were coming from this partner, which would be a huge problem because less than 1% of tweets actually had geodata.
We also experimented with user-provided profile locations, which had some help.
And also, this paper corrected what we thought were the relevant tweets and stored in the CSVs.
Getting a little bit more perspective on what that looked like, like I said, the NGO and the statement of work provided us with keywords to help identify the site that the tweets were looking for.
So the first part was tweets about people's experience in homelessness.
So that was divided into words that were related to the subjects.
We used in the story typical words of poor, crime, poverty, sex, camping.
We talked about sectors, so larger groups related to people from homelessness, so frontline workers, pay to supply, car reduction, and then actual organizations in the local community who were involved in this,
whether it was the districts, different cities, the businesses those cities.
And the second part was words related to identified tweets that were actually coming from Victoria, DC.
So a letter was the neighborhoods, a prior better word is cities, the affected call with, life, or the clothing and street.
Region identifiers, so again, the Greater Victoria, Victoria, DC, hashtag YYJ, the local airport, or influencers.
So in this case influencers began your local politicians, the mayors, organizations began helping people from homelessness in the community.
So as it was great for it wasn't difficult on its own, the underlying issues started rising to start to come up.
First was limited Twitter support, API support, even back in 2012.
There's no way to really get hold of anything on Twitter, no way to verify and ask questions.
We had to go into the feed and Discord a lot for actual technical advice.
There's a lot of issues around version 2 versus version 1.1.
And we were also even trying to hope to get a, sorry, after-miss account.
So we started looking at a historical purpose of feed to look at how feeds from Victoria were forming fast.
Of course we started blocking out different API restrictions, so we couldn't get that API, or the accurate API.
We couldn't get ahold of some Twitter to actually help us figure out how to get that space.
We had to go forward with the basic limitations.
So we ended up having to be only look at seven days of history of feed-fitted cards, which meant that we had to establish
some sort of routine collection that looked at some period of human life seven days.
That ended up affecting our feature decisions with the inspiration we were going to have with the dashboard map.
Another interesting issue with the Twitter API is you're limited on a number of tweets that you can actually make in a series.
You can make for tweets within a 15-minute window.
First you start with a batch scraping and break down that into X number of tweets for 15 minutes, over 15 minutes to fill in the scraper.
It's going to be difficult with our under-applied integration issues.
We started with some blue-nated keyword logic, sometimes adding some of the keywords together, which actually
for a search has some pretty powerful blue-nated keyword logic.
That did reduce the number of tweets you had, but still went over the limit.
And we ended up finding out that the limit was actually a little window, so to size things by applying a very simple
sleeve of 10-minute sections between our requests, we could actually keep the number of requests the limit of the API limit.
So with that, we started actually collecting tweets, first of all, about that word about the subject we're looking for.
Here's a couple examples of ones we found.
The very first one, at City of Toria, a Cormac houseless encampment needing attention, located waterside at Galveston Blues,
near Polar City and Dockside Green, featuring a 12-ton dam in the bridge.
So if you're familiar with this region, you'll know exactly what it is.
You can tell it's about the Toria, it's about the subject of the people with trans and homelessness.
So we see that tweets are starting to come in that are relevant to a subject.
And the other two tweets are saying things that are about Toria and about trans and actually.
There's one being about Toria, being about homeless.
So these two were brand tweets. Now at this point, certain things are relevant to the NGO.
So with these tweets collected, we needed to pass on the sentiment model.
So the next page was the sentiment model.
We ended up using a pre-trained official model, a human-based model, developed by Cardiff University.
Like I said, it was pre-framed. It was pre-framed onto their data, so it landed itself really well to our use case.
If anyone's not familiar with the sentiment model, it's simply assigned two positives,
negative, or neutral category to each piece that's passed through it.
There were some pre-processing instructions that came along with the model.
So it shows remove URLs, cache tags, these things.
We ended up not actually doing that.
We needed to get the information later on for the relevancy component, which we'll get to.
But we did verify the results and the accuracy was really good,
as though we didn't have that many pre-processing instructions at the end.
This is us actually downloading the model.
Like I said, it's super straightforward.
It's really easy to use.
I'm happy with it.
The veteran, we wanted to give the NGO the ability to interact with the data outside of the raw data format.
So we built a dashboard using the Streamlite for them.
The dashboard was also hosted using the Streamlite Cloud.
If anyone, if you guys aren't familiar, it's a completely free, open source,
platform-based framework.
And it's honestly very awesome.
If you do data science projects, it's super easy to build that beautiful layer in between your project and the user.
It's specifically designed for data science.
So I recommend you guys check it out if you're interested.
There were three main functions for the dashboard.
We wanted it to have the ability to fetch and summarize data.
We wanted to get the users to use their speech filtering abilities.
And we also wanted to give the user the ability to download the raw data in case they wanted to further analyze it in Excel.
All right.
So this is our pre-recorded demo.
On the left-hand side, we've got some folders.
So data tweet was created.
We've got basic time series charts in the dashboard using the data source, so the quantity of tweets over time.
Down at the bottom, we give the user the ability to search for tweets by sentiment category.
And then one of the filters on the left is the ability to search by specific agencies or organizations.
So if you know that some politician in the area has been quite vocal on Twitter recently, they can go in here, search for that creator,
pull up the tweets, quickly get a sense of is that person the most tweeting?
Maybe there's a positive tweet.
And then how many over the last whatever time period that they choose.
Okay.
That's good.
So, painting it all together is the integration layer.
I worked on this part, and we ended up electing to use four tools for this.
So the first was the Twitter API.
The second was GitHub.
The third was setting phase, and the fourth was Streamline and Streamline Cloud for actually hosting the application.
So the way this works is every time that ATM specific and GitHub action can drop, it kicks off.
And it expects a full virtual environment.
So, we ended up taking a pipeline script connected to the Twitter API, and we created our collectable that hit on the keywords that Josh was just discussing.
We download the pre-setting supplement models from the heavy-face repo to that virtual environment, run the new tweets through it,
and then as the devising process occurs, it gives a historical face, which our story in our GitHub repository.
We ended up selecting to have a 48-hour look back period for the spray face.
So even though it runs every night, it pulls for us two days worth of tweets, so we're always doing about 24 hours of overlapping data.
We chose to do this because we noticed that there was a little bit of variability with when the claim talks kicked off.
It's pretty good that it did fluctuate by about 30 minutes.
So, we ended up spending 48 hours to just be extra safe so that we're not missing any data.
So that's all on the back end, and then on the front end we have the Streamlight app, which again is hosted by Streamlight Cloud.
It connects directly to a Python script that is in our GitHub repository, and it's just pretty nice because anytime we need to make updates for the application,
we just push those updates through GitHub repo and you have automatically updates.
So a few decisions that went into this was whether or not we wanted it to be automated or if we wanted to allow the user to manually trigger this workflow.
We ended up going with the automated claim job for a few different reasons.
One was to ensure that new tweets were being captured daily.
We wanted to have almost no stuck-to-date data whenever the user logged into the application.
The biggest one was we didn't want to miss any data, so again we had that same little structure based on our limited Twitter account.
So if a user only logged in once a month and they were manually triggering that workflow, we'd end up missing a lot of data.
And then also just warning that the automated decided it was more user-friendly.
All this happens behind the scenes in the evening and there's no wait time when they log in in the morning.
Second was public repos. We ended up using both a public GitHub and a public hub in case we felt.
If they're public, they're free, which was a big factor for us.
And then assuming the file size is going to change for those new tweets that we're posting every evening, we won't reach the soft GitHub file limit for about 30 years.
So some challenges.
Biggest challenge was when running these scripts locally versus through GitHub Actions when we were calling those environment variables.
Certainly the syntax was required.
Biggest challenge in my opinion was just reading and writing data from the virtual environment to the GitHub repo.
We ended up using the 5Github library, which overall is pretty good, but you do need to use additional specific APIs if file size is exceeding 1 MB.
And then just the actual code, the code and encoded data correctly in Francis Transfer CSVs back and forth.
Just a little bit of time to actually implement it. It's not great documentation online for it.
So overall, it worked pretty well.
So this brings us to our biggest challenge of the project, which was relevancy.
So the app at this point was working according to the statement of work, but it was too broad.
We're pulling in a lot of false positive tweets with the keyword-based approach.
So a few examples here.
In the first few tweets you can see these are actually about Victoria or we are joined as a unit about Victoria based on the tweets in the tweet text itself.
But it's not actually about homelessness.
So poor wasn't the keyword, but it's not specific enough to homelessness.
It can have different meanings and different context.
The second few tweets are not actually about Victoria.
They do hit on the keyword camping and go into Central Park, but they're not actually referring to the greater Victoria area.
I'll pass it over.
Thanks, thank you.
Yeah, at this point we did, like you said, we had a practically working pipeline.
We were able to collect the tweets, we were able to file size, we were able to make them work for the dashboard.
But there wasn't a whole lot that was actually becoming useful for the engineering use.
So the first question I asked myself was, well, why is it happening?
Words have multiple meanings.
Last example is perfect where you saw camp and camping actually applied to the actual sports areas, summer camps and camping.