Thank you.
Hi, everyone.
Welcome.
It is my honor to welcome you to PyCon US 2023 in Salt Lake City.
This year we are celebrating 20 years of PyCon US.
So we have planned many special things to commemorate this special occasion.
And I haven't even been coming to PyCon for that many years.
I haven't even been using Python for that long.
So I asked for help.
I asked people to tell us what it was like at earlier PyCons.
And I asked people to share their photos and memories.
And thanks to those who have shared their photos and memories with us,
we were able to compile all of them into a video and a throwback of PyCon US
for 20 years.
And it is really my honor to share this video with you for the first time ever.
So let's take a look at the 20 years of PyCon US throwback.
Wow.
Isn't that amazing?
Like 20 years of memories, I watched that so many times.
And one thing that strikes me is that you come to PyCon
is not just about R.K.
All of that is about my mom, my level and all of that.
And she's the hostess of that show.
Would you with us, please?
But you see code.
The photos are full of people.
The people you see in the videos are all members of the Python community.
From all over the world come to PyCon.
It really gives you an idea of the kind of people who you will be interacting with for
the next few days at PyCon US.
By the way, my name is Marieta.
I'm the conference chair this year.
On social media, you can find me on Mastodon.
That's my handle.
I just want to start by saying thank you.
Thank you to the Python Software Foundation for taking the management and financial responsibility
of this conference.
We really wouldn't be here without its board and staff.
And I want to say thank you to PyCon and PSF staff who are helping throughout this conference.
And the volunteers.
And for the volunteers, except for about a dozen of PyCon and PSF staff, everyone else
who you see at the registration desk, the green room attendants, session runners, tutorial
hosts, even myself, we are volunteers.
A lot of people have been commenting, wow, I must be so busy running around at the conference,
but really it's not as overwhelming as you think.
And it's really thanks to all the volunteers who have stepped up for doing this.
So thank you so much.
I also want to say thanks to our sponsors.
I know it has been a challenging year this year for tech industry.
The year begins with mass layoffs everywhere.
Companies are restructuring, reprioritizing, changing focus.
I'm grateful that despite all of that, you did not back out.
You continued to set a priority in the Python community, continued to support us.
So thank you so much.
Thank you to all the presenters who have come here to share their knowledge and expertise.
I'm thankful for all of you for being here, either in person or online.
It really means a lot to us that you have chosen to spend this time with us celebrating
this special occasion.
I feel like we're having a 20-year birthday party with 2,000 people.
So thank you.
APPLAUSE
Now, to first-time attendees, I want to extend a very special welcome to you.
I think it's a very special thing, a magical thing.
I too was a first-time attendee not too long ago.
I too was a Python newbie, nobody, and just like you.
And my first ever PyCon US was in Montreal 2015.
At that time, really, I was a nobody.
And thanks to the financial aid program from the PSF and the PyLadies that I was able to
attend the conference, it changed my life.
At that conference, I saw so many women speakers speaking on stage.
And up until then, never in my life I thought this is something I could ever do.
Seeing them on stage not only gives me the idea that, oh, this is something I could do,
but also it made me believe that it could be done, that one day I could give conference
talk too.
APPLAUSE
And that's really how my ice cream selfie tradition began.
So for those of you who are not familiar, this is like a tradition for me.
It's a reward for myself.
Each time after I give a talk at the conference, I go for an ice cream and take a selfie.
And it turns out I've done so many of them.
And really, I was not exaggerating when I said PyCon US, attending PyCon US changed
my life.
It was also during my first PyCon that I really learned about the open source, the community.
I think for the longest time I took Python for granted.
I even thought that Python is like a product of Apple because it's just been there on my
computer.
So when I attended PyCon, first time that's when I really understood, I learned what is
the Python community.
I learned the terminologies like open source maintainer, Python core developers.
I had no idea what it meant before and I really had no idea that one day I too would become
a Python core developer.
I had no idea that one day, you know, instead of sitting there where you are, I'll be up
here welcoming you to the 20 years of PyCon US.
So for all of you, all of you attending here for the first time, getting introduced to
PyCon US, really welcome.
All I want is for you to have that same experience, that same opportunities that I found here.
I want you to have that magic too here at the magic of PyCon US.
I want you to meet the people, the community who have always been here for me.
They are here for you because you are part of the community too.
So take full advantage of the fact that you are here at the largest Python conference
in the world.
I wish for you to be inspired.
I know you might feel like a newbie today but I really hope by the time you live here,
you live with 2,000 new friends.
So let me now tell you about what's going to happen at PyCon US.
We are in fact on day three of PyCon US.
The first two days have passed, all the tutorials, some of the summits.
But as you can see, there are still lots of events waiting for you.
First of all on this stage, we will have four amazing keynote speakers.
Ned Batchelder will be here shortly and you will get to hear from James Powell tomorrow,
Margaret Mitchell on Sunday and Carol Willing will give the closing keynote.
We also have a few extra special guests.
The Python steering council will be here tomorrow to give their updates about Python and I have
invited the creator of Python, Guido van Rassen, to share his retrospective of PyCon US.
Even more special guests, we will have the diversity and inclusion panel tomorrow after
the steering council and Deb Nicholson will be here on Sunday to present the community
service award and to provide updates from the Python Software Foundation.
You can still sign up for lightning talks.
Lightning talks are five minutes long.
Anyone can do it, even if it's your first time at a conference, even if you've never
given any talk before and you can talk about almost literally anything, there is a sign
up board next to the registration desk.
One cool thing about giving lightning talks is that you get to be on the same stage right
here, the same stage as our keynote speakers who will give their talk.
So you will feel fabulous.
Now, at the expo hall, that's where we will have our meals, breakfast, and lunch are provided
for the next three days and it's all included in your registrations.
Our sponsors have set up their booths at the expo hall and again, really without our sponsors,
our conference would not be as good as you have experienced.
So we're grateful for their continued support.
Please go check them out and learn what they have to say and get some swag.
At the expo hall is also where you will find our community booths and startup rows and
the job fair and posters will also be there on Sunday.
So if you want to see the sponsors and booth, go there today and tomorrow.
On Sunday, same place, it will look totally different for different events.
All right.
The charlas are in a new room this year in room 250.
That's upstairs.
And the rest of the talks, it's a little bit of the walk.
You need to walk further down to the other side of the conference center.
The picture here is really not up to scale the walk to the 255 and 355 is kind of long.
It means take your time.
Don't wait last minute to get to the talks because last year I got turned away from one
of the talks because it was full.
I was late.
I should have highlighted this.
Let's go next.
Okay.
So this year we actually have 89 talks and five simultaneous tracks including the charlas.
And all of these are live streams and recorded and captioned and will be uploaded to YouTube.
I really recommend it.
If you are able to go watch the talk in person, after all the lockdowns, I really miss seeing
things in real life.
So go see talks, but don't worry if you miss any of them.
They are recorded and you can watch again later.
We also have a quiet room here tucked away at the end of the hallway.
Room can't even read that.
But there is a quiet room.
That's a place where you can rest and relax, take a break.
And it really meant to be quiet in literal sense.
Like quiet, no sounds.
And the lights there were intentionally turned off.
So please don't go in there and start turning on the lights.
And the quiet room is also not an office.
If you want to work, you want to take out your laptop, typing, which makes noises, please
do it outside, not in the quiet room.
There are several lactation rooms available throughout the venue.
And there is one all gender restroom.
I was told the other one near the expo hall here is no longer an all gender restroom.
And there are a number of elevators around the building.
And the conference center is ADA compliant.
However, if you have any concerns or need additional accommodation, please let one of
the staff members know.
Lost and Found is not at the staff room.
There is an info desk by the registrations.
And also you can also go to the Salt Palace Lost and Found at the guest services office.
They know that if they found something, it might belong to one of our attendees.
So you can check there, too.
And at PyCon US, we will be providing live captioning for all the keynote sessions, the
talk tracks and the charlas.
And this year, our live streams are also captioned.
So be sure to look for the captioning screen in each room and select a seat in that area
so that the captions will be clear and easily viewed.
So I want to say thanks to our captioning sponsors.
The hallway track at PyCon US is a unique feature.
I mean, when else are you going to have the opportunity to meet 2,000 people who are just
as enthusiastic about Python as you?
So do take this opportunity to talk to people in the hallway.
One thing that could help with socializing in the hallways by following the Pac-Man rule.
So the rule is when standing as a group of people, always leave room for one person to
join your group.
So this leaving room for new people when standing in a group is a physical way to show
an inclusive and welcoming environment.
It gives explicit permission for people to join the group, giving them the opportunity
to integrate into the community.
All right.
Now remember to pick up your swag.
So any leftovers that you did not pick up, we will sell them on Sunday, 11 to 1, at the
same place where you do the swag pickup.
By Ladies Auction is coming tomorrow evening.
Room 151 here in this venue.
So I think last year it was a different area.
This time it's right in the building so you don't need to leave.
And open spaces.
Open spaces are self-organized meetups that take place in one hour intervals in dedicated
rooms throughout the conference.
And these open spaces are really created in real time by you.
So to start an open space, you just need to sign up.
There will be boards across from the staff office.
This year we have our own mobile app.
And it will have lots of information about the conference, all the schedules.
The map will be there too.
It's open source, Apache 2 license.
And you can get them by using this, scan this in your mobile phone.
And you can even contribute to it by checking out the GitHub repository.
You can suggest features.
You can help fix issues and create your own pull requests.
You can engage, and I do encourage you to do that, engage with us on social media.
Our hashtag is PyCon US.
Hashtag PyCon US.
And now we are on Twitter and we are also on Mastodon.
And I learned that the equivalent of hashtags on Mastodon is like groups.
So now there is also a PyCon US group on Mastodon.
So if you, in your tweets, if you mention the PyCon US at chirp.social, it will automatically
be boosted by that account.
So if you follow this group, you will be seeing lots of PyCon US content.
Now let's talk about the health and safety at PyCon US here.
You know, in the past year, since I've started helping to organize this conference, I've
been receiving lots of inquiries about PyCon US.
Like many of these are in the line of, do we really still need to be masking at PyCon
US in the year 2023?
Now if you want to be here at PyCon US in person and have the opportunity to interact
with the amazing Python community here, the answer is yes.
And I want to say thank you to everybody in this room.
The fact that you are here, it means you've been following our health and safety guidelines.
Not only you need to be wearing a mask, you need to be wearing KN95 equivalent mask.
And I've heard concerns from attendees yesterday who said that we weren't being strict about
this or we weren't enforcing it.
And I apologize that we have caused you such distress.
We are taking this seriously.
So this is how it's going to work.
Starting today, we are enforcing this.
The way it works is that if I or any of the staff members we see you not following the
guidelines, we see you not wearing masks except when it's allowed, like when you're eating
in the expo hall or if you're giving a talk, we will come and scan your badge.
And that will count as one strike.
After three strikes, we'll ask you to leave.
And we might not even, I think we're not going to bother giving you warning or notice.
There will be no conversation.
There will be no negotiation, no arguing.
We'll just come and scan your badge.
We at PyCon, we really deeply committed to providing safe and positive experience for
everyone.
In order to ensure this, all staff, attendees, speakers, sponsors, volunteers at any PyCon
events are required to adhere to the code of conduct.
No one is an exception.
No harassment, whether verbal, physical or discrimination will be tolerated.
Every person here will be provided with harassment free experience regardless of gender, gender
identity, expression, age, sexual orientation, disability, neuro-type, physical appearance,
body size, race or religion or like thereof.
And you can read more in the full text in our code of conduct here and there will be
linked on, it will have links to the procedures for handling incidents and enforcement policies.
If you believe someone has violated the PyCon code of conduct, you are encouraged to report
it regardless of the severity.
At any point you can make a report by emailing PyCon-us-report at Python.org or you can come
to the staff room, find any member in the staff room to file a report.
So now that you know everything about PyCon, I have a personal challenge for you.
The challenge is this.
Give yourself one point for each thing here that you have done during PyCon-us, starting
Wednesday and all the way until the end of the sprints.
And the goal here is to get as many points as you can and your reward is bragging rights,
knowing that you did something really cool at PyCon-us.
Another reward is that even if you do just one of this, you made another person really
happy.
So shout out to Hugo who said, I checked yesterday, he said he has done nine points so far.
For myself, I haven't checked today, but for myself I think I accidentally agreed to speak
at PyLadies Seoul in South Korea, I don't know.
I'm not sure how that goes.
Anyway, okay, I know you're bored now, I know you're looking forward to listening to our
keynote speaker and he will be on stage real soon.
Before that, again I want to say thanks to our sponsors, our visionary sponsor Meta.
Itamar from Meta is here and if you would like to share a few words with you all.