Cool. Hi everyone.
I hope Lance hasn't made you very sleepy
and you can pay attention to us for the next three hours.
My name is Olga and this is my co-presenter Eya.
We both work at Bloomberg.
I work in a team that creates an API
for our instant messenger application and Eya works
on an alerting system we have at Bloomberg for market alerts.
We have been at Bloomberg for over five years.
Eya bought three something and we're both members
of an internal Python community we have at Bloomberg, the Python Guild.
Okay. So thank you for signing up on this workshop.
Some of you may know what Sphinx is, some of you may not.
We are going to keep, I think, a pace good enough for everyone
to follow along and there will be a few challenges for people
who want to try something more.
So if you have never heard Sphinx before, it is a tool
to create pleasant and beautiful documentation easily.
It can create a lot of different outputs like HTML,
latex or plain text.
Today we will be focusing on HTML.
And what's great about it is that it does a lot of magic for you.
So it can, when you create your documentation
and creates cross references to other objects
in your Python code, for example.
So all of that is done under the hood for you
and you don't have to worry about it.
The big great part about Sphinx is that it has a big adoption
and there's a big community and a lot of cool extensions
that you can try out.
We will be using some today and we have some links for some others
in our further reading section.
And yeah, about this workshop today.
So I mentioned we are part
of an internal Python community at Bloomberg.
And about a year ago we hosted an internal event
that is across the company about a lot of different technologies
and all of these communities showcase some of their work.
We were gathering some feedback on what people wanted to learn
about and we were noticing a pattern
that we could do a better job with documentation
and this is how Aya and I decided to come up with this workshop.
So its initial form was very tailored to Bloomberg technologies.
But we got a lot of great feedback from people who came
to that workshop and we decided to generalize it and to present it
to the wider public and to a few conferences.
So we did this workshop in September in PyCon UK,
an internal meetup locally in London
where we're both based, PyLadies London.
And now we're here.
So yeah, this is a good point.
Also give thanks to all the people
who have given us feedback so far.
And I hope we have done a good job
and you will also enjoy the workshop today.
And if you do have any feedback, good or bad, you can come
and talk to us later.
Okay, and now let's get into more details
of what we're going to do today.
So this is going to be a very interactive workshop.
We're going to have 10 sections, yes, where Aya
and I will be presenting the content of each section
and then you will be given some time to follow the steps.
We will be going around the classroom to help anyone
or answer any questions.
We also think that we ourselves learn good from others
so please feel free to help each other
and ask questions generally in the class
so other people can hear what you have to say.
Okay, and you can find the workshop link here
on this tiny URL.
We have the instruction to start the environment setup.
If you haven't or you just came in, don't worry.
We are going to go through it together.
Just in case there are any questions, you can ask them then.
So let's have a closer look at what we will be doing today.
I think this is the workshop instructions and it's a tutorial
that you can follow later at home if you missed any step,
if you want to remember something or you can share it
with your friends, whatever you like.
These are the different chapters that we're going to see.
And here up in the upright corner,
we have linked the example project we will be working with today.
So you can click on it and it will take you to this GitHub repo.
We will be asking you to be working with that later.
But for now, you can just browse what it has inside.
You can see the source code is quite simple.
Internet is slow.
So you can go and you can browse the contents.
You can see what it's about and you will be working
with that in the next hours.
So the documentation we'll be creating today will be for these modules.
And to give you a tease on what you will be creating,
this will be the final example of documenting this module.
So yeah, we hope it's...
Yeah. So this is like our Sphinx Epoch as we will be working on.
And you can go and you can browse its contents.
You can see the different classes that are in the source code.
And you can see, for example,
the documentation we have created for its methods.
You can, yeah, browse it already.
You can go and see what's there.
And you can see there are links that link you
between the different classes.
Here on the left side, you can see also
that we have different branches and different tags.
This is going to be the part about versioning.
The last part that we're going to see.
And I think, yeah, that is all to show from this page.
Cool. Yeah, for people who just came in, let me show again.
This is the link for the tutorial.
So if you can browse on tinyurl.com slash Sphinx.tutorial,
we're showing this, what's on the screen.
Okay. And if you have opened it, now you can browse
to the first section, which is the environment setup.
You can see that the prerequisites
that we have is to have Git and non-deprecated version
of Python installed.
We recommend 3.11, but I think anything
above 3.8 will work.
And here are the instructions on how to use the repo,
the example project that we have given you.
So this is a template, and you can use this template,
create a new repository.
You can give a name of your choice.
We recommend sticking with Sphinx
in case something goes wrong, and you can always follow that.
So then you can clone the repo on your laptops, and yeah,
CD onto that.
You can use whatever editor you like for this.
We recommend Visual Studio Code,
and we will be giving some extra tips for that,
but anything will be working.
You just need an editor for that and a terminal to work on it.
After you clone the repo, then create a virtual environment.
The instructions are here, and install the package,
and you should be all set.
Again, we have tested this workshop more extensively
on the UNIX-based machines.
If you're using something else, we can try to help out
or figure it out together.
So we're going to give you some time now to follow these steps,
and yeah, let us know for any questions.
Okay, so on the next section,
we're going to be starting with Sphinx.
So of course, you're going to be installing Sphinx first,
and then that ships with a handy quick start tool
that we're going to use to generate the basic files
that Sphinx needs to generate the basic website.
So you're going to run the tool,
you're going to go through the prompts,
and then that generates a number of files.
So the first file is conch.py, which is, as you could probably guess,
a configuration file that allows you to configure Sphinx's behavior.
We'll be slightly tweaking Sphinx's behavior as we go along.
You'll see how that's used.
The next file is index.rst.
So this is the source file for your documentation website's home page.
So that's going to generate the index.html file.
And the RST extension is for restructured text.
We're going to talk about it in the next section.
The makefile is a convenience.
Yeah, convenience has a bunch of make targets
that make it a little bit easier to build or clean your documentation.
The build folder is where your output documentation files will live.
So your HTML files will live there.
The static folder is where you can store all your static files, say images.
And then finally, the templates folder is where you can put little snippets
of HTML to customize the appearance of your website.
So yeah, use the Quick Start tool and just build the output that comes out of that.
And you can just preview the output that comes out of the box
from Sphinx Quick Start.
That's this section.
I'll give you a few minutes to work on that.
Let's move to the next one.
All right.
So I mentioned restructured text.
So restructured text is a plain text markup language.
It's the default one that Sphinx uses.
It also supports Markdown, but since this is the one that Sphinx supports
by default, we're going to teach you this one.
We're also not going to go into too much detail about the syntax
because there are a ton of resources out there.
We're just going to cover some basics so that you understand, you know,
how to create a basic page.
So for instance, this is the syntax to create a heading.
So this is what becomes the heading of your website.
This here is a table of contents tree.
You can configure it by specifying the max step.
You can caption it with a title.
We chose contents.
Yeah. Yeah, go ahead and get started.
The practical part of this section will be, yeah, adding a little section
and then also linking an image so that you also have an image here.
You can use our same image.
It's in the example repo or you can, of course, download your own image.
I'm Egyptian, so I'm biased towards this one, but you can,
of course, use whatever image you want.
And something I forgot to mention in the introduction.
You might be seeing that in the end of each page, we have this hint
that you have reached this part of the tutorial.
So you have reached this part of the tutorial.
So if you go in the example repo, you can see
that we have created different branches of each chapter of the tutorial.
So if for any reason you are left a bit behind or you want
to confirm what you have done, you can just browse the repository
that state and you can continue from there.
I hope, yeah, it's helpful this way.
So I'll be moving on to section four, which is documenting your API.
Again, so we've been working with this example repo.
It has, you saw, two Python files, Sphinx.py and Riddle.py.
And now we want to generate documentation for this module.
So the way we're going to do that is that we're going to add docstrings.
That means comments after a function signature or when a class is defined.
And Sphinx will do its magic and convert those docstrings
to the documentation we want to see.
There are a few different styles that you can write docstrings.
One style is the restructured text we saw in the previous section.
But you might agree that it can be a little bit cumbersome.
So for this reason, we're going to be using the Google style for docstrings.
We're linking here how that looks like.
There's a lot of rules and you can make it very strict.
We will just be following the guidelines for that.
You don't need to follow everything on the dot.
And we'll be using a very cool Sphinx extension called Napoleon.
So Napoleon is a preprocessor.
So before Sphinx does its processing, Napoleon takes NumPy or
Google style docstrings and converts them to restructured text
before Sphinx attempts to parse them.
So Google style is also generally recommended by a lot of different
organizations, that is the other reason we're going with that.
And you're going to see that it is very familiar and easy to read and write.
So in this section, we're going to start with a method.
Here we're choosing the checkReadLancer as it has a more interesting signature.
But the idea is that you will fill out both files and
all of the methods on your own.
And we will create a Google style docstring.
So the text we decided to write is this one.
We give initially just an instruction of what the method is doing.
And then we explain what the arguments are.
We explain if there's any exceptions raised and what the return type is.
If you're using VS Code, we also recommend adding this VS Code extension,
auto docstring, where you can just start adding double quotes and
will pre-fill whatever style you have selected for
the extension of your docstring.
So it's a quick way to do stuff.
So once you're happy with the docstrings you have added, then add and
commit your files and post them to main.
And that will be step four.
We're going to give some time for that.
Yeah, and again, like fill as, I don't know, creative or as lazy as you like.
You can just fill in one or you can fill all of them to make a more full
documentation.
And yeah, if you are really, really lazy as I tend to be sometimes,
again you can check out the brands on the example repo and
you can see what we have pre-filled in for the methods.
So from here I'm selecting 04 Document API.
You can go to SSC Sphinxy and you can open Sphinx.py and
see what we have filled in here.
If you missed this, the example project is linked from the top of the tutorial.
Okay, yeah, it's linked here.
So you can just open it up here to see the branches.
And yeah, some more logistics.
We know that there will be a coffee break at 3 PM, but
not because this step can take from very little to a long time.
If you want to have a 5-10 minute break, also feel free and
we will be waiting 10 minutes for this section anyway.
No shame here, you can go to the toilet filling water.
All right, anyone needs more time?
Take that as a no.
If you've documented one method, it's fine.
Yeah.
We can continue the regulation.
All right, so in this section,
we'll learn how to generate HTML documents from the docstrings that you just filled out.
So for this, we're gonna need two extensions.
First, autodoc, which pulls documentation from the docstring annotations.
And second is Napoleon, which Olga spoke about.
It's gonna help Sphinx understand the Google style docstrings that we use.
So yeah, you're gonna list the extensions that you need to use.
And then the main command that we're using in this section is Sphinx API doc.
So yeah, you're gonna point it to the output directory,
which is your docs folder, and then also your source directory where your Python
files live, so that it can generate RST files for
each Python file that you've annotated.
And this is what the separate flag here is for.
This is to tell it that we want to end up with one individual HTML file per module.
If you don't use it, of course, it's optional.
If you don't use it, then it would generate your documentation in one page.
But we thought it just looks nicer, so we used it.
Yeah.
Yeah, you'll also, so once you've done that,
you'll also link the module components in the content tree.
So this will allow you to be able to see the contents tree here.
Because the max depth, if you left it at two, is two.
So you can only see the top level.
You can also configure the max depth to be a little bit deeper if you want to see
the contents in the home page.
Yeah, so that's what this step is.
So yeah, you're gonna rebuild the documentation, and you should be able to
see by the end of this step something that looks like, well,
something that looks like this, except it's not gonna be using the cool theme yet,
cuz we haven't done that.
Okay, I know some people have run into a few issues, but
I think we're in an okay pace.
And we're gonna do the next step, which is kind of optional and
more fun, so people who have finished can play with something.
So this would be selecting a theme for your website.
So Sphinx comes with some built-in themes.
You can see them linked here.
So in your conf.py,
you can see that there is already a theme that is chosen called alabaster.
And now you can choose whatever you want from all the built-in themes, and
you can see what you like most.
So you can try, for example, classic.
You can always then make HTML, open your website again, and
see what look you like the best.
But besides the built-in themes, a lot of people have created their own themes,
that they get sipped with PIP.
So the theme that we have been using in our example project and
the final website you've been seeing is called Furo.
It was created by a Bloomington engineer, Pradhan, and yeah,
we want to support him.
Also, we like the theme a lot.
So to use a PyPI theme, you can PIP install Furo.
And then in your conf.py, you select that this is the HTML theme I will be using.
You make HTML again, and you can commit, push to have these changes as well.
And you can just refresh your website, and you can see how it looks.
What we like a lot is that it has a built-in dark mode for some of us,
full of black.
So yeah, have a try with that if you want.
If you like something else, that is okay, but
we recommend for the duration of this workshop you continue with Furo,
because at some point you will need to make some changes on the theme.
And yeah, it will work better if we're all on the same theme.
So that is one part of this section.
And then another styling element that you can add in your website.
If you're someone like me who has normally millions of tabs open,
you want to recognize them by their fabric.
So you're gonna add the fabric on your website now.
So the way you do it in your conf.py, you can just give a link,
give them directory where your image of the favicon is stored.
Generally we prefer to use this underscore static directory for
these sort of things.
And you can use whatever you like.
If you don't want to be choosing right now,
you can find in the example project under images, favicon.ico, and
you can use that.
And again, you can make it HTML, commit your changes to main, so they're there.
Again, this is like an optional step.
So if you're running behind something else,
you can continue working that and not worry about this section.
Although, yeah, we do recommend that you install Furo at some point.
So yeah, I think we're gonna give five minutes for this one, so
that we can move on to the next section.
And then we're gonna have a longer break, because yeah, we probably need it.
To make it also more exciting before the break, we're hoping that some of you,
most of you, will have their website hosted on GitHub pages.
And you will have a server link to sign with your friends.
It's a big milestone.
All right, hopefully you've installed Furo and your website now looks pretty.
Next, we're gonna learn how to host the website on GitHub pages,
which is really exciting because you'll have a link that you can share with people.
And yeah, they can visit your website.
Of course, there are many hosting options, but we picked GitHub pages because
we didn't want you to have to learn about a new tool.
Chances are your project is already on GitHub.
You already do your source control there, so
using GitHub pages is just one extra step.
Okay, so to use GitHub pages,
we're gonna be creating a branch called GitHub pages, gh-pages.
So this is a special name that GitHub recognizes.
And when you create this branch, and it just automatically detects that you're
trying to use GitHub pages, and it gives you a URL that your website will be hosted
on.
So for instance, for me, this is the example project.
I can't show you the settings because this is not my laptop.
But okay, but you will be able to see in the settings under pages,
the URL that your website is hosted at.
I also have mine linked here, but it will look something like this.
So it would be your username.github.io slash the name of your package.
Okay, all right, so to do that, we have a few steps.
First, we're gonna be creating the orphan GitHub pages branch.
The reason why we wanna create an orphan branch and
a completely empty branch at first is because we only wanna put our HTML files
there, so we don't want it to have any of the other things that we've committed
on our main branch.
Next, we're gonna create a local work tree that we mount at
the HTML output folder for GitHub pages.
And then first, we're gonna put a very simple hello world website.
So just in an index.html, it will only have a title saying hello world,
just so that you can get familiar with how GitHub pages deploys your documentation.
So you'll see that every time you push something to the GitHub pages branch,
this action kicks off.
So it's called pages build deployment, and it just rebuilds your documentation.
And once it's done, you can see your changes take effect on the live URL.
So that's the first exercise we're gonna do.
And then before we actually push our website on GitHub pages,
just a couple of small things that we're gonna do.
So first, a quick utility to help us clean our local working directory quickly.
And then also, we're gonna be disabling Jekyll,
which is a static site generator that GitHub pages uses by default.
But because we're already using Sphinx to generate our website,
we don't wanna use that, so we just disable it.
Yeah, and then you'll just be ready to put your website,
all the HTML files you've created so far on the GitHub pages branch.
And yeah, you should have a live website like I have here.
I'll let you get started on that.
Since a couple of people already ran into this,
when you were creating from the template, there was an option to include all branches.
So if you selected that and you're now on this step, there's already a GH branches.
So you have to push force.
So at the point where we ask you to git push origin GH pages,
use a flag space, that's F to force push and override what existed there.
Yeah, any questions?
Let us know about this.
Yeah, so probably the last up here.
This is a longer section, but we said that we're gonna send you for a break at 3 PM.
So if you are done, feel free to go.
But even if you're not done and you need a break, feel free to go.
I think we're gonna continue at 3.20.
Okay, yeah, so try to be there by then.
And yeah, from this step, as we said, this is a big milestone.
So hopefully, if you've only reached this step,
you already have something that you can keep working or showcase back to your companies.
Or I don't know.
And in the next sections, we're gonna see how we can run some automation on this workflow,
so that we don't have to keep creating these GH pages, brands, and do everything locally.
We're gonna use GitHub actions to automate the process.
So you're just gonna have to chill, push your changes to main and everything.
All the documentation generation will happen on its own magically.
And then the last interesting piece is to add versioning.
So the way that your API evolves, you're gonna be adding new features.
How can people refer back to all the documentation in the running and different version of your package?
Okay, so next section is automating updates.
So far, we've been manually going through the steps.
And now we're gonna learn how to put it together in an automated workflow.
For that, we're gonna use another GitHub feature.
Not because we're trying to promote GitHub, but because we're just trying to not make you learn too many tools.
But GitHub actions are very useful.
They allow you to, yeah, basically automate a number of workflows on a given trigger.
So for example, this is a very simple Hello World workflow.
You can create a file, a YAML file under this path here so that GitHub can recognize it as a workflow.
And this is the content of the file.
So you can name your workflow something.
We named this Hello World.
And then you choose a trigger.
There are many triggers that GitHub supports, but this is an example of a simple trigger.
We're saying here that we want to run this workflow every time there is a push to the main branch.
And then we're defining a number of jobs that we want to run.
In this case, we only have one job called Hello.
And it just has one step that just says Hello.
So we name the step, say hello, and the actual command involved in this step is just saying Hello World.
So this is just an example of a workflow so you understand the structure of GitHub actions.
But now we're going to create a workflow for deploying our documentation.
So similar to what we did above, we're going to create a YAML file under the GitHub slash workflows folder.
We're going to name it Publish Sphinx Documentation.
And the trigger again is on a push to the main branch.
We're going to do the following.
First, we're going to ask for write permissions for the content scope.
This will allow us to push to our GitHub repo.
And here are the steps.
So first, we're going to check out the repo.
We're going to set up Python here because we're working in 3.11.
We put 3.11 as the Python version.
But if you're using a different Python version, then, of course, modify the step to use the version that you're working with.
OK, now that we've set up the Python version that we need, we will install the dependencies.
You probably recognize these steps from what we've done earlier manually.
So first, we install our project in edit mode and then we install our dependencies.
So far, we've used Sphinx and Furrow, the theme.
Next, we're going to build the Sphinx documentation.
So first, we use the Sphinx API doc tool to generate any RST files that are missing from our Python files that are annotated with the doc strings.
And then we use the Sphinx build command to actually build HTML files.
This is the command that we've been using throughout, but we've been doing make HTML.
This is just a convenience so that you don't have to type out this whole command.
But that's what's really running under the hood.
Yeah, and finally, the deploy step.
So we're just using this action here called actions-githubpages.
We're telling it we want to publish the output to the GitHub pages branch.
The output lives in the docs slash build slash HTML folder.
And yeah, it's an orphan branch.
So it's all the steps that we've done so far, but just written all together in a workflow that GitHub will automatically run for you.
Yeah, here is the whole workflow put together so you can understand what it looks like, you know, all together.
And then, yeah, you're just going to commit this branch to GitHub and you're going to observe that because this is a commit domain or a push domain,
you're going to observe that GitHub ran your action.
You should be able to click through it and see.
Oh, OK, I have not been showing.
OK, I have not been showing this on the screen here.
Yeah, sorry.
Hopefully, what I said makes sense.
I'll just follow. I'll just show again the completed workflow.
So this is the name of the workflow.
This is the trigger.
So on push domain, we trigger the workflow.
And these are the steps involved in our job.
So check out the branch, set up the Python version that we need, install the dependencies.
So Sphinx and Furo run our Sphinx build commands.
So API doc and Sphinx build.
And then finally, deploy.
Yeah, deploy to GitHub pages.
Yeah, so once you've committed that workflow, you should be able to go to the actions tab here.
And you're going to see an action that looks like this.
It's going to have the name that we named it, which is publish Sphinx documentation.
And you're going to be able to click through it and see the details of each step as GitHub runs it.
So you can see here, this is the Sphinx build command.
And you'll see the familiar output that you've been seeing locally.
But now it's running on our remote machine.
Yeah, please do let me know if you have any questions.
Sorry, I thought I was showing all these steps as I was talking.
Yeah.
So how's it going? How many people managed to have their action working?
Okay, have a few.
I'm going to give another minute and I think we can move on to the next section,
which is the kind of more like, let's say advanced feature.
If you read the hosting on GitHub pages and then automating updates,
you have the whole workflow already working for you.
So you can see that now you can push to main any changes you make on your modules.
And then the action is going to rebuild the documentation.
And the publishing action for GitHub pages is going to publish it.
So everything works fine.
Okay, I'll give one more minute and then we move on to versioning.
Okay, let's start the next chapter.
So as we've said, your project continues to evolve.
Maybe you add more modules or you add more methods to your interface
or any changes might happen.
But you still want to support your previous version.
Someone else might be using that and they want to refer to the documentation.
For this reason, it can be useful to have different versions of your documentation as well.
Today, we will see how we can do that using a popular extension called Sphinx docs
multi-version.
There's a lot of different ways you can do that.
This one we found it was the easier to use.
And yeah, so we'll be going with that.
So first of all, we will be installing this new package in our virtual environment
and we'll make sure we use it in our conf.py.
And from there on, we're going to need to do some HTML magic.
I know everyone loves that.
But we're working with the theme Furo as we saw on chapter six.
Now we're going to need to configure it to allow to show the different versions.
You see in our completed example that here we have chosen that we want to be displaying
all different branches that exist in our repository and all the different git tags.
Traditionally, you might want to only display tags or something else,
but we're showing how you can do both and then you can configure it however you like.
So we add the extension and now we start configuring the sidebar as we like.
So we're going to need to create a document, an HTML file called under template sidebar
versus HTML where this one explains exactly how we want the branches and tags to be displayed.
So because we are kind of overriding how the sidebar is going to look like,
we need to tell Furo that, okay, we're overriding this, but everything else,
we want to use the default version. So don't think that we only need that.
So for this reason, in your conf.py, you're going to need to make this configuration
so that the website titles, edgebar, content tree, unscratchable section of the sidebar
still render as we like. So just add this on your conf.py.
And then we're ready to start using Sphinx multiversion to build our docs.
So Sphinx multiversion is going to replace the Sphinx build command that was getting
run whenever you were doing make HTML. So you're going to complete this section,
run the command as here in the documentation. And after that, we're going to commit the changes
that we have made on our conf.py and on our sidebar to have them on our main branch.
So then we know when we need to, in the next step, we're going to enable our GitHub action.
Everything exists there. So once you have done that, you're all set up to be using
multiversion and then we can try to test it out. So what you're going to do is we're going to create
a git tag of the current state of your project and you're going to push this tag to GitHub.
Then we're going to make a small change on your index rest file. It can be whatever you like.
Here we're just adding a new sentence after the first heading. And then we're going to push those
changes to main. From then on, we're going to run multiversion. And then locally, you're going to
see that multiversion has generated under the build HTML directory different directories for
all the different versions of your code. One is your main branch and then we have the tag that
we created with version 001. So you can go and you can browse those and you're going to see that
version one is different from main because we have added a new change in main. So after that,
you're going to push all your changes to GitHub pages so that you can see how now it looks with
the sidebar and the two different versions we have created, main and version one.
You can run into a problem and we're going to solve this way. So the problem is that because
now with Sphinx multiversion, all of your HTML files are generated under respective
directories of the git branch or the git tag that you're using. That means that there's no
index.html created. So for this reason, we're going to need to say that index.html is going
to redirect to the version that we would like. In our case, we choose the main branch. So we're
going to need to redirect the initial, the outside index.html to the main index.html.
You're going to need that by adding this logic and committing it and pushing it also to the
GitHub pages branch. And from there, you should be seeing success. So in your username,
github.io, Sphinx website, you're going to be able to view your main branch and your tag. And
the index.html is going to, like this page, should take you to the code as it exists on your main
branch. Finally, we have here some information. If you want to customize which branches you want
to display or something like that, and you're good with regular expressions, you can try different
things and you can see how this can be displayed. There's more steps here. So we're going to give
more time. Yeah. And you can go ahead with that. And after this section, we're going to see how we
can modify our GitHub action to support multi-version. Yeah. Something to note,
because a few people have asked, because we're doing this step now and we're using something
different from the GitHub action, you might see some failures. Do not worry about that. It is
normal because we have changed what we're doing. So in the next step, we're going to be fixing the
action and everything will be working again. All right. We're now ready to do the last section
of the workshop. So here we're just going to automate everything we did in the last step by
adding it in our GitHub workflow. Okay. So we're just going to make a few small modifications.
First, we're going to change the trigger that we had before. So before, to make things easy,
we were triggering our workflow on every push domain. But realistically, you're not creating
a new version of your documentation every time you push domain, right? You're probably creating
a new release of your software and that's when you want to publish a new version of your
documentation. So we chose this trigger here, which says when a new release is published,
that's when it's going to trigger the workflow. We're also modifying the checkout step to
fetch all the history of all the branches and tags. Oh, all right. Again, I'm not showing what
I'm talking about. Okay. Sorry. This is the trigger that I was talking about. So on release
published. So that's when you publish a release. Yeah. And then we're going to modify this step.
So we don't want to just fetch the main branch. We also want to fetch all the branches and tags
on the repo. That's because Sphinx Multiversion needs to see those to be able to
create all the different versions of your documentation. We'll also modify the
install dependency step to install Sphinx Multiversion. And we'll also modify the
Sphinx build step to of course use Sphinx Multiversion instead of Sphinx build.
So yeah. Also one more detail to add here. In the previous step, we'd created an HTML file that
redirects the user to a default version of the documentation. So we're just going to copy this
file into a location that GitHub workflow can see so that we can also have this redirect index.html
there. Yeah. And that's what the workflow looks like altogether. Yeah. So just go ahead and do
that and then commit it. And then you can test it out by actually creating a new release
of your project. So you can name it say version 0.0.2. And yeah, you'll see that the workflow has
kicked off and it has created all the branches for you. So you should be able to see all the branches
appear and also the second tag here from the second release that you created.
Yeah. That's all. I'll let you do that. Okay. If you're done, we do have a little feedback
form. We'd really appreciate some feedback if you can give us some. And it's on this link here.