Okay, good morning. Good morning, everyone. Did you have a good trip? Yep. Awesome. Okay.
Thank you very much. Thank you for enrolling to this tutorial. Okay. I just sent a message
a moment ago sharing this link as well. So if you're unable to type this, check out the
messages at our website or at the conference website. Okay. So I think we're going to
start now. My name is Ariel Ortiz. You can just call me Ariel. I'm a full-time faculty
member at Tecnologico Monterrey. This is a university back in Mexico. It's the largest
there. I've been in the teaching business for several years now. I've been actually
a full-time faculty member for 28 years. And I started coming here to PyCon recently. Well,
relatively recently, 2017 was the first time I've come to this conference. And it's really
awesome to be here again after two years of not being able to see everyone in person.
I've been working with Python since, I think it was a year 2001, so I have a little bit
more than 20 years using the language. I really, really like Python. It's one of several languages
that I use in my courses. And, well, this is a Pythonesis introductory guide to WebAssembly.
Once again, this is a really interesting topic, and it would take us a lot of time to actually
see it in much more detail. So hopefully after this tutorial, you should have a general idea
of what it is. And if you're interested in going deeper, well, I'll give you some pointers
so that you can check more information. But once again, just to keep our expectations
in place, just have in mind that there's a lot to see. And we're just going to cover
a little bit of this really awesome technology. So these are the tutorial notes. Hopefully,
I hope everybody is connected to the internet, to the Wi-Fi, because we're going to be working
on the cloud for simplicity's sake. So what we're going to be looking at today, these
are the four main topics. First of all, we're going to be looking at what is WebAssembly,
a general overview. And then as a second topic here, we're going to look quickly to
this technology called Piodite. This will allow us to see how we can use Python on a
web browser, thanks to this WebAssembly technology. Our third topic is hand coding WebAssembly.
We're going to have a hands-on experience on how to write a little bit of WebAssembly
by hand. And finally, our fourth topic is writing a tiny compiler. Actually, most of
the compiler is actually written. We're just really going to explain how it works, and
you're going to be having the opportunity to extend it with some additional functionality.
So what is WebAssembly? WebAssembly is a binary instruction format for a virtual machine.
We call it a stack-based virtual machine. So it is what we call an instruction set,
just like x86, just like ARM, just like the instruction set for the Java virtual machine,
or the instruction set for the common language infrastructure, which is the .NET technology.
Basically it's a series of instructions that are executed. In this case, we call it a virtual
machine because it's not really a CPU which is in hardware. It's actually a software machine.
But we can get some really interesting properties when we actually use this. So what's special
about this? Because once again, this idea of having a virtual machine is really not
new. It's something that we've had since many, many decades ago. Specifically, WebAssembly
was designed to be a portable compiler-generated language for implementing client and server
side applications. It's not meant to be written by hand, although we're going to do that here.
I think it's really interesting. It's really educational to do it. But strictly speaking,
the most common use case is to actually use a compiler for a higher level language and
let that high level language actually produce the WebAssembly code. But we're actually going
to see both situations when you write it by hand and when you actually use a tool in order
to generate our WebAssembly programs. So WebAssembly actually is a fairly recent technology. It
was proposed somewhere around 2015. They started writing an initial draft which appeared somewhere,
I think it was March 2017. And around, I think it was October, November 2017, the four major
browser players actually had an implementation that was actually being able to run programs
designed for this minimal viable product of WebAssembly 1.0. So as you can see here, there
was support at the end of 2017, there was support for WebAssembly in Chrome and Edge,
in Firefox and in Safari. What are the main features of this technology? Well, it's secure.
The WebAssembly implementation that runs on browsers actually uses the same sandbox as
JavaScript. So in general, it has been tested fairly well. And as usual, we always get some
security issues at some point, but most of the security issues have been solved so far.
So in general, we do consider this platform fairly secure. It's portable. We can run this
in not only web browsers, but it actually runs on a variety of devices. It runs on mobile
devices, in the same browsers that we mentioned ago. And actually, by the year 2021, last
year actually, it was estimated that 94% of all browsers in the world actually supported
WebAssembly. So it's a fairly ubiquitous technology that we can now depend on.
Another feature, and this is probably the main motivation that I had, it is really performant.
It runs very, very fast. This instruction set, which is WebAssembly, is really made
for a compute intensive processes. Okay? So typically, you will need to understand that
when we talk about WebAssembly, what we can do is fairly limited in the sense that we
can only do computations on numerical values. If we need to interface with the rest of the
world, it is important that we actually call some auxiliary functions written probably
in some other language. Typically, it could be JavaScript, but we're going to see that
it can be Python or some other language as well.
How performant is it? Well, the original design of WebAssembly was made to actually try to
run as close as possible to native code. I did a few months ago a little benchmark of
my own, which wasn't really scientific or any of that kind of stuff in the sense that
it wasn't really formal. I just wrote a program. It was a program that actually used numerical
integration to compute the value of pi doing a few, I don't remember if it was a few million
iterations. I benchmarked and saw how that program run, if it was running in Python,
and how fast it was when converting this same code in Python to C, and then using a
compiler to produce WebAssembly and to produce native code.
In the case of Python compared to the native code running on an x86 computer, the Python
code was 80 times slower, or the native code was 80 times faster, if you want to see it
more clearly, than the corresponding Python code. Then, once again, I translated that
C code into WebAssembly and ran the same benchmark. It was 40 times faster than Python. We do
have that this technology is fast, but it tries to be as fast as native code, but currently
it's not really as fast. More or less, what I was able to see is that was about twice
as fast as native code, but very, very much faster than Python. I didn't measure this
program with other languages like JavaScript, but probably wouldn't see, I guess, not too
much of a difference of what Python actually takes in a matter of time.
And lastly, and this is also something very important, it is an open standard. So here,
the browser vendors are able to actually implement their own versions and any other people that
want to have their own implementation of WebAssembly. They can just go and implement the specifications.
They don't need to pay any royalties. So it really makes it a very convenient technology
because there's no main company who owns this technology. Several companies actually are
involved in the design of the technology, but in general, the standard is open, so this
is very good news. So in 2019, what happened? Well, the World Wide Web Consortium, the W3C,
it announced that WebAssembly was now the fourth language of the open web, and this
is together with HTML, CSS, and JavaScript. One thing worth noting here is that WebAssembly
is not a substitute of JavaScript. They're actually complementary, okay? So it means
that a lot of the things that are done in the browser are typically going to still be
done using JavaScript, but now we have another option that will allow us to write parts of
our program in some more high-performant language like C or like Rust or many other languages,
and we're going to be able to integrate it with JavaScript or some other language, and
we should be able to actually get programs that still are able to interact with the user,
but in certain parts, they can run actually faster than typical JavaScript code if we're
thinking just in terms of the browser. But once again, the technology is not limited
to the browser, okay? Currently, there are several implementations of the WebAssembly
runtime that are able to run in embedded devices and in your ordinary laptop and desktop
computers, okay? So we're going to have the chance to actually see these use cases in
Python when it runs on the browser and when it runs on our computer, in a more generic
computer, okay? So it's worth noting that there are some few disadvantages at the current
technology, how it is currently at this moment. First of all, as I mentioned a moment ago,
it really only has support for numeric types, okay? It supports integers, it supports floating
point numbers, okay? But anything else is a little bit more elaborate, okay? You do
or you are able to actually accumulate and have support for other data types like objects
and strings and arrays and so on, okay? But it doesn't come directly supported by the
technology itself. You have to do some additional tweaks to actually get this running, okay?
But once again, this is because WebAssembly in this first version is actually designed
just to focus on computations, on numerical computations, okay? Another thing that is
a limitation is that it does not have garbage collection. Most modern languages actually
rely on garbage collection to manage their memory. That's the case of Python. But most
languages that have appeared in the past few years include languages like Go, traditionally
interpreted languages like Ruby and JavaScript, all of them depend on garbage collection,
okay? So the few exceptions to this are languages like C, C++ and Rust. So most languages will
find this as a limitation. So the work around currently is to actually add the garbage collection
as an additional supported sort of module to your code, which of course takes a little
bit of time. And hopefully next version probably of WebAssembly might actually have garbage
collection. So we'll have to see in the next few months if that's actually incorporated.
But this is something they do have planned to do, okay? But at the very moment, at least
how most browsers implemented, they do not have this support, not yet at least. And things
like that. So thinking of this as being as a Web technology, one of the main limitations
also is that there's no direct access to the document object model. Remember the DOM is
this data structure in memory that represents the HTML structure of a Web page. Okay, you're
not allowed directly at least to modify your DOM tree from WebAssembly. You need to do
it through some other language like JavaScript, okay? Once again, this might actually get
changed in the future. It might actually be different. But at this moment, you still
need to interact with the hosting platform to actually do that, okay? And typically that
means calling code written in some other language. So what languages, what tools are currently
available? These are probably the most popular ones, but there are many, many others and
many others are being designed at this moment, okay? So one of the most popular ones is this
compiler called M-scripten. This runs over the LLVM tool set or tool chain. This one
was designed actually to work with mainly initially with C and C++, okay? But actually
does support some other languages that actually are able to be integrated with LLVM. So this
is a very popular technology and has been used to actually port a lot of already written
in C code to WebAssembly, okay? Actually we're going to see in a moment this Piodi technology
is actually a port of CPython compiled using M-scripten so that it can be executed in a
web browser, okay? So this is a very central technology for us people that work with Python.
Rust, this is a relatively new language. It has a really interesting concept around shared
memory and it's considered much, much more safer than C and C++ to run really performant
code. So this is really interesting technology. If you haven't seen it or used it, probably
it's worth to check out. And a lot of what is done currently in WebAssembly is done through
Rust. Another technology that I've seen that has been becoming fairly popular is this thing
called Blazor from Microsoft. This allows you to use C sharp to actually produce your
WebAssembly modules. And there's this new language called AssemblyScript which is basically a
subset of TypeScript which is a variation or extension of JavaScript which is targeted
exclusively to run or to produce code for WebAssembly. So this is an interesting alternative
if you want to run, if you need to learn a language and you want to use a language that
is really designed to produce adequate code for WebAssembly, AssemblyScript is the way
to go. And it's worth mentioning there's this other technology. We're not going to go too
much into discussing it. Just I want you to know that it exists. It's called Wazzy and
this probably is going to be very relevant in the future. Wazzy is a WebAssembly system
interface. This is an independent technology from WebAssembly but it works with WebAssembly.
I mean, it's totally linked or bound to this technology. But it is considered a separate
project and it's currently being developed. And basically what Wazzy is, is it allows
to run WebAssembly outside the browser. That's probably the most interesting thing. It could
happen. It's not the current state now but in the future we might actually be producing
WebAssembly plus Wazzy modules written originally in some compiler, a compiled language like
C++ or like Rust or whatever. And we would have a portable executable that could run
without any modifications or without having to recompile it in other platforms. So this
sounds like a really convenient technology and we have to keep an eye on it. Okay? It's
basically a standardized API for WebAssembly modules that allows them to access system
resources. Currently, you're not allowed to access from WebAssembly directly things like
the file system or networking or any kind of interesting packages that we typically
use. But hopefully with Wazzy we will be able to do this in a very portable fashion. Okay?
So this is something that is once again worth keeping an eye on. Okay? So, Wazzy is a very
good developer. Let's go to our tutorial notes. Okay? Just a quick reminder especially for
the people who arrived a little bit late. This is the URL for our tutorial notes. Okay?
Once again this URL I sent it through the message board in the corresponding PyCon interface
in the Web or in the Web site that we have available for all of us. And let's go and
see what we have here. Excuse me. Okay. So here are the notes. Let's make this significantly
larger. Okay. So the slides that you saw are available from this link. Okay? So if you
want to check them again, they're available there. Okay? This introduction is the same
description that you had when you enrolled to this tutorial. So I'm not going to spend
any time with that. You've already read it. Okay. So what we're going to do here is use
this site called GitPod. Okay? And once again if you remember I sent you, I think it was
a couple of days ago, just a message saying that you needed just to make sure that you
had an account in GitHub. Okay? GitHub and GitPod are two different services. They work
together. Okay? But they're two different sites. Okay? So just have in mind that although
they work together they are not the same thing. Okay? So if you don't have a GitHub account
just make sure to create one before you proceed. And the only thing that you need to do for
this tutorial is follow this link here. This will open a new window or a new tab. And if
everything is working fine we should have a clone of my GitHub repository which has
all the software that we're going to be using now. Okay? You're probably going to see this
in a light color. Okay? And probably make sense to make this larger. Okay. So this is
the theme. Okay. So well there's some settings that you can change here. Probably you might
need to change, if you don't like the original light color you can change it to a darker
color. Okay? So just go here where the cog is at the bottom and there's an option that
says here settings. Okay? And for the color of the theme just type theme here, up here,
theme t-h-e-m-e. And probably you're looking at this site with something like, I think
the default is default light, something like this. Okay? So if you don't like it change
it to whatever it is. What you see here is actually a web version of Visual Studio Code.
Okay? So if you use Visual Studio, this should, Visual Studio Code, this should be practically
the same experience. Most of the functionality in Visual Studio Code in the desktop is here.
You probably have a message saying that if you want to run Visual Studio Code from the
desktop just close that window there. Okay? We're not going to be using the desktop version.
We're going to be using the web version. Okay? Because that is running a virtual machine
that actually makes sense for what we're going to be doing here. Okay? So let me make this
a little bit larger. Can everybody see here the words that we have over here? Is that
okay? Yeah? Okay. Thank you. So I know that the default sizes might be very, very tiny.
And if you want to change your font size, okay, just type over here in the settings.
We're still there. Just type font. And somewhere you should see the size of the font. Here
it is. It says editor font size. I'm currently using 18, but I actually made it a little
bit larger so that you can see it here. I think by default it's 12, but you can change
it to something that makes much more sense to you. Okay? Once again, put it according
to your personal preferences. Okay? So let me go back to the themes. I usually like a
theme that is called Dracula. It seems to be very popular. This is not installed by
default, so if you want to install it, go to this icon here in the left-hand side that
says extensions. Okay? And just type here. If you know the name of your favorite, your
preferred theme, just type it there. Okay? I particularly like this one called sweet
Dracula. Okay? And I already have it installed, but if you don't have it installed, you should
have a button like this that says install. So just put it there and you should be able
to install it and start using it. Okay? So I'm going to request it to change it to RDracula.
Dracula soft. Sweet Dracula, this is the one that I like. Okay? For some reason, most developers
actually prefer dark themes. Okay? I'm going to go back to the theme. Okay? I'm going to
go back to the theme. The problem is that if you use a light theme, many people say,
how do people know that I'm a hacker if I'm using a light theme? Okay? So they prefer
to use a dark because that's how it appears always in the movies. Okay? So let's take
some space here. And well, here's some information if you want to see how to use here. This is
the Gitpod workspace. Okay? So just a quick mention here. Whenever you go back to the
Gitpod IO URL, this is the main site for Gitpod, it will take you to the dashboard.
Okay? So if at any moment you need to go to the dashboard, probably the easiest thing
is just to put in your address bar, Gitpod. IO. Okay? And it will take you here to your
workspaces. Okay? As many as you have. Okay? And we'll probably go there and we'll probably
be there several times in a moment. Okay? We're going to be using the terminal a lot.
Okay? So I hope you don't get frightened by using the terminal. So depending on what kind
of system you're using, if you're using Windows, Linux, Chromebook, whatever, with Control-J
you should be able to open a terminal. If you're using Mac OS, Command-J should actually
open it. Okay? So let's go back to the workspace. Okay? I currently have it open here, but I
think you probably don't. Okay? So if you currently are not looking at the terminal,
the terminal is usually a window that is in the bottom part of your browser here. So just
type Control-J or Command-J and it opens the terminal. Okay? At any moment you can close
it and using here the little x or you can once again type Control-J or Command-J and
it will close it if it's open and open if it's closed. Okay? So it toggles the terminal
very easily. Okay? Something that is very important, please make sure that you get this.
We need to set some environment variables. Okay? So for simplicity I put it here in this
file that's called PyCon 2022. So just type at the terminal source PyCon. You need to
do this every time you open a new terminal. Okay? So just type source PyCon 2022. Okay?
And you'll see this little message saying PyCon USA 2022 tutorial and the name of the
tutorial and the prompt here appears with the name that you have probably in GitHub.
And it tells us the current working directory in our system. Okay? And here is just an ordinary
bash terminal. It's running here Linux. This is a virtual machine running in the Git pod
servers. Okay? And it's really nice. I really hadn't used this tool before. I've used other
integrated development environments. In particular I'm a very fond user of Cloud9 which used
to be an independent project but it was bought by AWS a few years ago. And basically you
have a full integrated development environment. You've got a narrative. You've got your terminal.
And it's really nice. And as a teacher, as an instructor, I really like this because
I get all my students working exactly in the same environment. Okay? In the past, for example,
whenever I taught web design, I had some issues because the people that were using Windows
didn't exactly work the same as the people who were using Mac or the people who were
using Linux. They usually weren't a lot but there were sometimes some people that were
using that system. So having everything in the Cloud is a really convenient way of everybody
working the same way. Okay? So that's the same reason why I'm requesting you to use
it here. We now have all the software that we need for the tutorial is here. We got
several important tools here. We got Python, the most recent version of Python available.
You can try it out. Just type here, Python. Remember, type this after what I explained
a moment ago. Always, you always, whenever you open a terminal, make sure that you've
actually executed this command source, PyCon 2022. Okay? And you should see this, okay?
This little title. And if you now type Python, okay, you should see that we're using Python
3.10.4, okay? Until I think yesterday, this was the most recent version of Python. I'll
see Python. Okay? And once again, this is Python running on the Cloud, okay? On a server
that's running on the Cloud at courtesy of this company called GitPo. Okay? To exit,
just type Control D, okay? This is Control D independent of what platform you're at,
okay? It's Control and D, okay? Not command if you're using Mac OS. It's Control, okay?
And apart from the most recent version of Python, we also have here some tools from
a suite called WebVet. Do you have a question? No? Okay. Okay. There's a package or a suite
of applications called WebVet. Okay, we're going to use one of those tools in a moment.
They allow us to do several interesting things with WebAssembly from the terminal. And we
have Wasm 3, which is an interpreter of WebAssembly, which we're going to use in a moment. And
we also have Wasm for Python installed, okay? So all these things work. They have been tested
and it doesn't matter what system you're using locally. Because we're running all this in
a virtual machine, this should work without any issues, okay? Hopefully. Okay, so just
a few words about GitPod FreePlan. Okay? Once you've opened and cloned our repository, GitPod
enrolls you or subscribes you to a free plan that is called open source. You get something
that is called some GitPod hours. By default, you actually get 50 in this free plan, which
is called open source plan. One GitPod hour is basically the opportunity to work in your
workspace for one hour, okay? So if it gives you 50 GitPod hours, you can use it for 50
hours per month, okay? So that's a fairly decent amount. You can open simultaneously
several work spaces, but each workspace is consuming independently. So for example, if
you open two parallel work spaces for one hour, it actually counts you for two hours,
okay? So just have that in mind, okay? Whenever you want to finish your workspace, there is
an option there. Please don't exit at this moment. I just want to show you where to exit,
but don't do it at this very moment. There's a button here that says GitPod, okay, in the
bottom left corner, okay? And you get a menu here and there's this option called stop workspace,
okay? So that's a way of stopping it at this very moment, okay? If you don't stop it, but
for example, let's say you just close your laptop and you go somewhere, 30 minutes of
inactivity will also stop your workspace, okay? So, I mean, if you really wanted to
stop right now, just select that option. Otherwise, whenever you stop using it 30 minutes afterwards,
you actually get disconnected, okay? So it doesn't matter if you don't necessarily stop
it by hand, okay? Another thing which is worth mentioning right now, okay, once again, go
to the dashboard here and once again you can go with typing gitpod.io at any new tab or
window that you have there open. You should see only one of this, I mean, the workspace
that you just created now, which is this one that is in green, okay? You need or it's recommended
that you go here where there are three dots, then you select this option called pin, okay?
Pin actually pins the workspace into your, well, your dashboard, okay? If you do not
pin it, 14 days after you last use it, it will automatically get deleted, okay? So if
you don't mind it to get deleted, you can leave it without the pin, but if you want
to pin it, this actually guarantees that it will still be there hopefully after two weeks,
okay? So just have that in mind once again because otherwise you might expect things
to be there and then come back and see that they're not, okay? So any un-pinned workspaces
get deleted after two weeks. So I think that's all you need to know. And of course, if you,
well, another thing that we're over here, if you go to the settings option here, the
settings tab, and you go to plans, okay, there are several things that you can check here.
First of all, there's the plans. I mean, if anybody is interested in using this and doesn't
mind paying, you can see that there are several options here. You should have been enrolled
or subscribed here to the open source one, which gives you 50 hours. But in my case,
I got the personal because I'm an instructor and I have some special benefits from GitHub
and these are extended to Gitpod as well. So I have 100 hours per month given by the
Gitpod company. But you have other options. But the most important part that I wanted
you to see is this one here. This tells you how many hours you have remaining in the month,
okay? Once a month has gone, it resets to 50 hours again, okay? So if you want to keep
on using it, just have that in mind, okay? But once again, if you just wanted to do this
during the tutorial and then forget about everything, probably the three hours that
we're going to be here is enough time for you to actually learn what we're going to
present here. So, well, let's go to our section number three, which is this technology called
Piodite. As I mentioned before, Piodite actually was developed using, was produced using the
M script and toolchain and its support of CPython, okay? So this is the most common
implementation of Python and M script and actually got, received all the source code
written in C and it produced WebAssembly and this allows us to run, as we've explained
before, to run Python on the browser directly, okay? So as a first example here, let's run
a REPL. Remember the REPL is a read, eval, print, loop, okay? So just click it here,
it should open a new tab or a new window. Let's make this a little bit larger. And this
is a standard, standard terminal for Python, okay? This is running on the browser, okay?
The Python that we saw a moment ago was running on the Web in some other server, okay? We're
the browser as an interface. But this one is running here locally on our computer now,
okay? Probably the first time you actually load this, it might take a few seconds because
I think somewhere the full module that contains all the WebAssembly code for CPython is somewhere
I think around seven or eight megs, so it might actually take a little bit of while,
a few seconds to actually load, okay? I think currently the, I did some tests on the speed
of the, of the Wi-Fi connections that we have here and they run pretty, pretty fast,
okay? So hopefully we shouldn't have any issues with, with the speed of the, of the Wi-Fi
connection, okay? But here you can put whatever you like. For example, let's say that we put
here a list comprehension to produce the, the first 11 powers of two, okay? So, I mean,
standard, standard code. And an interesting thing here is that they also ported here some
of the standard or, well, not, not necessarily standard but typical libraries used by the
people from data science. So we can import here NumPy, okay? Once again, the first time
you actually bring it might be a little bit, take a little bit of time because sometimes
it needs to download and, and convert this to, to the internal representation that it
requires. And I mean, you can do things as usual here, okay? And P dot, let's say, create
a vector of zeros, okay? And do whatever operation you want, okay? So as you can see, this, all
this is running in the browser, okay? It's running locally in your browser. And actually
this works the same in a tablet or in a cell phone, okay? Really interesting because once
again it's running locally in your browser. So this is a really demonstration, really
cool demonstration of what WebAssembly can actually give you, okay? So this is, this
is something to have in mind. But once again, I mean, this might seem just like a curiosity.
How do we really implement this in, in the context of, of a client that actually wants
to use some, some Python code instead of JavaScript? Or additionally, because once again, in order
to run this, we will need to, to add some JavaScript code, okay? So this is a Python
code. Here we're in section 3.1, okay? So these are, these are very simple examples
just to demonstrate what we could do. I mean, but this is, this is something that has a
little bit of Python code. It has a list with some, some quotes, some one-liners, okay?
We have a function here called getVersion, which actually gives us the current version
of, of Python, whatever is running in the, in the local system. GetDateAndTime gives
us a time of this very instant, converts it into this ISO, ESO 8601 format. And then
getQuote actually chooses a random sentence here from this list of one-liners, okay? And
we have some, some code here just to, to run it if you want to run it locally. So let's
do that, okay? So we need to change to the pyodite directory. If you're fluent running
in, in, in a Linux terminal, feel free to do it some other way. Let's just look at the,
currently what the terminal looks like, okay? So if you type ls, it will give you a listing
of the current directory, okay? We want to change here to the directory called pyodite.
So you can do it with the command that is explained here. This is a change directory
with a full absolute path, okay? But you can do it also changing with a local directory,
with a relative directory, excuse me. So, so we want to change to py, pyodite here,
okay? This is a standard bash terminal, so if you've ever used it, remember you can use
tab to do quick competitions. You can use up and down hours to go through the history
of your command, so that will allow you to, to go a little bit faster, okay? So if we
list the contents here of our current working directory, okay? We have here a five icon.
We got an index HTML, we've got some Python code dot py. Let's run this some, some Python
code. So the typical way of running this is just putting Python and then the name of your
script, some Python code. And this runs the three functions that we defined a moment ago.
The first one gives us what version of Python we're using. We're using 3.10.4. It gives
us the current date of your, of your system. Here, it's actually, I think it's using here
the UTC. Oh yes, it's, because we're running this on, on, on the web, on, on the cloud,
okay? It uses the hour of the, the time and date of, of our server, of the Gitpod server,
okay? It's not the local computer that we're using. It's the server that we're running
this, this code on, okay? Remember, this is being executed on the cloud, the GitHub, the
Gitpod cloud, excuse me. And here we have a, a random message here, okay? If we run it
again, and again, okay, sometimes you do get some different funny quotes over here, okay?
So, and once again, here the, the hour, the, the date, the, the time, excuse me, the time
specifically here is the servers typically work with a universal coordinated time. So,
so we, we get here a normalized time instead of our local time, okay? So this is the command
to, to run the code that we just used, and this is what you probably, something similar
you get to use, okay? So how do we integrate this with, with a web page, okay? We have
here, the index file actually has what we need to do in order to integrate this with
the Piodide and run our program in the browser, okay? So important things that you need to
do here is that you need to use a script tag over here where you're accessing actually
the, the Piodide code necessary to run all this. This is really just an ordinary web
page that has a few paragraphs with some IDs. We use the IDs to actually update the contents
of, of these paragraph tags, okay? And we need to put some JavaScript here. This is
the, the only JavaScript that we're going to be using during this tutorial. You have
here your, your main function that loads the, the, the Piodide module here. So we're using
some asynchronous code here. And then this part runs Python code of the code that we
saw a moment ago written in ordinary standard Python, okay? So we, we fetch it, we get it
in, in our browser available to, to be ran by the WebAssembly CPython implementation
that we actually obtained with, with this source of the script of, of our Piodide module.
And here we actually go, let's make this a little bit smaller. This part here is the,
the specific code on, on JavaScript that is calling our Python functions, okay? So here
we have, we call the get version. Here we call get date and time. Here we call get,
get quote. And all this actually calls the, the programs that we were, the functions that
we were looking at a moment ago. Okay, let's, let's open it here. If you want to see that,
that code open here, this section, that is the file explorer. And we're at the Piodide
directory now. So if we open some Python code, this is, this file contains here our, our
code that we saw a moment ago in Python. So the, the functions that are getting called
is this one here, the get version, the get date and time, and the get quote. And these
are being called by the JavaScript in the index HTML file, okay? So this is where they
actually get called. Anything in Python can be translated into equivalent JavaScript objects
and the other way around, okay? I'm, I'm keeping things a little bit simpler. This actually
returns get version, get date, get quote. They return strings. And strings in Python
are converted to strings in JavaScript, so this is a really direct translation and no,
no additional things have to be done. And here we just upload the paragraphs. We put
their inner HTML with whatever these three Python functions actually return, okay? So
in order to see this running, you need to type the command that we have just here in
a moment, okay, which is a standard command to run an HTTP server in, in Python, okay?
So just type, type that command. You can just copy paste it. Okay, this runs the module
HTTP server, okay? And you should see in a few moments a, a little alert message over
here and go with the button that says open, open browser, okay? Usually the browser, the
browser is gonna stop it because it's, it's sort of like a pop-up window there. So you
should see in your browser a message saying that, in this case the browser that I'm using,
Firefox prevented this site from opening. So just give permissions for this to, to open,
okay? And there's my web page, my index web page where what we have here was actually
produced by Python, okay? So we got Python, the version that is running here. Notice it's
not the same, exact same version that we ran a moment ago because when we ran it at
the terminal it was running the Python interpreter installed in our environment, our, our workspace
provided by Gitpod, okay? Here we do see the local time, okay, 944, and we also get to
see this, okay? The funny one-liner quote, okay? If we refresh it, okay, you'll see an
updated time over here and once again you might see a different funny quote over here,
okay? So has everybody been able to, to run this? Yep, okay. Once again remember to get
the full experience you should really be doing the exercises, okay? Once again, I mean,
anybody can decide if you just want to listen it's okay, okay? But if you really want to
have the experience it's, it's really worth doing these exercises, okay? So this is one
way that this could actually be seen in your, your browser. And just a quick mention here,
now you can use Control C at the terminal. Don't do it, don't do it at this very moment,
but at the terminal where the server is running just type Control C whenever you want to stop
it. Don't stop it yet, okay, because we're still going to use it. If you stopped it already
just run the command again to, to make this get executed, okay? Some typical errors that
people do is that they open a second terminal and they run again the web server and sometimes
you get a message saying that the port is already in use, okay? If that's the case you
probably need to check out all the terminals that you have open and use the, the little
garbage can here to close all those terminals and that will usually, that, that stops any
processes that are running including the web servers, okay? But in the most simple fashion
just type Control C at the terminal and that stops the browser, okay? So it's time for
you to do your first exercise. So we're now in section 3.2, exercise A. And it says here
modify the get date and time function from the Pyrodite's sum Python code, okay? So you
need to open this file if you haven't already. It's the sum Python code dot py, okay? I already
have it open over here. And you need to go to, this is currently in line 27, get date
and time. And you're required here according to the instructions, okay, to modify this
function so that it concatenates to the, the results, okay? Notice that there is a variable
called result. So before you return it here you're required to concatenate it with one
of these two strings, okay? So if today happens to be your birthday, okay, it should say happy
birthday to me, okay? And if it's not your birthday it should have the string concatenated.
This is a very merry un-birthday to me, okay? So you just need to put an if there somewhere,
okay? I'll leave that to you to check it out where that would go. And first test it out.
And once again here you can open a new terminal here, probably to do the testing. Let's open
it here. There's in this menu over here where you have the three lines. Do you know how
this is called? What's the?
The hamburger menu.
The hamburger menu. Yeah, that's how most people actually call it, okay? I think it's
called something like the collapse menu or something, okay? But here you click it and
in the terminal this allows you to create a new terminal here, okay? So let's open a
new terminal. Notice here that I'm currently running two terminals. So as usual make sure
that you, because we opened a new terminal type here source followed by PyCon 2022. Once
again remember it's very important that whenever you open a terminal that you type the source
space PyCon 22 command, okay? And once again you can go from one, the previous terminal
where the web server is running to the new terminal by just clicking here the corresponding
icon for that terminal, okay? So once again let's change to the PyOdi directory. And
once again do whatever change you need to do on this code and first test it locally
here, okay? So run Python and some Python code again. I mean we haven't changed anything
so far so we're going to get the same output that we did. But you need to change this so
make sure that it runs here locally. And once you're sure it runs there go to your window
or to your tab where you have this code already. And once again if the server is still running
you just need to refresh it here, okay? Just press the refresh button or use whatever shortcut
your browser uses to refresh, okay? And you should see now the new output, okay? So something
needs to happen inside this function, okay? So I'll give you, it's, I think it's easy.
Just a quick tip here so that you don't need to check any documentation. The now variable
actually has today's date, okay? This is the now variable. So that one has two attributes.
One is called day which is the current day and month which is the current month, okay?
So you can use those to hard code, compare it through the hard coded values of your birthday
or whatever that happens to be, okay? And once you've done that and if you've done it
properly you should see the, well, this additional string as part of your result, okay? And if
it's your birthday you should say happy birthday to me and if it's not very happy, a very merry
un-birthday to me, okay? So how many minutes do you think you can do this?
Almost done. Okay, great. So I'll give you five minutes. If anybody has any questions
you can ask me. I could go around answering any questions or solving any issues that you
might have.
Okay, great. Thank you. Can I see the... Yeah, sure.
Okay, let's go back to... Okay, sometimes you need to have a little bit of a
time to think. You need to do a hard refresh in your browser. So typically in many systems
you press... I think it's shift and then press the refresh button and it typically does it,
okay? But you're missing the if to actually ask if it is or not your birthday. So typically
you would put now.day and compare it to whatever day your birthday is and so on, okay? And
then according to that you actually place the correct string at the end of result just
like you did a while ago. Yeah?
That could be an issue, yeah, because as you can see, yes, the code is visible. So,
yeah, you have to be careful with that, okay? And use some other mechanism to store any
other information that might be sensitive. Okay, good point.
Okay, so I think that's it. Thank you.
Anybody else finished? Great. Let's have a look. Okay. Can you see the code? Okay, very...
Okay, sure. Great, excellent.
Okay.
Yeah, if you have hard coded to today's birthday. Okay, yeah, sure. Okay, thank you. Yeah, great.
Anybody else finished or has any questions? Okay, can we see the code? Oh, the code is
over here. Okay, sure. Great. Awesome.
Okay. Yeah, as long as it works. Okay. So it is your birthday today or you're just checking
if it does work. You put today's date. Okay, awesome. Yeah, thanks. Great. Okay. Great.
Excellent. Thank you. Anybody have any questions or any issues? No? It's working? Okay. Yeah,
sure. Thank you. Okay. Awesome. Thank you. Okay, great.
Okay.
Okay. So what I've seen so far, the people who showed them the code, the code is working
fine. So thank you very much. Let's go to the next section because there's still a lot
of things to cover. We're going to leave aside what we did a moment ago which is programming
or using Python to program code that is going to be run by the browser. As you can see,
we were able to have our code written in Python, running in an ordinary Python interpreter
locally in our cloud in the server provided by Gitpot. But also we saw that we were able
to use PyLite to run it in the browser. So that gives us some interesting new possibilities.
Let's look at WebAssembly a little bit more in detail. So far we've just been using WebAssembly
without really looking at how it works and how it actually behaves internally. So we're
going to do some exercises here that once again, this is not the typical use case of
WebAssembly but it does give a lot of insight. It's something that really is educational.
Once again remember, WebAssembly is typically produced by some other tool, by a compiler.
But it is possible to write it by hand. And we're going to use this format called WebAssembly
and text format. We're going to distinguish these two formats. When we talk about WASM,
we're talking about the WebAssembly binary format, which is really what the technology
is. But there is a counterpart that is represented textually, which is called WebAssembly text
format. And we usually just call it Watt. So there's WASM, which is binary, there's
Watt, which is textual. And when we actually write it by hand, what we're going to be writing
is Watt. And we need a tool to translate Watt, which is textual, into WASM, which
is in binary form. Just out of curiosity, has anybody programmed any kind of assembly
language before? Oh, several of you have experienced it. Great. I used to teach assembly language
about 20 years ago. X86 assembly language. So compared to those assembly languages of
the past, even when I was in school actually, I think I programmed assembly language for
the 6502 processor. 6502 was the processor that was available for the Apple IIs. I don't
know if you remember those kinds of computers. I mean, I'm talking about the mid-1980s.
Well, WebAssembly in its textual format is similar to that. It's a really low level language.
But we're going to see that it's stack-based. So this requires a little bit of thinking,
a little bit different from most traditional assembly languages that are available for
different real hardware CPUs, which typically are based on registers. Here we're going to
see WebAssembly is stack-based, and we're going to see what that means in a moment.
But first of all, we need to mention that WebAssembly actually works with, in the textual
format, works with S expressions. So this is what an S expression looks like. We're
in section 4.1. So an S expression is something that starts with an opening parenthesis, then
has some symbols or elements there, and then a closing parenthesis. Those symbols or elements
that are nested can be all their S expressions. So this notation was actually first used in
Lisp in the late 1950s. If anyone has used Lisp or any of its variants before, it could
be, I don't know, Scheme, Rackett, Clojure, any of these languages. This is the same notation
that is actually used there. They're called S expressions. If you haven't used it before,
no, don't worry. You'll have a chance to look at or use this notation just briefly.
So well, we're going to be writing our code using S expressions. A quick reminder here,
we mentioned this already. There are only four data types supported in WebAssembly.
So we got an I32, which represents a 32-bit integer. An I64, which is a 64-bit integer,
can be positive or negative numbers. And we also have two versions of floating point numbers,
32-bit float, which is called F32, and F64, which is a 64-bit floating point number. So
these floating point numbers usually are equivalent to floats and doubles in other languages.
Yes?
>>[INAUDIBLE question asked off mic.]
I think they actually decided to use these because that's typically what is supported
in most physical, real hardware CPUs. Okay? I mean, x86 actually supports also the extended
floating point format, which is 80 bits wide. But it's not very common in modern years because,
as I've seen at least, most of the variations of SIMD instructions and so on are typically
used at most 64-bit floats. Okay? So I think it was more of a decision because of what
hardware is currently used and what was easier to translate from WebAssembly to a real hardware
CPU. Okay? And, well, it is a coincidence actually here that F64 is the data type supported
by JavaScript. Okay? But JavaScript, for example, does not support I64. Okay? There's no way
of directly supporting in JavaScript 64-bit integers. Okay? Because in JavaScript, everything
is actually a float. Okay? A 64-bit float in practice. Okay. Let's just, let's just
mention here on our stack, what is a stack machine? Let's start discussing what a stack
is. Okay? A stack is a data structure. Okay? If you've taken a data structure course in
the past, this should probably be very, very familiar. So a stack is just a collection
where all the elements are inserted and removed from the same place. Okay? So if we think
of it as a stock, for example, here in our illustration stack of pancakes, whenever
you want to add a pancake, you put it on the top. Okay? And whenever you want to remove
it, you remove the one that is most at the top. So we say that this data structure works
using a LIFO policy, or you pronounce it LIFO, not really sure. Last in, first out way. Okay?
Sometimes if I pronounce words a little bit strange, just have in mind that my natal or
my native language is Spanish, so many of these words I only see them reading, so sometimes
I don't necessarily know how they're pronounced, I just pronounce them as I imagine. Okay?
But it's not necessarily the correct way. Okay? So this is how the evaluation of all
computations actually takes place in WebAssembly. Okay? So for example, if I want to add two
numbers, let's say that I want to add a 7 and a 5, okay? These are the steps that I
need to do, okay? As mentioned over here. So I want to add 7 plus 5. So what do I do?
I push first the 7 on the stack, then I push the 5 on the stack. Okay? So now we have a
stack if we want to imagine it going from the bottom growing upwards. Okay? We got a
7 and then upwards we got a 5. And then when we do the add, the add actually involves popping
the two elements on the top of the stack. Okay? We pop them, which means we remove them.
We apply the operation, in this case the addition. We get the result and we place the result,
we push it into the stack again. Okay? So this is described here, but we have a better
illustration just down over here. Okay? So this probably is a little bit easier to understand.
So there we go. In step number one we push the 7. Okay? Step number two, we push the
5. So as you can see here, we got the 5 and the 7. Okay? The 5 is the top, the top of
the stack. The 7 is just underneath the top. And then we do a pop here. Now the order of
the pops, I mean, you can only do the pop with whatever is there, okay? But we're doing
two pops. An important thing that you need to understand is that we pop the first element
and this is going to be the second operand in the operation. Okay? I mean, at this point
it really doesn't matter because in the example we're doing addition, but when you do operations
that are not commutative like subtraction and division, the order in which things actually
are carried out is very, very important. Now the easiest thing here to remember is that
if I want, for example, to subtract two numbers, okay, I push the elements in the same order
in which I think that subtraction is going to be taking place. So for example, if instead
of adding 7 plus 5, I want to do 7 minus 5, I still push them in the same order. Okay?
You push the 7, push the 5, and when it pops, even though the second operand is going to
be popped first, okay, it's going to be used in the correct place. Okay? So as you can
see here in the illustration, okay, we pop the first element and this is going to be
the second operand and we pop the one that was in the bottom here and that's going to
be the first operand and then we carry out the operation, 7 plus 5 or whatever operation
it was, and we push the result into the stack, okay, so we get the 12 here. But once again,
the order in which this is done is illustrated here and once again, it usually is the order
in which you think how things are actually carried out, okay? So in whatever order you're
doing the operation, you push them in the same order. When it's popped, it's going to
be popped in the reverse order, but the operation is done exactly as you might imagine, okay?
So this simplifies things. This is the code, the actual code in WebAssembly in text format
in Watt that actually does what we need here, okay? So we're going to use this instruction,
I32 const, okay, and we're pushing a 7, I32 const of 5, this pushes a 5, and I32 at notice
here that we need to prefix the type of data that we're pushing and that we're popping,
okay? So we always need to provide if this is an I32, an I64, or an F32 or an F64, okay?
So typically most of the examples that we're going to see, we're only using always one
single data type, okay? But it is possible to do conversions between the data types,
okay? But at this moment, we're not going to be doing that, okay? But it is possible
if it's required, okay? So let's have a look at a complete example here, okay? There's
in the Watt directory, there is an examples.watt file, okay? So let's open that one. We can
close this now and we can now shut down our server, okay? So open the terminal that currently
has your server and just type control C to abort it, okay? And I don't think we're going
to be using that one again, so we can send it to the garbage. And we currently only have
this other terminal currently here, okay? So we're going to change our directory in
a moment, but let's open here the Watt folder and there's only one file there, examples.watt.
Okay, so this is a complete full example of Watt, of a Watt source file, WebAssembly text
format source file. And here, does, do you get to see it in colors or is everything in
the same color? If it's the same color, if you want to see it in color, just go to the
extensions icon over here and the extension is called WebAssembly, okay? Type WebAssembly
there and it's the very first option here. I currently have it installed and thanks to
that we get to see it in colors here, okay? But probably makes sense that you also get
the support for syntax highlight, okay? We live in an era where we do have syntax highlights,
so we should use it whenever possible. I remember when I was studying my undergrad degree, in
the very first semester I had a classmate that actually, we were programming at that
time, it was Pascal, what we were learning. And we were using Turbo Pascal at that time
and didn't have syntax highlight. I mean, once again, remember, I'm talking about the
mid-1980s, okay? Syntax highlight was at least available in the Borland products like Turbo
C and Turbo Pascal until almost the beginning of the 1990s. But before that, everything
appeared exactly in the editor in one single color, okay? So I remember that he was working
in his final project for CS1 and suddenly everything stopped working. He started getting
a lot of errors and because he actually mistakenly closed or deleted the closing symbol or symbols
that were required for a block comment, okay? And it was very easy to do that. I mean, it's
just the line that he accidentally deleted. But because you don't see the colors, you
always see that it was actually the same, suddenly things stopped working and it took
him about, I don't know, three, four hours to actually see the error and he was really
getting very upset, okay? Until somebody said, oh, you forgot to close this comment. And
once again, it wasn't that he hadn't closed it originally. It was that he accidentally
deleted the symbol that was used to close the block, okay? So once again, this is a
situation that could have been avoided if we had syntax highlight. So this is a program.
Notice here it starts with an opening parenthesis and we have here a module. Everything in Web
Assembly, every program that we write in Web Assembly or that is produced is inside a module,
okay? The module can have several things, okay? I'm really omitting a lot of information,
but Web Assembly modules inside, they can have one big memory object, okay, which can
be used for any kind of information that you want to store as a big array of bytes, okay?
You have tables that allow you to have pointers to functions and so on. These are used for
implementing, for example, pointers to functions in languages like C or virtual functions like
are supported in object-oriented languages like C++. You don't need to use them and
we're not going to use them here, okay, but they are available to provide that functionality.
You can have functions. You can have global variables. You have a question?
Yes? Yeah, exactly. Yes, notice that we're not providing an explicit name of a module
not in the declaration line number one. It is the name of the module is the name of the
file with WASM extension. Remember here it's a WAD extension because we're using the textual
format, okay? So here, because this is probably the most interesting part, we're just defining
one function. Notice here once again it starts with an opening parenthesis here and this
one is closing it. The closing parenthesis that we have here in line 22 is the one that
corresponds to the module, okay? Remember this is the S expression format, okay? So
here we have several, we can call these directives. We have an export. This is the name that is
going to be available for external tools, okay? So any external tool that wants to use
this WASM module once it's converted into WASM will be able to use the name that we
are exporting. If we don't export it, it's private to the module, okay? Actually the
name of the local, locally here in line number 10, I'm using the same name AVG but just notice
that these local names that we use inside our WebAssembly text format code have to start
with a dollar sign, okay? So you can see it here, the name of the function if we wanted
to use it locally. Strictly this part wasn't really required because I never call it from
within this code, within another function here, okay? But if I needed to call it, I
would use this name but it's only available local here, okay? Because I export it here,
this allows other tools to actually call this code whenever it's required. Here we define
the parameters, okay? Notice that we're, I'm using here this, this is actually Python but
using some type annotations, okay? Just to explain what it is. It's saying here A is
a float, B is a float and it returns a float, okay? So this is really what I'm putting over
here. So A and B are F64 data types, variables of this data type, they're parameters, okay?
They're considered inputs. And the output, the output is a, notice here it says result.
We're telling that at the very end of the execution of this function, there should be
in the top of the stack one only item and that item has to be an F64, okay? If there
are more elements, this actually produces a validation error, okay? So we have to be
very careful that if we push elements into the stack, at some point we take them back
and that we only leave, if this function is actually returning a result, we only leave
one result in the top of the stack, okay? The function does not require to return anything
if we want to, okay? That would be an equivalent to a void function in other languages. And
if that's the case, you need to leave the stack empty, okay, without any elements in
the top of the stack, okay? And here is the code, what you see here in this sort of pinkish
color, okay? So you do a local get A, so what does this do? It reads the variable A, the
parameter A, and pushes it into the top of the stack and then we do the same thing with
B. So currently in the stack we have A and B, we have, in the bottom we have B and then
we have the value of A in the top of the stack. We do an F64 add here in line number 17 and
when we do that, we pop two top elements in the top of the stack, from the top of the
stack, we do the operation, in this case the addition, and we place the result in the stack
again, okay? And then in a push operation, okay? And then we push the value two on the
top of the stack and now we do a div, okay? And as I explained, in the order in which
the elements were actually pushed, this is how the division is going to be carried out,
okay? So the division is going to divide the result of the add by two, because those are
the two values in the top of the stack, those are divided and the result is placed on the
top of the stack, okay? And we leave the top of the stack with that value, that's what
is going to be returned, okay? There is a return instruction that you could use if you
wanted, okay? But it's not really required if it's a very last instruction in your function,
okay? Yes? It doesn't have any artificial limitation, okay? I mean everything in life
has a limit, okay? So I can't really say, oh yeah, you can use all your memory in the
stack. But there's no limitation initially, okay? Now remember that this code here, once
it gets translated to WASM, the runtime environment is typically going to do just in time, okay?
Just in time compilation of the WebAssembly so that it gets translated from this WebAssembly
binary format into, once again, this can be done in several ways, but the JIT or Just
in Time compiler takes the code and translate it into native machine code in your platform,
whatever platform is where you're actually running this code. So most of our real hardware
CPUs that we use are typically register based. They're not stack based. So this means that
we'll need to use some registers and some additional memory in case not everything fits.
But in general, all that part is actually sold by the implementer of the runtime system,
okay? So we don't really need to put any limitations. I haven't read anywhere that it says that
there is a limit to how many elements you can put in the stack. But in practice, I've
seen that you usually don't need more than four or five elements in the stack at the
same time. Yeah. Exactly. Yeah, just in case you didn't listen, the observation that he
does is that the specification and the way that the virtual machine works is as a stack
machine, okay? But once this typically gets translated using the Just in Time compiler,
once again, this really depends on how it's implemented by the runtime system, typically
needs to convert this same code into the instruction set of a register computer, okay? For example,
when you run this in your, most of you probably using an x86 based machine. Some of you, if
you're using a recent version of Mac OS, probably you're using M1. So when we actually
loaded Piodite, it translated into the corresponding native instruction set, okay? And most of
the CPUs used in hardware currently are typically register based, okay? But once again, that
translation happens automatically. You don't really need to be aware of it. Yes?
Yeah, you need to just check if there is an implementation of the WebAssembly runtime
system in some fashion, okay? And if that's the case, of course it is able in microcontrollers,
okay? Like Raspberry Pi or...
Yeah, exactly. Yes, WebAssembly, one of the use cases it has is working for devices, small
devices that you use in typical Internet of Things kind of things, kind of stuff, okay?
Yeah. Okay, but once again, you need to check and see if there is that support for that
particular hardware that you're using, okay? But if there is, of course you can use it.
Yes, there was a question over here.
It actually does, if you see, we actually push these two elements. Those got popped
with the add, then we push another element. And the diff does two pops and a single push.
So at the end, if you look at the stack, the stack is going to only have one element. And
it is consistent with this directive that says it should be a 64-bit floating point
in the resulting stack, okay?
It is required. If it's not, you actually get a validation error. Okay, there is before
your code is actually executed, there is a phase called validation. We usually don't
talk a lot about it, but it's part of the security of the system. So one of the things
that it does is it makes sure that the stack is being used in a consistent fashion. So
if you try to do, for example, a pop when there's no elements there, okay, or you finish
your function and you said that this is only going to return one result and you have, for
example, two values in the stack, that actually produces a violation in the validation. Yes?
You get a, I don't remember if they call it a trap. There is some kind of runtime exception
being produced. Okay, one second. You can always check the documentation to see all
those particular issues and I'll show you where it is in a moment, okay? Yes?
Yeah. Yeah. No, there is a stack per every block. A function creates a block, but there
are other instructions. There's one actually called block, but also there are loops and
there's ifs that create blocks and each of those have their individual stack independent
of any other stack that might be there, okay? There is no shared stack among blocks. Yeah,
that's right. Okay, so just to use this, the way that we're going to be using this is as
follows, okay? Let's go here. We need to change to the directory for wet, okay? Once again,
you can use this instruction. We have it here. We're here and it's still in section 4.4,
okay? So you can just copy paste this one. This doesn't really matter in what directory
you are. It will take you to wet. If you know how to navigate within the terminal, you can
just go upwards to this directory and then go down to wet, okay? But whatever way you
do it, it is important that you are in the wet directory, okay? The wet directory, if
we check here the contents, ls, we only have the example wet and this is consistent to
what we see here with the explorer, okay? So the first thing that we need to do is convert
the wet source file into binary WASM, okay? So in order to do that, we have a tool called
wet to WASM. Remember, very important, if the system says that it doesn't find this
particular command is that you did not execute the source PyCon 2022 instruction at the
very beginning when you started, when you opened your terminal, okay? You can just try
it. Just type wet to WASM, okay? And if you see command.find here, it did find it but
didn't do anything, okay? But if you get an error, remember, you need to go back to section
2.2 and remember to execute or open a terminal and execute at wherever the terminal opens.
This command source PyCon 2022, remember, if you don't do that, you won't have access
to any of the commands that we're going to be using at this very moment, okay? So if
everything's fine, we should be able just to type here wet to WASM and we just indicate
here that it's the examples.wet file that we need to translate, okay? You can think
of this being sort of like a compiler. Technically, it's what we would call an assembler because
it's going to translate assembly code and text format into the corresponding binary
code, okay? WebAssembly, the name is a little bit, I wouldn't say confusing, but it goes
a little bit against what typically assembly is. Assembly should always or at least was
always considered to be a text format, okay? But when we talk about WebAssembly and when
we run WebAssembly, we're usually talking about something that is in a binary form,
okay? So this might be a little bit confusing at first, but just have in mind what we're
discussing at every point and hopefully that shouldn't confuse us too much afterwards.
So wet to WASM, translate a wet file, which is what we have into a WASM file. So if we
list the current directory now, we get that now we have the WASM file, okay? If you try
to open it here in the editor, it will tell you this is a binary file, it cannot open
it, okay? So once you have the WASM, you can do something like this. You can run it. We
have a utility called WASM3. And here, this is also explained a little bit downwards over
here. It's WASM3. We need to use this option REPL followed by the name of the WASM file,
okay? The REPL opens a read eval print loop, so it's an interactive prompt here that we're
going to be able to use to test our code. So we just put it there. It's double, double
dash REPL. And the file is called examples that. It's the WASM file that we want to run
here, okay? Just a quick note, WASM3 is an interpreter. This is not a just-in-time compiler,
okay? But for testing purposes, it works perfectly well for what we need here, okay? So here
we have the prompt. And now what we need to do is call our function using the exported
name. Excuse me. It's AVG2, okay? And you provide, just separating these by spaces,
the arguments that are expected here. So this is going to compute the average of two numbers.
So let's say that we give it a 5 and a 10. You can include a decimal point and some decimal
fractions if you want to, okay? But you need to provide the two arguments that are required,
okay, for A and B. The 5 is going to be A and the 10 is going to be B as expected. And
you press enter, okay? And if everything is fine, you should see something like this,
okay? I mean, so far we hadn't really modified the code, so we would expect this to work
without any issues, okay? So this is the average two function working. To exit WASM3, to exit
this prompt, just type control C or control D, okay? It has to be control without any
regard if you're using a Mac or a Windows or a Linux computer, okay? Control C or control
D, okay? So let's have a look at exercise B, okay? Exercise B says add to the WAT, example
WAT file, the file, the WAT file that we were looking at, a new function called AVG3. It's
going to do the same thing, but instead of receiving three, instead of receiving two
arguments, it's going to receive three arguments, okay? It's going to compute the average of
three, three integer numbers, okay? So just in case, here's a link to the corresponding
operations, okay? And you can see some individual things or operations that are in the code
or notice individual particularities of these instructions following the corresponding links,
okay? So these are instructions that we need to use to solve this one, okay? So this is
probably very simple, okay? We can use this one here as our model, okay? So we would typically
do something like this. I'm going to do with you this example. This is AVG3, okay? And
we need to use an export, export, not expert, export instruction here with the name that
we're going to use, which is AVG3. And we're going to use param, okay? And we need to provide
here three parameters, okay? Let's copy this, paste this to do this quickly. This is the
first one is going to be called A, the second one is going to be called B, and the third
one is going to be called C. Remember, they need to start these local names and they need
to start with a dollar sign, okay? It's not optional. It's part of the notation, okay?
So how do we solve this? How do we obtain the average of these three numbers? What do
we need to do? Yes?
Okay. Okay, yeah. Okay, yes. So here we need to push the variable, okay? So we need to
add the variable. Remember, we can only add two elements at a time, okay? So we can, in
this case, the addition doesn't really matter the order in which you want to do it. We can
push A and B into the stack and then do the addition and that leaves the results, okay,
in the top of the stack. Then we can push the C and we call add again and that would
add the previous result of the addition plus C, okay, and puts that in the stack. And then
finally we push a three and do the division, okay? Once again, remember because addition
is commutative, the order in which we do the additions is really not important to the final
result, okay? So let's start here by adding first A and B. Here we have these two, okay?
What instruction we use to add? F64 dot, F64 dot add, okay? So that adds the two top elements,
pops the two top elements and pushes the results back, okay? Then let's load or push into the
stack C. Then what do we do? We add again, yes, F64 add, okay? Then we divide by three.
Notice that at this point we have the addition of A plus B plus C, okay? We got the three
numbers added and that's in the top of the stack, okay? That's currently what we have
in the top of the stack. So to divide by three, what do we do? We push using F64 const, we
push a three and we finally call div to do the division, okay? So just a quick mention
here in Gitpod you don't need to save your files automatically once you do a modification
into a file that actually gets automatically saved, okay? I usually instinctively always
press control C or command C, okay? But strictly speaking it's not really required, okay? You
can check that out. And, okay, so here at the terminal what do we need to do? Watu-wasm,
okay? We can use exactly the same command because we're modifying the same file here.
And oops, oh, I missed something here. Anybody notice what I was missing? The result. This
is why we're getting a validation error because I did not say that it was going to return
something. So here we need to add F64. This is the expected result in F64, okay? The code
is correct but I needed to declare that I'm requiring here to leave always an F64 in the
top of the stack once we finish here, okay? So there we go. Notice here that we get here
a type mismatch. This is the error that we got here. It was expecting. This means the
square brackets, empty square brackets, this is I was expecting an empty stack but I got
a stack with an F64, okay? So this is a validation error, okay, done by the translator. And we
call it again. And we call wasm3 again with the REPL option here, okay? How do I test
it? Well, we call AVG3. There are three examples that we can use here with 1, 2, and 3 or with
14.5. I mean you can use whatever data value you want to check, okay? But here are three
possibilities if you don't want to think on any test cases. So if we put just 1, 2, 3,
the average of 1, 2, 3 is 2, okay? But you can check it out with the other examples as
well. Okay, any questions? Once again remember what we're doing here is hand coding WebAssembly,
okay? This is not the typical way that you use WebAssembly, okay? But once again I consider
it very educational to do it, okay? Because if you do it, you're more or less understanding
how this is supposed to work, okay? But then we're going to see higher level tools to actually
get this done automatically, okay? I think it's a good moment to take a break, okay?
So let's, what do you think? Fifteen minutes? Is it enough or do you want more? Yeah, fifteen
minutes, okay. So if you'd like, let's continue here at ten to eleven, okay? Sure. Thank you
very much for being back here. Okay, so let's continue. And let's go with exercise C. I'm
going to give you a few minutes to solve this problem here. Just like we did with the previous
function AVG3, here you need to create a new function called toCell, okay? Here's the name.
This one only takes one parameter, okay? And you need to implement this formula here. So
hopefully with what we've seen so far you should be able to carry out this, convert
this formula into the corresponding instructions in the WebAssembly text format, okay? And
here we have a few examples that you can use, okay? So once again, try to solve this by
your own, okay? If you need any help, you can ask me. And I'll give you five minutes
to see if you can solve it in that time, okay?
Okay.
Okay. Okay.
Okay. Thank you.
Awesome.
Okay. How many finished? Okay. Well, great. Any questions with this last exercise? No?
Yeah.
There are several instructions that allow you to manipulate the stack. In those cases,
you can have local variables, and that's the easiest thing. I mean, if you need to put
something in a place that you'll later put it, just put it in a variable like you do
in most languages at the end. But once again, it is always much more efficient if you can
do all the operations only in the stack, okay? But if you can't, you can always use additional
memory to process whatever you need, okay? Okay. Let's go to the next section. We're
now going to section number five, okay? This is basically the last half of our presentation
here. Okay. As I explained before, WebAssembly, as the couple of last exercises that we did
in which we wrote the WebAssembly text format code, that's typically not the way that you
should use WebAssembly, okay? WebAssembly really isn't, I mean, you can do it, but it's
really not designed for coding it by hand, okay? So what do you do? Well, you use, you
typically use a tool to somehow convert or produce this WebAssembly text code or the
binary format or whatever, okay? So in practice, typically you would start from a high level
language like C, like C++, like Rust, like Go. If you think about it, these are languages
that are typically much more performant, okay? They're used to write code that typically
has to be executed faster than what you typically do in Python or in JavaScript or some other
languages are typically interpreted. So most of the time, once again, if you want to use
WebAssembly, even if you at some point use Python, typically you would use some other
language to produce the WebAssembly, okay? There is not currently a compiler that translates
Python code directly into WebAssembly, okay? Typically you use a lower level language to
actually do that, okay? And once again, even if you start with C or with Rust, the advantage
is that if you're producing WebAssembly, your code will be more portable than if you just
compile it directly into native code, okay? So that's the most common use case. So in
this section here, what we're going to do is we're going to see how to write our own
compiler, okay? So we're going to write that tool that translates some code in some language,
we're going to see what language it is, into WebAssembly, okay? Now, originally when I
was designing this particular tutorial, I thought of implementing an esoteric language
that is called Brainfuck, okay? That's its name. I'm sorry, I don't really like to use
these explicatives, okay? And I did during my Easter vacations, I actually did a prototype
and it did work, but I thought it was more complicated than it really was worth. So instead
of that, I decided to go for a language that is called Forth. I don't know if anybody has
used or heard even about Forth, okay? Forth appeared somewhere in the 1970s, and the advantage
of Forth is that its semantics is very similar to WebAssembly, it's a stack-based language,
okay? So you push elements in a stack and then you pop them and do operations and push
the result back. So the translation of the code in Forth to WebAssembly is very straightforward,
okay? So the language is going to seem a little bit strange at first, if you've ever used
a stack-based language, but you have to be aware that they're not that uncommon. I mean,
WebAssembly is stack-based, but also other virtual machines are stack-based. The Java
virtual machine is stack-based. The common language infrastructure that is used in the
.NET technology is also stack-based. Languages like POS script, which you use to, I mean,
typically send information to a printer, laser printer and so on, it also works with the
language and that language is also stack-based, okay? So this use of stack is really not that
uncommon. Most of the time we don't deal with it directly, okay, but it is there. But
this language actually does expose a lot of the semantics of using a stack-based architecture.
And the language that we're going to implement here is not Forth. I mean, Forth is not a
big language, it's fairly small, but we're going to be working with an even smaller language,
okay? And I'll call it here Chicky Forth, okay? Where Chicky is, in Spanish, it's sort
of an informal word to indicate something that is tiny or that is small, okay? Chicky
comes from the word chiquiton or chiquita, something tiny, something small. And I use
this name because everything, all other names were already taken. I mean, I said, well,
is there a tiny Forth? And yes, there was an implementation tiny Forth. Is there a micro
Forth? And yes, there is a micro Forth. Is there a mini Forth? Yeah, all these things
that had to do with Forth and something small, all these names seem to be already used, okay?
So I said, well, let's combine something in Spanish and surely the name is not going
to be taken. And that's exactly what happened here. So this is why it's called Chicky, Chicky
Forth, okay? But it's a very small subset of the Forth. And of course, I took some additional
liberties to make this work in a way that I found interesting, okay? So it is a subset
of Forth and many of the things that I'm going to say are true for Forth, but not everything,
okay? So Chicky Forth works as typically you would expect. Let's have a look directly
here in this example. I usually include a lot of explanations here just in case at some
point in the future you want to review them. You have the full context to understand what's
happening, okay? But I'm not going to spend a lot of time reading what's there, okay?
But you can read it on your own if you find it interesting or amusing or relevant. So
here's an example of a Chicky Forth program, okay? So whenever you find a number here,
for example, the one you push it into the stack, okay? Just see a number, push it into
the stack. When you see an operation, for example, here the plus, well, you do what
is expected to do, which is do two pop operations, do the plus operation and push the result
back into the stack, okay? So here, as you can see, we are evaluating one plus two, okay?
And the result, which is three, is placed in the top of the stack, okay? Then we do
three plus four, okay? And seven is placed in the top of the stack. And then we do a
star. In this case, we take the seven, we pop the seven, we pop the three, which were
currently in the stack, the result of the previous two add operations, and we multiply
it so we get a twenty-one. And the dot, the final dot, is that it takes the element in
the top of the stack and prints it, okay? So this is gonna print a twenty-one at the
end, okay? So as you might imagine here, this is exactly the same thing as in Python, this
instruction over here, okay? So it adds one plus two, three plus four, multiplies those
two values and prints the result, which is twenty-one, okay? So that's the general way
in which Cheki-forth and, fourth in general works, okay?
So let's add some additional things that Cheki-forth is gonna do. Well, to start off, something
that is very important, the input is just gonna be a file that contains these, this
text. We're gonna use a split, the Python split operation to separate what fourth calls
words, okay? Every single element that is delimited by spaces is a word, okay? A number,
like one is a word. Plus is a word, okay? The dot is a word, okay? So sometimes we
need comments. So in order to represent comments, we're gonna use parentheses, okay? So we open
a parentheses. This means this is the start of a comment. Until we find the closing parentheses,
that's where the comment ends, okay? And these comments are just gonna be eliminated, okay?
It's just for convenience for us to write some meaningful information that might make
sense to us later on when we inspect the code again and never remember what we did before.
And well, the comments hopefully help us to understand what we were thinking, okay? Just
have in mind, okay, for this to work, there needs to be spaces before or after the parentheses,
okay? Because we're just gonna split it here. So we're assuming that there exist spaces
between the different elements that we want to exist in the program in general and here
in comments. Just make sure that the parentheses, you do not put it together without any spaces
next to any other elements, okay? We're gonna be representing variables and in general,
variable is anything, any word that starts with a letter and follows, is followed by
zero or more letters or digits, okay? So like very similar like any other language, this
is how we're gonna represent variables. And if the variable appears by itself, this means
that we want to read the value of the variable, okay? So if my program says X, that means
that I'm gonna read the value of X, okay? And what does it mean to read the value of
X? It means that we get the value of that variable and we push it into the stack, okay?
When we wanna do a write operation, in this case we wanna update or set or assign a variable,
we're just gonna use the name of the variable followed immediately and placed together without
any spaces with an exclamation mark, okay? So if we have X, we're reading the value of
X, which means take the value of that variable and place it on top of the stack, do a push
operation. But when you find X followed by an exclamation mark, I think you typically
call it a bang there, okay? I don't know if most of you call it that way, but I've heard
that that's the term that you use here or at least many people in the States use it.
So if you find X bang or X followed by an exclamation mark, it means take the value
that is on top of the stack and copy it or pop it and copy that value to that variable,
okay? So we have getting and setting of our variables, okay? And look at this example
that we have here. So what's happening here in the first line? We are pushing a two, a
one, a two and then a plus, so we have a three in the top of the stack. And then we do X
bang. This, what it does is that it pops the three in the top of the stack and copies it
to the variable X, okay? Once again, we do that set operation because we have an exclamation
mark. What happens in the next line, in line number two? Here we read the value of X the
first time and we push into the stack and then we read it again and push into the stack
and then we do a plus. So at the end we are adding three plus three, that gives us six
and with a dot we print it, okay? So this little program would print a six, okay, using
a variable. Just a quick mention here. It is valid. I mean, you don't need, as you can
see in the program, you don't need to declare variables here, okay? And actually any variable
that hasn't been set before, I mean, if you have a variable that you're reading it but
you didn't place any value before that, by default it has a zero, okay? So in any moment
you can just introduce a variable and if you read it without setting it before, you have
a zero there, okay, by default. Okay? So that's the use of variables in Cheeky Fourth. We
got these instructions for input and output. Okay? We already saw the dot by itself. This
one pops an integer value from the top of the stack and prints it, okay? And something
that I didn't mention before, it adds single space afterwards, okay? So this allows us
to actually have several numbers and print them using just a dot because they're going
to be placed together. We just add a space so that not everything gets all placed in
just one single big string, okay? So we add here a space immediately after we do a print
here, okay? Then we have an emit. Emit actually, what it does is similar to the dot. It's going
to pop a value from the top of the stack but instead of printing that number, it's going
to consider that number the character code of whatever value we have there and display
the corresponding character, okay? Now, you can think in terms of ASCII, the American
Standard Code for Information Interchange. So if, let's say that we have a 65 in the
top of the stack, that 65 is the character code for the letter, capital letter A, okay?
So if I have a 65 and I use emit, what I get is an A displayed, okay? The character A.
Technically speaking, we can talk about ASCII characters, okay? But strictly, it's a Unicode
characters. It's a Unicode code point that you're placing there, okay? So remember that
ASCII is actually a subset of Unicode. The first 128 characters of Unicode are the same
character codes for ASCII, okay? So you can think in terms of ASCII but it's really much
more. It's a Unicode code point that we really have here, okay? So it is valid to actually
use, for example, if I want a euro sign or want some sort of emoji or some, if I know
the character code of that one, we can place that number and do the emit and it will display
that corresponding value, okay? The corresponding character. NL represents a new line and new
line actually prints or advances to the next line, okay? By default, that doesn't happen
so we need to explicitly put it. And notice here that the new line is actually equivalent
to this, these two words together, okay? A 10 which is the character code for the new
line, okay? And emit would actually print it, okay? So actually, new line, this is really
not a new operation per se, it's just the combination of these two, okay? And we also
have input. Input will read from the standard input an integer and it reads from the keyboard
technically. I mean, it's a standard input so technically it could be redirected if you
want it. But well, it takes that value and whatever is read is placed on top of the stack,
okay? If you want to later on copy it to a variable, we'll just use the variable bang
operation that we saw a moment ago, okay? So that's a general description of our compiler.
Let's see how we write it, okay? The concurrent version of the compiler is about 170 lines
of code. I mean, it's not huge, okay? But it's fairly tiny if you think of it what all that
it actually does, okay? So I'm not gonna go line by line what it is. Let's just look at
the parts that are more interesting, okay? So the code is actually available here if
you go back to your workspace. Let's close the file that we had here and let's go to
the fourth directory and let's look at the cheeky fourth file, cheeky fourth.py. Okay,
as you can see actually a lot of what we have here are actually comments or document strings,
okay? So the code is really smaller, okay? So let me just show you some parts that are
relevant for us to understand the compiler. I have some strings here as symbolic constants,
okay? The first one is a multi-line string that has what we need to have at the top of
the beginning of every module that I'm gonna be producing, okay? That my compiler is gonna
be producing. As you can see at the very beginning it has a comment saying cheeky fourth compiler.
I think I didn't necessarily mention it but anything that starts with two columns is a
comment in WebAssembly, okay? WebAssembly text format, okay? So here's our module. Here's
where it starts. We are going to import three functions, okay? Import here, what it means
is that this function is defined somewhere else. I'm gonna be able to call it from my
WebAssembly code here, okay? And as you can see these happen to be the input output functions,
okay? We have emit, input, and print, okay? These are our functions. This is, you can
think of it as being the signature of the function. If it takes parameters it's gonna
tell me so and if it returns something it's gonna have a result as expression here saying
that it's gonna result in something, okay? Notice that we're just using here I32 so it's
gonna only work with 32 bit integers, okay? And here we start the declaration of our
function, okay? Notice that I'm only placing here its export directive. I'm saying that
I'm gonna export our function as a dunder, well it's not dunder, it's just an underscore,
underscore start, okay? This is the name of my function and this is where the execution
of the function is gonna begin, okay? We're gonna use that name, the underscore start
to indicate in our Python code that we wanna execute this, all this function. And in line
number 32, notice here that we have here just two closing parentheses. This is one and this
is the second one. The first one actually closes the function and the last one closes
the module, okay? So everything, every program that I produce here in my compiler has to
start with these several lines of instructions and has to end with these two couple of closing
parentheses, okay? So this is something that has to happen here. And in line number 35,
we have a dictionary here, okay? And this dictionary is the mapping between the words
of our cheeky forth programs and the corresponding instruction or instructions in WebAssembly,
okay, in WebAssembly text format. So in line 36, you can see that for doing a multiplication,
okay, we have the key in this dictionary is the star, okay? It means that whenever I find
a star, I need to convert this into the I32.mul instruction in WebAssembly text format, okay?
It's actually contained within square brackets. It's a list, what we have associated to each
value because we can have several instructions. As you can see, for example, in line 41, we
got the nl word, okay? And this one actually gets converted into two WebAssembly instructions.
The first one is I32 constant, which pushes the 10 to the top of the stack, and then a
call to emit, okay? Call, emit, well, calls the emit function that is defined somewhere
else, which is available here thanks to the important instructions that we did before,
okay? So notice here we already have implemented the star, the plus, the dot, the period, the
emit input and nl instructions here, okay? So that's what our compiler currently is able
to do, plus some additional functionality that is actually provided later on that has
to do with things like accessing variables and so on, which is not here, but those are
special because they work a little bit different. They're a little bit more elaborate, okay?
So let's go to the very end of our code. We have the main, and this is actually designed
so that you can just read the main and have a general idea of how this works, okay? So
any moment, remember, if you want to see the implementation of any of these functions,
just, I think, if you tap, if you press control and then just click with your mouse on the
name, it will take you to the definition or use command, I think, if you're using a Mac,
so if you want to see, for example, how check args works or how it's implemented or remove
comments or whatever, just press command or control and then you hover over the name and
as you can see, there's sort of like a link there, so for example, here in remove comments,
if I press command and then click over here, it takes me to the definition of the corresponding
code, okay? So this is a standard Visual Studio Code behavior, okay? So this is a fast way
that you can see the implementation. But the general thing that it's doing is pretty obvious,
hopefully, I hope, by the names that I'm using here in the different instructions. So in
line 153, we check the arguments. This program is going to be run as a script in the command
line, in the terminal, so check args is just going to verify that I've sent one command
line argument that is the name of the file that I'm, the cheeky fourth file that I'm
compiling, okay? If it's not, it just produces an error and ends the program. Line 154 takes
from this argv, argv, remember, is the vector of arguments, it's just a list that contains
arguments in the command line, okay? So in index one, this is where the name of the cheeky
fourth file should be found, okay? So I just put it here in this variable called full source
name. This is the name, includes any directories if that's part of the path of the file. All
of this is included here, so full source name is the full name of our cheeky fourth source
program, okay? Then we do this thing called read words. Read words, actually what it does
is that it reads the contents of the corresponding file, if the file is actually there and it's
found and it can be opened, it gets opened and then as I mentioned before, it uses the
split operation, the Python split over a string and it returns a list of all the individual
words, okay? Remember, these words are just things that are separated by spaces or new
lines or whatever, okay? So this variable in line 155 called words contains all the
words of our program, okay? Separated as individual strings now, okay? There's a list of strings
representing the single words in our program. In line 156, remove comments looks for words
that actually represent or an individual word that starts with an opening parenthesis, so
when it finds it, it knows that everything that follows should be ignored until it finds
the corresponding closing parenthesis, okay? So remove words, remove comments, excuse me,
does what you might imagine, it actually eliminates the comments from our words, okay? So at this
point we only have the code that we really care about of our cheeky fourth input. Result
is a local variable here that starts as an empty list, okay? This is where I'm going
to be putting all the instructions that are going to go as part of my output once we
start generating it, okay? So it will include all the instructions, the part that goes at
the beginning at the end of my what source file and then all the individual instructions
that we need to place. So they get appended using, well, append, okay? So this is an ordinary
list, so we start here by appending everything that goes at the beginning, okay? Remember,
we saw this multi-line string that contained all the initial declarations that have to
go in a what source file at the very beginning, okay? Then in line 159, this specific instruction,
this function, well, if we look at it from the nested part, first this function is called,
this is going to look for all the variables that are used in the program, okay? So it
just looks and see which variables are used and they can be used in two ways. They can
be used just the name of the variable. If you remember, if the variable appears by itself,
it means that we should detect or whenever we use it, it's just read the name of the,
read the value of the variable and push that value into the top of the stack or we find
a variable name followed by a bang symbol, the exclamation mark, okay? And in that case,
we know that we need to set that value. But at the end, it doesn't really matter how we
use it. As long as we use a variable, we need to find it. So findVar is just returns me.
I think it's a list of all the variables that are used in the program in any fashion, okay?
And then once we found them, we declare them, okay? And the declareVar is actually, if we
look at the implementation here of declareVar is, okay? It uses this instruction here, local
followed by the name of the variable, starting with a dollar sign, okay? Because all local
names in WebAssembly have to start with a dollar sign. But here we put the name of the variable,
okay? And we declare it as an I32 and place everything within these parentheses, okay?
The opening and closing here. And there's this other variable, it's actually named constant.
Indentation is just a string with four spaces, okay? This is just for legibility's sake,
okay? Strictly speaking, it's not really required, but it makes our code a little bit easier.
To understand, okay? It just adds some nice looking indentation there, okay? So this declares
all the variables that appear. Any variable declared here has a default value of zero,
so we don't need even to initialize it, okay? Automatically these local variables all have
an initial value of zero, okay? So as we mentioned before, if we happen to use a variable without
assigning any previous value to it, by default it's a zero that we get there, okay?
Go back here. So declare virus is the one that actually adds any variable declarations
that are required here. And then this is really the core, the core of our compiler. It's called
code generation. This is really where all the code generation actually happens, okay?
Let's have a look at it because it is interesting and relevant, okay? So the code generation
function takes where the result is going to be placed and all the words of our program
that we're going to consider here for translation. We just do a for, okay? We iterate over all
the words. Each and each iteration, each individual word is called word, okay? And these are the
things that I'm considering here. First of all, if the word is a number, okay? If the,
here the word that we're currently analyzing happens to be a number, we just push it here
using this instruction that we used in the past, i32.const and then the, whatever the
word is, okay? So if we find a five, if we find a three, if we find a 42 in our input,
in our input cheeky forth source program, we just push it into the stack, okay? Using
the i32.const instruction. If the word that we're currently processing belongs to any
of the keys of the operation dictionary, remember the operation dictionary is this one here,
so if any of the words is a star, a plus, a dot, an emit, an input, an L, any of those,
okay? If it's any of those, what we're going to do is that we're just going to place the
associated statements that we have in the dictionary and we are going to just put them
in the result, okay? We use another internal four because there might be several and this
is just done two in practice just to make sure that we add the indentation to each individual
statement here, okay? If we find a variable, just a variable, plain variable to read, not
to set, okay? The variable that instruction just gets translated into a local get with
the name of the variable and the dollar sign at the beginning and this is the other case
when we have variables that end in a bang operation, okay? So here's the exclamation
mark at the very end of the word and if the rest of the word, the things that go before
the bang are a valid variable name, then we convert that into a set, okay? So get and
set, this local get and local set are responsible for, in the case of get, reading the value
of a variable and pushing it into the top of the stack and set does the opposite which
is takes the top of the value of the stack and copies it into the variable, okay? So
we got the two things that we want to do with variables which is read those values and then
update them, okay? Or assigning them which is what the set operation does in WebAssembly
and here remember it corresponds in cheeky forth when you use an exclamation mark, okay?
If none of these actually went in, it means that we found a word that we don't know what
it is and if it's not something that we want, which it isn't, we just throw an exception,
raise an exception here, okay? Once again, this example, this compiler is fairly simple
to a really full-blown compiler. I've been teaching compiler construction for 20 years
at my university. So typically building a compiler is something that we take a full
semester to do, okay? And we have to do lexical analysis and syntactic analysis, semantic
analysis and then we do code generation and optimizations and stuff. So all that takes
a lot of time, okay? But now, well, in just around 150 lines of code, we see a full working
compiler because once again the language that we're really compiling is very, very simple,
okay? The essence really, if you want to think of what does it do is that it takes the name
of a file, it reads a file, it uses split to separate the individual words and then
looks at each word and says, okay, what do we need to do with this word, okay? And most
of the words can actually be translated thanks to this dictionary called operation, okay?
So that's a general overview of our compiler, okay? And yes, we need to, in the produce
code we need to put something at the beginning and then at the end. So at the end we have
something that is a complete full valid WebAssembly text file, okay? At the end, if we follow
once again, go back to the description here in the main what's happening, okay? We were
looking here at code generation, okay? Once we've finished code generation, we just add
what goes at the very end of the two closing parentheses that were in the string. We put
that in result, okay? And then we do this magical function called join, okay? We're
joining all the strings together, just separating each string with a new line, okay? I don't
know if you've used join in other languages, but Python actually has the object and the
arguments switched in the opposite order in which you typically find the join operation
in most other languages, okay? Most languages typically you have an object which is a list
and over the list you do the join and just tell it, use this string to separate these
individual lines, but for some reason the...
Yes, but in other object oriented languages, I don't remember for example JavaScript has
a join, but if it does, typically is the method is associated to the list and the argument
is the string that is going to be used to...
I think it wasn't really that difficult to do it the other way around, but for some reason
they decided, I really don't know if it was Guido who decided to do it this way, but once
again, if you're using Python only, it's not a big issue because you already know this,
but I find it sometimes confusing because in other languages I'm expecting to use it
and the arguments in the other way, okay? But it's just a comment there, okay? It really
doesn't really have to be in a certain way, okay?
Here in line 163, 163, we separate, we extract the extension of the file that was provided
in the command line arguments, okay? So if my file was called hello world dot fourth,
the fourth extension we're going to use is a four followed by th, okay? It's a fourth
extension. We eliminate the extension, the dot and the extension, and now we have the
full name without extension of our input file and we use that file name for two things.
We're going to create a what file in our file directory as part of our local file system
and corresponding wasm and this wasm here, this actually calls, if we look at the implementations
right here, calls a function called what to wasm which does exactly the same thing as
the what to wasm utility that we use from the command line, okay? These happen to have
the same name but the one that we use in the command line was part of this webit tools
that you can use from the command line. This what to wasm is part of a package called wasmer,
okay? Wasmer python, okay? Which is another runtime, runtime system for web assembly
and this one particularly well runs with python, okay? But the general idea is the same. It
converts, in this case, what is contained in a string. It's converted into a binary
object, okay? Which we then in line 148 write into a file, okay? So I'm writing these two
files, the what and the wasm file. Strictly speaking, we commit the what file because
this was created just as an intermediately thing, an intermediate thing but actually
we don't really need it once we used it to create the wasm file, okay? But because it's
useful and educational, we can have the what file and we can open it in an editor and see
what it has. Especially when we're doing the development, it's very useful for debugging
purposes and see if we did everything correctly, okay? So this is why we're creating these
two files. Yes?
You need to use special tools to actually do that, okay? So just for example, I mean
if you want to look at it now, I'm currently still here at the web directory and I wasn't
really prepared for this but let's see if I remember. There is a utility available here
that is called wasm, I think it's wasm object, object dump it's called, obgdump. Where here
you can use for example the option minus d, this one disassembles and then you specify
here your wasm file. And this one will generate the disassembled code of whatever you have
in here, okay? This is not in the notes, okay? But just write it down if you find this amusing
or interesting. Here it actually displays the disassembly. As you can see it's basically
the same instructions but the rest of it is not using the names of our parameters and
even the constants as you can see are actually in hexadecimal so they might be a little bit
complicated to understand. But here these are the hexadecimal equivalent byte codes
you can call them, okay? For the program that we have here, okay? So this is a way of inspecting
your binary file if you want to. Okay, once again you can't or you shouldn't really open
wasm files in an editor but there are tools that allow you to inspect it like this one
here. Okay, the wasm hyphen or dash object dump, okay? Using minus d this allows you
to do a disassembly. So this you can see the corresponding code. As you can see this one
here represents the AVG2 function and this one is the AVG3 one, okay? And it has the
same instructions that we have here plus it adds some, for example we didn't put an explicit
end but here it's actually added. And instead of using the option minus d you can use the
minus x and this one gives you the disposition of the different sections that the wasm file
has, okay? It has a section for types, a section for functions, a section for exports and then
a section for code, okay? So this one allows us to see more in detail the corresponding
sections that are available, okay? So this utility is wasm dash obj dump, okay? If you
want to look at what's in the wasm file, okay? Once again if you try to open it, I mean you
can try it, open the wasm file you get this message saying the file is not displayable
in the editor because it's either binary or uses unsupported text encoding, okay? Do you
want to open it anyway? Well, let's say yes, okay? Use the text editor and okay, it doesn't
really look like anything useful, okay? As you can see something interesting that is available
there is that it contains a name, you can see the name of our exported functions, avg2
and avg3, here they are. Yeah, and another interesting thing is that it has a magic number
at the beginning, okay? It starts with, don't remember what's the very beginning here, it's
probably easier to look here at using an ordinary xdump. Let's see if this works. Okay, so this
xdump just places all the contents and you can see here the magic number at the beginning
of this file is zero which is this represented as this dot and here we have 6173 and 6D,
these are hexadecimal numbers, they correspond to the letters A, S and M. This is how we
can see that this is actually a binary as in WebAssembly text file, okay? Binary file,
binary file, okay? So this is using a standard Unix or Linux utility call xdump just to see
the content of the files. Notice that xdumps allow us to see an hexadecimal of the corresponding
bytes that are in part, so this is useful when you have a binary file, okay? But it
doesn't really give us a lot of information, it just, well, it's not immediately obvious
but it contains all the byte encoding for the instructions and here's the magic number
and as you can see here, this is a section of the exports, okay? That is in the previous
output that we had here, export two, it has A, B, G, 2 and 3 which we can see that they're
actually here, okay? And well, the rest is obviously valid information but an interesting
thing here is that the WebAssembly binary files that we can see here are fairly small.
I don't know if you've seen, for example, if you use any compiler for C or C++ or Go
or Rust. In C and C++ typically an executable binary file is, with all the information that
it requires, is typically a few hundred or maybe tens of thousands of kilobytes, of bytes,
excuse me, big, okay? So you might have a Hello World and it's, I don't know, just to
say number, 80,000 bytes wide or big, your corresponding file, okay? WebAssembly is very,
very, very small and this is very useful when you're transporting or sending your files
between a server and a client. You want really your files to be very small, okay, because
if they're very big, of course, it's going to take much more bandwidth to actually get
it there where you want to. So WebAssembly is a really compact and small format and it's
very useful as it is, okay? So going back, let's see, where were we? We should be able
at this point, here's a description of what we explained a moment ago. There's this thing
that we need to see. In order to run our code, remember WebAssembly needs a hosting environment
to run. The examples that we saw a moment ago using WASM3, that was a runtime environment.
That actually is an interpreter that allows us to see our code running. But we're now
going to be integrating it using this Python package called WASMIR, okay? WASMIR has all
the functionality to do most of the things that you would expect to process WebAssembly
and binary files, okay? It allows you to take a WebAssembly, a WAT file, a WebAssembly text
format, and it converts into WASM, to the binary format. It can take an already compiled
WASM file in binary form. It can actually take it, translate it, convert it, get the
module converted into an instance that it's called, and execute that, okay, within a Python
program, okay? So this is a really interesting part of how all this is integrated. And in
order to see that, there is this program here. I'm not going to look at it in too much detail.
But this one is in this program called execute.py. It has all the functionality. Let's open
it here quickly. Where am I? Oh, here we are. Let's close this. And let's open here execute.py.
So here, if you go to the very end, okay, this is what the main function does here.
Just as we did in the previous program, it checks that the number of arguments are correct
here. We're expecting to receive a WASM file, okay? If it is, we create an instance. This
create instance just encapsulates all the logic that is required. Here it is. This actually
uses extensively a lot of functionality provided by WASM. So if you really want to go and see
how all this works, check the WASM documentation. It needs to create several objects, a store
object, an instance, a module, and so on. So I'm putting everything here just together
so that it just works. As long as you send a file name, they're in line number 54, a
file name that is actually a valid WASM file, okay, it will be able to read it, to instantiate
it, and to do just-in-time compilation and everything that is required. Notice here that
we're using this operation called engine.jit. Okay, this is the just-in-time compilation.
Okay? And at the end, we return this instance object that contains all the information.
Now, another thing that is important here is that it calls this make import object,
which is a function that is just over here. And the interesting part here is that it contains
the code that we imported from our WebAssembly modules, okay? Remember, at the very beginning
of what we're going to be producing, we had three import instructions. And these are the
functions that are going to be called whenever we do a call to the corresponding function,
okay? So here we have the emit, the input, and the print instructions. These are Python
instructions. As you can see, for example, the print is very simple. It's, we receive
here an integer. We use actually annotations here so that the tool knows what we're expecting
to send as input and to produce as output. But here, we receive here an integer. And
we just use standard print. Actually, this function is called underscore print because
otherwise it would enter into a conflict with a predefined function called print. We just
print the value of x, which is an integer. And we put it at the end just instead of a
standard new line, which is what typically ends our print instruction, we're ending with
a space here, okay? For the input, we use the input instruction and we call int. If
this happens to produce an exception, a value error exception, we just return a zero, okay?
So the input doesn't crash, okay? If you put anything that is not a valid integer, it just
returns a zero, okay? And here we have the emit, which is very similar to print. We just
convert x, which is an integer, into its corresponding character. So we use the chr, which is a standard
function in Python, that takes an integer value and converts it into a string that contains
the corresponding character of that code point, okay? And in the case of the end, we don't
add a space, we just keep the cursor where it is, okay? So with all that in mind, we
should be able to see how this can work. So in order to make it work, we need to change
first to this directory called forth, okay? Once again, remember you can change it. Here's
the command if you want to change it from anywhere in your current system. So you can
use that one there. It's a CD instruction. Or you can, if you know how to navigate here
in Linux, you can go to the correct directory. You can change to a parameter directory and
go to the directory you want, okay? And here in the forth, so in order to run the compiler,
the compiler is called cheeky forth, okay? You just put the name. Remember here, the
cheeky forth actually has a hash bang at the beginning and it has execution permission,
so we can just execute it like this, okay? Dot slash and then the name, okay, has, it
knows, the operating system knows that we are able to run this program, okay? And let's
try it with first example, which is called numbers, okay? This is a forth program. Let's
quickly look at it. Here's examples and here's numbers, okay? So we have a quick description
of what this does. As you can see, it says adds and multiplies two user provided numbers.
So here we start with these two emit instructions. This actually just prints a greater than symbol
and then a space, so it looks like a prompt and then allows us the user to do an input
and whatever its input is placed on top of the stack and with this, we pop the stack
and just copy this into the variable x and we do the same thing with y. And then we have
all this, which will print actually the value of x plus the value of y and gives us a corresponding
result, okay? So this is our first program. Remember, this is forth. This is our input
program that we're, our compiler currently knows how to translate into WebAssembly, okay?
We run it. We shouldn't have any problems. Notice here that it creates two files, a wasm
and a watt, okay? We can inspect with the editor the watt file, okay? So we can open
it and see what it is, what we have here. So now this is the code produced by the compiler,
okay? As you can see, it's quite a lot of code. Our program was, original program was
much shorter. It was actually just 14 lines of code, okay? But the corresponding watt
code, well, requires much more lines, okay? But I mean, at the end, that's the point of
actually writing a compiler so that we don't need to write all this by hand, okay? I mean,
that's why compilers were actually born. Remember that when computer as an industry started,
all programming was done in machine code or in assembly language, okay? But then suddenly
some people realized, well, what if we had a program that we could write our code in
a much higher level and then translate it into machine code or assembly, okay? That's
exactly what we're doing here, okay? So very powerful, the idea of getting something written
in a certain notation, translating it into something that the computer can understand
more easily, okay? So how do we run it? Once again, you can inspect all this with much
more detail, okay? But this is exactly what we had in this program here translated into
WebAssembly. So just to run it here, once again in the terminal, we now run the execute
script and we tell it where to find the WASM file, okay? In this case, it's also, it's
placed in the same place where the source file was. So here we have WASM and Watt. We
run the WASM, okay? The Watt was useful to create the WASM. And it's now running, okay?
So think of it, what's happening here. We, WASM, this Python package that is the WebAssembly
runtime is able to read this file, okay, which is in this binary format. It does a just-in-time
translation of that file into the native platform, whatever is running here in our, in our Git
pod workspace, okay? It gets translated. This is actually an x86 computer. So it gets translated
into that native code based on, on, on registers and so on. And once again, the, strictly speaking,
the WASM code can't really interface with the rest of the world, but because we have
these imports, we're able to call Python functions that will do that, that job for us, okay?
But notice that even though what we're looking at, what, what gets printed, and in this moment
it's actually expecting us to type something, all that is being done through Python. But
the order in which the things are done and the arithmetic operations like the addition
and multiplication is going to be done, all that is done through the native code that
was translated from the WebAssembly binary code, okay? So, I mean, there's a lot of stuff
actually happening here, okay? But at the end it gives me just illusion of everything
working nicely together. So let's put, I don't know, a 10 and let's put a minus 5, okay?
And these two lines, 11 and 14, these are the ones in charge of displaying what we have
here, okay? So as you can see, it is, it is working. And we have a Hello World, okay?
We typically start with Hello World in many languages, but here it's not that really interesting.
As you can see here, we start in line number 4, we start pushing a 72. What's that 72?
It's the capital letter H, yes, exactly. And we do an emit, so that prints the H, okay?
And then we have 101 emit, that would be the lowercase e, okay? And we emit it, okay? And
so on. As you can see, putting messages here is pretty, pretty difficult, pretty error-prone,
okay? But it works, okay? And at the end it has a new line. So we can now try it out,
okay? So we first need to compile it. We use a Cheeky Fourth compiler. The file is in the
examples directory and it's called HelloWorld.fourth, okay? Once again, remember when we use Cheeky
Fourth, this creates two files and here they are. One has same, both have the same extension
of the program that it compiled. The program that received with, as input has a .f4th,
fourth extension, okay? And it produces two files with the same name but different extensions,
WASM and Watt. Once again, you can open the Watt to see what it has. So this is the HelloWorld.
As you can see, it's pretty, pretty long, 37 lines of code, okay? And in order to run
it, we use execute. And we specify the directory. And then we have the directory. And then we
run the file with extension WASM here in this case. And it says HelloWorld, okay? So it's
working fine. Okay. I don't know if there are any questions so far. No? Okay. Okay,
now we're going to give you, but basically there's only two exercises left, okay? I'm
going to give you some time so that you can solve them now. Okay, let's just quickly explain
what you're supposed to do in both these exercises, okay? So exercise D, which is section 5.5 of
our tutorial notes, okay? We're going to add a bunch of new operations, okay? And this
is fairly easy, okay? So, for example, if we want to have support for minus, which we
currently don't have, okay? What are we going to do? We're going to add this word, the minus,
to the dictionary called operation. And I'm giving you here so that you don't need to
look it up. This is the corresponding instruction that needs to be done whenever it finds a
minus, okay? So let me go here quickly. You would go to the cheeky forth file. Here it
is. Look for the operations dictionary, the operation dictionary, okay? It doesn't really
matter where you put it. I'm going to put it here after the plus, but it really doesn't
really matter. You put the name of the word. In this case, it's the minus. And inside a
list, you need to put a string with a corresponding WebAssembly instruction. What's the corresponding
WebAssembly instruction here? It's I32.sub. Remember, I'm putting you there a link if
you wanted to look at the documentation and see exactly how it works and variations of
this instruction, okay? But at this moment, if you just use the instruction that I placed
over there, that should do all the trick, okay? So you can even copy-paste it if you
prefer. I32 sub, okay? And you need to do exactly the same thing there for all the instructions
here, okay? Which are the one we just did, the minus, the slash, which does division,
and then we have equal, not equal, less than, less or equal, greater than, greater or equal,
okay? And please check out the corresponding instructions. Some of them are not necessarily
immediately obvious what they are, okay? But I placed it here. So you need to complete
that dictionary so that it has all of them, okay? And if everything works correctly, okay,
you should be able to test it for this exercise D using this file which is called operators.forth,
okay? So if we go and open that file, here it is, operators.forth, okay? This one tests
us everything, okay? The subtraction, the division, the equal operation, the not equal,
and so on, and it generates some values there, okay? All these operations that are like equal
and different and so on, the way that this works is that, for example, here it's asking
if x is equal to y. If they are, it pushes a 1 in the top of the stack, the 1 indicating
true, okay? And if they're not equal, it puts a 0 indicating that it's false, meaning that
they're not equal, okay? So I take the expected values here that are produced, add some additional
values over here and do some emits. So if you run this and everything is working fine,
it says here that it prints everything is working fine if everything is working fine,
okay? So if you did all your work correctly, it should print this. If some of the characters
are not correct, maybe you mistakenly did something else, okay? If something's wrong,
instead of looking at all these individual characters, you might see some characters
change, okay? So if it's not exactly this string, you need to check and see if you did
something wrong or if you get an error, okay? Something was missing there, okay? So hopefully
with that introduction, you should be able to solve this one here. And let's go directly
with exercise E as well, okay? Exercise E, what we're gonna do is we're gonna add a do
loop here, okay? Two words that actually correspond to like a while loop in other languages including
Python, okay? It basically works exactly like that, like a while in Python or in C or in
Java or in any other language, okay? So do indicates this word, indicates the very start
of our loop, okay? Then we expect a condition here. The condition is just a cheeky fourth
code that if the result in the top of the stack once the condition is evaluated is the
value of zero, okay? Zero, remember, represents a false value, okay? If we have a zero on
the top of the stack, well, we pop it. If we find a zero, we go to the end of the loop,
okay? That means go to whatever instruction follows the loop word here, okay? So just
like a while in other languages, okay? We evaluate. If this is false, we end the loop.
Exactly the same thing happens here. We evaluate the condition. If we get a zero on the top
of the stack, we pop it and we go to the end of our do loop structure here, okay? Or construct.
But if it's true, and true means anything that is not zero, okay? We go to whatever
is after the question mark and we call here the body. We execute the body here as many
times as we want, okay? So here's an example how this is supposed to work, okay? So we
start here X. We initialize it. Remember, this sets the value of X to whatever we have
on the top of the stack, which in this case is going to be a one. We want to print all
the numbers from one to ten, each number in its own line. Then here we start our loop,
okay? I'm using indentation not because it's required, just because it makes it simpler
to understand. We have this. I'm asking here if X is less or equal to ten. If it is, these
words here are going to leave a one in the top of the stack, so we pop the stack. And
if it's true, we'll continue with what falls. But if it's false, which means we had a zero
here, it goes and executes, continues executing whatever falls as a loop instruction here
of a loop word, okay? But if it's true, okay? I mean, if it's false, it ends the loop. But
if it's true, it does the body. In this case, this body is these instructions. We print
the current value of X, okay? And we print a new line. And in this last instruction,
we add X plus one and then we assign the result to X, okay, using X bang here. And we go again
to the beginning and ask if we, our current value of X is still less or equal to ten,
okay? So this prints one, two, three, four until the ten, okay? So once we add this instruction
here, you notice that we're not going to add an if instruction. The if, believe it or not,
can be simulated using a do with a little bit of imagination. It's probably not as simple
as to use a standard if instruction, but if you think of it, the do loop, even though
this is supposed to be repeated several times, you can guarantee that it only does the condition
once and then set another variable so it doesn't go in again, okay? So the do loop, even in
the primitive way, can actually support some kind of if construct, okay? Once we add the
do loop here, just as an interesting fact here, the cheeky fourth language is converted
into something we computer scientists call Turing complete language, okay? And in general,
this is CS jargon to say that our program, our language actually is able to do the same
thing that a Turing machine can do, okay? So we basically have a full programming language
here available that can do some pretty neat stuff, okay? And the good news for us is that
the do and the loop and the question mark are really straightforward to implement. I'm
not going to explain exactly how they do it, okay? If you have that kind of curiosity,
check out here the links of these instructions, block, loop, and branch, which are the ones
that we need to use. But notice here, you're going to change the operation dictionary just
like in the previous exercise, and when you find a do, okay, you put a list with these
two instructions, okay, as strings. When you find a question mark, okay, the associated
text or code in this case is these two instructions. And finally, the loop. When you find the loop
as a word in the cheeky fourth program, you convert it into these three instructions in
the corresponding, well, in the list, each one as an individual string, okay? And the
rest is actually, the compiler actually knows how to produce or generate all this code directly
as long as it's in the dictionary in the way that I just described, okay? So once you have
that, you should be able, well, just a quick note over here, and this is something that
was mentioned a moment ago. The do loop actually introduces a new stack, which is independent
of the stack that was actually available before the do loop started, okay? So you have to
understand that you start with a brand, when you have a do, you start with a brand new
empty stack, okay? And you have to make sure that at the end, the stack is empty, okay?
When you finish your code, okay, you have a condition, you have a body. At the end of
the body, you have to make sure, and at the end of the condition as well, you have to
make sure that the stack has no elements there, okay? The example that we just saw a moment
ago guarantees that that's how it works, okay? So most of the time it should make sense to
make it work that way, but if it doesn't, you'll get a validation error, okay? So just
mention that. So, yes?
Yes. Yeah, in this case, you need to use div underscore s because for integers, you can
have two interpretations. They can be signed or unsigned. In the case of floating point
numbers, they are always signed, okay? But integer numbers can have or not signed. So
you have two versions there. There's a div underscore s for signed values and a div underscore
u for unsigned, okay? And this is one of the reasons that I actually place explicitly the
instruction, okay? Because these are some of those things that are not necessarily obvious,
immediately obvious, okay? So yes, use div s. And this actually happens as well when you
use less than or less or equal. You need to specify you're using the signed version or
the unsigned, okay? Because it's a different instruction depending if you want to consider
or not your integers with or not a sign, okay? So once again, here you just need to add these,
associate these words in the dictionary, in the operation dictionary with these instructions,
okay? And if everything is fine, you should be able to run these remaining three programs,
one to t, one to ten dot fourth, triangle dot fourth, and pow two dot fourth, okay?
Just in the case of triangle and pow, I actually tested this code with my students a couple
days ago. And the immediate question is what am I supposed to input in these two programs?
So for these last two programs, try any value between five and twenty and see what happens,
okay? I'll be with you in just a moment, okay? So do these two exercises, test it finally
at the end with these three examples, okay? And if everything works, you're all done,
okay? I'll be here just to answer in general any questions that you might have. But just
let me tell you what's available here in the next section. These are some books. I've actually
read completely this one. This is a really short book and read a few chapters, not all
of it. But this is a very nice book if you want to have a really technical in-depth overview
of WebAssembly, okay? Both are available through the O'Reilly Media site, okay? But they're
also available on paper, I think. And some additional resources, okay? So check them
out if you want to see a little bit more in-depth any of the things that we've described so
far. And remember, the notes are full of links to Wasmr and to all the technologies that
we mentioned. So in any moment if you want to learn more about that, just follow the
link, okay? So please work on these. And basically, that's all the material that I'm going to
be presenting. So we have here until 12.30. If you have time and want to finish these
exercises, I've seen some people that needed to leave a little bit early. But I hope you
can try it because it's really interesting to see the final results of the full compiler
working, okay? And remember that at the end, this is typically the use case that we have
most of the time on WebAssembly. We've got a higher level language, in this case, Cheeky
Forth producing WebAssembly that we call from, in this case, a runtime system which happens
to be Python, okay? So here we're using Cheeky Forth, but in practice this could be produced,
the Wasmr file could have been produced by C compiler, C++ compiler, Rust, Go, et cetera.
There are many plenty of languages that you can use. But at the end, you typically write
it in a higher level language and let the compiler do the translation, okay? So what
we're doing here is writing our own compiler so that we can see how this process is done.
I hope you find interesting and amusing. A little compiler, I mean, it's fairly simple,
fairly straightforward, but it actually does produce a complete WebAssembly output, okay,
that we can actually run, okay? So please carry on with these exercises if you do have
time and I'll be here answering any questions that you might have at this point, okay? So
I think for recording purposes that would be all, okay? Thank you very much.