There are a lot of you in here because this is not as simple as it may seem as many of
you have probably found out through, like, your first attempts at setting up your computer
or the many follow-on failed attempts, you know, decades later as a seasoned Python developer
still trying to do this type of thing.
So a little bit of intention setting.
I think that's important for kicking off the talk the right way.
For those of you who may not be familiar, there is an Easter egg in Python that gives
you the Zen of Python if you import and run this module.
So I recommend to anyone who I've ever taught Python to or had the pleasure of teaching
them how to get started with Python is to print this out, put it in a frame, put it
in your bathroom, and read it every day when you brush your teeth, a couple times a day.
It's good for the soul.
It's good for more than just programming and coding.
But it helps just everyone on the same page about how we're going to think about this
kind of a problem of getting your computer ready to be your superpower tool that is going
to be the thing that you use day in, day out as the role of a developer or a system engineer
or whatever the role may be where you're going to be using Python, whether you're a data
scientist or whether you're going to be a software developer or engineer.
This is an important one.
And we're going to highlight a couple of these throughout the talk, and I'll get to those
in a moment.
But the ultimate goal here is to end up not here.
Some of you are familiar with XKCD.
This was in April 2018.
Randall Munroe posted this comic admitting he had did some bad things to his computer
at this point.
So if you've seen this, the Python Environmental Protection Agency wants to seal it in a cement
chamber.
And so that was the alt text on this specific one.
But it was funny.
It's like there's a lot of truth in this cartoon.
And I can tell you from being someone who's been I've used Python since the year 2000.
Very first version of Python ever installed was version one five two.
And all this is true.
And I've been through all of this stuff because I've been on a Mac or on Linux or on Windows.
And I've ended up with five different installs.
And I'm not sure where this Python is coming from.
I'm not sure where PIP's putting something.
I swear I installed something in one spot.
I go over to use it in the project.
And it's like module not found.
I think we all can relate.
And actually, if you all are, you know, if there's a quick question, don't hesitate to
like raise your hand.
I'll make sure I repeat it back.
But I want to avoid this situation for you all.
Because Python does live in many places.
It is provided by your operating system.
So if you're on a Mac or if you're typically on Linux, those are going to have Python preinstalled.
And I know it sounds great.
But be warned, that may not be the one for you.
You may have installed Python from an app store.
So for example, if you go to the Microsoft app store, there is a shiny Python that you
can search and install in there.
Great way to get started as a new developer.
But may not be the right one for you either.
You can download an installer from Python.org.
So there are some binary package installers.
There are source code downloads.
As a beginner, that is also daunting and confusing because you're not sure which one is going
to work for you necessarily.
Or you can be using a package manager.
There's lots of great choices there as well.
If you're on Debian and Ubuntu, there's apt.
If you're on the other Linuxes, you're going to have yum or whatever the latest installers
there may be.
Homebrew, which is actually a personal favorite of mine, and I highly recommend it.
And I'll be showing off some homebrew stuff in this talk.
If you're on Windows, there's an equivalent to homebrew called chocolatey.
And all these will give you a way to install Python onto your machine.
And you can also have Python installed via a Python distribution.
So if you aren't familiar, there are custom package distributions like the Anaconda Python
or the ActiveState Python that are kind of prepackaged and supposed to give you a great
experience out of the box.
But if you still are confused about these kinds of things, it may not give you that
great experience you're totally expecting.
So why should you care about all of this at all?
It just sounds mind-numbingly boring almost to me to think we'd have to still be dealing
with this in the year 2022.
But we do.
Because we want to make sure that everyone can stay zen.
I mentioned we were going to highlight a couple of these in a Python statements, which specifically,
the beautiful is better than ugly, the explicit is better than implicit, and simple is better
than complex.
I think one of the ways, if you've ever kind of heard the term the ceiling of complexity,
one of the ways to break through, the only way you can break through the ceiling of complexity
is to simplify.
So that last one is very important is to keep things simple until they can't be any more
simple.
And then we'll talk about that beautiful is better than ugly.
If it feels wrong, it might be wrong.
Kind of that smell test as a developer when you're going through and writing some code
and you're like, this doesn't feel right.
It's getting the job done, but I'm not sure about it.
Same thing goes for how you're installing and using Python in your local system.
And I'm hoping that today we can talk about improving that process, making it more consistent,
making it more simple, making it more explicit.
Implicit Pythons are troublesome because you don't know where they came from.
You don't know where the PIP's going.
You don't know where the packages are being installed into.
So let's start off with some ground rules first.
And quick rules that will keep you as safe as possible on your own computer.
So again, focusing on getting this right and having that foundational base is, in my mind,
just an important factor of the fact that this is how I make my livelihood.
I want to have this the most awesome killer setup on my machine that just makes me as
productive as I possibly can.
But we're going to start off with this first rule, which is no pseudo.
You should not have to type pseudo to do anything with Python, whether you're installing Python
or installing a package in Python or installing some kind of add-on for Python.
There is no reason to ever use pseudo.
I don't care.
No whining.
If you're using pseudo to do something on your machine or administrative privileges
to do something on your machine, you're probably doing something incorrect or, again, it should
feel wrong to you.
That smell test should tell you that something is awry if you're using pseudo.
I mean, the reason for this is you're most likely going to be installing a Python package
into a place that it shouldn't be, like in, for example, the system Python.
Do not use the system Python.
That Python that came on your computer, if you're on Linux or on Mac, that's not for
you.
That's not your Python.
That Python is for use by the system itself.
The installed OS is going to be running its own scripts and its own programs and own kind
of cleanup tasks.
Those are going to be using the system Python.
If you upgrade out from underneath the system Python some package that one of those scripts
is relying on, you could actually be making your whole computer unstable and you're heading
for a reinstall of the system or else a really terrible cleanup.
Don't use it for anything.
That system Python is not for you again.
I repeat that.
That's not for you because that is only for the OS.
So now I know you're saying, okay, this Python on my computer, but you're telling me I can't
use it.
What do I do, smart guy?
I'm going to hopefully encourage you to start down the right path.
I'm going to give you a couple quick tools and techniques that I find to be very, very
useful.
The first one is going to be Pyenv and not to be confused with Pimpenv or pip or a million
other tools that seem to be very, really similarly named.
Pyenv is a really, really specific nice tool that has been open sourced that allows you
to change your global Python that you would use.
So if you are sitting in a terminal and you type the word Python, what you expect to have
happen would actually be launching your Python that's yours.
You've installed through Pyenv and not the system Python.
So right now if you didn't have Pyenv installed and you typed the word Python, you're going
to be using the system Python.
Again, problematic.
You can have per project Python versions.
As a consultant, I deal with a lot of Pythons day in and day out.
We've got projects that are running from Python 2.7 straight through to I don't think anything
on 3.11 yet, but definitely 3.10, the most recent stable version of Python and everything
in between.
We've got projects on 3.7 or 3.8, 3.9.
I need to have an easy way to be able to install each of those and keep them clean so that
I can now have virtual sandboxed environments so that I'm not stomping on my own self as
I go and install dependencies for various projects.
Then the other quick tools here.
This works for Linux and for Mac.
If you're on Windows, there is a Pyenv win, but I probably wouldn't recommend using it.
I'm going to recommend something for Windows folks would be to investigate and seriously
consider using WSL2.
The Windows subsystem for Linux is very mature now, much faster than the original version
of it.
When I give you an experience that is going to line up with a lot of how-tos online where
people are using Linux, you'll just feel like one of the gang.
Because basically the WSL2 gives you a full Ubuntu or full Debian or whatever you installed
as your base Linux for WSL on Windows.
It gives you that full environment out of the box, ready to go, and you'll be able to
do everything you would see here today just like I'm doing on my Ubuntu here.
You can do it on Mac.
You'll be able to do it on Windows just the same.
You'll see this actually in action here.
Okay.
I've got my terminal and I have Pyenv installed, but the way to install Pyenv is going to be
with, in my case, I use Homebrew for everything.
If I'm on Linux, there's Linux Homebrew.
If I'm on Mac, the Mac Homebrew installs the same.
It has cross-platform support between the two OSs.
If you're on Windows and you're using WSL, that will work as well because you're just
using Linux.
Once you've done a brew install Pyenv, that will get you all the way there.
I already got it installed, so I don't need it.
Once I've got Pyenv installed, I can now see if there are versions of Python that are on
this system.
It's going to include out of the box the system Python in consideration for a Python you would
want to use.
Right now, it's showing me my global Python is set to the 3.10.3, which is installed into
a specific folder on this system, which is in my home directory.
Then you see I've got a 3.8 version available, I've got a 3.9 version available, and I'll
talk about those other versions up there that are named and don't have necessarily version
numbers in them.
They are going to be virtual environments.
If I wanted to just type the word Python, I will get a 3.10.3 Python environment.
That's just the one that's installed from Pyenv.
I didn't use sudo.
For example, if I want to install another version, for example, 3.9.4.
3.9.4, because we've got old projects that might be using that.
That goes in downloads from python.org and grabs all the stuff.
If you're using Homebrew, it's going to use all the zlib and read lines so that you've
got all the dependencies satisfied to make sure you're good to go to install Python.
We'll come back to that window here momentarily.
If I can find my mouse, here we go.
We can now also do, for example, if I go onto my desktop and I've got two folders here,
project one and project two.
If I go into project one and I want to use a specific version of Python here as opposed
to another version of Python, like the default Python.
I type Python, I get 3.10.3, which is that default global.
If I type Pyenv local and say I want to use 3.9.11, excuse me.
You'll notice my prompt actually automatically updated over there on the right side to show
that I'm using 3.9.11.
Now when I type the word Python, I get 3.9.11 by default.
I'm in full control of my environments here.
I know where it's coming from.
It's explicit.
I have said I want to use this version of Python when I'm in this folder.
If I go up a directory, you'll see that the 3.9.11 went away.
And when I type Python back in 3.10.3, excuse me, which is also super awesome.
So again, seeding into that directory, Pyenv is doing the magic here to automatically give
me now 3.9.3.
How is it doing it?
It's no serious magic.
It is explicit.
It has put a Python version dot file in that folder.
And so Pyenv is looking for that as I invoke the Python command.
There's basically a wrapper around all the Python commands to say I'm going to use the
version specified in that Python version, which also makes it easy to now specify across
a project what version of Python you're using.
Although I don't think I would do that with this Python version.
There are better Pyproject.toml files to specify specific Python requirements for your specific
project that we'll talk about later.
OK.
So that's a quick, quick intro to Pyenv and kind of the explicit over implicit.
I can say exactly what versions of Python I want and when I want them.
Pyenv, one of the reasons I recommend it is it has some nice plugins.
If you are using VLIMS right now, which you should be to make sandboxes, Pyenv supports
these out of the box and it's really snappy and easy to use.
If you're using VirtualLemv wrapper, it supports that as well.
Since I've started using Pyenv, I've stopped using VirtualLemv wrapper because the benefit
of VirtualLemv wrapper was it kind of hides that virtual environment sandbox away from
you and I don't really need it here.
So the way you can get these plugins, if you just do brucearch pyenv.
There you go.
Shoot.
Too much.
There'll be the Pyenv recipe, but you also have the pyenv-virtualenv.
Let's go ahead and I'm going to make a pyenv for you real quick.
The virtual environment.
So I'm in project one.
I've set up this 3.9.11, but that's not actually what I want to use.
Technically that is going to be what I consider my base install of the versions of Python.
I don't want to mess those up.
If I do pip freeze right here, it should be empty.
I should have no packages installed right now.
I've got this pristine, clean environment and I will keep it that way.
Instead, I will do pyenv-virtualenv and we'll make another one using 3.9.11.
I'll just call it proj1-env.
Oops, I misspelled it.
It doesn't matter.
Name, we can use it for whatever we want.
But now it still says I'm using 3.9.11.
I need to tell this project that I want to use my specific virtual environment right
here.
So I'll do that pyenv local command again and I will specify proj1 with the misspelled
evin.
And now the prompt on the right-hand side is updated to show that I'm actually using
a sandbox.
If I pip install into this sandbox, for example, like requests, very popular package.
And now if I do pip freeze, you'll see I've got four packages installed.
If I CD up out of the directory and do pip freeze, again, clean, pristine environment.
I'm not polluting my system Python with any packages accidentally.
I'm being very explicit and intentional about what version of Python and what sandbox of
this version of Python.
So for those of you who aren't familiar, that virtual environment is really critical to
keeping your world sandboxed off from the other projects.
And I'll show that here right now.
I've got another project here, project two.
If we go into project two, I've got a requirements file in there.
So if we look at that requirements file, it's going to install requests using an extra
called use sharday on py3.
So I'll do the pyenv.
Actually, I already made a virtual environment for this one just to speed up things.
Call it proj2, backup.
And if I do pip freeze, it should be empty.
Oh, no, I did install it already.
So this is going to have the py3 sharday version of requests already installed into it.
If I go back into project one, well, I've already done that.
So we'll just want to dip these real quick.
Well, I'll just go into project one.
We'll do pip freeze to compare it to the one that's up there right above it.
Like the joys of live demoing, right?
So you'll see there's a difference here that sharday version four is missing from the bottom
one where it was included in the top one up here.
Oops.
Oh, I scrolled too far.
There it is.
This line right here is missing in the bottom one because I've installed them in two different
ways.
I installed the same package in two different ways because I may have two projects that
need to use those kind of subtle differences between having maybe a different version of
requests installed in one versus another because maybe you've not run your full regression
tests against your code with an upgraded version of requests.
So you may be working between two projects where you need to maintain two different versions
of the same package even across those two spots.
And so pipenv plus, I'm sorry, pyenv plus the virtual environment plugin makes this
like just super seamless because you can now CD between the directories.
So you're not activating, deactivating, and forgetting because sometimes the biggest problem
I always have with virtual environments is I would forget to deactivate.
I'd CD into another directory for another project.
I would pip install something and it would end up over in the other virtual environment
and I'm like and then nothing works.
So to solve that problem, Python has a nice environment injection that basically CDs in
and out and lets you do that real quick.
So that is that part of this.
Now if you have simpler needs where maybe you aren't just wanting to go down the whole
pyenv path, since Python 3.3, Python has included bundled in it kind of a simplified version
of virtualenv called venv.
And so if you were to invoke Python with a minus m venv which basically says I want to
run the module venv that's packaged inside of Python.
You can do the same thing with pip.
So if you run Python minus m pip, it will run the packaged version of pip that is in
the Python interpreter you're dealing with directly as opposed to maybe some random pip
that's in your path.
So kind of a surefire way to make sure you're getting a virtual environment for the version
of Python you're currently running is to run minus m venv like that and it will use the
included virtualenv which is kind of a stripped down linear version of the standard virtual
environment package to give you a venv called venv in this case.
Now, some side notes here.
Sometimes you've got tools you want to get installed.
Like you want to use black and you want to use docker compose or HTTPX or all these kind
of cool Python command line tools.
How do you manage those various tools like that?
So I recommend to folks to use pipx.
If you've not checked out pipx, it is super awesome, super easy to use and it will greatly
simplify your life being able to install these kinds of tools.
So let's look real quick here.
I'm going to go to my home directory.
I already have pipx installed.
But for example, if I want to use who's here with HTTP, it's an awesome tool for messing
around with APIs and calling, making get requests and post requests and kind of a replacement
for curl but it does some cooler stuff like it will give you colorized output.
Normally it has a command called HTTP and when you ran it, you would invoke HTTP from
the command line.
The instructions may tell you to pip install HTTP but I'll implore you to install pipx
first and do pipx install HTTP.
And this is going to create in the background for you another little virtual environment
sandboxed away that you don't see, you don't have to deal with.
And then it's going to inject these three, in this case for HTTP, it's going to inject
these three commands into your path automatically.
So now you saw before where I typed in HTTP.
Now if I type HTTP, it's green and I can go ahead and grab a URL maybe.
There we go.
And there you go.
There's obviously a redirect to HTTPS because it's all good websites should be HTTPS.
That one doesn't.
Now you see it's all colorized and pretty.
HTTP is an awesome tool.
But install it into my system Python.
I didn't use sudo to install it.
I didn't even install it using like a user flag which I'll talk about here in a second.
I've installed into its own little environment that is now managed just by pipx.
So tools like you see here I've got black, isort, pipenv, watchdog which has a watch
me do thing.
Cool command line tools like that totally deserve to be installed via pipx and not put
into a virtual environment or into some other kind of non-standard place.
There's a good consistent way to do this.
So that was pipx.
The kind of pipx.
Let's do some damage I just showed you that.
All right.
And I mentioned this just briefly and if you didn't catch it, what about this user scheme?
There is in Python the ability to pip install packages with a dash dash user flag there.
And this allows you to install without using sudo.
So you're following like my number one rule.
Don't install using sudo.
But you're installing into a Python environment or location in your home directory that basically
gives you one version of whatever you just installed.
So if you're using requests 23 and you need request 22 for another project, using this
pip install dash dash user, you know, request sql 22, you know, 0.22, will end up overriding
the already installed version because basically it's just one little sandbox thing.
I find this just again confusing for folks who have never seen it.
It may be an allure or a way to like not use sudo to install a package, but you may end
up with, for example, if I installed HTTP into with the user scheme and then I proceeded
to install another tool that had a conflicting version of a dependency using the user scheme,
I would break my HTTP and no longer have the working script.
So again, not a good place to be installing packages.
Leverage tools like pipx for installing command-link tools because it keeps them all separate.
They all have their own dependencies, no conflicts there.
And when you're using your projects, make sure you're using the virtual environments
from pyamp.
But what about, I know there's so many options out there, right?
This is the mind blowing part about Python.
What makes it so hard, you know, what about Anaconda Python and Conda?
The kind of data science folks would be more familiar with the Conda package manager.
It's like, there's just, again, too many options.
ActiveState Python, pipm, you used to kind of have a tool that was in favor and then
kind of fell out of favor because of performance issues.
It was interesting in the beginning.
ASDF is a very similar tool to pyenv in that it can install multiple versions of a language,
any language actually.
You can use it with Rust or with Ruby or Python.
But it doesn't have the same plug-in environment that the pyenv one does have for doing Python
specific work.
For example, having that virtual element plug-in or the C cache plug-in for speeding up builds.
Poetry is a great tool if you're building libraries.
But as a new person to Python or if you're just trying to get work done and you're not
developing specifically on a library, I wouldn't recommend necessarily starting off there because
there's going to be an extra overhead of all the kind of poetry dance and protocol and
commands and APIs that you would need to use.
PDM, another Python package manager, kind of maybe less popular than say something like
pyenv.
And then pyproject.toml is also another place where you can specify dependencies for your
project.
And some tools like poetry, for example, would use that for understanding what your dependencies
are.
I think there's a lot of promise for using pyproject.toml files.
I think there's a PEP right now that I don't think has been approved.
But look for more to come there around build tools in Python and using that pyproject.toml
file instead of a requirements.txt file.
So, all that said, I just want repeatability and simplicity.
I want this thing to be simple and easy, kind of like Zen of Python.
I want to be a Zen Python master and I want to follow that simple is better than complex
line of the Zen of Python.
One of the tools I'll highly recommend to folks is going to be piptools package.
If you've not installed piptools, it has a piptools compile command built into it that
will allow me to manage my dependencies for my project.
So, if I'm working on a Django project and I got a specific version of Django, specific
version of requests, specific version of this and that, piptools allows me to specify my
main dependencies that I'm using in the project as opposed to every dependency I'm using in
the project.
Who here has had a requirements file where it's just gotten like 200, 300 lines long
and it's got every version penned, but there's always moving dependencies underneath the
covers.
One tool upgrades one dependency, you want to make sure you grab all of its recommended
dependencies.
You also want to make sure you're able to easily grab security fixes, performance fixes,
bug fixes that are coming in very minor versions of these dependencies.
So managing dependencies can be really tricky, especially if you're trying to pin them all.
Maybe everyone doesn't know what I mean when I say pinning dependencies.
If I look at, I've got an example.
Yeah, there we go.
Here's a requirements file that has got all the dependencies for this Python script specified
and it's using a double equals to say whenever you pip install, always grab exactly that
version and exactly that version and exactly this version because any other ones may not
work.
This will work most of the time and we want something that works all the time so we get
that repeatability and scalability, simplicity of being able to install and know that our
six months from now, when I come back to this project, it will run again.
It is a common problem we've all had.
You go update the dependencies, something has broken, maybe a minor dependency happened
or worse yet, you probably heard in the news a lot of the supply chain security issues
that come along with using some of these packages.
You want to make sure you're getting the exact same package you got six months ago.
So pip tool solves this problem.
I won't have full time to necessarily demo all of it but it basically solves this problem
by taking the cryptographic hashes of the various packages and the wheels that are on
PyPy and comparing those against the last time you installed it.
Pip tools allows me to manage instead of saying you see requests right here, 2.25.1.
Request has sub-dependencies which we saw in the previous demo of Charday and Certify
and IDNA.
I don't want to necessarily specify those.
I want to rely on requests to manage what he knows about its dependencies.
So I will only specify that requests is going to say this is my version of requests I want
and requests will specify the other versions but if I want to repeat it, the pip tools
will actually output all the hashes for me into another file where I can get exactly
the same thing over again.
I think with that I am kind of heading toward the end here.
One last thing if you really want really, really repeatable, it's going to be Docker
and pip tools.
Using Docker containers to really solidify and shore up exactly what version of Python
you are using is a great way to make sure you get exactly the same build over again
and you can come back to it a year later and rerun that container without having to worry
about installing things on your system to get things running again.
If you all have questions, I will be at the JetBrains booth in the expo hall right after
this so feel free to come down and pick my brain about setting up your system and building
your awesome killer workstation.
Thank you all for being here.