So before we start, just a small story.
So imagine me as an intern in my first company.
I'm just in the meeting room, and we
are discussing how to build a good back end application.
And database comes into the topic.
And me being an intern, I got all excited.
And I was like, you know what?
Google Spanner, we should use Cockroach TV.
We should use some niche databases that
were really cool at the time.
And that made everyone aware that I
was the intern in the room.
But apart from that, after the meeting,
this person who I like to think of as my mentor
pulled me aside.
And he gave me this advice that stuck around.
So he told me, now whenever you want
to pick a database that you want to use for your project,
think of three reasons why you should not use Postgres.
And if you can give me three solid reasons,
then go ahead and think of another one,
or else just use Postgres.
And that actually confused me a bit.
I was like, I always thought developers
like to play around with toys, cool new tools, the niche new
thing in the market.
We like to use it.
We like to play around with it.
But with databases, I always saw that people
just like to keep it safe.
They always go with the default option.
And that made database kind of mystical for me,
because it's like this black box machine that just works
for almost everything that we want it to do.
And we can just tune it to make it do things.
And we have data engineers, database administrators
who take care of things for us.
So we just have fun with it.
But what made it mystical also made me curious about it.
So I wanted to break down what it all meant.
So why build your own database?
That's the first question.
The fact that it's mystical is not a good enough reason
for sane people.
So it essentially kind of helps break down the abstractions
that make up the database, the black box that it is.
And you can also kind of reason about bad performance
and bugs, which you can face when you're
kind of creating database.
There are actually a lot of concurrency bugs
that happen even in production grade Postgres databases.
But the timing has to be exactly right for you
to face those bugs.
They're really cool, though.
And then you can actually write better queries
if you know how your database is working,
like how it actually kind of fetches the data internally.
You can write good queries that don't take an hour to execute.
And also, it's fun.
So as the Victorian man once said,
what makes a database?
So that's the first question I asked myself
when I went ahead to build the database.
And fair warning, I was an intern during this time.
So I did not have a good idea on how databases were,
you know, what are they made of, what do they even do.
So this was what I had in my mind.
So this is me.
And then I just talked to the database.
And there is a base.
I don't know, is it a base?
And then I consider base to be how you talk to your database.
So it can be like your Python SQL Alchemy engine.
It can be your PG CLI tool.
It can be Table Plus, literally anything.
And then the base kind of talks to the data
that's there internally.
And it kind of returns the results to you.
This is how I kind of imagined the database
to be, which is not actually completely wrong.
But it has a lot of things inside.
And there are a bunch of utilities
that are in the background, a lot of crazy things
which we're going to discuss later.
But this is essentially what I thought it looked like.
First is the base, the part of the database
that you can use to talk to your database, essentially.
And fun fact, the database that I built is a good listener.
So you can talk to it really well.
Cool.
So I don't know, the code might be a little small.
So you should find it in the repo.
If you can see, awesome.
Good eyesight.
So I chose repo as my weapon of choice to talk to the database.
Initially, I thought of sending it pigeons,
but you know, repo worked out well for me.
You can use this really cool Python library
called prompt toolkit that I used
to kind of build a very simple CLI that
can be used as your interface to talk to your database.
So what I'm essentially doing here
is just defining a while true loop
so that my terminal keeps running.
And then I have a session that I start.
Oh, and by the way, I call my database
YITDB because it's a throwaway database, and you call it YIT.
So after we define a session, we have a query executor,
which you pass a SQL query to.
We'll discuss what that is.
And once you run it, it kind of gives you the result.
It kind of gives you the time it took to run it.
It kind of gives you what operation you ran.
And it kind of returns the results if it can.
Or if it faces any error in between the steps,
it's just going to say, I can't do it.
It is an error.
Yeah, so we're going to discuss what exactly
is happening in the classes that are defined here.
But this is the general structure.
So I briefly mentioned SQL.
This is how you talk to your database.
So SQL is your database's second language of choice,
first being love.
So SQL can be used to talk to database.
And there are several dialects of SQL that are present,
like really, really crazy dialects,
so much grammar that's there, which kind of put me to sleep
when I tried to do research on it.
There was so much.
So I decided to keep it really simple.
And I kind of defined, really took parts of the syntax,
kind of defined a grammar for SQL by myself.
So it's no longer a structured query language for me.
The structure is gone.
It's just a query language.
So this is the grammar that I defined for my database.
So you have DDL, DML, DQL, the keywords that you hear.
So they mean data manipulation language,
data definition language, and data query language.
And you also have wildcards that you can use in your SQL query.
So my grammar is very simple.
So I can create a table, delete a table, or a database.
And I can also perform select and insert.
I cannot do altars.
I have my wildcard, which is going to be a star.
And I have my query languages.
So I can use from, where, and limit.
For the purposes of this talk, I'm
not going to go into the details of the implementation
of group buys and joins.
But if you want to talk about it, find me later.
I would love to discuss that with you.
Cool.
So this is how the query executor looks like internally.
So what it does is, so if you know how programming languages
work, this is similar to how they work as well,
how they take in your code, which is in English,
and interpret what they mean and execute.
It's very similar.
The query executor takes my query in.
It takes a simple SQL query.
And SQL queries actually make a lot of sense.
When you read them as a person who is not
accustomed with the whole database thing,
if you just show them a simple SQL query,
they know how it works.
So you have a SQL parser.
You have a SQL planner.
And you have your executor.
So SQL parser takes a SQL query and splits them into tokens.
SQL planner creates a tree out of that query.
And then you kind of create a tree.
So we're going to discuss what exactly those mean.
Cool.
So first, I write a query.
I write a simple select query.
So if you cannot read the query, it's
a select star from customer where name is JoJo.
So once I write the query, the query gets parsed.
And by parsed, I mean the database kind of
figures out that my DML is select, my wildcard is star,
I have from is my DQL, my customer
is the table name or the table reference,
I have where clause, which uses an equal operator.
And I have these objects that I have to compare.
A column reference, which is name, and the object is JoJo.
Cool.
So using this token, it generates
an abstract syntax tree, which kind of looks
like this for this query, which is very simple.
So if you want to look at query plans,
you can also perform explain on your queries
in databases like Postgres, where you can actually
visualize this tree for yourself for any query that you write.
And for this simple query, it's just a select star from.
You have customer reference, and you have a where clause,
and you have this operation that's
running on a column name and a constant.
So once I have a plan, I know exactly what to do,
because there is an order defined by SQL standard,
like how I have to kind of execute a query.
So I just go ahead and run it.
But you know the query that I wrote is really bad.
You cannot just select star all the data,
because you don't know the amount of data
that you're querying.
And when you query a lot of data,
you're going to face some problems.
So now our base part is kind of sorted.
We can talk to a database.
Now we get to the fun part, the data part,
where we're going to actually build the data out.
So first of all, I decided, you know what?
I'm going to keep it simple, and I'm going to write all my data
into memory.
So what I've defined here is a simple database class
that kind of creates a new hash map or a dictionary
in Python words for every single table.
And what I mean by an insert is just inserting a new key
and a record for a particular ID for a table.
So it's just a dictionary insert, a dictionary get,
and a delete is just a dictionary pop.
And this kind of worked for me.
It's crazy how easy it is, but it works.
And I can just define my database.
I could define a table, which is test.
I can insert name Barry, who is 35.
And I can just be like, you know what?
Select name and select age from the test table,
and it's giving me the results.
And I can also delete age.
And when I have to select, it's going
to give me a key error, which means there's no age,
and Barry's immortal.
But one thing is missing, which is persistence,
because when my database closes or if I close my session,
everything's gone.
So I need some kind of persistence.
So to do that, you always remember to flush,
which I do by flushing it to the disk.
So for every insert that happens to the dictionary,
I just write it to a file.
And deletes are kind of a special append operation.
I'm going to insert something called tombstones.
So for tombstone, I just use the tombstone emoji
in my database, which is a bad way because it
takes a lot of space.
But I want to have fun.
So append-only logs are nuts, because it's
so simple and sequential.
Writes on disk are performant, super fast.
It's one of the best operations you can do in the disk to a file.
I'm really happy about that.
But you have this issue when you move in from in-memory to disk,
because when you want to select something,
you have to go through every single key in your disk, which
gives you an O of n worst-case select complexity, which
is bad.
And you also have the issue of when you flush to a disk,
what if something happens?
You just flush partial records, or where did it go?
And also, you keep appending to a log file,
which can get really big.
And you run out of disk space, right?
That's also a problem.
So we're going to solve these issues one by one.
Good.
So we're going to bring back the in-memory concept, which
is like a cache which we're going to put on a disk.
So what it's going to have is contain where exactly
the files are present in the disk.
And what I call cache and in-memory dictionary
is what database calls indexes.
It's a really cool concept where databases kind of have
a secondary structure on top of your actual data,
where it kind of maintains where the exact data is located
in the disk or somewhere else, depending on the database.
And we can use that to quickly look up where my data is
and then directly just go there, rather than just
looking at the whole data, which can be really big.
So we're going to start really simple
and bring back our in-memory dictionary, which
is going to be hash indexes.
So by hash index, I just implement an in-memory mapping
of every key to the byte offset location.
So for example, I have written to my file a name called John
and a name called Don.
And the ID is like 1 and 2.
And the offset location is like 0, 9, 18.
And it just goes in multiples of 9,
because that's the size I'm giving the table to write.
This kind of is defined when I create the table.
I kind of define what size I'm going
to occupy for every record.
And if I go more than that, it's going to be like, you know what?
So this is bigger.
So if I want to look up, for example, the key 2
or the name Don, I just go to the offset 9,
which I can look up directly from the hash index.
So it's like, oh, I want to look it up.
And you just go and read it from the disk.
I mean, seek it from the file in the disk.
So it's super fast, right?
And cool.
This is the implementation.
The code can be really bad.
So you can refer to the repo.
So what I'm essentially doing here is what I just said.
So we kind of define the size for the record that we have,
and also the primary key.
And we just use the size to kind of exactly know the offset
in which the data is located.
So we just perform an insert.
And when we do an insert, we do actually two inserts.
So we actually insert to the disk
and also insert to the index.
We kind of tell the index where exactly my start
and end offsets are and where exactly my data is,
so that it can quickly look it up.
And when I do a get, I just kind of use those
to get the data out.
And when I do a delete, I just kind of look for that index.
And if it's like a tombstone, I just
be like, you know what?
The data doesn't exist anymore.
So we have actually solved the problem of speed,
because now we have indexes and data is super fast.
But we still have the problem of running out of disk.
So we're going to solve that problem
by breaking our logs into segments, which
is going to be very easy, because we're
going to be defining fixed size for every segment.
So if you have two segments where we have these append-only
logs, you're going to have repetition of keys that happen.
Because for every insert, you're going to perform an append.
And a key can have thousands of inserts that happen.
And you just want the latest insert
that happens for a key.
You don't care about what happened like 10 inserts
before.
So what you do is you perform this operation called
compaction that happens in the background
that you don't have to care about.
So what compaction does is it takes these older
blocks of segments that are there for the data
and kind of combine them into a newer segment.
And it creates a new segment.
It doesn't replace anything.
It just takes the older segments,
creates segments, creates a new segment,
and then just updates the mapping.
So when a lookup happens, the database
just looks up the newer segments.
And this is actually quite optimal
because this is happening in the background.
And merge operations are quite efficient
when you perform them on files and disk.
And then you have now smaller segments
that keep incrementally getting smaller
as you keep writing data.
So you don't have to worry about ever running out of disk size
if you have these operations running.
And when I say the segments get deleted,
we don't actually delete them.
We just say mark them for deletes.
And what happens is there is an operation
that happens in our database in the background, which
I like to call vacuum, which is a really cool name
for a process, which does exactly what it says.
It kind of cleans up all these segments
that are marked for deletes.
Cool.
So we solved both the problems.
We have speed, and we are not going to run out of disk space.
So we have super fast lookups that happen through indexes.
We have app-and-only writes that happen through logs.
Both of them are awesome.
Compaction happening in the background.
We are not running out of disk space.
And because of the presence of both these structures,
we have crash recovery.
Because whenever a database crashes,
we can generate the state of our index directly from our data.
And we also have concurrency, because you just
have one writer in your app-and-only logs.
And the tree can have multiple writer threads that
can run simultaneously.
So we have concurrency too.
But there is an issue with our hash indexes,
which is if you have a lot of keys in your hash index,
you can no longer have it in memory.
So it kind of fits well when you have less number of keys.
But more keys means more memory, and you're going to fail.
And you also have really bad performance for range queries.
If you want to look up data from index ID1 to ID100,
you have to look them up individually,
which is like, I don't want to do that.
That's slow.
Cool.
So we're going to solve this by introducing
a very simple concept, which is sorting.
And interviews will be happy that we're using sorting here.
So what we're going to do is rather than just storing it
in an app-and-only format sequentially,
we're going to make sure that what we write to the disk
is sorted so that we're not going to look up a range key.
We just know what range it is in.
And we don't also have to store an in-memory mapping
of every key.
We can just have a key that's kind of like we can just
have a sparse representation of the key
so that if there is any key between the two keys,
we know exactly where it is because it's sorted right.
So we can just quickly look it up.
So we don't also have a huge index file
that's crunching our disk.
So an example of an in-memory balance tree
that we can use to replace our hash index
is going to be a red-black tree.
We also have a lot of other sorted balance trees
that you can use, but I just picked this.
So red-black tree can, like I'm not
going to explain how the data structure works
because there are other Indians on the internet that do that.
So red-black trees essentially just
have really simple rules that it follows.
So you can just have a black node in the root or the leaf.
And red cannot have red children or parents.
So these are these two rules that it follows.
And then when you make an insert or a delete,
we just make sure to update your node
so that the rules still apply.
And when you do that, your tree is
going to be as balanced as it can,
and it's going to have a log-in complexity, which
is really cool.
So now, again, there is no persistence
because we're having this red-black tree in memory.
So we're going to have to write our tree to a disk.
So to do that, we're going to introduce what's
being the standard in the industry since the 1970s,
which is like a crazy time for an algorithm or a software
to live on.
And that is B-trees.
So in B-trees, we just take out these nodes
that we had in red-black trees, and we just
make them into pages.
And pages kind of work well with our OS
because the data in the disk is also
arranged in the form of pages.
So it kind of works.
So what we do is if we have this is also from DDI, by the way.
So we just have a page which has the keys
that we want in a sorted order, and it
has a reference to the keys that kind of move around
like a tree.
So for example, we have 100 to 500,
and there is a reference for keys
that lie between 100 and 200, which goes down.
And the key is less than 100.
There's another reference that goes down.
So if you want to look up, for example, key 251,
we just go by the third reference,
and then we know 250 is there.
It's between 250 and 270.
We just go down, and we find it.
So we have a fixed size for these segments,
and in certain update operations kind of
happen depending on the file size.
And yeah, this kind of just works.
So how do you perform operations on this B-Tree?
Again, I'm not going to completely go
into the details of insertion and deletion on a tree.
Again, there are a lot of videos for you to check it out,
or on the internet, it's all there.
So in general, if you just need a key,
you just check if there is a space in the segment,
because segments are fixed size, right?
So you must have space to insert.
If you have space, you insert.
If you don't have space, you split the key.
That's it.
And with deletions, it's a bit more complex.
It depends on if you want to delete what's in the leaf
or what's internal.
And if it's leaf, it depends on the number of keys.
If it's internal, it depends on the keys,
it depends on the children.
So essentially, it's like you either do the operation,
or you split the tree, change it around,
and then do the operation.
And again, B-trees have existed for a long time,
and it's a standard implementation
in almost every relational database.
And even non-relational databases use it as an index.
And it has, again, overlogging complexity
for performing these operations and maintains
the tree in a balanced way.
So B-trees are old, right?
But we're going to have a lot of improvements that
can happen on top of B-trees.
So one thing that we can do is copy and write,
which is rather than updating a page in a tree,
we're just going to create a new page
and then reference the new page rather than updating
the existing page.
And what we get out of this is something super cool,
which is really good concurrency.
Because for example, if someone is running a query at 8 AM,
and they look at the tree state at 8 AM,
they look at page at 8 AM, and after 8 AM,
there are several updates that happen to that tree, right?
So the references keep changing.
But since it's copy and write, there
are going to be new pages that kind of reference
newer queries.
So the query that you run at 8 o'clock,
it's going to return the result of the database at 8 o'clock.
It's not going to change as time moves,
even if your query takes a long time to run.
And this happens with every query that
runs at every point in time.
So we call this snapshot isolation.
And since we have this, we can actually,
so this is what databases call MVCC,
or Multi-Version Concurrency Control,
where you can have several versions of a single data
so that you have snapshot isolation in your database.
There is also the concept of wall logs,
where you just have app-only logs of B-tree operations
so that you can regenerate your B-tree if database crashes.
And you also have latches and latches.
So if a write happens, you can just lock a tree,
saying that there is a write happening so that concurrent
reads don't read dirty data.
Cool.
So just a quick plug.
EuroPython is another awesome conference
that is happening in 11th and 17th of July in Dublin, Ireland.
It's opening also remote.
And the program is going to be out in the next week-ish.
There is also a really amazing stuff called Maker Summit.
We have transcode.
Awesome stuff happening, so just check it out.
And thank you so much for coming.
I'm going to wrap this talk up.
Yeah.
Thank you so much for coming.
I'm going to wrap this talk up.
Yeah.