Good morning, everybody.
Thank you so much for being able to join us this morning.
We have one more talk and then glorious lunch.
I know you're all looking forward to it, but hang tight because this promises to be
really, really cool.
So, today we are going to hear from Henry Schreiner, building a binary extension.
Henry Schreiner is a computational physicist slash research software engineer in high energy
physics at Princeton University.
He specializes in the interface between high performance compiled codes and interactive
computation in Python, in software distribution, and in interface design.
He's previously worked on computational cosmic ray tomography for archaeology and high performance
GPU model fitting.
He's currently a member of the IRIS HEP project, developing tools for the next era of the Large
Hadron Collider, LHC.
Ladies and gentlemen, Henry Schreiner.
Thank you.
So I'm Henry Schreiner, and I'm working with the IRIS HEP project, which is basically
trying to build a set of Python tools to replace and augment the existing C++ that we've been
using in energy physics since the mid-90s.
We actually have a C++ interpreter, if you'd – you probably don't want to know that.
So we've been building up these tools, and one of the things that was really important
with this is we have very high performance requirements in certain areas.
We have the largest academic data set in the world, for example.
And so with this, it becomes really, really important to be able to do some of the things
you'll be seeing today.
So I'm going to start with a question.
Is Python fast?
So of course, this is a completely ambiguous question.
Good way to start.
But let's just take an example here.
This is an article that came out fairly recently.
Well, within the last two years.
And they had this problem where they're projecting a billion cells.
And this had a – they had this Fortran code, 1,500 lines of Fortran code, that did this
in six hours and 30 minutes.
And finally, they decided to rewrite this in Python.
And when they did that, it took four minutes.
And the reason for this was really they had this high-level language.
They had libraries that they could access.
It allowed them to easily explore different algorithms.
If you have a billion cells, you're doing projections.
You really want to use something like a KD tree.
There's one in SciPy, so they just use that.
And so the key behind this is that you have a library.
And in that library, you have compiled code that does the hard work for you, and you're
still able to stay in Python.
So Python has really great performance, as long as you can find a library that has your
desired algorithm in it, like NumPy or Pandas or something like that.
But what do you do if you don't?
What do you do if you have some sort of algorithm that's not already coded up somewhere?
How do you write that yourself?
And that's what we'll be looking at.
So the first possible solution to this would be you could just dump Python.
This is the Twitter and random article on the internet solution.
Maybe you're enticed by these other languages.
Is anybody enticed by C?
But they offer native performance.
Well, Python, though, is really easy to learn.
It's very quick to write.
And it has this massive ecosystem.
I would say each of these three things are equally important and incredibly important.
So you'll see, and this is where we'll get with the final solution, which you might have
already guessed that by the title of the talk, is you can split the driver code.
And that's the stuff that usually takes the most time to work on.
And that's what you're manipulating and working with.
That can still be in Python.
And then you can just move the performance critical code to something else and work together.
Before we go on, though, there's a few other possible solutions.
One is Numba.
This is a just-in-time compiler for Python.
This is just as fast or faster than any other solution you can come up with most of the
time.
But it does have some downsides.
You are going to have to do the just-in-time compiling on the device.
It's a somewhat heavy dependency.
There's plus sides and downsides.
But if you just want to make it faster, this might be the first thing to try.
This would be the first thing I would try.
Another solution is you can just make Python itself faster.
There's a variety of different packages and projects that do this.
You have PyPy, of course, for quite a while.
Pyjama is a bit newer one.
And then there's even forks of CPython to try to make it faster.
And CPython itself is actually interested in getting faster now, too.
These sorts of things are in the, say, 5x performance range.
Maybe get five times faster, at least for CPython.
But they don't really make heavy numeric code faster because that already sits in a
compiled language.
It doesn't need to be made faster.
You may need more algorithms, things like that.
And of course, the solution we'll be looking at today is this one.
You can precompile.
So you can write code using the CPython API.
Or you can have maybe code sitting in an interface somewhere.
And then that can be compiled into an extension.
And you can then distribute that.
And it turns out that a lot of things you use every day are actually, this is actually
done for those things.
And this works very, very well.
So first let's go into a little bit of what a binary extension is.
If you're using Python now, you probably think in terms of you have some code you're
writing.
And then you're using libraries.
And if you were to write your own library, you'd probably start with this first one,
this side on the left here.
You'd put all your library code in Python.
Well, that code in the library can also be compiled code.
It can be a binary extension.
And the first one is really easy.
But the next one traditionally has been viewed as complex.
The examples tended to be rather poor, tended to be things that a really large library like
NumPy would do.
And there are lots of details in building these and distributing them that, for example,
you need to compile on every different platform you support, that sort of thing.
But you can achieve really high performance.
And one of my goals in this talk will be to show you that this is actually not that hard
to do.
You can do this yourself.
And the tooling around this and all that has become very, very good.
And it's really not as complex or as hard as it used to be.
So here's an example of wheels.
So I start my example with wheels for showing you something that's not a wheel.
That's an S-disk.
And that thing has a setup.py or a pyproject.toml or some collection of tools that allow a
backend to build that.
So that's where your source code sits.
Then you have this.
This is a pure Python wheel.
This is something usually that just contains Python.
You'll see the name there.
It has the implementation API and platform.
That's just Py3, none, any.
And this doesn't have compiled extensions.
And then you have wheels that look like this.
These are the ones that have binaries in them.
And you see you have the implementation, the API.
Those have actually been the same most of the time in modern Python.
And then you have a platform, which is your operating system and your architecture.
And pip will actually do the smart thing.
It'll pick the most specific one.
So in mypy's case, they actually have a pure Python wheel.
And they compile.
So that way, if you're not on one of these systems, it will fall back.
But most of you will probably be on one of those systems.
There's only a few cases where you end up falling back.
So things like NumPy are shipped.
There's no pure Python version of NumPy.
And they still ship quite well with this.
And we'll be looking at how to make this third one today.
So I've already gone over one of the two main reasons to compile.
You can get performance.
It's also useful for code reuse.
There's already great libraries out in these other languages.
You can just use those in your compiled extensions.
You don't have to rewrite them.
Or maybe you want to write something that works in both languages.
So this is just a collection of some different libraries that ship binary wheels,
things like PyTorch and mypy, pandas, NumPy.
And you'll see non-scientific and numeric things in there as well.
You see UV loop and twisted web sockets.
So we'll start this talk also with a few disclaimers.
This will be a biased talk.
I'll be showing you things I work on.
But I like those projects enough to join them.
And those are the things I know the most about.
And we'll also be looking at good practices.
Maybe there'll be best practices.
But this is definitely not the only way you do things.
You might be now saying to me, well, but it's hard.
Compiling code is hard.
It requires that you do a lot more than just shipping a Python extension.
That's true.
But let's divide this problem up into three stages.
You've already sort of seen them.
First, you have the actual writing of whatever you're interested in.
So that could be something that's written in C++.
It could be something that is in something, let's say, like MyPyC.
So you write something that looks like Python and you still want to compile it.
And then once you have something you want to compile, then notice I'm skipping
things like here, because those don't fall into this area.
And then you have a build system.
This is something that takes that code and produces the binaries.
Traditionally, this has been set up tools and distutils.
But this is starting to become a more interesting space and
a little less tied to just that one specific view.
You'll see that again in a minute.
And then you need a tool to do the wheel building.
Because once you have these things, you need to produce wheels that are
redistributable that can go out to all the different platforms.
And we'll be focusing primarily on this path through here.
Of course, there's lots of different paths we could take, but
this is the one I'll be focusing on today.
But I like this because it's a mix and match.
You may find some other binding tool or coding tool better for you, but
you might still want to build wheels, that sort of thing.
Okay, so starting with this bindings and codings,
there's sort of two choices here.
You can access existing compiled code.
So some of the tools sort of focus on that.
How do you get C++ or Go or Rust or something out?
And there's also from scratch code, which is code you want to write and
you want to make it faster.
You're not trying to reuse an existing algorithm.
And you probably want something that looks like Python.
So Cython, MyPyC, things like that tend to be in this category.
And you might even be able to make your extension optional a bit easier with
this one, because maybe it's even the same code.
So starting with this idea of interfacing the existing library,
where you're not actually writing the binding.
You have this side.
That's how you would load a library from C types.
And then you have to build that shared object library somewhere.
And you have to do all of the work yourself.
And then Python also provides,
C Python provides this way to write your own extensions.
And that would be writing this.
Most of the time you probably should not be writing this by hand, but
I'm just sort of illustrating what you would need,
what all these binding tools are actually doing behind the scenes.
They're writing stuff that looks like this.
And there's only sort of two important things here.
And it's this, the fact that you have this name,
that's dependent on the name of your module.
And that's how it knows to look up what it has, and then you list what you have.
Staying on the C interface side,
let's just briefly mention a couple options there.
C types is built in.
It's very simple, but you're really, it's up to you to get everything right yourself.
So it's probably a good idea to try to wrap this in something so
that you have some sort of nice interface for your users.
And because it's not going to protect you if you do anything wrong.
This is a good way to get seg faults in C Python, if you make a mistake here.
And CFFI is a tool heavily for that, I think came out of the PyPy there.
They built sort of this tool that reads in the C headers.
It's a library you get on PyPy, PyPI, you know how to do that.
And you can generate some of this automatically and get some extra safety there.
Going back to the sort of traditional ways to do this,
Numba actually also has the ability, besides being a JET,
I remember I said it would not be in this area, but
it also has an ahead of time compile, which looks like this.
Where you can take a little function, you can put an export on the out and
you have to tell it what the module name is.
Remember it has to get that module name in order to produce a extension,
because that's part of the interface.
And you could compile it, they have this extension for
distutils that you can just stick in there.
And then you could actually just run this and compile this ahead of time,
ship it as a wheel.
It would not require Numba.
This is very limited, but it's an option.
And I've seen it used at least once in a real situation.
Another option is mypyc.
So this really piggybacks on top of modern Python typing.
So for example, you see this on the left, you see a little piece of code.
It has type hints.
It's valid Python.
I can run this with Python.
You see Python fib.py.
Or I can compile it with mypyc.
And then I can run it and it'll be ten times faster,
as it's actually compiling the function in the middle.
For comparison, if you did this with the JET, this would be 35 times faster.
You can't do it with the head of time compile because recursive is not
supported in that head of time compile that you saw.
Another popular option is fast not quite Python, Python.
And that's Cython.
This has been around for a very long time.
It's a very good tool for doing this.
You can see some code over on the right.
This is not probably what you are used to seeing with the Cython code, but
this is actually valid Python and Cython code.
There is an interface to do that.
There is also sort of this weird hybrid between C and Python that they provide.
So it also has a custom language.
That's what you see a bit more often.
And there's the code for writing it at the bottom.
And that's nine times faster.
So it's a little bit slower than the mypyc example for this little piece.
And Cython does have some downsides.
It can actually bind C and C++, but it wasn't really built for that.
It will be very verbose if you try to do that.
And it's got a few caveats and drawbacks.
But it's really good.
It was really designed sort of to allow you to write Python and
then make it much faster and compile it.
And it works well for that.
And then PyBind 11 is a header only pure C++ interface.
And just to unpack that a bit,
it means that it's really trivial to add it to a C++ project.
There are no special build requirements.
It's just C++ 11 or newer.
And there's no precompile phase.
You don't have to Cythonize or use one of these other sort of tools to prepare it.
It's just straight C++.
And you can kind of think of it as if it was a C++ API for Python itself.
It was really designed just to do the binding.
It was not designed to do these other things.
So here's a little example of what it looks like to use PyBind 11.
You include it.
You have your C or C++ code that you're interested in binding.
And then you create a module.
Remember, it has to get the name of that module somehow.
So this is how you're telling it what the name of the module is so
it can generate the correct entry point.
And then you just take your, the M is the module object in PyBind 11.
And you just can define an add.
And it will actually infer the signature and
things like that from the thing that you pass in.
Okay, and you can actually compile this yourself if you want.
And this would just work as is.
There's lots of great features of PyBind 11.
I list a few of them here.
I won't go into them in extensive detail, but it's quite powerful.
And it does, even supports WebAssembly with PyDyde now.
And it has a variety of different things that it does.
There is one more I want to go into before we sort of dive in a little bit deeper.
And there is a sort of sequel to PyBind 11 called Nanobind,
written by the same author.
And this is C++ 17 only and it's Python 3.8 only.
It's built on top of the FastCall API.
Very similar API to PyBind 11, intentionally meant to be more limited.
And some of these ideas are being backported to PyBind 11 as well.
And I have some plots here that show that it is much quicker to compile.
It was sort of designed with compilation time in mind,
because header only C++ libraries are really slow to compile.
The binaries are smaller.
Do keep in mind, this is for a very basic example, basically like a class and
a function.
So if your binary size is dominated by your binding tool,
then you're probably not compiling very much.
But smaller binary size, and the runtime performance is faster,
say if you're looping over something.
PyBind 11's a bit slow, because it has a overload dispatch mechanism built in.
Which is very powerful, and you shouldn't be looping over and
calling a function over and over and over in Python probably.
You should try to find some way to wrap the entire thing.
So this is an exciting new project, it's only a few months old now, I think.
So we're gonna dive into an example project.
I'm gonna show you every single line of code you need to create
a compiled extension for all platforms, everything.
I'll have a reasonable amount of code.
The sort of point of this is to show you how much code and
maybe point out a few things.
I'm not gonna walk through every single line.
And I'm gonna try to do something that's not completely trivial.
I'm going to try to take CLI11, which is a command line parser library.
My favorite command line parser library.
I also wrote it, so might be why.
But Microsoft terminal uses it, so.
So we're going to make a little wrapped version of this from Python.
This is not necessarily a good idea, but it's a library I happen to know.
It's a good idea to know the library you're trying to wrap so
you know how it works, so you know how to expose it.
And we're just gonna do sort of this minimal bit here.
So we wanna be able to create an app, we wanna add a flag.
We wanna be able to check and see if that flag exists.
And we want to make sure that sort of basic niceties are there.
So we wanna make sure that we can print the app and
that something nice will print out and that we get a keyer or something that
depends, or will check as a keyer out if we make a mistake.
So this is the entire binding code.
We're going to import PyBind11, and
it also has some wrappers for the standard library things.
And a little bit of setup there.
Here we're creating a new exception.
That exception is going to be, it's gonna come from a keyer.
It'll make a new rmodule.option not found for us.
And then that will automatically wrap the exception, so
we don't need to bother with it down here.
We could, we could throw a py colon colon keyer if we wanted to.
But this is more declarative, which is nice.
And then we create our app, and then in the app we're going to define a few methods.
And so we're defining each one.
Notice we even have some Dunder methods there.
We define get item and stir.
And then the thing on the other side can just be a lambda function.
Sometimes, it's like there in the middle you see that overload cast.
There it's actually wrapped, it's binding to the, to the function itself.
And it's overloaded, so you have to pick which one.
Or you can just use a lambda function in C++, just throw that in there.
And let the compiler figure out which overloaded one you're, you're after.
Or you can do, you know, more work if you want.
So it's, it's really quite nice to be able to just use the,
the lambda functions there.
And that's the binding code.
Okay.
I said I'd show you every line of code, so there's the init.py.
And also tests.
You should always test anything, so let's at least write some tests.
So this is basically the same thing I just showed you, but in, in test form.
Okay?
All right, we're gonna leave that for a minute.
When you go back to the yellow slides, we'll be back in, back in our example.
Let's talk about build systems.
So there are some great examples of pure Python build systems
that are now using pep621.
Things like flit and hatch and, and, and others, including actually setup tools now.
But building binary, your binaries, your choices are somewhat limited.
So setup, setup tools and disutils has a lot of, of drawbacks.
It doesn't, it is capable of building a file from, from C, C or C++.
But it really is, it wasn't extended and, and doesn't add a lot of things.
It's just sort of basic things that most build systems would have, like multi-threaded
builds or partial rebuilds and features of your compiler and just all these things
that are built into tools like CMake and Mason and stuff.
You can't even tell at what C++ standard you want to target.
It does actually have native Cython support though.
Setup tools does.
So this then has been extended by a lot of different packages.
So mypyc extends this.
numpy disutils.
There's lots of examples of things that then write sort of extensions and work with
this even though it's, you're kind of delving into the internals quite a bit.
And then there are a few from scratch.
I don't think, actually, in, in, in scons, I'm not sure if that fully counts because
that's, that's also using at least a little bit of disutils.
I've saw, I saw disutils showing up inside its, its code base.
But I do want to point it out just because it was one of the earliest adopters of
5.17 that supported compiled builds.
But Masonpy is out now and Motrin is one for, for Rust.
So we're starting to see some of those.
There's also Cykit build, which is sort of what we'll focus on today.
Right now, unfortunately, it just wraps setup tools.
But there is a planned move, and I'll talk a little bit about the plans,
to try to get it over into this sort of, onto that side of the screen.
PyBind11 actually has this nice little extension as well for setup tools.
So you can just grab this set of helpers and then you can add the,
or do a PyBind11 extension.
You can tell it what C++ standard you want and just go with that.
If you have something that's simple, you can do that.
So Cykit build is a tool from the makers of CMake to allow you to use CMake from
Python.
And this started back in 2014.
It was announced at SciPy.
It was renamed, it was originally PyCmake, and then it was renamed a bit later.
And two of our most popular packages are the CMake package for Pythons.
If you do pip install CMake, you get CMake for
pretty much all the binary in all these different areas.
It has some really nice tooling.
I helped sort of update some of that.
And you can do the same thing with Ninja.
You can pip install Ninja as well.
And that comes from the Cykit build project.
And this is really exciting because it would allow you to use a very powerful
existing build system, the most popular C++, C, Cuda, etc.
build system directly from Python.
It has a couple new maintainers that joined in the last six months or so.
And it's definitely an exciting example there.
And just also, if you need a refresher on CMake,
I wrote a book on CMake, so you can go check that out.
Years before this.
Okay, as long as you use modern CMake, it's actually quite nice, and
you'll see that.
So there are some plans.
The idea is that we'll try to develop a Cykit build core that will be a PEP 517
builder, avoiding setup tools and distutils.
That will give us, hopefully we can sort of give a compatibility layer,
so the existing users will still work.
We'll also have a way to do a direct build.
And then hopefully a proper setup tools extension,
because currently that's still sort of how you put these things together.
But there might actually be some generalization that's happening in the,
we're gonna talk about this a bit in the packaging summit later.
So it might be nice if we could sort of generalize and
not write an extension for every single system out there like HatchPoetry, etc.
And then also we need an extension discovery mechanism.
We might be working with CMake itself to do this.
Cuz it would be really nice if we could just stick this in our Python requires.
Say I want pi by 11, and then just immediately find it.
Right now you have to do a little bit more work to do that.
And you'll see in the next page that I just avoid this entirely.
In the example we'll be showing.
And you can read more about that proposal there.
All right, so going back to our project.
This is our CMake list.
This is the whole thing.
We're actually just grabbing both pi by 11 and CLI 11 from GitHub.
Because that way we don't have to deal with the fact that we don't have a nice
way to grab where pi by 11 is.
And we have to do this with CLI 11 anyway cuz it's not a Python package.
So we're just grabbing those.
Then we add a module.
This is added by pi by 11.
We link them.
We tell it we need C++ 14 cuz we used one C++ 14 feature.
And then there's install.
And that's the CMake list.
Right now you have to write this setup.py as well.
And this is what I mentioned about the wrapper for the regular setup.
And we have to stick this in.
Some of this does actually have to be inside the setup.py and
can't be pulled out to setup.config.
Not all of it, but some of it does.
Okay, so those are really almost the entire build system.
The only remaining thing is we need to also request scikit build and
our build system requires.
Okay, and we'll actually fill out some more of the PyProject.toml.
We're not done with that yet, but we'll leave it there for now.
The next thing we need to do is to redistribute.
So we need to build wheels.
So you could distribute on conda-forge.
I'm not gonna go into that in detail just because it's really mostly automated.
You just have to go out and write a recipe and their CI will build that for you.
And a lot of the stuff that we do, we really wanna make sure we distribute on both.
But we'll be focusing on PyPI.
And in there we have a variety of different things that we have to deal with.
So on Linux, we need to build inside of a controlled Docker image to make sure that
we're not using something that's not allowed in the mini Linux specification.
We don't wanna pull something in or
use the version of glibc that's too new or something like that.
So there's mini Linux and musilinux images.
And there's also multiple architectures for all of these.
And you really should be running audit wheel afterwards to make sure that this
is packaged up into a nice mini Linux wheel.
Mac OS, you now have to worry about the target version.
You have to pick what version you target.
It's a really nice feature of Mac, but you also have to think about it.
And you also need to make sure your Python was compiled with whatever that target was.
So you really wanna use the python.org Python.
You don't wanna grab the CI or whatever,
cuz that was probably targeting the thing it built on,
which was probably macOS 10.15 or something like that.
But you really wanna use the 10.9, one that targets 10.9 from python.org,
so that you have your choice of what you wanna target.
And then you have to worry about cross compiling for universal.
And there's a separate tool there.
Same thing again for Windows.
Windows is actually the easiest of these,
because you can pretty much grab Python from anywhere and it'll work.
Please make sure you still distribute 32-bit,
cuz you still see some 32-bit Pythons floating around.
And even laptop, I have one.
And then there's beginning to be ARM support on Windows as well.
And then there's also, there's beginning to be,
there's a very, fairly young tool called the Velwheel that's,
that's appearing here that also helps you sort of package and
make sure anything that you use is bundled into your wheel for you.
So I wanna go straight into CI Build Wheel.
This is a tool to do this, all of this for you.
It supports all the major CI providers and it runs locally.
It ran locally for Linux for a long time, but
it actually supports Windows and Mac OS locally now too.
And this tool has really, has really taken off in the last couple years.
I joined it I think in 2020.
And then made a push to get this into the PyPA, it joined.
And we have over, I think we have at least 600 users now,
which include almost everything you saw on that first slide.
Like MyPy and NumPy has just started, has just moved to it.
And so this supports sort of all the different possible wheels that you're
likely to want.
So you can target any version of Mac OS.
You can do Apple Silicon for all the Python versions that support it,
which is 3.8 and newer.
All the variants of MiniLimits, including the ones that you might have to emulate,
or some CI providers have native runners.
Musa Linux was added fairly recently.
PyPy supported.
And this will also go through, do the repair step I showed you.
It will test your wheels if you tell it what command you need to test it.
It'll install it in a brand new environment and
make sure that your wheel actually does what it says it does and
passes your tests pulled directly from the wheel you built.
And the defaults are all pinned.
You can't unpin those, but they're all pinned and updated regularly.
And then there's some new features that have come out recently.
Right after we joined the PyPy, we had CI build wheel two.
That included our PyProject.toml support,
which you'll be seeing in a minute, which I'm quite happy about.
And then over the last few months, we've been adding even more things,
like the overrides, which is powerful, but I won't be showing you today.
And as I mentioned, the local runs.
And experimental Windows arm support,
and we don't have any runners for that yet, in CI, that is.
And in 2.5, which was released this morning,
we also have a support for the stable ABI.
So you can do a limited API, stable ABI build.
And it will build the first wheel and then just test all the rest and
not try to build it again, because it's already built.
And you can also build directly from an S-Dist.
You can just grab an S-Dist off PyPI and then run CI build wheel on it, and
you can produce your wheels.
And we are supporting TomaLib now.
A few tips, this is how you'd run it locally.
When you do it locally, you just have to, and I'm just using PIPX run there, but
any way you like to run it, I would recommend that way.
You just tell it what platform you want to target.
That uses Docker for Linux, so that works on your Mac or Windows or
whatever, wherever you are, as long as you can run Docker.
You can target Linux.
But you always have to tell it the platform, and
that way it knows that you intentionally are trying to build wheels,
cuz it may take a while.
And then this is a really good tip for keeping it up to date.
We do provide an action, and this will keep your action up to date.
All right, so going back to our PyProject.toml,
I can now finish showing it to you.
Here we tell CI build wheel what command to run for testing.
That will turn on the testing feature.
And then we also tell it that I need to install with the bracket test when I
install the wheel, cuz that's where I put the dependencies.
And then this is how you would do this for adding Apple Silicon.
You have to pick for Apple Silicon if you want to use universal wheels,
which have both architectures put into one place, or
if you just want a native wheel.
And so you just opt in for whichever way you want.
Okay, and that's really the configuration.
There's a lot more options here.
You can customize that however you like.
And you can do it through, everything can be done through environment variables,
but this is a lot cleaner and nicer.
And it lets you run it locally without having to redo all your
environment variables, okay?
And there's the PyTest stuff.
Okay, so now I'm gonna show you the workflows.
This is the longest piece, but I think you'll see it's not too bad.
First thing here, for, and I'm doing this in GitHub,
you could do it in some other system if you wanted.
First, we're gonna do this whenever we click Publish, or
do Publish from the GitHub command line, whatever way you like to do that, or
if you want to manually trigger it.
And then, cuz this will probably take a while.
You're gonna be building a lot of wheels.
Then we're going to build an S-Dist, so you can just use build for that.
So PyPA build is a tool that can build wheels and S-Dist, and
you can just use that to build the S-Dist.
And PIPX is built into GitHub Actions, which is really nice and Azure.
So you can just do that one line.
You don't even have to get a version of Python.
You can just use PIPX.
It's a supported platform, which is fantastic.
It's actually used internally inside CI build wheels action.
The action's only about a page long.
All right, and we just added something to Knox that does that too.
Okay, and then you now wanna build your wheels.
I assume that you would think this one would be the most complex one, and
might technically be, but it's not too bad.
We mostly just do PyPA CI build wheel, and then it's a good idea to use an exact
version there, and then use Dependabot to do that update for you.
So every time we release it, it'll then ask you to update.
And that way your wheels don't crash because maybe we changed something.
And that's about it.
We're running on all the platforms.
Okay, and then finally, assuming you wanna upload this to PyPI,
you could also just download it from the interface and
manually upload it yourself, cuz it's an artifact.
But here's how you would upload it.
And you wanna make sure your wheels and your S-Dist are finished before you do that.
And we're done.
This is what comes out.
This is what that produces.
This is every wheel, and we put a minimum version of 3.7.
So this is every wheel.
It supports 3.6 in there.
And that's it.
You can see the Mac OS wheels there.
There's the universal.
There's the one for the Intel architecture.
There's Mini Linux, Mesa Linux, the two different Windows ones.
The PyPI for 3.7, 3.8, and 3.9 are over there.
They're all there.
If you're in the back, the biggest point is there's a lot of things here.
And you saw how much work had to go into that, not that much.
In this scales, this is something you can do on a very small little project.
If you look at the CI build wheel examples page, you'll see small little projects.
You'll see medium sized projects, and you'll see giant ones.
So this scales really, really well.
Simple enough for small projects and powerful enough for complex ones.
Also, maybe now that I've given you this sort of, in terms of what's possible,
maybe you could think outside the box and mix and match these things in unusual ways.
So here's an example of Clang format wheel.
And so that uses scikit build, which actually triggers LLVM's build.
It uses CI build wheel to then build Python independent binary wheels.
You only need one, so it just picks like 3.8 or something.
And then it makes sure that the final names don't have the 3.8 part,
because it doesn't depend on CPython, but it does depend on your platform.
And then these are like one or two megabyte binaries that sit on PyPI.
There's no binding here, this is only an entry point.
But this means you can just redo pipx run clang format, and
you can get clang format in a second or two on pretty much any system that you can run on.
There's even a precommit wheel, you can run this on precommit CI yourself.
Before this project came out, I've been fighting CondaForge to try to get this
thing under, I think it was 500 megabytes to try to get a Conda environment that
would fit in under 500 megabytes with clang format in it so
that it could run it in precommit.ci, because there was a limit.
Maybe it's 250, I don't know.
And this was one to two megabytes per wheel.
So this is a really fantastic use, I think, of some of these things we've been seeing.
If you want to just quickly jump in and start working on this,
I just want to do a little plug for something that I work on.
One of the products from PsychetHEP is this developer pages.
I'm going to try to do a lightning talk on this too, because I really like it.
And you can quickly make a package using even their cookie cutter.
So you could just say, PIPX run cookie cutter, give it there.
PyBind 11, and as of yesterday, now, CICET build our back end choices.
PyBind 11's been there for real.
Pure PyBind 11 setup tools have been there forever, but
Psychet Build just was added yesterday.
So we now have 11 different back ends, a lot of pure Python back ends,
Hatch, Poetry, whatever you'd like.
Setup tools, two different setup tools, one's one for PEP621.
And then for compiled ones, we also have Matron for Rust.
So if you wanted to start a Rust package, this can get you started too.
And all this is tested with Knox and GitHub Actions.
And we even have this also very new repo review page.
So you can just type in the name of a repository, and
you can type in a branch name, click the button.
And then PyIdeID will run Python 3.10 in your browser, and it will then spit out
the, what guidelines you're following and what you're not from the,
from the developer guidelines.
So that's quite, quite fantastic.
I would highly recommend taking a look at the Psychet Hub.
.org developer page.
So, key takeaways here.
The code you just saw is, I've just put that into the repository.
If you wanna look at it, and that's, you can just see exactly,
you can see it work, cuz it's there in the GitHub Actions.
Logs and things are there.
And then if you want to sort of find out a little bit more about this,
my blog is at isignempi.dev.
That includes links to the most important things,
I think, to, that are here as well.
There's a link to, to the Psychet Hub developer pages.
And there's links to the PyBind11 examples, and to the Psychet Build examples.
And PyBind11 has some very nice examples, including just using SetupTools,
using Psychet Build, or wrapping CMake yourself using SetupTools.
Okay, and then finally, to end with a little bit about me,
these are some of the things that I work on.
These are, these are the projects that I'm involved with and
a member in some, in some form or, or some form or way.
If you go to, but most importantly again, my blog link,
which is actually old there, that will take you there too.
But isignempi.dev or isignempi.gitlab.io will take you to my blog.
Okay, and I guess we don't really have any questions, so thanks for your time.
Thank you again.
We do not have any Q&A at this year's PyCon, so if you do have any questions for
the speaker, I encourage you to ask them over here outside of this room.
I also just want to take a moment before you leave for lunch to give a nice shout
out to our audio team and to our transcriptionist for kicking butt today.