Hello everyone, welcome back.
So we have second talk of the day, D&D and G, a Dating Tale of Dungans and Dragons and
also Grabs by Mohammed Adar.
Over to you, Mohammed.
Hey everybody.
Thanks for being patient with me.
It's hard to stand.
I'm usually not this rude.
Let's go ahead and get started.
Yeah, so since I have mostly spent my career in large corporations and my brain is broken,
I have to give you an agenda.
We're just going to really quickly talk about myself, do some level setting about where
you guys are at, and then I'm going to very briefly introduce graphs and why they're really
cool and why they matter.
And then I'm going to talk about a handful of algorithms that I've divided into three
different classes.
So yeah, let's go ahead and dive in.
If you want to follow along in this presentation, you can check out my link tree.
It's just Mohammed Adar and it's got a link to a PDF of the presentation and some other
stuff.
I'll be adding to that so, you know, check back occasionally.
So yeah, amongst my many, many interests, I really think graphs are neat.
Obviously, I like Python.
I like drawing and DMing sometimes, so this is a nice little intersection of all of those.
About you, hopefully you've got some programming under your belt.
This isn't going to be a real coding heavy presentation, so that should be all right.
If you don't, hopefully you're familiar with maps or dictionaries in Python.
Real basic object oriented stuff, nothing too hardcore there.
There will be some matrices here.
If you aren't familiar with those, don't worry.
You can always circle back to them and learn them later or just don't use them and use
something else because graphs are flexible like that.
So people who are familiar with graphs may recognize this map of the city of Konigsberg.
That's a classic problem in graph theory that presented a city separated by a river and
in between the river, or in the river there are two land masses.
That's four land masses connected by seven bridges.
The question was, can you take a tour of the city and cross each bridge exactly once?
I'd rather motivate graphs by asking you about your friend group.
If I was to ask you about your friend group, you probably wouldn't tell me a bullet point
list of their name and date of birth and height and stuff like that.
You're more likely going to tell me a story of something like, oh, this is my friend Alice
who I met through our mutual friend Bob at a party thrown by Claire where I lost a whole
bunch of money to my friend Dan and Ellen.
What that is, is you're describing these people and the relationships you have with those
people.
That's what's really exciting about graphs is there are data structures that can codify
systems as entities and relationships.
A lot of other data structures purport to do that, but graphs treat these relationships
as first class members and that's where their strength really lies.
Two special relationships that they can encode particularly well are directional relationships
where, for example, a friendship type of relationship is two directional.
If you're friends with someone, you assume they're friends with you, but if you're following
someone, say on Twitter or something like that, then they don't necessarily have to
follow you.
That's where graphs are really useful as far as encoding directional relationships.
There's also transitive relationships.
The example I like to use to motivate this is if an ad company made a viral video and
then paid to put it up on Twitter.
If you really liked it and you retweeted it, but you weren't really in the market for their
product, that ad campaign is a failure using classic analytics.
If you dig a little deeper into this, your friend may have seen the video, been in the
market for that product and bought it.
You can use graph analytics to encode those transitive relationships and dig a little
deeper into the success or failure of any particular ad campaign or other relationships.
This is a more classic illustration of a graph.
The more formal definition is that a graph is a collection of nodes and edges.
Nodes are just the fundamental atomic unit in a graph, and then edges are pairs of nodes
that represent a connection between them.
For example, we have node A, C, B, and D here.
We have edges between them.
We can also have directed edges.
That's just in a directed graph and your edges would have to be ordered pairs then.
One thing I really want to talk about but couldn't figure out how to wedge into this
presentation is pads and sub-graphs.
They're really useful tools.
If you're doing graph analytics, you'll definitely want to be familiar with that.
A path is just what it sounds like.
It's just a collection of nodes.
You get a starting node and an ending node, and you get a path through other nodes to
get to that ending node.
Then a sub-graph is just a portion of a graph.
These will be really useful if you ever do graph analytics more.
The last little awkward thing that I want to cover is labels, which are a way to describe
the class of a node.
For example, in this graph, we've got either servers or clients, and that's a label.
You can also add a property to any graph, and that's any other information.
That's where the real strength of graphs comes in, because you can add a name or a model
free space on a particular machine, or the latency between two machines and stuff like
that, and really start doing some really cool analytics and exploit your data a little further.
As far as applications, they're everywhere.
If you're here, hopefully you're already excited about that, but you've probably seen them
in maps, social networks, puzzle solving in state spaces, disease propagation, community
identification, chemical- I'm not going to read this.
You guys can read it later.
It's everywhere.
Okay, so this is PyCon, so I'm going to very briefly cover representing graphs in Python.
You can use either an adjacency or degree matrix, an edge list, a dictionary, or you
can use packages like NetworkX.
When you have a matrix representation, a matrix is just really a table of numbers.
You let your rows represent the from node, and your columns represent the to node.
For example, we've got the number 2 over here, so that's from A to D, and we have
two edges from A to D, so the number in the table represents the number of edges.
You'll see that along the diagonal, there's all zeros, because none of these nodes connect
to themselves.
One more thing is you'll see that this matrix is symmetric.
For example, from A to B is 1, but from B to A is also 1, because there's one edge from
A to B and from B to A, because this graph is undirected.
Just be careful if you're using directed graphs, because the matrix won't be symmetric, and
certain assumptions fall apart.
That just looks like a list in Python.
If you want to get fancy, you can use a NumPy array.
You can also just use an edge list, which is just pairs.
One thing to note here is that I've got the edge CD in here twice.
That's because there are two edges from C to D.
These are nice.
They're better for directed graphs.
There's a lot of redundancy in this one, because I want to represent the same graph over and
over.
They're also nice because you can use any hashable object as the key to your dictionary.
Depending on how you write up a custom node class, you can just use that object as the
key and just have a list of the actual nodes.
You can make your own custom-made node objects and your own graph objects and throw your
logic in there.
As much as I love graphs, they aren't great for everything.
If you're exploring graphs and graph databases especially, avoid them if you've got a lot
of writes, if you have a write-heavy system.
Or if you're querying large parts of a database, you lose a lot of the efficiencies that graphs
provide.
Let's go ahead and dive in.
Oh, that's right.
Quick disclaimer.
DND is inherently racist.
This is something that Wizards of the Coast is addressing, but it's baked in there.
If that's something that bothers you, I've tried very hard to not have representations
like that in here, but I'm not perfect.
If it does, please let me know because I'm always trying to be better.
It's not inherently violent, but there sometimes tends to be violence in DND adventures.
I've also tried to minimize that.
Let's go ahead and get started.
You meet in a tavern and you want to get a lager because the ales are gross.
The bar is all the way up here, but you're all the way down here.
You need to get through this very busy bar.
You're like, you know what?
No problem.
You come to a fork in the road.
Now you're like, oh man, okay.
I'm just going to go down a random fork.
I don't know, whichever one.
That means you end up hitting a dead end because you run into this nice, I don't know, it's
like a dog woman person.
This is the only picture I didn't draw, so I don't know everything in it.
The guy, I did credit him in the first one.
Noah QH, check him out.
Support artists.
Anyways, you run into this obstacle.
You end up backtracking to the intersection and you go down one of the other options,
the fork in the road.
You basically can keep doing that until you get to the bar.
In the worst case scenario, your triple looks something like this.
You start over here, you come to an intersection and you just make a decision.
If that decision leads you to a dead end, then you backtrack and you try another path.
This is known as depth first search.
Oh, just kidding.
I need to practice more.
First I'm going to tell you about converting maps to graphs.
You can treat the corridors as edges and entities and the intersections as nodes.
This is sort of less naturally than a lot of other things, but does naturally turn into
a graph.
You've got your nodes that I've just labeled alphabetically and then dead end nodes I've
just labeled as an X.
Then you have your edges connecting those nodes.
You can use depth first search, which is a nice simple recursive algorithm that is quick
to implement, easy to use, yada yada.
I can run through this.
Do we have time?
Yeah, we got time.
The way depth first search runs, it's recursive, so you always want to put that end condition
there at the beginning.
One little gotcha that always threw me off is to make sure you mark your current node
as visited.
The way these algorithms work is they will build lists of unvisited nodes.
If you don't mark them as visited, you're going to end up going in loops.
Then you basically just check every node if it is the target node.
Just recurse into it.
What that looks like, I wanted to go through just one or two iterations here.
We'll start at the node down at the bottom that we've marked as visited.
It's not the endpoint, so we're going to mark it as visited.
We're going to check every one of its unvisited neighbors.
We're going to perform DFS by going to the top of this.
This isn't the endpoint, so we're not going to return true here.
We are going to mark it as visited.
For every one of its neighbors, we're going to just recurse further in.
Eventually you end up recursing through the whole thing and getting to the end.
You can finally order a beer or a non-alcoholic beer if you're under 21 in America.
As you're ordering your beer, a little street urchin comes up to you and asks you for help.
You're like, oh, you know what?
I'm there.
I'm here to answer the call to adventure.
You get kicked out of the bar for drawing a weapon in the middle of a bar.
Everybody's just trying to have a good time.
He leads you to the sewers where there's been trouble, but it's locked.
You're like, I got to find a key.
He's all like, you know what?
Don't worry.
You're like, Alice or Bob have the key.
It's a weird town.
Everyone's names are alphabetically ordered.
You're like, you know what?
That's fine.
I'll just go ask Alice and see if she's got the key.
Alice is like, I don't have the key, but maybe you can ask Carmen or Dev.
You're like, okay, you know what?
That's fine, but first I got to ask Bob.
Bob is like, I don't have the key either and my face looks like toast, so maybe ask Ellen.
Then you're like, all right, I'm going to add Ellen to my list, but I first got to go
see Carmen.
I don't have the key either.
Go ask Bob.
This is where things start running circles and you're like, this is ridiculous.
Why am I just going down the list like this asking people when I have the magic of graphs
to help me organize this search?
If we revisit this search by treating people as nodes, the edges between each node represent
the relationships between those people.
This could be relationships like Alice knows Bob, Alice follows Bob, or Alice and Bob are
friends with each other, or Alice thinks Bob has the key, which is the relationship
we're going to use.
Let's revisit this problem using ... Oh, man, I have 15 minutes left.
Holy cow.
I thought this was a 45-minute presentation.
Dang.
Guys, breadth-first search is great.
Do it.
All right.
One thing, you want to make sure your mark your nodes is visited.
This is actually ... Yeah, you're crossing them off off the top.
When Carmen finally tells you to go visit Bob, you're like, ha, I already took care
of that.
You're on a trip, dog.
Then what else do you need to know about breadth-first search?
Oh, this is cool too because as you're solving a problem, you can build the graph on the
fly.
That's cool.
You don't have to know everything about the graph as you're solving whatever problem you're
solving.
That's another thing I really like about graphs is they are more than any other database, really
open to modifying things on the fly.
That's breadth-first search.
Everyone knows it.
Look it up.
It's great.
Your mark nodes is visited.
This is another thing.
This is what depth-first search would look like along this network.
This is what breadth-first search would look like.
It's cool because you can get to whatever solution in as few jumps as possible.
Whereas with depth-first search, you have to go to the end of a particular path.
That's definitely something you want to keep in your back pocket is breadth-first search
is the way to go for most simple things.
You get the key.
You are in the sewer.
There's a map.
You're like, you know what?
No problem.
I've already converted maps to graphs and I've done breadth-first search.
I can get there in two hops.
Easy.
You run off and the kid's looking at you like you're an idiot.
He beats you there.
You're like, what?
He's like, I know a faster way from a wizard named Dykstra because you didn't think about
the path lengths.
If you consider the path lengths, you can get a faster path.
Just because if you go from S to A to B, you're going to go along this big corridor versus
if you take a little detour from S to A to B, you can take B to E, which is shorter.
That's a really great algorithm that I'd love to talk you through sometime.
There it is.
This is all in the PowerPoint.
If you guys want to know about it, that's one thing about this is you just want to repeat
it until you mark your targeted node as visited.
It's a little gotcha if you're doing Dykstra.
Don't end too early.
Then you go into the evil guy's lair and you make Batman noises.
You find a ... Turns out this guy wasn't really a big bad.
He's just a messenger.
Now you have a whole bunch of messages that people have been sending to each other.
You say Frank's messaging Gina, Gina's messaging Hector, and so on and so on.
That's getting real confusing.
You turn it into a graph.
Now you've got a messaging graph saying, oh, these people are messaging these people.
It doesn't get confusing at all because graphs make the problem a lot more simple to illustrate.
It looks something like this instead of just a bullet point list.
The algorithms you can use here are how do you determine who's actually in charge of
this network.
There's a lot of different algorithms for this.
There's two classes.
points which sort of tell you what node or edge you can remove to separate the graph
completely from each other.
Basically turn it into two separate graphs or one disconnected graph.
Those are great if you have a point like that, but those don't always exist.
Another tool you can use is centrality, which is just determining a node's influence.
I'm going to use degree centrality because it's really easy to calculate.
It's literally just counting the degrees per node.
You can normalize it by n minus one, the number of nodes minus one.
That's the maximum number of connections any node can have.
That ends up looking like this.
Then you can take out someone that's sort of at the center, a high-influenced person.
There's a lot of other centralities.
Degree centrality is just the most simple one.
You definitely want to look at other ones.
You go and you make more Batman noises.
You get a big bag of money and you go to the mayor.
They're like, yes, this is great.
I can finally fund the town, but I don't know how to distribute it.
This is our town charter and we have to fund all these things.
I don't know where to start.
You can use community detection, which is another class of algorithms.
I'm only going to go over prims because I have zero time.
Basically you take that charter and every entity in the charter, you turn it into its
own node.
Entity 1, 1 is the mayor.
1, 2 is the mayor's aide, etc.
Then you connect them by basically saying, oh, are they mentioned in the same section
of the charter?
Then you can keep connecting them a little more loosely by saying, okay, if they're mentioned
at all in the charter, that's not as strong a connection.
I want to be aware of that.
I'm going to weight that connection by 2 to just say, oh, these entities are a little
more distant from each other according to the charter.
Then you have a list of edges and their weight.
I ordered them by their edge weight because you need to for prims algorithm.
You basically take out all the nodes and you start adding edges back to your graph until
you get what's known as a spanning tree.
That's what this looks like.
You add an edge and then you add an edge and then you're just going through your ordered
list of edges ordered by weight.
If you do that, you may end up getting a loop, which is contrary to what a tree is because
we're trying to get a graph that has the minimum weight while still being fully connected.
We don't actually need this one.
We can just remove that.
We keep doing this process and we end up connecting the graph with what's known as a minimum spanning
tree.
Then we can start removing edges to build out the community detection algorithm.
That is basically just going backwards until the desired number of groups is achieved.
We're going to take out the edge AF and the edge BF.
Now we have three communities.
We end up funding the mayor's office and the mayor's aid equally as much as water well
maintenance roads, animal crossing, fire medical and hazardous magic because graphs are not
a silver bullet.
One thing I did want to talk about is your algorithms only work the way they're supposed
to.
You should always ask yourself, what kind of results do I expect before running out
any algorithm?
This was, yeah, no, I'm not going to share that anecdote.
That's fine.
Basically, you want to know what success and failure looks like before you run an algorithm.
If you don't get results that you expected, check if it's implemented correctly.
Check if there's similar algorithms.
I did mention there's a lot of community detection algorithms out there.
Try it.
Then lastly, redefine what a node or edge is because maybe this arbitrary relationship
of being in the same paragraph of the charter, that doesn't really encode any useful information.
So wow, I made it on time.
I still have time to spare.
Great.
I practiced this like five times and thought I got it.
But when you're up here and the lights are shining, time doesn't matter.
But I just wanted to leave you guys with a few little things.
Graphs are great and, oh, I can't cross your arms over the mic.
They're really great because they encode systems as entities and relationships.
If you don't walk away with any other algorithm today, check out Breth for a search.
It's really useful.
You can use it for a lot of different things.
They're also very resilient to on-the-fly changes.
You can add information to your graph or to any node or edge in your database without
having to update the entire thing, without having to rewrite schemas and stuff.
The three big classes of algorithms we went through are paths, connections, and communities.
There's a lot of different stuff out there.
So definitely check it out yourself.
Check out my link tree.
It's got my GitHub on there that I thought I could populate between when my plane landed
last night and now.
But I will definitely have it populated later this week with more resources for you guys
to look through.
Great.
I can't believe I made it with time to spare.
Look at that.
You get five minutes of your life back.