I would like to introduce Georgie Kerr, Lorena Mesa, Anthony Shaw, and Reuven Lerner for
our diversity and inclusion work group panel.
Dangerous chairs.
Let me try.
Yeah, good morning everyone.
Come on.
Good morning everyone.
Yay!
Wow, Georgie, you're really bringing it.
I'm just like heating up the seats.
It's pretty cold here.
Yes, it is freezing in here.
I want to say hi to all those people watching on live too because we've not been saying
much to them.
But we see you.
So today we are having a panel chat here with a group of us.
So we are going to talk to you a little bit about what PSI, PSF, diversity and inclusion
work group is about, why we're here today, and how you can help us.
So let's do a quick self-introduction.
Hey, I feel like I live on the stage this morning.
My name is Lorena Mesa, pronoun she-day.
Oh, and I'm the current chairperson of the Python Software Foundation, do things with
Pylates, et cetera.
Hi, I'm Anthony Shaw, a PSF fellow around nuisance.
I'm Rufin Lerner, I'm a Python trainer.
I'm Georgie, I'm a woman.
Okay.
So the diversity and inclusion work group was set up in November 2020.
And there's a total of 20 members led by Marlin.
So here's a little map that you can see of the members around the world.
You might have met a couple of them in person, like Deborah, Christian, who's there too.
I don't know.
Deborah should be somewhere around.
So why do we create diversity and inclusion work group in PSF?
In 2020, there were four seats available in the PSF Board of Directors and received 26
nominees, nine from North America, four from South America, two from Europe, six from Africa,
and five from Asia.
It's part of APAC.
Yeah.
So by the end of the election, all four elected parties were from the USA.
We also realized that out of 1,151 members, only 40.1% of us voted.
Now let's look at the changes and achievements in 2021.
Now in 2021, we have actually three board seats available and 19 nominees.
So you can see that most of the members are mostly, mainly from Asia and South America.
Now this time we have elected parties from South America, one from Africa, and one from Europe.
Still no elected parties from Asia despite seven nominations.
We do have more members.
Sign up last year, that was like 1,538 members who were eligible to vote, but only 39% of them vote.
In 2021, we have more languages in our documentation.
Documentation for Python 3.10 were translated into 10 different languages thanks to all our volunteers.
With the help of over 200 Pythonistas, the Spanish translation was completed in January 2022.
We also see that the Python technical leadership mostly are core developers in North America.
If we look at the growth of Python developers worldwide, the developers grew from 8.2 million to 10.1 million in 2021.
That is like 1.9 million within a year.
That's amazing, Pythonistas.
So let's look at the geographic distribution around the market.
Based on the GitHub repo in 2021, although this data does not filter any languages,
but since Python is one of the main languages around the world, it's pretty accurate,
there is no doubt that Asia is the dominant market.
Now let's discuss a little bit about the slides based on the facts that we have here.
What do you think was the problem during the 2020 election?
I was asked what in the world is the Python Software Foundation.
As a director for six years, I have been saying the same thing over and over,
which is we are here to help build an inclusive and diverse community that is as inclusive and diverse as our users.
I think one of the things that started some of this conversation that led to the creation of the diversity and inclusion workgroup
was us thinking a little bit about the mandate of the Python Software Foundation.
Again, the Python Software Foundation, we help put this event on.
We help think about fundraising.
We help thinking about what are the issues around the world that Pythonistas are facing.
We own the trademark, et cetera, et cetera.
So considering that the board of directors, unfortunately, has historically had a bias towards people in the United States or North America and Europe,
what I think we're seeing is as we continue to grow and have a more global population of Pythonistas,
we're not maybe reaching the plethora of issues that we could otherwise be if we were having directors
or having more inclusion with voting members, et cetera, of Pythonistas around the world.
One of the things I think was really great with the end of the lightning talks is we see this growth of the regional conferences,
but again, we're continuing to kind of have a little bit of a stagnant issue with outreach.
And not to say that directors who come from the United States or directors who come from Europe don't understand these issues,
but we all know that the people that are in these given communities are best able to speak to things that are the unique challenges in their neck of the woods.
So I think that was one of the main things that led to this discussion.
Again, all of us are volunteers.
We're all very passionate about this community, but literally our mandate says we are building a diverse and inclusive environment
and community that reflects our user population.
So I think that was like a really big thing that kind of jumped in.
And that was something very glaring to us in the election was just seeing that we weren't maybe reaching people in a way that we could otherwise be reaching them.
Right. That's true.
Anthony, what do you think in 2021 we see some changes there?
We do have more members, but what do you think the changes actually cost in 2021?
Yeah, so things have changed quite a lot over the last couple of years.
The membership has expanded and there's been a lot more people sign up from Asia in particular.
So I guess the membership of the PSF has expanded and also geographically and in other aspects is a lot more diverse.
And in terms of the board nominees, at least, I think there's a lot more diversity in the nominees.
I think what we need to look at going forward is how do we make sure that we advertise that more and continue to try and recruit members into the PSF.
Well, we do see also that there's actually more still mainly the core developers from the US.
Does that mean that the experts are actually in the US only?
So, I mean, there's definitely a lot of skills in the US and that's kind of obvious.
But it's not exclusive to the US and there are definitely people with talents and skills elsewhere.
I think before we look at addressing this and trying to make it more diverse, we need to appreciate a couple of things.
One, the healthy discussion and community of core developers is critical to the success of Python.
And we need to protect that.
That doesn't mean that bringing new people in is going to make that worse.
And I think we just need to kind of plan things a bit further ahead.
Also, if you look at the poor requests to see Python, they are diverse.
So there's people from all over the world making their first changes to see Python, submitting poor requests and things like that.
But at the moment, you know, it's still a bit of who you know.
And it's easier to get a poor request merged if you know some of the core developers or you're already a part of the community or you're a known person.
So I think if we want to get more core developers from diverse geographically,
then we need to look at how can we spot or at least identify people who are trying to contribute and actually bring them in and have a discussion with them.
Because I don't know if anyone else remembers the feeling when they get their PR merged the first time.
It's just especially see Python like it's yeah, it's a you know, it's a pretty high bar to get something into see Python.
And there are people doing this every day from all over the world.
So I think we definitely need to look at how we can bring more of them on board.
I do. I do feel that living in Asia previously that a lot of people or developers in Asia feel that they're not capable.
They're not good enough. Is there a way to actually make them reassure that they can actually contribute and they actually good enough?
Anyone of you can.
I think mentoring is a has been demonstrated to be really effective with bringing on core developers.
So existing core developers mentoring people and there have definitely been cases of that with new core developers from from Africa and also from Asia and people existing core developers mentoring them.
I think that's been really effective in terms of the resources as well.
It's really important.
So, so what do you think how we can actually reach out to these people?
So look, I think a big problem is just sort of the perception of software in general and Python and open source software in particular that for many people, they're like, OK, I have software.
And when they see open source, they don't think oh, community supported and written.
They think free, right? I could download it. I don't need to pay for this thing.
Certainly a lot of companies say that and think that and the notion of oh, there's a problem with this or there's something that could be better.
I can change it. I can be part of that improvement that doesn't occur to most people and then take it even a step further.
The notion that there's an organization that's charter is to help people improve the language based on their needs.
That's like the furthest thing from their minds.
So the first thing I think we have to do is do a better job of telling these people the PSF exists, the community exists.
It's not just a word, oh, the Python community, it's all the people use it.
There is an actual community and you can join it and you can be active and you can influence its direction.
And once people have that sense of oh, we can influence it, then we can start to talk to them about the different ways to do it.
Code, documentation, translation, teaching, the works.
So one question here to the public. How many of you are PSF members?
Oh, wow.
How many of you actually voted last year?
Very good.
You people all there?
Can you hear me?
Online.
So let's see how you can help.
There are four ways you can help.
First, you can actually, if you feel that you would like to share with the discussion, you can provide us with your feedback, scan the local QR code over there, and answer the questionnaire, and tell us what you would like, how you would think that we can actually make a better global representation and help the community to grow.
Or if you are not a PSF member yet, sign up.
Sign up on PSF-org under membership.
And if you are already a PSF member, vote.
Another interesting thing that we, people that doesn't know about it is the Community Service Award.
Lorena, can you actually explain?
Sure.
And actually, later today with the PSF community update, you'll get to see some of these amazing fine folks.
We actually have some CSA recipients here on stage, like Georgie.
And something that I think is really important to think about is we're all doing amazing work in our own communities, and it can be that you are contributing to a project, you are running your meetup, you might be doing something really novel and interesting with Python.
All that being said, we like to support our community, and you can do that by writing in to the Python Software Foundation.
Just write a small blurb of who or whom, it could be a group, an organization, a few people, telling us why you think these people ought to, or this organization ought to, receive the Community Service Award.
We do them quarterly, and we are always looking for more people to lift up, particularly from spaces where maybe we don't have as much insight.
Again, one of the things we're always trying to think about is how do we support one another and how do we acknowledge all of the great work that we do, and a small way you can do that is with the CSA.
Yeah, exactly.
You can also look at the picture that's on the slide.
It's also one of the communities as a whole that has received the award from PyCon Japan.
They have donated, I think, $25,000, amazing amount of money to the donation.
Apart from that, they have been always active in whatever, all the Python related community service as a whole.
If you see anyone in your community around the world anywhere, do sign up.
Tell them, tell us, tell us that they exist and tell us what kind of job they have done, what kind of amazing job they have done, and let us know because we need to know.
Everyone needs to know that there are somewhere, a Pythonista that's doing the work, helping the community that's spreading out the word.
And when you have that kind of assurance that your work has been recognized, that actually makes a difference.
I mean, I'm sure every one of you felt it when someone come to you and say, hey, thank you, especially for example, like Anthony.
Do you actually see people coming to you and say, oh, Anthony, I love your contribution?
That's actually happened quite a lot this weekend and it's been really weird.
Yeah, it feels amazing and very, very humbling as well.
And I really appreciate it to anyone who has had any positive comments and stuff like that.
And also getting to meet people who I really respect and look up to at the conference and share that feedback with them as well.
And meet loads of new people and people who want to get involved and they're keen and they're enthusiastic and just trying to keep encouraging that is really important.
So how about you? Do you feel anything during this conference, Reuben, did anyone come to you?
Yeah, yeah, definitely.
And it's amazing. First of all, I feel what Anthony said, which is meeting people in person who you've interacted with online, whether it's my mailing list or Twitter or elsewhere.
That is of course great.
And look, there's so many people doing so many things for Python, some big and some small.
If you see them, tell them. If you see them here, if you see them online, let them know, encourage them to do this.
It's because people are doing these things big and small that Python exists as a language, as an ecosystem.
And I've been in technology for a while now and I continue to be impressed by the generosity and the kindness in the Python community.
And that just is going to encourage more people to join us, more people to come in, more people to contribute, which is good for everyone.
I've heard diversity and inclusion described as this.
Diversity is being invited to the party, inclusion is being asked to dance.
I heard that at, I think it was PyCon Columbia in 2018, and I thought that was a really great way of thinking about it.
When you hear diversity, inclusion, workgroup, you might be thinking, oh, we have some data figures that we're trying to hit or we have some explicit programming.
But really, the programming comes as a result of what we as a community care about.
I have quoted Brett Cannon more times than I care, which is I came for the language, I stay for the community.
Let me give you one example of the way I think about that.
Marlene, who is one of, who is a director from Zimbabwe, was doing this amazing work educating young women in Zimbabwe.
And I was reading the grant proposal and some of the impact of the work that she had done.
And I was completely fangirling. I believe it was PyCon in Portland in 2016.
I was doing my recruitment looking for directors to contact, and I just started talking to her on Twitter.
I was like, you're amazing, you're amazing. Have you ever thought about running for the board?
You have such a great perspective. You're doing all this really great work.
And I think over the span of like spamming her on Twitter over the entire PyCon weekend, I finally got her to sign up.
And now she's doing a phenomenal, not that she wasn't before, but she's continued to be doing phenomenal things.
And she's a community service recipient, has helped start PyCon Africa.
The PyCon African communities have been so instrumental, I think, in showing, again, a different perspective that we may not have otherwise seen.
I know Kodra, who I see here in the audience, we were at PyCon Africa the inaugural year and just seeing that explosion of growth.
And again, it starts with such a small thing, acknowledging the work that other people do and just supporting them can be a step in the direction,
again, to continue to build that inclusive and diverse community that we all as Pythonese do care about.
So that's my example when I think about it.
All right. So if you have any other questions, do reach out to any one of us when we are somewhere hanging out,
or Christian or Deborah or online on this web email.
And do vote. Sign up as a PSF member if you are not.
And help to let us know everyone around the world that's contributing to this community.
That's how we can be sustainable. Thank you.