All right. Is it time?
It is time. Welcome everyone.
Thanks for coming.
We are here for the documenting your code
from Docstrings to automated builds tutorial.
It's the first day of college,
everybody's in the right room,
don't need to go down the hall.
Okay. Welcome.
We'll get to them again.
So if you haven't got the links yet, no worries.
I am Jacob Deppen.
You can find me on Twitter if you care to read tweets
about my kids and Disney things and other stuff like that.
Also data science sometimes.
Yeah. We're going to talk about documentation.
Thanks to everyone who filled out the survey that I sent around.
We got really good participation in that.
It was super helpful for me to understand where you're coming from.
I've been able to refactor some things a little bit in the talk,
hopefully that we'll meet folks where they are,
and we can hopefully have a successful session together.
I want this to be open enough that you can ask questions as we go.
I'm happy to be interrupted.
If I'm in a flow or something,
I'll just tell you to hold on for a second and that's totally cool.
I'm going to now pass out some Post-it notes.
This is a thing that I love to do.
Has anybody ever taken a Carpentries Workshop,
Software Carpentry, Data Carpentry?
We do Post-it notes.
Everybody needs a green Post-it and a pink Post-it,
and you're going to keep them next to you.
These are your way of telling me that you're following along,
or that you are lost or you need help.
Something like that. So green is good,
red is I got some problem, I'm not done yet.
In a big group like this,
it's easier for me to see Post-its rather
than really walking around and finding out.
So just grab one of each,
one off the top, one off the bottom,
and please pass them towards the back as we go.
We won't need them yet for a while,
but get them circulated now.
So why does documentation matter?
I don't think I need to spend a lot of time on this.
You probably wouldn't be here if you didn't
think documentation mattered or you
didn't care about writing documentation,
building documentation. So hopefully,
we're past that.
But I want to get us all on the same terms.
This is how I think about the values of documentation.
First of all, we want to help ourselves.
You're the one who's going to read
your code more than anybody else.
So you want to help yourself with
documentation to revisit your own code.
What was I doing there?
Why did I make the choice that I made?
Next up from that, your team or
your collaborators want to be using your code,
and you might not be available to help them use your code.
So documentation needs to help
them get oriented with your code,
read your code, maybe for code review purposes,
you're going to have documentation and it's going to make
the code review smoother when they know why you made
certain choices or the way you did things.
Above that, we want to help strangers use your code.
That's the ultimate is getting people that
you've never met to use your code.
Whether that's people at your company in the future,
whether it's an open source project
that you're distributing to the world,
you want to build documentation that other people can use.
If it isn't documented,
then your code doesn't exist.
This is something you've maybe heard said before,
if it's not documented, it doesn't exist.
That's pretty much true to some extent.
Finally, reaching documentation enlightenment,
our documentations will actually do some teaching for us.
They'll do some teaching to other people,
to strangers about how to use our code.
What our code does, why it does it,
how are, what are some interesting ways to use the code?
You never have to interact with those people.
You think about all the open source projects where you've
never interacted with the maintainers but
you've somehow learned to use the code.
Maybe never taken a formal class in
some coding technique or whatever,
but you've somehow learned it because
the documentation was there for you to learn it.
That's what we're eventually want to try to reach.
But who am I? I have a bunch of different things going on for me,
but I'm a data scientist.
I work for Corteva Agriscience,
a big tech ag company.
I'm also simultaneously finishing up
my PhD in archeology at the University of Washington,
where I did a lot of data science stuff for my PhD project.
I maintain a couple of open source libraries,
one's called PandasVet,
which is a linter tool specifically designed to help you out with Pandas.
Prospect, which is a simulation tool for archeologists.
I like to do a lot of stuff in the community.
The Puget Sound Python community has been
something that's been really influential for me,
and I've tried to give back a little bit there.
The Carpentries, I mentioned that with the Sticky Notes,
a great organization that teaches groups of folks,
mostly people in research fields, how to start coding,
how to start using digital tools in various ways to make their work better,
more reproducible, and make them
better data scientists or better scientists who use digital tools.
But who I am not is any of these people,
people who really think deeply about documentation and do
documentation if not full-time job as a big part of what they do.
I wanted to put their names up there because
a lot of what I know about documentation is drawn from their work.
Some of the tools we're going to use today are built by them,
and they are the experts of the experts.
There's links to everybody's Twitter profiles and stuff like that in
that links page so you can find out more there.
But if I'm not an expert,
why am I leading a tutorial on documentation?
Like a lot of you, I suspect I like good documentation,
I value good documentation,
and I also want to get stuff done.
I don't want to have to become one of those people you saw on
the previous slide in order to be writing good documentation,
building good documentation.
I want to be able to find a way to make documentation a little bit easier for me,
find a way to make documentation a little bit quicker.
There's all kinds of incentives out there in, I work in industry.
Documentation is not part of my evaluation,
it's not how I measured in my job.
So for a lot of us,
it's a secondary thought,
but we still want it to be good.
So we want it to be as quick and easy as possible to get to that good stage,
or get to that stage,
whatever it might be, stage that works for you.
So I've gone through this process for a while.
I've thought about what works for me.
I've tried a lot of different documentation workflows,
and tools, and things like that.
What I'm going to teach you today,
what we're going to build together is a workflow that I think works pretty well.
For those of us who don't can't or don't want to become super deep in the documentation world,
but we still want good documentation.
I want documentation that I can build and write with tools that I already know.
I do a lot with Markdown.
A lot of folks do a lot with Markdown.
Markdown is everywhere these days.
So wouldn't it be great if I could write all my docs in
Markdown? I also do a lot of stuff in Jupiter notebooks.
Wouldn't it be great if I could write all my docs in Jupiter notebooks?
I write doc strings for my functions and classes and all that good stuff.
I want my docs to use those.
I want to just press a button and have it go,
find all those, give me some nice pretty documentation.
I don't want to mess around with CI-CD too much.
You're going to always have to mess around with CI-CD.
If you've ever tried to set anything up on any CI-CD system,
there's always 12 commits of you fussing with it and trying to get it to work.
A lot of us have been there.
But we can make it as minimally fussy as possible, I think.
That's a goal. I want it to look nice by default.
We don't want to have to spend a lot of time custom tweaking CSS,
which is something that I know basically nothing about.
I want it to look nice right out of the box.
I don't want to have to call in a product designer to get
some documentation that's going to be nice and readable and modern looking.
So what about Sphinx?
Sphinx, I know some people based on the survey,
have tried Sphinx or used Sphinx a little bit.
Sphinx is, I call it the human-headed line in the room.
Get it? It's a Sphinx.
It's a tool that has been around for quite a long time,
and it is the de facto standard in Python.
But if you've played around with it very much,
you know that Sphinx is of a time longer ago,
and it's not the most modern of tools.
It is incredibly powerful,
but that also leads to a lot of complexity.
It's often complexity that we're never going to
touch in the projects that we need to document.
Professional documentation writers use Sphinx,
and they use it to great effect to do really amazing things
and build really amazing documentation.
But for most of the projects that folks in
the Python community are going to be working on,
we're not going to have that level of documentation.
You might want to document a little Python package that you've been
working on for your team in your company,
and it doesn't need to be totally vetted for a broad audience.
It needs to be understandable to the people,
10, 12 people in your team maybe.
So that's the scale that we're thinking about here.
We're not thinking about the most complicated projects in the world,
and that's why I think we're going to try to touch on Sphinx.
Sphinx is going to be behind everything we do today.
So I don't want to make it seem like we're getting rid of Sphinx,
because Sphinx is actually there the whole time.
It's the backbone of everything we're going to do.
But I'd like to touch Sphinx as little as possible because of that complexity,
and we want to try to reduce that complexity for us as much as possible.
So there's pros to Sphinx.
It is the backbone of tools that we're going to use like
Jupyter Book and many other kinds of things that interact with Sphinx.
Has a really large ecosystem and this is part of that complexity,
different kinds of templates,
the extensions is what we're going to make use of today.
If you want to host your docs on Read the Docs,
you've almost undoubtedly found documentation hosted on Read the Docs,
if you've done anything in Python.
It works really nicely with Sphinx.
So there's a lot of compatibility there that's
very natural on both sides of that equation.
But Sphinx is complicated, complex,
maybe is better than complicated.
It relies on things or can rely on things like make files and
other technologies that you may not have a lot of experience with,
or you may not want to learn as part of documenting your Python package.
It may not be compatible with whatever system you're on and you have to find
a workaround and that's the kind of complexity that starts to
compound and ends up with people just not building the docs.
Not writing the docs, not maintaining the docs,
because it's a pain to update them and all of those things.
We don't want to be there. We want to keep our docs as light and
flexible as possible until you become NumPy and
a massive open source project that needs really complicated documentation
and really a lot of thought in it.
But most of us aren't doing that.
Sphinx in its original form relies on restructured text.
I don't know of things beyond Sphinx that use restructured text.
I'm sure there are some, but they're not common in
the daily workflow of somebody who's doing a lot of Python stuff.
Things like Markdown, Jupyter Notebooks with Markdown.
That's something we're usually a little bit more familiar with.
Restructured text is its own world of markup.
If you don't want to learn it, we can mostly skip it.
We'll do a little bit of restructured text here in a little while,
but just enough.
So we're going to do just enough to be useful.
In my pre-survey, I asked folks how many people had
tried to use Sphinx to build documentation,
and how many people were successful.
Ten people had tried and four people were successful.
This is a gap that I think it's a leak in the pipeline of documentation,
that I think a lot of people encounter in the Python ecosystem.
You try to do the right thing,
you try to build documentation for your project,
but Sphinx is a little more complicated than you
wanted and there's other priorities in your work.
So it gets pushed back and pushed back,
and something you're going to do later or something that just
never quite happens or never gets updated after you get it built one time.
So I think this is a common story where you try Sphinx,
maybe you get something working,
maybe you don't, and then maybe your project has documentation,
and maybe it doesn't.
So we're going to start with a little bit of a motivating case for today.
This is where I hope that we're going to end up by the end of our session.
We're going to build all this together.
Oops. We're going to build a web page.
It's going to be live on the Internet that looks something like this.
It's not the most glamorous.
There's the ability to add images here that I haven't done,
but it's live.
It has, let's check out some features.
Well, one, it has a search feature built-in.
We don't have to do anything special to get a search.
We can put a guide here.
We have a nice table of contents on the right side.
We get some code blocks.
We get the auto copy little thing.
This is becoming more and more common.
You start to see this in documentation,
and it's so useful,
just this little guy to copy what's in the box.
There'll be syntax highlighting and other things.
This is a Jupyter Notebook that I have added
some special little box to make a note.
You might add a caution or a tip or something like that, a call-out.
I can put code, I can mix it with Markdown.
This might be something familiar if you've used Jupyter Notebooks a lot.
But mixing all that together into
a guide or a more prose style documentation.
But we also get some technical documentation,
reference documentation that you're probably familiar with.
Function signatures, arguments, types,
all of that formatted nicely for us.
We can even click on the source and see the raw code that's behind it.
So here we start to have
a pretty good foundation for documentation.
We have the ability to drop a Markdown file in and add a new guide,
to add a new module to our package and get it
built automatically in the reference documentation
with nice syntax highlighting and all of that stuff.
There are some other extra features that we'll see along the way.
A lot of this functionality comes from Jupyter Book,
and that's the tool we're going to try today.
So that was our goal.
The sticky notes I mentioned.
Green is all good.
I'm finished with something that we're working on or I'm ready to move on.
Pink is, I have a question.
Some of you in the back, I still might not be able to see your pink sticky notes.
So if you do have a question,
please go ahead and raise your hand. That's totally cool.
But the sticky notes are good when everybody's working on
something and I can take a look around.
Or help, I'm lost. That can be good as well.
So if we haven't gotten the code,
we need to fork the repository from
GitHub and then clone that to our local machine.
Is there anyone who has not been able to do that yet?
I have time built in. We can wait.
So if you have done that,
put a green sticky note up. Yes. Thank you.
You can just put it on the top of your machine maybe.
That can help me know where we're at.
If you haven't, keep your green sticky note down,
or if you have a question about that,
you can put the pink sticky note up or flag me down.
All right.
Intruders. You should be ending up something like this.
If you can open whatever your preferred editor is.
So we have access to this.
What I've done here is created what is effectively in
its current state on the main branch is a runnable Python package.
Everything should work, I think.
I think it works. But it's not documented at all.
There's no documentation in it.
So what we're going to do is progressively over
the next couple of hours is add more features
of documentation to this existing package.
We're going to take it from zero docs to what I showed you,
hopefully the full thing live on the Internet.
This is setting up an environment.
If you haven't installed all the dependencies,
who has not installed all the dependencies yet?
Doesn't have everything going yet.
All right.
I like to use Conda to manage my environment.
So I'm going to activate my environment.
I'm going to do a git status.
Cool. I'm on the main branch here.
So you-all can work on the main branch if you want of your fork.
I don't care where you work.
But I'm going to switch to
a new branch just so that I don't mess up
my nicely put together tutorial
by accidentally putting something on main.
So I am going to just start from a new branch myself.
All right. I'm going to move forward.
If you haven't finished that,
keep working on it and you'll have time,
I think, before we really need to.
So I want to take a few minutes, explore the code.
So look at that randomly package.
There's four modules in there.
What are they? Facts, Palette, Points, and Password.
Take a look through those and see if anything seems familiar to you,
anything that you could see yourself writing.
They're dummy functions, so cut me some slack.
But something that you want to work with and then we'll
or you can work with that particular module
through the next series of steps that we're going to do.
I'm not going to ask you to document every single module and
every function in there through the whole workshop.
So see if anything seems interesting to you.
Get familiar with it, maybe what it does,
how it works as best you
can because we're going to have to write some documentation about it.
Flag me down if you need any help with setup or questions.
Selected a favorite module to use.
I'm just curious, how many people chose the Facts module?
How many people chose the Palette module?
How many people chose the Points?
How many people chose Password?
Interesting. I'm happy I hit
a pretty good cross-section.
I figured Palette would be the least popular,
but I'm glad. Great.
So let's work on what I call documentation level one.
This is this bare minimum stuff that we want to be there,
that you can control pretty easily without any building tools,
without any extra stuff.
Just regular, plain old Python can get you documentation level one.
Things like code comments,
type annotations, docstrings.
Some people don't maybe think of these as documentation,
but docstrings I bet you do.
But code comments are a very fundamental form of documentation.
Code comments, we start with the hash number sign and then something there,
we can write whatever we want in our Python files.
There's no limit.
Maybe there's some theoretical limit to bytes and things like that.
But there's no real limit to what we can write as a code comment.
It's the easiest way to add some documentation to your code.
Put something right next to the code that you're
writing and you can write whatever you want.
Some rules of thumb to try to keep in mind where to put a code comment.
Not everything needs a code comment.
Anything that you would consider clever,
anything that you think is like,
I'm proud of myself for that one,
that should get a comment because what's clever to
you is confusing to somebody else almost certainly,
or even confusing to yourself next week.
I found that's the case a lot of the time.
So if you feel like you're being clever,
great but document why you thought you were so clever,
because it might bite you in the future.
Things like nested data structures,
especially in Python where we have a lot of types being figured
out on the fly and not really obvious all the time.
Those can be useful to have comments with them.
Things that are poorly named,
maybe you're using a package and you think,
wow, this function has a terrible name.
It's called make square,
but I'm actually making a rectangle from it or something like that.
Those things are great to have a comment to say that,
okay, the function is called make square,
but really we're making a rectangle here.
Anything with a non-obvious type that goes
to the same point as the nested data structures.
Really the best thing to describe your reasoning,
to describe choices you made.
This is stuff that can't really be captured in your code.
Why this and not something else?
A lot of times when you work in a team of people,
there might be some blocker to doing something some way
that happens like three steps down the line.
So you change things back upstream a little bit,
and nobody else knows why it's in some really complicated form.
They look at your code a month later and they say,
why did Jacob do it like that?
That is so confusing.
We could just write it in this one line and it would be done.
Well, turns out the one line solution has some problem
three steps down the line and that's why I wrote it in the complicated way.
So those choices and decisions are really great for code comments
because they really communicate something really quickly.
Nobody has to go digging,
nobody has to send you a slack message at your company or find you or
reach out on GitHub to figure out why something is like that.
They just know because they can read it there in human readable prose form.
Things that don't need comments.
Things that are well named already,
your variables that have a really nice name or
your methods or functions that have a really nice name.
You don't have to repeat that.
If they have a nice verb and action,
what they're doing, that's fine and they probably don't need to be documented that way.
I've seen folks, especially folks who are newer to Python,
try to add comments between functions and all over the place.
You can stick that stuff in doc strings and we'll get to those later.
So things like a function signature can be documented in a doc string,
doesn't need to be in code comments.
Here's a couple of examples.
They're maybe not the greatest examples in the world,
but I think they get the point across.
At the top, we have something where we say,
okay, we're going to convert to the correct color range for plotting.
That gives us a little bit of the why.
Why are we converting to the color ranges so that we can plot it nicely?
That adds something. We're adding value maybe to
the code there by saying why we're doing it.
The one below, and I'm guilty of this as well.
When I write code, I often will write a whole bunch of comments that
outline what I want to do with the code
and then just fill in the code in between the comments.
Then sometimes I end up with something like this.
It says, read JSON and the next line is open and read JSON.
You don't need to comment that.
Nobody should ever get mad at you for adding something like that,
because it doesn't hurt, it can't hurt anybody.
But yeah, that's a place where a code comment wasn't really necessary.
But when in doubt, add the comment.
So I want you to look at the module that you chose.
I think each module only has one function, is that right?
I think that's right.
A previous iteration was more complicated, so I simplified it.
Try to add some comments there.
Figure out what needs a comment,
what doesn't need a comment,
what kind of information might be useful to
convey to someone who's reading this later.
Take a few minutes. Take your green stickies
down and you can put them back up when you're done.
So I'm going to go ahead and add a comment.
I'm going to go ahead and add a comment.
I wish I had that kind of time.
All right.
We're starting to get there.
I'm going to call it a quorum now.
We're going to push forward.
If you didn't get all of the code comments in that you wanted,
that's fine. No worries.
The next thing we're going to cover here is type annotations.
I was really surprised in the pre-survey how many folks are using type annotations already.
So maybe this is less of an introduction than I thought I might need to do.
But in general, type annotations describe the types of your objects ahead of time.
They're nice because we don't have to guess whether something is supposed to be a list,
or a dictionary, or a tuple,
or who knows what other type of object it might be.
They take a lot of that guesswork out.
So in the points module,
you have a function like this,
generatePlastNomPoints, and it takes two parameters,
bounds and rate.
But if I need to use that function,
what am I supposed to put in those parameters?
Type annotations are really quick way to tell people what is expected in that function.
So we have bounds here is a tuple of length four with floats in each position.
That's what it expects.
Rate expects just a single float.
The last line,
maybe hard to see at the bottom for some folks in the back,
but we have an arrow pointing to the return type of the function.
In this case, it's going to return to us a NumPy nd array.
So some nice things about type annotations.
They make code bases more maintainable.
That's what they were originally designed for,
and the purpose behind them was to help make
especially big code bases that a lot of people are working on.
They might live a long time.
They make them a little bit more maintainable,
a little bit less cognitive overhead for anybody who's joining onto a project,
and reading new code they haven't written themselves or haven't seen before.
They can make building your docstrings easier,
which we'll see, and they're not enforced at runtime.
So if you get them wrong, that's okay.
You don't want to get them wrong, of course,
but sometimes things are just really hard to type.
There's a question over here about a matplotlib figure.
Those things are very complicated or tricky to type,
and it might just be that it's not worth your time.
That's a decision you get to make,
whether it's worth your time or not to figure out
exactly the right way to type a matplotlib figure in the return type.
Cons, of course, are that the types need to be kept up to date.
If you change something, you got to change the types as well.
But there's tooling around this that can help.
Sometimes you have to import objects just to use them as a type,
and there are certain cases where that can be a little bit annoying,
a little bit cumbersome, can lead to circular imports in some cases.
Again, there's workarounds for that,
but these are complexities that we're trying not to add if we can avoid it.
Just some things are hard to type.
That's the way it goes.
The typing ecosystem is booming and growing really quickly.
There's a lot of tooling out there around the typing ecosystem.
There are tools to enforce the types at runtime or
accept types, enforce them in different ways.
But for now, we're just going to think of them as documentation,
as something that happens statically in
our .py files and doesn't do anything at runtime.
Okay. So now we're going to add some to our practice module.
We have a group of simple types, strings,
ints, floats, and bools that are all built in.
You get those for free.
Other ones you might have to,
like collections like tuple, list, dict.
You might have to import those.
So from typing, import something.
I think it's Python 3.10.
Some of those you can just use right away.
I think you can use list.
Does anybody know for sure?
I think you can use list and dict and tuple,
just in the lowercase native form.
But for purposes of compatibility here,
let's use the from typing import.
There's some other special types that you might want to know about.
Optional is something that could be none or it could be a value.
So we call it optional.
I'll show you an example of that in a second.
Iterable is a more generic type for something like a list or a tuple,
that can be iterated over.
Maybe your code doesn't care what it is,
whether it's a list or a tuple or something,
you just need to loop over something or iterate over something.
Then you can call it an iterable,
and then you can pass in whichever iterable you want.
Union as well. Union is a way of saying or this type or this type.
It could be a string or a float, something like that.
So let's do some examples together on that.
I think if I look at my password,
I have a function where there's a default parameter of none.
So this is something that's going to require optional.
The way that we specify optional,
it's not optional in the sense that it's an optional parameter,
it means it's optionally none or optionally something.
So we're going to from typing,
import optional, capital O.
Over here where we add the type next to invalid cares or cars,
we're going to say optional.
We're going to use square brackets,
and then I think in this case,
we want an int.
No. What do I want?
Somebody who's looking at that function remind me.
List of something. Yeah.
Oh, sure. I'm always the guy who's asking people to Zoom, so thank you.
Is that tolerable?
Yes.
So for hard code bases that aren't very well,
do you experience like multi-type or
a lot of type libraries or a lot of different stuff in that way?
I haven't. I've never used those.
Yeah. If your code exists already in
a large state and then you try to add types,
that's a painful experience.
Yeah. That's the situation at Dropbox for which
the typing was pushed into Python where they had
a large Python code base that was just so big and hard to maintain,
and types made it a lot easier to maintain.
So I don't know about any of that tooling that does
it automatically how well it works or anything like that.
Yeah. It's a real problem.
If you're going to use type annotations, use them from the start.
I mean, obviously you don't always have that choice,
but if you can use them from the start,
you're going to be in a lot better shape.
So here we're going to have an optional,
and I think this might even be able to accept an iterable here.
It could be a tuple. We're just looping through for invalid car, chair, whatever.
So I think it could be anything that we can iterate over.
Again, it doesn't really matter if we're wrong.
So here we get them nested.
We end up with optional iterable string,
or you can't see it all.
Okay. That's one of the more complicated cases.
Some of the other ones are a little bit easier.
But give it a shot with your demo module.
Try to add some types there.
Yeah. When you have your types annotated,
throw up your sticky note.
Don't forget to try to add a return type with the arrow.
This may be a little confusing because it's broken up over a couple of lines,
but the arrow to your return type
before the colon at the end of the function signature.
Yeah. So this is the question they asked earlier. It's tricky.
I'm trying to decide how deep we want to go into this.
Because in the case of documentation, types for documentation,
you do whatever works or whatever you need to.
If something is returning fig,
then in a lot of cases,
it's pretty self-evident what the type is going to be.
Maybe it's not worth the pain of figuring out those complexities.
But in general, you can import the parent class that it is.
Matplotlib figures are a little bit weird in that way.
So I put this example in there to generate this conversation,
to know that there are edge cases when it comes to typing,
and there are things that don't work so well.
So for a lot of tooling around typing,
we need type stubs,
which are defined whole other topic for another day.
But some libraries don't have type stubs or are still working on it.
I think if you want to add types to the request library,
you need to import stash requests like a whole separate library.
I think that's right. Somebody can correct me.
I don't use request very much.
So in the case of Matplotlib figure,
in that specific case,
I will. So we can cheat a little bit,
because what you didn't know maybe is that built into the repo is
all of these levels as different branches of the repo.
So if you really screw something up,
you can always fast-forward a little bit by going to a different branch.
So I'm going to move to level one.
So I imported from
Matplotlib.figure import figure and then I used that as my return type.
These days, especially with popular libraries like Matplotlib,
there's probably some resource out there that tells you how to
type something funky,
anything that's not immediately obvious how you should be typing it.
Somebody's had that same problem before.
That's a good question.
There's always a little bit of a book.
If you're not using any typing related tools on top of this,
you can put whatever you want and Python is not going to care.
I think that's right.
Is that right? Anyway, you play around with that.
But there's a get out of jail free card if you put it in quotation marks.
So if I put that in quotation marks,
it's not really going to be evaluated in the same way.
It says, this is the type,
but typing tools don't go looking for something because you're not going to
have the right information to figure it out.
I don't want to go too deep down the rabbit hole of typing because I'm not an expert in docs,
but I'm certainly not an expert in typing.
I don't want to give you bad info if I don't have to.
Cool. Has everyone got type annotations?
Sure.
So here, I didn't even tell it what had to be in the iterable.
But square bracket.
Yeah. So you can add this as well.
Go ahead.
I'm not sure exactly what you mean.
Maybe. So what you could do is you could say,
you can define a type like that.
Everything in Python is an object.
You can assign it to an object,
and then you can call that invalid type.
Is that what you're thinking?
So you mean enforce the type at runtime?
Usually, what you would do is just do a check of the first line of your code,
I think is the natural thing to do there.
There are tools like Pydantic that will try to coerce types.
So if they put something in and it's not the right type,
it'll error out right away or try to convert it to the correct type.
Again, I'm not a typing expert.
That's a good question, but I don't have a good answer.
Okay. Let's move to docstrings.
I was very pleased in the pre-survey.
Lots of people have written docstrings.
I know not everybody has,
but lots of people have and that's really good because docstrings
are the foundation for all the next bit
of cool stuff that we can do in documentation.
So PEP 257 defined a lot of
the conventions that we need to use for docstrings and best practices.
But it's a string that you have at the start of a module function class method,
and you can access it later using
the Dunder doc method or a special attribute rather.
In PEP 257, they define some good practices
always include at least a one-line docstring
for every class function method.
Usually you want to put more,
but at least a one-liner is,
let's see, softly required if you want to follow these conventions.
You want to use triple double quotes.
I guess it's not exactly triple quotes.
Triple double quotes and not single quotes.
This is not enforced by Python,
but it's just another good practice and standardization of practice there.
So the triple double quotes like you see up here at the top docstring.
When you're writing your docstring,
you try not to repeat the name of the function or the method.
It doesn't add any value to you.
So sometimes it's a really good exercise to try to think of
a different way to describe your function
that's not just saying the name of the function.
I know this is going to be hard to see.
I thought I was going to have a bigger screen.
But there's three main styles in use.
Python will actually let you use all kinds of different styles.
Really anything you want, I think.
PEP 257 outlines some basics,
and these are three styles that follow
those basics and then add some other extra stuff to them.
The NumPy style is the style that I like.
It's a little bit more verbose than,
for instance, the Google style.
But I don't know, I like it.
I got started doing scientific computing stuff and got used to that style.
NumPy and Google are probably the two most common styles that people
use these days and tooling recognizes that.
The restructured text style,
the native style for using Sphinx is the one in the top right,
and it looks a little bit less familiar,
I think, to a lot of folks if you look in raw code.
But you might see older code bases that they still use that style.
It just tends to be a lot more,
I don't know, I think a little bit harder to read,
a little less human readable than the other formats.
But my company uses Google style,
so that's the kind that I've started to learn. Yes, question.
So I was going to ask about that PyCharm.
I do the triple-soc,
and after that we use the program.
Yes.
So there's another way to do restructured type code.
Is there another way to update Google style?
I don't use PyCharm,
but I was looking this up before the tutorial because I'm sure there is.
Does anybody else use PyCharm and know that you can change that setting?
Yeah. I bet you'll be able to find that.
In VS Code, there's an extension called AutoDockString,
I think, that does the same thing. It's really nice.
So that's the way to level up your DockString stuff.
I intentionally saved those editor tricks for the end of the talk,
because I want you to try to craft them by hand,
but your editor might do it for you. Yes.
Yeah. It's a really tricky problem to solve.
Sometimes it's a bit of a cultural problem,
and about setting expectations about what has to
happen whenever you open a PR or something.
There are some tools that we'll look at later on if we have
time that are linters for DockStrings,
and those can go a little bit of way to make sure things are formatted correctly.
There's something called xDockTest or DockTest,
which is a tool that integrates with PyTest,
or you can run it on its own,
but you can run your examples.
So if you have examples at the bottom of your DockString,
I don't have any here,
but if you include examples,
it will run those.
So that's one way and it'll fail, a test will fail.
So that's one way if you get into the habit of adding an example to every DockString.
It's not going to enforce that your DockString is
perfect or that it's up to date,
but it's one extra check to say,
well, the example doesn't run anymore,
so this function must have changed in some meaningful way.
That is a good question and problem to keeping things up to date. Yeah.
Do you have a whole process so you don't know where that DockString is and everything?
You might have functions that are self-striving that are simple enough where you're just
going to make, I mean, I guess maybe a pump case,
but you have a heuristic unit or stuff like you're just giving a type of complexity,
like a function that allows you to have full functions.
How many of those do you have?
I mean, my heuristic is every function should have some kind of DockString.
Yeah. That's where it's either the one-liner.
If you're very good at
dry code and breaking things up into nice little tiny functions,
then it might only need maybe your function takes one parameter and
it's really well-named and does something very small.
In that case, you might not need the full parameters returns setup.
But having a line that says what it does is,
I mean, how much time does it cost?
Not very much. How much time might it save in the future?
More than that. At least potentially. You have a question?
Yeah. So how you've done it and what you've done in the other kind of code base
is that you have type of things and then it's a DockString that you specify,
you have to input any kind of output to it or what are your
automatic ways of like yield parking that and other kind of things?
Yes. Wait, you mean in terms of like then linting it with that stuff or?
Yeah.
That's a good question.
I don't know of that tool but that would be a cool one to build.
I think that's possible.
So you're saying you have your,
assuming your type hints are always right,
you then just compare your type hints to
the type annotation in the DockString.
Or auto-generate.
Auto-generate, yes.
I think that's what he was referring to.
I was going to save this for later,
a little bit of magic but we'll do it now.
So I am going to install an extension for my VS code called auto-DockString.
You were saying the same functionality I think is native to PyCharm,
you don't need any extension even.
I install it and now if I get rid of this,
well, I'm going to go to this other function.
If I get rid of this DockString,
I get a pre-populated generate DockString.
It's defaulting to Google style here.
But it'll add in your type annotations,
it will find those and add those already.
All you need to add are the descriptions for each of the arguments or the returns.
So that's the shortcut, make your life a little bit easier.
You don't have to type out all the colons and
all the little bits that are repetitive,
those get built for you.
Is that what you were thinking about?
Good. I should start with the magic next time.
All right. So have people been writing DockStrings as we've been talking?
If you have a DockString for your function,
give me a green sticky.
Awesome. So that's the end of stage one.
You might want to commit your code just to save it.
Then we're going to take a break.
We're past the hour already.
So if tired, break.
I have it at, time is 2.40.
So we'll get back here 2.55. We'll kick off.
I can be here to answer questions, talk about stuff.
All right, folks.
Ready to get back to it?
All right. In the meantime,
we learned the question that I totally didn't
understand because I don't know about TypeScript.
There is a way for something.
Was it on this function that you were trying to use the literal?
Right here with language here?
Is this where you were using the literal?
Yeah. So there's a type called literal.
If we're only going to accept,
in this case, if you look at the function,
if you haven't looked at it,
we're only going to accept English or Deutsch as valid inputs.
We can say literal.
Is it comma or?
Yeah. Comma. That's a way to type annotated so that
we specify exactly which values we might accept.
It's pretty cool. I like that.
I learned something. Maybe we all learned something.
So thank you. Thanks for asking that question.
All right. I'm going to undo that just because I don't know
what kind of havoc that's going to cause later on down the line.
Let's move on to level 2.
Let's make something that's a little more interesting.
We're going to talk about Jupiter book,
and then we are going to dive into Sphinx a little bit,
and take some pieces from Sphinx that are going to be very useful.
So far, everything we've done is inside our code base.
It's inside that.py file.
We have added the type annotations,
we have added our doc string,
we have added those code comments in the body of the functions.
But if somebody wants to look at that documentation,
they have to open your raw code file.
That's not a great expectation for when you want to share it out externally.
Might be fine for your team,
but it's not really fine for other users.
So we want pretty docs on the web.
That's what we want to aim for.
That's the standard is pretty docs on the web.
You can have images, you can have call-outs,
you can have links,
all kinds of fun stuff,
and that's what we're going to try to build towards.
So one way of getting there is Jupiter book.
It's a project for, as they call it,
for building beautiful publication quality books and documents.
It's not necessarily built as a documentation engine necessarily,
but it has a lot of advantages that make it nice for that.
First of all, we can use lots of formats side-by-side.
We can write in Markdown,
we can write content in Jupiter notebooks with Markdown,
and LaTeX, and other things.
We can write in restructured text if you have
existing docs that you want to keep around,
or somebody who's engineered
some beautiful restructured text thing that you want to not lose.
Also, MIST, has anyone heard of MIST?
Raise your hand if you've heard of MIST.
Markedly Structured Text is what it stands for.
It's really the glue of all of this approach,
where we're gluing together Markdown and restructured text,
and translating MIST speaks both,
and MIST is mystical to me.
It's awesome. It's a cool project that's not very old,
and it's really developing,
and I think it's going to be really productive for us.
The config and build system,
like any build system,
there's a certain level of complexity that we have to tolerate,
but I think it's fairly beginner-friendly.
Everything happens in YAML files.
We don't have make files,
which I think is a plus for folks who are doing it for the first time.
It looks great by default.
It has a lot of nice modern feel to it,
and we don't have to do a lot of tweaking just to make it look presentable.
It requires a little extra work to connect it with Read the Docs,
but it's definitely possible because it's Sphinx under the hood.
We can turn it into something that can be put on Read the Docs.
I'm not going to do all of that today because again,
that's more complexity,
but that's definitely something that you can do,
and is documented on the Jupyter Book documentation.
We can't always use the full range maybe of Sphinx functionality.
If there's some really specialized Sphinx extension or tool,
it may not be compatible with Jupyter Book for some reason.
So that's something to keep in mind, a potential downside.
Customizing the look is a little bit trickier.
There hasn't been a whole bunch of themes developed for Jupyter Book yet,
so it's a little bit trickier to configure for something fancy.
There's a really cool example.
If you go to the Jupyter Book documentation,
I should have put this in the links,
but there's a whole gallery of Jupyter Books,
of example ones that are out there in the universe.
There's one called the Data Sitters Club,
the Babysitter's Club book series if you're familiar with that,
like the young kid book series,
but it's done in the style of the Babysitter's Club,
like color palette and fonts and everything like that.
It's really awesome.
So there are possibilities for configuring it,
but it's probably going to require CSS.
I think I said earlier, I haven't touched it.
So let's get moving.
Let's create the basics.
So inside of our repo,
that the same level as the randomly folder,
we're going to create a docs folder.
Got nothing in it so far. Let's go back here.
Here's where we're going to use our links that we opened before, hopefully, maybe.
We are going to create a underscore config.yml file.
So let's just create the file first inside that docs folder,
underscore config.yml.
Now, I'm going to go to this link.
I already have it open.
It's in the list of links.
It's in here. This line here,
Jupyter Book config.
But what you'll see here is a nice copyable with a little copy button there,
with all the default configuration that Jupyter Book comes with out of the box.
I really like that as a starting point for,
I'll just customize that for what I need.
But most of the things in that config are things I don't need to touch.
So we'll start with that.
So I copied that and I'm going to paste it into my config.yml folder.
So let's customize it a little bit.
We're going to give it a different title,
call it whatever you want, author name.
YAML is a pretty readable format for doing these kinds of configuration files.
That's why it's become pretty popular.
There are a few weird edge cases,
but in general, I find it pretty user-friendly.
So I'm going to say Jacob Dippen.
Here, we're going to give it a copyright year.
So just so that YAML doesn't think that it's an integer,
we're going to put it as a string.
I'm going to change that.
I just opened a PR on the Jupyter Book repo
the other day when I noticed that this was still in 2021.
Get that changed soon. If you have a logo for your site,
you can put a path to it there.
We don't have one right now.
If there are certain files that are going to be in
your docs directory that you want it to skip by default,
things like DSStore, if you're on a Mac,
you might have that funny little guy laying around.
Notebook checkpoints.
This is the bane of my existence,
the notebook checkpoints always showing up when I try to automate things.
But we'll ignore them here.
Otherwise, I'm going to leave defaults on all of those.
We can give it some configuration of how we want it to execute and build the book.
I'm going to keep all the defaults there as well.
We don't need to change anything.
There are some built-in extensions that we can choose to enable or disable here.
Again, we'll leave those.
There's some other parameters about getting some nice little tabs at the top,
like an edit button,
an edit page button.
I'm going to change that to true.
Same with the other two buttons there.
Change to true.
These are nice because what they're going to do is add
a little box at the top of your docs on every page that will allow
somebody to open a PR directly against your docs to help.
If somebody finds something out of date in
your documentation or a spelling error or some mistake,
it can be really nice that they don't have to go find
your repo and find the part in the code where this thing is happening and which file it is.
They can go directly from the interface in
your docs to the place where they want to change something.
That's a pretty nifty little feature to use.
The rest I'm going to leave.
You can build LaTeX.
I'll leave that and we're going to come back to these launch buttons.
The repository, we'll come back to all of that.
I think we'll come back to the Sphinx extensions.
So like I said, Jupyter Book is built on Sphinx,
and everything eventually gets passed down to Sphinx.
So we can leverage a lot of Sphinx extensions and we'll do that in a little bit.
But for now, I'm just going to save this file.
That's a pretty good start for our configuration.
I'm going to now create another file,
underscore TOC stands for TableOfContents.yml.
Jupyter Book has some flexibility about how you build
your TableOfContents and how that left nav bar is going to show up,
and how the hierarchy works and some of that.
We're going to, well,
I've already made the choice about the structure that we're going to use.
We're going to use parts to organize chapters.
So again, I can copy this or click my little copy button.
I go back to my code and paste that in.
So right now, these are all placeholder pages.
We don't have these pages, but that's fine.
Let's save this and we'll come back and edit
them when we have some real content to start adding.
All right. The last thing I want to add right now is an index page.
So within this docs folder,
we can add index.
Here, you can choose your format.
I think most folks are going to want to choose Markdown.
That's what I like. But if you wanted it to be
a Jupyter Notebook to be your main page,
you could do that, index.ipynb.
It could be restructured text,
it could be all different formats that are supported here.
But since it's Markdown,
I'm going to use Markdown syntax to give it a title.
So that's single hash there.
I'm going to just call it home page,
really original high-quality content.
I'm not even going to add any text,
but what I am going to do is add a special feature here.
I have triple back ticks.
If you're familiar with code blocks in a lot of Markdown editors,
you'll see the triple back ticks,
you'll be familiar with that.
I'm going to open my curly braces there.
There's a special syntax we can use to add a table of contents.
All one word.
Close the curly braces.
Then close our triple back ticks.
So this is a feature that's going to tell Jupyter Book to go
into the table of contents from this page,
and this is our home page,
so it's the top level,
and go grab all the pages below it from the table of contents file,
and put them into this table of contents on this page.
So by using this,
our table of contents is always updated on the main page.
It always stays updated.
We don't have to manually add and subtract pages from there.
It's some automation.
So it doesn't look like very much here on the screen,
just a couple of lines of code.
But as we add more pages,
we're going to see the full table of contents can be realized.
Give me a green sticky if you're with me.
Pink sticky if you have a question or need a minute.
Any question or can I help with something?
All right.
What else can I help with?
A lot of green stickies out there. Cool.
Now we're going to add some real content.
We're going to add some narrative content.
There's all kinds of different documentation content that we can add.
But having something that's beyond just the technical doc string,
signature documentation can be super useful.
Something that is really human readable,
something that really explains things.
So that's what we're going to build now, a couple of guides.
So inside of our docs folder,
we're going to create a guides folder. Sorry.
The first file I'm going to create inside guides is another Markdown file,
install.Markdown or install.MD.
Let's take a couple of seconds.
You can write whatever you want.
That tells somebody how to install the randomly package.
The title that we give it is going to be the title that shows up in
the left nav bar of the Jupiter book.
So you generally want to keep it a little bit shorter.
It'll just read it directly from this Markdown and populate it from there.
You can have as much fun with your Markdown as you'd like.
I'm also going to add just for fun, a little tip.
So these are those call-out boxes.
They're called admonitions in the parlance,
where you see caution or warning or note.
Tip is one that you can add.
You can have your own custom type.
But I'm going to add a tip here that'll show up in the call-out box.
It's not the most useful or complicated docs,
but the actual writing part,
thinking about what is going to be a good thing to write in
your documentation takes a lot of thought and I don't have
the capacity to put in that thought right now.
It takes time to make really, really good docs.
This tip is not pure Markdown exactly.
Yeah. There's actually a couple of different ways to specify these admonitions.
But these are a feature of some of the underlying missed
in the executable books project and there's
a few layers here that add these extra features on top.
There's some other features.
Maybe on the next break,
I recommend going to the Jupyter Book documentation,
or I'll pull it up on the next break and you can look at some of
the extra special kinds of customization you can do to make it look really nice.
We're only going to super just scratch the surface here.
Green stickies? Any pink stickies out there? Wave them.
Thank you. I saw one person wave them.
I appreciate it. All right.
Let's move on and build a Jupyter Notebook.
So I have an install guide.
Now we're going to create a guide to
the module that you were working with before.
Just a how-to. What's it for?
What's it going to do? Something like that.
So I'm going to use the points module.
I call this points.ipynb.
My editor has a Jupyter Notebook thing built in, VS Code does.
I think PyCharm does as well.
Somebody verify that for me?
Okay. Some editors may not.
If you need some help launching that,
if you've installed Jupyter should have been
installed with the requirements that we installed.
So you should be able to launch Jupyter Notebook,
but if you haven't done that before,
I can help you make that happen.
So when I create this file,
it's going to create a Jupyter Notebook interface for me.
For those who haven't used Jupyter Notebooks,
you can have a code cell.
This one's a Python code cell.
You can have Markdown code cells.
There's other types of code cells or other types of cell,
Markdown code. Markdown cells.
There's other types of cells that you can have,
but we don't have to get into all of that here.
For our purposes, we're just going to mix Markdown and Python.
Now, you could do all of this in a Markdown file by
using those three backticks and saying Python,
and then specifying your Python there.
The really cool thing is that
Jupyter Book knows how to run a Notebook.
So when you build your book,
it will actually run the Notebook,
or you can tell it not to do that if you don't want to,
but we're going to run the Notebook so that it will update the content.
It'll maybe you have outputs or graphs or something like that in
your documentation.
Let's say you have some function that makes a plot,
and you document that in your Notebook.
Then later on, you change
that function so that the plot looks a little bit different.
But you just need to rebuild
your docs and you'll get the new version of the plot in your documentation.
So that's where this Notebook format can be really handy,
and a little bit more familiar for a lot of
folks that are used to seeing those outputs.
You can get a lot of the dynamic outputs that you might get from
a Jupyter Notebook like
a IPy leaflet map or things like that.
So if you know what those are.
For our purposes, we're going to keep it pretty simple.
We do need to give it a,
we're going to start with a markdown cell,
and give it a title because it needs a title.
Guide to points.py module.
Yes.
Are you using VS code?
You could drag it.
You might have to drag it down.
You might have to drag the Python one down.
You can also do if you click outside of a cell, like right here.
You can hit A, keyboard shortcut to create one above,
B to create one below.
It's a game changer if you use Notebooks a lot.
But here, I'm going to actually import my module.
So from randomly.points import generate.points.
I can run it. It works.
Check that out. Because we've written our doc string and everything,
we've added the type annotations.
Our editor is now aware of all of that and knows,
can parse it and give it to us in our visualization here.
Another value of writing that stuff.
So I'm going to give it some dummy bounds.
Come on. It's not used to zooming in so much.
I think that should be reasonable.
Let's assign this to a variable, points.
I can do points.shape.
So now, I have a little bit of code.
This is an example of how the function can run.
What I might want to do now is go in between and say,
give a more human readable prose version of what I just did.
I might say something like the function accepts arguments for the bounds
of a triangular bounding box.
A rate to use in generating plus on distribution.
What I write doesn't really matter right now.
So I want you to try to do that for whichever module you picked out.
One that you were working with before.
Try to write a little Jupyter notebook guide.
Does anybody need help opening Jupyter?
All right, folks.
More questions?
I'm going to keep moving along.
We can fast forward through our Git branches if you're still struggling with this.
We're going to keep moving on this and then we'll fast forward when you get through this section
and you'll have everything there for you.
Just briefly to connect the dots between, I guess, what's pulling from what.
Okay.
So in terms of environments and packages.
In terms of how we've created like key built notebook,
but when you open the notebook,
it shows basically open up a directory of the file under the guide.
So we know we missed something and I'm not sure where,
but that's what makes me wonder.
Okay. So I'm editing this notebook file inside of VS Code.
VS Code has its own engine for doing Jupyter notebooks.
It's a convenience thing.
You can run and edit Jupyter notebooks from the original Jupyter,
Jupyter Lab client and as long as they get saved back to the same directory in that guides folder,
you should be able to in Jupyter Lab open up that directory and create a new notebook there.
That's fine as well.
What's going to happen is that when it comes to building our book,
we need to have an environment with Jupyter in it.
Okay. It's a dependency of Jupyter Book.
So if you install Jupyter Book appropriately, you'll have Jupyter.
So that's the key bit is that in the environment where you build the book,
you have that engine,
the Jupyter engine behind the scenes that can run that notebook.
If you didn't get the notebook written,
that's fine. We'll fast forward through that part in a little bit.
What was the more important thing about the book?
Whereabouts? Oh, that is just my VS Code.
Do you have a cell in there that returns the dot-term?
I don't have a cell in there. This is just a pop-up.
Oh, so in Jupyter Notebooks,
you can have a markdown cell,
you can have a code cell.
So this is a markdown cell.
So we have those.
Now we're going to add them to our table of contents.
I go back to my table of contents.
You remember we didn't edit this before,
it's just the one that comes default with Jupyter Book.
So I'm going to change my caption here.
I'm going to call this section the guides,
and chapters are the different pages that go in there.
So the path to my first file is going to be guides slash install,
and I don't put the markdown there.
Again, Jupyter Book is quite smart at figuring out
what formats it's looking at and can handle many of them.
So you actually don't even need to specify the file format for that page.
So I'm going to guides install,
and here I'm going to say guides,
I think I called mine points.
Points is in a .ipynb file,
but again, we don't need to specify that, it doesn't care.
We can nest them a little further if we wanted to,
if you have more stuff, but I'm not going to do that.
So I'm going to get rid of that other boilerplate at the bottom.
Your table of contents should look something like this.
Now is the moment of truth.
We are going to go to our terminal,
and from our repo directory,
we're going to run this command.
So I'm in my documenting your code folder,
Jupyter-book, build.
I'm going to tell it where to look for the configuration file.
That's what it's going to look at first,
the configuration in the table of contents files.
That's in the docs folder.
Cross your fingers. Boom, something happened.
That went really fast because we don't have a lot of content in there.
All right. So we can look at this real fast.
Tells us where it's finding the config,
tells us where it's putting the built files,
that we're running Sphinx under the hood.
It's kind of walking on the left side of the screen.
It's using Mist to parse this.
It's building things into HTML, reads our sources,
it finds a couple of errors,
and then it finds something that my points file doesn't have a title.
But it did still build something.
At the end of our build,
we have a file path.
That's the local place where the built HTML is stored.
So let's stop there everybody.
If you try that Jupyter Book Build Docs,
put a green sticky up once you've done that.
We'll consider it successful if you get to this part with the output.
So your build can succeed
even if everything inside of it didn't work out perfectly.
The thing is if you make changes to one of the pages in your documentation,
you have to rebuild it.
You do have to rebuild it,
but depending on how you configure that,
it will cache, Jupyter Book will cache like a run Notebook and some of
the built files and only run through the things that are newly changed.
So you get some speed up there if you have a lot of documents.
You're using Jupyter Notebooks.
The default action for Jupyter Book is to actually run your Notebook,
like it's executing it from top to bottom when you build the docs.
If you don't want it,
there are ways to specify,
don't run this particular cell or sometimes what I do is,
I want to run my Notebook myself,
get the outputs that I want to be there and then freeze it.
You can tell it not to run the actual,
not to execute the Notebook.
That's in the config file.
There's something about execute and you can turn
off auto execution and there's a couple of different options there.
But if you turn that off,
then it will only just build what's there without actually executing it with Python.
If you make changes to what?
No, it will cache by default.
It will cache things that haven't changed.
It will only rebuild the new files.
You can mess with that behavior,
the caching behavior as well.
When it's executing your Notebook,
it's running the version of Jupiter that you have in your environment.
So hopefully, you're using a virtual environment or
a condom environment or something,
then it's going to use that Jupiter, whatever is live.
That's a good question.
In my case, I had to run a Docker container,
but it's a Jupiter server because I'm having WSL issues.
But I would like to point it to that Docker container right now.
That's a good question. You could,
I mean you could mount the files into your container,
and run it from interactively in the container.
If the volume is mounted,
then you'll get the files back out outside the container.
Where am I putting what? Great question.
So we're going to get there in a few minutes.
So I'm going to come back to your question. That's a good question.
The question was, if you're not running an open source project,
where do you host your built Jupiter book stuff?
That can be somewhat of a complicated system,
but we'll talk about that.
I want to get through one more thing before we go to break.
So again, after this section,
we can fast forward if you've had trouble building,
we can fast forward to your repo.
We're going to dip our toes into the Sphinx extension universe.
The three that we're going to use,
they're very common ones.
You'll see the AutoDoc extension,
the Napoleon extension,
and the view code extension.
So AutoDoc is going to take those docstrings we
wrote and turn them into that nicely formatted parameters,
and all that nice API reference documentation
that you're probably used to seeing.
Napoleon is going to read NumPy,
or actually it'll read NumPy or Google style docstrings.
I think Napoleon is now built into Sphinx.
It used to be that you had to install it separately,
but I think it's built in now
because so many folks are using it.
Before that, you had to either install Napoleon or
use that restructured textile we saw before.
View code was that feature I showed at the beginning where when we
see the API reference for a function,
function signature, you can click source and view the raw code.
I like that feature.
Some people may not want that in there,
but you don't want people to see how messy your code is under the hood.
But I think it's useful.
So we're going to use those three.
First, we need to add an AutoDoc template.
I'm going to create an API folder under docs.
So docs API.
I'm going to close some other things.
Now, you're going to pick your demo module,
whichever one you were using,
facts or palette or points or password.
We're going to create a that module name.rst file.
So I'm going to create under API.
So I'm going to create points.rst.
So we are going to use restructured text after
all after I said how tricky it can be to work with.
So now I have a restructured text file,
and I want you to copy this syntax here that's on the bottom right.
I'm going to read it out in case that might help people seeing it in the back.
This is restructured text, pure restructured text.
So a top-level title is specified with your title and then equal signs below it.
So in this case, our title is going to be the name of our module,
randomly.facts or randomly.points.
No file extension there.
Yeah. It's actually just going to be a string.
You could name it a whole bunch of things.
This is arbitrary. You can name it whatever you want.
This is. Let's see.
Then below it, any number of equal signs.
I think maybe you need three or something like that.
I'm going to skip a line and here's some classic restructured text.
We're going to do dot, dot, space,
auto module, colon, colon, space,
the name of your module, randomly.whatever.
This is not arbitrary.
You need to give it the real name of the module in your package.
Now at the same level of indent as auto module,
we're going to do this members,
undock members and show inheritance.
I think I got that right.
It should look something like that.
Now if you wanted to document all four modules,
you could create this exact same file just swapping out that last points thing,
and you'll get the same results.
You'll be able to get the same thing for every module.
Any pink stickies?
All right. So we've added this.
It's really boilerplate because you can change out some of these things.
You can look in the documentation for
AutoDoc to see what each of those is actually doing.
In our case, we don't need to worry about that,
but there are options to include private functions or exclude private functions.
Sphinx is so powerful.
You can do so much with it.
But we're not going to touch that complexity.
Now we need to add something to
our configuration to tell it to use those extensions.
I'm going to go back to my configuration file.
Under Sphinx, extra extensions.
I'm going to open a new line here.
Sphinx.ext.AutoDoc and Sphinx.ext.Napoleon,
and Sphinx.ext.ViewCode.
Those are the three that we wanted.
Make sure you save that .rst file too.
So now I have a list here in my YAML file of each of these extensions.
Green stickies, any pink stickies?
I'm going to leave that up.
I'm going to open my table of contents so we can keep moving.
This time I'm going to add a new section, a new caption.
I'm going to call it API reference.
My chapters.
This is a really killer feature.
I can glob for files here.
So I can glob for API star.
So now we will grab anything in that API folder that we have.
So I never have to change my table of
contents when I add a new module to my code.
I just need to add that RST file to
the API folder and Jupyter Book will snatch it up when it builds.
So glob, if you're not familiar,
is a Linux thing to search,
to find, I don't know how to describe it.
Find files with patterns.
Find things with patterns.
Yeah, in this case we're using a wild card.
But there's all kinds of complicated glob syntax you can use.
How are we doing? Does everybody have that?
Show me a pink sticky if you're still working on something.
All right. We did that.
Let's build it again.
So if you were able to build it before,
hopefully you will be able to build it again.
Make sure everything's saved.
We build our docs.
I fixed my errors,
so I don't get any errors anymore.
I'm going to highlight that code path.
Now we'll see a couple of things happen.
We have our table of contents is being auto-generated,
because we added that little thing on the homepage.
So it's being updated.
Over here, our API reference has this section points,
and we have our nicely built documentation from our doc string.
That's the end of level two.
So you're welcome to keep moving on that.
But otherwise, let's take a break, I think.
Let's take a 10-minute break.
We can be back here at 4.15.
I got 4.05 right now,
so let's be back here at 4.15.
I can help you finish up if you,
or if you want to fast forward,
I can help you with that as well.
All right, folks. It is time.
I want to keep moving so that we can try to get through
the big things and have something built by the end of the hour.
So now we're on to level three.
If you want to fast forward your code and everything,
you can check out to level two,
the level two branch.
Close all these.
I'm sure there's some conflicts or something like that.
I'm just going to ignore them.
Now I have fast forwarded to my level two,
and I have some API docs for all of the different modules here.
You can do that if you like.
But in any case, we're going to work with GitHub actions and GitHub pages.
These are not the only way to host your book.
Your book, when it builds,
it spits out HTML.
So anything that can render HTML and
host HTML is somewhere you can put your book.
You can configure an AWS S3 bucket to be a website,
and you can just send your built docs up there to
AWS S3 and you get a super long complicated URL.
But that's great, especially for internal projects.
If you want to put something in there,
you can manage security through your AWS stuff.
When it comes to private projects and GitHub pages,
there are now, I think a couple of years ago,
GitHub allowed pages to be available for private repos,
maybe only on enterprise GitHub.
So if you're, anybody work for GitHub?
That's something to confirm.
But if you are on an enterprise GitHub,
you can definitely, I've done this,
you can create a private page
that works just like the rest of GitHub pages.
So this workflow would work for that.
What we're going to do today is going to make it public to
the world but there are ways to make it private.
You can ultimately send these built docs wherever you want.
So GitHub actions.
GitHub actions are a CI-CD tool to automate things.
You can do a lot with GitHub actions.
I saw in the pre-survey quite a few folks have worked
with GitHub actions at some level.
You might run your tests,
you might run linting,
you might do your builds,
your deployments of code all from GitHub actions.
If you use GitLab,
GitLab CI-CD is very similar process.
Jenkins, I think Travis,
there's a whole bunch of tools like that out there
that do similar kinds of things.
But GitHub actions is nice because if you use GitHub,
it's already there for you and it
lives right where your code lives and that makes a difference.
So we're going to specify things in YAML files,
just like we've been doing with our configuration before.
We're going to write YAML files.
These days, actions have been around for four years, maybe,
five years and everything that you want to do is probably been done before.
You're not the first person to try to do it and that's really awesome.
So there's a lot of pre-built actions out there that you
can just use off the shelf without having to write the details yourself.
There's a whole world of GitHub actions that we're not going to get into.
We're going to do a pretty simple flow to build our docs and put it in GitHub pages.
You can do things like protect
your branches until certain things pass through your GitHub actions as well.
So what I like to do is you can't merge your branch until the docs have built,
or immediately upon merging your branch,
you build the docs and deploy them.
So let's add some actions.
We're just going to add one and it's this long thing on the right.
But there's a template for that.
We're going to create this directory structure first.
This is where GitHub is going to look for your actions.
So we're going to create it at the top level of our repository.
We're going to create a dot GitHub.
You need the dot GitHub.
Under that, I'm going to create a workflows folder.
Don't need a dot there.
Then inside the workflows,
you're going to create a YAML file.
You can name it whatever you want,
but I'm going to call it deploy.yaml.
Jupyter Book is well-documented and
has a template that we can use for deploying a book.
I'm going to go to that link.
It should be in the link list,
and copy the template and put it here in my YAML file.
Let's look through some things that it's doing.
We give it a name for this action,
then we have triggers.
So we want to trigger it when something happens on,
in this case, on push.
So when we push to the master or main branch,
you probably will have a main branch,
not a master branch.
So you might want to change this to main.
On push to main,
that's when this action is going to run.
So that's the trigger.
For other complicated or for
other GitHub actions that are not related to this docs,
you might want to trigger it on something else.
But push to main is where we're going to work.
Let's go down here.
We're going to do, this is a very generic pre-built action
for us that we're just going to make use of.
Let's check out an Ubuntu operating system.
We're going to install Python 3.8.
Again, this is a pre-canned action for us.
We don't have to write out all the steps to get that there.
We just say, use this action and then give it some configuration.
We're going to install our dependencies.
Then we're going to change our build directory.
We're not going to build from the top level.
We're going to use the command that we used before,
which was build docs.
That's important on line 35.
Change that.
The next thing is the real magic for taking
that built documentation and putting it onto GitHub Pages.
This is somebody who has already
built this action and written it out.
So what we do is,
it's going to look for a GitHub Pages branch.
Well, it's going to take the built documentation,
send it to the GitHub Pages branch.
That's a branch where GitHub Pages is going to
look to build itself, to build the site.
Here, we need to specify docs again in the last line, line 42.
There's one last step that we need to add to our workflow here.
We need to install randomly so that we can
run things in our Jupyter Notebooks,
so that the Jupyter Notebook can build properly.
It will need to know where randomly is.
Randomly is not in our requirements file,
so it hasn't been installed in this Ubuntu environment,
when it's running in GitHub Actions.
So to do that, we're going to
mimic the install dependencies command here.
We'll call it install randomly.
Then we're going to run colon.
The vertical bar is just a way of saying,
continue on the next line.
It's a little bit nicer formatting.
Then I'm going to pip install, period.
So we're going to install from the current directory at this point,
which is the top level of the repository.
You could do the dash E install if you wanted to,
but it's not really helpful because our module is not going to
change once it's going through this workflows,
so the editable mode doesn't help us.
All right. Show me green stickies if you're there.
Make sure to save your deploy file.
Show me pink stickies if it's
something you still need a little bit of help with.
Any other pink stickies out there?
All right. Let's see what we can do.
We're going to commit this and push it back to the GitHub repository.
Now, after you do that push,
you should go to your repository.
Yours should look something like this.
You should have your GitHub workflows here.
Your YAML file. Everybody there?
Show me any pink stickies.
All right. Now, we need to enable GitHub pages. Yeah.
In this case, you can merge it into main.
That's fine. You might have a different little bit
more cautious workflow on your own repositories,
but in this case, we're going to just merge it to main.
So once you're in your repository,
we can go to settings on top right,
and on the left side, pages.
We're going to tell it to build from the ghpages branch.
You didn't create that branch,
but the GitHub action will create it for you.
So that is a nice thing because then the built version of your docs,
all the HTML files and all of that,
doesn't end up in your main code branch,
polluting that branch a little bit,
it stays in its own isolated built branch.
We can specify the root of that branch as the GitHub pages.
If you say that again,
change it to docs. Interesting.
Let's see how others did.
So if you save that,
this should turn something.
This green box should change color or it'll
say your site is ready to be published or something like that maybe.
Thanks, Dicky.
I want everyone to go to the Actions tab,
and see what happened.
See if it failed.
Raise your hand if you got a successful build.
There were some successful builds out there.
If it's successful,
you should have a green box around the link,
and your link should open to your built documentation on the web.
Pretty nifty, right? But obviously, not everybody got there.
So let's see what we can do.
Let's see if we can get it to work.
Thanks, Dickies.
Flag me down.
Interesting.
Yeah, it's writing to that new branch, to that GitHub Pages branch.
All right, folks, I want to, we have 15 minutes left, so I want to get, make sure we cover everything.
We have covered all the steps to building something on the web.
Oh yeah, I have a slide for that.
So the last thing I want to add on top of all the things we've built so far is extras.
So one thing, one feature that we get with Jupiter Book is when we have notebooks,
we can turn them into something that is runnable on the internet pretty easily.
How many people have used binder or MyBinder before with a notebook?
Okay. Binder is really cool.
I'm not going to go into the details of it,
but really you can configure it in your config.yaml file.
I'm going to use the version that I have already configured.
So in the points module,
if I come up to this rocket ship,
I've configured it to look in binder.
It was just a couple of those parameters in our config file.
I can show you which ones in particular if you're curious.
But what it's going to do is launch binder,
which is going to dockerize our repo.
There's a tool called repo2docker.
It's really cool that dockerizes our repo and then installs some,
if it finds requirements file and it finds a setup file,
it will install stuff and that's what it's doing right now.
Then ultimately, it's going to launch a live Jupiter Notebook version
of the static Jupiter Notebook that we had in our docs.
So this is a cool way if you want to have
a tutorial that people can also interact with,
can change some parameters on.
Sometimes you might have widgets in there
that you want them to mess around with.
There's a lot of cool things you can do with this.
Ultimately, it's Kubernetes and Docker and everything under the hood.
Wait for it. It's going to launch.
Almost there. If you did it again,
like subsequent times, it will do it much faster.
Because the Docker container will have already,
the Docker image will have already been built. Yeah.
I'm just thinking about the private repository.
You have to have rights to the repository or to the page.
So is the authentication on your GitHub all right?
Yeah. That's the magical thing that GitHub figured out,
is just running all the auth to get to the page through the GitHub auth.
I have no idea how any of that works,
but it does work because I've done it before from private repos,
where you can build a page.
But I think you do have to have enterprise GitHub or
some non-free tier GitHub to do that.
Any other questions while this launches?
All right. We'll come back to it when it's done doing this thing.
There's a library called,
I'm going to run through these tools.
These are not tools that I use a lot,
but they're tools that are pretty nifty if you want to level up
your documentation setup in your workflows,
especially with Teams.
How many people have used the coverage tool for testing their Python code?
What it does is it goes through your code and goes through your tests and says,
okay, well, this part of your code has been touched by a test.
So ultimately, you get a report on how much of your code is covered by tests.
Imperfect measure, of course,
but it's a nice thing to have.
This is doing the same thing for docstrings.
So what we're looking at here is a report that I ran on
the randomly module or randomly package that tells us how much coverage we got.
So you notice we missed one something in every single one of our modules.
That's because according to PEP 257,
you should have a docstring at the top of the module that describes the module.
We didn't do that. I don't know how common of a practice it is or not.
I tend not to use it.
But now that I know that it's a PEP 257 thing,
maybe I will start using it a little bit more.
But that's why we got misses here.
This one's called interrogate.
The next one is py docstyle,
which is similar. How many people have used the linter flake8 to run their code?
What this does is it will look through
your docstrings and it will check for some of those best practices things.
We'll see what it flagged here.
So it flagged missing docstring in a public module.
That means I didn't have that line at the top,
so that one's going to appear every time.
The first line of your docstring should end with a period.
That's part of PEP 257 recommendations.
I failed at that a couple of times. What else?
I'm missing one here. Maybe that's it.
Oh, after your docstring,
you're not supposed to have blank lines.
I didn't know that that was an official recommendation.
But if you want to start enforcing that good patterns of documentation,
adding a tool like this to your testing or
linting things that you might be doing already in your code,
these could be part of GitHub actions.
Any of these could be incorporated there.
You could block merging a PR until all of these pass if you really want to.
It's up to you how strict you want to be with it.
But at least it gives you some insights.
Especially as your project grows,
you start getting contributions from multiple people.
These tools might give you some insight as to where you're lacking in docstrings,
or where docstring coverage is weak or needs to be improved.
I mentioned xDocTest before.
There's an older tool called doctest.
But I think xDoctest is really nice.
It integrates with PyTest. Here's how.
Let's say we have a Fibonacci function.
We create a Fibonacci series up to whatever number we give it.
As part of our docstring,
we can add an example.
We didn't do that in any of our docstrings,
but that's how you can do it.
You can add an example and you have the three arrows there,
chevrons, the three chevrons,
and then you have something that you would execute in Python.
In this case, we're calling the function and giving it a parameter.
Then on the next line after that,
we have the expected output.
You can think of this as a test,
a software test, a unit test where we say,
given this, I expect this.
What xDoctest can do is actually turn that into executable Python,
not just a string as part of the docstring,
it will turn that into executable Python and run it.
If it doesn't get this output, it'll fail.
That's pretty fun. I think it's pretty cool.
That's one way to do some regression testing on your docs.
If you try to keep your examples up to date,
that's an interesting feature.
We already talked about editor support for VS Code,
PyCharm, how you can use these tools to generate your docs for you,
or to at least generate the stubs of your documentation for you,
and make sure things are as easy and
smooth as possible when you're trying to write docstrings.
With that, I am done with everything that I have prepared.
I'm happy to take questions, thoughts.
You want some feedback on anything,
anything like that, I'm here. Thank you.
I should add, I would really love if you go out and build
some documentation to send me a message or share the GitHub repository with me.
I would love to see it. I'd love to see
what's happening and see all the cool things that you can build.
Thanks.