Good morning, everyone. I welcome all of you to the second day of PyCon US 2022. Let's
welcome Chris to deliver a talk on employing NumPy's NPOF format for faster than per-quit
data frame serialization. Over to you, Chris.
Thank you. Good morning and thank you all for coming. So a little bit about me to begin.
I am CTO at Research Affiliates. This is a finance firm located in Newport Beach, California.
I've been a Python programmer since the year 2000. And my earliest work was in music. I
have a PhD in music and I was a former professor of music technology. And I found lots of ways
to use Python in all sorts of different things like algorithmic composition and computational
musicology. In the last ten years I've been working on financial systems in Python and
that's led me to create an alternative data frame library called Static Frame. Static
Frame is based on an immutable data model, a more consistent interface than pandas and
support for all NumPy D types including Unicode strings, Daytime64 units as well.
All right. So as over those ten years building financial systems, many of you might be able
to relate to a sort of quest to find a complete data frame serialization format. And we've
tried many things from CSV, XLS, X, HDF5. Most recently Parquet has offered the best
performance and type retention. But it's not perfect. And no format supports all components
of a data frame and none support all NumPy D types. So if a data frame in Python can
be thought of as a collection of NumPy arrays, what is the best way to serialize a NumPy
array? Well for that we can go way back to 2007 to NumPy Enhancement Proposal Number
One. Now similar to PEPs, NEPs are proposals to enhance NumPy. And this one was proposed
by Robert Kern in 2007. It defines two things. It defines the NPY file which is a binary
file format that can encode all NumPy arrays and the NPZ which is simply a zip bundle of
NPY files. Now this format is still supported in NumPy. You can use it right now with NP.save,
NP.load. What's really interesting about these NPY files is we can memory map array data
with them. And that's something we're going to explore with data frames later on. So can
a data frame then be serialized as a collection of NPY files? That was sort of my first question.
And so I set off to do this. The way I first approached it was simply taking all the arrays
that are included within the data frame, package them up with an NPZ. And my first
implementation was using NPSave and NP.load. In addition, I created a special metadata
file in JSON that I packed into that NPZ to help me fully reconstruct the data frame.
And this worked, but it was slower than Parquet which was a little disappointing. Looking
into the performance of the NumPy routines, I found that if I re-implemented the NPY and
I was able to get massive performance improvements and end up with something faster than Parquet.
So I'll give you a little taste of that performance. If we use Pandas here to create a very simple
frame of 10,000 square floats and we create a data frame with that, we're going to write
this out as Parquet. But because Parquet requires that all column labels be strings, we're going
to have to convert those column labels to strings. And then we can go ahead and use
Pandas to write this data frame out as a Parquet file. And that takes about 10 and
a half seconds. Now, if we do build a corresponding frame in static frame and we export it, we
write it out as an NPZ, that takes 1.42 seconds, nearly an order of magnitude better performance
for writing out this very, very simple frame. What about reading? Well, we can read in that
same Parquet again using Pandas, reading in that Parquet file. We can read it into a Pandas
data frame in about five seconds. If we do the same thing from an NPZ using static frame,
we can do it in about one second. Not an order of magnitude, but a very significant improvement.
All right. So what we're going to do today is we're going to look at the components of
a data frame in detail. We're going to look at the NPY and NPZ format to get a sense of
how we can use these. We're going to talk about how we encode a data frame in an NPZ.
We'll talk about a few of the things I did to improve NPY performance. We'll look at
some very thorough performance comparisons. And finally, we'll close by talking about
how we can use the NPY now to actually memory map a complete data frame. After this presentation,
I hope you gain a clear understanding of data frames and how they're built. You'll also
understand NPY encoding, and you'll leave here with more options for serializing and
memory mapping data frames. So let's look at the components of a data frame in depth.
Now the first data frame was introduced back in 1991 as part of the S language. They've
been around for a long time, and many libraries and many languages have implemented data frames.
There is really no standard for a data frame, but what I'm going to provide for you is how
static frame defines a frame. And you can think of this as a slight superset over the
pandas data frame. So many of you probably worked with data frames, but it's important
to remember what they are. And they are not a two-dimensional array. A two-dimensional
array has uniform type and access to rows and columns only by integer. With a data frame,
we get the opportunity to have a table of columnar data where columns have heterogeneous
types. And we can label our rows and columns and access them with things other than integers.
Our labels can be any type. Our labels can be hierarchical. And those hierarchical depths
themselves can have different types. In addition, data frames have name attributes attached
to the rows, the columns, and the frame itself. And these name attributes give us a really
to either have an additional label or rich metadata attached to those components. Now,
I created this schematic diagram of a data frame to help us talk through how we are going
to encode this entire data frame. And what I'm showing here are the array components
in gray rectangles, the array types in the gray diamonds, the black diamonds are the
component types for the index and the columns, and the black circles are the component names
for columns, index, and the frame itself. Now, we're going to see this a lot, so I'll
help you understand it as we go. But before we do that, I want to compare that representation
to the representation of static frames, standard repr of a data frame. You'll notice this is
a richer representation than Panda's representation of a data frame, because in static frame,
we're very concerned about our types. We want to always show our users what types we have
at hand. And I'm going to relate this representation to what we were looking at previously. So
here I've highlighted in orange and yellow the values of the data frame. So we can think
of this as four or actually two arrays of first integers and then booleans. This is
the data in our data frame, and we can see it in both representations here. In blue gray
here, I'm showing the arrays of the columns, and we can see that we have two arrays that
represent the columns in this case, the hierarchical columns. I have two arrays also representing
the index here. And then finally in purple, I have the additional stuff, the types of
the index and the columns and the name attributes. And if we bring that all together, you can
see the correspondence between these two representations. We're going to see this frame diagram come
back, so you'll get used to it as we go forward. Now, an important part of how data frames
work is that they manage internal array stores called blocks. Block structure might deviate
from the actual column presentation. So what you see when you're working with the data
is not how the data is actually stored. And that's important because in consolidating
same type data into fewer blocks, we get better performance. In essence, we can do more in
NumPy and that will give us better performance. So there's maybe three block consolidation
strategies. We could have unconsolidated blocks where each column is a one-dimensional array.
Or we could have order-dependent block consolidation where adjacent same-typed columns can be consolidated
into two-dimensional blocks. Finally, we could have order-independent blocks where
all columns are consolidated into a 2D block per type. So I know that's a lot. So this
diagram here should help you understand what we're talking about. So on the left-hand side,
we have the represented values. Here you see a data frame that has a couple of columns
of integers, booleans and floats. You just see one type per column. But the blocks might
be constructed differently. On the right-hand side, we see these three options where we
have unconsolidated blocks, maybe one-dimensional array for each column. Order-dependent block
consolidation combines adjacent columns into larger two-dimensional arrays. Order-independent
blocks disregards order and simply consolidates column data by type. So this block consolidation
has trade-offs in terms of performance and complexity. So order-independent consolidation
as used by Pandas gives the opportunity for optimal type consolidation but requires more
complexity because we have to translate from those blocks to the representation that the
user sees. Order-dependent consolidation as used by StaticFrame is suboptimal in some
cases. We can't consolidate everything. But this gives us less complexity and, as we'll
see later on, improves our serialization performance because we don't have to do that translation
from the consolidated blocks. All right. I'm talking about complete data frame serialization.
So we'll talk a little bit about what that is. Now, no legacy format except Pickle supports
all data frame characteristics. And I really mean all characteristics. So generally, there's
some sort of limits on the array data types. There may not be a perfect mapping of your
array types into your serialization format. There's often limits, as we've already seen
in Parquet, on what the types of the columns and index can be. And there's often very limited
support for those name attributes, which, while not that important, can be really annoying
to not have come back and forth from your serialization. Now, Pickle, in many cases,
is the fastest at reading and writing data frames. We can always Pickle a data frame
in Pandas or StaticFrame. But Pickle is not really safe as a long-term store. As I hope
all of you know, untrusted code can be executed in a Pickle. And Pickle is not suitable for
long-term storage. A Pickle can hold on to references of objects that are no longer available,
and you can end up pretty easily with broken Pickles. So complete data frame serialization
needs to encode all the values and types. And encode all index and columns labels. We
need to support hierarchical labels. We need to support heterogeneous types per label depth.
And we need to get those name attributes. So I want to make clear that Parquet is not
a data frame. Parquet came out of the Apache Hadoop system and was designed for cross-platform
cross-language support. It is really a table implemented as unconsolidated columnar data.
And it's great for that purpose. It has very sophisticated mechanisms for handling large
data sets and rich metadata. But importantly, it's not a data frame. So we shouldn't be surprised
that we lose information in translating back and forth to Parquet. So let's take a deep dive into
NPY and the NPZ format. So the NPY format is a binary file format. What we have here is a header
followed by a payload of contiguous bytes. Now in order to translate contiguous bytes into an
array, we need three things for Numpy. We need the D type, which is going to tell us the bytes per
element. We need the order. Is it Fortran, column major, or C, row major style, two-dimensional or
larger array. And we need some specification of the shape of that data frame. So here's a little
example. You can do this on your own of going back and forth between bytes. Here I have a simple
three-element array of Booleans. And I can call the two-bytes method, which from any Numpy array
will give me the contiguous byte representation behind that array. And I can translate that back
into array by using here the from buffer constructor. I need to specify the D type. We need to tell
Numpy how to interpret those bytes. But as you can see, we get back the array that we started with.
So back to NPY. So an NPY file consists of a header and a series of contiguous bytes. In the
header, we have a number of things. We have what's called the magic prefix, which is a binary string
that has a special binary character and Numpy right there. So you know what you're looking at.
It has two bytes to provide the version number. And then it has the byte count of the remaining
header so that a consumer of this file knows how many bytes to read before we get to the contiguous
byte data. The remaining header has a binary encoding of a three-element Python dictionary.
And that dictionary is going to tell us the D type description string, whether it's Fortran order or
C order, and the shape of the array. We're going to have a little bit of padding there so we can
align at 64 byte divisions. So this diagram makes clear the structure of the NPY. We have the magic
prefix in purple. We have the version number in green. And we have the padded header length,
again telling us how far we need to read to get the rest of the header. The header here of the
array is given in orange. And we see that's an encoding of a Python dictionary to tell us how
to interpret that contiguous byte data. We have a little bit of padding. And then we have the
contiguous byte data, which you should recognize now as that same Boolean array we started with
consisting of false, true, and true. Now, the original NPY implementation supports object
arrays through pickling. But for our purposes, we're going to reject supporting object arrays
and pickles in our data frames. Even if we just have only one array that's an object, any pickle
compromises the safety and long-term storage of this format. So we're just not going to use it.
And if you need to encode object arrays, you're better off just using pickle, just pickle your
data frame and you'll be fine. Now, I mentioned that NPY supports many versions. These versions
aren't deprecated. They're a different kind of versioning system. So all versions are currently
supported. And if you use NP.save right now, it writes at the minimum version necessary. So very
likely you'll get a version one NPY if you use this. These versions are differentiated by the
available header size and the encoding. And versions two and three are really only there for structured
arrays. We don't need structured arrays for what we're doing. So we can just stick with version one.
Now, I mentioned that this nep one defined NPY and NPZ. So what is the NPZ? Well, the NPZ is very
simple. It's just a zip bundle of the NPY files. The original specification provides no standard
naming or no metadata file. In my work here, that is what we have added. You can write these with
NP.savez and we can read them with NP.load. And if you do this, you get back a dict-like interface
that allows you to get at your NPY files. Okay, so how do we encode a data frame as an NPZ? So what
we're going to do is we're going to create an uncompressed zip. We're going to store all of our
arrays as NPY files. We're going to store our values blocks as NPY files. We're going to store
our index and columns labels as NPY files per depth. And we're going to use a common naming
convention so we can find those NPY files. And we're going to define a custom JSON metadata file
to give us all the additional information we need. So returning to the schematic that we started with,
we can see how the components of the data frame are translated into the NPZ. We'll start with the
orange and yellow values arrays. We see each of those becomes one NPY file to represent those
arrays by type. We have two blue NPY files to represent the column data, two green NPYs to
represent the index data. And finally, all the other stuff, the purple, is wrapped up in our JSON.
If we were to look into some of those NPY files, this is what we would see. And hopefully this is
familiar by now. We see a block zero and blocks one represented, and we see that same header
followed by a bunch of contiguous bytes. Now the JSON metadata file is there so that we can define
the component types and additional metadata we need to recreate our data frame. We're going to
define the component types of strings. We're going to define the depths as integers, which will allow
us to discover our NPY files. And we're going to store the name attributes as a simple JSON array.
So now we have the same diagram, but I'm showing you where we pull information into the metadata
file. So in purple, you see that we have the name information gathered into a JSON array. We have
type information stored in the green, yellow, and orange components of this little JSON object. And
then finally, we have a depth JSON array that stores the depths of each of these components so
we can unpack them later. So if you want to use this in Static Frame, all you need to do is use
our simple constructor and exporter. If you're bringing in an NPZ file, you can just say from
NPZ, and if you're writing it out, you can just say to NPZ. As I mentioned, we spent a decent
amount of time improving NPY performance. And the reason is because NP.save and NP.load are not
designed for writing thousands or hundreds of thousands of NPY files, which is what we end up
doing when we serialize a data frame this way. And NumPy's implementation priority is on
compatibility, and what we found is a more narrow implementation can offer massive performance gains.
So a couple things that we did to improve performance. We removed support for structured
arrays. We don't need them, and this allows us to write version one NPY files in a very
straightforward way. We also omit support for object arrays. A really important performance
gain was achieved by removing backwards compatibility for NPYs authored in Python 2. NumPy does some
tricky stuff in order to handle that situation, and we're just not going to support that. We also
employ some header caching to improve the speed of translating that header into Python objects. In
the context of encoding NPYs in a data frame, you're going to have a lot of headers that are
the same, and so this cache header decoding really helps us improve our performance. Okay,
I've claimed that this format is faster than Parquet. We've seen a little bit of example,
but let's dive into some greater details of this. So we're going to look at a number of benchmarks,
reading and writing data frames, and we're going to use Pandas to read and write a data frame to
Parquet. We're going to do it both with the snappy compression, which is the default in Pandas,
as well as no compression. And then we're going to use static frame to read and write both NPZ and
pickle files. Pickle gives us another benchmark on the other end there. Now, of course, OS and
hardware affect performance of file systems operations like these, but I've tried this on a
few OSs and it seems to be pretty robust. Most importantly, shape and D-type heterogeneity
matter. Too often I see performance benchmarks of data frames where they just have done something
with one data frame, but the shape of the data frame and the underlying D-type heterogeneity
really matter. So we're going to look at performance across a million elements and a hundred million
elements in various shapes and D-type configurations. And I generated those values using a package
called frame fixtures, which allows me to easily generate a variety of frames. So we're going to
explore three shape ratios. So the shape matters in how a data frame can perform. We're going to
look at tall shapes, square shapes, and wide shapes. And we're going to look at three types
of D-type heterogeneity. We're going to look at columnar, where we have one D-type per column
with no block consolidation, mixed D-type heterogeneity. We have two pairs out of five
that are consolidated and uniform D-type heterogeneity, where we have one block that
can represent all of the data. So when I present these nine benchmarks, we're going to see them
in this presentation. So I just want you to get a sense of it before you see all these graphs.
We're going to have the shape variations across the columns, tall, square, and wide,
and we're going to have the D-type heterogeneity along the rows, columnar, mixed, and uniform.
Okay, so let's look at read performance. I know there's a lot of information here,
so I'll try to help you out with it. In dark blue, we have parquet with compression. In purple,
we have parquet without compression. In magenta, we have NPZ. And in orange, we have pickle. So
we see right away that pickle's very fast. Okay, that's our first observation. Notice that NPZ
in magenta is faster than parquet with and without compression in all cases here. And as the data
gets more uniform, as we go down, we see that NPZ performance increases. Notice also that with
the compression sometimes reduces parquet performance. That's going to be relevant when
we look at the trade-off in sizes, in file size on disk. Now, if I scale this to 100 million elements,
and we do the same examination, we see the outperformance of NPZ continues. And we see now
that the compressed parquet always underperforms the uncompressed parquet. And I want you to keep
that in mind when we look at file sizes. There's one case where that's not true.
But notice again here, lower is better in all these graphs, that NPZ in magenta is significantly
outperforming reading parquet. Now, what about writing? Well, here, NPZ does really well.
We see again in magenta NPZ, that bar is always lower than parquet. And again, lower is better
here. And we see NPZ writing in a few cases even outperform pickle, those tiny little lines there
at the bottom. So this is a really exciting observation. And this similarly scales to 100
million elements, where again, NPZ again in magenta, lower is better, continuously outperforms
parquet in writing out complete data frames. So what about file size? Well, we have to consider
compression when we consider file size. Parquet supports many types of compressions. And that's a
really fantastic feature of parquet. At this point, we're not doing any compression on our NPYs.
And we're not even using compressed zips, because that degrades our performance. Even without any
compression, NPZ size compares favorably, which is very interesting. NPZ is always smaller than
parquet without compression. But when NPZ is larger, it's generally not more than 25% larger than parquet
with compression. Okay, so here's a similar chart of the resultant file size on disk of NPZ,
parquet, and pickle. Again, parquet is in dark blue with compression, purple without compression. And
right away, we see that the compression works. Compression is always smaller. Notice also the NPZ
in magenta is sometimes always smaller than uncompressed, sometimes even smaller than the
compressed parquet. And that's a really interesting observation. Now, as we scale this to 100 million
elements, we see the benefit of parquet compression. Now, compressed parquet files are always smaller
than the corresponding NPZ file. But the NPZ file is still always smaller than the uncompressed parquet.
Now, we do get a smaller file size with parquet, but if you remember our performance numbers,
the compressed parquet read-write performance performed very poorly at this scale. So there's
trade-offs in compression, as I'm sure you're aware. Now, what about memory mapping these data
frames? So a memory map is a segment of virtual memory assigned a byte-for-byte correlation to
the bytes in a file. And for large files, this can increase read performance significantly and
can permit an incremental lazy loading of data into RAM. So how do we memory map an array? Just
so we have an array, what can we do? Well, we can use the standard library's M map to create an
instance from the bytes in the body of the NPY file. And then we can simply hand that M map to
an ND array constructor as the data buffer for the array. So let's do that. We're going to create
a simple binary file, and we're going to put the three bytes that hopefully you know by now
into that file. We're going to open that file back up as binary. We're going to give it to
our memory map, and that's all we need to do. We can create an ND array with that memory map
as the buffer, and we have a memory mapped array. So we can do that with our NPYs, but we can't use
a zip anymore. What we need to do is write all of our NPYs to the file system, and Static Frame
offers an exporter to do that. You simply say to NPY. We're going to give it a directory, and we're
going to fill that directory with NPY files. To get the memory map file back into memory,
we're going to use a specialized constructor that's going to give us back two things. It's
going to give us back a frame and a special function we need to close the memory maps after
we're done with them. So this gives us some overhead in working with memory map data frames.
We have to lay out everything on the file system, and we must remember to close those memory maps.
But even so, we can get even better performance. So NPY at the scale of 100 million elements
always outperforms NPZ, and we see, well, it just drops off the chart here, outperforming
Pickle itself in reading in a data frame, which is a very exciting result. So memory mapping a
data frame provides significant benefits in read performance, often being faster than NPZ, maybe
always, and offering better memory performance. And this is really enabled by Static Frame,
in part because the NPY structure is identical to the blocks, and those blocks are
adjacently consolidated, meaning we don't have to do any translation to get at that underlying data.
Furthermore, unlike Pandas, Static Frame has an immutable data model, and because it's a
mutable data model, we can memory map all of that array data into our frame, and we can take
views of that memory map data without forcing premature copies, which means we can keep our
memory map data and use it for quite a long time before having to make any copies.
All right, current state and future work. These NPY, NPZ, read, write routines are fully implemented
in Static Frame. We're already widely using them in production and have observed very significant
performance benefits converting from using Parquet to using NPY and NPZ. As mentioned,
you can export and import these NPZs with constructors and exporters with names that
should be familiar to you. If you want to go to an NPY, a directory of all of this data,
there's similar exporters and constructors. And finally, we saw the special NPY M-Map constructor
that allows you to memory map a complete NPY from NPYs on your file system. If you're using Pandas,
you can use this right away. You can simply convert from Pandas to Static Frame, write out
your NPZ, or do the same in reverse. Use Static Frame to read your NPZ and then convert it to
Pandas. Now, Pandas has drifted away from NumPy a little bit, so if you're using Pandas data frame
features that aren't part of NumPy, you're not going to be able to do this. But for very common
NumPy D types, this will work perfectly well. In the future, there's a few more optimizations
we have to explore to further increase the performance of reading and writing these
NPY and NPZ files. And we might explore NPY compression as we saw the benefits of compression
for very large data frames is potentially valuable. All right, so I hope you've gained a good
understanding of data frames and how they are built. I hope now you have a clear understanding of how
this 14-year-old encoding mechanism works and how we can redeploy it now to produce something
that's actually materially faster than the so-called gold standard of data encoding.
And I hope you leave here with more options for serializing and, in fact,
memory mapping data frames than you had when you started. Thank you very much. If you'd like to
learn more about Static Frame, you can visit us here. Thank you.