Welcome to the last block of PyCon 2022. Our next talk, first talk of this block is fast
and reproducible tests, packaging and deploys with Pants builds hermetic environments by
Christopher Neugebauer. Go ahead and take it away.
Thank you very much, Mason. Hello. My name is Christopher Neugebauer. I work as an engineer
at Toolchain. I'm also a maintainer on the Pants build open source project. Feel free
to tweet me at the handle on the bottom of this slide. If you can't see it just yet,
it will be at the top in just a moment. If you want to loudly disagree with me during
the talk, I don't mind. If you have legitimate questions, you can send them to me by email.
Today's talk is about hermetic environments, which is an approach that Pants uses to make
sure that we can predictably model the tasks that run while writing and testing your code.
First up, I want to point out that this is not a security talk. A lot of the approaches
that we're going to be talking about today have tradeoffs between guaranteeing absolute
correctness on one hand and security on the other hand and delivering speedy performance.
If you have different goals, you would probably make different choices here. So the focus
of today's talk is on how reproducibility can make your build tools perform better and
what sandboxing techniques can deliver that reproducibility without sacrificing performance.
That theoretical material is going to be sandwiched in between an introduction to Pants and how
Pants actually implements these things so you can see how all this works in practice.
We're going to start the talk with a quick introduction to Pants and some of the problems
that motivate the techniques we're talking about in this talk. So Pants build is a build
system which is a bit of a holdover from compiled languages where you need to run a lot of different
programs in a very specific order in order to get your code to run at all. In our case,
we orchestrate all the tools that interact with your code. That's everything from linting
and testing all the way through to building a package for deployment or for distribution.
So even in Python where you don't have a compilation step necessarily, we can still help orchestrate
tools like my pi or my pi or linters like Flake 8 and black so you can run them more
efficiently and only have to interact with one tool to run all of them. There's a small
amount of jargon I'm going to have to get out of the way first which will hopefully
make the rest of this talk go just a bit more smoothly for you. In the build systems
community and Pants in particular, there are terms for the units of work that get run in
your development workflows. The ones that I'm going to refer to are goals, rules and
processes. Goals are things that an end user will ask Pants to do for them. That might
be something like run this test or type check the source files in this directory or package
this library. Most CI workflows, most pre-commit workflows are made up of multiple goals. Rules
are the individual steps that Pants needs to perform in order to accomplish a goal.
A rule might be something like figure out which files to give to my pi in order to run
a type checking run or figure out which source file is the entry point to a Python executable.
Goals are made out of rules and rules can themselves run more rules. And processes are
when we run the actual underlying tools that Pants is orchestrating. Processes might be
something like run pi test with these specific source files. Now, today we're talking about
Pants 2. You may have heard of Pants before. That was the old version. This is a new tool
that's inspired by the original version of Pants that was developed at Twitter 10 or
so years ago. It's a complete rebuild from the ground up by a community of open source
developers including a bunch of us who work at Toolchain. The first releases were made
very much with Python in mind. We're trying to be good members of the Python community
and we want Pants to be a great experience for Python-focused code bases of any size.
If you use Pants on a smallish Python-only code base, we sort of fit into the same category
of tools as Tox. But the goal of Pants is to be able to grow with your code base. This
means both supporting multiple languages and also being as efficient within a large base
as it is within a small code base. So the ideal world for us is for a developer to be
able to work on Scala or Go or Python code and interact with exactly the same tool commands
no matter what language they use. And we want it to be pleasant enough for you to want to
do that. And finally, we aim to make it easier to use a mono repo development workflow so
you get the configuration management and code reuse benefits that come with that but still
being as efficient and easy to reason about as a multi repo setup might be. The goal for
us is to complete your goals faster while making underlying tools. And Pants can do
things like identifying which rules can be run in parallel or it can eliminate duplicated
or unnecessary work. The idea is that as your code base scales, the work that Pants does
to configure and orchestrate your tools will be more efficient and effective than just
running those tools in their default configurations. As an example, let's say you have a test suite
with two test files in it. Pants will run your test suite. That is not surprising. If
you edit one of these two test files, Pants will only actually rerun the test file that
you edited. You can see that the reading is reused. That's what this memoized thing means.
It's still not all that surprising. Most tools can do something like this. What is surprising
though? Well, first we can revert the tests again and note that both tests are memoized
this time. Rather than just saving the most recent date of the tests, Pants has cached
both of our previous runs. Since we're running tests that we've run in the past in exactly
the same configuration, Pants will reuse those results. Now what happens if instead of changing
a test file, I change the implementation file that is under test? Again, rerun the tests
run against the implementations that changed. Everything else is cached. That is because
Pants automatically understands the dependencies in your code base through static analysis.
And it can use that information to figure out what tests need to be run again. When
you start dealing with code bases with hundreds or thousands of tests and implementation files,
automatic decisions like this mean you don't have to remember which tests are relevant
to the parts of the code base that you've changed. When you have a huge and slow test
suite, which most probably are, this can make it quite pleasant to regularly run your entire
test suite as you develop iteratively. And we can run tools more efficiently locally,
but to scale properly, we're working to properly support remote caching and remote execution.
Remote caching means that if one person on your team runs a given rule and another person
needs an identical rule completed, we can fetch that result from a cache instead of
running it again. It is surprising how often a team can run exactly the same rule over
and over and over again. It's a huge waste of time and money. So solving remote caching
means thinking about a lot of problems around how we run the underlying tools that Pants
orchestrates. Questions like what rules actually need to be run in order to finish a user's
goal. Do we split our goals into one process or several? And then once we've split up the
rules, can we test with accuracy to see if a given rule is already run? And if a rule
has already been run, can we actually reuse its output instead of running it again? All
these boil down to one question. How do we make sure that the end result of a rule is
reliably reproducible? Can we be confident that if we reuse a result from a previous run,
the combined end result is actually going to be valid? If we can run rules and be confident
that running the same rule again will yield exactly the same result, then we don't need to
run those rules again. Which leads us to our first concept. Reproducibility. Reproducibility
is the idea that if you run the same rule, you will end up with the same result. It seems like
a simple enough concept, but there's enough of a sticking point that I'm going to need to talk a
bit about what we mean by the same. The elephant in the room here is this thing called reproducible
builds, which you may have heard of if you work in open source. Reproducible builds are a process
in open source that provides you with an absolute guarantee that a binary package corresponds to a
given set of source files. The idea behind reproducible builds is that if you start with
a given snapshot of your code base and run it in a very well specified environment and guarantee
that the dependencies are the same, you will end up with exactly the same package as the published
binary. Pants can be used as part of a reproducible builds workflow, but most development teams,
especially ones internal to a company, don't actually need this level of guarantee.
The ops people in your company who are installing internal software should have high levels of trust
of the developers who work for the same company as them. So that's our use case. We don't go out of
our way to be cryptographically reproducible. That's not what we're going to talk about today.
Our primary goal here is ensuring a useful level of correctness. We really care about the completion
time of your goals so that you spend less time at your desk waiting for your test to pass and you
spend less time waiting for your CI to go green. For us, reproducibility means being able to be
certain that you'll get the same results running rules sequentially or in parallel. And reproducibility
means being confident that...
...
Okay. Mathematically, we model each rule as a pure function of inputs that produce given outputs.
A rule with the same inputs should yield the same outputs. For rules that are implemented
entirely within pants in Python code, Python gives us all the tools we need. We make heavy use
of frozen data classes and those are easy to cache and easy to check for quality. The problem for us
is that processes are rules as well. Indeed, they end up being the rules that underpin basically
every other rule that gets run. The rules that run entirely inside pants are usually just setting up
inputs and configuration for the rules that run processes. But processes are really, really
difficult to model. They're impacted by dependency versions, by operating system
characteristics and more. Being able to parallelize or cache any rule means being able to make sure
that we can make the results of processes as predictable as the pure function codes that we
write in Python ourselves. Being predictable means modeling processes so that they're as
cacheable as any other rule that we run. So if we want to be predictable, we can't rely on works on
my machine because that is in no way reproducible at all. And full cryptographic reproducibility is
more of a guarantee than most internal development teams actually need. What we actually care about
is making sure that we don't get the wrong results as long as we start with a similar environment.
And annoyingly, this brings about the question, what does it mean for an environment to be similar?
This discussion is going to center on Python tooling, so I'm going to focus on that.
The same general concepts actually apply to other language ecosystems such as the JVM or Go, which
we also support in Pants. So in Python, the environment that we care about consists of four
aspects. The first is your operating system, and if you use Mac OS, that also includes the
architecture of it. Then there is the actual Python version that you're running. Then there's
the version of your dependencies, which Pants captures using lock files, so we do that right
down to the specific artifact of PyPI. And then there is the configuration of the tools that you
run inside each rule. Now, even without Pants, most of these things you tend to fix in your
day-to-day life. Like, your operating system very rarely changes from underneath you. It's very easy
to stay on a specific Python version. It's very easy to forget to upgrade. And it's easy enough
to keep your tools configured in exactly the same way. By far the most complicated of these in Python
land is how to handle dependency versions, which is particularly if you're the sort of developer who
incrementally adds dependencies as you go. If you spend a lot of time working in a given virtual
M, for example, it can be really easy for your dependencies to drift away from what your code
base actually specifies, which is what your collaborators are going to be working with.
This is because standard Python tools sort of encourage you to build up your environment one
package at a time, and then freeze your requirements once you're ready to release.
And this really runs contrary to this idea of environments being predictable.
A much better approach is to make sure that every process gets run in a configuration
that fully corresponds to your requirements or your lock file if you have one.
The best way to provide a predictable environment is actually to create a completely new environment
for every process that needs to be run. One advantage of this is that you can manage the
versions and dependencies of your tools separately to your code base. So the version of Black that
you run doesn't need to be tied to the version of PyTest that you run just because they share a
common dependency. The other reason why we care about starting from clean environments for every
process is that often processes produce outputs that we don't care about, or they might modify
the environment in ways that might impact subsequent runs of the same tool, or the behavior
of other tools. So in terms of modeling, a reproducible process for us is one where we
specify the input files in the environment, and we only collect the output artifacts that we actually
care about. Let's make this a bit clearer. If we retain the side effects of any given process,
modeling the behavior of the process becomes dependent on the order in which they get run.
You need to run a given process in order to collect its side effects from that run,
and you need to make sure those side effects are tracked. So rather than having a predictable
model of the process executions, you actually have a model just of one step in a chain of processes,
which really isn't worth modeling at all. Because what happens if we change some of the inputs in
one step of the chain? Well, you break that chain, and you need to rerun every subsequent step.
What's worse is that if you keep the side effects around somewhere, if you want to achieve the same
goal and do it in a way that's correct, you have to run everything again from the start because
the environment has changed. Now, you might be thinking, I can run make as often as I like,
and it's instant every second time. That's because doing it correctly is tedious.
Those tools reuse the environment. They assume that the side effects don't actually matter,
but this actually leads to subtle contamination which can break things, and this is why most
tools that you use have a clean command. That's to deal with garbage that gets left behind
if your tool doesn't do the right thing in a reused environment. On the other hand,
if you don't reuse the environment, then you actually break this dependency on ordering.
This means that you can reorder processes so that they're more efficient. This could be as
simple as running formatters before you run linters, through to dividing up a test suite
to run on multiple cores in separate processes, through to skipping rules that have been run
earlier or even by someone else. It can do this without an explicit clean goal because by not
reusing the environment, Pants actually cleans as it goes. So that's what a hermetic environment is.
It took me half the talk to get here. It's an environment that isolates the side effects of a
process from other processes in the same workflow. It means that if one process does something
unfortunate that would invalidate the behavior of other processes, that effect doesn't get captured.
Indeed, it means only capturing the effects of a process that we actually intend to capture
and discarding everything else. The way that we achieve a hermetic build is by preparing a
knowable environment containing dependencies that we can model into which we place known input files.
The only things that we preserve from this environment are specific output files.
So I've said that that's a good thing. I've explained some theory about what constitutes
a hermetic environment. Now we need to look at how we actually go about preparing these environments.
So we're going to talk a bit about sandboxing techniques. The goal of a sandbox is to isolate
processes from one another so that their execution does not interfere with each other. Isolation can
come in many forms, but generally speaking the things that we tend to care about are making sure
that processes are isolated from each other. Most operating systems these days do that automatically,
but also making sure that processes don't write over files that are produced by other processes
or making sure that OS resources are allocated fairly. These days like 90% of the processes
that need isolation can be adequately handled by Docker. Everyone uses containers all the time these
days. And honestly you can do this hermetic environment thing with Docker as well. Another
mono repo build system called Bazel does in fact do this, but it is amongst several sandboxing
options that you can choose from inside Bazel. And that's because Docker, even though it's much
lighter than a virtual machine, still has significant performance overheads. If you want to
replicate a containerized environment multiple times, that means you need to materialize a
containerized OS multiple times. And there's a lot of underlying files that just don't change very
often. So that ends up being a lot of repeated and often unnecessary work just to run tests in
isolation. Building up truly isolated environments, be it through Docker or through other means,
is really, really slow. So all sandboxing approaches need to trade between the level
of isolation and the level of speed in which your sandboxes can be built. And so this raises the
following question. How much isolation do we actually need in order to build up a predictable
process execution model? And the answer is actually it's not a lot. Again, our needs are
not really built around ensuring security. This is because most tools that Pants orchestrates
are trustworthy. This is a bit of a hand wave, but generally you're already using these tools to build
your software. That means that you've already audited their functionality as much as your
organization needs. I presume you audit your tools. Yeah, okay, I see a lot of nodding here.
Pants doesn't make these tools do anything that they don't do on their own. Beyond that,
build tools tend to do a predictable amount of work. They tend to do a good job of only reading
the files that you tell them to and only outputting files in places that you tell them to.
So unlike in cases where processes might run away, like on a server facing the internet,
the processes that Pants runs doesn't really need enforcement of isolation. They just need to stay
in their lane. So enforcement approaches to isolation, these are things like running
processes on dedicated machines or containers or even just running in a file system, all these
require some amount of operating system primitives to be put in place before you can even run a
process. But they give you some level of actual resource isolation in return. Guidance tools are
a bit less frequent, but in the Python world, we tend to use them all the time in the form of
virtual M. All virtual M does is modifies your path environment variable so when you ask to run
Python, the first thing your shell finds is the version you specified with the dependencies you
installed there. The key observation is that VM doesn't actually stop you from being able to run
other versions of Python that are on your system. It just makes it easier to run one specific version
of Python and a lot harder to run the rest. So Pants does more or less exactly the same thing.
Rather than putting you in a predictable place inside a completely isolated environment, Pants
will run the processes inside the host operating system. But the working directory is a temporary
directory in a completely unpredictable part of your file system and we set environment variables
from scratch. The tools that Pants runs are usually fairly well behaved. They'll only access the
files that you tell them to. And if you configure a Python tool to load dependencies from a specific
place, it will do that rather than looking to where the OS stores them. That's how virtual
M works. We just do it a bit more aggressively. So because the tools that Pants runs tends to be
trustworthy and they're configurable in a way that makes them not interfere with files that they
aren't told to, we're able to run these tasks inside the host operating system. We can run them
in a temporary directory that is created especially for a given process and we never run another
process in the same directory. So to create environments, all we need to do is copy in the
input files and the dependencies that don't exist in the host environment and we copy the build
artifacts out when the process is done. So there's still one more thing that we need to discuss here,
which is how Pants actually does this stuff in practice. Caching the results of rules is
only really useful if it's faster to compute a cache key than it is to run the rule itself.
Copying files around can be really, really slow and wasteful. And if we're preparing environments
and it's substantially slower to do that when we need to run the processes, then users just aren't
going to tolerate that because people don't like slow build tools. So once you decide you might
want to cache the results of rules, the execution steps look something like this. We create some
process request and we send that request into the internals of Pants. Something happens. We wait
a while and eventually Pants will send back a process result object. To a Python developer,
this is an async IO call and as a Python developer, you don't really care what goes on underneath the
hood. Underneath the hood, though, Pants makes the decision to either run the process or fetch it out
of the cache. The point where we can end up saving some time comes from answering the question
of whether we've already run a given task. So with hermetic environments, we can answer one
question, which is if we have the same files and the same configuration, the same dependencies,
will we get the same result? What it doesn't answer the question of is whether a set of files is
the same. And that's a problem because with build processes, especially on big code bases,
you can end up having hundreds or thousands of files and files on file systems are annoyingly
mutable. And that makes reasoning about files on a file system themselves quite slow and unreliable.
So Pants solves this by using content addressable storage. In our case, we use LNDB under the hood.
Having our own system to reason about the files that we're modeling means that we get to decide
what operations are cheap and what operations aren't. And we get to do that without the
constraints that file systems normally put on us. It's also useful because as people writing
orchestration code, we very rarely care about addressing individual files, but we do care about
sets of files. We want to work with a set of source files or we want to work with the resolved
collection of dependencies that an application has or perhaps we want to deal with a combination
of both. If you're a rule author writing Pants rule code, your window into this content addressable
storage is a thing called a digest, which is a reference to a set of files. When we run a process,
what we end up with is a digest which represents the files that we asked to copy out of the process
execution environment and nothing else. Similarly, when we talk about copying input files into the
execution environment, what we're actually doing is materializing the content that is specified by
the digest into the execution environment. Now, digests are lightweight, which makes them cheap
to use in a cache key. And importantly for us, unlike files on a file system, items in the
content addressable storage for us are immutable. That means that we can deal with them in the same
way that we attempt to reason about everything else that we reason about in Pants. Digests are
immutable, they refer to immutable content and most importantly, the operations that we perform in our
rule code in Pants are very, very cheap compared with doing the same sorts of operations on a file
system. This includes things like renaming files so that they have a common prefix, moving a batch
of files into a different directory, merging multiple digests and also under the hood, we can
only store relative pars which is important. It means we can materialize files into a temporary
directory just the same as the rest of this execution model requires. And speaking of
materializing files, the key thing is that we don't actually materialize files into the host file system
until we actually have a process that needs our actual files. And this approach means that we don't
waste our time doing piles of I.O. in order to maintain these hermetic environments. We only do
the bare minimum amount of copying files around to ensure that we end up with the files that we
actually want. And so now that we have digests that can reliably represent an input or output
file set, we can model a process entirely in Python. In Pants, when we request to run a process,
we supply the command that we want to run, a series of environment variables and the files
in the environment are specified as a digest. Under the hood, it's a data class which is efficient
to cache in Python. So now that we have that, we have a lightweight reference to a lot of immutable
files which is a thing that's accurate enough for us to use in a cache key and the result of that is
itself cheap enough to store into a cache. So now the question of have we run this rule becomes
easy and lightweight to answer. If we've got a process with the same arguments, the same input
digest, the same environment, et cetera, et cetera, then we can be confident that we've already run it.
What's more, this question can be answered equally effectively by a local cache or by a remote cache.
And that's it. For Pants, a process execution consists of the host operating system,
an environment that we can predictably model and the contents of a digest that we can reliably
store inside a cache. So that's basically the end of this talk. We've done our high level look into
hermetic environments and how they unlock some of Pants' more interesting time saving features.
We saw that we're able to make existing Python tools run faster or not at all if we can make good
choices about how tools get run and when. We saw that we need to be able to predictably model
processes which is quite difficult to do unless you have a predictable environment.
Then we did some hand waving that build processes don't actually need a whole lot of
isolation or at least we don't need a whole lot to be able to predictably model their behaviour.
And we saw that using a content addressable database makes it cheaper to do orchestration tasks
like merging these set of dependencies and the set of source files and also makes it much,
much easier to reason about file sets in a cache. So if you're interested in all this stuff,
we are going to be around at the rest of the conference. Myself, John and Benji, we're going
to be sprinting tomorrow both on Pants Build and PECS which is a project that the Pants Build project
stewards. One thing that we will be doing in particular rather than working on features in
Pants will be helping you onboard Pants into your open source repo. So if all this seems interesting
to you, we'll help you take advantage of it. You can come find myself, Benji or John in the hallway
track after this talk. We're happy to answer any questions that you had about this talk.
There are docs and demonstrations available at pantsbuild.org and there's also a link to
our community Slack where you can ask us or other maintainers questions. There are notes on this
talk, they're a bit sparse at the moment, available on the Pants Build blog right now if I got the
scheduling functionality correct. That is the end of my talk. Thank you for paying attention.
I look forward to seeing you in the hallway track.