Thank you.
Hello everyone.
My name is Mario.
And I want to make sure you're in the right room.
This is not the pattern matching talk, okay?
That's in another room.
I'm surprised to see many people here.
You still have time to go to the other one.
Well, as I was saying, my name is Mario.
I work at Bloomberg.
And yeah, I want to speak today about basically how to explore
some Linux features and concepts from Python.
The talk could have been just named that, but
it's all about the clickbait, right?
So after the talk, I'm gonna be around, I'm one of these people that love to get
stopped in the hallway and chat about anything.
There are a lot of topics you can speak with me about that doesn't have to be
necessarily Python.
But yeah, hopefully we'll get to meet and share some time together.
So as I was saying, we're gonna speak about Linux and Python.
And we'll see some basic Linux concepts, hopefully through APIs that
you already know.
The objective of this talk is that you will get to hopefully know a little bit
more of Linux through an environment that you're comfortable with.
I think we don't have time for questions at the end, but
I'll be at the hallway.
Okay, so first of all, Linux or Python?
You might be wondering, what does CPython build against?
There is output here to URLs that you can check that will help you figure out
whether the platform you're working on is supported at Python.
On the second link, there's a pipe that defines what that supported means.
There are situations where a release may be blocked based on issues in
that platform.
And there are some others where it is kind of like most best effort.
There is also the Python billboards, where it's basically the farm
that's building CPython against multiple platforms every day.
There is even a watch with a really cool shield.
It's kind of like a really slight group.
You have some people that belong to that here in the talk.
But basically, there is people that are making sure that CPython continues to
build and to run in multiple platforms whenever there's any new mic change and
whenever there is a new change that's made in the source code.
Additionally, you should be aware that CPython release managers only release
pre-built interpreters for macOS and Windows.
And what that means is that if you are using CPython in Linux in any of
its distribution, you are basically using something that's built from source.
You will need, I mean, everything is built from source, but
you will need to build it on your own.
Or in some cases, for example, you're using Ubuntu or something like that.
There will be some package manager that does that for you.
But it's not the Python release managers that are doing that.
It's some other third party.
So getting into the meat, I'm gonna speak through multiple modules that
allow you to interact with APIs that are at the end providing
you services that belong to the OS.
And before we start into that, there's something I'd like to tell you.
Because I work with a lot of Python developers, and
sometimes I find that people don't know about many of the modules that are
part of the Sunday library.
And we're proud to say that our language come with batteries included, but
we never get to know about all the batteries that include.
So here I'm basically listing some of the modules that allow you to interact with
the OS, and I'm sure that many people here in the audience have not seen some of them.
Some, a module, for example, I see many people don't know about, and
it's, in my opinion, quite handy, is filecmp.
That basically allows you to compare if two files are equal or
even compare to directories.
It's super cool, and I'm sure that many of you have written that code on your
own to compare it to directories of files, isn't it?
So if you have the time after this talk or after PyCon or whatever, you can.
There is a page in the CPython documentation
that lists all the module in the standard library.
Just go through it, I'm sure that you'll learn some new cool module.
So we can speak about Linux and Python without speaking about processes.
So a really beef introduction, when we're writing a program,
all we're doing is basically creating instructions, right?
And then those instructions define a program when it's in disk, and
you're gonna move it into memory, and that creates a process in some way.
The process is made of those instructions that we wrote,
together with some state, there is some memory around it.
If you have no experience with it,
I recommend that you read some information around the memory layout of a process.
I promise you, you're gonna be fascinated.
And basically, once you have that in memory, the OS through the scheduler
will prioritize what instructions are being executed.
And that's cool, but how do we create a process in Python, right?
So if you haven't seen it before, no, the slides are cut.
But so is there the media people,
is there any way I can make the, don't worry.
There is a part here in the corner that is going to put on all the slides,
I'll publish the slides afterwards.
But there is a main command for each of the slides that I'm putting that allows
you to go deeper if you want.
But I'll just say that, that's a pity.
So well, fork, through the OS model, you will be able to run the Cisco fork.
And what that allows you to do is basically get the current program and
create a clone on its own.
And that's gonna be a child process.
This is kind of like the most, well, the way to create new processes on Linux.
You can see that what the API allows you is you call os.fork, and
that's gonna give you a return code.
The return code is gonna be 0 in the case of the child, and
it's gonna be the PID of the parent, sorry,
the PID of the child in the case of the parent.
This is really handy way to just allow you to run some coding parallel, right?
Here you can see how in this example, we are basically starting a program, right?
Then we're calling fork, and those two things are going to be executed in parallel.
The child process is gonna run the first section of the if, and
the parent process is going to run the second part.
When I say that when you run fork, the process is duplicated,
you might be thinking that, wow, that has to be really expensive, right?
And there are many optimizations to make sure that that's not the case.
A good example is that, for example,
in Linux there's a concept what's called copy and write.
And what that means is that when you're actually forking,
you are not copying the whole thing.
You are only going to start to copy that part of memory when you modify them.
Which is really handy if you think about, for example, these functions and
all the code that are there, which is not going to be changed.
Something that I also wanted to mention here, and
which you can find in the man page if you read that.
And I really recommend that you run man fork if you ever have to interact with
any of this, is that threads are not copied.
When you run fork, only the thread that's executing that is going to be the one
that's going to be cloned.
Again, don't be afraid of the Linux manual, I promise you.
It's really nice and easy to read, especially when you know what
the thing is doing.
So it's a pity that we cannot see it here in the slides, but
there at the top it says man fork.
The second thing I want to speak about,
you can speak about fork without exec, is the exec API.
This is going to allow you to interact, well, there are multiple functions.
You can find in the OS documentation of Python the different functions that
allows you to interact with exec in different ways.
Because you might want to pass different,
basically the API just changes how you can pass parameters.
And some other things, so for example,
where the path environment variable is going to be used to find the command.
But basically what this is going to do is it's going to replace the current process
with the one that you passed it here.
So here we're just saying this program is just importing OS and
then it's saying, okay, replace myself with this new program.
And that's going to execute Python 3.9 and it's going to execute that.
You can realize that line number six is never going to be executed.
Because you're replacing the whole program and
therefore the instructions of the previous program,
that no longer sticks in that process.
At the top there, you can see a new man reference, which is man exec.
Okay, something else that might be handy when you are doing fork and
exec is that you can register at fork handlers.
What this allows you to do is to execute code before you fork or after you fork.
And you can customize that in both in the parent and in the child.
Python allows you to do this really nicely through this OS register at fork.
You can basically pass function there with what you want to execute.
Okay, so you might be wondering, okay, Mario, I've never used any of this.
Why are you speaking to me about it?
Well, have you used a subprocess?
If you have ever used a process to run anything like this,
this is a code example taken from the subprocess documentation.
You are indeed using this.
This is the source code behind subprocess, so you can see there.
I'm not lying to you.
And here is basically doing fork and exec.
Something similar to how we say go and
read the different modules that they have in the standard library.
There are some modules that are really easy to read and understand what's going on.
So I would encourage you as well to go and read the source code of some modules,
because then you can understand what's actually happening behind.
In this case, indeed, it's just calling fork and exec.
And you can see here how it's the same structure that we saw before,
where it's just calling fork, getting the PID of the child, right?
And here it's checking if the PID is zero, that means that we are in the child.
So it means that we are in the parent, so we are just returning.
Otherwise, here you have the code for the child.
You can see here again the code to the after fork in the child.
There is also another section in the code that does the after fork of the parent,
but I didn't include it in this slide.
Similar to how a process just do fork and exec,
multiprocessing does something really similar.
So believe it or not, you have been using this all the time, and
not only on Python, of course.
Some more things, if we start to speak about files,
something I love also to show some people is how you can just,
you probably know that your process is always writing to standard output, right?
And it's reading from standard.
Those are just normal files.
They're really not text files, but those are files that you
can even open on your own.
Here you can see how, for example, you can just open std out and
append to it and read from stdin.
Something to mention here that I know catches some people is
you can see here how we write hello, PyCon, add Solixct, but
only the first line is actually printed before we read stdin.
If you wonder why that's happening, in the sense of why do we see hello, Python,
we have to press Enter and then the other line appears when in the code we
can see that it's writing twice to std out and then reading from stdin.
That's because the output is being buffered.
I'm sure that many of you have loved to live cowboy lives and
have removed your USB-staking windows without extracting the device.
But that's actually the reason why it's happening, and that's because the Python
or the OS, depending, there are multiple layers, will be buffering the output that
you write to a file or to a media or anything like that.
So you need to make sure that those are buffered before you close.
If you want to go a little bit further and see what's actually std out,
because you might wonder, hey, if this is just a file,
how come that I can have multiple processes running right into it and
they are not colliding, right?
I can have multiple terminal screens and they are not interacting with each other.
How does this work?
So what's actually happening is that std out and
std error just point to this like, proc self.
If you haven't ever walked a little bit through proc,
I encourage you to do it as well.
You can find all the information about the process there.
And what's actually happening is that's basically just pointing to a file
descriptor, your process, and then I think I have time.
And that's actually, I'm gonna show you what actually happens there.
And that then is pointing to your terminal.
So for example, here, if you see proc self,
live demo, woo, fd1.
So that's actually just a symlink to my terminal.
You can see here if I run tty, that matches.
And what that means is that basically std out is being pointed to that file
descriptor, and then that file descriptor is pointed to my terminal.
And this is as fun as you can just take this and write things here.
You can write, hello PyCon from here.
And that totally works, it's just a file.
You can even write from a different terminal.
And that will work.
And of course you can do exactly the same thing from PyCon.
You can see it's here.
You can even cut it, you can even read from it if you want.
And then fun things start to happen.
Like for example, if you write here,
both of them are running and you'll see it in both places.
It's at the end, the API I'm working with is just a file descriptor.
So you can just work with it as with any other file descriptor.
Really cool stuff.
You can, yeah, let's continue because I'm actually running out of time.
Similar to how you can open and read files,
you can also read about the metadata from Python.
There's a stat command in Linux and
you have the stat module in Python that allows you to read all of that.
Okay, how am I doing with time?
Okay, so next thing is the locale module.
Again, you can read man set locale and that will allow you to learn a little
bit more on the Linux man pages about how the locale works.
But this allows you to handle all kind of like cultural
specificities about your code.
Here I'm putting an example of how you, for example,
can use locale to parse that string 43, 210 into a float.
And you can see that you get different results whether you're using the US locale
or the Spanish locales.
All programs start with what's called the legacy C locale.
But you can change that once you start by changing the locale here.
Probably when you are working with locale specific programs,
you're using more high level modules.
But it's always good to know what's behind the hoods.
And this basically what allows you is to read that information from the OS.
If you wanted to add more locales, what you need to do is basically install
the interior as some language pack and that will give you that.
Okay, so time, this is a topic I love.
If you might be wondering, what's so hard about time?
Why do I need the OS to give me the time?
Well, the thing is, time is not, hopefully this is not new to you,
but time is a complex concept to, it's just hard to know what time is this.
How crazy it sounds.
But the thing is like in Python, the time is being provided by the OS.
And the OS actually works with some hardware code,
which is just using quotes because that provides,
that gives you something that gives you a periodic event that you can check.
And then your PC is going to be able to track how seconds pass by using quotes.
And then your OS will be able to read that and
will combine that with the time from all the PCs which is being given to you by NTP.
At the end, the time is just given to you,
it's actually being provided by some atomic clocks that you don't have to worry about.
But it's good to know that whenever you are asking Python for
what time is it, all this is happening.
And the reason why I'm saying that is because you might start to build some
assumptions around it that you should not.
Like for example, that the time is monotonic and extending.
So that's something you can actually not rely on time.
Yeah, this basically allows us to call to the OS and get the time that it is.
And you might wonder, yeah, but I never use time.time, I use daytime.
Well, if you read the code, it's actually the same thing.
All time in Python is actually being provided by the OS by just calling time.time.
Here is the underscore time,
which is the extension that's actually calling them to the OS.
You cannot see the man pages here, but here actually it says man and tpd.
And it allows you to know how this protocol that synchronizes your time with
all the PCs work.
Because probably many of you here will have a watch.
And it's important to realize that your watch will have a different time from my
watch.
And even if we were to synchronize them right now, after a day or a month or
a year, because your watch is probably based on quarts or it's mechanical,
it will lose synchronization with each other.
And you need to synchronize them from time to time to make sure that you are
following the same time.
So you get all of this for free in Python because it's just asking the OS to give
it the time.
And in case you wonder, because you have seen this YouTube channel, Veritasium,
call like, how can I handle leap seconds?
Well, the thing is the OS is giving you the time in what's called Unix time.
And that's not include leap seconds.
So if the OS does not know about leap seconds,
Python cannot know about leap seconds.
Okay, so let's go with signals.
So signals are just a software interrupt to notify a process of an important event.
There are many events that your process might want to know about, and
the OS can pass that to them.
You can also just call kill and basically pass a signal to your program.
There are usual signals that you can customize yourself.
And then there are signals to tell the process to interrupt itself.
Or there's also a signal that surprised many people, which is the sigpipe.
What that means is that you saw how before we saw there's std out,
std in, in Linux when you have a command and
then you put the pipe symbol and another command.
What actually happened there is that the OS is mapping the std out of your first
command to the stdn to the first one.
So if one of the, there's no file there really, right?
So what's happening is that when one of those processes die,
the pipe is broken because one is not connected anymore.
So that's the OS is going to notify you via that pipe broken signal.
Something where you might have seen signals as well if you're running web
applications, a really common practice, is to basically handle the siginterrupt
as a way to have a way to tell your process like, hey, I want you to stop
because I'm running or start the machine or whatever.
So you can customize what to do with sigint and
basically clean up your process before exiting.
And if they don't exit, then you can just run sigkill,
which no one can overwrite, and it will just kill your process in a nice way.
And how is all of this handled in Python?
Well, you can call, you have the signal module, and
here you have an example of how to register a signal.
This might cause you a nightmare because you might have realized that now any
instruction in your Python program can run any kind of,
can raise any kind of exception.
Please don't start to capture zero division errors around time.sleep, okay?
So here you can see how to register a handler for any signal.
And something to be aware is how does Python handle those signals, right?
Because signals are done on a lower level.
So what's actually happening is that Python will always pass those signals and
call the signal handlers in the main thread.
And the same way that signals are handled in the main thread,
signal needs to be registered in the main thread.
You cannot register a signal in any other thread.
Something that Python will do by default for
you is translate sigint to a keyboard interrupt exception.
And sigpipe to a broken pipe error exception.
If for every reason you wanted to overwrite sigfold and some other signals,
that won't work as you expect in Python because at the end they're gonna be
passed again to the C level and your program will not behave as you probably expect.
So you have another module in the standard library called
fold handler that will allow you to do that.
Okay, so main pipes, I don't know why I love this.
They are a really simple way to have inter-process communication.
What this allows you to do is you can have a file where you can have two, well,
a file, where you can have two process connect and
pass information from one to another.
It's unidirectional and here you have an example on how to do that.
Something to note is that you need to have both sides connected,
otherwise they will by default block on it.
So that's why here you see some API's related to how to connect without blocking
and things like that.
And basically, yeah, you cannot see the man page there, but
you can read man.fifo and you'll get more information about that.
If you want to use main pipes, go and read that because maybe something that
surprises you.
Something I like to do when I'm using main pipes as well is on the reader
process I like to have as well an open file descriptor with the right permission.
That's a way to unblock myself if I have some kind of multi-threading application.
But if you like this, you would love Unix domain sockets.
So what this allows you to do is similar,
you have kind of like a file that allows you to have two process communicate with
each other.
But here you have a bidirectional channel.
So that means that you'll need to use send and recv.
But this allows you to have basically a communication between two processes.
Similar to how you can use a socket to communicate with a process in
a different host.
You can use Unix domain socket to communicate with a process in the same host.
Something that's amazing about this is that because it's a file,
you can control permissions.
Like who can read and who can write just with file permissions,
which I think it's beautiful.
Okay, so if you want to do this and
you want to combine it with fork and exec,
here we have an example that's kind of like full end to end.
So here you can see how you can use socket socketper,
which is another function that you have in the standard library.
And that's going to give you basically two variables that you can use to
communicate between each other.
So here you can see that we call socketper and then we have the call to fork.
So now you have to know, okay, so
I have now two programs running through this, right?
And we can see that in the child, we can use this child socket to send
information to the parent and the other way around.
Which is a super easy way to send information from one process to another.
If you wonder what is all of this useful for, that allows you to then create,
this is the sponsor slide.
This allows you then to create products like Mainbray.
So if you haven't heard about Mainbray, it's a new memory profiler that we built.
The reason why I'm including here is because if you like to know more about
some Linux feature, I would really recommend that you read through
the source code.
It has not only some advanced and beautiful concepts, but
it's really well documented.
And we have actually got some really cool comments from people
about how well and fine is to read the source code.
I promise, really.
It basically, have a look through it.
I am not one of these fanboys that will just publish
a tool with flags and T-shirts and everything.
Don't trust that kind of people, okay?
But if you have the time, I would really recommend that you have a look at it.
Totally objective, okay?
And yeah, check it out because you have many concepts that you might like that
are related to this presentation as well.
And that's all I have.
Thank you.