Okay. Thanks for coming and being here.
Okay. It's a story about getting started with OOP,
with signal processing which is a typical different domain.
My name is Francesco Bruni, came from Italy.
This is my first time at PyCon US and first time in America as well.
It's such a big honor that you stayed and choose
this tutorial among all other maybe
much more interesting tutorial that much.
Just a few words about this crash course,
a few words about me.
I'm a Senior Software Engineer in a company that is called
Planetegitalia in the southern part of Italy.
We play with Earth observation.
So we play with extracting data from satellite imagery,
running algorithms capable of running on top of
micro satellites just to look at the Earth.
I'm playing with Python for 15 years.
I'm still repeating myself as intermediate level,
not really expert and I'm not single-tech fanatic.
I typically use multiple technology in my daily routine,
so I'm pretty comfortable working for example with Java.
I'm going to see some difference between Python and Java,
for example, just to make clear
that I'm not that fanatic about the technology.
I typically use the technology to solve a particular issue.
Okay. Just a few words about my town.
Town in Italy are very different from town in America, I notice.
I always looked in the films but in
the reality is much more different.
Barri is located in the southern part of Italy around the sea.
It's pretty known for seeing astronomical.
But my personal point about this is the metropolitan area.
Barri is really interesting if you,
let's say, have some curiosity about the aerospace sector.
In fact, there are multiple companies that play with
this stuff like designing and implementing
electronic for running satellite as
well as software that runs on top of a satellite.
So this place in the southern part of Italy is very active in this sector.
Before beginning, my personal opinion
on why we still need to talk about object-oriented programming.
Object-oriented programming is very old topic.
Okay. So everyone is talking and talked a lot
about object-oriented programming.
My question is, why we still need to talk about
object-oriented programming in the era of artificial intelligence,
Web3, Blockchain, deep learning, whatever.
Just put any buzzword you want.
The main issue is that if you understand the guidelines,
the main principle of object-oriented programming,
which is somehow narrowed to a little small domain,
which deals with computer,
you can try to translate this concept,
this idea to something that is much more challenging,
like for example, software architecture.
So if you find yourself in a way to design systems,
to design for example, microservices architecture,
you can find that much more of the principle that we're going to see during
this crash course can be translated to the microservice architecture as well.
We're going to see samples in a while.
From my point of view,
I always and I say always played with,
learned and played with object-oriented programming through two different things,
animals and outer rooms.
I was very tired of trying to explain and trying to study all these really important stuff
with such boring topic like outer rooms or mammals, humans.
So I asked myself,
what exactly can be,
sort of crash course that tried to explain object-oriented programming and gets you
to get acquainted with some domain that you probably don't know,
but it is somehow overwhelming all of us,
which is signal processing like this one.
By the way, I turned a computer sciences.
I got a master's degree in telecommunication engineering,
so I pretty really changed to this topic,
which I really loves a lot.
The signals are basically analog and digital.
We play with digital obviously because we play with computer,
even if we are going to tell a few stories about the amplitude modulation,
which is applied to analog signal during this crash course.
But this is our topic.
So a few words about this crash course.
You are not expected to know anything about signal processing, obviously,
because this course is much more about,
let's say, object-oriented programming,
but the domain is signal processing.
So I cannot assume obviously that you know something about,
but if you know, that's good.
We're going to just scratch the surface of signal processing.
So we are not going deeper.
There would be a live coding.
For this, I asked them,
and I thank you, to put a table over here because I need to code with you.
You can just copy what you write,
understand, make question,
or you can just download all the code from my website.
So that's totally up to you.
We'll be for different exercise break at the end.
If you feel lazy, you can just look at the solution I uploaded on the website.
You know that Python is required.
We are Python conference.
But if you want to, let's say,
a more in-depth experience with signal and wave,
not with object, with signals and waves,
I strongly suggest you to use Jupiter because you probably are going to listen,
visualize signals as well.
Obviously, all the complexity has been
trapped in the node.utils in the classes module
because you are not required to know anything about signal processing.
So I just take with some implemented function,
all the things that you actually need to play with this code.
Okay. The only piece of theory about signal processing that you need is just this concept.
The difference between signal and wave.
A signal is nothing else than a mathematical formulation of something.
When you play, for example, a note of a piano like a C,
open C, what you have is that you basically can
constrain that sound to that formula.
Where the T, the independent variable is the time,
DA is the amplitude,
which in turn is related to the power of the signal and then to the volume.
So you can consider that scaling up down the value of the A,
which is basically a constant,
you can increase and down the volume of the note of the piano.
So it's pretty easy to be understood what exactly is A.
The F is the frequency of the signal or the wave.
IRF means a more acute sound,
while lower F means a more grave sound.
The phi, which is the last time is the delay.
So if you want that your sound starts,
maybe phi by two radians,
you just change the value.
But in our example,
we can consider that theta is capable of being zero.
When you compute this formula for different distances of time,
you get the diagram on your right, which is called the wave.
So signal is just a nice way to,
let's say, to express something mathematically.
The wave on the right is what exactly your ear is capable to feeling.
The main problem is that when you play, for example, with music,
the signal formulation is impossible because the sound is not very easy.
I forgot to mention that sin is a mathematical function,
which is periodic, so it comes after a period from the beginning,
again, again, again, again.
For this reason, you got the wave on the right when you
compute that formula for different instances of t.
Sometimes, you could work,
obviously, with signals of wave in different domain.
We typically do the different domain.
This domain can be called, for example, a frequency domain.
So instead of visualizing the time and the power,
sorry, the time and the value of that function in the previous slide,
you can obviously perform some plot like this,
where you plot on the x-axis,
the frequency, and on the y-axis, you plot the power itself.
This is very cool representation because this lets you to understand
what exactly is going to happen in terms of frequency itself.
If you play, for example,
because I'm pretty sure that you play wave,
you play an equalizer, for example,
you increase the power of certain range of frequency,
it's much simpler to understand the role and how the equalizer works
if you look at the wave in the frequency domain, not in the time domain.
By the way, you can switch from time domain as well
in frequency domain just reaching from wave to spectrum.
Then after the spectrum,
you can apply some filtering in order to, I don't know,
low-pass filtering to reduce all the voices from
song, for example, and then get back to the wave itself,
which is basically the main interface that you hear is going to fill.
With this introduction, we read the code.
Do you have a question about all this part? Perfect.
Sorry. Can I wear off the mask?
No. Can I remove the mask while talking?
Oh, yeah.
Okay. Thank you.
So just forgot the first part for now.
Okay. So our main issue is that we basically need to explain to
a computer how exactly signal and wave should be treated.
Okay. So we need to find a way to explain all these things,
all the complexity of this word to the computer itself.
And I think it's very common to use the concept of objects and
the concept of class to express all the-
Okay.
That's good.
So it's probably nice to introduce the concept of object and
the concept of class.
So we stick with the first definition.
A class is a data type.
So if you have, for example, an integer, a string, or a float,
okay, they are all data types.
A class itself is a data type.
So we need to find some sort of way to define this data type and
put all the logic inside.
So in order to do this, what we can do is using the keyword class,
define, for example, the class itself, like the signal.
Okay. The main two points of a class are basically two different things,
attributes and methods.
Attributes are the intrinsic characteristics of that object,
of that class.
So for example, if you think about a human,
human eyes, two different eyes, but
the color of the eyes is an intrinsic characteristic.
So you can define obviously this attribute inside the definition of
the class.
And the other thing is the methods.
So they are basically actions you can perform on that kind of class,
on that kind of object.
So if you are talking about signal wave, for example,
an action that you perform on wave is listening to the wave or
just looking at the plot domain of the wave in the time domain or
the frequency domain.
So the first thing that we are going to do, so
is defining the attributes.
We just saw that three main attributes are required to
being defined in the signal.
The first one is the amplitude, okay.
Second one is the frequency.
And the third one is the offset.
Okay, for now, let's just forget about the periodic function that's in, okay?
We try to talk a little maybe later.
Okay, those are the attributes.
The main point is that this kind of declaration is abstract, okay?
It does not exist.
You are just saying that the signal is composed by amplitude frequency offset,
but it does not exist.
Because you just say that, okay, man, this is composed by these three
different fields.
So what you need to do is creating an object.
So an object is an instance of the class,
while the class is just the declaration of a particular object.
So consider an object like some sort of template,
while the object is the existing concretization of the template.
In order to, let's say, set up the initial value of the object itself,
we need a special method, so a special action.
An actual data pattern is called init.
So we can define, for example, the init method, okay?
And try to write the implementation of real.
First of all, the solve, okay, is the instance itself.
You will understand it in a while, but think about it.
This is a method that works on instances.
So this is a method that works on the concretization of the signal itself.
So the first element should be the object itself,
the implementation itself.
Like any other method, you can obviously provide some parameters.
And we are going to provide, for example, the amplitude,
the frequency, and the offset.
Okay, that's good.
And our implementation will be pretty easy, because right now,
what we need to do is set up attributes of the instance itself
within this method to set up the amplitude,
to set up the frequency,
And set up the offset.
Okay, so I just can remove this one, because it does no sense.
You can obviously provide some default value, like for example,
the offset is zero, or I don't know, maybe the amplitude is one.
And once you define the template of your object, so
that you define the class itself, we need to create it.
So I can create it, just calling the class itself,
signal, open up parentheses, set the up, for example, amplitude 1.0.
Sorry, this is a float.
Let's put, for example, the fault frequency, okay?
600 and offset 0.
Okay, so if we run this code,
what I get is an instance of the signal itself.
Obviously, you can avoid setting up all these parameters,
because we provided some default value for this one.
Or you can just pass, for example, only the amplitude,
because you want, for example, a louder sound, and
let the constructor set up the other fields, like frequency and offset.
So it is basically the same.
We still got the signal, but
the signal is an object that is different from the first one.
We just say that, okay, the attributes are the first part of the signal, so
we need to identify this kind of object using attributes.
But still, we need to define actions that we can perform over this,
of the instance, once the instance has been created.
So we can, for example, define a new function that is called print period.
Period is just the inverse of the frequency.
And for example, this one is just going to print, for example,
at the period is delta f, okay, which is basically south dot frequency.
Oops, sorry.
Okay.
That's okay.
So we added an action over this class.
So we try to call it to see if it works.
So if I call, for example, the print period, okay.
Oh, sorry.
I just forgot this one.
Okay.
So for example, you get this one.
So we added a period over here.
Okay, that's good.
You got any questions till now?
Perfect.
Way much simpler.
Okay, we just saw the introduction that what we are going to use is not exactly
the signal, it's actually the wave, okay, our concretization of the signal in a way
that we can just listen it.
Okay, so we define, for example, another method that is called create wave.
Okay, first argument is obviously the instance itself.
And we need to create wave here.
In order to create the wave here, we need to set up few arguments to
decreate wave, first of all, the duration, okay.
Like for example, let's consider a duration by default by two seconds.
And the other one is the frame rate, okay.
That we could set up to, let me see, okay, 3000, okay.
So for now, we just define a new function, okay, with some default value.
Nothing complex, good.
Obviously, you don't need to know and remember the formula that we just saw.
So if you go from Alpers, import, create wave samples.
Let me see, yeah, perfect.
Create wave samples.
You can get the wave representation of the signal.
So if I go create wave samples over here, okay.
You can get the duration is the first argument, okay.
Frame rate, frame rate.
Frequency is the south of frequency, okay.
Amplitude is south of the amplitude.
Phase is zero, that's okay.
And the periodic function can be set, okay, that's good.
So this function is going to return me something like the ts, yeah, ys,
sorry, ys and ts, okay, that's fine.
And I can obviously set up to new for fields, south.ts, okay.
And return ys, okay.
So what we did, we just call a function defining the Alpers module.
The module that I made you download from the website and
I sent you via the introduction markdown file.
We call this method create wave sample that takes different kind of arguments.
It's not very relevant right now to know what exactly they are.
But if you're free, we can obviously talk later.
This is going to return ys and ts.
Ys and ts are basically the y value and
the x value of the wave representation of the signal.
So if you go back, for example, the implementation, this one,
the ys is the value of the amplitude itself, while the ts is the time.
So ts stands for time instances, while ys is the value on top of the y axis.
And we can obviously add a new kind of attribute, which is ys.
So I decided to, once I get the ys array, which is basically an array of points,
I try to set up as a new attribute, okay, that's ys.
And the same for ts.
So if I go over here, for example, and I call instead of printing period,
I call the create wave.
Okay, what you have is this one.
Obviously, you got this one, this is an array,
because basically I'm returning the ys.
So for example, if I define another method that is called plot, okay,
first argument is always the self.
This is going to return plot, sorry, return plot,
self ys from 0 to 100,
self dot ts from 0 to 100, sorry.
First argument is the yx, okay, it's the x.
This one, and I can import plot from here.
So if I write again, yeah?
Okay.
So the create wave function is not important problem, so what do we need to import?
No, create wave function is defined by me, so it cannot be imported.
Yeah, that was created by me.
What is important is the create wave samples function.
This is important.
That's important?
Yeah, from Alpers.
So Alpers is-
Because you probably are missing the Alpers module.
Yeah, let me see.
The one that you download from the website.
Let's go, let me see.
So I cannot find that one, because I'm missing Alpers.
Because, but did you upload the Alpers file?
That's all, that's the issue.
Okay, before using, I just remember for all of you,
before using all this file and the library that I provided to you,
you need to upload them first in the Jupyter.
And then, lots in Jupyter using the percent lots instruction,
like I point out in the description, and then you import it, okay?
If you're not following all these things, you can use the upper file.
Everyone has the same issue, I'm going to repeat it.
Okay, so everyone is working in scope?
I didn't get the mail until you played.
I think it's been long since I played before.
But did you sign up?
Yes. It's very strange.
By the way, go to, open up your browser.
This one.
Just download the Alpers file from here, okay?
You upload, then I new load, okay.
Okay, I try to rephrase again, just to be sure that everyone is on track.
What you need to do is when you go over here, you click for example on the,
this is a call up Google, okay, but it's basically the same if you are running
a local instance of the Jupyter.
You need to click on the upload.
You need to select the file, like the Alpers or the classes.
That's another file that I provided to you in the website, but
not in the getting started introduction and material that I sent.
And when you do this, you can just write something like,
load Alpers, okay, and then run the import.
And when you do this way, basically the Python module located system path of
Python has been updated to include also this module and then the function.
Okay, so we were playing with this one.
Okay, so once we create the wave, we can call obviously the plot function, okay?
And the plot function, sorry.
Let me see, sorry.
Okay,
here you find the plot representation of our wave samples.
So what we did so far is basically defined the signal,
defined functions, defined attributes.
What exactly are the attributes that are going to identify almost uniquely
our concretization of the signal, okay?
Then we add two different methods, okay, create wave and
maybe the plot in order to create wave samples.
Thus creating the array of values in terms of time,
in terms of amplitude for the waves and then plot them.
Let's try to update the print period function in order to print something else.
Like for example, let's print the YS size, okay?
It's good, sub.YS, okay?
Okay, so if I'm going to plot the print period.
Okay, that's one.
So I just updated the print period function in order to print
the size of the array, the YS.
The size of the array is 6,000, that's good.
But with this kind of implementation, there is a problem.
And the main problem is that the print period function won't work
if I not created the wave first.
So if I try to, for example, maybe, yeah, command this one, try again.
It's saying that signal object has not YS.
That's totally normal.
Because we basically have committed some errors.
Mixing up the concept of wave with signals is helping to the same class.
And make the methods, the pants, and
work on two different kind of pieces of the domain.
The signal from one side and the wave from the other side.
So this is maybe the issue.
Okay, this first part completes the get-start introduction to
object-oriented programming.
Now, what you basically can do is picking up the,
if you want, obviously, picking up the exercises, okay?
Like this one, okay, which is the file I loaded into my website,
users.com, okay, download it.
And you try to solve, for example, the exercise one.
If you feel lazy, absolutely, do not worry about it.
Because they probably have the solution file that you can find on the website
that show you the solution.
Let's just see the problem you're trying to solve.
Obviously, we forgot to add the periodic function to the definition of our signal.
Yeah?
Yeah, always the same website, exercise PDF file.
Exercise PDF.
Ah, sorry.
Yes, that was the beginning, sorry.
Okay, let me see.
Website is this one.
Mm-hm.
This is website.
I just scrolled onto the conference page.
I just, okay, I make them notice at the beginning of this talk.
You go under the conference page, okay, just go up and go up and up.
Up and up and up and up and up and up and up and up and up and up.
There's one, click on this one.
Yeah, click on this one.
Yes, exactly.
And these solve the material you basically are going to need to go through
this course, okay?
Yes, that was my fault, okay?
I just said at the beginning of this talk.
So once you download the exercise PDF, you basically are going to
see four different kind of exercise, one for each module.
Okay, we are going to use four different modules to explain these things about
object-oriented programming, and the first exercise would be about,
just one moment.
Okay, would be about changing the definition of our signal,
because if you remember well, we forgot to add another piece of the signal,
which was the periodic function, okay?
So you need to try a way to add the params to the constructor itself in order
to update our signal definition to include this new thing.
And we saw that we mixed up signal and waves together.
We saw the issue of the print period function.
So what you need to do is trying to apply the same logic to the final wave class,
okay?
They should be basically two different things, YS and TS.
The time instances and the amplitude values.
Those are the least.
Do not consider the non-py and the array.
Just consider them least, okay?
And you obviously need to refactor print stats method in order to overcome the issue.
Once you're done, you can download the other file,
which you can find on the website, classes,
which contain the implementation of the new version of the signal.
And so we are going to use that kind of definition to go to the rest of
the course itself, okay?
In general, on the classes file, you can find other definition of classes that we
are going to use throughout the whole course.
So there's no need to write again and again and again.
That's all.
You got 15 minutes.
By the way, I'm here, so if you want any question, you ask me.
Yeah, let me put the mask on.
Okay.
Orgain helpers.
Because there's no need to open up this file.
Okay, look.
Okay.
Okay, let me see what this one is useless.
Okay, so what you need to do is load helpers like this way.
Okay.
Okay, perfect.
So, Okay, because you need to install map.lib and
map.py, okay?
Go here, type in.
No, no, no problem.
You can start just here over here.
Just like this.
Sorry, your keyboard is different than mine.
Pip, install.
I'm using pip3.
I'm writing keys the same.
Math plot lib, no, py.
Oops.
Okay, okay, it's installing.
Okay, now you execute this one.
New model, map plot lib.
So the helpers.py file is looking in the same directory as this.
But this is very odd.
Because we just installed map plot lib here.
No, not the name, map plot lib.
I don't know exactly what is happening because we actually.
I'd rather not use a Jupyter Notebook and
just do regular import on the Python file.
I think that should work.
But did you do something that I'm missing now?
This is fine.
The file appers is here.
So it seems correct to me.
But you have this strange issue, but no model name map plot lib.
Give me one sec.
But you're not using the virtual environment?
No.
This probably be the issue.
It's a global install.
I can create a virtual environment and run it there locally.
But I haven't had a local on the global installation.
I don't know.
Here, I'll get it.
Can you use the Google Colab?
Can we try using our Google Colab?
The what?
Google Calendar?
No, Colab, this one.
This one is a very nice way to use Jupyter Notebook.
We've done installing all the files, okay?
You got a Gmail account?
Yeah.
Okay.
Okay, we try this way.
That's probably someone related to the environment.
I don't know.
Okay, that's fine.
New Notebook?
Okay, it's basically the same, huh?
Yeah.
You will.
You might typically use this one, because this one lets me do not install all the files
that I basically need.
So you go over here.
You disconnect it.
One moment.
Once connected, you upload the file here.
Okay.
So where do you have the helpers?
Helpers, this one.
Open up.
Okay.
Yeah.
Okay, we install again.
We install matplotlnp.
Okay.
Matplotlnp.
From helpers.
Import all.
Sorry.
Right.
Create with samples.
Just to be sure that it's good.
Yeah.
That's it.
It suggests you.
Just put enter.
Okay.
Which one is the shortcut to run?
Shift, enter.
Okay.
That's perfect.
Now copy and paste the code.
You just use this because you can see the code.
You can see the code.
You just use this because you probably messed up something with the global installation.
This is a very, my personal point, do not take it as an offense.
It's very bad practice to not use Python Virtual Lamp.
Okay.
Because otherwise you're going to mess up all the things in the EU system.
So if you want to play Python locally, use the Virtual Lamp.
You got issues?
No, I didn't understand what you were asking us to do.
As exercise.
Do you want me to rephrase the exercise?
No, no, if you want a problem.
Open up the exercise.
Okay.
So when we define the signal, the signal class, okay, we forgot to add the periodic function
attribute.
Okay.
The periodic function is a very important piece of the signal definition because it
defines how the signal, the wave form.
Okay.
So you need to change the implementation of the signal with class in order to want this
periodic function as well as adding and defining a new class for mapping the wave.
Because in this case, look, you will just look at the solution because in this wave
decreed with samples, the decreed with metadata encoded, okay, was returning the array, was
returning the list of values.
But you need to return an object, an instance of the wave class that you need to define.
That's exercise.
Is that clear?
Yeah.
Exactly.
You just need to define a new wave class.
Now, this is useless for you.
You just need to define.
You just need to define a new wave class as we did for signals.
But instead of containing attributes for signals, you should contain attributes for waves.
Yeah, because I'm trying to stick with the mandatory broke.
Okay.
Sure.
You got a question for me?
Yeah, because you didn't upload maybe.
Over here.
No, no, no.
Don't care about this.
Let me close this one.
Close.
Okay.
Go over here.
And for this one.
Ah, okay.
This one.
So once you did this, so you just need to load out this one.
Load out this dot.
Okay.
Okay, that's good.
You know why?
Because you are in the wrong directory.
Yeah, I couldn't find it.
Let me see.
You're here.
You're in the content.
You're over here, no?
So we can move out first dot PI on the...
Oh, sorry.
We have this different content.
Okay.
Oh, sorry.
What's like show?
This one.
There you go.
Lot.
Oof.
Albers.
Yeah.
Did you find it?
Okay.
That's fine.
Remember to work always in the content and on the in the...
So move.
Just move.
Okay.
So move.
Just move.
Do the same with classes.
Or you can upload directly into the content in the root for...
In the root partition.
Okay.
You got issues?
Perfect.
You solve the exercise?
You're trying to.
Okay.
Absolutely.
That's fine.
But at least write, huh?
Okay.
Please don't use this as the simplest part ever of the crash course.
Yeah.
Exactly.
You probably missed the introduction part where it's...
Okay, okay, okay.
That's clear now.
So you can just download the introduction already from the website in order to get understood
what exactly a signal is and a way it is.
Okay.
Sorry.
I didn't understand.
Exactly.
Excellent.
Oh, printstats is the method that is capable of printing the period of a function as well
as the size.
No, no.
It's a printstats because it's not printing just the period.
It's printing different things like I show in the tutorial because it's printing the
size of the array as well as the period.
So you need to refine it because basically the size of the array belongs to the wave
class on the signal.
Yes.
Okay.
Yeah.
Sorry.
That's correct.
So as your friend here is noticing, I did not implement the print period function in my
implementation of the signal.
I implemented a method that is called a plain stats which is much more generic.
So you need to adapt that method and call it print period or you can choose the implementation
of the printstats.
It's basically the same.
Yeah.
Mm-hmm.
But did you receive the instruction when registering to the form?
I did.
Let's go here.
There we go.
You showed the material getting started, this instruction.
I did all of that, but it didn't contain any more than the help of PY and this.
Mm-hmm.
And this.
Okay.
That's perfect.
That's all I got.
Okay.
That's perfect because you, okay, this is the implementation.
So you all sat.
You all sat.
You just need to call the, try to solve the exercise.
Everything is working.
So what's your issue?
Yes.
I didn't have any of that information.
I didn't have any of this information.
Okay.
So what's your issue?
We did some testing.
So you're not sure that you've got something?
Yeah.
Okay.
So if you have a question, just let me know.
I'm going to take another question.
So what's your issue?
Yes, I didn't have any of that information.
I didn't have any of this information.
About what?
Wave.
Yes, you maybe did not load the wave.
Did you load the wave module?
No, still missing.
By the way, you do the same.
You upload the classes file here, load it, and import that.
The wave?
No, classes.
Yeah, exactly.
Exactly.
Like this one.
Mm-hmm.
Okay.
Yeah.
I don't know why it's throwing an error,
self not defined, but it's correct.
Self, well, frequency is a parameter for this.
Yeah.
This is maybe an indent problem.
Indent problem?
Yeah, maybe.
Okay.
So, yeah, I don't know.
I don't know.
Is it an indent problem?
Yeah, maybe.
I know, you miss out.
The first argument of a function is self.
So for this reason, it's saying that you miss out.
That's all.
Okay.
Time's up.
This is what you find on the solution PIFI.
Okay.
It's just an example of solution.
Do not consider that there are no other solution ever.
You basically have to split the wave from signal.
Then define a class that is called, for example,
a wave that takes three different parameters,
YSTS and frame rate.
Frame rate is not mandatory because we just set up
in fixed wave.
So you have to set up a frame rate.
You just set up in fixed wave.
So what you really need to do
is YSTS.
Then define again, for example, a method for playing.
Okay, I'm playing the sound itself.
That's called...
It's going to call another function
to find the outburst module, like the create audio.
The method plot.
Because you're plotting the wave.
You are not plotting the signal.
So it's maybe much more better to put the plot method
not in the signal, but in the wave.
And then the implementation
of the signal itself is pretty similar
aside from adding these other parameters,
which is the function,
which is the periodic function.
Everything is basically the same.
Let me see, let me see, let me see.
Okay, so the create wave samples...
Sorry, the create wave method,
instead of returning directly the array,
it returns an instance of the wave
where the wave is classed
that you should have declared first.
Is the solution clear?
I'll take it as a yes.
Okay, good.
Good.
So let's get back.
Okay, instead of using your own implementation
of the wave and the signals,
you can just load the classes module,
okay, that you already uploaded
to the Jupyter Notebook.
Okay, and you can obviously import
from classes import signal and wave.
And you can use my implementation
of the object itself.
Okay.
The main point
that I want to talk about
is the way to create a wave.
So, let's say,
the main point here
is, okay,
you needed to change
the implementation
of the single class in order to add
another parameter to the constructor.
But this is not correct.
Suppose that code comes from your colleague
or comes from some legacy framework.
You can change that code itself in order to add
another attribute that someone
just misled or
you're not happy with or probably
you just forgot.
We need to find another way to, let's say,
augmenting the power
of the definition, the declaration
of the object itself.
And for this reason, object-oriented programming
has really an elegant way for solving
this kind of issue, which is called
inheritance.
Inheritance means basically
let's start from a base class, okay,
let's drive a new class that
inherits everything from
the base class, okay, as well as
attributes method as well.
And we need to customize
in terms of, for example,
adding other attributes
or other methods to this
new derived class. So if you are
not happy with the implementation of the
signal, because I just forgot to add the periodic
function, you can obviously change it.
But this is wrong because this could be
somehow related to some legacy framework
or you can extend
the signal base class in order to
define a new version of the signal class.
Let's do it this way.
So let's consider, for example,
the scene waveform,
okay, so instead of considering
the scene waveform, let's consider the scene
waveform. So I define, for example,
a new class here that is called
scene-based.
Now, just let me
see.
Yeah.
Scene-wave-4-based
signal, okay,
that inherits from
and it defines a new
attribute that is called, for example, a function,
okay, which is
the np-scene.
Okay. What we did,
we basically
defined a new class that is called
scene-wave-4-based signal,
okay, that inherits
from signal, so
inherits everything from signal, attributes
and methods, and define a new attribute
that is called n-poison.
In order to make this work, you need
to import np, so import
numpy as np.
Okay, so you can obviously
create an instance of the subject,
okay, like this way,
and now you got
obviously the scene-for-
waveform-based signal,
and you can call, obviously, all the methods
defined in signal, like,
for example, the print-period
method, print-period,
okay.
We didn't define the print-period
inside this class, but since we
are inheriting everything from signal,
we still are going to use the
print-period defined in the parent class,
which is the, just prints
the period, the inverse of the frequency,
the frequency itself.
This is very important behavior,
because what you probably are
going to do now is that you
are delegating
to somewhere else, to someone
else, okay, the
scope, the task of printing the period
itself. In fact,
what we can say is basically that
when you inherit something from a
base class, which is signal right now,
you're delegating everything,
every responsibility to that class,
if not explicitly,
obviously, defined
inside the new definition
of the class.
The main problem
with this implementation
is that if you look at the create
wave samples provided in my library,
the periodic function
is the NP-COS.
COS and SIN are similar, but
they are equal. COS and SIN are just
offset based on 90 degrees.
So we need to,
we are not very happy with
the default implementation of the create
wave samples provided by the common library,
and in general, we are not happy
with the create wave method
provided by the signal,
okay, because in the create wave
method, we didn't pass the
periodic function as well. We just used
the default one. So what we need to do
is overwrite the
method, define it again,
keeping equal
the same name,
because we don't want to break the code
because someone changed the name of the method
of the parent class. We still are going to use
the method of the parent class,
but we are going to use our personal
version of it. So we need to define
again the create wave method.
So if I go over here,
define create wave,
okay,
first argument is obviously
self, okay,
ys,
ds equals create
wave samples, okay,
and so the
signature obviously needs to
be the same of the previous one
and the, let me see, just one thing,
this one,
okay, this was our general implementation.
What we need to add obviously
is another parameter here, that is
the function as well, function.
Okay, so
if I, okay, execute this code,
instead of calling the print period,
I call for example the plot method,
okay,
sorry, sorry, sorry, sorry, plot,
oh,
sorry,
I call the create wave method,
okay, and then the plot wave.
Let me see the other,
oh, yeah,
sure.
Okay.
As you know,
he's complaining about the fact that
he cannot find the frequency
because frequency is an attribute,
an attribute defined in the parent class.
But we are not creating an instance
of the parent class, we are creating an instance
of the derived class. So we
still need to explain Python
how to set up
our basic attributes, frequency,
amplitude, and offset.
So what we need to do is obviously
define a new
constructor method.
Okay, solve,
okay,
and let's use this syntax.
Works and
works.
Okay, and then
let's do this one.
Oops, sorry.
Oops.
Bum, bum, bum, bum, bum.
Let me see.
I'm sorry.
Oh, sorry, didn't get it.
No, sorry.
Underscore?
No,
sorry, one moment.
Just one moment.
Oh, super
neat.
Sorry.
No, it's not the issue.
Sorry,
I committed an error.
The field is called frac.
It's not called frequency.
Yeah, exactly.
And this one is called
amp.
Okay.
Let me see this error.
Okay,
periodic function.
Yeah.
Should be correct.
Flat and API function.
Okay.
The function
while it
Okay.
NumPy is not plot, obviously.
Because the create wave should not return this one,
but should return a wave.
ts, ys.
Yeah.
Frame rate.
Okay.
Okay, that's perfect.
So if you plot now.
Okay.
So we did
We basically defined a new constructor.
Thanks for the suggestion. I didn't say it.
What we call the super.
Super is a very important keyword in Python.
Because it's saying, okay,
call some method, okay,
in the parent class.
So call the constructor method
in the signal class.
And provide all the arguments
that could be passed.
For example, when you declare a scene waveform
in the scene waveform base signal.
So if I provide, for example, amplitude and frequency here,
all these parameters get passed
to the constructor of the parent class.
Since I call this super.init method.
And obviously,
the create wave
implementation is this one.
It is basically the same as before.
But the main difference
is that you need to pass the
you need to pass the period
function as well as the last parameters.
Because the default
implementation of the Alpers library
does not accept a periodic function.
Okay. Or you provide out the
default periodic function that is different
from our one.
So there's an issue. I committed another error.
Because this one is ys,
yes.
Let me see.
Okay. Now it's good. Now it's fine.
So this is a plot.
So what we've seen so far
is basically you are going to
let's say delegate
some behavior to the parent class
like we did in the constructor.
And we were not happy
with the default implementation provided by the
parent class about the create wave, for example.
So what we did is implementing
them again, okay, providing
our personalized, customized
version of the create wave sample
scoring method.
But
there is actually another way you can
use to increase,
let's say, the model, the complexity
of your object, okay.
We use this one, which is basically
is, okay, inherit everything from
a parent class. But
there is some cases where this approach cannot
work. But you can use another approach
provided by the
object-oriented programming, which is called
the composition.
So you are going to compose
the final class
with pieces coming from
other classes. So
think about it.
A scene waveform based signal
is a signal.
So that's okay, inheriting
everything from the
signal itself because we can
probably reuse the print
period. Period is always the same.
Scene, cosine, it's a difference.
But the main issue here is that
if we can set up,
for example, the waveform, the scene
waveform, so setting up
a different waveform for the wave,
that attribute
is some sort of
a feature, okay.
So the waveform is a feature
of a signal.
So the scene waveform is
a signal, but it has
obviously a waveform.
So what we can do now,
we can compose this function in a different
way. If you notice
here,
I define a function
mpSine. mpSine is another
object. It's just an instance of something
that someone created for us,
Lumpai, in this case.
So we are composing
this scene waveform
based signal, inherits everything
from signal because they belong to the same family.
But at the same time,
we define, we compose
this class using another
attribute that is the same, that is
the scene waveform. So from
one side, it obviously
inherits something from someone,
okay, because its response
to the verb is, the verb
be, and from the other side,
it can be composed by something
else because it responds to the verb
have. This is a very,
let's say, this is a trick that I
typically use in order to understand
the difference between delegation,
delegation to the composition.
At this point, you
can obviously,
let's say,
think about inheriting
from multiple classes.
So suppose that
your object, your final object, like the scene
waveform based signal,
belongs to multiple families.
This is not the case, but just
suppose it. It would be good.
Okay.
But there is an issue. There is
an issue with this kind of implementation.
Think about the print period.
We know that when we
call the print period over the
scene waveform based signal,
okay, Python looks
at that name inside
this class.
It didn't find it, and then looks in
the parent class. But if
you have the multiple inheritance
and both classes
implement the print period,
which is the version that Python
will call?
Obviously, there is a rule, okay.
So Python will
won't pick up it
obviously, okay. There is a rule.
But this is a big issue, because if
you don't remember this rule, you
maybe can delegate to a parent
class that this is not exactly what
exactly you're expecting to call.
So in general, the
multiple inheritance in other
programming languages is just forbidden.
So the compiler won't work, like
Java, for example. For this reason, this problem
is called the diamond problem.
So you've got basically two varicatoxial triangles.
Okay. The
existing vertex is the, let's say,
the upper vertex is maybe the
final class, and the other vertex
are the implementation, the existing implementation.
So Python won't know exactly
how the method
you want to call. It tries to call the first one.
The first one that tries is group free.
But this is probably not the
best implementation ever.
Actually,
in multiple inheritance
works pretty well for solving
other issues. Okay.
For example, if you use Django,
Django framework is full of
mixin. A mixin
is a class that
has some custom behavior.
Okay. And this
behavior has not any
parental relationship within the
final class. So
supposed to have, for example, a function,
supposed to have, for example, a class that
is a mixin that helps us to
scale the wave,
reduce the amplitude of the wave.
Okay. There is no relationship
within this class and the
wave itself. This class, all the signals
itself. But it
can offer you some APIs
to do the job.
Let's see an example.
Let's go here. Let's create, for example,
a, oh, sorry.
Okay. Let's create, for example, another class
that is called scale by
to mixin.
Okay.
Okay. This class
defines a method that is called scale.
Okay. First argument is
obviously solve. Okay.
And it returns basically
solve.yS.
Yeah.
Okay. Sorry.
Okay.
So let's define a class that is called scale by to mixin.
It defines a method that is called scale
which takes the array
of the samples and just
divides them by two. So it
scales down the amplitude of the wave
itself. So
if we define, for example, a new
version of the wave, let's call it augmented
wave. Augmented wave.
The itinerary is from wave.
Okay.
What we can do is that
it obviously, that's the follow method
that is called scale. Okay.
And it returns
super
dot scale.
Self dot yS.
Okay.
So we extended the wave,
our wave implementation
with a new class.
Define a new method, a new API,
generic API that is called scale
that in turns equals
something like the scale. In order to
make this super work, we need to
extend the augmented wave
with the scale by to mixin.
So what we can do
is that basically go over here
and add this class.
Okay.
And now we need to define again
the signal class.
Let me see.
Let's call, for example,
a new signal.
Okay.
Sorry.
Def create wave.
Okay.
Let's take the implementation
from here.
Okay.
But instead of returning the wave, it returns
the augmented wave.
Okay.
So what you can do is this one.
You create a signal.
Okay. You call the method create wave.
It returns the wave.
And you
can call the wave dot scale method.
Okay.
Wave dot
offset yS.
Okay.
Is this one. Wave dot plot.
Wave dot plot.
But
what is this?
Yeah.
Sure. This one.
Oh, it's basically the same.
Just one moment.
Okay.
Let's see.
Signal.
Okay.
Yeah. Sure.
This is a function.
And this one.
Perfect.
So let's look at the code.
We define a scale by tubing same.
Which offer an API that is capable of
scaling something. Okay.
It's doing something. It's not very relevant now.
We define a new version of the wave.
Okay. That is called augmented wave.
But we
let's say from two different classes.
But the main problem, the main issue
or the main difference is scaled by two mixin
is not related by any parental
relation with the wave or
the augmented wave. Which we
just added this mixin
in order to add some custom
behavior to the augmented wave.
We then define an API that is called
scale. That in turn is called the
scale by two mixin scale method.
We then define a new signal that
in turn
is not going to call the signal
okay, it's not in reads from the signal
but in reads from the same wave form
based signal that we just
augmented with new feature like
defining the periodic function.
And then we define again the create wave.
Okay. Returning this time
an instance of augmented wave.
Obviously of this one. And then
you create a signal here and then
you call the scale and then you call the plot.
And you get all the things.
So the thing that I want to notice
is that the
inheritance is transitive.
So new signal in reads from
same wave form based
signal that in reads from
signal. So you are going to
let's say make an object
much much more complex until the
your complexity of the world evolves.
You want to try to explain
better to the computer itself
defining these classes, okay.
And you still in reading everything
from all the
ancestors. So what you have
here is that basically you
in reads from the same wave
waveform but the method print period
for example that does not be defined in this
class is defined in the signal would be
always available. So if I call
for example this method.
Okay.
So if I call the print period, the print period
has not been defined in the same wave base form
but is defined in the signal. And that's fine
because the inheritance is transitive.
So Python looks
for every ancestor until it finds
the method we are going to call.
This concludes
our second part about object
oriented programming. So let's try
to recap just two different things.
First of all is the diamond problem.
In this case
the
multiprogram inheritance
works pretty well because there is no
relationship between wave and scale to mix in.
Because scale to mix in
has no relation at all with wave.
So you can't have basically
some sort of methods that
have been called the same. So Python
cannot be wrong about this.
And we obviously
showed that
using the multiple inheritance and
stating that an object belongs to two different
families can lead to the
diamond problem. So Python doesn't know exactly
what methods you are meant to call.
Okay, because there are multiple versions
of the same method defined in the
parent class. But a
nice usage for example
in multiple inheritance, it is
mixing. It is very widely, widely,
widely used in all the framework around the web
in Python for example like Django.
If you want in Django for example add the support for
get trickest, pause trickest,
delete trickest. What you need to do
is just adding to your controller
to your view
mixing, different kind of mixing. Delete mixing,
update mixing, etc, etc,
etc. So even if the
form is the same, I want to stress you out about this
concept. Even if the form is
the same, the meaning
of wave and scale by
to mix in inside the definition of
the parented wave is profoundly different.
Because this one
implies a relationship between them.
Parental relationship.
While the scale to mix in has
only the same syntax, but
it expresses a very different concept.
Questions?
Okay, second exercise.
And then we have a pause.
Okay.
So your exercise
would be
number two. You need to
write up dictionaries, serializers,
and mixin. So a
class that should
implement a method that is called
serialize.
That this in turn is going to print
the amplitude, the phase, and frequency
of a signal as a dictionary.
So take a dictionary,
you need to compose it using this class.
Then you need to
extend the scene wave form based
signal that you can find on the classes
module
to include a new method
that call the mixin serialize
method, like we did with scale.
Obviously you can import the scene
wave form based signal from classes
module. That's all.
So if you have questions,
you ask me.
Okay.
I don't need this. I'm okay with this.
Is the exercise clear now?
No.
Okay.
Sorry.
Equals.
Okay.
Problems? Questions?
Yeah.
Okay.
Did you
load the class module?
Yeah.
You load it with the percent
load command.
Right here.
When I was able to
import the scene wave.
Let me see the error.
Yeah.
Just look for it.
Okay.
Yeah.
Sorry.
I spotted another error.
That class is not
defined in the
UTS. So you need to
maybe copy or just wait for me.
I push the code down just now.
You want to copy or push the code?
Yeah.
Push the code.
Okay.
What class is?
I pushed the scene wave form definition to the classes file,
so you just need to download it again and load it again.
Otherwise you can copy from the code.
Yes, sure.
Yeah.
Mm-hm, mm-hm.
This one.
One moment.
Okay.
You solved the issue?
You solved the exercise?
Let me see.
Yeah, perfect.
But you need to define, you need to add a new API over here that is calling the serializer
function.
Okay.
That's all.
Yes, it's not mandatory, but honestly my personal opinion is much more clear that you need to
call basically an API that is not taking any kind of parameters and call the serialized
function that takes all the parameters.
Because in this way, if you offer this one, serialized method would be available to the
client, but client needs to know that you need to provide you the AMP, Face, and Frac.
My AMP, Face, and Frac are the state of the object, so you have it.
So if you offer, you get the idea.
Oh, by the way, this is openable.
This is my personal point.
I typically prefer looking at this.
Yeah, the idea would be that you offer the user the simplest API ever.
Okay, so if you require that user can type your parameters, you make his life much more complex.
If you offer an API that takes not parameter as well, okay, it's much more simple.
We got a pause in 10 minutes, no?
We got a pause in 10 minutes.
10 and 30.
Sorry.
Ah, yeah, yeah.
As you want.
Okay.
Just one thing.
On the Wave, there is another method, an ether API that can offer you the library I sent to you
that is going to play the sound, okay?
So if you're going to play, you should have something like this.
If you press play here, you listen to some sound.
Okay.
You fixed it?
Did you solve the exercise?
Okay.
Do the exercise.
And I'll work until getting a gain.
Okay.
But I see my personal solution of the exercise.
And I want to add just a few different things.
First of all, the definition of the dictionary serializer mixing is pretty easy.
Okay.
It implements an API that is called serialize that takes amplitude, frequency, and phase
as arguments and just returns the serialization as a dictionary of those attributes.
And then you define the class that extends our base signal, function base signal,
that offers you a custom API that is called serialize that takes no parameters.
And it is capable to call the serialized method of the mixing itself.
So this is not actually the only solution ever.
Because if you think about it, you can try to do not implement the serialized function
inside the extended version of the signal.
You can call directly the serialized function of the dictionary serialized mixing.
But there is an issue using this approach.
If you call directly this function itself without implementing some sort of proxy over here,
you need to provide all these parameters.
But all these parameters are part of the state, the state of the object itself.
So you don't need as a client to know that you need to provide this kind of parameters.
Because it is inside the object itself.
I was just saying that general rule is offering client the much simpler API ever.
So if you can avoid to provide parameters, it's always better.
And hide all the complexity of calling something with parameters inside,
under the hood.
One more thing.
Yeah.
Yeah, it's a extended version of the signal.
Yeah, because this one is missing.
Yeah, correct.
I fixed the code and pushed out the line.
I'm sorry, this is how live coding so good.
Why does a person with a serialized not have a cell-amplifier frequently tell phase?
That's a fine question.
I tried to, at the very beginning, we got a break here, so feel free to leave, obviously.
At the very beginning, we talked about the difference between signal and wave.
And we state that a class for modeling signals and a class for modeling wave.
So you are a class for one single responsibility basically.
Which is a very important principle of object-oriented programming.
So I'm going to ask you, is the Dictionary Satellizer Mixin needs to know the internal state of the object?
In my opinion, no.
Because the Dictionary Satellizer Mixin is just an helper class to provide a way to serialize something.
And the thing is, they are just parameters.
I could write here, instead of amp, freq, phase, I could a, b, c.
It's totally the same.
Because the Dictionary Satellizer object in my mind has no knowledge at all of signal or waves.
It's just a new class that offered me a service.
And the service is serialization.
For this reason, there is no self-amp inside the Dictionary Satellizer Mixin.
Otherwise, if you think, it would be not a mixin anymore.
Because in this case, there was some sort of parental relationship between the signal and the Dictionary Satellizer Mixin.
But we say that mixin had nothing to do.
They just had some behavior, some other function, some helper's methods to solve a particular issue.
Other question? Yeah.
Is, sorry, I didn't get it.
Yeah, yeah, they are the same.
Yeah, they are synonymous.
Yeah.
If you study telecommunication engineering, the right name is phase.
It's not offset.
But in order to be understood offset, it's just the delay.
But if you talk delay for telecommunication engineering, they probably won't understand.
Okay, so talk with phase.
Yeah, obviously not.
This is the most generalized one.
I want to say one more thing.
Okay.
A method
that can be noticed,
whatever,
is Dictionary Satellite Mixin.
A method like this is somehow useless,
because it's basically using that constructor
takes every kind of arguments, it wraps inside arcs and quarks,
and calls the constructor method of the init class.
So actually, you can remove it.
But they just make this a sample to explain
the importance of the super, which
calls a method that comes from some ancestors.
It could be direct parent of another ancestor.
That's all.
So we have a bracket we see at 11.
Yeah?
Yeah.
So there's a concept in Python that is called method resolution order.
We basically state this thing.
If you have a method that has been defined into different two parent classes,
okay, Python, just look the first one.
So you basically go over the first parent class,
you look for the method, the method exists, okay, stop it.
If the method does not exist, you go for the fourth parent class, and
you look at the other methods.
If you find okay, if you're not fine,
you get the method not found exception that you basically are.
Yeah.
Yes.
Yeah, yes, the order of the parent classes, yeah.
But in general, it's not really, at least in my personal experience,
I do not ever feel this wave of using the multiple in a written slacking this way.
I always use mixin because there's probably there are some changes into
the Python version, so they change the real law of resoluting methods.
And this logic that you get used to, let's say,
to stick with is probably not applicable anymore.
So if you update the Python, you'll find that some code,
some piece of code doesn't work anymore because they just change the method
they resolve.
So for this reason, for this reason, if you are going to use the multiple in a
written, you can use the composition.
So instead of in a written, extending everything from the parent class,
you create a new class that is as an attribute that is an instance of another
class, so you compose a new class.
So think about the difference between composition and delegation.
You are delegating if you inherit from, but you can compose at the same time.
Java, for example, does not support, exactly for this reason,
the multiple inheritance.
So in Java, you can inherit just one class.
So Java has not concept of mixin, for example.
Mixin in Java can be implemented in other ways.
We have a bracket.
I cannot force to stay here.
11.
Half an hour, actually, but we lost 10 minutes.
Okay, so in this third part of this crash course, you're going to see something very
relevant that is not very widely used in Python itself.
If you came from other languages, you can find much more intense representation,
much more intense usage.
But in Python, it is somehow relevant to introduce this concept because it can
leave you some sort of, let's say, another guideline to be used when you develop
software using the object for the anti-programming part.
Let's start from the real world example.
We played with the note piano, but note piano is very boring.
At some point, you want to transmit, for example, an audio transmission to
somewhere else, to someone else.
But the channel, the wire, the air is capable of adding so much noise and make
the sound itself not being capable of understood when you reach the final destination.
So what we typically do as engineers is implementing a modulation system.
So a modulation system is just a system that is capable to add some sort of
transformation to the original wave.
It basically has two different areas.
One's for modulating and one's for demodulating.
So you take the original wave, you modulate it, you get the modulated wave,
and in order to, let's say, listen the modulated wave, you need to demodulate it.
So what we are trying to do now is defining this behavior.
Okay, let's try to define a new class.
Okay, this class is called modulator.
Okay, and you have two different methods.
Modulate and demodulate.
Okay, first argument is always self.
So first argument is the self.
And the second argument, this is the, let's call it information wave.
Information wave, okay.
And in order to modulate, in order to apply this kind of transformation to the signal
that you want to send, you need to have another wave.
A wave that helps you out to apply this kind of transformation.
This wave is called modulating wave.
Modulating, sorry, let's call it carrier wave.
Okay, and the same applies for demodulate,
which in turn takes the modulated wave as the input.
And the carrier wave.
Okay, wave, okay, pass, oops.
Okay, so instead of implementing the methods now,
we are just defining the behavior.
So we are just defining how this kind of modulation system will work from
external point of view.
We are not providing this now, the implementation of the modulation,
because I did not say which exactly modulation type we are going to use
to send the signal to your friend.
So what we can do now is, instead of implementing something, we raise an error.
Raise, not implemented, okay.
You need to implement this method before calling.
You'll understand everything in a while.
Just stick with me.
So if the user is going to use the modulator, he's going to get an error,
because he can't use directly the modulate and
then the modulate methods, because they are not implemented actually.
In order to enforce this kind of behavior of this strange class,
we need to import something from the library of Python itself.
From ABC, import abstract class method.
Abstract method, sorry.
And we can add a decorator over here that this method is called abstract.
Okay, what we define here is called in other language an interface or a contract.
You're just saying that, man, a modulation system should implement,
it should respect this signature.
But you can call directly this class, so you can create the object,
the instance of the modulator class and call the modulate and
the modulate method, because we need to provide some kind of implementation.
That could be different depending on the kind of modulation
we're trying to work with, okay?
So in order to enforce this at, let's say,
Python level, we added a decorator that comes from the ABC model.
ABC stands for abstract base class.
Instead of before, this class is abstract, so
it does not provide an implementation.
It cannot be used directly.
You need to provide some sort of implementation first.
And we just decorated all these two methods with this nice decorator.
The simplest modulation system ever is called the amplitude modulation.
You probably, if you have an old car, you find EM modulation.
Is the way that you can transform the original signal.
Let's say mapping the signal itself into variation of the amplitude, okay?
But there are other ways of modulating signal,
like the frequency modulation, FM, or the phase modulation, PM.
Actually, AM is the most simplest form of modulation,
because it requires very simple device in order to modulate and demodulate.
While on the other side, FM is much more efficient in terms of span power,
in terms of, let's say, resistance and resilience to the noise of the channel.
It could be a wire, it could be the, etc., etc.
But the amplitude modulation is the simplest form of modulation ever.
Obviously, we are talking about modulation of analog signal,
not the digital signal, because we're playing with, let's say, analog,
with old radio, okay?
But you can apply all these things to digital signal, but
obviously this is out of scope.
So what we need to do now is implementing the amplitude modulator.
So my amplitude modulator, amplitude modulator, would be a class, okay,
that extends the modulator, okay?
And it defines two different methods.
Okay, I need to remove this one, because it's useless.
I need to remove this one, this one, this one, okay.
The modulating method is very, very easy in amplitude modulation,
because it's just about multiplication between the carrier wave and
the signal wave.
So what I can write is this one.
Information wave, star, carrier wave.
And the demodulation is basically the same, but
instead of considering the information wave, you consider the modulated wave.
Good.
Okay, so now, let's import something from the Alpers.
Alpers import, let me see, create audio, okay?
Create audio, okay, takes a wave.
So you can provide your own wave, or
you can provide a sample wave that they sent you.
And if I run this code, okay, the creative audio is capable of,
just one moment.
Buh, buh, buh, buh, buh.
Sorry, it's not the creative audio, it's the get wave samples,
get wave samples, okay.
Okay, good.
So if you run this code, basically, you are going to use this function that
is defining the Alpers function called get wave samples.
You pass the audio that you want to read, and
this is going to return you some data.
You remember well, this is the S, this is YS, this is the frame rate, okay?
So frame rate is this one, just a few words about the frame rate.
We always play the frame rate of 3,000, okay?
But in general, for digital signal processing,
in order to be able to reconstruct the signal after it has been digitalized,
you need to work with the frequency of frame rate that is at least
double the frequency of the wave itself.
So if you know that our voice stands from 20 hertz or 20 kilohertz,
the frame rate is higher than the double.
So this is a very typical value, okay, because it's able to,
let's say, handling all the voice, just all the voice.
This would be maybe not sufficient for all the music.
So for example, if you work with this frame rate with the music,
you could lose, for example, some components in term of frequency.
And maybe you can sound your song in a different way.
But for voices, this frame rate is pretty good.
So this function is able to read the wave and get the array of YS,
the array of TS, as well as the frame rate.
So TS, YS, frame rate.
Okay, this one.
Perfect.
So we can create, for example, the wave, okay.
TS, oh, sorry.
YS, TS, frame rate, okay?
So we just created the instance of our wave.
Nothing complicated.
Okay, so this is our information wave.
So information wave is this one.
We need a carrier wave.
A carrier wave is another wave.
Carrier wave, okay.
So let's start from signal.
Let's consider, for example, a frequency of,
let's put the, for example, 100,000, yeah, 100,000 hertz.
Okay, that's good.
Call the method create wave.
Okay, so the carrier wave is another wave.
Everything clear?
Perfect.
So now we are going to use our modulation system.
So we create the instance of the amplitude modulator.
Look, the amplitude modulator, not the modulator abstract base class over here.
The implementation of the contract.
And we can call, obviously, the modulator, okay?
If you call, for example, the modulator, what do you get?
You pass the information wave and the carrier wave.
And you execute this code.
Good.
You get the seller.
Unsupported operand four star, wave.wave.
But the main issue is that how Python can know how exactly
it will be able to multiplicate waves.
You can expect that Python knows how to multiplicate flaws,
integers, maybe strings, I don't know, but now waves.
Because there is no concept of wave multiplication.
So we need to instruct Python to do this kind of operation.
And in order to do this, what we need to do?
We need to define another class.
The class we need to define is called, for example, let me put here.
Blah, blah, blah.
Okay, let's define for example a new class.
Class wave with mall.
Okay, so this is a class that basically implements the multiplication logic
that we see in a while.
That obviously, in reads from the wave, because we know that this is still a wave.
So we just need behavior, but can change the original code.
That's fine.
And the method we are going to implement is called mall.
Okay, solve.
And the only parameter that takes these methods is the other wave.
Okay, let's look at this definition.
We created a new class.
In everything from the wave, because we still know that the wave with mall is
still a wave.
With a finite method, we start with the double underscored that is called mall.
Okay, that takes just one parameter, the other.
Which is basically the second factor in the multiplication.
So the first factor is self, second one is the other.
Good.
If you notice well, mule starts with a double underscore like the unit,
like the constructor method.
Which means that this method can be called magic.
They are reserved.
They cannot be used for whatever task it is.
Because Python, when you write a wave with mall star,
another wave with mall, will execute this method.
And thus, the multiplication will work magically.
So the implementation is very easy.
What we do is just returning a wave, an instance of itself, okay?
Where you have the self.y s star.other, okay?
This is s, and so this is self.ts, self.frame rate.
Okay?
So the new samples will be just the multiplication of the
left factor multiplication, y s, and self.other.y s, sorry.
This one is wrong, y s.
The argument, dot y s.
So you take the, those array, you multiply it down.
Obviously, multiplication between array is not defined by Python.
But if you are going, if we use numpy,
in numpy someone defined the operation of multiplication.
So someone in numpy has implemented the same way of
multiplicating waves, by just under the hoods.
So if you run this code, yeah, let me check, is it correct?
Yes, so if you run this code, you get this one.
The main problem is that the, let me see, just one moment.
Yeah, the main problem is that the information wave is a web
instance, it's not a wave with mall instance.
So we need to transform it.
You could obviously change this signature in order to add
the wave with mall instead of calling wave.
But we are going to see another way.
Let's go back to our implementation of wave with mall.
Okay, let's define a new method that is called, for example, convert.
Okay, convert, so, okay.
But this time, instead of passing the instance as the first argument,
we are going to pass another object, an object that is totally different,
an object that is wave, okay?
So instead of passing the self, like we always do,
we pass the wave, which is another object.
So this method will return an instance of wave with mall,
okay, where you have the ys equals to wave ys,
ts, wave ts, and frame rate,
frame rate, wave, frame rate.
Okay, so we're basically accepting an instance of type wave.
An instance of type wave, okay?
And returning an instance of type with mall with this strange method that
does not accept self as parameter, so distance.
A method like this is called static.
And in order to let Python know that this method behaves differently from
other ones, we need to add another annotation.
Sorry, another decorator.
The decorator is the static method.
Okay, if you execute this code, you got no errors.
So we provide a static method that does not depend on the context of the object.
This takes in place the only task of converting an incoming
wave instance to itself, to an instance of itself, basically.
This is not very mandatory, you know, because we could have changed just
the definition of rear, okay?
The definition of rear, because we know that wave away with mall,
aside from defining the mall methods, are basically the same.
It's basically the same.
So if you can call the constructor passing the wave with mall,
everything is gonna work.
But in order to make you aware of the fact that there are other kinds of
type of methods that Python supports, this is static one.
This is typically usage of a static method.
Convert something into other one.
Because if you think about it, it's a static because it does not depend
of the state of the object itself.
It's some sort of an upper method.
It helps you just to map one thing to another one.
So if you run the code, okay.
So we need to adapt, obviously, this code.
Because now we need to call wave with mall, okay?
We call it the convert, okay?
We pass the information wave, okay?
And this is the information wave with mall, okay.
Sorry for the name.
Okay, we do the same here.
I know, sorry, one moment.
Okay, let's see this object.
Just to see if it's correct.
Okay, so this is an instance of main wave with mall.
So we need to do the same with the carrier wave.
With mall equals this one.
But instead of this one, this one, okay?
Okay, so if you run the modulation now.
You need to adapt this one with this one.
They're different, yeah, that's correct.
Signal.
Okay, because the duration.
Yeah, okay, sorry, one moment.
Duration.
Now they got different shape.
Let me see.
Just one moment.
Boom, boom, boom, boom.
Okay, create wave.
What's the issue?
Mm-hm.
Wave with mall.
Okay, that's fine.
That's fine.
Okay, we obviously need to have some constraints between the carrier wave and
the information wave, so we can just create a carrier wave from scratch.
We need to be sure that the direction is the same, and
also the frame rate is the same, otherwise the operation of
multiplicating waves doesn't work because they got different sides in terms of values.
So that was the issue.
So if I execute this code, I got this one, okay?
The obviously an instance of wave with mall, so
the modulate function is returning a wave with mall.
Modulated wave, okay, and if you modulated wave.plot.
Okay, fantastic.
It's totally wrong.
Now let me see, just one moment.
Okay, now this is wrong.
The ration.
Yes, okay, that's fine.
Okay.
Yeah, just let me, just one moment.
Sorry?
No,
it should be okay this one.
Yes, here?
No.
Okay, here.
Okay, let me see.
No, just one moment.
Okay.
So information wave.
Okay, now let's go.
Okay, was messing up with the, yeah,
the constraint between the carrier wave and the zero wave.
So what you basically learned is that,
okay, was messing up with the, yeah,
the constraint between the carrier wave and the zero wave.
So what you basically have to do, I will see,
just look at this one, you see something that the amplitude,
okay, is varying in according to the same function.
So it basically, the amplitude modulation shapes the information
it needs to send in according to the carrier wave,
which was the same.
And you see that basically here you got this something like that
looks like the same, obviously.
It's not the same, actually.
So this was the example.
And if you plot this now, if you remember the first part
of the introduction, I say that time to time is better to look
at the wave in the frequency domain, not in the time domain.
So if instead of calling the plot method,
you call the plot full FFT methods, okay,
you see basically this one, which is in this case
is the spectrum of the modulated wave,
actually the full one.
Okay, if you want to demodulate it, okay,
you can demodulate the wave, okay.
So let me take this one.
Amplitude.
Modulator, okay.
And the, sorry, first function is demodulate this one,
carrier wave.
Okay.
Plot.
Okay, and there was the original signal.
So what is basically needs to be understood is just as the part
about signal processing, but the part about defining class.
We start in defining an interface, a contract,
a template, something that cannot be directly used
because it's abstract, okay, and you can read it just
because we decorated all the methods,
adding the abstract method decorator.
So the user cannot use obviously this one,
but is forced to implement demodulator abstract by class,
providing for example the amplitude modulator,
which is just a way of modulating things.
So obviously the signature of the implementation
should be the same, needs to be the same
of the one defined in the abstract class.
And once you do this one, you can obviously play with the code
and get this one.
At the same point, we notice that we don't know how exactly
to multiply waves together.
Just one moment.
Multiply them together.
So we can apply a new instance of the wave with mall
with a cost-adding method capable of converting
an existing wave to a wave with mall method.
And then after that, what we need to do is just
instantiating the object over here,
call the modulator providing the converted version of the wave,
converted version of the carrier wave,
and then get back to using the demodulator.
Please.
Yeah, you can find it in the classes module as well.
Yeah, sure, sure, sure.
But in the context of object-oriented programming,
let's say you are not free to use functions
that are not related to objects.
So this is the issue.
So if you play with Java, you cannot define, for example,
functions that are not dependent on objects or classes.
Okay, so for this reason, we code it this way.
But yes, you can code a function, a general function,
in some sort of a model that takes an object and converts it.
We saw in this implementation declined in the object-oriented paradigm.
This is the issue.
So you can do whatever you want, but this is the, let's say,
the right way to do with objects in the object-oriented programming.
So in Java, your solution won't work, for example,
because Java is somehow pure.
Okay, thank you.
So the exercise.
Other questions?
Okay, so part three of the exercise.
Okay, in the classes module, you'll find a filter class.
A filter class is an interface.
It's not a class, so you can't use it directly.
What you need to do is implementing the high-pass filtering,
which is basically is a filter that is capable of cutting off
all the components, okay, greater than a threshold.
So if you go back, for example, to the spectrum,
so you have the spectrum on the x-axis and the value of the power on the y-axis,
an high-pass filter removes part of the spectrum, okay,
starting from a cutoff frequency.
So your first exercise would be look at the filter interface
I defined in the classes and implement the high-pass filtering method.
Second part of the exercise would be more complex, okay, it requires time.
So I'm not expecting that you can fix it.
You can solve it now, okay.
But what you basically have to do is this one.
I want to explain it.
This one is the wave in the frequency domain, the original wave.
So it's the signal that you want to send.
Good.
Once you modulate, you get this one, which is the same signal,
but you got a really bad product of amplitude modulation,
which is of course sidebands for replicas.
You see, those are basically the same as this, but they are being scalded.
Okay, this is a problem for just one issue because they consume so much power, okay,
that you can try to, let's say, avoid when you're sending
because you want to reduce the amount of power sent.
So your implementation, okay, and after you get back to the modulation,
you should have something like this,
which should be something like the signal you sent at the very beginning.
So the implementation, the task would be doing this.
Implementing an amplitude modulation with low-pass filtering.
That overrides the demodulate,
so you need to implement the modulator interface again, basically.
But you are not happy with the demodulation method that I provided to you.
So you need to override that method in the amplitude modulator,
not in the units, but in the class.
The new implementation should remove the sidebands,
so the bands that are laterally, okay.
And this modulated wave, okay, sorry,
these sidebands are totally useless when the wave reaches the destination.
Talking in code, did you understand the domain problem?
Or I'm going to repeat it.
I take a yes.
But by the way, if you did not understand the domain problem,
I try to rephrase it again.
Talking in code, you need to call the original demodulate method
of the existing amplitude modulator.
But you need to add something.
You need to add the filter part.
In order to add the filter part, you need to, first of all,
convert the wave to the spectrum.
At the very beginning, we saw that you got a wave in time domain.
You can get, using some custom function, the spectrum,
which is the same wave, but in the frequency domain.
So instead of considering the independent variable as the T, it's the X.
Once you compute the spectrum, okay, you can define, sorry,
these instance of the spectrum after you call this method,
basically are these fields, which is very similar to the wave one,
HS, FS, and frame rate.
And when you do this, so when you have the spectrum,
you can import the low-pass filter.
This has been already implemented to you, that implements the filter.
Call the make wave after filtering has been applied, and
then you should get the original representation of the wave.
So first part is very easy.
Take the filter interface, define in the classes file, and
implement a version of high-pass filtering, okay?
Obviously, in the upper side, you find the high-pass function, so
you cannot just write it, okay?
You need just to import it, it should be easy.
Second part is not very easy, because you need to understand the domain
problem first, and then apply it later.
By the way, I'm here to the conference, so
if you wanna solve it, we can obviously discuss maybe later.
But as always, you find the implementation inside the solutions file.
Okay, you got 30 minutes.
So be focused on the first part of the exercise.
The second part, we can discuss maybe later if the domain problem is not clear.
Yeah.
Okay.
We are first before getting to code.
Yeah.
Where is it?
In the classes, classes module.
From classes, import filter.
Thank you.
Okay.
For the second part, if you, I repeat, if you want to solve it, you need to be sure you understand the domain problem first.
And then talking about the code.
So if you want to have some doubts, we can obviously discuss maybe privately.
I just, I didn't, I know that this issue was, sorry, this problem was a bit more complex.
Okay.
So this leads us to the final part of our, of our crash course in object-oriented programming.
There is one more thing that you need to know to getting start with object-oriented programming.
Is the concept of design patterns.
Design patterns are solutions to recurrent problems.
Which means that when you play with object-oriented programming, you have grasped that it's all about defining class,
establishing relation between them, override methods, call supermetals, whatever.
You can't reinvent the wheel in order to solve something.
So there are these standardized solutions that help you work with object-oriented programming in a very standardized way.
I want to stress you out about the fact that it would be maybe much easier to reinvent the wheel all again in order to play with objects.
But this probably is a design pattern that have been designed and proved to be correct, proved to be scalable,
proved to be very interesting, very smart, okay, for solving your own issue.
But we're going to see an example now.
Design patterns are typically divided into three main categories.
Design patterns creationals that deals with creation of object.
If you remember well, at the very beginning, we defined a constructor with four different parameters,
Sorry, four different parameters, amplitude, phase, frequency, periodic function.
But it's a very, I don't like that much, that kind of implementation.
Because if your model obviously evolves and evolves and evolves,
you can end up obviously adding more elements of the constructor signature as well as
obviously implementing classes that in a risk from the previous implementation.
That's fine. But there are some design patterns that we play with objects in order to make,
to make their list of parameters not fixed at all and be ready to evolve.
So we reinvented the wheel, defining four different parameters in the constructor,
but we didn't know nothing about design patterns.
Behavioral pattern deals with how object behaves from the outside.
So suppose you want to hide some business logic, okay?
Okay, like the one we did for example, the serialize.
You did not want to force users to provide you the amplitude, the frequency at the offset
when you call the serialize method, because you hide that business logic inside the class itself.
So behavioral design patterns, response to this problem,
they establish some ways to wrap the behavior inside
let's say a series of the class in order to change how they appear at the site.
And last category, structural design pattern.
You got for example a different list of algorithms
that always belong to the same family.
Consider the modulation. The modulation is family of algorithms, okay?
But you have amplitude modulation, frequency modulation, phase modulation.
Structural patterns deals with the finding way to try
find out some solution to wrap up all these things
inside a common container, let's put this way.
And help the client define which algorithm should be used
without letting me know how the algorithm itself will work.
We are going to see one of this, one of the
design patterns. And let's say the one that we are going to see is called the
iterator. Iterator probably sounds familiar to you because Python
offers it natively. But the
we're going to see the orthodox implementation of the iterator using design patterns.
And we are going to see how Python implements it.
Before seeing how to implement the iterator design pattern, let me say what an iterator is.
Suppose you have a collection. So you have something that could be
iterated, okay? So something that is by definition iterable.
Like a list, like a graph, like a chart, like a tree for example.
So you can use it to create a list. List is very simple data structure. Think about
tree or graphs. Okay.
So you want to wrap the logic of traversing this iterable
inside the object and offer the final user just the way
to traverse this object. So you can find an object that can help you traverse, for example, the list
that you want. But you can have another object that can help you to traverse
the list from end to begin. Or another one that goes for the first to the last
to the second to the second last, et cetera, et cetera, et cetera. That's good. So you want to hide
this kind of complexity, okay, and let the user just choose the way
he wants to traverse the list itself, all the chart, the graph itself.
So what we are going to do, sorry, what we are going to need basically are two different
classes. An iterator, okay, this is the interface
of this object. The iterable, which is the interface that makes an object
iterable. So an object that can be looped through. So let's define
this one, for example, the iterator. Okay, that's good. And let's define
for example the iterable. Okay.
We should know that basically they are abstract classes, so they
are going to be treated like abstract, okay. So
if you think about it, what exactly an iterator is going to work?
It should support two different methods. A method for getting the nest element of the
collection and a method to check if the collection has been completed looped.
Okay, if I've been looped completely. So define, for example,
a method that is called next, okay, and a method
that is called as next, as next.
Okay, those methods are obviously abstract. Good.
And this one is abstract. Okay.
These rights are not implemented there, we know.
Okay, and this one. Good. So let's start from an implementation
of iterator. Let's consider the most simplest iterator ever. An iterator that goes,
that traverses this object from beginning to end. So let's call, for example, a sequential
iterator. Okay, that implements the iterator.
Okay, it does the same signature as well.
Okay.
Okay. So the first thing is
we need an object to be iterated. So let's define, for example, a collection.
Okay. And let's put up some known for now. Define, for example,
a unit constructor, so constructor self, collection.
Okay. Self dot collection.
Plus collection. Good. We can move this one.
Perfect. So the method next
should be able, when called, to return the next element of the iteration.
Okay. So what it's going to do is, I define an index,
for example, I index, set up to zero, and check.
Sorry. Element equals to
self, self dot collection.
Okay.
One return element.
So the implementation of the...
Okay.
So the implementation of the next method will be pretty easy.
Okay. It's looking for the hit element
of the collection, the collection interval. Okay.
Increment the and return the element itself. So the first time this method will be called,
it's on the first element. Second time, you return the second element, et cetera, et cetera, et cetera.
But still, we need to implement some sort of method to check if the collection has been completely
iterated in order to not rise an index error, because otherwise if we provide
an index that is bigger than the length of the collection itself,
it will fail, obviously. So the implementation of the as next
would be something like, return e is
less than length of the self collection.
Sorry.
Okay.
Does it sound correct to you? Okay.
From the other side, the iterable class.
It's very generic. Okay. It's just saying that
okay, this class has this kind of strange behavior. It can be iterated, but
it can add no more methods, no action, nothing. So it could define, for example,
our signal. Okay. So let's start from signal. Let's call the create wave.
Good. Wave.
Perfect. We need to state somehow
that the wave is iterable. So what we do? We do the same.
We define a new class, iterable wave, that extends from
iterable. Okay.
So we define a new class that is called iterable wave.
Inner is from wave. It does the iterable, which is basically just now a placeholder.
Okay. It says that, hey man, this iterable wave is iterable, so you can iterate
through. But the definition is basically empty. Okay. It has no method as well.
And from the other side, we can define, obviously, a sequential iterator.
Okay. Okay. So
suppose now you create the
iterable wave.
Okay.
Let's do this way.
Iterable wave.
Okay. Just creating an instance of iterable wave from the wave.
Perfect. Once you got the iterable wave, you can
create an instance of the sequential iterator.
Okay. That's here. And the constructor of the sequential iterator
gets called with a collection. So something that is iterable.
In order to do this, we are going to pass, for example, the Y samples.
Okay. Good. Sequential iterator.
Okay. So now when you have this subject,
you can start iterating things. So you can start iterate
each value inside the array of samples in the wave.
So what we can do is,
let's say, some school code.
So while sequential iterator has next,
sequential iterator.next.
So we check until the sequential
iterator has next,
so we check until the sequential iterator has next
element. And we know that has next element check if the
iterable collection has been looped through completely. And if we found it,
obviously, we can call the next method in order to get the next element of the
iterator. So if we run this code,
we can see that the iterator has been looped through completely.
And we can see that the next element has been looped through completely.
So we can see that the next element has been looped through completely.
Just one moment.
Yeah.
One moment. Let me see the code.
Just restarting everything. So let's load the game.
Okay. Load classes.
Okay.
Yeah. Sure.
Correct.
Okay.
Okay. In a way that it prints just the first 10 elements.
So is this code okay for you?
But did you get the general idea of the iterator?
Okay. Obviously, we define a sequential iterator because we want to start from the first, second, third, blah, blah, blah.
But you can define whatever logic you want in the sequential iterator. You just need to
Okay. You want to traverse from beginning to end? Good. Use the sequential iterator.
You want to traverse in reverse order? Okay. I will provide you a reverse iterator that obviously
implements the same interface as the sequential iterator one, which is the iterator.
This is pretty good. So this is the orthodox implementation of the iterator design pattern.
But actually, Python is much more elegant and much more simpler than this.
So we try to simplify all the things.
Let's change this code. First of all, there is a radia class, abstract class, that is called iterator.
So we don't need to implement it. We don't need to define it.
But we just need to import it from collections.abc import
iterator.
And the same applies for iterable. So all these things
are basically, oh, just one moment.
Let's copy and paste this code here. Okay. So this class is totally useless.
Okay? Because it just repeated. If you look at the implementation of the iterator now
inside the collection.abc is similar to mine. It's not equal.
So we're going to see why in a while.
So your sequential iterator now extends or implements the abstract
base class provided by Python. At the same time, the iterable
wave extends the iterable base classes provided by Python. So till now,
if you execute this code, you see strange error.
So we implement this class with abstract method next.
What is saying Python? It's saying, hey, man, you are implementing the
iterator abstract base class, but you are not defining a double, double,
and the score next method. There is an interface. There is a template. There is a contract.
It is being cloned. So you need to, if you want to use the iterator, you need to implement
it. So basically it is the same. Instead of using next method,
this one should be called next.
Let's run the code again.
Okay.
It's equal, no? Perfect.
Problem.
The main problem is that method that starts with the double underscore we saw are called
by Python under the hood. They are not meant to be public. So they cannot be
used by the client itself. So if they are not going to use by the client itself,
how can we print the next element of the collection? We can call this
one. Well, Python does a very wonderful solution,
which says for,
just one moment. Let's go back to
iterable. No, no, no.
For element in sequential iterator,
print element.
Is this syntax familiar to you? Good. It's much better than the while loop, no?
Good. So let's see this code.
Okay. In the sequential
iterator.
What is the error? Index 10 is out of bounds.
Because we forgot to add the as next check.
So Python did from the first to the
element and then it failed because there is no 10 elements. So we don't know Python
that needs to call the as next method before checking and increasing, always increasing
the element. We use a nice way of doing
this stuff. Let's refactor the method next. Okay.
You should be familiar with the try accept logic.
Accept X.
Let's try this way.
Let's try to get the element. If we catch this error,
so if this one is not valid because it cannot index the array,
we catch this error. What we do? We rise another error.
We rise a stop iteration, which is another
exception. Let's execute the code now.
It worked. Because Python
when called this method, try to get the first one. It reached
the ninth one. Okay. Then at the tenth it goes to the accept branch
and it raises the stop iteration. Python knows then when stop iteration is
raised, the for loop should stop. This is
the native implementation of the iterated design pattern defined before in the
orthodox way using the while, the interfaces, the as next, the next method, et cetera, et cetera,
in a much more elegant way. Python method. This is Python method.
I want to just add a little notice about this one.
Look, the implementation of this method is very different
from the original one. This goes under the name that
it's better to ask forgiveness than permission. Instead of
checking if there is another element in the collection, let's bet that
there is another element on the collection. And if not, let's catch the error
and then handle the error itself. Which is exactly the opposite
if compared with this one. You check first if there is an
X method and then if this condition is true, you call the next method.
This approach is very, very, very
widely used in Python. On the contrary, on other languages it uses the other one.
But in Python you will find that this approach rules. This approach is very, very
important to know. Remember, it's much easier to ask forgiveness, catch the error
instead of just putting an if than asking permission. So if we
refactor this one, the as next method is totally useless.
So the code obviously works. Questions? Otherwise I need
one more thing. Okay.
One more thing.
This variable has an underscore.
This is not the case. This is not the case. I put an underscore because this
variable in my mind is private. I want to offer
this variable outside the sequential iterator. I don't want that the user
knows this variable. Because this variable maps just the state of this object.
It helps me just to track how exactly the looping operation
has reached through. It's not meant to be public. This concept of
keeping public information accessible to the client and private information
not accessible to the client is very important in object oriented programming and goes under
the name and the concept of data hiding. You hide some data which is not
necessary, mandatory, useful for the client itself.
And you offer the user itself just the public part of the function itself.
So remember this one. Obviously there is no problem publishing,
offering to the user the state of the sequential iterator. But
let's suppose that instead of having just a simple expression like this one,
you've got a very complex algorithm that applies some sort of breadth first search
on graphs of trees. Okay, this variable would be much, much more complex.
And maybe could reveal the
data inside your database. If you apply this method to the database, offering this
information outside the class, making public to the class itself,
could expose you to a data leak. So think in mind about
these things. If you remember well at the beginning I said if you know concept of object
oriented programming, you can translate them to somewhere else. Like this one. You can translate the fact that
dividing some data and offering to the user a way to navigate this data.
But the way has been defined by you and you only.
Okay, questions? Yeah. Good.
Yeah.
No, don't think so. I think it's basically
the same. Yeah.
Okay.
Now can you rephrase? Sorry, I didn't understand.
Yeah.
It's not self
because outside the function self
can be used. So since I has been defined outside the function itself
can be used. Okay. I would have put basically on the constructor method.
Okay. I could have done self dot underscore I equals zero.
But think about it. Is why
are parameters that the user should let you know?
Why is internal state? It's not correct.
It takes part as constructor arguments because this is private.
Because otherwise the user can say.
So for this way it has no self but it takes part of the object obviously.
So it takes part of the object. It has no self because it's outside
of a function and that's all. If you want to use a self you want to put in the
constructor. But if you put in the constructor you let the client define the way.
Define the variables. But this is wrong because you don't want that client mess up with the
state of the object. This is just yours. Okay.
Okay.
You could do something like this.
Sorry. Thank you.
Okay. Propose you ten minutes for the exercise.
Okay.
So before in this part the exercise can be split into two main different parts.
Okay. The first part should be easy while the second one requires some thinking about.
So obviously as always we can discuss maybe later because you need to understand the domain problem first.
Then code. First part is defining an iterator
looping in reverse order. So instead just letting the client looping in
sequential order you want to offer the client another type of iterator that implements
the same interface that can help you out to loop in the
reverse order. Okay. The iterator is the abstract
mix class. You can find it in the classes module so you just need to implement it.
Okay.
Should be very easy. Just changing the way you
change the I. That's clear. No. While the second part if you're curious about
this. Suppose that you want to offer
a client a way to let him to say to you what kind of
iterator should be used. Because now you're offering a sequential order iterator and a
reverse iterator. But you want to offer a user a much more let's say human understandable
API that is capable of let's say saying you what
exactly iterator you should be able to provide to him. So instead
letting the client use directly the sequential iterator or the reverse iterator
you want to offer a client an API that under the hoods computes the fact
that the user wants the sequential one of the reverse one. And then you
implement it. So you define an iterator creator
interface so an iterator creator abstract mix class
with that create iterator method that accept a string
that say which kind of iterator should be requested by the user. Sequential or reverse.
You need to implement the interface because interface is abstract
so you can be used. And once you implement it
if the condition equals to sequential
then you need to return the sequential iterator. Otherwise
you return the reverse iterator. So you need to reflect the wave sample
collection class which is basically our augmented version
of the wave that takes and changes the role of the iterator
that you can find on the classes module.
You got eight minutes.
.
So you should have understood that defining interfaces or define these
abstract based classes is not a matter of let's say
uselessness. It's very important to define this kind of interface
because if you define this interface you know at the client side that that code
will work because every implementation of that interface will respect exactly
the same signature of the methods. So that's the idea
of interfaces. That's the idea of abstract based classes.
.