Hello. Good afternoon, everyone. Now we will have a talk on getting started with statically
type programming in Python by Peacock. And since COVID is still a thing, we're not doing
a Q&A here. The speaker will be happy to take your questions in the hallway. Thank you.
Okay. Thank you. It is first time speaking for being outside in person, so I feel so nervous.
So, okay. Let's start. My talk title is Getting Started with Statically
Typed Programming in Python 3.10. Okay. Oops. Before I start my talking, let me self-introduce
the table of contents. Okay. Previewed pictures or screenshots on suite. The hashtag is the
oops. Python US 2022. Slide is uploaded. You can also see there. Okay. That is me. Self-introduction.
My name is Peacock or Yoichi Takai. Social media ID is Peacock0803SZ. And so my full name is Yoichi
Takai. But please call me Peacock. Just. Okay. My hobbies and favorites is playing with the
clarinet and listening classical music, skiing, gadgets, or more. And I'm 20 years old. This is
my first trip abroad. So it's tiresome. Thank you. Okay. My works and communities is there. My company
is CMS Fulltime since 2020. There is my boss. I'm a web application developer using Flask,
Pyramid, or Brom. Yes. I have experience learning Haskell and TypeScript. And now I'm reading
program types and programming languages as well as for Tuple. And my communities, I belong to
my community. I'm a member of Brom JP. And I'm staff of PyCon JP since 2020. And this year,
2022 is Vice Chair and operating member of PyCon JP Association. I'm director of PyCon JP TV. It is
YouTube Live about local PyCons and other events monthly. There is today's topics. First, why I
talk about typing. This is motivation. And second, I introduce basically uses first step of typing.
That is what I most want to say. And then GenX and user-defined types. Oh, okay. It is best practice
is included. And last, update overview and background compatibility for 3.9 of before. And last topic,
overviews new features on 3.10. And one topic about 3.11. Okay. This is my motivations. Yes. It's
been seven years since typing the PRs in Python 3.5 at 2015. So many big tips were adapted and
updated over the years. So even now, I think many people don't know where to start because there is
coherent information. Yes. This is what I will not talk about. Yes. Configurations of MyPy is
so important topic, but it's so long, so I skipped. And for example, CIS, history, implementation,
and AST, I will not talk about. And yes, this is my bodies. Okay. Let's start look how to
the other start typing. Okay. This is what makes you happy. It knows type when you reference it
in such as VSCode or Vim. It gets angry when I try to give it long ones. And the dot computation
will work when accessing return value of the function using dot. Okay. Without typing, yes,
we can't know the errors. Yes. It will cause type errors, but we can't know. With typing,
but with typing, yes, like this. And as I can tell, argument is long, yes, like this. In code review,
this is actually in my experience that this, my boss said, what types do functionally dance?
Strings, false or null. That's made two types. So it is unhappy. But like this, yes. But with
typing, boss said, it looks like this function may return three types. Isn't that too much? I see.
That could be bad design. Let me fix it. Sure, please. Yes. Okay. Starting this, let's start
of definitions. This is nothing too difficult. Just the right type. After the arguments,
write colon and the types. Before the colon and the end of the function definition,
write arrow and the types. Okay. This is standard types using to do nothing. There are bytes,
floats, int and str. And null is used for functions that returns nothing, yes. Such as
main functions. Yes. Yes, this is very, very danger, final result. Any can hold instance of
any types. Of course, it is better not to use it. When using it, import use and then typing when
necessary. Yes. This is very danger, final result. Okay. Since stats from the upper case,
yes, collections, so it can use without import. Yes. Before 3.9, you must, you have to write this
sentence. But now it's deprecated. So you may use dict or list using stats with small case. And
these collections can be written with square brackets for the type inside. Okay. Other modules
are available in standard library. A collection is, for example, q or default dict. Collection.abc,
the interval or the protocol related. Yes. And RE has regular expression modules. And finally,
context-related items such as using data or data leave. Okay. There is so many types in
collections.abc. So it is better to use collections with few methods in case to readability and
portability. The next figure, next page figure shows that relationships that between collections.abc
and the sequence of the built-in types is defined by the method, instance method,
the implementation. It is good idea to look at method, fewer methods, so narrowing. Okay.
Let's see. Yeah. This is great method in 3.9. So it is complex but do not feel difficult.
The bottom of the figure, the fewer method it has on the top side, this side, you just want
the more method it has. For example, if you want to loop over sequence of the arguments in the
function, you can use the collections.abc.iterable. Yes. If you need random access, use sequences.
Or if you need change the value, the use type is immutable. Or if you simply specify the list
of the arguments type, you will not be able to pass or set or it can't. However, I think
it is easier to understand using this. Yes. There is the differences between tuples or the
sequences. If you are not, tuple is fix up the length information. You must specify the type
or the number of elements. Yes. Like this. Or you can use also mixing types such as tuple of int,
str, and float. Okay. A sequence such as this has the same constraints for the elements. Yes. This
is the difference of the tuples. It can be used regardless of the length sequences of the setting.
Okay. Next is advanced. There is a few advanced types. Okay. Looking. At first is union and
multiple types. Probably it's this style of pipes. Yes. It's a higher scale or type script.
The next code. This top code is the example is a function that accepts both integers or
floats and returns integers or floats. Next bottom examples. There can be tested equalities.
So first nested union are flattened. Next, this type is removed. Yes. This int is removed.
And all that is ignored. You can swap them. And convertible is typing.union. Yes. This is
3.9 or before styles and then this style is for 3.10. Okay. Optional types. It is shorthand for
the option of t. Union is now. Yes. So we have strikes that just like union of t pipe or now.
Yeah. If you type was a function of returns the value of something, it will propagate. So be careful
when you use it. Yes. This is a bad example for using optionals. It may returns nulls. So when
you use this function, you might be another girl so return unknown. So in this case, it would be
cleaner to raise the runtime error. Yes. As the keynote speakers, the cost of raising exceptions
in Python is relatively low. Yes. It is little performance impact unlike Java. And the lack of
the null safe method in Python is also a factor. JavaScript has null safe method, double questions,
but no Pythons. But if there are such as methods, they would be upset. Okay. And then next is
callable. Since 3.9 using this import, and it is various function such as flask or fast API. And
yes. That returns callable. It is function. Okay. Yes. It may returns this. This function is because
this is. Okay. And the next is user defined generic types. Yes. It is typically declared by
inheriting from the insertion of the class is one more type variables. Yes. Using defining and using
the KT and VT. And passing. New defining X and Y. And this using mapping. Yes.
This takes mapping of X and Y and returns Y. Okay. Yes. I talked about some new features. It is
backwards compatibility for older versions. Okay. What is the Dundar future modules? It is using
typing new features on the older versions. Like this import statement. In addition to typing,
it was also used to call to 3.x features in 3.x for example, which functions. Yes. That is Dundar
modules. Okay. Now I talked about I will talk about recent update. Yes. This is overview. Yes.
3.7 has data classes. 3.8 has F strings. Equals F strings. Yes. It is for debugging. And 3.9 is
union operators in the dict. And 3.10 as you know, pattern matching. And 3.11 it will be released 2022
October. Performance tuning. It focus on performance tuning. New features on type hints on 3.10.
There is four features. Yes. And there is difficult topic. Yes. This is I'm not sure so I can explain
well. Okay. As you know, new type of union operator is in pipe. The union above can be used operator.
You can also asking is instance. Yes. Like this. Option of T is also written by like this. T pipe
or now using this. Okay. Yes. This is very difficult. But I'm not sure I can explain. It's
motivation is needed represent function that returns same argument as a specified function. Yes. That
is readability. But approach is here. Adding the argument type code is like this. Using this to use
them. Use this import from typing. Yes. It can be used with cover to behave like a general cover object.
Yes. Before I'm logging to this. We can't know the argument of types. But after this, yes. Like this.
You can know that the keyword args is dict and args is tuple. Yes. And using this. Okay. The
second, third one, type areas. Motivation is we consider global bias with type hints is type areas.
This tends cause problem with forward experience, forward reference, scoping and more. So we are
going to make it possible to define type areas. Okay. Approach. Adding new typing to type areas.
You can write just like this. T colon type areas is equal. Yes. You can write like this using
double quotes for using forward references. Okay. This is before and after. Okay. This is global
expressions is areas. And typed global expression. And then this is using for forward references.
Okay. This is last week for 3.10 user defined type guards. Motivation is type checker to the
technical code type narrowing to determine the type of information. Yes. On this line, type of
var is narrow to SDR. Next, this line, narrow to null. Okay. However, that will not act as intended
as if user defined user function is used. Yes. This is invalid type. But type guards allows to
define user defined types because you realize a new typing. Yes. Writing like this. And the
narrowing type works like next. Yes. This narrowed in tuple of SDR and SDR. And next is one or two
SDRs. Okay. Okay. This is last topic. New features on Python 3.11. If you know, Python 3.11 is focused
on performance tuning. But there are also a new feature on typing. Yes. This is PEP 673. It's a way to annotate
methods that return instance of their class. Okay. Let's see. Motivation is here. The calling set scale of the subclass shape. The type checker is in first returns the shape. Yes. This is the shape not circle.
Using this, shape has no attribute set radius. So it occurs. But there is work around but intuitive. Yes. There is not so good to
read. But using typing dot self results that is import and using like this. This self starts with the upper S. And using subclass, it will be the circle. Okay.
This is my summaries I talked. First benefits starting with using definitions, building types. And using standard collections since 3.9. And collections, unions, options,
and then the next update overview and standard feature for compatibility. And last, new features on 3.10 and 3.11. Yes. 3.10 has new type union operator,
parameters, variables, type areas, user defined types, type guards. And last 3.11 has self type annotated. Okay. That is references. I want to say thank you. Okay. Thank you so much.
Thank you for listening. See you again next time in Japan, middle of October. Okay. See you.