Okay, up next we have Bernard Gabor with how we standardize editable installs, PEP660 versus
PEP662.
Thank you, thank you all.
Let me start with saying that I appreciate your presence here.
I know that this is not a light topic for anyone.
As Peter put it this morning, this is probably the place where everyone gets upset eventually.
I'm here today to hopefully help you a bit with that.
My goal here is today for you to actually have a better insight on how some of the packaging
works and hopefully if you're running some of those annoyances, you understand enough
of how the system works that you can figure out what the problem and hopefully fix it
with less annoyance at the end of the day.
Let me start with introducing myself.
Who am I?
I'm a software engineer at Bloomberg.
I work in a team that primarily focuses on quality control inside data ingestion pipelines.
But more importantly for this talk, I'm an open source contributor.
Primarily I'm a member of the Python packaging authority and I maintain the virtual and build
PEP6 and talks projects which are the more popular ones.
And also I'm the parent of two Yorkshire Terriers and I'll employ their presence at least in
the site virtually to hopefully give you a bit of relief for the dense subject of packaging.
Now let's start with what is editable installation.
But before we can actually understand how we standardize editable installations, we
have to understand how things worked in the past, then where we ended up today, only then
to realize what we propose and where the future is heading.
I hope you're all eager to find out more about how editable installs works in the past.
And for that we first need a very quick demo project.
Here is a quick demo project for your amusement.
You can see it's very simple, doesn't do very much.
It literally just has a simple say hi method or function and you can call that and call
it, you're going to see it, hey, it works or not.
Now if you just create this source directory and start up your Python interpreter and pass
in your testing code, basically calling the method, you'll see that it's not working.
And the reason for that it's not working is to actually test the library you first need
to install it.
So let's do that quickly.
Hopefully you're using virtual environments for this and not installing in your global
Python interpreter because that's the surest way to eventually have a bad day.
And as we know, packaging is already a bad experience.
You want to avoid getting there quicker.
So usually what you're going to do it if you have virtual environments, you're going to
use pip to actually install your package into it.
And I know the slide might not be the, I'm not sure how much they show up, especially
in the back.
But in the first slide there was a link to it so you can check it out later or whatnot.
I'm going to highlight the parts that are more important.
Here basically the only thing you really need to know that I installed the project.
Now if I run the interpreter again with my test code, you can see that, hey, it's work.
Now I can test my code greatly.
But you can see I kind of like made a bit of a mistake here because I said hello and
I actually didn't put an exclamation mark.
And if you're one of these grammar gnats, you're probably screaming at me already.
Let me fix that quickly.
I'm going to quickly put an exclamation mark in it.
I run again my test code and nothing changed.
It's the same thing.
You might be aware of the reason for this is that whenever you change a code to actually
test your library, you have to install it again.
And only then you're going to see that, hey, now you have the new change.
Obviously, installing your project, reinstalling your project after every change is not a good
day for anyone.
So there must be a better solution than basically whenever you change the code, install the
project again.
And the solution that we're looking for is editable installations.
Editable installations are basically a way of installation which allow you to test your
project without needing to reinstall your project between code changes.
Now, you still need to restart your interpreter to pick up code changes.
However, importantly, you don't have to reinstall it.
Now, the way this historically used to go, it was pip exposed as an editable installation
mode and it was exposed during this dash E flag.
So if you pass to pip this dash E flag, it's going to do a special type of installation
in which once you run it, you don't have to reinstall it after every code change.
It automatically picks up the new information that you put into your business.
Now, let's dive deeper.
Let's check out how actually those editable installations worked in the past, what happened
a year ago or potentially even today if you're using setup tools when you actually type dash
E to pip.
And what happens is basically it inherits a solution that was introduced back in 2003
or whatnot by this two tools and then generated by setup tools.
And the solution is essentially calling the python setup.py develop comment that magically
makes your project source directory be present inside the Python interpreters import resolution
system.
Let's check out what it means to install your project.
Let's find out how a normal installation works so we can kind of identify what are the differences
from an editable installation point of view.
And the way a normal installation works is that pip will take a look at your source directory,
will build a will from it and then it will install that will into your site packages
in your Python interpreter.
Now when it builds this will, this will have two kind of information in it.
It will have your actual business logic.
For example, here you can see like the demo.py is your business logic.
And then it's going to also generate some kind of package metadata.
And this is basically information that before building your will was stored inside your
project or something like that.
Now if you look further, the next step, as I said, after it creates a will, it will actually
extract that will into your Python interpreter.
And that extraction basically means that it's going to take your will and extract the content
of the will first inside the Python site packages folder and also generates the binary
compilations for those files that it extracted for the Python files.
But also enrich a bit the metadata that was available in the will.
Basically just provide additional information that's useful for the installer, in this case
pip, to find out how it can uninstall the project and all that kind of stuff.
Or even just for example, the installer is there just to point out that if you have another
installer than pip, pip can kind of get to know, hey, I shouldn't touch this because
it's not my package.
I don't know how to handle it.
Now the difference whenever we're talking about editable installation is that what actually
happened in the past, as you can see here basically on the highlighted on the output
of the pip install, it doesn't do any of this will building magic what not.
It just runs setup.py develop onto your project source directory.
And then that invocation somehow makes the magic happen.
And when I say it makes the magic happen, so what the magic is actually, it generates
your project metadata in line inside your source directory.
So that's why if you install a project in editable install or you used to install it,
there was this magical egg info folder in your folder.
Because it still needs the project metadata and this project metadata now is stored within
the your project source directory.
And then it uses a system called pth files and it adds this pth file, your site packages.
And what you need to do know about the pth files that whenever you add a pth file to
your site packages folder, that basically just gets picked up at the interpreter startup
and gets added to the sys.path.
If it's a path, if it's Python code in it, it will actually run the Python code.
So for example, in this case, you can see once I run setup.py develop, it generates
that egg info folder but also takes the source, my project source directory and injects it
via the pth file onto the sys.path.
From there, the Python import system takes it away and makes things work.
So you can see this was the old solution and you might ask why isn't this enough?
Isn't this all we need?
Do we need anything more complicated?
Maybe you already solved this problem.
And I'm here to tell you that no, this is actually not the full solution.
This is a partial solution to the editable installation problem.
One of the problems is that it still requires the setup.py file and the setup.py file
is basically some setup.
It's a slash distutious arch thing.
And for example, we have a lot of fancy new backends like fleet, poetry, or hatchling.
And all of these still need to generate the setup.py if they want to develop an editable
installation mode, which is not a good.
So we should have a better solution.
Also another problem is that, and this kind of like iterates back what actually we want
to solve here, we as a community never really got together and agreed what is an editable
installation other than the broad definition I gave it earlier on.
Or like where are the boundaries for what an instance should be able to do and shouldn't
be able to do?
And also furthermore, as I said, this thing that I presented until now is basically an
implementation detail of setup tools from the earlier ages.
You might ask, hey, Burnout, it's 2022.
Why is it still a problem?
I mean, Python's around for 30 years.
I thought we should have solved this 15 years ago.
And I'm here to tell you that it's not that because we did not try.
Oh, boy, no, we did try more than once.
We first initially came back then when we started to standardize the normal installations in
2015.
And it was so controversial back then at that point that the writers of the PEPFY and so on
explicitly stated that someone else, someone later going to solve it, we don't want to deal
with this because otherwise we'll never get anything accepted.
Then it came 2019.
We tried again part of the packaging summit at the previous in-person conference.
We even agreed on a solution and we all walked away that, hey, just we need to implement it,
ship it.
Then after the conference, there was more follow up discussion.
Not many concerns were raised until 2020 April when someone opened on again a topic that,
hey, we agreed that we're going to do it, but we didn't do actually anything.
Can we like start the work on it?
So that generated a whole new work only to prove that actually whatever we agreed at
the packaging summit, we didn't agree.
Like many people had concerns to it.
So fast forward another year, so this is like the fifth try when we go at it.
Someone again picked up like, okay, can we actually solve this?
And we then again it and then we even had two main threats.
Each of these threats I warn you are probably like 500 comments each thread.
Basically discussing various back and forth on the subject.
I'm happy to say that after that 2021 April, May edition, we actually did agree mostly,
but not really.
I'll let you know later on that.
But first in order to actually understand why we had so many back and forth,
I need to tell you about what were the drawbacks of the prior art.
Basically what were the problems that the previous solution did not actually handle
and many people felt that we should handle as a language.
One of the problem that the previous solution didn't handle is that imagine you have a project
and you want to basically include some files in your project.
And for example, Setup Tools has these packages thing where you can specify one by one what
package you want to include.
Now in case of an editable install, once you did this, this only exposed every package.
Even if you choose some of the packages to not include, the editable install still installed
all your packages or made it available all your packages in your editable installation,
basically driving the divide how an editable installation and normal installation was working.
Also, the reverse is true.
If you wanted, for example, to include your test files in an editable installation,
it wasn't possible.
If you put it within your project source directory, it automatically picked up
because the previous solution basically relied on the fact that we put your source directory
and put it as it is as a whole onto the site packages folder.
So there's no, let me add this or let me not add this type of logic possible to happen there.
Another problem that we don't have a solution is like, for example, generated code.
Imagine you have some kind of schema file in which your server API is defined and you
want to generate some Python classes, for example, using Python classes by using this
data model code generator.
You can set up a build where you generate this file during the build of your package,
but this will not be running during your editable installation and it's not clearly defined
how it should be even for an editable installation, basically including generated code as part
of editable installation, not just static code that lives on your disk.
And also another problem is editable installation work as previously were defined mostly for
Python file, pure Python file, but for example, in an ideal world, it should be possible to
also work for like C extension.
For example, if you have a sitem package, it should be possible to whenever you update
your sitem code, you don't have to rerun again the entire installation just to pick up that
sitem code change.
Ideally it should also translate automatically.
Again, for this we don't have any support.
The way historically it worked that during the installation, this extension were injected
into your project source directory and it was up to your responsibility whenever you
do change the C extension, just reinstall the package to pick up the changes.
But then we brainstormed throughout all those back and forth sessions that can we even solve
some of this problem or are they even worth solving and we did come up with a few new
solutions or also how some of the systems try to solve it.
Basically, how can we have a life without the PTH files that we had, something that's
more powerful.
One obvious solution or someone came up, why won't we instead of just using PTH file to
kind of like inject the source directory inside the site packages, why don't we just seem
links to basically take the source directory and seem link it into site packages and this
also has the advantages that now from the port of interpreter that files actually physically
live inside your site packages rather than kind of like living inside your source directory
and you can have like pad differences between the installation and the other installation.
Now this also has some benefits like there are no startup performance impact, you can
also basically install the mirror to normal installation mode.
There is one downside, if you seem link your entire folder, remember from the previous
bullet list where I say that we wanted to support addition, exclusion, code generation
and let's say C extensions, this solves you the addition problem but doesn't solve you
the extension because once you seem link a folder, everything in that folder is available.
So it's not the full solution but potentially can be better than the PTH file.
You can also choose to seem link the file individually, this has the advantage that
now you can support exclusion but that's not mean that whenever you add new files to your
project you need to read on the installation to update the seem links basically to your
site packages.
This is also not necessarily a perfect solution but sometimes can be better than the normal
PTH file.
Another great solution or great improvement that has been added through the last 15 years
the language are import hooks.
The import hooks that we were working at the end of the day if you think about it in Python
we import modules not files, let's use that.
Like why do we even try to solve the file problem if we had the day what we want to
solve is the fact that an installation load the correct module rather than we don't really
care where that file lives.
And we could for example with this thought we can extend the import system to manifest
the module at import time and manifest it from the correct location wherever it lives.
If it lives inside the site packages cool, if it lives in your code cool or if it lives
maybe in memory because it's generated cool it can manifest it from there and doesn't
have to actually exist under this.
It basically offers you full dynamic thing.
We brainstormed, I myself did the Paul Moore brainstorm run this in 2020 and he even made
a library that basically allows any backend to kind of like provide this kind of functionality.
Okay and the way it works it still uses some import hooks because it still needs to have
some kind of system to register the import hook at the start of the importer.
So some code needs to run at the interpreter startup time but that does a lot less because
now just register the import hook and then dynamically at import time it kind of like
can support both exclusion code generation or for example here you can see what we actually
do.
We map our demo module to a given in it dot file and then the import system will take
care of to load it from the correct location.
Yeah, so this is mostly a great solution.
Solves all our problems.
I hope I didn't put you to sleep though.
And let's have a look first now the Python build system.
So in order to understand the solution we propose there's one more thing that you have
to think about and that's the Python build system.
In order to build the wheel what actually happens to build the wheel?
And two distinct components need to work together.
First the build backend.
This is like setup tools, hatchling, fleet, whatever else you have which basically actually
builds the wheel and there is the build frontend which creates an isolated build environment
for your build backend in which it can run basically something that makes sure that you
have the correct version of the setup tools, all that kind of stuff.
And this also installs additional dependencies needed.
That is really smart, the text there.
But yeah, and then we can call the build backend.
The build frontend is the one that actually communicates with the backend to the API defined
in PEP 517 and the two main important methods kind of like the Python API are the get project
for build wheel which basically gives me what additional dependencies you need to actually
build the wheel and the other one actually build the wheel.
So these are the two main Python interfaces that need to exist in order to build the wheel.
You can actually see this if you use the canonical project, prior project.build to build your
project.
For example here I demonstrated the virtual app.
You can see when I say hey, build me a wheel of this, the first thing that happens is create
a virtual environment.
Then it's going to actually install in that environment your project's build backend,
in this case like setup tools and setup tools SCM.
And then it asks the backend hey, what other dependencies do you need?
And the backend comes back, I need the wheel.
So the frontend will now install that dependency inside your isolated build environment.
And then it just calls that build wheel method which actually builds the wheel.
And you can see at the end of it, you end up with a wheel.
Okay, so these are kind of like the main steps how a wheel gets built.
And with that now we know enough to actually solve the problem, yeah?
And this is the point where I have to say that after 12 years of arguing back and forth
on how we should solve the problem, we actually managed to not agree on how to solve the problem.
So we had two solutions.
So we decided to propose both solutions and pick the winner basically at the end of the
day.
Now the reason for this one that we kind of like as a community fail to agree who should
actually do the most of the heavy groundwork.
Should it be the build backend or the build frontend?
Who should actually be responsible of making the editable effect happen or work?
And we have a path for each of them.
We have the traditional wheelbase and we have for the virtual wheelbase which is one of
them puts them in the build frontend and one of them is the build backend.
Now at this point I should probably address that generally the way the Python enhancement
works is that people propose a solution and that the solution gets debated and the solution
should be something that the community agreed on.
Now obviously it doesn't, we're not always going to agree on and that's fine.
Sometimes we can agree to disagree.
And also it's not actually a bad thing that we as a community could not agree on a single
solution because if we have two solutions we can kind of like compare them against each
other and make the least solution because it's not always possible to find a solution
that fixes all your problems at least everyone's problem.
And often time it's even more important to pick a solution rather than instead of being
afraid of picking the wrong solution do not pick either solution just because as a community
we could not agree.
But with that being said let me tell you a bit about the first installation.
So the first installation mode that we came up with the PEP6060 and for those of you
wondering yeah this is the one that actually got accepted.
So the way this works this puts most of the heavy lifting onto the build backend and
it adds two methods to the communication channel between the build backend and the frontend.
It defines this that now the editable installations also have their own isolated build environments
and this editor build environment can have additional dependencies for example if you
want to build an editable wheel or a normal wheel you may be able to specify different
dependencies in order to actually build those wheels.
So that's why we have another endpoint that basically provides hey backend get me the
requirement for your building an editable wheel and then we have a build editable method
that actually hey backend provide that wheel that you build.
And the editable installation this is basically all this actual PEP actually contains because
now from this on it defines the editable installation works by first the build frontend will create
a custom isolated build environment.
It will install into that isolated build environment your project's build backend.
After the build backend it asks the or the frontend asks the backend hey what are additional
dependencies needed to build an editable installation and after the editable installation it installs
that it basically just has the backend build me the editable install and the entire installation
from this on and on installation works the same way it works for the normal wheels.
So there's no change needed on the installer side or anything of that.
It basically delegates all the responsibility on the backend and the backend should generate
appropriate files inside your wheel that makes the editable effect happen.
Now this has some benefits like for example the backend can choose to put an import hook
there instead of actually putting your source files.
It can put a PTH file so basically whatever was working until now can continue working
and also the backend the whenever about making which one should you actually use the PEP
kind of like say that well the backend should probably allow the user to choose whichever
they want.
And yeah now there's one solution out of the previous kind of like semi-solutions I presented
that this doesn't support.
You can see that we proposed that you could use SimLinks to achieve the editable effect.
SimLinks is not achievable today because the wheel standard doesn't support SimLinks.
There's no point to define it and the yeah and the kind of like the conclusion was that
if anyone wants SimLinks in the editable installations they should propose an additional PEP that
extends the current PEP standard to support SimLinks.
And the big benefit of this as I said before and for the installers or uninstaller there's
no change they use the existing mechanism.
Now here's SIG62 and this is the PEP that actually I wrote and proposed so this was
like my solution even if it wasn't accepted.
The idea with this one is that instead of making all this work be handled by the backend
why doesn't the backend just provide some kind of metadata file like a JSON file which
is basically list what modules need to be pulled from what files and then the front
end is the one that actually needs to make it happen somehow.
And the front end can from there on decide to use SimLinks, PTH files, sidecustoms, import
hooks all that kind of stuff.
This has potentially the benefit that it doesn't require extending existing standards because
the front end is not bound by the existing front end so it can choose for example to
use SimLinks or it can choose to use side customized files any of that.
Now ultimately choosing a winner the decision was primarily made by Paul Moore who's kind
of like our BDFL for packaging and after a week when none of the proposals received any
significant feedback he made the decision that he picked the PEP 6060 as the winner
and this happened the last year in June and his primary reason why he preferred the SIG60
to is that he felt that the PEP 6060 by just basically imposing on the backend to list
what type of files needs to be or modules need to be exposed and from which locations
it's a bit too vague and it doesn't really specify for the front end what it needs to
do and it does not really like that kind of like full control on the front end side.
While if you consider the PEP 6060 that is much more constrained because both the backend
and the front end knows exactly what files they need to produce even though the backend
still needs to solve all the problems how actually makes that installation effect happen.
Okay, so some lessons we learned.
After adopting the new standard a lot of the backend happily jumped on so from that time
it was a resounding success I suppose.
For example Hatchlink, PDM, ISKCONS, Fleet, Poetry within a few months implemented the
standard and now you can use that to install without setup.py for this project.
You may notice one significant omission from here and that's setup tools so basically the
one that 90% of us use doesn't actually and the problem here is a bit difficult like one
setup tools doesn't necessarily want to take PTH file and just add support for a PTH file
basically a direct migration they would like to improve the existing system but improving
the existing system and kind of like adding support for more smart editable installation
it's hard because setup tools is very much pulled down a lot of technical depth a code
base that basically goes back 25 years and adding changes like collecting all the files
that are actually going to be installed or modules that are going to be installed it's
a hard problem within the system of that project because of its architecture.
So not all great and what's not there's one more black swan we did not see coming and
this was kind of like well when I some of these projects I started using it and this
also proves that even with 10 years of disagreement we still can miss things.
We turned out that we missed with the import took solution that imports are great because
they allow you to solve all the problems and they allow you to dynamically make any kind
of logic happen the problem is they're really bad for any idea or static checkers because
any idea or static checker doesn't know doesn't execute any Python code so if they don't take
the Python code they don't know what type of import to do what kind of modules they
make happen and I'm not even sure that this is an easy problem to solve because if you
think about it if you go from a concern that you never can execute any Python code anything
other than explicitly stating what file additional files you want to expose inside the Python
interpreter will not work and this can like suggest that the proposal that the pep6662
was that basically proposed exactly this to provide a file to the front end that can basically
list hey these are additional files that I want you to make available.
Now this kind of like point that maybe we will not have pep6662 but if you want users
to actually use our edipro installations because not having auto complete on your ID is going
to be a major pain point we will actually need to extend pep6662 to still require the
backend to generate these additional files so that the static checkers and IDs can actually
know about them and index them as they did beforehand.
In the meantime we can still using the pth file but that's kind of like we did not really
so much but made maybe available some of the things to the people to the newer backends
made them work without needing to generate this custom setup.py file.
Yeah that's mostly it.
I'm not going to take questions right here but if you have any questions find me after
the conference or right here and right now and I'm happy to answer any of your questions
and with that I would like to thank you very much.