All right, so we're going to introduce the last speaker of our session.
This is Greg Komposteen from, looks like he's from, oh, he didn't put it up.
Oh, yes.
Bloomberg, I could not even read it on the slides.
So Greg is going to give us a talk.
It's going to be on how to succeed with Python across the enterprise, and the subtitle on
this one is by trying really, really, really, really hard.
All for you, Greg.
Okay, thank you so much for that introduction, and I'm surprised with how loud I suddenly
am.
I was having a little bit of a technical struggle with the display earlier.
Thank you for being patient with that.
Just a bit about Bloomberg first.
We celebrated our 40th anniversary just last year.
It was founded as a pretty small company that provides information to the financial industry,
and over the years we've grown to be a fairly large and well-established company.
We have offices all over the world, almost 200 of them.
They tend to be in real high-priced real estate locations because we're near financial districts
and world capitals and things like that.
We have over 20,000 employees at this point.
Almost 7,000 of them are software engineers, and quite a few of them are using Python today.
We've also appeared in television and movies.
If you have a drama or any kind of television or movie show and it finances part of the
story, to look authentic, you have to have a Bloomberg terminal on a desk somewhere.
This is from Billions, but our product has also appeared in The Big Short, one of my
favorite movies, Silicon Valley and Enterprise.
For much of its history, C++ was the development language of choice at Bloomberg.
In the mid-2000s, JavaScript started gaining traction for UI development mostly.
We did do some server-side JavaScript before Node.js was the thing, but that aspect of
it never really caught on.
Python was starting to make some inroads at around the same time.
Myself, I began working with Python at another company around 2007.
Mostly started off doing data massaging.
I did build this one, large-scale automation of processes that leverage Python.
I also wrote this pretty interesting testing framework that isolated some C++ libraries
in this really large, complicated application and allowed for essentially a level of integration
testing that hadn't been possible before that work.
Why Python?
I mentioned JavaScript was popular, but doing some code archaeology in our repos, I found
that there's a lot of other languages that the company has investigated or is using to
a certain extent within the company today, but none of them have really achieved the
level of success that Python has.
There are three pillars, really, to how we built up Python to be successful.
The first was strong community interest, but this in itself is a necessary but not a sufficient
condition for success.
On top of that, we put together organizations that helped us manage communication and coordination
throughout the Python community, and we also organized planned technical support for Python.
The community interest started out as it might do at a lot of other companies.
People were looking at it as this great general purpose tool with the batteries included.
You could do your data analysis with it.
You could play around with machine learning and other cool stuff.
You could stand up web services with it pretty easily.
Unfortunately, that wasn't enough at Bloomberg.
The company had a lot of bespoke network and database APIs that were used by most of the
applications there.
If you do all this work, you're an island unto yourself.
You really can't communicate the results of your work to other applications within the
company.
As often happens in innovation, an intern project got started.
This person took some of the more popular C++ libraries, created a wrapper around them
so that they could be embedded into the Python interpreter.
Suddenly, people were able to write real business applications and communicate with other applications
in the company, and things started to take off.
At about the same time, the company embraced this concept of the guild.
We have this nice bureaucratic definition here.
Essentially, a guild is a group of volunteers who are focusing on technology considered
important to Bloomberg and working to promote the best use of that technology.
The Python guild is just one of several guilds.
There's also a database guild, a JavaScript guild, a C++ guild, a testing guild.
Our guild is focused on helping to communicate with the internal Python community at Bloomberg.
They organize meetings, they send out newsletters, they contribute to internal projects.
There's also some open source contributions that go on.
Early on, they're also doing some work to maintain this extended interpreter that I
mentioned earlier.
For technical support, the Python infrastructure team was started in early 2016.
There was one person in San Francisco.
A few months after it started, I was hired as number two.
This is our office.
It's a really nice office.
It's one of the nicer offices I've worked in.
A lot of the Bloomberg offices are pretty spiff.
I'm fond of this one.
My team set out some objectives about what we need to do on the technical side.
We needed to stabilize what was in front of us.
The C++ extensions in this interpreter had some issues, and we had to deal with those.
We needed to figure out how we were going to move forward with how these libraries had
been wrapped.
We needed to figure out how to manage the interpreters and upgrades to them.
Packaging and deployment was also a bit of a challenge.
This was just two people.
We also were setting out standards about how to use the interpreter in these libraries
as well, trying to document a bunch of stuff.
When I arrived, the community was running ahead of what the Guild and infrastructure
team were doing.
They were downloading just random versions of Python and building up applications out
of it.
They were creating one-offs of the extended interpreter that the intern had created.
There was a lot of dependency management issues that were creeping up.
This was especially problematic in this environment because our infrastructure had been built
around this concept of C++ applications, which are distributed as big, standalone binary
blobs, and the notion of shared applications on a server running out of one interpreter
setup didn't really play well with that.
The C++ wrapper, it had a lot of drawbacks as well.
While it was popular and a lot of people were using it, it was a thin wrapper over the C++
code.
A lot of C++ idioms percolated to the top.
There was a bunch of classes there that you wouldn't need in a normal Python environment,
and the naming conventions looked like C++ code.
It looked like you're writing C++ without the curly braces.
It wasn't that great to look at.
There were also a lot of issues around memory management because writing this kind of code,
when you're a normal path for developing a binary extension is you write it with that
purpose in mind.
Wrapping code that was never intended for that is quite a bit more complicated.
The Python community, while it was largely volunteer driven early on, now they're relying
more on the guild or they're participating in the guild to help facilitate what's going
on in Python.
They're also contributing to what the infrastructure team is doing in various ways.
They're standing up their own inner source projects.
That's also really pretty interesting to see.
The guild early on had a lot of challenges it was facing.
It was all volunteer effort.
It was a very small team.
There was an awful lot to do.
Burnout was an easy thing to face.
We changed the guidelines for participation.
It used to be you had to be very experienced in the details of Python to join.
We said, well, all you have to have is an interest in participating.
It doesn't matter what your skill level is.
There's lots of work here to do.
We'll find something that's appropriate for you.
Or you can come with your own idea and work on that.
We adopted this structure of working groups, which are kind of like little committees.
So, my team's challenge is we had to get reined in all these different versions of
Python that were cropping up and get proper management of these things for rolling out.
We also had to smooth out the whole deployment process.
To do this all for multiple architectures where compilers and backends and various things
didn't really want to play nice with each other or with what we were trying to do.
So one of the first things we did was just draw some clear lines about what our goals
were.
We also adopted an intersource model.
So all of our projects are open.
Communication about what we're doing is very open.
We are very welcoming of issues and pull requests to the projects that we have.
We're constantly engaged in conversations with the community, often in online forums
like chat rooms where people come to us with various questions.
In fact, I was just dealing with one like three hours ago.
So it's a big part of our job is this communication aspect.
My team focused on using the guild as a representative of the community.
So we went to them to get feedback on the plans that we had for going forward and the
designs that were coming up for the APIs that were going to replace the C++ wrappers that
had been created before.
They helped us send out newsletters to update the Bloomberg engineers about what was going
on.
They also helped organize internal meetups where we could present the technology we'd
been developing.
We also got their involvement in the online conversations so that we weren't always asking
the questions.
The guild would step in and help us with those issues.
We also put together, got the documentation organized.
Before it was all kind of scattered and hard to find and we kind of centralized it a bit.
It began with a very simple mission statement and an FAQ and kind of grew from there as
we produced packages.
We built a lot of documentation for those as well.
There's now like reference manuals for each of the packages we support.
There's a bunch of how-to guides.
I have no idea what the total size would be if you print it out, but I think it would
be pretty substantial.
The other thing is that we needed a plan for how to replace that extended interpreter.
It was just too ugly to support.
We decided to provide packages for each of the important C++ libraries that were involved
and just dramatically changed the architecture of these things and really reduced the source
of maintenance on these.
To start off, we picked one of the most popular packages that was being used in the company
or popular C++ libraries really.
What is the minimum amount of functionality we can ship for this library that will gain
attention and be useful for delivering value?
We ran through our designs with the guild and worked hard to come up with something
that supported Python idioms, had really good performance because that was important to
people and wanted something that was really reliable.
We rolled out our first release and crickets.
Nobody wanted to pick it up first, so that took a bit of effort.
Again, we got help from the guild on this.
We had a lot more conversations with the community about what we had when they came to us with
problems about the old API.
We would suggest they try the new one as an alternative.
Over time, we showed that we had a really good track record both on the performance
aspects and on reliability, which also helped pick up adoption of these things.
Today Python is a first-class language within the company.
If you go to our careers site, we have a careers site, and do a search for Python, it's the
most popular entry in a job description for languages there.
It easily outnumbers what's there for C++ and JavaScript.
When we bring on new hires, we start them off with Python as the language for introducing
the concepts for how applications are built in the company.
There's really no reason to not use it when you're developing a new application, except
for very special use cases.
We've seen the internal community grow to several thousand.
We've seen a lot of growth in community-driven projects as well.
What I like is they've modeled how they do their projects after the way my team does
them.
And a lot of the other projects also come out with good documentation, high reliability,
good design.
What I thought was really interesting is the authors of the C++ library have also embraced
what we've done.
They're taking our libraries and using them in their own testing.
They're also using Python to write their own utilities.
The way the guild is currently structured is we have two co-leads.
them the, or two co-chairs, I like to call them the Python Devon, that sounds kind of
open and welcoming. We have about a dozen working groups, staffed by about 20 members.
Each working group focuses on a specific issue. There's one working group that was responsible
for helping organize all of Bloomberg's participation at this conference, and I don't know how we
could have done all this without them. We hold twice monthly meetings, and we have a
publicly shared agenda, so anyone is welcome to attend our meetings, and often they just
lurk, but sometimes they jump in with good questions or comments. My team has grown,
I'm happy to say it's no longer just two people. Four of my team members are attending
PyCon. Mario and Pablo are also presenting. They're pretty famous within the Python community.
Putting in and out. Matt Wasnicki is also attending. He is one of the contributors to
the memory project that we just open sourced, which has gotten a lot of buzz.
We continue to work with the guild. In fact, two of my team members are guild working group
leads, and we talk to each other constantly on a cross-consulting basis. It's a relationship
that works really well for us. Most of the C++ wrappers, the packages that we developed
are now in maintenance mode, and I'm really happy to say that they very rarely cause any
problems within Bloomberg in terms of production problems or just issues in general. We achieved
quite a bit there. A lot of our work now focuses on improving the upgrade cycle for interpreters,
and getting better development experience in our programmers' hands. It's just hard
to cut over to new versions of interpreters, especially bridging from two to three. We've
done a lot of work to try to help people with that. With packaging, package changes. Our
packages are very stable, but outside three-party packages, not so much. The developer experience
side, deployment is still a big issue. We've done a lot of work to improve that. We've
got a bunch of best of class diagnostic tools. Memory is one of them. I'm hoping we can open
source some of the others. We're constantly working on our documentation, and also communication.
It's all about communication. For cultivating guilds, if this is something you want to do
in your own company, your own enterprise, there are a few things that work. You can't
expect this to happen strictly on a volunteer-after-hours basis. It has to be something that is considered
part of the developer's responsibilities. It doesn't necessarily have to be a high priority.
Other things always take priority, but time has to be accounted for on the management
side. My team is globally distributed. I'm in San Francisco. Some of our team is in New
York. The rest is in London, in Europe. This is unusual. This predates the pandemic, in
fact. It's something that we proposed to them. The company has a history of co-locating teams,
but they made an exception for us, and we've been able to make it work really well. Other
teams are now picking up our model as well. The other thing we're working with on the
management is improving how the whole upgrade lifecycle works. A lot of people tend to look
at it as a secondary activity. It doesn't really improve revenue. If it isn't broken,
why do I have to pay attention to it? We have to inform people of the risks here and how
to plan it out as future activities for projects.
So one of the other challenges that we found is because we are globally distributed, not
just as a team, but as a company, a lot of our communication takes place in these online
forums. It's very easy to get tired or make a comment that comes off as too curt or sarcastic
or rude and cause a bad reaction. Now, Bloomberg prides itself on being a very, very, very
civil and inclusive community. Occasionally, this does happen though, where something inappropriate
or rude was said, and we have to have a conversation. Often that goes through the guild, and that's
all that has to happen. I'm happy to say that's become much less a problem over time. I think
that people participating in these conversations are setting a good example in keeping the
water level up on the conversation. I mentioned memory earlier. This is a fantastic tool for
diagnosing what's going on in the memory of your application. It not only looks at what's
going on in your Python code, but it will dig into the binary extensions that you're
using, regardless of what language it was written in, and give you a good view of what's
happening there. And I should mention that some other Bloomberg colleagues are talking
at PyCon as well. There's a great talk later today by Nandita and Sagar, and they're going
to talk about the transition to open source. Fred Phillips is talking tomorrow about the
import system, and Bernat, he's a great guy. He's going to be talking about editable installs.
He's also a big contributor to the TOCS project. So when I wrote this, I thought I would have
time for questions. As I understand it right now, questions will be taking place in the
open area. But thank you all for attending and for waiting a little extra for lunch.
So thank you.