The next talk is on how to make your Python Jupyter Notebook standalone and reproducible
to allow other users to replicate your experiments.
And the speaker is Maya Costantini.
And as a reminder, the speaker won't be taking questions after the talk here.
You can meet her in the hallway.
Hi, thank you.
Welcome to this talk.
First to begin with a few words about me.
My name is Maya.
I'm a software engineer at Red Hat.
I'm passionate about Python and open source, and I come from Paris in France.
If you want, you can find me on Twitter and GitHub.
And if you want to have those slides available to follow along, you can scan this code right
here.
If I am here today, it's to talk to you about a great project I've been working on at Red
Hat for seven months called Tots.
And I want to explain to you how you can use it to make your Jupyter Notebook standalone,
reproducible, easier to maintain and to share with others, but also to radically improve
the quality of your application software stack by choosing the best possible dependencies
for your notebook.
Before we start, I'm curious to know who of you has ever used a Jupyter Notebook?
Okay, a lot of people.
And who uses this day to day for work, for example?
Okay, great.
For those of you who are not very familiar with Jupyter Notebooks, I can start with a
quick introduction.
Jupyter Notebooks is an open source web-based application that allows you to conduct iterative
experiments and to create documents with life codes, equations, images, graphs, et cetera,
and that supports a wide variety of languages, over 40.
They provide a rich and interactive output and allow to leverage some big data and data
exploration tools such as Sparks, for example.
As you may know, Jupyter Notebooks are in fact already quite popular, especially in
the Python community.
Data scientists use them for things such as visualization, data modeling, data analysis,
and developing machine learning models.
They're also used by academics and by Python developers for things such as rapid prototyping
and proof of concepts.
So, what is the issue with Python Jupyter Notebooks?
What problems could we be trying to solve?
To understand that, let me show you an example.
Let's say I'm a data scientist and I want to create, for example, a computer vision
application.
And to do so, I would like to install the OpenCV library in my notebook.
To install OpenCV, I will run the following command in my notebook, which is pip install
OpenCV Python to get the OpenCV Python package.
Okay.
But what exactly is OpenCV Python?
OpenCV Python is a direct dependency of my application.
So, this is direct dependency from other dependencies, like for example NumPy.
NumPy is a dependency of my dependency, which makes it a transitive dependency.
So far, I have run pip install OpenCV Python.
I got OpenCV Python and NumPy.
But did I forget something?
What about the versions?
Maybe I would like to install some specific versions of my dependencies.
Well, last time I checked, OpenCV Python had over 60 releases and NumPy something like
80.
And if you take a look here at the release history for a package like NumPy, if you look
at the dates, you will see that releases happen approximately every month, which is very frequent.
So, this means one thing.
It means that if today I start developing my notebook by running pip install, for example,
I will have the same version of NumPy as I start to install NumPy in my notebook.
And I run this notebook once again in one month without specifying any version either.
I will probably not have the same version of NumPy installed in my notebook.
So, this is an issue, of course.
And also, what about hashes?
Hashes are a way to guarantee the provenance of a package and to make sure that an artifact
that you use in your application has been installed from a trusted source of your choice,
like, for example, an index.
Specifying hashes to identify the provenance of your dependencies is essential if you want
to share your notebook application in a more secure and reliable manner and allow users
to install packages from the same sources as you did.
But also, what about the Python interpreter version?
Every Python interpreter version is different, and your notebook will not necessarily be
compatible with all Python versions.
So, this is an issue, for example, if you used your notebook, if you developed your
notebook using Python 3.8 and you shared it with someone who uses Python 3.10,
maybe this person will not be able to run it properly.
So, we have issues with versions, with hashes, with Python interpreter versions,
but can we think of something more?
In fact, a Python application is composed of many layers, and each one of these layers
has the power to potentially break your code.
On the top layer, you have your Python application code, and this is really the only layer you
really have some control on.
For example, if your code is broken, you can still have a fix for it and propagate this
fix to other users, and they will be able to run the code as well.
But below this layer, as we saw earlier, you also have Python direct dependencies,
transitive dependencies, the Python interpreter you use, but also other things such as native
dependencies, like JLIPC or CUDA, for example.
You have also the operating system you use to develop your application with different
kernel modules, and finally, on the bottom layer, you have the hardware with different
CPU and GPU architectures.
This is why using the simple pip command to install your dependencies will not help you
achieve the goal of reproducibility you would like to have for your notebook.
To summarize, if you do something like this, which is pip install, your dependency without
specifying any version or hashes will not guarantee any reproducibility for your notebook.
Maybe you would think of doing something like that, which is specifying a list of requirements
in a manifest file such as requirements.txt, but here again, you don't have any information
about versions or hashes used, so this will not work and not guarantee either any reproducibility
for your Jupyter notebook.
My point is Jupyter notebooks are by default not standalone.
You cannot share a Jupyter notebook with someone else.
It considers that it will run on a different machine with different dependency versions
and using a different Python version.
In fact, dependency management in Jupyter notebooks puts constraints on the author of
the notebooks to provide a decouple manifest file like a requirement.txt or a pip file.loc
along with the notebook so that the notebook users can install the exact same software
stack that you used to develop the notebook.
Dependencies are also a problem when you want to containerize your notebook.
If you want, for example, to ship your notebook into a container and share it with someone
else, you have them to make sure that your Docker file or container file will be able
to adjust the dependencies accordingly.
Finally, the consumers that receive a shared notebook also have to set up manually the
correct environments, which can be difficult if no manifest file or any information regarding
the environments in which the author developed the notebook is provided with it.
This is often the case with shared Jupyter notebooks.
To summarize what would be the difficulties this creates for both authors and consumers,
they should both create an environment to run the notebook in, ideally a virtual one
that would not be polluted by any dependencies.
They will have to install the dependencies to create a kernel and update it every time
they have a new dependency.
In addition to that, the author had to maintain a requirement file to allow others to get
the exact same dependencies that the notebook was developed with.
What we are looking for is a solution that would help authors keep their dependencies
and manifest files up to date and thus achieve reproducibility of their notebook.
Earlier I introduced you to Project Thoughts.
Now we'll see how Thoughts can actually help you manage dependencies in your notebook and
get an optimal set of dependencies for your application.
First a few words about Thoughts.
The main goal of Thoughts is to help developers and data scientists create and maintain healthy
Python applications.
This project was started in 2018 after it had the office of CTO and now it is maintained
by a team of 10 engineers and has had over 50 contributors.
Thoughts is a cloud-based recommendation engine for Python applications which is able to solve
dependencies to their optimal versions using machine learning.
Of course Thoughts is an open source project so you can contribute of course if you want
to and involve yourself in the Thoughts community and share your ideas with us.
What Thoughts does is it provides an extension to manage dependencies in Jupyter Notebooks.
There is a JupyterLab extension.
So JupyterLab if you don't know is an interactive and extensible web interface to work with
Jupyter Notebooks.
That extension for JupyterLab is called JupyterLab Requirements and it allows you to manage your
dependencies without even leaving it by storing all of the necessary dependency information
directly in the notebook metadata.
It can provide an optimized environment unique to each notebook by solving dependencies using
Thoughts Depotency Resolution Engine.
So let's see what the user interface of JupyterLab Requirements looks like.
So when you work with JupyterLab you have your Jupyter Notebook open and typically it
looks like this and if you have JupyterLab Requirements enabled on JupyterLab you will
see this button called Manage Dependencies.
So if you click on this button you will have this menu where you will be able to add your
dependencies with a button.
It is not for example we import TensorFlow and NumPy and I want to say that I want TensorFlow
for example in version 2.2.0 and NumPy in a range of version from 1.0.0 to the latest
version possible.
So I will put the state of packages and constraints in the UI and save those dependencies.
Now I will have this menu where I will be able to choose a resolution engine.
So you can use the Thoughts Resolution Engine or you can use P-Pen which is used as a backup
to Thoughts.
You can also choose if you have the Thoughts Resolution Engine a recommendation type and
we will see later exactly what it is.
But now we will say that we want our dependencies to be resolved to the latest possible versions.
And finally you have this section with information about your environment which is automatically
filled by the extension but if you want to you can also modify it by hand.
So here for example I developed my notebook using Python 3.8 in a rel8 environment OS.
So now that everything is specified we are conducting Thoughts backend for advice which
take typically a few seconds or minutes.
And Thoughts backend is going to compute this fully pinned out software stack here with
the latest possible versions I have specified and send it back to us in the form of a log
file.
Now that we received the fully pinned out software stack we are installing these requirements
in a virtual environment and this is done with a tool called MicropyPen.
This tool has been developed within Project Thoughts to install dependencies and it can
sort of wrap around PIP to convert requirements file like requirements.txt or PIP and poetry
log files for example into a PIP tools compatible outputs.
So now we have our requirements locked and saved, they are installed.
We also created a new kernel and we can simply click to start working on our notebook.
Everything is installed and ready to use.
On the right side of your UI you will normally see an option to have the notebook metadata
which is a JSON file and here as I said earlier you will be able to see that your dependencies
as you specify them so with the right versions have been locked directly in the notebook
metadata.
If you scroll down you normally will see also your whole software stack with our direct
and transitive dependencies and the corresponding hashes they have so everything has been saved
there is directly in the notebook.
You can also have access thoughts recommendation using Horace magic commands so maybe if you
know a bit high Python you are already familiar with magic commands but if not it's okay.
So these commands basically allow you to do the same but directly into notebook cells
to speed up the development of your notebook.
So this is an example of the command that helps you lock your dependencies and outputs
but you can also perform those actions which are checking notebook metadata about dependencies
with Horace check but also converting PIP commands to Horace commands to allow more
reproducibility.
You can also discover dependencies already exist in your notebook and create automatically
a PIP file and do a lot of other actions such as adding or removing requirements in your
PIP file also.
If you take a look at the output for Horace check for example for checking for dependencies
you will have the following table with information about your projects about the advisor ID so
the advisor ID you send to thoughts but also for example here I left this warning which
tells you that you forgot to set a kernel so it will warn you that you have to run Horace
set kernel to set a kernel for your notebook before performing this action.
If you want to install and run JupyterLab requirements you can get this extension from
the Python package index by PIP by running PIP install JupyterLab requirements on your
machine and if you want to use this extension you can do so by running the JupyterLab command
to open a local JupyterLab instance and if you have JupyterLab requirements enabled you
will be able to run it as we saw just now.
And now what about containerized notebooks?
Does any of you work with containers?
Okay that's a few people.
So besides this extension for JupyterLab we thought it is also possible to manage dependencies
in containerized Jupyter notebooks using source to image.
Source to image is also known as S2I is a tool for building reproducible images and
it produces images which are already which are ready to run by ejecting an application
source code into a container image which assembles it into a new image.
And that provides minimal Jupyter notebooks container images which can be built on OpenShift
which is a distribution of Kubernetes to manage dependencies using that recommendation but
also container images for other types of application by extending the functionality of some base
S2I Python images to use that services.
Now that we have seen a few ways to manage dependencies in Jupyter notebooks and to
get an appropriate software stack using TOTS you might be wondering well how does that
work?
How is this recommendation computed exactly?
So that's what we will see.
The core component behind TOTS recommendation is called the resolver and the philosophy
behind the resolver is to recommend the greatest and not the latest possible versions for your
dependencies.
When you install dependencies using PIP or P-Pen or similar resolver the resolution
process uses a backtracking algorithm which will systematically solve your dependencies
to the latest possible versions.
However this is not the case with TOTS resolver which uses reinforcement learning to solve
dependencies in the cloud therefore using resources from a cluster and not from the
user's local machine.
TOTS resolver has five different recommendation types which can adapt the dependency resolution
process to user's specific needs.
Of course the resolver can solve dependencies to the latest possible versions but for example
it is also possible to configure the resolver to get the most secure possible software stack.
The security recommendation type is particularly useful if you want to manage dependencies
which are deployed in the production environment for example because the associated set of
dependencies will contain only versions that are free of non-vulnerabilities.
But for users developing programs where the focus might be on performance for example
the resolver can be adjusted to performance recommendation type to get dependency versions
which will maximize the performance of an application according to a user's hardware
and software environments.
An example of how we evaluate the performance of libraries by performing benchmarks between
different versions by using those versions of libraries in different kind of performance
scripts.
For example it can be matrix multiplication, convolutional filters or any kind of heavy
computational operations.
Then we can compare the speed for example of execution for different versions of I don't
know tensor flow if you're using for matrix multiplication.
The recommendation type for TOTS can also be set to stable if you want to get the most
stable versions of packages or to testing if you want to run software that can possibly
be unstable.
This recommendation type testing is more suitable for experimenting and because other recommendation
type can be more strict and not resolve any dependencies in this case.
TOTS collects a set of requirements and constraints about dependencies as well as the recommendation
type for the resolution and also information about the user's environments such as the
operating system and Python version used but also if the application uses a base container
image to run, has CUDA configured or what type of hardware is present and it sends back
this information to a component that we call the advisor.
The advisor is responsible for computing the optimal application software stack.
It uses a knowledge database containing information about dependencies and it dynamically constructs
a resolution pipeline which is made of different type of customizable pipeline units.
This pipeline units makes the resolution process optimized for each application and its runtime
environment.
So the advisor sends back a fully pinned down software stack including the direct and the
transitive dependencies in the form of a log file along with a justification to inform
the user on why some dependency versions were added or removed from the resolution process
and to warn or inform about some package specificities.
So what we observe in our knowledge graph, this observation include among other things
information about the application stack such as build time and runtime environments but
also about dependencies and benchmark of packages version performances.
We also have information about application binary interface, CVEs for libraries, different
kind of security analyzers and also source code meta information.
So now I want to talk to you about prescriptions and how they can help you heal your Python
applications.
So what we call prescriptions are in fact an example of configurable pipeline units
that we use in touch resolution process.
They are simply declarative YAML files stating how the resolution process should look like
and they are a way to formalize developers knowledge about dependencies into units which
are automatically consumed by the resolver to compute the software stack recommendations.
So prescriptions are present on open source GitHub repository under the dot station organization
so that every developer with any knowledge about dependencies can help improve dots resolution
process.
So now let's see an example of how a developer can create prescriptions from its knowledge.
So here I took this issue from the pillow repository on GitHub of the pillow library
and here we have this user who saw this issue which was that pillow 8.3 and NumPy are incompatible.
So for example you have this error when you try to run an application with pillow 8.3
and NumPy, type error array takes one positional arguments but two are given.
So we see that pillow 8.3 and NumPy have API incompatibility.
So what this developer can do for instance is create this prescription which is a little
yaml file and if you want to know exactly how to create a prescription it's quite easy
to do, it's something we have in our documentation.
So basically in this prescription or yaml file you will find information about the packages
that don't go together, the versions, the index that come from also and you will have
a warning which will be returned as a justification to the user.
For example pillow in version 8.3.0 does not work with NumPy and you also have the link
to the justification which is the issue that was open on the pillow repository at the end
so that users can check how white thoughts exactly didn't allow to solve pillow 8.3
and NumPy during the resolution process.
Some of the prescriptions we have are automatically created and refreshed on a weekly basis using
Python package data from different sources such as the Python package index, GitHub open
source repositories but also from publicly available data sets such as security scorecards
data sets which is created by the open source security foundation.
This prescription can contain data about package popularity, non-reliabilities for some package
versions, artifact size for example and all of this can be used during the resolution
process to assess the reliability of a given dependency.
So finally let's see what are the conclusions we can draw from what we just saw.
Managing dependencies in Jupyter Notebooks has become significantly easier for others
because of requirements being locked and embedded directly into the notebook metadata with no
additional file needed.
Jupyter Notebooks with embedded dependencies can be built using Jupyter Notebook source
to image without any additional files either.
And finally Notebooks can be shared as standalone units with an environment ready in a few clicks.
Using TOT to manage dependencies in your notebook both guarantees that your notebook will be
shared in a consistent and reliable manner and that your application will benefit from
the best possible software stack according to its purpose.
Finally I would like to thank you and also encourage you to contribute to Project TOTS
to help make Python dependency resolution better.
If you have any questions you can ask them to me.
I will be available right there.
So thank you very much.