All right.
Excellent.
And thank you for the, for attending.
This is the last, last presentation of the session.
We have Benjamin.
Bear-toe.
Benjamin Bear-toe giving us a presentation on how he, not we, migrated 3.8 million lines
of Python 2 without interrupting development.
All yours, Benjamin.
Cool.
Hi.
I'm Ben Bear-toe.
I'm a software engineer at Yelp.
And we're going to get right into it.
So first a little bit about me.
I grew up in Louisville, Kentucky, or Louisville if you're not from there.
And I went to Georgia Tech.
I was the class of 2014.
I got a bachelor's of science in computer science.
And I've worked at Yelp since graduating for almost eight years now.
I work on the core services team, which we do a lot of back-end infrastructure, things
like tooling, just test runners, stuff like that.
And we also are specifically on a lot of the Python infrastructure at Yelp.
That's things like our PyPI servers, a lot of base libraries for doing stuff in Python.
If you want to contact me, my Twitter is at Ben Bear-toe and my GitHub is GitHub.com slash
Ben Bear-toe.
So, first of all, I'm from Yelp.
And at Yelp, we're all about connecting people to great local businesses.
And to that end, our code needs to work.
So let's talk about Yelp main.
That's the name of the repo that we're concerned with today.
It's our monolith.
It was sort of the original code base at Yelp.
We've since moved to a service-oriented architecture, but it still exists and it still has a ton
of code in it that's really important.
So where does Yelp main exist in our ecosystem?
It's sort of important to understanding why we need to do this and what it looks like
when we're doing this migration.
So this is sort of a flow of a request.
And there's basically two basic ways it works.
First is we get a request from a user.
It goes into what we call the routing service, which is a reverse proxy layer.
That goes into Yelp main.
And Yelp main is responsible then for creating an HTML page.
It'll get data from its own database, and maybe it'll call into some independent services,
things we call backend services.
And then it will render a full HTML page.
That will end up being shown to the user.
And the alternative way, and this is the sort of more modern way that things happen, is
a request will have the routing service, and instead it'll go to what we call front-end
service, which is a different service than Yelp main that is responsible for creating
that HTML.
And then front-end service will call into some backend services to get data.
And it'll probably also call into internal API, which is the part of Yelp main that exposes
a restful JSON API in order to get the data that's in its database.
So either way you slice it, Yelp main is really important to when a user is actually getting
web pages from us.
So let's go a little deeper on how it's structured.
So first Yelp main has a web server.
This web server is responsible for serving all of the web traffic that it's responsible
for, which is six different sites, as we call them.
And so we have www.yelp.com.
That's sort of our consumer-facing website.
If you've ever used Yelp, that's probably what you've been looking at.
Biz.yelp.com, which is our business owner-facing website, and then as I mentioned, internal
API.
And in total, these are over 2,000 endpoints.
So it's a ton of logic and code.
In addition to the web server, there's also things that we call batches.
These are just background processes.
They're called batches for kind of historical reasons, but that's the terminology that we
use.
And we have over 800 individual batches, and these all run as independent processes.
So the web server is a single process, and then each batch is an individual process.
And it's used for all sorts of things, but anything that we don't want to do during
a web request, things like time-intensive reports, data backfills, maybe things like
billing, really anything that you wouldn't be able to complete during the course of a
normal web request.
So in terms of how we actually develop on Yelp main, we have about 20 to 30 changes
per day, and it changes just a branch.
So a branch can be huge, it can be small, but that's sort of how we measure it.
And we batch up these changes into what we call pushes.
And so that push or deploy takes about two hours on average.
That's part of the reason why we batch it is because it takes so long, so otherwise
there just wouldn't be enough hours in the day to push out all the code.
And about 800 developers are simultaneously working on this.
This is part of the reason why there's a lot of techniques in here that you might not necessarily
use on a smaller code base.
It really prevents the sort of one big branch-type migration.
And we also have about 700 Python package dependencies in here, which is not definitely
the biggest that you could get, but it's definitely a lot more than your typical Python app.
Also it's pretty old.
The first commit was in 2004, and you may or may not remember, Hey Ya was still topping
the charts, it came out in 2003, but it was still out.
And as I mentioned in the title, it's 3.8 million Python lines of code.
There's more of other stuff like JavaScript and CSS, which if you printed that out would
be about as long as 63 copies of War and Peace, which is a famously long historical fiction novel.
It has about 100,000 tests, which is just kind of an unfathomable number.
So I figured out, okay, how long does that take to run end to end?
And it takes about 35 hours.
We don't actually do that.
We have a parallel test runner.
But that 35 hours in total is about a little over three watches of the extended Lord of
the Rings trilogy, which I'm sure some of you have done that before.
It's definitely a marathon.
You can do that three times.
But this is all really important.
We have lots of users.
We have lots of people who use this stuff.
You'll get about 33 million monthly users, which is about the total population of Peru.
So let's talk about the actual migration and sort of what we needed to do in order to make
this happen.
So why did we do it, first of all?
It's kind of obvious, I think, to most people why you'd want to do this, but it's worth
saying anyway, which is that we knew that important libraries that we used were going
to drop Python 2 support.
Things like PyTest and PIP have already dropped Python 2 support right now.
And also it's really nice to just be able to use the newer language features.
It's a sort of developer productivity thing.
In terms of what we needed to do in order to make this happen, we knew that we couldn't
have normal development stop during this project.
We couldn't just say, hey, we're not going to ship any new features.
We're not going to increase revenue.
That was just not an option.
And also importantly, in order to make sure this was safe, we needed to make sure that
all the changes were rolled back safe.
So we couldn't be like, okay, we're going to make this big change, and if it breaks
something, we can't go back.
We don't want to get in that position.
So let's talk about sort of the different phases of this and what that timeline looked
like.
So first was basically making sure that the code parsed under Python 3.
That was a really simple task, actually.
There's a lot of, there were very few actual changes in that space.
So it took us about two weeks.
Importability was next.
This was basically making sure that we could actually import the code under Python 3.
That seems kind of trivial, but it's actually a good amount of work, and it took us about
two months.
But the biggest one by far is the third phase, which was what I call functional parity, which
took us about a year.
And this is basically just making sure that the code works the same.
I'll go into a lot of details about that later.
And then finally, once we actually were confident that our code was working the same under Python
2 and 3, we went to the rollout phase, where we actually rolled it out to production.
And that took us about two months.
So in terms of actually tracking this work, you have to understand what needs to be done
and making sure that people are coordinating all that stuff.
So this is sort of what we did for each of those.
First is the parsability, as I mentioned.
This was a really small part of the task.
And so it was literally like you just try and parse all the files.
You just kind of run Python 3 on it, did it parse?
Okay.
If it didn't make a ticket, that was like a single pass.
For importability, what we did is we just imported all the files and then inspected
the import error stack trace and looked at what was the last file that's actually in
our repo that caused this import error.
And then just sort of pipe that to unique dash C and then sort dash N. And then you
get, you know, here are your top files that are causing import errors.
And you just kind of run that script every week or something, file tickets, and then
pick up the tickets and fix them.
For the functional parity, most of it was about running tests.
So we have a test runner already, which groups all of the test failures by trace back.
And so we basically ran the test periodically.
We basically run it every day.
And then we would file the tickets of like what was at the top in terms of issues.
And then, you know, pick stuff off of the, out of that pool.
So an important tool in this, which some of you may or may not be familiar with, is Python
modernize.
So Python modernize is a great tool.
It's an open source tool that we used, which converts Python 2 only code to Python 2 and
3 compatible code.
Since we wanted to make sure that this rollout was, you know, rollback safe, we needed to
make sure that it was compatible.
We couldn't just use 2 to 3, even though Python modernize actually uses lib 2 to 3.
It uses a lot of the functionality in lib 2 to 3 to get you to that state.
Some of the 2 to 3 fixes are actually just totally compatible.
But some of them use 6 as a compatibility layer.
There's actually a similar tool called Python futureize, which uses future.
We were already using 6, so we decided to use modernize instead.
There's not really like a particular reason to use one or the other other than, you know,
your particular setup.
In terms of what it actually does is, you know, it fixes some of the syntax changes.
It fixes some of the standard lib import changes.
And also some of the behavior changes.
I'll go through this example that I have on the right in terms of each of the changes.
So first is in Python 2, you imported the Q object, the Q class from the Q module where
it was capital case.
But in Python 3, you import it from the lower case module name.
So you can't really import it from both at the same time.
So we use this 6 shim to import that class.
Another one is that the values method and the items method and the keys method, those
all return iterators instead of lists in Python 3.
So in order to be compatible, you have to wrap those in a list.
And it does that for you automatically.
Similarly, there was the iter items method, iter values and iter keys which were removed
in Python 3 because they were now redundant.
And so now there's a shim for 6 and automatically replaces the regular method call with that
shim.
And then finally, there's a syntax change which is that you used to be able to raise
exceptions like this where you would give the exception class comma and then arguments.
But you can't do that anymore.
So now it just constructs the exception for you.
So let's talk a little bit about some of the tooling that we used during this migration.
So one of the things is that we used precommit.
Python modernized is actually a precommit hook.
And precommit's really nice because it allows us to run all these linters and code mods
and make sure that they get run for new branches.
So we made sure that any new code checked in would be run through these code mods so
that they were as compatible as possible with Python 3.
And one of the things that was kind of cool is that we actually added black to this repo
during the work on this migration.
And it didn't require any extra dev time.
It just sort of happened and we didn't really think about it.
And it just worked.
So let's sort of take this piece of code.
I made up this silly piece of code which allows us to sort of go through the phases of this
migration and what those looked like at each stage.
So first is possibility, as I mentioned.
So in this case, you basically just run, we ran Python modernize.
And this fixed a couple of syntax errors.
As I mentioned, there's the change to the raise syntax.
There's also a change to the accept syntax.
You used to be able to say, accept, exception, comma, and then a variable name that you bind
the exception to.
That was removed in Python 3.
So you now have to say as.
And Python modernize just fixes this for you.
And that's it.
That's possibility.
So importability is basically, we're again using Python modernize.
And we did it in chunks mostly for rollback safety.
We wanted to make sure that our changes were relatively small.
And then we also had to fix our package importability.
So a lot of that was sort of upgrading those packages to versions that now had Python 3
support.
Some of them we had to replace because they never got Python 3 support.
We usually used some sort of fork or something like that.
And some of them we just kind of had to refactor away.
They never got Python 3 support.
And we were like, well, we don't really need these that bad.
We can just refactor it.
And then we also had our internal packages.
So those, some of them didn't have Python 3 support yet.
They were too old.
And so we had to upgrade them to have Python 3 support and then bump them in Yelp main.
And mostly that was just running Python modernize on them.
So now we get this piece of code importable.
And one of the things is that C pickle is removed in Python 3 in favor of being merged
into the pickle module.
So there's a sixth shim for that.
And Python modernize just fixes that and all of the import and all of the references.
So functional parity is the next thing.
Functional parity for this was mostly that, so first of all is we built this parallel
virtual AMP.
We made a second virtual AMP that was Python 3 based that used most of the same packages.
We had to filter out a few things that were mostly backports that you can't install in
Python 3.
Things like typing and features were things that we just didn't need in Python 3.
And this also let us do development against Python 3.
So people could use Python 3 to verify their code would work once we flipped.
Next we wanted to get our tests to pass.
As I mentioned, we need to fix 100,000 tests, which is a ton.
We still used a lot of Python modernize stuff.
Some of that was automatable.
As you can see on the right, this is our code again.
And one of the things is that we're using the Unicode built in in Python 2, which doesn't
exist in Python 3.
So we used a six shim in order to get around that.
So that was nice, but the elephant in the room is always going to be text, text and
bytes, and mixing those up was really easy in Python 2.
So we had to fix those in Python 3.
And mostly that was relying on tests.
There were some other tricky things, things like double under bool versus double under
non-zero.
These were in Python 3, double under bool is used for if statement truthiness.
That's how you customize if statement truthiness.
And in Python 2, it's double under non-zero.
So there were some custom classes that had double under non-zero defined but not double
under bool.
The thing about that is it's confusing because it just sort of passes the if statement or
doesn't pass the if statement when you expect.
So you have to make sure that that gets, that you sort of figure out where the actual error
is.
And the fix is simple, but actually figuring out where the error is is more difficult.
Similar with meta classes.
With meta classes, this is actually fixable by Python modernize.
Anytime you're using meta class, it uses a shim to make sure that it's working in both
Python 2 and Python 3, but the behavior can be confusing.
But our goal was always to have behavior consistency between Python 2 and Python 3 so that we could
make sure that everything worked when we rolled forward.
One of the other things we had to deal with was the fact that we had these caches that
used pickle.
And if you've ever had to deal with pickle across Python 2 and 3, it doesn't really work
super great.
It's sort of like weird gotchas.
So we just decided that we were just going to get rid of pickle entirely.
So what we did is we decided to switch to JSON.
But we didn't want to just completely bust our caches because these caches are important
for the performance of our website.
So what I did is basically started logging these JSON encoded values.
And then we would check the quality of the values once they were encoded.
So we basically make sure that the pickle and the JSON encoded cache values ended up
being the same.
And once we got those to a working state, we would basically switch to what we call
the mixed mode where we would try to read the JSON values.
And if that didn't work, we would fall back to pickle, read the pickle value, and then
we would write back JSON.
And then any time we were writing a new value, write JSON.
Eventually over time, if you wait long enough, you end up with mostly JSON and you can flip
to doing just JSON only.
There were a few things that were really complex, weird setups that we just couldn't fix.
And so we ended up just using a cache prefix.
So those things just were different on Python 2 and Python 3.
Another thing we had to deal with was context lib nested, which was removed in Python 3.
This was relatively easy to fix.
It just didn't have an automated fix, which is basically we wrote a function which used
exit stack to replicate the interface and we used a little bit of sed to replace the
imports and the usages.
Another thing is that you can actually end up, you may or may not be familiar with the
CMP function that used to be in Python 2's sorted and list.sort.
So that was mostly, that was the key function was added in, I can't remember what version
of Python 2, but eventually the CMP function was removed.
And these were just slightly different ways of dealing with sorting, deciding how to sort
things.
But it turns out you can actually use both.
There's a shim function for converting a CMP function to a key function in func tools,
func tools CMP to key, which is really useful.
But it turns out that sometimes you can use both and that wasn't really supported.
So we wrote this function which takes both of those functions and converts it into a
new key function.
And all it really does is it just calls the CMP to key on the CMP function and that calls
the key function on the value that's passed in and passes that new value to the CMP to
key created function.
Sorry, I should just, whatever.
So that's, and that was really useful because there are some situations where that was just
really hard to refactor.
So rollout.
This is I think the coolest part.
This is the part that I found was the most difficult.
But we came up with a way of dealing with the situation that I think is really interesting,
which is that since we had these parallel Python 2 and 3 virtual ends, we were able
to actually run separate instances, some under Python 2 and under Python 3, but running the
same code otherwise.
And we would use a reverse, we would use the reverse proxy layer that we have to basically
look at the URL prefix and go to the Python 3 instance or the Python 2 instance.
And this allowed us to granulately roll out individual URL prefixes.
And it was really great because if we were having errors with a particular prefix, we
didn't have to roll back everything.
We just had to say, oh, that prefix is bad.
Let's roll it back.
Let's fix the issue and then roll it back forward.
This was really valuable because some of the errors were just not caught by tests.
Our test coverage is okay, but you're just never going to be 100% perfect in that way.
So it was really valuable that we were able to do this.
And we coordinated using an ownership spreadsheet.
There were about 800 end point prefixes across the six sites.
And then we did a similar thing for batches.
Since they were individual processes, we could actually just flip them to Python 3 independently.
And we did a similar ownership spreadsheet.
So in terms of the outcomes, it was very much a very long tail, especially during the functional
parity page.
This is a graph of our test failures over time.
So we started out really high test failure or sort of passing percentage.
We started out really low passing percentage, but we quickly got up to very, very high.
But the last few percentage points took a lot longer because we were doing less impactful
fixes each time.
Type annotations would have been really useful.
We thought about adding type annotations before this project, but we decided that was a huge
project in itself, so we didn't do it.
But it would have been exceptionally useful, especially for the text and bytes issues.
The rollout did take longer than expected.
We were originally scoping for a month.
Part of that was that we were blocked by teams doing verification.
And that was kind of our fault for not really notifying them earlier.
So because of this sort of this curve, we didn't really know exactly when we'd be done.
So we just kind of like, oh, we're close to done.
Let's let people know.
But that was a little bit too late.
In the end, we ended up with about a 15 to 20 percent speed up, which is great.
We were not going for that at all.
We just wanted to get our code working on a newer version of Python, but it was faster.
It was great.
Plus we used about 26 percent less memory.
I think both of these really show that this type of basic sort of maintenance can really
have an effect on your bottom line.
And it's really valuable to do it for reasons like this.
In terms of the future, what we're doing right now is we're automating minor Python version
bumps.
We're trying to leverage the existing tool that we already have, which is used to bump
packages.
We're using PIP tools to do targeted upgrades and then run tests to ensure functional parity.
And this is actually running as one of our internal tools.
And it's actually running right now.
And we can do these upgrades where we go from, you know, to newer minor Python versions.
It's really great.
So that's it.
I know that there's no, like, official Q&A, but I'm not doing anything after this.
So if you want to ask me any questions, I'm happy to do it in the hallway.