Hello, how's everyone doing today? Great, awesome. Okay, so we can start with our next
talk. It's by Jason and oh, I love this talk title. If an async IOTask fails in the woods
and nobody's around to see it, does it still page you at 3 a.m.? Right? Over to you, Jason.
All right, welcome to my talk. This was the longest title I could think up. But if it
helps you can refer to it by a handy acronym, IATFITWOHCDDISPY3, but that should be less
cumbersome when you want to talk about this talk in conversation later. I actually wanted
to see what that looked like on the... I guess we don't have time for that. I'm currently
a production engineer at Meta. I've contributed irregularly to CPython and various other open
source projects. And I've been writing software for a while. I spent seven years writing C
code and then ten years writing Perl and basically I started writing Python when I started at
Facebook in 2011. So I've been involved in Python development for ten years, a little
bit more. At Meta I drove the Python 2 to 3 conversion way back when just so I could
use async IO in production. Though back then it was still called Tulip and we were still
on before 3.5. And when you're a pioneer you have to forward a lot of rivers. And you have
to make do with whatever you can build yourself. So we had rivers that had to be crossed before
appropriate bridges had been built in the standard live or PyPI. So I had to build them
or to solve problems like async unit tests, async context managers, we needed an exit
stack. But fast forward to today we have hundreds of back end services written with async IO.
There are tens of thousands of people authoring Python commits every month at Meta. So I have
seen lots of code. I've seen the good, I've seen the bad, and I've seen the ugly. And
in this talk we're going to cover the ugly in very humorous detail. Things like nested
event loops, bad async IO bootstrapping, anonymous tasks, calling coroutines in the init method,
bad signal handling, ignoring cancellation, and not using timeouts. So on the subject
of event loops, now this is mostly for library writers. You have existing callers. You're
not an async dev, but you want to call a coroutine. This seems very simple. I'll just hit the
default event loop and I'll run it to complete. Well the problem comes is that you have some
caller way up in a call chain that you're not even aware of that's already running the
loop. And they get an exception about the loop already running. And because you would
have to change a whole bunch of unrelated functions outside of your own project to have
async dev variants, you figure it's just easier to hack it. So you decide to pause the existing
loop and use your own loop. So this pattern is called the nested event loop. Basically
trick async IO into thinking that there are no event loops running so that you can create
your own and start it while you block the current one. The example above is obviously
shorted and we have some many slides to go into detail, but it's really a dirty hack.
And it has some very bad unintended consequences. And we'll probably get you paged at 3 a.m.
because the service owner is seeing timeouts in their event loop once you stop blocking
it. Look, I've seen this kind of logic used at Meta and people still try to do crazy shit
like this because we all know writing quick and brittle unmaintainable code is better
than taking time to do it correctly because it just seems easier. Well, it's easier now,
but in the long run it's going to be very hard. The first thing is that this is completely
unsupported behavior. It requires you to reach into the guts of async IO to make it work.
And the next thing you will find is that the original loop has things scheduled on it that
you were not aware of. And those things have timeouts. And those timeouts will get expired
because you have blocked its event loop. The last one is you will end up having tasks
on the new event loop that you had created and they will throw some strange stack traces
when you'd have to close up your own event loop. And in the future you might have other
work that gets somehow added to this sub loop and you might have loops within loops nested
very far down and it'll be very hard to reason about what's going on. I've given up trying
to help people when I find them doing this and I tell them to just point them in the
right way. But the more magical your Python code gets, the harder it will be for you to
support it. Understanding what it's doing when something does go wrong is just a wasted effort.
So the solution is just to use async IO dot run. You may say, well doesn't async IO dot
run have the same issues as we had before? Well yes it does, but it lets the caller easily
put it into a different thread using an executor. Because it creates a new event loop instead
of assuming that there's a default one, which is not true on threads other than main, and
that exception thrown is a good thing. It lets the caller know that they need to put
the function in a thread pool executor. Or you could do it for them if you happen to
live in a giant mono repo shared code base like meta because you need to land your own
changes and you don't want to break their tests. Now the best solution, but it's not
always practical or possible, is to provide an entire async def call chain from their
code to your code and maintain a separate blocking call chain that used to exist. It
sounds daunting, but that's probably the best solution. So some tips is you only own
the event loops you create. Respecting ownership means that if you do not own it, you don't
mess with it. Like you don't come to my ranch and mess with my goats and I'll ford you
the same courtesy. A core tenet of Python is that we are all consenting adults. We don't
need the language to make us behave or respect each other's privacy. And in the case of event
loops, don't stop it. Don't start it, don't block it, just leave it alone. You can do
normal stuff, but you definitely don't set up a magic sub nested event. This violates
the number one rule of async IO that you're just now going to hear about because I made
it up this week. You are not allowed to block the event loop on purpose. Sure people block
it all the time out of ignorance, but when you do it on purpose that's malicious intent.
Right there that makes you a bad person, but you should feel bad. So you should be using
async IO. And ideally only ever have one event loop. If that's not possible, have one event
loop per thread. But you should never have more than one loop on the same thread. It's
just madness. Also let your callers decide what to do. They have more context than you
about the event loop and maybe what might be scheduled there. And they have the ability
to put in an executor. You don't have that from a blocking call. Now let's look at the
bootstrapping async IO and why it's important you have clean async bootstrapping. Bootstrapping
is the process of starting up the event loop, scheduling the initial work, and also concerned
with handling the results and handling cleanup and taking care of signal handling so that
your application can terminate sanely. You've probably seen code like this in the past.
I've seen it all over the place. It's a holdover from a pattern before we had coroutines, before
we had async IO run and it was encouraged that people use callback style async IO. So
this is super old. It's terrible. You're in and out of the loop. We start the loop.
We run it. We get some value. We go back into the loop. We create a task. Then we run forever.
Well we don't ever actually stop the loop unless somebody stops the loop. If that task
died, we're still running the loop. And if we do somehow do stop the loop, we have to
So we have to cancel the task and then we have to run the loop again and then we're
finally finally close it. So that task, while it has a name, it might as well be anonymous.
We don't ensure that it stays running. This might get you woken up in the middle of the
night to find that your running service is actually doing nothing. This is kind of a
maintenance nightmare. So even if you do get your task canceled, you have no knowledge
or basic you can't ensure that the callbacks, if there are any callbacks on it, actually
get run before you complete and run on to complete. The solutions pattern is easy and
much cleaner. Like the last issue, the solution is async IO.run. It handles all the crazy
bootstrapping cleanup like cancellation of task and some basic signal handling. And it's
just less code and easier to read. Now we have, we're doing pretty much the same work,
but we pass, we basically take a coroutine and we do all initialization and pass it to
async IO.run. If that very important task, some server that we had before, if it fails,
the code just exits like it logically should. And since we're talking about tasks, let's
look at the problem of anonymous tasks or what I call set it and forget it pattern.
It also applies to daemon threads. Unlike an infomercial kitchen or tessery, tasks should
never be created and forgotten about. This is exactly the kind of thing that gets you
paged at four in the morning. Turns out that something important happens in the do something
coroutine, and it has been printing exceptions all night. But because we didn't do anything
with the tasks, nobody noticed. They just get printed to the standard error. And nobody
noticed until four in the morning until it started breaking other things. You should
have some mechanism to ensure that your tasks are inspected when they have exceptions. Your
unit test should look for these unhandled tasks. The solution to this is simple, use
async IO.run. Okay, that's a joke. Not everything is solved by async IO.run. It can't solve
all your problems. One possible solution is the nursery from Trio. I don't know the origins
of the name, but we can generally reason about how it should work. We don't let small children
just wander around unattended, and we put them in a nursery so that we can watch over
them and take care of them in case something bad happens. Now, don't get the idea of killing
all the other kids when one kid has an issue. That kind of gets dark and mirrors the disturbing
terminology we use when we talk about the POSIX process model about killing children
when their parents die and sometimes there's zombies involved. To get back on track, the
gist of this idea is you have this failure domain of tasks. If a task in the nursery
dies for whatever reason, the other tasks are canceled. An application-wide feature
domain is useful for important tasks for your service that if they failed for whatever reason,
would be really bad. You can get this functionality in async IO using the AO nursery or the later
package from PyPI, though later calls them watchers. They basically have the same goal.
So you might ask, well, I don't care if the task fails. It's best effort. I'm logging
or doing something like that. So sure, if it fails every once in a while, maybe that's
fine, but what if it started failing every time you called it? Is that still best effort?
You should have some mechanism to ensure that not all of these best effort activities fail.
Maybe set some kind of SLA. Like if you start failing a certain percentage per hour, maybe
you should do something about it or go ahead and set your alarm for 3 a.m. so I can call
you. You might say that you're just using tasks for this abomination. So this is a something,
example I've seen in talks, I've seen this online, is we have this bound queue and we're
putting an item on it and they're like, oh, I don't want to get blocked, so I'm going
to put that in a task. So this pattern, I've seen this pattern talked about, like what
the hell are you actually doing? Because this is so much more performant, just having an
unbound queue and using put no wait. Like think, would you rather unbound memory growth
potential or unbound memory growth potential and slow ass event loop cycling through an
unbound list of tasks, which has in effect become a second queue, which if you know anything
about queueing theory, you don't do secondary queues. But one thing that is, but this one
secondary queue is way more expensive than the original queue because the bigger it gets,
the slower your event loop gets because your event loop has to cycle through all the tasks
to check them if they're ready. So if you're going to do something like this, then just
use an unbounded queue or use the put no wait, but if you're going to use a bounded queue,
use it for what it's supposed to be for. It's supposed to be for flow control so you can
get back pressure. You can know that the queue that we're working on is filling up. Maybe
I should report to the user that we're overloaded. Let's move on. So calling coroutines from
a knit. People always seem to want to get in the situation, like I got to call this
coroutine from my knit method. I see code like this and I personally think, do you hate
me? Like are you doing this on purpose? So by doing this in a knit, you have barred me
from using async IORun, which according to this talk you'll know is my favorite thing
in the world, which you should be using by the way, since it creates its own event loop
that anything you produce or start here is in a different event loop. Some people use
that nasty magic nested event loop that we had talked about before and it has all the
same problems and it's weird. Or they create anonymous tasks, which we just got to finish
talking about. The problem with these patterns is you're doing some kind of async activity
in a place that was not designed and is ill suited for that task. Like what are we really
trying to do here? Like any IO inside of a knit method is bad design. Good in it method
should not block or affect any state outside themselves. So don't do this. You don't need
it. There are better alternatives. The solution is the async context manager. To initialize
any async state of an object. By using an async context manager, you have a method that
is well suited for initializing async stuff. And as an added bonus, you have a well suited
method for cleaning and canceling your async stuff. Because they're code routines. That's
what they're made for. And on the subject of using context managers, I have seen code
like this to like you get a random package, somebody's downloading PyPI and they want
you to help them get it running. And you have to go read through their docs and you have
to find what they decided to name this method that you have to run for it to work. Well,
there's no conventions. This method can be named anything. Here it's like, oh, let me
go read your docs again so I can see what this is going to be called. But then you sometimes
have to worry about clean up and you have to go find out what that's called. Though
with an async context manager, there's a better pattern. It's the same amount of work except
that the maintainer of the better async web server can do it for you. This pattern is
less error prone. It uses less of your own head space to keep track of. The API is defined
by a PEP which means it's well defined in part of the language. You learn it once and
it never changes. Well, hopefully. The async context manager and well context managers
in general are pretty awesome. They're like the perfect system for writing like a plug-in
or extensions. No matter what my object does, everyone already knows how to enter its context.
They know how to clean it up. It's built into Python using the with statement or in this
case the async with statement. So let's move to signal handling. Every application needs
signal handling, especially async code. Async I O run, which I love to talk about, gives
us some helpful defaults for control C and which is a case again. But you probably will
need more. This is essentially the signal handling example in the async I O docs. I've
shortened it and I've cleaned it up because I didn't like what they were calling functions.
But basically we have our main method. We get the loop, the running loop, the correct
way, and we set the signal and we set the sig term, the first one being control C, and
we add the signal handlers and we do some partial magic so we can pass it the loop and
And then in our handler we print that we got the signal that we're exiting and then we
do a loop.stop. This is straight from the docs, like what to do when you want to handle
this. This is terrible. This practice of handling shutdown of an application, it's like the
adding signal handlers, that's a good part. That's actually useful. But what we do with
the signals is the problem. We just called stop. And if you do call loop stop, your application
will raise a runtime error to be raised wherever you happen to run the loop. Because we all
know that your application should explode with unhandled exceptions when you handle
a signal and everything goes as expected. The exception lets you know it's working. Okay,
nobody thinks like that. If you tell me that you're just going to catch that exception,
I'll be paging you tomorrow at 325 a.m. If you're not using async I O run, then you need
to start the loop again to handle cleanup by yourself. We saw that in the bootstrapping
example. And if you are using async I run, you better be okay with all the tasks being
canceled at pretty much the same time. And there's a good chance that you will care. Like what if
you have an async web server, we'll say that runs a status page of your application, and when it's
shutting down, you would like to update the status page so you can know that the process is still
going and shutting down and know what it's doing. Well, because some of your tasks might take a
little while to shut down, and maybe they can update on this page. Well, if you use loop.stop,
your web server will probably be the first thing to get canceled. And you're still going to have to
wait for your other tasks to finish. One solution is that you could instead cancel a task. This task
might be what you're primarily concerned with. This, your shutdown logic could be just handled
in cancellation flow. You could combine this with maybe a later watcher or a task nursery. Later
watcher has a method you can call on the watcher to cancel all the tasks and fall through the
context. That's what I use in my method for terminating my applications from signal handlers.
If you, and I do that from the non-signal things, if you combine this with an async context manager
and exit stack, you have this like, subscribable system that you can handle well-ordered startup
and well-ordered shutdown. It all happens in the order you specify. So if you want your web server
to be the last thing that gets canceled, you enter its context first. So all the other things
have to be canceled and exit and then your web server shutdown. Shutdown logic and signal
handling logic should be the same because most of the time, how else do you shut down your
application but sitting at a control C or a SIG term? And even if you have some other non-signal way
to shut down your application, you probably want to do the same thing anyway. So just make them the
same. Or you could use an event. That might be a solution. Your task could wait on it. They can
use it as a looping flag. Multiple places in your code could monitor the same event. It's not as
robust as task cancellation in the watcher solution with the async exit stack, but it's better than
the blast creator that's created with loop stop because that provides zero customization about how
things get turned off. So we talked about cancellation a few times, so we should probably go over it. So
let's spend the next 40 slides to quickly introduce cancellation. Okay, I'm kidding. We're not going
to do that. But I am going to go over some of it. Cancellation is tricky and it's hard, but it's not
that hard. Many people screwed up just by ignoring cancellation, either on purpose or out of ignorance.
Like this code above or maybe this code where we still do the same thing but we're catching
basic exception. Or maybe this code where we're still catching cancellation error but we're just
very terrible about it because we're using naked accepts. So if we go back to the original code
here. So what are we doing here? Like what were you trying to accomplish? Like I see patterns like
this and the only time you should ever do something like this is if you have just canceled a task
yourself and you are waiting for it to ensure that it cancels. And even then it's not so simple as
we'll see later. So people generally expect to be able to cancel a task, but task writers never
expect their task to be canceled. Cancellation is a contract. It's not a clear one, but you agree to
it the moment you start writing async IO code. I cobbled together what the contract looks like
by just reading through the documentation. It's in a couple different places. Number one, in a
wait statement, any wait statement can raise a cancel error. It could be somebody canceling you,
it could be somebody canceling a task you're waiting on, it could be both. You can have be
canceled more than once. That's a little weird. You can catch the exception, but you should never
ignore it and always re-raise the exception. When you get canceled, you don't have to exit right now,
but you should move towards shutdown. Like async IO run expects that all tasks will eventually
cancel because it attempts to do just that before it returns. And as per the documentation, the
canceled error exception can be caught to perform custom operations when async tasks are canceled.
In almost all situations, that exception must be re-raised. Well, but what about the other ones
where you don't have to re-raise it? Well, I guess nobody knows. We'll figure that out later. So,
it's not hard to comply with the contract. When you get the exception, start your cleanup and stop
accepting new work, move towards exiting, and then raise when you're done. This also means you have
to stop catching base exception or using empty accept clauses with your async IO code unless
you're being very careful to check that what you did catch was not a cancel error. Because it is a
cancel error, you have to re-raise it in most cases. And the other side of cancellation is easy,
right? You want to cancel a task, you just call cancel. Wrong. That task isn't actually canceled
yet. It's scheduled to be canceled for the next time you await something. Yet, I see people
canceling things and expecting that this is what this happens. For this reason, I have long held
the opinion that cancel should return an awaitable. So, canceling things correctly is not too hard.
You can cancel on a task, but it doesn't actually cancel until the next event loop cycle. If the
task has never been run, then it's canceled without ever the coroutine ever being started.
But if the task is already running, the next cycle of the loop will cause a cancel error to be raised
from whatever await statement it's currently paused at. And this affects all the things that
it's awaiting on as well. So, it goes all the way down the chain unless it's shielded and throws in
a canceled error. Even then, a task is not considered canceled until it re-raises the canceled error.
The docs seem to say it should be the same canceled error. So, we do this in the coroutine above,
we cancel the task, and then we await on it and catch the cancel exception. Because we know it's
going to happen, we don't want to raise it because we're purposely canceling something. But what if
the task takes a long time to cancel and someone has come from above you and attempted to cancel
you while you're waiting on the task to finish? But you're supposed to re-raise the cancel you've
got, but we're suppressing it. So, maybe it's not as easy as I've let on. So, I've come up with this
monstrosity. So, you can see that what we're doing is we're trying to prevent ourselves from being
canceled until the task we are trying to cancel has finished canceling. That's a mouthful. So,
we check that the task was canceled every time we catch the canceled error. And if we catch one and
the task is not done, we save that exception to raise later to complete our part of the cancellation
contract. We also cycle the event loop after the task cancel so we give a chance for the callbacks
to get a chance to run. You may notice we also use shield. So, this is when we are canceled,
we can prevent that the task that we have already sent a cancel message to from getting a secondary
cancel while we are awaiting it. Yeah, you could do all this every time you want to cancel something
or you could use something like later.cancel from the later package in PyPI. And I will be pushing
out a new release sometime tonight to update with this new extended behavior. But let's move on.
So, you need timeouts. You should use timeouts in your application because in the real world,
things get stuck. Now, you may tell me that you have never used timeouts
before. And you don't have any issues. I call you a liar. But no, so what are the chances that an
async call won't complete in the expected time? Well, in your dev environment, that's zero. Look,
we've all heard the lament, hey, it worked in my dev server. Everything works on your dev server
because that's where you stuff. But in production, it's a little different. Everybody has experiences.
Things don't always behave expected the first time you run it in production. But what you may not know
is that running something in production makes your service actively hate you. Not people in general,
just you. So, during standard business hours, it seems to change based on whether or not you're at
your desk. It fails more the moment you step away from your desk. And because even more unstable the
moment you're out eating lunch with your friends. And I'm not sure exactly how this one happens,
but it does. And things also fail more often during weekends than they do on weekdays. Things
never seem to fail when you're actually working. There are some obvious modifiers that have been
observed on holidays. When you're sleeping, when you don't have access to your laptop,
things fail more often. And then later, the later the night gets, the more things fail.
So, if you're sleeping at 5 a.m. while having forgotten stuff at work, on a holiday, that's
170%. Wait, you say that's over 100%, Jason. You're not doing probability correctly. Well,
at that point, your service has broken all the rules of probability and is going after all the
other services in your infrastructure for sport. If you sleep until 10, that's a site-wide incident.
And then you are somehow taking down random pieces of the internet and your CEO is calling
you because they have to release a press release. Okay, I've made all that up, but the idea is that
your service is going to fail at certain times. You may think it's directly related to you because
it'll just fall on its face at random times. Timeouts are kind of a way to keep things in
check when you're not there to manually intervene or to interrupt it when it gets stuck.
So, look, things fail. Prepare for it. Sometimes things don't raise exceptions when they will
never complete. They might raise an exception eventually, but that could be on geologic
time scales, not human ones. This is why we have timeouts in software. You have a few choices.
There's wait and wait for, but neither are as elegant as the async timeout package from
PyPI. Things inside the timeout context get cancelled if they run too long. And outside
the context gets raised a timeout error. When you are waiting for something that could be delayed,
consider adding timeouts around the code. When you don't want to have to be woken up in the
night, figure out why your service is doing nothing at all. In our example above, we are
using nested timeouts because the request timeout we want should, we should plan to
retry them when they timeout. And how long we should attempt to retry them, that's a case of
a budget we've set like 100 milliseconds. So that we, that they should only ever take 100
milliseconds total if they have to keep retrying. So, look, shit happens. Try to make the best of
it. Async.io can be a powerful tool, but used poorly will cause you lots of pain. So let's wrap
up this talk. So, inclusion. Never assume intent or violate ownership expectations.
Nested event loops is a bad idea. If you want logical startup and shutdown, use async.io context
managers and async exit stacks. Tasks fail or sometimes never complete. Use timeouts and handle
your exceptions. I've had people tell me that cancellation is too hard. Look, it's not that
hard and it's not that painful set up. It's definitely better than being paged in the middle
of a cold night while you're sleeping. I suggest async.io run because it's the best bootstrap we
have. Even though it raises exceptions, it's awesome because I'd rather know that you're
attempting to run an event loop that I can easily put in execute without having to worry about
threads getting default event loops. That's it. Thank you for coming to my Ted talk. Any questions?
Questions will be out in the hallway.