The usage of the term in the previous slide is quite different from what we are going
to discuss today.
Some of the key ideas that I found from back then that really resonated with me and that
expresses the essence of what middleware is are terms like glue.
It's an interface between hardware found above the transport layer but below the application
environment.
I can't really exactly express why but somewhere those terms gives me the essence of what we
truly use middleware for today.
Of course we are not talking about hardware but generally just as a glue between different
parts of our application.
Now for today consider a web application which consists of one or more API endpoints or views.
When middleware is code you write to implement functionality that is common across one or
more of your endpoints or views.
Examples count of page views centralized error handling caching and many others.
The WSGI specification PEP333 describes middleware as a way to provide extended APIs content
transformation navigation and other useful functions.
This leads us to our second topic of the talk middleware for WSGI applications.
I will start us off with discussing Flask applications.
Consider a very simple Flask application where we create a blueprint and define a single
route which handles all the requests and let's refer to that as the view function.
Now of course I have omitted a bunch of stuff from here because they are not relevant in
this context.
To define middleware in Flask we use decorators.
One example for decorator that we use is the before request decorator.
When you create a function or define a function and decorate it with the before request decorator
that function always gets called before your view function gets called when a request has
been made to the application.
Similarly if you want a function to be called after the request has been processed and the
response has been generated you decorate it with the function with the decorator after
request.
Of course here I have shown the example of blueprint but this equally applies to non-blueprint
applications as well just to be clear.
A typical example is shown here as a use case for where you might want to use this.
Let's say you want to print or not necessarily print perhaps record the latency of your page
rendering.
What you would do is you would use the Flask G global variable to start a timer in the
before request function or the function where you decorated with before request and then
in the function you decorated with after request you would find the difference between the
time now and the time that you recorded at the beginning of the request and that gives
you the latency of your page rendering.
So that's marked as an optional because I may not have time for it.
So if you do check out the slides I think that might give you more insights into how
this before request and after request are implemented within Flask itself.
Now it's very common to define not one but multiple such before request sorry not define
let's let's let's rehearse that.
It's very common to define multiple functions which you decorate with before request as
well as after request.
Now the ordering matters for the before request functions which I have specified here as before
request underscore F1 before request underscore F2 the order in which they are defined is
the order in which they are called.
For the after request functions they are called in the reverse order.
So when the response is generated from the view function the function you defined last
gets called first and then subsequently the other functions in a last in first order manner.
Let's consider a Django application now.
This is a simplified view function which I have called index.
It takes a single parameter request which represents the current request that is being
handled.
Please keep this in mind this is going to be our key for the next couple of slides.
So in Django you can define middleware using two approaches.
You can define a class or you can define a function.
Now the first example I have here is a class based approach.
You define a class you define a constructor which takes in a single parameter get response.
This parameter represents either the next view function or the next middleware to be
called.
The magic really happens here in the magic method call.
So what happens here is the first thing note here is the parameter that call takes.
It takes a parameter request which represents the current request that is being handled
and this is exactly what the view function also took in as a parameter.
Now in the call method is where we implement our middleware.
Now in this case the middleware we are implementing handles exceptions.
The desired behavior is if there is no exception we return the response as it is.
If however we got an exception we want to return a custom response.
I've omitted that from here for our brevity.
Code is really hard to put on slides in a way that actually it's legible.
So I've omitted that from here.
And that's your middleware which is using a class based approach in Django.
A function based middleware looks as shown.
We define a function called of course you can call it exactly what your middleware does.
In this case I'm calling it as latency underscore reporter.
And because I'm measuring latency of a request using this middleware.
Now the key here is the latency reporter function takes in a parameter get response
which points to the next middleware or the view function that we called for the request.
Now this function returns a closure that closure is again taking that parameter request
which represents the country was being handled and that is returned.
And the Django middleware machinery invokes this function whenever a request is being handled.
Now inside the closure what we do is we again start a timer with an assignment to a variable
request underscore begin and then we go through.
Sorry and then we call the view function or the next middleware which is get response.
And then after we have got the response from that function we can print the latency here
in a more practical use case you push the latency to your monitoring system
and then return the response from here.
Now once you define your middleware this is how you activate those middleware in Django.
You update your settings dot pi and you point and you update the middleware list
which is a module level variable to the middleware you want to activate.
The ordering here matters once again.
So consider that we have a middleware A B and then we have your application handler
or your view function whatever you want to call it as.
So when a request is being processed like basically when the request is coming into
your application first the middleware A is called then your middleware B is called
and then finally your view function is called.
Once the response has been generated the response first goes into middleware B
and then goes up to middleware A and then finally the client.
One key difference between Flask and Django middleware is that in Flask your middleware
may not be invoked for both parts of your request that is when for the request as well
as the response because you control that with the decorators before request and after request.
In Django it's different.
Every middleware that you define gets both the request as well as the response.
It depends on your middleware whether you want you can ignore the request or you can
ignore the response.
It really depends on what your middleware is trying to do.
To recap using middleware you define custom code to run before and after request processing
and how the middleware works is a framework specific detail which you usually can find
out by looking at the framework source code.
I did it myself but I have omitted it from today's talk because I will not be able to
cover it in the time.
I thought I had a 45 minute slot initially.
And WSGI frameworks define their own mechanism to define the middleware.
So let's pause a bit.
So as we have seen we write a middleware for Django application and we write a middleware
for Flask applications and the way we do it is quite different.
And the reason it's different is because each framework implements their own mechanism.
Now my question is could you write middleware in a framework independent way?
It turns out we can.
These are after all WSGI frameworks which means they define WSGI applications and there
lies the answer as we shall see next.
So I'll take a step back and define what is a function, a function which instantly
is a WSGI application.
I don't know how many of you actually know that this is a WSGI application.
I mean I knew something like this is how you define a WSGI application but before I did
this talk I had no idea.
But this is how a WSGI application looks like and that is it.
You don't have to do anything else.
So it takes two parameters of a dictionary called environ and a function startResponse.
The dictionary environ contains key value pairs describing the current request and startResponse
is a function which you use to send back the response to the client.
So the commented lines are where you do your processing in your handler and then when you're
ready to send the response you first call the startResponse with two arguments.
The first is a string containing the HTTP status and the second is a list of headers
that you want to add to the response and then you send back the response itself.
The response needs to be iterable.
So here it just contains a single byte hello world.
Let's look at how we can write a WSGI middleware.
So it looks very similar to the Django middleware with certain differences.
In fact, in fact, let me go back to this.
It looks, if you look at the call method, we'll ignore the init because it's not relevant
here.
I mean it's quite clear, I hope, what it's doing.
The call method signature and the WSGI application signature is exactly the same.
And what we do here is, once again, one of my favorite examples, it seems like, to handle
exceptions.
So what I do in the call method is I call the self.wisgiApp attribute which points to
the original WSGI application.
If there is no exception, the response is returned as returned by the WSGI application
itself.
If, however, there is an exception, I call the startResponse with a 500 status with some
headers.
And then I return a custom response which is an error occurred.
And that's really useful because you hide your internal exception details from your
client.
You should have a logit which I haven't shown here.
And how do you integrate the WSGI application with the middleware?
It looks like this.
You create an object of my exception processor type which is the middleware we defined.
And you pass in the WSGI application itself.
And that's your WSGI app.
And you can use a server like Junicon app to run it.
And there you go.
You have your WSGI application running with WSGI middleware.
I'm going to refer to this as the wrapping technique of defining middleware for WSGI
applications.
So let's pause again.
So frameworks implement their own mechanisms to define middleware as we have seen.
Now WSGI middleware is another WSGI application.
So that means if we implement a functionality using WSGI middleware, they are framework
independent.
Let's see how they work.
So this is the OpenTelemetry WSGI middleware.
It's an open source middleware that's available from the OpenTelemetry project.
It doesn't quite matter.
I shall not get into what OpenTelemetry itself is.
But this is an example I was familiar with of a WSGI middleware.
So this is the source code of the middleware.
And you can see the similarity with the middleware we defined here.
It's pretty much the same if you ignore the specific functionality.
So that's the OpenTelemetry WSGI middleware which is available as a third party package.
And how can you use that with Flask?
So when you define a Flask app, there is an attribute WSGI underscore app which points
to the WSGI application.
And what you can do here is we set the attribute to an object of the OpenTelemetry middleware
type which we create by passing the original WSGI app as an argument.
So this results in the OpenTelemetry middleware wrapping our original WSGI application.
And that basically gives you the functionality that the OpenTelemetry middleware provides
for your Flask application.
Now for Django, if you look at the file WSGI.py in your project, you will find this code where
top level variable called application.
And that gets set to the return value of the function getWSGI application.
And that points to your underlying WSGI application.
Remember when I said that this framework abstracts a lot of these things, but somewhere in there
there's a WSGI application.
So this is the WSGI application.
And the way we use the OpenTelemetry middleware, it looks similar to Flask.
We create an OpenTelemetry middleware object.
We pass the original WSGI application.
And then we update the value of the application, which is the model of a variable, to that
object.
And that's all you need to use WSGI middleware.
So this sounds like a win, right?
Like you can write a WSGI middleware and you can use it in a framework independent way.
Now I'm not sure if there are any pitfalls to doing that though.
I haven't explored it enough.
Maybe that's something for you to go and explore back home.
All right.
So let's see one last example of how we can use a middleware.
Consider that you have a Django application and you're moving some of your backends to
Flask.
What you can do is you can define a middleware which embeds the Flask application within
your Django application.
If it sounds like magic, that's how it seemed like to me when I actually implemented it.
So you define a class called, you know, you can call it anything really, but I have called
it FlaskAppWrapper.
The key again is the special call method.
So here I call the FlaskApps WSGI app method first.
You know, I pass the environment and start response exactly how I found it here.
And I pass it to the Flask app.
If I get a non-404 response, I return the data as it is.
And that indicates to me that that request was handled correctly.
If however I get a 404 response, I fall back to the Django application.
And that's one way you can use middleware to help you in migrations perhaps in your
project.
And this is how you use it.
It looks very similar to how you use the OpenTelemeter middleware.
So the result is when you make a request to the polls V2 path, the Flask application gets
called.
But when you make a request to the polls path, the Django application gets called.
So to recap, Flask and Django implement custom mechanisms to allow users to define middleware.
However, as you have seen, when we define a WSGI middleware, they become, they are framework
agnostic.
And we can use the wrapping technique to use this WSGI middleware.
Okay.
How much time do I have?
Seven or eight?
Eight.
So this is going to be like a turbo section I think.
But let's see.
So this is an ASGII HTTP application.
It's similar to what we saw for the WSGI application.
You define an async function.
It takes three parameters, a scope, a function receive, and a function send.
Scope essentially describes the current request.
Like you can think of it as the lifetime of the current request.
The receive function is used to get any request data.
And then you use the send function to send back any response.
So remember the signature.
That's all that's needed for this section.
And I'm going to skip over this because we'll cover it later.
Okay.
Now let's consider a fast API application.
This is how we define a very simple fast API application.
You create a top-level object of fast API type.
We define a route, expensive, and it's a super expensive route where we sleep for 10 seconds
and then return a response.
Now let's say I want to write a middleware as a caching.
I want to cache these expensive results.
I don't want to calculate a result every time.
So what I do, I define a middleware.
I define an init method.
It takes in two parameters.
The first parameter is the ASGII application itself.
And we have a second parameter, excluded parts.
Now this is any custom arguments that your middleware needs to take.
And we can specify as many as you want here.
I just have one.
The key here again is the special call method.
It should be an async function.
It takes in three parameters, scope, receive, send, exactly like our ASGII function here.
And in this function, we define the logic for the middleware.
If there's a cache hit, we return the cache response.
If however we did not get a cache hit, we call the original app using the original arguments,
scope, receive.
Cache and send is a wrapper that I created, which caches the response and then sends back
the response.
You can find these examples in the resources I have shared in my website.
And so, again, you have defined the middleware.
How do you add it?
In Fast API, it provides a helper method, addMiddleware.
And you first define the class of the middleware that you want to add.
And then you specify any additional parameters.
In this case, I have got a parameter called excluded parts, which is a list of parts I
don't want to cache.
So chat actually is a WebSocket backend, which I've implemented.
And that brings me nicely to my next slide.
So this middleware actually works very well, you know, as for HTTP applications as well
as WebSocket applications.
And the key to that is because the scope lasts as long as WebSocket connection remains open.
So when you call this awaitServe.app, that function doesn't return as long as WebSocket
connection remains open.
So I've got some logs down below where you can see that the request lasted for 30 seconds,
which is how long the WebSocket connection was open for.
I will skip over this.
You can look at the slides.
Okay.
Now if you notice, if you compare what the default behavior of the WSGI framework and
the ASGII framework is, I quite like the default behavior of fast API because it allows you
to define ASGII middleware directly.
In fact, that is the first thing they recommend in the documentation.
They talk about a more specific approach later on in the documentation, but I quite like
the fact that they ask you to just write a generic ASGII middleware, which means if there
are other ASGII frameworks, you could use the middleware with those as well.
I quite like that about fast API.
So okay, the last middleware example we're going to see is how can you embed a WSGI application
instead of an ASGII application?
This is as magical as it gets.
So what you can do is you define a fast API app, and then fast API provides a special
middleware called WSGI middleware.
You call the mount method, and any parts starting with V1 will be passed on to the WSGI middleware
and hence to a WSGI application.
And the result is, I've got a brief example.
So when you call anything with V1, you get hello world from Flask because that's been
processed by Flask.
On the other hand, when you call anything with V2, you get a response from the fast
API application.
The WSGI middleware implementation, if you look in the Starlit source code, looks like
this.
Very, I'm sure you're beginning to see the sort of pattern now.
So you look at the call method, takes in three parameters, and then there's the special WSGI
responder class, which if you go into, it defines a WSGI method which takes in two parameters,
which is an environment and start response.
So your WSGI application essentially.
I will skip that.
So key takeaways.
Middleware can be defined generally as an WSGI or ASGI application or be framework specific.
Middleware is code that's acting as both a client and a server.
A client for your other middleware or for your views and the server for other middleware
or for your original client.
And middleware enables decoupling and sharing of non-functional requirements.
And it also helps us in migration between application frameworks as well as WSGI and
ASGI.
So I have an exercise for you.
Go back, not today, maybe after you have recovered.
Look at the source code for the built-in middleware and the community-contributed middleware.
You will easily be able to see the pattern and hopefully the talk has given you enough
to really go dig deep into those and understand how they work.
So thank you.
Thanks for choosing my talk over some of the other excellent options.
And I hope you have gained insights into the internals of the middleware as they apply
to WSGI and ASGI applications.
And go away with a few new neural pathways formed in your brain.
I have written a few books.
Those two are my books I'm most proud of, I guess.
Go, yes, I know it's a Python conference, but I'm a Python as well as a Go guy.
So please check out that book if you're taking your first steps into Go and looking for something
practical.
And doing math with Python, I wrote that a few years ago, but I think it's still relevant.
So please check it out.
Feel free to contact me with anything related to this talk or anything else really.
Yeah, that's all I have.
Thank you.
Applause.