And thank you very much for coming to the last set of sessions, our last session for
the day.
Our presenter today will be Juan Gonzalez, I think, right?
And the title of his talk is Improving App Performance with Snapshots.
Hey everyone, thank you so much for being here.
My name is Juan and I'm here to talk to you about improving your app performance with
snapshots.
I am a staff engineer at Cedar and Cedar is a digital health startup.
Our mission is to make the patient billing experience a lot better, a lot smoother and
a lot more transparent.
And a big part of that is making sure that we have a very reliable app.
If you want to have a reliable app, a big part of that is having an app that performs
pretty well.
So this is a very important topic for us.
Now I'll be honest with you, every application is unique and because every application is
unique I cannot give to you today one perfect bullet, golden bullet to solve all of your
performance issues.
Every application's performance issues are going to have a different unique solution
to it.
So at best what I can try to do to you is give you some advice from my own anecdotal
And from what I've experienced for a lot of applications that have been started up in
a very fast way and are starting to experience scale for the first time, they'll often realize
that their database is actually their bottleneck.
And if they're not seeing that, then it's a good chance that in a few days or a few
weeks or a few months that they will actually realize that their database is actually now
their bottleneck.
And the reason for that is pretty simple.
A lot of applications start off with a single server database model, meaning your database
becomes a single point of failure.
And it's just so easy to set up a database that way and it's just also a really good
idea to start your database that way and not overcomplicate it.
But another reason why is because databases themselves, they have tons of IO that they
have to go through and IO is just a notoriously slow set of operations to deal with.
So it's not uncommon to realize for the first time, hey, my application is slow and you
realize, oh wait, it's actually my database.
So today, I want to kind of get us to focus on improving your database's performance.
And that's what I kind of want to focus this talk about.
And there's really kind of two different categories for improving your database's performance.
One of them is database scaling.
And there's kind of two different ways you can do that.
One way is vertically scaling your database.
And that's the approach of taking your single database and basically beefing it up.
That could be improving its CPU, increasing its RAM, increasing your database's disk speed.
That all falls into the category of vertical scaling.
Another way you can do it is horizontal scaling.
Horizontal scaling is the approach of taking your database and basically splitting it up.
You can do that in a few ways.
You can add other databases to handle all the reads in your database or you can split
your database up in ways such that different reads go to different databases, aka database
sharding.
But they all fall under the same category of horizontal scaling.
And that's basically infrastructure scaling.
But there's another way to do this and it's actually query tuning.
So for some of you, you may not know what I mean when I say query tuning.
And what I'm basically talking about here is the process of taking your SQL and basically
cleaning it up.
So what that means is you're taking your queries and you're finding ways to rewrite them so
that they are doing the same jobs but doing them in a much more efficient way so that
you don't have to actually improve your infrastructure of your database and you can actually just
improve your application code itself.
And query tuning is great, but unfortunately it's actually really hard to do.
Surprisingly horizontal scaling and vertical scaling, two complicated tasks themselves
have many step-by-step instruction guides for how to accomplish them.
And actually nowadays there's tons of tools built into cloud infrastructure or your databases
themselves to help you out with this process of vertically scaling or horizontally scaling.
But query tuning on the other hand is not easy.
There's no step-by-step guide for query tuning because every application, like I said, is
unique.
So the issues with an application's queries are going to be different for every application.
And it's going to require tons of research to figure out what is the issue.
So it's not an easy task.
But with that said, it's actually quite worth it.
Horizontal scaling and vertical scaling, that requires you to actually spend more money
to accomplish the same task of improving your database performance.
Whereas query tuning is actually a process that actually reduces infrastructure costs
because you're actually putting less load on your database.
And hopefully also reducing complexity because it could end up with queries themselves that
are easier to understand but also less of them in general.
So query tuning is hard.
We understand that.
But there's another complication to this all.
We are at a PyCon conference.
So it's easy to guess that applications we're talking about here are Python applications.
And because they're Python applications, if they are dealing with a database, they're
probably using an ORM.
And in case you don't know what an ORM is or what it does, an ORM is basically a tool
to help you deal with your database's operations in a way that is object-oriented.
And that allows you to do things such as define all your tables as classes, batch all the
rows of table data as objects in memory, and also just offer some tactic sugar for joining
together data that are related to each other.
And ORMs are great.
They're very popular for a reason.
We use them at Cedar.
But they also make query tuning harder.
And it's kind of hard to explain them without giving you an example of why.
Sorry.
Catching my breath here.
So yeah, ORMs make query tuning harder.
And I'm going to try to explain this to you by example.
So imagine that you are working for a company.
And this company has made the perfect restaurant app.
It's an app that's made for restaurants to download and for eaters that enjoy their times
at these restaurants to download as well.
And it's supposed to make a perfect little synergized experience for restaurants and
consumers alike.
And you are a newly hired site reliability engineer for this company.
And the company has experienced tons of growth.
And unfortunately with that growth, they're experiencing tons of database performance
problems.
So you come in and you are now becoming the savior to try to fix all these problems.
And you learn that this application is written in Django, which is a very popular ORM.
But unfortunately, you are not very familiar with Django.
You do not know yet that Django has some issues that are going to make query tuning harder
for you.
So you naively agree to tune these queries in this ORM's code.
And you run into three problems along the way.
One of the problems that you run into are ORM code can look very different from SQL
that is executed by that ORM.
ORMs are basically just translators of Python code to SQL.
And what you see is not always what you get or to someone who's not experienced, at least
that's what can be the experience.
And I'll kind of show you an example of this.
So here on the right, this is some Django code that allows me to see every dish that
is ordered by this customer named Juan.
It looks like very clean Python code maybe.
If you're familiar with Django, you might know exactly what's going to happen.
But if you're not familiar with Django, you might be very surprised to see that that Python
code that you just saw produced this query here, which was operating on three different
tables.
And you actually saw four different tables because the Python code itself almost suggested
it was acting on just this dish table.
So that's the first problem you run into and you find that to be very annoying.
But you start to learn the ins and outs of Django and how it produces SQL.
But you run into the second problem as well.
Even after you understand Django, you're working in a Python application.
So you start to realize there's another problem here.
You know, Python code is written in such a way that functions call other functions and
those functions call other functions.
And they call them for different reasons.
And you're having a hard time understanding exactly when and where these ORMs are actually
triggering query execution and why.
And what you would really love to see is like a stack trace explaining what exact line of
code is actually triggering these query executions.
So as an example, if you're not familiar with Django, you might look at this code and wonder
how many queries are being executed here.
So on the first line, you might notice, hey, there's orders.
Maybe we're dealing with all the orders in this table.
Are we executing a query there to grab every object from the orders table?
On the second line, you're doing an annotation.
Is that where we're running a query?
Is that where we finally run our first query?
Or is it on the next few lines?
Or is it at the end?
And if you're familiar with Django, you'll probably know right away it's actually at
the very end here.
This is the first and only place where a query is actually executed.
But then again, you may not be – you may be surprised to see that this is the actual
query that gets executed.
It's something very complicated.
But that's really the second problem you start to notice.
You're not sure where and why things are happening because you're not an expert on this yet.
And then the final problem really kind of – you know, really kind of grinds your gears here.
And that's that there is this n plus 1 queries problem, which technically is not unique to
ORMs, but can happen in ORMs much easier than an application that was written in pure SQL.
And that's because an ORM makes it easy to fetch related objects from another one.
And unfortunately, this can make it extremely easy to accidentally query one table many
times when you could have actually queried it exactly once to fetch all these different
objects.
And as an example here, we have some bad code that is trying to get all the orders that
include a dish named Kobe beef.
And at the end of that, once we have all these orders, we want to get the customer name for
each of those orders.
Now if you're familiar with Django, you might realize this is bad code because what's
going to happen is you're going to do an additional query for every single order to
grab the customer name on that order.
And to see that in pure SQL, here's what happens.
You do one query to get all the Kobe beef orders.
And then for each of those orders, you're going to query the customer table to get the
name for the first customer on that order.
And then you're going to get the customer for the second order.
And then you're going to get the customer for the third order.
So you just did a bunch of unnecessary queries on the same customer table that you could
have gotten in actually one execution.
And that's a pretty bad problem.
So the better code is to select all the customers at once when you're grabbing all the orders
as well.
And that's what using this nice and tactical function on your original query set to select
all the related customers when you grab all the orders.
And that's going to produce a much more performant query execution where you do actually just
one query.
The problem with that is that you have to basically be an expert in Django to know that's
the case.
And even still, it may not be obvious after the fact that you wrote code that actually
did this the right way.
So you see this, and you think that you might have taken on this task prematurely, and you
kind of just come to the conclusion that query tuning is probably too hard with an ORM.
You may even think, hey, maybe the team should just stop using ORMs altogether.
And you may think that the act of query tuning is not a worthwhile endeavor.
It's basically impossible.
You should always just scale your infrastructure and call it a day.
But that's unfortunate because in reality, query tuning can actually be pretty easy.
The problem is that there aren't enough tools to really help this problem.
And that story I just gave to you, it kind of hits very close to a home procedure because
in 2019, we were experiencing tons of growth, and our database was the bottleneck for us.
And we did do infrastructure scaling.
We introduced read replicas.
We scaled our database horizontally.
We beefed up our database, made it stronger vertically.
But we still wanted to find a problem to this query tuning problem.
So one of our models is no mediocrity.
So we didn't want to just settle with the idea of having a non-performant ORM code.
We wanted to kind of find an answer for this problem.
And so we kind of introduced this concept of query snapshots.
And what we wanted from it was kind of simple.
What we wanted was a way to see every query that we were executing in our ORM code.
And we also wanted to understand exactly where those queries were executing.
And we also wanted to actually isolate the Python code that was triggering those queries
very quickly.
And we wanted to get this info at basically every stage of local development.
And it's important to make that to kind of pause in this one statement here.
There are tons of tools available today where you can actually do query inspection.
A popular one is Django debug toolbar, which lets you do this deep dive of queries that
are being executed on a browser page.
But you have to do everything from a browser.
So that's kind of what I mean by we wanted to be able to use this at any stage in local
development from a terminal and the browser and middleware and tests basically everywhere.
And because we have a model of no mediocrity, we also wanted this to have a very simple
and intuitive interface as well.
And what we ended up doing was we created this tool called snapshot queries, which is
now today an open source ORM query capture.
And I'm going to kind of show you what it looks like.
So it is out of the box a context manager.
What it does is it lets you look at, it lets you capture every query that any block of
Python code that is using Django or SQL Alchemy is executing.
So on the right here, all you have to do to use it is run this little snapshot queries
context manager.
And what gets returned back to you is a list of all the queries that were executed.
So on the right here, what I would expect is after this block of code exits, I would
see all the queries that were executed to grab this customer named Juan, to see the
query that was executed to create this order for Juan, and to see all the queries that
were executed to add all these different dishes to his order.
And that's right out of the box.
That's what you get from this tool.
And that's great as is.
But after we introduced this tool, we also started to enhance it, added more features
to it, and I kind of want to talk to you about the top five features that were added to this,
because I can't go over all of them in probably in time.
So I just want to highlight the top five.
So feature number five is kind of what I described to you.
You get to see every query that's executed.
But not just the query itself.
You get to see the query SQL, which is probably pretty obvious to you all.
But you get to also see very quickly all the Python code that was executed to trigger that query.
Sorry, when I say Python code, I mean the line of Python code that was executed to trigger that query.
And then you also get to see exactly how long it took to execute that query, which from
my own personal experience when I was in 2019 helping us figure out ways to reduce our site's
impact on our database, just these three features alone were extremely useful for me, as I was
doing local enhancements to our code to make it a lot faster.
But it's still number five.
So that means that there's four better features than just this alone.
Number four is right out of the bat, when you use this tool, when you have this list
of queries that are executed, there is a method on this object that lets you display a beautiful
summary of every query that was executed for you.
And it gets printed to the terminal with nice formatting and also nice coloring to kind
of just give you a quick snapshot of all the information that is probably going to be relevant
to you.
An example of this is on the right here, we have an output from this query executed.display
call.
The first thing you're going to see is the amount of time it took to run this first query.
You're going to see the actual line of Python code that triggered it.
You're going to see the actual code itself that triggered it.
And you're going to see the SQL statement printed in a nice formatted way for you.
And that's just out of the box.
It's a pretty great feature.
I use it a ton at work when I'm just trying to debug something or trying to figure out
what's going on with code.
So number four.
So there's three better features than just this.
Number three.
Like I said before, the stack trace is really important if you want to know exactly where
code is called because knowing where a function that is used throughout your code base is
is not enough if you need to also understand how you got to that path because code is complicated.
Code calls other code and that code calls other code, et cetera, et cetera.
So this to me is one of the top features because in the beginning when I just saw the lines
of code that were being executed to run queries since our code is pretty dry, just seeing
the code itself wasn't enough, I had to get a full detail of the entire stack trace for
these queries that were being executed to get a fuller picture of what was going on.
So I consider this to be the third best feature because it just does so much for us when we're
trying to optimize our queries themselves.
So not the top feature.
So a better feature than that is this one here.
This is an answer to the N plus one selects problem that I think is pretty neat.
What it does for you is that query executed object that I showed before, it has a method
called similar and what it will do for you is group together all the queries that look
similar to each other and display them out to you if you want to or you can just loop
over them.
What we mean by similar are any queries that have the same SQL besides the parameters themselves.
So in this example here from this output that you would see from the top, you can see that
there are two similar queries that have been detected.
The first query is similar to the second query because the queries themselves only differ
on the customer ID.
So for us in this simple example you just see two queries but for us when we ran this
production, sorry when we ran this on our code locally we started to see tons of info
about queries that were similar that gave us a lot of insight on potential areas of
our code base because again you can see the lines of code themselves to try to figure
out hey this might be a place where we're doing the N plus one selects problem.
Let's figure out a way to fix it.
And this is the top feature.
It may seem there's not a lot of details here.
I wish I could fit more details on this slide because there's actually quite a lot to unpack
here but this feature is something that we use all the time at work.
In 2019 when we were improving our app's performance, when we were improving the load times of our
home pages or like the pages that customers go to to see all their bills, things of that
nature we did tons of work using this library to help figure out what was going on but we
were very afraid that this work would eventually undo itself because we can't always be there
to improve your app.
Eventually you have to stop and you have to get back to do other things.
So we came up with this solution here.
So how many of you are familiar with HTML snapshot testing?
Okay so not a lot of you are.
So let me kind of give a brief explanation of what that is because I'll give a lot of
insight on what this will do.
So for a lot of apps that render HTML it's hard to verify the HTML that's getting output.
So a common strategy is to have your tests render the HTML with some specific inputs,
save a snapshot of that HTML to some local file and then on each subsequent test run
the HTML be re-rendered and then compared with that snapshot.
If the snapshot changes you can see a very quick diff to understand what has changed
or nothing has changed and if there is a difference it will fail explaining why and that's called
HTML snapshot testing.
It's a very common strategy for front end development and I thankfully have some experience
with front end development and when we were doing this, we were dealing with this issue
of performance enhancement.
We got this idea to capture every query in our code that was particularly hot, that had
a lot of performance problems, capture those queries to a file, save the output including
where those queries were executed into that file so that when something changed on that
particular hot piece of code we would get a test that failed explaining exactly why
with a diff so that the code owners of that test would be able to inspect the difference
and understand why it changed and give the okay or the thumbs down if there was actually
a new performance problem being introduced.
That's what we call query snapshot testing and I call it our top feature because it's
the feature that we use the most.
It's the thing that we kind of take for granted that runs every day on our code base.
We run it in all of our tests and it has made the burden of maintaining quality a lot easier
so we can sleep at night better because of it and that is the query snapshot testing
tool that we have at Cedar.
It helped us grip through 2019 really well.
I'm happy to say today we are performing a lot better.
The problem with query tuning seems like a much less daunting task for us and we're still
obviously dealing with performance issues as we get bigger and bigger but this is I
think a very big win for us and it is available for you to try out.
We have a, that URL, that QR code there should actually reach through our GitHub page for
it.
It is very recently open source so if you guys want to take a snapshot of that and just
take a look at it, if you want to improve it, test it out yourself, give us ideas of
how we can make it better or give us ideas of what tools have done this better if you
can find any.
We would love that and if you have any questions about Cedar as well and you are interested
in maybe joining us, you can take a look at cedar.com and if you scan the QR code because
you're interested in joining us, you can see our careers page and see what is available
for us, for you to join us and that is my talk.
Thank you all for being here.