Welcome, everyone.
You're in room 355ABC.
And we have Nandita Viswanath and Sagar Ariel.
And they're going to talk about in-house to open source, stitching the past to the future
with Python.
Hi, everyone.
I'm Nandita.
I'm a software engineer at Bloomberg.
And I'm Sagar.
I'm also a software engineer at Bloomberg.
And I'm also a software engineer at Bloomberg.
And we're going to be presenting our talk, in-house to open source, stitching the past
to the future with Python.
So today we're going to be discussing how you can leverage open source software when
thinking about migrating away from legacy code.
Our talk is loosely broken up into four sections.
We're going to start with an introduction.
We'll then move on to identifying our right open source candidate.
We'll touch up on how you can integrate your open source candidate into your existing
tech stack.
And then we'll wrap up with some conclusions.
So before we jump into why you should think about open source for migrations from legacy
code, let's first understand what legacy code even is.
Legacy code is typically code that's no longer engineered but is just patched for fixes.
So it becomes nearly impossible to add new features, which makes them great candidates
for migrations.
So when you're thinking about migrating software, I think open source should be one of the first
things that come to mind.
And the first reason why is because you already have access to high quality pre-built software.
Chances are there's already software within the open source community that can address
your needs, even if not entirely, to an extent large enough that it would take minimal effort
for you to go in and tailor it to your specific needs.
Which brings me to the second big advantage, customization.
Now, since the code is open source, you know what's going on.
You can maybe just add a plugin to tailor it to your requirement or go in and modify
the code base yourself.
Another advantage is that in some way you have access to latest innovation.
As more and more people start adopting that open source software, more people become invested
in its growth and development.
So in a way, you're always on top of the cutting edge technology.
And it's not just me saying this, we're all at PyCon.
And some of you guys have also found that IT leaders think the usage of open source
is going to boom over the next couple years.
But even while open source is great, there are some things to still keep in mind.
The first is that support and maintenance may not always be available.
But there are some companies and enterprises that offer maintenance at an additional fee.
So that's something to keep in mind.
The other thing to keep in mind, especially when you're building critical applications,
is the maturity and the stability of the software.
If there is an issue, you might end up relying on someone to fix it, or you might have to
step up and fix it yourself.
So that's an added consideration.
And the last is that usage of open source does not eliminate hardware costs.
You have to budget for hardware if you want to adopt open source at scale.
At this point, I want to introduce a case study that we're going to be walking through
as the talk progresses.
We're going to be trying to migrate an orchestration framework.
So let's think of a really complex framework that has to use some metadata to decide to
schedule some processes, and then has to account for process dependencies, monitor events,
and then finally write some data to a database.
Let's build a little more clarity around that.
So say we have some metadata based on which we decide we need to schedule a process.
Our process is that little red circle you see there.
Figuring that one red circle can actually set off a bunch of other processes, our purple
circles, which can in turn set off another set of processes, our orange circles.
So our red circle is not really done until all of the purple and the orange processes
complete.
And like I said earlier, what these processes are doing is just writing data.
And we're looking at data in the range of about 50 million data points.
But this is when the complexity really kicks in.
We don't want to just schedule and orchestrate one of these red circles.
We want to do hundreds of such processes and in turn write billions of data points with
no room for error.
Now next I'd like to talk to you about how it is that you can actually go about identifying
the software that you want to migrate towards.
We're going to go through this in a three-phase approach.
The first being understanding your requirements, identifying what it is that you're actually
looking to replace, and then researching for a solution that would address these requirements.
And finally, you want to narrow down the potential solutions that you've come up with to one
final system.
So in terms of understanding your requirements, in our use case, we had to first get rid of
all the business logic as well as the specific intricacies that were unique to our problem
and try to boil it down to the highest level.
We came up with one sentence that we believe perfectly describes our use case, and that
is the automated coordination of events and data streams leveraging domain-specific metadata
to intelligently schedule and trigger processes.
It's a bit of a mouthful, but from this we can derive these three keywords that describe
the system, and that is scheduler, orchestration, and dependencies.
Now we came up with a list of must-haves as well as nice-to-haves.
In terms of the must-haves, obviously modeling dependencies, that's the first and primary
goal.
We want processes to be able to trigger other processes.
We also want to be able to do this for historical runs, and obviously we want permissioning
since this is going into production.
We want to make sure there's no vulnerabilities.
Performance is also another consideration.
Like I mentioned, on a production cluster, we don't want it to take up all the resources.
In terms of nice-to-haves, we did say that a user interface as well as the ability to
monitor all these processes would be nice to have, not necessary though.
And parallelization, these processes are being run on off-peak hours, so it wasn't a necessity.
Now, when it came time to research, obviously the first thing everyone does is go to the
internet.
You take your keywords and you post them into search engines, and you try to come up with
potential options.
Going about this, we eventually landed on Apache's website, where most open-source systems are.
We found two systems which closely match what we're looking for, namely Apache NiFi as well
as Apache Airflow.
Another way that we were going about doing research was word of mouth.
Obviously conferences like PyCon can give you potential solutions that might fit your
use case, as well as networking, from which internally at Bloomberg we support Argo.
That's another solution that we came across.
We have these three potential options.
We want to first figure out the evaluation criteria.
How can we narrow it down to a specific system?
We broadly categorize it into these four different metrics, first being adoption.
Systems that have more GitHub activity are bound to have more support.
Your questions will be answered quicker.
Any bugs that come up will be fixed sooner.
That's a very important one.
Then compatibility.
Does this system meet your technical requirements?
Does it address the problem that you're trying to solve?
And then of course extendability.
Once you do integrate an open-source system, it'd be nice for it to eventually evolve into
something more.
Can it address other problems that you haven't particularly foreseen until you start using it?
And then finally ease of customization.
No system is a perfect match, but if something is flexible and is easy to customize for your
specific use case, then that's obviously better.
This is what we ended up categorizing these three systems into.
Airflow was a very popular Apache project.
It's very actively maintained, very extensible, lots of plugins and lots of support for them.
It's very flexible with permission control and very easy to adapt.
It's actually pure Python.
Apache NiFi, also a great solution, but it didn't match our use case specifically because
it's very data pipeline focused.
Now we do already have the ETL infrastructure.
That's not the part we're trying to replace.
So it didn't exactly match what we were looking for.
Argo, again, it was supported internally at Bloomberg, so that communication link is even
more direct.
That's why it had such a high rating on adoption.
It's focused on containerized applications, whereas we're looking for more of a bare metal
Linux solution.
Again, this is very subjective evaluation criteria for our specific use case, not necessarily
going to be true everywhere.
Now Apache Airflow, like I mentioned, it's based around the directed acyclic graph, DAG
for short.
It's pure Python, like I mentioned.
It didn't support every particular use case that we had, but it had a lot of support for
plugins, and we did find plugins that were very useful.
And of course, a very nice and easy to navigate web UI.
Now with that, I'd like to hand it off to my colleague, Nandita.
Okay, great.
So now Sagar has helped us pick Airflow, and we know Airflow is what we want to migrate
to.
But where do we even start?
We have this huge complex framework that's been working just fine.
The only issue is that we're not able to iterate and add new features to it.
And it's doing a lot of things.
It's monitoring for dependencies.
It's writing billions of data points.
There's so much scope for error.
So before we even move further, let's break this down into independent but connected components.
What are we really dealing with here?
We have a scheduler that uses some metadata to decide which process to kick off.
We have an orchestration engine, possibly, that kicks off that first process and monitors
it for completion.
And we have, let's say, a job management system that monitors the dependent processes
that were kicked off.
These are the three independent chunks of this huge framework that we're trying to migrate
from.
If we want to move away from all of these three in one big bang, there's just a lot
more risk and the scope for failure balloons.
Instead, we could just start by replacing the easily replaceable components.
To me, that looks like the scheduler and the orchestration engine.
So we can just try removing the scheduler and the orchestration engine out of that framework
and replacing that with Airflow.
But how?
The scheduler, orchestration engine, job management system all work perfectly together because
they were all natively integrated.
And they were probably built around the same time.
They were built to be compatible with each other.
But then when we integrate with an open source solution like Airflow, it's not been built
for our specific use case, but it still works really great.
So we need a way to really make Airflow and our job management system kind of speak the
same language.
And I think we all know where I'm getting at with this.
We're at PyCon.
So this is where we want to introduce PyHero, our Python component that's going to help
stitch together Airflow and our legacy job management system.
And we have a lot of superheroes out there.
So why should we think of PyHero?
There are essentially three superpowers that we're really looking for.
We want to be able to integrate easily with our existing code base.
So it should be easy for us to integrate with something that's not necessarily Python
based.
The second superpower that we want is we need to be able to write this component really
quickly.
Eventually, in the future, our job management system is going to go away too.
And Airflow is going to take over everything.
So at that point of time, PyHero will unfortunately have to step down.
So we don't want to invest too much time building out PyHero.
He's eventually just going to go away.
And the third thing that we're looking for is production quality PyHero.
Even though PyHero is temporary, it still has to be production quality.
Because we want it to run in production, we cannot cut corners in terms of its performance.
So let's now jump into discussing how Python possesses all of these three superpowers, starting
with how we can use it to integrate with an existing stack.
So let's assume the worst case scenario.
Our job management system is not Python at all.
It's built in a completely new language.
Now we need Python to kind of interface with it.
What are the different ways that we can go about this?
The first is, like I said, an interfaced approach, where we want to directly use our non-Python
components within our Python module.
In this case, we have, honestly, multiple options.
If you had a C or C++ library that you wanted to use, you can compile it into a .so or
.dll file and then import that within your Python code.
An alternative would be to use the Python API to expose our C, C++ libraries by our
Python interface.
But both of this will require you to kind of go in and modify your libraries themselves.
There is another easier, non-intrusive approach that you can take, wherein your non-Python
components are treated as independent entities in themselves.
You modularize them and package them as executables, and you just invoke them as subprocesses from
within your Python script.
So this is where you really have to kind of balance your requirements, and you have to
make a trade-off.
If you have things within, let's say, our job management system that we want to reuse
even after our migration is complete.
So let's say we had a C++ library that was super powerful that we intend on using even
after we fully move to airflow, it might make sense to just go with the first approach,
even if it's going to require more development time.
But in our case, we were really looking at completely replacing our job management system,
in which case it was just easier for us to modularize it and package it as an executable
and invoke it as a subprocess.
So now that we've discussed how we can integrate Python with an existing stack, let's move
on to discussing how Python can help us write production quality code quickly.
So we've talked about how we want this PyHero component to be running in production.
And one of the most important things that that comes with is awareness when something
goes wrong.
When something goes wrong, you don't want to find out, let's say, hours later or days
later.
You want to know as soon as PyHero went down in production.
And to do this, we actually found ourselves using a feature of Python that most of us
are already aware of.
I learned about it in theory, too.
But this is how we could really see it being used while writing production quality code.
So we have a decorator that we use within our group that takes in three arguments.
It takes in a severity, a group, and the name of the component.
And based on these three arguments, it creates a ticket with the appropriate severity level
and routes it to the correct group.
So all it does is really just wrap the function code in a try-catch block and create a ticket
based on the input parameters and route it when something goes wrong and execution fails.
But this was great when I was trying to come up with this component quickly because I could
just focus on writing the core functionality of my module without worrying about the bells
and whistles around alarming because it really just came for free.
But it's not just sufficient for us to be able to write our code quickly.
It's also important that we're able to debug this code quickly, especially when we're interfacing
with a legacy component.
With that, I'd like to walk you through an example of a bug that we faced when trying
to implement Airflow and how the PDB as a superpower of PyHero really came in to help
and save us.
So here we have a screen, the login screen for Airflow.
And as you can see, there's an error message at the top.
So the way that we generated this was we tried to sign in using SSO, which redirects us to
the SSO page.
And we log in and it redirects us back here.
Now we knew the credentials were correct, so that wasn't the issue at hand.
But we didn't really have much other information on this page about what's causing this.
Now the first place anyone really starts to debug is by checking the logs.
And when we did check the logs, this is the only message that really came in with any
relevance.
It was this error message right here.
Now we see that there's some issue with OAuth.
We see something about an invalid audience, but it's still fairly abstract.
It doesn't give us much information.
However, we do know exactly what line and what file this error is being raised.
So with PDB, let's step into that file and try to figure out what's going on.
So we went to that file and these are the lines that the error was being thrown from,
as you can see the log message right there on that fourth line there.
And we put a breakpoint.
Now with this breakpoint, we are able to halt execution of the program while trying to log
in on the web server itself.
And we pause execution and from there we're able to observe the variables, including these
abstract variables like app builder or .sm.
Now what we realized by observing these variables live is that these were actually instances
of classes that we had defined in the web server config.py.
So let's dig into this rabbit hole a bit further and see where it leads us.
After that, we put another breakpoint in web server config.py and while the rest of the
code isn't too important, we step through line by line to get to this line.
This is where the error was really being raised.
And so that invalid audience makes a bit more sense as you can see the issue is in that
key error flow right there.
Now the great thing about PDB is that while the execution has been paused, you can retry
code lines of code with that environment.
And so you could retry other keys until you find the correct one.
Needless to say, that is what we did and it helped us solve this issue.
An issue that was rather abstract to begin with could be solved in a matter of a couple
of minutes using PDB.
So this really goes to highlight some of the advantages of PDB and first and foremost is
that you don't have to rebuild your software every time you put in a new breakpoint.
You simply have to restart.
And so that's one of the great powers of Python is that it's much quicker to put in a breakpoint
and to then start debugging.
There's also command line interface which allows for remote debugging.
The issue that we showed earlier was debugged on a server.
And then it also comes default with the Python language so you don't have to install it separately
or anything like that.
There's two ways that you can invoke it.
The first one we already showed you in our example is just by adding it into the script
directly and the second one is calling it via the command line which is very similar
to other debuggers you might have encountered in the past.
Another aspect of Python that really enables rapid development is how easy it is to customize
it.
And so I'm going to walk you through one specific use case that we had with Airflow to really
highlight this point.
And so by default Airflow uses SMTP for email.
And as you can see in the email.py file it's using some SMTP lib which under the hood uses
SMTP.
Now SMTP wasn't ideal for our use case.
It's not important why but there is an alternative and that's what we're going to try to implement
as a plugin in Airflow.
So what we did was we copied this email.py file and we modified it to use the mailx command
which is something we already had code for written somewhere else in our tech stack.
And all it required on Airflow side was a simple configuration modification as you can
see here.
So we're going to use the same configuration as we did with Airflow.
We're going to use the same configuration as we did with Airflow.
And this is actually a file path to the actual plugin that we've defined.
And with Python since you can use dynamic importing of libraries Airflow doesn't need
anything else than this configuration change as well as this file being copied into the
correct directory from which it's able to pick it up and on restart seamlessly integrate
and use it for emails going forward.
Now that's the function definition that you see there.
This was simply copied from the other email.py file.
But that was essentially it.
And that really goes to highlight how easy it is to integrate your own code into Python
code bases.
And that's why another major advantage of a pure Python system like Airflow for open
source migrations.
Great.
So now we've spoke to you about some of the things about Python that make it really easy
for rapid development.
But let's go on to how Python makes it easy to create production quality software.
In the case of any open source system you don't really know the extent to which it's
valuable to you until you actually start using it.
So the best way to actually learn about an open source system is to use it.
And to do that you have to be able to deploy it into your production system quick.
In our case we were able to deploy Airflow into our production system in an isolated
manner using virtual environments.
And therefore we didn't have to modify any configurations or touch any other part of
our production cluster.
All you really need is one isolated file path where all your dependencies even the language
itself are going to be stored.
And tomorrow if you don't want to use the system anymore you simply delete that directory
and it's gone without leaving a trace.
Now in the case of Airflow it's fairly simple since the only overhead was really creating
this requirements file which as you can see doesn't have too much extra.
After that you create an isolated build and it runs on your production cluster.
And that's it.
Another thing that I'd like to highlight is PyTest is what we use for creating unit tests.
And so in production environment you want to make sure that code changes don't break
it.
And so before any release we're able to use PyTest to determine that previously working
behavior hasn't been affected.
Great.
So now we have a half new system and an half old system and we have Python stitching them
together.
But we still want to make sure that this half new system hasn't broken anything.
So we want to go about we want to figure out how we can reconcile it.
With that I'd like to hand it back to my colleague.
Okay great.
So now we have like Sagar said a half old and half new system up and running.
It's churning out some data.
But how do we make sure that our old system and our new system are really doing the same
thing.
One level of a sanity check could be to just check what processes are kicked off by the
old system and the new system and then compare it and see if they tie out.
But this does leave room for error because if we don't capture a failure correctly or
stall process correctly in the new system we won't ever catch it.
And that's when you really have to ask the question what is really the output of your
system.
And like we discussed earlier the output of our system was data and it was columnar data
to be more specific.
So the best way for us to ensure that our migration has gone through correctly and that
our old system and new system are doing the same thing is to compare the data that was
generated from the old system and the new system and make sure that they tie out.
But we're again looking at the scale of millions of data points here and it can be very intensive
to make sure that every one of these million data points tie out correctly.
But to help with that we have a data reconciliation framework that we use within our team which
is built on top of pandas.
And if you want to learn more about that definitely stop by our booth we'd be happy to chat.
So we used that tool to compare the data that was being produced by our old system
and our new system to ensure that there were no differences in terms of the output that
was being generated.
So quickly wrapping up on everything that we discussed so far let's do a quick recap.
So we started with this complex orchestration framework that we wanted to migrate from.
We identified keywords and then identified our three options that we could potentially
integrate with three open source options.
We brainstormed came up with an evaluation criteria based on which airflow one.
And then we broke down our existing architecture into independent but connected components
to start integrating with airflow.
And instead of integrating everything big bang we first replaced the easily replaceable
components which in our case were the scheduler and the orchestration engine.
But we still needed a way to connect airflow to our job management system and that's where
by hero stepped in.
And while integrating with existing code with our existing code base we had two options.
We could either interface directly with the code components and use them within our Python
module or we could just invoke them as sub processes.
And we went with the second approach and then added some test cases like Sagar said using
pi test packaged it with a virtual environment and then came up with this half old half new
system that was churning out some data.
But at this point it was important for us to ensure that the data that we were churning
out was in fact correct.
And we used a data reconciliation framework built on top of pandas to ensure that correctness.
OK so in conclusion open source is a great option for software migrations.
But remember integration doesn't have to be a big bang.
Small steps are usually better.
Now once you have integrated your system don't forget you want to customize enhance and extend
it.
And once once all of that is said and done don't forget to contribute and give back to
the community.
On that note Bloomberg has recently open source I think as early as two days ago a new memory
profiler for Python on Linux.
And this can also help you debug the memory usage of your C extensions as well.
So if you decide to ever integrate with your code base by exposing your C libraries by
a Python interfaces this could even help with that.
We'd like to thank everyone here for helping us with our talk and helping with all the
work that went into this presentation.
A special shout out to our manager here who is with us here today.
These are their references and thank you so much for attending our talk.
We are hiring and please do stop by our booth later.
Thank you.