Hello, everyone. Let's give a warm welcome to Mr. Jeremiah, who is going to speak on
Introduction to Introspection.
Good afternoon. Thank you, everyone, for coming out to this final talk of a very long PyCon
day. I am Jeremiah Page, and today we're going to get a little intro to introspection. So
quickly, if you don't know introspection, it's basically the ability for code to look
at itself. So we're going to take a little journey today to see how we can maybe figure
out what the interpreter sees when it's running our code ourselves and have access to that
same information.
Python's not new to introspection. It's always had strong capabilities for this. Currently
there's about 70 built-in functions, and today we're going to use 15 of them just to look
at code and decide, pull out information from it. Some of this information is hidden,
some of it's magic, but none of it's meant to be secret. Python's not trying to keep
it away from you. It's just trying to keep it out of your way as you code. So where do
we start if we want to know something more about one of our objects? Well, we could start,
especially from the interactive shell, with a simple call to help. We can just say help,
and it'll tell us help's a function, so we can call it for more help, and we can even
call for help about help, and we'll learn more about help than we'd ever want to know.
But if we wanted to learn about something maybe a little more interesting, we could
maybe just hit that tab key on our interactive shell and find this weird name, Pickle. What's
up with Pickle? If we ask for help, help will tell us a lot, pages and pages. It'll fill
our terminal and scroll off more than I can fit on several slides. Everything we could
ever want to know how to use the Pickle module as we're running Python. But if we break it
down, it's pretty straightforward. It starts by telling us about the object we actually
passed to help. What is Pickle? It's a module. Its name is Pickle, which seems pretty obvious,
but it gets this right even if you use an alias. And it has a doc string, which should
help us in implementing, making use of this module. Once we get past the opening, help
is going to detail all the classes defined in the module. It's going to give a quick
hierarchy of how they relate to each other in inheritance and to other objects in Python.
And then for each one of these classes, help is going to list them with their full definition.
Every method that's attached to them, whether directly or through inheritance, it's going
to tell us which ones are static, which ones are class methods, which ones are instance
methods. It knows all of this. And once it's done going through all the classes, help is
then going to show us all the top level functions in the module. Again, it's going to show us
the name of the functions and the signature so we know how to call them. And it's going
to give us the doc string. Once it gets through the functions, there's a few more bits of,
there's a few other names at the top of the pickle module that aren't either classes or
functions. So for each of these, it's going to show us their names and their values. So
these are in pickle a series of constants that it uses for the serialization. And at
the very end is the file, which tells you where did this code actually come out of.
So that's all very helpful information. When we quit help, it returns us to the interactive
shell and we're back where we were with our code. So we'll try and capture that information
and use it to make some intelligent decisions in our program. Except help doesn't return
anything. It doesn't leave anything on the screen. When you're done with help, there's
nothing left that your program can find and make any sort of decisions about. All that
very valuable information went into our eyeballs, but unless we're going to copy it or memorize
it, it's of no use to the program. So we're going to need to go and find this information
somewhere else. We're going to go exploring the object model in Python a little bit and
find some of the magic that's in there. Before we go and find the magic, a little definition
of what magic is. Magic in Python is a common way to refer to special methods, which are
also called Dundas, which is any name in the language that both starts and ends with a
double underscore. If any name both starts and ends with a double underscore, it's reserved
by the interpreter, even if it's not being used right now. It's where the interpreter
puts all the data it needs to run your program and keep it out of your way as you're doing
your normal job. But because it's the only place the interpreter has to put its own information,
it's a great place to look for more information about running code. So if we're not going
to use the built-in help, is there something else we could use? Well, there's another built-in
function that we probably all use to debug a program, which is you can just print the
thing. Print can take any random object and throw you a representation of it. And this
works because string actually calls a built-in stir function on all its arguments, which
in turn calls our first magic method, Dunder stir. So for any objects you want to print,
that object is actually asked to execute its Dunder stir method to give back a string,
and that's what's displayed to the screen. So we can print a module, pickle, and it'll
tell us its type, its name, and its file location, just like help is able to do. But since we're
on the interactive shell, we could just print the name, type the name instead. Same data
comes out. This is not because the REPL or the interactive shell prints this object.
It actually uses a different built-in function called repr. repr looks the same on the surface.
It takes a random object and returns a string to display for it, but it has a different
mirroring magic method Dunder repr. In many cases, it defaults to the same string, but
it can be different than what print, than what stir puts out. And so if you're typing
a program on the interactive shell, and you're typing names, and then you go and make a program
that just prints the same names, you can get very different output on your terminal. And
since both repr and stir can be overwritten by magic methods, this information that we
want, this type and name, aren't completely dependable. So we're going to have to go even
deeper into the object model and go to the source of where did help know where these
things were and where did string know where they were when it used them. So if we go back
to the help output, all this information that help told us about Piggle exists in the object.
We just have to go find it. So we're going to look at some Dunder attributes and recreate
this entire text output. So the type, it knew, help knew that this was a module without us
telling it. It's stored in the object's Dunder class. The name, the canonical name, is defined
with is in Dunder name. Its doc string is stored in Dunder doc, and the file it was
created by lives in Dunder file. This is part of the object model. After help was done with
the actual object we passed it, it then showed us all the classes. So for any class we want
help on, we can find the same information inside the class object. Its type is in Dunder
class. Its name is in Dunder name. Its doc string is in Dunder doc. Now classes don't
have files because they belong to modules. So there's no Dunder file, but there's a Dunder
module. If we were to go look up that module, it would have a Dunder file and so on. And
then the unique thing to classes is that they have inheritance, which modules don't. So
we can find the direct parentage of this class through Dunder bases. And the method
resolution order is also in the MRO. It's not shown by help because it thinks for a
class this simple it's not very interesting. After it was done with all the classes, it
then showed us all the functions. There's some repetition here. The type is in Dunder
class. The name is in Dunder name. The doc string is in Dunder doc. And again, functions
belong to modules. At this point, there's only one thing that's unique to a function,
which is its signature. How do we actually know how to call this thing at runtime? At
this point, you might think there's a Dunder signature and we're done. We finished recreating
help. But in this case, it's much more complex. Python needs to dispatch calls to your function
many, many times during execution. Maybe millions of times. It wants to be very efficient about
this. And the way we write this code is not very parsable on a machine. So we're going
to have to dig a little extra deep to recreate this. A function, if it's not function call,
if it's not empty, has parameters. And those parameters have names. So that is found in
the Dunder code attribute, which is the object representing your code compiled for the interpreter.
And inside there is a lot of stuff, but there's one very attribute called covar names. This
stores all the names of the attributes for your function call. It's actually pretty complex.
It tells you which ones are positional only, which ones can be passed by position or keyword
argument, which ones can only be passed by keyword argument. But essentially, it's all
there if we go and look for it. After we know how many variables the function accepts, we
want to know which, if any of them, have defaults and what those default values are. So with
that, we'll go back to the loads object and look at Dunder defaults. Except for this function,
we're going to look at Dunder keywords defaults. There's two locations and you're going to
have to look at both. And finally, some of you might have noticed we're no longer looking
at help for the pickle module. We're looking at help for Tomolib. Because this function
has something nothing in the pickle library does, which are annotations. This function
has a return annotation and type annotations. We can pull those out of the objects Dunder
annotations. So with this, we're able to get back all the information help had, but in
a way we can actually store in variables. But that was kind of a lot of rummaging through
the object model and having to go pretty deep. And maybe it looks kind of ugly. Maybe
you're hoping there is a better way. Well, because this is Python, there's not only a
better way, but it exists in the standard library. The inspect module is a module designed
to inspect running code. Rather than trying to access any of these magic attributes on
objects you're holding, you can just pass the object to a corresponding inspect function.
And they're much safer. They work on more types. You don't have to do any kind of special
casing. And they cover many more cases. Each one of these functions that can take an object
is really a question we're asking of something we're holding onto. We want to ask an object,
what is your doc string to maybe find more documentation about it? Or what file were
you defined in? Which if you ask it through inspect, we'll be able to tell us for any
kind of object, not just modules. But some questions are a little nonsense. We can't
ask the number one what its signature is. It doesn't have a signature and it's never
going to have a signature. So some of these questions are a little unsafe and they'll
raise exceptions even using the inspect module. So we know how to ask the questions. But maybe
rather than just wrapping all these questions in some very broad try accepts, we could be
a little more specific of when we ask them. We could do that if we knew what the heck
the object was before we started asking questions. So only functions are going to have signatures,
but integers aren't. And maybe you want to know where a file or a module came from, but
maybe we don't care for some string. So there's some built-in functions to help with this.
There's the type, very basic. You pass an object and it tells you the type. But unlike
all the other questions we've been asking of our objects so far, type is a question
you will always get an answer to in Python. Not something you can save many objects in
a dynamic language, but because Python is an object-oriented language and everything's
an object, everything has a type. So if you ask what the type of pickle is, it says it's
the class module. Because everything is an object under the covers in Python, even modules
are just classes, a little dressed up. There's only one other question that's always safe
to ask of anything in Python and expect an answer, and that's what is your ID. Not nearly
as interesting as what is your type, but you will always get a unique answer per object.
Everything else is kind of up for grabs if it actually exists on the object. Another
great built-in function is callable. So things that are callable have a signature, and we
probably want to call them before investigating them further. If they're not callable, then
they're probably a value that we should start poking at right now. But what things are callable?
Type could tell us this if we really wanted to go through the trouble of it, but there's
more than one thing that's callable. Not just functions, but classes and instances of classes
under certain circumstances. And generators are callable, but not everything is. So this
is just a quick answer to know whether you should go looking for a signature or not.
And there's also the is instance and is subclass built-ins to know if something you're holding
has a class in its inheritance tree. These are overrides by magic methods in much the
same way that print and repr were. Now, you might wonder why Python allows classes to
override their definition of inheritance at runtime, why Python just doesn't reach into
the definition of the class. There's a very useful implementation of this in the standard
library. The abstract-based classes module, or the ABC, is a collection of classes that
represent interfaces expected across different parts of Python. So there's the iterable protocol
for things that can be looped over, the sequence protocol for things that can be walked and
indexed by a number. There's a mapping protocol, which are things that can give you values
based on keys rather than attributes. And Python has concrete implementations of each
of these types. There's lists and ranges and DICs, but you can make your own, and they
work perfectly well in just about any Python code without having to inherit from a list
or a DIC. You just have to have the right shape of a class. So if you ask is instance
list, you'll know whether it's subclasses list or not, but you won't necessarily know
if it's indexable. But if you ask the abstract-based class sequence, is this thing like a sequence?
It will say, yeah, that thing quacks like a list, even if it doesn't inherit from list
or the ABC sequence. So it will give you the right answer. You know that this thing can
be used for looping or for key access. So with that, we know when to ask our questions,
and we know how to ask our questions. We've pretty much recreated all that help could
do for us, except for one thing, which is that when we ask help about the pickle module,
help told us about pickle, what its docstring was, what file it came out of, but also went
through and told us every class that was defined under pickle. And for every class,
it told us every method that was defined on that class, even though we had no idea what
any of those names were. So how did help even know what the heck it was calling for help?
In our original example, we just typed out help, and we hit tab because we were in the
active shell, and we got this weird name, pickle, so we tried it. But in a running program,
you can't just hit tab to get some new variable names. So there's going to be some more built-in
functions to help with this. First up, vars is going to return a mapping of names to values
for the object you passed it. So you pass it an object that tells you the names that
are attributes and what their values are currently. If you pass no arguments, you get the same
for the local scope. Vars actually provides access to the magic attribute dict, which
is a private dictionary that actually is what supports attribute access on objects in Python.
So vars is very literal. You ask it what are the variables for this object, and it tells
you, but it doesn't try to tell you anything that would resolve for a .name lookup. So
Python won't just stop at looking in the dict of an object when you're trying to attribute
access. If it doesn't find it there, it might go looking elsewhere. If it's not in locals,
maybe it'll try the outer scope. If it's not there, maybe it'll try globals. If it's not
in this class, maybe it'll try the parents, and that could work. Vars won't do that. It's
very literal, and it just tells you the objects that the names that would definitely resolve
for a certain object. Some helpers for vars, there's also locals and globals, which provide
the same thing, dictionary mapping for the local scope or the global scope. But if these
aren't enough, there's dir. Dir tries to be very helpful. Instead of returning a mapping,
it's returning just a list of names, but it does its very best to walk the inheritance
tree of a class to look in the class of an instance for you and find all the names that
would resolve if you actually tried to go and find them. And it's supported by a magic
method dunder dir. So it doesn't get everything. It's really hard to get everything in a dynamic
language, but it tries really hard, and it gets there most of the time. And our favorite
new standard library module inspect also has a solution to this problem. If you pass
an object to get members, it will kind of do the best of both worlds. It will return
you names and their current values, both for the current object and for other names that
would resolve, for instance, their inheritance. But it's not a built-in, and also it doesn't
work with no arguments, so it doesn't work on locals or global scope. Two more built-in
functions, hasAdder, getAdder. These are no use if you don't know what you're asking about,
because you have to pass the name you're checking. But they're the most precise, because they
go through all the same steps that a .attribute access goes through. If you ask the question,
does this exist on this object, you will get the real definitive answer.
So I hope that you realize that Python's not really trying to keep anything secret from
you. The only reason these magic methods are hidden is to stay out of your way, and so
that you don't accidentally use them in your day-to-day programming. There's no real risk
in looking at them. If you're really afraid, just when you're in the interactive interpreter,
non-emission-critical application, just look at it. There's no harm. You can even change
it. You're not going to bring down your computer. You're not going to kill Python. And I hope
you go out of here and are not afraid to ask questions of your objects. Thanks, you all,
for coming.
Thanks a lot for the great presentation. Any questions?
The is instance and is subclass. So the question was, why would you want to override is subclass
and is instance? And I was trying to answer that with the ABC module. So in the ABC module,
there is several classes, but one of them is, for instance, sequence. And sequence is
the instance that is the subclass. So the question is, why would you want to override
is subclass and is instance? And I was trying to answer that with the ABC module. So in
the ABC module, there is several classes, but one of them is, for instance, sequence.
And sequence, when it is asked if it is a superclass or a super instance of an object,
doesn't look in the inheritance tree. It looks for certain methods that would be used by
protocols in Python on the specific object. So for sequence, it doesn't look if list is
done to index, which is the special magic method that is called when you use square
brackets is implemented for that class, because that's all that's required for indexing and
a few others. So it looks for inheritance through ways other than the bases, which we
saw at the very beginning. Any other questions?
Okay. Well, thank you all for coming out and enjoy your night.