So hello.
Sorry about the slight delay, but I hope that you are well prepared.
So if you still have some set up questions and stuff, we'll have time later when we do
the break.
So don't worry about that.
Like maybe I explained a little bit or you have looked at the slides.
So sorry about that.
My computer just restarted, so it's like weird things going on.
So yeah, so the tutorial basically will consist of two parts.
I will explain a little bit later.
So there will be a lot of information given to you and then we will do some hand-on exercise.
So without further ado, this is me.
Hello, I'm Chirk.
I am from, I live in London, so I came all the way.
I spent 20 hours traveling yesterday, so fun.
So I work for TerminusDB, which is the tool that we tried to use a little bit today.
But the information, the knowledge that I gave you is not tied to TerminusDB, so I hope
you have learned something that is universally useful for you.
Also I just love giving talk and talk to people.
And so if you have more questions, feel free to ask me.
I was a data scientist, so maybe some of you are data scientists, maybe?
Yes?
Or work with data?
You work with data?
Yes.
So I work with data a lot.
I still work with data a lot.
So I'm a Pythonista.
I love Python.
I love open source software.
So if I'm on Twitter, minor stuff.
So in this workshop, we would learn what is a semantic knowledge graph.
So this is, again, I emphasize again, this is a universal knowledge.
It's not tied to TerminusDB.
So we'll try a little bit of TerminusDB, which is open source software, but you don't have
to use it if you don't like it.
I hope you like it, but if you don't like it, you don't have to use it.
So why we store data in a semantic knowledge graph?
Why we don't want to use a relational database like we did all the time?
So why is it different?
And how a knowledge graph is constructed.
So there's some building blocks in a knowledge graph that we're going to learn today.
If you haven't heard about that before, if you haven't heard about triple, quad, all
these crazy wordings, we're going to have a look today.
Also we would do some hand-on exercise.
Like I said, we would try to use TerminusDB a little bit.
We would try to build a knowledge graph schema.
We would try to code in Python.
Amazing stuff.
And we would try to make some query using the things that we learned today.
So these are just technical details.
We will figure it out later.
We will have trouble with time, like I said.
So everyone can learn this knowledge.
It's not tied to Python.
Like I said, it's a universal knowledge.
You don't have to learn TerminusDB.
You don't have to learn Python.
But the knowledge that I gave you today in the knowledge graph, so it's actually anybody
can learn about it.
But of course the hand-on exercise will be in Python.
So also the setup will be using Docker and using Python.
Or you can use the cloud version if you can't use Docker.
But otherwise you can just enjoy the lecture.
So we're here.
I'm just giving a brief introduction.
We are slightly delayed.
But hopefully we'll have time to catch up later.
So there will be a presentation.
So around 60 minutes.
It depends on how much stuff I'm saying or how much questions I receive.
Feel free to ask questions at any time.
I love questions.
Then we have a break.
We'll try to figure out all the setup problems and stuff.
Also get yourself charged.
Refill your coffee.
And then we will start the hands-on exercise, which we will be coding together.
So actually there's a tutorial that I already written a while ago.
But we'll try to do it step-by-step together.
If you have questions, you can ask me immediately.
So at the end we'll just have a brief closing, review what we have learned, and how everybody
can go in and ask more questions if you want to.
So yeah.
So this is a knowledge graph.
So there's some kind of keywords that we go through today.
Learning what is a triple, what is a quad, and then how a graph data model is different
from a relational data model.
So I always compare them with like, oh, one is 3D, one is 2D.
What does that mean?
There's also other terms that we use describing things in a knowledge graph, like objects,
elements, properties, and other stuff.
So we'll explain that.
Yeah, so also we'll look at a use case, kind of a use case that I make up.
But through that you can build your first knowledge graph.
So what is a triple?
So the triple actually, if you kind of talk to someone who loves semantic knowledge graph,
you always come across something that's called triple.
It's a building block of a semantic data model.
So a lot of times when you go through a semantic data, you'll come across some file formats,
like some of them is called RDF, some of them is called Turtoi, T-T-L, something like that.
So they're actually a different file format that we use.
So instead of, on the other hand, you have your relational database.
It will be stored in a tablet format, in CSV, in a database, or in Excel, something like that.
So, but today we focus on the knowledge graph.
So we have triple, which we store everything in triple.
And triple consists of three main things.
So there's a subject, a predicate, and an object.
So yeah, it's kind of like remind you of the lesson that you had when you first learned
the English lesson.
Let's say I learned English as a second language.
So for me, it's like the teacher would tell us how an English sentence is structured.
You have your noun, your objective, and all this stuff.
So it's kind of like that.
It's logical.
You always have three things.
You always have two things, like subject and object, and the predicate to describe their relationship.
So some example would be Apple is red.
But it's not like one to one equivalent to a language because instead of like Apple is red,
sometimes you can have multiple kind of word in one, for example, predicate.
Because for example, you have past tense.
I don't know why, but Apple used to be red.
Maybe now it turned black because you haven't eaten it for months.
So predicate could not just be a word.
So it's not a direct one to one relationship between a triple and a sentence.
But the logic kind of goes the same.
So it's kind of like you can construct a complex idea with triples.
So here, these examples are very, very simple examples.
It's just one idea at a time.
So each triple carries one idea.
So Apple is red.
So Chuck teaches a workshop.
And Cal loves duck, for example.
So this is kind of kid-like stuff.
So anybody can come up with some example of triples?
Very quiet.
Coffee is good?
Yes, I agree with that.
Anybody else?
Python is awesome, of course.
Yes.
So yeah, that's just a very simple idea.
They are triples.
So they are atoms.
They are the most basic things that construct a knowledge graph.
So for example, here, you can see it's like a kid's bedtime story things.
So like, oh, there's a cow says moo, and then a duck says quack.
But in this picture, if you want to describe this picture,
so instead of just one idea at a time, you
may have a lot of ideas in this picture.
You can have like, oh, cows have always a cow.
So cow has four legs.
Cow will say moo.
And then duck has wings.
And duck will say quack, things like that.
So if you combine all of them together, then it will paint the picture.
It will construct a more complex idea that's not just one single idea.
So this is world building.
This is how we build a knowledge graph.
This is how we build a graph that can describe everything in the world,
ideally.
Of course, I would come up with some other more complex stuff that will come up.
But in theory, you can describe everything
by just using a lot of, lot of triples.
You can build a world with all these triples.
So sometimes we have problems, right?
What if I have two cows?
And they're actually from two different farms, right?
So they are different things, and they speak different languages.
So one cow says moo, one cow says meow.
I don't know why.
So yeah, so how can I distinguish these two cows from different farms, right?
So sometimes a triple is not good enough to distinguish different things.
You will see the practical reason why later.
But this is the problem that we have.
We have two cows.
They're both cows.
They're not different animals.
But they're just from different farms, and they're slightly different.
Then how we should solve this problem is to add an additional identifier
to identify these two farms.
They should not overlap because they are a different world.
For cows, the farm is their whole world, so it's different.
So we add one more element to the triple, so it becomes a quad.
So triple, quad, three and four.
Straightforward.
So now you can compare the two different cows from two different universes, right?
Because you can identify them specifically with a quad.
So you can cross-reference.
You can even cross-reference between the two of them.
So that expands the idea of using triple to represent anything.
You cannot just describe the whole world with many, many triples.
You can even describe the two worlds that are similar but also different,
then you can compare them.
So why is this good?
Because we do that all the time with Git.
Right?
So with Git, you have two sets of codes, but they are slightly different
because someone makes some changes and you want to compare them.
So by using not just triple but quads, we can also do something like what Git does,
which we'll come back to later.
So that's the basic of what is triple.
So is there any questions?
Is it sounds really crazy or does it make sense?
Yes?
What is just a triple with an extra element or attribute
to identify what graph is this in?
So we can have many, many triples in one graph,
but we have multiple graphs and we can compare them.
Yes?
We haven't go there yet.
In theory, you can, but I think because at the beginning,
triple is good enough.
Like I said, you can link up all the ideas together.
But when you do something similar to Git,
you want to compare the two sets of things, then a quad will help.
So I haven't think about how we can make it five or six, but yeah.
Any more questions?
Yes?
Is there a fourth element in the graph?
Sorry, I can't really hear.
Sorry.
Is there a fourth element in the graph?
Yes, the fourth element is the ID for the graph.
So triple lives in a graph.
Triple forms a graph.
And the last element that we add to a triple
is to identify which graph they are in.
So yes, kind of ID, but ID for graph.
Anything else?
Yeah, so in relational database, for example,
you have multiple tables, right?
So graph is kind of like that in that sense.
But how relational database works is different from a graph.
Then we will compare about them soon.
So yeah.
So maybe I will move on.
If you have more questions, feel free to ask at any time.
So in the graph, let's talk about relational database model first.
So we are familiar with it.
We use it all the time.
Even though you are like, oh, I am a Python programmer.
I code.
But you come across it all the time, right?
For example, you use Django.
Django use the back end is relational database, right?
No matter you use MySQL or Postgres, they are relational database.
So SQL database.
Or if you, let's say, oh, I'm a data scientist.
I do CSPs.
They are also tablet format, right?
Or if you are like, oh, at work, I use even
I use a lot of Google spreadsheet just for administrative stuff, right?
So they are all tablet.
They are all kind of in the same sense of models.
They are all like SQL kind of table, tablet format of data.
So I use CSV a lot in the past when I was a data scientist.
Of course, it's not just comma separated.
You have some kind of weird stuff.
Sometimes you have like, oh, maybe the, how do you call that character?
There's a line.
I don't know.
Pipe, yeah.
So pipe separated values sometimes.
You know, they use different characters.
But they are the same, right?
So they're also just a file.
So the thing is that when you work with them,
when I used to work with CSPs or the SQL databases, a lot of times,
what I really struggle with is to do a simple thing,
find a simple answer by joining many, many tables together.
Sometimes you aggregate and join it back to itself.
So you can very easily write 1,000 lines of SQL
just to get an answer from your data.
So that's why sometimes I just want to write a Python program
to deal with it, you know?
But sometimes it's not possible.
I remember when I worked in a company, they have a legacy database,
very, very huge.
And I can't load them all in Python to find out my answer.
I have to use SQL to do the stuff.
So not always possible.
Sometimes it involves lots of very awkward joins and aggregations
that I don't like.
Maybe you like it, but I don't like it.
So on the other hand, knowledge graph, it sounds a little bit
complicated, right?
Because relational database is a table.
So it's very easy to visualize, right?
You look at this column, this rows.
You look at it.
It's easy to understand.
But knowledge graph, I would say, is the 3D,
because you can link everything.
It consists of triples.
You can just link things together.
It's not limited to rows and columns, which I describe as 2D.
You can link it in multi-dimension, not just 3D,
but multi-dimensional, right?
So yeah, so a lot of common format instead of CSV
is stored in this RDF XML format, which is a markup language.
So it looks very similar to HTML, but it's not.
It's an XML format.
We follow some kind of RDF standard.
That's why it's called RDF XML.
This TTL file, the turtoys sometimes, I call it.
I don't know.
It's TTL.
So again, it's something that is designed specifically
of describing how triples are linked to each other.
JSON-LD is what we use in TerminusDB.
I would say that's the easiest to use, because if you look at XML or TTL,
it looks like HTML.
Those brackets and stuff is so difficult to read with human eyes.
But JSON-LD looks like a JSON.
JSON looks like a Python dictionary.
So it's very easy to look at it with human eyes
until they get too big, until they become too big
and the indentation go crazy.
And it's difficult to see.
So the difference between the knowledge graph
and a tablet format or a SQL database is that data
is kind of unstructured.
Like I said, it's not rows and columns.
You can link everything together.
Imagine you have like Legos.
You can just put them together without any limitations.
So it's not really confined to just rows and columns.
So it's kind of unstructured, if you think about that.
I would say that you use triple to paint a new world,
paint a new picture.
So same with data.
You can model your data to work this way.
So it's not limited to just rows and columns to describe your data.
You can just describe the relationship
between different things.
So how can we do that?
How can we do that?
We'll find out today.
So yes?
That's a very good question.
Because I would say that actually, I'll show you later.
Actually, you can automatically write a script to convert them.
Because a knowledge graph is like a 3D.
So it's more flexible than a relational database.
So if you can store things in rows and columns
and maybe multiple tables, you can actually store them
in knowledge graph for sure.
It's just how to convert them.
So how to convert them will require the knowledge
of how to model them.
That's actually similar to the exercise
that we will do later, how we have a relational database
and then how we can convert them into a knowledge graph.
So a knowledge graph, I would say, is like a bigger
set than a relational database.
If you can store things in a relational database,
you can store it in a knowledge graph.
So yeah, that's one of the advantages.
It's more flexible.
So the knowledge is very flexible.
Things you can store in table, you can easily store it
in a knowledge graph, no problem.
Also, you can actually add some constraint to it.
So rather than just free for all, you can link anything together.
If you build some governing structure on top,
which we will talk about, schema later,
then you can have a very flexible way structure
to store your data.
So sometimes if you have data that is not too differently,
not good installing in a tablet format, for example,
you have some data that's very nested
or you have a lot of cross-reference.
So instead of using some key to refer to each other,
you can easily just link them.
Let's say two people, you can link them together.
And each people can have their own attribute and stuff.
So that's actually why some people find that a knowledge
graph is the only option to store their data.
Because if they try to flatten it, store it in 2D,
all these cross-reference, all these nested format
will give them a headache.
So that's why it's the best way to do it,
is to store it in a graph format.
Also, if you make queries, like I said,
the advantage of doing knowledge graph
is that you don't have to join things back together,
because they are already linked.
So let's say you have two people that
is cross-referencing each other.
You just have a link from one object, which is the person,
to another person.
So you don't have to find the ID and then join them back
together.
So you're kind of like, oh, I know that now this is related.
Because they are naturally linked together by the triple.
And so it very naturally works as a graph.
So sometimes it's easier to find the answer you want from data
to just traverse the graph, instead of making a lot of joins
and connecting everything back together.
Because let's say you only need to find the relationship
between two people.
You don't have to join the whole graph of every users
that you have.
Let's say you have users, and you just
want to know that, oh, who referenced this user?
Instead of you have to do a lookup, which
look at everything, you can just traverse the graph,
because they're already linked together.
Who are the referencee?
They can just, oh, I found that person.
So yeah, so that's sometimes it's better.
So I know that recently or in the last few years,
data lake is a big hype.
Lots of different cloud service is providing data lake.
You can store a lot of things in it.
It's just referenced by a link.
So you can have a blob that put in the data lake,
and you just find the link to that blob of things.
So it's like a lake.
Everything can put it in.
So the advantage of that, but sometimes we want structure.
So with a knowledge graph, you can add a schema on top.
Then you have structure.
Then you can find the things you dumped in the data lake
much easier.
Rather than just have a bunch of links,
you don't know what they are.
But with a schema, it will help you
to find important information from your graph.
So how do we do that?
A schema is needed when you have cases that, for example, you
want to monitor what data come into your graph.
So naturally, a graph, you can just
link all the triples together and build something.
But sometimes you don't want that.
Sometimes you want to have a structure that, for example,
a person always have a name.
Let's say, we first name, last name,
but it's a bad model because some people only
got one name, but anyway.
So let's say a person needs to have a name.
Let's say a person needs to have a contact number,
because if we can't contact them,
they don't exist in our database.
So you can build a schema, a structure,
to govern how your data look like.
For example, contact number need to be digits.
Let's say contact number need to be only digits.
Let's say, again, it's a bad model, a bad example,
but let's say you designed it that way.
Or a person's name can't have emoji on it, something like that.
So you can actually, having a schema,
you can govern governance, like how your data will look like.
You can't just have anything that just come in.
You need to confine a certain format to be in your graph.
So that's what schema is for, and that's why it's useful,
most of the time.
So I'm using TerminusDB as an example here,
but generally, you have similar design
for graphs to be useful, to be honest.
Because you have objects, first of all.
You have a lot of objects in it.
Even though you can describe anything with triples,
but to make things more systematic in the schema,
you will have objects.
So it's kind of like Python, everything is an object.
So you also need to have objects in your graph.
So just like Python objects, they also will have properties.
Another object can be their property,
so you can build anything with it.
Also, there's documents.
So documents and objects, they are very tricky.
They are basically the same thing.
So how we design it is that document will have an ID,
object don't have an ID.
So later, we rename it into sub-documents,
and it just goes into more like quite a crazy terminology.
But just imagine they're the same thing.
Sometimes I use the word interchangeably,
like objects and documents.
But just remember, documents always have an ID,
objects doesn't.
Enums.
So enums is sort of very useful.
Well, we are all familiar with it.
But yeah, so more details.
So objects, we are not alien with it, right?
Because Python, naturally, you would already
come across object-oriented programming
if you use Python.
And so you can create an object in a schema,
or document in a schema, that is like a class.
So you can create instance of it.
So that's how I see it, is that documents or objects
in a schema is the class.
And then the data you put it in is the instance of it.
So again, like I said, objects are sub-documents.
They don't have an ID.
Documents, they have an ID.
It's just a funny naming things.
So later, we'll see the example there
that I would have a person, a person have an address.
So in an address, we just get all the street numbers,
a postcode, or zip code, city, town, county,
all this stuff into one package.
So address will be an object with a lot
of different properties of all those things.
So or attributes in Python, there are attributes,
but it could be properties.
So just different naming, right?
So you can also put this address as an object
itself into different things.
For example, you have different users.
Or you have one user, they can have different address.
Or different users can share the same address.
So you can also reference it to another object as well.
So yeah, document is just, again, having an ID.
The reason why we made this difference,
because sometimes you just want, for example, the address
that I mentioned, you just, so let's say two different users
can't have the same address.
You design it this way.
Don't ask why.
So an address always lives inside a user,
lives inside a person.
Then you don't have to cross-reference it.
And it's just a package of stuff.
But a document will be, let's say, different users.
They will have to have an ID so you can identify them.
So you can find out who they are.
So you can cross-reference each other.
For example, one user is referring the other user.
So they both get a discount or something like that.
So you may want that.
You need to use an ID to identify them.
So each of them will have a unique ID.
So that's the only difference, really.
It just makes things a little bit different
when it works in the graph.
So pretty confusingly, we also have different naming issues.
But that's how we name it.
So this ID, which is a unique identifier,
try to ignore the one before the slash.
Because I put it there because the old version
used the old naming, which is on the left.
But we're focusing on the right of the slash.
So ID is the unique identifier, just like a key, a pyramid key.
And name is a human readable name.
So you can use emoji in there.
So has anybody tried to import something as emoji?
So my friend has tried to import pandas as panda emoji.
So yeah, you can use emoji in there.
Or sometimes, let's say ID, you need to be confined.
Because of how we store stuff, so ID need to be, let's say,
URL save.
But name, sometimes people's name will have those accent.
So then the ID doesn't reflect the name correctly.
So you may want to store the name as a different thing.
So it could be any string as a name.
And then you have a longer description and stuff.
So that's how all the documents, we make it work like that.
And so again, it's just an example
how a document works in TerminusDB.
But I think that's a really good model.
Because you will need an ID and a name and description.
Just like every talk, right?
Imagine a lot of things are like that.
Let's say you submit a proposal to a conference.
You have an ID of your talk.
And then you have the title of your talk
and the abstract of your talk.
So a lot of things work like that.
So that's why it's kind of like that in TerminusDB.
Of course, you can add more properties in there.
So these three are the defaults.
You can add more properties in there.
For example, like I said, the talk, the proposal you submit
is to a conference.
Then you may want to have other things, right?
You may have the duration or the type of this proposal.
Or you may want to add your bio in there as well.
I don't know.
So it will have more stuff.
But the basics are there.
So enum.
Enum is just like enum in SQL or enum in Python.
It's just a list of values.
So a lot of times, we need to use enum
because we want to limit the choice of what people have.
Like if you're in a farm, a lot of times,
you came across a drop-down menu of choosing things.
For example, which country you're from.
So there's lots of different countries you can choose.
Things like that.
So any confusion about documents, objects, and enums?
So there are three different things that we have.
When we build our schema, we're basically just creating
these three types of things.
We will create a enum.
We will create a document.
We will create an object or sub-document.
Yes?
A document is the object itself, but with an ID.
Yes.
I know it's very confusing.
So that's why I want to pause and see
if people are clear about that.
Everything is an object except enum,
which is just a list of choice, which that's
why it's structured a little bit different.
So it's kind of like, is that Python?
So it's like, let's say, Python classes and Python name
triple kind of thing.
It's just different things.
But yeah.
So for the objects or documents, they will have properties.
So the property itself, so this is actually,
when we do hands-on exercise, this is not going to,
we won't use this information.
But I'm giving this to you again because this
is how, when someone describes a semantic graph,
sometimes they describe things this way.
So that's why I give you extra information to understand it.
But in our exercise, we will use the same information
to understand it.
But in our exercise, we won't use this just to warn you.
So if you think it's complicated, don't worry.
We won't touch this.
So properties.
So so far, so how we look at things, right?
It's like, oh, I have an object and I have a relationship.
And another object, let's say, I'm my mother's daughter.
My mother, so like give birth to me, let's say.
So there's like three kind of things,
triple relationship, all this stuff.
But now we want to look at it differently.
So look at, OK, so there's a relationship.
So my mother, me, relationship.
Look at the relationship itself.
So we will look at the two ends of it.
So it's kind of like that property.
Let me think of a better example.
So let's say I am the object.
So I have an ID.
My ID is 001 because I'm the first person that I created
in the graph.
And then name will be my name, right, check.
That's usually how we look at things.
So there's a thing and then a property.
And then that would be our name will be check.
Check is a string, right?
But sometimes we want to look at things a little bit different.
We look at the property itself.
So we look at name.
So name is a property.
But a name will also have a domain and a range.
So what is that?
So name is a property of a person.
So that's why name's domain is a person.
It's a person object.
And the name's range would be a string
because it's store string.
So it's kind of like a property-centric way
of looking at things.
Instead of looking at, oh, name is a property of a person,
which name will be very passive.
But now I look at name actively.
So what is name's domain?
Oh, it's person because it belongs to person.
And its range will be a string because it stores string.
So we talk about that.
We mainly just look at, oh, person,
we have a property name that stores a string.
So it's the other way around.
But sometimes we mention domain and range,
and that's what we mean.
So sometimes range can be another person.
Let's say later you see in the examples
that we have a lot of employees, and they'll have managers.
So you can have employee, and then manager
will be another employee because your manager is
another employee.
So range could be another object.
So it could be not just a string or number or any data type.
So it comes to two things.
It's like, make it more complicated.
So there's the data property or object properties.
So a data property means that things are just data.
How can I describe it?
We call them data types.
It's just text, like string, or it's just
like integer or decimal, or they are Booleans.
You can be more complicated, like unsigned type,
you know, the unsigned integer or something like that.
But they are not another object.
That's why they are called data types.
They are sometimes literal data types,
because they're literal.
They are just what they are.
They are not another object.
Of course, you can say, oh, in Python, string
is also another object, and integer is another object.
Well, not in our case here.
That string is just like text.
It's not another object.
So object property, on the other hand, is another object.
So for example, like I just described,
so employee is an object.
So if the property, if the range of that property
is another object, then it's an object property.
You can think of it as a link between two different objects.
It could be not just employees.
It could be like someone, let's say, a user
has the billing address.
But you make billing address is an address object.
So you have user, an address, two different objects.
You link them together, because this is the billing address,
it's the property of the user.
So billing address will have a domain of user
and a range of an address.
So OK, hands up, yes.
Data about the relationship.
So you would have to think about what this data mean,
because you can also, for example,
we have the billing address thing again.
So you could, oh, how can I describe this billing address
that is a billing address that is not a residential address,
let's say?
Or can I have a property for this billing address,
but not just a, how can I describe it?
Is that what you mean?
That describing the relationship.
Yes, so in this case, this link is a property.
So it really only makes sense when
it belongs to the user.
The billing address doesn't make any sense
if it does not belong to a user, because it's a property.
It's the property of the user.
So yeah, in this case, it's not bidirectional,
because the domain and the range is obviously
two sides of the thing.
So you can't have the other way around.
So you can't have the, well, if you
want to go back in the other direction,
let's say you have the address, and then
who this address belongs to, then you
may have to add a property for the address
to link it back to the user.
But by nature, the properties, the link between the object,
the object properties, they are one directional only,
because they have one side, which is domain,
and the other side, which is the range.
So it's not bidirectional.
So wow, it's information overload.
How can we do this?
How can we represent data in a knowledge graph?
So let's say we have a case now, a case study now.
So in the next slides, I will give you
an example of things that I made up.
It's a database in a tablet format,
and then we could try to create a schema
to model it into a knowledge graph.
So it's governance by the schema,
so that's why we build a schema.
And then also in exercise, we try
to put the data in it as well.
So it'll be nice.
So don't worry.
I know that there's a lot of information.
It may be your first time thinking that way, the data,
but we'll do it step by step and slowly.
So for example, I hope it's clear enough.
Otherwise, you can refer to your notes.
That I have made up this is a small company.
It's a small startup company, only four people working there
at the moment.
So it's a phone book.
It's a phone book database.
So I've made it very, very simple.
All this data are fabricated and generated randomly.
So don't ask me why I have all these names.
They are just generated, so I don't even know.
So there are four employees, and then they
will have the name, the title, and then which team they
belong to, and the manager.
This table is describing the whole company structure.
But there's no personal information in there
because they are sensitive.
We only allow, let's say, certain people to access it.
So we store it separately.
This is another spreadsheet or database
or whatever that store the contact details of the employee.
So they have the ID, because we need to link them back together.
Joins, we love joins.
And context numbers, and then home address, and then
postcode and stuff.
So this is a relational database.
And there's two tables.
You can imagine they are just two tables in your database.
And they have the primary key, which is the employee ID.
They should be unique.
So let's start modeling.
So what we'll do now, we will try
to design the schema together first.
And then later, when we code, then we
would put that really into practice.
But to make things simple, we would just
decide on some design first.
So documents.
So what would be our documents in this case?
So what would be the main things that has an ID in our graph?
Anybody want to try?
I know you have the slides, but yeah.
So that would be, obviously, employee.
Yes, I heard it.
I heard it.
So employee would have an ID.
So naturally, there would be objects or documents
that has an ID.
So OK, good, good.
We have employees.
So now we have to populate the information about them.
So they will have properties.
So what properties do we want to have?
So of course, they'll have a name.
And then they will have their title and then a team.
So oh, team, we only have two teams right now.
So maybe make it an enum.
Yeah, that makes sense.
And oh, they have a manager.
And then now we have object properties.
I can link employees together.
Yay.
So we have, wow, all these cases.
And then to make it more tidy, we
can get all the address or the contact detail in one thing.
We can have the address.
Even break it smaller, we can have the town.
So this is still pretty British.
The postcode is also British, I know, because I live in the UK.
So you have, let's say, the street number and street name,
the town, and the postcode.
So we can tidy them up into one sub-document object.
It's address.
So yes, let's work it this way.
So this is the summary of what we would do.
So you can see the thinking process behind it.
So first you design on what will be the object,
and then what would be the property.
Sometimes it helps to gather some property together
into some sub-documents.
How we do it.
So name, just a string.
Simple title, just a string.
Simple name.
You can also try to break it down
into first name, second name, whatever.
But because name is a very tricky thing,
if you have seen my tweet or something about name.
So let's not make it complicated and just have name.
And then team, it would be enum, so just two team right now.
Managers, there will be object property.
And then contact number, little type.
So just, I will start a string because we have
the crazy bracket there, so just a string.
And then home address, we make that nice
into an address object, or address sub-document.
And then postcode, I'll put that into address as well.
So, yeah, employee ID.
So okay, here's the caveat.
I think I've changed my mind a little bit here
when I designed the exercise.
So actually it's not necessarily to give them the ID,
like 01, 02, all those stuff.
Because if you put a document into Terminus DB,
Terminus DB will say, oh, you haven't given ID
to the document, I'll give one for you.
So just randomly create it, or you can actually tell
Terminus DB how to create an ID for it.
But I think in the exercise, I want to make things
more simple, I just create an ID for them
to make things easier.
But it's not necessarily.
So I won't spend too much time into ID because
it could be a lot of other sidetracks and stuff.
So not going to sidetrack myself too much.
So, yes.
So I can insert the first person twice, right?
So how can I make sure that is unique?
So what happened is that in Terminus DB,
so I just said that, oh, if you insert a document,
it will just generate an ID for you.
So if you insert the same document twice without an ID,
so I'm talking about when you're actually coding
and do the stuff that we are doing later,
then it will just treat as two things.
If you don't give it a unique ID, then you just,
oh, you have inserted the same set of things twice,
so I'll just treat them as two separate things.
So there will be two person with the same name,
same title, same credential and stuff,
which may not be something that you want.
But if you give them an ID, give them a unique ID,
for example, let's say I hard-coded as 0010203,
they would just be like a relation database,
the primary key.
If you insert the same ID twice,
then there will be an error.
You have to tell TerminusDB that, oh, I'm repasing it
or I'm updating it, then it will update it.
Otherwise, it will be like, oh, you can't insert
the same things with the same ID twice.
So in TerminusDB, you can also say, oh,
I don't wanna hard-code it, I don't want to make it random,
you can find a middle ground of, oh, can I use the name
as the unique identifier, so generate an ID using the name,
something like that.
Exactly.
Yes, you have to create a unique identifier.
So yeah, if you don't specify it, TerminusDB
will just generate one randomly for you,
and it will ensure that it will be unique.
But for example, you're migrating your database,
you need to find what is the key,
what is the unique identifier,
and then use that as the ID.
So yeah, so that's why you will see it when we code.
Okay.
So,
yes, you can.
So I don't wanna drive into detail, but actually, yes.
You can have, so there are different ways
of how you can generate an ID.
So I've mentioned two, one is hard-coding it,
every object you give it an ID.
The other way is randomly, but there are also other ways,
like this one that's called,
yeah.
Yeah.
So, wait a second.
Let me answer that question.
So you can combine different things.
So there's literal things that you could have,
not just one field, not just the name.
Let's say you need the name and the title to be unique.
So you can be like name and title,
and it would generate a unique ID
based on the name plus the title, right?
You can have to combine.
So for the second question, that you need to have,
so if you insert the same document with the same ID,
you have an error if you use insert.
So what if I want to change things
for something that I already know,
that I already inserted before, I wanna change it?
Then you have to replace it.
You have to use replace.
So you can't mix up the two operation.
You can, in the Python client, I added some function
that it would check whether it's already exist.
If it does, then it will replace it.
If not, then it will just insert it.
But in the raw design,
you can't mix up the insert and the replace.
So if you insert the same thing twice,
you'll have an error.
If you want to update something, you have to use replace.
Yeah.
Okay.
So, yeah, I've talked a lot about how Terminus DB work.
So Terminus DB, again, is open source.
So everybody can get it for free on Docker.
It will be open source forever.
That's what my boss told me.
The founder said that it will be open source forever.
You can always just download it and use it for free,
or build from source if someone,
if you are very, you know,
if you're tech-savvy enough to build from source,
you can do that, source code, open.
Okay.
So it will have some feature that you may like.
You know, like revision control.
If you like it, you may like it.
Also, we tried to create a cloud version
which you can easily collaborate
to share a database within two people, like GitHub,
that can share a Red Bull between people.
You can see whether they can merge something.
You know, there's a lot of kind of roles
that you can give them, what access level they have.
So that's the idea of what we want to achieve
for original control and the collaboration.
So open source, I think I don't have to explain it.
You know, we all love open source.
We know what is open source.
It means that the source code is up in open,
is for the community.
The license is Apoche2, I think.
So it doesn't mean that you can do it wherever.
You have to follow the license.
But generally, it's a very common open source license.
So it's not saying different.
Yes, so Neo4j works a little bit differently
from what we are.
So I don't have a benchmark like to like comparison.
Maybe my colleague has done it in the past,
but we have improved it over the past few months.
So the answer is I don't have a good answer for that.
Also graph database, like you just mentioned,
there are other graph database in the market,
Neo4j and stuff, but we just work slightly differently.
You know, choose your own adventure.
I'm not trying to say that you must use TerminusDB,
but there are a few things that we are different
from Neo4j.
Let's say Neo4j, the query language is Cyper,
so it's a text-based query language.
We use JSON-LD, so it's a JSON format.
So we think that JSON is better
because you can't inject a tag it.
So that's one thing.
So also we try to do revision control.
I know that MongoDB can't do revision control,
so that's why we try to have some way
that you can actually do this comparison
with MongoDB as well.
So we're just trying to build more feature
for people to use.
If you think a feature is very important for you,
talk to me and we'll see how we can help.
So other things, you know, we have this document API,
so we found that after a few years
of development and experimentation,
inserting data as triple is quite tricky,
especially when you have a schema.
So we built this document API recall,
so it's kind of like you can build a schema
more in an object-oriented programming style
instead of writing triples,
but we also try a little bit of triple things at the end,
but that will be a query, not as inserting data.
So there's Python client, proudly maintained by me.
So if you find any bugs, you can complain to me.
So we used to have these graph representation in D3,
it's very nice, but we have put it down for a bit,
and then hopefully we're coming back up again,
so I won't talk too much about it
because it doesn't exist anymore.
So TerminusDB is on Docker Hub.
I hope that you can get the image
or just have one version of TerminusDB,
the latest version of TerminusDB working in your computer.
If you don't, the workaround will be signing up
on TerminusX in terminusdb.com.
So that's the cloud version.
Right now we are not charging.
We are still letting people to try and test it.
So I can't say what the future will be like,
but right now it's free.
That's what I can tell you.
So there are two clients that are working.
Platform client we'll be using today, JavaScript client.
If you are building web app, you may be interested in that,
but that will be another time.
So we're back to here.
I'll let everybody to take a break.
I'm so bad with time.
Let's say we take, how much time do you think we need?
I don't think we need 20 minutes, right?
Let's say 15 minutes max, then we'll come back,
and then we will try to do some coding coding stuff.
If you are struggling with getting either the Python client
or the TerminusDB running, then let me know.
I'll try to help.
Any other questions?
Also let me know.
I'll try to help.
Otherwise, I think, let's say now it's 4 T past 2
or 20 to 3.
Let's come back at 5 to 3 p.m.
Okay.
Okay, hello.
It's a bit small to see and difficult to see, isn't it?
Sorry about that.
Just shout if you think this too small.
And like, you know, things like that.
Because I need to find a right balance
that I can see what I'm doing,
but at the same time you can see what I'm doing.
So let's put this away.
This is not what I'm doing right now, I think.
I may need some help there, but that's later.
Okay, so let's zoom this in as well.
Awful.
Okay, we'll adjust it when we're using that.
So let's come here.
If you go to the tutorials, devices,
I would just see.
Yeah, so I hope everybody's fine.
I know some of you have some issues with that.
I'm so sorry if you really can't get it set up today.
I'm so sorry, but all the information is given to you.
So if you want to try it at home, feel free to.
And if you have questions later, you can also contact me.
Happy to answer.
So I hope you also have the Python client installed.
And I'm using poetry as well.
So also advertising for poetry.
I really like that tool.
I recently converted to it.
I was using the Python virtual anthem for it,
but now I fall in love with poetry because it's nice.
So I hope everybody's okay with the setup.
So like I said, if you really struggle or something,
everything is hosted online.
So you can catch up or follow or do the lesson
that I didn't cover today by yourself at home as well.
I'm happy to answer questions.
Just give me a shout online or something.
Or you can join the discord and talk to the team.
Sometimes they have better answers than me
because they know inside of the database.
So we are going to use this getting started tutorial.
So we have developed a lot of tutorials.
Not all of them are my work.
Some of them are my colleagues work,
but we're focusing on the Python client
getting started tutorial there.
It should be working the link.
If you click on it, it should go to this page.
And then we are focusing on lesson one, three and seven.
There are more than that in this.
Again, feel free to try everything at home,
but I don't think we have time to go through seven lessons.
We're focusing on one, three and seven.
Also one thing before we start,
all the codes are actually available in the Red Bull,
but you don't have to clone the whole thing.
All you need is the two CSV, these two,
the contact and employee CSV.
But they're very small.
Even though you can't clone it,
you can just copy and then paste it in the text file
and rename it the same thing as I did here.
That's all you need.
And then we'll do things step by step.
Even though the code is available,
I would recommend you try it yourself
or do it differentially.
Because it feels better if you make it work by yourself,
rather than copy and pasting.
The code here is just for me to cheat when I'm struggling.
Because you know live coding always have accident
and it doesn't work sometimes,
then I can cheat by using the code that I've written before.
But I highly recommend you to not copy and paste
and try to write your own code.
If you're really struggling,
yes of course you can do what I did, copy and paste.
But yeah.
So yeah, let's look at it.
So first thing.
So again, what we gotta do here
for lesson one, three and seven is to create a schema.
Like we talked about in the slide.
So we'll actually go back to the slides
when we create a schema.
We'll use what we have designed as the blueprint.
So we'll follow that and how to convert it into code
and make it work.
We'll do that.
And then we would also try to insert data
how you can have the CSV and do some data handling.
Yeah, to make it into the database
and see how Python client make everything work as an object.
Yeah, so that's what lesson three.
And then lesson seven is actually the fun bit
that we would try to make some query using triples.
So yeah, triple.
We learned triple today.
We want to use it.
So that's why we are doing that.
So right now, so go to start a new.
So you can start it in a new directory.
So you will have things like that.
Oh, sorry about everything.
I'm here.
I was testing it before.
So that's why I have so many things.
It's still a bit small.
Why is it so small?
Please.
Is it big enough?
Was it not good?
I don't know.
Also it's dark mode.
So give me a shout if it's too small for you.
For those at the back, you may struggle a little bit,
but let me know if you want me to make it bigger.
So I'm using poetry.
So this is my poetry shelf.
So I have TerminusDB installed.
If I do a list, you'll see this bunch of things.
So what we have is TerminusDB here.
Who is it?
Yeah, TerminusDB client.
So I'm good to go, I think.
I have it.
Yes.
So yeah.
And then I'm also clearing again.
So I'm in a new directory.
So I have, well, it's not really new for me.
So I use poetry.
That's why I have the poetry log and the pyproject.toml.
So it doesn't really matter for the substance
in the pyproject.toml, but what is vendor?
I don't know what is vendor.
I don't know why it's there.
But anyway, I have the two CSVs there.
That is just the CSV I showed you before.
You can find that in the tutorial red poll.
So it's just this, right?
I have them.
But otherwise, I haven't done anything.
Imagine I haven't done anything else, right?
I just have poetry.
I got the thing installed.
I have just copied the CSV.
This is how I start.
So also, oh, one other thing.
I have my Docker running.
So if I do Docker, this is so small,
but this is not important, so I won't make it too big.
So Docker PS, it should show me that it's running.
Yeah, I have my container running.
So all good?
Right.
So I will demonstrate it with the local image.
So if, oh, sorry.
Zoom in a bit, yeah, sure.
Okay.
Is it better?
Yeah, I'll create as well, so it go back to the top.
So for, I'm using it locally, the Docker container.
If you're using Terminus X,
it will be a little bit different
when you connect to Terminus X.
I would also explain it, but I'm using the local one.
Okay, so if I start, we would have,
so when you install the Python client,
there is the Terminus db command should be,
typing with one hand is very difficult.
So the command will be available to you, Terminus db.
So I built it using click,
for those of you who are interested.
So there's a bunch of commands that you could do.
They kind of basically help you to work with your database.
But before that, you have to start project.
So you see there's a start project.
It's kind of similar to Django, right?
I got the sign from there.
But yeah, start project makes you kind of,
you have to set it up how, for this project,
it kind of connects to the database.
So that's why I start the project
and store the configuration there.
So if you do start project,
oop.
So I hope this is also complete, but I'm not so sure.
Okay, so if you just start project,
it will ask you a bunch of things.
So a project name, so I would,
you can do anything, but remember this name
because you would use it again
when you use it in the script to connect to the database.
So I would call it workshop, maybe.
Yes, and then okay, here is the,
when it got different if you're using Terminus X.
So if you're just using locally,
you can just press enter and that's it for you.
But for those of you who are using Terminus X,
let's see if I can demonstrate it with my Terminus X.
So, oop, sorry, it should be dashboard.
Yeah, oop.
I hope I have logged in before.
I don't know, I'm not so sure.
Oh, I haven't logged in, but I can just log in.
Logged in, yes.
Ah, right, it's very small, right?
So if you're using Terminus X,
oop, I have other things, don't worry about that.
Oops, then I should be in this one as well.
Okay, so I have other things, don't worry about that.
But what you can do is you will see something like that.
Not my bit warden, sorry about that.
So you'll see something like that, right,
if you're using Terminus X.
So you can go to your profile and then you will see the,
so you will see how you can connect to it.
So now, when you ask here, can you see the last line there?
Yeah, when you ask, oh, what's your endpoint location?
You just have to copy this one.
This is your endpoint location there.
I think we felt the team name, just until .com, right?
Just the domain there.
So clouds.terminusdb.com, and that's your endpoint location.
And then you would also ask other questions,
like what is team?
So when you ask about the team,
so the team will be the team you set up here.
So this will be your team, it will be different from yours,
but just look for the team and then put the team there.
And then also it will ask whether you want to set up
your API key, you can either set it up yourself
in your console like this, or other means.
I know someone just set it up with Python.
So you can say, oh no, I don't need to set it up.
Or you can just say yes and then set it up
by generating an API key and put it there.
So if you have any struggle using terminusx to connect,
then let me know, I'll try to troubleshoot where I go.
But for me, I use it locally, just enter.
Easiest way to do it.
Now, if you look at, so I use Atom, so sorry about that.
If you don't like Atom, I'm using Atom.
I don't care what you think about Atom, but I'm using it.
So you can use other things,
but I'm not saying you have to use Atom.
So in your project, you should now have
this convict.json file.
So you have the name of your database,
your endpoint and your team.
If you have, yeah, you have a different thing
if you're using the terminusx, the endpoint and the team.
I think it will also maybe also ask about your login
or something, just answer the questions
by grabbing the information you have on the dashboard.
So you have something similar to this.
Also you have a schema.
So this is, like the title said, this is an example.
This is not a schema that we're using today, right?
Just a bunch of other things.
But we'll start from here,
because it demonstrates how a schema should kind of look like.
So you'll see that we'll have to import the certain things
because all the objects are actually,
actually all the documents,
including the sub-documents, which is objects,
they are inherited from the document template.
And also all the enums are inherited from the enum templates.
So for the hash key and tag union,
we are not using them today, I think,
so we can just ignore them by deleting them.
So, yes, question.
Yeah, Wacol is, well, history of a Wacol.
So we decided this query language called Wacol,
which we'll try a little bit at lesson seven.
But it's just, it's a very silly naming mistake
that we made, we just called everything Wacol
at the beginning, so it's just like everything
start with a Wacol here.
But even though they are not related to the Wacol query,
but yeah, just a stupid name, sorry about that.
Yeah, so we have to type four characters.
Anyway, I wish I would rename it one day,
but it's still a work in progress.
So here you can see the example of how,
so I'll go through this example first
and then we'll build our own.
So you can see how we can declare a document class.
So this is not a actual document object
because we are building the schema.
The schema is kind of like, like I said before,
this is the class, right?
And then the document itself would be the instance.
This is just the schema,
it's describing how things will look like.
So that's why it's a class.
So this is a country class,
it's inherited from document template.
And then here you can add the docstring here,
which will be used as an explanation.
So remember all this stuff they have,
they talk about all the documents,
they will have an ID, they will have a name,
and then they will have a description.
So this is the name of this class will be this,
and then this is the description.
And then all these attributes
will actually add the attribute to these properties.
So it's just documentation, right?
I won't go through too much detail in it,
it's just how you can actually document it
just like you document your docstring.
So this is very familiar for me
because it's just like NumPy documentation.
Oh, you can also document the whole schema as well.
But again, like this is, you can change it,
but it doesn't matter too much how things function,
just a good practice to document things.
So here is how we make the key of the document work.
So the thing is that we set an underscore key here,
it need to be the key object that we kind of,
oh, I just deleted it.
But yeah, it's a key object that we need to get from here.
So this one won't work now
because I just deleted the hash key.
And hash key just means that use the name field.
So this is how we kind of do the,
tell TerminusDB how to generate the key, right?
We won't make the example too complicated
so we won't mess with the hash key or the literal,
is that called literal key?
I think it's called, I can't remember,
but there's different keys that you can use.
But we just hard code the key here for the document
so we won't play with this setting.
But if you're interested,
you can find all this information in the documentation.
So this is basically saying that,
oh, use the name field
and then generate a hash key based on that.
So but we're not doing that.
So we will delete it anyway, so let's leave it be.
So name is a property of that,
that thing which is a country and is a string.
So it is how we,
is kind of making some attribute
and then using the typing to tell,
to create the schema.
So also if it's a list of string,
you can do it this with list.
So this is just typing.
If you know how to do typing in Python,
this is just how you do it, this typing.
Okay, so if you're new to typing,
don't worry about it too much,
you can just copy the example.
But if you know typing, this is just typing.
So how to make a sub document?
A sub document is, well, this is black doing this for me
because this is too long,
but sub document is just, you can basically just do this.
Let me make it easier.
You just do this.
Just add an empty list to a attribute call
and this was a sub document.
That's how you make this document a sub document.
So this one will have an ID.
You don't have to worry about ID of the object,
of the address because you make it a sub document.
It shouldn't have an ID.
Okay, and it needs to always live
within the document as well.
Yeah, so,
so this is again showing how you can reference another,
so person can link to a person.
So this is an object property.
So this again, this is just like typing.
I'm setting that oh, friends of need to be a set of person.
Anything else I want to tell you?
Oh, maybe enum.
So you can also do other more complicated things
like inherit location from address and code on it,
but we won't go into detail here.
So tech union, I want to show this.
Yeah, forget about tech union, we won't go through it.
So enum is that you just need to,
so this is just like a Python enum, that's how you do it.
It just works slightly differentially than a Python enum
because we have created this custom enum template.
Just have some enum working that when we push it
to TerminusDB, it will do something.
But it's just like making your Python enum.
So it's just like that.
Yeah, so let's start working on our thing.
So let's go back to our blueprint,
talk about the blueprint.
The blueprint, where is it?
I think somewhere here, yeah.
So this is how we're gonna base on this, this page.
We're gonna build a schema.
So first of all, we need an employee object.
So let's go back to our schema.
And okay, so we already have an employee object,
but we don't want it like this.
So it's got a bit different.
So let's start from scratch.
Let me try to delete all this stuff.
So is it okay if I don't use a mic?
Yeah, it will free my hand and I can talk at the same time.
So we have employee.
So it needs to be a document template.
So you put it there.
And this, okay, so like I said,
we don't have to worry about the key
because we are hard-coded IDs
which make things more simple.
But we need to put all the property in.
So what property do we have?
We have a name, right?
So name will be a string.
So this is how you do it.
This name will be a string.
You can also make some doc string here if you want to.
Doc string here if you want to,
but I won't bother with it at the moment.
So name, what else do we have?
We have the title.
All right.
Contact number.
Oh.
Contact number, yes.
Yes, but do we, oh yeah.
Contact number and string, you're right.
No, like that.
Yep, and then what else do we have?
We have address.
Okay, address is interesting
because address will be an address object.
Just like that.
Because we haven't make the address class yet.
That's why we need the quotation.
So in general, I just add quotation to everything
because I can't remember where I put the stuff.
So what else do we have?
We have the, so postcode will be belongs to address.
We have the manager and the team.
So team would be a enum of teams.
Again, I haven't created that yet.
And then also manager would be another employee.
Right?
Kind of like that.
Sorry?
Come here.
Yeah, I'm changing that.
Yeah, this is the file that I generated.
I deleted all the other stuff.
You can see that.
Yeah?
Yeah, it has, but it will be different.
So I rather start from scratch.
Yep.
Yes, correct.
I oversee it.
Then thank you for reminding me.
So optional means that some,
because if you look at the table, right?
If you look at the table,
some of them don't have a manager
because the manager doesn't have a manager.
I remember the first employee, not this one,
first employee, yeah,
so Dynasty doesn't have a manager
because she is the manager herself.
So we will make it optional.
Otherwise, when we created the schema
and then when we insert Destiny in it,
then we have a problem because we are expecting
Destiny to have a manager, which she doesn't have.
So we have to make it optional to give it a,
so it can be a missing data, right?
So it's kind of like, remember,
every data scientist's nightmare, missing data.
So optional just make it like, oh, it's okay to be NA.
It's okay to be missing.
That's basically what it is.
Address, okay, let's move on.
Address is also a document template.
Any questions?
Is that okay?
Yeah.
So addressed is also document template,
but this one is different because this is a document.
So just make it like that.
Sorry for typos.
Okay, and then address will have a bunch of things.
We have, I forgot how I designed it.
I think we have a street number or something like that.
Yep, close code.
So street number,
I think I've made it an integer or something.
Yes.
Don't worry, I would copy and paste at the end.
I would make it meet at the end.
So we can make mistake now.
It's fine, it's fine.
Street name maybe.
STR, and then postcode, yes.
Will be a string because there is some,
because it's UK postcode, there's other letters in it.
We also have a,
I don't remember, oh, town, maybe town.
Let's say town, I don't know.
And then I think that's it.
I think that's it.
Yeah, it's fine.
Like I said, I would cheat at the end
because I want the demo to work.
So it's okay to make mistakes, okay.
So next one is enum, so we have the team.
So we have to create a team.
So team would be a enum template.
Ooh.
Lots of stuff.
So we only have two teams of marketing.
And then you can just do it like that to make it simple.
Yeah, because we don't have a value actually.
We just have two options.
So I think that's it for this.
So yeah, it should work.
But like I said, I would cheat a little bit.
You don't have to,
but you're also welcome to cheat.
After you have created it,
then you can actually check,
maybe check against the one that I've created
in the tutorials.
So would you show how you do the team in there?
Oh, team is enum template.
Instead of document template,
you have to use enum template.
And then when you do that, it's just like,
you can just, so there will be two options here now.
It will be marketing and IT.
You can just assign a empty triple to it
because normally when you do enum,
you assign a value, but we don't have a value.
So we can do it like that.
And you just did like a straight version
of the pillars in marketing
and the multiple marketing?
Yeah, I did that in the example,
but and then I realized that it's more efficient
to do it this way when I insert the data.
So I just do it like that.
Yeah, because otherwise I don't have to fiddle around
with all the underscore,
this blank space become underscore, this stuff,
which may get more complicated.
Because I think when you have the value,
it has to be, it has to be,
it will, you know, internally it will do something with it.
So it's a bit crazy.
So yeah.
Yeah, I think that's more or less what we do for the example.
Let me see if I can pick up the example here.
So, let me have a look.
Okay, schema apply.
This is the one that I already did.
So you see this is more time to make it nicer
or it look like that.
Also typing, we only use optional here.
Okay.
You can also document everything if you want to.
So the thing about it is like,
we won't have this employee from CSV.
This is generated from lesson two or something.
So we won't need it.
So we just copy from the team.
So we just copy the three objects that we have.
Let's copy this.
So I can make sure that it works.
Yeah, like that.
Also I don't need list and set.
It doesn't matter, but if you like black it,
it will just correct it for you.
I love using black.
It's just making so nice.
But yeah, anyway, it's fine.
It's just, you just have to make it work.
So yeah, you can check against, again,
like you can check your,
the one you just written with the,
with the one, the model answer.
If you are confident, you can just move on.
Otherwise you can just copy it to make sure that it works.
But yeah, just not very confident
about my own coding, but yeah.
Okay.
So now we have created a schema.
Make sure you save.
Save, double check.
Okay.
So it's, but it's not there yet.
We just saved the text file.
It's just a text file, right?
How can we put it to TerminusDB?
So I have created this very, very handy command
called commit here.
So now go back to this terminal,
whatever that you're doing.
So TerminusDB, type it correctly.
So use commit.
So this one will just get what you have in a schema.py
and put it as a schema for your database, right?
So this is, oh, again, like this thing we internally,
in my company, we call it a scaffolding tool
because everything is just done for you.
Yeah, like you can do it yourself
with a pattern script as well,
but it's just easier if you do it like this.
So also you can add a commit message.
Like let's say create schema, something like that.
You can add a commit message as well.
So when you do this, this work.
So you can see that workshop,
the database is named workshop, right?
Workshop is created, workshop schema is updated.
So now if you check, if you type TerminusDB log,
you will see that now we have created schema, okay?
So yeah, this scaffolding tool also make it more git-like
so you can do things like that to check
because for the Docker image,
we don't have the web interface like TerminusX.
TerminusX, you can also check it on TerminusX
if you are using TerminusX.
For example, do I have it here?
Yeah, for example, I go to a random,
I go to a random repo that I created before.
I can look at the, yeah,
you can see all the commit message here.
You can see what's inside, right?
So, but if you're using TerminusX, you can check this.
You see a very nice graph here,
but if you're not using, it's fine.
We can just use the command line.
It works well.
Where was it?
Just use the command line, it works well, it's fine.
Sometimes I prefer the command line
rather than the web interface, so.
So that's our...
What was the command line?
Sorry, the...
V3.
Yeah.
You mean the command, the commit command?
Whatever you can do is very easy.
The log, you mean?
Oh yeah, log, yes.
TerminusDB log.
So, commit is one thing.
Sorry?
Commit is the schema.
Yeah, it's pushing the schema to,
it's committing the schema only.
Yeah, you can also update it.
If you, oh, I made a mistake.
You change it, you can commit again.
Then we change it.
Can I ask a question?
There's a concept of like,
branching and learning,
so is this to allow what we're doing
in our organization and the organization's
humanization?
So, you mean like all this binding,
I think, with the SQL, like the schema?
Yeah, what's the purpose of that?
Does this allow for any kind of like,
different things?
Yeah, so those things are something like,
we quite keep like, kind of,
we usually don't do things.
So, what happened is that, for example,
well, I can't tell you how to use it,
no, like I can't tell you when to use it.
You have to decide that, oh,
for example, I want to do some experiment,
I want to change something,
and then you can create a branch
and then message it,
and then if you don't like it,
you can go back.
Or you can, or if you like it,
you can merge it back,
and merge it not here yet,
because we have to,
I think we just finished developing work,
because merge is more complicated.
So, we're not going to do it.
We can, like, if it's a bit too short,
no, we can use a key type.
I'm sorry.
Like, the key type is like,
you can change the key type,
and then you can learn how to include your graph.
Yeah, you can change the schema and the graph,
instance graph, which is where the data is.
Yeah, can you follow the flow?
When you create a branch,
it's just like a,
you create a new...
You know, I know what it's like when you get
the data in my view.
Oh yeah, yeah, I mean,
I can't really, like,
exactly how you learn,
but yeah, the reason why is because
you want to experiment with things,
you know, or maybe you collaborate with someone,
or something like that,
is, yeah, whatever you can imagine.
Okay.
Okay, so,
has someone finished, actually?
Very easy, right?
So, lesson three.
Yeah, we are not doing everything,
so lesson three.
So lesson three, we are inserting the data.
So, we have to look at our data.
We have our employee CSV and the contact CSV.
So, what we have to do is to create a new Fiber file.
So, data.py.
It's a data.py, so,
to start with, we have to import stuff, right?
So, import.
So, terminus db client.
Actually, I normally, how I do is,
I would only import the thing I need, so.
So yeah, again, like,
Vaco is just a seeded name at the moment,
so I know it's still stupid,
but we try to rename it in the future.
So, the client is the,
well, it's just the API client
that it will communicate with your terminus db.
So, I have to create a client,
which I will have to communicate.
So, let me teach you how to use the client first.
So, to create a client, you just need to
create a Vaco client object with the endpoint in it.
So, remember the endpoint was,
you can look at it from the convict.json,
it's convenient, just copy this one,
whatever you're using.
Let's copy it back to here.
So, this will create a client that talks to this endpoint.
So, for those who are using terminus x,
you may also need to use the team equal to that,
and then also,
so it's also use token
equals to true or something like that.
I can double check for you later,
because I think I have it in the,
I have it in the model answer script,
we have this one as well.
But for those who use locally,
you just need to have this,
because you don't need API token lock-in,
so you can just connect like that.
And then, how can you connect to a database?
So, you just connect,
and then db equals to the database,
the name of the database.
Okay, so this is how you connect to a set database.
There are also other ways of using a client,
you can create a database,
you can, all this,
but we just follow the workflow for this use case today.
You can explore a little bit further,
if you're interested.
Yeah, but because we already created a database,
we will just connect to it.
So, here we go.
So, now we have to get our data, right?
So, how we gotta do this is to use a,
you can use pandas,
for those pandas lockers,
if you have pandas installed,
feel free to use it,
sometimes I use it,
but in this example, I use CSV,
because not everybody have pandas,
not everybody like to have something heavy-weight,
like pandas, to do this task.
So, I will also import CSV, okay?
Oops, why are you doing this to me?
I just want CSV, okay.
Right, so, now,
what I can do is to,
to, I need some helpers to help me,
because I need some things to intermediately store the data
when I load things from the CSV.
So, I will need to have a few dictionaries.
So, for example, I will have the employee dictionary,
just create a dictionary,
for employee, I don't know,
like, you can, yeah.
Sometimes, if it's dictionary,
I like to edit, so I know it's dictionary,
but it's a small script,
so it doesn't really matter here, I think.
And also, I want to have a one,
that store the relationship
between the employee and the manager,
because I would need to,
yeah, I would need to handle that later.
There's actually many, many ways of doing it, I think.
The way I'm doing may not be the best one,
so just do whatever you like.
Some of you, of course, you're better than me,
and do better stuff, so you don't have to follow it.
So, I need a manager, so, also an address, yeah.
Do you mind, what we're trying to do,
what we're trying to do in this page now?
Oh, yeah, so what we're trying to do is to, yeah,
read the CSV, and the other one as well,
to put it into, so we use a Python script
to scan through this, and then create some object
that we can put in TerminusDB.
Okay, so TerminusDB require a dictionary,
how can we use that?
Yes, we'll come to it in a bit, so, yeah.
Your question will be answered.
Sorry, I'm also slow, I'm just thinking as I go,
but if you look at the answer, you already know it,
so what we'll do is like, open,
actually I really want to cheat right now,
because I really can't remember.
What am I doing, okay, sorry about that.
Sometimes, just like, I'm still having a jet lag,
I'm like, this is very late for me,
so I'm like, I'm just living on coffee right now,
and I'm like, sometimes doing silly stuff
and don't know what I'm saying, sorry about that.
So, that's lesson three, right?
Lesson two, lesson three, I think, yeah, so.
Yeah, right, so.
Oh, also I forgot to import the schema,
so yeah, that's what I mean, like I'm too tired.
So, we also need to get all the classes
that we created from schema,
that's why you have to question,
I know why, because I forgot something.
So, you have to also import everything
that we created in schema.py,
reason being, we are creating the instance of these classes,
remember this is the schema, this is telling that,
oh, what the document will look like, right?
So, the document itself is the instance of them,
so that's why we have to import it, right?
So, after you import that,
and after you have these dictionaries,
again, I will cheat by copying this,
because yeah, I think that is quite complicated
when I set it up, so yeah, that's why I said,
you can do it better than me,
like by how to read the CSV and stuff,
I'm not doing it very efficiently.
So, okay, so, I will cheat by just copying
the first three lines,
because this is just how you open a CSV, right?
So, I'm now opening the context of CSV,
I think I want to create all the address object first,
that's why I'm doing this.
So, I created a bunch of dictionaries,
which help me to store the stuff intermediately in Python,
before I can put things in terminal,
before I can put things in terminus db.
So, I opened the CSV file, just like, you know,
and then I used the CSV reader to read the files,
which it would give me every single row,
as comma separated, that it would be the list of stuff.
So, here, I would do a next at the beginning,
because I want to skip the header,
again, I'm not very efficient in doing that,
I'm sure that you will have a better solution for this.
So, now, for row in CSV file,
for each row, I will have those four values, right?
I will have, what do I have?
I would have employee, and then the contact number,
and then the address, and then the postcode.
So, what I'm doing here is that I would break them apart,
not break them apart, but like, store them one by one.
So, addresses, so there will be,
there will be their ID, so the employee ID,
so they will be the first one, right?
So, it will be row zero, would be the key of the dictionary,
and then I will store their address,
so I will store their address,
the address will be an address object,
right?
So, address object will have,
what would the address object have?
The address object will have a street number, so,
oh, I can't remember, I can just look at this,
what am I thinking, okay?
So, I have street number, so street number,
what would be the street number?
So, the street number will be actually quite tricky,
let me break it down first,
so the street number will be the,
so now look at it,
so this is zero one two,
so this is this one that I want, right?
So, one marketplace, I want the one,
so it will be the row two,
and then I break it up to what I want, so,
the row two, and then I do a dot split,
and then I want the first one,
or something like that, I'm not so sure,
this is, well, I think it would work.
So, I take the whole address,
I split it up with the spaces,
and then I take the first one, I think.
So, look at that again, so, like I said,
this is more like data handling,
or data, you know, we just break things up,
and put them into their place, so,
street name, street name,
or just street here, I think I call it.
So, again, row two split,
this time I want to split with the comma, I think.
Over here, I want the comma as well, sorry about that.
No, this one, no, it's a space, because it's,
so I split it by the comma,
and then I want the, huh, it is tricky.
So, maybe I should do it like this, so,
split by the comma first, right?
And I take the first one, and I split it again,
and then I would put them into,
street number will be the,
will be first one of it,
and then this one with the second one of it.
Okay, so I split it with the comma,
and then the first one will be the street number,
and the street name, and I split it again with the spaces,
and then I just take the two,
two different things,
I think you can do it like this, right, like street,
something like that.
I think you can do it like that, I think.
Correct me if I'm wrong.
Sometimes I don't know what I'm doing.
Okay, so, split it and put it into the thing,
and then you can also do the town, I think, the town.
Okay,
okay, row two, and then this time,
I want the second one of this, right?
So, and then, after you have this, you can put it here.
You can put it like, oh, street number will be street number,
right, and then street,
be street,
and then town will be equals to town,
or something like that, and then,
so you just create a bunch of,
so what we're doing here in principle is,
I just create a bunch of address instance,
and then for each instance, they are the sub-documents,
and then they will have the properties,
and the properties, I get it from the CSV.
That is what I'm doing here.
So all this, also, I will store them
as an object within dictionary.
The key of the dictionary will be the city,
the key of the dictionary will be the ID of the thing.
Okay, so this is how I do it.
You can also have the postcode later,
but I will put in the postcode later when I read the,
what do I have the postcode in here, sorry.
Let me see.
Oh, the postcode is, yeah, the postcode is the postcode,
so it will be the zero, one, two, three,
and the first thing in the CSV.
So I will put the postcode.
So what I'll do is that,
just so, this time this is already an address object,
so I can do postcode,
equals to the third object in the row, something like that.
Does it make sense?
Or does it not make sense?
Well, I'm crazy.
I think in the model answer, I do it differently,
but I hope you get an idea, so it's just like,
now every, so now every value of those,
the values in the dictionary are address objects
that I created, and later I can put them in the,
in TerminusDB.
So I will actually cheat a little bit and skip all this,
because this is just, like I said, it's just data,
data managing, how you can split up all the CSV
and then model it into different objects.
But instead of me struggling to,
with my very sleepy brain to make it work,
I would just copy this and then I would explain it.
I think I explained a little bit as well,
but I think this will be better if I explain that in full.
Oh, so here, so this is what it's supposed to be like.
So here you see that I, for each row,
I would break it up into different things.
So the contact number is,
so I created the contact number, this is what, okay.
So I have the contact number as a dictionary,
so I also have always, the key is always the ID
of the employee, and I will store them,
and I also break up the street address,
and then I would create address object like I did here,
and I just put everything together like that.
So these are the address instances,
they are the address object that we created.
We just store them with the key being the ID of the employee,
I store them in the dictionary,
which we will be putting it in later, haven't done it yet.
So same with the employee CSV,
I read all the information there,
and then, so this is a bit tricky, the team,
because it's supposed to be like this, right?
So this one, if I don't do it like that,
it should be team.it or team.marketing, right?
But this needs to be in the code,
so that's why I use eval to do it like that.
So that's why it's easier to just call it it and marketing,
because I can just read it and I just lower case
and then do eval with it.
But in enum, you should do it like team.id
or team.marketing, that's why it's the eval there.
So also I artificially create ID for it,
it's how I hard coded it, I read the,
so role zero will be 001, 002, right?
So I just created employee slash 001, employee slash 002,
that's how I create a unique ID for them,
it's not the best way to generate,
I think the best would be make terminus DB creative for you,
but I just want to make it simple
and not mess with extra features, so.
Yeah.
And address, I put the address in,
I put the addresses in, so you can see that,
remember the address, all the values in the address
dictionary are the address object we created, right?
So now I just put it in, so a property,
so this address property, right, this address property
of the employee would be an address object, okay?
Does that make sense?
And the contact number team will be the team
that we create with eval here, okay?
So how do you use the address property?
How will it affect the contact number team?
Yes, it's because this address role zero,
remember this is the, so addresses become a dictionary
with the key that's 0102034,
the values will be this address objects that we created, okay?
So we just put that in here.
I temporarily store them in dictionary
because I have two CSV to read,
that's why I temporarily store them in dictionary,
but then I can put it, but then I get it back
from the dictionary and put it there
as a property of the employees.
So when you see how I do the manager, maybe it's clearer,
because like manager, right now I only store like a map page,
it's just a map page from one ID to another ID right now.
So we haven't put the manager yet, actually.
So how we put the manager in is to use this.
So I get all the mappings,
because I want to read the whole CSV
and understand all the mapping before I put it there.
Because for example, if I haven't created a manager yet,
so I don't have a manager to put it in here, which is bad.
So that's why I store the mapping of the manager first
and then later I can get back.
So I use the employee ID of the employee
to get back the employee object
and I can just dot manager.
So if you don't want to do it this way,
you can just like do it similar to this.
You can just use the employees and then the ID
and then dot address equals to address and then this one.
Yes.
So here, how we design it is that addresses
are sub-documents.
So they have to live inside the employee.
Once they go into the Terminus DB,
the addresses need to live inside the employee's object.
They can't live by themselves.
If you want to address to be able to live by themselves,
you have to create it as a document, not as a document.
Yeah, so if you want to just link the address
and the employees,
so you can have a bunch of address floating around.
You can also set what their owner is
by linking them to the employee,
but then they have to become their own document.
But in this case,
because we make the address a sub-document or an object,
so sub-document doesn't have an ID, right?
It needs to live within a document.
So you can imagine all this stuff.
Actually, you don't need to have an address sub-document.
If you don't want to,
you can just have a bunch of these things.
You can just have address street, address street number,
address name, no, address street name, all that stuff.
You can just...
Mm-hmm.
I don't quite get your question.
So are you talking about exactly this use case
or imagine that we don't have the employee?
Yeah, yeah, maybe that's easier when we talk one-to-one.
So in this case,
every employee has to have an address,
and the address has to be living inside an employee
when it got created in the database.
In Python, it's fine.
In Python, whenever Python allows, you can do it,
but because now we only put it in Python,
we haven't put it in TerminusDB yet.
So it's just that the limit is your Python knowledge,
basically, of what Python allows you to do.
So yeah, now it comes to the last bit.
How we can put all these...
So we have a bunch of objects.
So we have a bunch of employees' documents
that live inside this dictionary.
But how can I put that in a TerminusDB?
So this is how.
So the last thing we have to do is to...
So we already connected,
so we can already use this client.
So how can I use this client?
So what I can do is to insert documents.
So what should I insert?
I should insert all these employees back, right?
So I think I just call the employees.values,
and then use it as a list.
Something like that, I think.
I'm not sure if I would double check.
So I just get all the employees from the dictionary
and put it into TerminusDB.
Yeah, something like that.
And you can also add the commit message as well.
So I'll just click this.
Yeah.
So I just grabbed all these employee objects, four of them.
You don't need the address object because it already...
So remember, we already put them in the employees object,
and they should not be living by themselves.
They should always live inside employee objects.
So it's okay, we don't have to insert them separately.
We only need to insert the employees object.
It will include the address already.
So to get all of them, put them in a list,
and then put them using the insert document,
and then you can add a commit message to make it nicer.
Adding four employees.
So in theory, this one should work.
So let's test it out.
Okay, so let's test it out.
So this time, I just run the Python scripts of Python
in search data.py,
and then doesn't have an error message.
Good sign, but we don't know.
So let's have a look at the log.
Oh, so we have another commit, which is good.
So I've done something, at least.
But is it correct?
We don't know.
How are we gonna do it?
So terminus db, and then all docs.
This is how we do it.
But look at all the documents.
So wow, a lot of things.
So these are the four employees that we have inserted.
So if you look at it, address will be this,
is the address.
So you can see that even though address has an ID,
terminus db won't allow it to be its own thing.
So you always need to live inside the employee object here.
Okay, so yeah.
This is how it looks like inside terminus db.
So it is in JSON-LD format.
So you can also, if you can write this,
you can insert it directly.
But for me, myself, I find it easier to write script like this.
Like this is already complicated enough, right?
So if you also have to construct a JSON like this,
then I would be, no, I don't want to do that.
So yeah.
So both the employee and the address are documents?
Yeah, the employee's documents, address are sub-documents.
Sub-documents is object which doesn't have an ID.
Even though you can see that, oh, no,
but you were lying because there's an ID here.
But this one is the ID that terminus db generated for it
to use internally.
You should not be able to give it an ID.
Yeah, it should not be visible to you actually,
but you just print everything.
So it's used internally, but not for your use.
So it shouldn't have an ID.
That's why.
And also if you look at it, it's very weird, right?
It has the employee address and an address like that.
And then that's how you see the ID.
You know this is a document because it lives
within another object which is employee for 004.
So both the command and the c is output?
Hmm?
What was the command?
Command is all docs.
So this one, all docs.
So in case you forgot, you can always use dash dash help.
It will give you all the command options.
Yeah.
So okay, now we have everything.
So fun bit, we got to do query using cryptos.
So now it's lesson seven.
So lesson seven, we got to do some query
with what we have learned.
So again, lesson seven, we will create new file,
new Python file.
So mark all query.py.
Okay, so this time we need the client of course.
So let's do the same thing from,
kind of spell it.
NSDB client, import again the Wacl client.
This time we also need the query.
So we have created the Wacl query
which we now mainly use for queries.
So Wacl query.
Also we noticed that we have to type this a lot.
So what I'll do is just shorten it
just like pandas, right?
PD or NumPy or MP, you know.
Yeah, why not?
Just to make it shorter.
So this one, I'm getting myself ready to make queries.
So how Wacl query works is that you would have to,
so Wacl query, first of all,
warning, Wacl query is very complicated.
Yes, because today we just learned triple.
If you can do the query today, it's really good
because you know, you can already use what you learn
and make some queries and make some logical reasoning.
But if you really want to dive it down,
it will require some practice.
Even for me, sometimes I have to, you know,
wrap my head around and think,
oh, how can I query it?
Things like that.
So we'll give it a try, we'll give it a try.
So again, we need a client, so let's do that.
We can actually copy and paste what we did.
For those of you connected to Terminus X,
it's quite complicated, so just copy it.
Just do the same thing, connect to a database as well.
So we just do this.
Similar to what we did before, nothing to add here.
So now we create a query object.
So for me, whenever I do the query,
I will first want to look at at least some of the things,
not everything, but like, if you can look at everything,
that's good, because you have an idea how it looks like.
Sometimes the database is too big,
then maybe you have to not query everything.
But I'll show you how to query everything.
So you can make a query by using WQ.
Or you can type the whole thing,
but I just shot this WQ.
So it just needs to be an object itself.
And then you can start query things.
Like for example, you can do like triple,
and then ask for triple or something.
You'll go into it later.
Right now I just want to do star,
which star is just like star in SQL,
it gives you everything.
But use it carefully, because if your database is big,
this will probably have consequences.
So right now our database is not big, so we can do that.
So let's try to see everything as triple inside the database.
That is not like all docs.
All docs you can see all the documents as documents, right?
They are very nicely presented to you
in the JSON-LD format as documents.
But now we also look at it as JSON-LD, but as triples.
So it's going to be very interesting.
So this is our query, but we have to execute it.
So how we do it is to do .execute,
and then put a client in it.
Oh, actually this will give you the results.
So let's just print it out to see what's happening.
Scary stuff, okay.
Oh, actually what is better is to use preprint,
because it will be messy.
I love using preprint, so maybe .pprint.
So let's print everything within the database as triples.
Let's see what happens.
So go back to our beloved terminal.
So now what I want to do is to do the query thing.
What was that called again?
Awako query, yes.
Whoa, what's this?
Look at all this.
Wow, it's a very, very big,
well, even though our database was small,
it's only four objects.
It contains a lot of triples in it.
It's, wow, all this stuff.
What are these?
So let's have a deeper look inside.
So let's pick something that we kind of understand.
So let's look at,
here we have a, okay.
So we have, what does this mean?
So we have an object, okay.
So, oh, by the way, for all this query,
when you get a result,
so it's kind of like API getting the result,
but your result will be stored in bindings.
So we just look at bindings most of the time.
So we have object, predicate, and subject,
because remember all triples,
they are object, predicate, and subject, right?
Well, the order is a little bit different here,
but doesn't matter.
Order doesn't matter in the dictionary,
so unless it's auditing,
but order doesn't matter.
So we have object, predicate, subject.
So there's these three things.
So these are all the triples, every triples,
that you can find in our instance graph.
You can also get it from the schema graph if you want to,
but we are not doing it right now.
We only look at the instance graph.
So these are all the instance, all the documents,
but as triples, that's how it looks like.
So very interesting, right?
You have something that is employee slash O one,
so that's the subject,
and then the type of it is an employee.
So it tells you something.
It tells you some information about this object.
Employee slash O one.
It's an employee.
That's what it's saying.
I'm trying to translate it.
So another thing, let's look at this.
Whoop.
So employee slash O one,
schema, contact number,
and then object is another dictionary.
It's saying it's a XSD string,
and then it's a string.
The value is a string.
So it's saying that employee O one
has a property called contact number,
which is a string.
The value is that one.
Okay, so this is how it looks like
within TerminusDB as triples.
So this is how a knowledge graph look like, actually.
Yes?
So where does the concept of ranges come to be?
Yes, good question.
So if you look at this.
So this contact number, right?
What do you think the range is?
The string, yes, XSD string is the range.
And the domain is the employee O one.
Okay, this is, huh.
Huh?
Because of?
Yes, so this XSD string actually is telling you
that it's actually a string.
Because everything is a string here, right?
It just, well, I just print everything out there all string,
but it means that that value there is not a number,
it's a string.
Even though I don't have the bracket, right?
Imagine it's only this one month free, free, six, seven.
It can be an integer, it can be a string.
So because the type is saying XSD string is a string.
That's how you declare a type.
So that's why you don't have the problem of,
sometimes Excel thought that,
if you import a CSV in Excel,
sometimes it thought that, oh, it's an integer,
but actually it's a string.
So then you lose all these trailing zeros and stuff.
So it won't happen here because we have the type.
There's no ambiguity, there's no guessing.
That thing happened in Excel because Excel was guessing.
But in here, there's no guessing.
So this is how it looks like.
And by using this knowledge, we can ask some questions.
So in lesson seven, we have make some assumption.
We have an imaginary situation
that we want to contact someone in the company.
So let's take this out.
It's scary when you take this out.
So, okay, so let's think that,
so instead of looking at these two CSV,
we want to find the contact information of Darcy, right?
So we only know the name of Darcy
because we are not working in a company.
We don't have access of this spreadsheet or something.
We just know that, oh, I want to ask a question.
I want to have the contact number of this person.
How can I do that?
By asking the database.
So let's ask the database.
So let's make a query.
So query equals to, oh, before that,
what I do is like, because remember,
every string we have to declare the type, right?
Otherwise, ThomasDB don't know that it's a string.
Well, for Darcy's case, the name is obviously a string,
but because we don't guess things,
we always have to declare the type.
So what I do is that I create this state called,
so Darcy, I will have to declare it as say, wacl string.
So this is how I declare it, it's a string.
And then it's, what's the name of Darcy?
Oh, sorry, where is it?
Yeah, here, this is Darcy's full name.
I'll just copy it.
It would be nice if I can just do like a fussy search
for anybody who called Darcy,
but well, we are not stepping into that yet.
So let's just look at it.
If I know the full name of Darcy,
I want to find her contact detail.
So before that, I have to declare
that it's not a normal string, it's a wacl string.
It's a string type that we use in ThomasDB, okay?
So now we really make the query.
Query equals to wq.triple.
So what questions should I ask?
Okay, so I have a person, right?
So we have to make a variable in the query
because we don't know the ID of Darcy, right?
I don't know what Darcy's ID within the database,
so I will just ask someone that I know, a person.
So that name, so I have to do schema, I think.
Schema like that, name, I would double check.
So I have to say that, oh, there's a person,
name is Darcy, oh, not this one, but the wacl string.
The other way won't work
because it doesn't know that it's a wacl string.
So this person, so this query, if I run it,
it would give me the ID of Darcy, but it's not helpful
because I want to know the contact number, right?
So I have to add another one, add some condition,
add another triple.
The other triple will be the same person
who have a contact number.
And then I also don't know the contact number,
so phone number maybe, phone number.
Give me the number.
Like that, right?
I can't remember actually.
Oh, like this?
Oh, yeah, like that, yeah.
Actually I would double check whether I have the type
because I really can't remember whether I need to add or not.
So let me double check.
Yeah, I need to add, so it should work like that.
Sometimes I also have to reference it back
because this syntax is complex.
But I'm showing you the basic of the basics
so you can do it deeper when you want to yourself.
So, okay, so this is how I make it very simple for a query
is that I ask questions and then I will get the answer back.
That's variables, okay?
So now I want to know the phone number is a variable.
Well, I also accidentally got the ID, but well, I don't mind.
So when I have to query, I have to get the results from the query.
So result equals to query.execute.
Put the client in here, remember to put the client.
So now I should have a result back.
And I can print it out actually.
Let's print it out and see what happens.
Hello, yeah, we can debug as we go.
So let's do this again, right?
Clean it up and then do this and,
oh, I doesn't got anything.
I must have a typo or something.
Wait a second, let me fix it.
Oh, yeah, I spread it wrong or something.
Don't worry, I can just copy this.
Yeah, that's why it's quite difficult
because for someone like me, oh, no, not here.
For someone like me that make typos a lot,
then it's quite challenging because it's difficult to debug.
Yeah, I got it, okay.
Let's replace this.
Yeah, I just felt something wrong.
So yeah, let's try again.
So, yes, I got something back.
I asked the right question this time.
So there are the findings.
So this time we have the bindings.
So we have the person.
So actually, I accidentally also got the ID,
but I didn't care.
But what's important is that I have the phone number,
which is this one here, right?
So you can peel everything off like an onion.
You can peel it off and find the answer here.
But I think I already did in the code in the model answer here.
So, yeah, if I found it, then I just go to the bindings,
get it, and then get the phone number and the value and stuff.
Otherwise, I can't find anything.
So this is a very nice Python code.
We'll just paste it here.
We'll print out the result for you, thank you.
Yeah, so this time if I run it,
it will be very nicely presented to me.
All right.
Yes, now I have the contact number.
Good.
So this is how you can query by using the triple.
There are simpler way to do it.
It's called query document.
Then you can get all the information about Darcy, actually.
But, well, this is more fun.
It's more fun to just make triple and stuff.
I love it.
So now ask a more difficult question,
which I think is better to answer with triple
than query documents, is that now imagine Darcy is on holiday
and I really need to talk to someone in a company
about something.
So maybe I should talk to Darcy's manager, right?
So how can I do that?
Because, well, imagine if you are making SQL query,
you'll have to first find the manager of Darcy
and then find the phone number of Darcy's manager.
But in Wacol, we can just traverse the graph
instead of joining it back using the key.
Remember the employee ID is the primary key
and then you have to join back together
to find who is the manager of who.
We can just traverse the graph
and use triple to find the answer.
So here's how we do it.
So this time, Darcy's on holiday,
so we make another query.
So query is, so this time,
so I know someone who's called Darcy,
so let's get this begin, right?
But this time instead of getting Darcy's number,
I want to get who's Darcy's manager.
So I do the similar thing,
but it's just I'm a one manager.
So I want manager,
and this time I should call the manager a manager
because I don't even know the name of the manager, okay?
I don't know anything about the company, imagine.
So I would have,
I have two variables here so far.
I would have a person, which is Darcy,
but I don't know the ID of Darcy.
And the ID of Darcy's manager,
but it's not good enough because I know the ID,
but I don't know what's the name
and the contact number of this person, so, of the manager.
So what I'm gonna do is to also get the phone number
of Darcy's manager.
So it's very similar to what we did here.
So we just recycle the code.
So here is that person, I want manager.
And then also maybe I should have the name as well
just to be polite and be able to call the person's name
on the phone number.
So I want to have the manager's name.
So is that phone number, maybe I should be manager name.
So something like that.
So if I run this query, I should be able to get
Darcy's ID, which is person.
I should be able to get the manager's ID, which is manager.
I should be able to get the phone number of the manager
and the name of the manager.
So again, I can do result.execute.
And I put the client in it, remember to put the client in it.
Oh, result equals to, sorry, query.result.
Because we have merging result and query together now.
I'm like so crazy.
So let's print the binding of it.
Let's try to just imagine it works and print a binding
of it to see whether we can see something.
Code bindings, yes.
Let's see if it works.
Oh, manager, manager, man.
This one?
Yeah.
I love this like live debugging.
I wish my robot can do the same thing.
It will tell me you have to talk.
Okay, well, right.
Let's see.
Okay, so ignore what we did before.
So we have the binding, which I have a manager's ID, yes.
Our manager's name is a string, it's called Destiny.
Oh, good.
So we have ID for the person, which is Darcy.
And we have the phone number of Destiny this time.
So we can probably print it out like before
to make it nicer.
So if you copy the code from the model answer,
it should print out very nicely for you.
Yeah.
Copy the whole thing and paste it the whole thing.
Okay, and it should work.
Let's see.
Yes, so now I have the manager's name
and the manager's contact number.
So this is a taste of how you can make use
of Wacom Query to actually,
when you see how I do it, right,
of course I think about that before,
but this is exactly my thought process
when I'm creating this query.
I'm like asking question.
I'm asking, oh, what do I want to know?
And then making variables to link up all this information.
It's just like linking triples to build a world.
But instead of building the world for sure,
I have variables in it.
But by answering, so what happened is that
Thomas DB will take this query and then put it,
so you have some variables, you have a hole in it.
It's fine, it's okay.
You just put this on top of the graph
and then the answer will shine through this hole
and come back to you as an answer.
So this is very efficient.
Imagine you have a big company
and you have to do a join,
like using the table and join it back to itself again.
Or maybe you have to also join a contact table together
and all this stuff to get this answer,
which is crazy.
Now you just need to think of how I can get the answer
by using the variables and go through the graph
and then you can get the answer.
So this is very different from what we know.
You run applications like
counting, working with it,
keeping the group of the group in mind.
Yes, exactly.
We also have that in Wacol, but that's more complicated.
And if you're interested,
you can have a look at the documentation.
Yeah, it's available there.
There's the count.
If you look at the Wacol documentation on the website,
actually, yeah, we're still building it,
but yeah, we do have the counts.
We do have the goodbye and all this stuff,
but that will be more complicated.
That's very scary for me to do those things,
but it's available.
That's all I can say, tell you.
Yes.
You talked about the impact in the TRIBLE packet.
Why is there a B colon compound
with the app team on the community climate for us?
Yes, the B colon actually is a variable.
So you see that here,
all the B colon will get the answer at the binding.
You see all the bindings.
It's giving me the manager, manager name.
So these are the variables we created
by using the B colon here.
So that's the answer that we will get back.
We can also use this to link up different questions,
different TRIBLES.
That's how we do it.
Also for the schema thing,
this is just saying that it's a property.
So it's a property from the schema.
It's just saying that, oh, what is this manager?
Because manager is a name that's very ambiguous.
But a schema just means, oh, look it up.
Look at the schema.
So yeah, it's a property.
It's declared in the schema.
Look at it.
So that's why there's this.
Are there other side-frames?
There could be, there could be a team-wide or other?
There are.
I have to look it up.
I'm not so sure, but if you look at the big,
this star thing before,
all you can see are the schemas.
Usually the thing we start with add
is some keyword that we use internally in TerminusDB.
So there are also other stuff like RDF.
So RDF is declared because we are knowledge graph, right?
So it's a hidden feature.
So every graph hidden, there's an RDF document
that kind of store all the default things for the graph,
so all the settings for the graph.
So this is RDF type.
It's just saying that it's a type keyword
that is declared in the RDF file internally,
so something like that.
So also XSD is a standard type or something like that.
So yeah, there are a few of these things,
but yeah, it's more advanced, I would say,
if you want to dive deeper.
So yeah.
Yes.
Can you describe in some detail
how this makes a difference,
if you say MOTO or NOSECRO,
where you're looking at some sort of document
and you're making a mark on the object
in the document,
how is that coming into your graph
to say they're for a different page and then,
I think you call it that in Terminus?
Yeah, so.
So NOSECRO, well.
And why do you use MOTO again?
Yeah, NOSECRO is the thing,
it's like how we do this triple phase,
because NOSECRO is more similar
to the document interface that we created.
This is what is more unique to Knowledge Graph
that we are looking at at the end here.
So a document, that's why we have both available,
because this is very scary.
Unless you are from an academic background
that you deal with as an academic Knowledge Graph
all the time, then you're afraid,
humans will make sense, this is no problem.
But most people can work with what the document interface
or the syntax closer to NOSECRO much easier,
because it's very structured in a way that is,
oh, these are the object
and this is the property of the object.
So it's more like an object-oriented programming,
the object-oriented programming.
So at the beginning, when we have TerminusDB,
so we only have this, so it's a Knowledge Graph.
So everything is a Knowledge Graph.
Internally, it works like that.
For someone who worked with it, you need to understand it.
And then later, we discovered that it's too limited.
So we created a document interface
that you could actually use for syntax to work with.
So that's why today, we are trying to use both.
We tried a little bit of the document interface
at the beginning, it's simpler,
it's got us to work so faster, you can see,
you already have a simple Knowledge Graph very quickly,
it's been an hour or so.
But then, at the end, we try to apply what we learned today,
but it takes practice to be very fluent with it.
So we kind of start to use a little bit of triple,
understanding how triple works and stuff.
How triple works and stuff.
Ooh, good, I hope I did okay.
So you can see that TerminusDB can work with both.
So I think it's the advantage.
You can use both.
Yes?
If you have a more than knowledge graph,
it may be often a more kind of connection,
more kind of relationship,
and you will find a lot of it,
you don't need to keep a label,
because maybe, oh, what's that the algorithm is?
That came from a way to do kind of self-collection graphs.
Are you thinking about the A-class, like this,
or something like this?
Yeah, you mean the graph.
It's kind of a lot of what people know.
So you're talking about the graph algorithms, right?
Like, oh, how many neighbors are there?
Those are not available yet, I can tell you.
Because I know it's available in new projects,
but actually, you just need to,
actually, it could be something that just add on,
because our core team, well, we are a small team,
the core team basically work on the inner working of this,
try to optimize it, build a foundation.
I would say this is the foundation.
All those things that you mentioned,
the graph algorithm and stuff,
are the stuff that you can edit on top.
It takes time to implement, but it's not as difficult as,
like, to, our most effort now is to polish this,
to make this foundation work well.
And then, when we grow, when the company grow,
when the team grow, then we can add those algorithms.
You just need someone who just specialize
in writing those algorithms, put it on top.
I won't say it's not difficult,
but it's just like, it's not the main focus for us right now.
So, well, hopefully in the future, we have those.
Yeah.
Yes?
Sorry, I just wanted to ask you,
but so we've been talking about graph editing,
so you said you do that in a way that you know is an edge.
You know, and can you help us understand
how triples equate to those in the way
that you can get all the data?
Yeah, I would say that you can think.
So, yeah, I also have the same question
when I started to use the triple and all this stuff
to understand semantic knowledge graph.
Sometimes it seemed that we are talking
about two different languages because, you know,
oh, triple is so big, you know,
you can also describe the properties of that.
But if you think about it, right,
if we can look at it as the document interface.
So, if we look at the documents,
you can imagine documents are notes, right?
And then you can imagine the object properties
are the edges that we talk about.
But then you will be like,
oh, what about the data type properties?
Then it's a bit complicated.
Then you have to also consider the XFD types,
the literal types as also notes,
which doesn't feel correct.
So, if this is a graph that you ignore
all the data types, properties,
if you only look at object properties,
it's like what we said, they're objects, they're notes,
and they are the lanes, which are the edges.
But if you include data type properties, it's more,
and then it doesn't seem that it aligns.
Does it make sense?
Yeah.
Any questions?
I don't know about the time,
what time does this tutorial end?
Double check?
Yeah, sorry, I'm so bad with the time.
I think we, okay, we still have half an hour.
So, I would say that the rest of the time
you can feel free to play around with the other lessons.
Or if you have more questions
and you want to ask me one-to-one,
or yeah, then feel free to do so.
I think I would leave this podium,
but I would come around,
and then you can play around with stuff.
You can ask me questions more one-to-one
so I can answer it better,
because sometimes I can't hear you or something.
So, yeah, so the rest of the time is yours.
Do whatever you like.
Or if you have other plans,
you want to leave early, it's fine.
You're welcome to do that as well.
But I will stay here and answer your questions, okay?
So, oh, oh, I forgot the closing.
So, let me quickly do the closing,
and then you can do whatever you like, okay?
So, just a few slides just to close it.
So, this is summarize what we have learned.
So, we have learned a few things.
We have learned that what is Knowledge Graph.
We've learned that Knowledge Graph model,
that's something that they can do.
That's how they work different from the relational database,
and there's lots of good questions about how they compare.
There's like what's the advantage of thinking things
like the scary triples.
Also, how we have already achieved
how we can model a data from 2Ds
with the spreadsheets or CSVs into a graph.
And then we also try to play with triple,
try to use triple to ask questions and make queries.
So, I think we have achieved quite a lot today.
So, you should be proud of yourself.
If you have more questions, this is how to find a team.
We have Discord, if you use Discord, join that.
And like my colleagues, they are more knowledgeable than me.
They can answer your questions.
Sometimes specific questions about internals of the database
or questions about JavaScript,
how to use the drafts for quiet and all that stuff.
Please come and talk to us, love to talk to you.
And I think that's it, so do whatever you like,
and I will stay here and answer your questions, okay?
Thank you.