I'm super happy to be here.
And in case you don't know me yet, let me introduce myself.
Hi, I'm Jessica, but you can call me Jess.
My pronouns are she and her.
And I work as a senior developer advocate at Auth0.
If you don't know what Auth0 is, not a problem.
We are an identity platform, so we make it as easy as possible for you to implement authentication
on your applications so that you can focus on the fun stuff that you want to do for your
users, right?
We all want to do that.
I'm also an instructor at Data Boot Camp and LinkinD Learning.
I'm Brazilian, and I have the first podcast about data science in Brazil called Pizza
de Dados.
My last project that I just created is called Git Fishes, and it's a collection of Git
study cards.
So if you need help with Git, check it out.
Also, you may find me on most social networks under the handle Jess Temporal, so if you
are shy and no one that asks questions right here, you can find me on Twitter later.
Cool?
But enough about me.
And a little disclaimer before we get started.
So I come from Brazil, and I know for a fact that most countries that don't speak English
as a first language prefer to call JSON Web Tokens JWT.
But if you come from an English-speaking country, you might hear the word JOT.
So I'm going to be using those two terms along the presentation, so just get used to that.
It's a little weird, I might be honest.
The first time I ever heard about this, I was like, oh, interesting, something new.
But anyways, you're going to get used to it along this presentation.
So it is impossible to start talking about JSON Web Tokens without mentioning the amazing
effort that was made to create a collection of standards and specifications that is known
as the Hosea specification.
Hosea stands for JSON Objects, Signing, and Encryption, and it brings light to many things
that we need to work with JSON Web Tokens and other objects that we might need while
working on the web.
So part of the Hosea specification is the IFC, the Request for Comments 7519, that is
commonly known as the JOT or JWT specification.
And that's going to be our main focus for today.
Let's discuss it.
So a JOT or a JSON Web Token usually is a standardized string that represents some information.
So it conveys some meaning depending on context.
But let's take a closer look.
So we have three words, JSON, which means how we're going to structure the information
that we want to pass from 1.8 to 1.8.
So JSON Web Token is the part where everything happens, where we make this information go
from one point to another.
And the curious thing is it is a very space-constrained environment.
So we need to be mindful of the information we are carrying along these points.
And the last part, the token, as a friend of mine likes to say, it usually is a unique
identifier that conveys some meaning.
So if you've never seen a JSON Web Token before, for those that are new to it, I introduce
you to your first JSON Web Token.
At a first glance, this gigantic string looks like a random sequence of characters and numbers,
but actually it has a structure.
So usually a JSON Web Token has three parts.
The header, that's the beginning of my string.
The payload that is right in the middle is also known as the body.
And the signature is the last part, one of the most coolest ones, if I do say so myself.
So the header usually has the information about the token.
So what token it is, the token ID, and what type of algorithm was used for signing the token.
It is a JSON object, and if you're a part-time user, you probably know that it looks like
a dictionary, right?
And this JSON object is then turning into a basic string so that we can make the first
part of our token.
Then we have the payload.
And the payload carries information about a given resource.
In a login scenario, this means a resource is my user.
So for example, here I have information about me in a scenario that I was like picturing it.
So I have the name of the user, I have what it prefers to be called, I have the sub, which
is the subject of the token, and in this case, it would be the user ID, and so on.
The cool thing about the payload is that it also has the information about when the token
expires.
So you also have that in there.
It's one of the steps that you do for verifying a token.
It's also basic CIFO encoded, and you can take that and decode it anywhere.
So that is one very important thing about the payload and the header, because they are
a little bit different from the signature, is that each key value pair here is what we
call claims.
And there are actually three types of claims.
So the first type of claims are the reserved claims.
These claims came from the JOD specification.
So they are very important because these are the claims like the expiration date, where
you can check if a token is expired or not.
They have information on who issued that token.
And be mindful, this is just an example.
And the second type we have are the public claims.
They are standardized in a way by IANA, one of the organizations on the internet.
The public claims are made to carry the most common information we usually share when using
a token.
So for example, if you were to give the information of the first name of the user and the last
name, IANA has a standard that says, oh, we're not going to call it first name.
We're going to call it given name.
And we're not going to call it last name, but we're going to call it family name, and
so on.
There is a long list.
The idea is to provide a way for interoperability between systems to happen so everybody would
be speaking, well, the same language.
And the last type of claims that we have are the private claims.
And they are the coolest because the private claims are supposed to be anything that you
want, anything that your systems need for properly functioning.
So as long as you keep a valid JSON object, you can put anything there, anything really.
But that is a caveat.
First, the more information you put on the JSON token, the bigger the output string you're
going to have to pass along the request that you make.
So be mindful of the data you put in there.
Keep only the relevant data is a general advice.
The second one is because both of the header and the payload are only base64 encoded, we
don't put sensitive data in the token.
Well, because anybody that has internet connection could Google up how to decode a base64 string.
It doesn't even have to code.
And they could get a hold of that data.
So we don't want that to happen.
We don't want the data to be publicly available if it is sensitive.
Now you know about the header and the payload.
Let's talk about the signature.
And the signature is really special because the signature takes the header and the payload
to happen.
And depending on the algorithm, a secret or a key.
And the interesting thing is right here I have a symmetrical algorithm that's HMAC SHA256.
It only takes a secret.
But you may notice that my secret is your 256-bit secret.
Not that safe.
In real life you would have something like this.
A random string that is generated has a lot of characters to make everybody's lives a
little bit safer.
So we take the header and the payload together with the secret and a key for signing the
token.
Now, speaking of algorithms, we have two types.
This one takes the secret.
The first one is the symmetrical algorithm.
And you can think of a secret.
You don't want to share that with everybody, right?
So the secret is shared in between the party that signs the token and the party that needs
to verify the token.
But there is a second type of algorithm.
That's the one that I like the most.
The asymmetrical ones.
Because the asymmetrical algorithms takes a pair of two keys.
For one for signing, the private key, and one for verifying the token, the public key.
And you can keep the private key safe and secure and you shouldn't.
And you can publish the public key so that anybody could verify the token that you signed
to make sure that it was really you.
If you were implementing a web application, for example, and if you were using Auth0,
for example, Auth0 would create the tokens for you and you could get the public key from
a well-known endpoint so that you could validate that the token came from Auth0.
You could also validate whether or not this token must tamper with because the signature
allows us to do that.
Because the only person that should be able to sign the token is the person that is holding
the secret or the private key.
Keeping your data a little bit more safer.
Now, speaking of keys, there is a format for you to share your keys alone.
And if you're following OpenID Connect, you're going to have an endpoint that has a format
like other JSON token.
And this is defined by another RFC that is the 7517 and looks like this.
So it has a bunch of information there.
Because key pairs are bound by mathematical properties that you don't need to know if
you don't want to or if you're not interested in cryptography.
So well, it is up to you.
And most of the packages and libraries that we use today, they support getting this key
from this endpoint so that you can actually use it without having to know what each of
these parts means.
But there are two important things that you need to notice here.
So we know what algorithm usually this key is used for.
And we know the key ID.
Because you can have more than one public key for a user depending on how your systems
are set up.
And let's see some code, right?
Because I like to code in Python.
Don't you?
Well, there are a few libraries that you can use to handle JWTs in Python.
My favorite one is PyGWT.
I'm a little biased.
And it does all the cool stuff.
So the first thing you want to do is install PyGWT with the cryptography dependency on
your Python environment.
And then you can just import JWT on your Python console and give it a token.
And it's going to do its magic for us.
So the first thing I'm going to do is actually import my JWT module.
After that, I can copy the token, put in a variable for me to use as a string.
And then the easiest part comes.
We call the JWT.Decode method.
And you pass it on the token, the secret, and the algorithms.
Now this assumes that you know the secret and you know the algorithms.
Once the decode method does its magic, you are going to be able to retrieve the payload
of the token.
That means the verification process was well done, was successful.
And of course, now I know every little thing that needs to know about this token.
I know the secret.
I know the algorithms.
And once I pass it along to the method, I can see the result in there.
And it comes as a dictionary.
So you can save that into a variable and use that on your applications whichever way you
want.
But let's say, for example, that somebody told you the secret, but they forgot to tell
which algorithm was used for the token.
So that is a way actually you can find that out.
And it's using the method get unverified header.
It also gives back a dictionary.
So I did the same process.
I imported JWT.
I put my token in there.
And then I use the method get unverified header, pass along the token.
I do a lot of typos when I'm coding.
And then I can get the header.
After that, I can see the header.
It is also a dictionary.
So I can put that into a variable so that I can use on my code.
So you don't have to actually know beforehand what was the algorithm used.
And then I put that header data because, well, what better name?
And then I call again JWT.code, pass along the token, pass along the key.
Well, in this case, a secret because the algorithm is still HS256.
And please don't use that secret.
It's not the good one.
And then pass along the algorithms in the format of accessing the dictionary data.
And there you go.
After that, we are going to be able to get, once again, my dictionary of the payload.
This means that everything was successful on verifying the token.
Now, let's say you are not successful.
Something goes wrong.
What should you do?
Well, I have an answer for that.
JWT, PyDWT actually gives you all the exceptions it raises when something goes wrong.
So if, for example, you get an expired signature, it will show you an expired signature.
And you, being the good Python Easter that you are, the good developer that you are,
you are going to want to try and use that exception to treat it, to maybe log the error.
So I did that, right, except with my code in, they try.
Then did I accept?
I know this is a possible error.
I put error in there.
And then I can use that information to log what went wrong because, well,
you want to keep track of these things, right?
Now, there I'm just printing.
So be mindful of that because it's just an example.
But in my systems, I would be logging it out.
And then I can use a string that I know and I can find that information on my logs.
And there you go.
After I run that, I'm able to see that, well, it didn't blow up in my face anymore.
The last part I want to show you in code is there is a possibility that you are not using
a symmetrical algorithm like the examples I just showed you.
So you can either request a key or you can load the key yourself from your machine.
In this case, this example token that I have, I created it using an SSH key.
So I can load that in using PyGWT.
And after I load that in, I can use it with read because I want a string of it.
And then I can use the serialization module of PyGWT to load any type of key that you might have.
For example, this is an SSH one, but you're going to see that we have other methods in there.
Like, for example, the PEM type of keys.
And I'm going to load my SSH key because I want to verify the token.
I passed it along as a byte string.
So I encoded.
And then I can use that back again with my decode method.
Now keep in mind, if you are using a service as out of zero as an example,
you would have to make a request for the well-known endpoint to get the key.
And you need the well-known endpoint and the key ID for that.
And that is a way to do that.
I linked that information in the description of this slide.
This is going to be available to you, so you can check it out.
And then again, I put it along the algorithm that I'm using.
And if everything goes well, you should be able to see the payload data.
There you go.
Awesome.
So now you're wondering, okay, I know everything that is to know about JWTs.
I know how they came to life.
I know what the payload and the header are.
I know that I have a lot of algorithms that I can use, two types of them.
I know I have claims and so on.
But where do I find JWTs in the wild?
Where do they live?
How do they feed?
So the first time I think of JWTs, and
the first time that I actually saw one, was actually making requests to protected APIs.
So when you are talking about protected APIs,
you're going to think about access tokens.
So let's say you wanna make a request to a protected API,
you need an access token to access the protected routes.
So the access token is going to have all of the information that you need for
dealing with that API.
Now, access tokens doesn't necessarily need to be JWTs, but
there is a new IFC in the block that came out last year.
It was authored by Vittorio Bertotti,
our Zeroes Principal Architect, that outlines how
JWT as an access token should behave, what kind of information needs to have,
how the information must be structured, and so on.
It's a very interesting read.
If you are curious, you should check it out.
The other type of JWTs you may find in the wild are the ID tokens.
And they are the coolest, at least for me.
Because they carry information of the user after the user did the logging,
for example.
So that way, your front end doesn't have to make an extra request to get,
for example, the user profile.
It is going to be able to have that information in there.
Also, because we're talking about tokens, you may have heard of refresh tokens.
Refresh tokens are not JWTs, that is why I'm not going to be speaking about it.
Maybe in a new talk.
So now that you know how you can use that JWTs, how they work,
how they come to life, how you can structure the information,
you may be wondering, well, this seems a little bit dangerous.
There's going to be information in there.
How do I, I don't know, be safer with it?
Well, I have a few tips for you.
So don't store your JWTs in local storage.
That's a bad idea, because it opens you up for a type of attack known as XSS attack.
And we don't want to do that, because once JWTs are out there,
you cannot call them back, it is a hassle.
So don't start that in local storage.
If you need to start somewhere for verification process, you may do it in memory.
That's the best idea.
The other tip is, we don't verify JWTs in the front end.
Because, well, let's say you have a JWT that was signed using a symmetrical
algorithm, you will need to have the key for it for translating the token,
for verifying the signature.
And we don't want to have that in the front end, because anybody could go
inspect elements on your page and get that information.
And we don't want to do that.
The last one, and I cannot stress this enough, me being an ex-data scientist,
well, if you're a data scientist at heart,
don't put sensitive data in the payload of your token.
It's a bad idea, because once again, anybody can inspect your web application and
get a hold of that token.
And then your sensitive data is going to be out there.
So it's not a good idea to put that in the token.
Finally, I want to give you some tools to help you out.
Because I know, JWTs may be hard.
I made this talk thinking of me a few years back that I wanted this content and
I didn't find any.
I had to figure it out by myself.
So the first one I'm going to tell you is JWT.io.
This was made by Alt Zero.
It's going to help you debug your access tokens.
And it's going to make your life easier.
You can check out, right in browser, the information of your token.
Now be mindful where you're placing the token,
because if it is a real production token, it's not a good idea.
But JWT.io is a safe environment where you can check out your token if you need to.
And we don't store the tokens for ourselves, so it's safer.
The other one is you may need more information about JWTs,
because we're very curious about it.
So we actually made a handbook with a few examples and
use cases of JWTs, and I encourage you to read it.
And that was it.
I don't know if you have time for more questions, but you may find me on, again,
on most social networks under the handle jaztemporal.
And my slides are on that link, slides.com, jaztemporal, jwt,
if you want to check out all the links.
That's it.
We don't take questions as part of the presentation, but
please come forward and ask Jessica directly if you have any questions,
or just swing by the O0 booth.
We are on the line 600.
Thank you.
See ya.