Good morning, everybody. Good morning. Thank you for everyone that decided to come this
early to the first of the lightning talks. We really appreciate it. We have a couple
speakers before Emily comes back and we have keynotes coming back. So let's welcome them
up to the stage to get ready and we can kick it off. Right?
Indeed. I think everyone is still waking up, waiting
for the coffee to kick in. First up we have Jeff who is giving us a talk on teaching Python
for community outreach. Let's give him a very loud round of applause because there's not
many of us here. Hi, everyone. Thanks for coming up this early.
So, yeah, I'm Jeff. I'm a bioengineer at the rehab neural engineering labs at the University
of Pittsburgh. But I'll be talking a little bit about teaching Python and community outreach.
So this is a picture of my lab from a couple years ago. We've grown to this large group.
I have our lab mission up here, but I'm not really going to talk about that if those words
confuse you a bit. I'm happy to talk about it if you find me later. But I'd like to show
that in the past couple of years, especially, my lab has formalized a list of both scientific
and community values. And we've really emphasized that, you know, it's not just about doing
the technical work and the science, but, you know, we've emphasized the importance of dignity
and respect, diversity, equity and inclusion, actually being anti-racist, not just not racist.
There's a difference. Of course, especially in education, there's always been a big focus
on mentorship and training. That's what education is all about. And I think these ideals, you
know, really overlap with open source software, too, right? Like, we want to share knowledge
and provide opportunities to all with this software. So, you know, these are just some
important things to keep in mind. And I'd also like to talk about the context of my
university in the city that we're in, Pittsburgh. So if you've never been to Pittsburgh, it's
a pretty cool city. I recommend checking it out. We are surrounded by these three rivers.
So most of the city kind of forms this triangle. And so on the west side here, on the west,
we've got downtown. That's really this triangle area. I've highlighted the university in red,
where it's in this neighborhood called Oakland. We've also got Carnegie Mellon University,
our neighbors to the west, also in Oakland. So it's this really big kind of second downtown
area that's this, like, hub of education and technology. But in between that and the main
downtown area is this neighborhood called the Hill District. It's actually like this
really big hill. And, you know, of course, these are our literal neighbors in the city.
This was, like, it's an interesting neighborhood. In the, especially in the earlier decades
of the 20th century, it was actually known as Little Harlem. It was this really thriving
center of African American culture, and especially, like, jazz, things like that, in Pittsburgh.
Like many cities in the U.S., it unfortunately faced a lot of decline and, you know, issues
later in the 20th century. I highlighted here that they constructed these highways, and
they put up some sports arenas. They actually had the knockdown housing to do that, and
they kind of cut it off from downtown. And so now it's seen as this really disadvantaged
neighborhood after that. It's really unfortunate. But these are our neighbors, and we'd like
to engage with them and, you know, help change things for the better. So some of the grad
students in my lab planned this intro to the Python course. The university actually
has this community engagement center in this neighborhood. Something I'd like to emphasize
is that the students who put this on are not expert coders. I mean, they are bioengineering
PhD students, primarily. But they planned some short lectures to go over the fundamentals
of programming, things like variables, control flow, loops, functions. But actually most
of the course time was spent just doing programming practice. And we really emphasized one-on-one
help from volunteers. So we got a big group of volunteers from the lab. You know, we had
different people come each week, but we tended to have about as many volunteers as students,
which really meant we could do one-on-one time throughout, like, the whole class. And,
you know, we had a lot of interesting students of various ages. We kind of targeted adults,
they ranged from high school age to senior citizens, different career backgrounds. You
know, some had had a little bit of program experience, most had none. You know, the woman
shown here actually brought her son with her, which was really cool. He was interested as
well, even though he was very young. So since we had all these different ages and career
levels, the one-on-one tutoring really helped. And the course ended with some final projects
where they had two weeks to work with us to do something really creative and really impressive
considering how little time they had to learn. They did things like creating password generators,
actually creating a Python tutorial and cheat sheet in Python, music playlists and games
like Hangman. We ended with this graduation little ceremony where they presented their
final projects. And, you know, the feedback from the course was really great. They wrote
these sticky notes. We tried to teach them how they could learn more in the future and
keep this going. So it was just a really great experience and I hope this encourages more
people to do something like this. You don't need to be an expert at coding or teaching
to do something like this and to give back to your community. So with that, I'm out of
time. So thank you.
Thanks. I realize I forgot to explain what I was doing up here with my fingers. If you
haven't seen the lightning talk before, it was tiny clapping which is what we do as the
speakers get close to their five-minute mark to give them a little signal, time to wrap
it up. Lorena?
Yeah. I was going to say, as someone from Chicago, I can connect with the cool Python
teaching all that jazz. So thank you so much for speaking. And up next, we have Jessica.
I'm very intrigued what we're going to hear.
Good morning, good afternoon, good evening, guys, gals, and non-binary pals. My name is
Jessica and I'm a data engineer at Elastic. I like to call myself a career data pusher
but I also do a lot of automation engineering and scripting in my current role. And most
importantly, I am a devoted cat mom which may not be relevant to this talk but is pretty
relevant in general so you should know that. Now, over the next few minutes while you're
enjoying your coffee here in the PyCon ballroom, I am going to change your life. I'm going
to tell you how removing one word from your vocabulary will not only make you a better
developer but a better teammate and mentor to those around you. This is a personal philosophy
of mine but I think it will work for you. Maybe not exactly but I hope you get something
out of this. So a little bit of background. My previous job was at a consulting company
where I spent most of my career there as a data-decent developer in some way, shape or
form starting in the humble role of data warehouse developer in 2014. As a data dev
and if there are any data engineers in the audience you may feel this as well, you get
a lot of questions along the lines of hey, why are the numbers like this? I would as
best I could explain how the data pipelines work, you know, but I'm not the business owner
of the data so if there's some issue with the source data that's not really my purview.
I can only explain how data gets from A to B, how C is transformed into D but not why
the source value N was correct or incorrect. So one day during a stint with my second data
warehousing client I was chatting with a business analyst about a dashboard and she
was confused about a few numbers. To her they just did not make sense. I was as usual explaining
limitations of what kinds of things I could do, like why the source data couldn't fit
into the report she was expecting but she just looked at me and said why can't you
just do this thing with the data to make the numbers better which what does better even
mean in this case. Then a couple months later I was transitioning off this client and I
was handing the work off to another consultant. As I was explaining a rather complex data
pipeline which needed much ugly manipulation to even get from source data to a number resembling
the output, he looked at me and said but why didn't you just insert technical solution
that obviously works because I don't know the context of anything that you're talking
about and clearly you should have done instead. I hope you can all see where this is going.
Since these two occurrences I have been on a campaign against the word just when posing
a question with someone I'm working with. To me just implies that the person you're
just asking a question to is missing something so obvious, so inconceivably unmissable that
they should have thought of it in the first place. With the first story the BA was saying
it kind of out of frustration, there was a number she didn't understand and wanted to
have me fix it but the second one it was definitely with an air of arrogance, this idea of like
I didn't know enough to do the correct solution. So by phrasing the question in a way that
promotes discussion rather than blame or ignorance which in my opinion is what just implies you
can go much farther and maybe even learn a little something along the way. So here are
a few of my favorite ways to rephrase can't you just, so like what if we tried, what if
you did something, have you considered, did you know about next time you come across this,
would you be able to explain why? And to me taking the time to rephrase this question
may even get you thinking about why it even came up in your mind in the first place, like
was there something that I missed or is there something I didn't consider? So to me phrasing
questions in this way paves the way to more understanding teams and colleagues who are
willing to learn from one another. Also if you find yourself using it don't worry I caught
myself using it in this presentation. So basically be gentle to yourself, know that you're all
learning. As an ex-jerk programmer every day I'm still thinking about how I can remove this
word and be kinder to especially the junior devs around me. There's not, we don't know
everything some of you may all know that ex-KCD comic of like every day there's like one person
who's learning something that you thought was very obvious for the first time. So I'm
here to leave you with this very relevant motivational poster which is if your question
starts with can't you just, the answer is no. Thank you for listening to my talk, come
find me the elastic booth I'll be there around 11 if you want to share cat pics with me.
All these photos come from the Canadian Internet Registration Authority they have the best
stock photos on the internet and you should use them. Thank you so much.
I think Lorraine is getting her phone out now to show you cat pics. I'm sorry, I'm so
sorry. I love that talk. Another word I strike for my vocabulary is simply. Nothing is actually
simple. Just stop saying simply. All right. Next up we have Roy with biometric attack.
Let's give a hand to Roy. Hi. My name is Roy. I'm a security software
engineer and today we're going to talk about biometric attack. So is anybody in the audience
using Face ID like I do or any other technology? Cool. Have you ever stopped for a moment and
thought about how this magic actually occur? How you can show your face to the phone and
the phone recognizes you as yourself and unlock itself? And more importantly have you ever
thought how secure is it? So let's dive straight into it. When your phone see a picture of
yourself or any other person it firstly detect where the face is inside the picture and using
a deep learning algorithm provide us a feature vector of that face. Those features can be
anything from the length of your nose or something weird as the ratio of your eye length and
your mouth. We don't really know what's the meaning of those floats but because they are
generated by a deep learning algorithm but we know that this feature vector which is
sized 128 most of the time supposed to represent you very well. So all your phone has a feature
vector. So what you have to do is save this feature vector inside of it and compare every new
photo to that feature vector. So let's simplify thing a little bit. I will take this 128 feature
vector and make it into a 3D vector so our mind can comprehend better what's going on here. So
point number, point A is our first scan when we bought our new iPhone and we don't really
try to match that exact point because today I look a bit different than I look yesterday. My hair
is a little bit longer. I didn't shave. So we're trying to do some circles, some sphere around
that point that everything inside it's fear like point number C which is a bit different than
point number A represents me. Point number B on the other hand is very far which means it's not
me. It's probably one of you who tried to hack my phone. So now I understand the process. We got
a picture and deep learning algorithm provide us a feature vector out of it. So we've got
ourselves a feature vector which is a representation of our face but is this representation any good?
Let me show you something a bit weird. So we tried to put many, many images of many, many people
into many, many iPhones and most of the people got exactly one hit. They were able to open their
own phone but this dude here at index number 27 has something really weird going on with him. He
was able to unlock more than 50 phone with his face. So let's try to understand how is that. So
if we take the example from before about the length of your nose, most noses are two inches or five
centimeters for non-American friends. And although you can have a little bit of bigger nose or smaller
nose, most noses will be at that range of five centimeters. And we found out that most of those
features are normally distributed as well. Now let me show you. We were able to hack a phone 13 times
in a million attempts which means your phone is secure as in five-digit numbers. So let me show you
how this attack was done. We generated here many, many faces. We as human can see that those faces
aren't real at all but because we were able to generate the distribution map for each feature,
we could create the most generic faces from most generic to least generic. And during this attack,
find a face that will be close enough to yours in terms of iPhone and unlock your phone so no one
is safe. Thank you very much. This is my mail and please feel free to approach me with any question.
Thank you so much for your talk. Up next we have Gajendra continuing on a really relevant topic on
security. Good morning everyone. My name is Gajendra Deshpande working as assistant professor at KLS
Institute of Technology India. So I'll be delivering a short talk on security considerations in Python
packaging. So in brief we are going to discuss three tools. One is Bandit, second one is the safety,
and third one is SemGraph. So why hackers are targeting Python is that we know that Python is
gaining lots of popularity and especially in TOB index it has reached number one position and even
in stack overflow it has been ranked third and even in non-JITUB stats you can see that in terms
of number of active repositories Python is on third position. Now there is a general misconception
about the security of the open source software. So some people cite that the major reason is that
the code is open source. The code is available to everyone. But generally speaking open source
software are secure by design and security issues are mostly due to the lack of understanding of
secure coding principles and Python is secure but vulnerabilities may be present in the Python
packages. So importance of secure package is that insecure package will make your application
vulnerable and prone to external threats. Compromise and unauthorized disclosure of information may
result into personal and company reputation and money. So unsecure code may damage the system of
users and sometimes it may also lead to the physical damage. Now these are some of the articles which
you can go through later. So these articles have been published recently and they have highlighted
several security issues such as dependency confusion attack mounted by a PyPy repository,
then JFrog detects malicious PyPy packages, stealing credit cards and injecting code,
and potential remote code execution in PyPy and supplies and flaws found in the Python package.
Let's see the Band-Aid tool. It's a tool designed to find common security issues in the Python code.
So to do this Band-Aid processes each file, builds an abstract syntax tree from it and runs
appropriate plugins against AST nodes. So once Band-Aid finished scanning all the files it generates
a report. So this is how you can use it. You can run it independently. You can run it against a code
repository. You can also specify a profile. So in this slide the shell injection profile has been
mentioned. So you can also write your own custom tests using Band-Aid. So there are some plugins
and these are the various types of tests you can perform and there are various tests. These are the
categories. So these are the tests under those specific categories. The next is the safety check.
So safety checks your installed dependencies for known security vulnerabilities. By default it uses
the Python vulnerability database safety DB but can be upgraded to use pyapp.io safety API
using key option. It supports Python 3.5 and above versions. Now how to test it is by installing
an insecure package. So these are some of the commands how you can use it. So this is a screenshot
you can find out. This is the screenshot before installing insecure package and this is the
screenshot after installing insecure package and you can see that it has appeared here but these
are the insecure package installed on my machine. Now you can use safety DB. It's a database of
known security vulnerabilities in Python packages. The data is made available by pyapp.io and it is
synced with the repository once per month. So you can visit the URL mentioned here, the first URL to
see the list of insecure Python packages. It doesn't mean that just because it appears in the list it is
insecure. So there are some safety DB tools which you can use. The safety CI, safety Django, then
safety bar, pip and check and so on. The next one is the semgrep which is the open source static
analyzer. It works on mostly 17 plus languages, supports Python also. It is not vendor controlled
and it has
thousands of bugs which onioned private
developers. JPEG, it forMUSIC. If you want to run some optim tast a fewノ
a package maintainer, then ensure that the package you are maintaining is secure and
practice secure coding principles.
So as an application developer, follow secure coding principles while writing, then use
tools to check vulnerabilities, then periodically scan your environment, sign and verify packages
using PGP keys, use Twine for improved security, scan packages before upgrading, ensure that
you install code from package from trusted source.
Thank you.
Great talk.
Very interesting to me personally as well.
Thank you for giving it.
And next up we have Diamond, who is giving us a talk on scaling PyTorch and fraud, real
world ML with Torch package and deploy.
Let's give it away for Diamond.
Hey, everyone.
Morning.
I'm Diamond.
I'm an engineering manager over at Meta.
In particular, I work on PyTorch, which is I'm sure your favorite machine learning framework
for Python.
Apologies if we have anyone here from TensorFlow.
But it's a great framework.
I'm going to be talking about one of the things that are near and dear to my heart, which
is scaling this for production use.
Really awesome when people use PyTorch for learning machine learning, for research, for
everything like that.
But one of the really important things to me is that we make sure it works really well
in production as well.
We're going to be talking about one particular aspect of that in this lightning talk.
The solution to the Gill problem.
Solution put in quotes here because we're not actually solving the Gill problem.
Someone much smarter than me is doing that.
Instead, I'm looking at a small part of this problem, which is if you're running a production
scale machine learning framework or machine learning system, most of the time you actually
don't want to just write everything in Python.
There's a bunch of different reasons for that.
I know it's kind of a hard thing to say at a Python conference.
Usually you end up writing your service in C++ or something that is really highly performant
because you want really high throughput.
What you want to do is have this model that you've trained in Python and use it in this
potentially C++ or other faster framework service that is very efficient.
That's really hard to do unless you take the model and translate it into some other language.
Translations are incredibly painful.
Instead, you want to be able to use Python, run it with C++, and profit.
How do you do that?
We have two different libraries, two different features that we've actually introduced pretty recently.
One is called Torch Package and one is Torch Deploy.
Torch Package lets you serialize and de-serialize your Python code.
Keep your model in Python so your scientists can be happy, your machine learning engineers
can be happy.
They don't have to do all this messy translations where you end up losing functionality of Python
that you really want because we do love actually keeping the model in Python, writing the model
in Python, training the model in Python.
You're able to then deploy that and use it in your C++ system.
Under the hood, the way that works for a Torch Deploy is that we have actually an interpreter
manager so that you have n Python interpreters.
You're not just running one because if you were just running one, you'd have run into
the Gill problem where you have the global interpreter lock that makes it so you can
only run in one thread.
Instead, if you have, let's say, an EC2 instance or something else that has tons of cores that
you're paying for, you can actually use each of those cores.
Each core is able to run a copy of your model and we do that by having a separate Python
interpreter per core.
An example of this is pretty straightforward.
You've got your C++ program.
Once you package up your model, you can make a call straight to it.
We have here that you're loading up the model from your package.
Then at the very bottom, you can see that we're actually going to run inference with
it, execute your model with the tensor that you're passing.
That tensor represents the data that you have in the real world interaction.
How do you actually put your model into that state?
Use Torch Package, which is part two of this.
It's hermetically sealing dependencies in with your source code, your source model.
It's Python-ic so you can make changes to the dependencies that you're covering with
it, that you're wrapping with it, and you have fine-grained control of it.
Torch Package example here.
This is in Python, not in C++, so it's not as ugly.
This is something that you can see.
We're packaging up the model.
In our situation, we're saying extern is really when you're saying we're going to rely on
an external dependency.
We're okay with that.
It doesn't need to be hermetically sealed.
Intern is when you're saying we're going to actually pull this in as part of our package.
This is an internal package dependency.
A couple different options you have here.
These graphs are hard to parse, so apologies.
The main important thing is that there's a bunch of different ways, like TorchScript,
which is turning it into another language that you can use to make this much faster.
Instead, we show that you naturally, without having to do any performance work, are able
to get higher performance than your single thread for certain types of models, most small
to medium-sized models.
Larger models are a bit more complicated.
We get some improvements, but not as much as we'd like.
Here are the public docs.
I'm going to actually be hosting an open space as well at 5 p.m. for anyone who wants to
talk about PyTorch or machine learning in production.
You can come talk to me.
We can chat about it.
I love to hear your pain points.
In particular, I have a whole group that really focuses on how do we make PyTorch better for
you, better for production.
If you are using it or you're using machine learning in production and you want something
from us, come by.
I'm always trying to figure out what else we can do to make it easier and better for
everyone.
Software is eating the world, and ML is eating software.
So please help us make that happen.
Thank you very much.
I might be at that open space.
Up next we have Manabu who's going to ... I think it's a really relevant topic, so I'm
just going to pass it on to you now.
Hi, good morning.
I will talk about the spread Python community with COVID-19 in Japan.
My name is Manabu Terada from Tokyo, Japan.
I was tough to live from overseas, but I came back to here very nice.
I'm board chair of PyCon JP, PyCon Japan Association, and a PSF follow-up member and more.
We launched the PyCon JP, PyCon Japan in 2011, about 10 years ago.
At that time, the Python community in Japan was very small, so Masuda-san and Ikubara-san
and Ian-san and I took the land.
Other Python users who were active in Tokyo and other parts of Japan started from PyCon
JP.
At first, it was only 150 people joined PyCon JP.
Now, we are able to have 1,000 people at PyCon JP.
Thank you very much.
Of course, this year we will have an in-person event in October.
If you can come to Japan, please join us.
Other activities were to promote Python all over Japan and create more valuable community
all over Japan.
One of those is a tutorial event, Python Bootcamp.
This could be introduced in the poster session in US PyCon 2019.
We supported PyLadies Tokyo, PyLadies Caravan.
It makes local women's community and connecting all over Japan.
However, you all know the world has changed in the spring of 2020.
But we thought it would not be good to stop our activity here.
So we made some activities.
The first one, we held Python Charity Talks in Japan.
It was donated to the Python Software Foundation.
The first time we donated $10,000.
Total is $25,000.
So we held three times.
Other activities, we have a YouTube Live every month.
We share some news for Python and Python community and introducing some events.
And a new feature for Python 3.10 and more.
Last, we are taking the interview for the next PyCon JPTV.
This is my PyCon JPTV.
We have an open space session at 2.50 F.
It started at 13.30.
Please come to the room if you have a message to Japanese Python Easter.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.
I just want to reiterate that $25,000 donation was really awesome.
The folks at the PyCon JP Association got a community service award.
Many people.
Thanks for that.
Thank you.
Next up, Jay is going to talk about DevRel.
Sharing your company's skills with the world.
Give it up for Jay.
I'm going to be honest.
I did the sliding talk for two reasons.
One, a lot of people ask me what is DevRel.
And I go, eh.
The other reason is when I talk to all of my friends in DevRel, they all say, hey, do
you know anybody that would be interested in a job at DevRel?
It's growing.
Every company I've talked to is hiring advocates.
We're hiring content creators.
If you've ever thought that getting up on stage and giving a lightning talk or going
to PyCon and getting to walk around and talk to your friends and then getting paid to do
that is something that you might be interested in, hey, let's figure it out.
Like I said, DevRel.
I don't know.
It's a good thing, though.
Don't worry.
Every company that tells you what DevRel is, they're telling you what their version of
DevRel is.
It's going to be different every time.
It may change with the seasons.
It may change with the weather.
And again, this is a good thing because static sites are cool.
Static teams and companies, not so much.
We have to be flexible.
We have to be able to adapt to what is happening in the space.
So your job is to be a communicator.
Your job is to communicate to the community that you serve.
But it's also your job to communicate to your company the needs of your community.
If you're not doing both, I'm sorry you're wrong.
I'm hoarse.
I don't have time to argue that point.
If you can't provide value to both the community and your company, then you're doing a disservice
to one of those two.
So how do you get into DevRel?
This is going to be the quick three-minute version.
Choose at least one of each of these three kinds of things.
Ephemeral content, a recurring presence, and a longer sustained commitment.
If you do more than one, great, you get bonus points.
That will also give you an idea of what type of role in DevRel you want to take on.
So we're going to start with the first one, ephemeral content.
This is a Twitter space.
That's the new hotness.
I love Twitter spaces.
They're amazing.
I did my first one when I was driving, and then I was like, I want to talk, but I also
don't want to crash.
And that was like, all right, pull over to the side.
Tell everybody why this is amazing.
Okay, then get back on the road.
We'll do safe stuff here.
YouTube Live, Twitch.
If you've always wanted to tell people to like, follow, hit the bell, do all that stuff.
Like, hey, maybe this is a way that you can do that and not have to, A, fight the algorithm,
or B, worry about subscribers, clicks, and downloads.
Or TikTok.
I'm not going to do a TikTok dance.
You can't make me.
I'm sorry.
IG Live, YouTube Shorts, all of these things, all of these pieces of content that happen,
they're like a flash in the pan.
Then they're gone.
If you like doing that, maybe being a developer advocate is for you.
A recurring presence, being at meetups, being at conferences, joining online communities
and discords, Slack channels, appearing on other people's podcasts, doing guest posts
and things.
These are things where people in the community will see you or at least hear your name.
You don't have to worry about whether or not you did good because you're going to come
back and you're going to do better.
You're going to iterate over time.
Just like when you're learning to code.
Your first code, your first lightning talk, you're nervous.
You're scared.
You want to push that button and your buddy Seth is like, don't worry, you got this.
That was a true story.
That was the story of my first pull request.
But the more you show up, the better you get at it.
The better you get at it, the more people notice that you're getting better at it.
And then the more people are going to want to talk to you because then you go from being
the person that was learning to the person that's now teaching.
And then finally, the longer sustainable commitment.
This is your blog.
This is your podcast.
This is your personal YouTube channel.
This is your newsletter.
This is you posting cat pics on Twitter.
Sorry, I've been trying to convince some people to get into dev role lately.
So anything that allows people to see you, know you, know who you are, and feel like
they can connect with you and they know exactly where they can find you, that is going to
be the thing that you need to focus on.
And like I said, it's not just being an advocate.
You can be a content creator.
You can be a writer.
You can get in the video team.
You can do all of these things.
But I know what you're going to tell me.
I'm introverted.
Me too.
I'm going to go home and go to sleep for a few days.
You might have ADHD.
How do you focus on all these things?
Me too.
Having a lot of different things to focus on actually makes the job fun and easy.
And you can bounce from one idea and then when you're tired of that idea, you put it
down and then you pick up another one and then you work on that stuff.
And you're not the most tech savvy.
That's fine.
Your job is to learn and to show people what you've learned.
There are a lot of people in the expo hall.
If you're interested, you can find me or find someone in a booth and ask them.
Your favorite part, your least favorite part.
Thank you.
So I have two Maine Coons who I'm very, very proud of.
One of them is named Per Card after Jean-Luc Picard and all those things.
And yes, I do put them on Twitch.
I'm very excited for this next talk and we have Jack.
Yeah.
Hi, I'm Jack.
You might be able to tell by the title of this talk that it's going to be a bit different
in terms of content from the other talks, but I'll be talking about what I think is
an interesting use of binary search.
And I swear this is more interesting than Leap Code.
Okay, so as a quick review, I'm assuming most of you are familiar with what binary search
is, so we're going to go over an easy problem.
So you have this list of a positive number of zeros followed by a positive number of
ones, and your task with binary search is to find the index of this first one in the
list.
So how we can do this is that we have two pointers, low and high, to indicate the current
search range.
And then in each step, we try to reduce the search range by a factor of two until
eventually we end at our answer.
Okay, so that's pretty simple.
So now we're going to look at how we can apply this to solve a harder problem.
And this is the problem statement.
Partition a given list with n positive integers indicate contiguous segments such that
the maximum segment sum is minimized.
That's a lot to take in, so I think this is best explained with an example.
So we have this list here with 10 elements, and we want to partition it into four parts.
So one way we can do it is like this.
So the sums are 10, 18, 6, and 8 respectively.
So the maximum segment sum is 18, and this red number here is what we want to minimize.
And it turns out that we can actually do better than 18.
So we can do better than 18.
If instead we partition the list like this, where the sums are 10, 10, 12, and then 8,
the maximum segment is 12, and it turns out this is optimal.
So to get to solving this problem, it isn't very easy.
We have to first make a few observations.
So the first observation is that if we fix some number m, it's easy to construct a partition
where no segment has sum exceeding m.
So here's this function I have called constructPartition.
We take in a list, k and m, and then we either produce a partition satisfying these constraints,
or just for convenience we return none if no partition exists.
So the idea is to just build each segment one by one.
And once we get to a point where our segment sum is about to exceed m,
we add the segment to the partition.
And we're going to keep doing this through the whole list, and you get the idea.
So eventually we end up with our partition from the previous slide.
Okay, so now with this function constructPartition, we can decide whether or not we can partition the list
so that the maximum segment sum is at most m, and we can also provide a construction.
But what we want is to partition the list so that the maximum segment sum is minimized.
So to do this, we have to make another observation.
And we're going to look at this funny-looking list comprehension here.
Here we're going to construct a partition for just about every possible value of m
that might be interesting to us, from zero to the sum of the whole list.
And this list has a few special properties.
First of all is that the last element is not none,
and this is because any partition has the property that the maximum segment sum
is at most the sum of the whole list.
And also the elements in this list, which are all the same,
and also the elements in this list, which are partitions, are suffix of the list.
So if you think about this list comprehension structurally,
it's some number of none's followed by some number of partitions that you can construct.
And then if you look at the first partition, it also has maximum segment sum of exactly j
if we say that this partition is at index j.
And then using the same proof-by-contradiction logic,
we can also show that this first partition is actually your answer.
It's the partition that minimizes the maximum segment sum.
But if we treat all the none's as zero's and all the partitions as one's,
this problem of finding the first partition is basically the same
as the problem that I discussed earlier of finding the first one in this list of zero's and one's.
So this is the code.
That's a pretty short code,
and you'll notice that it's actually pretty similar to this first problem that I described.
And now I want to take some time to revisit the title slide.
So actually, an hour before this talk, when I was preparing,
I realized that this is actually a Leak Code problem.
But nonetheless, I still think it's pretty interesting.
So this is Leak Code Problem 410.
If you want to have a crack at it, maybe during lunch,
I think it'd be pretty interesting.
And that's all. Thank you.
Thanks very much.
We have Henry who's going to give us a talk on Scikit-HEP Developer Pages.
Let's give it up for Henry.
Okay, thank you.
So I want to talk about the Scikit-HEP Developer Pages.
So Scikit-HEP is a GitHub organization that was built around providing high energy physics packages.
So we have a bunch of high energy physics specific packages
that have been built up over the last few years.
You can see a few of them listed here.
But we have also worked on some general purpose packages as well.
So we have some packages that are there like Vector for vector manipulations,
Awkward Array for JSON-like data structure, but NumPy-like access, and histograms.
But one of the products that has come out of this is the Scikit-HEP Developer Pages.
And this is the most general, I think, of all of these.
And that's why I wanted to talk to you today about it.
If you want to find these, you can just go to scikit-hep.org.
It's also linked to my blog, isinumpy.dev.
And you'll get to a page that looks like this.
You can click on either of these two places, and you'll get to the Developer Pages.
So when you get to the Developer Pages, you'll be greeted with something that looks like this.
You have a variety of different pages there, and it'll guide, sort of walks you through the different pages.
These pages can sort of be grouped into these areas.
There are some tutorial-like pages that sort of tell you how to set up a development environment,
use PyTest, static typing, things like that,
including a very nice GitHub Actions tutorial, including how to do binary packages,
regular PurePython packages, and a discussion of how you'd use a TaskRunner like Knox.
And then there's some specifications.
The packaging is in two different sort of groups,
so a classic packaging and a simple 6.21 style packaging.
And then there's a style guide, and then there's a couple extra tools,
which I'll show you, Cookie and repo review, that support this.
So this is the simple Python packaging page.
It used to be called PurePython packaging,
but hopefully this is sort of going to include some binary packaging soon.
And so you have this little toggle here,
and you can actually just switch this toggle from Flit to Hatched, PDM, Setup Tools.
The whole page is the same. All this part on the page is the same.
It's really just that tool that changes,
just those two lines, which is a really nice feature of PEP6.21.
And so this can be a guide for any one of those.
For style, there's a bunch of different things.
It sort of tells you how to set up pre-commit hooks for all of these different tools,
with recommendations for how you would configure these.
And sort of describing what each one is.
Now, this all comes together in Scikit-HEP Cookie,
which is a cookie cutter package.
It gives you 11 different backends to choose from.
So if you want a Setup Tools traditional package,
or if you want a Setup Tools PEP6.21, or Flit or Hatched, or PDM,
or several others.
And it even has some binary packaging,
which you don't see very often in sort of a general cookie cutter.
So you can go to Scikit-Build, or just plain Setup Tools C++,
or even Rust is supported there.
So to do this, you could just do a PEPX run cookie cutter,
or however you like to run cookie cutter,
and then that's the path that you can put in.
And this is all backed by the Scikit-HEP Developer Guidelines,
so you're not just thrown at a bunch of different styles and things.
You can actually go look up and see why each choice is made,
and why each package is there.
And then there's the Scikit-HEP Repo review.
And this is something that I sort of wrote for myself.
This is a rich application.
And you can just run this,
and it will see how close a repository is to following these guidelines.
So it'll go through and check a variety of these different guidelines.
There's lots of different ones here,
and tell you if it matches or not.
And this is really nice,
but it's still something you have to go manually run.
So what I've recently done
is written the Scikit-HEP Repo review Pydite app.
This Pydite app sits there in the Scikit-HEP Developer pages.
It's just one of the pages in that list.
You can just type in your repository, pick a branch,
and click a button.
And in your browser, Python,
and this is a Python 3.10 application that uses pattern matching and things,
but it's able to just run right there in your browser
without installing anything
and give you a report that looks like this in your browser.
So you don't have to leave the Scikit-HEP Developer pages anymore.
And a day later, another HEP user took this.
I was also really excited just in this technology and the ability to do this.
One day later, another of our Scikit-HEP developers took this
and adapted it to one of the other packages there.
So that was something that was exactly what I wanted to happen from this
and was really excited to see other applications.
Okay.
So, Fett, thank you very much.
Applause
Thank you so much, Henry.
I just want to do a quick plug.
PyLadies Auction is tonight.
It's a really great organization, hence the shirt I'm wearing.
And it helps us raise money for folks to come to PyCon
and do really great things.
So thank you for the support that you've given us.
And I'm really grateful for the support that you've given us.
Thank you so much.
Thank you.
Okay, I'm here to tell you to stop running your tests.
But Chris, I hear you saying,
tests are how I am confident that my code works.
And that's true.
Having good test coverage is a great way to be absolutely certain
that your implementations are correct
and making sure that you don't break things as you develop.
But on the other hand, tests have a lot of problems.
They're slow.
When you run your full test suite, most of the tests you run are irrelevant
but you don't run your entire test suite except in CI
because it's slow.
So in short, you have tests but you don't run your tests.
You have no tests.
What would be better is if you could keep not running your tests
as often as you do now,
but still know which of your tests are correct.
That world actually exists.
I'm a maintainer on an open source project called PantsBuild
where a tool that orchestrates all the other tools that you use
is running through to testing and packaging.
Our goal is to make the Python tools you already use
more efficient than they are in their default configurations
even on huge code bases with complex interdependencies.
We do that by identifying work that can be run in parallel
or redundant or duplicated work
which will save you from having to run at all.
Watch this. You can run an entire test suite.
That is not surprising.
You can see we run PyTest under the hood
and it takes 20 seconds wall clock time to run this 60-second test suite.
That's great but not completely surprising.
A lot of test runners do this.
What else can we do?
Well, if we change one of the test files and rerun the entire test suite,
it looks like this.
It looks like it runs everything but it actually doesn't.
All of those tests that we ran before and we didn't change get reused.
Only the test that we change gets rerun.
That is because Pants will cache every single run down to the process level.
The 60-second test suite takes only 10 seconds to run now.
That's still not surprising. A lot of test runners do this.
Let's reset that change and run those tests again.
Pants will cache every test run,
not just the most recent one.
If we run a command that's identical to the one we've run before,
Pants will pull all of those test results out of the cache and reuse them.
Our 60-second test suite will now run instantly.
Now, what if instead of changing a test file,
we change an implementation file that is under test?
We can rerun the entire test suite
and this time the only test we rerun
is the one that tests the implementation file that we changed,
that we're testing.
With this, you can make all the changes you want to your implementation files
that you like and you can rerun the entire test suite
and Pants will only rerun the tests where you change the code.
This is because Pants does automatic dependency inference.
It will do static analysis on your code base
and it will figure out all of your Python code sets
and it will map those dependencies automatically.
This Pants Dependees command will show that dependency analysis for you
and again, it has figured all of this out automatically.
We didn't need to do any configuration.
This is all the configuration we needed to do.
We just said there are some source files, said there are some test files.
If you've ever written a build file before, you know how short this is.
You don't have to map any dependencies yourself.
Our static analysis, if it misses a dependency,
you can add it manually, but normally you don't need to.
If you want to modify yourself, we have scripts
that will automatically generate all of your build files.
If this is interesting to you and you want more of a demo
or you want to talk about how Pants could help in your code base,
you can find myself or Benji or John.
They're wearing shirts with the Pants logo on it.
I've got a talk on Sunday at 1 o'clock
about how Pants does all this fine-grained caching
underneath the hood and we'll be sprinting on Monday
where we will help you run Pants on your own code base.
This is how you can use Pants to stop running your tests unnecessarily.
My name is Christopher Neugebauer. Thank you very much.
Cantaloupe!