And we'll start with the
first speaker.
Welcome to lightning talks.
Real quick, we're going to go over how lightning talks work.
We're going to have a series of speakers.
They're each going to talk for five minutes or less. No more
than five minutes.
They're going to talk on any topic that they suggested.
And real quick, this is what we're going to do as they get
started.
We're going to have a little one-finger clap.
Let's practice everyone one finger clap quietly.
You can barely hear it.
And then as they get closer, we'll do a two-finger clap.
Make a little more noise and they'll say, I have to wrap up.
And then once they get to five, we'll do a full-on applause.
Thank you, get off the stage. Next speaker, please.
All right. Cool.
Thank you, Justin.
Okay. Good life. Hi, I'm Samir. I'm the head of privacy at
Devron. Let's take a moment to think about what is data
science without data?
Can we actually do anything when we don't have data?
The answer is generally speaking, no.
That's the start of data science.
Then what does data science without data mean?
Does it mean just science?
Does it mean data privacy?
What does data privacy mean?
If you have data access problems because of the emerging data
privacy regulations and laws or if your data is split into
multiple different trust domains or if you would like to retain
ownership of your data but still like to make use of this data,
you would be interested in what we're doing at Devron.
If you're interested in knowing more what we do, please come
and get it.
I'll buy them archives, 말이- маски,
what Kelly said like we're interested in you.
Thank you.
Simpson if you're interested in
Steam today, I read the chat.
Yes, absolutely.
Cultural shock.
I'm already shocked because this room is so big.
It's my first time physically attending PyCon US,
which is, so, spoiler, I was lost in the venue.
The first day I went to lunch and I got lost.
So I'm check.
Hit me up on Twitter if you want to.
I am living in London, UK, so this is what it,
well, it's not what it looks like,
but it's what people think it looks like.
And also, I, so my company is based in Dublin,
so I visit Dublin quite a lot as well,
so I also have some tip about Dublin for you later.
So what I think here in the US is everything is so big.
It's very big, like this room is so big.
The venue is so big.
The rows are so big.
When I cross the row, I always have to run
because I feel like I don't have enough time
to cross the row.
It's so big.
The bed is so big in my hotel room.
This is my hotel room, by the way.
You can see that that's my teddy bear there.
It's very small.
So, yeah, but the teddy bear here are so big as well.
So, yeah, and anybody see this in the airport?
Like, that really shocked me, right?
Wow, the teddy bear is so big.
Yeah, like, it really shocked me.
Another thing, hotel rooms, they have no kettles.
So, you know, well, I would say that I'm kind of British.
I live in UK for a while, you know,
and then, like, we love tea.
We need to have a cup of tea.
So there's no tea.
No, there's tea in the hotel room, but there's no kettle.
I was like, but I was prepared
because I was told that there's no kettle here,
so I bring my own kettle.
I forgot to take a picture of it,
but I do have a travel kettle that can collapse,
which is very good.
For any of those of you who would love to buy one,
talk to me, I can give you a tip.
But anyway, so, also, I was scared.
Luckily, in this city, you don't necessarily need to drive
because there's a tram, there are buses,
but I was so scared because before I came here,
I was like, oh my God, do I have to drive?
Because I'm horrible at driving.
I only drive maybe once or twice in my life.
I'm a city girl, so am I super scared?
So also, there's something that's called Ice Cream Sprint
that I do in all the PyCons in Europe
that will run for ice cream during lunchtime.
So I was worried that it would become
an ice cream speeding ticket instead of ice cream sprint.
So yeah, but luckily, it didn't happen.
So I was shocked, but I don't want you to be shocked
in case you are going to these following conferences,
PyTator London in June, EuroPython in July,
and PyCon UK in September.
I really want to see you there.
I really love seeing people coming to my country,
yeah, my place, so that would be great.
So I want to give you some tips
so you won't have cultural shock like me.
So the weather, it's gotta be a bit wet, you know,
London, a bit wet.
Bring some clothes that is waterproof or water-resistant.
Also getting around, you don't need to drive, don't worry.
You can take trains, you can take buses.
They're very convenient.
The underground train in London is called Tube,
so if anybody telling you to take the Tube,
that's what you mean, it's the underground transport system.
So eating out, definitely try fish and chips.
There's something called Sunday Roast.
They're only available on Sunday in pubs,
but usually they are yummy, so try that.
Also, tips are optional in Europe,
so don't worry about the tips.
If you don't want the tips, that's fine.
Also, show, show, the Brits, they love drink.
They could be a bit shy in the conference,
but after a few drinks in the pub,
they can talk anything with you.
They can introduce their family to you
or something like that.
Also, Guinness, if you go to Ireland, go to Dublin,
Guinness is a must drink.
It tastes different there, so trust me.
Accommodation could be expensive,
but look for something like Airbnb,
but be careful of the scammers.
Also, student accommodation could be an option
because summer, nobody's gotta be in the student
accommodation, or I have a small room,
so be my friend, that I could maybe host you.
I don't know.
So people are there, just very nice, like people here,
so don't worry about it.
Come to visit me.
Come to PyData London in June, Europe Python in July,
or PyCon UK in September.
So that's it, thank you so much.
Thank you.
Thank you so much, Chuk.
Up next is a gentleman who I don't think many of us
need an introduction for, Lukas.
Hi there.
We've seen each other already in the morning,
so I'm just gonna quickly make you a typing expert.
This is a concept that many of us struggle with
because we don't have nice examples,
and the property of nice examples is obviously
to have cutesy animals explaining them.
With that, everything is easier.
So imagine some abstract animal,
and we have some subtypes of that abstract animal,
namely a dog, a cow, a cat, this sort of thing.
So covariance, contravariance, and invariance
are concepts that explain us whether we can replace
one of those with another,
and what will happen in that case.
So covariance, the most kind of natural intuitive of those,
means that whenever we have an animal accepted,
we could put cow and it should work.
Like one example in Python is that if you have a function
that prints an animal, if you have a function
that prints many animals by calling print animal,
what you can do is you can define a function
called print cats that just uses print animals
and everything works fine.
So this is in fact something that does work.
You can do that.
So the property of the covariance here
happens in the sequence of animal
that can be replaced with sequence of cats.
The opposite happens for contravariance,
which means in some context,
you can replace a cow with a generic animal.
How does that work?
Well, this is the weirdest of the examples,
but in fact, it deals with callables.
So if you have some print with implementation
where we want to print a cat,
I don't know, as JSON or whatever else,
and we wanna provide an implementation for it,
so we by default want prints cat
because we know that this is something that can print cats.
Can we put a function that can print any animal there?
Well, we can because it can print any animal.
So this relationship between those callables
prints cat and prints animal is reverse
to what you would think about with inheritance
because you can in fact replace the more concrete thing
with a more generic one.
And finally, we have invariance where you cannot
replace the cow with a generic animal and vice versa.
It's just impossible.
And in fact, this is something that very, very many users
of typing fall into faster or later
because of an example like this.
If you have a function that allows us to add animals
to an existing list and we have a function that adds a cat,
we would think that we should be able
to just use this add animal function
in the implementation of add cat, right?
Because it's natural, it doesn't do really much weirdness.
It should work.
But it doesn't because in general,
if in the add animal function, we did something funky,
this is just an example, but the point being,
we would add an animal which is not a cat,
then the function below add cat that takes a list of cats
would suddenly change the type of those cats
into cats plus some other animal.
And what type is that?
Well, we don't really know.
This is something that you might break in Python
all the time because containers don't really limit you
from putting incompatible types next to each other.
But with non-py types or with other programming languages,
the memory layout between different types
might be different.
So this becomes more important then.
So in this particular case,
that would not be possible to be done.
And now you understand covariance,
contravariance, and invariance.
And cutesy animals, thank you.
пАдăц, и падъц
Awesome, thanks, Lukas.
All right, next we have Seth,
who told me earlier he'd never met another Python-ista
until he came to this conference.
I met all the Python-istas.
So welcome, Seth.
Seth's gonna give us a talk
on the future of trust stores in Python.
Give it away for Seth.
So, I'm Seth Larson, I'm maintainer of Uralib 3 requests and some other packages, and a
lot of the work that's done here is also done by David Glick, who's in the audience.
Okay, show of hands.
Have you seen this error?
I've seen this error so many times.
If you've worked at a corporate proxy environment, you've seen this error.
Usually you see this when there's no root certificate and you can't verify your cert
chain and you're trying to use TLS.
Okay, so first off, what is a trust store?
Trust store is a collection of certificates that your system uses when you're doing a
TLS handshake.
The server gives you certificates back, you verify them against that trust store.
And so in Python, because we're strongly tied to OpenSSL with our SSL APIs, usually takes
the form of a file or a directory of certs.
So today in Python, trust stores look kind of like this.
Linux distros, they ship things that are compatible for OpenSSL, but macOS and Windows don't do
that and Python is strongly tied to OpenSSL.
So what do we do on macOS and Windows?
We use certify.
So certify is a Python package that basically takes the certificates that Mozilla bundles
in their CA bundle and then repackages it, uploads it to the Python package index and
then you can use them.
But there are a couple of problems with using OpenSSL and certify, especially on macOS and
Windows systems.
So certify, you only get the certs that are bundled with certify.
You don't get to follow some central policy on your system.
For example, in a corporate environment, if your system administrator installs an additional
certificate into your system trust store, certify has no idea what that even is.
And so that means you're going to end up with one trust store per application.
It's really tough to maintain.
You don't get any auto updates and now the Python package index is a CA certificate distribution
channel, which is not what it's for.
And so here's why system trust stores are a lot better.
You get one per system instead of per application, so that means there's one place where all
the certificates get updated.
The system itself manages and updates everything and you get a whole bunch of fancy features
that the operating system usually gives you that OpenSSL wouldn't necessarily give you
or you'd have to configure additionally.
So this is kind of that future that we're envisioning.
So there's this new experimental package that me and David have put together called trust
store.
This code is very new, so it's experimental.
Don't deploy it.
It's only been alive for about four months now.
You can get it on GitHub.
There's a URL there.
But essentially what it is, is it provides an SSL context API.
It works on all of the major platforms and does the native system trust store thing to
make sure everything works.
And we tested against a whole bunch of libraries.
The only kicker is it requires Python 3.10 because it uses some special private APIs
that if you really are super interested, I wrote an entire article about it.
So go to the GitHub.
You'll find it.
And so then this exists.
What happens now?
Look at the project.
Be interested by it.
Like learn about it.
But do not deploy it yet, please.
It's very, very young code to be doing something that's super, super important.
So just wait for a little bit in that case.
But I think one of the future directions that this is going to go in is we would like to
get this functionality added to Python so that all applications that use Python can
immediately take advantage of it.
And I think that there is an avenue for more incremental adoption by some libraries and
tools of the specific library.
So that's kind of it.
Thank you.
Fantastic.
Love hearing that there is a space for you to collaborate, but do not yet deploy to prod.
Huge emphasis there.
Up next, we have Pablo.
Hey, hello, PyCon.
So I'm Pablo Galindo.
You may know me from my work on CPython, but I'm here today to talk about something that
we have released from the company that I work for, that is Bloomberg, and this is MemRay.
So MemRay is a memory profiler that we have open source two weeks ago.
Many of you may know it because apparently it was quite popular on Twitter during a couple
of days, but I hope to give you an overview over what it does and why it could be useful
for you.
So the escape of memory profilers and profilers in Python is a fantastic landscape because
there's a lot of cool tools.
But let me help you cover what MemRay does that other profilers may not do or may do
a bit worse.
So one of the things that happen is that, for example, in the standard library, we see
with some memory profilers.
It's called TraceMalloc.
The problem with, for example, TraceMalloc and many other profilers is that they can
see allocations that the Python interpreter does, but not allocations that other things
underneath do.
For instance, in this case, we are allocating a huge amount of memory.
This is like 90-something megabytes using MemMap, but this could also be done in a C
extension or NumPy or things that are not communicating with the Python interpreter.
And the problem is that, for instance, in this case, if you ask TraceMalloc how much
memory was allocated, it tells you that it's only 80 bytes, which is not great because
there is a huge amount of memory here.
But if you do the same with MemRay, this is one of the example outputs that you will see.
In this case, it will tell you that, oh, we detected one allocation is 9 megabytes and
it's because one allocator happened.
So MemRay can see not only allocations that happen in Python, but also a lot of allocations
that happen in C extensions.
Other profilers can do this, but something that many other profilers cannot do is that
if you have one of the outputs of MemRay, which is this flying graph, for instance,
in this case, some memory is allocated in this Python code, MemRay can also tell you
what happens underneath that Python code, and it can tell you all the C code that is
executed underneath and what happened.
And as you can see, you can go here and see that actually there is some NumPy cache that
the actual responsibility to allocate the memory for that instruction, which is super
cool, especially if you are using data science libraries that use the extension or Cython.
But we have many other things.
For example, we dump all the information that we collect to a binary file, and then you
can produce a ton of reports, depending on what you want.
You can get the statistical reports, you can build tree reports, flying graphs, tables,
and for instance, you can even get live reports when you can see what your application is
doing as it's running.
You don't need to generate one, you can see what's happening, which is very cool.
I know people like moving things, so here you go.
But yeah, the idea is that we also have an API, so you can use the API to track just
parts of your code, you don't need to track the entire program, because you may be using
Unicorn or other things that make tracking the whole thing very difficult, so you can
just say, okay, track only what happens here.
And the cool thing about MemRay is that, as opposed to other memory profilers, is that
anything that happens outside this context manager has zero overhead, because MemRay
activates everything in a very special way that makes sure that any code that is not
under this context manager has zero overhead, so it runs at full speed.
We have also a Python explain, which you can use immediately by installing, adding dash
dash MemRay to your invocation of Python, that after the test suite passes, it will
show you a bunch of statistics.
So for instance, it will tell you how much memory was allocated, how many allocations
happened, meaning Instagram of the allocations that happened, and the places in your code
and your test when there were more allocations, which is quite cool.
But you can use also despite this plugin to say, okay, I have this test, but I don't want
anything under this test to use more than 25 megabytes, and MemRay will make sure that
this test will fail, even if the test itself passes, if it uses more than 25 megabytes.
So you can use that your functions are limited by whatever you want.
So yeah, this is the profiler.
It's just one among many.
There is many, many other good profilers, and this is just complementary to them.
But we think it's quite cool.
We put a lot of effort into developing this thing and open sourcing it, and we hope that
you like it.
You can check it in that URL, so github.com BloombergMemRay, and I hope that you use it
for finding why your programs are getting so big.
Thank you very much.
Super cool.
Very excited about that.
Okay, next we have Graham, who has no slides, but is going to talk to us about the grief
cycle, data security breaches, and how we could code the future of America and the world.
Let's give it away for Graham.
First of all, I think that title is a little bit grandiose because coding the future of
America and the world is a little bit of a challenge.
It's a little bit grandiose because coding the future of the world is a big topic.
Can I get a show of hands?
Who here knows someone that has been hacked?
Now, who here has been hacked?
Now, raise your hand if you are proud that you got hacked.
I didn't think so.
One of the big things that I encountered when I was doing research in my master's program
was a real issue with shame that came with being hacked.
And it kind of built onto this grief cycle concept where you start, people actually are
going through a grief cycle because of the shame of the fact that, oh, I'm compromised,
my data, myself, it's my fault.
And it made me reconsider how we as, I mean, Python, this is PyCon, we should be the
people to be helping people with this sort of thing.
And in the future, we're going to be building things that will shape the minds of everyone
that uses the internet.
That was loud.
And for that reason, I think it's really important that we look at it from a holistic
perspective because I think there's some parts of this grief cycle that people are going
through, like in the workplace, even on our teams or our friends or even our clients,
that there's lots of people that we don't know they're in the anger phase, and we try
to sell them something.
And while in the anger phase, they're just not going to buy something because who would?
And I think that there's a lot of potential.
There's a, I don't think it, I know there's a lot of potential in machine learning and
specifically, I think, in reinforcement learning for the advancement of even our understanding
of the way social dynamics work.
I'm kind of excited to see what the next couple years hold in terms of modeling social change,
like figuring out how we can create models to maybe do conflict resolution with people
that are in a grief cycle, with maybe a chat bot that helps people to calm down before
they talk to a human so that the poor customer service people don't have to deal with that.
And this really came to my attention whenever I had to do cold calling.
And that was one of the hardest jobs I ever did.
It changed my perspective of that whole industry, and it really made me appreciate those people
and what they go through.
And I think that's the kind of people that we serve with open source software.
And that's the kind of thing I'm excited to work on with all of you is this working on
making machine learning without bias, working on building things that work and that can
actually enact change.
And I really, really appreciate being here this year and for everything that PyCon offers.
On that note, we appreciate all of you being here at the end of a long day or for many of you
who have been here many days.
But up next we have Mason, who is going to be talking to us about what is synthetic data.
There it is.
There we go.
Okay.
We'll try that again.
Hello.
My name is Mason.
I will be talking about synthetic data today.
Usually whenever I try to do a talk, what I'm trying to do is I'm trying to do a presentation.
I'm trying to do a presentation on how to do that.
And I'm trying to do that.
So I'm going to be talking about synthetic data today.
Usually whenever I try to do a new topic, what I'm trying to do...
Keep going with this.
Yeah, we'll do that.
You know I speak with my hands.
Okay.
We'll try this for the third time.
Synthetic data.
My name is Mason.
One of the first things that I do whenever I learn about a new topic is I usually try to find some sort of
definition on the Internet that gives it some sort of explanation.
So the definition that I've found is that synthetic data is artificially annotated information that is
generated by a computer using algorithms or simulations and it's commonly used as an alternative to real world data.
After I read that definition, I was just as confused as I bet some of you are.
Let's look at a couple of examples and some of the problems that synthetic data solves.
So data is one of the biggest problems that developers face today.
Getting access to usable testing data is usually pretty difficult.
The data could be in a production database or you don't have some sort of access to it, you're not on the right team.
The data may contain private information such as social security numbers, credit card numbers, all of these kind of things
where it's not safe for a company to allow every developer within the company to have access to this data.
Another problem that developers have with data is the limited data sets.
35% of the time that goes into building a new ML model is spent just in the data gathering phase and it is the
largest phase that happens in the ML thing.
Trying to find relevant data that helps us is very difficult.
And also our data is biased. We very often don't have a complete data set.
This can be intentional or unintentional, but very often the data has a really slanted view in one way or the other
and it's a problem that we have to deal with.
Synthetic data comes to the rescue in almost all of these situations.
One thing synthetic data can do is it can make private data accessible and shareable.
What you can do with your production data is you can take this production data and run it through a synthetic data generator
and then generate an entirely new data set that is statistically equivalent to the production data set,
would give you the same things through any sort of testing, any sort of machine learning algorithm,
but it has now been completely anonymized and you would not be able to know that this came from a production data set.
You could then in turn share this data and use it wherever you want it.
It also allows us to generate more samples if we have a limited data set.
Say we have a data set of only 5,000 elements and we need a much larger data set because our model will perform better
if we have more data to train it on. We can generate as much of this synthetic data as possible as we want.
We can generate a million records, a trillion records, however much you want,
and we can with pretty good accuracy tell you that this data is still statistically equivalent to the original data set.
We can even reduce bias in machine learning data sets through a combination of some of these techniques.
So a really good example that is in this slide, and I'll give these slides and all these links after the presentation,
is reducing AI bias in predicting heart disease with synthetic data.
This slide talks about a case study where they were looking at heart disease data from patients.
70% of the data which came from men, because that was the data that they had, 30%, was from women,
and it was very biased towards the men's side and it didn't perform very well.
We were able to then take this data set, shrink down the men's size to a 50%,
and then take the 30% that we have for the women's set and expand upon it using synthetic data, generate it,
and then the model actually improved in accuracy from 88% to 96% because we were able to de-bias the data.
But a lot of you may be going, well, isn't synthetic data just fake data?
And the answer is no. There's actually a very big difference between synthetic data and fake data, or mock data, if you will.
When a lot of people think of fake data, they think of faker.
And one of the problems that I've had people tell me is that faker sometimes gives too perfect of results.
Like all the data sets are always filled, they're always meaningful.
That's not how data comes in the real world, and we all know that.
So fake or mock data has no accuracy. It's purely random.
Synthetic data, on the other hand, is nearly as accurate or in some cases, as represented by this paper as well,
can be more accurate than the original data set when trained on a specific model.
So where can you use synthetic data? The answer is everywhere.
Automotives, financial services, cybersecurity, health care, and life sciences with genomics, all sorts of things.
How can you, as the audience member, start using synthetic data?
Gretel, the company that I work for, has open sourced our synthetic data model.
We have one right now. There are more coming.
So if you have a really good GPU or are using Google Collab, you are more than welcome to try to use it.
Or you can use our cloud offering. It has a free tier.
It also gives you all the synthetic data scores to tell you how far your data has drifted, differential privacy, a whole bunch of things.
You can check out this blog. I'm doing an open space, 250 AB tomorrow at 4 on Saturday.
And that's all the time I have.
Thank you, Mason. Love synthetic data.
All right. Next up, we have Sophia who's going to talk to us about HoloViz.
Take it away.
Hello, everyone.
Hi. My name is Sophia. I'm a data scientist from Anaconda.
Today I would like to talk about HoloViz.
HoloViz is my favorite Python visualization ecosystem, which comprises seven libraries,
panel, HVPlot, HoloViews, GeoViews, DataShader, Param, and Colorset.
With more than hundreds of thousands of downloads per month, it is one of the most popular Python libraries.
So my data visualization workflow really starts with HVPlot.
I use HVPlot with panel to build dashboards, and I use HVPlot with DataShader to visualize big data.
HVPlot, you might be familiar with pandas.plot API.
HVPlot just works and looks and feels just like pandas.plot.
To the left here, we have pandas.plot API plotting x, x, and y-axis with matplotlib as the backend.
To the right, we replace dotplot to dothvplot.
So you can see this is HVPlot plotting.
This is the same plot with bokeh as the backend.
In the HoloViz ecosystem, you can actually use different backends from your preferred library like matplotlib, bokeh, plolly, and et cetera.
Next, I want to show you an example of how to build a dashboard using HVPlot and panel.
So you might be familiar with pandas.pepline.
To the left here, we have a pandas.pepline.
We define, this is a pandas.chain method.
This is with a car data set.
We define the cylinder and manufacturer, and we group by some variables and calculate the meaning of the horsepower.
What if we want to interactively select the cylinder, manufacturer, and all that?
Instead of using those defined values, we can actually use panel widgets.
Here I define three panel widgets, cylinders, manufacturer, and x-axis to define the variables we want to take the mean of.
And then the result is an interactive table or interactive data frame, which you can plot interactive plots on.
So here is the final result with a few more lines of code.
If you want to see full example of this, full code of this example, please go check out my GitHub page.
It is this link here.
And then finally, I want to show you a simple example of how to visualize big data using HVPlot and data shader.
To the left here, again, we have pandas.plotapi plotting 11 million data points of NYC taxi drop-off locations.
As you can see in this plot, it is a blob, and it's very hard to extract meaningful information from this.
With HVPlot, we can use the restorize equals true option, which uses data shader under the hood to plot this data meaningfully and interactively really fast.
If you want to learn more about HoloViz, please check out the documentation at holoviz.org and also the documentation of HVPlot panel and data shader.
I have also written several blog posts on data visualizations at Anaconda Nucleus, Anaconda Cloud.
Anaconda Nucleus is a data science engagement content and community platform.
Please go check it out. It's pretty cool.
Thank you. Please feel free to connect me at Twitter and LinkedIn.
Thanks, Sophia.
Excellent. Thank you so much, Sophia.
Up next, we have Shabai, and I'm really excited about this.
Go ahead, without further ado.
With a little ado, because we need to put the dongle on the computer.
A small ado.
A dongle-sized ado.
Oh, no. We're going to do a comedies get up here.
No, I don't think so. We should.
All right. Let's give them another round of applause.
One moment.
Hello.
First of all, welcome everyone to the lightning talks.
I'm Shabai. I'm a contributor and sponsor for Robin.
Robin is an async Python web framework with a Rust runtime.
Today I'm going to be telling you all about it.
First of all, let's get to know about how Robin actually started.
It's a project from one of my really close friends, who is one of the original creators of this project.
Basically, back in April of 2021, he was in his final year of college.
He was basically preparing for his final thesis.
Along that same time, there was a huge build with Rust or basically rewrite in Rust.
A lot of different software were being rewritten using Rust because Rust is such a popular language.
Because of its performance.
At that point of time, he was also working on a side project that was being built with Flask.
He also was working a lot with Node.js.
He wished that Flask could actually get async support, which it lacked at that point of time.
He decided that why not just create another framework that could actually become the next async Flask.
He was aware of Fast API, but he just wanted to create his own Rust-based framework.
That's how Robin actually came into play.
One of the biggest benefits of Robin over other Python frameworks is that everyone should be knowing about the notoriousness of the global interpreter log that is there in Python.
Which does not allow it for being truly concurrent.
That's where Rust, because it natively implements multi-threading, is much more faster as compared to other Python frameworks that might have been built using Python or CPython.
Robin also comes with a coupled server.
That means that it does not have to depend on an actual or an external ASGI.
If we just compare it against all the major frameworks as compared to, such as your Flask, Fast API, Django.
This test that you see in this table was done over 10,000 different requests for a simple HTTP request, get request.
You can see that Robin is actually the fastest as compared to all of them across different kind of stream workloads.
Quickly coming to the architecture.
Essentially, since it's a Rust-based runtime, we are basically compiling the code of Python into Rust, so it's getting converted.
Now, if you can see the worker event cycle, this is sending requests to the router, which basically contains various Python-based code objects, which basically are there for each and every separate route that is being generated.
Now, once this basically, the router sends this code directly to a thread pool, which then distributes it along the different threads based on the workload of the CPU.
And this sort of becomes really great if you want to truly scale it, because each of these worker events can be distributed amongst various CPU cores.
And if you truly want to scale it further, you can distribute this workload across various CPU cores, and that makes it super impressive, as you can see from the results that we saw from the comparison.
And of course, if you want to get used to it, you can simply install the Python packets for Robin, and you will be able to use it very simply, as you might actually use something like Flask, of course, with the added benefit of being async.
And well, if you want to get involved, if you like the project, you can give it a star by going to github.com, and you can also join the Gitter community for the Robin project, and you can also follow the Robin project on Twitter.
And of course, if you want to connect with me, you can connect with me on Twitter at the rate HODL up.
But thank you so much for attending today's lightning talk.
All right. Yet another web framework, just what we need.
I'm just joking.
We can always make them faster, right?
I think you need a Donald?
You got one. Oh, sorry. I'm vamping because I thought we were moving on.
All right. So this is Chris.
Chris is going to give us a talk on elegant code in three steps.
Is the first step just use Python?
Maybe. Yeah, maybe. So, okay.
Give it away for Chris.
I'm told in America they make things bigger.
Anyway, my name is Chris May.
I'm excited about talking to you how to make code elegant.
To make code elegant, we need to refactor.
And that is because it is practically impossible to make elegant code,
code that is well documented, code that you can understand,
code that you can maintain the first go around.
And thankfully, since people have been writing code for decades,
we have decades worth of tools that you can use to refactor, such as code smells.
People have categorized specific things they call code smells,
which are things that suggest opportunities for improvement.
In addition, there are specific methods you can use to refactor your code.
Each of these have a list of specific steps you can follow to make sure that
your code is always going to run and it's going to be more elegant when you're finished.
But there are a lot of them, right?
How are you going to keep them straight, especially when we don't have this list there, you know,
or you don't know which one you need to follow?
Wouldn't it be great if there was a way that you could just follow something simple
to make your code more elegant?
Well, thanks to Heineck telling me about this book, 99 Bottles of OOP,
I've been really impressed with Sandy Metz and Katrina Owen.
They spent two years trying to figure out how do you tell people,
how do you explain how to refactor?
And they created this thing called the flocking rules.
So these are the three rules.
But if I were to read them to you right now, I mean, you're not going to get it.
So we need a little code to kind of walk through, right?
So in trying to learn the flocking rules, I started creating code
that would recite the 12 Days of Christmas song.
So here are two verses that I started working.
So first thing we need to do is identify the things that are most alike.
In this case, there are two verses. That's easy.
We need to find the smallest difference between them.
I'm going to focus on the first lines of each of these cases, right?
The only difference is the word first or the word second.
And next, we need to make simple changes that will remove the differences.
So the first and second, we need to come up with a concept that encapsulates this idea.
When verse is one, this thing will be first.
I'm going to use the word day.
It makes sense to me. We don't have to stick on this.
We can always refactor it later. So day.
So what we need to do is create new code that represents day.
With Python, we just make a function.
Next, we need to make this code ready to return the data that we want.
And I should say, I made tests for this. We should be running tests.
I ran the test. The test passed.
And that is good because we know we have valid code.
We now add what we need to return, run our tests.
It passes again. We know we're ready to incorporate it in.
So let's do that.
Parse, execute, and use the results.
So we insert that in, right into this first opportunity.
Run our tests. They pass. We're doing good.
So technically, you can say we can go to the next one, delete unused code,
but we've got all code that's being used, so we could go back through the flocking rules.
Or you can kind of focus in and say, let's just stick here and refactor this whole thing through.
So the next thing we need to do is incorporate the second.
So it can return second. So Day needs more information.
Let's give it to it.
We pass in something that we know we can delete later,
because we want to make sure the tests pass at this point, which they do.
So let's do that. Let's add the code to return second.
Let's incorporate it into the code.
Now let's make the two pieces of code the same.
Just like that.
And hey, look at that. They're identical now.
So we can delete unused code, which is this little extra code that I put in here.
And we now have code that's more elegant.
And at this point, you can go back through the flocking rules again.
And the thing I love about the flocking rules is that it's always kind of fractal in nature.
So no matter where you are, you can just jump back into them, make your code better.
And if you get pulled away while you're in the middle of refactoring and you don't know where you are,
you're going to have working code that works, obviously.
And you can always jump back in and make it better.
Well, thank you. If you want more tips like this, check me out at everydaysuperpowers.dev,
where I want to give you the superpowers you can use every day, and on Twitter at underscore Chris May.
Thank you very much.
Thank you so much, Chris.
And up next, we have Chris, who's going to be talking to us about getting to 100% coverage
and why it matters.
Check one, check two. Thank you.
Thank you all for staying for the last lightning talk of the day.
So I'm going to talk to you about 100% test coverage.
100% test coverage is when we have all lines of our code covered by test.
I want to talk about, is it worth it? Is it worth getting to 100%? And how can we get there?
So this comes out of my two-year journey to achieve 100% test coverage on an open source project called Static Frame.
I achieved that goal, and I got that 100% banner there.
It was really hard, but I made it, and it's very satisfying.
Initially, I was very skeptical about this goal, because 100% test coverage does not mean 100% behavior coverage.
And aren't all those new features you want more important than 100% test coverage?
I believe 100% test coverage is worth the effort.
At least we have exercised all lines of our code when we have 100% test coverage,
and this is critical in Python where unexercised codes will not be evaluated.
It does not guarantee correctness, but it does offer many additional benefits.
So this is my journey through the CodeCov timeline of my coverage.
And you can see in January of 2020, I set out to get to 100%.
I didn't make it. I got to about 98%.
And then you can see my coverage wander and start to slip away.
And then I realized one day my coverage was slipping.
So I tried again, and then I got distracted, and my coverage drifted, drifted.
And you see this pattern repeat over and over again until finally in January of 2022, I got to 100%.
And it's much easier to stay at 100% once you're at 100%.
So that's really one of the important takeaways here.
So what is it in that last 2% that was so hard?
Well, one of the things is non-trivial, unreachable code.
This is not the unreachable code that Pilent tells you about.
This is the unreachable code that is due to a logic problem that you haven't evaluated correctly.
So that's one of the things that I found.
But overwhelmingly, what you find is hard to test code.
There's a reason that's the last 2% is because it's hard.
And that often leads to valuable refactoring of your code and improving your designs.
But is less than 100% good enough? If you have like 93, can you say, well, I tried?
Well, many popular open source packages do not make it to 100%.
And we can see one example here.
So I argue that less than 100% is not good enough.
And there's a number of reasons.
So the first is, as I said, the last 2% of lines is the hardest to test code.
And there are probably real bugs in that code.
It's also, while you're working on your code, hard to tell if you are growing or reducing coverage if you're not at 100%.
I mean, you can check your coverage every day, but it's going to be harder to follow if you're not at 100%.
Furthermore, without 100% coverage, you have less confidence that any refactoring you do is not going to break things.
Without 100% coverage, it's hard to tell if pull requests are adding enough coverage.
And this helps make test expectations really explicit for your contributors.
So, for example, here in a GitHub PR using the CodeCover Report tool,
we can see that I added 10 lines of code in this PR and I added 10 lines of tests.
And if you merge all your code through your PRs and you have code coverage looking at your coverage with each of these PR,
you can maintain 100% coverage in your project.
So how do we get to 100% coverage?
Well, the first step is building coverage into your continuous integration.
And I've used CodeCov.io for a number of years. I've been very happy with it.
There's probably alternatives out there, but it's worked very well for me, and it's free for open source projects.
You'll need a couple of packages. The coverage package has been there for a long time and is a great utility.
The PyTestCov plugin works with coverage to derive your coverage in your PyTest runs.
Now, you need to get this in your continuous integration.
So I use GitHub Actions, other continuous integrations. You can probably do the same thing.
You can see here I just run PyTest with the Cove plugin, and I tell it to give me an XML report.
And then I use the CodeCov action tool to upload that to CodeCov, and that's all we need to do.
Set this up with your continuous integration, and you'll get constant coverage updates.
So a couple of practical tips. So not every line needs coverage.
You can use the pragma no-cover declaration to skip immaterial lines.
Now, you don't want to just skip stuff because it's hard.
You want to skip stuff that really doesn't need coverage.
And a good example is unimplemented abstract base class methods.
Like, that's code that should never be called. We don't want coverage on that.
In addition, while you're studying your coverage, I recommend putting comments in your code.
When you identify lines that do not have coverage, it's a good idea to put a comment in your code right away
to tell you coverage is missing there.
So later on, when you're not looking at your coverage and you're maybe working on your test,
you can find what's missing and work on getting that coverage.
Finally, you can debug when you're test writing tests to get coverage.
It's useful to debug on that line because you might think you're getting coverage there, but you're not.
So I implore all of you, stop adding new features and chase down that remaining coverage.
Thank you.
Right down to the wire. Nice job.
All right. Next talk is by Indra.
Is your mic working? I think it's probably on.
Yep. Thank you.
All right. Let's give it away for Indra.
Hi, everyone.
Thank you so much. Really excited to be here. My name is Indra.
I'm a Python developer and I'm a big fan of frameworks.
So I worked extensively with Django and GraphQL and SQLAlchemy and more recently with Keras and TensorFlow.
I was part of Bankpipers in Bangalore and I attended PyCon in India,
but this is my first time attending PyCon in the U.S.
So really excited to be here and talking to you all.
Today I wanted to talk to you about a medium article that I wrote called Pandas to Production.
And as I said, I'm a fan of frameworks and I'm becoming a fan of frameworks that help data scientists
very quickly take their models from a Jupyter Notebook and make an API service out of it.
There are many sort of frameworks that do this today.
There's FastAPI, there's Kubeflow, MLflow.
And I have used BentoML, which is one of the open source projects that also aims to do this.
So what's the problem it's solving?
Machine learning models are easy to build and prototype iteratively on a Jupyter Notebook.
But then we don't, like typically data scientists have to hand this off to a DevOps team or a MLOps team more likely these days
because someone needs to understand the machine learning side of it, the DevOps side of it, writing APIs.
And everyone can hire an API engineer and an infrastructure engineer to do these things.
So here's a very quick tutorial on how you can do all of that if you sort of work with one of these frameworks.
So step one is sort of the easy bit, which is the model.
I guess not easy, it's the bit that's easy for the data scientists.
So I'll skip over this.
I'll just tell you that I'm using a pre-trained sentiment analysis model that I pulled from Kaggle.
And so what's step two?
Step two is defining the API service contract.
So what does your endpoint take as input?
What does it provide as output?
How does it respond to queries?
And in this example, I'm going to try and step through code live.
And this may or may not work very well.
But you can see that I have imported BentoML and the framework itself has ways of interacting with model artifacts.
So in my case, my model is a SKLearn model.
So I'm importing that kind of artifact.
And also I'm telling Bento that I'm expecting a JSON input.
And really all I'm doing is writing a very simple sort of Flask API endpoint.
So you can see my class is a sentiment analysis class.
It's a Bento service, which means this is going to be exposed at a certain endpoint.
There's a couple of big packages that I'm declaring I need.
And this is important because it gets packaged into the runtime environment.
And I'm defining that I expect a model artifact which will be pickled.
So it's going to be loading from a pickle file.
And then I just have to implement a predict function.
All this does is says, okay, I'm expecting some kind of JSON input.
And then here's all the code that I have to write to make my model an API.
I'm saying, let me parse the JSON.
Let me load the model artifact and run predict on that.
This is going to load the SKLearn model, run predict on my text.
And then for each prediction, I'm just constructing a JSON response.
I'm saying, here's the sentiment score.
Here's the sentiment score name.
And then here's the text that I predicted on.
Seems simple enough.
So from there, the next step is to package this model and serve it.
So all I need to do is import that particular model, call Bento service, and say,
hey, this is the service I defined.
This is the model that you need to run on.
And then all it's going to do is it's going to load those two together,
load up a Docker environment, install the pip packages at the cloud,
and ready to serve.
So that exposes a Flask endpoint, which you can see right here.
It comes with a bundled health metrics and other endpoints.
And I'm able to execute and get responses from this API.
With a couple of quick changes to that, and I'm coming up on a minute,
so I'm going to run through this.
With a couple of quick changes to that, we can instrument error tracking
and performance metrics measurements.
So I will skip down to the end and show you how I've done that.
So relying on our good friend Sentry here, so import Sentry SDK,
set up your Sentry config, and you're ready to go.
Sentry will start tracking errors as long as there is a try except block
and you're doing capture exception.
Bento ML comes bundled with Prometheus for performance metrics tracking.
So I have two metrics that I've defined here.
There's a request time metric, which measures latency,
and there is a text length, which is more of a custom metric.
So I'm interested in how many queries am I being asked at any given time.
And with that, you can see some zero division errors that I forced here
and Prometheus logs out of the box.
So this is part one, hoping to do part two with A-B testing and more.
Thank you.
All right. Thank you, Indra.
And that does it for tonight's lightning talks.
But if you enjoyed these lightning talks, you might also enjoy lightning talks
tomorrow morning, tomorrow evening, and Sunday morning.
If you want to give a lightning talk like these fine folks that just gave talks today,
you can sign up for tomorrow evening and Sunday morning lightning talks
in the boards directly out that back door right next to the registration booth.
Anyone can sign up to give five minutes to talk about whatever they want.
And as a point of clarification, if you are selected, you will be emailed.
So look for an email.
And write your email really nicely on the board, because if I can't read your email,
I can't email you to tell you that your talk has been accepted.
Exactly.
All right. Thanks, everyone. Have a great night and see you all tomorrow.