.
Hey, everybody. Good morning.
It's 8 a.m. What does that mean? Do you know what that means?
I don't know. What does it mean?
I think it means we should start lightning talks. So first up,
we have Pandy who is going to talk to us about, I can't see
the slide, how to write a test case, of course.
Hey, y'all. My name is Pandy Knight and I'm the automation
panda. I'm a developer advocate at Apple tools and director of
test automation university. Today, I'm going to show you a
simple but powerful technique for writing test cases like a
pro. First, let's define testing. Testing is interaction
plus verification. That's it. You do something and you make
sure that it works. A test case is a procedure for making those
interactions and verifications. There are several kinds of tests
like unit tests, integration tests or end-to-end tests. But
all functional tests do the same basic thing. They try something
and report pass or fail. That's how testing keeps us safe.
Testing provides an empirical feedback loop for development.
Without tests, we know when things break. Without tests,
coding can be dangerous. The last thing we want to deploy are
big old bugs. So if we intend to spend time writing tests, how
can we write good tests? There's a simple but powerful pattern I
like to follow. Arrange, act, assert. Arrange, act, assert is a
tool that helps you capture your test cases. It prescribes an
order of operations. First, arrange inputs and targets.
Arrange steps should set up the test case. Does the test require
any objects or special settings? Does it need to prep a
database? Does it need to log into a web app? Handle all these
operations at the start of the test. Second, act on the target
behavior. Act steps should cover the main thing to be tested.
This could be calling a function or method, calling a REST API,
or interacting with a web page, or anything else you need to do.
Keep actions focused on the target behavior. Third, assert
expected outcomes. Act steps should elicit some sort of
response. Assert steps verify the goodness or badness of that
test. Sometimes assertions are as simple as checking numbers or
string values, but other times they may require checking
multiple facets of a system or using something like visual
snapshots. Assertions will ultimately determine if the test
passes or fails. You may have seen arrange, act, assert in a
different way. Grrken's given when then format from BDD is the
same thing as arrange, act, assert, just with different
parameters. So here's a basic unit test for Python's absolute
value function. I wrote this using PyTest. This test may seem
trivial, but we can use it to illustrate our pattern. The
arrange step creates a variable named negative for testing. The
act step calls the abs function using the negative variable and
stores the return value in a variable named answer, and the
assert step verifies that answer is a positive value. I like to
use this as a reference to noting each phase of the test
case as well. Let's kick it up a notch with a more complicated
test. The example test, this example test, the duck duck go
instant answer API using the requests package that I'm sure
many of you have used. The arrange step forms an end point
URL for searching for Python programming. Notice the base
URL and the query parameters. The act steps call the API using
the URL with requests and then parse the response body from
JSON into a Python dictionary. The assert steps then verify the
HTTP status code was 200, meaning okay or success, and the word
Python appears somewhere in the responses abstract text. We can
clearly see that arrange act assert pattern works for both
unit tests and feature tests. So why should we use arrange act
assert? It makes each test focus on an individual behavior
independently. If a test fails, you'll know the reason clearly.
Remember, simple is better than complex. So thank you for
listening to my lightning talk. Again, I'm the automation panda.
If you want to learn more about testing and automation, check
out test automation university. We've got about 70 courses for
free. And I'll see you today at 1.45 for my talk managing the
test data nightmare. Thank you.
Applause.
Excellent. Thank you so much. Up next we have Shreya.
Thank you. Hi, everyone. I'm Shreya and I'm a product manager
at Microsoft. Today I'm going to talk to you all about
computational thinking and the potential effects of incorporating
it into school curriculums. So when I was in the fourth grade, I
had to figure out what day it would be 100 days from Tuesday.
So to come up with my answer, I wrote on a page the days Sunday,
Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday, and so on until I filled the whole
sheet of paper. And then I counted from one to 100. And I did
this about three times because I really, really wanted to make
sure that I got the right answer. In contrast, today, if I find
myself repeating the same task even once, I think to myself,
you know, there must be a better way. Like, I could probably
automate this or something could be different here to make this a
more streamlined workflow. But this kind of reasoning can also be
classified as pattern recognition. And this reasoning should be
taught to students in all disciplines, across all curriculums,
because it can really change the way we solve and analyze problems.
So what is computational thinking? The way I like to think about
computational thinking is that it's computer science concepts at
their very core. So it's the ideas behind inventing effective
solutions, but with no regards to the syntax or the structure of
writing the actual code. Computational thinking contains four
main components, decomposition, pattern recognition, abstraction,
and algorithm design. These concepts directly play a role in
computer science, but they also have a lot of value across all
other disciplines, as well as real world scenarios. So when each of
you got here to this convention center, at some point or another,
it's probably likely that you had to go out of your way to find a room
for a talk. For me to find this room, I went through the following
steps. First, I looked around, are there any signs to the room? And
if so, perfect, I found it. And if not, I picked a random direction to
walk in and went back to step one. And I kept repeating this process
over and over again until I found the room. So what I want to explain
here is that without even knowing it, without even thinking about it, I
was using decomposition for so many different scenarios this weekend.
And by calling out my thought process, I can now optimize for better
results and also carry over this logic to other aspects of my life.
So you might be thinking now, why focus on computational thinking,
right? Why don't we just teach everyone how to code, especially
because we've had really good results with Python, which is an excellent
introductory language, and we've seen how young students are able to
successfully pick it up. So I really want to emphasize that my proposition
is not that we replace teaching code with teaching computational thinking.
Rather, I feel that computational thinking is a really solid precursor
before we teach coding. And I feel like given the educational resource
constraints that do exist across the world, and they do contribute to the
barrier in entry when it comes to development, I think computational
thinking is a great way to start, especially because we don't have to make
a new class for computational thinking. So it's not like you're adding a
subject to coursework, nothing like that. It's really actually just adding
material to existing curriculums and reframing different conversations to
make them more computational thinking based. So when I talked about finding
the room earlier this weekend, or this week, all of you probably thought,
well, yeah, I did that too, right? I somehow found the rooms that I went to.
And my point is, you know, like, you didn't do anything new because I talked
about that. It's just that you looked at it in a different way. You framed how
maybe you see that same problem. So in that same theme, I feel that
computational thinking should really lie beneath lesson plans and change the
perspective in which the next generations can solve and analyze problems.
As you go on for the rest of the day and perhaps the rest of the week, I
encourage you to think about what medial tasks that you're completing and what,
if any, component of computational thinking they might fall into. With that,
thank you all so much for listening. If you want to discuss further or have any
questions, please feel free to reach out to me. Thank you.
All right. Next up, we have Patrick, who's going to talk to us about latest.cat.
Okay, let's see what it is. Latest.cat, give him a round of applause.
Yeah, hello, everyone. Today I wanted to show you a tool that I've been building
for a couple of weeks. And I never showed anyone, to be honest. But I think it's
quite useful. So my issue was that every time I wanted to install the latest
version of Python or the latest version of 3.7, I was having to go to
python.org, then try to find it maybe in the homepage. And then you had to find a
couple of steps to go and just find the version and then put it into your favorite
tool for installing Python. So I built this tool that's called latest.cat, where
you can write the software name, which works with a couple of languages at the
moment, but can be improved. So you type it and then it gives you the latest
version for the Python that you want to check. And it should work also for 3.6,
but that works on command line. I'm going to show you an example now. So yeah,
made this quick demo here that you can use it using curl. So you can do curl
dash L dash S Python and then it loads the latest Python version. Also works with
other tools like Node.js. And it also works for some reason with SSH, which I think
is quite cool. It was just fun to do. There's going to be a demo for that in a second.
This is probably useless, but it was fun to do. Yeah. And hopefully it's going to be
useful for any of you. It's open source, so you can add additional languages by
going here. Software.yaml, it works with Go, Swift, Python, PHP, Rust and other
things. And yeah, if you need something like this, if you need other tools, you just
send a request and happy to merge it. Yeah, and that's me. That's not my cat, but
this is my cat. Thank you. I'm a huge cat person, so that makes me very happy. Up
next we have Ray. Hi, I'm Ray from Data Science Rebalanced. We make data science
tutorials to help bridge the gap between academia and industry. Today we'll talk
about behavior-driven machine learning. So let's say you want to build a machine
learning model. You're going to need some data, push it through a training pipeline,
and ultimately end up with model parameters. So how was I taught to do this in school?
I was usually given a data set. Let's call it a binary classification. The two colors
here represent the two classes. And I would be taught to use all of the data available,
split it into a train test split. But not all data is actually equal. If I look at this
data set, some of this data is more important than the rest. This data in particular. So
how would I do it now that I'm in an industry? Well, I would think of my data set as a
collection of behaviors, and I want to iteratively find all of the behaviors that are
important from my data set. If I look at this data set, you might think, well, just take a
random sample. But there's an issue with random sampling. It actually can lead to increased
bias. For example, if I have a certain portion of my space where there's a dense amount of
data points, if I randomly sample, that portion of the space will be overrepresented,
therefore producing bias. As such, I actually want to take a clustering approach and then
randomly sample, let's say, three data points from each one of my clusters, represented by
the three green dots in each cluster here. Those green dots represent my initial training set
that I build a model with. Now, if my model is represented by this red line, my model thinks
everything above the line should be a blue dot and everything below it should be an orange
dot. But clearly it's got a few things off. So how do I correct this? Well, that red line also
happens to be the area where my model is confused. In binary classification, this would be a 50%
confidence score. And so I want to select items that are around that 50% confidence score and
add them to my original green dot training set. So now I have a larger data set, slightly larger,
and I build a new model. I go from my first model to my second model. That's a little bit better.
But I can repeat this process again with my second model, grabbing data points near 50%
confidence, slapping them into a training set, and going ahead and going from my second model
to my third model. But what does this actually mean in the real world? I'm probably going to
actually run this process about 100 times, every time adding extra data onto my data set. And what
each dot represents is a newly trained model. So my performance metric will improve and at some point
it will actually top out. And after that, as I add more data, I'm actually going to get worse
at performing models. So what does this end up buying us? A few things. First, if I have a labeled
data set, I can actually build the best model possible, which probably isn't the one that uses
all of my data. If I have an unlabeled data set, I can save a lot of time in labeling because I don't
need to label the entire data set. And as we discussed already, I can reduce the bias in the model
with this approach. If you're interested in this topic, in academia it's often referred to as
active learning. There's a wonderful book called Human in the Loop Machine Learning by Robert Monarch.
And if you're interested in any other data science content, please reach out to Data Science Rebalanced.
We have a link tree. We teach all kinds of courses on Skillshare and provide medium articles.
So reach out at any time. Thank you so much for your time.
Applause.
Awesome. Thank you, Ray. And next up we have Geir, who's going to talk to us about reading PEPs, right?
Oh, I see it now. Reading PEPs. Let's give him a round of applause.
Applause.
Yeah. Thank you so much. And my name is Geir Aniala. I work with RealPython, creating content there.
And now I want to talk to you about the joy of reading PEPs.
So I suppose one of the things you hear quite early in your Python journey is the PEP 8 document.
But the PEP part of this is often not really explained. So what are these PEPs?
They are Python enhancement proposals. And these are actually fairly technical documents that are
specifications for how Python should work, new features of Python, and also how the processes, the governance
of Python is implemented. Really technical stuff that really needs to go into the details to show off
all kind of edge cases that you have with them.
One of the things I really like about reading PEPs is that they're also historical notes.
They show how the language has evolved over time. They often capture some of the discussions that were made
before introducing a feature and also some of the decisions and especially also which things were left out of the PEPs.
It's been available online essentially all the time. And it's also on GitHub.
And that's a nice place to go back and look at history of this.
But in February this year, they redesigned the web page and now launched peps.python.org.
And we can have a quick look at this. So it's this very nice page.
And if you just go to peps.python.org, you come to the index of all the PEPs.
And we can kind of scroll down and see that there's a lot of documentation here.
The PEP 8 that you may have heard about is here, the style guide for Python Guide.
And this is definitely one of the more readable PEPs that really goes into some of the more ways that we agree
that we should write Python to make it Pythonic.
What I've also done since I've been reading quite a lot of these when I'm creating tutorials,
I've also created a small Python package called PEP docs.
And this provides the PEP command which makes it easier to just download these PEPs.
So if I go into a terminal like this, I can also just type PEP 8 and we see, okay, something happened here at least.
So let me just pipe this into less. And we can see that this is the same document that we saw.
So here we have the same introduction and these kind of things.
But now I have it in a terminal so I can start to play with things in the terminal.
Additionally, there's a few more things I can do here.
So if I look at the help, we can see that I can also actually open this web page quite easily just by typing minus W.
It pops up. So if I don't want to go to the browser and actually play around with this,
I can also convert this to markdown.
So the format of PEPs is that they're in REST format, Restructured Text.
But sometimes markdown is easier to work with for many tools.
So for instance, now I open a different PEP. This is PEP 13 about how the language is governed.
It talks about the steering council which we'll also get to see afterwards.
But I can now also then save this to a file.
Now I have it here and I can for instance use the nice rich project to just look at this.
Let's see, page. And we have a much more nicely formatted markdown here.
So yeah, thank you, Rich.
And also I can then use something like, let's say, PEN.
Let's see, we need the markdown. PANDOCK to convert this directly to PDF.
So if I now do PEP 657 PDF.
I now have a PDF file of this. So I can read this nicely like this.
And one of the cool things with the PEPs is that they have, as I mentioned,
these discussions about how the features are implemented.
So if I go to the motivation, I can see why was this feature included.
And some of the more interesting discussions are within the rejected ideas,
what things were not included and why were they rejected from the PEPs.
Okay, so just to sum up a little bit, PEPs, they're fantastic to read if you want to figure out
why some features are designed as they are.
PEPs are not tutorials. There are a few exceptions to this.
PEP 636, for instance, is a great tutorial on the pattern matching thing.
But there are usually better ways if you're looking to learn how to use a feature.
Then you should go out and look for the tutorials.
But in general, PEPs are fun to read.
So, yeah, thank you so much. And this is me. Thanks.
Awesome. Thank you so much for that. Up next we have Jonathan.
Hello. So I'm Jonathan. I like to build fun things.
Not all of those things are useful.
This talk will be about a fun thing. I don't know if it's going to be useful.
So many of us use PIP. I don't know if everyone knows,
but apparently PIP is also a backronym for PIP installs packages,
which got me thinking, what exactly is a package?
I mean, we know of source distributions. We know of wheels.
If we've been around a while, maybe we've heard of eggs.
But I was at a talk yesterday, I think, and they mentioned that you can put
a command line tool inside of a package.
And it was a compiled binary. It was Clang format.
So we can put command line tools. So I thought, well, how about C Python?
Could we put that in a package? Specifically, could we put that in a wheel?
In which case then PIP wouldn't be PIP install packages.
It would be PIP install Python.
So we're going to do a demo. I want to say that there's no shenanigans here.
This is actually like, okay, there's a little shenanigans,
but only because I didn't want to rely on the conference Wi-Fi.
And nobody wanted to see something download for two minutes.
But you can follow along. You have to be on Linux.
I just thought of this yesterday, so I didn't have time to build everything.
So let's go to a terminal.
So this is the Python 3.7 slim image.
So we have Python. It's an older version.
We can't use the walrus operator.
So let's just PIP install. Unfortunately, someone's already taken the name
C Python, and Python is like locked. You can't give it.
So I said, give me Python. Give me Python.
And we're going to want a version that is, let's say, compatible with 3.9.0.
Yeah, that's not going to work. We need an equal sign.
So this is going to be used to cache wheel. It would download,
but it takes like two minutes to download, so nobody wants to see that.
This is a real wheel. It's Mini Linux 2014.
It actually passes the Mini Linux 14 standard.
It's run through audit wheel.
That said, it does vendor a whole bunch of shared libraries.
And this could be done for other operating systems.
Unfortunately, this is the boring part where we all sit and wait for PIP
to do some things and install a whole lot of files.
And we also see that I'm running as root. I'm sorry. YOLO.
So now, of course, we have Python now 3.9.12, but we're not going to call it
Python 3.9 because that might shadow your system Python.
So it's going to be GM for give me Python 3.9. It works.
You can do things. It has shared libraries.
So what? So we installed CPython by PIP.
Of course, could we install packages in that PIP as well?
Like, could we do Python inside Python inside Python?
So let's try it. So we need to do GM Python.
We're going to run PIP and we're going to install give me Python.
So this will work. It takes a while.
And oh, I need to say install. Yes, that would be helpful.
So this will go and fetch Python 3.10. It's going to take a while.
So I'm going to skip over to this one that already has this installed.
Unfortunately, you don't get a command line shell.
Because this is inside another Python, it doesn't work.
But we can just run the module. And now we have free time.
All right. Thank you.
Oh, that's it. All right. That is awesome.
I'm waiting for the inevitable future when just everything is on PIP.
Yeah, it's going to be great. All right.
Next up we have Jelle talking to us about PEP 6.88.
Let's give him a round of applause.
Good morning. I'm Jelle Zellstra.
I'm a Python core developer interested in static typing.
And I'm here today to talk about the buffer protocol.
The buffer protocol is a way for type implement in C to allow access to the raw bytes inside the representation.
Like you can use it as a bytes object, a numpy array, but not, for example, a string, which isn't a raw array of bytes under the hood.
But I told you I'm interested in typing.
So when I write a function like this, I want to put type annotations.
And the problem here is I don't have anything to put in those question marks.
There's no way in Python right now to say any buffer type.
So I want to fix that. And I wrote a PEP for it, PEP 6.88.
And the first version that I wrote, which is now up on the PEP's websites, adds this new buffer type that you can implement in C.
It has a subclass implementation that just checks whether the buffer protocol is implemented.
So you can check that the bytes object is a buffer, a numpy array is a buffer,
a string object is not a buffer. And it works fine for the function that I showed.
But there's a problem. What if I want something more than just the buffer protocol?
Like I want to also have a buffer that provides a length, which is a pretty common thing to have for a buffer,
because inherently it's a collection of bytes, so it has a length.
But in a type system, there's no way to say you want both a concrete class, like buffer is right now,
but also a protocol, like sized. So I have another problem. I still can't write the types that I want to write.
And I don't know how to fix that yet, so I'm going to show some ideas,
and I would like to hear from people who have feedback on these, what they think the right solution is.
One thing I thought of is to actually make it possible to implement a buffer protocol in Python
by adding a DunderBuffer method that you could just implement in your own types too.
The nice thing about this is that PyPy actually has the same thing already.
I guess they need that, because in PyPy everything is Python, so you have to implement this in Python.
It's also nice that this is useful outside of static typing potentially.
But it's also a lot more complicated in just adding support for typing,
because it changes the runtime representation of buffer types.
And in the C protocol, there's this slot for releasing a buffer, and I don't know how I would represent that in Python.
So there's also a simpler idea. We could just add a DunderBuffer flag to these types.
You set it to true if it's a buffer, and if it's not a buffer, it's not there.
It's a lot simpler, but it doesn't really feel like other Dunder attributes,
because there's nothing else that really works this way.
It also makes it pretty easy for types to lie about being buffers, which I don't like.
So yeah, if you have any feedback on which of those approaches would work well,
I'd love to hear about it. Come find me during the rest of the conference,
or talk about it on discuss.python.org, or just email me. Thank you.
Excellent. And up next we have Nick.
All right. Good morning, PyCon.
So today I'm going to be talking about post-pandemic meetup and an organizer's dilemma.
So my name is Nick Mo. I am the CleePy meetup organizer.
So that's the Cleveland Py... Yes, thank you.
Cleveland Python Meetup group, and I work as a data scientist at Trimble Transportation.
You can see my little logo at the bottom.
So the last CleePy meetup was two years ago, March 9, 2020.
I have a little picture here. It was an amazing day, filled with pizza, laughs,
and so the occasional, does anybody have a dungle here?
That was the occasional thing, right?
But as you all well know, I'm a big fan of the CleePy meetup.
The pandemic has changed everything. So what has happened since then?
We had to go virtual, right? And everybody was like, virtual meetings?
Ooh, yay. Right? So there was a lot of uncertainty about that.
So how did this affect us?
As I said, once we shared the news with the community,
it was like, oh, I'm going to go virtual.
So there was this dilemma about how can we get them engaged?
So as I said, there was a lot of uncertainty.
CleePy seemed to last people think about the pandemic was going on.
There were so many things going on.
There was so much uncertainty about what was going on in the world.
Figuring out a way to engage the community,
figuring out how to engage the community,
figuring out a way to engage with the community was tricky.
The best way to get them excited about going back to virtual meetings
after being in countless meetings at work all day.
Finding people to give talks, you would think, would be easier.
It's a virtual meeting, less pressure in person.
No, it's not as easy.
And overall, personally for me as one of the co-organizers,
it was pretty taxing having to deal with my life work
and worrying about how to get our community back together and still strong.
So how did CleePy fair throughout the pandemic?
Well, I think we crushed it, right?
We've had 21 very successful virtual meetups since our last in-person meetup.
What does it mean?
For the last two years, 2020, 2021,
we've had a virtual meetup every second Monday of the month, nonstop.
The community has been amazing and the turnout has been super encouraging.
Honestly, there were days where I felt like we had to cancel it
because I don't know what to do.
But you can see here a couple of pictures we have here about all our virtual meetups.
So it was really encouraging and really wonderful.
I loved it.
So what's the goal for 2022?
In-person CleePy meetups again.
That's the goal for 2022.
And thanks to my company, Trimble,
they are going to be sponsoring us and giving us a venue and feeding us too.
So we're really excited about that.
So if you're in Cleveland, please come to CleePy every second Monday of the month.
You can see our next one is on May 9th.
So if you're in the Cleveland area, please come by.
You can see that's our Twitter handle and that's my Twitter handle,
at Spirx on Twitter.
Thank you so much.
Thank you, CleePy.
If you guys are watching this, I love you guys so much.
Thank you, PyCon.
All right. Have a nice day.
Awesome.
And next up, we're going to hear from Dustin about what is it going to be about?
Next up, we have a parade of regional conferences.
So I'm going to ask the organizers to come over here by the side.
So we're going to go through just some excitingly upcoming recent and,
sorry, regional conferences that are going to be happening in the next year.
So if you like PyCon, maybe there's a conference happening near you.
And let's see, where's Chook?
All right.
Let's give all the regional conferences a round of applause,
and they're going to tell you why you should come.
You first.
You know, EuroPython.
So, yeah, EuroPython is in July.
I would say that the best PyCon in Europe will be EuroPython.
The second one will be maybe PyCon Italy.
Yeah, so it's like very similar format.
Who really enjoy PyCon here this week?
So, yeah, it will be very similar.
We also have tutorial.
We have conference talk for three days, and then we will have sprint.
So also we have PyDataTrack for those data folks.
You will find something that you like there.
And also we have a lot of Guinness.
I think that will be the main difference.
So if you really like PyCon,
if you really want to have another week-long conference at maybe somewhere closer or further,
I don't know, then yeah, please come.
So, yeah, I think that's it.
Looking for my notes.
Okay.
Hi.
My name is Phoebe Polk, and I'm here to invite you to join me and many other Python people
in beautiful Mission Bay, San Francisco, on Saturday, September 10th.
It is a one-day outdoor Python conference in the park.
Tickets are on sale now at our website, pybay.com.
Call for proposals are open.
Please submit a talk before June 3rd, and I hope to see you again very soon at PyDay.
Thank you.
Hi.
I'm Yoshida.
And I'm P. Kok.
We are co-vice chair of PyCon JP 2022 from Japan.
PyCon JP is the largest conference in Japan.
This year, PyCon JP will be held in mid-October.
The CFP application will be start next Monday, 9th of May.
You can also make a talk online.
The sponsor application will be start also this month.
You can appeal to Python users with the largest PyCon in Japan.
We will inform you of the latest information on our blog, Twitter and Facebook.
For more information, please visit 2022.pycon.jp.
Please join us.
Thanks.
I'm the only one from Taiwan, as far as I know, in this conference.
So if you're by chance also from Taiwan, please contact me in this last set of conferences.
So Taiwan is hosting the PyCon APEC this year, 2022 on September 3rd and 4th.
And it's unfortunately a virtual conference because we still have very strict travel restrictions.
Code for proposal, unfortunately, has ended.
If you have already proposed, I hope you get selected.
I don't make that decision, so good luck.
Also code for sponsors, obviously we are representing the talent group in Asia in the APEC area.
So you have access to the best talents in the world.
Takes it on sale now.
Right now it's early bird.
I think there are some late bird and some corporate selections.
Please come join us online and meet us all.
Thank you.
Hello everyone, I'm Patrick.
I just wanted to invite you to PyCon Italy, which is going to be next month in Florence.
It's going to be really nice.
We have awesome keynoters.
We have a PyData truck, we have a web truck, and lots of interesting social events.
And if you cannot join, because I know it's in a month, we also have an online version, which is going to be free,
which should probably be announced out soon.
Thank you.
Hope to see you there.
Good morning.
We are here to invite you to go to Python Brazil this year.
It will be between 70 and 23 October in Manaus in Amazon Forest Zone.
And we will see talks in Portuguese and Spanish, roundtables, sprint, tutorial, lightning talks, open space, job fairs,
and all activities have signal language.
It will be an online and in-person event, and there is a kid space.
We are also going to have the PyLadies Brazil conference.
We always have every year during Python Brazil, so I would like to invite every PyLadies to go to.
And I hope I can see you there this year.
Thank you.