Hello everyone.
Welcome back.
So we have our first talk in the evening by Zachary Sala Corleason on Localize Your Open
Source Documentation, a Kubernetes case study.
Over to you, Zach.
Hello.
So as advertised, this talk is about localizing documentation for open source projects based
on the experience of localizing Kubernetes documentation.
My goal today is to encourage you to localize your project's documentation.
I will do that by sharing advice based on what the Kubernetes project has learned about
localization in our own documentation set.
I have given previous versions of this talk that focus on different aspects of the Kubernetes
experience.
If you are interested in research and tooling, I recommend watching my talk at FASDEM in
2019 titled Multilingual Kubernetes.
If you are more interested in site analytics relating to localization, I recommend watching
my talk at Write the Docs EU in Prague also in 2019 titled Found in Translation.
So who am I and why am I up here talking to you about all this?
My name is Zach or Sarah.
My pronouns are they, them or she, her.
Feel free to use my names and pronouns interchangeably.
I am currently a staff technical writer at Stripe, previously at the Linux Foundation.
And I served as chair for Kubernetes documentation from 2017 to 2021.
And I'm still an approver for the documentation in the Kubernetes project.
And I'm also here because one of the maintainers of the NumPy library invited me to submit
this talk and I said, sure.
So what is localization?
To paraphrase the W3C definition, localization is the adaptation of documentation to meet
the language, cultural and other requirements of a specific target market.
This definition, I like it because it highlights that localization is more than translation.
And when I first started learning about localization for Kubernetes, I wondered why isn't machine
translation good enough?
Why can't I just plug all of this into Google Translate and have it work?
And the short answer is that while machine translators are powerful tools, they often
return translations that lack linguistic and cultural relevance.
So in this talk, I'm going to speak to you as if you are all project maintainers, but
this talk is for contributors in any role of an open source project.
So TLDR this talk, I absolutely believe that most open source projects can and should localize
their documentation.
And while localization does require some effort, the rewards greatly exceed the work required
to do it.
So here I say expensive and costly to differentiate between two different things.
Localization doesn't have to be expensive or costly.
And by expensive, I mean the financial expense of localization tools, tool subscriptions,
things like that.
It doesn't have to be expensive.
And by cost, it doesn't have to be costly.
I mean the cost of attention and labor in projects where maintainers already struggle
with the burden of maintenance in the project.
So localization doesn't have to cost you a lot of money or impose a significant burden
of labor.
That said, localization does require maintenance.
It requires maintenance to do and then some maintenance to upkeep.
And for localization to be sustainable in open source projects, that means choosing
our maintenance wisely.
And I said on a previous slide that the benefits of localization are greater than additive.
When you localize, you get more back than you put in.
And one way in which localization benefits projects is that when localization...
Sorry.
My time has me hurrying along and I'm just going to stop that.
So one way in which localization benefits projects is that when projects localize,
they usually attract a new set of maintainers, new contributors and new maintainers.
So when you localize, you open the door for more people to become contributors and maintainers
to your project.
So with the need for selective maintenance in mind, based on what we've learned in Kubernetes,
some of these things we've learned the hard way, here is some advice about how to localize
and scale your project while minimizing the amount of required maintenance.
This is probably the single greatest factor to being able to scale localization in Kubernetes
docs.
Be indifferent to the origins of localized content.
Don't care where it comes from before it shows up in a pull request.
And this applied indifference is one of the keys to sustainable maintenance.
There are some reasons to be indifferent to localized content before it shows up as a
pull request in your repository.
And one of those reasons is that different tools work better for different teams.
There are a host of tools out there.
TransFx, CrowdIn, Google Translate, your time and attention as a maintainer gaining expertise
in these tools and then trying to support them for multiple localizations that doesn't
scale and your attention and time are not valuable when you try to support these things.
So applied indifference is one of those things that saves you maintenance.
And every team has tools and processes that are going to work better for them.
And that kind of non-standardization is healthy, but it also means that you as a maintainer
have to be selective with how much attention you put into the origin of localized content.
One of the benefits of this as well is that it is somewhat tool-proof.
If machine translation somehow becomes the perfect localization tool tomorrow, you're
already prepared because you already don't care.
That said, once localized content does arrive in a pull request to your repository, you
must care deeply about how it's reviewed and approved.
So here are some tips for a good, strict review process.
Don't allow authors to approve their own pull requests.
This is seldom a good practice.
It's especially not a good practice in localization.
Require a review process.
And in addition to requiring reviews, it's good to limit who can review localized content.
I highly recommend requiring reviewers to have native or equivalent fluency with the
content they review.
I have zero fluency in Mandarin.
I do not approve Mandarin language content for Kubernetes documentation.
I know that strict reviews are required.
I know that content, when it is approved, meets the standard of quality, that it is
legible and meaningful to the people who consume that content.
So establish a canonical source language and branch.
A canonical language and branch are useful for the same reason that upstream Git remotes
are useful.
A canonical source language and branch helps your project scale.
It means that localization teams are working from the same understood source.
And it's an efficiency piece.
I recommend matching your canonical source language to the primary language of your contributors
and matching your canonical branch to the project's published branch.
Whatever branch it is that you publish to the website, use that as your canonical branch.
For Kubernetes, English is the canonical source because it's the primary working
language for the majority of contributors, both to documentation and to feature development.
Main is the canonical branch in Git because it's the most current version of docs published
on the website.
It doesn't have to be English.
If your contributors work primarily in another language, consider using that language as
a canonical source.
I recommend establishing a minimum viable documentation set.
The origin for this phrase, minimum viable documentation, is Heidi Waterhouse, who is
seated here.
Identifying a minimum viable documentation set serves a couple of purposes.
I think the most valuable is that it clarifies your project's most critical content.
This will help you develop empathy for your users.
What do they most need?
What can they not live without?
Another reason is that it establishes a threshold at which a localization meets the requirements
for inclusion in your published docs.
You have a very clear understanding of what is the requirement for a localization to meet
before it can be published.
I recommend scripting away common functions.
These links are to Python scripts.
They're in very tiny print, for which I apologize deeply.
These are Python scripts for tracking diffs between localization branches and for tracking
diffs from upstream source, from the canonical branch.
I talked earlier about how some translation tools, how it's good for each team to have
their own workflow around creating localized content.
As a corollary to that, there are some tasks that every localization team shares in common,
and it's good to standardize those.
Every team needs to track diffs across their own collaboration branches.
This is a script to basically find out what did everyone else work on since the last time
I ran the script.
Where are we as a localization?
The other script tracks upstream changes in order to keep that localization current.
What changed upstream that we need to now localize?
Unlike translation tools, which remember we don't care about, diffs are automatable.
If it's automatable, it's therefore scalable.
This also standardizing in this kind of scripted way makes it easier for you as a maintainer,
and it makes it easier for teams to be able to support each other in a decentralized way.
This is another one of those greater than additive benefits.
I recommend using tools that support localization or internationalization.
Choose a content management system and static site generator that have built-in support
for localization.
For example, Hugo and Gatsby are both static site generators that have built-in support
I recommend using a tool, whatever it is that you use for a static site generator.
Choose one that is built on a language that aligns with your own projects, languages,
and source of expertise.
This increases scalability.
Kubernetes uses Hugo because Hugo is written in Go, and unsurprisingly, Kubernetes has
a deep pool of Golang expertise.
Avoid hard-coding strings.
This is an efficiency piece, and it's also a scalability piece.
I will say little about partials apart from mentioning just don't hard-code them.
Instead, I will refer you to the Hugo documentation for partials and for the Kubernetes website
repository as an applied example of what localized partials look like.
Partials only work once you solve for repository permissions, or rather they're an example
of what you need to solve for with repository permissions.
Permissions are tricky to solve for.
The permissions required for localization teams to work effectively don't map well
to the granular permissions that Git allows repo admins to assign.
I do have a recommendation for how to solve for permissions, but I want to dig into the
specifics of why and how permissions are problematic for localization projects.
One example is branches.
Neither GitHub nor GitLab permit granular permissions to only create a branch.
When you assign permission to create a branch that is bundled with the permission to merge
or to delete not only a particular branch but any branch in that repository.
The easiest way for localization teams to collaborate is on shared long-running branches
in the project repository.
This creates a challenge in projects where people contribute by forking the repository.
There's a whole set of reasons why it's a poor idea for multiple contributors to work
on a branch of one contributor's fork, especially for a long-running fork.
Conversely, there are good reasons to localize on a long-running branch that is off of the
project's main repository.
That means assigning a localization team the permission to perform right operations in
the project repo.
That raises a whole host of concerns.
With that comes the question of permissions for approvals.
You will almost certainly not be able to assign repo permissions in a way that matches the
permissions that localization teams require to configure themselves and only themselves.
For example, Hugo requires that localized markdown files be placed along a language-specific
path, slash content slash two-letter country code.
It would be for Korean, it would be slash content slash KO.
Hugo requires that localized content exist on that file path, but Hugo performs the site
configuration for a localization in a root-level config file, config.toml.
The Hugo parser will fail a build if content exists on a file path and it isn't properly
configured in the root-level file.
Localization requires permission to alter root-level files, and that's concerning for a whole host
of reasons.
Partials are another example of that.
Hugo puts all of its string partials into a directory off of the root-level that is
not on the localized content path.
Granular permissions, it's impossible to assign them in a way that the Venn diagram is 100%
overlap.
Assigning permissions, giving localization teams enough permissions to do what they need
to do, creates a problem of trust.
The intersection of team needs and get permissions creates choices about security that are unfortunately
pretty either or.
It's all or nothing.
Not 100%, but it's pretty hard binary sometimes.
So let's talk about trust.
And trust is where you as a project maintainer decide what kind of maintenance you want to
engage in.
Low trust means engaging in the custodial maintenance of periodically creating, merging,
and deprecating branches at increasing scale, which is to say that it doesn't scale.
Or you can have higher trust and engage in occasional forensic maintenance, forensic
as opposed to custodial, forensic maintenance of undoing disruptive actions.
Please note, disruptive, not malicious.
There have been many disruptive actions related to localization work in the Kubernetes repo,
but none of them were malicious.
We're very fortunate in that regard.
It does require vigilance.
It does require maintenance.
But this is where you as a project maintainer and you as a project figure out how you think
about trust.
So I recommend treating localization teams with the same trust that you would give to
any release branch.
And to treat localization maintainers the same way that you would any other release
lead who has right permissions.
Not everyone who contributes localized content needs right permissions, but in order to scale
as a project, every localization team should have someone who serves as a team lead and
with whom you as a maintainer have explicit and well documented conversations about security
and trust.
Perhaps unsurprising coming from a technical writer, but document everything.
A frank and explicit conversation about trust and permissions requires a thorough written
understanding.
Every project has norms, expectations, and boundaries about what people who have certain
levels of permission can do with those permissions.
Because expectations and boundaries are cultural and because localization is also about cultural
relevance, it is important, I would say critical, to document the expectations and boundaries
around localization work in your project.
Every single disruptive action in the Kubernetes website could have been prevented with better
documentation about the expectations for permissions and what people can and can't do with them.
So I recommend making issues and pull requests filterable by language and one of the easiest
ways to do that is with repo labels that are specific to a language.
They are an easy solution to what otherwise is a big maintenance burden.
Without the ability to filter by language, it's just it's toil and as with any form
of toil, I highly recommend automating it away.
So I recommend language labels that follow the format of language plus the two letter
country code or a two letter language code, excuse me.
This tracks to the same standard that you use to set that content path in a repository,
for example, and it makes it easy to correlate that this label applies to this content.
And you can automate these with a GitHub action.
There's a GitHub action that will specifically apply a label to a pull request based on the
content in that file path.
So when localization contributors identify something that needs to change in the upstream
source, it will often open a pull request that includes both the change in the upstream
source and their own localized content.
And these are the most noble and well-intended pull requests and they almost always languish
because multiple languages require multiple approvers.
It's a bit of a hassle to say to somebody, hey, can you do this in two pull requests
rather than one, but they will get approved more quickly based on practice.
I recommend preview builds.
It just makes the review process faster and easier for everyone regardless of localization.
Kubernetes uses Netlify to generate preview builds.
We use it as our content delivery network.
It's what actually publishes our rendered content.
And it works great.
It works great as well with the site CI-CD.
So this is one of the best kept secrets in the Kubernetes website and I wish it wasn't
a secret because I wish every project had a smoke test page.
A smoke test is one page generated from a single markdown file that contains an instance
of every syntax or formatting element in your docs.
And this is great for figuring out whether a proposed change works as intended.
When you localize different languages have different site element requirements.
And this is a great way to test that.
And you can follow this particular path to a smoke test on preview builds so you can
see whether it works before you approve it.
So this page, the smoke test page is crawlable by robots, but it's de-indexed from site search
so it doesn't interfere with organic search results.
So handy.
So it is easier in some ways to set up a framework for localization before any of the work actually
happens.
On the other hand, there are real benefits to adding localization tooling and workflows
in equal partnership with the contributors who are actually doing that work.
So both of these approaches are valid.
Do it before you need it, wait until you need it.
It's kind of a wash.
So is localization worth it?
All of the advice that I've offered so far has been on the level of implementation detail
and systems level process.
So it's not clear from my advice what maintaining a localization looks like in practice.
So I want to examine some specific maintenance cases.
And I would like to use the example of Korean language content on kubernetes.io for the
month of March 2022.
So in March of this year, six people contributed Korean language content to the kubernetes
website.
And site traffic for Korean content constituted approximately 2.1% of site visitors.
At this point, you may be asking whether the advice that I'm giving you is worth the work
for six contributors at 2.1% of site traffic.
So let's unpack those numbers a bit.
So in March, kubernetes.io had 1.4 million visitors for a total of 4 million sessions
and 10 million page views.
Forget those millions for a moment.
For 1.4 million visitors, 2.1% of site traffic is 30,123 visitors.
And those six contributors in March sustained a one to many support ratio of just one to
over 5,000.
One to 5,000.
Each one of those people who contributed localized content had the net effect of supporting 5,000
people in one month.
And that is a phenomenal number.
So yeah, 1.4 million people.
Of those site visits, only 52% of those visitors viewed content in English.
total monthly traffic was to localized content.
It is absolutely worth it.
So localization teams contribute more than just their own language content.
Localization teams contribute to upstream source.
They contribute to each other's mutual support.
Localization teams in related language groups consult with each other for their own mutual
benefit.
Localization teams contribute to shared tooling.
Both of the scripts that I linked to earlier.
None of the English language maintainers contributed those scripts.
Those were from the French and Korean teams respectively.
And those are a benefit to the entire project.
And localization teams often become not just contributors but maintainers to a project.
So what's the point of all of this?
Why do we localize?
It is not for its own sake.
We don't localize for our own sake.
We localize to increase access to our projects and to drive adoption of our projects.
And when you open a door, people come in.
And that's beautiful.
So here are some resources for this slide.
Again in tiny print, deepest apologies.
This is to the Kubernetes documentation for how to contribute localized content.
This is a link to the website repository and the Python script directory.
This is a link to the Hugo static site generator.
And here's a link to the NumPy projects, that library's own localization work and the ongoing
discussion there.
Shameless plug, buy our book.
Last year I co-authored a book called Docs for Developers, an engineer's field guide
to technical writing.
I co-wrote it with Heidi.
It's a good book and you should totally buy it.
Thank you very much.