Welcome, everyone, to our second session, talk here in the session.
And today, right now, we really have the privilege of having Pablo here, who works at Bloomberg,
but he also is a very active CPython core developer, and he's here to tell us about
improvements to error messages in Python.
So please join me in welcoming him.
Hello, hello.
Well, I've been told that I speak very fast, so buckle up, because this is going to be a ride.
Awesome.
So who I am?
Well, thank you for the introduction, so I will keep this brief.
So CPython core developer, I'm serving on this year Python stream council member.
I'm also the 310 and 311 release manager, and also I work at Bloomberg.
But this is kind of boring, so let's talk about error messages, right?
Cool.
So let me, you know, all good talks start with a story, so let me tell you a story.
So before joining, I started doing computer science and engineering.
I used to be a physicist, so I was doing my PhD.
And although I'm a theoretical physicist, something that you need to do from time to time is that you need to do simulations.
So at that time, doing those simulations is when I started using Python.
And it was this day when some friend of mine that was also using Python, also doing their PhD in physics,
came to us, we were three in the room, with one syntax error that they couldn't figure out.
And we spent 15 minutes trying to figure out what was the problem.
Think about that, right?
Three physicists doing their PhD.
We had the tools to solve the most deep mysteries of the universe, but we couldn't solve a syntax error.
Quite bad.
So, you know, syntax errors are important, right?
Because, like, they impact developer time and other things.
So let me give you a tour over, like, how the syntax error were before Python 3.10, with, like, a fancy image there.
Okay, so some of them.
For example, this is a syntax error that I couldn't solve back in the day.
What about that?
What is wrong with that?
Ah, interesting.
So let me give you some context.
Not the full program, but the program looked like this, right?
It was a bunch of things there.
And does someone see the error?
So the error is equivalent to this, right?
Like, you have a dictionary.
You don't close the dictionary, and then you have a function definition.
So the parser continues after the dictionary that should have ended, but it's not end.
And then it tries to find the function and says, well, this function doesn't fit into a dictionary.
And then it says, yeah, that is invalid syntax.
But if you just see the thing, it's kind of not good, right?
Like, it's quite bad.
So this is just one example, but there is more.
Like, for instance, what about this?
What is wrong with that?
Who knows what's wrong with that?
The error is this one.
It's kind of natural, right?
Like, you want to write the tuple there and then generate a comprehension.
But it turns out that you need to parenthesize the tuple because otherwise the parser doesn't
understand what you're writing.
Not the best.
What about this one?
You have a list.
You don't close the list, and then you have a bunch of things.
Like, for instance, you are assigning here something like that.
And the parser says, yeah, that equal, I don't like that equal.
It's invalid syntax.
Or, like, what about this?
You have, like, a nice dictionary.
So you map, like, core developers to their GitHub user names.
You forget a comma over there.
And then the parser says, guke-slanga is an invalid syntax.
If you ask me, it's quite rude.
But, you know, not good.
What about this?
You try to do an exception handler, but with multiple exceptions.
You forgot the parentheses around, which you have to place there.
And it tells you that that is invalid syntax, which is quite confusing.
Especially if you're not used to this syntax with multiple exceptions or if you are starting
to learn Python.
What about this?
You are writing a dictionary, and then you, I don't know, you freak out and don't put
the value here or something like that.
And then you close it, and it tells you that, yeah, that bracket, not good.
So invalid syntax.
And this is the worst one of all.
Like, raise your hand if you have found this thing a single time.
Yeah, yeah, I thought about that.
So this is, like, especially, like, you know, like, EOF.
Like, you know, how many times you have explained to someone what EOF means?
Yeah.
So the idea here is that, you know, in the previous version, we look at these things,
and then we say, look, the reason this works here is not because we are, like, lazy or
something like that.
It's because writing these things and integrating these things on the machinery of a big
language like Python, it turns out it's quite hard.
But it turns out that now, after Python 3.9, we have a new parser.
So I will talk about that in a second.
And this parser has allowed us to start thinking about, like, can we solve these things?
Like, can we improve the experience of people writing Python that make error messages?
Like, they make syntax errors, and they don't know what they mean when they get their own
message.
And this is quite important because many people think that this is crucial for people
learning the language.
But it turns out that I have plenty of experience using this, and I have been extremely happy
that I have fixed many of these error messages since I did.
So, you know, it's also important for people that are experienced.
So let's cover, like, how we fix these errors using the new PEC parsers.
Many of you may not know about these things, so let me introduce you about the PEC parser.
So the PEC parser is something that we did together with Lisandro and Angido on PEP 617.
And basically what we did is replace the parser in CPython, which originally was introduced
in 1990, one of the first comings of Python from Gido.
This is the old one, the old parser.
And the new PEC parser was made 30 years after.
So, you know, like, the old parser was a very resilient piece of technology, but, you know,
we thought that we needed a new parser because there was a bunch of things that we couldn't
do with the old one apart from maintenance-related topics and other things.
So things that we can now do with the new parser are things like parenthesized context
managers, which for technical reasons that I'm not going to go into detail, we couldn't
do.
These are much better because now you can put this kind of, like, you know, open parenthesis
on the subface over there.
And also, like, for instance, match statements.
Who likes match statements?
Yeah, I thought, yeah, they're cool.
You can match a lot of things.
So this is only possible with the new parser, which is great.
But there is a problem.
And I think that people see these things and they are quite angry because they think that
the new PEC parser is like the devil, right?
Because now we have a lot of war of darkness and horrible conclusions because now the PEC
parser allows us to do super funky syntax and whatnot.
But I want to convince you that the new PEC parser is actually quite helpful because,
you know, yes, allow us to do things that you may like or not may like, but those were
possible anyway, and we have a process to improve Python syntax, and that's not the
PEC parser's fault, right?
Like, you know, if you have a knife, the knife can serve multiple purposes.
I will leave it to your imagination what you can do with a knife.
But like the idea here is that the PEC parser now finally allows us to do these new error
messages, which is quite cool.
So let me, to convince you in case you have not seen them before, let me show you some
of the new error messages that we have in 3.10.
We have quite a lot of them, so I'm not going to cover all of them, but some of them.
So for instance, new error message in Python 3.10.
So in mind that you have this conditional, right, and then you forget the colon over
there, which is a common mistake, especially for people learning the language.
So now we told you, yeah, expect the colon.
That's cool, right?
More things.
So for instance, now similar things that we have before.
You're writing a dictionary.
You, for whatever reason, forget to write the value over there.
And now when you do this thing, the parser says, oh, I actually expected an expression
after the dictionary key on the colon, which is also quite cool.
And this is quite common, apparently.
Many, many people were super happy when we showed them this one.
You are comparing something, and then you forgot here that you should put a double equal.
If you're writing C, this seems to be quite bad, because you're assigning to whatever
you put on the left.
In Python, it's a syntax error.
But now we make you a suggestion.
Maybe you actually meant two equals instead of the single equals.
More things, for instance, if you forget a comma in a dictionary, here it's quite obvious.
But like in Maya, you have those big configuration dictionaries instead of .py files or elsewhere.
And you forget a comma, which is quite common.
So instead of getting Gukas, langais, invalid syntax, you get this error that tells you
maybe you are forgetting a comma there.
This has saved me at least 10 times already.
So for example, this one as well, if you are writing a conditional or many other blocks,
and then you don't indent them correctly, now it tells you, oh, we actually expected
an indent block.
And then now we add that the indent block was after the if statement online, whatever.
So you have the context, especially if you have the block after the if is quite big.
And when you mess the indentation, it's quite far from where you write the if.
Now it will tell you exactly what construct was wrong when you unindented the thing.
And of course, everyone's favorite, when you don't close a dictionary and you have the
function, now it tells you, hey, that bracket was not closed, which is very cool.
This is probably one of the ones that people like the most because this is quite common
and the error is one of these unexpected file or your function definition is wrong.
Cool.
So this is a bunch of them, which is nice.
But it turns out that adding error messages is quite hard.
Let me show you some of the interesting stories that happened while we were developing error messages.
So let's say, for instance, that you want to develop the following error message, like
the missing comma, right?
So for instance, you say, I want this, right?
Someone is writing a list and is missing a comma between two elements, so there is no
comma there.
You want to write this thing.
So you are forgetting a comma.
How will you do that?
So you go to the grammar and then you need to teach the parser how the problem looks like.
So here we are, don't forget if you don't understand the syntax, this is the back syntax.
But here we were saying that if you see an expression followed by another expression,
then you're probably are missing a comma, right?
Like things about a variable followed by a variable or one plus one followed by three
or x or something like that.
In those cases, that's invalid syntax, but that probably means that someone is missing
a comma, right?
And then you're happy and then you say, OK, in that case, I'm going to raise this invalid
syntax for how you're missing a comma.
And everything is good, right?
No, no, no, no, no.
Because what about this?
Now someone forgets the in keyword and it tells you that perhaps you're missing a comma,
which is wrong.
What about this?
Someone writes a valid string prefix and now it tells you that you are missing a comma,
which is wrong.
What about this?
You don't close the tuple here and then you put a b after that and it's looking at the
variable on the next line and the two on the previous line and it tells you that you're
missing a comma.
What about this?
This is quite bad, right?
Like look at this.
It turns out that I don't know what is wrong with this, but apparently I'm missing a comma.
It's not good, right?
What about this?
You're writing a bunch of numbers.
I mean, that's a bit crazy, but like it's telling you, this is quite weird.
It's telling you that you're missing a comma, but not at the beginning.
It's the last one.
Okay.
So what about this?
Apparently, match starts to work.
It stops working because it's a soft keyword and now when you do match foo, it's actually
two names following together, the symbolic syntax, and then it goes and tells you that
you're missing a comma.
So we broke match statements.
Sorry, Brent.
Not good, right?
It turns out that this is actually real.
Here you can see all the PRs that I fixed when I introduced the missing comma thing.
Apparently, you know, knowing a lot of our parsers doesn't make you not fail about missing
commas.
That's a quite hard thing to do.
But what about this error?
This is quite funny.
So it turns out that our parser is a PEC parser.
It turns out that by nature, they run in exponential time.
This means that when they are parsing your input, they take a time proportion exponential
to the number of characters that you input into the parser.
To avoid that, we have something called, well, we do something called a pack wrap parser,
which is basically introducing memorization.
So we use a cache in a fancy way.
I'm not going to go into details, but the interesting thing is that once you put the
cache into the thing, the parser runs in linear time and it's very fast and everybody's happy.
But if you forget to put the cache, bad things can happen.
For example, this thing in Python 3.10 takes two seconds to parse.
It's a syntax error.
So if you put a bunch of open brackets and then you put a column, which is bad, but it
takes two seconds.
The parser takes two seconds to realize that this is invalid.
If you add a bunch of brackets, it takes over an hour.
So this is fixed.
So don't worry about that.
We fixed it here.
You know, someone was very happy that we fixed that one.
Probably they can, you know, now they don't need to spare one hour after to know that
they commit a syntax error.
But the reason is because you need to be very careful when you add error messages.
The reason is because we have validated the real grammar of the language many, many, many
times.
We know it's fast.
We know it works.
We are quite sure about what's going on.
And that is great.
But it turns out that adding error messages is a whole new world.
The reason is because the grammar, like parsers, like to know about what is correct about your
language.
That's what they are made for.
Right?
But now you are starting to use a parser into a world which is infinitely big.
It's the world of things that are not Python.
And that is much, much more tricky, especially if you start using some of these invalid rules
from invalid rules and combining them with the real language.
And the problem is that validating that those things are correct and they don't raise weird
syntax errors in weird constructs like the comma that you saw before or, for instance,
these fancy brackets is quite hard.
And it requires, what we found, is that it requires much more effort and much more validation.
Since then, we have made a lot of improvements to the parser and to the techniques we use
to validate these things.
But as you can see, sometimes they slip over and people make fun of us in Twitter.
So please don't make fun of us in Twitter.
We work very hard.
If you want, you can use this thing as a timer.
So if you made your lunch and it takes an hour, so you can put this thing running and
then come back when you finish, which is cool.
Okay.
So these are the syntax errors, which is great.
We solved a bunch of them.
And you can see all of the ones that we added in Python 3.10 on the What's New document
of Python 3.10.
But you can also see the ones that we have added in 3.11, and we will add more in the
future.
But we have even more things.
For instance, we have runtime suggestions.
So what are these things?
These are not syntax errors.
These are errors that happen at runtime.
For example, this one.
Now in Python 3.10, if you do, sorry, collections is the module collection.
So if you type incorrectly some attribute of the module, now we offer suggestions.
So for instance, if you say name topple, which is not good.
So now we tell you, okay, maybe you mean name topple.
And this works with everything.
This works with modules, with custom classes, with things in the library, third-party module,
everything.
And this is great.
We not only offer this thing on attribute access, we also offer this thing on name access.
So for instance, here I'm assigning one variable to a varsal black hole.
I pronounce it correctly, I hope so.
And then you mistype this thing because it's very easy to mistype, and then you get a correct
suggestion.
Believe me, that is the correct version.
So which is very cool.
You know, it's a small improvement, but it turns out that it saves a lot of time, especially
when you mistype a variable in a big, big function, because it immediately will tell
you what's going on.
And I have, this is one of my favorites because since we added this one, this has helped myself
even when we were developing this one.
So it's quite cool.
But the question is like, okay, so how these errors are done?
Because it's a very interesting like category of errors, right?
So let me explain to you how we did this one.
It's very interesting.
So the first thing is that now we have extended some exceptions, in particular attribute error
exceptions, with two things.
Now these exceptions in three times know the name of the attribute that you were trying
to access and the object in which you were trying to access.
So this was the collection module, the object will be the collection module, and the name
will be named topple, badly written.
In this example, it will be X and something.
And then, which is written there.
I don't know why I don't read my own slides.
But then this is an attribute error, it bubbles up.
And then we run a word distance function.
This is a very simplified version that fits into slide.
The one that we use is, I don't know, 200 lines of C code.
Not really great for presentations.
But the idea is that this is a very simple algorithm.
It uses like some version of Levenstein distance to know which are the closest strings to the
one that we provide.
And then it will tell you, okay, so maybe these are the ones that we think is the best
match.
And then it will tell you the correct string of the object to distinguish which ones are
the great.
So basically the algorithm is that once you have this word distance function, you do something
like, okay, so I'm going to use the dir function to know in the exception all the possible
attributes that are in the object.
And then I'm going to one by one check the word distance to that one.
I'm going to pick the smaller one.
And that's probably the suggestion.
We have a ton of extra checks here and there to make sure that we don't do weird things
with those.
But this is basically the algorithm.
But wait, there is something.
Think about this, right?
Attribute errors are raised all over the place.
If we start doing this algorithm to check where are the problems, like exceptions that
are closer and the names, this is very, very expensive.
So we don't do this thing on attribute errors because it will make Python much slower, right?
So what we do here, and basically what I'm saying is that this thing needs to be fast
because if you catch the attribute error, nobody will see those suggestions.
And we need to make sure that this kind of code is still as fast, right?
So what we do here, this is C code, don't freak out, but I will explain.
So what we do here in this C code is basically that instead of doing this thing when you
raise the exception, we do this thing on this fancy function that is called print exception.
So we only do this thing when the exception has bubbled up to the top level and the interpreter
is going to crash already because nobody has catch the exception.
So when we are printing the trace back and all those messages because the interpreter
is going to finish, then at that step, the last thing that we do is this print exception
suggestions, which runs the function that I just showed to you, and then it goes and
it offers you the suggestions that we just showed.
So basically that function over there.
Which is very cool, and so that way we keep Python fast.
We only do this thing when the interpreter is going to finalize and a code that runs
normally and catches exception keeps being faxed.
This is just an example to show you that error messages are quite hard because now you can
try to be nice to people, but you need to make sure that normal usage of the language
is still fast and people don't pay the cost of good error messages in normal code that
doesn't raise error messages.
So more things that we have added.
I'm very excited about this one.
So this is better trace back on Python 3.11.
So let me show you what this is about.
So this is pep 657 that I did with Amaras Kaya and Batu-Hantas Kaya.
It has this horrible name, include fine grained errors location in trace back, but I assure
you that the thing is actually much more great than the name that we placed there.
And it looks like this basically.
So if you before have like a bunch of errors, this is a trace back for some code.
And here it's telling you that in this long expression, so absolute value of this, this,
this, this, this, this, this, the error is none type object has no attribute x.
It means that something in this long line is none.
But which one it is, you don't know.
You probably need to attach a debugger and know what's going on there, which is not cool.
But now in Python 3.11, we might, we show you exactly which one of this is none, which
was this one, which is much more better, we believe.
And we also show you like in the, this fancy underlying credits in all the trace back.
This is also very useful when you do dictionary access.
So before, for instance, you are actually in a big JSON, some response and a bunch of
things here.
And the error is none type object is not subscriptable, which means that in this,
response, some of these levels is none, but you don't know which one it is.
But now in 3.11, we tell you which one is the one that is none, which is great.
Much better, and you know, you can see also like in the trace back, which part of the
function calls were running.
Because for instance, in this particular line here, you could, could be this one over here
with user one or this one here with user two.
Now you know which one it is.
So now you don't need to attach a debugger, which we think is fantastic.
Also, if you are doing like some heavy math, super complicated, this division thing is
quite, quite hardcore.
But now it tells you division by zero.
Which of those divisions are zero now in 3.11 will tell you which one, that one.
So that's great.
So how we do this thing?
So we do this thing basically by injecting into every bytecode instruction extra information.
Like for instance, if you disassemble that dictionary access, you will see that it's
made of Python instructions, which is what we call bytecode.
And what we do is that for to every of those instructions, we attach extra information.
You can actually check this extra information using the disk module.
And it will tell you that for every, for instance, in this binary subscript, one of these dictionary
access, now it has the line number when that happens, the end line number, the colon object,
and then colon object.
And we use this information to know and to show you where that happens.
The actual code to print this thing is quite hardcore.
It doesn't look great.
But it's just that it's quite complicated, but it's very nice because we take into account
many things like, for instance, if you have a binary operator, we point you to the exact binary,
like the plus or the minus or whatever, and we underline different in both sides.
So this is just to show you that we put a lot of effort to make sure that those errors
look nice, they are not intrusive, and we can highlight as much information as is possible.
So basically how we do these things?
So imagine that you have this code.
So once we know there is an error with this code, we analyze the bytecode instructions
from the bytecode instructions of that code with the line numbers and the colon objects
that we have already there.
Then we basically reparse that expression because we know that it has to be valid,
because it's valid Python code.
We get the abstract syntax tree of that expression, and then we combine these two to offer a customized
error message.
In this case, for instance, we use the abstract syntax tree to know that this is a binary operator,
and then we use the error positions to know that we need to point here, and then we use
that information to also add this little carrot over here apart from the underscores, which
is not easy, but it looks very great.
Nice.
So this is all great, but now you may be thinking, how can I help this?
Because I like error messages, I would like to help developing new error messages and
making Python great, and we would love you to help us.
So I'm going to teach you how you can help us do error messages.
Well, the first thing that you can do is to open issues.
Now Python, the issue tracker runs on GitHub, which is quite nice.
Finally, we managed to do that.
More in the keynote tomorrow with the steam council.
But now you can open an issue on the data tracker for CPython telling us suggestions
that you think we should care.
We will tell you sometimes that that suggestion is actually very difficult or it will mess
with other things, so have an open mind.
Don't get frustrated if we tell you that it's very difficult.
Don't get frustrated if we tell you that it's very difficult or impossible to add your
error messages.
But many times this has been happening already.
People have come to our issue tracker and have suggested, oh, what about this particular
error?
And we have implemented that.
So if you have ideas, especially if you are starting to learn Python, for instance, and
you have been frustrated with some of these error messages, it will be super useful if
you come to us and tell us, okay, this has been super hard.
I struggled 20 minutes.
I'm doing a PhD and I was not able to do this.
So that's a good candidate, right?
Also, if you're an educator, you're teaching Python, and then you see a lot of your students
struggling with error messages, we would love to know which ones are the ones that people
struggle with the most.
If you want to be more hardcore, I want you to call them yourself.
The best place to start is to go to this guide that I wrote in the Python Dev Guide.
So you will go to the Python Dev Guide parser.
Here is this big document called Guide to CPython Parser.
It's very technical, but I think it's quite nice.
Some other core developers can validate this assertion.
But the idea is that here you can understand how the parser works in very good detail,
and at the end of this guide, there is a section about how to add newer messages and how to
validate your error messages.
So you can read that, and then you can try to add some error messages.
You add a bunch of test cases, and you can submit a PR to CPython, which will be very cool.
Not only that, but a lot of people have already been doing that.
This is a bunch of error messages that have been proposed by members of the community,
not by myself.
And they have improved, and some of them, except this one, which is an issue that is still open.
But all of them will ship in 3.11, which is super great.
So you can be one of these people, maybe with cooler avatars.
But you can propose newer messages, and I would love to review your PRs.
It's just that you need to take into account that, can we do this thing with an open mind?
Because as you saw, error messages are quite hard, and sometimes people are very excited
and they bring their little error message that looks super great on some particular cases.
But it turns out that we need to turn it down because it's quite complex.
So have an open mind when you propose these error messages.
And that's basically it.
I hope that you have learned a bit about this thing.
I think the moral of the story is that if you are doing your PSD and then you lose your battle
against some syntax errors, then you can study it during years about parsers and grammars.
You can make a new version of the parser of one of the most popular languages in the world.
You can join the Core Dev team, and then you can improve the situation.
Or you can alternatively wait until someone else does this, and then you can use it.
Thank you very much, and I hope you have enjoyed it.