Good afternoon, everyone.
Today we are in room 355 for the 2.30 talk, all the way from Rio, Brazil, software developer
Bia with her presentation, observability driven development.
Hi.
Just testing.
Okay.
Hello.
I'm super thrilled to be here at PyCon and I'm going to talk about observability driven
development or more like invite you a little bit to think about observability before things
start to crash in production.
I hope you've all been there.
It's a fun ride when things start to crash in production.
So first, just like I've been presented, I'm Bianca.
I'm also known as Bia.
I'm from Brazil, from Rio more specifically, which is like amazing city, beautiful.
If you ever want to meet Rio, it's going to be amazing.
And we have an amazing Python community in Rio, too.
We used to have meetings every last Saturday of the month before the pandemic.
So at some point we're going to resume all the meetings and hopefully get back to a more
active community.
And right now I'm building something new at a startup called Lumos.
My focus is engineering, but we are like this super tiny startup.
It's still in stealth mode and we work around the field of productivity, identity and compliance.
You're going to hear from us soon hopefully.
And previously I worked at HeadHead building a platform for Relford Edge Systems and at
Stone which is like a Brazilian fintech.
And most of the time I was working as a backend developer, DevOps engineer, sometimes leading
small teams, sometimes doing a little bit of management, but that wasn't for me so I
came back to an IC world.
So again, before I dive to deep, I want to talk about like I like all things DevOps, CI,
CD, cloud infrastructure, observability.
I also like Go a lot.
I'm a Go developer just like I am a Python developer.
I am still a World of Warcraft player.
I grew up playing Pokemon and Ragnarok during countless nights.
I'm passionate about coffee and beer.
I used to listen to a lot of rock and roll but nowadays I listen to pop and reggaeton
so I don't know what happened.
I think it's the 30s catching up with me.
And I like web, distributed systems, systems architecture and Python obviously otherwise
I wouldn't be here at PyCon.
First question is like why do we develop software?
Like why are we software developers?
I know that some of us think that's going to like this is going to be just a job but
even if it is, why do we have that job?
Like why is there like a need in the market for that?
Why is it such in high demand?
There are like many possible answers to that but one that I particularly like is that people
need it or people want it.
People are the users of our software, the end users.
We can have like a lot of discussion of whether like this software is going to benefit our
society or not but even if it's like something super silly like a game or not, people are
going to use it and you want people to use it.
So someone's needs have to be met.
And software needs to meet someone's expectations like even in machine learning when you don't
interact with it directly, you do want something out of it.
You want like your software to learn something and give you a particular output.
When you're just studying, you want to get something out of it.
And what happens when that expectation like is in math?
It's a bit hard to manage.
Sometimes like a user wants to load a webpage and it can't.
A user expects you to do something and they just can't.
They just couldn't do it because software crashes sometimes.
And not meeting expectations generates a lot of frustration.
And business like that means money loss.
We lose money because we're not meeting our users' expectations.
So normally there's frustration and we enter the problem-solving mode and start putting
out fires.
And normally there's a bug in production.
Software goes crazy, goes insane and tries to fix it right away, especially when it's
a P01 bug.
And we often realize that we don't have enough data.
We think of observability way too late when there is a problem that is already happening
and it's already hard to figure out what's going on.
So this is sort of an open invitation to live fight or flight mode, the anxious moment where
you have to fix everything super fast because it's broken.
And think about this like beforehand.
What can we do when we're just starting, when we are just creating our POC or MVP or studying
our app?
What can we do so that when it reaches production, it is easier for us to figure out what's going
on?
So I'm going to go through APM logging tools and setting up your application, a small problem.
I'm going to talk about good logging practices and a slightly more complex performance issue.
I have to fix that slide.
And find the root cause of that problem.
When I talk about observability, I think one of the first things that come to my mind when
my background is mostly around back end development focused web is that we need an APM logging
tool instead of an app.
Most of those apps, most of those solutions come with both.
So it's fine to just like one tool or a combination of two.
There are some famous ones over there.
We have elastic with elastic search, we have new relic, we have data dog, we have honeycomb,
we have lightstep, we have Splunk.
I use the couple over my jobs, my career.
I don't have like a preference and I don't work for any of these companies.
So I also like, I actually chose new relic because it's the one that I have more experience
but I like a particular preference.
It really depends on your use case and you have to go through the functionalities.
And if you want something to think about and consider, like there's open telemetry, which
I highly consider if you like open source, if you want something that is not going to
lock you in particular vendor.
Open telemetry is going to be like a collection of tools.
You export telemetry data and that telemetry data is going to go from your app to a solution.
So new relic can consume data from open telemetry, data dog can probably do the same, elastic
can probably do the same.
So you can just learn how to have that data exported in a format that is famous and known
by tools.
Like I said, new relic for that example.
The reasoning, like more experience and I didn't want to learn something new just to
present here.
I'm anxious enough just without learning something new.
So let's not do that.
And I came up with the most boring example app that I'm letting you come up with.
I am going to open that app and I want to go through it and show how new relic is set
up on it.
So let me do that here.
This is our example app and new relic is set up here through, I have a main.py over there
And you just import new relic agent to your app and you initialize it in register.
When you do that in your application, new relic is going to be plugged in and going
to look at all of the function calls that you have in your app.
It's going to inspect your application when it's running in production mode.
One thing that I think there's no reason to not do that when you're just starting
an app like with new relic or another tool because it's like four lines of code sometimes.
So we don't do that because no, we want to do it faster but we end up with less data
in production.
So here we have a flash cap, very simple one, non-production ready code, don't copy that.
I also created a database here, populated schema, there are a couple of things here.
When I run Docker and Compose here, this application is going to be up and running.
If you're curious about other things that I have here, it's going to be on GitHub so
you can go to later.
I'm going to just make a request to make sure it's working.
I'm going to bring that here.
You just have to figure out the whole monitor setup because...
Options.
Move this right here.
So here we have a different kind of postman which is Insomnia.
I really like it too so if you ever want to try it out.
You can do a health check on our app.
We can create a new task.
I have a cat, his name is Marcelino.
I bought a leash for him and I go out with him.
It's funny.
He has a TikTok.
So I can create a task to go out with Marcelino and there are a couple of things that my app
can do.
It's just a to-do list.
It's a very simple one.
Like I said, we have new relic setup so I'm going to move that to a new window.
Also move that.
So whenever there's a new request, I just send one.
A new relic is just going to look through my app and it's instrumentation platform.
You can see all the requests that happened, transactions.
There was a patch.
There was a list task.
There was a create task here.
Error rate, success, slowest trace, which is amazing.
One thing that I really like is service maps.
So if it makes external calls to a service or a Postgres database, it has everything
here but I don't work for new relic so I hope they give me swag after this.
And it also shows logs, something that is really cool too.
You can have info endpoint hit and have your log here with a couple of cool things.
And let's go back to presentation now.
So problem is, what happens if a user tries to add a task without a description, something
like that?
Let's try that.
I'm going to try to create a task here without a description, like just empty body.
I know that normally you're going to check for that, the user is going to get the feedback,
but what if you forgot something happened?
User got internal server error.
It's complaining.
I cannot create my task.
You suck.
You're a bad developer.
I'm not going to sign up for your to-do list anymore.
And when you look at the logs, you just say like exception.
Okay, exception.
Could not create.
What happened?
Like, how can I make that user happy again?
How can I let them know that, oh, okay, what happens if I try to create a task without
a description?
I had a problem.
I didn't create my API in a way that you would have a good feedback about it.
How can I make this better to actually give a good feedback to my user?
We can add logs.
That's what's missing, like logging.
When we talk about good logging practices, this is a thing that I really like and I'm
very passionate about, so if you ever want to talk about it, DM me on Twitter.
Let's talk.
I have my very own definition of what's good logging, but I didn't dream about it.
It's personal, opinionated, but I was very backed up with researches and open to discussions.
So if you think that I'm talking about something that you don't really agree, let's chat about
it.
Let's fight about it.
I'm happy to do so.
When I talk about logging, I like plain text messages without variables.
So when you look at the logging message that has a variable, it's very nice for you to
see like, okay, a task was created with an ID X.
Awesome.
But if you want to group these log messages in a tool like Splunk or New Relic or Elastic
Search, you should write those logs for a computer to process it, not for a human to
But also make it so that a human can read and understand.
So your log messages should be like plain text messages.
You should be able to group it, and you should be able to actually give me all log messages
with that message.
I'm going to have a sum of operations of task creators that I have in my app if I just did
that.
But also should have enough information for humans to read.
So how can we, like with plain text messages without putting the task ID, how can I get
that information?
Well, use extra fields.
So you take off the variables of messages.
You take something called extra fields that Python standard logging library has.
And you can use those.
You can add like a big dictionary of variables.
They're important for that log message.
You put as much info as you can.
Don't abuse it in the sense that you're going to send like this huge payload.
But these fields are normally hidden by default view.
And they're extremely useful.
So you like put as much info as you can, like what customer, what is the request ID, all
of that.
And speaking of request ID.
Traceability.
We should have like for every web request, we should have a unique identifier for it.
And this unique identifier should be present in all of our log messages that are related
to that request in order to be able to trace exactly what happened in a particular request.
So I've found myself a couple of times with a JSON payload and going through my code to
understand where the heck this code broke because I have absolutely no idea.
And I had to like go through, read all of the ifs and else and everything to see what
would happen.
So if I had a request identifier, I would be able to like in good logging, I would be
able to see every single thing that happened.
Like I just get the same identifier and get all the messages with that one.
I can see every single thing that happened.
So it's amazing.
And also business traceability.
Like what happened with that customer?
What's going on with that customer?
What's the kind of thing that they use in our app?
So something that is really nice to have too, like customer identifiers, existing log requests
in order to measure the experience of a particular customer.
You can also create a particular SLA for a subset of customers that you have.
So how do you figure out like, okay, what is the time that a particular request took
for a particular customer?
You can do that through logging.
Keeping track of IDs is something that I really like too.
Like every time that I save an object, I write a log line about it.
And I also keep the ID as an extra field.
This allows easy inspection.
If I have to ever go through my database and see like, okay, was that really added?
What's going on with that data?
Is everything okay?
So it gives me a really good overview of things.
And the last thing is that we normally go like writing log lines, just whatever.
I'm just going to go log info, log info everything.
We should be more intentional about logging levels.
You know what kind of information you want to see while developing, what kind of information
is only useful for production.
My rule of thumb is that error is something to pay attention.
Like, I should worry.
Info is extra info in production environment, and the bugs just made for my local development.
That is like my rule of thumb.
But you can also have like different rules across your teams.
Like it's very particular.
But I think that you should be very, very intentional.
And like how can we apply this to our problem?
How can we literally like get these things that I just said and make our customer happy
with the tasks that was created without the description?
So there's a cool thing about using a log handler or a library that is already established
that most of the things like request ID traceability are already set up for us.
So if you look at that log line here that I showed before, like there is like a trace
ID here.
I'm going to make it bigger so you don't suffer too much.
There's a trace ID here.
So Neuralic is already, there's a little log handler that is kind of an adapter of
Python's log handler that does that.
So there are a couple of things that are already here like file name, where the exception happened.
A couple of things that are already like free for us.
That is happening because of, let me open my to-do list app.
That is happening because here in our logger API, make it bigger, we're using a new Relic
log handler that is actually imported from Neuralic libraries.
So this is something that I don't have to worry about when using Flask in Neuralic because
it's already like for free set up for me.
But we talked about like, okay, we lost some information.
So how can we add that here and have more info?
We can add some logs.
So when I create a task, that's the spot.
Bye.
We were creating, right?
So we can just come over here.
We have a logger here.
And I can just say like logger.info, creating task.
When we said like let's use extra fields instead of variables here.
I'm going to make sure that when creating a task, I'm logging my body.
Okay.
We can have that here.
And other than that, like when I save a task, I also like doing the task created.
Instead of doing like task created with ID, I just do task created.
And then I come here.
Task ID.
And in the case of an exception, logger exception, message.
And we're tempted to do this, aren't we?
Could not create that, please.
And your exception can be an extra field.
I really feel like this makes it a lot easier for us to understand where the exception came
from.
Because you can see like, okay, that was what happened when that error in particular happened.
Otherwise, you would have to have like very specific exceptions for every single thing
that happened.
So you could see good errors over there.
I think this has auto reload unicorn.
So I can probably, if the demo gods are with me today, if they are not.
Yeah, I don't think they are.
Oh, okay, yeah.
Because I don't know what I'm doing.
I don't know how to write Python anymore.
And you see like, name is not defined.
I have to do that.
Okay.
Let's see if it's good now.
Wow, it's taking a while.
It did take a internal server error.
Maybe I do want to log that as an error instead of an exception.
Oh, no, I think that's good.
That is okay.
Let's see the log lines here.
Let's see if we have something new.
We should.
Yes.
So smaller a little bit.
So we do have like the same exception that we had before because it's still like, raised
it an exception over there.
But we have a message before.
And these two messages, also I have my error message.
And I can say, oh, okay, description violates not new constraint because the customer didn't
give me a description.
So I can create a bug.
I can fix that now.
And I can actually understand what happened.
And the trace ID here is also equal to the trace ID over there.
So oops.
It's going to laugh.
Supposed to be like equal to this trace ID, supposed to be equal to that one.
So you can actually like look through all log messages with that trace ID.
And that should give you a good idea of what happened with that particular customer.
Which is super cool.
So okay.
First thing we solved.
And did I forget something?
Yeah.
We did plain tags.
We added extra fields.
New relic log gave us a little bit more traceability.
We kept track of the IDs.
We used roughly the right log levels because those are logs that I care about in a production
environment.
I could add even more logs if I wanted more information in development mode.
So when we get to a slightly more complex performance issue, like, okay, I update a
task and it's going to be fine.
You're going to see that.
And here.
Okay.
Updated test.
That task.
And it's fine.
But if I update like a bunch of tasks, it's going to be extra, extra, extra slow.
So New Relic is going to give us like tracing data for that.
Extra, extra, extra slow.
I'm doing something very, very wrong.
Very wrong.
So if you look at traces.
Here you're going to have a couple of trace transactions.
Slow transactions.
Didn't show yet.
But I do have one that is already.
I have a backup link here.
Open.
And it really shows like by segment.
Like the duration of the thing that I did.
And I really did something very, very common when we do patches that I did one at a time.
So I do 100 selects on Postgres.
I do 50 updates.
A couple of rollbacks.
And I called the logger API for 50 times for every log line that I did like updating tasks.
So I really did that.
New Relic is giving me like the time, the duration, all of that.
Which is something that APMs really do.
And once you learn how to read that, performance issues get like super easy to fix on your app.
I am not going to have time to code the actual thing that is going to fix that.
But there is a branch here.
Like I'm going to share that.
Move to new window.
There are a couple of problems here.
One of them, like we said, like Postgres was actually we are adding a select and an update for each task.
So actually updating your patch to do a bulk save would be like the thing to fix here.
So we get many instead of getting just one.
We do a bulk save here.
That also fixed the 50 updates.
And we did just one update on Postgres, which is awesome.
And for the log, for calling the new Relic logger a couple of times, we are still going to call the API 50 times.
But it could make it a sync.
I actually made the log handler asynchronous by creating a sync new Relic log handler.
So the response is going to come back to the user.
The response time is going to be lower.
And the log is going to be sent to new Relic in a different sync IOL loop.
So I'm going to open that PR and leave it right there if you want to check in a little bit.
And let me go back to the presentation.
We found the root cause.
It was nice.
I once had this problem.
I had to process roughly 8 million messages a day and write to a Firestore database.
We had a couple of transactions, like 132 per second.
And that was a performance issue because it was supposed to be real time.
New Relic showed really easily to me that my issue, my bottleneck, was a commit on Firestore.
So that was like a real case where Firestore, I was doing a bunch of updates on Firestore
and doing too many commits.
And that took a lot of time.
When I saw that on New Relic, I was able to do a bulk update on Firestore.
And that brought it up, my performance, to like eight times faster.
And it was great.
It was one of the best feelings in my life.
I think that's because I'm a nerd.
So in this particular problem, it took us like two months to solve this because we just
didn't have the data.
So I was a developer of UACs with good logging practice, APM monitoring, even if turned on
by a flag.
They often grow too fast and observability becomes an issue faster than we are able to
foresee.
So thank you.
Follow me on Twitter for random things in English, Portuguese, sometimes Spanish.
I answer them very, very slow, but I always try.
Slides are here, codes are here.
Thank you so much.
It was great talking here.