All right.
And now we're just going to take a minute to switch out the speakers, but I am very
pleased to introduce Peter Wang, the CEO and co-founder of Anaconda.
All right.
How's everyone doing?
I want to give a big, big thank you to the conference organizers, to Emily, the chair,
to everyone, all the volunteers who have worked so hard to bring us all together here.
It is really wonderful to be in person with everyone again.
I know everyone keeps saying that.
I just want to reiterate how awesome it is to see everyone here.
Actually, I can't see anyone because the lights are very bright, but I'm assuming everyone's
out there.
But today I'm going to go through a bunch of different things.
I'm going to talk really fast.
I apologize.
But there's a lot of ground to cover, and it's super exciting.
Some new stuff we've been working on I want to tell you about.
But the title of my talk is Programming for Everyone, or the Next 100 Million Pythonistas.
You'll see why I call it that.
But to get started, for those who don't know who I am or are not familiar with Anaconda,
I am the CEO and co-founder of Anaconda.
And about ten years ago, Travis Oliphant, the creator of NumPy and SciPy and my co-founder,
we had this insight that Python's scientific tools, the ones that Sarah was just talking
about, that the scientists have been nerding out on for over a decade at that point, that
those tools were really, really ready for prime time in business data analysis and business
data processing.
At the time, it was Big Data and Hadoop and all these things, but we were a couple of
weirdos at strata conferences saying, use Python.
And since that time, we've created a lot of things that now I hope are recognizable to
many of you, open source tools, as well as really important things like the NumFocus
nonprofit, the PyData conferences, a lot of different things like that.
So that's where we started.
And the reason why, I guess, one of the things that is really important to appreciate why
we did this is because there's a lot of things about Python that make it different and special.
There's a lot that we love about Python, and hopefully this is not controversial to any
of you.
But I think there's a lot of other languages out there.
If we just focus on software development, there's many different choices.
Why are we, why was Travis and I, why were we so opinionated about taking Python to data
science and to data analysis?
And the reason is because of these things.
It is something that is approachable by lots of people, more than just people with CS degrees.
And this last part, too, this last bullet point, the fact that the communities are welcoming
and generally pretty pleasant, that's a really, really big deal, a really big deal if you
want to keep growing user base.
There's one other thing that people don't talk about too much, which is the Python interpreter
has essentially an under the hood capability to be extended with native extensions, as
we call them, binary extensions.
So I call it like a Honda Civic with mounting bolts for warp drive.
And so it's very unassuming.
It's a very common sort of thing.
Learn how to do basic scripting with Python.
And then you go into the trunk, you pop it open, and you bolt on warp nacelles.
And now you're running faster than C or C++ in some cases.
You're getting direct access to GPU.
So this is one of those other things that is a little bit underappreciated.
It's something that's obvious to me because I've been doing this stuff for 20 years.
But it's something I think really bears repeating.
It's not just like every other language.
It's not just like Node.
It's not just an alternative to Ruby.
The actual architecture of the CPython virtual machine itself has enabled, well, the kind
of research you just saw, right, and research besides on cancer research, on everything,
right?
Like the reason why Python got picked up by Wall Street 10 years ago, 15 years ago, was
precisely because of this warp drive capability.
And that's what's led this incredible growth.
If you look at these charts from Stack Overflow, from TOB, you know, this year actually just
hot off the press.
TOB ranked Python as number one again, continues to grow.
We continue to add users and popularity to the language.
But all that being said, there's some things that are not so great, right?
So here among friends, I'm sure we can talk candidly about what sucks about Python.
And I'll be the first to go out there and say that, you know, packaging and installing
all the bits, right?
On the one hand, we have a diverse ecosystem of a huge number of libraries, over 100,000
on PyPI, I believe.
But at the same time, getting all these to work together is difficult.
And although there are many solutions, they all are about 80%, right?
Which means everyone's having a bad time about 20% of the time, which is not great.
Secondly, this is a really odd thing.
For the world's most popular language, which we are, woohoo, the challenge is we can't
actually build things that have interfaces with.
Like you can't go and build an iOS app with Python very easily.
Rolling a native application on Windows, which is what runs on most corporate desktops.
Trying to roll an application even with a web front end.
You have to write JavaScript and CSS and HTML.
So the fact that it's the world's most popular programming language, but we can't easily
with user interfaces is kind of weird, but kind of interesting, right?
And the consequence of one and two, of course, makes it hard to share our work.
And I know some of you are thinking, aha, but that's why I use Docker, right?
And that's peculiar.
When you're using Docker, you are literally compressing, zipping up a hard drive and shipping
it to someone.
And that cannot be our way of getting this into kids' hands and getting people, millions
of people to be using this stuff, right?
There's got to be something easier.
But again, despite all these challenges, Python continues to grow.
Python continues to be the most popular language taught in schools at every level.
And to some extent, I think Python is the victim of its own success.
Precisely because it's so good at gluing together so many things, it's stuck to all those things
it glues to, because it's glue, right?
And so much of what we do in computing is tied to ideas, architectures, things that
were built really in the 70s and maybe the 80s.
And that is everything from the C programming language and the Unix process model and the
compiler tool chains around all that to concepts like common internetworking, TCPIP and all
these other kinds of things.
There's a lot of infrastructure that Python's able to get into the nooks and crannies of,
but then it itself gets dragged into.
And so the thing is the language proper.
So if you read a Python tutorial, you can teach that to a child in an afternoon.
You can teach that to anyone in a weekend.
But if you really want to go beyond that, if you want to go from there to, let's say,
a native EXE on Windows or an iOS app on an iPad, that's a lot more work than an afternoon,
right?
And so can we, the question I would pose is can we unshackle Python from all of this,
When you look at the stack overflow rankings of language popularity, JavaScript's right
up there at the number one, and then there's HTML and CSS at number two.
Python is right there sitting comfortably on the podium at third place.
And can we ever get over that?
Because the browser clearly has won the operating system wars, right?
Is it the year, is 2022 the year of Linux on the desktop?
I don't know.
But I'll tell you 2022, there's a lot of web browsers on desktops, right?
And the problem with the web browser, the reason why JavaScript is stuck there as king
in number one is because it's the native language of the web browser, right?
And so if we want to grow beyond that, right, we have to go where the people are.
We have to use Dinglehoppers, or rather WebAssembly, to do this, because WebAssembly fundamentally
changes the game.
WebAssembly for those who are not familiar, it is a virtual CPU instruction set that recently
became a standard.
It has a 32-bit memory space, but it supports 64-bit arithmetic.
And there's a compiler tool called mscripten that operates as sort of a pseudo operating
system layer.
It compiles a lot of C and C++ code to target WebAssembly.
And it's also WebAssembly because it's a standard.
It's well supported by most modern browsers, including mobile browsers.
For those of you keeping track at home, Python, CPython, is also a C program.
A lot of the Python numerical stack is also written in C and C++.
So the work that was done over the last couple of years by projects like Piodide and Jupyter
Lite, they've been compiling a large part of the Python data and scientific stack to
target WebAssembly.
And so if you go to Piodide.org, you'll get a nice little REPL, three little friendly
angle brackets that you can import NumPy and Pandas into.
If you go to Jupyter Lite, you can actually get a full JupyterLab environment, no server
process at all.
It just completely runs in your browser.
And most recently, Christian Himes has been talking a lot about WebAssembly and doing
some great work on this stuff.
WebAssembly is going to be soon getting official CPython support as a tier two supported platform.
So again, it's a virtual CPU kind of instruction set, and it would be an alternative at an
architecture level to things like the ARM instruction set or the x86 instruction set.
It's just another kind of thing that the Python code base, the interpreter, can target.
So we've been looking at this stuff for a little while at Anaconda, and we came up with
an idea for how to really maybe leverage some of this work and increase the accessibility
of tools like Python to many, many more people.
And so I'm very, very excited to announce a project called PyScript.
So what is PyScript?
I'll show you what PyScript is.
I realize I am live coding my first PyCon keynote here.
Maybe my last.
Everyone is like, what the hell?
What's going on over here?
Are you all ready for this?
Whoa.
Forgot the language I was in.
And because we're good citizens, we're going to close out that HTML tag right there.
So that is an HTML file, and it is stored here.
Where's my mouse?
There it is.
Here it is.
If I double click that bad boy, there it is.
Can you guys see that?
It's HTML.
Let's go have a little fun with it.
Let's have a little fun with it.
Let's put a blink tag in here.
I say reload.
No blink tag.
See, I'm old school, right?
I came from a time when there were blink tags, and now I have to explain to kids there's
no more blink tag.
So we're going to have to do something a little different.
We're going to do, we're going to create a div out here.
I'm going to call it output.
All right.
In our Py script, we're going to make our own blink tag.
See where this is going.
Hey, Vim, I love you.
You've got to love me back.
All right.
This is not going to work because code.
What do you guys think?
What's going to happen?
So that's Py script.
So what's really going on here?
When you look at something like this, it's very simple.
It's about ten lines of code.
And we are just embedding HTML in the browser.
It's a framework for creating rich Python apps in the browser.
We interleave Python with HTML.
We have full access to the DOM.
And we can call and be called by JavaScript libraries.
So all of your app logic, all your code is in one language in the browser.
There's actually no web server needed.
That was just an HTML file that I double clicked.
I could put it on a USB stick and give it to somebody and they could double click it.
Now, granted, you're like, okay, you have a script source equals.
Yeah, there's a little bit of something you've got to do if you want to have the script locally.
But the point is, all of the stuff is there in the HTML.
Okay?
So this is how it all works.
So we have the HTML.
We have the HTML.
All of the stuff is there in the HTML.
Okay?
So this is how it actually works.
It is not a variant of the Python language.
I want to be very clear.
This is the same CPython that all of you all run on your laptops and on your servers.
It's just been compiled to target the virtual CPU
sitting inside the browser tab.
and because of the Piaudide work
from the Piaudide team, that project,
We're able to leverage all of the NumPy and SciPy
and a lot of the core data and scientific stack in Python.
in Python. The PyScript infrastructure itself, it's kind of an opinionated framework with
these tags and a way to do some FFI stuff, a way to kind of talk to the various bits
and pieces. And the idea here is that Python, you know, we have wrapped C, C++, we've swallowed
them, right, we've swallowed C, C++, Fortran, we can also go and wrap and call JavaScript.
Why not? So this is actually truly serverless computing. You can run client side only. So
let's look at a couple of additional demos. So here's a basic REPL. All right. One plus
three. Print. Hello. Well, you guys already saw this, but there's that, right? But you
can also do, because it's just a DOM. Well, and you got a little autocomplete thing there
going on. So, let's look at a couple of demos. So, let's look at a couple of demos. So, let's
look at a couple of demos. This is the most number of people I've simultaneously Rickrolled.
So there we go. Right? Yeah, we'll get a little bit of that going on. Anyway, so that's your
REPL, but this isn't Jupyter. I want to be very, very clear. What is this? Let's look
at what this, what this code for this looks like. Because this is a coding conference,
so we're looking at some code. Okay. There's some stuff here. But at the end of the day,
you have just a little REPL. And we have this little pyreple thing. And we have this autogenerate
equals true. So pyreple is one of the primitives that PyScript provides. Autogenerate means
that every time you execute, it will create a new line for you. But you can also, you
can also change where that output goes. So here, this is REPL 2. There's a lot to kind
of parse in here. But the key thing here is we are able to redirect standard output and
standard error to different divs. So if I go here and I load up REPL 2, I can do this.
And this is not, just to be very clear, this is not Jupyter. Many of you are familiar with
Jupyter as the way of authoring and doing REPLs in the browser. This is just Python
in the browser, PyScript, and then putting your output over here. So it's really nice.
And you can, I won't rickroll you again, but I assure you, you can get rickrolled with
this as well in the other div. No one needs to see that again twice in one day. Let's
see here. The other thing I want to show is this little to do app. And so, you know, when
you do web programming, the blog post, the to do app, these are kind of canonical examples.
So eggs, we're going to add some things here, add the task. Hold on, I got to, oh, I know
what's going on here. This is to do that HTML. Let's do this guy. All right. So we give this
a little second to load up the Python infrastructure. And then if we do eggs, bacon, ham, and you
can, you know, do this sort of thing. I don't know if you can see it, but it's actually
crossing out the item when it clicks on it. And the code for this, I will show you, the
code for this looks, oh, really? Oh, I'm in the wrong thing. Hold on. To do dot HTML.
There it is. Okay. So the to do list app, most of the, this is it right here. This is
the HTML. It's about 50 lines. There's a lot of like formatting and stuff, but ultimately
what happens is we have a button here, this new task button, and we click it, we call
the add task function, which is actually defined in all of our actual Python logic we put in
a little helper file here just to keep it a little bit cleaner. Okay. My Vim is, there
it is. Okay. So your add task, what we're doing here is we're really playing with the
DOM, we're able to pull things out, we're able to set the check mark on things, we're
able to do all these kinds of things here. This is a really, the point here is that there's
no, there's not a whole lot of translating back and forth to server state, to client
state and all these other things. You're literally just writing Python, you're able to import
that Python code right into your page here and you just kind of play with all of it.
Right? So it all sort of works. And that's nice. Okay. These are some toy examples. That's
kind of cool. Let's see, showing you what's going to happen. Let me just walk through
these a little bit. So you can load the JavaScript and the CSS and all these things from a local
server or a server you run, or you can run it off of PyScript.net. You can output to
divs, you can do all sorts of fun things like this. The REPL can output to various different
places so you can build a nice little flexible set of REPL things. And you can do, actually,
this is loading all of Python in there. We're able to do more sophisticated examples. Right?
We're able to go and load, for instance, scikit learn and the panel dashboard library with
bokeh, plotting and things like that. And so I'm able to sit here and actually do interactive
scikit learn in the browser with zero install. So just to be very clear, this panel came
inside HTML, which is this guy. Okay. Again, there's a lot of stuff in the head which we'll
clean up. This is all very alpha. But we'll make a lot of this stuff get much simpler.
But the core of the logic here is we have Pyenv. Oh, sorry. This is plotted with Altair,
I guess. But we're declaring what we need in the environment to run. Those things get
loaded up. And then the actual code here for this dashboard is all this Python. Right?
We're using Vega to declare the plots. And so you have interactive selection here and update.
All this stuff just runs client side. And if I take this HTML file, again, similar to
with the little REPL or any of those other examples, if I take this HTML file, I zip
it up and give it to someone else, they can just run it. There's no install needed. So
this is a really, really powerful example of how the distribution, the sharing, all
those things that I said, you know, what's Python not so great at, this, because it uses
the browser as the primary interface and as the portable CPU, it just skips over a lot of those
kinds of challenges. But you can do one step further. You can go and say, you know, there's a lot of
really great stuff in JavaScript. What if we could just leverage all those libraries in JavaScript?
Deck GL is a fantastic example of one of these powerful JavaScript visualization systems.
And this example, again, uses the panel dashboard library, embeds a little visualization of the New
York taxi cab data. We can animate it and see how, let's make the speed a little faster. So you
can sort of see in these hex bins the number of taxi cab pickup and drop offs there are on the
Isle of Manhattan. But what's, and you can modify this. So you can change the radius of, you know,
how many, how big the radius is as you're contemplating these or creating these bins.
You can also change kind of visually, configure the thing. This is all pretty cool, right? You
can slide this along. It's actually kind of neat. All this is running in the browser. No install.
I could put this on a USB stick, give it to anyone here. You load up on your machine and
it would definitely work. Maybe. But pretty much. Look, I've been doing this a while. I know not to
make sort of these absolutes. But, you know, the other thing you could do, though, because this is
actually running in the browser and because you have a full Python environment here, you can actually
compile, you can just play with all of this. Right? And notice how this changed this up there.
Let's go back to 50. Right? Oh, also you can, when you click on a thing, I don't know if you guys can
see that, but it shows you where the taxi routes actually went to. Isn't that neat? It's actually
a really beautiful viz. But you can also access the data frame of data itself. So the data frame,
DF, this is in the format is a little tricky here, but it's 50,000 rows. But I can actually say,
look, I just want to look at, let's say the data frames where the trip distance was less than five
miles. Can you guys see that? And it's interactive. So this is, you can do more complex expressions.
I want to find the big tippers. See what's going on here. There you go. Where did the big tippers go?
Right? So this is a really interesting capability where you have access to all of NumPy, SciPy,
Scikit-learn, like I showed you. All these things just sit here in the browser, and your distribution
is, you know, copying this on a flash drive, putting this on a file share. It's a dramatic
simplification of what has been thus far a very difficult process, especially building interactive
web applications like this. So Gary Bernhardt many years ago gave a fantastic PyCon talk,
not the what talk, actually, the birth and death of JavaScript, as he called it. And he talked about
this possibility happening, ASM.js becoming WebAssembly, and we're just making it happen.
Right? This is what this is about. So I've got some of these demos. Oh, another cool demo here is
there's, you know, because we can wrap JavaScript libraries, here's folium, which is very nice. I'll
let this load here. I'm on conference Wi-Fi, so it's going to take a little bit. But, you know,
how many people here have heard of D3? Know of D3? JavaScript Vis Library? A lot of Python data
scientists have been lusting for D3 for a very long time. In many attempts, they've made a Python
to wrap D3. This is actually a Python wrapper of D3. The code looks like this. So part of this code
shows you what the D3 code looks like. This is actually the D3 JavaScript code. For comparison,
that makes the left side. The right side, this is the PyScript code. I mean, just look at this
right here. Import to D3. We can finally do that in Python now. Right? And the cool thing about this,
this wrapper for D3 was done by one of the team members in two days. Now, it's not complete,
but it's a pretty good job. And so this shows the power of when we say Python wrapping things and
calling things. Python's never been about re-implementing the world. It's always been
about going where the things are, going where the users are, binding to them. So that's,
that's, anyway, kind of cool there. And then there's also, of course, there's 3JS. So this
is interactive WebGL. The logic for this is actually written in Python itself. Again,
I forgot what it's called, though. Oh, yeah, here it is.
So here you can see there's a little bit of preamble in the head to load some things and
install some things, but the actual logic from JavaScript import 3, we're actually using JavaScript
to do the math. And here you're just doing raw WebGL in Python. This is the logic to generate the
particles, all of the animation for this. It's not bad, right? But not only can we access JavaScript
libraries, one of the really cool things we can do, oh, here's Foleum. Nice little Foleum example.
One of the really cool things we can do is also we can take different JavaScript libraries and
bind them together. So let's see if we actually make this work in a live demo environment. No
pressure. Oh, it's got to load the model up over conference Wi-Fi. I'm going to keep blaming the
conference Wi-Fi, although I appreciate the people who set up the Wi-Fi because it's very fast.
Okay, here we go. Start the video. And when I move my hand, it's going to make Mario jump.
And you're going to watch me die because there's a little bit of a lag. Oh! Woo! I can't jump very
high, though. I'll always be a little Mario. Can I do that? No. But the point is this is tying
together two different libraries. One of them is this JavaScript Mario clone. Don't go back on a
demo. One of them is a JavaScript Mario implementation. The other one is it's a
JavaScript-based gesture recognition library. And so the code for this looks like this. So this is
not one of the trivial examples, but using a mushroomfireflower.js. There's a lot to get
loaded here. But if you look here, the Python is doing all the work of binding these things together.
We're turning on the video. We're going to use hand track to start the video. When we go and we
get the detection, we're going to go and look at the prediction. We're looking to see if the user's
trying to move the thing left or right. If the hand is open or closed, then we make the jump or,
oh, I guess crouch is closed. But we're doing this in Python to bind these two JavaScript
libraries together to do real-time camera video recognition to play a game. And I actually didn't
get killed by a little goop. This is actually really, really neat. I think it's pretty cool.
To do list app. So the recap. What have we seen here? We've seen we have Python and data science
MLAI running in the browser. We've got performant stuff. We can harness the GPU. It's good enough to
play Super Mario. That can keep me entertained for a number of hours at least. There's zero
install. It runs everywhere. I'm the anaconda guy. You don't have to install anaconda to use this.
You basically get a light anaconda in WebAssembly to run all these things that you need. So the idea
here is that the most accessible language for the web should be the language that we already love
and know. Let's make that happen. That's PyScript. The other key thing about this, though, is if you
think about traditional web applications, what makes them complex isn't just that JavaScript is
kind of a terrible language. Well, I'm willing to have beers with someone about that. But the
point is what makes really a lot of them complex is because we have this client server architecture
that splits the server state and a lot of the half of the session state puts on the server
and the client is all the stuff written in JavaScript or TypeScript. And so it's a really,
it's a hodgepodge of different things. It's very complex. Actually much more complex than I think
it needs to be. And the thing we don't talk about is the fact that because we split the session
state in half, a tremendous amount of stuff goes back to the server that, like in the 1980s and
1990s, you wouldn't ever send back to a server. You would just, it would be part of the object
model state kind of living in the app itself. And this is the root of a lot of modern evils in tech.
I think many people here who understand how this stuff works know that's true.
So if we do PyScript, we put all this power capability on the virtual CPU here in the browser
tab, we can get rid of all of that stuff. Now we will still need to do, we'll have to talk to
databases, we'll need to have synchronization primitives, but if we use libp2p and we use things
like hyper or IPFS, we could really kind of maybe bring about a version of Web3 without the NFTs.
We could actually do something where we're building applications that are properly client-server.
And so what's next? Well, there's a lot of work. I mean, this is really, real cool stuff. I mean,
some of the demos I think are pretty compelling, but there's a lot of really cool things that we
can do, right? First of all, we've got to wrap all of the cool JavaScript libraries
and make them even cooler. Like there's a SimCity clone out there, there's DOSBox,
like JS DOSBox, where you can go and reach into the DOS emulator for any of the games that
the older people here grew up with. We can port other languages, right? We call it PyScript,
but there's no reason you couldn't have the PyScript tag have a language equals and embed
much of Julia or R or like the PyData tag having SQL in line with your Python. So there's a lot
of really cool stuff we want to do. We'd love to get other people to help us on the project and
everyone's collaboration on this. There's a lot of really interesting problems, like what is the
nicest native binding to React that we can do, right? What are some better ways to do efficient
memory transfers back and forth between Python and JavaScript? All these different kinds of
things, right? Better tooling for debugging and things like that. And there's a lot of hard
problems too. Obviously packaging is a hard problem. We'd have to sit down and really think
about how we're going to do this in a way that lets people deliver secure web apps, but at the
same time, let the community quickly iterate and move forward on things. We want to avoid
any additional kinds of things that we've seen in the JavaScript ecosystem when there's lots of
packages moving very quickly. So there's a lot to learn here and to think about. There's
async and multi-threading things. There's a lot of potential here for beautiful, really cool stuff
with multi-processing subinterpreters and server-side stuff, but at the same time, it's pretty
subtle work. So we've got to make sure all this stuff works. And then we can actually build
multiple interpreter backends because many of the interpreters for Python, they can be targeted for
WebAssembly, the alternative interpreters, and with all of the extension modules being targeted
for WebAssembly now, all the other alternative interpreters to CPython can actually be on a level
playing ground from an extension perspective, which has not been the case for a very long time.
The reason why everyone keeps using CPython, not because the CPython devs aren't cool, they're
awesome, but the point is that there's a giant ecosystem of native libraries and extensions that
only speak to CPython. So this is, but now how do we do this without burning all the devs out?
Because this is also a lot of really hard work. So as a community, we have to get together and
really think about this and do this thoughtfully, but I think everyone recognizes there's a massive
price to be won here. It's absolutely massive. Ariel can get her legs. We can just go on land
and go where the people are and solve the most fundamental and important problem, which is
doing programming for the 99%. And what I mean by that is this. I think this is something that
most people maybe don't think about. One of the things that I've known for a long time, but
I think it bears repeating, is that Python has a unique position as a programming language
because it was designed, has this design ethos from the founder of it, this creator, and all of
the core devs around it. There's this ethos about Python being approachable as a teaching language,
as a language to learn, really, really prioritizing education in the community.
Things in the Zen of Python like readability counts and explicit is better than implicit.
These are lots of these little things all come together to make it so that Python is a language
that can be learned not just by the programmers who learn a new language every year, but by all of
the other people in the world who don't consider themselves programmers, but they can do a little
bit of something on their computer. This is one of the dynamics that has allowed Python to
dominate the way it has over the last 10, 15 years. So how do we extend this? And how can
PyScript help? One question I like to ask everyone, and just give you a moment to think about how many
software devs are there out there in the world? 100,000? Probably more than that. 100 million?
Definitely not. How many are there? And when I did some research into this, the numbers all seem
to converge somewhere around 25 million. Maybe a little bit more than that, maybe a little bit
less than that. But if you put that in perspective on how many people there are on the planet,
it's 0.3%. So can we turn the house lights on here real quick? Is that?
Let me do the PyScript. Turn on house lights dot. No? Okay. There's a few, I asked a few people
beforehand as my volunteers to stand up. Can my volunteers stand up? Who are my volunteers?
All right. Oh, house lights, it worked. PyScript works. Great. So six people.
If this room was the population of Earth, those six people are your software developers.
Now, can three of you, this is a distributed computing problem, can three of you sit down?
All right. There should be just three people standing. Okay. That's your Python programmers.
Can one of you sit down and another person crouch?
Okay. That's your number of people who know enough stats and whatnot to do some data science in ML.
And then if we let the crouching person finally sit down and rest their legs, the one person
standing, that is your AI ML engineer. All the rest of you have to use the systems that she
builds, that she twiddles the knobs for. 0.3% and actually less than that, 0.1% of the population
has anything approaching the skills and capability to do machine learning, ML, AI. And you can turn
the house lights off now and thank you, you can sit down as well. The point of this is that
this is not a good state of affairs. This is the state of affairs today
and it will continue to be the state of affairs unless we do something dramatically different.
One of the things that I found very inspiring when I lived in Boston was the Boston Public Library had
this huge engraving on the side. It says the Commonwealth requires the education of the people
as a safeguard of order and liberty. So all of us here, well, many of us, most of us here are
coders and we like to code, we like to create things. Python is a wonderful language to help
us do all those things. But we really have to ask ourselves, why do we code? What is it for?
And I think it's really, really, really important that we keep our eye on the prize,
which is that democratization and literacy, computational literacy as well as data literacy
are foundational to ensure an open and free future for mankind, for humankind, sorry, for humankind.
So when we created SciPy and Pydata and we did all these things to try to spearhead the open data
science movement, that was to ensure that machine learning and business computation in a cybernetic
world had at least some open source and accessible foundations. With PyScript, I'm really hoping that
we can broaden that mission to the broader web and to computing in general, computing for the people
and for their communities. So I would like to see kids' first introduction to programming to be
PyScript. Install nothing. You have a tablet, you've got a little laptop, whatever it might be.
You can go to the library computer and you're rocking and rolling, right? We don't have to
reinvent anything because existing educational materials on HTML and CSS and Python, all these
just pretty much will work. We can focus on productivity and quality of life issues for
casual programmers, not the experienced software developers because you all will happily take on a
ton of pain, obviously. You will, if you bash your head into a wall enough, eventually the wall turns
into a pile of yaml, right, which is a softer thing to bash your head into. And so the idea here is
that I would love for us to make the web a friendly, hackable place where anyone can make
interesting things and share it with other people. The remix aspect of this culture has really been
lost, I think, in the last 20 years or so as the stacks have gotten more and more complicated.
And so the idea here is to put joy back into all of it, really to promote creativity, for everyone
to have fun, really want everyone to bring some crazy and quirky stuff into it. And by that, what
I mean is something like this. You know, the old XKCD thing that everyone saw, right?
This is this comic where Randall Munroe was first getting introduced to Python. He just loved how
it made him feel. Of course, later he added XKCD where he made fun of the packaging mess that we
had, so that was not so good. But, you know, can everyone see that?
Let's do that. Let's do more of that.
All right. Well, thank you all very much. I want to thank the people who made this possible. This
project has been kind of crazy, but it's been a lot of fun. Fabio, where are you, Fabio? Stand up.
I don't know where he is. He's right there. Fabio, Fabio's the man. So tremendous amount of the work.
All the credit, kudos to him. The Anaconda team making some of these demos and, you know, my late
night slacks and everything, thank you all very much for being so responsive and making all this
happen. The Piodide maintainers, so Roman and Hood have been amazing to work with and so friendly.
They have a talk on Piodide and WebAssembly if you want to nerd out on the internals. They have a
talk later this afternoon. Please go to that talk. And then Michael Dropboom and Christian Heimson,
very supportive and very helpful with their feedback on all of this. The project is, again,
I just want to reiterate, super, super, super alpha, right? In fact, when you put alpha in the
URL for the JavaScript, you are signing the EULA to say you acknowledge this is alpha. But still,
play with it. Kind of like mess with it. Figure stuff out. Piscript.net. Come check out our open
space that we'll have later today. Or come by the Anaconda booth. Follow us, the Piscript dev on
Twitter. If you are the squatter that has the Piscript Twitter tag, talk to me. I'll pay you
money for it. And then also, please contribute and give us your thoughts on GitHub. So thank you all
very, very much.