Hello, everyone. Welcome back. Let's welcome Jess to deliver a talk on productionized research-oriented
code by Python. Over to you, Jess.
Hello, everyone. I'm Jesse. I have been in education and technology industry for several
years. In this industry, I have tackled the issues between data science and engineering
in AI ML projects. So based on my experiences, I'm going to talk about the process to productionize
research-oriented code by Python.
Let me share background first. Python engineers assigned to AI ML project and the few countries
that are involved in the process can help make AI ML projects work more smoothly. The
target audience might be Python engineers who are involved with R&D, data scientists,
product owners in AI ML projects, or data engineers.
So three years ago, I made a five-minute talk about this topic in Python US 2019. This was
my first talk on the stage in my life. So during the three years, I made the talks about
Python data science topics around the world and published a book about them. Then I came
back to Python US today.
So this talk is aggregated based on my three years' experiences of the projects with data
scientists, what I wrote in the book, and the past talks in Python.
So I abstracted the four steps to transform research-oriented code into products. Understand
the code, modularize the code, refactor them, and then make them product. That's it. It's
very simple. I will explain each step one by one, much deeper.
So the code samples in the four steps are written based on item response theory, also known
as the two-parameter logistic regression, which is a classic statistical model mainly
used in educational psychology. But this model is normally used for predicting how many students
can get correct answers based on the features of questions. So this talk, I use the code
based on this statistical model, but the model is not the main topic in this talk, so I will
not talk about the model itself.
So let's look at the first step. The first step is to understand the research-oriented
code. So in general, a research-oriented code is implemented for figuring out something
new and summarizing the results into paper. So research-oriented code, AI, project, is
the code written mainly by data scientists or researchers for figuring out new knowledge.
So finding something new is the highest priority when writing the code.
This is a common life cycle to write paper with code. Only one person starts to collect
data, pre-process it, train or calculate the data, and then see what the results are telling
you. If the results present new knowledge, write paper with it and publish.
So this code is pre-processing code written during this process. This code seems to be
a long function and used for loop, but it tends to be visually traceable from the top
to the bottom, also it can be easily and quickly written. It's not critical, but it's enough
to quickly get results. So this is an example of calculation code. This code uses .pand
and uses data frame. It easily handles the input data and it trace output data with data
frame.
So on the other hand, what is the code in production level?
So according to this thesis about how we can evaluate ML production system based on the
rubric, the thesis scores ML system from 0 to 12 plus. So 0 points seems to be more like
before transformation. The ML system scoring from 7 to 12 plus is the product a few years
after deployed on the production environment. So the target goal of the four steps I suggest
in this talk is the product scoring from 5 to 6. That means reasonably tested, but it's
possible that most of those tests and procedures may be automated.
So the product quality improved through these kinds of development cycle. I have had experiences
to be only one Python engineer in a company for a few years, but generally engineers develop
applications with a team. So they make architecture, implement features, test and review, and release
product. So they receive feedback all the time unless they develop very perfect product
with no bugs. So they need to keep repeating, release and fix the product. So this means
that production code needs high maintainability, scalability, and processing speed.
This is an example of both previous code I refactored in a PySonic way. This code seems
to be shorter than previous code, and there are less complications and set complications.
There are two simple functions at the bottom. This code can be the model in a faster and
simple way. So I identified three differences between
research-oriented code and production code. There are different scripts, different characteristics
for coding style, and different objectives coding style. So researchers focus more on
writing pre-processing code and ML code, calculation code. On the other hand, engineers have responsibility
to write whole part of the code in production level.
The research-oriented code seems to be easily handled and visually traceable. On the other
hand, production code needs to be concerned about high calculation speed, high readability,
and should be testable and modular. This is because researchers focus more on finding
the most efficient and suitable machine learning model or calculation code. On the other hand,
engineers have responsibility to make the code work on the server correctly and reliably.
So what are Python engineers supposed to do for research-oriented code at first? So what
is the first thing to do? So deep-typing the code. So read the code before write it.
The left picture is a Jupyter notebook with just long lines. I used to frequently receive
the code. On the Jupyter notebook from the... Okay, I will continue. So, I will read the
code. After you receive the research-oriented code, take notes for deep-typing the code
as if you were scribbling. So there are three strategies to take notes. Prepare for modularization.
Just quickly take notes while reading the research-oriented code. So first one is to
write comments by using SHARP. Second is add to comments. These two things everyone already
does. So third one, third is mobile documentation. So, the third one is to write comments. So,
mobile documentation is very useful to efficiently understand the code with the team. So, if
you're using a VS code, install a Live Share extension of VS code which enables to share
code and edit together. So after mobile documentation, the team members who joined this mob can be
on the same page and do not need to extra wiki and documents about this code. So, also
if you do with junior when you hire, it can be good for onboarding. So, this is an example
of part of the research-oriented code with comments. So, while reading the code, add
what you understood from the code with comments and to do memo. So, this should be done for
understanding more about the code, not only for remembering the code and to do. So, the
conscious and attitude about understanding more about the code and getting more familiar
with the code is going to make different in the way to take notes on the code and easily
lead to the next step. So, next thing to do is to modularize the code by using SHARP.
Using the levels. A research-oriented code has three types of scopes such as the code
to prepare, pre-post-process, and calculate data. So, based on the comments you wrote
in previous step, categorize the code into preparation code, pre-post-processing code,
and calculation code. So, after grouping each code with levels, we can break them into functions
and make them testable. So, while grouping each code, you would find duplicated codes
and use lines or libraries or small bugs. You can fix them in this step. So, then we
can get modularization outcome like the table. So, we could get modules for each from one
page of research-oriented code. We could get preparation.py which has functions to access
database, execute query, and load input data. We also could get pre-processing.py which
has functions to replace categorical data with discrete numbers, filter input data,
and rename columns. So, finally, we get prediction.py which has functions to calculate logistic
regression and output results. So, now as a result of that, so the research-oriented
code became loosely coupled. So, you can make directory structure mapping
each module. This is one of the directory structure examples of API developed with Flask.
I found that this kind of directory structure is very simple and easy to work with. The
directory structure on the left box has API directory and module directory and main root
directory. The danda-init.py module located in API directory has a routing list. Each
logic for each endpoint is implemented in each module located in URL directory. So,
if you are working in a small team from one to three members and implement new modules,
you can just add it to a new endpoint in URL directory. If the number of team members increase,
you can split each module into each version and work together staying loosely coupled
between modules. So, I wrote the directory on the slide in the case of API with Flask
and fast API also can have similar directory structure, but generally the way of mapping
relies on the manner of each framework and what you want to develop.
So, now we reach to the step to refactor preparation code and preprocessing code. So, before starting
to refactor the code, we should write test code roughly at the doc thing such as restructure
the ticket style, numpy style, and google style and execute code formatter such as black
or alt-pep 8 and check if code correctly work by using py-test and check the consistency
of coding style by using flake 8. And other than that, type annotation could also be one
of the options as code documentation if all team members are familiar with the grammar
of type hinting. You can narrow down more about requirements of each code through these
three processes, then we can finally start to refactor the code.
Now which part of the code should we refactor? Just focus on preparation code and preprocessing
code. In general, ML library and mathematical library are used in prediction module, so
the code does not have many lines to write and refactor. The optimization of CPU bounding
processing can be done later after we could make sure if the code can work correctly on
the server. Also, we have chances to figure out if the prediction is not valid yet through
refactoring here. So we are trying to refactor I.O. Preparation.py has a group of codes to
access to database or object storage by using query and current library. So let me share
a few examples I frequently have faced and how I simplify them.
In exploratory analysis phase or data wrangling, data scientists are not sure of which data
is specifically useful. If you receive the first query with a star, so narrow down the
data to extract from database and it could be much faster and lower cost like the second
code. In accessing the object storage, sometimes you might make effort to write a code that
write many lines just for loading CSP5 by using current libraries. So one of my suggestions
is that you wrap the code and make it simpler, then it can be reusable and cost effective.
That's because this kind of code is the same code even though anyone write. Everyone in
AI and ML projects such as data engineers, Python engineers and data scientists write
similar code. Not only your team members but also the members in other team might be writing
the same code just for loading the data. So also it might be chances for Python engineers
to make a big impact internally. Next, let's look at the preprocessing.py. The
libraries for analysis use and development use are different. A group of the code to
preprocess or post-process the data tend to include various kinds of libraries and data
type is also mixed. As one of the common cases, there are three ways to preprocess the data
like Python only and SQL query. The common operations are filtering, replace, duplicate,
and there is the data for each three ways. So most of research needs Python SQL query
or both. So these three ways have different features. The code with Python is iterative
to fix and write the code. Python only code can be testable and SQL query has high processing
performance and simple grammar. It depends on the architecture and the project scale
but the first thing to think about is whether the SQL query is necessary or not and refactor
them into Python only code for making them more testable. If the data using for calculation
is already specific and extracted in preparation.py, we don't need to write many preprocessing
codes by Python. So last step is to make them product which is API. So what products can
be generated from research oriented code? So output is not paper, it's a product which
means a code working on the server and users can access to it. But there are several kinds
of product appearances. So quickly let me narrow down the scope about the products in
this talk. So the products can be web application or web API. So this is drawing of the flow
chart of transformation from research oriented code into products. So in this slide, POC
is more like products and analysis scripts are mainly written for business reports. So
when having a look at general overview of data oriented projects, both type of the code
can also exist in this flow but this talk focuses on research oriented code. So the
four transformation steps could be mapped on the flow chart like this slide. There are
four patterns of transformation from research oriented code into products. One is the model
or the calculation code extracted from the research oriented code is directly integrated
into web application. The second is that we can implement API based on the research oriented
code. Third is that when we use ready-made API or third party API, we normally integrate
them into web application for using them. Last one is that when the model or the calculation
code is already integrated into web application, we extracted this part of the code and make
it API for public use. So this talk focuses on developing web API. So in order to transform
our research oriented code into web API, we have to implement how to route request
and check request, check error and the routing points which are endpoints. So let me share
the tips to implement request routing and URL. There is a table of input data on the
left side on this slide which is used for two parameters logistic regression. On the
right side, there is a table of output data calculated by the model. The input data is
about whether students answer each question correctly or not. Their item name which is
the name of question, item ID, how difficult each question is, subject name, exam name
and correction which is binary data. On the other hand, output data is about probabilities
to answer questions correctly. So the role of this API is to get probabilities so we
can directly level probabilities as endpoint name. So based on best practices, function
name should be verb or verb plus now. So the role of this function is to calculate the
results or get probabilities so we can level, calculate the result or get props as a function
name. So understanding what data is input and output which means understanding what
data the code calculates and makes is considerably important step to make API. Next is implementation
of request parameter check. My suggestion is to implement request parameter check. So
request parameter check with JSON schema. This request call command has student name
and student grade as parameters. This JSON file is sample JSON schema. In this file,
you can define what data should be checked and how the data should be checked. So this
make name grade of JSON file is defining the data type of student name as string and it
must be included as request parameters and the data type of student grade is also defined
as string and it must be included as true and maximum length of character is limited
to 120 and minimum length is one character. So in this example, request parameters are
not allowed to be empty. So based on JSON schema, the JSON validator.py is defined as
validator request parameters. The first validator JSON function checks whether the JSON schema
exists or not. The second validator schema function checks whether the request parameters
are correct or not based on JSON schema defined in previous slides. In order to execute these
functions, write function name as syntax sugar and as endpoint. The code with JSON schema
seems to be complicated, but most of the code are like this on this slide. So you can
refer to this code. I will upload this slide on my Twitter as well. So last implementation
is error check. So before implementing the code, we need to think if processing should
be stopped or continue for each code. So whether the processing is stopped or not depends on
service specification. For example, if you implement recommendation system, sometimes
you do not want to stop services and continue recommendation even when the preparation
code failed to load certain data. So this is an example of error handler with Flask.
If you stop processing, you can use a board function and detect error. If you do not want
to stop processing, you can just return the results with JSONify. It's very easy to implement
it, but it's more difficult to decide which part of the code processing should be stopped
or not. So I suggest to talk with product manager or QA team about the service specification
before starting to implement error check. Okay. So let me quickly summarize four-step transformation
from research-oriented code into products. First thing is to understand the characteristics
of the code and figure out how it is working by taking notes. They can modularize the code
based on the code documentation by labeling the code as preparation, preprocessing, and
calculation. Thirdly, refactor the preparation code by simplifying I.O. and the preprocessing
code by changing the coding style. So lastly, make them product, which is an API composed
of request routing, request parameter check, and error check. So after deploying the product,
we need to optimize the speed and the stability by doing load test. So there are useful load
test tools such as Locust and Vegeta. Locust is a Python-based load test tool which can
make it possible to manage load test scenario by Python code and monitor the loading of
the server by GUI. Vegeta is a Go-RAM based HTTP load test tool. It can be used both as
command line, utility, and library. If you are looking for the light load test tool,
Vegeta could be one of the options. And you can do Vegeta attack on your code. So by using
those kind of load test tools, if we figure out the performance is not good enough, we
do parameter tuning of web server and application server. And think about asynchronous, asynchronous.
Even if it is not improved, we think about architecture, infrastructure, or refactoring
the code with different languages. So just in case again, four-step transformation from
research-oriented code into product is very simple. Understand the code, modularize the
code, refactor them, and then make them product after you deploy the code, check the performance.
Thank you.