Hello and welcome.
Our next presentation is about to start and for this presentation we have Tadej Hakobian
who is going to be talking about programming your way up Skye Scrapper Python in the BWR.
Help me welcome Tadej without a round of applause.
Thank you everyone.
Hope you can hear me.
And by the way if you guys want to get a preview of the presentation before I get started if you want to catch up,
I have the QR code and the tiny URL at PyArch.
And I'll have it again at the end.
So let's get started.
A little bit about me, Tadej Hakobian, a program manager, background in architecture,
and I have experience with architecture engineering construction, using data, VR workflows.
I've been teaching people about all these things, low code, Python coding for a couple of years now.
And in my experience one thing that was a big deal to me is that Python makes it possible.
And this is a showcase of how Python can support architects and design in a lot of different ways.
And just as we talk about these examples and I go over them, consider how you use your built space,
your environment around you, how you interact with it, and consider what it takes to get there
as far as the design, the intent, and making the concept into reality and the challenges therein.
So to get started.
We've got architects.
Architects, I mean architects.
So when people think architecture, especially this crowd,
we're thinking like systems, pattern languages, what have you.
And that's a big part of it, right?
There's a lot of people who have a CS architecture background.
But there's also architecture.
Look at these examples of floor plans.
And they actually have a common ground.
The reason there's so much jargon shared between them is that there was a source material from the 60s and 70s
called Christopher Alexander, who was a traditional architect who talked about design patterns.
He's like, you know, in pattern language, he's like, you know, you can repeatedly use a pattern
for designing a building, a floor plan, using windows in a certain arrangement.
That makes sense for a small building, for a apartment block, for a city.
And you can just scale this up.
And some computer science students picked up on this in the 70s and said, hey, this is a great idea.
So they borrowed a lot of his concepts and created the idea of pattern design patterns,
which is where you get all these ideas of architecture into computer science.
There's actually a lot of shared knowledge between the two groups as a lot of crossover appeal.
So there's already a lot in common.
And talk about architecture.
This is what people usually think about what architects do.
They think about, you know, a guy drawing on a board, coming up with ideas, being artistic, which is a big part of it.
But these days, that would be more of a design sketch, whereas back in the day, they would just spend all day drawing.
They only needed to do like 20 drawing sheets to get the whole building across, a couple of facades, a couple of plans, and you're good to go.
These days, you need a couple thousand drawings to get anything done.
So we moved on from this to something like this.
This is kind of how we work today.
It's not just a two dimensional image.
Our buildings are fully 3D realized and not just in a plain 3D geometry.
It includes the elevation of the buildings, the geometry, the every single account of the doors, windows, gross square footage, volumes, volumes of the walls, so forth.
So a lot of data is embedded into how we work today.
So it's not just an image or example.
It's the real data.
And now that we have this data rich format, we can have an easier time accessing it.
It was before it was literally just sketching and drawing and just not very useful data.
And this system, for reference, is called building information modeling.
It takes the design intent, geometry and data and put it together into a common data environment where we can have access to all this at once.
And I have to have different ways of storing the information.
And it's just basically a relational database.
All you saw there is just tables connected to each other.
And this is how it works in the world today.
We use some software.
I'll just use the one that's very common just as a reference in this world of building information modeling, BIM, Revit.
It's like billions of people use it.
So there's other ones, but we'll just use this as reference today, which itself has the 3D modeling capability.
And databases, which can give you something like an elevation.
It'll just create drawings.
You probably if you had been in a building of any kind that's either been renovated or built ground up in the last 10 years, that's probably how they put it together.
So it's a lot more data rich and accessible than it's ever been before.
But in order to access that, we need some special tools.
And this plaid looking thing here is called Dynamo.
It's a low code solution that connects the data and geometry from these BIM solutions so we can manipulate it and get some custom workflows out of it.
And it's simple as this.
You might have seen something like this before.
Node-RED, for example, is the one that's pretty popular out there.
It's just what they call a graph of nodes connected to each other with wires.
It's basically your inputs, process, outputs, low code or no code solutions.
That's what Dynamo looks like.
It could use it to connect to the Revit API.
And you know, you could do anything like do arithmetic operations.
You could put two numbers together and get a result.
But you can go further with it.
You can actually use it for working with geometry.
So you can draw a line in your model, select it here and actually figure out things like how do we point something on a line, especially something like this with a curve.
You can just put the integers in there as a slider.
And then you can just put the numbers in there, have the code block spacing out and you get a result.
And you can input that in your model, which is really neat because you don't have to sit there and try to figure it out yourself and draw it out or it takes forever.
So this is really cool automation technology.
It's visual, on the spot, and you can see the results.
And we can go further with it.
I can create something like a floor plan.
Let's say a rectangular floor plan.
On the left there, I have 30 feet and 60 feet.
And I just tie in my X, Y, Z coordinates for four corners.
And then over here, I have my different kinds of materials, a curtain wall and levels, how many levels I want, and a concrete slab at six inches.
I connect the dots on that rectangular corded set to create my shape.
And then I embed the types of equipment I want in there and materials to get some output of floors and walls and levels.
And we go from this geometry preview to this result.
And that's about 70 stories of a tower.
So we just built our skyscraper in like two seconds.
It's that quick.
If I did that manually, it would take me an hour, maybe two.
So it's pretty cool results you can do with Dynamo.
And you can also do some unconventional things.
You could take these kind of code blocks, use some kind of wavy pattern on your wall.
You could put some art on it if you want to do something a little unique.
And again, you can replay all of it.
And you don't have to be an expert in coding to use it.
And also, you can just preview geometry.
You can play around with, connect things, just see how things play out, which is really neat if you're kind of into that whole touchy feely kind of molding clay idea, which a lot of designers are not too comfortable with just visual textual code.
But you might be asking, this is all cool, great.
What does that have to do with Python?
So I'm getting there.
It also has a Python script node within it.
This was my kind of gateway into the world of Python years ago.
I was really wanting to use it, but I had no way of using it at work since I didn't do anything with Python for the most part.
But Dynamo did have one.
It has a little ID in it.
You just import the runtime.
You import the geometry library that comes with Dynamo software.
And you have an input node.
So you have to have a wire coming in.
And you have an output node.
It's a little different from your typical Python script, but otherwise very similar concept.
And what's great about it, you don't have to use the API.
You don't have to know anything about the SDK.
You could just use this Python script plus Dynamo to get things into your Revit database.
And that API for Revit is a beast.
It's not user-friendly.
And it's nice to get around it.
So instead of using all that, you can just run with a Python script in Dynamo.
And it uses iron Python or C Python at this point as for implementation.
So I can give you an example.
We could just do a loop to make a bunch of stuff.
In this case, this happens all the time.
With your keystrokes, you're trying to get things into your model real quick,
whatever you're trying to build.
So even with a low-code script, it will take me a little bit of time to create a loop.
Because I'm saying, OK, how can I get some coordinates going on?
So here's an example of a little script we have here where we just import our runtime environments,
the geometry, and then also I want to write into Revit, so I have to import the Revit stuff in here.
And all I'm doing is saying, whatever family I want to put in there,
family being just the object you want to put in there, create some coordinates.
So I can just do xyz000.
It can be an output list.
So it's an x range at 0 to 100 feet in 20-foot increments,
less than the for loop for y in that x range, same thing, 0 to 120, and a z in that range.
So I get my xyzs at however many intervals and however many steps.
And then I spit out a point by coordinates, an xyz.
I say, OK, the column is going to be the family instance times the point by coordinates,
and then append the column to that.
That's it.
So that's the entirety of the effort.
So I could take something like that, put it into the IDE for the script, and I push out all that.
So I get, without having a bunch of nodes and wires and all that,
I have the entire geometry listed right there in front of me,
which is really neat because I could hand this off to just about anybody,
if they don't know anything about coding or Python, just change those numbers.
They're good enough.
It's like, yes, just use the numbers, change them, and you can figure out the rest there.
So that's really easy to read.
It's compact, and it's just nice because you could take that and actually push that into your model.
Recently, I've done this where I had to do this exact same thing, like, I don't know, 6,000 times.
I did not want to manually do that 6,000 times or any other way.
This is just a quick, as long as you know your range, it will spit out everything pretty cleanly.
So it's kind of things we could do here, just some basic scripting and examples
that we can't easily attain even with those low code nodes.
And you could take it further.
You can put everything in the script.
If you know what you want, you could just assign, say, width and length parameters
and have an origin point, have an axis, and tell it to turn the axis,
and get this cool twisting tower effect.
So the skyscraper I had before, which was like one of the semi-levels,
if I had to use those nodes with all the strings, that would take a minute.
But I could use this to just, say, twist it. And twist it it does.
And you can have a lot of fun with this.
Again, it's pretty easy to read. There's nothing really crazy about it.
They can get longer, of course, but these are just compact examples.
This is an example of just very easy, accessible use of Python in the design world.
And you could take it further.
You can use examples of how you can do something as complicated as having these array of steel girders
and beams aligned in a weird way.
You can use the script to help you to create that as well.
Otherwise, it would be a bit of an effort.
Some of our software is not very friendly to change.
So this is great to have something like this between the low-code solution and the code solution
to create geometry that we can use for some cool projects.
And you can take it even further. This example here, I'll link it.
It's this whole sample of how you make a train station canopy with these kind of tools very quickly.
So you can manipulate all the diamond shapes you see here without having to spend literally a month modeling
like the old-fashioned way.
So these are kind of possibilities we have now with Python and all these other solutions
that we didn't have even 10 years ago.
And that encouraged me to make my own course about it.
This was a couple years ago that I made my own course.
I learned about it. I studied it.
And I created my own little course about how you can do all this stuff with Python, with Dynamo,
in this environment, so I could show other people in the design industry
how they can use it for all sorts of different purposes.
And of course, like anything else with code, you do have to debug it.
That's what happens when things don't work, when you have errors and warnings.
You get those yellow boxes. So you're not free from errors and all that.
It's part of the reality of any coding.
But it's a pretty fun learning experience with this because you can see your results.
Either you have some crazy shapes that shouldn't happen or you have way too many objects or not enough.
So it's kind of fun to see those results pop up in front of you.
It's very encouraging. It's a very good experience for first-term learners.
And you might ask, what about other things? What about drawings?
Well, here's the thing. Everything we just saw was just the Dynamo solution, which comes with the Revit software.
There's a whole community working with Python to create their own solutions.
This, for example, is called PyRevit. It's a rapid application prototyping solution.
The idea here is that if you really want to, you can skip all that stuff with low code,
and Dynamo just have this sit on top of the software, and you instead have to worry about C Sharp and the SDK and all that.
You just run with this PyRevit solution, which is built on another open source solution called Revit Python wrapper.
So the whole community out there, nobody really wants to use the SDK for Revit.
That's how badly you want to get around this. It's very painful.
So everybody just kind of made their own solutions.
So PyRevit was on project, the RPW, the Revit Python wrapper, was another project.
And they just put their heads together and made this.
And what's cool is there's a whole toolbar that does a lot of automation for you out of the box, and you can make your own tools.
And people have been doing this, using these solutions for a couple of years now.
It's been great because you can take inside of your software, you don't have to use the low code environments directly there.
You can share it with your coworkers as an application.
It's all kind of prepackaged batteries included for you.
And it looks like this. That's the monstrous API nobody wants to use. You still have to learn how to use it.
Fun story, this website here is actually another open source project called Revit API Docs that somebody else made,
because the API documentation that the developers released was really bad.
So this guy basically put it online, and the developers then used it themselves.
They probably figured out their own documentation for different versions of the software.
So that's an open source solution to figure out all the code samples.
And then you can use, it's kind of hard to read, but that's Python based, not C Sharp, that you can use to create your own applications,
to do cool things like edit unconventional shapes or weird shapes and things you can't do out of the box,
or you have to spend a lot of money on third party solutions.
So now you can just directly edit with Python into the model, which is great.
And if I say I created it, it works. I can share it with anybody else, all for free.
And we also, stepping outside is also the BIM software. We have Blender, a very popular software, general modeling.
It does a lot of cool things. And everybody, it's like one of the most popular 3D modeling software out there.
You can use it for animation, industrial design, you name it.
And it's written in Python, it's written in C and C++, but it has a lot of support for Python with scripting.
And this image has nothing to do with my talk, I just thought it was really cool.
It's kind of what you can do in Blender. It's like animations and shading. It's really cool.
It's a really awesome software. It's pretty user friendly too.
And it's open source, totally free. Just grab it.
And the way it works is it uses things called meshes, primitive meshes to create geometry.
And it's pretty easy to play around with. As you see at the bottom there, it too has a low code solution.
So these kind of solutions are pretty popular. You can use a low code, you can use a Python scripting, you can just use the keystrokes in the UI.
It's pretty easy to play around with. But you can't use it immediately for architectural design.
That's where the Blender BIM Admin comes in. It's an open source software that was like,
hey, it would be really cool if we could just use Blender to model our building information modeling.
Because right now, Blender just meshes and geometries, doesn't do the whole database side of things.
But if we took the geometry and meshes and push it to the database.
So this is the middle man here that can quickly take your model ideas into a software and continue working on the database side.
And that's what happens when you have the geometry and meshes from the Blender solution and scale it up for a building.
And all you're doing here is just taking those meshes, making those shapes, the shapes that have solids, the solids that become loaded with walls and doors, architectural elements.
And then you can at the end see that section of a floor plan. They can then put on a sheet.
Very, very fast, very cool. This is kind of like everybody's dream. Just quickly do something in the software.
And I think this is kind of where things are going. They don't want to eat it to get to their awesome ideas.
A lot of architects and people in engineering construction, they have to eat it to get to anything nice.
And this cuts out a lot of that. And what's really cool is you can combine Blender BIM Admin with the IFC.
IFC is like the JSON of the BIM world. It's industry foundation classes. So it's like a non-proprietary.
And you can use that to then take the Blender stuff, use this IFC format to then through Blender into these other softwares that you can then load as an exchangeable file.
And then you could start editing those in your proprietary BIM software, which there's a bunch of them, not just Revit, there's a whole gang of them.
And you can do cool stuff like this. You could take your ideas as a giant mesh or a series of meshes, create generative options of a loft of a tower like this where the base is a bigger shape and the top is a smaller shape.
You loft that up so the top and bottom connect. You give it a twist. And before you know it, you get architecture.
And this is an amazingly fast way of doing it all in Blender. You can push it to your other software and work with it. It's very cool stuff.
But we're not done yet. There's also this cool Ladybug. And what's cool about Ladybug tools, it's for climate and weather analysis.
We're increasingly concerned about how the built environment of any kind is using energy, is good for comfort.
And so there's been a whole spread of solutions, and one of them is Ladybug. And it works with just about any popular geometry engine.
It's all written in Python. You just pip install lbt dash Ladybug if you want to try it out. It's all free.
And what it does is stuff like this. It can help you do solar path analysis. A big old arch tube thing, look at the top there.
That's just every position the sun would travel throughout the year in a given latitude.
So you can just study a building and figure out what the solar properties were, what it looks like when the sun pops in through your window,
what parts of the room at a given time of year are getting sunlight, what aren't, what's a good way to make it a comfortable space, not too much heat, not too cold.
So you have to run the heater to make it efficient. These are the kind of tools and solutions coming around to help people study that and make a better design, better building,
lower energy building that has a better carbon footprint for the environment.
And this is just an example of running in that dynamo low-code platform, but it wouldn't do a lot of other things. So that's what's nice about it.
It's very versatile. And it has its friend, Honeybee, which also does similar things. In this case, it does visualization for data energy analysis.
So you can figure out highs and lows throughout the year, throughout a day, 24-hour period, a six-month period, whatever.
It gives you some visualizations. They have a whole tool set here. Now you could do this all with the tool sets, but you could also do some cool stuff with generative design and optionaries that they call it,
where you can just use the AI machine learning tools to your advantage to figure out every possible scenario, like different sizes of your room, windows, alignments, what have you,
get a bunch of different results and help you kind of determine what is a better set of parameters you can use to move forward with and narrow down your selection.
So you don't have to do that manually. These are the kind of tools people are using right now for just working on buildings and structures and making sure we have really sound ideas and sound design solutions.
And again, all done through tools that you would use from either built on Python or from Python libraries.
And that's what's great about it. The future is just going in a direction where Python is going to be a great exchange of data between all these different sets.
So you can feed data from all sorts of different model formats and databases, SQL, integrate them through open exchanges to Python,
and then for Python, use your different libraries like Pandas, what have you, to get some analysis out of it so that it's not stuck.
That's been kind of the issue with the world I'm in, in the built environment. Things get stuck in one place or another.
They look great until, like, you want to extract data. But this is one way to release that data, is through these open standards, accessible coding solutions for people at every stage, and use Python to create some data analysis.
And the future, moving forward, will be, like I mentioned, more data science because there's more interest in how we can use data and things like machine learning to help us understand what's going on in our buildings.
They're very complex. You only see the facade, but there's a whole engine of stuff happening under the hood that needs to be studied.
Building something, depending on how you look at the references, it was like 20, 25% of our carbon footprint comes from buildings.
So how do we better design buildings that have a lower carbon impact?
IoT, things like MicroPython that can help us develop IoT solutions, digital twin solutions to help us monitor our buildings.
Just about everything is moving in the direction of visual twins for structures small and big.
And everything in the building industry is also kind of like 10 years behind the times.
So if everything was already IoT, kind of kicking off 10 years ago as a big wave, this watch is an IoT device of my heart.
So I'm with it. So we try to see, can we do something like that for the entire structure and get some real good data of like, you know, are we using too much energy?
Are there spaces people aren't going to because it's inconvenient? Maybe like this room.
Custom applications. Of course, I saw the demo this morning by Peter Wang of all the cool stuff you can do with Python, PyScript with WebAssembly.
I'm like, well, there you go. So there's also the cool custom applications. I mentioned PyRev, what have you, earlier.
You could just, if you don't want to buy a real robust solution because you don't need it or you don't know what to do with the other tools out there,
you can at least try to make your own tools that are a lot more compact or use somebody else's tool set that's, you know, to the point and direct solutions for what you want.
So this is all the fields that Python can feed into. And you know, shout out to all the open source maintainers out there.
Everything I just talked about here was an open source project. Dynamo, even though it's based on a corporate, from out of this themselves, it's an open source.
I could make my own copy, do whatever. They're a great team. I didn't show you Grasshopper this time, but that's a similar looking thing by another corporate sponsor.
Blender, of course, completely open source, one of the best examples of open source, PyRev and all the other tools I showed you.
These guys are great. I would not be able to speak to you guys today if it wasn't for these kind of tools.
So I always like to shout out, show my appreciation, and of course, the Python Software Foundation. They're awesome, too.
And you know, programming should be fun. That's why I picked Python. JavaScript's great. C Sharp's great. They're all great.
But Python really made me enjoy what I'm doing with architecture and design. They feel like I was hitting a wall of pain trying to figure out how to debug something.
It was way more accessible. So that's why I like this program language.
Just to repeat, Python makes it possible. This is the beauty of Python. It does so many things great.
And if you find interest in any of these things, any of the solutions I've shown you today, consider getting involved in any of these things, those tool sets,
or if you're interested in any of these things, you can reach out to me about them.
Because really at the end, we want more people to be aware what Python could do, not just in its traditional features, but also the built world.
I think if we all kind of put eyes on what we can do for the built environment with automation, coding, data, it'll be a better built environment.
Because at this point, it's kind of like everybody eyeballs and uses their intuition to design.
But if we had more robust processes and better tools, we get a better version of the future.
So it's kind of spreading words like to get more involvement in there into Python, into the built world.
And this is all the resources for all the stuff I showed you today.
On the right is all the links to the different repos and learning libraries for the different software.
And on the left there is special thanks to all the contributors. He did that Brave API site.
Asan for PyRev, Dion, Dimon for BlunderBim, Mustafa for Vladybug, Dynamo Team, and Grasshopper Team at their companies.
I always give a shout to them because I'm really dependent on them. So thanks to them.
And thank you so much, guys, for attending my talk. I really appreciate it.
I got the QR code right there if you want the link. I guess it'll be in the video.
So if you want to reach out, I'm not hard to find. Tadej Akopyan.
And that's it. I can open up questions or I can whatever, here down the hall, as if you guys. Thank you.
Does anyone have any questions that would like to?
Otherwise we can meet the speaker here later and he can answer any questions, any doubts that you have about the presentation.
Are you one at the mic? Okay. Give me a second.
I just wanted to ask you where you think computing for design architecture is going to go because Revit and all the many of the open source tools that you mentioned are sort of hitting Revit, which is a proprietary infrastructure.
But you also mentioned IFC, which is the open standard for buildings.
And I was wondering what you think about IFC or which direction is going to go.
We're going to remain proprietary or do you think this will go fully open source?
My hopes and dreams is that it will go very open source to the point where the proprietary software is optional.
You can use it. Maybe I'll give you like the better version of the workflows.
But if you don't have to use it, you can use the Blender BIM and the IFC and all that to get your work done at a pretty high level.
Though it's really I think the way I would say is the more interest and uses of these open source solutions people are pursuing at the grassroots level, the more the I guess the proprietary software solutions have to respond to that.
They have to listen to customer demand and they fight each other all the time with these different companies that lock you into their thing.
And then it's like, OK, you have to use this even between the different BIM solutions from the companies.
They don't like to share anyway. You're locked into their format.
So if we had something like an IFC, like a real robust one, which people are getting towards and people want more of that would accelerate it.
I think it's totally possible. But it's got to be like people have to be aware of the companies that work at the who access the software,
who work on these kind of solutions that they do want more of that open source without locked in to a vendor.
So I think it's just a matter of like spreading the word, spreading the knowledge.
And the more you spread and just kind of show these examples of like this is what's possible.
It's pretty accessible. Then the more it will gain traction.
So it's a matter of like grassroots movement in that direction.
I do really think that so long as the people want it, the users want it, the companies, the vendors will respond and make it a lot more IFC friendly.
But I'm not sure if it'll be IFC as like on the like we call like a let's call it a desktop version of it versus the Web.
I'm not sure what would it all be going through the Web because everything's easier on the Web exchanges.
It's a little more open there versus like exporting a file, manipulating that a little more.
That's a little more old fashioned. A lot of friction.
A lot of friction. So there might be a marriage between the IFC solution.
I believe there is an IFC.JS that can help.
So it might move in different directions, but I think it will move eventually the direction of like a better version of IFC if the people want it.
I'm optimistic.
So any other question, please? Today we'll be more than glad to continue this discussion.
I'm sorry we run out of time, but as I said, he will be more than glad to continue the discussion.
And thank you, Tede, for the great presentation.
Thank you.