Okay, hello everyone, thanks for coming. Thanks to all the organizers and all that. So we
are two of the PiedEyed maintainers and we're here to tell you about PiedEyed, which you
may have heard about in Peter's talk this morning. We are a Python distribution for
the browser. So a quick about us. So I am a UCLA, a National Science Foundation assistant
adjunct professor, which means a postdoc, but there's like title inflation. So yeah,
so this work that I've done is partially supported by NSF grant, Department of Material Science,
number whatever, mathematical sciences. Okay, and here's Roman.
And I'm Roman. So I'm a data scientist working mostly as an independent consultant and I'm
a core developer for At-Sec-It Learn and PiedEyed, so mostly projects that are difficult to pronounce.
So today we're going to talk about what is PiedEyed. We're going to review some of the
most common use cases, which include interactive computing, educational use cases, and machine
learning. And then we'll discuss a bit more in detail, like the technical developments
on in the last several years in PiedEyed. Sorry. So as you all know, if you have a Python
code and you want to run it in the browser, and this is also what was presented in this
morning's keynote, essentially the setup is fairly complicated because you have to have
some front-end code in JavaScript, probably some backend code in Python, and some infrastructure
that you either need to maintain or configure if it's a cloud provider. And so the idea
is fairly simple, is could we just run, take this Python application and run it directly
inside the browser. So this is possible with WebAssembly and the general implications of
this were really well presented this morning in the keynote by Peter.
So we're going to talk to introduce you PiedEyed, which is the distribution of Python in the
browser, and with the focus of not so much just running the interpreter or being able
to execute Python code, but essentially being able to run packages, existing packages and
existing tools in the Python ecosystem.
Okay. So first, what is WebAssembly? So WebAssembly is the second programming language available
in the browser. It's a binary instruction format for a stack-based virtual machine.
It's portable. It's designed for small code sizes. It's designed for security, and so
as part of that security, it doesn't come with any sort of standard library that it
always has. It just defines a set of imports, and it has a system for calling a function,
and so it can call the imports. And so the host application has to define what it gets
to import. It's implemented in all modern browsers, mobile browsers. You can run it
in non-web environments like Node. There's WebAssembly system interface. So yeah. Anyway,
that's what WebAssembly is.
And so then we have the inscription build tool chain. So as I said, WebAssembly itself
has no standard library. It can't do any input or any output. It can only do pure computation.
All contact with the outside world has to happen through imports. And so the inscription
build tool chain is a compiler tool chain that compiles C and C++ code to WebAssembly.
This uses Clang, so you can set up a WebAssembly target for Clang, but then we also need an
environment that supports system calls that actually interact with the outside world,
and so it also provides JavaScript bindings for all the system calls that you need. It's
designed for porting POSIX Linux applications. So it has POSIX Linux system calls implemented
in JavaScript. So then you can load this from an HTML page and serve it to a web browser.
So the main components of Piotite are we have CPython, which we have some patches for. We'll
talk about upstreaming those. It's an ongoing process that's mostly going pretty well,
thanks to Christian Himes. And then we have a Python and JavaScript foreign function interface,
which is really rich. It allows for very easy usage of one language to the other. We'll
talk more about this in a bit. And then we take the CPython interpreter and our foreign
function interface, which is like a C extension of Python. We take these two things and we
compile them with them scripted into a WebAssembly binary with a JavaScript host that provides
the operating system, all of the standard library. We also compile most of the popular
Python binary extensions, including NumPy, Panda, SciPy, Matplotlib. Also, we can compile
cryptography, so now we have Rust support very recently. And then we have a package
called MicroPip, which is for installing pure Python wheels from PyP.
Yeah, and we want to call out Michael Drutbom, who was a Mozilla employee who originally
made Piotite and did really great work on it. We've sort of been polishing the stuff
that he set up. Right, so I mentioned upstreaming RC Python patches. So we used to have to patch
all sorts of stuff in order to get Python to run because WebAssembly and Emscripten
is a very different sort of host environment than like x86 Linux. And so in order to do
signal handling, in order to handle certain extensions, we needed to patch a bunch of
things. And so, Christian Himes and Brett Cannon and I guess Ethan Smith have been involved
in a process, and many other Python maintainers have been involved in upstreaming a lot of
our patches and a lot of other fixes that they're adding to see Python in order to
add sort of third party support or tier three support for Piotite in Python. And so this
includes like upstreaming our patches. The compiler itself has a lot of bugs. It's fairly
new. There's not a huge number of maintainers for Emscripten. And so we're hitting a lot
of edge cases, a lot of bugs, trying to get the Python test suite to pass. So over time,
this should make Piotite more sustainable and also help like the rest of the ecosystem.
So other people who are trying to compile Python to WebAssembly might hit these same
edge cases in the Emscripten compiler, and so it should help them too.
So for context, Piotite isn't the first project that builds Python for the Web. You have a
number of those. So you have, for instance, Brighton, which is a Python 3 re-implementation
JavaScript, which re-implements the interpreter and parts of the standard library. There's
the PyPy.js, which is essentially fairly similar to what Piotite does, but it was like several
years ago, and it used a different technology rather than ASM.js rather than WebAssembly,
and this project is no longer maintained currently. And there is the Rust Python project that,
because it's like, so it's a re-implementation of the Python interpreter in Rust, and because
Rust has already a pretty nice toolchain to port things to WebAssembly, you can essentially
with little effort run it in a browser. So the difference, let's say what we are focused
on is not so much having the interpreter in the browser, but it's having the whole ecosystem
run there, like the whole Python ecosystem. And what matters there is essentially very
good compatibility and being able to run your code with minimal changes. And this is, for
instance, difficult if you re-implement your interpreter from scratch, because then you
will have some edge cases. For instance, in Brighton, it's difficult to have exactly the
same behavior as the standard CPython. So by using the standard CPython, we remove a
lot of those compatibility issues. And so I'm going to present next how we package the
library ecosystem. So we have a tool called MicroPip, which allows to install pure Python
wheels from PyPI. So essentially it's like a pip, but very simplified, so it has very
rudimentary dependency resolution. It's only allowed to load pure Python wheels, so wheels
that have the file extension as you see below. On the contrary, a lot of packages that have
binary extensions will not be able to install them. And instead what you have to do is,
well, use the PyRide build system to build them specifically for WebAssembly. So we use
a configuration format very highly inspired by Conda, so it's MetaYAML, where you can
configure how you would need to build your package with a binary extension. There is
a cross-compilation setup. And since recently the output is wheels, so you get Python wheels.
Those are, however, not still very standardized, because in particular, well, for instance,
Emscripten doesn't have a stable ABI, so if you update the Emscripten version, your wheels
are not going to be compatible with the previous ones, so that's still a significant problem.
There have also been a lot of improvements in the build system, so since recently we
used PyPI build tool to have build installations. And we'll do also some custom post-processing
steps. For instance, we will un-vendor tests so that the package that you install is a
bit smaller, because probably you don't need to have tests when you just use NumPy. However,
you will be able to install NumPy tests as a separate package. And so all this is currently
distributed with just deliver. So we have, you probably heard the scale of what is involved
in distributing Python packages with PyPI. We're clearly not at the same scale, so we're
much smaller, but there are still some challenges in making sure that if anybody puts a, you
know, a PyIoDiode import, loading PyIoDiode on some high traffic webpage, and everybody
is going to download those files, that we are able to support this. And we're really
grateful to just deliver who are able to do this, mostly because they're supported by
a number of CDN providers. And just to mention, there was also some related work to do with
have a build system, which is more closer to Conda, which is to also build essentially
packages, Python packages for VASM, which was done in M scripting forge project.
So to give you an overview of the packages that we currently can use, well, some of them
were mentioned before. So we have all the core scientific computing packages, NumPy,
Pandas, SciPy, MetalCleave, et cetera. So this also means that we can actually build,
for instance, packages that use Cyton. For SciPy, SciPy was very challenging. We'll
talk about this later. But SciPy uses FORTRAN. That's fairly difficult to build. So it requires
external libraries such as BLAST and LAPACK for linear algebra. And then with this, we
can also use all the downstream, build all the downstream packages, Scikit-learn, Scikit-img,
and statmodel. So we can load packages from PyP, and MicroPip, and also we have a number
of different other packages that are not part of the scientific computing. So PyIdiode
is not a project for scientific computing. It's just that we have a lot of scientific
computing packages because those tend to have binary extensions. But you, for instance,
can use SQL Alchemy to set up a SQLite database. So that's the only type of database that currently
works. And use it for something completely unrelated to scientific computing. And since
recently, as Hude mentioned, we also are able to compile the latest version of cryptography,
which was implemented in Rust and uses the PyTree library to expose the Rust code to
Python. So overall, we have over 120 packages in PyIdiode, and those, in addition to those,
you can install from PyP that are just for Python.
Okay, so I'm going to talk about the foreign function interface. So we have Python, the
interpreter, which you can run in the browser. But the browser's host system is all in JavaScript.
So if you want to directly talk to the DOM, you need JavaScript functionality. And so
it's important that we can sort of interface well with existing software that's already
written for the web. And so we have a very pleasantly designed foreign function interface
that makes it very easy to do this. So if you want to use JavaScript from Python, you
can import JavaScript objects that are in the global JavaScript scope directly from
this sort of magic JS module. So for instance, setTimeout is a JavaScript function that calls
a function at some delay. It's in the global scope, so you can import it from JS, and then
you can call setTimeout, and it will call a function at 100 millisecond delay.
On the other hand, you can also use Python from JavaScript. So like at the start entry
point of your application, you want to call into Python to call your main method. So a
Python object that's in global scope can be accessed from JavaScript. So here, this is
an example where we load the sum built-in method, and then we use it on a list, and
you know, it sums the entry. So sum accepts any iterable. That argument is a JavaScript
array, but we can make JavaScript arrays into Python iterables, and so sum accepts it and
successfully iterates over it and sums the values.
So we automatically convert simple types, so float, string, int, void, none, null. Most
other types are proxied, so we just make like a wrapper object that allows you to make sort
of convenient idiomatic calls in the current language that go across the other language
and do operations in the other language.
So here's some examples. So here's some examples of using Python utilities from JavaScript.
So Python has all these great standard library utilities. So for instance, here is the reduce
function. Okay, I can use the mouse here. So the first argument is a lambda. Now this,
this is the Python functools package. We imported it and returned it, so this is functools,
the Python object, it's a module object. So functools.reduce now is a method, and we can
call it, its first argument is supposed to be a function that takes two arguments and
returns one. Now this argument is a JavaScript lambda expression, right, multiplies the two
arguments. This is a JavaScript array. Reduce expects its second argument to be an iterable.
It expects its first argument to be a callable. This is a callable, this is an iterable. It
successfully reduces it and gets a 10 or something.
So right, okay, here's the second example. So math is like another, you know, standard
library package. We can import it, it returns the module, the math module, and then math
has a least common multiple method, and this will compute the least common multiple for
6 and 13 from JavaScript. So, you know, again, another example which is a bit more complicated.
So here we import the random module, and so now random does not take an iterable as its,
random.sample is going to sample from a list. And it does not take an iterable as its first
argument. It needs a list. Now this is a JavaScript array which is different from a Python list.
So we need to convert it into a Python list. So we have this converter function, pi dot
2 pi, which takes the JavaScript array and converts it into a Python list so that it's
acceptable for random sample. Then this samples five random elements from the pair red and
blue so we're going to get like red, red, blue, blue, red or something. And then, but
that returns a Python list, but if we want a JavaScript array then we need to convert
it back. So that's this to JS function. So here, so that previous example actually leaks
a couple of Python objects. They'll eventually get reclaimed by the browser garbage collector,
but it takes a while. Whereas like Python garbage collector because its reference counter
tends to get called much faster. So here's an example that actually doesn't leak these
objects. Where this is basically a wrapper function which you would use to call it from
JavaScript. And so in general you might have like some application which does some data
processing. It receives some data structure from that you collect from the user interface
and then you call into like the main entry point of your Python application. It does
some processing and then it returns some data back to JavaScript for display. And so this
shows you how you would do the translations at the boundary of the application. So here
we have like the sample space. So this would be red and blue. But that again we're expecting
this to be called from JavaScript. So we're expecting this sample space to be a JavaScript
array. Now sample expects again a Python list. So first we convert space to a Python list
using the 2Py method. And then we sample from it. We get a Python list and then we want
to return it to the UI potentially that's going to display it to the user in some way.
And so we convert the result list back to JavaScript at the boundary. Yeah. So here's
another example. So this uses the fetch API. So fetch is a way to download you know like
URLs in the browser. So we fetch example dot com. We can specify some options. And it
looks very much like normal Python code but it's calling into a JavaScript method. You
will see in some of this in Peter Wang's talk if you went to it too. So here's another example
where so this shows using low level memory buffers. So NumPy has a multi-dimensional
array interface. So it makes like you know fast memory buffers. And you can actually
call like make direct memory accesses from JavaScript. So for instance if you want to
use a JavaScript image or video processing library you can pass it an indie array from
NumPy and you can access from this buffer the strides and the dimensions and all the
stuff and you can hand it to a JavaScript indie array library and then call into whatever
this image processing or AI library you want to use as.
So what we're doing is essentially we're running our Python code in the scripting host environment
which we use as a VM. So it's essentially as running Python code on any like a bit strange
VM. So the features of this one is that it's a 32 bit architecture. So well normally it
works but some Python packages are a bit like less well tested on 32 bit. We have in file
in memory file system so Emscripten provides this. So you have a file system you can write
files like your Python modules are loaded from files but it's in memory one.
So and the limitation is that you cannot use for instance super ss's you cannot use threading
because those are not allowed by this VM. You can also not use sockets and some system
calls are implemented but not all. So it's also difficult to use some of the standard
like IOS streams such as STD out because like if you want to show something you need to
render it on the HTML page not like as you would normally on an OS.
And next we'll present some of the use cases we have that are used by that.
Right so I guess our three main use cases that we want to talk about are interactive
computing as was discussed by Peter Wang and then education and machine learning are sort
of special cases of the interactive computing that we're particularly good for. It's very
good for like scientific communication and that sort of stuff.
So we want to talk about client only architectures which is what Peter Wang again talked about
this morning. So the idea is that if you have a back end server you know so then the user
is using your website your web application it sends data back to the server. The server
does some computations with it and then it sends the results back to the UI to be displayed
and so the client only architecture the server's only role is to send a set of static files
to the user and then all of the logic all of the computation happens inside of the browser
and you know so this has benefits to privacy it has benefits from the right I guess we'll
talk about here right okay so usability benefits right so you don't need to install Python
so if you're like doing scientific computation you can share your work with other people
they don't need to have Python installed right so there's big benefits to scalability so
you don't need to have a web server you don't need or you need to have a static you need
to sort of static files you don't need like any containerization you don't need any cloud
you don't need to figure out how to organize the compute because it all happens on the
client side. Yeah and generally packages only need to be downloaded once and then the browser
will cache them so it takes a long time on the first use but if you're using it like
every day as part of your like scientific computing workflow then you'll only see that
time hit on the first load right so it also has big benefits to privacy so because all
calculations are run locally no data is sent to a remote server which is you know good
for users because their data is private it's good for developers because they don't have
to fill out as much paperwork so for instance there's this talk analyzing sensitive data
at scale doesn't have to be a headache which is about analyzing you know children's financial
data with python where they have a lot of trouble installing software there's a complicated
paperwork they have to do to install software but they also cannot use software as a service
because they cannot send out that private data so what they do is they go to a website
they download the python application with Piedide and then they can turn off the internet
airgap the computer plug in a flash drive with the children's sensitive financial data
and then do the analysis there.
And so what's also interesting that lately there has been a growing ecosystem of tools
that allow you to make client only python applications so there's PyScrip which was
introduced in this morning's keynote which allows you to create rich python applications
in the browser using HTML there is Iridium which is a tool that allows you to make interactive
documents and data visualizations like they use a lot of markdown so it's nice to write
there are also attempts to essentially interface react like to use react from python using
the Piedide type translation tools and then there's like project like VC code which runs
essentially python snippets as HTML type so there's like a growing ecosystem of tools
we can also mention all the projects that allow you to run notebooks on the client side
so one of the most popular ones is Jupyter Lite currently which is essentially the code
base of Jupyter Lab which normally requires a kernel on the server but in this case the
kernel was moved inside the web browser and it runs on Piedide and there's also Startboard
Notebook there's Baston which is a fork of Jupyter Notebook with the same idea as Jupyter
Lite so this allows to have interactive computing in your browser without having to stop servers
and for instance if you go now on the NumPy page there will be some examples that use
these tools to illustrate NumPy another significant topic of applications Piedide applications
has been education so to give an example for instance currently python is mandatory in
French high school curriculum and so the problem they face is that well teachers are not really
python developers so they don't have time to try to install python on students laptops
and on the other side if you actually want to have some centralized infrastructure that
allows you to execute python code well this is costly both in terms of servers, compute
time and in terms of maintenance and so what they did is to essentially run one like to
develop a notebook solution Baston which is backed by Piedide and they deploy this massively
in high schools in France and so they have like 100,000 weekly users while only having
to maintain a very small like essentially just serving static files and generally there
have been a lot of different projects that try to use some of these ideas for either
for education or for research.
Another use case that I'm personally interested in is how do we deploy machine learning models
so the traditional way to do this is you train your model which is often python code so it's
going to be I don't know scikit learn or tensor flow or PyTorch you serialize it on two disks
somehow so there's you can use the standard pickle format which is like the standard way
to serialize python objects or there are some specific serialization formats then you
develop a web service you package it probably in a container and then you deploy it somewhere
on some server so this is again this is complicated and there are tools that actually work with
this custom serialization formats that allow you to do inference in the browser so that
support web assembly however they only work for a fairly limited set of operations so
for instance if you use TensorFlow.js you will be able to run tensor flow operators
but you will not be able to run arbitrary python code that you might need to pre-process
your data or transform it somehow and so the idea is that well since you now have python
running in the browser you can just use pickle so pickle is a standard python serialization
format it has some disadvantages because it's a bit unsafe since you're running arbitrary
python code it's a bit brittle to environment changes but it's essentially portable and
non-epic meaning that once you just realize it you get your original python object and
you can explore it and so the steps to now to deploy scikit learn models for instance
with pyodide would be just you create the environment which needs to match between the
environment where you train your model and the environment where you predict you pick
your model you unpickle it in the browser and then you run inference on your python
object so also training can also happen directly in the browser we can illustrate this with
the following example yeah that was not it yeah I did that before the time sorry sorry
the home key is a bit of a okay so here we have an example which is a react application
that's used to display classifier decision boundaries using matplotlib so it loads it
has uses some example data it trains a model in it and then it displays the decision boundary
here so you have here for instance you have three classes and you see the decision boundary
here with the logistic regression model and then switch browser tabs no it's not sorry
so you can see the three boundaries three classes that are categorized with this model
and now you can just change that for instance your model it's going to be retrained live
in the browser you're going to have it change fairly quickly and then even here in this
application you can like add extra points for instance and your model is going to be
retrained each time you do this and it's going to be adapted and like fairly very very quickly
okay so now I'm going to talk about latest developments in Outlook right there were a
bunch more fancier demos at Peter Wang's talk this morning so you can see more of the stuff
that we can do with this right so now I'm going to talk about some of the technical
things that have gone into making Pydide work recently which we think are really fun so
what issue is packaging SciPy and Fortran so there's not a working Fortran compiler
based on LLVM RM script and toolchain is based on LLVM and so this is a problem for us there's
three work in progress compilers there's LFortran and there's Flang Classic and there's Flang
and then so I mean you can do even like very desperate things like there's a GCC plugin
called Dragon Egg which allows you to produce LLVM IR and then you can like hand that over
to LLVM and like compile it to WebAssembly but this is sort of a desperation move so
we use FQC which is a program to convert Fortran 77 code to Z code one problem with this
is that much of the code in SciPy is Fortran that's newer than Fortran 77, Fortran 90
even newer ones and FQC sometimes exceeds on it but we have lots of trouble with it
so we use a mix we have an automatic source transformations that we do on the Fortran
input we have automatic source transformations on the C output that we do both before and
after conversion and then we also have a lot of sort of manual patches and this gets most
of the SciPy test passing but it's sort of a big effort.
Okay so another big issue for us is function pointer casts so Python C extensions define
C functions and then call them with the wrong number of arguments. The C standard says this
is undefined behavior but most C compilers generate code that doesn't crash so if you
define a function that takes two arguments but ignore the second one and then you call
it with one argument usually on native architecture this doesn't crash. WebAssembly however puts
the signature of the function into the assembly and the runtime will validate the function
pointer at runtime and check whether its signature matches the asserted signature if it does
not it will crash with call indirect function pointer signature mismatch.
So here's an example so here's your C extension like numpy or something so we define the function
called do something now this function actually just doesn't do anything it just returns
none and it takes a single object which is the representation of this function as a Python
object and it's going to return none all the time. So then you need to tell the Python
virtual machine the Python interpreter how to invoke this so we say its name is do something
and we say that here's the function pointer that we're going to call when we want to call
this and then we give it the calling convention which is no arms. Now people in the back probably
won't see this at the bottom but in method object dot C in the interpreter it will call
this function with two arguments see this null here so it's going to put a null in
as the second argument you know of course the reason we didn't take that as an argument
is because it's always null so it doesn't give you useful information so C developers
forget about it but in WebAssembly this is a crash and there's tons of these right so
I mean all the solution would be to fix all of them in the packages but we don't have
the maintainer effort to do that because there's so many of them. So the solution that we finally
found after much contemplation is that calls from JavaScript into WebAssembly are flexible
they can be called with the wrong number of arguments and it just works. So we use a trampling
call we call from WebAssembly back out to JavaScript and we say JavaScript why don't
you call back into WebAssembly with this function these arguments and then it calls back into
JavaScript and that accepts the wrong number of arguments is fine. This solution has been
upstreamed into Python 3.11 thanks to encouragement from Christian Himes you know and that's why
I have a blog post about this you can see the poll request if you want it's a big thing.
Okay so another issue of this veramind. Right so another problem that most like a lot of
PyLite users face is that you cannot use essentially HTTP client or requests or all those libraries
that need to interact with the network because sockets don't work. So what you have to do
instead is to use JavaScript API such as fetch but then there is another problem that those
APIs are often async and Python expects those functions to be sync. So there is a work in
progress solution which tries to use a WebWorker so WebWorker is essentially like a process
in classical Python so it's another so it's another worker you can run in your browser
to which you can actually send the requests to download your package async and meanwhile
you block your main thread with atomics to until that fetch completes. So there is a
project that's being worked by hood called sync link which aims to make this process
easier and so as an example another thing is for instance because you are in the browser
sandbox you cannot access files on your file system due to security reasons however there
is a Chrome file system API which allows you to essentially using this system to mount
point like a local folder inside the M scripting file system and then you can directly write
into the host OS file system.
Okay so right so we have async IO in the browser so this is each browser process I guess we
are going to call it comes with its own event loop and Python has event loops you can implement
and so we have a custom event loop for async IO which basically all it does to do is schedule
tasks on the browser event loop. So it has certain limitations like async IO dot run
until complete cannot work as expected because it blocks the same process that's actually
doing the Python computation and so it cannot block and we also have no control over the
event loop lifecycle but one of the big benefits of this is that you don't need to control
the event loop lifecycle no one wants to do that you know you really just want to run
your async code setting up the event loop is sort of baggage that like we have to go
through to get to the running the async code and so yeah.
So another frequent question is how big are like packages you download so for instance
if you have an application on the right here that loads pandas well you have to load pandas
and all the dependencies of pandas so including numpy here and then you have to load CPython
the standard library so in this example at the very bottom you can see that we in total
downloaded 18 megabytes and around 30 megabytes we get around 30 megabytes after it's uncompressed.
So this is a significant issue because while Python ecosystem was never optimized for size
because if you install local it doesn't really matter there are historically large packages
such as CPy which has a lot of modules that maybe you are not going to use in the given
application but they're still there when you install CPy and also as you mentioned before
some packages will include tests.
So what can we do about this?
Well there are several possible ways so we could try to break large packages into smaller
ones the problem is basically it changes your dependency graph so you have new packages
that are created and that's a bit difficult to manage.
A different approach is to use a bundler tool so a bundler tool it means that we have some
Python code that we need to run we know the code in advance we're going to run it in the
PIO diet and we're going to check at runtime which files are actually accessed and then
we're going to recreate an archive with just those files which should be much smaller than
all the files that were installed.
And finally last approach is using dynamic imports so essentially fetch the file when
you import it however there are often like more than 50 modules that a given application
can import so it's a lot of like it's probably a significant performance concerns.
And finally the last solution is to well we can just wait for the average webpage size
to grow larger I mean it's a sad situation but it turns out that it's a trend that goes
in our favor.
Okay so now we're going to talk about the roadmap so what we're up to in the future.
There's a lot of maintenance work to do so we need to keep up with inscription releases
currently we're stuck on an old version of inscription due to a bug in recent versions
of Firefox combined with recent versions of LLVM but it's a fair amount of work to keep
up with them scripted in because of very weird bugs.
We need to upstream patches so NumPy has a lot of patches we'd like to upstream them
many other packages have like a few patches and it would be nice to get more of those
upstream.
Yeah support for synchronous I.O. and web workers as we talked about a couple minutes
ago it would be nice to re-implement certain standard library modules that use web APIs
like HTTP client you know could use fetch.
Reducing size of packages improving the sustainability of the build system maybe someday threading
support so there's a lot of work to be done both upstream and downstream you know in fact
it would be very valuable to work on the inscription compiler and improve some of these weird edge
cases that we had.
And of course to actually get this to users our project is very much sort of down the
trenches of doing platform compatibility problems that we're trying to solve but we're also
trying to be useful tool to downstream so there's documentation work there's all sorts
of work to be done.
We love anyone that has issues please write your questions on our issue tracker please
Any help with the docs any work on our package or work downstream we're very happy to see
exciting projects downstream.
And so just last note is that there's still a lot of things to be done and some of those
things don't require that much work to finish.
Yeah there's a lot of very accessible problems.
So we would also like to thank all the people who contributed to Piedad directly and indirectly
so there are directly the Piedad contributors starting from Michael Dordboom who created
Piedad.
There are like users who report bug issues our sponsors and then the community so M
scripting Piedad wouldn't exist without M scripting CPython for the improvements that's
like for the support for WebAssembly that's happening now all our downstream libraries
that like that will make creating client side application with Python in browser easier
so Jupyter, Jupyter Lite, PyScript, Redim etc.
The iodide team so initially the Piedad was created as part of the iodide project at Mozilla
and also the all the package maintainers that help us to review well they review our patches
when we try to fix things.
So thank you.
So do a sprint at the end of PyCon if you want to work on any of those subjects or related
subjects don't hesitate to come.
Thank you.