Hi, everyone. Let's get started. Hello. Yeah. Welcome to Python Types for Fun and Profit.
I'm Pradeep. This is Shannon. Where's Jia? Okay. He's hiding over there. Jia. So we
work at Meta on the Pyre Type Checker, Meta, Facebook, on the Pyre Type Checker, which
runs on millions of lines of code every day, including Instagram's Python and helps catch
bugs before they land into production. So we wanted to share some of that experience
with you. So we've helped a lot of users adopt types in their real world projects and thought
we'd share some lessons and tools that we have come up with along the way. And just
upfront, this is not just the three of us. We've also got a lot of contributions from
Stephen and Alex and Simran. So they'll also be around to help you around doing the exercises.
So the overall structure is that we have four topics. In the first hour, I'll talk about
why we need type checking and how that looks in Python. You'll also spend a bit of time
working through exercises right in your browser to get a feel for how types work. Then next,
Shannon will talk about how you can set type checking for your project, say, in GitHub,
in your terminal and so on. We'll have a short break at midpoint. Then Shannon will talk
about number three, which is typing in the real world where things get messy. Not everything
is cleanly typed. So we have some tools that will help you adopt types in real world projects.
So Shannon will talk about that. And finally, in the last hour, Jia will give you a tour
of various Python features and how we can use typing for them effectively. Sounds good?
All right. So let's begin. What are types? Why do you need type checking? First of all,
Python is already pretty awesome. We all love Python. We're here at PyCon. Why do we need this
thing called type checking? First, let me agree with you. We, too, love Python for many reasons.
One of them is clean syntax. We all know that Python has short readable syntax for things like
list comprehension, F strings, all kinds of features. The ecosystem has a great set of
libraries for whether you like Django or PyTorch or whatever library you like. We have a bunch of
them. And then finally, Python is dynamic, which is probably the biggest selling point for it.
You can customize what happens when you look up an attribute, when you call a function, or you
instantiate a class. All of that is customizable. So Python already comes with a great set of
features. However, there are a few pain points that you and I might have run into. Let me give
you an example of that. So we'll take a simple code snippet here, a get nickname, where you take
a user ID, say a number like 42 or whatever, and you look up the user corresponding to that ID and
then return the nickname for that user. It's a small made-up function, just four lines of code.
In reality, it could be hundreds of lines long. I'm just giving it short for the sake of the
example. So upon reading this, you and I might form a mental model of this saying that this
function accepts an integer user ID and returns a string nickname. Right? And being good software
engineers, we might even write that down in the form of a doc string so that future readers don't
have to read the entire code. They can just read the doc string and live by that. So we can think
of the doc string as the contract of the function. So as long as the caller satisfies their end of
the contract, the function will satisfy its end. So for example, if you have someone calling get
nickname with this ID, it's satisfying the fact that the user ID has to be an integer. So the
function will return a nickname that is a string. So here it might be Shannon, and if you run the
code, you'll get hello Shannon. So if everybody satisfies the contract, things will go fine.
How can things go wrong? For one, the contract that you have could be violated by the caller.
We said we wanted an integer, but there's nothing to stop a caller from just calling it with a
string. So what if they pass in string 1033? They won't realize it immediately, but if you
run the program, you'll get an error saying that you couldn't look up a user ID of type string.
Or they may just fail to provide any arguments at all, and then that would blow up at runtime too.
So what? This is pretty simple code. You might say just run the code, find the bugs, and fix them
within seconds. But in reality, this function might be thousands of lines long. Your program
might take five minutes to reach the point in the code where it blows up, and that will make
your debugging cycle pretty long. We want to get these bugs as quickly as possible. So in a sense,
it takes a while to figure out among all your callers which of them are violating your contract.
This is the first problem that we have. Another issue is that the contract that you have could
be violated by the function implementation itself. So this doc string claims that it returns a string
nickname, but is that always true? So you can see that if user is none, it just returns none as the
value, which is not a string. So if someone just passes in some ID like 9999, they're adding that
to a string, which will blow up at runtime. Again, this is a small function. If it were
hundreds of lines long, you would not discover it for maybe minutes, maybe not months, until a user
files a bug report against your project. So again, it can take a while to figure out where in your
function you are violating the contract in some subtle way. So this was just a simple example,
but I hope it gave you a hint of the problems that many of us run into. So you might say,
okay, I use unit testing a lot, so that should prevent all these issues. So unit testing is
great, and we write a lot of unit tests. We hope everybody does. But one issue is that unit testing
usually tests within the contract of the function. So if you're testing for the function that we had,
you would check for cases like minus one, zero, one, 999. You would test for various cases,
but you probably wouldn't test for things like strings or lists or dictionaries or none,
cases like that. In general, we assume that surely no user is going to be crazy enough to
send in a dictionary as a user ID, but if you've written enough production code, you've probably
seen much stranger things than that. And even with unit tests, we may miss branches. So even in top
Python projects, statement test coverage usually goes up to like 75 to 90%. There are always going
to be gaps in your code where you haven't checked for the contract, and those gaps are probably where
errors are going to look. And if you say I'll write great doc strings, yes, doc strings are great,
but the problem is that either when you write them, you missed something and your doc string
was wrong from the get-go, like ours was, or your doc string was right and the code changed and your
doc string became stale, which could be worse than useless because it could mislead users and then
cause subtle bugs. All this contributes to make you lack confidence in your code, because for one,
you don't know if you're subtly landing bugs and causing crashes in production, or if you're too
afraid of that, you may be hesitant to touch legacy code because you don't know what will break
downstream. You may hesitate to make large refactorings across your code base even though
it desperately needs it because you don't want to risk breaking things. So I hope it's not just me,
I hope you've also come across such issues in your code. So let me now talk about how type checking
can address these issues. So first, the way you would describe the contract of a function using
type annotations is by saying this function accepts an integer, so you say user ID colon int,
so that means user ID must be of type int, and then you say that it returns a string by saying
arrow string. So this is valid Python syntax since Python 3. You don't need a special plugin
for this. To a first approximation, you can think of this as basically a comment that is embedded
within the code. It usually has no runtime effects. It won't affect the way your code works,
but what it will do is help tools analyze your code, tools like Pyre or MyPy or PyWrite, which
are type checkers, which use this to check your body. So if we run Pyre on this code,
it will tell us that return user returns none, whereas this function claims to return string.
It will highlight that spot right away so that you can fix it. So the way you would fix that is by
saying this function can return either a string or it can return none. So the type for that is
optional string. So optional string means it's either a string or it's a none. And once you do
that, you fix that, and then you run Pyre again, it will tell you that there are no errors because
right now everything you return is either a string or it's a none, so your function is valid.
So this is how we can solve the first problem of checking our function body against its contract.
Second, we need to check our callers and restrict them from passing in arbitrary nonsense.
If you have a caller such as somebody who's passing in string, you run Pyre, it will tell you that
this function expected an integer and you passed in a string. So it will warn you right at the call
site so that that cannot go any further. Likewise, if somebody fails to pass in arguments, you run
Pyre, it will show you that this function expected an argument. And we also want to make sure people
are using the return value of our function correctly. So we saw that we're returning an
optional string. Somebody might take the nickname and try to append it to a string.
And as we saw, the return value could be a string or it could be a none. And Pyre will
warn us about that because that could blow up at runtime and we need to fix our code.
So again, this was a simple example, but I hope it showed you some of the ways in which type
checking can help you out. So for one, type checking automatically checks all your function
bodies and all your callers, no matter how many they are or how long your code is. So you can be
guaranteed that your contract is being checked at each point. And because it's automatic,
you can catch bugs as you edit. You don't have to wait for minutes for the program to run and then
crash and then figure out bugs one by one. You can see all of them at once without running the
program. So your debugging cycle basically shrinks usually on the order of seconds.
And more importantly, that gives you confidence in your code. So we talked about silently landing
bugs into production. You can be confident that you're not landing bugs of these kinds,
like type mismatches. Likewise, you can confidently refactor code or like change touch legacy code
which needs to be updated because you know that if you break something, Pyre will warn you about it.
And if it doesn't, you can generally be confident that there are no errors lurking in your code.
So my takeaway for you from this sort of short series was type checking lets you have the best
of both worlds. You have what you have and what you love about Python. Syntax remains the same.
Your code usually doesn't change. It's your function signatures that get type annotations.
So you get the same syntax as before. You may not have known this before, but many of your favorite
libraries have been using this. So you can use it to get the same syntax as before. You may not
know that your favorite libraries already come with type annotations. So if you use PyTorch,
a SQL alchemy, the standard library, all of that already has types for you to take advantage of.
And you can keep your dynamic behavior, your decorators, meta classes, all of those,
and you can still get the guarantees provided by a static type checker.
So I'll pause at this point and ask you if you have any questions, comments, strong opinions.
Anybody have any questions about what we've seen so far? No? Also, I was curious. Sorry, go ahead.
I've heard rumbling that like static type checking in Python is this feasible or something. Any
thoughts? What do you mean by feasible? Like, it's a territory I'm not familiar with, so I don't
know how to elaborate, but I've heard that and what is your response?
I would say, yeah, I think the whole tutorial is premised on it being feasible and doable. Yeah,
it is. Yeah. So if you have any sort of concerns, we can deal with individual concerns. Yeah, I
would definitely say it's feasible. Any other questions, comments? Yeah? Can you repeat that?
Yes. Yes. We will mention that when we're talking about the real world messiness. Yeah,
somebody else out there? His question was, does Pyre work with type stubs? So they are one way to
inform Pyre about what a library exports, so we'll come to that in the later part of the tutorial.
Yeah?
Okay. So in this talk, what we're going to talk about applies to standard type checkers like Pyre,
MyPy, PyWrite, so what we see here shouldn't differ among the three. So we can talk about the
advantages and disadvantages maybe in a later section. So right now, what you see should be
applicable to all three. Yeah. Anything else? Yeah? Yeah, and I was also curious, how many of you
had little experience with types, like have used Python types in your code? Okay, a few of you.
And how many, like this is the first time you're seeing types or you're learning about types in
Python? Okay. Yeah, any of you? Also, I have one request, because you're all wearing masks, it's
a bit hard to sort of connect, so I'll ask you if things are clear, so if things are clear, I'll just
give me a thumbs up, if not, give me a thumbs down so I can sort of focus on what's not clear. All right?
One second.
So let's say you're convinced that you want to use types in your project and you want to know how.
So I'll give you a brief whirlwind tour of the basic features of Python, so functions, classes, lists,
variables, so the idea is that if all you take away from this tutorial is just this, you should be
able to type check the majority of your Python code, and if you want to do further things like
decorators and so on, we'll have that in the rest of the tutorial. So the idea is that for the next
10, 15 minutes, we'll go over some of the theory and we'll try to make it interactive, we can ask
questions. After that, for half an hour, you'll be playing around with Python in your browser, so
get ready for that. All right, so we've already seen one example of a typed function, so if you want
to have a typed parameter like name, you say name colon string, it's okay to have default values, you
can have prefix colon string, colon string equals hello, so Pyre will check that. If anybody passes
in a name, it is of type string, if somebody passes in a prefix, that's also fine, it should be of
type string. If somebody passes in a one, and if you run Pyre, it will warn you because the name
doesn't have a string, so it will catch that right away. Likewise, if somebody passes in something
unexpected, it will catch that too. So far so good, it's pretty basic. Let's look at star args.
So suppose you have a function that accepts any number of arguments and you want to make sure that
all of them are, say, integers or strings, the way you say that is by saying star args colon string,
which means that every single element of that argument list will be a string. So if somebody calls it
with A, B, both of them are strings, so Pyre is happy with that, no complaints. If one of them
happens to be a string or something not a string, then Pyre will complain about that, saying that it
has to be of type string. Yeah, does that seem clear? Yeah. Star star quads are pretty similar.
If you want keyword arguments where all of them have to have value of type, say, string or int,
you can say star star quads colon int. So if I pass in foo equals one, bar equals two, that's fine
because each keyword argument is given an integer, that's fine. Pyre has no complaints. If I try to do
something that is not an integer, Pyre will complain about it. So I'm using integers and strings
here, but in reality that applies to classes as well. We'll see that in a bit. So let's look at our
first class. I'll take a simple example of an employee. We have this constructor here. It takes in an
ID, takes in a name and an email address. Now I want to tell Pyre somehow that I want IDs to be
restricted to ints. I want names to be strings and email addresses could be, say, either string or
none. So how would I do that? For a function, the contract is in its function signature. For a class,
it's in its constructor. So the way I say that is the same way as for functions. I say ID colon int,
name colon string and email address is an optional string. So it could be a string or it could be none.
So once I've specified this contract, Pyre will make sure that this class is being used correctly
both within its methods and outside this class. So let's see a small example of that. Say I have a
method called print email address. So this print employee's email is self.emailaddress. Should that be
valid or not valid? What do you think?
Yep. Can everybody see that? So email address was specified to be an optional string. So Pyre knows
that this could have the value none. It need not be a string. So it will warn you about that because
this could blow up at runtime. So the idea is if you want to prevent runtime errors, so it will catch
these errors upfront. Is that clear? Yeah?
Likewise, if somebody is calling a method, say we have a valid method called print name. It prints
the employee's name. And say outside this class, I just construct an employee object with some ID,
some name and some email address. And then I call print name with OK. Should that be valid?
So this is a very simple method. So let's see a small example of that.
So let's say I have a method called print email address. And then I call print name with OK.
Should that be valid? So does print name accept any extra arguments? It does not accept any
extra arguments. So if you run Pyre, it will warn you that this method is not being called properly.
So just like it checks functions to check if they are called correctly, it does the same for methods
Any questions here? OK, I'll move on.
What about attributes? So here we have a method called print salary. It prints self.salary.
Now nowhere have we declared that this class has an attribute called salary, which means that if you
run this at runtime, it could blow up, right? So Pyre will warn you about that, saying that this class
hasn't any declared attribute called salary. The reason is that if you try this in the
REPL, if you construct an employee object and call employee.printsalary right away, it will
fail, and Pyre doesn't like that. So it will prevent that from happening.
And very quickly, I think if you construct an employee and then try to set name to something that is not a string,
you can expect that Pyre will complain about that. So it makes sure that your class is being used
appropriately, no matter where in your code.
So let me know if anybody has any questions about classes, any lingering doubts.
Yes, yeah. The general practice is that you want to specify the return type so that if somebody calls
your function, the type checker will use that return type to realize what the type of that value will be.
So it's a good practice to always annotate that.
Any other questions? All right.
And we'll have a couple more of these, and then we'll go on to the exercises. So bear with me for a bit.
So let's look at lists. We have a small snippet called find employees by ID. It accepts a list of employees,
it accepts a target ID, and then looks for an employee whose ID matches that target, and then returns it.
So we want some way to specify that. Employees must be a list where all elements are employees.
So the way to specify that is by saying, so we say that it's a list bracket employee.
So this is syntax for every element of that list is guaranteed to be an employee.
So if you try to use it, so here I'm initializing employees to a list where every element is an employee.
I don't need to tell Pyre about this. It can already see that this is a list of employees.
So if you ask for the type, Pyre will already tell you that this is of type list employee.
So you don't need to change your code for that. And if you try to pass it in, that's a valid input,
because this function expects a list of employees, and you're passing in a list of employees.
So Pyre is happy with that. No errors. What about this case?
Yeah, if you have employees where each element is a string, the type of that variable would be list of string.
And if you try to pass that in, Pyre will catch that right away.
So this is how Pyre checks that lists are being called appropriately.
And there are other ways too. So if you have, say, a names variable, which is a list of strings,
so every element is a string, so it's a list of strings.
If you try to get the length of that, what should the type be?
It should be an int. So if you're ever curious about what the type of something is going to be,
you can always write reveal type of that expression and run Pyre.
So it will tell you what it thinks the type is. So here it already knows that the type is an int.
So this is what I meant when I said the standard library already comes with types.
So things like lists, dictionaries already have these for you to take advantage of.
What happens if you transform a list? So you have a list comprehension here.
You have names. So you go with names and then you capitalize and append a string.
So what should the resulting type be?
So it's a list. So what is each element going to be of type? String.
Can everybody see that? So if you ask Pyre, it will tell you that the type is a list of string.
So we don't need to sort of tell it about each list that we create.
Is it okay to index a list with an integer, which is fine. We can always look up an integer, an integer index.
So Pyre is okay with that and it will know that the return type is an int because each element of the list is an int,
so a string rather. So it will tell you that the return type is a string.
What if I look up a string? So if I have a names list and I say names of foo, that's going to blow up at runtime.
So Pyre will warn you saying that this, you can only look up an index, not something like a string.
Likewise, if it names a list of string, so you can't just insert arbitrary things into it.
So you can't insert an integer. If you do that, Pyre will complain about it. Sounds good?
Dictionaries are very similar, so I'll just kind of breeze through it unless you have questions.
So suppose you have a function that accepts a dictionary where all the keys are employees and all the values are ages,
so ints, let's say. So the way you specify the type of a dictionary like that is dict employee int.
Okay, so here, yeah, go ahead.
Go ahead.
Maybe get ahead, but for dictionaries, you have deeply nested JSON, and it's like keys are string,
and values are another dictionary, which that dictionary is string, and values being dictionaries, and so on and so forth.
Is there a good way to get around that without having the type that's 100 characters long?
Yes. So first, you can always have nested dictionaries. So that's the long way around.
And there are ways to have aliases, if you like, and there are things called recursive aliases where you can say that this dictionary
can go arbitrarily deep. So there are more advanced features for that, if you'd like.
So it's like type and alias, you're saying?
Yes.
Okay.
Yeah. So the question was, can you have nested dictionaries and other sort of shorthand for that?
Yeah, there are ways around that. We can discuss that later if you're interested.
So yeah, is it clear that you can just use the employees to int?
So if you ever look at, so we're iterating all the items and getting the keys and values, right?
So the key type is known to be of type employee. So if you ask Paya, it'll tell you that.
The value type is known to be int, so Paya already knows that.
What if you had a dictionary like this? What is the type of this dictionary?
You can guess. There's no wrong.
Yeah, dict from string to int. So all the keys are strings, all the values are int.
So if you ask Paya, it'll tell you it's a dict to string int.
So if you look up a string, that's fine. Paya will allow that.
And it could be an arbitrary string, not just one that is known to be in the dictionary.
So Paya doesn't know what the exact contents are. It just accepts any string as a key.
So if you look that up, you'll get back a value of type int.
Like same as the list thing, you can't.
So if you try to look up an integer, that's going to fail, guaranteed,
because this dictionary is known to have only strings as keys.
So Paya will warn you about that, prevent you from doing any mischief.
Likewise, if you try to assign some non-integer as the value, Paya will again complain about that.
I'm going a bit quickly, but let me know if anybody has any questions or confusion.
One more data structure before we move on to the exercises.
So we have tuples here. Say this function that returns h, which is hard-coded as 42,
and your favorite language is Python.
So the way you specify that as a type is tuple with whatever individual types you have.
So tuple in words, t-u-p-l-e. You can't just use brackets.
You have to say the type is t-u-p-l-e tuple.
And because we have two elements, we have two types here.
The first element is known to be of type int, so we say int.
Second element is known to be of type string, so we say that.
If you had three, then you would say tuple int string bool, and so on.
So if you try to unpack this tuple or try to look up elements,
Paya knows that the first element is going to be an integer.
The second element is going to be a string.
What if you tried this?
This is going to blow up at runtime.
So Paya will warn you about that, saying that this is known to be a tuple of two elements,
and you're trying to unpack into four.
And a quick note about global variables.
So in general, you want to help out the type checker by telling it what the type of the global variable is.
So if you have something like login counts, you want to tell it that it's going to be a dictionary
from user to integer or whatever it is.
In general, you don't need to annotate local variables.
As I told you, you could see that employees was automatically inferred to be of type list of employees and so on.
But in some cases, especially with empty containers,
say you have this function which has visited equals empty list.
Now, it's a list, sure, but what is it going to be a list of?
It could be a list of integers, a list of strings.
So Paya needs to know what the type is so that it can prevent incorrect use of that list.
So in such cases, you can help Paya out by giving the variable an annotation saying visited is a list of nodes and then the empty list.
So this is usually needed when you have empty list or empty dictionaries, empty sets, and so on.
So quick recap. I know we went through a lot.
So functions, how do you annotate them?
Basically, you look at each parameter, you give it a type, and then you specify the return type as well.
Classes, you do the same thing but for the constructor.
So you say ID is an int and so on.
And if you have lists and dictionaries and so on, you just say it's a list of employee or dictionary from string to int,
tuple of int to string, and so on. Right? Makes sense?
Also, I want to give a quick two-minute example of how Paya works,
but if you're not feeling pretty overwhelmed, we can sort of tune out for a couple of minutes,
but I think this might help you to figure out why it does what it does or how it does what it does.
So let's take this example where we had an error called get nickname where it returned an optional string, but we only had string.
So the way Paya starts is by assuming that the user ID is going to be of type integer.
So it starts out knowing that user ID will be an int, then it goes on to the next expression.
So we come to fetch user.
So it needs to check the contract and check whether we are respecting fetch user's contract.
So it looks up the type signature for fetch user.
Let's say it's something like this. It takes an int and returns an optional user.
So at this point, it checks whether the user ID we're passing in is an int, which it is.
So that's fine. No problems there.
And what is going to be the type of user?
So user is being assigned to fetch user of that. So what is the type of user?
Guesses? What's that? It's an optional user.
So it's being assigned the value of this function, so the return type is going to be the type of user.
So Paya remembers that as well. So it sort of stores that in its memory.
Next, it checks whether user is none. So it goes into that branch.
Now Paya is smart. So it knows that even though user was optional string, that is it could be an optional user,
it could be either none or user, within this branch, because we checked for none, user is only possibly none.
It cannot be a user.
So now when you return user, it realizes you're returning none, whereas this function expects you to return a string.
So that's how it figured out that you were making a mistake at that point. Sounds clear?
It doesn't match, so it raises an error at that point.
Next, we return from that branch and we're going to the other branch.
Again, Paya is smart. It knows that you already checked for none.
So what is the only possible type of user in this case? It's only user. It can't be none anymore.
So Paya understands that it's only user and then it needs to look up the nickname attribute.
So again, it fetches the user class. Let's say that class has a constructor like this, where nickname is a string.
So now Paya knows that user.nickname is a string and you're returning that, so that's correct. There's no issue there.
So I hope that gave you a brief idea of how Paya walks through your code, refining its understanding of what the type of each variable is.
How completely does the code need to be developed?
So like a fetch handler?
That's exactly why I wanted to give you this. So you can sort of see where Paya might fail to check things.
So I said it looks up the type signature of fetch user. So what if the user hadn't, the programmer hadn't written any type annotations for fetch user?
At that point, Paya wouldn't know whether it expects an int or a string, so it wouldn't be able to check if you're passing the right argument.
Likewise, what if I didn't annotate user ID? So in that case, Paya wouldn't know if I'm passing in a string or an int or so on.
So that's why you need type annotations and that's what can happen if you don't add type annotations.
Shannon will talk more about that later in the talk.
So yeah, go ahead.
Yeah.
Yep.
We have a URL if you want on some sticky notes. If you want to look at them now.
Okay.
Okay. Finally, we're done with theory. Let's do some exercises.
We have a series of six short exercises where you will play around with Paya in your browser.
We'll start with something simple. The idea is that if you're done, just paste a green sticky to your laptop.
If you're stuck or feeling confused, just add a red sticky and one of us will sort of walk around and help you out.
Okay.
So the playground is basically simple. You just write your code, run, check.
So that runs Paya and tells you where there are errors in your code.
Okay.
So your aim in the first exercise is to, there's a bug in the code. You need to find it not by sort of understanding it.
Just add type annotations, run Paya and see if you can find out where the bug is.
Go to this URL, shorturl.at slash psbg9 and then open.
We have a series of exercises. Open the first one in a new tab.
Open. So can you see a link for simple function?
Can everybody see a link for simple function? Anybody not able to find it?
Okay. Yeah, the first one, simple function.
Open in a new tab.
Yeah, green means good. Red is bad.
Okay. Yeah.
Okay.
Are you able to run?
Yes. Yeah. You have to annotate function signatures before Paya checks it. So we saw why, right?
It doesn't know what the type signature is so it doesn't enter that code.
There are. Yeah. We'll see them later on. Yeah.
Okay. So I recommend it. So if people don't want to use it, right, it will be noisy for them.
So by default it's off. But if you want to be strict, you can turn it on to strict mode.
So the green is hash tag by dash strict.
Okay. So we'll see things you can do for opt in, opt out, and so on.
Okay. I see some green stickers already. Anybody stuck or are you still trying out stuff?
I'm not able to think you just said that we don't need to annotate anything, right, because it just automatically.
No. It doesn't know what user ID is, for example. So it's sort of.
Yeah.
Yes. Oh, you don't need to use typing.list. You say. Oh, wait. Is it a list, though? So it's meant to be a string, right?
Yeah. So you could try different things. But yeah, the intention was that it should be a string.
All right. Yeah. It looks like most people are finished. So I share the solution here.
So if you're still confused, we can sort of walk around. Do you need some assistance? Simran?
Okay. Yeah. I can just show you the solution for the first one. So I hope everybody got that it accepts a string and it returns an integer.
And the error was where you passed in a list instead of a string. Yeah. And if you're super fast and you're finishing the exercises really quickly, feel free to move on. You don't have to wait for me.
But if you want to move along with the tutorial class, you can sort of go one by one. All right. Let's go to the next one.
So if you have a same URL, go to the link where it says multiple functions and open that in a new tab.
Simran? Okay.
Yeah.
Yeah. You need to tell them about this. Yeah.
Yeah. You should do it. Yeah. We want people to use. That's why we started creating a tutorial. Yeah.
Run a type checker. Right. So even if you're not using a type checker, it serves as documentation. But the idea is you want the documentation to be checked so it's most useful when you have a tool. Otherwise, you can write something as a string or an int, but then it's actually a list.
Yeah. So there is something called a runtime type checker. So this is a static type checker. It doesn't run your code. Runtime type checker checks at runtime whether it is an int. So there are tools that do that for you. They are like bare type and they're like a few.
Not yet. Not yet. Yeah. So the philosophy is that Python is always, types are always optional. If you want it, add it. But yeah. Yeah. That's the philosophy. Yeah. Is everyone sort of done? Anybody stuck?
We can move on. Okay. I'll share the solution in case I think most people are done here. So anybody want to share? Like what is the return type of get name? String. And greet name. What does it accept? String and returns? None. Right.
And I hope you all got the error saying that num-vovels is an integer. You can't just add it to a string. Okay. So far it was pretty straightforward. We'll get into slightly more involved exercises from now on. So your first list exercise. So you can go to the third item, which is a list, and open that. Okay.
Yeah. It's kind of a hygiene thing, but it's also useful when you want to, suppose somebody uses a return type and treats it like a string. You want to prevent that. Like somebody who says x equals greet name and then says x dot capitalize. We want to stop that.
So in that case, it helps to have that none.
Yes. So you added as, so what is name expected to be?
Yep. Okay. And what is the return? But it's not returning any value at all, right?
Oh, right.
Right now.
How do you see it is not squared? Because something here is.
Yeah. So can you remove that and make it string again?
No, this one is wrong.
Okay.
So can you see that it says on line 17, return type is expected to be string, but then implicitly returning none. So it wants you there. So the errors help you sort of figure out what you should do.
You have like two minutes.
For this one?
Yeah.
And if you're done quickly, you might want to experiment. Maybe try adding some code that you're curious about and see what Pyre thinks about it.
Like for example, yeah, like at the end we have a couple of questions. You can try to answer that. Try using reveal type to see what the type of each expression is.
It's a statement. It's just a statement that you add. So you say reveal type and then the expression. So when you run Pyre, it will print the type of that expression. And at runtime, it doesn't do anything.
You have to like import that.
So yeah, right now it's we're in the process of adding it to typing, but all type checkers sort of treat it as a magic built in.
So yeah, if you run the code, it'll probably blow up right now because it's not a valid thing, but it's useful for debugging your type checking code. So you don't land the code. It's when you're trying to figure out where your program is going wrong. If you're curious, you can just add reveal type and then foo.
Figure out what it is and then remove that. So in the future we'll be adding it to typing in the official library so that everybody can just import it and leave it in code if they're lazy.
Pyre will flag it.
So yeah, it won't go silently.
Yeah, so the idea is you never want to allow people to have runtime errors as far as possible. The aim is to catch as many of them as you can up front.
Shannon, how are we doing on time?
Okay, yeah, time's up. Did everybody get it or are you still stuck on a few steps?
Jia?
I see quite a few green stickers. All right, let's look at.
Let's look at.
So what did you get for the first function? What does it expect as an argument?
List of string and what does it return?
Yeah.
So let's look at the doc string, right? So it expects a list of strings and then it returns a list of list of strings. Did everybody get that?
So it's a nested list. If you want to convince yourself by looking at each element. So it's a list where each element is again a list and the element of that is a string. So it's a list within brackets, list within brackets, string.
Any questions or anybody has?
What's that?
Lowercase list.
Yeah.
And did everybody get the bug?
Right, so the bug is that we're passing in something that is an integer in the middle of a list.
So yeah, here's the solution if anybody is still doing it.
And I hope you tried out like some of the questions below. If you try to reveal type of a variable, you can see what pyre thinks it is.
So you can sort of experiment with that if you like.
I'm going to move on to the next exercise unless there are any pressing questions. No?
Okay. Yeah, if you're stuck, please add a red sticky so that we know. All right.
First exercise with classes.
Go to the URL for classes. I think it's called simple class.
If you want to make it returns an instance of the same class.
Okay. So yeah, the Dunder init doesn't always return none.
But yeah, in case you want to return something of the same class, I think in later versions, I think from 310 onwards, you can just import.
You can just use the class. In older versions, you have to use either from future import annotations.
You said you could like quote it?
Quote it. So you can say like return is like quote top.
And then that way the type checker views that as the same thing, but you don't run into the runtime error of like referring to something that is.
Is that pyre specific?
No, it's standard. So everything here is standard. Yeah, this is, yeah.
Like a lot of us have come into these dynamic patterns and like figured out workarounds.
Yeah.
Just need to keep that.
Oh yeah.
Perfect.
We expected.
Just make it very of none.
Yeah. So greed expects a string to be returned.
So that's what it says. Expected string.
So what you because you're not return anything by default means you're returning none.
So that's the mismatch.
Okay.
I want one of these.
Yeah.
I don't have a guess.
We should be like whoever wins like whoever finishes first.
I know.
Yeah, we have 30 seconds left.
So.
How's it go?
So I annotated this up here.
I think directly.
Yeah, that's.
I see that.
Yeah.
And then down here.
I have a bug talking about how our.
Sorry, our.
String.
So here.
I'm just trying to figure out.
How to like this looks like a string to me.
So wait.
This is on nine twenty two.
Oh, okay.
Okay.
Thanks.
I think I see a lot of people already done with this.
So yeah, what do you end it for the constructor?
Title.
What do you get for title?
String.
R is int and the constructor returns none.
And what were the errors?
What are the bugs?
Line number.
Okay.
Yeah, you're trying to passing in.
You're trying to pass in R as a string.
I think that was the error.
Was that?
Yeah.
So like input is already defined in the standard library.
So it already comes with types.
Fire knows that input returns a string.
So that's how it figured out that you could get something wrong.
So if you tried this at runtime, it would blow up.
Yeah.
XS five.
This is slightly more complicated.
So it's okay to take a bit of time on this.
It's fine.
Oh, it's a bit really formatted.
Yeah, we had to increase the font at the last minute.
Sorry about that.
So it's under multiple classes.
So we didn't hand these out at the end?
No.
Next section.
Okay.
Any questions?
I know this is a bit involved compared to the previous exercises.
Yeah.
So yeah, what does it return?
String?
Yeah, string.
So if you try it and ask Fire, it will tell you.
So on line 23.
So that's the button.
No, you're right.
Yeah, you just sort of figured out that somebody just uses input and passes it.
It's a string which will fail later on.
Yeah.
Just to show that you can find out what's here.
People are routinely getting confused because of the line number.
Even though we showed highlighting.
Okay.
I'm going to call time.
Is everybody done?
Is everybody sort of still stuck or needs some help?
Okay.
What did you get for?
So did everybody annotate the constructor?
Can you show me the code?
I don't have the code in front of me.
Oh darn, what is this?
Multi classes?
Yeah.
Okay.
Did everybody get location as string?
Yeah, as int.
Did you annotate the talk, self.talks?
Yeah, wait.
It's a list of talk.
Oh.
Oh, can you look into that?
It should have been a list of talk.
Did you get that?
Is that what you got?
So self.talks is annotated as a list of talks.
So yeah.
Okay.
Cool.
No worries.
Yeah.
So yeah, you can follow along here if you missed it.
So self.talks is an empty list.
So we need to help it out by saying this is a list of talks.
So we annotate add talk.
So add talk expects a talk.
Calendar returns a string.
And so you also need to annotate functions because we want Pyre to analyze them, right?
So we say get start r takes a talk and returns an int.
Did we get that?
So did you catch the error?
So we're using talk.start r, but talk doesn't have start r.
It just has r.
So this is the kind of sort of subtle bug you might miss if you're just reading code by yourself.
But then if you have a type check, it just catches all these errors across your code base.
Any questions about this?
Yeah?
Okay.
This is a good question.
So because the parameter was annotated, so locations, location, and the other one was annotated up in the parameters, you don't need to sort of say self.location colon string because Pyre can figure that out.
But for things where you're initializing on the spot and not using a preexisting variable, you usually want to help Pyre out by saying this is a list of talks and things like that.
Okay?
So yeah, it doesn't hurt, though.
You can always add an extra annotation.
It doesn't hurt, but you don't need to do it.
Any other questions?
All right.
We'll move to dictionaries and tuples.
This is again a bit complicated, so it's okay to get stuck.
If it takes some time, it's fine.
Go to the next URL under dictionaries and tuples.
I noticed for this one, like the ID didn't pick up the type error on this one.
Is there like Jeff Reigns integrations for Pyre?
Oh, are you doing it in ID?
Yeah.
Yes.
So VS code comes with support.
So I don't know if you have instructions for this tutorial, but yeah.
There are some issues.
There's issues with it?
Yeah.
So I would just run Pyre.
Pyre comes with VS code.
That's one option.
Or you can just run Pyre in the terminal.
Yeah.
So yeah, we are sort of improving our ID support so that you can see stuff.
You can do stuff like code navigation.
Will there eventually be any Jeff Reigns IDs?
I'm guessing, yeah.
But yeah, so right now it's like the only Pyre ID is the major one.
We have like LSP support, so anything that reads in like language server protocol should be able to use it.
I'm not familiar with LSP.
Oh, okay.
I think a lot of editors communicate file changes and expect responses, so like syntax highlighting and stuff, or like error highlighting.
So it's like a common API for all editors.
Yeah.
So yeah, we're not trying to demo it today.
But yeah, so in the future I think Pyre should be able to support like...
Oh yeah, I think he wants JetBrains in particular.
JetBrains?
I don't know how that communicates with...
I'm not familiar with JetBrains.
Okay, so if JetBrains is what you use, we can sort of figure that out.
But then, yeah, if you really want to use type checking, I think right now Pyre is an option.
I think in a few months we'll have support for Pyre as well, but then yeah, these are your options right now.
I mean, you can just run it manually every time you do anything, but ideally, yeah, with...
Yeah, that is ideally what we want to as well.
Yeah.
We're working on that.
We can probably answer all these in the final email to the attendees.
We can just follow up questions.
We can answer them later in the...
Okay, yeah.
Is everyone done or...
I know this was a bit more involved than the previous one, so it's okay.
Should we go ahead with the solution?
Okay.
What did you get for the constructor?
Int, int, and it turns on, and then what...
Did you annotate seating?
Dict from...
Okay, so dictionary from where the keys are ints and then the values are list of strings.
Perfect, yeah.
And then what was the bug?
You didn't get it?
Okay, yeah.
Did you at least get a Pyre error at the bottom when you annotated the functions?
Yeah?
Okay, so let me show you.
So yeah, as you said, you use a dictionary from integers to lists of integers, so I hope
that part is clear.
I can walk through that if anybody is still not convinced.
Yeah, what about...
So did everybody get the type of the attendees parameter?
So we can see that it's a list, right, because we are looping over it.
Let's assume, let's say we know it's a list, and then we sort of...
Each item is a tuple of three elements.
Can everybody see that?
Right, because we say for row, column, attendee, right, so it's a tuple of three.
So what would be the type?
It's a list of...
Yeah, tuple of three things.
And what are those three things?
So we have row, which we know is an integer, column is an integer, and then attendee is
here, string.
So it's a list of tuple of int, int, string, right?
So I hope everybody got that.
So Pyr would have pointed you to saying that this attendee is wrong over here.
So I'll sort of walk through the error.
So if you run Pyr, it says that...
It's a bit hard to understand.
It says list.setItem cannot be something that is a...
Like, can't be a string.
It has to be something that is indexed.
So what does that mean?
So I'll walk through that.
So we know that cell.seeding is a dictionary from int to list.
So then we know that row, row minus one is an integer.
So if you look up an integer in that dictionary, you get a list of strings.
So this whole thing is a list of strings.
And we know that attendee is a string.
But you can't index a list by a string, right?
We saw that earlier.
You can't do foo of some string because that will be an error at runtime.
So that's what Pyr is complaining about.
So in reality, what do you think this should be?
Anybody has any idea?
Column, column minus one, something like that.
So in reality, we should probably...
We intended this to be column minus one.
So again, this is a dictionary.
You look up row, you get list of string.
And you look up the column, you get the string that you want.
Make sense?
So...
Okay.
Dictionary.
Okay. Which one?
The first one?
Okay.
So it's a...
The outer thing is a dictionary comprehension where you have the key is a row.
So row is an int.
So we know that all the keys are ints.
So it's a dictionary from ints to something.
And then now we have to look at the values.
So we know that it's a list.
And then each element is going to be...
A string, is it?
Each element is a list again.
And then each element of that list is a string.
So we get it's a list of strings.
Does that make sense?
So dictionary from integer to list of strings.
Yeah.
Any other questions?
No?
Okay. Everybody's good.
Do we have time for one quick refactoring exercise?
No?
Okay. We're over time.
All right.
I'll...
We have a couple of take-home exercises in the read-me there.
So feel free to try them out.
And if you have any questions, they're always available.
You can ask us.
Oops. Am I going up or down?
So we've learned how to add types to basic constructs like functions, classes, lists, variables.
So with this, you should be able to type check the majority of your code.
For the rest, we'll see the rest of the tutorial.
I'll pass it on to Shannon.
Thank you.
Oh, I should turn this one off.
Okay.
All right.
Oh, okay. Awesome. This works.
So I need my hands to type.
Different mic here.
And this next section will be pretty short.
We're just going to be sort of setting...
Let me also do this.
Setting up an example project so we can try out type checking outside of just the web UI sandbox.
And then after this, we will adjourn for a break.
So this part's kind of like installation heavy, and there's a little bit of demo on your local machine.
So if you have any trouble at any point, just use the red sticky.
People will come around and help.
And then also in the break, which is 30 minutes long, feel free to stay after.
We can help with anything.
So just a heads up.
All right.
Where's my mouse?
Okay.
I'm having trouble clicking.
Okay. I'll use arrow keys.
Okay. Cool.
So first, let's acquire the example project.
We've set up a GitHub repository for you that you can fork or clone if you prefer.
And if someone can come around and pass out these pieces of paper,
we also have the setup instructions on paper in case you need to refer back to them
or you want to take it home and try it on your own project later.
For now, let's all just use this example GitHub repository.
So again, if you run into trouble, please use the red sticky and flag us down
and put up the green one once you get this working so I know that I can move on.
Also, if you had cloned this ahead of time, just do a quick git pull to update
just in case there are any changes that you missed, and that is up to date.
Okay.
There's nothing on the handout that isn't up here, so that's just for reference
Just for reference, so you don't have to read it all.
I wonder if the upstream is set correctly.
So did you fork it or did you just directly clone it?
Clone it directly?
Hey Stephen, could you help us with a git pull?
I think you have to maybe set your upstream to point to the right,
because the git pull is not getting anything.
Reminder to use the green sticky if you're done.
Sorry, I stepped out.
What's the purpose of SSH access?
Because what we're going to fork it and maintain our own?
So this is just for the tutorial.
So we're just going to mess around with a local project.
So just clone it.
The trouble thing is, I don't know, common issues with cloning.
Let me know if you run into it.
So I would also recommend cloning this project,
just because we're going to be using it for examples.
So rather than if you're working on your own project.
In case you clone it a few days ago, make sure you get the most up to date.
If you just pull again, yeah.
Okay, I'm going to flash the next screen.
No rush.
I think most people won't need the next screen.
But if you haven't installed Python already or need to install Watchman,
which is a file monitoring tool, that's also a good time to install these tools.
I mean, Python is pretty self-explanatory.
But for context, Watchman is a file monitoring service.
It basically updates when your files change locally.
And Pyre is kind of built for really, really big code bases,
like millions of lines of code.
We want to be able to give you type checking results within seconds
based on your local changes.
So that's why Watchman comes in handy.
For a tiny project like this one,
you can flash of a performance difference.
So if you don't have Watchman and don't want it, you'll be fine.
But if you want the full experience of fast type checking,
then also install Watchman.
Yeah.
I'm using PyCharm, WSL, and I'll get a message like,
oh, file watcher has failed repeatedly, ceasing indexing or something.
Do you have any thoughts on that?
File watching has failed?
File watcher has failed.
It depends.
I mean, Watchman is one file watcher.
So I'm not sure what the editor is using in that case.
Yeah.
I don't know.
I think I would probably just go with the docs of what's going on there.
Is this Pyright? PyCharm, right?
PyCharm.
They probably have, I don't know,
I would recommend Googling around their forums.
I think they have really decent...
It's a little bit irritating that if I kill the app and then restart it,
then usually it's kind of okay,
and it only becomes a problem with like...
Like big changes or something like that?
Or moderately large code bases.
Or yeah, big changes as well. Yeah, yeah.
Okay.
It'll just give up.
So Watchman is really stable in our experience,
but I doubt that that's what they're using.
So we'll do big rebases in million line code bases,
and Watchman pretty much keeps up.
But I don't know in that case.
For troubleshooting Watchman, usually we just ping it
and see if it's running.
Maybe you can do that under the hood too from the...
like whatever watching service that editor is using.
But yeah, I guess this is pretty common across any of the type checkers
that are trying to do the fast updates.
Okay, I see green stickies.
If you're not able to get this working,
put up a red one.
Someone will come around to help, but I'm just going to keep moving.
Oh, okay.
Okay, cool.
So hopefully everyone now has a project
and Python and maybe Watchman.
So now let's actually install the type checker.
It's available on PyPI as a package.
So these instructions just show you how to set it up
within a virtual environment, just in case you prefer that.
And yeah, the package works on Linux and Mac really well.
Windows support is still on the road map,
so if you do have a Windows machine, we have a repo it,
and we also have a Windows subsystem for Linux instructions.
And those are all in the email that was sent out earlier
and also on the worksheet,
there's a link to those detailed instructions if you need them.
But again, use the red sticky here for sure if you need help.
Yeah, I think that's it.
Give it a try.
Thanks.
Running into issues?
Oh.
That'll do it.
Oh, I'll tell you.
You just run a slightly different command,
but you can run a different command
that will run on the same command.
So I'll tell you how to run the command.
And I'll show you how to run it.
So let's run the command.
So I'll tell you how to run it.
I'll tell you.
You just run a slightly different command,
but everything will be the same.
Oh, don't follow a lot.
We'll actually do everything on the slides,
so don't worry too much about the take-home next steps.
If you haven't seen it up here, don't worry about it.
Yeah, this is for you to take home
if you want to try this again on your own project
or if you need to refer back to something
that we've already covered and I already moved on.
No, no, I haven't done that yet.
Yeah.
Well, actually, I guess we can hopefully move on.
Anyone, again, if you need help, red sticky.
Okay, we can get to the fun part now.
We've installed everything, hopefully.
Okay, cool.
Let's run the type checker on your machine for the first time.
So you have a project, you have a type checker,
and if you did have problems installing anything,
there is a sandbox version of the upcoming exercise.
It's kind of limited.
I would recommend you do the local setup if you have it,
but that's there in case.
Okay, great.
So now let me also drag...
Oh, are we in full screen mode?
What's going on?
Oh, okay.
The orientation is not what I expected.
Okay, cool.
So that's just there for reference
so you can kind of see what I'm doing.
All right, so let's CD into the project that you just pulled.
And then you can quickly take a look around.
So we have a few directors in here,
but for now let's start with demo project.
So please CD into demo project.
And if we look around in here,
we just have basically two little Python files.
There's a greet.py, a planets.py.
If you're curious, this is just a little program
that asks you how many times to say hello
and then prints hello world that many times.
Pretty simple.
So let's try to run this through a type checker.
The first step to do that...
Oh, let me also make sure that I'm...
Can I make it bigger? Probably.
I don't know if that's actually helpful.
Okay.
Oh.
So everyone should run pyre init.
This is a really easy way to set up a pyre configuration.
And you can just hit enter, accept all the defaults.
Just for context, you can run pyre init.
You can run pyre init.
You can just hit enter, accept all the defaults.
Just for context, you can run pyre
by passing in what you want type checked manually
on the command line.
But a configuration is just an easy way
to avoid typing that every time.
It lets pyre create that server
that does the fast type checking with watchmen
that we talked about before.
And it makes sure that your project
is sort of consistently defined as a set of files
for future type checking.
So I always recommend just running pyre init.
And then...
Let me CD into that project down here, too.
Okay.
So now if everyone has run pyre init
and just hit enter a couple times,
let's just try running pyre.
And you should see a type error.
Just type pyre.
Yep.
And again, red sticky
or raise your hand if you need help.
Yes, we're expecting to see an error.
So if you see a type error,
you've done it right.
Hey, what's up?
Oh, do you already have a configuration set up?
Can you do ls-la?
Oh, dash...
Oh, yeah, that's fine.
Can you open up your local configuration?
Okay.
Local configuration.
Oh.
It's just...
Sorry, the dot pyre configuration local
is cat.
Oh.
Oh, oh.
I would just put a dot in the string there
just to say I want to type...
Maybe that was like a weird input into that prompt.
Just in the quoted string.
Yeah.
Yeah, and now try it again.
Oh, do you have something higher up?
Did you run pyre in the...
Oh, so go back up and just delete that.
Yeah, yeah, that's why.
Anyone else need help?
Oh, hey.
Oh, I'm sorry.
I'm just getting a...
Saying that pyre's giving a non-zero.
No watchman binary.
Okay, so you don't have watchman?
Oh, just run pyre check instead.
I thought that maybe it would just handle that.
Yeah, space check, yeah.
Oh, what happened here?
So I'm on like an engineering computing
build for my company, so I'm on like Suzy 11.
Did you successfully install pyre from PIP?
Like did that work?
Yeah, the PIP, yeah, installed from PIP just fine.
The init stuff was kind of weird
where it was asking me about...
It's going to give me the error saying I'm a...
Oh, that's okay.
Yeah.
Oh.
So...
Let me get...
I should move on, but let me...
Hey, could...
Maybe help here.
There's like a weird...
Pyre's not exiting with a weird error.
Oh, yes, break is almost here.
In case anyone's hungry.
Hi.
Nice to see you.
I forgot to do that earlier.
Oh, yeah, we're on track, yeah.
If you're really struggling
and you don't...
I'm going to move on just so we're on time for food.
You can use the sandbox link
if you want to follow along with the rest of this example,
but don't have it working locally.
And then the break is 30 minutes long,
so we can also help with more gnarly stuff
if you're running into installation problems.
Okay, let's move on.
Again, feel free to use that sandbox link here
if you need to,
but hopefully most of you see a type error.
So now let's do something about that type error.
Let's investigate.
So it says it's in greet.py, right?
So let's all open up greet.py.
Okay, and if we look at this function,
it looks like we ask the user
how many times you want to say hello,
and then you print that many times.
You know, based on the output here,
does anyone spot the problem
or know what we would change to fix it?
So, yeah, let's see.
Or know what we would change to fix it.
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
So you need to make sure we're passing an int
into greet.
So that's definitely a type error.
Pyre is complaining about it,
and if you are curious, if I can find my mouse,
you can also try this out at the runtime, right?
So if you do Python 3, greet.py,
you ask you, okay,
how many times do I want to greet?
Let's say three times, and like bam, this crashes
because you can't pass a string,
which I just passed in, to this function
that's trying to iterate over
a number of times to print.
So let's fix this.
So everyone should just follow along here.
Maybe like the easiest fix
is to cast the input
to an integer.
My...lost my cursor.
Okay, cool. So we should fix that.
And then you can go back here
and run Pyre again.
And now it should tell you no type errors are found.
If you don't have watchmen set up,
you can run Pyre space check.
That will basically
not try to look for file updates.
It will just recheck your whole project.
You might notice that this run was like
a tiny bit faster than the previous one.
It doesn't make a big difference
in a small project like this,
but in a really large project,
even if we had like millions of other files here
and we just ran Pyre like this,
this speed would be consistent.
So if you're running incremental with watchmen,
you aren't like
blocked on rechecking all these other
unrelated files just because you wanted
to update based on what you just changed.
Alright, I'm going to
keep moving.
Again, we'll be around to help
if you need to...
if you need to get help after.
So yeah, we should see no type errors found
after we made those changes
to greet.py to cast to an int.
So now let's say that
we realize
that actually it's kind of silly
to greet the same thing
multiple times, and this is actually not useful.
And we want to refactor
our greet function here to no longer
take repeat count.
So let's all change that.
We can delete this input.
We're just going to just print the greetings straight up.
We don't need this anymore.
And we can also, of course,
don't forget to refactor the call site
to no longer pass in the parameter
we don't support.
So let's write that.
And then
we can run py again.
Just to see.
Like, oh, oh boy.
Okay.
So we actually got...oh, sorry.
We actually got a type error.
Maybe we weren't expecting this because
we were just heads down in greet.py
changing things around.
But it does turn out that our project
has another call site
somewhere downstream. Like, maybe we don't own
this code. Maybe it's just something
that depends on our...
the function that we just
changed. And it does turn out that if we
look at greet.py...
Oh, whoops. Not greet.py.
Vim planets.
So, you know,
here we do see that we have
another function that depends on greet.
And it is passing in a parameter.
And we, you know, just didn't know about this call site.
So when we made the refactor,
Pyre is checking all the call sites
for us to inform us that this is a problem.
So you can feel free to fix this
locally if you want to.
We also have...
Oh, I think my window
is maybe gone.
That's okay.
Just in the interest of time, I will skip that part.
But if you do make a pull request
here and upload that pull request to GitHub,
you can set up Pyre
to run on all pull requests in your project.
So if someone were to say,
make this refactoring change, not fix
the planets.py call site, because maybe
they weren't running type checking locally, and they made
a pull request, you can have
a check that will run Pyre on
every PR and inform you that this isn't safe
to merge until they fix it.
During the break, I can pull it up if anyone's curious.
But, yeah, I think
that's it. So we've, you know, covered the
sort of basic motions of how you interact
with the type checker on the command line.
Pyre can also integrate with
code editors to show errors in line
as you type. But for now,
we will just adjourn for a break.
You can kind of continue to
mess with the example project if you want
to. We'll use it again right after the break.
And, of course, feel free to stay
if you have any questions or you just
want to talk to us not about this
specific installation process. We're also
happy to talk about other things.
And, yeah, I think the break is 30 minutes long, so we will start
at 2.30 sharp back here
with the next section.
Oh, sorry, 3.30. I'm on the wrong time zone.
Yeah, enjoy the break.
Thank you.
Thanks.
Yeah, so this will run a full
basically whichever project you want to define,
you can just check in.
I actually, it's in the...
Well, can you tell me the YAML file
that you figured out the Pyres in the...
Well, so we have a Pyre configuration file
like we created that just says,
oh, this is the directory to type check,
and the YAML file just calls into the Pyre action,
like GitHub action, and that's on the GitHub marketplace,
so you could download that.
But yeah, so you can sort of see,
okay, something went wrong.
And then...
Yeah.
Sure.
Oh yeah, okay.
Yep.
Yeah, I mean, it's not practical to...
Yeah.
No, it isn't, yeah.
Yeah, that's a great question.
It's actually kind of the focus of the next section too,
but yeah, so we basically, I guess for context,
and I'll mention this to everyone,
we went, we basically type checked
all of Instagram's server code base,
which is some of the many millions of lines,
and it went from pretty much lacking types
to I think 99% covered over the last few years,
and so we built a lot of sort of auxiliary integration
tooling on top of a type checker
to maybe make it really visible
whenever anyone's typing anything,
oh, are you missing types?
What's the type coverage of this file?
On CI2, you can sort of show type coverage
and the effect of your current change on type coverage,
so sort of making it really visible
to anyone who's changing or writing new code,
because it's always easier to add types
when you have that context,
rather than someone sweeping the trash after,
you know, trying to keep up, and...
The store manager, right?
Yeah, yeah.
So we would track contributions of individuals too
for better engineering pushes,
or just kind of over the long term,
are you generally contributing to typing efforts,
or is it just like, wherever it's convenient for you,
we have automated tooling
and a lot of other things too to add stuff.
Sorry, I'm talking a lot, but I'll go into all of this.
Yeah.
Oh, okay, yeah.
So like, yeah, we're, I'm trying to find like, okay,
what tooling can I like pick up,
that will kind of give me my best like,
thinking from my box,
because like rather than being like,
hey guys, do we need like a little...
Yes, yeah.
Because right now we're even like,
yeah, we're trying to get CI2 going,
but it's kind of like, you know,
to like make sure it's like,
yeah.
Yeah.
Yeah, that makes sense.
I think practically speaking for like,
I want this today,
I think there are a lot of other type checkers
with like better open source support right now than Pyre.
Pyre has a lot of like really awesome tools,
but a lot of them we haven't ported to open source,
so we want to do it soon.
So like some of the things I'll mention like,
oh, like gutters, where they show the coverage,
and that's just integrated into your editor.
Like we use that internally,
and we want to make it open source soon.
It's just like, you know, we need the hours to do it.
So in that sense, like some of the things I talk about,
like the tooling itself might not be
immediately ready for Pyre,
but I do think that like PyWrite has really good
editor integration, at least for showing types.
I don't know about like actually showing coverage
or things like that.
Yeah, yeah.
I know the type annotations are relatively new.
Relatively, yeah, yeah.
I mean, they used to just be comment strings,
and type checkers are parts of comment strings.
And so now they're in the syntax,
and I think it's growing really fast,
which is kind of exciting.
But yeah, like trying to like tooling for coverage.
I'll show you some like automatic type inference engines too,
to just like kind of do a lot of the trivial work at scale,
and that's available right now.
Yeah, some other stuff too.
Like we'll talk about like type checking modes,
and you know, if you want to like enforce
that all new code has types,
like what you can do that, things like that.
Yeah.
What do you mean?
Oh, like just having like a trick.
Oh yeah, no, it really makes a big difference.
Yeah.
Yeah, like even, I don't know,
if it's not even like an enforcement trick,
it's just like, hey, don't you want this?
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Because like we've made like dashboards internally and stuff,
and I think that it's really helpful
if people would just like be able to know at a glance,
like what the state is.
That's pretty motivating.
Yeah, yeah, of course.
Hey, what's up?
Oh really?
Oh gosh, I always hate watching myself speak after the fact,
but I hope they're okay.
Oh, thanks.
Five years.
Yeah.
Oh cool.
Uh-huh.
Yeah, yeah, just like, like how.
Yeah, I think maybe a lot of it boils down
to like interview advice even.
I actually think a lot of tech companies,
I think Meta Included aren't super like strict about formal,
like oh, you have to have done like XYZ like previous things.
I think so, yeah.
So you'll do the interview process.
I mean, it really depends on like,
I guess like what level you're interviewing to join at,
because that, like I think they'll ask more like
system design questions or like previous experience
working at a software company questions
for like the non-entry level positions
in the interview process,
but I mean, I joined straight out of college,
and so I had no.
I didn't do an internship even.
Like I just interviewed,
so I had no like previous job experience,
so I interviewed for entry level position,
and they really just,
entry level position, yeah, yeah, yeah,
and they just, like they will just ask you
like coding questions so you can kind of just like demonstrate,
like they just want to see your thought process
like while you're coding and things like that,
and so I guess that's the only context I have.
I don't know if it's actually useful advice,
but yeah, oh, okay.
Yeah, so they also have a rotational engineering program
for people who are switching in from like,
you know, non-traditional background,
so maybe you should look at that program.
It's called the rotational,
okay, I don't have like off the top of my head,
I don't know, but I think if you Google like
Meta rotational engineer,
you can probably find something about it online,
and I also know that Meta has a booth at PyCon.
I think we sponsor PyCon,
and so in some of like the, you know,
when there are tables,
you should go ask someone there too
about like how to apply to the rotational program.
Yeah, that's right.
Yeah, so actually someone on our team
from a couple years ago joined the company through that
because she had like switched
from a different profession as well,
so that might actually be a good, yeah.
So Boot Camp is not a track,
it's every new hire goes through Boot Camp,
it's just like a way to introduce to a company.
No, it's not really like a,
it's not a test and it's not like,
it's not like a,
Boot Camp is maybe a harsh word for it,
it's really just like,
oh here's like, get to know like our internal tools,
you can pick a team,
like it's like that kind of stuff,
it's like onboarding, it's like basically onboarding.
So Boot Camp is not actually a Boot Camp,
it's like the, what we call the onboarding process.
So everyone does Boot Camp,
it doesn't matter like what job you have,
if you join the company, you do Boot Camp.
But this is actually a track of,
I think a hiring track where,
as far as I know,
and I'm probably not the person who knows the most about it,
you kind of sit with,
I think you may like work on an engineering team
and you get to try two,
I think like for six months at a time
before you commit to like a full,
joining like a team full time.
So that way you get like a little bit more
diversity of experience on like different teams.
And then, yeah, yeah, so you should,
oh cool, yeah.
You should definitely talk to,
so like I'm just telling you like what I remember,
so I don't, I might not,
I might not know everything,
but you should definitely find the Metabooth
and ask them about it there.
So, I think so, yeah.
I don't, I'm not,
I also don't know the schedule very well,
but like whenever the tables are,
like I know there are a lot of people tabling, yeah.
Yeah.
You can ask them about,
yeah, ask them about the rotational program.
At least if they don't know,
they'll probably get you to another person.
So I'm just passing down the chain,
but like, yeah, at least,
and the website should probably say something too,
I think, but yeah, yeah.
Ooh, I don't know.
Oh yeah, so security and programming languages,
so no, I don't know about that.
Yeah, I have no idea.
I don't wanna say that one thing, so.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, okay.
I hope that, yeah, I hope that's helpful, but.
Yeah.
No, degrees are not necessary.
I don't think, yeah.
No, I don't think they even ask,
like I remember when we were applying out of college,
like they don't even ask for your transcript.
Like I think it's really,
a lot of it's based on the interview.
I would really recommend preparing.
I think it's like, it's not something you wanna go in blind
because I think you can get a lot out of like,
just being familiar with the types of questions,
like reasoning about like data structures,
because they're all.
Yeah, we're good.
It starts again at 2.30.
Yeah, yeah.
I will have to speed a little bit of my second section.
I'll make sure to leave you 65 minutes, but yeah.
What?
Yeah, yeah, actually you might wanna even set up another one,
but yeah, you can, or we can just transfer actually.
It's fine.
No, it's okay, it's okay.
Well, I'll just give it to you.
Sorry, interviews.
Cracking the Coding Interview is a really great book.
Cracking the Coding Interview.
Yeah, I remember when I was studying for it.
I just, I was, I found it really helpful to like,
do a lot of the, like read through it,
do a lot of the exercises,
but then save a lot of them to just simulate,
just simulate interviews where like, you're asked a question,
and then at the time we were doing in-person interviews
where you would whiteboard the solution.
So yeah, yeah.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, so I really,
I remember I would book a room with a big whiteboard,
and I would just do the problems on the whiteboard
to practice.
So that helped me a lot.
I think actually after you do a lot of them,
you start to like, get a feel for like,
oh, like what kind of problem is this?
Kind of like on site, you can kind of like bucket like,
oh, this is like a, this kind of a question.
It typically uses like mappings,
or like it typically uses like a tree search,
or typically, so I found that super helpful
for preparing for interviews,
just like doing a lot of those questions.
And you can find some online too,
like just typical coding interview questions,
like Googling for them.
A lot of those are, yeah.
Yeah, well, I did some on the computer.
So usually the interview process is like,
the first round is online,
so it's on an editor, shared editor,
and then like final rounds, they used to do,
at least when I interviewed,
they did in person on a whiteboard.
These days, I think they're all online still
because of the pandemic,
but I might transfer back, I don't know.
Yeah, so I practiced some on the editor,
and some on a whiteboard,
and I thought it was, I thought that was helpful.
Yeah.
Yeah, it's, I don't know,
interviewing is like a whole,
like a whole thing to worry about.
I feel like sometimes it's not exactly what it's like,
it's not exactly the same skill set, I think,
as like developing a project in a large code base,
but you know, it's just something
you kind of have to hammer at.
Yeah.
Oh.
I don't, I think it probably really depends
on like where you're starting from,
because I'd done a lot of prep before
for like internships and stuff, like at other companies,
so I don't know,
I don't think an estimate would be very helpful,
but there are hundreds of problems in that book,
and I spent like a good couple weeks,
like just a couple weeks just doing problems,
but that was kind of from the point
of having already read the book,
and like kind of familiar, so yeah, I don't know.
Yeah, yeah, I mean that's just, again,
it's just my own perspective, so I don't know, yeah.
Yeah, yeah, no, I think that book really helped,
and just like hammering out a lot of the questions
really helped me prepare for that.
I'm mostly, I think I did most of the book.
It's a lot, it's a lot, but I think it's really helpful,
like once you start feeling like, oh, I see a question,
and like already know where to start,
I think that's really helpful,
because sometimes what hits you is like,
someone asks you a question in the interview,
and you just like don't have a starting point,
and that can be really stressful,
and like kind of throw you off,
but at least if you know like, oh, like this is,
this is what I can start talking about,
or start thinking about, it's like a lot easier
to just like, I don't know, like not get surprised.
What?
A little bit, yeah, at least to like, you know,
what framework should I use
to start thinking about this problem?
I think that kind of helps.
Yeah, but again, that's just how I happen to study for it.
But yeah, and if you have questions too,
like Alex and Simran are both Facebook engineers,
and they've both done, or at least,
I think, you guys both interned, right?
Yeah, I know.
Did you?
Oh, okay, she went through the interview process
more recently, if you have questions.
But yeah, I don't know if my knowledge is outdated.
Yeah.
That is definitely okay.
Is there water outside?
Yeah, just go out and take a right, and then another right.
Okay.
Yeah.
Do you mind if I leave this in the corner?
Okay, thank you.
Yeah, I did some major kind of,
whole full screen thing, I mean,
I don't know what it's about.
Really, okay, people struggle with it?
I'm so surprised that they don't do this.
I'm curious, like what the best solution is.
Oh, okay.
Yeah, yeah.
We, yeah, we honestly were gonna do that.
Oh my gosh.
Press the S button, oh.
So like go full screen, then pop up the presenter notes,
then drag it over, then make it full screen again.
Okay, I'm not gonna try this right now,
but thank you for doing the research.
That's good to know.
Yikes.
I'm shocked that people hasn't figured this out.
Okay, okay, okay.
Yeah, yeah, that's true.
That you can install, yeah.
That makes sense.
That just runs what?
Oh really?
I just need enough information so I can.
Oh.
All right, I mean, your screen looks like
it's got kind of crazy stuff going on on it too.
Seems like.
Oh yeah, I mean, it sounds like that's a good reason
to get a laptop as well, but it's, yeah.
Yeah.
And that's what it is, it's a really cool thing.
Oh, wow.
Yeah, it looks like that's all.
I'm gonna see if there's actually beyond the water.
I don't know if there's water in there.
I'm gonna see if I can do it.
Good, he actually did a bunch of research
into the full screen thing.
The forums are all full of angry people.
I can't get it to work.
Yeah, so he was just like the top voted comment
in everything is converted to a PowerPoint.
So I guess next time, next time we know.
Yeah, that's a.
I know you have it working nicely.
Apparently it's horrible.
A forward looking.
Hopefully I can answer them.
It's kind of nice.
Yeah.
Yeah, and so actually, okay, well,
I'm a senior developer.
My company finds it hard to convince junior developers
to do this.
I could beat them with a stick about it,
but what approach have you taken
to get a code base realistically converted?
And I was like, wow, I'm glad you asked.
That's great.
Yeah.
There's a basic car company,
and they work there and they try to add items.
And people there are also today trying to convince
the one we brought to make it different
from the data pipelines.
Oh, that's cool.
All right.
Can I get the mics?
Thank you.
Oh, sorry what?
Oh yeah, like whether.
Sorry, pretty big.
Okay.
Oh yeah, okay.
Hi everyone.
All right, we're gonna get started again.
It is 2.30 and we got more stuff to cover,
so I wanna make sure we get to it.
What's on the screen right now, if anyone was out,
is just like what the GitHub CI looks like
when you submit a PR with breaking changes.
So that's just for context,
but I will move it off the screen now.
Oh gosh, where'd it go?
Okay.
Okay, great.
Okay, so where were we?
All right, so just as a reminder,
things that we already went over in the first half
included what are types, why we might bother using them,
and then how to type the basic Python data structures,
and also how to run a type checker on your local project.
And so in the second half, things like,
the first one are
that you might take when you're
actually looking at preexisting projects that are huge,
not just like toy examples that we've been looking at already.
And then in the second part,
we will be talking about interesting features
in the type system and how you can express
more dynamic patterns in the type system.
So that's what's on the agenda.
Okay, so as you might guess,
and I think some of you have mentioned this already,
adding types to a real existing project
poses some challenges that you won't run into
or we haven't run into already.
So let's kind of identify them
and talk about how we might approach them.
And a lot of this is based on our experience
annotating the entirety of Instagram's
Python server code base, which is definitely a real project,
millions of lines of constantly changing production code.
So that's kind of the experience that we're speaking from.
So first thing that you might run into
is that you may find yourself adding type annotations
to a huge existing code base.
And thousands or millions of lines of untyped code
mean that when you run type checking over
for the first time, you're just hit with a wall
of type errors.
And you might not have a week or two weeks
to put aside to just dedicate to fixing those errors.
Like you have other things going on,
you can't just halt all other work.
And on top of that, you might feel like adding annotations
one at a time, it's really just a drop in the bucket
and you're never going to get anywhere
with real runtime guarantees,
just going one manual annotation at a time.
So that's one issue.
Secondly, many projects have multiple developers
and they have code bases are constantly changing,
code is being added, et cetera.
And so we care about maintaining a consistent developer experience
for everyone touching this code base.
And we also want to make sure that any hard earned coverage
that we do add doesn't just slowly erode over time
as that file gets changed and updated.
So finally, realistically, most projects have some legacy code
that might contain really highly dynamic patterns.
And you may not have time or the desire to refactor it upfront,
but you might still want non-noisy type checking
on the rest of your project where it can provide value.
So we'll talk about how we can get around this.
So given all of these things, you might be feeling like
it's really daunting to be adding types to a pre-existing code base
and it's not like we all aren't busy enough already.
So what can we do about this?
Thankfully, there are some tools that make this task
more incrementally approachable and doable and practical
even in a massive code base like Instagram's
with constantly changing production code.
So we'll talk about approaches that let us gradually but efficiently
convert a large untyped code base into a typed one.
You know, how to circumvent some of the extra tricky bits of the code base
while still providing some useful stand-in types
or escape hatches to just shut up the type checker when we need to.
And then we'll also talk about how we expose consistent expectations
for type checking and defend your progress.
So starting with the first thing on the list, which is gradual typing,
we're pretty lucky that the Python type system
was defined with a built-in solution
for onboarding large poorly typed code bases.
Namely, as we've run into a little bit already,
type annotations in Python are always optional
and there are a few ways in which this is true.
So first of all, type checkers will not analyze the body of any function
whose signature doesn't contain at least one type.
And this way you can add annotations at your own pace
and resolve errors that are kind of local to the context that you have
and whatever you just added annotations to.
And under the hood, the type system comes with an any type
and all omitted type annotations are implicitly treated as having the any type.
So this type is compatible with every other type in your type system
so you can always take any, you can always pass any,
and there will never be a type error that involves any.
And if types are omitted, the type checker assumes
that the omitted type is an any
and this effectively stops any type errors
from propagating further against that value.
So a function that has no types is assumed to take any,
is assumed to return any,
and the body of that function is omitted from type checking.
And this is true of all type checkers,
this is kind of defined in the Python type system.
And this behavior sort of creates a waterfall effect
where you'll very likely see few errors, if any,
when you just start adding types to your first module.
Any errors you see will probably be against the standard library
or against literals in your code,
but gradually every annotation that you add to your project
will have more to check against.
And so as any's are replaced with meaningful types,
type information can start flowing through your code base.
And we usually recommend therefore starting
with a very centrally connected dependency
or like a commonly used module when you start adding types
to just see the most benefits early on in the process
of onboarding a large untyped code base.
So all of these features together
describe what we call a gradual type system.
This means you can type check your project
even if not everything has types,
and the type system supports features
that let you add annotations incrementally
and deal with the fallout of those type annotations
incrementally.
And here we see a fun zoomed out picture,
it's a dependency graph of Instagram's server code base
from many years ago, and it's only grown a lot since then.
And so you can kind of see like,
you can start with some interconnected modules,
there are many to pick from,
and sort of go outwards at your own pace.
And hopefully this just helps visualize
just how unrealistic it might be to try to add annotations
and deal with all of the downstream fallout in one go,
and without sort of the hard stops
that gradual typing introduces.
And in case you want more detail for yourself to read after,
PEP 484, PEP is short for Python Enhancement Protocol,
but PEP 484 is the PEP that introduced the type system
and sort of defined the gradual type system,
so you can explore that on your own
if you're curious about some of the more of the details.
Okay, so now let's kind of poke at some of these
gradual typing features in our demo project
that we cloned before the break.
I don't recommend using the sandbox,
but if something happened with installation,
that's still an option, so you can use that short URL.
All right, let me pull up my,
all right, okay, so let's quit out
of whatever we had open before.
You can CD back up into your parent directory
and follow along locally,
and then let's now enter into another directory,
which is called gradual typing project.
Okay, so I'll CD into that.
Cool, okay, so there's a lot here,
but at a glance we see like, okay, there's a pet.py,
like maybe we have some pets,
maybe they interact with each other.
We don't have to worry about that for now.
Let's all just first open up main.py.
Okay, so here we see two functions.
Basically, if we focus on run,
I am also behind here.
Okay, so we see two functions.
There is run.py, this calls the other function in a loop.
You know, more or less it does some printing,
it does some math, that's about it.
So let's run pyre in it again to create our configuration,
and you can take all the defaults,
and then just run pyre.
So before we run pyre, what output are we expecting
from pyre?
Any guesses?
Yeah, yeah, no errors.
Okay, we run it, no type errors found.
Okay, you know, and this makes sense
because even if there are type errors
within the bodies of these functions,
there are no annotations anywhere in this file.
And so the type checking is aware that these functions exist,
you know, in case they're imported somewhere else,
but it's not type checking the body
of either of these functions.
So let's change that.
Maybe starting with run,
let's just add a slap on a really simple one.
So this doesn't return anything,
so let's just say it returns none.
Really the difference here is now there's a type annotation,
so we've opted this function in to type checking.
So let's run pyre again.
Interesting, okay, so it's now complaining
that on line 19, I'm not allowed to be adding a string
to a float, okay, that makes sense.
But, you know, if you notice on line 18,
right above line 19, doesn't it look like
we're basically doing the same thing, right?
That line is pretty much identical,
we're adding a string to a float.
Any guesses as to why pyre caught the one on line 19,
but not the one on line 18?
Is it this one?
Shout, louder?
And does it know anything about the in-cat-now ratio
because it's not the other one type-per-in-the-mix?
Yes, exactly.
So in case you didn't hear it,
pyre is looking at get-cat-dog-ratio, this other function,
and it's saying, oh, the return type's missing,
so it must be any, I'm gonna treat it as any.
But on line, so that's line 16.
But on line 17, we see that we're using
the built-in division, and that is typed,
it's returning a float.
So really, the gradual typing is kind of putting
a hard stop on the return annotation
of get-cat-dog-ratio, it's just treating it as any.
So anything that calls this function
is going to assume that it's gonna get back any.
So that's basically suppressing the type error on line 18.
So let's also change that.
Why don't we annotate this correctly?
So this returns a float, right?
Okay, and now let's run pyre again,
and I will also catch up our slides.
Okay, I think we're on the right track,
so let's run pyre again.
Okay, we see both type errors now.
Does that make sense to everyone, like, what happened there?
Okay, so let's also say for the sake of example
that while I was annotating get-cat-dog-ratio
and saying it returns a float, I realized that,
actually, doesn't it show this always return a float?
You know, what if we don't have any dogs, right?
This is gonna crash, so maybe we should say,
if dogs is greater than zero, then we return,
then we return this float.
If you run pyre after this, you will notice that
this function body has already been opted
into type checking, we will catch this.
It's pretty similar to some of the examples
we maybe have seen before.
All right, great.
And again, use your red sticky if you aren't getting
to three type errors at the end of this exercise.
If you do see three type errors,
go ahead and fix them just for fun.
Don't spend too much time on it,
but it shouldn't be too bad.
I will go ahead and do the same thing here,
so maybe first of all, we want an optional, right,
because it sometimes returns none.
We fix that.
Okay, we have some more errors.
You know, here we maybe, since this is sometimes none,
we kinda have to handle that, so maybe we want this
to be none, if not else this.
And we probably wanna cast these to string.
Oh gosh, this is so confusing.
All right, and if you did a couple casts,
you know, did a little non-handling,
you should get back to no errors.
Again, red sticky if you're stuck,
and someone will come help.
So hopefully this kind of provided a very scaled down,
let me get back to the slides,
you know, very scaled down inside and outside
of insight into how the gradual type system works.
It basically allows you to incrementally address
type errors against things that you're currently annotating
without having to tackle the whole project at once.
All right.
Okay, so in the interest of time,
I will just leave this as a take-home exercise,
like the continuation of this example.
Yeah, I want to make sure we get to some other things,
but in a gist, like what we're covering here
is essentially like, oh, if I practically were trying
to annotate this project, maybe I would recommend
starting with pet.py.
That defines a bunch of pets,
and the other files kind of use those pets.
So if I add annotations to pet.py,
and then I start adding annotations in the rest of my module,
gradual typing will mean that I have something
to check against, and I'll start seeing
meaningful type errors kind of out of the gate.
So I won't actually demonstrate this live,
but if you have questions about it,
or you want to try it even at home,
and you want to message us about it after,
that's also totally an option.
Another thing I kind of mentioned here
is if you wanted to basically hand wave a type
that you didn't know, like say,
I guess I'll just show it, but you don't have to follow along,
but if you wanted to say, let's look at park.py,
we have a function in here that takes in a JSON input
and turns it into, basically looks at all these fields
and turns it into an object.
So I think there was a question earlier
about how do we handle gross dictionaries
with nested inputs?
So the very, maybe not recommended,
but a possible instantaneous workaround
is to just say, oh, input is a list of a dictionary
from string to any, and any can really be anything here,
and I'm just gonna say whatever I take out
of this dictionary is fine, just don't worry about it,
but there are some other things we'll explore later,
like data classes, type dictionaries,
or I think Pradeep earlier mentioned,
recursive type aliases that could let you actually specify
every single nested type in this dictionary.
Yeah.
Is there some tool where you can point it
to a JSON bot, say hey, come up with the specific
type of list?
We have a tool that essentially looks at what object
you're passing in at runtime,
and then compiles a type out of that.
So basically, yes.
Yeah, I'll demo it on a future slide.
It's called monkey type, and we use that a lot,
actually, for a lot of these situations.
Yeah, so that's a bit hand wavy,
but let's just keep going.
There's some more concepts to cover.
So we've talked a little bit about how
you can just incrementally add types to a large code base,
but we haven't really addressed
how we scale out this effort,
so we get to a point where we're actually
getting meaningful guarantees.
If you sprinkle a few types here and there,
you're not gonna get the confidence that
any change I make is really gonna catch everything.
So some approaches we've taken at Meta and at Instagram
to really drive type coverage include having tools
that expose coverage visually.
So this might be making it clear to authors,
like program authors, what is and isn't covered,
where type errors might be missing,
especially in code that they're already touching
or have context on, and then we can also use
coverage tooling to expose progress over time,
individual contributions, and kind of track,
like make it at a glance clear,
like what the current state of the world is
in terms of coverage and what effect you're making on it.
Another thing we rely on heavily
is automatic type inference.
So like the tool I just mentioned,
which uses runtime types to guess
and apply type annotations,
we have, yeah, the runtime one,
we have a static one as well that just,
based on the control flow, tries to guess types
and just bulk adds annotations for you.
And then finally, we have different type checking modes
so when you're ready to kind of move away
from the leniency that gradual typing provides,
different, like stricter type checking modes
can basically provide stronger guarantees
in exchange for that leniency.
So now let's kind of talk about each of these
in some more detail.
So first one, coverage visibility.
This is kind of a simple idea,
but it's actually really useful in practice.
We've driven, I think, the Instagram code base
from basically untyped to 99% typed,
that's millions of lines of code
over the past couple years,
and this is one big way we did it.
We kickstarted some better engineering pushes
that really relied on coverage tooling to track progress
and identify hot modules where type coverage was low
and we maybe want to prioritize first.
So let's kind of look at the raw data
that the type checker can provide about coverage.
So in your project,
so we're still in gradual typing project,
you can run pyre statistics.
I'm covering up the command.
Let me move this to the other side.
Pyre statistics.
And dash dash print summary is just a human readable version
so we can start with that.
And so it tells us, okay, overall annotation rate,
globally accessible values that could be annotated,
13% and some other stats.
If you're curious about the machine output,
you can run pyre statistics
and just it dumps a huge JSON,
but we have a lot of dashboards
and other tooling that consumes this JSON
and we can expose it in dashboards
for high level metrics.
We can show gutters in the editor
to demonstrate where coverage is and isn't missing.
We can also show this at pull request or diff time
so that authors know what the impact
of their current immediate change has on type coverage.
So those are some downstream consumers of this data.
Yeah, so.
How long should that take to finish?
I believe it may take a minute.
Oh, are you running it in gradual typing project?
No.
Oh, okay.
You should CD into.
Print summary.
That's for the human readable version.
Also, red stickies if you want personal help.
But yeah, other questions about this before we move on.
Okay, cool.
So that's the first one.
Yes, we'll get into that a little.
That's a good question.
So unsafe is what we call gradually typed modules.
So any module that's gradually typed
into the account is quote unquote unsafe.
We'll talk actually,
I mentioned earlier type checking modes, right?
So strict is another type checking mode.
So that's what it's telling you about there.
And yeah, again, we'll cover that
right after inference tooling.
So not all type coverage has to be added manually.
Although human input is usually a really good
starting point that a lot of tools,
like automatic tools kind of feed off of
and scale out once you have a little bit started.
And you still need the human expertise
for a lot of tricky cases.
But we've leaned really heavily on automatic type inference
to just bulk take care of all of the simple cases
that the machine can guess.
And so we both have PyreInfer,
which is a best effort static analysis tool
that right now it's kind of undergoing some changes,
but it will guess all of your simple cases.
And then we have MonkeyType,
which is the dynamic runtime one
that will sort of read in what the objects are at runtime
and then create types out of that to add to your project.
So let's give both of these a try.
I will move this back over here.
So for the first one, let's just run PyreInfer
dash dash in place.
And the in place flag just tells the tool,
I want you to directly change my files.
Otherwise it'll output them in a separate directory
so it doesn't touch your stuff.
Okay, so we did that.
Let's run PyreStatistics again.
Dash dash print summary.
Am I missing a Y?
Okay.
Okay, so we were at 13% before.
And PyreInfer just slapped a lot of nones on honestly
a lot of returns and like a lot of really simple stuff,
but we're at like 48.
And in practice too, that is a big proportion of types
in any real world project.
A lot of them are pretty simple.
A lot of them are non.
Maybe you wanna do this like a module at a time
and it's a little easier than going through it manually.
Let's also try monkey type.
So you can feel free to just watch
if you don't wanna do this,
but if you wanna follow along, you're welcome to.
So pip install monkey type would be the first step.
And then you can, let me actually before I do this,
there is a type error that we did not end up fixing
because we skipped some things.
So I will quickly comment out the problem.
Okay, so now let's do a monkey type.
Run main.py.
Okay, so this ran the program, printed those stats
that we were dealing with earlier with like floats and things.
And we can just show monkey type list modules,
tells us what modules monkey type knows about
and could add types to if we wanted to.
So let's try monkey type apply to each of those.
So it's gonna add a bunch of stuff.
Monkey type apply to another one and the final one.
Okay, and now let's do the statistics again.
Like, oh wow, we didn't even do anything.
We're at 83% covered.
And if you want to, you can kind of get this.
Look around at some of the annotations that have been added.
Again, feel free to play with this at home.
So you can see like, it's guessed a lot of these types.
I don't know if this is helpful, but yeah, see we,
oh, I added the any manually, so that's there.
But yeah, a lot of these are inferable
either at runtime or statically.
So we can get a lot of coverage for free kind of
with a lot of these tooling.
Any questions about this?
Nope, okay.
Cool, and the last thing that we mentioned earlier is,
gradual typing and how this quietly accepts
untyped values as any and doesn't check function bodies.
So like, what if we spent a bunch of time
manually adding annotations,
automatically adding annotations,
and now we're ready to trade this leniency
for stronger type guarantees?
So strict mode can be turned on per module
or all at once for your whole project
if you're ready for that.
And it will throw a type error on any non-local value
that's missing an annotation and would have injected
an any into your environment.
So as you convert more and more modules to strict mode,
the number of any's floating around in your code base
will decrease and you'll hide fewer and fewer errors
as a result.
Strict mode is also another really useful way
to kind of prevent anyone else from adding
new untyped code to a module.
And you can kind of use it to avoid
coverage decay over time.
If you've fully annotated a module,
you just want it to stay that way,
indefinitely into the future.
You can try this if you want by opening up,
say like pet.py.
Pyre strict is the way you opt in just a single module
and an otherwise unsafe or gradual project.
And if you run Pyre now, you'll kind of see like,
missing return annotations all over the place.
And these need to be fixed
because they're introducing any's.
So now that we've talked about gradual typing,
which provides smoother onboarding
and then strict typing which provides stronger guarantees,
I wanna be just a little more specific
about exactly what guarantees you can actually expect
when we're converting things to strict
and at different stages in the process.
So when you just have a module that's strict,
you do guarantee that all code in that module
is visible to the type checker and being analyzed.
And that module itself is not introducing any more any types
into your project's environment.
However, if you have dependencies that are poorly typed
or not strict, those dependencies
could be giving you any types,
like injecting them into your local logic
and that could still result in missed type errors
even in a strict module.
So it kind of follows that
strictifying your entire project
provides stronger guarantees.
I mean, part of it's linear.
Now, all the code in your entire project
is analyzed by the type checker.
But part of it is also that you now know
that all of your dependencies aren't feeding you any's.
So you can't be getting basically suppressed errors
because you're calling a dependency that,
oh my gosh, I'm sorry.
Yeah, you're calling into some dependency
that was not well typed
and therefore you're getting an any from there
that's suppressing errors within your module.
That said, poorly typed third party libraries
or dependencies or things you don't control
could still inject any's into your project.
So that's kind of third party boundaries
are kind of where problems could still lie.
So what now?
All right, so enter type stubs.
So we know that even in a fully typed strict project,
any's can still flow in from dependencies
that you don't own.
And maybe you own them,
but you can't type them like Cython code.
So stub files are one way to address this.
Basically stub files are a public interface
of type signatures that override the implementation logic
of that module.
So you can kind of create a stub file.
It can live right next to the file in question
that it's annotating.
Or you could have a whole directory of stubs
that you just import in and add it to your configuration
and Pyre will know about it.
So TypeShed is a sort of open sourced collection
of built in stubs, commonly used libraries.
All of these already come with stubs
and they come pre bundled in with the type checker.
Basically any type checker you use.
So you may have noticed that all of the standard library
functions we were calling were already well typed.
And that's because those types are defined in TypeShed.
It is a GitHub project you can play around with.
But those are all bundled in with the type checker
and we already know about that.
And then just as an FYI, in case anyone is surprised,
type annotations have been around for enough time
that actually most commonly used libraries
like the top 100 I think was what we looked at.
The majority of these do come with types.
We even have a PEP that specifies a way to bundle
and distribute type information as a package.
So chances are if you're using a library heavily
and you want those types, you can find them.
They exist for most commonly used libraries.
Hopefully we have a somewhat decent understanding
of how to approach typing a large code base.
Any questions before I keep going?
Okay, we'll power through.
I think we're almost done.
So the final question that we might wanna answer
is what if I have very dynamic code?
Maybe I'm generating a bunch of classes on the fly
and they have variable names
and there's no way I can statically know what they are.
Or other legacy code that I just don't wanna refactor.
But I still want the benefits of type checking
on the rest of my project.
So we'll kind of get into how to express
more dynamic patterns that you might think fall
under this category but actually are expressible
in the type system in the next section.
But let's assume that you really can't deal
with it right now.
So we have some escape patches to accommodate these cases.
We've already seen the any type.
It's often implicitly used when annotations are missing.
But you can also use it manually
to just tell the type checker,
I know you have a type guess for this,
but I want you to treat it as any.
And not err against it for the rest of the control flow
no matter where it's passed.
We also have type casting.
So if you maybe know that the type of this value
is something more specific or different
from what the type checker thinks,
maybe because of some side effect
or some other weird condition,
you can just tell the type checker,
trust me it's an int, don't ask any questions,
and it'll be an int from now on.
You have to be careful because if you're wrong,
then the type checker is just gonna lie at you later on.
But that is an option.
And then finally, if maybe you don't want to cast
this whole thing as any and have it ignore errors
against this value forever,
you just want this one assignment to stop complaining.
You can use an inline suppression
to just shut up the type checker in the moment.
And finally, you can kind of use stubs
as type casting at scale, right,
because we're overriding the whole interface of a module,
essentially casting.
And we also have error suppressions at scale,
which we'll talk about next.
In some really tricky cases,
we also support stuff that basically tell you anything,
any name, whatever gibberish you want,
you can import from this module
and the type checker won't complain about it
and just treat it as any.
So that's what a placeholder stub is.
It's not super often needed,
but if you have questions about it, feel free to ask.
All right, so let's quickly review.
We've seen all of these already.
There's strict mode.
This is usually the goal.
So where we stop introducing implicit any's
and we get some stronger guarantees
the more modules you have.
If you have high value code or sensitive code
or maybe hot modules that a lot of things depend on,
usually you probably want to get it to strict
as quickly as you can.
We've seen gradual typing.
So this is the default mode for type checking.
And all annotations are optional
and it kind of smooths out the process for onboarding.
And then finally, I mentioned earlier,
if you want suppression at scale,
you can just tell the type checker,
just don't error on anything in this file.
I don't care.
And so that is also a type checking mode.
So we often use these along with continuous integration
to sort of lock in all the forward progress that we make
and prevent any backsliding
as we gradually migrate sort of a large existing
poorly typed code base one step at a time
at whatever pace makes sense for us.
All right, so this is the initial set of challenges
and some of the approaches that we've talked about
to sort of address each of them.
I won't read them to you,
but what this combination of approaches,
at least we have had a really good experience
driving Instagram's millions of lines of code
to over 99% type annotated over the last couple of years.
And that's like without slowing down
all the other things that are going on,
other timelines or roadmaps
and without doing a huge overhaul upfront.
And we've also through this process kind of found
that a well typed code base has been pretty invaluable
for like increasing development speed,
reducing the number of crashes that like take down the site
or actually result in what we call a SEV,
like a production problem,
building smarter code mod tooling and linting
and also detecting privacy and security issues at scale
without having to do security reviews of,
well, we also do that,
but in addition to doing security reviews
line by line manually.
So those are just some of the applications we found
as we went through this journey
of converting a huge untyped code base to use types.
And yeah, that's it.
Any questions?
You mentioned this like to private CTN
or security and capacity
would you allow for a little bit of a verification?
Yeah, so actually Pradeep is giving a talk on Saturday
about one of the applications that a PEP just came out
that we're using the type systems or leveraging it
to enforce secure by default APIs
to prevent like shell injection
and other kinds of problems.
So I highly recommend going to that if you're interested.
But there are also other applications
just based on the semantic understanding
that the type checker has of the code.
We've built a analysis tool on top of our type checker
shares the same backend
that basically tracks data flow through code
and looks for bad data usage
or like user controlled data flowing somewhere it shouldn't
things like that.
We've also used, yeah, we can,
I could talk about it more.
Yeah.
Extending these types of like,
like this is the data of this level or whatever
and then if it's in range regions of the code
that's widely accessible in some places
you can have some tool that will flag those regions
where it's doing some of that.
Yeah, so either you can represent that kind of sensitive data
directly as a type or you can use the type knowledge
to basically build a really accurate call graph
of like your whole code base.
And that enables a lot of other static analysis
that's very similar, I guess, in concept to type checking
that like models that data and checks it.
And so we actually employ that
to catch a lot of security abilities before they land.
All right, I think I am at time.
Gia is going to talk about,
basically spend the rest of the tutorial
getting into like interesting Python patterns
and how to express them in the type system.
Yeah, I'll pass it off.
I'm gonna come get the mic.
Thank you.
Bing test.
Does this work?
Hello, test.
Hello, hi.
Yes.
Bing test ABC.
Right, okay, cool.
All right, so I'm Gia.
I'm gonna tell you about typing common program patterns.
I hope that at this point,
you are all familiar with the basics of typing.
This section will mostly focus on the trickier cases
and it will take you through
some of the more advanced utilities
you are gonna find in the typing module.
Content in this section are mostly focused
on the type system itself.
It's not tooling specific.
Like you can most of what I can tell you
is gonna be generalizable for most type checkers.
This is also designed to be a mixed session
of me presenting and you doing exercise.
I'm gonna be talking for a while
and then we're gonna do some simple exercise for practice
and then I'll come back and keep talking
and then we'll do exercise, rinse and repeat.
It's kind of difficult to estimate
how long the exercise is gonna take.
So I provided extra amount of content in the slide
just in case we're blasting through all the exercises.
But on the other hand, it may also happen
that we spend some extra time
with some of the exercises
and won't have enough time to go over
all the prepared contents.
That is totally expected.
If that happens, no big deal.
Slide for the remaining contents are there online.
So you can check them out at your leisure later as well.
So whenever you see this icon,
that means that I'm done talking and it's exercise time.
All the exercises in this section is located
as the typing pattern exercises subdirectory
in the GitHub repository
which is cloned in the previous section.
Please CD into this directory right now
in case you forget it later.
They are grouped by topics.
Each file is pretty self-contained.
Exercises can either be done locally
where you just CD into the most specific directory
and run pyrecheck to verify our answer there
or you can follow this short URL
where I provide pyre playgrounding
so that you can do them online
in case your setup or your installation has some problem
and you still want to follow along
with all the examples that I have here.
During the talk, I plan to go through only a subset
of all the provided exercises.
Those are not covered
will be considered take-home exercises
where you can just do them offline
if you're really into them.
Okay, so this section,
I'm gonna organize it into three topics.
First topic is about how to work with functions
that deal with more than one type of values.
The next is about issues you might run into
when working with classes.
And finally, we'll consider how one could type functions
that operate on other functions.
The first two topics,
I think I have enough time to cover live today.
The third topic is likely going to be the bonus part
of this talk where we may or may not skip it
or stop in the middle
depending on how much time is left at that point.
Okay, so first, how to work with functions
that handles multiple values,
handle values of multiple types.
I'll talk about three techniques
that can be used to annotate these kind of functions,
unions, generic functions, and overloads.
Let's start with the simplest technique, the union type.
In previous section,
we have gone through a lot of examples
and exercises on functions
that are relatively simple like this.
Parameter types can be uniquely determined,
return type can be uniquely determined.
There's no doubt and no ambiguities
on what this function operates on
what the function produces as a result.
But not all functions are written like that
especially in Python, which is a very flexible language.
You would run into functions
that work on more than one data types.
For example, we have a function here
that tries to send a piece of data to the network.
Its behavior depends on the argument data we pass to it.
If the data contains wrong bytes,
we forward the data directly to a lower level API.
But if the data contains string,
what we do is we encode the string first
and then send it through.
Send any other types of data
will be considered a runtime error.
Now the question here is what type annotations
should we give to this argument data here?
We can't just say it's a bytes,
we can't just say it's string.
We need a way of saying that it's either a byte or a string
and to represent that kind of or relation,
we need to use a union.
Here's how you use a union.
Before Python 3.10, this is what you do.
Import the name union from the typing module
and then you use union square bracket
to enclose all possible types
and use that as the annotation as we've shown here.
If you're on the most recent Python release,
then there's a syntactical shortcut you can take.
You no longer have to import anything.
Just use this vertical bar here
to separate the possibilities.
So I can just say my data is a string or a byte.
That means the same thing as union, string or byte.
It's just more compact and it's shorter.
Regardless of what syntax you use to annotate the functions
and the result is gonna be the same.
The type checker will happily let you invoke the function
with strings or bytes but will point out anything else.
They are not accepted.
This should be pretty straightforward.
We've seen an example where union types appear
on the parameters.
Turns out they could appear
on some return position as well.
Let's just do an exercise here
to see if we can figure out how this works yourself.
You can find this example in the subdirectory
topic one slash union slash example zero dot py
to check locally CD into topic one slash union.
Everything is up there for you
so don't worry about running pyenit or anything like that.
Just go to that directory, run pyre check
and you're gonna see the type checker outputs.
Or you can go to this short URL
to find the pyre playground links
with the relevant examples on the page.
It is recommended to right click on the pyre playground links
and to right click on the playground links
and open them in the new tab
and keep a reference to this short page
because we are gonna revisit that page later
throughout this section.
So let's dive into the exercise
and see if we can figure out how to do this.
Oh, if you're down, use the green sticky.
If you're running into problems,
use red sticky, same protocol as we had before.
Okay.
I was just curious, I didn't even know
you could do this in Python,
line five, these three dots here.
Oh.
Is that equivalent to what, like pass?
Yeah, it's like pass, don't care.
Has that always been a thing?
Yes, the runtime is gonna crash
if you remove that function.
Oh, they won't run that?
It won't run but it's just a way of like,
for us hacking, quickly hacking examples
for the type checker too.
Yeah.
Okay, are we, I see a lot of green stickies.
Is there any problems?
Should we move on or?
Okay.
Okay, for the sake of time,
I think we need to move on.
This should be a fairly straightforward example.
This is, the return type can either be a string or a bytes.
The parameter type can either be a string
or it can be none.
It's also fine if it's.
You can do optional string earlier in the talk.
It means the same thing as string or none.
Like these two function signatures
are just equivalent to each other.
Any questions on this exercise?
A ridiculous question but if you're doing
union string or that,
is just the order there matter?
Like, you know, from like a,
just from a user's development,
it's a ridiculous question.
Should I say norm, not for a string,
or a string or not?
Is it whichever is most much more important
than the left one?
I think it's a most matter.
The question is like, does the order matters
for the annotation?
The answer is it doesn't.
You can just use whatever orders that you prefer.
I think or none is like kind of a common pattern you see.
So I, but really it depends on like
your personal preference,
what the rest of the team does.
It's mostly a cosmetic concern.
It doesn't really affect how the type checker
consumes this annotation.
So unions are great.
It allows you function to handle values
of many different types in a very simple way.
But I also want to point out a caveat,
which is not so obvious as first glance.
You might have already noticed this in your exercise.
The caveat is that unions,
this is consumer to do split.
Remember this sample that we had earlier?
Here's on the parameter type.
And inside the function body
where we want to consume that parameter,
what do we do here?
We use instance check to branch out the logic
in the case by case basis.
This is required for safety reasons.
The encode method actually don't exist
if your data is a byte.
It only exists if your data is a string.
So it is not safe to invoke the encode method always.
So we need to do the case split
to make this thing, make the entire thing work.
The same issue of union appear on some return type.
If your function returns a union,
then every single caller of your function
that consumes your return value
must also first check exactly
which branch of a union the value belongs to.
It is safe to pass data to a downstream function
that exposes a string only if we're sure
that this data is actually a string.
Same for bytes.
But without doing this case split,
we can't say for sure which is which.
And as the function only hands us a union back.
So this often makes your function kind of awkward to use
because of the additional border plate
that you have to write for whenever you want to consume it.
But remember our intention when writing this function.
If the encode, then we don't do any decoding
return of bytes directly.
But if the encoding is not known,
we decode the byte into a string.
So in this particular case,
the parameter type and the return type are correlated.
We can sort of predict what the return type would be
by just looking at the parameter.
This kind of correlation is unfortunately
not expressible with union types.
We'll talk about what to do in next.
But before we go into the next section,
any particular question about union types.
Cool.
Onto the next topic.
In this section, we'll talk about a technique
that allow us to establish some simple correlation
between parameters and return.
Let's take a look at this example.
We have a function here called process data.
To make things simple,
let's assume that all the processing we do here
is just to log the data somewhere
and return the data intact.
So what we expect here is that
when you pass this function a string,
we get a string back.
If you pass it a bytes, we get a bytes back.
Pass it an int, we get an int back.
Basically, whatever we pass into it,
we get exactly the same thing back.
How do we type annotate this function?
Well, obviously union is not an answer here.
Say if we annotate this function with union,
not only does it suffer the same issue we mentioned before,
that is it can't really detect the correlation
and will always give us a union back,
which needs to be case split further downstream.
The other issue is that this type annotation
only works with these three types.
It's not super extensible.
If I say define a custom class myself and pass to it,
the type checker is gonna complain here.
This is definitely not our intention.
This function should be whatever we pass into it.
Another thing you might be thinking is
how about using the any type like this?
Well, the type checker definitely won't complain
no matter what you pass the function if any is involved.
The issue with this approach is that it completely destroys
the type info we have on the return type
because all of them are gonna be considered
to have the any type.
For example, if you try to invoke method
on the return value and you made a typo,
the type checker won't be able to help you catch this issue
because, well, you have any there.
We don't know exactly what methods are defined on there.
Now, let's take a step back and look at this function again.
Observe the properties of this function.
First, the return types and parameter types are correlated.
In fact, they are exactly the same in this particular case.
Second, the function body looks the same
regardless of what the parameter type.
When your function satisfy both properties,
that would give you a strong hint
that generics needs to be involved.
Here's how you do generics.
First, import this name called type var
from the typing module.
And then define a type var on the top level
of your source file.
There's one string parameter to this type var constructor.
That string is for runtime tooling only.
It's not relevant to the type checker,
but the convention there is that you should use
the same name in the string as the variable itself.
In this case, you should just use duty
if your variable is called t.
Now annotate your function we just defined.
Here, I'm using t as both the parameter and the annotation.
This means that this function takes any type as an input
and it will give us the same type back.
If you annotate it like this, they are guaranteed,
then like any of all of these things works.
If you give it a string, we get a string,
give it a byte, we get a byte.
If you have a custom class, no problem,
we're gonna get that exact thing back again.
So that is how generics and type words can be used.
Let's see if we can put this into practice.
Let's do some exercises this time.
Let's do both of these examples and use the green sticky
after you finish both of them.
If you're doing the exercise locally,
make sure you change your current working directory
to type-var.
If you're doing exercises online,
make sure to open the prior sandbox links in the new tab.
And yeah, let's work on this.
So, it's not like that.
It's not like that.
Yeah, so every reference has been the same signature.
It is down to your name.
And then you might have other.
Which is, however, you can see all the things
that are not probably gonna happen.
And then it's like this.
And then a lot of times, like you're doing it.
When you're doing it, you're gonna get it.
So, it's important to get all the attention
that you've got.
We don't get it in every day.
I've heard people say that.
But is this a resumption for that task?
So, it's a question.
Yeah, it is.
It's kind of like the age distinction.
Yeah, it's hard to get the attention.
Okay.
So, it's a question.
.
Are you guys doing okay?
Do you need any help?
Nope?
Any issue?
Oh, I'm really screwed at this one.
Oh, okay.
Yeah, the issue is that you're using the same var here, right?
This means that the type of X and Ys are the same.
Oh, so you have to have a separate...
Yes.
And the return here is also not a var.
It's a two-fold, right?
Okay.
.