Our next talk is Python for Threat Intelligence.
Everyone please welcome Aaron Stevens.
Hi, everyone.
Thanks for coming.
My name is Aaron and this is Python for Threat Intelligence.
A little bit of background.
I work at a company called Mandiant and we provide cybersecurity services for other businesses.
You may have heard of us before.
We investigate some of the most high profile hacks around the world, whether that's criminals
get rich or nation states conducting espionage or other intelligence operations.
As you may have guessed, my team focuses on threat intelligence.
If you're already lost, don't worry.
I'm going to go over what that means and how we do it in the next few slides.
I had to summarize what my specific role is.
It's to provide capability and automation for my team.
So basically enabling our analysts to do more of the work that they do and help them do
it faster.
And last, a little disclaimer, I'm not a software engineer and I never have been.
I'm an analyst myself.
So I'm not here to tell you how to write code or to show off some new cutting edge
project.
My goal here today is to show you a little bit about what threat intelligence is and
how we use Python to help us do it.
And by sharing some of the things that we've had success with on my team, my hope is that
it might inspire some of you to do something similar in your own work.
So what is threat intelligence?
Threat intelligence is knowing about adversaries, what they do, and how they do it.
Mandiant conducts hundreds of investigations every single year and it's my team's job to
look at all of those investigations and keep track of who's doing what and how they're
doing it.
Why do we do this?
To help defenders make informed decisions.
This may sound like common sense, but it helps as a defender to know what you're defending
against, right?
So a customer may ask, what are the most common threats targeting my industry and what tools
and techniques do they use?
And last but not least, we do this with data, expertise, and technology.
I know that sounds super vague, but I think it's actually really important to understand
that we need all three of these things working together in order to be successful.
To illustrate this, let me walk you through an example.
Say we have an investigation.
One of the first things that we want to do is collect data.
Now when I say data, I'm talking about things like files, event logs, network telemetry,
pretty much anything that we can use as forensic evidence during our analysis.
At the same time, we're documenting what happened.
I know this sounds similar to collecting data, but I think that the key distinction is organization.
So if the data that we collect are puzzle pieces, then documenting what happened is
putting those pieces together so that we can begin to see the bigger picture.
That usually means building a timeline of events and doing something that we call modeling,
which I'll talk about in the next slide.
And with this bigger picture beginning to take shape, we start applying context to the data.
This means taking a deeper look at the information that we have, expanding that information with
additional sources, and beginning to derive meaning from it.
For example, our collected data might show a program is being installed or executed,
but we still want to know what that program does.
By reverse engineering the file and understanding what its capabilities are, this can help us
determine whether it's relevant to our investigation.
And when we do this for every investigation, it helps us identify patterns across them.
These patterns become the backbone of our analysis, which ultimately allows us to make
assessments about the adversary, their tools, and their objectives.
Looking more now on expertise in technology, I don't think it's news to anyone here that
computers are better at some things than humans, and vice versa.
I think this is especially true here.
And the more that I thought about it, the more that I realized there's kind of this
transition between the two as we work through this process.
Computers are really good at collecting and organizing data, and they can help us apply
context and identify patterns if we tell them where to look and what to look for.
While ultimately in the end, we still need humans with the right expertise to analyze
the data and turn it into knowledge.
The last point I want to make here is that this process is a cycle and when done well,
feeds itself.
The assessments that we make and the patterns that we identify allow us to apply more context
and better informs our collection.
Now I want to quickly cover data modeling, which I'll define as a framework for documenting
both our data and analysis.
Throughout the course of every investigation and research project, our analysts are carefully
modeling key information, enshrining the work that they've done into an ever-growing graph.
This graph serves as the authoritative knowledge base for all of Mandiant.
So everything that we know about adversaries, what they do and how they do it lives here.
Again I think it's easiest to talk about via example.
So let's say that we start with a Word document that maybe we found attached in an email at
a customer.
It might seem harmless, but on closer analysis, we determine that the document contains a
macro that when executed, installs a malicious file of some sort.
So we model that by connecting these two files or nodes with an edge.
And we're already beginning to document what we have and apply context.
So let's keep going.
After our reverse engineer analyzes the file, they report that it communicates via HTTPS
to a domain.
And continuing to expand what we know, we may also notice a code signature for the file
and a resolution for the domain thanks to our passive DNS source.
Eventually we have enough information to assess that this file belongs to the malware family
bad apple.
Using malware families is often the first big step toward attribution as adversaries
tend to use the same malware families across multiple intrusions.
Which makes sense when you think about it.
Bad guys are people too and they like to stick to what they know.
Imagine having to learn a new piece of software every time you came into work.
It just doesn't really make sense.
So we've applied our malware label to the file along with all the data linked to it,
signifying that each node is a component of the bad apple ecosystem.
Let's keep digging.
We know our malware communicates over HTTPS, which means a TLS handshake and an X509 certificate
for the domain.
And here's where things get interesting.
We can't find any more direct relationships to our certificate, but we're able to identify
a pattern softly linking it to another certificate with a similar organization name.
Maybe we saw it recently and we just happened to remember.
Or maybe one of our teammates codified that pattern into a detection which made the link
for us.
Either way, we've just uncovered a big clue because this certificate has already been
attributed to the adversary, Dr. Evil.
Now we have to be careful when we make jumps like this.
Just because two things are similar doesn't necessarily mean that they're related.
But as we continue to traverse the graph, we find that this certificate is tied to another
bad apple sample, including a document much like our own.
And I'm simplifying here, but with all of these identified overlaps, we're eventually
able to attribute our activity to Dr. Evil, expanding our knowledge of this particular
adversary.
And because we modeled all of it, our team can now use that intelligence in their own
analysis and investigations.
Okay.
Now let's talk about Python.
Thinking about what analysts need to do, how can we enhance or automate parts of that process?
As I mentioned before, I think collecting data is the easiest.
Our analysts work with so much data, they shouldn't have to wrangle it all manually.
So we can automate most of this with some good I.O. functionality.
And once we have that data, we can also organize it according to our data model and publish
it directly to the graph.
This way, analysts don't have to create every single node and edge by hand.
They can jump straight to analysis and focus on the really hard questions that require
their expertise.
Applying context and identifying patterns gets a little bit harder, but we can still
help by giving analysts easy access to data sources, extract and model the key information
we get from those sources, and generate detections.
And finally, our mission is to enable analysts, but we can't replace them.
They still need to be in the driver's seat telling us what they need so that we can go
and get it.
In other words, we need a UI.
So over the next several slides, I'll be covering the Python packages that we use, the features
we like, and some examples of how we use them.
The first one I want to talk about is argparse.
We use argparse for all of our command line input.
We like it because it's part of the standard library.
It's really easy to use and it's well documented.
It comes with a ton of default functionality without having to write a lot of code, but
it's still flexible enough for our various use cases.
You can see here that with five lines of code, we get a ton of functionality telling our
analysts about the tool and how to use it.
Another thing about argparse that we really like is that it allows us to define arguments
that we can then use across multiple argument parsers.
So for example, say we want an argument that allows us to define the log level that we
want to output.
We can store that in, say, like a core args module, and then in another module, we can
just import it and stuff it into an argument parser, and as you can see, it's right there
showing us exactly how to use it without any extra code.
This makes it really easy to have a good base of arguments that we can then use across our
project.
Speaking of logging, we try and use a logging package really heavily throughout our project.
It not only helps us test functionality and triage bugs, but it also gives our analysts
more control over the output that they get.
Specifically, we like to use this for file I.O., HTTP requests, and error handling.
The exception method there on the bottom right, I think, is particularly cool because it not
only tells us that we got an error, but it also logs the entire trace back for us as
well.
For console output, we really love the package rich, and I'm sure a lot of you do too.
Rich gives us automatic highlighting, colors, styling, and even emojis.
And that's really just the surface of it.
It also provides things like tables, syntax highlighting, markdown, better trace backs,
progress bars, and so, so, so much more.
I highly recommend checking it out if you haven't already.
And for the specific things that we need highlighted that might not be covered by the default Regex
highlighter that's included, we can make our own.
Pretty much anything that you can specify with a Regex, you can easily make a highlighter
for, and then that just becomes automatic when you print things out.
So you can see here that we've made one for MD5 hashes, something that's really common
for us in threat intelligence.
Another feature of rich that we really like is the logging handler.
The rich handler, by default, adds a ton of extra output to logging, things like timestamps,
a better formatting, all of the same highlighting that we get with the print statements, and
the location in the file where that log message was generated from.
Because we interact with so many different data sources, we need to be able to make lots
of HTTP requests to various APIs, both internal and external.
We really like to use HTTPX.
One reason is because it's both synchronous and asynchronous, so depending on our use
case, we don't need multiple packages to do one or the other.
We can just import HTTPX, and that's it.
Also it's really similar to requests, so if it's something that you're interested in and
you're already familiar with requests, it makes it a lot easier to port over.
One particular feature of HTTPX that I think is really cool is the event hooks.
For any request or response, if we want to do something to that request or response before
it goes out or comes in respectively, then we can create an event hook to make that happen.
For example, if we have, say, an API that we need specific authorization for, then we
can create an event hook that will automatically add a token in when it sees that we're making
a request to that specific host.
Then we can just import that client into another module, and we don't have to worry about authorization
in our other code.
In thinking back to data modeling, we need a way to represent data as nodes and edges.
We do this with simple classes.
For example, we have a class node that it might take a type and maybe some properties,
and then we have a method so that we can add tags to it, aka apply context.
Building on top of that, we can also create an edge class that takes nodes and relates
them together.
Then we can use those to build a data model, which specifies the exact types of nodes and
edges that we want to be able to create.
At the same time, we can also build in some validation here to make sure that we're not
modeling anything that doesn't make sense.
In the same class, but I couldn't fit it here, so we had to just pretend it's further down,
we also can create a payload which transforms those nodes and edges into whatever it is
that our API accepts, say it's JSON, and we can use our auth client that we just talked
about from HTTPX and submit that automatically to our graph.
For an example, let's say that we want to model network scan data.
We have a function here, model scans, and say it takes an instance of our data model
and a bunch of scans that maybe we got from an API.
For each scan, we pull out the IP and the port, and we can model that as a node.
If we're particularly interested in TLS data, we can then parse out the certificate, model
that as a file, apply some context for say if it's self-issued, and then we can link
those two nodes together with an edge.
Then we can display all of that information that we've modeled, and by the way, it looks
super awesome because of rich, and then we can submit that to the graph if the user so
chooses.
As far as modeling data from sources, we also often need to inspect files that we found.
The most common type of file that we deal with are PEs, so executables on Windows.
One of the packages that we use a lot is called PE file.
This package is really awesome for parsing pretty much anything and everything that you
could ever want out of a PE.
For example here, we pass it some bytes, and then we can pull out the things we want like
the compile timestamp, the rich hash, the import hash, so on and so forth.
Then going a little bit further, we can also parse out the code signature.
It's not as easy to do, but I've got an example here of how to get that done.
Once we have the bytes, we can hand it off to another package, ASN1 Crypto, which will
then automatically parse all of the certificates for us.
Much in the same way, we can then pull out the specific data points from those certificates
that we're interested in and do whatever we want with them, display them, use them for
detections, all that good stuff.
When I talk about generating detections, I think probably the most common one, not only
for us but across the industry, are Yara rules.
I've got an example here and a link if you want to check it out.
Yara rules, like I said, are pretty much industry standard.
It's all open source.
It's extensible and there are a bunch of default modules for things like PEs, for things like
generating hashes, and it has a Python package, Yara Python, which lets you run all of your
rules against files and all that other good stuff.
At the end of the day, Yara rules are really just strings.
Once we have the data from these files that we want, it makes it really easy to then generate
these boilerplate detections.
For example, if we have a serial number and a common name for a certificate that we're
interested in, we can create a Yara rule and then we can look for any PE file that might
contain that certificate.
Or with a rich hash from a PE, we can use the hash module and PE modules to look for
that exact same hash in another file.
These are both really good examples of ways that we look for similar malware across our
data set.
And then finally, I want to talk a little bit about engineering without engineers.
As I explained before, we don't have any engineers on my team.
We're all just analysts trying to make do with the Python that we know.
And so my advice for others who maybe are in a similar situation is to start small.
Think about the things that you do every day that take a lot of time, that are tedious,
but that don't require a lot of brain power.
The boring stuff.
The more that you can automate these things, the more that you can focus on the stuff that
really matters, the stuff that really needs your attention, and honestly, the stuff that's
more fun anyways.
Next, I would say invest in your environment.
Get yourself an IDE that really works for you.
I love VS code.
PyCharm is great, too.
There's a lot of built-in extensions specifically for Python, and some of the folks that work
on that are here at the conference.
Then I would say look at things like automatic formatting and linting.
Things like black, like pylint.
These can really help you catch bugs and make your code more readable, more understandable,
not only for you, but for others.
And then remember that productivity is better than perfection.
We're not software engineers, but we don't have to be.
We're not trying to ship a product that needs to be absolutely perfect, that has no bugs.
We don't want bugs, but we're not afraid of them either.
Any little improvement that we can make in our process is a win.
Any time that we can save, it allows us, again, to focus on those things that need our attention more.
And that's pretty much it.
Thank you.