All right. So is everyone awake? Sort of. Okay. So my name is Trey and I help folks level
up their Python skills through on-site and remote team training, mostly remote the last
couple of years for obvious reasons, and with Python Morsels which helps experienced programmers
develop a habit of deepening your Python skills every single week through hands-on learning
because you don't learn by putting information into your head by trying to retrieve information
from your head that you actually learn. So when I do team trainings, I often see some
very weird code because my students are playing with Python, which is lovely because playing
is a wonderful way to learn. Sometimes though, when I'm trying to explain something that
Python is doing, I realize that I don't really know what Python is doing. Or at least I don't
understand why it's doing what it's doing. So this talk was inspired by all of the individuals
who asked me weird and confusing questions while I was holding a Python workshop at your
company. So thank you for your confusion. This is a Python 3 only talk. If this was
a Python 2 oddities talk, it would be much longer and much funnier. Feel free to ask
me questions about Python 2 oddities later if you're strangely interested. All right,
let's get started. So first I would like to talk about variables. Let's say we have a
variable X that is equal to zero. And let's say we have a variable numbers, and that variable
points to a list of numbers. If we loop over this list of numbers and assign Y to the square of each
of these numbers, what do you think Y will be after this loop? What's your guess? Who thinks
it'll be zero? Who thinks it'll be eight? Who thinks it'll be 64? Who thinks it's an error?
We can't see what Y is. So it turns out we can see what Y is. It's 64. And if we access X,
who thinks it's zero? X is still zero. Who thinks it's eight? Who thinks it's something else? So
it's not something else. I'm not sure what you were thinking it was though. It's eight. And it's eight
because inside of a loop, variables leak their scope. Loops don't have their own separate scope.
So this 4X in numbers, this is actually an assignment that happens during each iteration
of our loop. It works the same way that an assignment statement happens with an equal sign. The part
between the 4 and the in, that X there is the same thing as the left-hand side of an equal sign.
So if we take those same X and the same numbers variables and we make a list comprehension
representing the squares of these numbers, and we use that X as our looping variable,
what do you think X will be after we've executed this code? Who thinks it's zero this time? It wasn't
zero before. Who thinks it's eight this time? Still eight. So it was eight in Python 2, but
it's zero in Python 3, which is kind of nice. List comprehensions have their own scope. That's the
last time I'm going to mention Python 2. It's just Python 3 from here on out. So let's say we have a
global variable numbers, and we want to add more numbers to that by using the plus equals operator.
What do you think will happen if we call add numbers, this function here with the list four,
five, six? Now, it could modify numbers. It could just give us an error. It could make a local
variable number. So who thinks it's going to give us an error? Who thinks it's going to make a local
variable numbers? Won't modify the global. Who thinks it's going to modify that global variable
numbers? So very mixed here. Most of you seem a little bit confused about what it's going to do.
As you should be, this is a strange thing to do. It turns out it gives us an error. It gives us an
error because this plus equals operator both reads from and assigns to the variable that's on the
left-hand side. So we're trying to read from a global variable and assign to a global variable,
and Python doesn't like that. But it's not because of the plus equals, not in particular. If instead
we used an equals with a plus, we would still get an error. When we defined this function, Python
actually parsed all of the assignment operations and claimed all of those variable names as local
variables. Since numbers is a local variable, we can't read from it before we've written to it.
That doesn't make sense. So let's look at one more example of the same thing. If you don't believe
me yet, hopefully you'll believe me after this next one, if we make a similar function that prints
the global variable numbers and then assigns to it right afterward, calling that function gives us
an error. Variable names in Python cannot be both local and global in the same scope. So we're allowed
to read a global variable and we're allowed to write to a local variable but not with the same name.
Python doesn't allow that because that would probably be a bug in our code. This really
doesn't make sense to do. We're allowed to read from global variables without writing to them,
but once you assign to a variable, that variable magically becomes local. So if we swap these two
lines of code, our function will not give us an error. This function actually does what's expected.
But our global numbers variable hasn't changed because we're assigning to a local variable here
and then we're reading from that local variable. So the global numbers variable and the local
numbers variable both have the same name, but they're different variables pointing to different
objects. Assignments in Python only change the local scope. You can't change the global scope with
an assignment. Actually you can. There's an escape hatch to do so. I'm not going to mention it,
though, because you shouldn't change the global scope with Python. You can only change the local
scope with Python. All variable assignments are local. So this will always assign to a local
variable here inside of a function. Now, what if instead of doing an assignment in this add
numbers function, we use the extend method on this list? How is this any different? So when we call
this function, Python might print out 123456 or it could give us an error or it could do something
else. So who thinks this will give us an error? Python might print out 123456 or it could give
us an error. Who thinks this will print out 123456? Who thinks it's also going to change the global
variable numbers? All right. So a lot of you got this one right. You're right. This prints out
123456 and it changes numbers. Now, what's going on here? The reason this works and a lot of you
had some intuition about this is that the word change is tricky in Python. It's an ambiguous term.
What are you changing? You can change a variable or you can change an object. So assignment
statements change a variable. That is which object a variable is pointing to. That's what we
talk about when we talk about scope. That's what we've been talking about. This isn't an assignment,
though. This is changing an object. We're not changing which object a variable is pointing to
with an assignment. We're doing a mutation which changes the object itself. So we can't assign to
a global variable, but we can mutate any object that we can get our hands on as long as it's a
mutable object. So you're allowed to read from global variables in Python, but you can only write
to local variables. Every assignment statement assigns to a local variable. There are some
escape hatches in Python to get around that limitation, but you shouldn't use them.
List comprehensions have their own scope, but for loops do not because Python is function level
scoped. It's function scoped, not block scoped. We don't really have blocks in Python. And Python's
scope rules are entirely about assignments, not about mutations. Speaking of which, that's our next
topic, mutability and mutations. Assignment is about changing variables, which object those
variables point to. Mutability is about changing objects. So let's say we have a list of numbers
and we assign numbers two to numbers. If we append to numbers two, how many elements will numbers two
contain? So who thinks three? Who thinks four elements? Who thinks something else? There's a
couple something else's. There's always a couple something else's. I'm curious what those would be.
It's four elements. Numbers, what is numbers at this point? We append it to numbers two. Who thinks
it's three still at this point? Who thinks it's four at this point? You're right. It is four,
and it's four because these two variables are referencing the same object. So we have two
variable names that are referencing the same object. These are not two different objects.
Mutating one of these lists mutates the other because they're the exact same list. Changing
objects and changing variables are distinct things. Assignment statements change which object a
variable is pointing to, but mutations change the object itself. And that will change or seem to
change any number of variables that might be pointing to that object. So
can we make a tuple with a list inside it in Python? It's a weird thing to do. Is it possible?
Who thinks you can do this? Python will allow it even though it's weird. Who thinks this is an error
because it doesn't really make sense? So Python does allow this. We can do it. What if we call the
append method on the first item in this list? Well, Python allow this. Who thinks it'll allow it?
Who thinks this is not possible? Shouldn't be possible. So Python allows this. It does allow
us to append to this list. It doesn't give us an error at least. The first item in this list has
now changed. Now tuples are immutable, meaning we can't change them. It seems like we've changed
this tuple though, but we haven't. We haven't actually changed the tuple. Not technically,
not from the tuples perspective at least. If we take the first thing in this list and we assign
a variable to it and then we append to that variable, we've changed the list that that
variable is pointing to, but we've also changed every other reference to that variable because
we changed an object and not a variable. Variables don't store objects. They're not like this
bottle here that stores liquid. They don't contain a thing. They refer to something. They point to
something. So variables are more like pointers or references. They don't actually contain objects.
Now, what would happen if we make a new list and then we try to append the list to itself?
Who thinks this is possible to do in Python? You think some weird things are possible in Python?
I like you people. This works. You can append the list to itself. Now, this makes an infinitely
recursive data structure. Python represents a bit strangely at the REPL. It does this to not break
our machine. Otherwise, there would be an infinite amount of square brackets. Python represents this
strangely, but it is possible to do. This really demonstrates that that analogy of a variable being
a bucket that contains an object doesn't make sense because a bucket can't contain itself.
A bucket can have a piece of paper in it though that refers back to itself. Lists are not buckets
which contain objects. Instead, they're lookup tables that reference the memory locations of
an object. Data structures list dictionaries, tuples, anything else that might contain something.
They don't actually contain objects. They contain references to objects. Variables also don't contain
objects. They just refer to or point to objects, which means that change is an ambiguous term in
Python. We can change which object a variable is pointing to with an assignment statement,
or we can mutate an object which actually changes the object itself. Regardless of what variables
or data structures might be pointing to that object. If you feel rusty on this topic, I wrote
an article on it recently called Overlooked Facts about Variables and Objects in Python.
It's all about pointers. I highly recommend Ned Batchelder's talk from years ago at PyCon called
Facts and Myths about Python Names and Values and Brandon Rhoads' talk from quite a while ago
called Names, Objects, and Plummeting from the Cliff, which actually goes into quite a bit more
than just this topic here. All right. Let's talk about ducks. Let's say we have a list called duck
list. What do you think would happen if we used the plus equals operator to add a tuple of two
values to this list? Will Python let us do this? Who thinks this will work? It will do something.
Who thinks this will give us an error? It doesn't make sense to do. Python actually allows this.
It allows us to do this. And what happens is Python loops over the tuple and adds each of the
values to our list. Let's make a tuple called duck tuple that has two strings in it. Will Python
allow us to use plus equals to do the same thing but with a list to a tuple? So we're trying to
add these two items in our list to the tuple. So who thinks this will work? Still works. Who thinks
we get an error at this point? We do get an error at this point, but the error isn't because we
can't use plus equals with a list or rather plus equals with a tuple. Plus equals works with tuples.
We're allowed to use plus equals on tuples as long as it's with another tuple. So plus equals on
tuples only works with other tuples. It doesn't work with lists. That's the weird thing. And in
fact, tuples aren't actually the odd one here. Lists are the odd one. Let's take an empty list
and try to use a plus equals operator with a string. Who thinks this will work? It'll do something.
Who thinks this is an error? So this does actually work, but it might not do what you think it does.
It loops over the string and adds each of the characters to the list because the plus equals
operator on a list accepts any interval of strings. As long as it can loop over it,
it will loop over it and as long as it gets strings, it will add those strings to the list
individually. So plus equals on lists does the same thing as the extend method on a list. The
extend method accepts any interval and it loops over it and it pins each of the items to the list
from that interval. So plus equals on lists is consistent, but not with plus equals on tuples.
It's consistent with the extend method on lists. The list extend method and this plus equals
operator on lists, they're not an isolated issue. Many other operations in Python accept any
interval. For example, the string join method accepts a list, but it also accepts a tuple
and even accepts strings. But again, it might not do what you expect it to do. What happens when you
loop over strings? What do you get? Characters. Technically strings that represent characters
because strings are recursive data structures. That's a whole other oddity, though. So when we
loop over strings, we get substrings and that's what we're doing. We're joining together each of
the characters in the string with space, which is a strange thing to do. So if we give the dictionary
constructor in Python an interval of two item intervals, it will accept whatever we give to it
as long as there are two item intervals and make the first thing a key and the second thing a value.
Lots of things in Python accept any interval as long as it fits the shape and the style they're
looking for. They don't really care what you give to it. What's the word for this? What's the animal
that we use to describe this? I'm sure someone knows. A duck. Right. We're practicing duck typing.
Rather, Python is practicing duck typing. So the idea behind duck typing is when we're trying to
identify an animal, we don't check its DNA to see whether it's a duck. Instead, we observe it.
We observe it and say, you know, if it looks like a duck, it walks like a duck, maybe it sounds kind
of like a duck, then it's a duck. That means that checking the behavior of an object instead of
checking what the actual class of that object is, we don't check its type, its class, we check its
behavior. We don't usually care whether something is a list. We care whether it's a sequence or
maybe whether it's an iterable. We don't care whether something is a function. We care whether
it's a callable. We tend to use generic words for describing behaviors of objects instead of
discussing the types of those objects. All right. So the list extend method accepts any interval
and the plus equals operator on lists works the same way as the extend method. It's consistent with
extend. But the plus equals operator works differently on tuples and in fact on most types
of objects. And in many cases, Python doesn't do type checking at all. Because it's practicing duck
typing. It's checking the behavior. It's trying something out and hoping for the best. So if you
embrace duck typing in your own code by thinking in terms of behaviors like an iterable instead of a
type like a list, you'll better understand what Python is doing. But you'll also probably write
better Python code. Your code will fit in better in the Python ecosystem. So familiarize yourself
with terms like iterable and callable and hashable, sequence mapping, these generic terms that describe
behavior instead of the type of something. And if you're interested in specifically how iterables
work in Python, I gave a talk on this some while back called loop better, a deeper look at iteration.
Although it really dives into how iterables work deeply. You don't really need to understand it.
But it's nice to embrace these generic terms when you're talking about types. Because in Python,
we think in terms of behavior, not in terms of concrete types. Okay. So we're going to take
a very quick mental break before our next session. Here is a dog in a mailbox.
A chipmunk enjoying some tea. And a cat debugging its code.
All right. That's a long enough break. Let's look at the plus equals operator again.
Let's take two variables and assign them to the same tuple. Then let's try to use the plus equals
operator to modify one of these tuples. Does Python allow plus equals on tuples? Who thinks
Python allows plus equals on tuples? Okay. Good. You should know by now Python allows plus equals
on tuples. We just saw it. So Python does allow plus equals on tuples. And we can use it with
another tuple. So A at this point has four things in it. How many things does B have?
Two or four? What do you think? Two things? Four things? So it turns out it has two things.
So A has four things. B has two things. Because we changed A, we didn't change B. So plus equals on
tuples is really the same as a plus operator followed by an equal sign. We're not mutating
the tuple. We're just making a new tuple and then reassigning our variable to it. So X plus equals
something is the same as X plus something followed by an equal sign afterward. Both of these statements
make a new object and then afterward point our variable to that new object. All right. Let's take
two variables and do the same thing. We'll assign them to the same list. Now let's use the plus
equals operator to modify the first list. So our first list now has four things in it.
How many things does our second list have? Two or four at this point? Yeah, at this point our list
has four things different from the tuple. So the plus equals operator doesn't mutate tuples, but it
does mutate lists. Now I find this interesting because that means that on lists A plus equals
something does a mutation, but A equals A plus something creates a new object and then reassigns
the variable to that new object. So in Python A plus equals B is not always the same as A equals
A plus B. It is sometimes, but not always, these two things are the same on strings, on numbers,
and on tuples, but they do different things on lists. Now this seems a little bit inconsistent,
but from Python's perspective it's perfectly consistent. So this is because lists are mutable
and plus equals is an in place addition operation, which means it performs a plus operation in place.
So you're supposed to do a plus operation in place on mutable objects. It's actually supposed
to mutate in place if it can, but it's convenient to use plus equals on immutable types like tuples
and strings and numbers. This is a convenience for us because we don't want to have to type plus and
then equals all the time in our code. So on immutable types in place assignments they just
fall back to returning a new object instead. So on mutable types in place assignments mutate the object
and on immutable types they return a new object to us. Now if we take a tuple with a list inside it,
who thinks we can put a list inside of a tuple? Okay so we've stuck a list inside of a tuple,
you remember that. We've already seen this, it's possible to do, but what happens if we say
X sub zero plus equals a list three four? Now we've got a list in this tuple, who thinks it will
mutate this list? It's actually going to mutate the list. Okay who thinks that this won't work,
we're going to get an error. Who doesn't know what this is going to do? Okay so that was most
of you here. Now it turns out that the first two of you here, you have an interesting situation
going on. It actually does give us an error, but it also mutates the list. So everyone's happy at
this point right? Now this is probably the most obscure Python oddity I've seen, and it's never
going to bite you in real code, because why are you trying to mutate a list that's inside of a tuple
by subscripting the tuple? Nothing seems like it's a good idea here, but we're going to take a look
at what's going on anyway. So whenever we use the plus equals operator in Python, Python will try
to call the Dunder i add method on the object that we're pointing to, and in that case it's our list.
After that it will do an assignment. So the exception happened because the assignment failed,
but that was after Dunder i add successfully mutated our list. So the list Dunder i add method
mutates our list and then returns itself back for the sake of that assignment statement. But we're
not allowed to assign into a tuple, so we get an error at this point. Now this isn't ever going to
bite you in real code, because again why are you doing this in your code? What's the situation
where this makes sense? But this is an implementation detail that we found an interesting
excuse to learn about here. So some takeaways. The plus equals operator always performs an assignment,
but plus equals and other augmented assignment operators, or in-place operators as they're all
also called, are also allowed to mutate the object that they're called with. If that object chooses
to mutate itself, if it's a mutable object, lists mutate themselves with plus equals, but tuples
don't. Now this might seem inconsistent, but consistency is really about your frame of reference.
According to the Python documentation, in-place additions are supposed to do their operation in
place whenever possible, and lists just happen to be the most common data structure where it's
actually possible to do that. So if Python doesn't do what you expect it to do, that doesn't necessarily
mean you found a bug in Python. It does mean that what Python's doing doesn't match up with your own
sense of reality. The way Python sees the world isn't the way you see the world. So
I'd like to leave you with a few closing thoughts. Regardless of what programming language you're in,
it's important to understand how the fundamentals of your programming language are different from
other languages. How do function calls work? How do variables work at a fundamental level? And how
do objects work? Also, what is an object in your language? It's important to understand the way
that your programming language thinks about the world and more importantly thinks about itself.
What does the world look like through the eyes of the Python interpreter? And if you think you found
a bug in Python, it might just be that you're misunderstanding what tradeoffs the Python core
developers were taking when they were implementing the particular bit of functionality that you're
using. So if you see something odd going on in your code, before you fix that bug,
poke around and see what there is to learn from it. Because breaking things is one of the best
ways to learn. Also, if you find a Python audity of your own, use the Python audity hashtag if
you're going to tweet it or put it on social media. Over the last many years, I've probably
put out over 100 of these because there's lots of little weird things hiding in every programming
language. So join me. Tweet out a Python audity if you find one. Also, if you would like Python
morsel stickers because my logo is adorable, find me in the hallway afterward. Thank you.