And now I am thrilled to introduce Sarah Issaoun, member of the Event Horizon
Telescope collaboration, an Einstein Fellow.
Thank you.
Hello. I'm really nervous. This is my first talk since before the pandemic, so
in person. So bear with me. My name is Sarah. I'm a member of the Event Horizon
Telescope collaboration. I'm here to tell you about how we managed to make an
image of a black hole. You're probably familiar with our famous image from 2019.
This image here, this is the image of the black hole in the galaxy M87. It's
55 million light-years away from us. And I want to tell you a little bit about
our journey to get to this image. What we've learned since then about this
black hole, because we've had results last year that came out about this black
hole, and also the role that software development actually plays in big
science like our project. So one thing that was really shocking when we
released the image was that it actually went on front pages of newspapers around
the world. This is not something that happens to science results. This is
really not... People don't like to talk about... I mean it's like on page 12 or
something in a newspaper if it makes the news. But to see it on front pages the
day after we made this result really made us understand that we were giving
the world something special, something they could be part of, something that
shows that science is bigger than just one person. It's about collaboration,
it's about teamwork, it's about overcoming differences in cultures, in
countries, in career stages, gender, age, etc., and actually come together for one
goal and be able to be part of this moment. And this particular event, seeing
it on front pages, was really a shock to us. We knew some people would be
interested in this image but we didn't know really the response that the public
would have. One thing we also did not know is that the public would come up
with a lot of memes. And this was really interesting because we were trending
number one on Twitter. Like that doesn't happen to science results. So we
actually understood that as a collaboration it was our job to make sure
that you're all part of our story, that you understand that you're part of
science, you're part of progress, you're part of this big community that makes
the world a little bit better, a little bit funnier, a little bit more joyous.
So I'm just a member of the collaboration. I only play a small part,
we all play a small part in this big story. The Event Horizon Telescope
collaboration is 300 plus members, we're across over 60 institutes, 18 countries
and regions in Europe, Asia, Africa, North and South America. We're a really diverse
group of people, we're not all astronomers, they're software developers,
they're computer scientists, they're engineers, they're telescope operators,
administrators, all being part of this story, all playing their important part
in making this project happen. And I only play a very small part and I get to
represent all of these amazing people I get to work with today.
So hopefully this plays... So if you go...
Just a little bit slow. If you look up in the night sky,
there's a constellation called the Virgo constellation. In this constellation,
there's a bright dot that is the galaxy M87. This galaxy is 55 million light years
away from us, that's very far. And if you look at it with optical telescopes
like the Hubble Telescope, you will see the streak of matter, of gas that
comes from it. What is that? If you actually chase this streak down,
you look at it in the radio waves because radio waves allow you to peer
through the entire galaxy. You follow it with better and better telescopes
all the way down to its core. You find what we found with the
Event Horizon Telescope, the supermassive black hole. This streak of gas is
emitted by this black hole. This black hole is incredibly tiny compared to
the size of the galaxy and yet it creates a jet of plasma that
pierces through its entire galaxy and even its galactic neighborhood.
This immense power is kind of incredible and it's something we don't
quite understand. This is the most powerful process in the universe,
how black holes power their jets. And we don't understand how these happen.
Seeing a black hole up close with the Event Horizon Telescope allows us
to make the connection between what happens near a black hole and what happens
throughout its entire galaxy. So this is our goal with the EHT,
to understand how black holes look, how they feed, how they eject these
powerful jet of matter and how these jets also affect their nearby galaxies.
So we want to see the M87 black hole. It's very far away.
Its predicted size on the sky is about 20 to 40 microseconds. That's the
size of about a doughnut on the surface of the moon as seen from here.
So telescope size is proportional to observing wavelengths, the wavelengths
which we are looking with the telescope, and angular resolution of the telescope,
so the size of the telescope.
So the angular resolution we need to see M87 is 20 microseconds,
based on the predicted size. The observing wavelengths we need to peer
through all of the gas between us and the galaxy is one millimeter wavelength.
This is what we call the Goldilocks wavelength, to peer through all of
the gas, but that we're able to observe using Earth telescopes.
And it's also in the radio, and radio waves are not bothered by anything
between us and the black hole. So if we make this calculation,
what is the telescope size we get to see M87? It's actually 13 million meters.
Unfortunately, we tried, but no science agency wanted to fund building a
telescope this big, so we ended up with the next best thing,
which is actually right below our feet, the Earth.
The Earth's diameter is 13 million meters, and we can use the Earth as our telescope.
So how do we do that? We use a technique called very long baseline interferometry.
We find telescopes around the Earth that would form fragments of our telescope
mirror, and then we synthesize a virtual telescope the size of the Earth.
This is what we do.
Now, in order to do that, it's actually quite a challenging technique that won
the Nobel Prize in the 70s in physics, and I'll try to explain briefly how we do that.
So we have the black hole, it emits radio waves that's very far away.
The waves that it emits arrive as plane waves on Earth, so they're flat.
Now, the Earth is curved. I hope you all know that.
Because of that, telescopes that are at large distances from each other,
they actually see a signal at different times.
So if you look at this picture, the telescope at the bottom actually sees
one of the straight lines earlier than the telescope at the top.
Now, the Earth's curvature actually causes a problem because we need to see the
signal from the black hole at the exact same time at each telescope in order to
reconstruct an image. Each telescope has to see the same signal so that we can
correlate the signal and make an image.
Now, how do we get by this problem? So we have different telescopes at different
sites. The distances between each telescope is what we call the baseline
distance. Each pair of telescopes gives us a part of the image. So telescopes
close together, they tell us about large scale structure in the image because they
see more signal in common. Telescopes further apart see less signal in common,
and they tell us about smaller scale structure. So we need many telescopes at
different distances and different orientations on the Earth to reconstruct
all the information that is on the image. Then we have this time difference that
we have to deal with, and this time difference needs to be taken into account.
So what we use is extremely accurate clocks. They're called maser clocks,
and they are so accurate, they lose about a second every 100 million years.
That's how accurate these clocks are. So these clocks at each telescope,
they're about the size of a mini fridge. They're expensive, but they work.
And so these clocks help us time tag the arrival of the signal at each telescope,
and then we record that signal onto hard drives. So essentially,
every piece of light that arrives at the telescope is time tagged and then frozen
into hard drives. And then we play it back at a separate time later when we
combine all the signals from all the telescopes, all the hard drives.
So this is what very long baseline interferometry is, and this is how the
EHT is made. So the progress to getting the Event Horizon Telescope was a really
long one. The first dishes of the EHT started in 2007, and then we had more
and more as the years go by. Some telescopes were lost,
unfortunately they were decommissioned, and others joined until we reached 2017.
This is the year we finally had enough telescopes, enough combinations of these
different baselines that we were able to reconstruct an image.
We had six different locations, six single dish telescopes, and two phaser rays.
Phaser rays are basically telescopes in one place that can be combined into the
same way we do with the EHT, into a bigger virtual telescope that gives us
more sensitivity at that site. So we had eight telescopes for our observations.
The South Pole Telescope did not take part in the M87 results because it's in
the southern hemisphere and M87 is actually a northern hemisphere source,
so the South Pole cannot see it. Now you'll notice all these telescopes look
completely different from each other. The reason for that is because we didn't
build them. We borrowed them. We happened to just find telescopes that can observe
at the wavelengths we need that happen to be at high and dry enough sites such
that the atmosphere and the water vapor in the atmosphere that can scramble and
destroy our signal doesn't affect us as much. So these telescopes all are in the
most extreme locations on the planet, the driest deserts, the highest mountains,
and they were built for completely different science. They were built for
standalone science. This is why they all have different designs, different looks,
but they have one thing in common. Actually, two things in common, the clock,
the mini fridge that we have, and this. Wait, one more thing. I forgot I added
this slide. Another thing is we don't observe alone with the EHT. So we've told
this story that we have all these telescopes on Earth that we combine. We
also observe together with other telescopes that observe at different
wavelengths. So there are lots of telescopes that combined with us can
teach us a lot more about the black hole. Not only do we have the black hole image,
but we also know what the black hole is doing across the electromagnetic spectrum
at the same time. And this is something incredible that goes beyond our
collaboration because it also involves collaborating with multi wavelength
partners with other telescopes, other collaborations to come together at this
exact time and all look at the same thing. And this is really incredible. And
one of the big results that came out last year is this. This is what M87 looks
like across the electromagnetic spectrum. So you know our famous image,
which is down there. In yellow, there's kind of all what it looks like in the
radio where we see this jet of plasma. And then we have views of it in the X
ray. In the optical, you see the nice Hubble image, which is HST here at the
bottom one of the middle row. And then also what it looks like in the high
energy and X ray. And this view of M87 during our 2017 campaign was really
important in understanding the physics of the black hole, how it ejects this jet
of matter and how it varies with time. Now, as I mentioned, all our telescopes
are completely different. They have two things in common, our mini fridge and
this on the right here. This is what we call our EHT backend. It's our recording
equipment. This big block of things is what records our data. So we have a
telescope that has a receiver on it. The receiver receives the signal. It goes
through some wires and then it gets down converted to a lower frequency so that
we can measure it. We digitize it because we measure an analog signal. It needs to
be digitized into a two-bit sampling signal. And then we record it onto our
hard drives. Each of these little boxes here is called a module. Each module has
about eight stacked hard drives. We recorded on 736 hard drives during our
entire campaign. We recorded about three and a half petabytes of data across our
entire campaign. About one petabyte of that is M87. During our campaign, we
observe in April of each year, March, April. This is because weather is a big
part of our observing. As I mentioned, water vapor, atmospheric turbulence
destroys our signal. So we need really good weather. And so how do we do that
We try to find the best time window in which we have the most consistent, decent
weather for half the planet, which is very hard to do. And during the campaign,
we have a set window of days to observe, about 12 days. And we pay very close
attention to the weather and technical operations with our VLBI monitor to make
sure we make the right decision. On each day, we make a go or no-go decision. And
so mere hours before observing, that is when we decide to go on sky. So our
operations, our telescope staff have to be on it at each time and be ready to
observe if we trigger. And there are multitudes of reasons why we trigger on
certain days. Parts of it also comes from our multi-wavelength partners. For
example, if X-ray observatories are observing at the same time, like the Chandra
Observatory, then those are more likely days for us to observe. And then, of
course, the weather and telescope operations play a major part. So in our
2017 campaign, across our 12 days, which triggered five days of observation, and
four of those had M87. So this is a nice picture of the 2017 observations as all
the different telescope staff and observers that were at the telescopes
during the campaign. You'll see everybody's happy faces. We're normally
not that happy. It's high altitude and we don't sleep much. It's very tiring. But
we're happy for photo ops. And so in the top right corner, you'll notice there's a
woman in that picture. That's me. I was at the 7-millimeter telescope in Arizona
during the observations. This is one of the central telescopes. So I had sometimes,
you know, 30 to 35 hours without sleep. So that's fun. But it seems it was worth
it. So I think we're okay. So after the observations, we pack up our modules,
our hard drives, and ship them to this guy. This guy is Don Sosa. He is our
shipping expert for the EHT. Every single package of EHT, data, equipment, goes
through him. And he used to be a police officer for the state of Massachusetts.
And now he's in charge of all our shipping. And he's never lost a single
package since he's been doing this job. We had one mishap in which we
thought we had South Pole Telescope hard drives, but it ended up being a bunch of
silk. But, you know, everything was solved and we got our hard drives back
and the silk went back to where it belonged, luckily. On the left here are
filled modules. You'll notice they have green stickers, whereas the ones in the
big box I showed you had, they have red stickers and the ones in the big box had
green stickers. Green stickers means modules are empty. Red stickers means
modules are filled. So all of these modules have our precious data. What
happens to them? They get shipped half to one place and half to another. So I want
to talk a little bit about the data reduction process of the EHT. So we
measure petabytes of signal at the telescopes. Part of that signal is what
telescopes can see in common. So at the correlation stage, where we correlate the
signal between telescopes, we end up with terabytes of data. So we only keep the
signal that the telescopes see in common. Then we undergo a calibration stage in
which we reduce the data by solving for a bunch of processes and atmospheric
effects that scramble our data to unscramble it so that we can average
down. Just like constructive or destructive interference, right? If you
have destructive interference, you average it down, you destroy your signal.
If you have constructive interference, you can build your signal. So our goal is
to have constructive interference, build signal, and get higher sensitivity in our
data. And this is what happens in the calibration stage, and then we're left
with megabytes of data files. These data files are what are used in imaging. And
then our final image is actually a few kilobytes. You can send it on your phone.
And I always find this totally incredible that from the moment we measure the
signal to the kilobytes of data you can send on your phone, we undergo 12 orders
of magnitude in data reduction, which is kind of amazing. And this is the process
that happens in the EHT, and there isn't many experiments that go through this
amount of data crunching for their final result. Now, half the data go to Westford,
Massachusetts, an MIT Haystack Observatory, and the other half go to
Bonn, Germany at the Max Planck Institute for Radio Astronomy. These are our
correlation centers where they go onto these giant supercomputers that take into
account the earth's curvature, realign the signals, and make sure that they get
every combination of common signal between each pair of telescopes. So,
essentially, the correlators then create our virtual telescope. Then there's a long
process to understand the data. So, after correlation, the data go to a dedicated
team that builds pipelines. These pipelines correct for correlation errors.
They also correct for atmospheric effects, and they help build the signal,
like this constructive averaging. There are three pipelines that were built.
One is called hops, one is called CASA, one is called APES. Each of these
pipelines are supported by many Python packages. And, again, this step is one of
the most important steps of the entire process, because it requires really
understanding of the data, separating between what comes from our instrument and
the atmosphere, and what is the true black hole signal. Nothing, all the signs,
all the analysis after that really depends on this step, and this step is
Python supported. And then we go through a data validation by a dedicated team
where we compare all these independent pipelines, their outputs, making sure that
we understand that we're seeing the true black hole signal. And this data
validation also involves a whole bunch of suites of data tests that are, again,
supported by many Python packages. And this entire process was like a cycle of
about four or five times that we did this, from correlation all the way to data
validation, and this took one and a half years. So if people ask, you know,
why does it take so long for pictures of black holes, we observed in 2017,
one and a half years was spent on this. And then about half a year later,
we released the image. So it was a two-year process. And this part is
incredibly important. Understanding the data is one thing. The next step is
understanding of the telescopes. So we need to understand our telescopes with
incredible detail, such as the atmosphere, how our telescopes move, how they behave.
And as I mentioned, all our telescopes are different from each other.
So this is not a trivial thing. It requires really paying attention and
understanding each part of our instrument, and we don't really have a part that
repeats. So this was quite a lot of work. Another thing we have to do is, in order
to make images of polarization, which I'll explain later, we have to also
decouple leakage. So we observe in two polarizations, and we have signal that
sometimes leaks into the other. Because of that, unfortunately, the Earth's
rotation helps us again. Because the Earth rotates, the telescopes on the ground
don't move, but the source on the sky moves. And so by decoupling the signal
that changes over the sky compared to the one that stays put, we can actually
separate between what is the instrument and what is the source signal.
Then M87 is finally ready for analysis. This is what our data looks like.
As a radio astronomer, to me, this is the most beautiful figure I've ever seen.
And honestly, I like it more than the image. And not because it's map plot-lib.
So why is this so beautiful to me? If you look at the data, all the different
colors are different pairs of telescopes. And the x-axis tells us about the
baseline lengths. So short baselines see more signal in common, long baselines see
less signal in common. You'll notice we have this dashed curve on it that
represents a uniform ring. So if this was on the sky, we would see the dashed curve.
And to me, that's incredibly beautiful, because the uniform ring is a beautiful
mathematical concept. It has a analytic solution. It is a sync function.
And it looks like this beautiful bounce. And to see this in the data,
to see the data also make this beautiful bounce, actually tells us that we're
seeing probably one of the most beautiful and simple objects in the universe,
just a ring. And another interesting aspect is that at this baseline length,
there are two pairs of telescopes that see different things. And what this tells
us by looking at these two pairs is that there is a brightness distribution that
changes. So one part of the ring is brighter than the other. And this data
tells us that it's brighter on the bottom. So even without making an image,
I already know what it looks like. Isn't that amazing? Just looking at this one
plot, we already know it's a ring brighter on the bottom. But of course,
we have a lot of questions about whether we're seeing what we're truly seeing.
And our data are publicly available, so you can actually go and download it and
download our imaging pipelines and make your own M87 image. The next step is,
what is imaging? So we again use the Earth as our telescope. So aperture synthesis
is a process where the Earth's rotation helps us fill a virtual mirror in the
middle there. And we combine data on temporal and spatial scales. So as the
Earth rotates, more and more telescopes see M87. We have more and more pairs of
telescopes. So the data kind of form in our virtual mirror. And then we stack the
data in time. And then we see how our image improves as we add more and more
data. Now, how do we decide what we're looking at? So if we're looking at the
data, okay, we think there's a ring in there. We think it looks a certain way,
but does it really? Are there other combinations of images on the sky that
could give us the same thing? So we were thinking maybe we should use machine
learning or just let computers decide what we're looking at and not have a
human component because we have such an expectation to see what we want to see
that maybe we're biased in that way. So it turns out people have done tests of
computers trying to decide what they're looking at. For example, is it fried
chicken or poodle? Or is it blueberry muffin or chihuahua? Or is it a sloth or a
chocolate croissant? It turns out computers don't know the difference,
which is surprising because as a human, at first you might be taken aback and see
if similar images, but if you take a closer look, you start critical thinking
and actually making up the difference between these. So if you take a little bit
of time, you can tell the difference. Computers can't. And so we just said,
oh, computers struggle, so let's just have humans have it go. But we structured the
imaging process in a way that tried to minimize the human bias. So this is our
imaging process. So we have a data calibration stage, which I went through.
Then we went through the first step, which is blind imaging in independent teams.
Then we had a bunch of feedback on data quality in this process. And then we went
to step two, which is pipeline building per independent software. Again,
a lot of our pipelines are supported by Python packages in which we build synthetic
models where we have a truth image and then we validate our images based on how
well they fit the data, how consistent they are with other sources we observe,
and how robust the structure is. So in the first step, we divided the imaging group
into four independent teams. Two of them, teams one and two, were focused on newer
forward modeling techniques, and teams three and four were focused on more
traditional inverse modeling techniques. Each team were asked to blithely
reconstruct images, and this was in order to assess human bias. So we spent a period
of seven weeks in our teams not talking to the others. I was in team two,
and in this process, we were kind of worried because in team two,
we saw a ring pretty easily. And we were thinking, what if we're the only team that
saw a ring? What if only the newer techniques saw a ring because our team was focused
on newer techniques? So what if us and team one saw a ring but teams three and four
didn't? How do we reconcile these differences? How do we end up working together if we have
opposing views of what we're seeing? So in the excitement of seeing the first image
of a black hole, we also had a lot of doubt and a lot of worry about what our scientific
path was going forward. So seven weeks in agony, and then we met at a workshop in
Cambridge, Massachusetts, and we were asked to have one image per team to show. And we all sat
in this room, all quiet, and Katie Baumann, who was leading the comparisons of the images,
she put on the screen four images. And there they were. These are the first images of M87 we saw as
a collective in the collaboration. These four images from the four teams, as you can see,
you know, they're a little bit rough on the edges. They were the first try, but they have
huge similarities. Every image gets a ring of the same size, and every image is brighter on the
bottom. So this was incredibly exciting, and it led to one of the most exciting and probably one
of my favorite days in the EHT. We took a picture, we averaged all the images together, we put it on
the screen and we took a group photo. This is everybody who was there at the workshop, and there
were many people also joining us remotely in the imaging teams. And, you know, you can see everybody
smiling. We were so thrilled that we had finally captured the image of a black hole. And this was
in July 2018, so about a year before we revealed it to the world. And in that evening, of course,
we went drinking. It was super fun. We went to a bar, we had some drinks, we sang karaoke. You can
see there in the bottom left, in the middle there, that's me and Katie Bellman and other members of
the imaging team blasting and singing really loud Bohemian Rhapsody, karaoke classic. And it was a
lot of fun. And really, this is one of the most memorable days for me as part of this project. It
was incredible. So the next step is how do we convince the rest of the world that we're seeing
the right thing? So we have our imaging software. All of these imaging software have knobs to tune
to make a final image. And two of these software, the ones that were built for EHT, are on GitHub
and also supported by Python packages. So we decided to create synthetic data, so fake data,
in which we know the truth, the underlying truth image. So we wanted to pick the knobs that best
reproduced all four of these images. So these were designed such that they have similar data
that looks like our bounce ring pattern, but that the underlying image might not be a ring. So one
of them is, or two of them are rings, but two of them are not. So we tested thousands of imaging
parameters systematically to decide which is a ring or how well they reproduce all four of these
data. And then the best ones that reproduce the best images were used on M87. So these were the
final images by the three softwares. You'll notice that you can't tell by the differences. That's how
well we were able to reconstruct them. And in fact, the famous image that you've seen, the first
image of a black hole, is actually just the average of these three. But as I mentioned,
we observed M87 for four days, and this image is only the April 11th day. So here are the other
three. And these are all independent observations of the black hole, and they all give us a ring of
the same size brighter on the bottom. No significant changes are observed, and M87 is a supermassive
black hole, and the image should change very, very slowly in this time period, which is what we see.
We also have polarization images. These were released last year, about almost exactly a year
ago. And these polarization images have, you know, these streaks added to it that show us
the polarization pattern. So light around the black hole comes from electrons orbiting magnetic
fields. So there's magnetic fields that thread the disk where the black hole feeds, and then these
magnetic fields have electrons gyrating in them, and then these electrons produce light that is
polarized, which means it oscillates in a certain direction. And what these oscillations tell us
is that they can actually give us information about what the magnetic fields look like.
And what the magnetic fields look like tell us about how the black hole ejects this jet.
So what is a black hole? So, you know, you all know about, you know, rockets escape velocities,
and objects escape velocity on Earth is independent of its mass. A rocket has the same escape velocity
as a balloon to leave Earth. And Reverend John Mitchell in 1784, he asked this question,
how small does an object need to be to have an escape velocity faster than the speed of light?
So how compact would you need an object to be for a rocket to need the speed of light or higher to
leave its surface? And once the escape velocity exceeds the speed of light, even photons, even
light, is trapped and the star becomes dark. So this was first called the dark star, and this
concept evolved into the black hole. So in 1915, Albert Einstein published his general theory of
relativity. In this theory, he predicts that light is affected by gravity. So light bends around
massive objects. And then in 1916, Carl Schwarzschild in the trenches of World War I,
he derived the first non-trivial solution to this equation, which is the Schwarzschild black hole.
It predicts a singularity that depends on a certain radius, and this radius is
creates the event horizon in which light cannot escape. Now, a lot of decades of work have been
put into understanding what would black holes look like if they existed? What would it look
like to an observer? What would it look like from Earth? Then in 1979, Jean-Pierre Lumenez makes the
first simulated image of a black hole. His simulation looks like this, which looks a lot
like the interstellar image, by the way, so not so many progress in the space. But it's a very
interesting simulation, by the way, so not so many progress, you know, since 1979. And his
simulation was run on punch cards. You know, you remember punch card computers? And he painted
the dots of the image by hand and took the negative. And to me, this is just such an incredible
story, you know, just the effort that went into the first simulated image of a black hole.
So it's that black hole simulations have gotten a lot more complicated. We, you know, this is all
just a simulation of a black hole. We have the black hole in the center, the gas around it,
we have this magnetic field that thread them, and these magnetic fields emit light and also eject
this jet of matter. And the black hole shadow is created by the gas illuminating this dark region
where light cannot escape. So the black hole actually lives inside this dark region. And
depending on the inclination, the viewing angle that we see this black hole and the gas around it,
the brightness distribution on the ring changes. So some part is brighter than the other,
depending on how we're looking at it. This is because if we're inclined, the light that moves
towards us appears boosted, it appears brighter than the light moving away from us. This is the
Doppler effect. So then the light around the black hole that comes from this gas
gets deflected by the black hole's gravity. So if you have a lot of light rays that get deflected
by the black hole, and then you look at it from a camera far away, what you see is that the black
hole deflects light rays further from the event horizon, and it kind of puffs up into this shadow.
And you have this shadow of the black hole and then this bright ring around it.
And this is the image of M87. This is what we see.
Then a lot of work went from our theory teams at the EHT to simulate the black hole image.
So make our simulation library based on lots and lots of different parameters of what it could be
around the black hole. These parameters change everything from how fast the black hole is spinning,
what is the gas like, what is the temperature of the gas, what are the magnetic fields, etc.
All of these processes are astrophysics related. But you'll notice all of these look pretty similar.
They have a dark patch in the center and a dark ring and a bright ring around it.
This is because what we see in our image is the pure effect of gravity.
No matter what fancy astrophysics you put around it, you will always see at the edge of a black
hole what we see. Dark patch in the center, bright ring around it. Because fundamentally,
what makes this happen, what is dominating the image, is gravity.
The polarized simulation library also looked at the astrophysics of the gas.
Here, actually, polarization helps us understand astrophysics in much more detail. Because
while our first image depended on gravity mostly, the polarization is not gravity related.
It's related to the magnetic field. And so our image last year taught us a whole lot more
about M87 and the gas around it. Then the next step is to measure the mass of a black hole.
So we had two measurements for the black hole from other experiments. They differed by a factor of
two. That's why we didn't know how big the black hole would be. We measured this with three different
techniques. I'm running out of time, so I'll just quickly go through this. We measured it directly
from the image. We also measured it using simple shapes. So just make a disk, make a hole in it,
move it around, and then kind of fit through all of the different combinations of moving these
disks and blurring them. And then find the size of the black hole through that, which you can see
how it converges to the solution. And then we also fitted individual frames of our simulations
to see which frames actually taught us about the black hole. In the EHT modeling software,
we used three different software libraries to model the mass and the size. All of them
supported by Python packages. One is an MCMC sampling framework. One is a genetic algorithm,
and one uses nested sampling. Then we measured the mass of the black hole. So the ultimate question
to life, the universe, and everything. What is the size of the M87 black hole shadow? Do you know
the answers to this question? It's 42! It's 42 micro arc seconds. That is the size of the M87
black hole shadow. And because the size of a black hole is proportional to its mass, we could measure
the mass of the black hole, which is six and a half billion times the mass of the sun. This is one of
the most massive supermassive black holes in our universe. What more did we learn from the M87
black hole? This is the polarization image. The polarization pattern are these kind of streaks
that form a spiral. The spiral polarization tells us that the magnetic fields around the black hole
are also spiral shaped. And they tell us that the magnetic fields are actually strong enough
and ordered enough to be able to launch the jet. And they also tell us that this process uses the
black hole's rotation. The black hole is spinning, and its black hole's rotation is
powering the magnetic fields and powering the jet. So that we learned last year.
The size of M87 in perspective, so there's the sun in the center, the orbit of Pluto,
Voyager 1, which is the furthest human-made object, is just reaching the edge of the shadow.
That's how big M87 is. So is Einstein right? That's one of the questions we always get.
So Einstein predicts the black hole's shadow to be fairly circular. There are other theories of
gravity that predict deviations from circularity. And so we found a circularity within 10%, which
means Einstein is right yet again. So what's next for the Event Horizon Telescope? Just a quick
overview about where we're going. The other black hole we looked at is Sagittarius A star.
It is the supermassive black hole at the center of our own Milky Way. And Sagittarius A star
has these stars that orbit it, this dark region. These stars are bright in the infrared. And in
fact, the orbits of these stars measure the mass of Sagittarius A star with great accuracy. So we
know exactly what Einstein's theory predicts for the size of this black hole shadow. Because of
this amazing research, which actually won the Nobel Prize in Physics in 2020. Then we had,
you know, we've observed it in the radio. Unfortunately, because it's in our galaxy,
we have this big cloud of matter, of gas, that blurs our image. So at other frequencies,
we cannot see the shadow. But the EHT can. And actually on May 12th, the Event Horizon Telescope
is going to reveal groundbreaking new results about the Milky Way. So that's something to look
forward to. We're also growing with the EHT. We've added new telescopes over the years at
different locations. More telescopes means we fill our mirror. And we're hoping to add more and more
telescopes to improve and make sharper and sharper images. Another bigger project is the
Next Generation EHT, where we want to put lots and lots of smaller telescopes at different locations
in the earth to enhance the imaging capabilities that we have. And eventually we want to go to
space, because we don't want to be limited by the earth's atmosphere. We can go to higher observing
frequencies where the atmosphere doesn't stop us. We can have a faster filling of our mirror with
the orbiter going very fast around the earth. And also have higher resolution, because we get the
distances between the earth and space. And that's, you know, much longer time scale. Then finally,
I just want to close off by saying that really the Python community, the software developer
community, open source community has been a pillar of modern science. Not just for the Event Horizon
Telescope, but for big science projects in general. You save us a huge amount of time.
Because all our analysis packages, everything I've presented today, all our different pipelines are
key process of the scientific method. We need to cross-check each other. And in order to do that,
we need to look for novel ideas to do the same thing. And we need variety in packages, variety
in techniques. And we find that variety with you. And so big science is not possible without open
source software. So this is where I end. Stay tuned for fun EHT results coming up. And thank you very much.