Hi, everyone. We'll start off with our next talks. We have Jigya Sir Grover and Rishabh
Mishra, who will be talking about sculpting data for machine learning. We do not have
Q&As during or after the session, but if you would like to ask questions to the speakers,
feel free to meet them in the hallway. Yeah, that's pretty much it. Over to you guys.
Hey, everyone. I'm Jigya Sir Grover, and I work as a machine learning engineer in the
performance ads ranking team at Twitter. And my co-presenter, Rishabh Mishra, he works in
the content quality team at Twitter. Today, we'll be talking about how we can sculpt the
right kind of data for our machine learning models. The last couple of years have seen an
immense growth of machine learning in multiple domains, from influencing our shopping carts to
cars self-driving themselves around the town. Unquestionably, machine learning is the most
used and the most abused and the most used subdomain of artificial intelligence presently.
It is being wielded in improving healthcare and advancing warfare, scrutinizing your resume to
determining your credit worthiness, in creating music and meaningful lyrics, to synthesizing
pictures and videos of people non-existent on this planet. Regardless of our fascination or
loathe for it, it is influencing our decision making power heavily and is dominating our lives
every millisecond. So dominant leaps are leaving the scientists, investors, policymakers, business
leaders and audience bedazzled that human-like intelligence in machines might be just around
the corner. Nonetheless, progress in machine learning has been very impressive, but there's
a lot of pending explanation and examination which keeps this research going on. So for the
state-of-the-art machine learning algorithms to work their magic, it's important to focus on three
key dimensions, well calibrated data, sophisticated algorithms and efficient computation. Since we
have progressed from the rule-based approach to a more data-driven approach, it goes without
saying that machine learning algorithms are trained to capture implicit information from the data
provided. It is true that these approaches are very data hungry and without going into a lot of
details, for example deep learning algorithms, they have a lot of parameters that need to be
tuned and therefore need a lot of data in order to come up with a more generalizable model. So in
that sense, having a lot of data is the key to coming up with good training sets for those
approaches. So look at this pyramid which is the AI hierarchy of needs. It is drawn parallel to
Maslow's hierarchy of human needs by Monica Rogati, who's a renowned data scientist and AI
advisor. She puts forward that wordy data collection forms the foundation of this pyramid of the AI
hierarchy of needs. Data literacy, data collection and data flow. These forms the basic needs which
must be satisfied in order for us to achieve self-actualization or Nirvana, which in our case
would be the attainment of artificial intelligence. So nonetheless, the quantity of data we also have
to take care about the type of data that we feed into the algorithms, which has a profound effect
on the success of the algorithm. As we say garbage in, garbage out. So machine learning models are
essentially as good or as bad as the data that you have. Peter Norvig has put it in very clearly
that more data beats clever algorithms, but better data beats more data. So in that case,
we should talk about data curation. And first of all, let's talk about academia. Core machine
learning and data science research groups in academia are oriented more towards novelty and
advancing the fields, many a times weighing it much more than the money making logic or performance
scaling. In this attempt to work on new problems, finding collaborators from pertinent domains and
seeking funding for research groups are not the only obstacles they face. They also have to look
for relevant data sources in the absence of in-house data, contrary to corporate giants like Facebook,
Google, who have access to tons of data. So these established organizations on the other hands,
seldom have obstacles in obtaining computation power, hiring folks with expertise in corresponding
domains or accessing relevant data. The challenge, however, comes in scaling up the solutions to
massive user base. Any organization that would have a lot of unstructured data available on its
hand in the form of raw logs, however, developing data processing pipeline for them remains a task.
And for creating such resilient pipelines, apart from relevant technology, we also require the
skills to identify and curate meaningful data sets, unbiased data sets, from the sea of unstructured
data that we have. And that's where we go for search of data sources. And you should be able to take it.
So, yeah, so there can be like different approaches to building like a good quality data set. And like
we'll be like giving you guys some overview on like how we can approach that, basically some
pointers regarding that. But before we can do that, like, let me introduce you to three of our data
sets that we have collected ourselves. And these are available on Kaggle. So feel free to explore them.
So the first data set is clothing fed data set. So this data set was collected from our e-commerce
website called ModCloth. So there people kind of report their transactions that they have done,
and what all like they have liked about the product, and specifically whether the product was fitting
to them or not. So the data which we have here is user ID, product ID, feedback, size purchased,
ratings and reviews of the product that has been purchased, and some sort of like customer
measurements. And second data set we have is sarcasm detection data set. So these we have collected
from two websites, so the Onion and HuffPost. So past studies in sarcasm detection were mostly
done from like extracting data set from Twitter, but they tend to be like noisy in terms of like
the labels they have and the language they contain. So people use like lots of abbreviations, they're
like spelling mistakes. So we collected this high quality data set from two news websites. So the
Onion contains like, if you know about it, like sarcastic versions of like the current events going
on. And the HuffPost contains like real news reports. So we can treat them as like non-sarcastic. So we
kind of combined them and made this like one good data set. And lastly, like we also have like news
category data set. So this was extracted just from HuffPost. So these contains like real news
articles. And we have details like headline, preview text, tags, authors, and date published.
So essentially, if we have like news from different categories that could potentially help us in
extracting like exciting, sorry, I'm just kind of blanking out, exciting, yeah, exciting findings.
Sorry. So yeah, I'll be talking about those like later on, like how that is kind of relevant in our
case. So let's talk about searching for the data sources to build good quality data sets. So there
are like basically two types of scenarios that we'll come across. So first would be that we have like
a problem statement in mind that we want to solve using machine learning. So for that case, like we'll
be using a guided search approach. And second case is when let's say we don't have any specific
problem in mind, but we would like to like contribute something like worthwhile to the
community. So in that way, like we'll be using like unguided search approach. So I'll be talking
about like the guided search approach first. So this is where like we have like specific
problem in mind. And so the main challenge for this type of data search approach is that when
we know what problem we have to solve, we have to kind of formally state it out and understand
the problem thoroughly so that we can identify what all data we actually need to collect so
that like we can address the problem. So it could be daunting, but like we'll be sharing some pointers
so that it's like a little bit easier. So first step for that would be defining the problem formally.
So what I mean by that is let's say we are trying to solve this size recommendation problem where
we have like a customer and we have to recommend like a clothing product to them so that the size
for that fits kind of perfectly to the user. So defining the problem formally means like identifying
all the aspects of it and what are like all the variables involved. So for size recommendation
problem, like we can say that given a user and a product with different catalog sizes, we have to
recommend a product size that fits the user's best. So this essentially kind of lays out all
the variables that are kind of involved in solving this kind of problem. So after we have
done that, like we have to determine essential data signals that are involved in like solving
this kind of problem. So in this case, like as you can see in the formal definition, so we'd see
probably user ID, product ID, size of the product purchased and the feedback from the user are kind
of essential things that would help us in like addressing this kind of problem. So basically
these will then contain, these will constitute all the essential signals that we need to like
address this problem and we could have like other types of data as well like product category or
price, but they could help in solving the problem in a better way, but they are not like absolutely
essential. Then next is like data volume consideration. So whenever we are looking for
the data source, we have to see that we are able to build like a sufficiently large data set. So
for example, if we go to some websites that don't have like enough reviews on the product or let's
say if you are looking at like news website, they don't have enough historical articles that
they have published. So those might not be like very good kind of data sources for us to construct
our data sets and the reason is like if we don't have like a good enough data set where each let's
say entity has sufficient amount of information available, our machine learning models might not
be able to like learn good parameters from such like underpowered data set. So yeah, this was it
for guided search. Some pointers that can help if you have like some problem in mind, so like you
can follow maybe these pointers to see like how you can collect like a good quality data set.
So now the next scenario is like unguided search. This is let's say for like creative souls who,
so this could be like similar to let's say if you want to do research and you're looking for the
problems to solve, so this could be like drawn parallel to that. So if you want are looking to
make like data set contributions and don't have like specific problem in mind, like you can try
to follow this approach and see if like it provides any help and we'll be referring to the news category
data set for this because that was like specifically collected without having any problems in mind and
then kind of backtracking to see how it can be like useful. So yeah, so the biggest challenge for
unguided search is that it has like lots of uncertainty. So we don't know like what problem
we are going to solve, so there's no like proper structure in the way like we could approach our
search operation. Let's say when I say search operations, it's just like Googling on the web.
And so although it makes things a little difficult, but the pointers that I'll be just talking about
will provide some structure to that. So first like we have to see whether the data that we are trying
to collect, whether it can address some practical problem or not and whether it has the ability to
lead us to some fascinating insights or not. So yeah, to take an example like for the news category
data set, so we can train a classifier on this data set and it can help us identify some writing
style of the news articles, whether some writing style belongs to like a political category or humorous
tone or it's based on like fashion trends or something like that. And it can also help us to tag
and track news articles and understand how basically the writing styles kind of differ and so on.
Yeah. So then the next thing after we have determined, let's say that something is worth
estimating, we have to see that we have sufficient metadata available around that. So having enough
metadata will help your machine learning models to draw associations between like different
attributes and will help in ultimately like predicting the target. For example, let's say the
news category. So another example would be like, let's say if you are trying to predict like a
product price from just like user ID, product ID, so that might not go very well and we need like
sufficient data around the product, let's say brand of it and the fabric of it for us to able to like
give like a meaningful predictions. Now data volume requirement applies here as well, but this has like
a relaxed constraint because we are not looking to solve like any specific problem we have in mind.
So we can always like adjust the problem definition according to what data we have. So for example,
in the news category data set, like we had many instances where let's say there was some news category
which had less than 100 articles. So if you have some underpowered category, our machine learning
model might not be able to learn well, but that didn't stop us from making it a high quality data set
because our purpose was not specifically to predict some category, just that like we have like different
categories and if those have like sufficient data, then only like we'll be able to train good models
on it and make the model useful. So yeah, so based on the data availability, we can like always adjust
the problem statement. And finally, like this is just like, it's like a critical point, like we should
always, because there is some uncertainty involved and we don't know what all is out there. So if we
have some ideas, always try to check if something of that sort is already not on the web. So we don't
want to like duplicate the efforts and if something is already available, we just want to see, let's say
what are the shortcomings of those and try to kind of improve on that. Now, yeah, so that was some
pointers on like how to structure your search operation and now after, let's say we have collected
the data, like we have found out the data sources, extracted the data out of it, that is just the
beginning. So that at that time, we have like a raw data available to us, but still we have to like
kind of groom it for it to be like very useful to our machine learning models. So we'll be talking
about some of the techniques that can be used to kind of groom your data set. So first technique is
data trimming. So data trimming, so I'll take an example from the clothing fit data set. So there
could be like some reviews, so it's not always the case that all the essential signals are available
in each transaction. Like the data could be very noisy and if we don't have like a transaction with
fit feedback available or size purchase, those are not really useful. So and then our job becomes to
kind of let's say sanitize our data set, try to trim all the records which won't be ultimately
helpful in predicting what we want to predict. Basically, let's say I recommend whether a
particular product fits a customer or not. So we have to kind of remove those and one thing to keep
in mind is after we have done data trimming, like we still have to ensure that the volume is kind of
good enough. Let's say we are not like drastically reducing the data volume. So yeah, for the next
few set of data preparation techniques, Digasa will be talking more about that. So we've already
talked about how we can collect a data set and build a data set from different sources and in
an ideal scenario, we would assume that we are using a single web source to create that data set.
For example, for the clothing fit data set, we use mod-cloth. But there would be many circumstances
where we would have to gather the different attributes from different kind of sources to be
it for a more inclusive, meaningful and a valuable data set. So coalescing these data from separate
sets, separate sources into one unified view is what is called data integration. For example,
let's talk about vertical integration. Remember the data set that we had for sarcasm detection.
There was data collected from the onion which was non-sarcastic and then we had data collected from
half-posts which was non-sarcastic. So in that case, the attributes collected from both these
sources were exactly the same and all we needed was to integrate them in a vertical sense because
the attributes were the same. So we created a final data set with the label, say, one sarcastic
and non-sarcastic by combining the data from these two sources. This is called vertical because
the attributes that belong, for example, the headline, the author and is it sarcastic or not
sarcastic were kind of same across both the sources. The other could be horizontal integration,
which is when, for example, to create one single record of the data set, you have to combine
sources. For example, let's just assume we are building a data set for different cities and their
attributes. So we would assume fields like state, country, area, population come from one kind of
source and the others like administrative, religion, language festivals come from the other. So in that
case, you would be identifying one city ID and integrating them horizontally. In such case, this
is how you would approach the data integration and it is very important to try and make your data set
as exhaustive as possible to have as many records and attributes. Further down the line, when you do
feature engineering, you can always trim that, but it's always necessary to have a good quality
robust data set. And for the other thing, you also need to do data transformation to make it more
robust, as I said, because there's so much content available on the web these days that it's impossible
to check the correctness of all. For example, in the reviews or the content posted by the publisher,
like the product name, the product sizing, they have to be moderated to some extent. However,
people might use small, large, medium as sizes or someone would use like 12, 13, 14. So it totally
depends. Some people use different, just two letters for identifying the state. Someone writes
completely the state name or someone would just use like month, date, year or someone. So depending
for the date formats. So it's very important to sanitize the data, to transform it so that it's
all in one form for it to be a robust data set. And so to say, the data transformations,
a primary focus is to scrub the data sets raw values to remove redundancies and correct the
language and the logical semantics that you have. So the some, like some techniques for transforming
your data set could be handling special characters, handling grammar, spellings error, encoding the
sizes in numerical order, changing the format of date, etc. So these are just a few cues on how
you can scrub your data set. So as I mentioned that once you have your big data set, with all the
records and with all the attributes, it's necessary to proceed to feature engineering before you input
this data set as is to your machine learning model. So if you consider data to be the crude oil,
features are the fuel that we need. So feature engineering is nothing but applied machine learning.
It is also one of the key techniques and the processes that does not get the due limelight in
the machine learning workflow. Much of the success of machine learning algorithms is attributed to
the success in engineering features from the data so that the learner can understand. This is where
your intuition comes into play and you know, black art and creativity and domain knowledge. So this is
the step that should be considered much more important than the model itself or hyper parameter
tuning and whatever shenanigans people do and because machine learning algorithm as you said,
is as powerful as the data you supply. So you have to take care what your intuition says, domain
knowledge, trial and error. So that is what feature engineering is all about and choosing the right
features in right format can by far boost the performance using even using simpler machine
learning models. So it increases the transparency. You can better explain the model if you have fewer
features, but they are much more powerful. It reduces the need for heavy ensemble learning
techniques and also further reduces the need for hyper parameter tuning and model optimization.
So the bottom line for this entire talk would be that typical machine learning workflow looks
like this. You go from defining a problem statement to developing an intuition of how machine learning
can tackle your problem, get the data, process the data and defining the appropriate success
metrics, choosing the model that you feel would fit your problem the best, deploying the model
and then monitor it. The problem comes when you focus more on defining the success metrics and
choosing appropriate model and just get stuck in this loop. However, the focus should be on how you
source your data, how you create your data set and how you do feature engineering because these
form the part of applied machine learning and can boost your machine learning algorithm by 100x.
And that is what our experience has taught us. Even Andrew Ng, who is a machine learning expert,
has started a campaign for data-centric AI and he says that machine learning model is nothing
but code, like AI is equal to code plus data. And for so many years, we focused on code,
which is like how to create a more complex architecture, how to include more layers by
keeping the data stagnant. But now is the time that we have state of the art algorithms and the
focus should be on data. How can we enrich our data? How can we make more creative features and
how we can have more signals into our data to basically boost the performance of a machine
learning algorithm. So that being on the same lines, we've co-authored a book called
Sculpting Data for Machine Learning. And this is a QR code if anyone wants to check it out on
Amazon. It's also available on Kindle. And it talks about how to identify signals from web sources to
creating your own data set using Python, Selenium and all the other open source tools. And it also
does a synopsis of data preprocessing and feature engineering, introducing you to machine learning
algorithms from a data perspective. And we are glad that is endorsed by leading ML experts in
the industry. And you can read forwards by Lawrence Moroney, Julian McCauley and Mengting
Wong. And that's it. Thank you so much. If you have any questions, please feel free to reach us.
Thank you.