Open-source security team.
And today he's going to talk about us, how we can secure our open-source software supply
chain.
Thank you.
Dustin, take it away.
Thanks.
Hi, everybody.
Oh, it's so nice to be in person and have you all here.
So like Bernat said, I'm Dustin.
I have a couple hats.
One, I'm a software engineer on Google's open-source security team.
This is a new team at Google.
Our mission is to make open-source software that Google and the rest of the world uses
more secure.
I'm also a director of the Python Software Foundation, where I help ensure the long-term
success of one very big open-source Python project that you have probably heard of, Python
itself.
And I'm also a maintainer of the Python Package Index, where I help ensure the long-term success
of hundreds of thousands of tiny little Python projects that you might have never heard of.
I'm going to be a bit unconventional and start with a Q&A, but I'm also going to be the one
asking the questions and then I'm also going to answer them.
So bear with me.
And the reason is because I think there's some really important questions that we should
all be asking around open-source security right now, or the questions that you might
already have.
I'm going to try and preempt them.
The first is, is it safe to use open-source software?
This might be a question that you came here with today.
Maybe you've heard a lot about security challenges in open-source, things happening in the news.
You might have doubts or fears about the viability of using open-source.
So I'm here to tell you that is it safe to use open-source software?
Yes.
The reality is that every day all kinds of open-source software is deployed and somehow
it all works.
And as someone whose career exists because people use open-source software, I want to
tell you yes.
Like, yes, it is secure.
But you might say, wait, Dustin, didn't you just say that your job was to make open-source
more secure?
Doesn't that also imply that open-source software isn't quite as safe as it could be?
And so kind of also yes.
So I really want to say yes with like a giant asterisk.
And so basically it depends on how you use it.
And also it depends on what your threat model is.
You want to read that whole paragraph, catch me afterwards.
So maybe a better question to be asking is this.
How can we use open-source software safely?
If we're already using open-source, how can we use it more safely?
And if you're not, what should you be aware of?
So I want to start with what the software supply chain is.
Software supply chain is everything that it takes to produce your software, every other
piece of software, every piece of infrastructure, just everything that is a dependency for you
to create and use software.
So what is the secure software supply chain?
This is all those things and they're also definitely not compromised.
You may ask why is software supply chain security such a big deal?
And the reason is basically because virtually everyone uses open-source software.
Anyone who says they don't probably don't have a great idea of what software they're
using.
And in the past we made a lot of assumptions about how open-source software is created,
how it's distributed, how it's consumed, et cetera.
And some of these assumptions were that things wouldn't go wrong and these assumptions were
wrong.
But these problems have always existed, so possibly a better question is why is software
supply chain security such a big deal right now?
And part of this is because there's an incredible amount of scrutiny being paid to recent compromises.
We have all sorts of things happening.
Malicious libraries are published on package indexes.
There are new types of supply chain attacks affecting large corporations.
We have an unintentional remote code execution in an extremely widely used Java logging library.
That vulnerability was so fun that we did it twice.
We had an entirely new class of malware, protestware.
And we have SolarWinds, which I think just about everyone and their mother has heard
about by now, but this was described as a worst nightmare cyber attack.
And mostly it was described as a worst nightmare cyber attack because it was extremely sophisticated
and it directly attacked the US government.
But the main reason why so much scrutiny is being paid to the open source software supply
chain right now, the main reason is because of this.
Executive order 14028, which is on improving the nation's cybersecurity, which means that
actually the reason that supply chain security is a big deal is because the president said
so.
Does anyone get that reference?
I don't know.
So for anyone not based in the US or for anyone based in the US who isn't up on how their
government works, an executive order is kind of like an email from your boss telling you
what to do.
So this has the effect of setting policy for the entire executive branch of the federal
government in the US.
And it's also kind of like placing an order at a restaurant in the sense that you kind
of say what you want to happen and then people go off and they try and figure out what that
means and how to make it happen.
And maybe that takes a while to come back to you.
So this executive order was published about a year ago and we're still at the everyone
is kind of trying to figure out how to make it happen stage.
This executive order has a number of directives, but it specifically calls out the software
supply chain.
And if you think for a minute that this is just limited to the government, remember that
the government uses a lot of software.
They use a lot of the same software that you and I use.
So in terms of this order, they sort of have a viral effect of improving software security
for everyone.
This is a good type of virus.
So one last question you might have, how are we going to make this happen?
And that's what I'd like to tell you about in this talk.
I don't have all the answers.
I don't have a crystal ball, but there's some really interesting stuff happening and I want
you to be aware of it all and also how it might affect you.
So let's go on to part two.
Before I launch into a bunch of new tools and new technologies that you might have never
heard of because they were like maybe created last year, I want to take a minute to sort
level of understanding, define some terms, draw some parallels to stuff that you are
already familiar with.
And we're going to do the AVCs of secure software supply chains.
So A is for artifact.
An artifact is in this context a single unique blob of data.
It's probably a file.
You might also call this a package, a project, a release, a distribution, a wheel, a B-disk,
an S-disk.
They're all artifacts, right?
We don't really use the word artifact too much in the context of Python and packaging,
but basically you can consider every single individual file on PyPI as an artifact.
A is also for attestation.
Generally this means that there is evidence or proof of something and in the context of
supply chains, this is a cryptographically secure and verifiable proof that something
happened.
Really anything that you want.
But the attestation itself is metadata, which can be anything, and then that's cryptographically
secure which means it's been signed.
And it's verifiable meaning that I can go and see where the attestation was generated
and ensure that the output is what I'm expecting.
Don't worry, I'm not going to do this many for all the letters.
A is also for...
There's a lot of As though.
A is also for advisory.
An advisory is the public disclosure of a known vulnerability for an artifact or a series
of artifacts.
So you might call these CVEs.
They are created by maintainers or security researchers to share knowledge with the public
about a known issue.
And advisories only exist for vulnerabilities that we know about.
That's important.
B is for build.
Build is the process of turning a source tree, like a Git repo, into an artifact.
So sometimes this is also called compilation maybe.
Some ecosystems, they build on release and they distribute built artifacts.
That's kind of what we do with Python.
Some ecosystems only distribute source and they let the build happen when you go to install
it.
We kind of also do that with Python.
A build environment is the place where the build happens.
So hopefully it's not like your laptop.
Hopefully it's something else, maybe a little more secure.
But that's what a build is.
C is for certificates.
Certificates underpin a lot of modern security on the web.
And it's a way to derive trust from some root called certificate authority.
So in the past, getting a certificate was a long, lengthy, potentially expensive process.
And now with new technology like Let's Encrypt, it's very easy to get a certificate.
And we'll see how certificates can be used in the supply chain later.
D is for digest.
When I say digest, I'm almost always referring to a hash digest, which is essentially a unique
value that will reproducibly represent some blob of data.
And it's not reversible.
Think of like if you've heard of MD5, SHA-256, these are hash digests.
E is for ephemeral, meaning short-lived, transitory, disappearing quickly.
And when I say ephemeral, I'm almost always going to be talking about the ephemerality
in the context of cryptographic keys and signing.
So normally when you do cryptographic keys and signing, your private key is something
that you generate once and you try your best to never lose.
But an ephemeral key is generated on the fly when you need it.
It's used once or for a not very long period of time.
And then you throw it away.
I'll explain why I want you to throw away your private keys later.
F is for fuzzing.
Fuzzing is using special tools to generally wildly varying inputs and unexpected inputs
to your program.
It's not super widely used in Python, but it's generally starting to be considered a
best practice in terms of software security.
G is for Google.
Oh, hey, that's where I work.
I didn't have a great one for G, believe it or not.
So I wanted to take a minute to just try and kind of explain why Google even cares about
supply chain security.
Because you might have heard that Google has a monorepo.
And what this means is in practice, while software engineers at Google can use third
party packages, we don't install them from PyPI.
Essentially, a single version of the source is checked into the monorepo and then everyone
uses the same version.
And generally what that means is that a lot of the open source tools and technology I'm
sharing with you aren't directly applicable to Google itself.
But that's also a gross oversimplification.
In reality, there are teams at Google that do install software from PyPI.
And we also have lots of customers who are definitely installing software from PyPI.
And we want to protect them.
And we probably have to protect them because the federal government is almost definitely
one of our customers.
So we have a lot of experience in bringing untrusted third party code in and ensuring
that it's secure.
So we're interested in applying these things externally so that everyone can benefit from
it and that our customers and et cetera can benefit from it as well.
H is for hardware key.
This is different than a public private key.
It's a physical device that you put into your computer and it gives you the ability
to do two factor authentication.
It is arguably the best way to do two factor authentication.
They are not cheap, but I recommend getting one if you currently use two factor authentication.
If you're not using two factor, you should be using that as well.
I is for identity.
Generally, when we're talking about identities, we're referring to the identities of individuals.
Email addresses, GitHub handles, that kind of thing.
But we're kind of entering a point where pretty much anything can have a unique and verifiable
identity such as a workflow on GitHub actions.
These identities, along with some new technologies I'll talk about shortly, can be used as signing
identities, which is really interesting.
J is for Joe Biden.
Shout out to Joe Biden for the executive order.
The executive order is going to be great.
It's going to inject a lot of time, money, and energy into an area of technology that
desperately needs it.
A lot of people have been working on this for a long time and suddenly everyone else
is seeing the light.
K is for key.
We were talking about public keys before, but by the power of math, a key lets you sign
something with your private key, distribute that thing, the signature, and your public
key, and consumers can verify that it was indeed you, the key holder, that signed it.
L is for lock file.
A lock file is a complete itemization of exactly what artifacts should be installed for an
application.
This includes version pins and artifact hashes as well, hash digests.
Support for lock files varies from ecosystem to the next.
This is like go.mod, package lock.json, pip file.lock.
Python has historically been not super great about supporting lock files, but it is definitely
getting better.
M is for money.
Real talk.
We don't always like to talk about it, but software costs money to make even and especially
free and open source software.
A lot of the new tools and technologies that I'm describing were not created for free out
of goodwill, but in exchange for money.
Providing the security practices of the entire software supply chain is not a small feat
and is not going to happen overnight and is not going to happen for free.
There are a lot of organizations that are making huge commitments of money to ensure
that this happens.
N is for non-forgeable.
Non-forgeable is mostly used in the context of an attestation, and it means that the content
of the attestation, the thing that you're actually attesting to, can't be modified.
So if I'm attesting that I ran a build in some build environment from, let's say, a
get-sha and a non-forgeable attestation is going to tell me that it can't be modified
by someone, by some malicious actor.
It's only going to refer to that build.
O is for open ID connect.
If you haven't heard of this, I suspect that you're going to start hearing a lot more about
it both in this talk and afterwards.
So this is an identity layer on top of OAuth 2, and this allows services to provide, verify,
change identities, the identities that we talked about before.
So already a lot of CI services are providing OIDC identities for the runs of their workflows,
and this is really powerful for reasons that I will get to later.
P is for provenance.
Provenance is the paper trail.
This can take a lot of forms, but think of it as a series of verifiable attestations
that tell you everything you need to know about an artifact, where it came from, where
it was built, who built it, who signed it, everything about it.
Basically the history of an artifact.
P is also for policy.
A policy is a way that you describe the sort of security features that you want or expect
to be present, either in your library, your application, your repo, an organization on
GitHub, and ideally this policy can then be evaluated to tell you whether you're within
the policy that you defined or not.
Q is for quick.
Let's move on to R. R is for remediation, and it's usually used in the context of vulnerability.
It can also be used to refer to policies as well.
Remediation means to fix something that's wrong, and so for a vulnerability, if you
remediate it, you've removed the vulnerability.
You've upgraded to a fixed version.
And also ideally remediation is easy or possibly automatic.
S is for signature.
A signature is what you get when you sign something like an artifact with a cryptographic
key.
It represents a verifiable proof that the key holder was in possession of the key that
generated the signature.
Think of it as a rubber stamp of approval.
T is for transparency log.
Transparency log is a public immutable record of signed metadata attestations.
That's it.
I sign something.
I publish the details to the transparency log, and it is there forever for anyone to
look at and verify.
U is for vulnerability.
A bug in software with security-related consequences.
These are either known or unknown, and if you find a good way of turning the ladder
into the former, I want to talk to you afterwards.
And Z is for zero.
This is the number of questions I'll take about what happened to W, X, and Y.
All right.
I hope you enjoyed that.
So part three, how can we use open source safely?
Now I explained some of these kind of details and concepts to you.
Let's put them all together into something that we can do.
I did a talk on this last year, and a lot has changed in the last year.
So last year, what I said what we can do, circa 2021, is let's use HTTPS everywhere.
We're kind of already doing that.
Lock files, compile dependencies, vulnerability notifications, tough namespaces.
Cool.
I'm not going to explain any of that.
That was a year ago.
We've made a lot of progress.
You can go back and watch my talk if you're interested in those things.
I'm talking about what else we can do to fix this.
My talk last year, I kind of waved my hand.
Here's some hypothetical stuff we can do to do better.
And we've kind of started to implement that, and those things have started to happen.
So I'm going to outline those that exist that you can use now and introduce you to them.
So the first thing that's new is community advisory databases.
Actually, some of these existed before, but the Python one did not.
And this is a centralized ecosystem-specific public repository for a security advisory.
And the goal is to make it easier to both report and discover security advisories.
Remember, an advisory is a notification about vulnerability.
So these exist for most major ecosystems.
This is what the Python one looks like.
It's a PyPA advisory database.
And what it does is it has a list of vulnerabilities listed in the open SSF open source vulnerability
format.
OSV also has an API, and it acts as a vendor neutral aggregator.
And it pulls in advisories from all these different repositories and redistributes them.
So OSV actually pulls from this repository when new advisories are published, and then
actually in turn publishes those back to PyPI.
So then PyPI knows which dependencies or which projects have vulnerabilities.
Here's an example of a recent advisory for Django.
It's not a great example, actually, but it's kind of just a giant YAML file.
But you're not supposed to read these by hand.
Definitely not.
So the other thing we have to go along with this is vulnerability auditing software.
And so these also aren't specifically new.
Similar software has existed before.
But we now have for the first time a community-supported open source vulnerability auditing software
for the Python ecosystem, and that I'm really excited to introduce because I helped build
it.
And this uses the advisory database that I previously mentioned and the API that OSV
provides to PyPI.
So this tool is called pip audit.
I helped create and release this.
It's a third-party tool.
It's not part of pip itself yet.
You run this locally maybe as part of your release or your process, your integration
tests.
You can run it in a container.
You can run it against a requirements file.
And it will tell you if there are any known vulnerabilities present in your environment
or requirements file.
This allows you to be confident that you're not going to deploy something with a vulnerability.
Use it kind of like this.
You can audit local environment, just run pip audit.
You can pass a requirements file.
This behaves just like pip install, same flags and the same syntax and everything.
When you run it, it'll tell you, I found a vulnerability.
It's in this package.
Here's the version you should upgrade to.
Here's the vulnerability ID.
You can also automatically remediate that.
You can read that.
So this, if you run pip audit double-fix, it'll just go and upgrade those and fix it
for you as well.
It'll rewrite your requirements file to fix it as well.
So this is really cool.
I'd love for people to start using this more and just sort of avoid these vulnerabilities.
Go ahead and run it on your laptop right now and see if you have anything installed that
has a vulnerability.
Okay, another thing that's kind of new and fun and interesting is artifact signing.
And you might say, wait, signing is definitely not new.
Because historically, this has meant GPG.
And that technology has been around forever.
And if you're not familiar with GPG, historically, this post by Donald kind of sums up how the
Python packaging community has approached signing.
And if you actually read this post, you realize that the issue is not with signing as a technology
itself.
That's the boring, easy part.
The hard part is about trust and identity.
So right now, you can sign anything that you want on PyPI.
You can upload that signature alongside your release.
But distributing your public key is up to you.
And having people trust that public key is also up to you.
And so in practice, nobody does this.
Why?
First, GPG is confusing and unfriendly.
Who has manually signed something with GPG before?
Who enjoyed that experience?
Case in point.
It's not like automated git commits and things like that.
It's not a fun, it's not a friendly experience.
Second, GPG requires humans to not be humans.
It requires users to maintain their private keys essentially indefinitely.
I was talking to Paul before, I don't know if he's in here, and he said something which
I really like, which is GPG would be really great if you could go around permanently stapling
everyone's private keys to their foreheads.
You can't do that.
People will lose their keys.
Third reason why, GPG relies on a web of trust.
So GPG is great at signing.
It doesn't solve the problem of trust and identity.
Even if an artifact, let's say on PyPI, is signed, how do you know that you can trust
that signature?
It assumes that you or someone you know has met the signer, verified their public key
and their identity, and it's not actually a reasonable thing to do with the size of modern
open open-source software.
So we have a new technology called SigStore.
It's a new project by the Linux Foundation that's being built across multiple vendors,
including Google, and it's a new way to think about signatures, identities, and trust.
First, when you go to sign something with SigStore, you throw away your keys.
The first thing you do is generate an ephemeral public and private key, and that means that
the signing keys are used once and then they're gone forever.
You never see them, you never touch them, or interact with them.
You are supposed to lose them.
The second thing you do is you provide an identity.
This could be an OIDC identity created by an identity provider.
Right now, SigStore supports Google, GitHub, Microsoft.
Remember, this is built on top of OAuth, as well as some fine-grained OIDC identities
provided by environments like GitHub Actions.
The next thing you do is bind that key and identity to a signing certificate.
You provide your public key that is ephemeral to a certificate authority, and it gives you
back a certificate.
This authority binds these keys to the identity and the artifact, and sort of like let's encrypt
but on a micro scale.
You're getting a certificate essentially for every time you want to sign something.
Then you sign it quickly, because signing certificates are only valid for a short period
of time to prevent abuse.
Then you publish in the transparency log.
Every signature is stored in a log that can be searched and can't be tampered with.
This is used later when you go and verify a signature.
The end result is you have the artifact that you started with, you get a new signature,
you get a certificate that binds the identity you provided, which might be your email address
or your GitHub repository, to that signature.
Then you put that entry in a public log, which records all of it.
If this sounds like a lot of manual steps, you are not wrong.
This is why Sixdoor provides clients.
Originally Sixdoor was primarily focused on the container ecosystem, but it has now grown.
We just produced a new Python native client for Sixdoor.
It's called Sixdoor on PyPI, but you can install it directly there.
It's a native Python client for signing and verifying signatures with Sixdoor.
Not focused on containers, focused on signing any binary blob, but this could be a Python
package.
It could be anything you want, really.
This includes detecting ambient credentials, which means if you try to sign in an environment
that provides an OIDC identity, it will use that automatically.
Right now it just supports actions.
This is not feature complete yet, but there is a beta release now on PyPI, and we are
working towards a 1.0 release.
Some other things we can do.
Better, more secure build infrastructure.
There's lots of different environments, ecosystems, where software can be built.
Some properties increase security, others don't.
There's a new standard for describing the level of security for where artifacts are
built, and that's called SALSA.
I don't know if you can see that super well.
SALSA is S-L-S-A, Supply Chain Levels for Software Artifacts, pronounced SALSA.
It's a security framework.
It's not a framework in the sense of a tool that you can use, but a way to think about
how secure is this supply chain that I'm using to produce an artifact.
Given build process, it might produce an artifact that's also level one.
Another thing that is new is attestations.
Attestations are where we're going to prove that an artifact was created at a certain
SALSA level or at a certain level of security.
One exciting technology in this space that you might not have heard of is Intodo.
Intodo is a way to, well, here it is.
It's a universal standard for all ecosystems to describe the integrity of an artifact and
proof of what was done at each of the levels.
proof of what was done at each step to build it.
Make it transparent, make it public, show people exactly how something was built so
they can verify it.
New is also ways to enforce security policies for source control.
So we have some tools in GitHub right now built in that allow us to do this.
This is above and beyond what you can do with your regular source repository.
So All-Star is a GitHub application.
It enforces best practices, allows you to set a policy for your repository or your entire
organization and do things like branch protection, detect if you have checked in
binary artifacts, whether you have outside collaborators, enabled fuzzing, that kind of thing.
So I was talking about Six Store at Python.
Here's one that I just generated the other day because we had people that were admins
on the repository who weren't actually in the organization because we had just
transferred it there.
So this is cool because it will alert you when there's security violations that
violate your policy.
And the last thing I want to highlight, super exciting stuff, is new security features
for PyPI.
And these are kind of announcements because we haven't really publicly said that this
stuff is happening.
So I hope you're excited.
Coming soon to PyPI is voluntary two-factor authentication requirements.
So if you're a project maintainer on PyPI, you will soon be able to check a box that
says all of my collaborators must have two-factor authentication enabled or they will not be
able to do anything to this project.
The reason we're...
Don't clap.
There's a long list.
Clap at the end.
The reason we're doing this is because we're also implementing a two-factor mandy for critical
projects.
Don't clap.
Clap at the end.
Top 1% of projects by downloads plus some other critical projects like dependencies
of PyPI itself will be included in this mandy, which means that all collaborators on those
projects will be required to use two-factor authentication.
That's going to be a lot of people.
Most of those people don't have hardware keys.
I said hardware keys are expensive before.
What are we going to do about that?
We are doing a hardware key giveaway.
We're going to give away 4,000 Google Titan security keys to PyPI maintainers of critical
projects.
This doesn't happen yet because we're waiting for them to come back in stock.
It's too large of an order, but it's going to happen very soon and you will hear about
it and it's going to be very exciting.
Another thing that's coming soon, credentialless publication via OIDC.
One really nice thing that OIDC enables when you have it in your build environment is that
OIDC allows you to exchange identities.
If you have an authorized identity of a build environment and you've told PyPI, I trust
that identity to publish to PyPI, PyPI can exchange that identity for an identity on
PyPI.
I'm waving my hands here because we're not totally sure what that means yet.
That will allow you to publish a package to PyPI and say without passwords, without API
tokens or anything at all just by trusting the repository that has the workflow and that
identity.
Also coming soon, I feel like I say this every year, but PEP 458 is actually happening and
that's for repository signed metadata via TuF.
And PEP 480 is going to get a big update to talk about developer signed artifacts which
is end-to-end signing which you might guess what we're going to talk about there.
All right, to wrap up, what else can we do to fix these things?
One improvement is vendor neutral collaboration.
The reason that Sixstore and Salsa and all these things are going to be successful is
because we have lots of people and lots of organizations working together at these companies
via the OpenSSF.
This is a new nonprofit, part of the Linux Foundation that brings together all these
large organizations including Google to work together on essentially making the software
supply chain more secure.
This organization is also bringing and collecting more funding for security projects.
The cost of these projects is being supported by big vendors, but there's likely need for
support in your ecosystem as well.
So financially sponsoring your local Python Software Foundation makes things like this
possible, allows us to contribute to these security features.
Your organization can become a member of the OpenSSF.
And other thing is more users and more contributors.
Use these tools, come contribute, they're open source.
Try this stuff out.
Tell us how it works for you.
Share your experience.
Possibly become a contributor.
It's all open source.
So here's my predictions for the next year.
If you're an open source software repository or package installer or maintainer and there's
a couple of us in this room, brace for interest and funding.
And I hope you can ride that wave and make the most of it and really invest in your project.
If you're an open source maintainer, brace for people asking you to adopt new security
practices and ask you to pick up new features and do new things and turn on two factor authentication.
We're trying to lift the entire ecosystem here.
So you're going to get a lot of feedback from everyone asking you to help do that.
If you're an open source consumer, educate yourself.
You're likely going to hear a lot about this stuff more and more as there's this increasing
crescendo of voices and make yourself aware.
Real quick, I want to do two shout outs.
First to William Woodruff and Alex Cameron at Trail of Bits.
They've been instrumental in helping build both Six-Store Python and PIP audit.
Shout out to them.
I also want to give a huge shout out to the PyCon staff.
Everything they've dealt with with the pandemic to bring this conference back and in person,
they absolutely deserve your thanks.
If you see them, let them know that you appreciate them and the work that they're doing.
Thanks.
I'll see you all next year.