Hello, everyone. We are ready to start our next session. I'm very happy to announce that
we'll have Pradeep and Graham talk about how we can use the Python typing system to actually
improve the security of our application. Yeah, give them a big shout out and take it away.
Thanks. So today we're going to talk about securing code with the Python type system.
Very briefly, my name is Graham Blini. I'm a security engineer at Meta, the artist formerly
known as Facebook. And I focus on all things Python security. I do security reviews, framework,
stack analysis, and trainings for the Python security world. I'm Pradeep. I do work at Meta.
I work on the Pyre type checker and the Pisa security tool, which is run every day in Instagram
on millions of lines of code to catch security vulnerabilities. The way this presentation is
going to run, we're going to have a quick introduction, and we're going to spend most of our
time talking about security solutions that types enable. After that, hopefully you're going to be
sold on the concept of types being useful for security, and you're going to want to be adding
more or adding types for the first time to your code, and we're going to talk about how you can
do that. Then we're going to finish off with some conclusions. So to start off the introduction,
we're talking about this concept of security that we focus on at Meta called shifting left.
The idea is there's this continuum of bug badness, and the rightmost side of the continuum is the
worst place to be. It's when a bug is out there and it's been exploited, and that's awful. Things
have happened, user data has been compromised, whatever. We don't want that. So we want to shift
left. The next best case scenario that's still pretty bad is the bug is never found. We don't
find it, but the bad guys don't find it either. Better than that is when it's found externally
by someone who reports it to us, so through our bug bounty program or something like that. Even
better after that is we find it ourselves through some kind of manual review. So we've got a team
of security engineers, they look at the code, they find the bug, and we get it fixed. Even better
than that, and we're getting into good scenarios now, is when it's found automatically. So our
tooling finds the bug and tells us about it, and a human doesn't need to be involved to find that
bug at all. And then finally, our absolute best case scenario is we prevent the bug. We just make
it impossible for that bug to exist. And so these sort of middle pieces here, the human review
aspects where it's either done by a security engineer at the company or by like the external
bug bounty program, those are necessary, but they don't scale, right? You can't run that on
billions of lines of code, and you can't run that on all the changes that happen every day, too. So
the ideal state for us is always to have all of our bugs either being prevented or found
automatically. And now if we shift over and start thinking about a sort of a small security team,
either your open source project or a company that's not tens of thousands of engineers,
the only realistic place to be for security is in the prevented and the found automatically
space. I don't know how many open source projects really have like a team of security engineers
looking at their code or a robust bug bounty program, that kind of thing. So we want to focus
the talk on the prevention and the automatic detection side of things. And the thesis that
we're going to present in this talk is that typing annotations can help continuously prevent and
detect vulnerabilities. So you can be in those sort of left two spots where everyone wants to be
using type annotations. And the goal is you're going to end up leaving this talk, leaving the
thesis, and you're going to want to adopt types in your project if you don't have them, or
critically, you're going to want to improve type annotations in your project if you've already
got them. The way this talk is going to go is everything's going to be framed around a sample
application. So a simple web server that lets you load photos and look at them, and it's just set
up and contrived such that there are some vulnerabilities in it and there are some ways that
you can detect those vulnerabilities. The main two endpoints we're going to talk about are pictures
by user, and it simply takes a request for a username, you're looking for Susan's photos, and
you get back a list of Susan's photos. The other endpoint we're going to talk about is picture by
ID. You're going to give it a picture ID for what you want to load, and you get that ID back. So now
I'm going to hand it off to Pritip to talk about the first security solution that's enabled by
types. Thanks, Graham. So welcome to the first talk of the morning. I hope you all had some
caffeine because we're going to see a bunch of Python code on the slides here. So let's look at
the first scenario here. Let's say our toy website becomes popular and celebrities start using it.
One day we might get a complaint from a celebrity saying that their pictures have vanished. We try
to load pictures for that celebrity and get a blank screen. Looks like an attacker somehow
deleted all their pictures. How could that have happened? So a legitimate request for pictures
looks like this. You pass in the username for the celebrity, and the code for that is basically
something that builds a SQL query which selects pictures where the username matches the given
username, and you execute that SQL query and return it to the user. Digging into the logs,
we see something like this where the attacker passed in a weird username, and if you insert
that into our SQL query, we get something like this. In SQL, this is actually two commands. One
to select pictures and the other to delete pictures for our celebrity. So this is known as a SQL
injection attack where you're injecting the SQL into your existing command and thereby the attacker
is running arbitrary SQL commands or deleting or reading data that they're not supposed to.
In this talk, I'll use SQL injection as an example because many of you are probably familiar with it,
but what we see in this section will apply to things like shell command injection and
other kinds of vulnerabilities. So SQL injection has been known for decades now,
but it's still widespread. It's so widespread that the docs explicitly warn you never,
never, never use Python string concatenation or string interpolation to insert variables into
your query, not even at gunpoint. So what they say is don't use F strings like this because it
mixes the command with the data and allows the attacker to do mischief. What you're supposed to
do is to separate the command and the data. So the way you do that is that libraries usually have
some way for you to substitute parameters into your query. So here it might be a question mark,
you pass in the data separately. The library guarantees that no matter what data you pass in,
the only command that is run is this one. However, it's frankly more convenient to use the unsafe
F string approach. New users may not have read the docs, they may not know that a parameter
substitution approach exists or that F strings are dangerous here. So the point is it's not much
good having a best practice if the path of least effort is to do the unsafe thing. So is there a
way library authors can somehow make the unsafe approach inconvenient? So one option that you
might have heard about is a security linter. You probably heard of tools such as Bandit. So if
you have unsafe code like this and you run the linter, it will warn you saying that you're running
potentially unsafe SQL, change your code, which is good. However, in practice, we found that these
tools can be inflexible. So for example, if you have harmless SQL code like this, where there's
no user input going in, all you've done is just extract the query into a local variable, the linter
will warn you about it, which is frustrating for users because this should be fine. Likewise,
you might check a flag and then append, say, another part of the query to the existing query.
Again, there's no user input going in, but the linter will warn you about it, which is annoying
for users. So we wanted something that is user friendly so that people trust our tools and keep
using it. So it's not like library authors have no way to restrict how their API is used. For example,
if you try to execute a query such as 42 and you run a type checker, so just pyre or mypy or pywrite,
it will warn you right away saying that a query must be a string. You can't just pass in an integer.
You probably heard in the keynote where a type checker is just like a powerful linter that runs
all over your code and checks that inputs are always valid here. How did the type checker know
that an integer was invalid? How did it know that the string was expected? Well, the library authors
have specified that in the function signature. So they said query must be of type string. So this
is valid syntax in Python 3. It essentially has no runtime effect, but tools such as type
checkers can use it to prevent misuse of this function. So we wondered if we could use this
to prevent SQL injection, for example. So let's try that. If we have the safe parameter substitution
approach, the query, as we can see, is of type string. So the type checker is okay with it,
which is good. But then if we use the unsafe f string approach, the query is still a string,
and the type checker still accepts it, which is not what we want. We want to accept the first
approach and reject this unsafe approach. So the problem here is that the string type is too
permissive. We want something that is more discriminating. So that end, we introduced
a literal string type and recently added it to Python. You can import it from the typing module
if you're on 3.11 or from typing extensions if you're in earlier versions. So what that represents
is any string that is built purely out of literal strings. So say you have a function called expect
literal string, for example. If I call it with a pure literal string, the type checker sees that
this is what we expect, so it's okay with it. If I call it with something, say, if I try to add two
literal strings together, again, the type checker sees that this is, again, built only out of literal
strings. If you try to pass it in, it's okay with that, which is good. However, if you try to use
input, the type checker knows that this returns an arbitrary string. And if you try to pass that into
the function, it complains. So you can probably already imagine how we might use this for SQL
injection prevention. So if you could change execute to expect a query that is a literal string,
now if you use the safe parameter approach, we see that the query is a literal string,
so the type checker accepts it. If you use an F string, for example, now we're inserting name
into this query. Name is an arbitrary string, which means the entire query is an arbitrary string.
The type checker knows that, and it complains right away saying that this query was expected
to be literal string. So thanks to the literal string type, we can prevent the SQL injection
as you're writing the code. This extends to the earlier examples we saw as well. So if you simply
extract the query, the safe query in a local variable, the type checker sees that it's of type
literal string. It remembers that. And when you finally pass it into you execute, it's okay with
it. That's not a problem at all. Likewise, if you check a flag and append another literal string
or use string.join where all the inputs are literal strings, the type checker sees that
it's a valid input and it's okay with it. So this is user-friendly and people can use it without
getting in their way. Overall, the advantage of using type annotations like this is that it
shifts the burden of security thinking from the library user to the library author. So we're not
depending on the user to have read the docs or have kept up on later security vulnerabilities.
And by shifting control to the library author, we could prevent a variety of command injection
vulnerabilities across the ecosystem. We're not limited to the ones that the user knows about.
So I mentioned SQL injection as an example, but this applies to things like shell command injection
where you have a shell command, you're inserting user input into it which allows attackers to run
arbitrary shell commands or server-side template injection where you have web application and
you're inserting user input and that leads to arbitrary code execution and so on. So using
this single feature, you could prevent this vulnerability across a variety of libraries.
Finally, if you want to detect this continuously, you need to use a type checker just like you use
other linter such as Flake. So people usually set it up in their GitHub CI so that no one can
check in bad code. You can also run it in your terminal and IDE so that you get this direction
as you're writing code. And finally, a constraint is that type checking is only as useful as the
type annotations you add. If you don't use type annotations, you won't be able to get the benefit
of this. So overall, we hope that more library authors use literal string type in their sensitive
APIs so that programmers like you and me don't have to worry as much about command injection.
So we saw one security solution enabled by types. Let's look at another scenario here.
So Graham mentioned another API called picture by ID where we expect a picture ID and then return
the picture corresponding to that ID. So the code for that is essentially you do JSON loads on the
request that you get. You look up the picture ID field and then you go to the pictures directory
and look at the file corresponding to that ID. So here in this case, it might be picture slash one.
You read the file and return it to the user. One day, though, again, we might find our server
passwords being spread all over the internet. So looking at the logs again, we see a request like
this. And apparently, if you just run this, all our server passwords could be returned to the user.
They could see any other file on our server essentially. So how could this work? Once again,
we do JSON loads on our request body. We look up the picture ID field. Here it's not an integer.
It's a string like this. And now when you try to look up this ID under the pictures directory,
we essentially return our HC password file. So the attacker could traverse our file system
and look up arbitrary files. So this kind of vulnerability occurs when we trust that user
input matches our expectations, which means that they could do unsafe things. So the body is just
a string. We assumed that it would be a JSON object. It would have a picture ID field. It
would have a value as an integer. The user passed in a string and then made our code do unsafe things.
So we want to validate that our expectations are being met. You've probably seen code that does
manual JSON validation. So very briefly, it looks something like you write a function called get
picture ID. You could take a string, use JSON loads, check that it's a dictionary. If it's not
a dictionary, then you raise an error. You get the field that you care about. You check that it's an
end. If it's not an end, you raise an error. And then you finally return it to the user. So yes,
if you write all of this boilerplate, you will be able to prevent such an error and raise an error
when somebody tries to pass in a string. But as you can imagine, this gets really hairy for real
world JSON. It's inconvenient to have to write all of this boilerplate. It's error prone. You might
miss some cases. Once again, we see the pattern where the unsafe approach of just using JSON loads
seem to be much more convenient than the safe approach. So can type annotations help us prevent
vulnerabilities without this inconvenient boilerplate? Not surprisingly, the answer is yes.
Use runtime type validation. So there are a few libraries that do this. I'll use data class JSON
as an example. So you pip install it, import from that library. So we want a picture request that
is guaranteed to have a picture ID field that is an integer. So we say so in just as many words.
We say picture request, picture ID colon int. Once you write this, instead of using JSON loads,
you just use picture request schema loads. Now, if someone passes in a legitimate request,
we get back an object that is guaranteed to have picture ID of type int. But if someone tries the
etc password string hack, for example, you will get a validation error saying picture ID must be
an integer. So with just a couple of lines of code, we're able to prevent this vulnerability
and keep things convenient. This scales to arbitrary JSON. This was just like a small example.
Imagine you had JSON like this, which you don't need to go into. It's just something that has
nested objects, lists, optional fields, all kinds of crazy things. The code to validate that is,
again, just a few lines of declarative code that states our intention and validates that
JSON matches our expectations. So the benefit of using type annotations here is that we could
prevent vulnerabilities like external, unvalidated external data without much boilerplate. So type
annotation means safe code doesn't have to be inconvenient, doesn't have to be laborious.
And as we saw, it scales gracefully to complex JSON. It also serves as documentation for future
users and developers, which means it's good practice. And in the real world, Instagram
extensively validates the inputs to its Django, HTTP APIs at runtime. So there are thousands of
them. It validates them and which doesn't just help with correctness, but also helps prevent
security vulnerabilities like the ones we saw. So these are two examples of how
types can help prevent security vulnerabilities. Of course, there are many more. You can type
somehow help there or to grant. Thanks. So let's talk about a third solution called
data flow analysis. Or for some who are more familiar with this from a security perspective,
also taint flow analysis. We're going back to the idea of the photo. This is Susan's photo that we
talked about at the beginning. And the way that the APIs to load this work, Susan's friend is
going to be sitting there and her phone is going to send a request to this API. It's going to,
we've left this out before, but it's going to include like a user ID or something that identifies
her. And she's going to get back a list of Susan's photos. But from everything we've described so far,
when some stranger on a train that Susan doesn't know, not her friend, goes to load data from this
API, they'll send a different user ID, but everything else will be the same. And they're
also going to get the photos back. And there's kind of something missing from this, right? Like
a modern application has to have some concept of privacy built in. Like not everyone wants
everyone else to be able to see their photos. So this is the, you know, the simple loading code.
And you can see that there's no privacy check right now. Like you have this query that you've
seen before, SQL injection is still there. And it loads data from the database and it returns it
back to the user. What we really want is we want some sort of like checking function, right? This
is a really contrived one, but we just want something that has this can view operation that
says like, hey, can the current user ID view the photos that belong to this user Susan? So that's
what we want our application to have. And so this is talking about typing. Let's think about types
for a second. Like the stranger sends this request. Susan's friend also sends this request. They look
pretty similar. Only difference there is the user IDs. But when we talk about typing, like all the
types are correct, right? They're both integer IDs at a type system level. There's no difference
between these. So everything we've talked about so far can't help us solve this problem. And the
problem we're really trying to solve is like answering this question. Are we returning data
to the user without it passing through some kind of privacy check? One way we could try and solve
this is through security reviews. And as we talked about earlier, when we're talking about shifting
left, security reviews are good defense in depth. And it's possible that, you know, a security review
might be the thing that surfaced this issue in our application initially and told us like, hey,
you need to add some concept of privacy or whatever. But it doesn't scale, right? When we're
constantly making changes, when we're wanting to look at the whole app, security reviews just
aren't going to scale up here. So we want to go back to this concept of like continuous prevention
and detection. So to answer this question, we want a tool that can basically detect a data flow,
right? We want a tool that can say like data went from database all the way back to user and know
that like what a privacy check is and know that it didn't go through a privacy check. The way that we
do data flow analysis at Meta is using a tool called Pisa. So this is free and open source.
It's built on top of the Pyre type checker. And it tracks data as it goes throughout the program.
So you start off and you have some kind of data that you know you care about, right? So some source
of data. And it tracks it when it's assigned to a variable. It tracks it as you perform an operation
to add something to it. It tracks it as you convert it to a string, as it runs through different
function calls and gets returned by that function, as it goes through an F string. Pretty much any
transformation, any flow of data through the program, we want to track that data as it goes.
And we want to see where it ends up. Taking this and applying it to our concept of this application
where there's no privacy check right now, we want the source of data that we track to be the data
from the database. And the place where we care about it ending up is where the data is returned
to the user. And so we apply the data flow analysis tool. We run Pisa or there are other tools as well
that can do this. And we kind of want to track that and see it goes through this list comprehension,
gets returned. And eventually we say, oh, it went where we cared about. There's a data flow detected
and this is an issue. There's no privacy check in between here. And also with this tool then,
when we introduced that privacy checking code we were just talking about, we want to, we can tell
the tool basically this is what a privacy check looks like. And also we've updated the code here
just to call the privacy check version. And now when we do the data flow analysis, similar things
happening, right? We're seeing the taint flow or the data flow going through that list comprehension
and being returned here. But because we've taught the tool that this function is doing a privacy
check, it's going to stop propagating the data at that point and it's not going to detect it.
I've glossed over a bunch of details in depth here because this is not a long enough talk, but
you can teach a tool to do this. And now we have a way to differentiate between a data flow that's
problematic and one that's okay. Now, why do type annotations matter here? Like we've talked about
this data flow analysis tool, maybe you think that's cool, it's awesome, but like nothing I've told
you so far is how to do types. So to kind of demonstrate this, we have this little piece of
code, right? We're creating our SQL connection and then we're executing a query. Now, if we import
this create SQL connection function, it's unambiguous. Like, you know, I know the type
checker knows that we're calling the SQL, the create SQL connection function that we imported.
But what about this execute method? So you and I probably know there's going to be some SQL
connection class and it's got an execute method. But, you know, in our application, there might
also be this task class that also has an execute method. And the type checker, you know, from what
we've seen so far or what we're looking at right now, doesn't know which of those two execute
methods would be called on this connection object. What we really need is we need to know the type
of the connection object in order to be able to figure out which method is being called. And so
we need to update the signature of create SQL connection. And then the type checker is able
to infer, okay, the connection type is a SQL connection. And then unambiguously, we're able
to say it's the execute method that's being called. So at a really granular level, this is the kind of
thing that makes a type checker and types in Python really important to enable data flow analysis,
because then we can actually figure out which method calls are going where. That's at sort of
a very granular level, but at a sort of a macro level, like running on a whole application,
how important are type annotations? So we took a web server and it was like fully type annotated,
and sort of started stripping out type annotations and measured how many data flows that we were,
that we cared about that we could detect. And the effect was pretty dramatic. So on the right side
there, you've got like 100% of the data flows we could find when it was fully annotated. And
just removing like 20% of annotations sort of randomly across the application made us able to
detect more than 40% fewer data flows. So at the scale of a whole web application,
like type annotations and having really good type annotations enables complex analysis like
data flow analysis. So doing something like this, having a data flow analysis tool, gives us this
continuous detection that we talked about for any kind of vulnerability that can be modeled as a
data flow. Now I talked about a sort of privacy issue here, but so many security vulnerabilities
can be modeled as data flows. You've got service-side request forgery, XML external entities,
leaking secrets, format string attacks, the list goes on and on and on. And in fact, it can find
some of the same vulnerabilities that we also talked about preventing earlier in this talk.
As I mentioned, we do this at Meta using Pisa, a free and open source tool. It comes configured
for all your kind of standard web servers like Flask and Django, as well as a bunch of common
libraries that do SQL, shell commands, that kind of thing. So it's able to kind of detect all your
common vulnerabilities on your common web servers. It's also available to run in your CI through a
GitHub action. Now I don't want to oversell this tool to you without talking about limitations as
well. The first limitation is that data flow analysis tends to be too slow for interactive
use cases. So Pradeep was talking about type checking with Pyre and that can run right in
your IDE. You type an error and almost instantly you're going to see a little red underline that
says this is bad. With something like Pisa, you're going to have to run it in your CI and
wait a couple minutes to get the results. Next thing is false positives and false negatives do
happen. We're essentially trying to simulate an entire program and it's hard to do that very
accurately. And so sometimes you're going to miss things and sometimes you might find something
that's not actually a flow that you care about. So you'll get results from a tool like Pisa right
off the bat, but to get really good results and get really tuned the way you want it, you need to
invest a little bit of effort. And finally, as the graph on the previous slide showed,
type coverage is really important. So adding more type coverage is needed to get really good results.
But to sort of, you know, hopefully convince you that this kind of thing can give you really good
results, at Meta, more than 50% of the vulnerabilities that our products Qt team finds comes from tools
like Pisa. So we don't just do it in Python, we do it in Hack and Java and a bunch of other languages,
but this kind of data flow analysis tool finds more than 50% of the vulnerabilities that we find
at Meta. Now, hopefully you're sold on the idea that there's a lot of different ways that types
can add value and make your code more secure. So let's quickly touch on how you can add types
easily. Instagram provides a really good case study. Instagram went from no type annotations
to having millions of lines of code type annotated. And there's sort of three different ways that they
did it. One was using monkey type. Monkey type is a open source tool that grabs runtime type
information and saves that so that you can add it as static type information after the fact.
Two is Pyre and Fur. So once you've already got some types in your code, Pyre and Fur is able to
basically propagate that information through your code and use this knowledge of what types are
already there to figure out what types aren't annotated but can be known to be a certain type.
And finally, manual effort is still required. You know, Instagram didn't get to all that type
coverage just by running tooling. Sometimes people had to get in there and write some type
annotations as well. With that, we're going to finish off with some conclusions. As a reminder,
the thesis of the talk was the type annotations can help continuously detect and prevent security
vulnerabilities. If you had to summarize this whole talk in one slide and give you your
roadmap for what you should do when you leave this room, this is it. The first and easiest thing you
can do is enforce types at your API layer. So enforce the data coming into your system is what
you expect it to be. Next, you want to start making sure you have a type checker running locally and
in CI. So something like Pyre, but there's also lots of other type checkers you can use.
When you've got that going, you want to make sure that either you or your libraries are using
literal strain, which helps enforce and prevent injection and vulnerabilities. Then you've got
your type coverage started. You've got your type checker running. You want to start expanding
types as much as you can in your code base using Pyre and Fur, MonkeyType, manual work,
whatever you've got to do to get as good type coverage as you can. And finally, when you've
got to the point, you've got some good type coverage. Start running Pisa and start detecting
more complex data flow-based vulnerabilities. And all of these add up to great layers of defense
and depth that will help make your application a lot more secure. Thank you to so many people
who helped make this talk possible and who helped get PEP 675 landed as well. Here are some resources
and that's the end of our talk. We'll be hanging out in the hallway afterwards for anyone who wants
to ask any questions.