Good afternoon, everybody. Welcome to this next session. It should be an exciting one
here. We have Paul Carer and Alex Gaynor here, are going to tell us about shipping a Rust
Python extension many, many times a day. So take it away.
All right. Thank you very much, everybody. So welcome, everyone. It's nice and intimidating
to see you all in one room again. We're doing this talk as a cooperative presentation, so
I get the honor of introducing my co-presenter, Alex Gaynor. Alex enjoys describing himself
as a software resilience engineer, which is an accurate if understated way to describe
his passions. He currently works for the U.S. government at the FTC. However, he is here
in a personal capacity and is not representing his employer in any way. As for me, these
days I am a Zoom-based bobble head and I moonlight as a security architect for Oracle cloud infrastructure.
Again, I am here in a personal capacity, although if you're a cryptographic or security engineer,
I'd love to talk to you. Alex and I are the co-maintainers of the entire Python cryptographic
authority suite of libraries, but we spend most of our time and effort on PyCA cryptography.
The goal of this talk is to tell you about how we incorporated Rust into PyCA cryptography.
But first we need to explain why we did it. And to set the table, we think security is
important. As a cryptography package, we think our users expect that we go above and beyond
to keep them secure. After all, if you're encrypting something, you probably care that
you're encrypting it securely. PyCA cryptography depends on OpenSSL. We use OpenSSL for all
the cryptographic algorithms like AES and RSA. And before we did all of the work we're
going to describe here today, we used it for parsing structures like X509 certificates.
OpenSSL is written in C, and C is a pretty low-level language. This can be useful if
you're trying to make an AES function that runs as fast as is humanly possible. But C
is also memory unsafe. This means that it's very easy to introduce vulnerabilities like
buffer overflows and use after freeze. And indeed, OpenSSL suffers from these from time
to time, perhaps most famously heartbleed, which you may have heard of. A full analysis
of OpenSSL's security is beyond the scope of this talk. But in short, we think it's
both reasonable to rely on OpenSSL and we want to minimize our exposure to vulnerabilities
in OpenSSL. Paul and I have done a bunch of analysis. And in general, for large code bases
written in C or C++, about two-thirds of their vulnerabilities are going to be because of
memory and safety. Or put another way, two-thirds of these vulnerabilities are avoidable with
a different programming language. That's the case for why not C, but why Rust in particular.
Well, first and foremost, it's memory safe, meaning that as long as you don't use Rust's
unsafe keywords, these vulnerability classes like buffer overflows and use after freeze
are impossible. It's high performance in the same way C is. You can control the exact layouts
of objects and memory allocations. And it's got a very modern set of tooling, such as
a package manager, build system, code formatter, and even integration with Python bindings.
And it's widely used. At this point, many, many of the sponsors of this conference and
many other major tech companies are using Rust. Having identified that we thought Rust
was a good choice for PyC8 cryptography, that was really enough for us to commit to figure
out how we were going to use it. But we have another motivation as well. When Paul and
I look at the problem of memory safety, we see a problem that goes way beyond PyC8 cryptography
and OpenSSL. We see a problem that impacts operating systems and web browsers, chat applications
and video and image libraries. And we see memory unsafety vulnerabilities used against
women's rights activists, human rights activists, nutritionists working on a sugar tax in Mexico,
and ethnic minorities. And we believe something must and can be done to improve the state
of security that makes exploiting these vulnerabilities so practical. Part of improving the situation
is making it easier for more people to adopt memory safe languages. We have a pretty significant
place in the Python ecosystem. A lot of people rely on us. As you may have gotten from the
title of this talk, we have millions of downloads a day. We regularly are in the top 20 Python
packages on PyPI by downloads. We want to use that position to make it easier for the
next library that wants to adopt Rust to improve their security. As you're going to hear, we
have to do a bunch of work to make this practical and realistic. We want the next person to
choose Rust not to have to deal with the challenges we had to. So how did we actually go about
adopting Rust? Well, first we had to figure out which tools we were going to use beyond
the Rust programming language itself. And the first choice we made was which library
we were going to use for binding between Python and Rust code. We chose a library called PyO3
and it drops the CPythonC API. It's got a very ergonomic API. It's well maintained.
It has support for basically the entire Python API surface. And here's some example code,
creating a module with a single function in it called double that takes an integer and
multiplies it by two. We're not going to fully explain the Rust programming language, but
hopefully this is pretty reasonable, readable to you. And PyO3 handles a lot of the details
behind the scenes automatically for you, such as converting between Rust integers and Python
integers, noting when a Python integer is too large to fit into a Rust integer, all
the details like that. So we find this to be pretty ergonomic. And I just want to take
this opportunity to say that PyO3 maintainers have done an amazing job. The work we're going
to strive here is really a testament to the quality of the library they've built.
Now that we have some Rust code, we need to know how to build it. How do we make this
a part of the pip install process that everybody uses to actually get our library? We wanted
something that would be drop-in as possible, that would integrate with our existing setup
tools build process. Ideally, users would just have to have Rust installed and then
everything would work. For that we chose SetupTools Rust, which is also from the maintainers of
PyO3. It adds the Rust extensions option to the setup function, setup py, and it kind
of does what you'd expect. You point it to the directory with your Rust code and it will
compile it, put the .so in the right place, and you're off to the races.
So we picked our tools, and so we put together a small little PR, just a basic integration,
data module, one function, no problem. Everything breaks. So here's what we have to do in order
to get even the most basic pull request to green. Well, first things first, we need Rust
to be installed in our continuous integration environment, obviously. The base image for
GitHub Actions actually comes with Rust installed, so we're good there, but we also run some
tests in some Docker containers, so we need to install Rust into those environments. And
on top of that, we also used a service called OpenDev for continuous integration where we
also need to install Rust. Fortunately, installing Rust is pretty simple, just a matter of a
single line of shell script. Speaking of CI, we also used the Read the Docs service to
build our documentation, and it didn't have Rust installed in its environment. This was
also pretty straightforward, but we were able to contribute upstream here, sending a pull
request to the Read the Docs official Docker image to add Rust to that environment. Now
anybody using Read the Docs can easily build a Rust documentation for a project incorporating
Rust. Now we get to the more challenging pieces. For many years, CPython has supported something
called ABI 3 or the Limited API. The basic idea is in exchange for using only a subset
of the C API, you get wheel targets that are forwards compatible. This means you build
one wheel for all your Python 3 versions instead of needing to build one wheel for Python 3.5,
one wheel for Python 3.6, one wheel for Python 3.7, one wheel for Python 3.8, and so on.
We currently support five different versions of Python 3, so ABI 3 is more or less a hard
requirement for us to keep this maintainable. It's also a really important user experience
thing for when a new version of Python 3 is released. We don't have to scramble to get
a wheel out as soon as Python 3.11 ships. Unfortunately, PyO 3 didn't support ABI 3.
It always built libraries that targeted this full CPython C API. This was a pretty involved
fix. We had to send about seven pull requests, a few thousand lines of code, and refactoring
to the PyO 3 team. Again, they were fantastic contributing code reviews and even working
on this feature themselves once we sort of got the ball rolling. The good news is this
is all upstream now. Anyone using PyO 3, you can simply turn on the ABI 3 option and they'll
be able to build ABI 3 wheels with Rust. It's even nicely documented. We also ran into
some build challenges with SetupTools Rust and Alpine Linux and Windows 32-bit. On Alpine
Linux, the challenge is that Rust treats muscle libc, which is what Alpine uses, a little
specially, which the Rust maintainers agree is a bug, but fixing it's kind of hard due
to backwards compatibility. As a result, we had to send a pull request to SetupTools Rust
that has it detect when the system libc is muscle and pass the right flags to Rust to
not treat it specially. On 32-bit Windows, the challenge is that very often people use
a 32-bit Python on a 64-bit Windows operating system. SetupTools would get confused and
think it needs to build a 64-bit Rust library because it's a 64-bit operating system. Again,
fix was thankfully pretty straightforward. A small pull request to SetupTools Rust to
have it detect that actually it's a 32-bit Python on a 64-bit Windows and pass the right
flags. Going through all this was pretty involved. It took us a couple weeks, maybe a couple
months to get to the point where all of the different tools we rely on supported the
full range of functionality and targets that we and in turn our users need. The good news
is that this whole cost basically only needs to be paid once. Having done all this work
ourselves, it's A, been smooth sailing for us ever since, and all of this is available
to the next user who wants to pick up PyO3 or SetupTools Rust. We think we hit one of
that objective of making it easier for the next person.
As we did the engineering work, we concurrently developed a roadmap for how to actually ship
this. We are a foundational component of the Python ecosystem, and that has made us acutely
aware that difficulties installing our package have profound ripple effects. However, refusing
to drop support for anything or move to more modern solutions is also untenable for security
and maintainability reasons. We attempt to balance the two inherently conflicting requirements
as best we can. We're going to talk a little bit now about how we generally make choices,
why we think about these things, and how Rust altered our math.
Cryptography has, broadly speaking, four unofficial levels of support. First is what we test in
CI and ship via our binary wheels. These are, to use Rust's parlance, tier one targets,
which we have high confidence in and have thoroughly tested. Cryptography will never
ship a wheel for anything we do not test in RCI. Second, we provide best effort support
for environments we can't test but we are aware have significant use in the real world.
For these, we will accept patches and we will potentially even perform significant effort
ourselves to provide a reasonable experience. Examples of this right now include things
like ARMHF and MIPS platforms. Third, we have, yeah, sure, why not? Where we will accept
patches for less important architectures and OSs as long as they're reasonably written
and pass RCI gates. Finally, there's the set of things we consider entirely unsupported.
For example, versions of OpenSSL that are too old, Python versions we have chosen to
drop and arcane architectures where support would require significant modification of
the code base. A good example of this is something like S390, not S390X. If you want these things
to work, you're going to have to fork us. Sorry.
We have the data that we want to use but we get it from this big fire hose called the
PyPI statistics. How do we use that? First, usage of Python versions. We actually choose
to drop support. We would love to drop support when the upstream drops support. This is unfortunately
not practical. We drop support as usage drops under a threshold, like, for example, 5% or
less. Dropping a version for us is a concrete barrier because when we drop support for a
Python version, we tend to immediately start using features from our new minimum. This
means that there's typically no way to run our code on an older Python. When we began
this work, Kropotography still supported Python 2, but PyO3 did not. We had already chosen
to support Py2 well past when CPython did. In fact, we had made a decision early on that
we would support it at least one year past the final sunset date. And pip and drop support
as well. But this gave us an even stronger reason to finish our deprecation. Fortunately,
the statistics that we had showed usage dropping very rapidly, and this was not actually an
issue for us. Within the set of Python 3s that we were interested in supporting, which
was 3.6 and above, our Rust dependency that we were adding through PyO3 was not affected
after the work that Alex and the PyO3 maintainers had done in the previously mentioned contributions.
Next, of course, operating system. We support Linux, Mac OS, and Windows directly in our
CI, but we of course provide best effort support for other operating systems like FreeBSD,
OpenBSD, and even some more esoteric things. But of course, Linux is itself not a monolith,
and at the time we were looking to ship Rust, pip only supported many Linux wheels, which
excluded Alpine and other muscle-based distributions. This meant that adding Rust would, at minimum,
require Alpine users to install Rust C as part of their build process in addition to
the existing GCC and Clang requirement. GCC or Clang. I mean, you're welcome to install
them both. Obscure operating systems might also lack Rust targets, but ultimately we
decided that holding back the entire ecosystem for niche areas wasn't reasonable. Those unusual
edge cases can and should get LLVM and Rust bootstrapped in their world, much like they
did with their C compiler. So cryptography tests and ship wheels using x86, x8664, and
ARM64, both ARMv8 and Apple Silicon. We get occasional requests for various other architectures,
such as ARMHF or PowerPC64 Littlendian, but as previously mentioned, we only directly
support what we can test against. However, those best effort targets should still compile
and generally work, so we needed Rust to support at least the broadly popular CPUs in the desktop,
mobile server, and even some of the embedded world. Rust supports all these targets, along
with many more, but we realized that there may be some silent users lurking where this
could be challenging. So even though most of our users get a wheel, we do want to allow
users to compile their own versions. This means deciding on a range of open SSL versions
to support. We support various versions of LibreSSL and most recently BoringSSL, in addition
to all the versions of open SSL that we currently have supported. The PIP data that we get is
critical in making these decisions about when we can drop older versions, which frequently
carry significant support burden. But it didn't affect our Rust release, so I actually mention
it here only for the sake of completeness. And then, of course, as you might imagine,
we're interested in the version of the Rust compiler that users have available, so we've
recently convinced the PyPA folks to add that. So the data we had gave us reasonable confidence
that the vast majority of our users would either be entirely unaffected or would be
able to continue using the project with some changes to their build pipeline. But how do
we let people know this change is coming so they can make plans and invest in the areas
needed to ensure their chosen platforms still have access to this project?
We first announced that we were considering adding Rust code to PyCA cryptography on August
2020 on our cryptography-dev mailing list, along with a GitHub issue we invited people
to comment on. We followed that up with another email in December 2020 that also outlined
our general release plan, which we can summarize as the next release, which would be 3.4, would
include a Rust extension module which would be built by default but would not be required
for cryptography to work and could be disabled at build time with an environment variable.
The release after that, which we ultimately versioned to 35, not 3.4 for reasons we will
get into soon, would include a Rust extension module without which cryptography could not
work. In other words, we would depend upon Rust for actual core functionality.
This two-step plan was a result of community feedback, specifically Jeff T., so thank
you very much, Jeff, and designed out of a recognition that very few people follow mailing
lists or our issue tracker on a consistent basis. They wouldn't be aware of this change
without us putting it front and center, but breaking them with no escape valve was an
anti-goal. It was not our desire to break people.
So after all this, we released 3.4 on February 7, 2021. Hooray! This allowed us to both let
people know Rust was coming but also let people who weren't quite ready to add the
cryptography don't build Rust flag to their environment variables so they don't have to
immediately make changes to their build pipelines. Well, we expected feedback and, well, we got
it. So the vast majority of our users experienced no breakage in this transition. However, amongst
the minority who did, and to be very clear, we consider that minority significant and
important to us. There existed a subset who were willing to provide feedback. It took
various forms. It also started getting a bit heated. We also saw this release got some
attention in places you wouldn't expect, which ultimately spawned some other articles talking
about tradeoffs we had chosen to make. So throughout this process, we were taking
what we learned from our users and trying to provide improvements as quickly as we could.
First we got a bug in our new type hints, which there's a lesson there. Don't ship other
stuff with your big Rust change. We also realized we should provide more robust debug output
when compilation failed for people who aren't C and Rust experts. One of the unfortunate
things when we build these things is we become experts in the very things that are the most
opaque to the users who are having problems. So day two was spent improving our documentation,
making our errors even more debugable and generally learning from user confusion to
build more paved roads. And again, don't ship other invasive changes with a Rust transition.
After this, we added a test in RCI that tests for all possible import cycles because that
was really annoying. And finally, on the 13th, we released a version that dropped our MSRB,
our minimum supported Rust version, and also pre-announced a new versioning scheme. So
what lessons did we learn from all this? Well, one common point of feedback we got initially
was that while we documented the don't use Rust environment variables in the documentation,
it wasn't clearly linked to from either the error message or the change log. The flag
was simply not as discoverable as it needed to be. Errors out of PIP when compilation
fails can be extraordinarily verbose. So catching that and then emitting a more friendly message
with both a set of relevant environment information as well as links on how to surmount common
problems went a long way towards minimizing the time it took users to get their environments
working again. This is the difference between a pile of Rust C or GCC failed output and
one that has like a pretty output that says, hey, look, you should consider doing the following
things. And if those fail, please submit an issue. Additionally, for users who were willing
to immediately jump into our Rust requirement, we didn't provide enough information about
required Rust version or how to obtain it. Typically, users obtain their C compiler directly
from the operating system and the version barely matters. But in the Rust case, our
minimum supported Rust version was higher than some of the older Debian and Alpine installations,
requiring the user to learn how to install Rust up, which is an alternate mechanism of
installing these things. These items were potentially foreseeable errors on our part.
Our own familiarity with the code base and tooling required resulted in a failure to
systematically examine failure cases and think through user experience. We considered some
of these but failed to give users with problems good enough tools to fix their issues. We
also discovered just how many people pinned cryptography assuming semantic versioning.
When 3.4 made this change and their build pipelines blew up, this shocked them as they
believed we were breaking an unwritten contract. While Alex and I both have very strong feelings
about the value of semantic versioning in general, as well as specifically in the case
of security-critical libraries like cryptography, we also don't want to surprise users. So accordingly,
we re-versioned our library such that every feature release is now a new major version,
35.0, 36.0, et cetera, in the vein of Firefox's version numbers. A talk about versioning could
fill 30 minutes alone, so if you want our full hot takes, you'll have to find us in
the hallway track. Finally, when things aren't working and people are under pressure, tempers
run hot. We had passionate people both defending us and registering their objections to some
of our decisions. But an issue this emotionally charged results in that defense occasionally
looking more like an attack. And many users couldn't tell the difference between those
overly zealous defenders and the actual core maintainers. This led to a less civil discourse
than we would have preferred.
So having shipped a module that incorporates Rust into the build process but ultimately
does nothing of use, the next step was do something useful with Rust, you know, get
the value out of it that is the reason we're using it in the first place. Luckily for us,
we had a few concrete use cases in mind. First, we wanted to replace the small amount of C
code we'd written ourselves for handling things like cryptographic constant time operations.
And second, we wanted to replace OpenSSL's X509 layer and all of the parsing code for
ASN1 that it contains. There's actually not a ton to be said about the process of
replacing these things because mostly we just stuck to the best practices you'll hear about
any time you think about rewriting things. Make sure you have great test coverage, don't
rewrite everything at once, you know, break up your rewrite into small components, make
sure things are working all along the way, right, don't leave things in half broken
state. And so really the process of migrating to Rust is just a series of small pull requests
that keep tests running, add new test cases where we got concerned there wasn't enough
test coverage and attempting to measure how we were getting benefit from this. So for
example, even though our primary motivation in this effort was security, we also got some
really big performance wins. In the benchmarks we've got here, we migrated the parser for
the OCSP request class from an OpenSSL and CFFI implementation to the Rust implementation.
The result is it is now ten times faster than it used to be. This might come as a surprise.
OpenSSL is written in C, C is fast. C may be fast but it's not magic. OpenSSL's parsing
code performs a significant number of allocations and memory copies. Because of Rust safety
features, we were able to easily write parsing code without any allocations and without any
memory copies while still having confidence that we weren't introducing these memory safety
vulnerabilities we talked about at the top. We also got big benefits out of this in terms
of architectural improvements. Specifically, our X.509 API's implementation used to be
deeply intertwined with the OpenSSL implementation of other components of our library. This meant
we'd have APIs that said things like, takes a private key but in practice would be totally
broken if it wasn't an OpenSSL private key. Rewriting this code in Rust let us make the
API boundaries between these two components actually much clearer and now things like
sign a certificate with a private key in a cloud key management service actually just
works. And here's what our adoption curve looked like. The blue sectioner downloads
the versions with no Rust, the redder versions that contain the optional Rust and the yellower
versions that require Rust. There's really two things I noticed about this. First, adoption
of a new version happens in two phases. First it happens all at once and then it happens
slowly. Immediately after you release a new version, nearly half of our users will be
updated indicating they're almost certainly not using any sort of version or hash pinning.
After that, adoption increases very gradually. Right now we're at a point where approximately
80% of our downloads are processed in a facility that contains Rust and we'd like to get that
to 100% obviously. We know the blue section and no Rust is a mix of causes though. Some
of it is folks deliberately pinning to versions before we had Rust. Others are users pinning
to our 2.x series presumably because of expectations around semantic versioning that are not actually
accurate for us.
So we hope we've convinced you in this talk that Rust is now a viable choice no matter
how popular your project is. Much of this ecosystem work was done out of necessity
but the vast majority is now complete. We were also thrilled to see that other developers
took up the challenge to implement the muscle Linux standard across PyPA and PyPI which
gave Alpine Linux users access to wheels much like we already had for Debian Ubuntu, Redhat
and other G-lib C-based distributions. And of course we've hopefully weathered the storm
of legitimate concerns, well-meaning but confused people and angry trolls. If we can do it, so
can you. Next time you find yourself reaching for the Python C API to eke out some more
performance take a second and maybe reach for a nice cold glass of PyO3. There is however
room for future improvement here. For example alternate OS's such as FreeBSD and OpenBSD
are still required to build from source. It would be nice to be able to potentially define
standards where that is no longer required. Additionally to streamline the experience
even more we could investigate better binary build tooling, moving setup tools Rust into
setup tools or better integrations with CPython itself. The experience today is excellent
for most users but we can make it better. Oh and as announced via the Python announce
list and in this talk right now the next release of Bcrypt will be pure Rust. Thank you very
much.