Hello, everyone. Welcome back. We have a next talk by Paolo Alkein on software development
for machine learning in Python. Over to you, Paolo.
Okay. Now it's better, right? We will have like a constraint to my hands a lot, so let's hope that
it works. Okay. So first of all, welcome everyone. Thank you very much for attending. I'm very happy
to be here and thank you also to all the crew that made this possible and makes it possible
every day for this amazing conference we're having. I'd like for us to have the following
minutes discussing a little bit about something that is very interesting for not only for me,
but also in the latest developments that we've been having in the machine learning industry as
a whole and it's trying to discuss a little bit what kind of software development we need in
general in machine learning. So let's begin by taking a very simple problem, right? This is a
very well-known problem that happens everywhere. If you go to a tutorial of scikit-learn or many
pages that try to ease you into the classification problem, you probably are aware of the Iris
classification, right? Here we have the Iris flowers in which the idea is for us to be able
to classify them all by four of the features. The petal length, the petal width, the sepal length,
and the sepal width. And from these four features we have to figure out which of the variety it
belongs to, right? If it's setosa, versicolor, or virginiga. Just like a first disclaimer,
first of all, since these are going to be slides, you will see like the strings of the columns being
way too shortened, right? This is not something that I encourage. It's better to have like the
best column names as possible, but we are like saving real estate in the slides in this case,
right? But I want to say not in favor of naming columns like this in production code, right?
Now, the first thing that you can do when you take a look at this problem and how to solve it,
usually you like spin up a notebook or a Python interpreter or whatever, and you start working
with it as a playground, right? Like trying new ideas and figuring out how to solve this problem.
So a very, very simple solution to this problem can be this one here, right? A very simple solution
to this problem in which we are using the technical stack that is very usual for machine learning
developers or data scientists that is basically using pandas and scikit-learn, right? So you can
see like the bunch of imports in the beginning, and then we are basically loading a data set,
okay? From the data set that we've loaded as the CSV, we recognize the features and the target,
right? And then we build a classifier with the pipeline object that we have from scikit-learn,
right? In this case, this pipeline object consists of two steps. In the first one,
we select the two best of the features according to the specific criteria. Even we can choose if
we want to, right? And from those features, we classify them with a logistic regression
directly to see, to figure out which variety they belong to. This is like the declaration
of the classifier. In the next step, we actually do the fitting of the model,
what we normally know as training of the model of machine learning. And then we compute the
accuracy score that we have over the training set, right? This is only just to show one of the things
we can do. Again, I'm not saying that you should figure out the accuracy of your model on the
training set, right? But after we calculate the accuracy, we simply inform and realize
what's the accuracy score that we got. Whoa, I didn't expect that. There's something strange
going on with the slides. It's like I'm having like a sub slide under my slide. This is not being
shown here. Let me just try to quickly sort this out. Okay, so this is like live settings. Oh my.
Okay. Wow. Okay, so yeah, it looks like some machine learning model understood what I was
trying to do, right? Okay, let's get it from here now. Okay, it might happen again. I don't know how
I solved it, so probably I'll have to shoot it again if it happens. Okay, now this is what we have
as the playground, right? Usually, actually, this pipeline that we are seeing here is what I took
almost verbatim from the tutorial that you have in Scikit-learn when you try to implement the
pipeline, right? Now, when we have to put this into production, there are several hurdles that
appear when we try to put this tiny source of code in production, right? This is a very well-known
image from a paper known as Hidden Technical Depth in Machine Learning Systems. I recommend every
data scientist, machine learning developer, or machine learning engineer that hasn't read this
yet to take a look at it because it will allow you to see what's on the other side of your scope,
right? If you are a machine learning engineer, you realize what are the problems that typically
data scientists have when taking a look at, when working with production code and vice versa.
Putting things into production implies a lot of different challenges, right? I won't name all of
them, but basically, I think that the ones that we usually don't consider when thinking about this
are the, at least we as data scientists, right? Sometimes we don't consider the continuous training
in the deployment, the provisioning of infrastructure to actually do the training of the models, the model
tracking, and then how to serve it, right? This is only like a subset of the multitude of problems
you can see, not problems, but challenges you can see when you have to put this into production.
And one of the key elements of the paper that we are seeing here is that the machine learning code
that we've just built is only like a small part of this whole structure, right? And I'm going to
discuss today how we can make this small but very fundamental part of the code, how we can make it
work so it can serve the purpose of going into production and also having an easy exploration
for the scientist in general, right? So why do we say that it's important for the data scientists
or the machine learning developers to know how the codes are going into production, right? What we say
is that the developer experience of the data scientist is very tightly coupled to what production
looks like, right? So in the first example, let's suppose that we have a first data scientist that
does a couple of changes, maybe on this base model we've just seen, and deploys it to production
directly, right? By saying deploy to production, what we're saying is that he or she is the one in
charge of actually writing what we call production code, right? What is going to belong to the
structure we've seen before. Even in this case, it's clear that the data scientist or machine
learning developer has a lot of coupling with what production code looks like, but it's also
relevant to notice that if the next data scientist comes and they try to do some changes on top of
this, they have to be able to understand what the production code was, right? So the coupling
between the experience is both for the first writing of the code, but also for understanding
the code to actually do changes afterwards. Now there's another extreme solution, right,
that we can think about it. Let's put like a barrier there, right? We put the machine learning
engineering team between the data scientist and the production code, and we say, hey, you're not
going to be the one writing the production code. Don't worry about it. You just like think about
the model, think how it works, do it all in your playground, and I will be in charge of writing
this into production code. And while this looks like can decouple the data scientist from the
production code itself, the problem remains when the next data scientist comes and try to understand
what's happening, right? They have to get the latest code that we have into production, and they
have to understand what it means and how to work with it. Now this can be solved in many different
ways, right? One possibility is to say that the machine learning engineer is the one that's going
to explain the production code to each of the data scientists. Another possibility to say that the
data scientists have to talk among each other, and these are all like very usual solutions that work
in many different aspects. But today I want to discuss with you a software design solution for
the productionization of machine learning code, right? What if we can learn how to write this code
so that it works according to the following four pillars? The first one is that the code has to
have fast and easy exploration. We know that the solutions that we have for these problems are very
speculative, and the models change way too often, right? So we have to allow the data scientists to
work with new ideas on top of the production code. But we also want it to be declarative and
intention revealing, right? Martin Fowler put it much better than I probably can do, and one of the
things that he said was that the code is the only artifact that we have that is sufficiently
detailed and precise to act as documentation. This doesn't mean that we don't have to write any
documentation apart from the code, of course. That's not what I'm saying. What I'm saying is
that we have to seize the opportunity of this production code here, right? We have to be able
to take advantage of the code that we have in production, right? We have to make it as
declarative as possible. Another important thing that we need is to have what we will call sensible
checkpoints, right? We will then try to define better what I mean by this. But the main goal that
we have here is that if we have a pipeline in which we are doing many different stuff in the
whole production code, we want to be able to hook into a problem, right, with our own solution that
we had before and simply reuse one of the steps. And we also want to be able to hook out of the
problem, right, and use the previous steps as things for our exploration and so on, right? So
the reusing of these steps is very important. Keep in mind that sometimes it's even necessary,
right, because some of these steps can take way too long to run. And if you have to wait like four
or five hours for a step to run, you won't be able to do a faster and easier exploration.
And another very important thing is that we need to have seamless tracking and monitoring of the
code that's working in production. And by this I mean that we have to track the code, but we cannot
track it in a way that pollutes the declarative and intention code that we've just described,
right? Suppose the case in which we are seeing like the same playground code that we have,
but we have like 30 or 40 calls to log this, log that, and so on, right? This is a solution that
while it does log the model, it pollutes a lot the development space, right? So we want to avoid it.
Now with these four pillars that I've just discussed, we're going to do like a cautionary
tale on the productionizing of the model that we have just seen. Now this is the training file
that we've just written down. The imports are now collapsed, and they will probably collapse for
some part of the talk. But just keep in mind we're importing whatever it takes for it to work, right?
So this is the code that we've just had. And one of the things that we realized from the code we're
seeing here is that there's no way that this is going to go into production, right? Why? Because
the model that we've just trained in the classifier.fit line only lives inside the scope of this Python
file, right? We need to find a way to persist this model somewhere for us to be able to load it later
on to do whatever we need to do. For example, I don't know, like an online serving of the model
and things like. So the first thing we realize is that instead of checking the accuracy of code,
what we actually want to do is to save the model as a pickle file, for example, right? We know that
pickle is a library that's very useful for this, and we can load it directly with this very simple
two sentence here thanks to the with statement, right? Now, when we do this, then the prediction
part of the file that we have will actually load the model file that we have. And on an unseen data
set, this unseen iris that we're seeing here, we will predict and actually checking the accuracy
score here, right? Now keep in mind that this is just one of the possible implementation of the
prediction. Of course, we can do it this way. From the moment we decouple the training from the
serving, we can actually serve with, I don't know, through a REST endpoint or through fast API or
however we want, we are free to do it in any way. So consider these files as a token for all the
possible ways in which we can serve the model once it's persisted. Now, the first thing we realize
in the code that we've just written is that we are exposing implementation details, right? When we take
a look at these two things, we're saying, hey, maybe we don't want to tell in the code that we
are seeing how we are saving the model. If we're saving it with pickle and however it's something
and we want to abstract, right? We want to abstract it away. We know how to do it, right? We abstract
this into functions. We create the save model function and the load model function that is in
charge of actually doing this under the hood. The moment I do this, two things, two very important
things start to happen. The first one is that you can see in the train.py file that we've
just removed this with statement that was like maybe two verbose and put it in a declarative
fashion, right? Now we know that we are actually saving the model somewhere. But another thing that
starts to happen is that we've now split the whole codebase. Well, the whole codebase, just three files,
right? Anyway, we split the whole codebase in two different semantic spaces. One is the one that
we are seeing on the top. That's what we're going to call the library space, right? These are the
things in which we're going to develop all the tools that are going to be used in the application
space that are the things in the bottom, right? So what we are going to do now is work on the
library space to see how we simplify the application code that is what we expect the data scientist or
the machine learning developer to iterate on top. Now, after we do this, right? After we build the
save model function, yeah, and the load model function, this is now what the train.py file looks
like. See that this is important. That's why I left the imports here, that now we are not importing
pickle directly. We're importing from our own library the save model function. And now we take
a look at this that we have and we say, hey, there's something similar to what we've just seen going
on here, right? What's going on with this classifier that we have? Can't we do something similar to
what we've done with the load model and the save model? We have this idea, right? We need to abstract
them into functions. And with this idea, I will give you a little spoiler. This is where like the
fall of our approach begins. So I want to make it very, very clear. I didn't know how to make it
clear enough that this is how we start to go down a slippery slope that we will see what kind of
thing it goes beyond, right? So it doesn't matter, right? We don't know the spoiler yet. We're very
happy and we're like building this feed model function that what it's doing actually is loading
the classifier and doing the feeding itself, right? So this is the part of the feeding of the model.
Now, one of the things that we know and Sandy Metz put it in an awesome fashion in a talk that is
called, I think, All the Little Things. If you haven't seen it, I recommend you go and see it.
That when you're seeing this kind of pattern in which you have like a repeated prefix or a repeated
suffix in your code, what you're seeing is actually an object in there being tortured, screaming to
get out, right? There's an object here that we have to find out its name. And it's very clear here
that the object that we are seeing is the model object, right? So we do a small refactor and we
change the function that we have into methods of this model object. See that now it looks even
prettier, right? Because the classifier now belongs to the init part and the feed only does the
feeding. And the train.py file still looks very declarative, very intentionally building, and now
more in this like object-oriented fashion, right? Now, we're not only content with this path we've
gone through. We also say, hey, there's something similar going on with that asset, right? Can't I
do something with that asset similar to what I've done with the model? And again, I'm not going to
start like putting this into functions and so on. We already know like the end of this tale. We will
build the data set object, right? So the next step we do is to say, hey, maybe like the features and
the target that you are seeing here are part of an abstraction that is called the data set object.
And we want to give it a name, right? We have the data set. That is what we're going to do. And the
features we have written down there inside the constructor what the features and the target mean.
And now we take a look at the train.py file that we've seen. And man, doesn't this look like much
cleaner than what we had before, right? We have a much more concise code and we even got the chance
put our abstractions in here, right? See that now the model.fit doesn't take like the features and
the target like it used to before. It now takes the data set that we've just built, right? Our own
abstraction. Now we're very happy with this, but as I told you, this is not how the story ends well,
right? Because now all of a sudden someone tells us, hey, we don't want to pick always the best
two of these features. Sometimes you want to pick three, sometimes you want to pick one. Can you work
your code? Someone that is just trying to do an exploration of this data set, right? They just
want to see how it would perform if we didn't have to pick the best two features. And we say,
okay, we know how to do it, right? Let's keep calm. We know how to do this. Instead of hard
coding the two there, we pass the number of selected features of the parameter, right? And
now we are very happy because we've saved the day, right? Now you can pick the number of selected
that you want, right? The requirement is fulfilled. And all of a sudden they say, hey, well,
sometimes we don't actually want to pick. We want to do a logistic relation on all of the
numbers that we have. On all of the features. And we say, okay, we can make this work, right?
Because I'm going to put a contract with you in which if the number of selected that you're sending
is none, then I will completely disregard the selection step, right? And now this is feeling
kind of weird, right? I mean, having this comparison with none is not something that we enjoy a lot.
But also we are in the drift of making all these changes that people ask for us. And all of a
sudden someone tells, well, actually we don't always want a logistic relation. We want to try
out like a multi-layer perceptron. And we are like so deep in this train of thought that we've just
shackled us into that the only thing we can think of is just adding another if to this constructor,
right? This is something that happens a lot while you're trying to give to your library the
flexibility that it's needed, right? So now if the previous part was a bit eerie, now this is
completely terrifying, right? We have the comparison with a string. We have to raise an error if
someone even did a small typo when passing the classifier type. This doesn't make any sense at
all, right? I mean, we're not going through the right path here. There has to be a better way to
do this. And then we realize that the problem is that we don't actually know what is the model
that we want, right? All the things that have been changing, what I'm actually explaining is that the
model, as we said, is very speculative and we will never know what the model looks like. So the main
problem that we're having from the beginning is to say that the model has to be instantiated in
here, right? That the classifier has to be in here. What if instead of instantiating the model here,
we simply pass it as a parameter, right? In the constructor, instead of doing like all those weird
stuff that we've done with the strings and with the number of selective, with none and so on,
we simply say that the backend model, and I mean backend in terms of the one that is actually going
to be doing the computing of the feed, can be passed as a parameter in the constructor.
Now, this is what the model looks like when we start doing this and what we've just figured out
here isn't anything new, right? We haven't discovered anything. It's like a very well-known
design pattern of object-oriented design that is called dependence injection, right? Actually,
if you are familiar with the solid acronym, dependence injection is the D in the solid acronym,
right? That's how important it is. For us in Python, usually dependence injection just means
parameterizing something in the constructor, right? And as typical in these dependence injection and
composition mechanisms, what we end up having is the delegation of the methods, right? So the feed
that we are calling from our model class actually delegates the call to the feed of the backend
classifier, right? This is like a figure that you're going to see happening a lot when you
start doing dependence injection and composition. Now, this is what the model looks like and see
that what we have done is removing the coupling from the model that we've just built. We've
removed the coupling from it and the actual implementation that we want to do, right? Now,
the implementation is also back in the surface. So now we have this idea of dependence injection
as fixing some of the problems we've just put ourselves into, right? Then all of a sudden,
someone tells us, I want to remove a feature, right? From the data set that we had, I want to
simply remove a feature away. It's not something that is going to go into production. I just want
to know how the model would perform if we didn't have one of these features. And we take a look at
the code that we have and we say on one hand, well, yes, maybe some dependence injection can
help. I'm not saying that it doesn't. But nonetheless, if this is what we want to do,
we will have to re-implement the removal of features inside of this code, right? I mean,
we will have to write it, we will have to document it, we will have to test it,
we will have to troubleshoot any problems that the users are going to have. So what we're seeing
here is that in this data set .py file, there's something different that we have to do. And what
we need to do to answer the question of what's the challenge that is put down here is to reflect
on what we've done actually when doing the dependence injection, right? I argue here that
what we've done isn't only the dependence injection of the scikit-learn model in the model step,
but we've also exposed a known library to the data scientist, right? By doing the dependence
injection, we didn't introduce any dependency. The dependency that we are introducing is the
scikit-learn library that data scientists are very familiar with, right? They come already with this
stack. If they have any question, they know how to Google for it, they know how to go to stack
overflow, they know how to communicate with each other about possible solutions. So what if we take
this lesson from what actually worked from here, and we do a similar thing with the data set. Right
now the data set, instead of loading the CSV file and splitting into features and targets,
and the target, sorry, now it simply fills the data frame attribute and we leave it exposed for
everyone to use it, right? So the target and the feature selection are done in the application
code and any change that we want to make is right away, right? It's at the tip of our hands when
developing the application. So what is it that we have been building here, right? And I'd like for
the moment to reflect on how it is that this works out. What we have been building with the
data set, with the model and so on, are just abstractions, right? And there are many ways in
which you can define the abstraction in software engineering, but one that I really like a lot is
the one that Joel Spolsky wrote that is very simple but also cuts to the core of it, right?
That an abstraction is a simplification of something much more complicated that is going
on under the covers. And why do I like this explanation a lot? First of all, because it's
like in a very plain language, but also because it exposes the subjective thing about what's an
abstraction, right? What's an abstraction? What's an implementation detail? All of this is very
subjective, right? We cannot know beforehand what should belong under the covers. We don't know
what is much more complicated. Much more complicated for whom, right? Probably for the data scientists
working with Scikit-learn. It's not much more complicated at all. It's something they have been
doing for a lot of their professional time. In this article that is called The Law of Leaky
Abstractions, that is 20 years old, this still amazes me, right? It's 20 years old and to me
it's evergreen. Joel Spolsky writes The Law of Leaky Abstractions. What he says is that all non-trivial
abstractions to some degree are leaky. What does it mean to have a leaky abstraction? What it means
is that no matter how hard we try to hide the implementation details under the covers, some of
the things are going to go back to the surface, right? Some of the things are going to appear.
They're going to leak into application code, no matter how much effort you put in hiding them in
the library code. Does this mean that we don't have to build abstractions? Absolutely not, right? We
have to build abstractions, but we have to be wary of this because what we are seeing here is not only
like the law of leaky abstractions working out in the wild. We're also seeing pressure for these
abstractions to leak, right? The data scientists, the users of the application code are putting
pressure for us to leak these implementation details or what we thought were implementation
details. There is pressure for them to go back to the surface, right? So we have to make this
compromise in our own abstractions, right? We have to let the abstractions leak because they will
eventually do it, but from the moment we recognize that this is something that will happen and that
simplifies the exploration, we can choose how they leak, right? So what we have been building here
is not like simply a library. We're not trying to recreate pandas, nor recreate scikit-learn. What
we're trying to do is to provide a framework for the code development, and while we're doing this
framework, we're leveraging the knowledge of Python, of pandas, of scikit-learn that the
application user already has, right? We are using them in our favor, and this would work also in the
case of many other different libraries, right? If the library was PySpark, TensorFlow, PyTorch,
whichever of the libraries that we have in the stack, we can do a similar approach in which we
leverage the knowledge that the application user has and use it in our favor. So let's take a look
at how this tries to fulfill the four pillars we discussed in the beginning. First of all,
the fast and easy exploration, and I want us to think now that suppose that one of the things we
want to try out is what would happen if, I don't know, if we remove the long sepals, right? What
would happen if in our data set we wanted to remove the sepals that are longer than five? So
the exploration is trivial, right? Data scientists already know how to deal with pandas. They already
know how to write this query that is maybe like too verbose for us. We don't think about putting
this like this directly into production, but they can do it if they want to, right? So we are allowing
the possibility of this kind of exploration. But now, how do we make this declarative and
intention revealing? And this is where the power of abstraction works in our favor, right? Not only
the leakage works in favor of the application code developer, but the abstraction works in our
favor as well. Because we can remove the weird query that we had that can be much, much larger,
right? And with much more detail. We can abstract it and reify it into a method that is declarative
and intention revealing enough. So now when we take a look at the code in train.py, we are very
clearly seeing what's going on in here, right? We're not seeing like a query in pandas out in the
wild. We are seeing that we are removing the long sepals from the data set, right? Another important
thing here is what we've discussed as sensible checkpoints, right? The ability for us to latch
on and latch off the production code whenever we want. And for this, I want to say something. There's
a lot of stuff we can discuss in the checkpoints, right? From persisting to, I don't know, to change
temporal views and so on. But I'd like for you to consider the idea of exposing the basic types,
and by basic types here I also mean data frames, right? Consider exposing the basic types instead
of your custom abstractions. This is what is going to bring flexibility between checkpoints,
right? Because this is what will allow people to feed the features, to feed, sorry, to feed features
and data sets however they built it as pandas data frame, right? So we would prefer or at least
consider the idea of doing the implementation on top that has the feature and the target explicitly
written down there instead of the feature on the, instead of the implementation on the bottom part
of the screen. Now, I should say something. Just be wary when you do this. We don't have to pollute
completely the code with basic data types. This is like a very well-known code smell that has,
to me, one of the best names of the model. It's called the primitive obsession. We don't want to
be obsessed with using the basic types, but we want to know when using them is a good compromise
to provide the flexibility. How does this help us for seamless tracking and monitoring? Again,
now the abstraction is working in our favor. Now inside the feed model that we were seeing there,
we can add simply a logging line, right? With the custom logger, however we want to build it. There
are many tools to do it automatically. I'm not saying that you have to write the logger by yourself.
What I'm saying is that however you get to that logger, you can insert it in the code in the
app, in the library part without touching at all the application, right? And this is one of the
advantages that we have. Again, the abstraction playing in our favor for us to work on it.
One word of caution when you start to do this kind of stuff that is going to happen. The API
might be wider than what you expected. This is like a recurring theme when you're working with
library development is that you want to have your library as narrow and as deep as possible, right?
Not to expose a lot, but expose things that have a lot of depth, that do a lot of stuff,
that abstract several things. Again, this is something that we should strive in general when
trying to develop the code. But keep in mind that because of the abstraction leakage that we're
going to have here, we will probably end up with wider APIs than we wanted to. This is an example
that I write here that will probably happen the second you start doing this kind of development,
in which different people say, I want to load sometimes from a data frame, sometimes I want
to load from a CSV file, sometimes I want to load nothing, right? These kind of things are
going to happen and we need to make sure that we provide this flexibility. Always, as I said,
being very cautious about what you're using for exposing to the application and what you're using
for your internal development, right? This is like a distinction that probably you can make in order
to handle the complexity that will come eventually with this. Of course, if the APIs get too wide
eventually, you might think about doing a little bit of refactoring and thinking about how this is
a composition of different methods. But essentially, keep in mind that one of the goals that we cannot
we cannot forgo here is that we have to give sensible checkpoints and fast exploration for
the people that are going to be using our library. Okay, now as conclusions, first of all, one of the
things that I've learned while doing this kind of stuff is that what is an implementation detail
lies in the eye of the beholder. What for one can be a detail of very complicated things that we
actually want to happen under the hood. For some people, it's the core of what they are developing,
right? We need to understand the duality of the implementation and whether it's a detail or not
as quickly as we can so we can use it in our favor instead of fighting against it, right?
Another important thing is we have to allow the flexibility of the application code by letting
it speak the language of the developer. We have application code developers that already know a
lot about pandas, that already know a lot about CycleLearn, about PySpark, about TensorFlow. Don't
hide this away from them. Allow them to write the code in the same way that they have been learning
for their entire professional lives, right? Allow them to write things in a language that is common
for these application developers, right? So they can troubleshoot questions with each other. They
can even ask them in a wider forum and leverage help from different sources. Another thing is,
as we mentioned in the... As we just mentioned, some of the abstractions will eventually leak
to the application code. Instead of thinking hard about how we can make these abstractions,
how we can prevent them from leaking, we can just be in peace with the fact that they are going to
leak eventually. And instead of fighting them, channel them to leak in a way that allows us to
have the code with fast exploration that eventually gets to be declarative, that has the sensible
checkpoints, and that allows us to have seamless tracking of the experiments. That's it that I have
for now. Thanks.
Thank you, Paola, for the excellent talk.