Hello everyone. Today we have the pleasure of having Mr. Kidman present a paper on testing
machine learning models.
Yes.
Echo, echo, echo. Yes, yes, yes. Fantastic.
All right. Well, thank you everyone for coming. Testing and quality of ML systems. That's
what I'm going to be talking about. Just like they said, my name is Carlos Kidman. A few
things about me really fast. I'm the head of engineering at an AI company right now.
Before this I was an engineering manager at Adobe around an organization called Automation
and Productivity Engineering. We use machine learning there as well. I do lots of stuff
with open source including my own projects. The one I'm most known for is PyLinium,
which is just a simple wrap around Selenium and PyTest. I do lots of keynote speaking
all over the world. This is my first PyCon. Yes, I'm so excited. Yay, PyCon. I also have
a stream on Twitch once or twice a week depending on how I feel. Then I have a YouTube channel.
My most exciting one I feel is that I'm the founder of QAP or QA at the point, which is
the software testing and quality community here in Utah. Yes, Utah based for anyone else.
If you are a tester and you're in Utah, you should be part of this community because it's
pretty amazing. Going right into it. I feel like when it comes to software testing and
quality in traditional software developments, it's a pretty common topic. You have software
testers. You have people that are in the testing space like SREs, stuff like that. When it
comes to machine learning and AI, it's as if it's a new field it feels like. There's
not a whole lot that happens in that space. This is what got me really interested in how
do we monitor, how do we measure, how do we test and measure the quality of these ML systems
that we're building. Now that I've been in this space for about five years now and building
these models, they've definitely gotten better from when we first started even just five
years ago. Some people have been doing it way longer than I have. Like I said, testing
is relatively new to this space. Toolsy and Jacqueline back in 2019, they learned at Google
that if they didn't do software testing early and often, they ran into a lot of problems
once they deployed their models into production, once they deployed these systems. In their
talk here at Google I.O., they talked about here's some of the things that we learned,
here's some of the things that we do now and we try to bring in software testing as
early as possible. To make sure they're all on the same page, because I don't really know
where everyone is at, you may be brand new to Python, you may be a machine learning engineer
right now, I don't know. We're going to go through a very simple exercise here with a
very common machine learning application, which is prediction. Jay Alomar said this
really well. He said prediction is predicting values based on patterns and other existing
values. Once we understand this a little bit, we'll be like, wow, machine learning. Let's
say that we are the machine learning engineers at this grocery store and our job is to predict
how much we think customers will spend when they come in. Let's say we have this as our
data set. A group of one person comes in, they spend $10. Group of two, they spend $20.
Group of four, they spend $40. If I were to ask you how much do you think three people
spend, what would you say? 30, right? How did you come up with the answer of 30? Because
we're smart, Carlo. Yes, you found this magical number of 10, which happens to be the relationship
between the numbers in this table. If you were to grab three and then multiply it by
10, very easily, 30. If I said seven, you would say 70. On and on we go. Someone said
regression. Exactly. This is essentially how machine learning models work. In this case,
this is a supervised learning thing. Yes, it finds these relationships between the data
and that's what it outputs. In the top here, this is the paradigm of traditional programming
where we define the rules, put in the data, and then we get answers right back out. Let's
say we had a function that was called is even and you passed in the number three, you'll
have some rules in there to determine that it's either true, it's even, or false, it's
odd. Writing unit tests for that should be fairly simple. Assert that if I pass in three,
I get false. If I put in two, I get true. Machine learning is a little bit different
because here you input the answers and the data and the machine learning algorithm determines
what the rules are instead. The output is going to be different. What makes this difficult
when it comes to software testing is the fact that it is not guaranteed that the group of
three people are going to spend $30. They might spend $28. They might spend $50. They
might walk in and then just go to the bathroom and then leave. They might not spend anything
at all. Because of that, it's difficult to say, well, let me assert that $30 is the case.
Instead, you have these rules that get outputted. You have these ranges, these boundaries. It's
traditional programming. In this case, there's different points of fault inside of machine
learning system. One of the big ones is obviously the data set. The data is what drives the
entire machine learning system. If there's problems inside the data set, you're already
going to have issues with what gets outputted. Software testing can happen really early and
later as well. That's what we're going to be talking about today is the testing and
quality of these things. In software testing, we have this concept called shift left. Does
anyone want to take a stab at what shift left means? We were hired by data stack. I like
that a lot. Anyone else? Do it earlier. The white text there kind of throws it off. Anyway,
if you were to take the software development life cycle, which is usually a circle diagram
and it's like step one is planning, step two is design, step three is implemented,
and you deploy and all the good stuff. If you were to take that circle and flatten it
out where step one is on the left, step one is on the left, and the last step is on the
right, when we talk about shift left, we're talking about trying to bring a lot of these
quality and software testing practices as early in the process as we possibly can. A
lot of companies, they will do all of their development right in the middle. Usually,
you'll get requirements from UX or product or business. You build the thing and when
you're ready to deploy, you give it to someone else. They deploy it. They observe it. They
monitor it. They operate it. Shift left is talking about how can we include our software
testers, our developers, as much of the team as we possibly can as early in the process
because the more you are there in the design of things, the better things will happen downstream.
Let's say we take an example project that we're building, a new ML project, and let's
go through the process here so we can see what this will look like. Step one is we want
to define the problem. What are we trying to solve? In the previous example with the
grocery store, the problem was we want to predict how much people will spend. That's
not a very good problem statement though because why are we wanting to do that? It could be
that for the grocery store, we care about preventing understocking or overstocking,
especially with perishables like milk or dairy. If I buy too little of milk and then people
come in expecting milk, well, now I'm losing money as a business because I don't have
any milk for them. We overstock. We buy tons of milk, but then we only sell half of our
stock. Then the rest of my stock goes to waste. I lose all that money. It's also a problem.
It could be that we're using machine learning to help prevent the understocking and overstocking
problem. A much better problem statement than can we predict how much money is going to
be spent by people? Moving on, who is the ML system for? Again, back in our example
here, is this for the people doing stocking at night? Is this for the store manager? Is
this for the VP of the region? Is this for who's going to be using this thing? It could
be that the ML system is to feed another ML system. That could be the case as well. Who's
the system ultimately for? Then, of course, does this even need machine learning? When
I first started, you better believe I was like, wow, I know how to do a few little simple
machine learning things. Can I apply to everything? A lot of the time, the answer is yes, but
sometimes you don't want to do that. What the is even is odd. Imagine applying machine
learning to. Tell me if three is odd. Probably not the best example.
Moving on, number two is define, success, and assess risk. Success, assess. Man, English
is hard. You want to start by defining initial baselines. In doing this, let me go a few
more right here. That creative proof of concept is one of the most underrated pieces that
teams miss right now. Because it's so easy now to build these machine learning models
with things like transformers, for example, you can get to predicting things within a
few lines of code. You might try those out and say, well, this is good enough to start
just building things. When instead, if you build a proof of concept and actually start
defining these baselines for what success looks like and what risks you want to avoid
or mitigate or prevent, this is going to force you into building something that's a lot more
practical rather than the shiny toy that is a transformer, let's say.
We're dealing with a lot of data, so of course there's going to be privacy and security
risks as well. Again, another piece that a lot of people don't think about. Then of course,
one of my favorite questions here is do we even have the proper resources to do this?
If we were building an ML system that was meant to detect cancer in patients, let's
say, me, Carlos Kidman, am the worst possible person to tell you if this thing is working
or not. Even though I may be a software tester by trade, I would suck at testing that system
because I myself don't know how to detect cancer even manually. Do we have experts that
can help in our team to make sure that we're building the right thing the right way that
is actually helping? Another example would be sentiment analysis. I'd probably want some
linguists on my team, for example. Do we have the proper resources?
Number three is design the initial architecture. Which database or tables are we going to pull
data from? What does our ELT process look like? Is this going to be behind a rest service?
Is it going to be on a mobile device? It might not have internet, if that's the case. How
are we going to monitor this, monitor and measure it as we're developing it? What about
when it's inside production? How are we going to monitor things as well? Yeah, I'll just
keep going because of time. Number four is to collect data. Where is the data coming
from? This is a little bit different than what I asked before in the databases because
this might be our data is coming from recordings at a traffic camera. This could be we're recording
user session data and that's being streamed in. The different sources you have will also
determine how you do a lot of this as well. Is this different than staging your dev? Are
you just grabbing things from production and cloning it into a staged database? Or are
you doing some different filtering? How much of it is synthetic versus actual prod data?
Where are we storing the data? Is the data being streamed or batched? Basically, at the
end of the day, what I'm trying to get at is you've got to understand the data journey
that it's going through. It's not enough to just say, well, as the machine learning engineering
team, I just know that Snowflake has all my data in these few tables. I don't need to
know what happens before that. All I care about are my tables and that's enough for
me. It's really hard to do software testing if you're oblivious to what's happening beforehand.
Let's take a simple diagram here. This is a very simple ELT process. On the left, it
starts there and then goes to the right. We have our sources coming from user sessions.
Customers on a website, they're doing things and kind of like Google Analytics, data is
being streamed in. In this case, we're using Kinesis to stream the data in and loading
it into S3. We're using that as our data lake, let's say. From there, we have some
DAGs that do transformations and there's different transformations depending on where the data
is going to eventually land. For example, we have Neptune and Snowflake and we're putting
data in those places. As software testers, we care about every single one of these steps.
Why? Because each one of these steps, there's going to be risk in each one of those. If
down for whatever reason, then everything downstream gets screwed. We want to make sure
that we have not just testing and monitoring in place, but also fault tolerant practices.
If Kinesis were to hiccup, would we know about that? Would we be able to automatically get
it back up and going again? That's all part of software quality. We care about these steps
to make sure that once everything on the right hand side over here, you can't see it, but
this is probably where the machine learning stuff lives, that that has the best data that
you possibly can. When we say what's good data, we have to define those things. You
don't just get good data by writing these theoretical tests that I'm talking about.
Number five is then preparing data. Now we're getting into actual machine learning stuff.
Now you're preparing data. What shapes does data need to be in? What are the data types?
Are there any missing values or errors? Basically, poop data makes poop models. This is where
a lot of our machine learning engineers, the AI, the data scientists, they're doing a lot
of testing here already. I'm going to go through this part pretty quick, but already
lots of experimentation, lots of testing happens here. I have data analysts for things like
this and data engineers because I am not the best. We have these people because we know
that this ML systems, the lifeblood is the data. We want to have people, you may call
them testers, but they'll be data analysts in your HR tool, but they're still testing
the data. Next up, we have training and validating models. We experiment and compare models,
capture training validation metrics, visualize results, tune weights and parameters, and
hopefully using tests, exploratory and automated, to help you as you're doing this. In a previous
team that I had, they would do all of their experiments all locally and they would open
a new tab in VS Code and be like, here's the results. Then for the next run, they'd
open a new tab and be like, okay, here's the new results. Very manual process. Nowadays,
we have companies and platforms that are building tools specifically to help you track
all of your experiments and test results. Hopefully, you can use some automation as
well to help out, to speed things up. We'll have some examples here soon.
When I talk about validation, the reason why I call it that is because I want it to be
a little bit different than what we refer to as testing. Validation is how well does
the model perform against a data set it's never seen before? Even though, yes, you can
call it testing as well because it kind of is. You do a test, training split and whatnot.
I'm calling it validation just so that we don't overload the word test too much because
it's pretty overloaded. You can think that during training, maybe our model has a 95%
accuracy. Wow, so smart, so great. Then during validation, it's 76% accuracy. Some people
would say, well, this looks like a great indication of overfitting because my model knows the
training data really, really well. Yet, I'm saying testing is a different thing than
this as well. The only reason I have facial hair is so I can do this.
Step number seven is then testing the models. What behaviors does the model show? Does it
demonstrate harmful biases? Does it meet those actual privacy and security requirements that
we have? Is it performant and reliable? Performant in this case is, for example, can it have
a very large load of users using it at one time? Can it withstand things like adversarial
attacks which is now more about the robustness of the model than anything? Does it solve
the problems that we set out to solve? So the understocking, overstocking, is it actually
solving that problem or not? Or is it only doing a really good job of predicting how
much people spend? Then, of course, do our customers enjoy using our ML system? Sometimes
they may not even know that they're using it. That might be a good indication. Who knows?
Do they enjoy using it? A lot of people are wary of AI because, like, I don't want the
machines to do everything and they have, you know, there's some truth in that. So you want
to make sure that they can trust your system, they like using it, and they want to keep
using it.
Number eight is then deploy the model. Again, is this going to be, is the model itself going
to be behind the rest of GraphQL service? Is it going to be on a mobile device? Maybe
an airplane or self-driving car? Maybe it's a model to tell you that you need to restock
your fridge and buy some more eggs. You ran out. Or maybe it's supposed to give you diagnostic
information about a turbine, right? Is it a serverless function? Maybe feeding other
things? For software testers, when you talk about, like, a rest of GraphQL service, well,
there's lots of API testing techniques we can use, right? We can use the requests library
in Python in order to make these requests and see that the responses we get back are
good. We think of performance, we can use Locust IO to do performance testing and see
how many requests can my model handle at one time? Can it handle a million predictions
within a second? Interesting questions that you ask in order to test and, you know, measure
the quality of things.
And then step number nine, you observe and iterate. And this is, you know, you monitor,
measure, learn, insights, learn. This is, you're operating in production now. So big
terms like observability, operability, these things come to mind when I think of the step
nine. And if you're not sure what these terms mean, it's a great thing to note down, do
some research afterward because they're pretty awesome topics.
All right. So through all those steps, what we're thinking about is how can we prevent
risk? How can we mitigate risk? How can we detect risk or problems? Right? When I think
of prevent, that's where the shift left happens. It's not easy to prevent if I don't holistically
know what my ecosystem is going to have. If I don't holistically know the problem we're
trying to solve, how customers are going to end up actually using this thing, it's difficult
to prevent problems. Right? And so in software testing, we'll do things like risk storming,
example mapping, and different collaborative techniques. You've probably heard of behavior-driven
development. In order to get the team on the same page as to what do we care about, what
heuristics matter to us when it comes to this MLSystem we're building. Mitigation is, when
I think of mitigation, I'm thinking of things like blue-green deployments, feature flags,
TB testing. How can we prevent or mitigate as much risk as possible? For example, going
back to the cancer detection, I may want to just release my MLSystem to one doctor that's
working with us closely to say, how is it working for you, and get some feedback from
them. If things are working well, let me release it to the whole hospital now. Let me release
it to then 5% of my customer base, then 50%, and so on and so forth. Right? And then detection
is where you'll have test automation, because those kind of functional tests can detect problems
and that kind of stuff. So lots of different techniques you can use when you're thinking
about software testing and quality. So Zillow, this is a very common problem. Hopefully people
have seen this before. Zillow is a real estate company, and they wanted to build an MLSystem
back in, I want to say, 2019 and 2020, that would allow them to automatically buy properties
and then sell them at a higher price later on and make a bunch of money. They would hire
hundreds of people in order to do all this analysis themselves, and so they thought,
well, we don't need hundreds of people if our machine learning system can do this all
on its own. Sounds fantastic. And at the beginning it worked really, really well. But then eventually
it went down very fast. Right? They actually had to let go, I want to say it was like 25
to 50% of their workforce. They let go. Because, oh, there it is. Because there was a huge
problem. And this person tweeted on the right-hand side saying, I sold my house to Zillow last
week for 550,000. They called me to buy it back. I offered 350,000 and they accepted
it on the spot. So within a week they made $200,000 just because they took advantage
of the MLSystem that Zillow had. So what do you think happened? How could that possibly
happen where things worked so well and then eventually things went obviously so bad? Anyone
have any ideas? There's an adversarial attack. What was that over there?
Yes. Whoa, yes. Lots of different things, right? And I would say every single one of
you are absolutely right. What was that, sorry? Yeah, the feature engineering could have been
off as well. And yes, that was definitely a huge part of it too. There was a lot of problems.
So we'll go through this part really quick. But there was poor data quality. There was
it was easy to game the system. They were entirely dependent on the MLSystem. So there
was very little to no human intervention for this MLSystem. So it could automatically
buy properties and sell them however it wanted to. Now this was done before COVID as well.
So when I say risk from external factors, once COVID hit and the market went crazy,
instead of pausing the system going, well, let's take a second to step back, it stayed
on. And so as the market changed and it was trained on historical data when there was
no COVID, all of a sudden there is COVID and they didn't do anything about it. Goodness,
lots of problems. So the one that I took away from this was it was good at first and it
got worse over time. And this is one of the big problems that we have, not just in machine
learning but in software development as well. You have a team of developers, they build
something, deploy it, and then they immediately move on to the next task because that's what
we do. So it may have been great for the first three months. Oh, Carlos, we monitored
for three months and everything looked great. It's time for us to move on to the next thing.
And yet after three months, COVID happened and then things blew up. So this is where
the concept of shift right comes into play. Who would have thought, right? Doesn't that
make sense? Shift right. This is what happens post deployment and maybe during deployment
too, but post deployment. And so I mentioned SREs or site reliability engineering. A lot
of them live in the right because they care about what happens inside of production and
you have probably a team of people observing this and working with it. So I made this diagram,
a really simple one just so you can kind of see that instead of it being this linear thing
that I talked about, right? It's meant to be this infinity loop. It's meant to be,
and this is a diagram of MLOps by the way, but it's meant to be you continue to observe,
you continue to iterate, and you don't stop, right? There's going to be things that you're
going to optimize in your data collection, optimize in data preparation, optimize in
your training and probably retraining. If you're not doing these things, then you run
the risk of things like data drift happening to your application, right? And then immediate
biases like historical bias get introduced. So of course MLOps requires good processes,
testing and automation. This is much easier said than done, of course, as is with anything
that involves humans. It's pretty difficult to have something that's really robust that
everyone feels great, you know? But alas. So let's go right into testing techniques
now so then we can wrap it up with concrete things that you can take away. So the first
one is adversarial attacks. This is you trying to exploit the model, trying to find its weaknesses
and take advantage of them just like the person did with selling their house and then rebuying
it. So on the left here you see a turtle, and in this case the MLO system that's already
been trained, deployed to production and everything is identifying this turtle as
a rifle. I think this is a rifle, Carlos. Well, it's funny and yet at the same time
what are the potential implications or risks that happen because it thinks a turtle is
a rifle? Hopefully no one's walking their turtle and then the SWAT team shows up and
picks it up. On the right hand side here we have a stop sign. And in this case the self-driving
saw this as a 45 mile per hour speed limit sign just with a few stickers placed on top
of it. Now again this may seem like a really simple example but that's not uncommon in
the real world. There might be graffiti on the stop sign. If there's a graffiti on the
stop sign and doesn't see it as a stop sign anymore you're probably going to kill someone.
Interesting. Moving on, in this case this is security AI. On the left hand side it detects
a person very nicely. On the right hand side this person is completely invisible to the
system. All because they're wearing a colorful little square. And I have in my house right
now I have a security system like this that detects animals. There's a dog walking across
your driveway. It can detect these things. So if people can be invisible to this MLO
system, security AI that I purchased, that I'm spending money for, they can just walk
right into my house no problem. Well that's scary for me as a consumer, right? So become
the attacker. I'm going to go through this really quick. It's not only for computer
vision. Obviously I'm showing computer vision because it's the one that you can see and
look at. You don't have to be a data scientist or an analyst to create these attacks. You
don't have to know how to code either. If you take my course on test automation university
that is called Intro to Testing Machine Learning Models, I actually show notebooks and code
that you can use in order to do these kinds of attacks. Be a part of threat modeling.
If you don't know what threat modeling is, that's another thing to write down and do
research afterward. And then of course be creative and design tests and attacks. Sometimes
you have to be creative to find these solutions like us using the earth as a satellite. That
was pretty insane, right? Being creative with these kinds of things.
All right, now for behavioral testing. This is us when I talked about testing behaviors
and whatnot. This is what I'm talking about. Behavioral testing. This is beyond accuracy
in those lost metrics. You have to define those desired capabilities during design,
right? That's the shift left aspect of it. You can't just say, well, let's make sure
that turtles don't look like rifles. That might not fit your context of what you're
building. You and your team have to decide what are these capabilities we care about?
What should it be able to do and what shouldn't it be able to do? If there's a problem with
it, how are we going to raise that problem in an elegant way to our users?
The second part, testing behaviors, gives a more accurate picture of model performance.
This team that actually wrote this white paper, they said that they created twice as many
tests and found almost three times as many bugs because they were doing this collaborative
design, that shift left approach and then moving into development.
So what does this look like in the real world? On the left hand side, you can see the capabilities
that they defined. One of them was vocabulary. If you could only have 5,000 tokens inside
your vocabulary, well, those 5,000 tokens better be high quality words. For example,
the word and, probably you don't want that in your vocabulary, right? The next one,
any R is named entity recognition and then negation as well. Those are the rows. The
columns they had were different testing types. You have the minimal functionality tests,
invariance and directional. We'll get into some examples of this. On the right hand side,
they have a table of test cases that they're going to be using to test these different
capabilities. So you can see like on the right hand side, it says, I can't recommend the
food. They expected it to be a negative sentiment and yet the model returned, it was a positive
sentiment so the test failed. Enough of these tests they had and after all the tests executed,
it had a failure rate of 76.4%. Why does this matter? Well, it matters because, and I'll
go through this really quick, it matters because you're able to test multiple models at once
very, very quickly. Now I know this is a little hard to see. All of these rows here, these
are all the capabilities. So you see like robustness and temporal, there's different
capabilities here. But what I care about the most is this section here. This is the failure
rate for all the models they're comparing. To zoom in on one of them, they have the failure
rate for there's a model from Microsoft, a model from Google, a model from Amazon and
then Burt and Roberta. The two tests they have here are the companies Australian, that
should be neutral sentiment. This is a private aircraft, that should be neutral sentiment
as well and yet Burt had a really hard time determining this. And these were all state
of the art models. So again, past just the training and validation, there's more to be
tested, right? These behaviors especially. Now fair and responsible AI, this is testing
for harmful biases. So in this case, if you look at like this is, in this paper they were
trying to show here's data generation and in here all the red bits you see are different
types of harmful biases. Zillow had the historical bias problem where they trained the model
on things before COVID and then it sucked during COVID. Representation bias, measurement
bias and then as you're modeling and building things, even more biases, biases everywhere,
all around. So fairness, when we talk about fairness, there's a few aspects. You can
have fairness by data, fairness by measurement and modeling and fairness by design. Let's
go through some examples. Back in 2017, Google wanted to create an MLS system that could
detect toxicity online. This would be great for moderators in a chat room, maybe a video
game or whatnot, right? So on the top they had, if they put in I am straight, the model
said this is 4% toxic, basically not toxic at all. But if you put in I am gay, the model
said this is 86% toxic, showing a harmful bias. So they decided, well, I wonder what
other things it has a harmful bias with our system. So they put I am gay, queer, Muslim,
Jewish, Christian, straight and notice the score of how toxic the machine learning system
saw this as. While us changing just the token, that is an example of invariance testing.
If I only change one word, does it change sentiment? How positive or negative, in this
case how toxic does this become? You can measure these things and do a lot of software testing
against them. In this case, this is Google Translate. On the left-hand side you have
Turkish. Turkish doesn't have gender. For example, in Spanish you do, right, like you
have lasilla and things like that. When it translated to English, it automatically assumed
that a nurse is she and doctor is he, showing a harmful bias, right? Another example, Casey
is my friend, how do we know if Casey is male, how do we know if they are female, non-binary?
We don't. We don't have that context. So by design what they did instead was how about
we show them the different answers and the user can select the option that matches their
context. So when I want to translate friend into Spanish, you get amigo or amiga, which
one fits what you're trying to do. So to recap, we have the shift left, shift right,
adversarial attacks, testing behaviors and the overall experience, test fairness, harmful
biases, and of course, hopefully this helps you get some ideas as to what you can search,
different testing techniques you can use in order to test for these different things.
And if you need help, software testers are here. You should leverage them because they
can help you out. We need better testing all around in a very holistic way. So with that
said, that's it. That's all I have for this presentation. I do have code examples for
anyone that is interested in seeing how these tests can be written in a test automation
format, but otherwise I'm ready for questions or I think we're actually close to time.
So thank you.