Hi, I'm David Foster, and yeah, welcome to the typing summit.
So I thought it might be useful to present a roundup of some new typing features that
are in the current version of Python that we have right now, Python 3.10, and the new
version of Python that's coming up later this year, Python 3.11.
So I'm just going to go through them somewhat quickly.
First, I guess I should introduce myself a little bit further.
David Foster, contributor to MyPy and especially typed dict.
When I'm not doing open source, I am chief technology officer at TechSmartt where we
are bringing world-class computer science education to the next generation of K-12 students
and teachers.
So getting kids excited about coding.
And you can find me online at these places.
So a couple of years ago, just last year actually, just in early 2021, I wrote an article that
was proclaiming that Python was in the middle of a type checking renaissance because we've
had so many peps recently that are introducing new typing related features.
And this year, 2022, no exception to that.
So as mentioned, I am hoping to in this talk to go through some of the specific features
that are in both the current version of Python and the new version of Python 3.11 that will
be released later this year.
So let's talk about where we are right now with Python 3.10.
We've got four typing related peps here.
A couple that are introducing new kinds of types.
So param, spec and type guard.
There's other types of notation that's been added.
And one theme that I think is recurring is eliminating imports required from the typing
module itself, which makes typing annotations more easy to use.
So just to go through some of these briefly, I'll show an example of code before the introduction
of the feature and what you can do after the feature.
In 3.10, the first thing I have up is param spec, which is particularly useful for annotating
decorators.
Before it was difficult to annotate, annotate the types of parameters that you put into
a callable in particular.
The dot dot dot that I have here is actually what you write.
Dot dot dot.
It's not a placeholder.
The type checker isn't able to understand in this case that there's an association between
the input callables parameters and the output callables parameters.
But if you introduce a param spec, you can use that as a placeholder for any set of parameters.
And so then it becomes possible to have this decorator nicely typed, which has been a problem
for some time.
So you can do that now.
Moving on.
Type guard.
So this is particularly common in JavaScript, but it also happens in Python where you have
a function that is used to check whether something is of a particular property that a type checker
can't figure out.
So in this case, we have an example of a function that checks whether something is a list of
strings.
So we have a function that just returns a bool here, which is okay, but it would be
nice that if you called this function and it returned true, that a type checker could
narrow the type of the thing that you pass to this function to be a str of list.
And with type guard, you can do that.
If you set the return type to type guard list of str, you return true.
Narrowing happens.
Beautiful.
Moving on.
Type alias.
So in Python, we've had the ability to define type aliases for a long time implicitly by
assigning effectively a type expression to a variable.
And then that is interpreted by type checkers as a type alias.
However, there are cases where you want to be explicit that that's actually what you're
doing.
And at the moment, if you do something very similar, which is you assign a stringified
type expression to a variable, a type checker will not be able to figure out that you actually
wanted to make a type alias there.
So now with type alias, you can make the otherwise implicit aliases explicit, and you can now
use forward references for stringified references, which is useful.
So that's kind of cool.
Next up, one of my favorites, is the ability to write union types and optional types, which
is a variable or the constant none using the pipe operator.
So this eliminates a few imports from the typing module.
So no more import from typing module, and you don't have to type as much either because
Instead of writing union, you can use a pipe.
Instead of writing optional, you can just say pipe none.
Works great, is explicit.
So that's Python 3.10.
That's what we have access to today in the final release.
There is also Python 3.11, which is just about to enter its first beta, I believe, either
today or tomorrow.
I heard a clarification.
Next week, okay, 3.10 beta one next week.
So these types of types are now available.
So we have, let's see, one, two, three, four, five, peps here, so I'll just briefly go through
those as well.
So let's talk about literal string.
So there are a number of APIs that expect some kind of fixed format string, a command
string of some kind.
And in the documentation for such APIs, they may say that you really should just use a
string literal, but there's no way for it to actually enforce that because that's just
in the documentation.
So common cases, you have something that's running like a SQL command, or as a second
example I'll show you in a moment, if you're writing a format string to a logging function.
So right now there's no way to tell a type checker that this string that you're passing
in should be a literal.
But with a literal string, you can actually annotate it that there should be specifically
a literal passed in.
And if you don't do that, a type checker will tell you that that's no good.
So that's pretty cool.
So you can avoid command injection for people who use APIs with literal string who also
are running type checkers on their code base.
And for many large code bases, this is already done.
So as mentioned, there's a second example here of formatting strings, which is another
type of command string.
And in particular, we had an issue recently with log4j, where you had some unexpected
use of things in command strings.
And that would be harder to exploit if you had something like this used to type annotate
a function expecting a format string.
So that's literal string.
Type guard double.
So this is interesting.
So there are a couple of libraries that define array-like classes.
So NumPy's ndArray class, TensorFlow's tensor class.
In there are many cases where the data inside these has either a particular set of expected
data types or dimensions.
And right now, the only way that you can...
Right now, you can only put that information in comments and documentation.
It's not enforceable automatically in any way.
So here, I've just got a comment here that's saying, like, this is a image, and it happens
to have a height and width as its dimensions here.
But with type guard double, you can define array types that you can just give generic
properties for each of either the dimensions or the data types or whatever property that
you think is useful to be enforced as consistent.
So here, we're doing...
You can actually just say height and width explicitly.
And because they're new types, it won't allow you to, like, mix them up.
Like, instead of height width, maybe you put width height.
Easy to get it mixed up if you have column-based ordering versus row-based ordering.
So that's type guard double.
Self.
So there are a number of APIs that are written in a so-called fluent style, where you have
methods that...
On a class that return the same instance of that class after they finish.
So they return self at the end.
Before it was possible, although rather cumbersome and verbose, to annotate the return type of
such methods to describe to the type checker that it's actually still returning self.
You can do that with this fancy thing with a type bar.
Well, now you can just do it directly.
So if a function returns the value self, you can also say that in its signature that returns
the type of self, and it will do all of that magic for you, which is great.
Data class transform.
So this one's interesting.
So there are a number of libraries that define things like data class, model classes of various
kinds.
So you have adders, there's an old one, pydantic is a newer one, but there are many of these
libraries that define classes that act like the built-in data class.
And right now, in order for a type checker to support these various libraries, there
has to be a special plugin that is written for each library and each type checker.
So a lot of times these plugins simply don't get written.
Well, now there's a way for library authors who are making something like a pydantic model
or an adders-based model to specify on those sort of meta models effectively, they can
add this data class transform decorator, which tells type checkers that it acts like a data
class.
And so then you don't need the definer of the meta model, doesn't need to start writing
a series of plugins for all the type checkers.
So that's great.
And last but not least, there is an extension to the existing typed dict, typed dictionaries
data type.
Previously, it was possible to define a typed dict, which is a dictionary with a set of
a particular expected keys that have expected values, very common in JSON.
It was possible to define a typed dict where some of the keys are either required and
some of them where they are not required.
You had to do this weird hack where you had one typed dict inheriting from another typed
dict in order to mark some keys as required or as not required.
Well, now you can just mark it directly.
So very common is you have a lot of keys that are required and a few that are not required.
So much, much simpler to write.
So that is what I've got.
If you're looking for more information for, for example, a list of typing related peps,
I've assembled an updated list in that blog post, Python's Type Checking Renaissance.
If you search for that, you will find that list of typing related peps and you can get
the pet links there as well.
Thanks for listening, folks.
So I've got like, I think, two, three minutes?
Three minutes for questions.
Hit me.
So the question was, are the features that I mentioned available in typing extensions
or will they be available in typing extensions?
In general, all new typing features are added to typing extensions first and they will work
in any version of Python.
So yeah, you can use these today, even if you're using a older version of Python in
most cases.
So pep604, could you tell me what that maps to?
Type unions.
Sorry.
What was the runtime of the older version of Python?
The old version for unions.
I heard many different things.
Sorry.
X, pipe, Y.
X, pipe, Y?
Okay, repeat the question.
It was my question, the clarification that that will work at runtime, so you have to
have a front-future Python.
So I'm going to go ahead and ask you to repeat the question.
None Pipex?
I do not know if that works or not.
I learned something.
Okay.
So yeah, the question was does we have x Pipe none, but maybe not none Pipex?
Apparently from research here, both work.
Got a question here.
What are we going to get in 312?
312.
Let's see.
So there are two things that I know about.
One, which is tentatively called either type form or annotation type.
That's something that I'm working on, which will allow you to label the type of a type annotation object, which is very close to type of T.
The type of T doesn't accept certain things like unions and a few other things.
That's something I'm planning on adding.
And there is a second one from that article, which I do not remember offhand.
You'll have to go look it up for me.
Do we have any more time?
Yes, please.
Can I ask a question?
In the spirit of being controversial from yesterday, optional is one of the most confusing words I have ever come across in my life.
Because optional x is not in data classes, for example, optional.
Could we call it not required?
Could we replace it with required and not required?
We're counting it in favor of 5 and a half.
So the discussion that was made that was related to that, the thought was that optional was basically too, that it was too deprecating.
So probably we're going to be with it for a long time at the very least.
Rather than either reclassifying the use of the word optional or going completely eliminating it.
That was more or less the consensus that seemed to be the case.
So, yeah, for those of you who don't know me, my name is Aras Ponsu.
And today I will be talking about basically the work that has been going on around tensor typing in the past.
What is going on now? What is the next step today? And overall, what is going on in the ecosystem?
So first of all, like, tensor typing is a very nervous topic.
Because it really works a lot of things and you don't have anything that appears in numerical numbers.
So on the one hand, we have very clear aspects like creating a tensor or getting a simple tensor.
Or doing some basic matrix multiplication or concatenation.
And this is something that comes to everyone's mind when you think of tensor typing.
But by extension, when we think about machine learning, we have neural networks and layers.
And because at the end of the day, the layers are just performing tensor multiplications.
If we are capable of typing tensor, we can also type like neural networks.
And do things like verifying that the inputs and the outputs of the layers in the neural network, they are correct at type checking time.
And then we also have a wider range of operations that are a bit more sophisticated.
That appear nonetheless very often in numerical entries.
For example, we are getting things like tensor, we are flattening tensors, we are doing forecasting.
Or some very popular operations like armix, armax, anion, transpose, etc.
So unfortunately, there isn't one perfect solution for solving everything.
Instead, we aim to solve this problem with a combination of tools.
And these tools, we can put them into three main categories.
One, variadix, another table arithmetic, another custom operator.
And each of these tools contributes in a different way to solve this problem.
So variadix allows us to solve some fundamental problems.
For example, it's aligning itself with the concept of tensor.
Like as a graph with a variable number of parameters, which is in the dimension sizes.
It also allows us to say that we are moving to a dimension, or for example, in the matrix multiplication.
And then table arithmetic is key every time that there is an arithmetic operation in the dimensions.
For example, concatenation and slash operation on convolution.
And then custom operators are needed for those operators that cannot be expressed any other way, but are very common.
For example, broadcasting. Broadcasting is all over the place in numerical areas.
And it cannot be expressed with arithmetic or with other methods.
So as of now, I think something to be very proud of is the huge milestone that we achieved with respect to last year.
That is the instance of F646 that now is available from Python 3.
I think we have talked much about this in the past years.
It's one of the reasons why many people started working together in tensor diving.
So that this is already done, it's quite an achievement.
And I think they are very winners.
Then on the departmental side, I'm working with Kravitz on having an app that is ready for BOSO.
Although for the ones who tried, you know that this is available in Python.
Python is from the very beginning.
And it's also nice to have it to show that it's technically possible to implement it and to get insights about what are the implications of an implementation.
And then custom operators is a more amused topic.
They're having a lot of discussion about what other operators are important for timing.
Some of them, as I mentioned, are forecasting.
It's very, very common.
All the products that this is already available in Python, they are available in Python.
So what are the effects?
Let's take a look at what we used to have and what we have now.
So basically before, we couldn't express that we have a tensor of any number of dimensions.
Instead of working with a dimension in tensor, we need to have at least define a class for every number of dimensions.
Tensors of one dimension, two dimensions, three dimensions.
And this applies also to methods.
So you need to work those for any number of dimensions.
And here there's only one parameter.
There are two or three parameters and you need to work those.
This gets to a combinatorial conclusion that is crazy actually.
So we actually, if I remember correctly, must have created a library that was trying to use this idea.
And at the end, that was the problem, that there were so many combinations that people didn't understand.
But now we have exactly what we wanted.
At least we were able to express that we have a tensor, not a one-dimensional, not a two-dimensional, of any number of dimensions.
And I think this is a very nice thing to have.
And it makes it also very easy to work with dimensions later on.
For example, you see that now we don't need to be overloading, but as well that I was to express something that are not necessarily tensor-specific.
For example, when you define the A method, you don't pass a tensor.
You pass a variable number of numbers that will be converted into a set of the tensor and by servers that you can force it.
And you can extract the dimensions and put them in the top.
So yeah, having this makes a big difference on what can be modeled and open the doors to a lot of things.
So once again, having this is really great news.
Then, type arithmetic.
Well, now that we have very early type arithmetic, it's kind of one of the most clear things that would open the door to support in many other use cases, especially in the mathematical machine learning.
So type arithmetic basically appears anywhere where you need to do some arithmetic operations on the dimension.
For example, if you want to multiply into the tensor, you will need to add some of the tensor.
You want to get any slice into the tensor, you will need to do the subtraction.
If you need to generate tensor with values in some range, you will need to do subtraction and division or something like social classification again with the quantum multiplication.
Perhaps the main exponent of what type arithmetic can be is a convolution.
Convolutions have a pretty intimidating formula when you look at it, but then you think more carefully and you realize that at the end it's plain arithmetic.
It's true that the formula is very convoluted by definition, but it's pretty simple.
There is subtraction, multiplication, division.
So basically if we are able to support arithmetic, we will be able to support something so complicated as this, no matter how we combine it, how many layers there are, we should be able to verify that what is happening here is correct.
And this is a challenge for humans, for programmers, because these formulas are so complex that you can easily get lost on them.
So to have it verify that on bad timing is great.
And then by extension, by supporting this, we are also supporting symbolic arithmetic in the sense that we are also capable of giving to variables that represent dimensions, we are able to represent their expressions.
Because this way we, for example, can verify that the input that you're providing to an error in what is correct and you are not passing something that would fail at content.
So how do these operators work? Well, at the end, the semantics of the operators are quite straightforward.
First of all, we assume that we are going to be using iterative integers for defining the values of the sets of the dimensions.
And then basically the arithmetic operators are behaving like they would if they had frontends. So literal 2 plus iterative 3 would be 5 and so on and so forth.
There will be x cases that we consider as how are we handling any, how are we handling them and what.
This requires some more discussion, but this is one of the last things that we are covering.
But that's a simple summary.
And then the other key part of supporting the arithmetic is equality.
Because so far, like what they have been commenting doesn't look like that surprising.
Okay, you have a system where you have to press 3 and you're supposed to press 5.
But it's not enough. So it's not enough.
Because at the end, you are going to be doing all the time expressions in tensors that they are going to get equivalent, but with different expressions.
And the problem is that you will get an error from the type checker telling you, hey, for example, here you have a tensor of size a plus a and this one is of size a plus a.
So they are not the same when you're operation is invalid. But for us, like, this is obvious that they are the same, right?
Because it's not as common to me. But for the type checker, this is far from obvious.
And this applies to a very wide range of expressions that they will appear in absolutely normal circumstances.
So supporting them is a must to make this feature useful.
But at the same time, we want to make sure that this is not going to make the language way more complicated.
Because nowadays, we have the language that can do such a thing are dependent typing languages where basically they need to provide a proof that there is an equality between expressions.
And that's definitely far from the vision that we have for Python as an engine.
So basically the idea is that we need to ensure that whatever we add is going to add zero overhead for the program.
And the only kind of advantage that we have is that we are limiting ourselves to a few number of operators.
We don't want to express absolutely anything in the tensor.
We only want to express a few number of operators. So can we optimize for them?
Well, we can. And that's basically the idea behind the proposal.
That is to create a canonical representation.
Basically, the idea is that we have two expressions which are equivalent.
They should be internally represented the same way. And if we achieve this, then equality comparisons are free.
So how does this work? Well, for the case of addition, subtraction, multiplication, we can think about this as polynomials.
So the problem becomes just how can we compare polynomials to the problem.
For this, we go through a series of steps that goes through expanding the polynomial into monomials, grouping them, raising zeros, setting up that order.
And we can guarantee that if they are equivalent, they will be represented in the same way.
It's not that much that we know exactly how to do this since there are libraries that can automatically check this properties.
But I think in this case it's quite clear how can we achieve it.
In the case of division, it's a bit tricky because this is not just division. This is integer division or floor division.
So this is not such a common mathematical function. And there is not that many rules about it that are popular.
But basically, some rules that are applied for integer or normal division don't apply to integer division.
Perhaps the most obvious is n divided by 2 plus n divided by 2 is not even...
We have an example, right? 1 divided by 2 plus 1 divided by 2 is actually 0.
So all these things will be kept in mind to make sure that the rules of type arithmetic are consistent with the runtime behavior of the corresponding Python functions.
So that's an overview of the rules of equality.
Here is just a brief comment about some experience that I have had myself implementing differently with type arithmetic in Pyre.
So I was typing some code on ResNet, this neural network, with Pyre.
There are many challenges that I'm not going to answer until I tell you what makes it hard to type it.
The fact is that at some point I could type this part of the neural network where there is a long series of convolutional layers.
If you remember well, the formula for convolutions is quite sophisticated.
So just imagine doing this five times, one side of your color, the formula gets pretty complicated.
But the interesting bit here is that if you look at the return value of the function, you see that the actual dimension of the tensor that is returning is really simple.
And this is because the quality, the automatic equality system is capable of realizing that despite making a lot of sequences of this complicated transformation,
a lot of things can get simplified and overall get simplified very simple.
So I think that's a good way of solving that problem.
Finally, let me tell you something about custom operators.
Again, this is like a broad category to put together many different ideas that would contribute to potential typing.
But clearly one of the most valuable is broadcasting because so far we have claimed that we could support many operators in the support for variarities neural network.
But the fact is that in most libraries, almost all operators have a variant for their broadcasting case.
Basically, if the tensor doesn't match, then they do broadcasting.
So to fully support all these libraries that do broadcasting, we need to be able to express it.
And the thing is that broadcasting appears in all the cube operators, like addition, subtraction, multiplication, division, comparison.
They're all over the place. They all have a broadcasting variant.
And being able to express this is super important.
Fortunately, broadcasting is very standardized with semantics.
And it behaves really much the same in non-bi-bio-tensor flow.
So that's, I would think, well.
Nonetheless, again, we have been broadcasting the challenge of making sure that even different broadcasting expressions, we can verify that they're the same.
We don't want to be in a situation where we don't realize that broadcasting is the same as BMI broadcasting is commonly.
Or it's also a striptease.
And overall, there are multiple situations where we need to guarantee that they are equal.
About other operators that we have talked about in the past, for example, I mentioned many times the product.
Basically, often you need to make the product of all the dimensions of a sensor.
For example, when you want to do a resave or a WDT sensor, you are going to do this.
It's true that you would overload a bunch of multiplications.
Nonetheless, this is not something you're going to do, especially when you have multiple parameters and you can start having too many combinations.
And then a pattern that appears very often is when you are removing a dimension from a sensor, when you are replacing a dimension from a sensor.
These operators were mentioned by Pradeep not so long time ago.
I remember with some checks, there were like 40 or 50 or more different operators in Python that would need these to extract themselves.
So this shows how common this pattern is.
For example, in Armax or Armint, that is something very commonly used.
You are exerping this, removing one of the dimensions of the sensor in one of the positions.
Or, for example, when you are doing a transpose by definition, you are transposing two dimensions of the sensor.
So you will be doing exactly this.
So having support for this certainly will help a lot.
That's basically a summary of all the key elements for achieving sensor typing.
I think, again, it's important to realize the future step forward.
There has been C4.6 and how happy we should be about the work that has been done there.
And also to be excited about what we can be achieved for the month.
So, yes, that was everything from my side.
Thank you very much for your attention.
And Pradeep has kindly offered to my discussion.
And Pradeep, you can invite me.
I'm going to challenge you and I'm going to try to get you from here.
So, yes, thank you very much.
Hello.
I have questions.
Oh, thanks.
Okay.
Is it on?
No.
Okay.
Let me know if anybody has questions.
So I just have a question about broadcasting.
Do you think what broadcasting is and why it's complicated?
So broadcasting means that you can add tensors that are not identical in their dimensions,
but are aligned along across certain dimensions.
For example, if you have one tensor of dimensions 5, 1, and the other one of 1, 4,
so they're not identical, so you might think they can't add them.
But in reality, it allows you to add them and get a tensor of type of shape 5, 4,
or 5, all the ones that ignore basically and collapse into it.
So that's the idea from a shape point of view.
So we need that because without that, we will be really in shape.
So we need broadcasting to be able to support usual thoughts and tensor operations.
The easy example is if you take a matrix and add a scalar,
it doesn't just matter if they work even though the scalar is not a matrix.
Any other questions?
Yeah, for your custom functions, so is your idea in the long term that there's that concept of custom operators for specific functions?
Yeah, so that was the fear that we had.
We need kind of custom operators for each one.
So I went to all the tensor functions that we have right now
and I'm sort of classifying them what operators we need for each one.
So I found that remove add in the case of the main things that we need.
And that would cover basically almost all the tensor operations we have.
There are a couple niche ones, which I don't think it's okay to ignore them.
And say that we can't type them.
So it's not really going to help.
Any other thoughts, questions?
Yes, so I didn't understand one part of the slides where I think you said we didn't need a zero-prover to make this work.
But it sounds like you're lifting the whole context for system into typing.
And typically, from what I know from like the post-process, I know we look at it sometimes,
but you need a zero-prover for that.
So I think it's like ordered monomial, is that problem?
So if I understand your question, you're using how we avoid having a TM for this?
Yeah, so the thing is for addition and multiplication, you're able to get a canonical representation for that.
So you don't need to prove that these two types are equal.
But for division, right now we sort of have a best effort in simplification.
And if you have, so it's like if you divide, because it's integer division,
and as Alphonse mentioned, you have n by 2 plus n by 2.
They're not equal to n, right?
So we do have equivalent expressions that the type checking will not always work.
So it's important and very contributory.
So it's a subset.
Yeah, I would like to add that since the last year,
I was actually surprised by the power of SimPy.
I think SimPy is the right library.
And they have some specific functions for doing pretty much the same, but in the context of parametric.
And like change variables to variables in the Cypher.
And I think that they do guarantee that the integer division and quantity checking is totally covering all these cases.
So I think that from a implementation point of view, this could be leveraged and unaltered.
Any other thoughts? I can pass it on to Sharon.
Yeah, yeah, you're up next.
Thank you. Thank you.
Thank you.
David already told us about all the new tests that you're getting in.
He saved the larger group direction.
Yes. Thank you.
Now you guys can hear me.
Yeah, David already told us about all the new paths in back-up quick with the lab.
There's actually a bunch more smaller features that we're also getting and going to introduce those.
Like we have all these paths.
I'm not going to talk about them.
Instead, what we have is reveal type, never, assert never, assert type, get overdose,
changes to final, and any as a base class.
It's time to reveal type.
When we started talking about this, everybody thought reveal type was already implemented in platform 4 and specified.
It wasn't.
It just doesn't matter.
We all decided it's so useful, we're all going to use it.
So the other thing to typing in 3.11,
the advantage of I think the thing about runtime includes that you can run your test suite at the same time as you're debugging your types.
And if you're using it in education, you can run your examples,
which reveal type in them and they will actually work at runtime.
We have never.
No return has been in the type system since pretty much the beginning.
But it was meant to be only used for functions that never return.
But every type checker basically decided we want to bottom type and we're going to use never for that.
To make that clearer, 3.11, you're adding never as basically an equivalent of no return.
I recommend that type checkers treat them as the same in their internal representations.
But in error message, I would recommend you output never when you're on 3.11 or in New York.
Relate to never, we add the assert never function.
This isn't actually a type system feature.
You could implement this in user codes just as easily.
But it's kind of hard to discover and a lot of people have to discover it independently.
So we're adding it to typing to make it easy for our quality to find out how to use it.
So the use case is that you want to assert that some code is unreachable and the type checker can prove that it's unreachable.
In this example, we know there's only two booleans.
So if it's not true or false, then it's obviously impossible.
And with this explicit assert never call, the type checker will tell you if there's a third boolean,
we expect it to switch to ternary logic, and you didn't update your code.
The next thing to add is helpful for asserting that if you put type annotations in the type checker,
it actually understands them the way you intended them.
In this simple case, you put int in the type function annotations.
So obviously the type checker will think that x is an int.
In this case, it's of course trivial.
We majorly discuss this in the next class.
We majorly discuss this in type chat, where we want to test that the stuff we provide actually result in the types that we think they result in.
Because sometimes we do pretty complicated things with overloads and generic self types and protocols and what not.
We want to make sure that type checks actually understand what they're doing in the way we intended it.
And actually, so, yeah, go ahead.
So I was going to ask whether, is it null of the runtime?
It does nothing as runtime.
I think in this case we're going to do literally nothing.
It's purely for checking that the static type is what you think it is.
It returns the values.
Oh, right, yes, it returns the values. So then you can put it in an expression and keep using it.
Does this do the exact type check or is it something like type check?
So, not how like, what's the question?
It's exact type check.
It's possible if you have to think more about details.
One thing that I actually got into recently was if you have two protocols that have the same methods, should that assert type thing do the same thing?
And the way you can get the night time, it doesn't think they're the same thing, but then you shoot.
What does a reveal type do at runtime? Does it print it out or just something?
It prints the type of the value.
It returns the value also.
Yes, it also returns the value.
Yeah, that's one of the things we found out while trying to standardize is it's effortlessly implemented, but not effortlessly implemented exactly the same.
The returning the value thing is not night time, I guess.
It's useful because then you can just put reveal type anywhere in the expression and night time tells you what type is a different point.
So that's the way to standardize it.
I think I like that to change the information a little bit.
The basic plain devil's advocate is that that code is going to surely enormously confuse new users who see that and they assume that they're going to hard check it at runtime.
It's possible, yes.
We went over a lot of possible names for this function and ultimately you could say that the development was better than assert type.
We tried to make clear the information in the documentation when it does.
If you have suggestions for how to make it even more clear, we can still change the information.
One fun trick here is that the SOAP never does have a runtime SOAP, but it's so that it's not a runtime SOAP.
This is true.
So it's shaggy type?
Yeah, it's possible.
I guess I didn't want anything too long either, but shaggy type.
Shaggy type can be something even more likely to get in your runtime.
Yeah, I think we went over many of these and couldn't come up with anything that's really better.
I guess the last thing I want to say if you are already using this in TypeShed right now, Alex Weigut added it for PyRat.
Last week I think.
And MyPy added to MyPy.
We just released support, so we're going to have MyPy assert type checks in TypeShed also very soon.
If the PyR people want PyR to do the same thing, please contribute and save for PyType.
I think one thing that's worth saying about that, the naming is just, the use cases for this are mostly for implementers and type checkers are a very complicated type library.
So it's not the kind of thing that's likely to show up in the beginning of the season.
Yeah, I guess the main risk there is you see it in either the typing notification, you see it in either the download form.
That's your grant that most people want to see it very much.
This is a feature of PyPons right now?
Yeah, so it's in typing.py at runtime.
It's in 3.11, it's in typing extensions.
But obviously the runtime just, I guess we established it just returns the value.
The interesting implementation is in type checkers.
And MyPy and PyRy support it.
I believe PyType already supported it on the disk name.
Is that correct?
Yeah.
We support a PyType extension that assert type.
I think we need to just like alias it to something in typing.
Okay, yeah.
All right, that's a certain type.
I'm going to say more questions.
Then the next thing we have is around support for runtime use of typing.
The way that Overload was implemented, it would just completely throw away the overloads after the actual function is defined.
So in this example, before PyPy with 11, the overload is for a function that is not in the type.
And then after PyPy with 11, the overload is for a function for f.
You just never reopen it again because it's lost in the module namespace and there's no more reference to it.
And this means it's impossible for type checkers that look at their runtime types to ever find an overload back.
So we added something that gathers the overload in basically a dictionary in the typing module at runtime.
So that you can then call the get overloads function to retrieve the overloads again and see what they are.
I was motivated to add this because in the type checker network only I need this to get an overdose.
Another use case is that in health outputs and other documentation, we will now be able to show overloads because again, they are completely accessible to runtime and you couldn't even find them.
How does that work at runtime? Does the decorative fashion have some secret name somewhere?
There's just a dictionary in typing that's I think the way they end up doing this for module to function name to the list of overloads.
The downside is that the dash offices are never used because they keep these things around and they add overloads a little bit slower than runtime because it has to do a little bit more work.
Similarly for final, also it was impossible for a runtime type checker to support not subtesting a final class because final is returned to class unchanged.
There's no way to know that this class was decorated as final.
So now we add this number of final attributes on the defined class or methods when you apply it.
I think this now means that all typing decorators are in respect to the runtime if you need them.
Last but not least, a recommendation from Shansu.
Be ready in staff supported subclassing any for cases where you have something that you can basically do anything with that's also wants some custom behavior.
The most common example is mark objects which you can use to pass anywhere, but they also have some methods that are just a panel from box.
So this will also be allowed in runtime.
Yeah, and some takeaways from this include that there's still room for improvements.
There's more things we can have at if there's new ideas that you think are useful, we can consider them for people 12 or if you're really ambitious for three with the left and for future trees.
Eventually, two days of spring that conference.
So if you have some idea of how likely and then you can get it.
Yeah, so maybe you can make people 12 and better if there's more new ideas.
And last, there is, as I mentioned, the bonus slides.
This is something that's service to check out, which is very active core developer.
There's the PR for today.
Currently, at runtime, it's impossible to make a generic name to pull just because of some cost.
Thanks to the implementation.
Even though to be at least this seems pretty natural.
Like in this example, he has a name to pull one field is the other field is the 10 depends on the generic.
So anything plans to allow these three with the left and worst PR and make this work that runtime.
My only hesitation is that maybe there's some reason in the static type system that this opens a giant hole and there's some reason not to do it.
So if you as a tech checker maintainer things, this is a bad idea.
Please let me know and we can.
We consider it.
That's what it work with my pie out of the box.
No, my eyes actually the main reason I think it doesn't work.
Doesn't work.
Yeah, I think my my internal support doesn't go to the next level.
So generic things are not going to work.
And as I think that shouldn't stop us.
Like I think it's to be it seems like a natural way to extend the time system.
I said that doesn't support it, but we don't have to wait for that.
There's nothing uses for runtime things like.
Maybe I mean maybe you can use generics anywhere.
We have generic version of the model.
Yes, yeah, it's getting because I know it's happening, but thank you.
People seem to use them.
I have never used one of the options.
I don't understand.
But I suppose your classes are just classes.
So that's that's what already work.
It doesn't need this.
So you are.
Generical variables.
Like.
I think so.
Yeah, I guess I.
The art of this morning.
I haven't read that much of this out of the slides ready for presentation.
But I think it should just be general generics.
You can make a generic of her type of people probably.
One thing I was concerned about is the variance.
Should it be unlikely covariance because two goals are.
What happens if he is contravariant?
Yeah, I guess that's something for type.
That's probably something that's the runtime doesn't need to care about.
I guess the fields.
Yeah, I mean, both areas.
But you also have methods on the two.
So then you might want a different experience.
If you have a method arguments that's generic, you probably want it to be.
Contravariance.
Yeah.
Well, also, I think that's going to happen for type.
I know the type of people can't be there right now.
Yeah, it actually is better to do the same thing for tactics.
I think I should be sitting near you who will.
That's a quick thing.
That's granted.
It doesn't work.
We have to ask support for that.
And I think there's possibly work with respect to you.
That's any day.
This is one of the four things.
So I'm looking at getting an eventually generic type.
It's looking at that as a feature.
So you can stand in inspection that this has a square record.
Intercept.
Right.
I guess that's after tech checkers.
Julie, you've incurred from the from the aspect of tech.
So if you do and see one to the tech checker, we've heard that.
I think it should just work like any generic class.
I will say I tried to use this and was surprised that it didn't work.
I just did something else because it wasn't essential, but it was surprising that you couldn't get it.
Yeah, I feel the same way.
Like it feels like it should work, but it doesn't.
Yeah.
Yeah, there's also like, my type also doesn't support generic normal people.
Like not many people because generic people aren't supposed to wear my type.
Yeah.
There's just an artifact that's the way these types are represented in AIPy.
The paths for generic and paths for tuple just don't have to work with each other.
Are you saying that my type doesn't support generic tuples?
Yep.
Yeah, so much than any type.
Yeah.
Are there any more questions?
Question about the previous slide.
For the final one, so like, sorry about runtime usage.
Like if you mark class as final and you try to inherit from it and like run your code, does that result in a runtime error?
No, it doesn't.
It doesn't get checked by anything at runtime.
It's just that this attribute is there so that if you want to check it, it's there.
Is it feasible now to add runtime usage because of this final field?
And you could do it.
I think it's, maybe it should be a different decorator because final as of existing now already means,
like it's established that it doesn't get necessarily checked at runtime.
So there might be people depending on that and not there anyway.
That's if you want to be good at the decorator in the somewhere that actually makes the class not so passable.
You could have it as an argument, final, or here in course.
Yeah.
I guess if there's an interesting that then you could add that.
I personally don't feel like a very strong need, but you could do it.
Have you also considered individual methods?
I mean, just a little bit from the beginning.
Yeah, it's also done from methods.
So it's not an exclusive class on the example, but basically the main final works that are done at runtime is it tries to set up attributes.
It infills it, ignores the error, and it just recurs whatever it wants to do.
I have a question about get overloads.
If it sees a function that is a single dispatch function, would it be able to read that registry of overloads?
Or does it only look at the ones that are?
Overloads, yes.
I think that this is a generalizing to single dispatch, but we decided it's two different.
It's better to just keep it to just over that.
I might implement something else.
The last thing I want to provide with named tuples is that there's also the R-concretory that makes it possible to inherit anything and make it named tuple.
Actually, if I could not do that, I feel like it would make it too harsh to region-guard named tuples in the text system if they can inherit from arbitrary non-named tuple classes,
because named tuples are pretty different things.
But I'd also be happy to hear more opinions about that.
I have a question about get overloads.
You said it's like a mapping of multiple function names to overloads.
Yes.
What happens if you have overloads?
Not that I've ever used this.
I'm just curious.
You mean you define the overloads inside a function?
Yes.
Yes, they will get overwritten.
So every time you do it, I guess it will create new overloads and put them in the same place.
Actually, this was something we thought about a lot while implementing this.
It was a concern that if you keep doing this, you just get unloaded memory.
You used to do it every time you do it, you'd get more overloads.
So the way it results, actually, is that the line number of the overloads part of the key.
So if you define a new overload with the same line number, it gets overwritten.
This can have slightly unexpected effects if you generate invested functions.
But we didn't think there was a penalty on it.
So I'm guessing that's your thing of like in a for loop.
I was actually thinking of like, yeah, two functions that both define the same code inside of that with the same name.
But if the line number is part of it, then I guess that solves that.
Yeah.
I guess I have to say, name it in the same module.
I'm sure both of them can actually make the keys be nice and confident.
I am ready.
If there are more questions, I can answer them.
If there's no more time, then we can move on to the next.
Yeah.
In regards to name-cubable thing, I feel like there's been many times where I wanted not necessarily a name-cubable,
but just an immutable, no boilerplate, struct essentially.
Data class-cruiser.
Yeah.
But then you have, well, I mean, it's still data class.
It's doing runtime stuff.
Check that.
I don't know.
I always, I go for name-cubable.
It's internal.
I don't care that it's a name-cubable.
Yeah.
I guess that's kind of a style question.
I think we don't want to add too many more things to name-cubable because data class is generally a better solution.
It doesn't make you generally into a tuple and make you iterable, which is usually not what it was.
Yeah.
Depending on who you are, of course.
Can you get back to the reveal time thing?
Quick interruption.
Just because we're running late, let's do a 10-minute break.
So a 10-minute break, if you still have questions, we can say if you could, unless you're on your break.
But yeah, I think we'll start the next talk at 1, sorry, 2.35.
So yeah, just at FYI.
I don't want to cut this off, but I also want to give people a chance to look at it.
Hi, everyone.
This is B.I.
My name is Rebecca.
I work at Google on the PyType Checker.
Today I am not talking about PyType for once.
I'm talking about a possible extension to PEP647, which is the user-defined type guard.
These slides were made in collaboration with Eric Trout, who is the author of PEP647.
He was not able to make it to PyCon, but he was a huge help in putting together this presentation.
So I'm going to start with a brief refresher on PEP647.
We wanted some criticisms of the PEP, then look at extension proposals to cover these criticisms,
and then we should have some time for discussion at the end.
So first off, what is a type guard?
It's an expression used in a conditional to narrow the type of another expression.
So if we look at this example, val is not none is a type guard that narrows the type of val.
In the positive case, when the type guard returns true, val is narrowed to the non-none type option,
and in the negative case, the type is narrowed to none.
So what PEP647 does is that it allows users to define their own type guards.
So this case is stir list, is a type guard.
In the positive case, it narrows the type of its input to list of stirs,
and in the negative case, it leaves the type unchanged.
So for some background on this PEP, it was inspired by type guards in TypeScript.
Eric talked with the TypeScript team a bit about what would they have done differently if they could go back in time,
and based on those conversations, he made type guard in Python as flexible as possible.
There are no restrictions on the type guard type.
So that's why examples like the previous one worked.
It narrowed list of objects to list of stirs, even though there's no subtyping relationship there.
So this flexibility does lead to some trade-offs, which is what I want to talk about next.
To motivate this, I start with an example.
So NumPy is a popular numerical computing library.
It has this function called isScaler, which, approximately speaking,
what it does is it takes in a value that can be of any type,
and it will return true if the type is string or supports float.
So if you pass isScaler a value that is either supports float or a NumPy nd array,
then with isScaler that was true, you know that it supports float.
Otherwise, you know it's an nd array.
So this is pretty obviously a type guard in the cool old rule sense,
but if we annotate isScaler using PEP647 type guards,
you'll see that a type checker would actually infer the wrong types.
You remember we wanted supports float in the positive case,
an nd array in the negative case, and we would get these both wrong.
So why is that?
So in the negative case, the problem is that type guard does not do any type narrowing,
so we aren't able to get rid of that supports float.
And in the positive case, the problem is that the type guard type is actually a union
that contains this stir element that we should be able to tell is impossible based on the input type,
but type guard does not do this elimination of impossible union elements.
So quick question, why doesn't these type guards do these operations to refine the type?
And the answer to that is that they're not always safe,
because a type guard can do checks that aren't encoded in the type information.
So if you have a type guard that checks whether something is a list of single character strings,
then when the type guard evaluates to false, the input can still be a list of stir.
You can't actually eliminate that type.
And Python type guards especially, there's no guarantee about the relationship between the type guard type and the input type,
so it's even more unsafe to try to do these sorts of operations.
So even though these operations are unsafe, we saw that there's an obvious use case for them.
So the next thing I'm going to talk about is a few proposals made to extend type guard to do these things.
I'm going to cover the proposals basically in chronological order.
First show a couple of the earlier ones that were determined to not really be sufficient,
and hopefully that will show why the final proposal is what it is.
The first and most obvious proposal was to add a to argument form of type guard.
In this case, the first argument was specified in the positive case,
and the second argument, the type generatum in the negative case.
And one sort of nice thing about this proposal is that it would actually give a way to express type asserts,
which are functions that raise an exception if the type isn't, sorry, if its input isn't of a specified type.
We just put no return as the type in the negative case to show that it raises an exception.
But as appealing as this proposal looks, it has a couple of disadvantages that were considered to be deal breakers.
So the first one is that it doesn't address that issue of not eliminating impossible union elements in the positive case,
and that's just because that was a requirement that came up somewhat later in the discussion.
And another problem is that for this to be useful, you really want to be able to say sometimes that the type in the negative case
is anything but the type in the positive case, and this proposal does not give a way to express that.
There's a last sort of minor thing, which is that it would also be of an unusual definition for type guard,
different from other generic types, although that's not as big of a deal.
So that brings us to the second proposal, which is just to modify the semantics of the existing type guard type.
So say if you pass in a union type to a type guard, and the type guard type is on the types in the union,
then just go ahead and apply type narrowing in the negative case.
This seems like a pretty straightforward change. Again, there are a few disadvantages.
It doesn't address that issue of impossible union elements in the positive case,
and also this would change existing behavior in an unsafe way.
If you have user code that's already using type guard, you make this change and somebody doing the wrong thing.
And the last concern is that you start adding all these rules for what type narrowing does and doesn't occur.
It starts to get pretty complicated.
So that brings us to the last proposal, which is to forget about modifying the existing type guard construct
and instead add a new construct called strict type guard that does all these things that we wanted for its scalar.
Apply type narrowing in the negative case, eliminate impossible union elements in the positive case.
In order to make these operations a little safer, strict type guard would also enforce that the type guard type is a subtype of the input type.
So this would be the complete solution. It's also pretty complex.
And strict type guard is already prototyped in Plight Ride today. You can try it out if you want.
But what Eric told me is that he hasn't gotten much feedback on strict type guard, good or bad.
So the question at this point is sort of, is there much interest or appetite in this, like, in having to do forward with the path or no.
And that's about all I have. So I'd love to hear your thoughts on this.
Is there a thread specifically around strict type guard, either on type C or in another location?
There are several. I did not think to link them in the slides.
I did not know that there was a question that this would even be considered as a yes or no thing. So yeah, I'd like to sign the support.
This is a comment.
So the last one I think is going to be very hard.
For the strict type guard scenario unions, would that make how the work depends on...
Yeah, for the strict type guard, if the input type is a union, then we use special narrowing.
Wouldn't that mean that the way you think work depends on whether the type checker happens to incur a union in your case?
So if the type checker infers some different type than a union, it's going to be very different.
So, talking about this case here?
Yeah, so in this case it's obvious that the problem is a union because it's in a function rotation.
But in the general case, it might be some local variable.
And whether or not it's a purposeful union depends on basically how the type checker does its type inference.
Yeah, I think that is...
I mean, if you have a variable that's assigned to different line shapes, different types...
Yeah, so like if it's defined as either a valid or something else, you might refer to your temporal literal types or the common type of both of them, depending on what type of type checker uses to the type that it is.
So just to mention here, the type checker type includes a union, but the only way you know whether it includes a union is based on some specific decisions in the type checker on how it does inference.
So I guess if I provide the type guard type here, I mean the type that's specified between the values of the type checker and the type that's specified between the values of the type checker.
So I guess if I provide the type guard type here, I mean that the type that's specified between the brackets after the type guard.
So whether that's a union should be pretty obvious, but it's definitely true that whether it can play as a union should depend on the type checker.
So the union cases and eliminating some possibility, do you ever consider overloads? I know overloads would be perfect on these issues.
Like having an overload in the type guard, in the type function. As far as I know, that is not something that has been considered.
So I can grab that slide that is an A-Lar case and you have an overload on it. Oh, if a string is passed in, then it like, makes sense.
If a string is passed in, then it like, makes sense.
Okay, that was quite slow.
Yeah, that's definitely a good idea. You have to think about that some more.
When you're calling it, it's only an object. So you don't know the exact type. Overloads help when you already know the type.
So if you go to the next slide, with this one, you can have two different implementations of this table.
So it's conveniently supports load or any other type. So in case where you have just object to bring the overload on there.
I think we should be overloading the scalar. If a string is passed in, is scalar a support?
Well, yeah, you can't pick the right one. So you wind up hitting, catch all the children with this.
Okay, that's what you're saying.
I'm not really understanding the proposal, but was there any consideration of going with the two parameter type card approach, but also introducing an operator to handle the narrow zoom in that case?
I actually like that.
So basically go with your proposal one, but also introduce something like narratives to a like,
or basically the proposal would be instead of having a new string type card, you should have a new string type operator that's like narrow zoom,
that would let you selectively make type card perspective.
I'm just not understanding. So this example of saying the narrow's tube would be like in that first part?
Yeah, it would be type card that narrows to the third and then narrows to the last five.
And you would push the responsible depending on the size of the narrows.
I'm not sure if this is already mentioned as an alternative, but could you make the typing of val in this third, for example, a type card and basically like put it on the types of the valomys,
so then later on you have a vector that takes in that type card and also the union of supports flow and string and kind of intersects so that now you get a narrowed union type that's returned from the ceiling.
That way like when you have the positive phase, it would only have supports flow because you kind of intersected the type of union supports flow in the array with the union type of supports flow and string, which only gives you a union type of supports flow.
So this question is you could use a type bar to capture the type that you don't want. Is that right?
Yeah, so like this scalar in this case when you pass in val, it's a type bar and the tracker knows that it is a type supports flow and the array.
And then the output, the type bar type, is an intersection of the union string supports flow and supports flow and the array with the input.
So like it would be an intersection of all the things that are inside of type bar.
Do you need an intersection operator for that?
Yes.
That's fine.
Right, but I feel like that's a great and useful thing to do in a first place.
There isn't an intersection operator. I guess this would be the potential use for it.
I want to get back up a little bit. I tried this before.
The main thing I have these cases for is not just one, but something very similar of the function that takes in a type variable and then it returns that same type variable.
If you use a type bar, then right now with the non-strict type bar, it loses information that is stored in the type variable.
If you use a type error, it tries to return afterwards.
With the strict type bar, you keep the input type and the type variable in the path.
Oh, saying right now with the type bar, if you take the input and the type bar type, that's like the same type variable and it loses that function.
Yeah, so I'll give a function that's the EIM function that if type bar function X, return X, right now if you use the normal type bar, it will give you a type error of X is no longer related to the type variable.
With strict type bar, it reserves it.
I'm just saying like try out strict type bar and it gives you that behavior.
That's it.
Congratulations.
Thank you.
Applause
I've actually got two talks here back to back.
First one I have here is all about the future of typed dict.
So just briefly in case anyone came in a little bit late, I'm David Foster.
I did the initial implementation of typed dict and I'm generally shepherding related features to it at this point.
And when I'm not in doing open source things, I am the CTO at TechSmartt and we are inspiring kids to code in the K through 12 space.
So I thought it might be worth briefly reviewing the history of various features that are related to typed dict.
It was originally introduced with just a functional syntax and then later on a class based syntax was added, which I think is the kind that most people are using at this point.
At the same time, we got the ability to declare typed dicts with total equals false, which means that all the keys for it are not required.
And just recently with new PEP 655, we have the ability to declare individual keys as either required or not required.
So that's where we are right now.
So there are a couple ideas for things to add to typed dict in the future.
These have been proposed on a typing SIG mailing list and in some cases other places such as issue trackers and similar.
I thought that it would be interesting to just give a review of what these types of extensions might look like.
And yeah, so let's get started.
So one thing that is a bit of a pain point with typed dicts is at least with MyPy you can't have a recursive definition of typed dicts.
So common case is if I'm trying to, in this example, make a structure that's like a file system, I can't have a directory that contains other directories.
But if we were to add support for recursive typed dicts, then this would be okay.
At this point, currently, this does not work as far as I understand.
So recursive typed dicts.
You'd think it would work, but oh, I see a question.
Typed JSON.
Yes, it would make a typed JSON type more feasible than it is right now.
There may be some other challenges with that, but it's probably a prerequisite for a better type on that.
I do not know if other type checkers support it or not.
I'm hearing from the audience that PyWrite does support recursive typed dicts already.
So cool.
More things that we could do.
So another idea is, so right now, if you declare a typed dict with a particular set of keys, because the standardized form of typed dict in, I forget the pep number, the standardized form allows subclassing of typed dicts.
It will actually allow you to add keys at runtime to a typed dict value that aren't in the original definition.
So typed dicts are open by default.
But there may be some cases where you have, you want a more strict usage of typed dicts such that, for example, in this example, we have a point 2D that declares only an X and Y key.
But at the moment, if you were today to try to set an additional key Z on it at runtime, that would actually work.
But you might not want it to work.
So an idea is there might be some way to declare a typed dict as being closed.
Here, just a provisional syntax idea is maybe use the final key word or the decorator on a typed dict definition, which would then mark it as being closed.
So I thought this was an interesting idea.
Next one I have up is something that's a little bit similar.
Read-only typed dicts.
So right now a typed dict is a dict.
And because dicts are mutable, you can change them after construction.
But sometimes it might be useful to have a read-only type of typed dict.
So right now the read-only version of a regular dict is called a mapping.
So I was like, well, maybe we would call it something like typed mapping if we wanted this type of support.
So I think this is kind of interesting.
And another sort of, see, I'd have to review my type theory.
But because this is a immutable type, there may be something that can be invariant here that wouldn't be possible in other cases.
So there might be some interesting uses for that.
So that's read-only typed dicts.
And the fourth idea, which was actually mentioned earlier during the summit, was adding support for generics in typed dicts.
So this is, for example, a point 2D where you could instantiate it with an int parameter.
So it's an x, y integer coordinates.
Or you could instantiate it with float.
So it's an x, y of float float.
And so, again, I guess this is actually provisional syntax as well.
But it seems like this would be sort of the obvious syntax.
And in some cases, you may even want to have, say, like a type alias that is using these integer or these generic parameters.
And then you could instantiate the alias, which would be kind of interesting.
That's not something that would be a straightforward thing to support, at least in MyPy.
So I'd have to.
So that would definitely require some thought on the specific syntax and then implementation difficulty and similar.
But this does seem like something that may be desired.
And it was even mentioned, as I said earlier.
So, yeah, that is just a couple ideas.
So I think a number of people in this room are probably already subscribed to Typing SIG.
And these are just ideas.
Like, I'm not saying that I'm personally going to implement all of them myself.
But I'll definitely provide some support.
But anyone who's here and who's interested or who's watching at some later point, yeah, love some help on making Type Dict better.
Put some designs together, put some peps together, write some code.
You'll be great.
So, yeah, I think I've got a couple minutes for questions.
All right.
Oh.
Some types, let me think.
I think so.
The question was, are type dicts the canonical way to do some types in Python?
And I think that would be a union type is what you're looking for.
Or union is one idea.
But sometimes I want to have a subtype that includes multiple things.
Subtype includes multiple things.
Product types.
So let's see.
So a product type could be done with a typed name tuple, which is the capital form of named tuple.
So that might be what you're looking for there.
That's immutable, right?
Correct.
It is immutable in that situation.
You could also use a given class.
I think it's immutable.
Let's see.
I think I've got another minute for questions.
One in the front.
Excuse me if this is a dumb question, but is there a way to declare the type of everything else you have?
So like you said that z in your example, everything else, is that possible?
And if not, is it a consideration?
So I believe the question was, if you have just a regular type dict, can you add z onto the end of it just in today's syntax?
Can you restrict the type of z?
Can you say, elate like tuple, you can type dot dot dot?
Yes, you can do this.
So if you know in advance that there could be a z key added, and you knew that, for example, that it needed to be of typed int, you could use the not required key to declare.
What do you mean by using z?
So you're saying, okay, so is there a way to declare that for any unknown key added to a typed dict, that it must be of a particular fixed type?
There is no current way to do that that I know of.
And I don't believe, I believe there was something proposed on a typing stick thread that was like along the lines of this.
There was a thread about this.
It's possible to do if we have, you'd have to make it final to avoid a collision with subclassing rules.
We would need a pet for it, and we need to figure out what's the best way to specify the type, which could interact with the rules for scoping on generics.
But it should be possible if we have a use case that needs it.
Okay. Sounds like this capability could be added, but it might also be a little bit tricky, so probably a pet person would be required.
If you're on control of the data, the thing that works really well today is just nesting all the unknown stuff, and it takes their...
Cool.
Well, that's all I've got for this little, little talk right here.
So thanks for listening for that first bit.
Applause.
So now I've got a different thing to talk about.
So I wanted to give an overview of a number of tools that are in the Python typing ecosystem right now, which manipulate type annotation objects at runtime.
There's a lot of interesting things that's being done here, so I just did a survey of all the ones that all of the libraries that are doing this type of thing that I could get my hands on.
So it's probably worth saying as some background that type annotations were originally designed only for use by type checkers to use statically.
And while the syntax for declaring type annotations has been a subset of the expression syntax in Python, and therefore you can actually get a hold of these objects at runtime, I think that originally perhaps runtime usages were not necessarily focused on.
But because you can actually get expressions with types, there are many libraries that have found alternate uses for actually using these type annotation variables.
So the things I want to go through are several different libraries, several different tools that are using type annotations at runtime, sort of categorized by the type of usage.
And I thought it would also be worth highlighting four of those tools that are using type annotations at runtime, showing where they run into problems or challenges that are especially unique to the runtime usage of annotations that don't come up in the static case.
So here are more or less four patterns that all the libraries I've looked at are using. One is just straight up doing type checking at runtime, like adding a decorator to a function to verify that its inputs and outputs are what they are expected.
There are beefed up versions of built-in type introspection functions that exist, which can look at not just runtime class-based types, but can look at things like unions, can look at things like typed DICs.
So sort of written it as like the enhanced version of is instance or is subclass or the type functions.
Another thing that comes up a lot is related to the stringification or unstringification of type objects.
In the case of the PEP5 something something where type annotations would become strings by default.
This becomes PEP563. This becomes something that would have to be dealt with on a more regular basis. You would have types as strings everywhere, not just as a forward reference exception or similar.
So there are libraries where usually as part of their utility functions they are either stringifying or unstringifying types.
And the last area that I want to go over is using types when they're parsing and formatting typed structures.
So let's get into runtime type checking. So there's a couple libraries. I'm going to go over Typecard, PyTypes, and BearType.
Typecard is specifically advertised for doing runtime type checking for functions.
PyTypes provides a generic type checking toolbox and one of its tools happens to be runtime type checking.
And BearType is interesting. It also does runtime type checking.
So all three of these libraries give some kind of type checked decorator that you can put on a function.
And then when you at runtime call the function the decorator inserts some code to check the parameter types coming in and the return value that is going out.
So all three functions do this. The Typecard library in particular has something pretty fun where you can install an import hook where it will just add this decorator to everything within a particular module at runtime as it is imported.
So that allows you to just put these checks everywhere in a particular module very, very quickly without a lot of invasive code modifications.
So I think that's interesting. That's unique to Typecard at this time.
I'll also mention that the last library I mentioned, BearType, also allows you to add new types that are custom that you can have logic written in Python to see whether something is of a particular type.
This is similar to the type guarded functions as well, but it's just expressed in a different manner.
So this is kind of interesting. So this is an example of a type that a NumPy array is float.
It's worth mentioning that one big difference between these two, between these three libraries is that in general we have libraries that are just exhaustively checking the type.
So if you have something that's annotated as like list of str, it will actually look at the list and then go through every element in the list no matter how long it is and check that all of the items are str.
So that is a very correct way to check it, but it's also kind of slow. BearType is interesting in that it advertises that everywhere its type checking operations are amortized constant time.
Now the way that they do that is that, for example, in the case of list str, it uses a probabilistic algorithm.
It just picks a random element of the list and checks that random element rather than checking all of them.
So that's something to take into consideration depending on where you would be using these types of decorators, whether it's a best effort type of checking or whether you are depending on it, for example, for a security property.
Like you probably wouldn't want to use best effort checking on a parsing function that's getting something from untrusted network input or similar.
So that is runtime type checking uses.
I had mentioned that several of these libraries provide either directly or as part of their infrastructure type introspection functions that are enhanced versions of similar functions in the standard library, except that they are aware of a large subset, if not all, of the PEP 484 typing hints annotations.
The libraries that apply here, some familiar faces, we have PyTypes, which is that type checking toolbox, so it's sort of specializing in lower level things.
RunType, which is a newer entrant.
TriCast, which is dealing with is instance specifically.
TypeGuard and baretype again.
The top three libraries listed here specialize in one or more type introspection functions, whereas the bottom two libraries specialize in other things, but they export their internal type introspection functions of this kind.
So for example, is instance.
All five of these libraries have some variant of is instance.
For example, TriCast, which specializes in is assignable, which is a version of is instance and a cast function.
Yeah, so that specializes in it.
And let's see, TypeGuard has a check type, but you have to, but it uses, it generates an error message with if it fails, so you have to give it some thing to put in that error message.
Everything else uses pretty much the same signature.
They do vary in whether they support, say, capitalist versus lowercase list for generic lists.
They do vary and they support typed DICs versus not.
They do vary in whether they support other types of things.
So these libraries are not all created equal in terms of like all of the things that they support.
And as mentioned, bare type is a probabilistic check as well, so you have to be a little careful with that under certain circumstances.
So that's is instance.
Is subclass is a type.
Given a potential subtype and a potential supertype, is this relationship actually true?
So we've got two libraries that expose a version of this.
RunType and PyTypes expose this.
Sometimes with some caveats.
And the last one is type.
So the type function, normally you give it a value and then it will give you what is the type annotation object that describes it.
And PyTypes has a version that does its best to guess, especially for collection types.
If you give it a list of all string objects, it will try to infer a list of str or a list of all integer objects.
It will try to infer a list of int.
This is, naturally speaking, a little bit hard to do.
Like if you gave it a list of integers that are all of value 1, technically you could, one type that could be used to write that would be list of literal of 1, which would be pretty strange.
But I guess my point is that this is always going to be a bit of a lossy operation.
A best effort guess because type information is not preserved at runtime for a particular type.
A value that is encountered at runtime.
So this is always a best effort case.
So those are all like type utility functions.
Now I have libraries that are dealing with the problem of stringifying and unstringifying type annotation objects.
So in this case, what I think about it is you have type annotation objects that you are either formatting as a string or parsing from a string to be a type annotation object again.
So in the case of formatting, the only library I could find that attempts to do this is actually PyTypes.
Again, that sort of collection of generic type operators that's just the toolbox.
So it will do that for you.
Parsing is a little bit more interesting.
I believe the only library that does this is TriCast.
TriCast when you pass it in its function that accepts both type objects, it will also accept a top level string type.
So if you give it a top level string reference to a type, then it needs to be able to resolve that to an actual type annotation object.
So it has a library that it exports for that purpose.
So get type hints works if you already have...
get type hints will deal with string types in the middle.
So if you have a list of string int, it can deal with that.
But if you have a top level thing that is just a string, it can't deal with that without additional information about an assumed set of locals or an assumed set of globals.
This... it can't get all strings to figure it out, but it will automatically resolve things that are in built-ins like lowercase list.
I think it only will do things that are available in built-ins.
So if you want to use capitalist, you have to say typing.capitalist, and it will look for a module name and import that.
And then it may not be able to figure out in some cases still.
So best effort here.
So it's saying the difference is exactly when the string is trying to talk the app to the string in case the form is not located at the end of the string.
Correct. So it parses the string to find the module first and then get that out of the module.
And then once it's actually gotten it out of the module, it actually does delegate internally to get typing hints to resolve it the rest of the way insofar as possible.
Yeah, so I guess that's it for stringifying and unstringifying types. There are just a couple things that do that.
And the last topic I have here is related to dealing with parsing and formatting typed structures of some kind.
So an example here is you get some data off the wire. You're a web app. You get a dictionary off the wire which is describing a movie.
Matrix is one of my favorites. So you get a string off the wire.
Typically, so this is a JSON string. So you use JSON loads to get you an actual dictionary object with the stuff inside of it.
And so then the question is, what next? So then you just have a plain dictionary object.
There are a couple things that you could do.
You could use a typed dict. So then you still have the same dict object, but then the type checker will tell you whenever you're using it improperly.
Or you could use a specialized model class of some type, such as, for example, data classes.
Or you could use a Pydantic model. And so the general goal is that you're taking something that is just a plain dictionary and then putting it into some kind of type structure that is either enforced at statically or enforced at runtime.
And it's worth noting that all of these typed classes, let's see, I've got, it's like I have three minutes left here.
So yeah, so all of these, all of these model like classes use type annotations to declare what the expected types of the fields are.
So because the types of fields are available at runtime, you can have libraries like Pydantic that will read those field annotations and use it to do enforcement of those types at runtime.
Let's see. So I mentioned that in general there's, so there is a pattern where there is some kind of parse function and some kind of model class. If you have Pydantic, you have Pydantic models.
If you're using data classes, data classes the model, then there's a separate package called data classes JSON, which will actually enforce that information at runtime.
There's the older adders package, which is similar to data classes that declares a model type. And then there is a separate package called c adders, which actually enforces it at runtime.
And then if last but not least, we have typed dict, which already exists. And if you're using typed dict, that's interesting because that's actually the type of the dictionary itself.
So you can just use an is instance effectively. You can use an is instance function to see whether it parses correctly or not.
So since I'm running low on time, I will just show that this is how you do it in Pydantic. You declare a base model.
And if you pass in something that doesn't conform to the declared annotations, it will fail at runtime.
If you're using the strategy of using typed dict, you can use either in this particular instance, it's easier to use a smart cast function, which actually checks to see whether something is assignable to the movie type in this case at runtime and then returns it if it is.
Turns not if it's not.
So this is one way to do it. Or you can just use an is instance function. And there's many different modules providing an is instance function.
This is the one that's from TriCast. But as mentioned earlier in the presentation, there are several others as well.
So I'm pretty much out of time. So I will just briefly put this slide up as some challenges that are there.
Libraries don't support all of the typing stuff that's done everywhere. Sometimes there are speed issues with checking things like list of stir.
Some types of annotations are erased entirely at runtime, such as new type and typed dict. So that's tricky.
If you're dealing with pidantic, it will treat things that are actually strings, like it will treat the string of one as an int, so it's looser than you might expect.
There's also the interesting case that is instance at runtime and the equivalent is instance from pep-it-484 disagree on a couple things, especially like booleans and ints, which is kind of interesting.
And then there's ever the problem of string being also a sequence of itself, which is kind of bizarre. So that's all I've got.
Thanks for listening, folks.
Yeah, so apparently this was a topic that a lot of you wanted to hear about. So Shannon asked if I would talk about it, and I foolishly agreed to do so.
So that's why I'm standing here now. I'm going to start with a brief history of how we got to where we are.
The OG typing pep was at 44, actually 43, but 44 was the one that specified how it all works.
And it said that at runtime annotations are eagerly evaluated. So we have this propagate function.
The names sum of and none are evaluated as the module is executed as this function is being constructed immediately to whatever they refer to.
And that works great in simple cases. But if we have, say, circular references like this case, we will get to this child annotation and not yet have a child class.
So that name will refer to nothing and we'll get a name error, which is unpleasant. So pep-44 recommends that we should put that in quotes to avoid that problem.
A similar case is the self-referential case because the body of the class is executed when the class name has not yet been bound in the namespace.
We also have to manually quote that type of annotation.
Another case is if you have circular references between modules that only involve annotations, sometimes you'll hide some of those imports using type checking to avoid a runtime import cycle.
And again, that name is not going to exist in the namespace at runtime, so we have to quote that annotation.
So this all works. All the type checkers support resolving these. And at runtime, you can use typing.getTypeNits to introspect some function or class and get its annotations.
And getTypeNits will look up the stringified names in the namespace, the global namespace of the module and resolve the real objects when you ask for them and give you back the dictionary of the annotations resolved to real objects.
But as people began using type annotations more broadly, this was just unpleasant.
It also explained to people why in writing you have to put quotes around annotations. It looks strange. It makes it look like types are kind of a hold-on feature of a language.
So people wanted to avoid this. And there was another problem, which is that eager evaluation meant that in a large code base, you could spend a significant amount of CPU time and memory compiling and evaluating all of these annotations, even if you may never use them at runtime because it looked like it really interested in the static type checking.
So given all of those issues, a smart fellow named Uka Shuana came along and said, we have the support for annotations to be strings, so why don't we just make them all these strings all the time and resolve some of these problems?
So under PEP563, you can say from, to, triple annotations. And now, even though we don't manually quote anything, these annotations become strings and we just get strings back. They're never evaluated.
Unless we again call typing.getTypeHints, which as we already saw, is able to resolve those to the real objects once the namespace is complete. This approach solves the circular reference problem. We don't call getTypeHints until the model is done executing. All the names will exist and everything is happy.
It solves the performance problem because strings are very cheap. So we can load those strings up really quickly. It doesn't have an extensive runtime cost. Another nice benefit that it has is that once value that annotations provide is documentation.
People want to know what does this function take, what does it return. The ideal documentation uses the annotations as they are typed in the source code. An example of runtime documentation is the built-in help function. If you say help some function, it will tell you about the signature of that function.
Ideally, if you have a type alias referring to some massive union, you would prefer the help function to tell you that the parameter takes this nice semantic type alias name, not some massive unreadable union. It happens that annotations as strings serves this use case very well because all of the strings, exactly as they were typed in the source code, represent your runtime.
Can I ask a quick question on that? Yes. Presumably the annotations still have to be valid syntax, right? Yes, that is a very good point. So with pet.py63, the annotation must be valid syntax, it must parse. It does not have to compile, which is an important distinction that we'll review later. So you can say it's a type or module you haven't imported.
You can say it's anything that's valid syntax and the runtime won't care unless you call it get type and then all of a sudden it will care and you can't find it. Static checkers also care. It's true, static checkers care doesn't exist at all.
Okay, so at first it seemed that pet.py63 solved all the problems and made everyone very happy, but as it turned out later, we know now that not everyone knows that. Because people, as we just saw in the last talk, people do use type annotations for things that are not static type checking, it turns out.
We saw many libraries in David's talk, I just have a few of them mentioned here, typecar and pygantic. And people even do things like writing code in nested scopes in Python, it turns out. And sometimes they reference names from nested scopes in annotations.
And get type-nets is not that smart when it is resolving a string. All it knows how to do is look things up in the global namespace of the module. In this particular case, it will try to look up these two names, they aren't in the global namespace and it will fail.
So that makes pygantic users unhappy. So last year when pet.py63 was scheduled to become the default behavior in Python 3.10, users of pygantic and other libraries said, oh no, you're going to break our code.
And around that same time, another smart person named Larry J. Steens came up with an idea called pet.py649. Larry said, it turns out that in Python, when we have some code and we want to delay its evaluation, we have this neat trick for doing that, it's called a function.
And functions already know how to look up names in various nested scopes and keep track of those as a closure or as a global associated with the function and all that already works in Python. We don't typically preserve code for later use as a string.
So Larry said, why don't we do the same thing with annotations?
So under pet.py649, every annotated function or class has a DUNDERCOAnnotations attribute, which is a Hillary function. And when you call it, then you will get a result dictionary of all your annotations with the values as the fully resolved objects.
Or if you just access the DUNDERCOAnnotations attribute, it will behind the scenes call COAnnotations for you and cache the result and give you that same dictionary.
So now this example works because the annotations are stored in the function, the function is a closure, it goes about the nested scope, with the names in it, everything just works.
So I can ask another question?
Yes, of course.
Before pet.py649, so we wrote pet.py563, what was preventing you from just using getTypen to look up the actual frames?
In an example like this nested one?
Or just in general, I guess the nested one is still a problem.
So in general, with simple cases of only referring to global module level names and annotations, getTypens works just fine.
The problem is that people do do more complicated things and then what you resolve over on time was more complicated, nested things don't work.
There was also a debate about getTypens calls eval, so it's slower, but there's a tradeoff because Typens you're not using getIgnored, but the material could be slower.
Yes, okay, so pet.py649 does seem to solve that nested scoping problem.
However, it did introduce a few new problems that pet.py563 didn't have.
If we look at the data classes feature in the standard library, it is one case where the standard library cares about annotations and wants to resolve them in a class decorator.
Now the fun thing about class decorators is they run immediately from the classes defined.
So in this example with the circular reference among data classes, the data class decorator runs on parent and once again child is not yet defined.
So all of this work we've done to delay the evaluation of annotations is not very useful if we then go ahead and try to resolve them eagerly without waiting.
So this is an issue that pet.py649 introduces.
Now the interesting thing about data classes is that data classes doesn't really care all that much about what is in the annotation.
All it really cares about is whether the annotation is wrapped in a class var or in a midvar.
The rest of the annotation it doesn't care about.
And we'll come back to that point later, but for now we'll just say this is an issue we need to resolve with pet.py649.
Another potential issue with pet.py649 is that it is less friendly to the documentation case or the wide help case that we discussed earlier.
Because you're only going to get whatever the fully expanded runtime representation of your annotation is.
You won't get the nice semantic name that was originally typed in source code.
So we'll need to look at how we can resolve that.
So that brings us up to today where the future remains unclear.
So we have a little bit of a delay here.
Pet.py63 was accepted in Python 3.7, which is now on hold.
The steering council decided not to make it the default behavior in 3.10 because of these issues that come up.
And so it's kind of in limbo.
And pet.py649 is still in traffic.
So in order to hopefully move this forward a little bit, I'm going to try to present a high level comparison of those two pets along three axes.
So that's the migration path to the final state.
Starting with usability.
We kind of already started this discussion, right?
And looking at history.
We saw what some of the usability problems with each of the pets are for different use cases.
So now I'm going to talk about some things that have been proposed that could resolve or patch up some of those usability rules and what that would look like.
So for pet.py63, we saw that it can't handle names and nested scopes.
Lukas, the author of the pet, has proposed that we could expand this implementation so that it does track reference names from local scopes and keep around on the object some kind of closure of those names that will be needed to resolve the annotations.
And then get type names could be made smart enough to use these to help resolve the names.
So if we implemented that, pet.py63 would be able to handle this type of case.
Now even with that kind of improvement, there are still many cases where pet.py63 is going to surprise people at runtime.
It still ultimately is preserving code as a string, which has no useful metadata around it, and then making a best effort later on to stitch that string back together with some names because then hopefully it will come up with something that works.
For instance, don't copy the annotation strings anywhere else to any other object and then later try to resolve them because they'll lose their names and they won't resolve them.
This might seem a bit theoretical, but in fact the only two things in the standard library that really care about annotations, type dict and data class, both have this exact bug.
And it's been fixed in type dict, but not yet in data classes.
So both type dict and data classes in one way or another need to take annotations from a base class and copy it over onto a subclass.
And so they both do that. And on the pet.py63, that breaks if you have a data class in one module and then a subclass of it in another module and you try to resolve some type dicts on subclass.
It's going to be trying to resolve annotations from the base in the wrong namespace and it just breaks.
So this has been worked around in type dict. It could also be worked around with some special case code for data classes.
But I think it kind of illustrates that with pet.py63, it's a bit working against the grain of one-time resolution annotations.
And it's likely that this kind of issue is going to continue to bite people at one time indefinitely as they try to do creative things with the annotations.
Okay, moving on to pep649 and how we could address some of the issues with it.
We saw this case of the cyclic reference in data classes.
And as we saw, the data classes actually has very limited introspection needs.
So if there is only some way we could reliably figure out if an annotation is a class bar or an emit bar without needing to worry about whether the other names in the annotation resolve, that would be nice.
If you're observing, you may have already been asking yourself, why doesn't this break on the pet.py63?
Because even on the pet.py63, if data class tried to resolve the annotations using get type hints, it would break in exactly the same way.
And the answer is that data class avoids the issue entirely with a fairly unpleasant hack, which is that it just looks at the string annotation and looks for literally the text class bar or emit bar.
And if it's there, it's probably a class bar or emit bar.
And so it never resolves it.
And of course that could break trivially if you alias or shadow those names in strange ways, but it was decided that was a better tradeoff to avoid causing this problem.
With pet.py649, we can't use that workaround because we don't have a string to regex match against.
You just have a function.
But there is something we can do.
Turns out we can eval a code object, which is not as expensive as evalving a string because we're not parsing and defining the code.
It's a code object. We're just calling it in a fun way.
We can call it with our own global dictionary.
And we can make the global dictionary a special dictionary that finds that we're missing.
If there's any missing name, we'll just return some kind of miss and wrap object.
And this is fine for data classes because, as I said, it doesn't care about all the other stuff in the annotation.
It just wants to look for that class bar or emit bar.
So if we do this, all the names that are there will resolve.
Names that aren't there will give us back an object.
We won't get a name error.
And that is how this case works.
So this behavior could be in an agility function.
It could be in a type-ins.
It could be built in data classes.
It's not something that looks a little ugly.
It's not something that end users would have to do.
We built it into the right tooling.
But most importantly, it solves the data class case.
We can use a similar technique.
I might skip through this pretty quickly because it's a little iffy.
We can get annotations, the original annotations of strings.
We can do that in a similar way where we define some kind of stringifier class that takes a name.
And then if you get item it, it puts together a longer string with the brackets of the dot.
It kind of reproduces the original code that would have been written there.
And it turns out this works.
And we can do a similar thing where everything just becomes one of these stringifier objects.
And if we do that, we can get back the original annotation, my areas in this case.
So that's one way we could satisfy this use case on our PEP 649.
Another way we could...
Oh, I inserted this slide at the wrong point.
Okay.
Another way we could is just say if you want the original text in the source code,
just go look at the original source code.
Maybe a simpler approach.
You can use inspect.getSource to get the source of the function.
You can parse the AST.
You can use AST.onParsed.
Essentially, you can produce what PEP 563 does and get back the original text of those annotations.
Again, this could be built into a utility function that these documentation tools could use.
So that's another option.
Another important limitation of PEP 649 that we touched on earlier and we should consider
is that under PEP 563, tagged annotations must only be valid syntax.
Under PEP 649, they must compile.
And that's important because some people like to use new type syntax that's only been introduced
in, say, 310 and use it on the 38 code base.
And if they're using PEP 563, they can do that because it's valid syntax.
But it won't compile.
So in a case like this where we're on Python 3.7, we're trying to use in pipe string.
Under PEP 563, this would work fine.
Under PEP 649, it would not.
Sorry, wouldn't that still work?
It works as long as you don't inspect the annotations, right?
Oh, sorry.
This would work as long as you don't inspect the annotations you're writing.
Yes.
Sorry.
It compiles.
It doesn't run.
Yes.
I'm sorry.
I got that wrong on the slide.
This does compile.
It doesn't run.
So if you inspect the annotations, this wouldn't break.
Okay.
Moving on.
Performance.
I added that slide at the last minute and clearly it's a mistake.
Okay.
So I wanted to look at performance.
Now Larry has said that we shouldn't consider performance as the primary factor in making
this decision because the important thing is to get the right semantics for the language
and then we can optimize them.
Generally, I agree.
I think that's right.
It also doesn't hurt to look at the current state of the performance comparison and see
what the starting point is for whatever optimization we're doing.
So I wanted to benchmark a real production codebase with a lot of tech annotations like
Instagram server codebase, but the PEP649 reference implementation is based on a 3.10
alpha and getting any real codebase to run on a alpha.tyton is impossible.
So I didn't have time to actually forward port the implementation.
So instead I did a synthetic benchmark where I generated a module with 10,000 classes and
functions.
Person zero, person one, and person nine, nine, nine, nine.
They all look identical, but they're all separate classes.
Let's build that for 666.
Oh.
And yeah, I'm using this typing in a fairly simple, typical way that you might see type
annotations used.
So I think it's not a ridiculous benchmark, hopefully.
I timed it like this using user bin time.
Just importing the module.
Obviously, we did a warmup run to do the very slow initial compilation of that massive module,
but what I'm actually timing is the subsequent runs where we have a PYC and we're just importing
it.
I did a bunch of runs and averaged them.
Didn't do any fancy statistics.
The numbers did not vary a lot, so I didn't feel they were pretty consistent.
This is where it came out.
As we probably expected, we see that PEP563 has a bit of an advantage both in time and
in the max memory usage, but the difference is not huge.
You might expect particularly the memory usage difference to be more than that when you're
talking about strings versus code objects, but actually it's not a lot.
And another thing that's worth pointing out here is it has been proposed that we could put the
annotations into a separate section of the Marshall data in the PYC file and only load that
section lazily if the annotations are actually requested.
If we could implement that, that would essentially reduce the overhead for both of these approaches
to zero, so it would erase any difference between them.
In the case we're not expecting.
Do you know how these compare to the Eager Evaluation PEP44?
Are they both faster than that?
They are both significantly faster than PEP44.
I could revise the slide and put PEP44 numbers on, but I don't think I'll do that here.
I didn't really include 44 in the comparison, but I think for a number of reasons nobody is
seriously proposing that we stick with Eager Evaluation forever, so I just considered these two options.
Okay.
All right.
Going on to the last question, which is the question of migration to reach one of these end states.
So a couple possibly debatable assumptions that I'm making in this section.
It is a bit subtle, but although PEP649 and PEP44 both resolve annotations to real one-time objects in a way
that should look very similar, in practice if you rebind a name to a different value in a module, you could
get different results from PEP649 than you would have gotten from 44.
Now, you can argue how likely that is, how common it is, how much of a problem it is, but it has the potential
to create code, which I think means that we would need a future import for PEP649 and a transition period,
not just a flip-and-switch in one version and suddenly we have new semantics.
Second assumption, which in my opinion is less debatable, someone could debate it, which is that libraries,
particularly libraries that use a lot of annotations and have already started to adopt PEP63, I think those
libraries need to be able to write multi-version code, code that supports all the supported Python versions
without being forced back to PEP44 semantics to do that.
And what that means is that if we choose to move to 649, the existing PEP563 future import has to stay in Python
and keep working until the oldest supported Python has 649 available.
Since the earliest version at this point 649 could go into reasonably is 3.12, that means that 563 would need to
stick around until 3.12's end of life, which is many years down the road at this point.
So we'd be going for quite a while with two side-by-side implementations available.
So, yes, given those assumptions, what does the churn look like with this migration intent, for whom?
So there's a very clear split here between different communities of users.
For PyNantic style users who've never adopted PEP563 in the first place, migrating from 484 to 649 will certainly be
a less disruptive transition than 44 to 563. As we discussed, the way that 44 and 649 look at runtime is very,
very similar, whereas 44 to 563 is almost certain to be some issues, even if we do the improvement for nested
scopes. So that community of users would definitely have a less disruptive transition if we go to 649.
On the other hand, for users of static typing who have started adopting 563, obviously the less disruptive
transition would be to not do anything, to keep using 563.
I do think that even for this community, if and only if we can do the lax globals thing so that existing data class
circular references don't start breaking suddenly, if we do that, I think that the migration from 563 to 649
for those users should not be too bad. In most cases, apart from things like data class, which do it, which introspect the
annotations without you wanting to, most of these users aren't even introspecting annotations anyway, so they aren't
really going to care.
This brings us to the overall winner and the part where I cop out. So obviously how you evaluate all of this, it really
depends on what you value and how you weigh the different use cases and factors and communities of users.
I will give you my opinion, which is if we assume that, and these are things that I do believe, that annotations are
certainly at this point not only for static typing and for documentation, but that I think all of those other
run-time use cases we saw are equally valid and equally supported use cases for annotations, if we believe that,
and if we also believe that it's worth some medium-term turn, like two competing future annotations for future
future annotations available for a number of releases, if it's worth some medium-term turn to reach a preferable
long-term state, if both of those things are true, then I do think that 649 semantics are a more natural fit that
integrates annotations better into the entire language, which is something Steering Council has said that they want,
and will generally lead to less surprising behavior and bugs at runtime when people try to use annotations at runtime,
and probably should be preferred. If we want to negate one of those two assumptions, either of them, I think,
that would tend to point towards Pet563 as maybe a preferable option, and I feel compelled to observe that even if many
people in this room would like to say that annotations are for static typing, that doesn't mean the Steering Council will agree with us.
So, that's my conclusion, and I'm interested, very interested, in hearing your thoughts.
What do you think of Larry's forward-class definitions? Larry's here?
Larry is here, hi Larry.
Larry is also here, hi Larry.
A lot of time getting deep into this, I think that they aren't necessary.
I think that one thing that I think is important for making the transition from Pet563 to 649 doable for existing
large-scale users of 649 is that this data class case, I don't know, I can't find any more.
The self-referential data class, that this case needs to keep working in existing code bases when they move from
563 to 649 without changing the code, without doing a viewport declaration thing or anything.
It just needs to keep working, which I think means we need the lax global solution in data classes either way.
Even if we wanted to do forward-class declarations, we would still need to do the lax global solution.
I think that's all that needs to be said about that. Right now I'm debating merits of forward-class declarations on my own merits
probably at another time, but that's where I think it's relevant for this question.
How do other languages solve this problem?
That's a good question and one I have not looked into at all.
Compiler!
I'm not aware of other languages that impact on type annotations relating to language evolution.
Type script doesn't preserve annotations of properties.
How many languages have that much support for front-end annotations of personalities?
I don't know.
Anyone know what Googy does?
No annotations.
I don't know what those annotations are.
There's a whole bunch of tables full of data people.
I'm not sure if we need to bring that up.
We erase that on time, but there's a concept of read by generics where you can compile and generate specializing for the word.
You can do the parsing without implementing those specializations instead of providing general access to annotations.
In Rust you can use a macro as your ultimate escape hatch to get access to the code.
I was going to say that I work in opening API generators in space and no language has as good support as Python does.
In Python you can introspect everything and generate primers and Rust every library is a bunch of macros.
It doesn't support anywhere near as much as you can get in Python.
Anyone know what Julia is doing?
The next version of this talk will have a survey of the language.
Yes?
I think Julia suggested that with PEP 649 using new syntax from later versions could be a problem.
It seemed unclear whether it actually was.
I just wanted clarification.
That was the slide I added late this afternoon.
The new versions must compile, but in general when people want to use...
When we introduce new things like the type operator working on built-in types, that compiles fine on older versions.
It just doesn't run because those types in older versions don't have the render or method on them.
This would actually work fine as long as you don't introspect annotations.
Thank you.
I'm Kevin and I work at DeepMind.
We've implemented another type generator.
I want to talk a little bit about Python subtyping.
Subtyping is really important. Why is subtyping important?
There's a PEP 483 which gives some of the theory behind the original type in PEP.
It defines a relation called is consistent with.
This is basically what some of them would call something like signability.
It tells us when we have an expression with a static type 2.1
and we pass that or assign that to a variable with an annotation of static type 2.2.
That includes parameters, passing arguments for parameters.
It includes returning values from functions of a return type annotation.
The first clause of the rules for consistency is that a type is consistent with another type if it's a subtype.
If we want to implement this signability check, we have to implement subtyping inside of a type checker.
That's why subtyping is important.
The PEP 483 also covers subtyping a little bit.
It's not entirely complete. It doesn't try to be.
It says that it's a start point to a speckle. It's not intended to be a speckle.
As such, it's not always clear what the intended behavior is on subtyping.
Another drawback of using this PEP as a speckle is that it's never been updated in the presence of new typing features which are constantly being introduced.
I list a bunch of things there. That all depend on subtyping or impact in some way.
Obviously, the PEPs are going to constantly be updated to do those things.
What we frequently do is we'll black box test some type checker implementations to figure out what the intended behavior is when we implement a checker.
As a jumping off point to talk about subtyping, I found a couple of conversations on Slack channels or chat forms that I've done.
Where people who are experienced Python developers or who understand Python types quite well were talking about typing.
I said, I think that union of any and foo is equal to any. Wolf, who is actually an implementer of a Python type checker, says that too.
In a different conversation, Frog said you should use any as a type connotation which is the same as optional.
I wanted to use that as a jumping off point.
Obviously, first of all, these people speaking don't mean double equal or same as in any sort of formal sense.
They're speaking informally. I did want to ask what it means formally in terms of subtyping.
I'll focus on the second one. Is any the same as optional?
From the standpoint of subtyping, it would be the same if they were subtypes of each other.
Here's a little quiz. There is some money in this situation.
What is the subtype relation between any and optional any?
If you think that any is a subtype of optional any, raise your hand.
Excellent. If you think that optional any is a subtype of any, raise your hand.
Got some? So there are some bulbs there. If you think that neither of these is true, raise your hand.
Nobody is going to go for neither.
If you think it's unspecified or rather should be unspecified, check your sheet of paper. Raise your hand.
We have a few takers for that as well.
PEP 483 does have some rules for subtyping of unions. I put them on the slide to see that it's dense.
I'm going to give an alternative definition of subtyping for unions.
This is pretty standard. There are two rules.
The first one tells us what it means for something to be a subtype of a union.
A type is a subtype of a union if it is a subtype of at least one of the components of the union.
The second rule, so-called union on the left, tells us what it means for a union to be a subtype of a type.
That is if all of the components of the union are subtyped for that type.
In the PEP 483 definition of subtyping for unions, a lot of those points were consequences of this more simple definition.
Which I claim is the one.
We'll use this one.
Now we can ask part of that question. Is any subtype of a polyoptional union?
Yes?
Is X a subtype of that union? When we say subtype, are we always including itself as one?
I believe so, yes. I believe we want that property of subtyping, yes.
Is any a subtype of optional any?
The answer is maybe. We need any to be a subtype of any or else any to be a subtype of none.
According to the rules that I gave.
I think it's intended that this is true because any is a subtype of any.
I believe it's intended that any is not a subtype of none.
PEP 483 is actually not crystal clear about this.
Because it's using just plain English instead of formal English.
It just says that any is not a subtype of every type.
Which could be read to mean that there exists some type T that any is not a subtype of.
I don't think this is exactly what it's intended.
But that's a sort of perversity to that.
It also says that every type is not a subtype of any.
Which could be interpreted to mean that there is no type T that is a subtype of any.
Including any itself. I do believe that we intend that any is a subtype of any.
That subtyping is requested. Even for any which is kind of a wild card special case.
So can we observe subtyping? Is there any place where we can observe subtyping?
There is one convenient place where we can observe subtyping.
If we have two components of the union that have a subtype relation.
We eliminate the subtype from the union. So the example is that manager is a subtype of employee.
And we eliminate manager from the union.
So I wrote a function. It's a generic function.
Generic and two type variables T and U. And it takes a T and a U.
And returns the union of T and U. And I gave it an implementation.
Because Pyright was a really clever, all kind of inline specialized function.
And all science and type checkup. So I gave it an implementation that would defeat Pyright.
And then I used reveal type.
To show what the type of that is. And I used CAS.
Which allows me to ascribe a static type to an expression.
To ask what is the union of any and optional any.
If any is a subtype of optional any. We would expect that
What would survive in a union is optional any.
MyPy says yeah. That's fine.
And Pyright says yeah that's fine. So that is what I expected.
I tested Pytype and it just says any.
Which seems to indicate that perhaps optional any is a subtype of any.
And there was some takers for that when I asked the question.
And Pyright says the same.
So is Pytype wrong? Is that a plug against Pytype?
I say maybe not. So I say reveal type is not standard.
It will become standard. So that's good.
But maybe. But still a little bit unspecified what is happening with reveal type.
So perhaps Pytype is implementing the union internally.
And when it renders that type it's only showing it as any.
So it really has internally optional any.
We saw that some expert QGN programs thought that was the case. Those were the same.
So I asked a more graphic question. What is the type of optional any?
And it did show me optional any. So it's not the case that it's doing something different.
It's rendering the type.
So what is really going on is I pulled a fast one when I gave this function union.
That was a generic function that took two arguments.
And claimed that it would return the union. It doesn't necessarily actually return the union.
So the way that generic functions work is that at a call site they're implicitly
instantiated. We choose types or the type variables T and U based on the static types of the arguments.
So the static types of the arguments will generate constraints on T and U.
We'll do some sort of constraint solving to find out what the solution to these constraints are.
And that will be the answer.
Parameter passing was based on consistency.
I claimed.
And so the constraints that we generate must be consistency constraints.
So what we really need is that any is consistent with T.
And optional any is consistent with U.
I'm saying these are not subject constraints because
assignability is based on this consistency relation.
So one solution, the one I acted as was the expected one, is that
T is actually equal to any and U is actually equal to optional any.
But another solution is that those are both any.
Because any is consistent with any type.
And so a valid solution to this system concerning this would be any.
And I feel like that's what PyTex is actually choosing. It's choosing a different solution.
Another solution would be that T is tuple of int and int.
And that U is optional string.
And there's lots more. So because I put any in there and any is consistent with anything we can do a lot of weird things.
So the punchline is we'd like to talk about
what is the best solution to these systems of constraints.
And we don't quite have the machine we need for that.
So given that there's some weirdness going on with this generic function, let's just directly ask
what happens if I ask for the union of any and optional any.
So we would expect that this is optional any.
That was my line. And PyWrite and PyTex would agree.
So PyTex is finding a different solution to the constraints of the generic function.
But they both agree. PyRest still says any.
So PyRest seems to really agree that those two types are actually the same.
And MyPy did a really weird thing.
It showed me that the union of any and optional any was any and any and none.
So that's interesting.
So maybe that is a bug in MyPy.
I don't think I would actually believe that any is a sub-individu.
So by black-boxing, I can't tell.
Another way to task would be with a conditional expression.
So we have conditional expressions and two su-expressions.
We would expect the type of this to be the so-called least upper bound
of the static types of the two su-expressions.
So the least upper bound is a common supertype.
So we want it to be an upper bound because that's safe.
We want it to be the least upper bound because that will avoid
spurious type errors if we try to use this somewhere else.
And the least upper bound always exists in Python because we have unions.
It's always the union. So there's always a least upper bound with respect to subtyping.
So we should be able to ask this question of our four type checkers.
And find out what they think about that.
And Pyright and Pytype gave me the answer expected.
Mypy gave me something different. Pyre gave me something. Pyre is consistent with
what Pyre showed me before, which is that things those are the same. And Mypy again
surprised me because it's not finding the least upper bound. It's doing something
more like solving some constraints on some
implicit type variables.
So the join with the two types instead of the union.
So the join with the two types. My py doesn't believe in the terms.
My py doesn't believe in the terms.
So Pyre said that
Pyre didn't believe in those two types were the same. So as Pyright
should optional any be a subject of any? And again maybe
the product thought it was. At conjecture there's no program where you can put
any instead of optional any or optional instead of any
and detect a difference in terms of static checking behavior.
Other than the string representation of error messages for instance.
I've spent a lot of time talking about this one.
About that union of any. One more interesting question is what about the
union of any an object?
So Mypy says that this is union of any an object.
Py type says the same. Pyre says this is any.
So it's treating any as kind of a top type in the
subtype hierarchy. The object is somehow a subtype of any.
The PEP 483 actually has a line that's interesting. It says that
there's a corollary that union of anything that includes object returns object.
I think that might just be a bug in PEP. But that implies
that any is a subtype of object. Because by the rule
you would need that to eliminate any from that union.
But that's actually not ridiculous. It does have some nice consequences.
So if we said that any was a subtype of object, then
any would have the methods that are on the type step for an object
in a type check. And we could specifically say that if we invoke something like
for instance hash on any, we would get the
return type int instead of any. Which is not
a good thing. We have a little stir so it can't just have the castor
strength. So that actually might be something we want.
So that was all
about any. And any is a really weird kind of wild card.
So maybe you think that there's something weird going on with any.
And so there's a couple other cases that don't involve any that I found interesting.
So what about tuples?
So we have rules for subtyping of tuples. Basically a tuple
type is a subtype of another tuple type if they have the same length.
And the components are component-wise subtypes. That makes sense.
We also have variadic homogeneous tuples.
And I think that you could obviously extend the subtyping rule to say that
two variadic tuples have the same length as each other because they both have no length.
And that no fixed size tuple has the same length as a variadic tuple.
So I think it's an obvious way to extend this rule to include
subtyping of variadic tuples. The question I wanted to ask
is what is the subtype relation between a fixed size tuple
and a variadic tuple? So another little quiz.
What should the subtype relation be between a variadic
tuple against and a pair of these?
So if you think that the variadic tuple is a subtype of a pair,
raise your hand.
No takers for that.
What if you think that the pair is a subtype of a variadic tuple?
Yeah, lots of people make that. So there's no way to decide.
What about neither?
Okay, we have one person who says neither. Who thinks that this should be unspecified?
We shouldn't know.
I tried to test this and it seems like all the checkers agree that there is no subtype relation.
You put those in the union together, it doesn't eliminate either one of those.
And that surprised me a little bit. Because I actually did, I
agreed with most of the people there and thought that there should be a subtype relation. It's safe to pass
the pair where I expect a variadic tuple.
So maybe what's really, but I do know that the checkers actually allow me to do that.
So what might be going on is that it's a kind of a consistent, it's not a subtype relation
exactly, but it's a kind of consistency relation where it says that the
pair is consistent with the variadic tuple.
So I wrote another function to try to test that out. It's a generic function
that tries to force me to find a type that is consistent with two types.
So X and Y have the same type, T.
So I'm trying to generate constraints to find a type that's consistent.
And what I found is that my pypyreg and pyre
all pick the variadic tuple, which is very nice
and that's a good behavior for type checking. So I do seem to think that they're
consistent. Py type kept the meaning.
So py type found the solution. So that means that maybe py type does believe that they're consistent, but
they found a different solution to, again, there's some system of constraints, we don't have any meaning
solution necessarily. So do we all
agree they're consistent? So I wrote another function that would allow me to upcast from a
pair of ints to a tuple of ints. This should be okay
if I can cast implicitly up from a pair to a
variadic tuple of ints. And everybody agreed that was okay.
Can I downcast from the pair of ints
to the variadic tuple? And my py and pyre said it's an error.
Which is probably good, but they don't agree that there's a
subtype relation, which is interesting. Py type and pyre both actually said that was okay.
So my interpretation is that py type and pyre are
treating this as a kind of consistency relationship. It's not subtyping.
And just like any, it allows implicitly upcasting and downcasting.
Though one of those is not safe. And then my py and pyre
was treating it also as a kind of consistency, but it's not allowing downcasting.
And finally, what about
function signature subtyping? So we can subtype for functions, not just palpable.
And this is pretty confusing because we have
positional only, named only, optional parameters. It makes it pretty complicated.
You can write out all the cases. You can decide
them. Writing a single rule that determines
if a pair of functions signatures are subtypes is not that easy.
So another little quiz is
what is the relationship between a signature
that has a pair of
arguments in str and another signature that has
a required argument and an optional str argument?
So if you think that the signature with two required arguments
is a subtype along with an optional argument, there's your hand.
It takes a while to think about that.
Nobody does. The other way around.
Okay. So how many things both?
Does anyone think that there's neither?
And I think we should leave this unspecified.
So it actually should be. I think it shouldn't be. And this is actually important here
because if we do compatible override checking for subclassing
we need to actually allow this kind of relationship to be ferment.
So I asked
all these type checkers this question. And so my pi and pi type
said yes, which is what I expected. And again
I put it in a new mean and see if one gets eliminated. Both with caveats.
So in corner cases they're doing good things. I have a pretty
exhaustive test suite. So there's cases where maybe the implementers
of those tools think those are bugs. Pyright Pyroball said no,
but again with caveats. It's too bad that not Pyright people are here
because one interesting thing with Pyright is that it depends on which
order you put things. When you're solving constraints to a generic function
which solution it will choose. Which I think is a very undesirable behavior.
And then the last thing about function subtyping is
what about generic function signature subtyping? So we have
generic functions. I would expect that a generic signature
was a subtype of all of its instantiations. So in other words
I have a function that needs a callable that takes a mass of string to a string
and I have a generic function that takes
a mass of t to t. I would expect that
the generic function is a subtitle of that instantiation
so that it's safe for me to pass the generic function
to a decorative function.
So I asked that question. So we don't have syntax for
unfortunately we don't have syntax for a generic callable.
I suggested on the typing stick that we use lambda and then I put a smiley
so I thought it was joking, but I was actually dead serious.
So it's exactly what it is. So we say that there's a generic callable
and is that a subtype of the instantiation? And my Pyright says yes.
Which is what I want. And all the other tools say that.
So what we really need
is something that we don't actually have spelled out, which is something like
consistent subtyping. So we need a notion of consistency
and we need a notion of subtyping and we need to combine them in a way that makes sense for the Python
subtyping system to come up with something like
consistent subtyping. So if we go back to the PEP again, we have a rule that says
that a type can be a subtype of another and another rule that says that any is consistent with
everything and that everything is consistent with any.
And this is pretty standard from what's known as gradual typing.
But these rules aren't complete. It doesn't allow us to conclude that
list of int is consistent with list, for instance.
Because there's no rule that lets us do that. So we have to allow
that the type argument has some relation. We also want to
conclude that, and we have to be careful there because list is invariant, so we don't want to
have a rule that allows us to conclude that list of int is consistent with list of flow.
We don't want that. We also want list of int to be consistent with
sequence. We would like,
I claim, to be able to characterize what is the best solution
to system constraints.
So we need something more than just
subtyping. So the conclusion of the call for action
is that we should actually respect for what we intend
to implement. Because perhaps we're building on this already.
Like, for instance, the variadic generic path assumes that there's some kind
of subtyping relation between variadic tuples. And not only variadic tuples,
variadic tuples can have a variadic bit in the middle somehow.
And we don't know what that is for sure. Of course checkers are always free to implement
anything they want, but they should be able to intentionally
implement a difference of intended behavior. And they should be able to
characterize what that is. And then we should be able to recognize bugs in the implementation.
So we should be able to eventually produce some kind of performance testing.
That's it. Thank you.
Applause
Questions?
Question?
definition of what should happen if you access the attribute of a union.
I don't think we have that specification.
I think that's a good point. I think you might be right.
And then I think we should write that down so we know that's what we should implement.
It's also not just a matter of what we should implement,
but it's also a matter of how we explain this to developers.
Because listening to developers talk, they actually do believe that they're the same.
So I think you might be right that they're different.
I think that interjection should be wrong.
This was again the slide that I put in at the last minute.
But I think you could be right.
I think we should decide that that's what it is. We should write it down.
I'm curious what the use case of any is.
Do we actually want it to be part of the type system?
Because I think right now Pyre paints it as an escape hatch,
where it's like, I don't want you to type check things against this.
This should just be excluded, essentially. It should be consistent with everything.
In that sense, if you join something to it, we basically say,
since it can sometimes be any, you still don't want type errors against it.
So in that sense, it's a different application than just an object, I guess.
So Shannon was saying that what is the status of any?
I think there's different answers to that.
So the system that Python has seems to be based on gradual typing.
And the gradual typing view of any, or dynamic, or whatever you call that type,
is that it's an arbitrary static type.
So at some point, there's some static type that you could eventually write in there
that would be the static type.
And so from that standpoint, so that's one view of any.
Another view of any is that you just take a very naive, stat theoretic idea of what types are,
their sets of values, and then any describes a set of all Python values.
So it's a kind of top type.
That's what we did.
Yeah, that's what we did in Dart.
Object is a top type, and any was a top type.
But any had a special property that you can then reverse that type error.
I think Python has intentionally chosen something which is a little more subtle than that, though,
that it's not explicitly a top type with respect to subtyping.
Kind of both a top type and a bottom type.
Well, it's why we have this separate consistency.
So the comment was that it's both a top type and a bottom type.
I would say that I think it's a top type with respect to consistent subtyping,
and a bottom type with respect to consistent subtyping.
But not with respect to subtyping.
That's the way out of that maze that we're in.
Please write a new version of that for a free version.
Anybody?
Yeah, I think that's a possible way forward.
Another pat.
I know this hearing council requested one type of piece of this stuff.
I think you've got those specifications.
It would be potentially really great to have this shed as sweet as possible.
Do you have a subtype, Tom?
Yeah, I agree absolutely with that.
Those are the other...
Over here.
You have made a claim that we need this notion of the best solution of constraints.
I was wondering what the envision usefulness other than the new type.
What is it useful to have the best solution?
Well, since we want sub-order on types and we want to choose the least solution...
When are you forced to choose the solution?
That's the question.
When are you forced to solve, choose a solution?
Yes.
The way that generic functions usually work is that when you apply the function,
you choose instantiation of the function based on the types of the arguments.
At that point you have to generate constraints and then choose a solution.
If you choose a solution that's too big, then you can have spurious...
Another question.
I think one other similar place where type checkers vary on overloads.
What overload do you take?
Whenever there's some having really different type checkers will kind of take their own overload.
You need to see what their own...
So the comment was about overloads.
So yeah, type checkers should somehow statically resolve overloads.
And that's completely unspecified.
Okay.
Excellent. Thank you.
Applause.
I do have slides, but they're just talking points.
And yes, panelists might want to...
I'll try to read them. They're not very much.
I went over my inbox and looked for a few juicy quotes from people who don't seem to completely have bought into the typing overloads.
Here's a really long time Python core that he was in the Python community since 1994.
I'm going to come out as a strong minus one for sneaking anything typing related into even any built-in.
I don't know why I'm doing this. Maybe I...
Okay.
And this was...
The discussion was normally about should we add any as a built-in, but he read a whole lot into it and sort of clearly vented it.
Some of you may recognize who this is.
Python looks more and more like a language with typed declarations as a built-in particle language.
Its beauty has always been its simplicity, such is not the case anymore.
And then Fredrik Lund or someone else have both collaborate, set one, two, three, four, five, whatever.
I think they both said it.
But who said it first?
So here's another core dev.
Not quite as ancient, but someone who says, I do actually like typed annotations in straightforward situations.
They even found blogs for me and tool tips and PSPode are nice.
What I don't like is not being able to stick to simple stuff and not bother in annotating complicated bits.
Or being pushed into over strict annotations because it's too hard or too proposed to express dynamic type constraints.
This sounds like someone who would like to sprinkle generous amounts of any throughout their code or just leaving things unannotated.
And I know that VS Code in particular, or Instrict Mode, is really annoying about that.
Here is someone who's not a core dev, but I thought there was a general understanding that when typing was added to Python,
I presume he refers to Python 4.4, there would be no impact or at least minimal impact on people who didn't use it.
Oh, I remember who this is.
Now we see another instance of the attention creep.
This person has a really good view of where Python is going.
And then there was a core dev who just said, my grasp on the details of typing is tenuous and mixed.
Ah, okay, well I'll unplug because clearly my USB ports are not what they used to be.
Thank you, thank you.
It's okay.
I would also interject that the most recent talk you just saw, sorry, my own fancy statement, Kevin.
Almost everyone who's a core dev who's not in this room and several core devs who are in this room would feel that went straight over their head.
And also too esoteric, too bothered to learn more about Python.
So this sort of gets into the sort of accusation that the typing folks, the folks who either implemented type checkers or are heavy users of type checkers,
and want all their code to type correctly have lost sort of touch with the vast majority of Python core devs and possibly Python users.
I have no questions prepared.
I think that we had sort of an email thread where we all vetted about what kind of things went wrong between some typing folks and the core dev team and the steering council.
I think Matthew, I'd like to hear your experience a bit.
Can you say a bit more about your experience with getting a big typing company accepted?
Yeah. So with PEP 646, variadic generics, we initially thought, oh, this is just going to be the small things, like necessary prerequisite for other types of typing.
I mean, no problem at all. Maybe a few weeks. Two years later it's finally been accepted.
It's been accepted twice, by the way. It's been accepted twice. Wow.
I think the takeaway I actually realized while all the other folks were typing on this thread was just the importance of really aiming for keeping the practices as small as possible.
I think we both just weren't strict enough. We weren't strict enough about this in the first place, but I think also PEP 4.8.4 is a precedent of, hey, you're introducing a new feature.
Implement all the things. Whereas I think in retrospect we should have literally just been like, hey, what's the smallest chunk of this we can implement first?
And then go from there. I'd say other than that, though, my experience was very positive.
I thought the steering council was very understanding of the fact that, oh yeah, we had this last minute realization that there was a bug we needed to fix.
And the steering council did charge us a little bit, but we were very appreciative of the implementation process and accepted the second time.
My advice on that one is really we should have a policy of trying to keep PEPs as small as possible.
So encouraging people who are writing PEPs to do that. But yeah, some members of the court have, like, yeah, they have to have that confidence.
I'd like to say, the chiding bit, you had the bad luck of being the second one PEP that came with changes after we started considering it.
So we felt we needed, not for you as such, but for everyone, to remind everyone, don't waste our time.
And I mean, it's not that big a deal, but if everyone does it, it does become a big deal.
It's also important to understand that to you, especially when you modify it, it's a lot of time.
Because it doesn't work in a way that we go into the room and say, what do you think, what do you think, plus what have I done.
And that's not the way because our job is not to decide ourselves.
Mainly, that's the last resort is to reflect what the Python community thinks.
So it's literally going to all those mailings and like all be mailed by email, making sure that we understand all positions, what are the different gaps if they are,
and to make sure that every possible complaint that people have or things like that is reflected.
And if there is a last minute addition or change, it's just we need to go back and check everything against the new version.
So it's not about like, you know, we are very important people with, you know, our time is ready.
It's also like, it just doubles the time and we have like a huge queue.
Well, not anymore. We have a huge queue. We have to work through it.
Yeah, for now.
I'd like to invite Pradeep to say a few things about your experience with a PEP that didn't get accepted after,
I would say a lot of the dates in this group.
Yeah, so that is the callable syntax.
I think most of the typing sync community wants nice syntax for callable.
It's the most complicated type we have.
So beginning of the middle of last year, we all started discussing it.
Huge debates, lots of possible approaches.
We sort of narrowed it down, read on stuff.
But then when we went to Python there, we got a lot of strong pushback in one thread towards the end saying that it's troubling to see Python becoming more complicated for the sake of typing and making the language syntax more complicated.
So I think from that point onward, it's like a pretty hard set.
Several of those people.
Yeah.
Yeah, I think one question I had was what recommendation do you have for somebody who is ready to type a syntax book?
Should we try to open more non-typing code for folks early in the process?
It's hard to say because I understand the need for a lot of those changes is from the typing theory, which is fairly esoteric, if that's fair to say.
So for someone who doesn't care about static typing at all, or type announce at all, or dynamic typing at all, for them to be pulling and saying, hey, what do you think of the syntax for this use case, if they don't understand the use case and why it's important to be able to express those things, that's not going to end well.
That's just...
Well, I mean, they have to put in the effort to understand it, right?
So if there are core developers who are interested, then absolutely, if they want to.
But if it's not, you know, if you don't find something...
The core developers who are interested are probably already on the typing side.
Well, yeah, it's always me.
I think there is two sides of this story, because what happens for...
I mean, this is true for typing, but it's also true for other very specialized.
When you discuss, you say, okay, we have this problem, right?
And then you go to the specialized group and you say, can we find the best solution for this problem once we all think it's a problem?
And then you spend all this time and you iterate that it's hard work and, you know, like, I understand how hard it is.
But then you go to the general community and they may actually have questions about the problem at the end of your stack, right?
They say, okay, maybe it's a problem, but it's not worth solving, or at least with new syntax or the cost is not big.
So, you know, maybe you are spending all this time trying to find the resolution for the problem,
while maybe the bigger community doesn't think it's a problem worth solving with the cost that you're adding.
And trying to find, like, a solution or if that is the case, it's actually very challenging,
because as Thomas said, if you go to Python there, you now need to filter all the people that don't understand the problem.
And it's very hard for us as well, because we need to balance both things.
And many people don't understand that, you know, sometimes they come with a problem and they say, okay, but this is a problem, right?
And this is the solution and this is the best solution.
And then we say, no. And they say, why?
It's the resolution, because, you know, yes, it's a problem, but maybe it's not worth solving with more syntax, right?
Or whatever it is. There doesn't need to be syntax versus non-syntax.
So, I understand this quite hard. I don't think we have a magical solution.
We are quite approachable in the sense that you want to contact the string class before some kind of early recommendation,
or like maybe we say, for instance, a paper like the Collabor syntax that involves a lot of, you know, big changes.
You could contact the string class and say, okay, so what do you think is the best strategy here?
So, I can contact Python and I'm like, what do you think may happen?
So, you may be, you will have as much information as possible so you can have better decisions.
I know this is going to take a lot of time, but it's a tough problem, because it's a human problem at the end of the day.
And I think the thing is, there's a problem that needs to be solved.
The problem has a cost, like the fact that a problem exists causes all kinds of extra work that needs to be done, unreadable code, etc.
The solution also has problems. It also has a cost.
And those costs will be different, because if you don't use static typing, then the cost of not having all those syntax is zero.
So, any solution that's going to cost you anything is going to be a negative.
So, we need to make sure that we make clear how big of a problem it really is and how costly the solution is for others.
So that we can convince people that, yes, this is worth the cost.
Now, for the callable syntax, the Serial Council would announce on our own, like not even, ignore, not ignoring,
but not even considering the rest of Python Dev, that the syntax, the cost of the syntax was just too big for the problem.
And, I mean, it's an art thing to say, it's like, yeah, that problem isn't important enough to solve.
It is important, and we wish it could solve it, but not form the cost of that particular syntax,
because it had all kinds of small issues and larger issues, and it made complicated rules about precedence.
And, yeah, that's why we decided that particular pet is not worth it.
But that doesn't mean the problem isn't worth solving. We just don't have a good way of solving it.