All right, everyone. Welcome to PyCon 2022. So, it has been three years since we were
all last in person together. I spent a lot of time sort of trying to imagine what it
would feel like being back here in person, and I can tell you that anything that I imagined
has paled in comparison to what it's like to be back. And so, a lot has happened since
2019. I think we all know this. We've gone through things that we never could have foreseen,
and in a weird way, life sort of continued on throughout the pandemic. We've all had
losses and struggles, and I was first invited to chair PyCon back in 2018. And so, typically,
you sit in a chair for a year and then chair for two years. And I remember having a conversation
back in 2018 with E, who was the conference chair at the time, and I was like, I just
don't know where I'll be in that many years. And I just could not have possibly imagined
the things that this would have thrown at us throughout the pandemic. And so, one of
the most valuable things about our community is how accepting we are. And you see this
in occurrences like this. We were able to shift online and find other ways to still
try to connect as a community, how willing we were to come in with an open mind and creative
solutions. But none of that could really compare to what it would be like back in person. And
so, in the last three years, things sort of passed in this weird time vortex. So much
has changed, yet here we are again, like nothing's changed. And so, I'll see friends that I've
known for years or people that I've exclusively met over Zoom calls and it's like we just
saw each other yesterday. And that is what I think makes our community so unique. And
so, with that, I'm Emily Morehouse. I'm honored to have served for the last three years as
your steward of PyCon and I'm grateful from the bottom of my heart that I'm here with
you in person today. So, on behalf of the PyCon 2022 staff, I want to start by saying
thanks. Thanks to all of the volunteers who make every facet of this conference possible.
To the PyCon Software Foundation, its board and staff for taking on the management and
fiscal responsibility of this conference. To all of the sponsors who supported us through
our time online and have come back to sponsor us in person. To all of the presenters who
have come here to share their work. And to all of our attendees, both all of you in person
and those who are watching this live stream, we would be nothing without you. And so, welcome
to Salt Lake City. I really hope that you all can take the time to sort of see the sights
and experience what this awesome city has to offer. There's definitely something for
everyone. Food, a bunch of outdoor things to do, hiking, museums, tons of beautiful
churches and just a really great way, great transit system and I hope that you get to
experience a little bit of something about the city outside of these conference walls.
So, let's talk about what PyCon is. This is your very first PyCon. Congratulations and
I am sorry because PyCon has grown to be such a giant event that we just can't give you an
overview of every single event in this welcome. So, if this is your first PyCon, I hope that
you were able to attend the newcomer orientation yesterday with Kojo Trey and Melanie. But for
those of you who didn't, we have these little green pins that some folks are wearing on their
badges that say ask me. And so, if you have any questions about the conference or how to get the
most out of your experience here, find one of those people and I'm sure that they will be
absolutely thrilled to tell you about all things PyCon. So, from a high level, PyCon is separated
into three sections. The first doesn't really matter because it's over but that was our first
two tutorial days. So, starting today we have our three main conference days which will be followed
by two days of sprints. So, zooming a little bit further, today and tomorrow your day will start
with a keynote or keynotes followed by talks for the bulk of the day and then we'll close out with
lightning talks. On Sunday we've got a little bit of a different schedule. We're going to have a
couple of panels and a keynote in the morning and then you're going to go right into the job fair.
And then we'll have a smaller bulk of afternoon talks followed by our closing keynote and PSF
state of address. So, our keynotes. Right after this we're going to have Mukesh Langa. Tomorrow
we will have Sarah Isawan and Peter Wang. Sunday we'll have the Python Steering Council and Sunday
we will have Naomi Seder to close us out. But make sure you get here early on Sunday. We will still
start at 9 a.m. and we're going to have a special diversity inclusion work group panel at 9 a.m.
After the talk today, before keynotes tomorrow morning and again tomorrow after talks and then
Sunday morning before our keynote you'll find our lightning talks. And so these are fascinating
little events. Definitely take a chance to come in and peek in if you can or if you're interested
in giving a lightning talk we will have a sign up for this. It is something where you can talk about
anything and everything as long as it adheres to our code of conduct. It doesn't have to be
Python related but certainly can be and it's just a great place to share all those super weird little
ideas or things that you learned last week that you would love to share with others.
So, let's take a moment to sort of familiarize ourselves with the space that we are in because
we have quite a large space and we are a little bit spread out with a couple of things.
So, right now you are here in the grand ballroom which will host our plenary sessions over the next
three days. To your right, my left through these doors or out those doors and around the corner
we have our expo hall. This is located in exhibit C, D and E. It should be super obvious we are
sharing the space with another event so definitely take a look and make sure that you are seeing
make sure that you are seeing Python related signs wherever you are going. But all of our garage
doors should be open. It should be very obvious where the expo hall is. This is really going to
be the main hub of the conference and it contains tons of things so let's list at least most of them.
All meals for Sunday will be served in the expo hall. Please note that coffee and snacks
that happen during the breaks will be located directly outside of the talk rooms. So, don't
think that you have to run back from a talk to the expo hall to grab a coffee in between.
They will be very closely located to you. If you have indicated that you have any allergies or
dietary restrictions on your registration, make sure that you take a look for signs to direct
you in that area and if you ever have any concerns about ingredients or the food, please make sure
that you find a conference staff and ask them. And also, please take note and be aware of traffic
patterns while you are in the expo hall. We've tried to sort of facilitate a one-way flow
throughout a lot of the spaces. Some areas will have arrows on the floor. Just please be aware
of the ways that you're interacting with your fellow attendees as we are still trying to
maintain a decent amount of health and safety as much as possible. You will also find all of the
sponsor booths and the startup row in the expo hall. Definitely check out our sponsors. They are
doing really cool things. They put a lot of effort and money to put together really awesome
booze and bring swag for everyone. And honestly, these are just the people who have continued to
invest in PyCon and in the PSF who have allowed us to continue to flourish over the last couple of
years. All right. And then the posters and job fair. If you are looking for a job or are interested
in the posters, this is when the expo hall will transition over. Expo hall will be sponsors and
booths Friday and Saturday and then it's going to transition overnight. So when you come in Sunday
morning, it's going to be a whole new experience and we'll have all of our posters as well as the
job fair. All right. So talks. Talks are in three different areas of the conference space.
So charlas will be on this floor in a room number that I can't read but there's another slide that
has that room number on it. Otherwise, all of our talks will be on the second level or on the third
level. Again, check out those PyCon signs. They're going to be directing you which elevators and
escalators to use and how to get to those spaces. So this year we actually have five talk tracks on
our first two days and four on the last day with 92 sessions this year, which is incredible because
that's almost what we've had during our pre-pandemic in-person events. But unless you
have a time turner, you will only have 18 opportunities to see talks. But don't worry,
most of the talks will be recorded and available online as soon as possible. So definitely take
this into account for how you are scheduling your time. Don't burn yourself out going to talks.
Make sure that you are taking time to, one, take care of yourself and two, talk to other attendees
at the conference. We also have open spaces available. So these are an incredible opportunity
to meet with other attendees, share and learn and maybe find those people who have those funny
little interests or topics that you also really, really love. So you can organize your own or just
attend someone else's. So check out this URL, PyCon.us. And there will be a recent-ish photo
of the open spaces board. But be sure to check out that board in person if you want to sign up
for something. It will be outside of the stack room in 150A. And so PyCon has consumed the bulk
of this conference center. And so one of the best unofficial events that PyCon and many other
conferences have become known for is the hallway track. So again, join a table, meet somebody new,
open a laptop and work on a problem together. Track down that person that you've been wanting
to meet in person or that you haven't seen in years that you just want to say hi to.
And always keep in mind that when you are standing in a group of people, always leave room for one
extra person to join. This is a quote from air culture and it is a really excellent way to sort
of model inclusiveness in our community. So if you're standing in a group of people and somebody
wanders up and says, hey, can I chat with y'all? Make sure that you introduce yourself, say hi,
and maybe ask them, you know, is this your first PyCon? What are you excited about? And just start
up a conversation. All right. Some more fun logistical things. Okay. So there are two gender
neutral bathrooms throughout the conference center. One is near the first aid room on this floor. So
it's just around the corner from the gendered bathrooms. And then there is another one upstairs
near room 255 near one of the top rooms. There are also mother's rooms. While they are very poorly
named, they are located at nearly every bathroom. But please note that some are inside the women's
restroom. Some are outside. But they are indeed available to any lactating person. They're equipped
with a nice comfy chair, fridge, and sink. And if this applies to you, come find me. I'm a new mom
and I would love to meet my fellow PyCon parents. All right. And then if you find that you need to
take a break, focus on some quiet work or just breathe, we do have a quiet room located in 151B.
So that's, again, just going to be a little bit down that hallway on your right-hand side,
down one of the smaller hallways on the right. There's a sign out front. So if you need to take
a break, just breathe. Please make sure that you are taking into account the rules of this room.
Please don't listen to music, play videos on your laptop, take phone calls, etc. This is really
supposed to be a quiet space for people to take a step back and recharge on their own. Feel free to
use headphones, but please be mindful of the other people who might be using that space with you.
All right. So one of our favorite events is the Pi Ladies auction. That will be taking place
tomorrow night at 6 30 p.m. at the Marriott that is right across the street. Don't go to the one
that's 15 minutes away. You don't have to go that far. Please make sure you're going to the correct
Marriott, but it is directly across the street from the conference center. It's a ton of fun.
You get to bid on a bunch of items, have some food, hang out with people. It is often a rowdy good
time with lots of numbers being spewed at you and people throwing money at a really, really excellent
cause. This event is currently sold out, so if you have a ticket and you aren't planning on
attending, please consider giving it to somebody else to make sure that we can use up all of those
tickets. It helps reduce our food waste and ensures that we can keep this event very lively.
Okay. We're getting there. All right. So there's tons going on at PyCon this year. As you can tell,
our mobile application through Guidebook is the absolute best place for you to find our up-to-date
information for the conference, view maps of the venue, create your own schedule, have access to
all of this information offline in your pocket. So definitely download the Guidebook app. You can
get it really easily at PyCon.us slash Guidebook, or there's additional information on installing
and getting access on the PyCon website. All right. So I've mentioned a few times the
PyCon Software Foundation that takes on the financial responsibility of running this conference.
We would not be here without the work of our PSF board and staff. So if you are able to,
or your company is able to, please consider donating. You can navigate to this URL and
get access to the PSF sponsorship page. We also have our swag pickup. I noticed that some people
were already out there grabbing their swag. This year we do just have stickers and anyone who
ordered a t-shirt ahead of time, those are available to pick up currently. We will have
a limited number of t-shirts available for sale tomorrow afternoon around 1 p.m. But if you want
to purchase this shirt and you haven't already, you will have to wait until tomorrow to do so.
We also have a small locations change. The Charlotte's Track is no longer in 253 A&B.
It is now in 151 D, E, F, and G. This has been updated everywhere that you will find your
information. The PyCon site, guidebook, and signage have all been updated, but we wanted
to call this out to make sure that you are going to the proper location. Also, if you are taking
photos of the event, please be aware that any attendees with yellow dots on their badges
have opted out of photos. So please take care not to post any photos for anyone who might have
these dots on their badges. Additionally, if you want to opt out of photos and you haven't
gotten these yet, they are available at the registration desk. Finally, if there is anything
that you need, you can tweet at the conference or at staff at PyCon on Twitter. We are monitoring
that account pretty closely. If you want to post about the conference, please use the hashtag
PyCon US 2022. Now, one of the most important things for us to discuss today is health and safety.
Oh, and apparently my notes for health and safety are gone, so that's
not the best thing to happen. So give me one second because I do want to make sure that I have this
as close as possible.
Okay. So we'll go back to slides in a minute. But we wanted to say that we are incredibly grateful
to how positive the response has been to all of the health and safety policies that we put in place
and how strict our measures have been to ensure that PyCon US can occur in the safest way possible.
And so I need to remind everyone that masks are only to be removed while actively eating or drinking,
or if you are a speaker who is up at the podium speaking, please make sure that you are putting
your mask on right afterwards before you talk to any participants who might have questions for you.
But this is really for us to make sure that we are participating in the safest way possible and
protecting all of the individuals here. There's just no way to know what somebody else has going
on, right? There are a lot of folks who have small children who are immunocompromised or who have
other risks, and one of the ways that they are able to be here attending and that they were able to
balance that risk was this agreement that we all made to continue wearing masks. So this is your
verbal warning. Monitoring starts now. If you are spotted without a mask on, a staff member will
remind you to put it on and they will have a small hole punch and they will put a small hole
in your badge so that we know that you have been given your first strike.
Second strike is going to be a discussion with the staff. If we catch you without a mask on for a
second time, we're going to bring you into the staff office and have a conversation and make
sure that it is very clear what the next strike is, and that is because your third strike means
that you are going home for the rest of the conference. We will gladly switch you over to
an online ticket so that you can still participate and watch talks and whatnot. However,
we will not allow you back into the conference or for any of the outside ticketed events for the
conference. So. All right. And with that very fun announcement, I also want to call out
accessibility. We will be providing live captioning for all of our talks this year,
very similar to what you see to my, oh, I actually can't see them. I think they're on,
I hope that we have captioning on this. Maybe we don't. Oh, thanks. Hey, look at that. So we do
have captioning. So additionally, each space will have reserved seating for wheelchair access. It
will be noted on the floors. It's generally going to be towards the center of the room. And as well,
the conference is ADA compliant. However, if you have any concerns or need any additional support,
please let a staff member know. We also want to say a huge thanks to our captioning sponsors.
These are all folks who have supported the funds to have captioning not only for all of our
Planneries but also all five of our track rooms, which is incredible.
And so our last and also very important item is PyCon's code of conduct. So we are deeply
committed to providing a safe environment and a positive experience for everyone here.
In order to ensure this, everyone here, all staff, attendees, speakers, sponsors, volunteers,
anyone who is here that is related to this PyCon event are required to adhere to our code of conduct.
Absolutely no one is an exception. No one is above the law. So no harassment, whether verbal
or physical or discrimination will be tolerated. Every person here will be provided with a
harassment-free experience regardless of gender, gender identity, expression, age, sexual orientation,
disability, neuro-type, physical appearance, body size, race or religion, or lack thereof.
We take this incredibly seriously and want to make sure that everyone here can have a safe
as an experience as possible. So you can read more in the code of conduct as well as the
linked procedures for how we approach handling incidents and what our responses are going to
look like as well as what enforcement looks like. So you can find all of these documents at the
URL on our screen or at the PyCon website on about slash code of conduct.
So if you believe somebody has violated the code of conduct, you are encouraged to report it
regardless of the severity. At any point, you can make a report by emailing PyCon-us-report
at python.org or during the conference, you can come by the staff room and that's in 150A and we
will make sure that we find the right person for you to talk to.