We have an event loop, so it's going to call update and it's going to call draw at maybe
60 times a second.
Update has the responsibility of updating all of the game logic and draw has the responsibility
of drawing it to the screen.
So the first thing that many game engines do, and this includes other games engines
in Python like Piglet, Pygame Zero, which is my educational game framework, and Wasabi2D,
which is what I'm going to be talking about today, they will absorb the event loop and
they'll just give you, you have a hard coded event loop and we just have a function called
run that is, you know, there's some way of passing update and draw into it, whatever.
And then the next optimization or the next advancement in structure here is to have an
object called a scene graph and a scene graph is going to be a data structure that represents
what is drawn and the engine can handle drawing that.
So it can build in considerations like make it pretty or don't draw what isn't visible
in order to go as fast as possible.
An update, of course, is still going to run 60 times a second but its responsibility is
now to make those changes into the scene graph to be drawn when a draw happens.
So from this point forward we're going to talk, we're not going to talk about graphics
in a game, we're just going to assume a scene graph exists.
So now I want to take a little look at the state of the art for concurrency in games.
I've got a bit of video here.
So in this game I'm moving lots of objects.
They are all moving at the same time.
You could easily see how this could be written as one function and maybe vectorized.
And that view is always going to be useful.
That's going to be possibly a faster way of animating many objects at the same time.
But if you look at a different example where you have two actors in the game that are doing
completely independent behaviors, this is much more easy to see as two tasks, two sets
behaviors that just happen to exist within the same game engine and the same game loop.
If we look at the logic for the update function world, there are lots of problems with this.
So it's messy, there are lots of state variables.
This function even gets called when there's no work to do so there's an early return at
the top.
And this is, it's hard to refactor because it's all woven together.
If we look at a coroutine based version, things get a lot simpler.
So the coroutine syntax in Python is if you have an await, you are pausing, suspending
the execution and you'll be resumed later.
So we're delegating back to the event loop, the game loop.
Lots of things drop out of this.
So the current state of a task is captured by local variables and the position in the
coroutine function.
And a coroutine function now has a much bigger slice of an object's behavior.
So you can see a behavior end to end within a function.
This is a full example from Wasabi 2D.
So I'm going to walk you through this briefly.
The scene object is the scene graph.
Then random position is a function that just returns a random position within the screen.
That's obviously a sync function.
And then drive ship is an async function.
It's going to create a ship sprite at a random position and then forever it will pick a new
random position and then over time it will turn the ship to face that and then over time
it will move it to the next position.
And then we pass that coroutine into the run function in order to run that as our game.
That coroutine becomes our game.
Taking a look around the world of game engines, Unity has support for coroutines.
And this is what it looks like in Unity.
But this is quite limited.
It has a limited capability and the syntax is quite clumsy.
This is apparently C sharp's state of the art for generators.
They're still at this phase of using generators as coroutines.
Another example from the world of UI.
In fact, like JavaScript, you would expect it's doing a lot of UI.
So there would be lots of these frameworks.
And actually this is the only one that I could find that is using coroutines in order to
do animations on screen.
So Python has superb coroutine support and let's go use it.
Another example, if you have children perhaps or you are a child, this is code from a programming
language called Scratch, a graphical programming language.
And it has forever loops and it doesn't have a break.
So naively, this would run forever.
This would just hang.
But this is where you do animation in Scratch.
You do a forever loop.
So there is an implicit yield somewhere in there.
In fact, in a few places.
So now we come onto the meat of this talk, which is structured concurrency.
So we've seen concurrency.
We've seen the ability to run tasks that delegate to the event loop.
What is structured concurrency?
I'm going to steal a quote from Nathaniel Smith, who is the author of Trio.
Here's the core idea.
Every time our control path splits into multiple concurrent paths, we want to make sure that
they join up again.
And I'm also going to steal Nathaniel's slide.
The green task is, so it's a task that's running.
It starts doing something concurrently.
And then all of those tasks must finish before the green task can continue running.
But we can look at that in code.
This is the code from Trio.
And so imagine you have a fetch function that's fetching a remote URL or something.
We have an async with block that is opening a nursery.
And the nursery is the scope in which we can start more tasks.
And the exit of the async with block is the point at which we wait for those tasks to complete.
So unfortunately, in Python, it's a really important point, a really important await
point.
And unfortunately, it's just indicated by that dedent.
So keep your eyes peeled for that, because it's going to be crucially important.
So we await both tasks at the dedent of that block.
And then we can compare.
You could contrast this to what we can do with async.io today.
It looks superficially quite similar.
But there are a few differences.
So first, with async.io, you can still create tasks outside of a gather.
So you could at any point create a disown task that survives a function.
And in fact, the way that I've written this, the tasks that are created, if you moved one
of those outside of the gather, it would still be a task that is running.
You can also pass code between functions into gather.
And then the task is you don't have the task object.
But you can't pass the gather object around.
And you can't add more things to it.
But more deeply, there's no concept of ownership here.
So if one of the tasks raise an exception, then the exception will be raised here immediately.
But the other task will continue running.
This isn't bound together.
In wasabi 2D, you'll see code that is super similar to trio.
Some things are spelled differently.
We embrace coroutine objects.
But the behavior is exactly the same.
And coming in Python 3.11, there's task group.
And it looks super similar to wasabi 2D.
So in asyncIO and task groups in Python 3.11, if you are only using task groups, then yeah,
you're doing structured concurrency.
It's not going to enforce that you are only using task groups.
And I still think trio has more power.
It's further along in its adoption of this model.
So the fact that we can only start tasks through a nursery and we have had to enter that nursery
before we could do it means that we can construct a tree of the tasks.
There is logically a tree by which tasks are connected to one another.
And this tree could go deeper than this.
So we don't need to know what driveship is doing.
But if that was running tasks, then this tree would be deep.
So you have to bear in mind that there's a tree structure behind this because that's
going to be important later.
So let's look at a few examples of why structured concurrency is useful in games.
And to do this, I am using a game that I wrote for Pi Week in September last year, Pi Week
32.
The theme was never ending.
So it's going to have a never ending succession of waves of enemy ships approaching.
And I'm flying around and shooting at them.
And there's a little bit sped up.
So how do we do an infinite progression of waves?
In this code, it's tools.count will loop forever.
And it's just going to count up.
And at the start of each wave, let's pause for a moment in order to let the player get
into position.
I say pause.
I mean, like, sleep this coroutine.
The player will still be moving.
And then we start a nursery.
And we can spawn enemy ships into it.
The enemy ships were called Threx.
So that's why it's the odd naming of that function.
And the nursery isn't going to exit until all of those ships are dead, which is why
we can write it like this.
But something that surprised me as I was adopting this in writing games is that it was really
natural to use nurseries to decompose the behaviors of a ship or any game object into
a bundle of tasks.
So most of them are defined as closures in this function.
In Pi Week, you write code quickly.
But your style preferences may vary.
But there's a benefit here, which is that we can really easily share behaviors between
game objects and not by inheritance, but by running their behaviors as part of our nursery
on our game object.
But the behaviors individually become easy to write.
This is a compelling thing.
In the top example here, we're waiting for input.
Oh, yeah, you can wait for input.
So we're waiting for the controller button to be pressed.
And at the moment that the button is pressed, we create a bullet object.
And then we sleep, which puts a limit on the maximum speed at which the player can press
the button to shoot.
And something else to note is that we're spawning the bullet into an outer nursery.
So lifetime isn't coupled to the lifetime of the ship.
In the bottom example, I'm just sort of illustrating how this could be refactored.
So this is the kind of model where you can only have one bullet on screen at the same
time, which would give the game a retro feel, I think.
But it just requires a little bit of pivoting in the code.
And the behavior is really obvious in both cases.
But the thing that underpins being able to split apart behaviors as different tasks is
cancellation.
So any nursery, in fact, the primitive that could be canceled is called a cancellation
scope.
And a nursery contains a cancellation scope.
So here, we're creating a ship object with a nursery.
And when the code at the bottom is a separate task that is running collision detection,
when the enemy ship collides with a bullet, we just cancel that nursery.
And cancellation means that an exception is thrown inside every task.
And when all of the tasks are finished, the exceptions are propagated such that they've
all finished.
Then the flow continues outside of the nursery block.
And that means that the explosion effects here that we'll play, that's a graphical explosion
effect and a sound effect.
So the collision causes the death of the ship.
And the ship's code can react to its death.
But also, outer cancellation implies inner cancellation.
If you had a nursery, the nursery that is running your task will imply if that is canceled,
it cancels the task within your nursery and your nursery.
So going back to the model of tasks as a tree, you can cancel at any point.
And flow returns at that point.
And all of that tree is collapsed and thrown away.
So here, the bottom coroutine is running the entire player's existence.
It's giving the player three lives.
And then after those three lives are up, it's going to cancel the nursery.
And that's going to cancel the level as well.
So game over.
We go back to wave one.
So returning to the ship, then, there are two ways out of this function.
Remember we were awaiting at the exit of the nursery.
And we either are canceled in this scope, in which case the flow continues afterwards
and we'll play the explosion effects, or the entire level is thrown away.
At which point an exception is raised at that point.
And flow doesn't continue.
And that means that we can start using things like context managers.
So here, there are a couple of context managers to show the ship's sprite on the screen and
delete it afterwards and to turn on collision detection.
And both of those are turned off regardless of how this coroutine exits.
So this is really important.
This became really compelling.
In games that I've written without structured concurrency or concurrency as a paradigm,
Cleanup was really, really hard and buggy because the state is everywhere.
So we can cancel by throwing things away and we can use context managers when we're doing it.
So I'm going to talk a little bit about some of the synchronization problems or the parallels
between synchronization in games and synchronization in I.O.
So there's another example video here from Axiom.
Oh, what's that?
Can you take that away, please?
Who's at the desk?
The speaker notes have popped up on there.
OK, I'll just talk through it a little bit.
What you're going to see is an example of play in which there is a repair drone and
there is an iris door which will open to let out the repair drones.
And I'm also going to be picking up power-ups.
I'll go back from there, backwards.
Yeah, can I get back to it?
OK, cool.
So I'm picking up power-ups.
The power-up building factory things are going to start building another power-up.
Keep your eye on the iris opening and closing to let drones in and out.
Cool.
I can move on from there.
So this is achieved through event objects which are a thing in Trio as well as Wasabi2D.
And they allow tasks to communicate not by cancel.
So cancellation just seems to be a concurrency primitive as well.
But if you don't have anything that you actually want to cancel, here we want generate power-ups
to continue running.
And it's an infinite loop.
It's going to do the build-up to create a new power-up.
It will create one and set an event that it hasn't been collected yet.
And then it's going to wait for that event.
So wait for that power-up to be collected.
Then turn off the lights when it is collected and do it all again.
And we use set in the collision handling to initiate that event.
And the iris turned out to be really satisfying when I actually implemented this code because
I thought this was going to be really hard to write.
And it turned out to be really easy.
I needed two event objects.
And I had to make the iris control its own coroutine.
So you can imagine there's a program running on that spaceship.
And it is waiting for a request to open the iris.
And when the iris is open, it signals everything that's waiting to go through it that it is open.
And then it waits for a second and times out and closes the iris again.
And the function openiris there requests the iris to open and waits for it to be opened.
And that dropped out very nicely.
So why would I write Trio in my game engine when Trio is a thing?
So, oh, okay, that slide has moved.
Maybe come back to that.
One reason is that we're waiting at different points.
So in Trio, we're waiting on IOs.
So we're waiting for a father scripture to be ready.
And the call to do that is a select like thing or a selector.
And in Pygame, we're waiting for input events or a timeout.
So both cases, we maintain a clock, which is the next thing that we need to wake up for anyway.
But we're using different functions to drive the point that we block the entire thread.
And we could combine those two maybe.
We could run two threads.
We could pass events between one and the other and it would work, but it would be a little bit clumsy.
But there was a deeper issue, which is that when multiple tasks are ready to run,
we have to have some opinion on which order they run in.
You can't just not have an opinion.
You have to pick one and run it.
So which we run, the one that's waiting longest or the highest priority task.
If you had priorities and there's no right answer, it just depends what you're trying to optimize for.
So here Trio and Wasabi2D diverge.
Trio currently just picks a task at random, which doesn't necessarily optimize for anything.
But Nathaniel justifies that as avoiding users having any expectations of what it's optimizing for so that he can change it later.
Wasabi2D always runs the earliest created task first.
So it's a deterministic ordering that prioritizes determinism.
And that's because if you picked at random, a task could be scheduled at the end of one frame and the start of another frame.
And then it's not seen a whole frames worth of changes in the rest of the world.
So we want it to see approximately one frames worth of changes every time.
The order then might be relevant, but at least we don't have the jitter to deal with.
But our ideas of time diverge as well.
So in Trio, we have an idea of continuous time.
So, or a normal time.
I'm calling it continuous here.
Every time you ask the clock for what time it is, it will tell you a different time.
Time will move on.
And we could schedule frames every 60th of a second, but I would be worried about a task being suspended into the next frame.
When it absolutely had to happen in the first frame.
So we have a model of time where it's a discrete model where time doesn't move forward within a frame.
We have a bundle of stuff that has to run and all of it has to be run before we can say, okay, we're done.
So we can just draw a frame and the clock will just return the same time within that unit of time.
So, summing up, in games programming, structured concurrency lets us split behaviors into multiple coroutines.
And cancellation seems to be the important thing for implementing this.
And code seems easier to write because, as we saw, behaviors are more simply stated.
We can have more of them and they can do independent things, even though they're acting on the same objects.
There is a slight shift in focus, which is that exceptions are pretty unimportant for Wasabi 2D.
Exceptions cause cancellation, but exceptions in a game are probably less expected than if you're dealing with I.O.
It's more likely to indicate a bug in your game logic.
So Wasabi 2D doesn't bother with handling multiple exceptions or exception groups.
So all of this led to a model that practically eliminated state keeping up bugs in a game.
And it was very easy to add more animations, and animations are good in games because they add graphical richness.
And every time that the world changes, you want to have the player see that as juicy.
There's this model of games programming where you're trying to keep the player engaged.
And avoiding a global nursery using structured concurrency helps make code refactorable
because you can always call a coroutine function from another or you can pivot your entire program
because they're guaranteed to be self-contained tasks.
So thank you. This is all on GitHub.
The coroutine stuff is on the master branch and it's documented, but I'm still working my way up to a release.
I've got kids now, so I have less time to play with this stuff.
Axiom is on the PiWeek website and PiWeek is at piweek.org.
So maybe you could join us for the next competition, which will be in September.
Thanks very much.