All right, hopefully this will advance my slides and I can move on.
Okay, so, yeah, my talk is entitled Will It Blend?
And it's about writing a custom constraint solver for Blender using Cython.
So the agenda in terms of what I'm going to cover is a bit of motivation and background
about why I looked at this particular problem and then go into the backend of why I chose
to use Cython, looking at a toy problem for this, going over the Python package structure
when you're using Cython, and then compiling Cython packages.
And then moving on to performance, so how you can use Cython to release the gil, how
you can profile Cython, and then on the front end, why did I choose to use Blender, and
then going into some information about Blender developments and Blender add-ons.
So a little bit about me.
I used to be a structural engineer, so I worked on some landmark transit projects and, like,
some of the big museums, but for the past year, I've worked on software before that.
I've been writing Python since 2015, but I've made the switch to entirely just working
on software, mainly focusing on full stack web applications, doing a lot of data visualization,
and you can find me at my blog.
I write about some of this kind of stuff, and also I'm on Twitter.
So I could do an entire talk about the state of software for structural engineering, but
the 30-second bit about it is that it's not great.
You model building and commercial software to understand how it behaves under loads.
You know, you want it to move, but not too much, and then you use an analysis program
that might have a way of doing design, so how big should a column be, how much steel
should you put in the floor, but often in consulting design practices, you usually go
back to designing all this in Excel.
And then most often you're using proprietary software to exchange data with other disciplines,
so architectural, mechanical, electrical, and plumbing, to basically figure out how
all of the structural stuff will fit together with all the other components.
So having worked on software for a while, I have a lot of issues with the state of software
in the built environment.
The UIs are usually super outdated, and also it's very difficult to get information without
pointing and clicking and going through a bunch of different submenus.
It's very not developer-friendly.
It's pretty expensive.
Standard structural analysis software is usually about $10,000 a license, even with the terrible
UI.
For reference, the starting salary for a structural engineer is somewhere between $60,000 and
$70,000 a year.
In terms of how the software operates, it's pretty slow, I would say.
There are a lot of matrix inversions required for the math behind structural analysis, and
there really isn't any immediate feedback loop.
You click on something, you walk away, you come back, and you see the results.
Probably my biggest issue with it is that it's all a black box.
If you're lucky, you'll get a manual that will have simple test cases and validations,
but looking at the actual code is not possible.
Before we had computers, some of the most exquisite buildings constructed used physical
modeling methods called form-finding.
The idea was that you could take a hanging weighted chain and tension and then invert
it in order to find the form of a structure and pure compression.
You might be familiar with Antonio Gaudi's still unfinished cathedral in Barcelona called
the Sagrada Familia, which actually used this technique, as seen on the left, with his hanging
chain model to form-find the pure compression form of the building, which is still unfinished
and you can see on the right.
Today the construction of the cathedral is being undertaken using computational geometric
techniques as well as computational form-finding.
I also became interested in computer graphics a few years ago, as it's a field that's
miles ahead of structural analysis in terms of using real-time simulation.
There was one particular constraint-solving algorithm for form-finding and real-time physics
that actually has made it into built environment software through two plug-in implementations
in a commercial 3D modeling software called Rhinoceros.
The examples shown here are from the original implementation of the algorithm called Shapeop,
which was developed at EPFL, but the one that's widely commercially used now is called Kangaroo
So, you might ask if these already exist, why would I rewrite it?
My issues with this are that I still don't think the UI is great for that particular
software.
It's based on visual programming, which is really great for rapid prototyping, but it's
not great for documentation or having reproducible processes.
Even in this interface, it's not free.
It costs about $1,000, a license, which might put it out of reach for a hobbyist.
These implementations are not slow.
What you were seeing on the previous slide was all real-time, but there's still a little
bit of a black box around the implementation, while Shapeop is open source.
It's kind of academic abandonware, but the physics engine for Kangaroo 2 is still not
open source, but the constraint formulation, all those geometric constraints that feed
into the engine are, and they're written in C-sharp.
So, with those caveats, I wanted to try my hand at implementing this algorithm myself
in Python, so to make it open source, accessible, and extensible.
So, moving on to the back end of how I built the Scython plugin, which I called Pimaxian.
So, obviously, the first stumbling block you get when you say you're going to build something
in Python is the complaint about how slow it is.
So, I turned to Scython as a way to keep Pythonic syntax that I'm familiar with, but improve
the speed significantly.
So there are several wrappers and ways to get C or C++ execution with Python as a front
end.
In fact, you can generate Python bindings for Shapeop still using SWIG.
However, this still means that if you want to extend constraints or change anything,
you're going to have to write them in C++ and then compile them with the Python bindings,
and I wanted to write as little C++ as possible.
Some of these other libraries, I thought it would be a little bit more difficult to sort
of translate the constraints because they're very, like, matrix operation heavy.
So, basically, I wanted to create a general framework that I could build upon and keep
the look and feel of a Python package.
Most critically, I wanted to be able to write functions that would release the global interpreter
lock in Python, the gil, to gain significant speed ups and also possibly use parallel computation.
So what is Scython?
It's an optimizing static compiler that allows you to wrap C or C++ libraries in Python.
You can also compile Scython, which is a superset of Python, to C or C++, and then that compiled
library can be imported into a standard Python script as an extension.
So to get myself started, I picked a pretty simple static analysis problem, the loading
of a cable at a midpoint.
So this is actually a pretty difficult problem to solve by hand because the deformed shape
of a cable changes significantly under the load.
Fun fact, most of structural analysis is based on assuming that deformations are really small.
This problem only involves three types of constraints, and there are five constraints
in total.
You've got anchors that will keep points zero and two from moving towards the center as
the load is applied.
The force itself is a constraint, and then there's a relationship between points zero
and one and points one and two that are based on the material properties of the cable.
It's basically how stretchy it is because it wants to snap back to its original length.
So what the shape-op algorithm does is consider these constraints independently and projects
the ideal position at each point separately based on the constraint, which is a local
solve.
The constraints are then weighted against each other to find the position of the particle
that best satisfies the constraints applied, and this is an iterative process.
The key feature of this algorithm is that the local solves for each constraint can be
applied independently of one another, which means that you could possibly run this in
parallel.
So, ultimately, what I ended up with for this small problem was quite a large library,
large number of files.
So PXD and PYX file extensions are unique to Cython.
Those PXD files are basically borrowing from C++ for header files, and then classes and
methods are defined in the .pyx file.
Okay, so I did end up writing a really small geometry library in C++ rather than dealing
with wrapping an existing one, and that's just because I didn't want to deal with all
of the licensing issues or large builds for some of the typical C++, like geometry libraries
like CGAL.
So the rest of the constraints were defined purely using Cython constructs, so each one
of those required a PXD and a PYX file.
So, why do I need all those header files?
In Cython, if you're planning on importing a module, you have to have a PXD file that
corresponds with it.
So one thing that did jump out to me in Cython is that you can't just subclass all over
the place.
You only get one level of subclassing, though a subclass can inherit from more than one
superclass.
So for my purposes, this was fine because I could just set that a constraint was the
parent class, and then each type of constraint, so those anchors, those cables, those forces,
those are a child class with its own calculate implementation based on the constraint.
So this is a typical header file for the parent constraint class with all of the type declarations.
So each of these types are prefixed with CDEF, as they are data types and methods that will
be used for running the program without the GIL, which means that they can't be Python
objects.
So CDEF methods also cannot be called from Python.
If you'd either need to define a CPDef method to do so, so that's something that will run
either in Python or as a C extension, or you're going to have to write a Python wrapper around
that function.
So with the actual methods for the general constraint class, the calculate method is
going to be overridden based on all of the constraints, so it just has to have the same
signature.
The sum moves method is common to all of the constraints because that's the local solve
per constraint.
So the calculate method for an anchor point is really simple.
It's just a 3D vector in space that will return the point wherever it is in space to the original
anchor point.
The calculate method for a cable is a bit more complex, and you can think of it like
the forces from stretching a rubber band, where the rubber band wants to return to its
original slack shape, so it imposes opposite forces on the two points that you're holding
in the system.
So getting back to my first slide with the XKCD joke, you do have to compile Cython.
I wrote a bunch of helper functions to make sure that Cython would properly identify all
of the different components in different directories, as well as attaching some extra compilation
arguments to compile against OpenMP in case I wanted to use OpenMP in the future for parallelization.
So by default, Cython compiles to C, so I needed to specify C++ as the language.
For the actual build command, the inplace flag ensures that the compiled files are going
to be in the same directory as the base files, so that importing from the package is really
clear.
It just looks like it would be if you were importing a standard Python file.
So once you've compiled the Cython package, you're going to get the dynamic library files.
I'm building on a Mac, so I've got an SO extension.
You're also going to get new C++ files that are at the same level, and these are giant
files.
There's like thousands and thousands of lines of generated C++ code, so not necessarily
something you're going to want to go digging through.
So I tested this out.
It was significantly faster than the original, like only vanilla Python methodology that
I used.
But while it was faster, I wanted to know how much faster it could be, and I wanted
to figure out what the best way was to profile Cython code.
So I mentioned wanting to use Cython so I could release the GIL to improve runtimes,
but there are a number of steps you have to do before you can run Cython functions without
the GIL.
So you've seen this on previous slides a bit, but static typing and variable declarations
are required.
Other things that you can play around with to improve performance are taking some of
the training wheels off on Python through adding compiler directives at the top of your
files.
So in this case, I took a bounce check and wrap around and turned those off.
You really have to use these with caution because you'll get really funky errors if
you build it and then accidentally index something that would wrap around, and this might be
difficult to debug because you're just going to crash Python.
And then I also highly recommend writing Python wrappers for the functions that we'll compile
just to see because otherwise you can't access them, so you're going to have more code,
but it will be easier to debug and test out.
If you're not writing no-GIL functions, you can just use a CPDef function within
Cython and those can be called from either C or Python.
So other items for no-GIL functionality, use CDef rather than CPDef or standard Python
def functions, though if you're not trying to optimize for no-GIL, you can absolutely
mix these around in Cython for other use cases.
Python is pretty good about warning you when it compiles if you have incompatible Python
objects that are still embedded in your code, and for these CDef methods, you'll also need
to make sure that the signature matches in your PXD file and your PYX file, so all of
the arguments as well as the no-GIL flag.
One thing to note is that writing no-GIL in the signature of a method doesn't mean that
it's automatically going to default to no-GIL when you run it.
You're just indicating that the method can be run without the GIL.
One of the biggest lifesavers for this project was a feature in Cython that lets you see
inside each PYX file just how much Python is being called in the method.
So if you pass the dash A flag to the command line, it will automatically generate an HTML
file for whichever file you're looking at, and that file will highlight just how much
of a method is accessing Python objects.
So you can see in this block, because I'm using NumPy to create arrays, that means that
I'm creating Python objects.
So ND arrays are Python objects.
How can I have arrays that work without the GIL?
You can use memory views to access NumPy arrays and update them within a no-GIL block, and
so this was really useful for me to be able to keep track of particle positions as a 3D
position array that I could pass to the calculate methods for each constraint.
Okay, so it's all this prep work, and once you've done that, it's time to release the
GIL.
All you have to do is add with no-GIL to the part of the function that you want to run
with no-GIL, and you just have to make sure that any of the functions that are called
within that block are also designated as no-GIL, and you've checked all of those previous steps.
So you should see serious speed-ups in your code.
I was able to see more than 100 times speed-up once I released the GIL, which gave me near
instant convergence for thousands of constraints.
I still wanted to try out profiling with Cython, so I turned to PySpy, which is a low overhead
profiling option that's implemented in Rust.
So integrating this profiler into my code required a bit of setup, including adding
some additional flags to my setup file to make sure that the generated C++ code from
Cython would include line numbers, and then you also had to add it at the start of those
compiler directives in each PyX file to have line trace set to true.
My personal computer is a Mac, which works fine for some of the functionality of PySpy,
but you can't profile native functions.
So I ended up making a Docker container and ran PySpy with Linux.
This was kind of fun to figure out how to make a container that would have the right
permissions, so that's what that first command is.
The second command includes flags that ensure that native subprocesses are recorded, and
then all of that is going to be output for the results to a flame graph.
And then the last command is just copying the flame graph out of the Docker container
into my regular directory so that I can take down the container once it's finished running.
So what I was able to get was a flame graph that gave me an idea of which processes during
my simulation were taking the longest.
It actually turned out the assembly of the particle system and translating all the Python
objects to C, so basically initializing all of the objects, that was what was taking
the longest.
So moving on to the front end, this is great.
I've made something that runs fast, but I can't see it.
So I don't have any nice visual as a simulation yet, and I didn't want to reinvent the wheel,
so I decided to integrate Pymaxion with a well-established open source 3D graphics program
called Blender.
This comic's going to make a little more sense in a few slides, but needless to say,
there's a lot of fun with Blender Python versus system Python versus a virtual N Python
up ahead.
So what is Blender?
As I mentioned, it is free and open source with the new GPL license.
I've only listed a few of the possibilities with Blender, which will exceed the capabilities
of Rhinoceros, which was the other 3D modeling program I was familiar with.
Though figuring out how to do anything in Blender is like drinking from a fire hose.
There are a lot of different things you can do with it.
I barely scratched the surface with Blender with what I was doing with Pymaxion, because
I was just mainly working with meshes.
Blender also has a really well-developed Python API, though most of its underlying code is
written in C or C++.
So there's a very robust Blender ecosystem of add-ons.
I've added some of my favorites from the built environment, though Sphere Chalk is
more general purpose because it's a visual programming interface that's similar to Grasshopper,
which is really commonly used by architects with Rhino.
So how do you get your newly minted Cython package into the Blender Python?
You're going to need to build Cython against the same version of Python as Blender Python,
You can interrogate everything about your Blender Python install from the scripting
tab.
There's an IPython interface to basically put in sys.path or sys.versioninfo.
I decided to symlink my Cython package into the site packages for the Blender Python install
rather than copying it or building it with Blender Python.
And then so now PyMaxion is part of the Blender site packages, but I still need to add how
Blender is going to interact with that package through its UI and operators.
There's a lot of disagreement about what the best way to develop with Blender is.
I've typically just created something to close and relaunch Blender whenever I'm making changes
because hot reloading doesn't always work, and its efficacy keeps changing as Blender
evolves, things that work in 2.9 for hot reloading don't necessarily work in 3.1.
But at a minimum, I do recommend adding Blender to launch from the command line because then
all of your outputs or debugging is going to print to a separate console window.
So I put my Blender package into the addons directory also using a symbolic link.
Sorry.
So this is the typical file structure for a basic Blender addon, and on the right you
can see that there's this side menu, and that's actually the menu that I created for the PyMaxion
interface for Blender.
The Blender context in which you can use PyMaxion is the object and editing context on one of
the tabs.
So I have a number of buttons that are part of this menu as well as some pop out panels.
And the Blender operator file is where you're going to find all of your UI actions that
call PyMaxion.
So it has a specific Blender class structure in terms of attributes and methods.
And it also has a number of requirements for, like, unique labels, so that's, like, underscore
ID name, underscore label, and then here you can see that I have to define execute, which
is also has return a specific set of values.
So for all of those nice panels, you have to have a specific prefix in order to the
specific attributes.
Otherwise it won't register when you tell it to basically add your package.
So within I've got these pop out panels, you have some additional attributes that you
can set basic values.
So in this case it's adding the strengths of the constraints with the typical notation.
And all of these UI panels have a draw method.
So most typical add-ons also have a property file, and you have to register every single
constant that you use for those menus, which in my case resulted in a lot of code pretty
quickly.
So rather than using a properties file, I decided instead to put those constraints and
basically their bounds, so like all of the options for, like, how precise that value
is going to be that the user can set.
So I put that into a JSON file that basically groups each set of values by the type of constraint.
And then within my actual menu file for loading into Blender, I was able to import and iterate
through that JSON file to automatically register each one of these properties.
So it's going to be easier for me in the future to add on to this JSON file rather than having
to write a bunch of classes.
And so what do I have after all that?
Pimaxian currently only supports a couple of constraints as basically a proof of concept,
but I was able to replicate the kind of hanging cloth form finding that I showed on that first
few slides.
I'd like to do more to make it more interactive.
You can use modal operators within Blender to sort of allow for some interactivity, or
I was looking into possibly using sockets that would be able to feed updated geometry
back so that the user can have more interaction with the simulation.
So in closing, I'd really like to thank the Python Software Foundation and PyLadies for
the opportunity to speak here, particularly the New York City PyLadies group who acted
as the sounding board for a much shorter version of this talk.
And I'd also like to thank the Recurse Center because I worked mainly on the Blender part
of this project when I was doing a retreat there last summer.
So thank you.