Welcome, everybody. Hopefully everyone can hear me. Welcome to the afternoon session
of PyCon 2022 in Salt Lake City. Before I begin this entire presentation, it's on my
GitHub. If you're running a Jupyter Notebook, you can run it on a Jupyter Notebook. The
PDF slides are up there. My GitHub is vic-humor-1981.
All right. So a little bit about me. I work for Excella. We are a technology consulting
firm based out of Arlington, Virginia. We do three things that people sort of give us
money for. Modern software delivery, AI and analytics, as well as agile transformation.
The website, excella.com, is up there. We have openings right now for data engineers
and data scientists. So feel free to go to the website or reach out to me afterwards.
Right. And some projects that I'm currently involved in. Gotocode.io. It's sort of like
a leak code meets remote interview. Again, we have Jupyter Notebook integration in several
languages. So if you ever want to play around with Rust and Jupyter kernel, go ahead and
If you use the registration code, PyCon 2022, all lowercase, you can get a free extended
subscription. Yeah. And I'm also working on HBCU Digital, which is an ESPN sort of app
for historically black colleges and universities. We're trying to add a lot of live content
there. We are on Roku, Apple TV, as well as mobile apps. All right. Enough jibber jabber
about me. Let's talk a little bit about functional programming. So in the last five, six years,
I'm sure all of us have sort of heard of, played around with, experimented with some
of these. Let's call them like the new kids on the block. These newer languages. We have
React.js out there in JavaScript. There's F sharp for all the .net folks. There is obviously
And Kotlin are still going strong in the JVM. And for IOS development, we now have Swift,
so you don't have to write Objective C. And as well as there are more traditional functional
programming languages still out there, like Haskell or OCaml. So the idea behind functional
programming is a pretty straightforward idea, but one that has far-reaching consequences,
which is why I think I like it. So the idea behind functional programming is that we are
going to impose a restraint or we're going to try to sort of constrain our code, put
a restriction whereby we write our code only using pure functions. So what exactly is a
pure function? A pure function is one that does not have side effects. So the next logical
question, well, then, what is a side effect? So side effect, it turns out, is anything
a pure computation. If you mutate the state of variable, if you modify a data structure
in place, if you throw an exception within your code, if you deal with any sort of IO,
the console, networking, these are side effects. Another way of sort of looking at or thinking
about this is that a function has inputs and it has outputs. And this is sort of ubiquitous,
not just a Python, but in just programming in general, a function has inputs and it has
outputs. If we do anything inside that function that doesn't explicitly deal with the inputs
or outputs of that function, then that is by definition sort of a side effect. It's
not explicit in the signature of the function that it's doing this thing. And so that's
kind of the idea behind the side effecting. Right. Okay. A pure function has the property
of referential transparency. So when we talk about side effects and what are pure functions,
it's sort of like something we can prove. It's like mathematical. We can go through
and I couldn't paste the definition there of what referential transparency actually
is. But there is an easier sort of way to think about this. So, yeah, let's get to some
coding examples so that we can actually understand this a little bit better. So I have a function
here. It just adds a list of numbers. So we're going to start by creating a variable, sum,
we're going to assign it to zero, we'll go through every item in our list, and we will
add the numbers. And we can see that it gets the sort of the right output when we add those
numbers. But if I think back, you know, to like algebra class or math class, and I know
that's why everyone is here, because they wanted to go back to algebra class, when I
say something like x equals one, y equals two, what is x plus y? I would tell you that
it's three, because in my head I took x and I replaced it with the value one, and I took
y, I replaced it with the value two, and one plus two equals three. So on this first block
of code, I said sum is equal to zero. And when you tell me that sum equals zero, then
mathematically if I use sum on the right-hand side of any expression, it should yield the
same result. So let's take a look at how that works then, right? So instead of sum
equals sum plus n, I replaced it with sum equals zero plus n, because you told me that
sum is equal to zero. And as you can see, it doesn't give the same answer. It actually
gives an incorrect answer, because it gets to the, it iterates through the list, it gets
to the last item in that list, and it says, okay, sum equals eight plus zero, so it's
equal to eight. But that's not the same value we got before. And even though this code
block is sort of like very innocuous, very, very simple, we can see that perhaps there's
some things that we don't like about it. I could easily imagine that the list that we're
trying to add up might become very, very large. And so now we might think, okay, let's try
to apply some concurrency to it. Let's add some threads and run the same block of code
using threads. And obviously we could maybe partition the list so that, you know, the
threads are operating on different parts of the list. But if we get to that line, sum
equals sum plus n, and we do this mutation, we can't have two threads mutating the variable
sum at the same time. We'd have to do something like a lock, a metaphor, sorry, a mutex, some
sort of lock, or maybe an atomic operation. But in any case, we're going to have to deal
with this in a concurrent sense if we ever want to make this multithreaded. So the problem
really here is the mutable state of sum. We want to sort of get rid of this mutable state
because as we saw in the previous slide, mutation is a form of side effect. And we can see that
this function isn't referentially transparent. When we substituted the value zero for what
sum was, it didn't return the same thing. So all right, let's try to then rid ourselves
of the mutable state sum. And there's some pretty straightforward ways that we can do
which is just let's use recursion. So if the list is one item, just return that. Otherwise,
return the first item plus the sum of the rest of the list. And we can see that that
gives us the same value and does not have the consequence of a mutable state within
the function. Okay. The second way that we could deal with the same problem is by using
what we call a higher order function. A higher order function is a function that takes in
a function as a parameter or returns a function as its output. And so here we're going to
import this cool function called reduce from itertools. And itertools' first parameter
is obviously it's a lambda. It takes two things from the list and returns one item and then
sort of recursively applies it to the list. And so this concept is going to come back
up in a few slides. In functional programming, we like using higher order functions to abstract
around things like having to mutate state. So we see two ways here that we can get rid
of that mutable state. The two examples here, add numbers two and add numbers three, are
referentially transparent and these are peer functions versus the one up here we know that
it's not. We've sort of proven that this is not referentially transparent and therefore
that function is impure in a functional sense. It doesn't obey the properties and laws that
we like in math. And that's sort of where this premise is going to go with functional
programming. All right. So now that we've sort of accepted the idea that we want to
use higher order functions, I sort of did a thing. I don't know if it's a good thing
or a bad thing, but I added some classes. So this is a library that you can pip install,
pip install PyFX. And so it's like my first attempt at trying to introduce some of the
classes that you might see in a language like Haskell and most certainly in Scala.
You will see these types. And so the types we're going to discuss today are option, try,
either, actually we're not going to cover either, but we are going to do option, try,
and future. Either is there in the library, but we're not going to cover either today.
So yeah. So let's talk about abstracting away certain behaviors, some common behaviors.
And the way that we're going to sort of approach this is we're going to use classes. So the
option class is a parent class or like some sort of interface. And it has two child classes,
actual implementations, one of which is called sum and the other one is called empty. So
if there is a value, we encapsulate it in the sum class and otherwise it's empty. And
as always, let's go ahead and create an example data model that we can sort of play around
with. So the idea here is that we're going to create some classes. We're going to have
a person. A person is going to have a contact. And the contact is going to have a name. And
the name has the property's first name and last name. So this is sort of like a nested
sort of hierarchical class structure. And so let's say given a person, I want to go
ahead and find the first name of contact number one. So I use data classes and then I, let's
not worry about the get functions, the get last name, the get first name. Those are just
wrappers and we're going to use those so that we can see how the option class sort of works.
But first we're just going to sort of use the attributes directly. So our example is
we're going to be given a person and we want to go ahead and try to find the first name
of contact number one for that person. So we create this like person object and you
can see we're just going to use like if statements. So all along the way anything could be empty.
That's really what we're dealing with. We have this nested hierarchy. We want to get
to this thing in our hierarchy. But along the way we have to do these checks because
things can be, have no value. They could be empty and that would cause a problem. So we
have to do the checks that if the person is there, if the person's contact one is there,
if they have a name, then return this value. Otherwise return none. Right? And this could
get more complicated. The more nested and the more hierarchical structure that we have
to our classes, the more complicated branching and conditional logic that we're going to
have to use to get from this class to that class. Okay. So let's take a look at how this
works with the option class. So this is where functional purists sort of what they like.
In the second example we don't really have any, the branching logic is abstracted away
for you with an operation called flat map. And so flat map is a way that we chain or
combine inputs and you're going to see the same techniques with the other classes as
well. So it takes the output of one and puts it as the input to the next function. And
what functional purists would really like about this sort of function is as you can
see the second function below, we get an input, we apply a series of functions and we're given
an output. To a functional person this is how every program should always work. We get
an input, apply a series of functions and get an output. And it does the same thing
that the first function does. The other sort of observation that we can make between the
two functions is that the first function, even though it tells me that it's returning
a string, it doesn't tell me anything in the function's signature that this string could
potentially be empty. In the lower function I can see that it returns an option of string.
So the caller of this method now knows that this value that is being returned could be
forced to deal with the case of emptiness. And in the case of an option class you have
something get or else. So if there's no value you can supply a value there. And right. So
all the functions there, the get contact one, contact.get name, name.get first name, if
I go up a slide, sorry, those functions are just simple functions that return an option.
And that's really what FlatMap is doing for us. It's just chaining the options together
so that we can rewrite this logic in a way that reads left to right. The second API is
also what we call, it's a fluent API. It reads left to right, just like how English reads.
You don't necessarily read English like inside out with if statements and while loops. You
kind of read it just left to right. So we get the benefit of chaining our operations
and sort of seeing a fluent API style. Okay. So that's sort of how we can deal with emptiness
using the option class. The second example is going to deal with now with exceptions
because what we talked about before is that an exception just like that example that we
did with the sums and we mutated sum, that function was impure. So any time I raise an
exception within my code, I'm also suffering from the same problem that my code is not
referentially transparent and the function is not pure. So the same way that we dealt
with option where option was a parent class and we had two child classes to deal with
the behaviors that we wanted, we have a class called try. And the try class is also a parent
class. The try class has two children classes, the first of which is called success and the
other one is called failure. So success encapsulates the successful value of something happening
without an error and failure encapsulates the exception that might be thrown in that
event, like an accept. So let's take an example here where something that could potentially
fail, it could go wrong. So we're going to look at an example of JSON parsing. So we
have two strings. The first string is going to be parsable. It's going to parse to our
model. It's correct. The second string I've deliberately made a mistake. There's no attribute
called first name is wrong. So when I try to sort of parse my JSON and get it into my
model, it is going to raise an error. It's going to raise an exception. So let's take
a look at how we might do this in a very straightforward way. So we have like parse person, we're going
to do a JSON loads, we'll load it into a dictionary, we'll check some attributes from that person
and we'll parse the contact and from that contact we'll go ahead and parse the name.
The parse name function there, we can see, accept, it raised a type error. I couldn't
deserialize the name. So that function is not pure. And similarly like we saw with option,
when I just look at the signature of parse name, it tells me it takes the dictionary's
input and it returns a name. Nothing in the signature of that function tells me that this
could potentially throw or raise an exception. Perhaps it's there in the docs and stuff like
that, but I think we could make it more explicit. So the example there, it works. It gets the
first name of contact one from our JSON string. If you go back, sorry, Alice is the correct
first name there. So it works. But the function definitely raises an exception and perhaps
is not as explicit as we would like to make it. So we'll take an example. Oh, yes, I forgot
about this. So this is what happens if we sort of parse the second string, which is
invalid. We'll get the error that the first name, there's no attribute called first name
is wrong. So we can see that we get this exception when we try to parse the name because the
second JSON was not a good JSON for our model. Right. So let's try to rewrite this using
the try class. So the parse name function here, we're going to use try.of, which will
encapsulate like a callable object. And if that callable succeeds, it will return a success.
If the callable fails, it will return a failure. And in the signature of the function, we can
see that, okay, it takes in the same dictionary as the input, but the return value is not
just a name. It's a try of a name. So someone who sees that code, who reads that code can
see that this function could fail. It could succeed or it could fail. And just like we
saw with the option class, we're going to have to sort of deal with the case of failure.
Oh, sorry. Okay. And so we're going to go ahead and test that function. Oh, yeah, sorry.
I forgot one thing on this. The way that we deal with failure in the try class is very
similar to how we would deal with the failure in the option class. In the option class,
when it was empty, we applied a method called get or else. So when it was empty, we said
get or else do this. And we can do that with try also. But in this case, we're going to
use or else supply, which is like get or else, but it takes in a callable as its parameter.
So in this case, we're going to call a function called handle parse error, which will create
the contact, but it will just warn us that we couldn't parse this. So if we have, like,
a lot of JSON that we're parsing, we want to be warned. We want to know that an error
happened. We might want to continue parsing, even though there was some kind of mistake
or error. So, yeah, these are the tests. So person one, that's the good string there.
And you can see it does the exact same thing that we saw before without throwing an exception.
It gets the first name Alice. And then in the second one, it tells us, oh, there was an error
parsing the contact, contact one. And it gives us the second person, and it says that the
contact name is none. So that's sort of like the same thing that we saw with option. We're
trying to just be more explicit with how we deal and handle errors using the try class.
So we've abstracted the behavior of emptiness. We've abstracted around the behavior of try
accept blocks. And the third class that we're going to briefly touch upon is how we can
use the same concepts to deal with concurrency, futures. I'm sure futures are there, and,
you know, a lot of different languages we've seen, promises. Future works a little differently
than option and try in that there is no explicit parent class and child class. What future does
is future is going to start off, and it's going to have no value. The value is not completed.
It's none. After some period of time, future will eventually behave like the try. Once the
future completes, either there's a successful value from the future or there's a failure value
from that same future, which encapsulates your exception that you're going to get back.
So let's go ahead and see how this works. The simplest thing that we can do is sort of just run
something asynchronously in a new thread, and that's done with future.run. So we just have a
real easy function here. It sleeps for three seconds, and it will go ahead and return the value
100. So we're going to check some things. The first thing we're going to do is sort of time the
whole thing, and we're going to, once we get the value, we're just going to do a little map
statement and add one to the resulting value. We're going to check if the future is done
immediately. It's not going to be done because it just started, and there's a three-second wait,
and then we're going to wait four seconds. We're going to check again if the future is done, at
which point it's true, done equals true. We'll print out the result of that sort of value, which is
101, and we've got the overall execution time, which is roughly four seconds. The time that's
sleep for in there is what's causing it to be about four seconds. So yeah, pretty simple example.
We can easily run something in a new thread using future. Okay, but what about combining two things?
Just like we saw flat map to combine our options and our tries, we can do the same sort of higher
order function that we saw to combine futures. So here we have two threads. One is going to sleep for
three seconds, return 100. The other one is going to sleep for five seconds, return the value 50,
and then what we want to do is sort of add up those two results, right? So you can see result one we
call future.run. Result two we call the second function, and then we say result one, we flat map it
into result two, and we add their two values, and we add a little callback. So the callback here is
doing the same thing that we did in the more imperative example where we're trying to calculate
what is the total overall running time, like you see. So in this example, one thread took three seconds,
and another thread took five seconds. Both threads executed in parallel. Once the longer thread was
done, it combined the results. We got the value 150. It was roughly more or less five seconds of
execution time. Okay. So what happens then if something were to go wrong, though? So in this example,
we'll deal with an error. So the first function is actually going to do the same thing. So the
first function is actually going to just throw an exception, which we know is impure, but for this example,
we'll go ahead and do it anyway just to see what kind of happens. And now on our callback, we have the
same code to flat map and map, but on our callback, because once the feature is complete, it sort of
behaves like a try. It has a success and a failure, and we can check that. So in my callback on this
example now, we can simply check, did the result fail or did it succeed, and handle those two use cases
separately. So in this example, again, it ran both things in parallel, the three-second thread and the five-second thread.
The three-second thread failed, so it never actually had to... The five-second thread kept running,
but for the purpose of the computation, it actually finished in three seconds because it got the error,
and it erred out. So we have this sort of callback style on the feature that we can use to check if the value,
once it's complete, succeeds or fails. Okay. But I'm going to go up a couple slides here. So in this example
where we are combining features using flat map and map comprehensions and stuff like that, we could easily see...
Okay, so we have two threads running here, two results, values, asynchronous computations that we care about the result,
but what if there was three or four or five or more results? This could get map, flat map, map, flat map,
over and over and over again. This can get a little complicated. And the real thing is so when I do feature.run,
I'm getting a future value back, and I get another future value back and another future value back,
and eventually I'm left with a list, a list of future values. And what I really want to do is I want to sort of invert that.
Instead of having a list of future values, I would like a single feature with a list of values that have the combined results
of all my threads. And in a language like Scala, that function is called future.traverse. It inverts the two things,
so it will take a list of futures and make it a future list, a future of a list. So let's go ahead and take a look at how that works.
And so we have result one, which is the same thing, feature.run, delay result one, feature.two, result two,
and here we call future.traverse and we supply the list of futures. And then the same thing,
we just call the on complete handler to get the execution time and sort of like our final result to print it out.
Right, so future.traverse, we can see if we're dealing with like a lot of different sort of computational results,
we can quickly invert a list of futures into a future of a single list. All right.
So some of the key takeaways here is that when we use side effects, we can see that sometimes our code is not as explicit
as we would like it to be. It makes the code a little bit harder to reason about. If the functions are more referentially transparent,
if they're pure, then it allows us to sort of reason about our functions in a more localized manner.
And it opens up us to using higher order functions and abstractions to sort of deal with common behaviors that we might have in our code.
We saw the examples dealing with emptiness, dealing with concurrency, and dealing with exceptions.
And all of these examples, as you can see, they sort of just like English, they read left to right.
We're no longer sort of writing if statements and things that are nested and harder to read.
Everything is just reading left to right. We get an input value, we apply some functions, and we get a return value.
And that is sort of how a functional programmer thinks about the world, how they think about programs, and how they want every program to kind of behave.
And that's really all I had. Thank you guys so much. That's my Twitter handle, vicumr1981, and that's my GitHub page.
Thanks, Vic, for that wonderful talk. I would now like to open the floor for discussion and invite questions from the audience.
Any questions for Vic?
Thank you.
In the future example, why was it a list of int versus a list of tri-event?
Yes.
Okay, so on the callback, it's just a single tri-event. So you have...actually, you might be right. Maybe I do...I'm going to have to look at my slides.
That's a very good question. You might be right, because it's optional static typing. Maybe I did screw up the optional annotation on that.
Let me actually check my slide real quick.
So the previous example, without the traverse, had the tri-int.
Okay, this example right here, right?
Yeah, versus the previous example that had just result as a tri-int.
Oh, right, right, right. So handle result takes in a list of int. Here, the handle result takes in a list of int versus this example where it's a tri of a single int.
Yes.
Okay. No, that could be...that's an error on the slide, actually. You are right. It should be a tri of list of int on that, because you can check success and failure. It is a tri of list of int. I should have probably corrected that.
Nice. And then what would this be a list of tri-int versus a tri-list int?
Okay, so what is the difference?
Yeah.
So a list of tri-int is sort of a little harder to...because each individual tri, now you have to check the success and failure. But if you have a tri of list of int, I can check the success and failure of the whole thing, right?
Did this all this succeed or did all of it fail? So inverting it becomes like a little useful, because now I can just check the whole thing, right? Does that make sense? Does that make sense?
Yeah, makes sense. Thank you.