Welcome, everyone.
I have the pleasure of introducing Kevin Modzelski from Anaconda, and he will be giving the talk
on writing performance code for modern Python interpreters.
And he'll take the questions at the end of the talk.
Thanks.
Hi, everyone.
I condensed the title of the talk a little bit.
So it's now how to write fast modern Python code.
And my name is Kevin Modzelski.
I'm an employee at Anaconda where I work on the piston optimized Python interpreter.
And today I want to focus on the word modern.
There's a lot of Python tips out there.
There's another talk across the hall that's also about Python performance.
And this talk, I wanted to do this talk because there's a lot of work that's currently going
into optimizing Python that has downstream effects for what you as a Python programmer
can think about to make your code even faster.
So some of the tips that have been around for a while are not quite as useful anymore.
And there are some new ones that if you get onto these new systems, you might want to
start thinking about.
The structure of the talk is first I'm going to talk a little bit about what makes Python
slow, what we're doing to speed it up, and then spend the rest of the talk going into
specific examples of how those optimizations affect you as a programmer.
Why Python is slow is a bit of a divisive topic.
Everyone seems to give different reasons.
This is my personal take on it.
The most commonly given reason is that Python is interpreted, interpreted languages are
slow, so Python is slow.
But in my personal measurements on web servers, the interpretation overhead is about 10% of
the time.
So it's significant.
People don't want it.
But it doesn't explain why Python can be 10 to 100 times slower than C. For that, you
need to go to a different set of things, which I'm generically calling dynamic behavior.
Python is a very dynamic language, as we know.
And I'm not going to list all the ways it could be dynamic, but I'm just going to call
out a couple today.
So the first is maybe the most obvious way it's dynamic, which is you don't write types
before variables.
So the interpreter doesn't know what types any of the variables are.
And yes, there are static annotations, but do you really want the interpreter to crash
if your annotation is wrong?
Those aren't used to optimize performance yet.
So this is slow because it means that any time you want to do anything in Python, you
have to check what is the type of this object, how do I do the operation I want on this object.
The second thing that I call slow here is dynamic variable lookups.
And this is something that we might not even think about because it doesn't seem like it
should have to happen sometimes.
But say you have a print statement, print hello world or whatever.
Print isn't a special word in Python.
Print is just a function.
And when the interpreter sees print, it says, OK, let's look up what this function is.
And it does this whole lookup mechanism to see where that is.
In particular, it asks, did anyone in this module override what the print function is?
And it has to do that every single time you want to print something, every single time
you want to take the length of something, cast something to an integer.
All of these words require expensive lookups.
And then the third thing I'm pointing out here are dynamic attributes that even within
a single class, you in general don't know in advance what attributes exist on that class,
which means that you need a dynamic representation of the attributes, which are pretty fast for
what they are in Python, but they're still much slower than static languages.
So with that little primer on where we started, there's three projects that are sort of coming
out in various forms either last year or this year.
The project I work on is Piston.
It's a fork of CPython being run out of Anaconda.
There's the Faster CPython project, which is working directly inside CPython.
And all that work is going to start showing up in 311 in October, and that's being run
out of Microsoft.
And there's Cinder, which is out of Instagram and is also a fork of CPython.
And these are all available right now in various forms.
So this is going to be the controversial slide of my talk, which is why it's not filled in,
because I'm going to go step by step with a lot of disclaimers.
This is going to be the set of projects in this space and the benchmark, my benchmark
numbers for them.
So I think I'm going to get a lot of flack for this slide, so that's why I'm disclaiming
it a lot.
The first controversial thing is even choosing a set of benchmarks for analyzing performance.
There's a very common semi-standard set of benchmarks called PyPerformance.
And it's nice in a lot of ways.
It's like well-established.
A lot of people present their numbers for it.
I personally think that it tends to overstate performance benefits, and so I tend to like
to look at more application code.
So I wrote a Flask benchmark as well.
Flask is a web server for Python and maybe web application library.
And it's one of the simpler ones, and I chose a simple one so that I could get more projects
working with it.
The next controversial thing is the selection of a baseline to measure everything against.
I picked Python 3.8 because that's what Piston is based on.
And specifically I picked the Ubuntu build of Python 3.8.
I didn't know this coming into this, but actually different builds of Python can be pretty different
speeds.
So the same version of Python but built in different ways will be different speeds.
So the Ubuntu build is a pretty fast build.
I believe the Mac and Windows builds are slow builds.
So anyway, this is a Python 3.8 Ubuntu build.
And we're measuring relative numbers here, so it's the same speed as itself.
The next controversial thing is I get to list my project first.
So Piston, we show improvements on both of these benchmarks.
And you can see the relative improvement is quite different between these two benchmarks.
So it is not getting into which is more accurate, but it is important to choose which benchmarks
you use that are actually representative of your programs because you'll get very different
numbers either way.
The next is Python 3.11 alpha 7, which includes most of the faster CPython work.
This came out I think earlier in April.
And they also show good improvements on both of these numbers.
This is controversial because they say a different number for their PyPerformance numbers.
I don't know exactly where the difference is, but they say 25%.
But when I measured it, I got 15%.
Then there's Cinder.
They don't have releases, so I just grabbed their GitHub and built it.
And very oddly, it was quite a bit slower than standard CPython.
So I put question marks here because I don't really believe these are real numbers.
They're using it internally, and I think they're smart enough to not use something that's slower.
So I don't know what's going on here.
I think they didn't open source all of it.
I'm not sure.
Now, this is going to be a little controversial.
I put PyPy on here.
This is a little bit more of an established player in the Python performance space.
But they make a very different set of tradeoffs, which I think show up in these numbers, which
first they can't run PyPerformance, so they don't support all of the dependencies of PyPerformance.
And then they're slower on this web serving benchmark.
And the controversial thing here is I did not put a question mark after their Flask number
because it is in line with other numbers I've seen of PyPy.
And then I also took the time to benchmark Pigeon.
I think it's a little bit less well-known, but I still wanted to know how it did.
And I don't know what happened here, but Pigeon was 1,000 times slower.
So that gets like a double question mark.
I assume that that's not the behavior that they get, but I didn't have time to sort all
these things out before this talk, unfortunately.
So this is sort of the state of Python optimizers that aim to support all of Python.
There's lots and lots of Python performance tools, but a lot of other ones fill more niche positions.
So in terms of going back to what makes Python slow, we can start talking about what these
projects do for those things I mentioned are slow.
The first is interpretation overhead, which is kind of just gone now, that a lot of these
projects such as Piston and Cinder add JIT compilers, and JIT stands for Just in Time.
So it means that instead of compiling your code during your development process, we will
compile your code as it's running and convert your Python code into assembly instructions
that is your Python code.
And so this sort of definitionally gets rid of interpretation overhead.
I'm not going to really talk about this today, because while it's really cool at a technical
level and 10% is really nice to get, it's not something that really you as a programmer
can affect that much.
You just kind of get it.
You're not going to really improve or diminish it in any way.
So I'm not going to talk about it for this talk.
What I'm going to spend the rest of the talk talking about are the dynamic features.
I listed a bunch of projects, and all these projects do a bunch of things.
But if I was going to make a sweeping generalization, I would say the sort of bread and butter technique
that all these projects are doing in many different areas is to use the combination
of two theories.
The first is that most code does not use the full dynamic power that it could at any point
in time.
And the second idea is that we can quickly check if code is using the dynamic power that
it could.
And so this lets us say that we can very quickly check to see that nothing strange is happening
right here, and we can do something fast instead.
And this is pretty much the source of most of the speed ups I showed you earlier.
So this is quite effective.
And this sounds great.
You know, Python has dynamic features, but you're not paying for them if you're not using
them anymore.
But if we kind of reverse that statement, it kind of says that you are paying for dynamic
features that you do use now.
That before they were kind of free because you were paying for them whether or not you
use them, so it didn't matter if you used them.
But now, because you no longer pay for them when you're not using them, it is something
that you as a programmer could think about and speed up your program even more.
To be clear, you don't need to.
Your stuff will be faster no matter what.
But if you want to get the very best performance out of these new systems, thinking about these
things will make your code even faster.
All right.
So the rest of my talk is going into examples.
So the first one is that global variable and I suppose built-in variable case that I talked about.
So say you have a print statement or you're printing out a bunch of things or using when
to get the links of things and you're looking up that name a whole bunch of times.
In Python, there's a, in the implementation of Python, there's a very quick way to check
were any global variables assigned since the last time I did this lookup.
So you can very quickly check were any global variables assigned and if not, then we know
that the global lookup resolves to the same thing it did last time.
And I should be clear here about what it means to assign to a global variable.
I have two snippets of code here.
The one on the left assigns to the global variable.
It takes a new value and assigns it to the name of the global variable.
And the one on the right, I would call that mutating a global variable.
And the one on the right does not affect what I'm talking about.
That's fine.
But the one on the left, that assignment, L equals new list, will slow down the following
print statement.
I put together a benchmark and the numbers in this table are the time it takes to lookup
a global variable.
And the two columns are, I did a first benchmark where we're sometimes also assigning to global
variables.
And a second benchmark where we're never assigning to the global variables after initialization.
And you can see what I mean by you're not paying for dynamic features in Python 3.8
because these are the same speed.
It's doing the same amount of work.
It's doing the full dynamic work each time regardless of whether this optimization could
be applied.
The story is very different with these modern implementations that with Piston especially,
it's six times faster in the not updated case.
I wouldn't take these numbers too literally.
This table I think is going to evolve very rapidly.
I think I was surprised a little bit by these numbers.
I think the faster C Python people might have some ideas from it.
So the exact numbers are going to change.
But I think the general conclusion that the no reassignments case is almost always going
to be faster than the reassignments case is we'll hold up over time.
This leads to a pretty simple tip that I'm giving out which is try not to reassign your
global variables.
Performance might not be your primary concern, but if you're considering performance, assigning
to global variables will slow things down.
And if you still want global mutable state, then store it within an object as an attribute
on an object or within a dictionary or something like that.
The next set of dynamic behavior are attributes that I talked about before.
As I said, you generally don't know what sets of attributes are going to be on an object.
And this means that we use dictionaries in general.
There's lots of special cases in Python.
But in general, Python objects are backed by dictionaries, otherwise known as hash tables.
And Python dictionaries are very fast as dictionaries come.
But they're still much slower than say in C where it's just a direct pointer look up
in a single memory load.
So even though each individual access is not that slow, because attribute access is such
a common operation, a large part of the runtime does end up doing this.
So we're going to apply the same optimization to this, which is we're going to assume that
you're not using the full dynamic power, that you're not having your objects of different
shapes and changing the shapes all the time.
And we're going to say, I'm saying this a little vaguely because the exact technical
restrictions are a little bit involved.
But at a high level, we say that if a repeated look up looks the same as it did the previous
time, then we can execute it the same as we did the last time.
And there's all these cases and all these special cases and different things that that can mean.
It's actually quite complicated.
But at a high level, that's what we do.
And as I said, there's a bunch of different things that lead to these technical restrictions.
But I'm going to call it two as things that you might run into that could affect this.
The first is what I'm calling different shapes.
It's the snippet on the left.
We have two objects of this class and they have different attributes on them.
This forces a less efficient representation of the class's objects because we can no longer
say all the objects of this class have a single shape.
So once you do this, this snippet on the left, accessing attributes on those objects will
be slow for the rest of your program.
The other case that hurts is what I'm calling type mutated, which is when you change attributes
on the class of an object.
So you can see here in the second case, we have an object, we set an attribute on it,
and then we change an attribute on the class.
And the reason this is really difficult for performance is the class has a lot of ways
that it can intercept attribute lookups on its objects.
And generally they're not used, so we have a very fast way of saying, did the class decide
– sorry.
We can say we know in the past the class did not intercept them and nothing changed on
the class, so now it's still not intercepting them.
But if you change something on the class, we no longer know if you might have changed
something that could now intercept attribute accesses.
So we have to do the expensive check.
I made a benchmark, and the third column is what I call the happy case, where all the
technical restrictions are met and the fast path can be taken.
And you can see from this example that, again, in Python 3.8, you're not really paying a
cost for your objects being different shapes.
You're doing a full hash table lookup no matter what, and it's the same cost.
You already were in Python 3.8.
I think it goes quite a bit back beyond that.
You were paying a cost for updating your classes because that doesn't validate a bunch of
caching.
And now in the optimized interpreters, the happy case gets way faster, but the other
cases not so much.
And again, the exact squares that are good are going to change over time, but the general
idea here is that having your objects of different shapes or changing the types will generally
tend to have the effect of slowing down your attribute lookups.
So the tip here is basically just don't do either of those things if you can avoid it,
especially the shape one.
In looking at some code, I've seen code that has objects of different shapes, and they
were doing that, I think, to save memory by not assigning variables they didn't need.
But that's also not a great tip anymore because by having different shapes, you're using this
less efficient representation and using more memory in general.
So in general, you want to set the same attributes in the same order.
I'm not going to get into it in this talk, but if you know what slots are, those are
now the fastest way to do attributes in Python.
They don't guarantee good performance, but they give you the best chance.
They resolve a bunch of the technical aspects that I didn't really go into in this example.
There's a special case of attribute lookups, which is where you look up in an attribute
and then you immediately call that attribute object.
I'm calling this method calls.
So that's sort of a two-step process.
You look up the attribute, you take that object, and then you call that object.
There's this common piece of advice that if you're doing that a lot in a loop, you should
try to do the attribute lookup only once outside the loop and then call the object inside the
loop.
That looks something like this, where you might say we want to append a bunch of things
to a list.
Let's forget about list comprehensions and whatever else, and just say we want to append
a bunch of things.
We're going to cache this list.append method and just call that attribute inside the for loop.
In doing a benchmark, in Python 3.8, this is decent advice.
If performance is what you're looking for, this does improve performance by about 10
percent, but 66 percent in this case.
The problem now in 2022 with these smart optimizers is the optimizers want to see more of your
code at once to optimize more of it, especially in this particular case.
This particular case is very special of fetching an attribute and calling it, and there are
a lot of special optimizations just for that case.
But by caching the method and separating them, those optimizations will no longer apply.
Now with these modern Python implementations, caching this method actually slows down your
code by a fair amount.
The situation is getting pretty complicated.
To be clear, this is just for functions on built-in types like list.
If we look at Python types, the numbers are a little bit different.
It was a little bit less of an improvement before versus the built-in type, but the improvement
is even smaller now.
Basically as attribute accesses get faster, the benefits of this approach get smaller.
I looked at another case which is not exactly the same but looks very similar, which is
where you're calling functions of modules.
I picked the function that I could find that does the least amount of work.
I think math.square root.
There's a square root instruction, so this is a single instruction.
Everything else is overhead.
This is the maximum amount of improvement that you'll ever see from this case.
In Python 3.8, it was pretty big.
In these new implementations, it is considerably smaller.
Maybe you consider 15% to be enough, but it is quite a bit smaller than before.
As I said, math.square root was picked because it is the fastest function I could find.
If we look at a more typical function, say os.path.join, the improvement was much smaller
than before.
Again, the improvement has decreased a lot.
Now you're talking about a 0.4 to 2% improvement by doing this.
I've shown you four different cases.
There's different numbers for them.
Sometimes it helps a decent amount.
Sometimes it helps a tiny amount.
Sometimes it hurts.
What is the takeaway?
What should you do?
My personal advice now is just don't cache methods anymore.
I think it's not worth the mental overhead.
I don't think it's worth the readability hit.
I think the improvement will get smaller and smaller as the implementations get smarter
and smarter.
You don't have to rewrite it if you already did it, but I think in general, this is something
that we can leave behind as the implementations get smarter.
In this slide, I'm calling out a couple of other dynamic features.
I'm not going to go into them a lot, but the point I want to make here is these, unlike
the ones I talked about before, these were already expensive before.
But now these particular features are getting even more expensive because they inhibit other
optimizations.
So not just are they expensive when you use them, but they might affect other parts of
your code that can no longer be optimized.
In particular, a problem that we need to solve as a community is attaching a profiler to
this optimized code.
At least in Piston, I don't know about FastReceivePython and Cinder, will tend to just disable almost
all of the optimizations.
So the code that you end up profiling might look very different than the code that you
meant to profile with optimizations on.
This is in general a hard problem, and we might need a new profiling API.
I don't know exactly what it will take, but this is an unfortunate part of the situation.
The last thing I wanted to talk about is the situation of C extensions versus pure Python.
That generally C extensions are thought of either as bindings to another language or
as a way to speed up Python code.
A common piece of advice is use Cython, convert it to a C extension, stuff like that.
But this situation is getting pretty murky now because all of the optimizations that
I've talked about today, they currently only apply to Python code.
So this means that C extensions do a certain set of optimizations, the Python interpreter
does a different set of optimizations, and it's very dependent on your code which set
of optimizations helps your code more.
And unfortunately, it's very hard to give a good rubric for this case you definitely
should do it in C, this case you should definitely do it in Python.
But to illustrate this, I took the benchmark from before, the attribute lookup benchmark.
If you remember, this 18.4 nanoseconds was the amount of time it took before.
And I used Cython to convert this benchmark to a C extension.
And then I ran it in Python 3.8.
And indeed, it does make it a fair bit faster.
And so that advice was good before that converting it to a C extension is good.
But if you remember the slide of the other numbers, the other implementations sped up
this benchmark much more than Cython did.
And then also, the optimizations that these implementations do don't help Cython at all.
So Cython could adopt all of these same optimizations.
I don't think there's a technical reason that they couldn't.
I think it will probably happen over time, but they currently don't.
So this means that if you're particularly hitting the optimizations I've talked about
today, you might actually be better in Python.
As I said, there's not a really clear-cut rubric for when it's better one or the other.
If I had to say, I would say that object-oriented code is going to be helped a lot more by the
new interpreters.
And numeric code is going to still stay best in C code.
But this is something that you're going to have to verify for yourself, because as I
said, it's fairly complicated at this point in time.
Which brings me to my last point, which is that unfortunately, there's not a lot of help
that you're going to get with these kinds of issues.
I'm trying to give you the best tips I can now, but these things are changing rapidly.
There's all these corner cases, and there aren't tools that will say, hey, this was
slow because you did this over here, and so this optimization was turned off.
That stuff doesn't exist yet.
So your only method of telling how to optimize your code is you're going to have to benchmark
it and see what works and what doesn't.
So to wrap up my talk, as I said in the beginning, the general idea is that we're trying to make
Python programmers not pay for dynamic features they're not using.
And this is great, but it adds this new complexity that you get rewarded if you do think about
these dynamic features and trying to not use them.
I put the GitHub links up on there.
You can find all these projects.
They're already available in different forms.
I believe that these are also the best ways to get in touch with the relevant teams.
So I work on Piston.
If you want to reach out to me online, you can go to the Piston GitHub page, and then
I will also be hanging around here after this talk.
Thank you.
Thank you, Kevin.
I would now like to invite questions from the audience.
Do you think the Rust extensions will be any different than the C extensions, given cryptography
starting to use Rust libraries underneath?
I don't think so.
I think the only thing might be, I think these optimizations are probably too much work for
individual C extension writers or Rust extension writers to do.
If I were to guess at how they would start appearing in C extensions, it would be that
a intermediary tool like Cython would adopt them.
So in that sense, unless Cython can generate Rust extensions, it might be a little bit
slower getting to Rust.
But at a technical sense, there wouldn't be any difference.
Yeah?
Would it make sense to move your dynamic features in a different file or a different class and
the not so dynamic one somewhere else, and separate the concerns, so give the optimizers
more way to do it?
So just move everything that's dynamic to one place and not dynamic to the other place
instead of mixing them?
Would it help?
I'm not sure exactly what you're proposing, but I think the general idea is very much
happening.
We're not doing it in Piston because we don't want people to change their code, but Cinder
has this thing called static Python that might be similar to what you're talking about, where
you sort of commit to not using certain dynamic features, and then the compiler is able to
speed it up even more.
Is that what you're talking about?
No, I mean, if you use one of the dynamic features, instead of one class, you have two
classes, one that uses dynamic features, the other one not, that you can speed up the one
that doesn't.
Would it help?
If you can do this easily, if it just fits your, if you have the design decision to make
and it wouldn't be any more work just to split into two classes, for instance.
Yeah, I guess that could work.
If you have some type that you need to update a lot, then I guess you could have a different
type with instances that you look up things a lot.
I think you probably have some trade-off with readability and maintainability, but for performance,
I think that could work for sure.
What is your thoughts on optimizations like using MyPyC and stuff like that?
Like passing your programs into MyPyC?
Yeah, I'm not super familiar with MyPyC in general, but as I kind of alluded to earlier
in the talk, there are a lot of tools that, there's sort of a spectrum of how much Python
versus how fast they are.
And so the more Python you support, the less fast you can go.
And if you support less Python, you can go way faster.
And so it's kind of nice that there are options all along that trade-off curve that you can
use.
I assume that MyPyC has some sort of issue with supporting everything, and that's why
we don't just run everything through MyPyC all the time, but that's a little bit of speculation
on my part.
So I was wondering, as far as typing is concerned and as things get more static, I know in some
languages, like in Scala, where types are sort of pseudo-dynamic, the type inference
engine can get pretty slow when things are sort of missing.
I was wondering if that's something, have you all seen any sort of performance issues
in terms of the performance or doing type inference on the fly?
I would say that we do very, in Piston, talking just about Piston now, we do very lightweight
profiling, which is basically for each bytecode, what did we see happen at that bytecode?
And it is quite cheap to do that.
There's no cross-function analyzing, whole program analysis, anything like that.
I don't know for the larger projects in terms of actually the type inferences or the static
Python project that I mentioned, but for us it's not really an issue.
Anyone else?
If you have any other questions, I would suggest talking to the speaker after, either outside
this space.
Great, thanks.
Thank you.