Welcome, everyone.
The next talk is titled five steps to build Python native GUI widgets for Bware.
And our speaker is Dan Yaw.
A round of applause for him, please.
Hi, my name is Dan Yaw.
I'm so excited to talk to you about how to build your own GUI widgets using Bware.
A little bit about myself.
I'm an engineer who helps design safety into complex autonomous and electrified technologies
for Ford Motor Company.
And in my free time, I have been working on trying to build open source engineering tools.
After a while, I got so frustrated with GUI widgets for Python.
I really wanted to be able to create one app and put it on all my devices and instead,
you know, the GUI widgets are available, we're wrapped or introspected from C or C++ APIs
or some of them kind of look like they're a blast from the past.
I wanted to really try to create great Python code and instead I was kind of felt like I
was working against the green of Python a little bit.
So that's Bware.
It's a set of software libraries and tools that provides cross platform native app development
from a single Python code base and tools to simplify app development.
Today we're going to be talking about one of those software libraries, Togo, which is
the GUI widget for the Bware project.
And I'm going to show you how you can build your own widget for that project.
Here's a Hello World example.
So you would import Togo, which is that GUI widget, and you would create a class called
Hello World which uses Togo.app, which is the main application that Togo provides.
It has a single method called startup.
And then in that method, you create a main window and it takes one parameter, the title
of the window.
And then you create a Togo.box.
Togo uses a box to lay out widgets on the main window and give those widgets space in
the window.
So then you add that box to the main window and tell Togo to show the main window and
it should appear on the screen then.
And there's a single method called main and it returns that Hello World class and provides
Hello World as a title for the app.
So that's how you would create a simple Hello World example.
Next, I'm going to go through a little bit of background on what a widget is and also
some background on the software architecture of Togo.
And with that knowledge, then we'll go through the five steps of how you could build your
own GUI widget.
So a widget is the controls and logic that a user interacts with in a GUI application.
So this is a simple Togo example app and on the right-hand side are two buttons, Hello
World 0 and Hello World 1.
On the top, there's two action buttons that have images and labels.
And on the left-hand side are two tabs.
The one visible is a table and the other tab is a tree.
All of those are widgets.
Now not all widgets have been implemented in Togo.
In fact, when I was trying to build my own open source app, there was no way to draw
on the screen.
So I implemented a Canvas widget.
And I definitely implemented it the hardest way possible.
So now I want to show you how, now that I've learned that, we could, yeah, you don't have
to make the same mistakes I do.
So we're going to go into the software architecture for Togo.
This is the black box view of how Togo works.
On the left-hand side is the application you'd be building using Togo as a GUI framework.
So that would be like that Hello World example you saw where you use this interface layer
to write your Togo app.
On the right-hand side is the native platform you'd be writing for.
So that would be Windows, Mac OS, Linux, iOS, Android, or the web.
And connecting the Togo toolkit to that native platform is a native layer.
Togo provides an abstraction level above all these native platforms.
So each abstraction level from that GUI application down is a layer.
So here we see those two of those layers, interface layer and native layer.
To go from Togo toolkit to the native platform for a C-based platform like Linux, for example,
is pretty straightforward.
CPython can use GTK and that already has language bindings called PyGeObject.
For other platforms, it's definitely not so easy.
So then you need some type of bridge or transpiler.
These are three other software libraries that the Bware project provides as these bridges
are transpilers to some of the other platforms.
For example, for Mac OS or iOS, Rubicon provides a bridge between CPython and Objective-C.
For Android, Vox provides a Python transpiler to convert Python into Java bytecode.
And then you can load that Java bytecode into your Android device.
For the web, Bware provides Batavia.
It implements a Python virtual machine in JavaScript, which then you can load in the
browser and run your app in the browser.
So zooming in on the Toga GUI toolkit itself, this is a white box view.
On the left-hand side, you see that interface layer that we talked about before that you'd
be interacting with with your GUI application.
And on our right-hand side is that same native layer we just talked about.
There's two main software components for Toga.
One's called Toga Core.
The other one's called Toga Imple for implementation.
And it has another API or another layer between those two called the implementation layer.
So there's three main layers in Toga, the interface layer, implementation layer, and
native layer.
And there's two software components, Toga Core and Toga Imple.
A couple more terms you need to understand because we're going to see these terms in
some of the software code that we'll show demos of.
To go from Toga Core to Toga Imple, you need to call self.imple.
And to go back the other way from Toga Imple to Toga Core, you'll call self.interface.
So just keep those terms in mind.
One final thing about the software architecture for Toga.
So we use a factory pattern in order to create the Toga Imple implementation layer.
And that's to improve testability of Toga.
So we can really improve the test to make them more maintainable and easier to read
by not requiring the test to know how to create the implementation layer.
So in this case, instead of each backend inheriting from Toga Imple, we have a factory
method in Toga Core.
And it looks at sys.platform of the Python it's running on to figure out what platform
it's running.
So for Linux, that'd be Toga GTK.
For macOS, that'd be Toga Coco.
And there's one other one called Toga Dummy.
And that's for testing.
So we use that to smoke test Toga Core to check that when Toga Core calls a widget,
that that widget is created in this dummy backend.
And then the test, we can pass in dummy into the test through this factory parameter.
And the test doesn't have to know how to actually create that backend.
So that was kind of some background in the software architecture for Toga.
And now we're going to get into the five steps.
And there's kind of one pre-step.
And that is you need to pick the platform you want to implement with.
So that choice might be kind of made for you.
It'd be the operating system that's running on your laptop, whether that's Windows or
macOS or Linux.
But you could also develop a widget for iOS or Android if you want to do mobile or even
the web.
macOS and GTK are the most developed platforms.
So they're often a really good choice.
But Android and Windows need the most help.
So if you have knowledge about those platforms, definitely we could use all the help we can
get with those.
So now that we have a platform selected, we're going to go on to our five steps.
And this step is probably the most important.
And that is you need to research your widget.
So like I said before, Toga is creating this nice Pythonic API.
And it's creating an abstraction layer above the native platforms.
In order to create a good abstraction, you need to understand specific examples.
So we need to understand specific examples of these widget toolkits on the different
platforms.
And then we can take that knowledge and constrain the API that we're creating and really create
a nice abstraction layer.
And so through our research, we need to understand how other users are going to use the widget
that you create.
So my use of a Canvas widget might not be the same use other people might want to use
it for.
And finally, get feedback as soon as possible.
So that could be through creating a GitHub issue or even a draft pull request.
Start discussing the widget right away with others and get as much feedback as you can.
So going through examples, I'm going to go through two examples.
You'd probably want to look at other platforms as well besides these two.
Tkinter is the GUI widget, or excuse me, GUI toolkit that's built into Python in the standard
library.
So in order to use Tkinter to draw on a canvas, you would initialize Tkinter and then call
And then on that canvas, call canvas.createRectangle, pass in width, x, y, width, and height, and
a fill color, and then call canvas.pack.
Pack is the way that Tkinter assigns space for the widget on the screen and allows it
to be shown, very similar to the box that I showed for the TOGA example.
Here's another example for GTK.
The canvas for GTK is called a drawing area.
So we're going to initialize GTK.drawingArea to create our drawing area.
And then GTK uses this connect method.
So this is also a common pattern you'll see with these GUI toolkits is they have callbacks.
So what a callback is is if you had a button and a user clicked on the button, you'd want
to be able to assign a function to that button click that gets executed when the button is
clicked on.
In this case, GTK uses event callbacks for almost everything.
So an advantage of this is if you have a drawing operation like this and you resize the window
or move it around, an event callback gets called and the canvas would be redrawn automatically
by GTK.
So in order to connect to that drawing operation, we create a draw function that takes in two
parameters, a drawing area and a drawing context.
And then you call context.setSourceRGB, which is the color, and context.rectangle and pass
in x, y width and height again.
Then you have to tell GTK to manually fill it by calling context.fill.
So this is a very simple drawing operation.
You'll notice that some of these C or C++ APIs require you to be very repetitive.
So imagine you want to draw more than a rectangle.
You're going to have to have a lot of calls to set source colors, create an object and
then fill them one after another.
It becomes kind of repetitive.
So when we're creating our nice Pythonic API, maybe we can do a little bit better than that
and not be so repetitive and make use of some nice features of Python.
You'll also notice there's four main patterns that a widget needs to support, and that is
to be able to create the widget, modify the widget, create some type of event callback
and finally provide some type of pack operation or give a widget space on the screen.
So we've gone through some research on the different GUI widgets.
There's definitely lots of others we could look at.
HTML DOM has a canvas, WXPython, Qt, Cocoa.
Definitely look at as many examples as you can to try to see how they would do a similar
drawing operation.
Now we're going to go through some use cases.
So I said I was trying to make an engineering tool, but let's look at what other use cases
would be for using a drawing operation.
So you can imagine a simple drawing app where a user wants to put a shape on the screen
and add text or do some basic drawing.
A vector drawing app where someone wants to put lines or a shape on and then edit those
nodes of that line after the line is drawn.
Or finally like a platformer game.
So you'd have a lot of objects drawn to the screen.
You want to be able to create a drawing context just for your superhero and then allow that
across the screen or jump in the air but not accidentally modify all the other objects
in the environment.
So we'll definitely keep those use cases in mind when we actually create our API for our
widget.
We're done with our research at this point.
Remember it would be good to create that pull request or draft pull request or create an
issue and start getting feedback.
But we're on to step two.
Step two is write docs.
I recommend using documentation driven development.
So our goal here is to create this nice Pythonic API, this nice abstraction layer for this
widget we're creating.
So let's write the documents for that API first.
This is iterative with step one.
So we can do this to start writing our API and do more research.
Here's an example of some docs we had to write so we'd explain what this canvas widget is
used for and then provide a simple example of how you'd use a canvas widget.
In this case we import toga, call toga.canvas and pass it in a style to create our canvas.
And then we're using the with statement or context manager which is a really nice feature
that Python provides.
So we call with canvas.fill.
We pass in the color to the fill operation and we can give it a name.
In this case we just called it fill.
And then call fill.rect and pass in the x, y width and height.
This is where we can really make use of these nice features that we all love about Python
since we don't have to wrap around some type of C or C++ API.
So if we had more drawing operations, we could put them all in this context and when the
context exits, then all of the drawing operations would automatically get filled with the right
color.
Instead of you having to manually keep on creating all these fill operations.
So that's a really nice feature we can provide.
So next we want to write a code outline for our API.
So we wrote kind of the documentation of how it's going to work.
Now we're going to outline our API code.
So in this case we create class canvas and it inherits from the Toga widget class.
And that class, that Toga widget class takes three parameters and an ID, a style and a
factory.
And so our canvas class needs to take those three parameters as well.
And we would do this for the rest of the methods for our class and really outline all the code
for our API.
So we've written our docs, outlined our API.
It's time to now implement Toga core, which was that first software component.
So we're going to use test driven development to implement Toga core.
So we're first going to write the test for Toga core and then we're going to code the
outline we created in the previous step.
So here's a test for Toga core to actually create the widget.
Toga uses unit tests for testing.
So that first line says assert equal.
We need to check that the object on the left matches the object on the right.
And remember the impel and interface terms we talked about.
So we're checking that canvas.impl.interface is equal to canvas.
So we're checking that the canvas in Toga core, when it's translated to Toga impel and
back to Toga core, is the same canvas we started with.
Another example, we talked about the dummy backend, the self.assert action performed
is a method that comes with our testing for the dummy backend.
So we're checking that generally our canvas is created on the dummy when we create a canvas.
So that was a smoke test for the canvas itself.
And now we're going to write some tests for our drawing operation.
So how do we actually create a rectangle?
So we call canvas.rect to create a rectangle.
Now we're going to modify our rectangle after it's created.
So we're going to pass in a different x, y, width and height and tell Toga to redraw
the rectangle.
And then that's that same action performed with for the dummy backend to make sure that
we successfully created a rectangle with those modified coordinates and width and height.
And those are our tests.
They should be failing now because we don't have an implementation yet.
Next we had the code outline we created in the previous step when we were creating our
docs.
Now it's time to implement Toga core from that code outline we created before.
So this is that same canvas class that you saw before that's inheriting from the widget.
It has two main methods, a dunder init method and the rect method to create a rectangle.
In order to inherit from widget, we call super dunder init with those three parameters, ID,
and the factory.
And now we're using the factory pattern to assign self.impl equal to self.factory.canvas.
So that's creating that canvas factory for us and assigning the interface to self.
So that's creating that Toga Impl object for us.
Now that we've defined self.impl, which remember was going from Toga core to Toga Impl, in
the rect method we call self.impl.rect and pass in the x, y width and height.
So this is that implementation layer that we're defining now and telling when we call
the rect method from the interface layer in our app, then it will call that Toga Impl
layer in the software.
We're on to step four.
So we've implemented all of Toga core.
Now we need to start implementing Toga Impl and that comes in two steps.
The first step we're going to implement the dummy backend and then we're going to implement
the backend for our platform.
Here's an example of the dummy backend.
Remember we're using that for testing of our widget.
So we're going to create a new class called canvas, which also inherits from widget.
So we've got two methods, a create method once again and a rect method.
And notice this self.underscore action is part of what's built in for the dummy backend.
So the dummy backend will call this self.action create canvas when that API endpoint is hit.
And the same thing for the rect method.
So we'll call self.action rect and then set x, y width and height to those values.
So then when our tests are run, that create canvas will actually be in the, be able to
be tested by the test itself.
So once we implement this dummy backend, now all of our tests should be passing.
We're on to the final step.
Step five.
So we have our working dummy backend, all tests are passing and now we're implementing
Toga Impl for our platform.
One nice thing about implementing the dummy backend first is we now have something we
can copy from that Toga dummy to our platform backend because the API endpoint will be exactly
the same for Toga Impl.
And so we can copy what we did there and make use of it when we're implementing it for our platform.
This is an example for GTK.
So we are actually, like we showed in the research in step one, calling GTK directly
from Python because we are now at that last native layer of the software.
So we call class canvas again where we create a class called canvas which inherits from
widget.
It has three methods.
Two of the methods you saw before, one called create and one called rect and the other one
is a drawing callback that GTK needs to make use of.
In our create method, we set self.native equal to GTK.drawing area.
So we're creating that drawing area using GTK.
And then we connect that drawing area to the drawing callback.
In the rect method, then we use the GTK drawing context to create a rectangle.
So we call it draw context.rectangle and pass in that x, y width and height.
So you'll notice this looks kind of a lot similar to Toga Core.
But remember, Toga Core was that abstraction level away from this.
So it doesn't have to know how to call the native GUI widget.
And then in this Toga Impl, now we're actually calling that native GUI widget for whatever
the platform is.
A big advantage of this is now once this is created, we can now implement another implementation
of Toga Impl for another platform.
For example, this is how you would do it in Cocoa if you wanted to implement it for macOS.
If you ignore the first class for a second, the second class at the bottom, once again,
looks exactly like GTK or looks very similar.
You have a class called Canvas with two methods, create and rect.
Something that's a little bit different is you set self.native equal to this Toga Canvas,
which is the other class, and you call alloc and init on it.
And that gives the widget memory for Objective-C, because now we need to bridge using Rubicon,
which was that other bridging tool software library I talked about.
And we need to give that Objective-C some memory space.
So classed Toga Canvas, which inherits from now some Apple APIs and NSVU, Rubicon provides
a nice decorator called Objective-C method.
And we add some type hints for the Objective-C to work.
So I don't want to go through that in too much detail, but as you can see, it's not
too difficult to now implement our widget for another platform.
So we created a canvas, and I showed you a simple example of creating a rectangle.
I think that would actually be a good way to implement a widget if you're actually creating
one.
Make something small and simple that works through these five steps.
Now I'd go back to step one and implement the rest of the widget.
So you need to be able to draw circles and lines and write text to the screen, all the
other drawing operations that your widget needs.
So now I'd iterate back through steps one through five and create the rest of the widget.
And we're done.
We've gotten through our five steps.
We've iterated through it.
On the screen is a Toga window, and we drew on a canvas.
This is Tiberius, who's the mascot for Toga, and we drew it using our Canvas widget.
And we're ready to submit a pull request and get it merged into the Toga project.
A quick summary of what the steps we talked about.
Really important is we need to research our widget and understand how all the other GUI
widget toolkits provide that widget that you're creating.
So we need to research our widget and create those use cases.
We want to do documentation-driven development and write our docs next and outline that API.
And then we're going to implement Toga Core using test-driven development, using and coding
that outline we created in step two, and then implement the two Toga impels, one for a dummy
backend and one for your platform.
My name's Dan Yaw.
Thanks so much for coming.
I think we have a few minutes to take questions and also be available after.
Also the Beware project's going to be sprinting for the next three or four days.
And if you come make a contribution, you can get a nice challenge coin.
So definitely come sprint with us on the sprint if you're going to be here.
Thanks so much.
Thank you, Dan.
If you have questions, please use the microphone.
Hi.
Great talk.
Thank you.
Can you contrast for us some what the difference between Beware and other toolkits like TKWX
widgets and maybe other platforms like PyQt and PyForms and PyGoObject, some of the others
that are out there.
And the second question is about does Beware provide an executable to be installed or does
it require Python to be installed in all these other platforms and what are the cross-platform
problems that might occur?
I mean, that's two separate questions, but thank you.
Thanks for your question.
So a lot of, I guess, as I kind of talked, a lot of the other GUI toolkits that exist
are either wrapped or introspective C or C++ APIs.
So an advantage here is we're creating abstraction level from the truly native widgets for the
platform.
And then so this is a truly native implementation.
A lot of other GUI widgets can provide some cross-platform, but they're not native widgets
for what that platform is.
And then that allows you to pull in everything like accessibility and all your shortcut keys
automatically work.
And also we can make the API a lot more Pythonic because we're creating that one abstraction
level that then all the GUI toolkits can use.
So I think that's the big advantage.
As far as you're kind of talking about deployment as well, do we need a Python executable?
So there's another tool called Briefcase, which packages up your Python app that I guess
you could create with Toga or you can even create it with a different GUI toolkit or
it could be a CLI app and packages all the libraries it needs and Python together.
And that makes it really easy to distribute on all the platforms.
What happens when you want to implement a widget that has features on one platform but
not on another?
So for example, some platforms have capabilities that others don't.
For example, you probably don't need a GPS widget on your Windows computer.
Maybe you do.
Some of those things like a camera GPS would only be available for mobile.
And that's okay if a widget's only supported on certain platforms and we just document
that in Toga.
So that's actually okay.
But for most of the main widgets that are cross-platform, then we'd create a single
abstraction level even if they're called different things on each platform but they're mainly
doing the same type of widget operation, then we'd try to kind of make as common of an API
as possible.
I'm sorry, but we don't have any more time for questions.
If you have further questions, you can work up directly to Dan and you have them answered.
Thank you once again for Dan, please.