And he will show us a guide to software engineering
for visually impaired.
Please give him a warm welcome.
Thank you, everyone.
I was at PyCon last year, and it was such an amazing feeling
to meet this awesome people and listen to inspiring talks
that I decided to come again this year,
but this time as a speaker.
So thank you all for coming in, listening to me
talk about a guide to software engineering for visually impaired.
My name is Abraar Shaikh.
I work for Yelp as a software engineer.
Yelp's mission is to connect people
with great local businesses.
It's a search engine for finding the best business around you.
I work for the ranking platform team within Yelp,
and my team is responsible for building and maintaining
search infrastructure and providing search
as a platform for other application teams inside Yelp.
We leverage technologies like Apache Kafka, Apache Flink,
Elasticsearch, and use a lot of Python.
I was born with a genetic disorder called albinism,
and albinism is mainly characterized by two factors
or two things.
One, severe lack of pigmentation in body
that results in discoloration of skin and head.
And severe loss of vision that restricts my ability
to do certain daily routine tasks like driving a car
or using a computer.
As I was growing up, I was extremely
fascinated by computers and always
wanted to pursue a career in software engineering.
And with the right support of my parents,
I was able to achieve just that.
So today in my presentation, I'm going
to talk about some of my journey in software engineering.
And what are some of the challenges and roadblocks
that I hit along the way, and I was able to overcome them.
So this is just a concise journey of my past experiences.
In today's presentation, we will first
understand what low vision really means,
how it impacts certain population sets,
and what effects it has on the society.
What challenges people with low vision
face in academia and professional environments.
And what are some of the simple strategies using which they
can overcome these challenges.
Really, my hope today is to convince you
all that software engineering as a profession
need not be that difficult even for someone with low vision.
This chart should be likely familiar to most of you.
It's called Snellen's eye chart, and this
is what your regular ophthalmologist would
use to measure how good your eyesight is.
And the metric that we are calculating here
is called visual acuity.
A visual acuity of 20 by 20 is what
is considered to be normal vision.
That's on the lower end.
And the idea here is that the lower down the chart
you're able to read, the better your vision is supposed to be.
A vision of 20 by 70 or lower is what
can be considered as a low vision,
and it becomes worse if you're not
able to read anything from the top.
But this is not a very accurate representation
of what low vision really is.
I prefer a more functional definition of low vision,
because the metric of 20 by 70 might not
apply universally to everyone, depending
on what work they want to do.
So a better representation of low vision is really this.
It states that uncorrectable vision loss that interferes
with one's daily activities, or to put it in simple words,
not having enough vision to do whatever
it is that you need to do.
And this can vary from person to person.
For example, a visual acuity of 20 by 70
may be perfectly fine vision to have for someone
whose profession is driving, but it might not
be sufficient for someone whose profession is a surgeon,
for example.
So now that we have a better understanding of what
low vision really is, let's look at some statistical data
around demographics of US population,
specifically for people with low vision.
The numbers that I'm going to present to you
were published by National Foundation for Blind
in the American Community Survey conducted in 2015.
About 2.3% of the total US population
suffers from some degree of vision loss.
And this is a significantly high number, enough that all of us
in the tech community should be responsible for making
our software more accessible to everyone.
Let's look at some educational data.
Close to 25% of the total US population
that suffers from some degree of vision loss
drop out before high school, whereas the national average
stands at about 6%.
Some data on unemployment rate, around 70%
of the total US population that suffers
from some degree of vision loss were unemployed in the year
2015, whereas the national average stands at 5%.
These are some staggering numbers,
and they tend to depict a distinction in our population
sets.
And the reason why I believe these distinctions exist
are for following reasons.
Lack of supportive and learning environment in our classrooms.
Restrictive access to reading and learning material
for students with low vision.
Lack of documentation around easy access to technology
and lack of structure and awareness
around creating a more inclusive work
culture in our professional environments.
Throughout my presentation, I'll be
touching upon the details of each of these points
and try to articulate a plausible solution
to overcome these challenges.
Next, let's look at some academic challenges
that a student with low vision would face.
Our education system is centered around classroom learning,
and this has been the fundamental way
of consuming knowledge for ages now.
But the fundamental problem with the system
is that for someone with low vision,
even with the best optical correction
and the proximity to the front of the classroom,
it's extremely difficult for them
to read contents of the blackboard or the projector.
And all of these factors pose significant roadblocks
in terms of obtaining a good quality education.
Some of the strategies that a student with low vision
can apply within their classroom to overcome these challenges
are as follows.
They can seek help from the student registrar
or the student council within the school or university.
These bodies within these organized institutions
can help facilitate appropriate classroom accommodations,
and these can vary broadly based on what condition you have.
Some things that have worked for me in the past
are extra time during examinations and assignments,
seeking help from an assistant who can help take notes
during a classroom.
Another thing that students with low vision can do
is reach out to the faculty or professors for each lecture
and make them aware about their own condition.
This way, the professor can help facilitate appropriate classroom
accommodations, like getting these students access
to previous years recorded lectures
or even provide them with the lecture notes
before every class.
This way, the student is more prepared before each class,
and the contents within the class are more predictable,
and the learning experience becomes just better.
Something that has worked for me really well in the past
is use of a monocular within a classroom.
A monocular is a visual aid device
that lets people with low vision see distant far-off objects.
It's kind of like a binocular, but a more portable version
of a binocular.
People with low vision typically find it extremely challenging
to read contents from books and research papers, especially
when these materials are not available in large font
printable formats.
One easy solution that can overcome this challenge
is with the help of a magnifying glass.
Any magnifying glass with an optical zoom of 3x to 5x
should sufficiently offset the difficulty in reading.
However simple this sounds, this is one of the most often
overlooked solutions, because it usually
takes a lot of time and practice of getting used to.
Students with low vision typically
find it extremely challenging to get easy access
to the contents that are presented on a computer screen.
This is significantly more challenging than reading a book,
and the primary reason for that is
that the kind of content which is presented on a computer
screen is more dynamic in nature.
Just to elaborate, text that is presented on a computer screen
rarely follows a prescribed pattern.
Layout changes drastically between application
to application.
All of these factors pose a significant challenge
for someone with low vision to get easy access
to the content that is presented on the computer screen.
On the other hand, it's kind of hard to imagine
a career in software engineering without having easy access
to technology, and this is increasingly
becoming true for other professions
as well in this modern age.
Fortunately for us, early developers of operating system
have built accessibility as a key focus into their product.
Both Mac OS and Windows ship with great on-screen magnifiers
which help assist students or people with low vision
get easy access to the content that is presented
on the computer screen.
Just to put things in perspective,
I think it's really important to show you
what I'm talking about.
How does an on-screen magnifier really
feels like how does it feel to use it in reality?
So I have this web page in front of me,
and I know it's kind of hard to read because I've
reduced the resolution.
And this might be the first time you might actually,
like a speaker, has actually reduced the resolution
so that the audience cannot see the content,
but that's on purpose.
So yeah, now this is really hard to see.
This is exactly how a person with low vision
experiences content on the computer.
For example, I can tell you offhand
that I kind of have an idea of what the layout of this page
looks like.
There are an array of businesses as form of a list,
and there's an image, and then there
is some short description.
But I don't really have any sense
of what content is on there.
I cannot really name the name of the exact business that
is being presented here.
So let's start engaging with the on-screen magnifier
and show you how that looks like.
So now this is better.
As you can see, anything under my cursor
is automatically magnified.
That gives me a very detailed idea
of what that localized area of the screen looks like.
Just scanning through the top three results,
this one looks better because it has good reviews
and good ratings.
So this should be a good business.
So this was just to show you how someone with low vision
engages with an on-screen magnifier to use a computer.
If that was kind of hard to imagine,
if you're wondering how I was able to swiftly navigate
my way through the screen without actually seeing
the content on the screen, let me try to explain
that with a driving analogy.
Imagine you just moved to Cleveland, Ohio,
and you have no idea how the city layout looks like.
The only way you're going to get from point A to point B
within a city is with the help of a navigation
system in your car.
Now, a navigation system is really
good at giving you a very broad, high-level layout of the city.
It tells you where what is, but all the while,
the driver is engaging with the windshield of his car
to make those in-the-moment driving decisions,
to look around and to figure out where to take the turn,
at what exact time.
So the on-screen magnifier, which
is on the top half of the screen,
is really what is the windshield of your car.
Try to think of it in that way.
And the bottom half of the screen
is that navigation system.
So a person with low vision does have a clear view
of a very localized area of the screen
at any given point of time, but all the while,
engaging with the lower half of the screen
to fit that into the broader context of what's really
happening on the screen at the moment.
Next, let's understand what professional challenges exist
for someone with low vision.
Getting hired, like this is the big one.
When I graduated from college and started
interviewing for a technical role with companies,
one of the biggest challenge I had to fight
was with my own insecurities.
I would constantly have to go to the office
and get my own job done.
The biggest challenge I had to fight
was with my own insecurities.
I would constantly retrospect and analyze
my own physical limitations and conclude
that there is no way any company is going to hire me.
And I think to a small or large degree,
we all find ourselves in this situation.
The next time you find yourself in this situation,
I want you to remember the following.
All your hiring manager really cares about
is the answer to the following three questions
about the candidate.
Does he or she have exceptional analytical and problem-solving
skills?
Does he or she have the right leadership skills
to drive business value to the company?
And are they a strong team player?
However simple this sounds, in reality,
your physical limitation should have no correlation
to your ability to perform these job requirements.
At the same time, it's kind of hard to have.
At the same time, if you do need certain accommodations
as part of your hiring process, do not
hesitate to bring that up with the recruiter.
After having spoken to a lot of recruiters myself,
one thing I can say with confidence
is that your physical limitation should
have no impact on the hiring decision that is being made.
It only depends on how good of a candidate
you are, like what kind of skills you bring to the table.
But if you are a recruiter looking
to hire an engineer with a certain physical disability
or low vision to be specific, here
is a word of advice for you.
Ask the candidate if they need extra time
as part of the hiring process.
Second, and this is the most important one,
make sure all the interview questions are being carried,
all the discussions and the interview process
are carried out on a whiteboard or a computer
of the candidate's choice.
The second one is particularly important,
and I'll touch upon this briefly in the next slide.
Being successful in a career for someone with low vision
takes a lot of self-drive and self-initiator.
But at the same time, it's also a community effort and support.
So here are a few ways in which your peers can help you.
As a manager, you can help provide
appropriate workspace accommodations.
And these accommodations can change or depend
from person to person.
A few things that my manager does for me,
which I found extremely helpful, are he
ensures that I have a desk away from windows or sunlight
because the rightly lit environment
make up for a very difficult working experience
and extremely challenging.
He ensures that I have the, he ensures
that I have the right environment
and he ensures that I have access to the slide deck
before every team meeting.
This is particularly important because it's not always
the case that I have visual access to the contents that
are presented on the projector or the computer screen.
Next, if, for example, if you're on a team
and you're working on a problem with a fellow engineer who
suffers from low vision, for example,
ensure that all the discussions are carried out on a whiteboard
and the context around the problem
is shared on tickets and documents.
Try not to engage in pair programming.
And the reason for that is people with,
engineers with low vision have a certain way
of using their computers with all the accessibility features
turned on like the one I showed you.
So they're seamless in, they're seamless at their work
when they're particularly on their own,
they're doing work on their own computer,
but not so much when they're working
on someone else's computer.
As a tech community, we should strive
for consistent coding standards, have
high amount of documentation and code coverage in our code.
This is important other than the obvious reasons.
This is particularly important in the context
of this discussion is because for someone with normal vision,
he or she can read about 10 lines of code
without moving a visual muscle.
But for someone with low vision, they
can only read about three lines of code
in the same amount of time.
So that's an inefficiency of about 3x.
So anything that we can do to make their experience better
and make them more efficient is worthwhile.
Just to put some context and show you
what I'm talking about, this is a piece of code
taken from the Avro library.
And I know this is hard to read, but that's again on purpose.
So we're looking at this function.
Let's try to look at this with the normal zoom.
So you see, when you're looking at this function,
you're constantly scanning back and forth.
The details of this function are not important.
When you're looking at this piece of code,
you're constantly scanning back and forth
between those lines, trying to make sense of what's going on.
But remember, you have the context of,
so when you're looking at this function,
you're looking at this function as a whole.
But for someone with low vision, this is how it looks like.
When you're trying to read this code,
you're only scanning about three lines of code at a time.
So going through this function three lines at a time
and then back again is time consuming.
And the point that I'm trying to make here
is, if this function has a good documentation,
then all it takes is one linear scan of reading
through that documentation and trying to get
a sense of what's going on here.
So the better the documentation, the better the reading
experience becomes.
Just to recap everything that we've discussed so far,
here are my top three recommendations
for someone with low vision trying
to be successful in a career of, say, software engineering.
The first thing's first, gather all your tool sets.
And these tools can vary from person to person.
Some of the tools that we discussed
during this presentation are use of a magnifying glass
to get access to books and reading materials,
use of a monocular to get access to a classroom,
and use of an onscreen magnifier to get access
to computers and technology.
Now, once you have your tool set ready,
spend enough time and practice your skills with those tools
so that you become as efficient as a person with normal vision.
And this typically takes a long time.
So the sooner you start, the better.
The more efficient you become over time,
and the better that will be in your subsequent career.
Lastly, but the most important one
is do not hesitate to ask for help.
It's in your best interest to make sure your teammates are
aware about your condition so that they can step in and help
you whenever necessary.
Just to finish this off, I think I showed you
how I use the computer.
But I think it's important to show you
how I actually code, which is a slightly different experience
than reading stuff.
So for the demo, we're just going
to write up a simple binary search function.
And I want you to be focused on the top half of the screen.
And I know you can't read the lower half of the screen,
so that works.
So as you can see, as I'm typing along,
I'm moving the cursor with me so that I have the context of what
is that I'm typing.
This is the worst binary search ever.
So just a minute.
Sheet a little bit.
Assert if that really works.
Cool.
Let's see if that works.
It works.
So yeah, that should give you some sense of how I use the on-screen magnifier to read
and write code.
Yeah, that's all I had for today.
Finally, as I said, I work for Yelp.
We are an awesome team.
I highly encourage you to come check out our booth on the exhibition hall.
Please read through our engineering blog post.
They are awesome.
We write a ton of good technical and non-technical content like this.
Thank you.
Thank you, Abra.
So we have time for questions.
You can find the microphones in the back.
Hey, thanks for your talk.
I was noticing that when you were using the magnifier, you had to keep scrolling the mouse
cursor down so you could see where you're going.
Would it make sense for the magnifier to follow the cursor?
Yes, for sure.
And I think I typically like such IDEs, but for the demo I was using Sublime, which doesn't
have that for some reason.
But IDEs like Visual Studio do that, and that's extremely helpful.
Thanks.
So again, thanks for your talk.
I noticed when you're using the magnifier, it really like blows up the text that you're
looking at, and it can be kind of blurry.
It seems like you're looking at an old school super low resolution video or something like
that.
So how important is it when you're developing products with accessibility in mind is the
overall resolution of the visuals so that you can see?
Is there a specific sort of density that's recommended for visually impaired users so
they can use the magnifier effectively?
Yeah, that's a great question.
And I think my comment on that would be this has definitely gotten better over time.
And I think it looks a little more pixelated now just because I've reduced the resolution
here.
So if I take this to the normal resolution and try to apply the zoom now, this looks
much better than what I showed you before.
So yes, it definitely helps to create those front end objects with high amount of pixel,
but yeah, I don't really have an exact number in mind.
Thank you.
Thank you for your talk.
A similar question but targeted to developers.
As a developer, what would you want to change in terms of linting or style guides that would
address something that would make it easier for you to read as a low vision reader?
For example, like there's a tension of the size of how descriptive a variable is versus
how much of your visual field it's going to take up or things like that.
I think all the standards that we've already established in PEP, which is hey, do not exceed
80 lines within a like 80 characters within a line, keep your function to about 10 or
12 lines, have documentation, document your arguments.
If we did follow them consistently, I think that would be a great first step.
On the tooling front, one package that I really recommend or tool that I really recommend
for especially Python projects is this project called precommit, which basically runs your
linter and fixes the code and ensures that the entire repository is in one consistent
style.
As long as that's taken care of, I think that is a sufficient good step.
Does your toolkit also include screen readers?
Not me specifically.
Screen readers are definitely a tool that a blind person using a computer would use.
For me, I haven't found it, like I found my efficiency to be much better just with the
onscreen magnifier.
But yeah, for people who have extremely bad vision, at which point the onscreen magnifier
is not helpful, a screen reader is definitely a good option.
Thank you.
Hi, I'm curious on your workflow.
Do you work with a lot of data, with charge, with some visual element?
Yeah.
So my workflow is typically either one of the two.
Most of my time is spent on bash shell because I'm an infrastructure engineer, I'm mostly
doing log analysis, looking at logs on bash.
Also spend a lot of time writing code in IDs like sublime or IntelliJ.
Those are the two main ones that I spend the most time on.
Yeah.
But looking at logs is difficult.
Yeah, I think that's a good point.
Logs is definitely difficult to scan, specifically if you're using an onscreen magnifier.
Just to go through all the logs is kind of hard.
So I usually end up writing scripts to do that work for me so that I'm only looking
at subset of the logs or looking at those logs in Splunk.
If a normal engineer is just making sense of logs, just by looking at the raw logs,
I typically take that extra effort to load it into Splunk so that I have a better visualization
and I'm not missing any tiny details.
Second question, I'm curious on any particular elements that are difficult for your magnifying
class to work with.
For example, does your magnifying class work with a pop-up tool where you hover your mouse
over and then the pop-up was way over another size?
For sure.
Everywhere.
That's a feature I've given up on.
Stuff like Amazon, right?
You hover over a product and it gives you this pop-up.
I can never get to the pop-up because by the time I move to the pop-up, it's gone.
In circumstances where I know that there is no alternative way of reading to get rid of
the pop-up, there is another version of this onscreen magnifier which lets you magnify
the entire screen and not just the one specific segment of the screen.
So that variation of the onscreen magnifier really helps with the pop-up.
Okay, thanks again, Abrah.
Please give him another round of applause.