Hello. How are you all doing today? Enjoying your PyCon so far? All right. Help me welcome
Lady Red, aka Chris, to tell us more about Medieval DSL.
Thank you. Hi, everyone. All right. So welcome to my talk, Medieval DSL. Just to clarify,
this is about heraldry, and heraldry is the medieval swords and knights kind of thing.
It's not like a new cloud platform like someone was guessing earlier. So here's why we're
here. This is the intersection of my two interests between gnarly medieval stuff and cool computer
stuff. So I was able to get a talk out of that. Heraldry is interesting to me because
it's this combination of graphic design, medieval history, self-representation, and just an
absurd amount of rules. And we're going to get into some of the rules and some of the
like interesting programmatic things that they ended up doing in the Middle Ages that
kind of predated a lot of what we have now. It's very interesting. So the original purpose
of a coat of arms was to identify someone in battle when they're wearing full armor.
So you want to know who to follow, who to kill. And they also provide family and state
personal identification in a society that's really obsessed with lineage and hierarchy.
And also after this talk, you're going to start seeing coats of arms everywhere. Wine
bottles, cars, buildings, logos all over the place. This is essentially the logos of the
Middle Ages. But one of the fundamental problems is now we have a logo. You see the Twitter
logo at any point. It's going to be pixel perfect. It's going to be the exact same bird.
But in the Middle Ages, there's no way to exactly copy an image from one thing to the
other because there's no copiers of computers. It's just going to be a guy in a castle painting
a shield. How can you define what is the actual information that's different than the artistic
embellishment? So the answer is they actually boiled it down to a DSL called Blazon, which
is reads something like if XML were to marry French, were to marry English, you'd get something
like this. All right. So let's just go into what we're looking at with the coat of arms.
This is the coat of arms of the UK. And just to get some terminology out of the way, this
top thing, this little line on top, that's the crest. So the whole thing is called a
coat of arms or a heraldic achievement. People sometimes call it a crest and that's wrong.
The crest is only the little animal or symbol that appears on top of the helmet. Then there's
a crown on this one. They don't always have crowns. There's a helmet. The style of the
helmet determines the rank of the bearer. So does the style of the crown. So like you
could tell you if you're nobility or if you're a common person. Then mantling usually reflects
the colors of the crest or the coat of arms. We got these supporters, which are these animals
that hold up the side. And then there's this order around it. So most achievements don't
have all of these things. Just the coat of arms of the UK has almost every single thing
because they kind of invented heraldry. So the coat of arms are called the escutcheon.
That's the shield itself. There's also a compartment at the bottom and a motto. So that's just
the full thing. And all of that, this is like an SVG I got from Wikipedia. And this isn't
I mean this is the coat of arms of the UK. But in a more fundamental way, this is the
coat of arms of the UK. This is the blazon representation of what we just saw. So if
you read it, it's crazy. It's a lot of words you don't know. What's ghouls. And then it's
just kind of hard to parse what's going on. There's a lot of words that aren't even in
English or French or whatever. So we're going to go into how to parse this. At the end of
this talk, we're going to successfully parse that. A couple other things about coats of
arms as we're getting started. Arms are inheritable but usually the way land is inheritable, not
the way a name is. So if you find out my name is Smith, is there a coat of arms for someone
named Smith, that doesn't mean you're a coat of arms. You have to have been the first son
of the first son of the first son of the first son of that guy to inherit it. Although that's
different from country to country and across time. I'm calling this medieval DSL because
it's amazingly consistent. But given the fact that it was written over 500 years, Python's
what, 30 years old? How many different versions have we had? This is a language that's been
written for 500 years. In the high middle ages by groups that were constantly at war
with each other. So it's been simplified. Okay. So let's look at some blazon. Azor.
All of the colors are formulas. There's only seven colors. Azor is a word for blue. This
one I'm actually going to try and I'm trying to describe the blazon for the Python logo.
Because I was looking at it and I said, hey, that's actually heraldic. We could describe
it. So we have two serpents. I'm calling them serpents because it looks like in the middle
ages Python meant like a wyvern like creature. But a serpent was like reliably a snake. And
then we have to describe the position of the serpents. So I was kind of going into that.
Here's a bunch of different words for positioning of animals. So I went with erect as the rough
shape of the serpent. And also that they're kind of combined against each other. Adorst
on the other side. That they're combined but facing away from each other. And then they're
also intertwining each other. And then here's an interesting thing. Of the field and or,
the sinister inverted. So of the field means it's the color of the field. So in blazon
you can have references to other parts of the same shield. So when you say of the field,
azure is the color of the field. So it's kind of like a reference to a variable reference.
Or it's the color for gold. And then I'm saying the sinister one is inverted. And you might
say, wait, doesn't sinister mean left? The right one is inverted. That's because the
coat of arms, you always imagine someone is holding it. So the like holding the shield.
So it's the left side or the right side of the guy holding the shield. Not of anyone
looking at it. So there's a lot of gotchas and little edge cases in this. And you can
really just go forever. All right. So let's try and build a parser for this. If you start
looking into Python parsers, you'll find that there's more than you can count. I decided
to go with lark. Most of the parsers support similar rules that are all in back as an hour
form. So you can kind of take one rule set and go from parser to parser. But I decided
to use lark because it's got good documentation. And it's got a couple different parsers in
there that like under the hood that you can switch between. So let's look at just like
this introduction to this parser. Let's try and parse hello world. So if you've written
regex's before, parser is like regex's on steroids. So hopefully you like regex's because
it's going to be a lot of that. So here I'm saying for this hello world, lowercase letter,
uppercase letter, defining both of those cases. And then you can say a letter itself is either
uppercase or lowercase. And then a word is many letters. So that's sort of familiar syntax
if you've seen regex's before. And then I'll define my start rule as a word, a comma, a
word, and then an exclamation mark. So I'm able to parse hello world and get out what
is actually called an abstract parser. So that's like a way of taking text and taking
into a symbolic representation of that. So let's start building this for Blasen. As
I said, there's only seven colors. Five colors and two metals. So that's easy because those
are all going to be keywords. So I'm just going to define all of those. And then I'll
be able to say that tincture is metal or color. Tincture is the rule for the combination of
those two things. And the lowercase indicates that it's like a... So if it's uppercase rule,
that means it's like a leaf node. It only has keywords in it. But if it's lowercase
rule, that means it's like just a node in the middle of the graph. So that's just useful
to understand. All right. So now immediately we're already able to understand these two
codes of arms, which are very simple, but they're real codes of arms that people have.
There's a little bit of a name grab domain squatting thing going on with codes of arms
where the guy who got blue... Yeah. So then let's look at some more. We actually have
some patterns that are a nice step up in complexity. So here's two. Ermin and Ver. And then we
have Ermin is symbolized... You guys know a picture of a king and he's got a white fur
with little black dots on it. It's a very luxurious fur, so that's Ermin. And then Ver
is, I think, symbolized like squirrel fur. But what's interesting about these is not
only are they just those things, they actually kind of are like functions. They can take
arguments. So here's Or, Ermin, DeGoole. And the next one is very Or and purple. So it's
interesting that the Ermin one is kind of infix and then the Ver one is kind of prefix.
And they're pretty consistent about that. So we can put that into our parser. So for
our fur parser, it could be Ermin, Ver, Or, a fur and a purple. So that's a pretty interesting
pattern. And then two tinctures. Or it could be a tincture, a fur that goes as an infix
fur, and then another tincture. So we can have Ermin or Ver as a fur and we can kind
of define the way it can include other rules inside of it. And then we can redefine our
tincture rule to include metal colors or furs. Okay. So then just these are kind of the base
cases that we'll start with arms. Arms are right now just a single field and a field
is just a single color. So that's kind of the full rule set. So now I'm able to do with
this rule set parse this very Or and Gools. And as you can see, we have this heroic abstract
syntax tree that gives me like a understanding and code of what this thing is. And when I
was... I built a giant database of a ton of code of arms and I was running it against
this as I was writing these. And I would add a rule set, run it again and see I got like
2% more codes of arms of the 100,000 I had indexed. So that was a fun way of building
this. All right. So let's go on for more complexity. Ordinaries are the names for geometric shapes.
And then we also have... So these are the main ones, the most honorable ordinaries.
And then here's the ones that aren't as honorable but show up still sometimes. And there's a
lot of them. You can kind of... The real way to get this list is just to look at a really
old book. But you keep on finding that like, oh, in South Africa they have additional sub-ordinary
that doesn't appear anywhere else. So a lot of this has been adding on to these lists
of keywords. But yeah. Some of these are really interesting. Like you might notice that there's
a... A escutcheon is a mini shield sub-ordinary. That one and a canton, they both often have
an entire code of arms on top of them. So these things are like fully recursive. Yeah.
So let's see. So now we can parse these ones. Azure, a bend, very, or in Google. So I'm not
going to read all of them. But you can see that it's got a bend on it and then the bend
has its own pattern. So there's kind of... Now there's ordinaries that have their own
tinctures. And you can start to have ordinaries that have ordinaries on them. So there's stars
on a stripe. And then this one over here, there's a saltire with diamonds on it with
a dot on that. So it's like three layers deep of dependent clauses. Yeah. So let's talk
about how we can do these groups of things on things. I make this ordinary charge, which
has got a number, then the tincture, and then the number of ordinaries. And then I make
this charge group rule, which has got that it could be two charge group and charge group,
or charge group on and then another subgroup, or on a charge group, a subgroup. Sometimes
Blazon has the Yoda thing where they say, like, on this, do with this. So it just comes up
with this. So just covering both those cases. So then our arms is now a field or a field
and some charges or just some charges. And then that makes us able to parse this thing,
which means we're scaling up in complexity pretty quickly. So this is the arms of the
Duke of Braganza. And as you can see, it's pretty complicated Blazon, but it's all ordinaries.
And we're able to say this charge group and then recursively another charge group of five
escutcheons. And then on top of each of that, there's five Bizons. So we're able to parse
this whole thing. All right. Next, the next thing I have to tackle is, of course, animals
and other objects like that. In the Middle Ages, they knew about a lot of more animals
that we don't know. Like, for instance, sea lions at the bottom. Yeah. So this one you
can really just spend a long time finding out new animals that they invent. There are
some that only ever appear on a single coat of arms. There's like six coats of arms that
have elephants on them. So I found that out and added it to my list. This is a very small
subset, but you can see this is basically a list of a ton of keywords. And then animals
have a special modifier that can happen to them where they have a position. So whether
a lion is roaring or crouching or looking at you and crouching, that's actually defined.
But also, that's defined here, but if the artist were to draw the lion and maybe the
tail is going in a different direction, that's not defined. So there's like a thing where
people would recognize that certain element here is part of the actual coat of arms and
part of it is just artistic license. But it gets down to this much detail. So there's
a lot of different positions of animals, and there's certain things that only certain animals
can do. So it gets pretty complex. For instance, only the peacock can be in his pride, which
is my favorite. It's the peacock with the full tails, because only the peacock has a
tail that can do that. So yeah. Anyway, these are mostly just a big list of keywords that
I then add, but then also sometimes they can be multiple different attitudes that they
can have. So then, yeah, so that's animals. And then the next challenge is quartering.
So as I said, these things are fully recursive. They actually did recursive coats of arms
very frequently. So whenever you would inherit from two different families that both had
arms, then you'd get to quarter. So the simplest one is the princely house of Hohenzollern,
which is quarterly saber and gul. So you can actually see each of those sabers and guls.
That's a complete coat of arms, and then they're quartered together. Another great one is Castille
et Lyon, which has a castle and a lion, because sometimes they were clever like that. And
what's interesting about this is that the actual emblazement of the arms of Castille
et Lyon is quarterly one and four Castille, two and three Lyon, which means that they
are like reference them by reference, that you'd have to know what Castille looked like.
And so I've included those beneath so you can understand it. But yeah, they have like
references to whole other coats of arms you'd have to go look up and then paint that one
on. So that was usually for state level stuff that you'd be like, I'd have old France on
a canton or something like that. So that's interesting that they can also reference other
coats of arms. And here's the coats of arms of the entire EU. So yeah, it can get very
complex. But because of the way we've kind of built this, it's not very hard to extend
our thing to be able to parse this. So I can say quarterly of a certain number, and then
have this quarter group kind of just repeat. So like, you know, quarterly, then one quarter,
two quarters, three quarters, separated by like and or something like that. And that's
included in the rules. So because it's recursion, it's easy to just use the same thing multiple
times. So that actually is all we need to parse the coat of arms of the UK. So just
going over this, it's a quartered one. So we're going to have three separate quarters.
The first one is for England. That's three lions, passant, garden, arranged along an
ordinary of a vertical. And then it has the colors that they are. And then the second
quarter is a lion rampant inside of an ordinary, which is the border. And then the third one
is a harp. That's ore stringed, it's got white strings. And yeah, that's actually a fully,
we're able to fully parse this whole thing, which I think seemed very daunting at first.
All right. So let's talk a little bit more about some of the obscure rules. One of the
most important ones is the rule of tincture, which is that only certain coats of arms are
valid. So if we look at this one, which is a sable with a bend ghoul, which is this red
stripe on the black, that is not valid. Any herald would spit at you if you tried to ask
for that. But this one with a yellow stripe, that's totally valid. So that's because it's
a metal on a tincture. They had some rules that were to enhance contrast. And you can
have black, you can have a color on a metal or a metal on a color, but you couldn't do
metal on metal or color on color. So yeah, with the exception of Jerusalem. Jerusalem
could do color on color or metal on metal because it's very resplendent. Anyway, so
the trouble with this is it becomes, certain countries care about it more than others,
and also it starts to get very complex with what happens when charges go from one to the
other. And you might not want to just refuse to parse one that's wrong. You might want
to parse it and then handle it in some other case. Be like, hey, technically this is wrong,
but still have understood it. So this is why I'm saying that when you get to these more
complicated rules, like the rule of tincture, it's too complicated for a parser. So that
would be the kind of thing that you would check in a validation step. So yeah, so here
would be like if you wanted to go from Blazins to full code of arm renders, this is what
you would do. And I've actually only done this part, the parsing for this talk, just
to keep it simple because I'm sure drawing the shield is its whole own bag of worms.
But yeah, so we've built this whole abstract syntax tree just from the Blazon, which is
getting to the point of why this is a PyCon. So now that you've seen all of this, you're
fully qualified to read the Python grammar. It's actually shorter than the grammar I wrote
for Blazon. So this is your homework, by the way. Enter it in your phone at some point,
like next week when you're back in your regular life, to just Google Python grammar and read
this. I mean, let's look at some of these things. This defines an if statement. If,
then there's a test, colon, then there's a suite that it's supposed to do, and then there's
an optional elif, and there could be multiple, and then there's an optional else. And there's
a wow statement, which is even simpler than the if. So hopefully now that you've seen
these parsing and you've seen the medieval context, you can see this is actually very
simple compared to the heraldic one. And I think that really everyone who's using Python
ought to read the grammar because there's, you know, kind of like, there's a difference
between knowing what things you can do and what things work, but then there's also a
difference between understanding why it works and kind of going to the source of figuring
out, like, you know, how is this language actually processed and taking away the magic
there? So I mean, this is, I'm just taking some samples of how the Boolean logic works
where the or can take an and, or, you see what I mean? They're kind of nesting and calling
each other. Here's like the, a statement is either a simple or a compound statement. For
a simple statement, it could be one of these import lines, global assert lines, or it could
be like a compound statement that's like a whole block. But yeah, I'm not going to explain
the whole Python grammar right now because it's your homework. Great. So here's me also
parsing a print statement and the same thing. Any questions?
Thanks.
We have about five minutes for questions, so please feel free to approach the mic and ask questions.
Also, does anyone in the audience have a coat of arms? I'm always curious. Shout out if you have one.
I'll be interested.
Cool. It's relevant to one person.
Hi. I was wondering if you said you built a database of all the coat of arms you could find.
Yeah.
I'm wondering if, like, did you have any idea of how many permutations there were with this language?
You mean how many total things are in my database?
I guess it's a two-part question. How many things are in your database and how many things are theoretically possible?
Oh, infinite. I mean, it's recursive, right? So you could always be like, take all the ones that are theoretically possible,
put that in the corner, and then multiply it by, you know, them again. So it's easily provable to be infinite.
And I have about 150,000 in my database, but I mostly have like two or three sources that was like most of Europe in the 1850s.
But there's a lot of more, like, coat of arms that I haven't even included because after 150,000, I felt like I had enough, you know?
Really quickly, was there a limit to the amount of recursion?
Like how deep it could go? There's no limit in the language.
The most number of quarterings I think they've ever seen is 719 quarterings.
So, yeah, there's a lot of inbreeding.
So sometimes you get the same one showing up a bunch of times. You're like, huh, there's a lot of that one lion coming back.
Hi. So I was wondering if the language also describes how to find out the rank from the crown.
Sorry, what was that?
The rank from the crown.
What? Sorry.
The rank of the bearer, king, prince, by count.
Oh, oh, the rank. Yeah, yeah, yeah. So the rank is determined by the crown.
Yeah, so that would tell you if you were an earl or a duke or whatever.
And I mean, everyone's trying to improve their status.
It's not on the actual shield itself because I guess hopefully it changes a lot.
Yeah, but yeah, it's on the full achievement that you'd be able to tell.
And I think that if you were a nobility in a country, you would know almost everyone else's coat of arms, you know, of the inner hierarchy by sight.
Yeah, and also I was wondering if the database is available somewhere for us to play around with if possible.
The database is what? Is it online?
Yeah, it's on my GitHub. So I'm MC Scope on GitHub and I published it.
I don't know if it was okay to publish it, but most of the stuff I got from like a book from the 18th century.
So I think that's probably public domain. Anyway.
Thank you.
Hey, awesome talk. So has any work been done on trying to automatically render these things from the past description?
Yeah, so I didn't cover that for this talk because I felt like I had enough just in parsing it.
But this website, drawshield.net, you're able to type in a blazin and they'll render it for you.
Oh, sweet. Didn't see that. Okay.
Yeah, so that's awesome. That's a great source to know Hey, Audrey.
Also, I really recommend reddit's our Hey, Audrey community.
And also I recommend really old books about it because there's a lot of resources on Gutenberg. Yeah.
Two questions. What percentage of your database did you end up being able to successfully parse?
Yeah, I maxed out around 70 percent.
And then it started being there's a lot of like, you know, things that only ever appear in this individual like long tail, you know, like, oh, they invented a new kind of bird.
I lived in this guy's hometown, you know, and that appears on there. It's like, you know, yeah.
So there's a lot of long tail things. But yeah, 70 percent of what I maxed out at, which I thought was good.
I mean, given that this thing I did this in, you know, like a week or two and they wrote it for 500 years, you know.
Yeah, that's that's great. Good job.
Also, where do you find these old books?
Yeah, so a lot of them are on like Project Gutenberg or stuff like that.
But I actually got linked to them. So from like, Josh, you or Wikipedia, I got linked to these books from there.
Really, Josh, you have an awesome resource.
They have a lot of they have not only can they render the code of arms, they have a lot of like information about her older too.
So, yeah.
Did you find that the order of things describing objects on the shield, if that makes sense, matches the order that I sometimes run into online where they talk about the adjective order that people expect in English?
Did you find that the language you were seeing resembled language that's used today?
Or can you talk about that a little?
It definitely doesn't parse like natural.
Like when you're seeing it, there's a lot of times where it's a little bit ambiguous where exactly something will be because they only really had commas.
They didn't use like parentheses to separate whole blocks.
So sometimes like the one thing that Reddit's heraldry community does, which is really interesting, is they do a telephone game where they'll have someone draw a shield and then someone take the shield and write the description.
And then someone takes the description and then draws the shield again.
And you kind of run into these issues where like it can be really ambiguous.
Is this charge supposed to appear like at the top of the area we're currently in or at the top of the whole thing or at the bottom?
And so some of that is like a little bit of ambiguity that's just kind of built into the language.
And then, yeah, the way things like adjective order, sometimes you see them where they're like kind of like on a blank a blank, which is not really how you would say it in English.
You'd say there's a blank on a blank.
You kind of would do infix, but instead they have like a prefix thing.
So and I think part of that is because it like partially comes from French.
I don't really understand why.
Yeah.
Thank you.
I have one question.
What prompted you to be interested in this?
Well, as I said, it's got a ton of rules and I think that's really interesting to my mind.
It's also something that I felt like there is a programming talk in there and I could talk about Middle Ages stuff.
So, you know, that was very appealing to me.
I had this idea for this talk last year at PyCon and then I just kind of had this inspiration that, hey, I could actually get on stage and give a talk.
So if you're here in the audience, consider submitting a talk.
You know, like if you're here, you're qualified to talk and you should you should try it.
Please help me thank Lady Red.