Thank you.
Thank you so much.
Hi, everyone.
My name is Shawna Gordon-McKeon.
I am a Python programmer.
I've got a background in a bunch of different things including social psychology, community
building and governance.
And I have to start this off by saying that I was not at all a part of Python's recent
governance changes, nor do I have any experience in the governance of Python itself, but I'm
really interested in the topic of governance in general.
And I asked around to see if anyone was going to be presenting on this at PyCon, and the
answer was no.
And I was like, well, someone should present on this at PyCon.
And here I am.
So why do I think this is such an important topic?
Well, I saw this tweet recently.
And I really love it.
Because I have spent many years as part of this Python community without really thinking
about how things run.
And I was just like, oh, Gito's the BDFL.
The PSF exists.
Things seem to be going fine.
And sometimes it takes a kid's relentless curiosity to go ahead and actually ask, wait, what is
a BDFL?
What does it mean?
How does the PSF run?
What other roles even exist?
And how do people get into those roles?
Another thing that can get us asking questions like that is a big conflict or shakeup.
And I think that's what happened to a lot of folks last year when Gito announced that
he was going to be stepping down as the BDFL.
So this talk is meant to try and answer some of these questions.
And it's going to be roughly chronological.
I'm going to start by talking about how Python used to run.
Then we'll go into what changed.
And then finally, we'll talk a little bit about how things work now.
So let's get to it.
So I made this chart.
I'm not a professional chart designer, so my apologies.
But I made this chart to help myself understand all of the different elements of the Python
community holistically.
So this represents how things used to be about a year ago.
So one of the first things that may leap out to you is that the Python Software Foundation
and the Python language are two distinct groups with two distinct governance processes.
And this is something I did not understand myself, despite having been involved in Python
and coming to Python for close to a decade.
I think part of why this has been a little confusing for people is that historically
Gito has been the leader of both groups.
So even though they're technically separate, they're sort of like united in their leadership.
So people assume that they're more legally entangled than they are.
So which group does what?
Well, the PSF manages the intellectual property of Python.
And they're also responsible for a lot of community building and community management.
For instance, they run PyCon, and they do a great job with it.
They also sponsor other conferences and meetups, run diversity initiatives and more.
Whereas the Python language is focused on developing CPython.
So I'm going to focus mostly on the Python language, but I did want to take a moment
to talk about how the PSF runs, because after all, it's an important part of our community,
too.
The PSF is a 501c3 nonprofit, and all nonprofits have a board of directors who govern the project.
Now most nonprofits have what's called self-perpetuating boards of directors, which mean the boards
appoint new directors themselves.
They do have a legal responsibility as a nonprofit, but to be frank, a lot of boards decline into
irrelevance and mismanagement because there's not a ton of accountability because they're
self-perpetuating.
I could do a whole talk on some of the problems with self-perpetuating boards, but I won't
because I am pleased to say that the PSF is a member-elected board, which means that PSF
members elect their own leadership.
And so because the PSF is member-elected, let's take a second to talk about how that
membership works.
So there's five kinds of members.
There's basic members, and anyone who wants to can become a basic member.
All you have to do is agree to follow the code of conduct.
However, basic members are the only kind of PSF members who can't vote.
There are four kinds of voting members contributing, supporting, managing, and there's also something
called a Python fellow.
And so you can become this kind of member through donating, through contributing in
a variety of different ways, or being selected or nominated and then elected by existing
fellow members to be a PSF fellow.
And so those latter four kinds of members are voting members.
And I think limiting voting to people who have contributed to the community in some
concrete way is a useful way to make sure that the people who are voting on leadership
have a real stake in the community.
And the PSF actually does some other interesting things regarding voting, like they require
people to declare their intention to vote at the beginning of the year.
And in order to keep your voting eligibility for the length of the year, you can't miss,
I think, more than four votes in a row.
And again, this rewards participation and encourages sustained engagement so that the
people who are making decisions at any given time are the ones who have been engaged with
the community in a sustained way, which I think is really great and interesting.
But enough about the PSF.
Let's go back to Python the language.
So it's with the Python language team that we get the idea of Guido as a benevolent dictator
for life, because as I just stressed, there is never a way in which he was a dictator
of the PSF because member-elected nonprofits simply can't have dictators benevolent or
otherwise.
So instead, he was the BDFL of the language side of things.
So what does it mean to be the BDFL?
In theory, it means that you're in charge of everything.
But Python's a big, big project with a lot going on.
And so really, there's a whole group of people who are involved in the day-to-day work of
And that is the Python core team and the sort of Python contributors who are a wider group
of people of whom the core team is a subset.
And so these are the people who are doing the work of creating Python, making decisions,
and it's when there's a conflict or a high-level design decision that Guido would step in and
have the sort of ultimate say.
And practically speaking, a lot of how this authority got exercised is through deciding
which PEPs got accepted or rejected.
So sidebar, what's a PEP?
So PEP stands for Python Enhancement Proposal, and it's how the community makes decisions
about language, designs, standards, and processes.
The most well-known of these is probably PEP 8.
Who here has heard of PEP 8?
Yeah, almost everyone.
So that's the one that lays out the style guide for Python, but there's actually several
hundred PEPs out there.
PEP 1 goes into great detail about what PEPs are and how they're decided on, but I'll give
you the TLDR here.
So first off, someone authors a PEP.
If that person who's authoring the PEP is on the core team, they can just directly submit
the PEP.
If you are not on the core team, you have to get a core team member to sponsor your
PEP.
And there's a period of debate where people talk about it, discuss it, give feedback,
and there's a specific person who is given sort of a managership of that PEP who can
kind of say, okay, I think we're ready to vote on it, or I think it needs more work.
And sometimes, historically, this was Guido.
Sometimes it was the BDFL delegate, so the idea being that Guido was delegating his authority
as the decision maker to someone who is better, more experienced in that area can make a better
decision.
Sometimes Guido asked them to take the role, sometimes they self-nominated, but it's my
understanding that there was little to no conflict ever around who took that BDFL delegate
role.
So in the end, Guido or the BDFL delegate would rule that the PEP was accepted or rejected,
or one of a couple of other less common end states that a PEP could end in.
So to come back to our chart of how things used to be, you can see that we've got this
group of contributors, the group of core developers who sort of manage the contribution process,
and then the BDFL who can sort of step in when there's conflict and say, this is how
we're doing things.
So it's a system that worked for us for many years, but it's not our system anymore.
So what happened?
So there was a PEP, 572.
There's a talk on that PEP that happened the other day by Dustin Ingram, if you're interested
in learning more about it.
For our purposes, it really doesn't matter what the content of the PEP was.
What matters is that it was a heated discussion, highly controversial, very stressful for the
people involved.
And at the end of it, as you heard Guido say this morning if you went to the steering council
keynote, left him with a feeling that he just didn't want to be BDFL anymore.
So he sent out an email saying essentially, I resign, you figure out what you want to
do next.
So Python was faced with this question, who's in charge now?
So they could have just selected another BDFL, but there's no one obvious person with the
sort of trust or legitimacy or history to just step into that role.
So really, before they could tackle the who's in charge question, they were faced with the
question, well, what is our governance model even going to be?
But they didn't really have any way to decide that either because Guido had always just
been the BDFL and he didn't want to unilaterally pick the new governance method.
He wanted the community to make a decision.
So really, before they could tackle what our governance model is going to be, they were
faced with the question, how do we decide what our governance model is going to be?
So three distinct layers of decision making happening here.
And it's important for all communities that are making these kinds of governance decisions
multiple levels which have to be tackled separately.
So I like to use the United States as an example because I am from the United States and therefore
I am intimately familiar with it.
So how did the United States government or the community people who became the United
States answer these questions?
Well, they started off with the question, how do we decide what our governance model
is going to be?
And they decided they were going to have a constitutional convention in Philadelphia
and they were going to come up with a model that was going to be ratified by the states.
Actually, that's a little bit of a lie.
A lot of people came to that convention thinking they were going to be fixing the Articles
of Confederation and when they got there, it was like, surprise, we want to do a whole
new constitution.
But that's the sort of venue in which they made that decision.
What is our governance model going to be?
That was the actual US Constitution.
And then the question of who's going to be in charge is the first president, the first
Congress, the first judiciary system.
And as you can see, these needed to happen in a specific order and time.
You can't get the George Washington as the president before you have a president and
you can't know that you're going to have a president until you decide how you're going
to decide whether or not you want a president.
So back to Python.
So let's start with that first fundamental question.
How do we decide what our governance model is going to be?
So there are several months of intense online and in-person conversations about this.
In September of 2018, there was an in-person meeting of the core team in Redmond and those
who couldn't make it in person joined remotely.
There was a lot of discussion on the threads and discuss.python.org.
But eventually they consensed around an answer which was laid out in PEP 8001.
And the short version is that people could submit proposals for new governance models
in the form of PEPs and that after a period in time, the community was going to vote on
which one to choose.
So who got to propose?
Well, it was through submitting at PEP.
So the answer is core developers or someone who could get a core developer sponsor.
But practically it was just core developers who submitted proposals.
Who got to vote?
So the PEP says active core developers could vote and it was a bit of an honor system there.
The PEP says we are asking core developers to self-select based on whether the governance
situation will affect them directly.
And I think it's a really good idea.
There's a lot of research that says that communities function best when the people most
impacted by a decision have the primary say in making that decision.
And if you want to learn more about that sort of research background, I gave a talk at Libre
Planet back in March which I've got a link to at the end of my slides which goes into
some of the research that leads us to believe that statements like the one I just baldly
made are true.
So the final thing that PEP 8001 lays out is how the vote works.
There was a whole discussion thread before this about what voting method would be best.
I won't go into it here.
But there's a long thread about it on discuss.python.org if you're a voting methods nerd.
The end result was I chose a condorsant method of voting which is a form of ranked voting
which is believed to be a better way of getting consensus than the sort of majority first
past the post system that we're used to.
That I am used to in the U.S.
And it was administered by the PSF in the person of Ernest W. Durbin III also our PyCon
chair who is the PSF's director of infrastructure.
And again I think this was a great idea, a good way to take advantage of the fact that
the PSF exists as a relatively neutral third party.
So we've got PEP 8001 is the equivalent of the Constitutional Convention and ratification
of the states.
So let's move on to what the actual governance model is.
So they started out this discussion by doing a survey which is in PEP 8002, the open source
governance survey.
They researched the governance of Rust, OpenStack, Jupiter, Django, TypeScript, AstroPy and Microsoft.
And this document is a great resource far beyond the Python community itself because
it gives a series of case studies about how other projects have made these kinds of decisions.
So I wanted to give a shout out to the five authors of this PEP.
Barry Warsaw, Lucas Langa, Antoine Petrou, Doug Hellman and Carol Willing.
Thank you for doing this work which I think will benefit all of us.
And I actually am using this to start off a new project, hopefully it will remain a
minor project, which is just collecting case studies of governance in open communities.
So if you're interested in that I will be linking to that at the end of the talk as well.
So here are some of the specific models that ended up getting introduced.
I will go through this pretty quickly because after all we only ended up using one of them.
But there's some interesting options in here.
So there's the technical leader model which is an elected BDFL, so really a BDFN, benevolent
dictator for now, or it was meant to be for every three releases, so BDF3R?
I don't know, I don't know.
It loses a little bit of its punch.
And they would be helped by a council of people who would all be core devs.
There's the trio of Pythonistas model.
And what I thought was interesting about this one is that everyone had to run as slates,
which would ensure, hopefully ensure that the people who were elected worked well together
because they were running together.
Yeah.
The community governance model, which is one of my favorites, expands on the idea of the
experts index.
So for those of you who don't know, there's an existing thing called the experts index
which is a way to keep track of which members of the contributor community have expertise
in given areas of Python, and you can use that to get feedback on potential peps that
impact those areas.
So the community governance model would have taken that and said the people who are listed
as experts are the ones who decide on the peps in those areas with the ability of the
core devs to get together and overrule a specific decision if they were like, no, that expert
made a bad decision.
There is the external council governance model.
The most interesting thing about this one is that people could not be core devs.
So the goal here is to put power in the hands of a neutral third party, which is an interesting
goal.
It's definitely the only one of these proposals that really is trying to take power away from
the core devs.
So interesting.
There is the common slash anarchist governance model.
So the title of this proposal is the commons governance model.
But the author says that they used commons instead of anarchist as a phrase because anarchist
has negative connotations.
But the pedantic person in me who studies commons governance is like, no, commons governance
and anarchist governance are separate things.
So I just did a little bit of editorializing and crossed out the commons and put the anarchist
back.
And my understanding of this proposal is it has a sort of council of elders who make a
lot of context based decisions about whether a PEP should be voted on or whether there's
already consensus.
I'll be honest, I don't really fully understand this one.
There's the steering committee model, which has a three member committee who make high
level design decisions but do not decide on PEPs.
They're not allowed to decide on PEPs.
Instead they can either select a PEP delegate or hold a vote of all of the core team.
And finally, there's the steering council model, which is a five member committee elected
for the length of a release.
They can make decisions about PEPs, but the proposal, the language they use says, please
don't try to delegate responsibility as much as possible.
Only step in when you really have to and try instead to make decisions that will enable
other people to do it instead of making one off decisions yourself.
So these were all discussed online before the vote happened.
And you can see the debate there.
It's really interesting.
Victor Stinner, I hope I'm pronouncing his name correctly, did a nice comparison of the
proposals.
I've got it linked at the end of my slides and talked about some of the different ways
in which these proposals differ.
So some of them distributed versus centralized power, the number of people in leadership
roles, the importance of being a core dev.
One of the proposals was like, no, you can't be a core dev.
Other proposals were like, you have to be a core dev.
How PEPs are handled, how leadership that people don't have confidence in any longer
is handled.
Other things that people considered were how much burden was a particular process going
to put on the core devs, many of whom are unpaid volunteers.
And another interesting thing was some people were arguing that formally implicit processes
should be made explicit while other people were saying, no, let's leave things informal
and only make them explicit once we have to.
So finally, they held the actual vote.
You can see it yourself at the civics website.
Again, linked at the end of my talk.
The winner was PEP 8016, aka the steering council model.
We'll go into that in just a minute.
But first, I want to update my little chart here.
So the steering council model is our sort of constitutional equivalent to the U.S. Constitution,
which leaves us with the final question of who is in charge now.
So the PEP proposal specifies how people become part of the steering council, which is through
elections.
So this January, elections were held again in the PSF, again administered by Ernest W.
Durbin III.
And the first steering council was elected, Barry Warsaw, Brett Cannon, Carol Woolling,
Guido Van Rossum, and Nick Coughlin.
And many of you probably saw them today earlier at the keynote.
And this election is documented in PEP 8100 because everything's a PEP.
All right.
So we've got our people down here, the equivalent of George Washington and the all-important
judicial and legislative branches as well.
Can't forget them.
Balances of power.
Theoretical balances of power.
So this is how we got where we are.
But okay, where are we now?
So you can see on this chart, we've replaced our BDFL with a steering council.
But it's not quite as simple as a one-for-one replacement because where Guido was in a fairly
clear position of authority over the core team, the steering council is in a more equal
role.
So let's get into a little bit of detail about how actually the core team and the steering
council relate to each other.
These are all taken from PEP 13, which is the PEP that describes the current constitution
slash governance.
So the core team is very similar to the existing core team previously.
Membership is granted by receiving a two-thirds positive vote from the existing core team
and no veto by the steering council.
So the steering council now has a veto over membership.
There's no time limit on being a core team member.
Once you join, you can stay.
But people who haven't made contributions in a while can be made inactive and temporarily
lose their voting privileges until they become active again.
The steering council is five people.
They make decisions via a majority vote of non-obstaining members.
They're nominated by the core team and they're elected by the core team.
No more than two people who are employed by the same company can serve on the council
at the same time, just to avoid the sense that the steering council is biased towards
any one particular company or employer.
The core team has authority over the Python project infrastructure.
Hold on a second.
They have authority over the Python project infrastructure, like the project website,
the GitHub repositories, bug tracker, mailing list, etc.
And they have the responsibility of electing the steering council.
The steering council has the mandate of assuring the reliability and stability of the Python
language, making contributing accessible and sustainable and diverse.
They help liaise with the PSF.
And they're tasked, especially now at this beginning part, with establishing decision-making
processes and resolving controversial decisions.
The steering council is explicitly given the right to accept or reject PEPs and enforce
the code of conduct.
But as I said before, the proposal specifically stresses that they should try to do as little
of that as possible.
So the proposal says instead of voting, it's better to seek consensus.
Instead of ruling on individual PEPs, it's better to define a standard process for PEP
decision-making.
It's better to establish a code of conduct committee than to rule on individual cases
and so on.
So both the core team and the steering council have recourse if members of the other group
are causing problems.
The core team can have a vote of no confidence.
In individual steering council members or in the council as a whole, that has to happen
via a two-thirds majority.
If the council as a whole is removed, there's an immediate election to create a new council.
And similarly, the steering council can vote to reject members of the core team, again
requiring a two-thirds majority.
But obviously the hope is that none of this will be necessary.
So as you can see, there's a sort of balance of power between these two groups.
That said, PEP 13 outlines how PEP 13 itself can be changed, which is by a two-thirds vote
of the core team.
So the fundamental authority here is still with the core team.
Because if enough of them believe that the governance process needs to be altered, then
they're the ones who can do it.
And if the steering council wants to alter things, they have to convince the core team
to do it.
So that is our current governance system.
So going forward, what's going to change?
Now, unless you're already a Python contributor or a member of the core team, probably not
that much is going to change from your perspective.
But that being said, the governance transition is still happening.
The steering council has been tasked with figuring out the details of the transition,
figuring out which of the previous processes that worked with the BDFL may no longer work
and may need to be changed.
So there may be some more visible changes coming on down the line.
And if you're interested in the work that the steering council is doing, you can take
a look at the keynote from this morning and also engage with them in various other ways.
If you want to get involved in this, the best way to start is to start by contributing to
Python.
As I've talked about, leadership is drawn from and accountable to the community of active
contributors.
So becoming a contributor is your first step towards participating in leadership.
And there's some great resources for getting more involved.
There's a very detailed contributing guide at devguide.python.org.
And I've linked to that again at the end of the talk.
Python also has a core mentors program.
So if you're serious about this, you can get matched up with an individual mentor who will
personally work with you to help you contribute.
And again, I've linked to that at the end of the slide.
You should just assume if I mentioned something, I've linked it at the end of the slides.
And if you're more interested in the community side of things, there's many great volunteer
opportunities with the PSF.
So I want to take a moment to talk about the lessons of the Python project for Python projects
as a whole.
Because I think this is really relevant lessons here.
So many projects have only informal governance systems.
And it's important to stress here that all projects have some kind of governance system.
Just because it's entirely at the whim of a single person doesn't mean that that's not
a governance process.
It's just a really informal and spontaneous and implicit governance process.
And many projects start with a single person.
And as the project goes, that founder sort of just by default retains their authority.
And when governance is formalized, it's often, though not always, codified into this BDFL
model.
So the path that Python and Guido took is really very common.
A number of projects have sort of a partial formalization of their governance.
They'll specify who's in charge, but not necessarily how we change our governance model.
So that foundational level of decision making.
So when they do have to change, either because someone retires or flakes out or moves on
or is abusive or just for whatever reason that their current governance system isn't
working, they're at a loss for how to change it.
And there's a bit of a tension here.
Because I know that for many people, if you're trying to build in explicit governance processes
it can be seen as adding unnecessary bureaucracy to the project.
But the alternative is often worse.
Because many projects discover the need for governance processes only once there's an
active conflict in the community.
And when that happens, the people involved are already deeply invested and have chosen
sides in that conflict.
And it's a much rougher place to be making governance decisions from.
Because you have to make all of these complicated choices from positions of mistrust.
And the different levels of decision making get entangled.
Because you want a specific person to be in charge because you know that they're on your
side on whatever the specific conflict is.
And it's hard to separate making the decision about making the decision from that person
you want to end up with.
So it's not a great place to end up.
So my recommendation for projects is to get that first level of decision making done.
How to decide how we're going to decide step.
And it doesn't have to change anything about the experience of participating or who the
leader of the project is.
Because you're not saying anything about who's going to govern or even how they're going
to govern.
Just how you're going to decide how they're going to govern.
So you can keep your BDFL, but just spell out if you were going to change away from
a BDFL model, how are you going to make that decision?
So for Python that would have been the equivalent of already having PEP 8001 before we had a
shutdown.
And your version of PEP 8001 might not look like PEP 8001 and probably won't, but it should
cover how the decision about what happens next will be made.
Is it going to be vote, consensus, what type of vote, majority versus supermajority, and
also who is going to get to make it.
Who can propose options and who can decide on the outcome.
And then finally another lesson to take from Python.
When you're changing the governance of an existing system, think about what resources
already exist.
The Python language team made extensive use of existing PEP processes of the core dev
team and of the PSF.
And I think the results would have seemed less legitimate if they hadn't done that.
So that's the end of my talk.
I think I have a few more minutes.
Do I have any time?
I have about a minute.
So I'll take questions outside in the hallway track.
But I just want to give a brief thank you to Carol Willing and Brett Cannon for answering
some of my questions before I give this talk.
I did not egregiously misrepresent anything.
There's a whole bunch of links here for some of the things that I've mentioned.
I have a talk on Libre Planet from Libre Planet back in March that talks about governance
from a more abstract perspective, talks about Python and a few other different projects.
And if you're interested in nerding out with me about governance, please come find me because
I'm a little bit obsessed.
All right.
Thank you so much, everyone.