Hello, good morning. A few housekeeping items first. If you have a cell phone or other device
that makes noise, if you would like to make sure that is in silent mode, that would be
fabulous. Please hold your questions during this talk until after the talk. Katie will
be taking questions at the Pi Ladies booth so you can find her there. So please welcome
Katie who will be giving the talk titled, A Right Stitch Up, Creating Embroidery Patterns
with Pillow. Thank you.
Good morning. A long time ago in a conference far, far away, I gave my first ever lightning
talk. It was in a series of lightning talks that were specifically about other skills.
It was any lightning talk you wanted but it couldn't be about computers. There were talks
about bread making, there was talks about acquire and I gave a talk about a cross stitch
that I made. The original artwork was created by a pixel artist from Melbourne, Paul Robinson.
He's known for his work on Scott Pilgrim vs. the World, the video game, Mercenary Kings
and the video clip for Architecture and Helsinki's Do the Whirlwind. Pixel art, especially those
with really distinct colour palettes, map really well into cross stitching. Every single
pixel on that image can be converted into a single stitch and you can import your designs
into one of the many closed source Windows only programmes and generate a chart for your
reference. Each cell has a colour and a symbol that you then transcribe by hand onto your
canvas. This particular one took three months to make. But several years after my original
lightning talk, this particular design was auctioned off as part of the Pyleadies charity
auction in Portland in 2017 and the money raised went directly to Pyleadies. Now as
part of the lightning talk that I gave those many years ago, I mentioned that the programme
that I used was a closed source Windows only programme and I said, if you know of anything
about image manipulation, colour setting, cross stitch charts, if there is any free
and open source software out there, please tell me, otherwise I will make my own and
present it here next year. Unfortunately that was in 2014. I am not very good at estimating.
But based on my own unscripted ramblings from now five years ago, I set myself three problems
to solve. One, image manipulation. Two, colour setting and three, cross stitch charts. First
step, image manipulation. If I am provided an image, I want to be able to go through
and iterate over every single pixel of the image and work out what colour it is. In Python,
we can do that with Pillow, the Python imaging library. It is a go-to language if you want
to do image manipulation. It is a go-to package for image manipulation in Python. You can
use it to load images, resize them, rotate them and save the result. You can also interrogate
images using image.getPixel and it does pretty much what it says on the tin. If I have a
3 by 3 pixel image zoomed in here, I can identify exactly what colour each of those pixels are.
The coordinate system in Pillow starts at the top left and works its way across and
then down. In my terminal, if I pip install Pillow, open up my Python terminal. From Pill,
import image, open up my image from my local file system and then run getPixel with the
coordinates 0, 2, I get out a triple, so a three element tuple of the RGB elements that
make up that colour, 2, 5, 5, 0, 0 being red. From here, I can iterate over every single
pixel in my image and get all the colours. So that is problem one solved. Problem two,
colour setting. Yes, with a U because I am Australian. But first, let's talk about floss.
Dolphos Mjøg Egkompanyet is an Alsatian textile company founded in 1746. Not to be confused
with a hip hop group of a similar name. When I talk about DMC, I mean this stuff. If you
go to a Michael's or a Joanne or Australia, a Spotlight or a Linkraft, you will see a
set up like this. This is known as DMC floss. DMC have several hundred colours of this floss
available all referenced by a code. This is a multi strand medium that you can use one,
two, three, however many strands you want in your cross stitching and then you build
up your pattern by making crosses. They however don't only sell floss. I work in tapestry
wool also by DMC. It is slightly thicker and I prefer to work with it because I already
have vision issues. But it makes for a more chunky aesthetic and it works really well
with pixel art. But the problem is that floss and wool are not cross compatible. They do
not share product codes and all of those closed source Windows only programs had floss as
the only palette you could use. So I was having to manually translate between the two mediums.
These colours are part of the Cranberry set. And while the names aren't strictly official,
the codes are important. There is a guide for cross compatibility that you can find.
But it is absolutely supposed to be a guide. This is useful when you need to convert between
floss and wool. But you can see that there is a little bit of a problem here. There are
missing colours. In this particular set, there are six colours for floss and only four for
wool and my local shop only had three that I could take a picture of. This is slightly
annoying, but it will get worse. We are also working with computers here. And computers
don't understand arbitrary colour codes. They understand RGB. So we need a way to be able
to convert between RGB between the DMC colour and RGB. Now, officially no mapping exists.
This is proprietary information. Colours can drift over time. In fact, if you are working
on a large project, it is recommended that you buy all your threads at once because there
can be slight variations between the different dye lots. And this is a company that was created
in the 1700s and it could be really easy to recreate or steal these kind of colours and
thus undermine the entire ecosystem that this company is trying to make money from. However,
there are ways around this. You can find unofficial mapping spreadsheets around the place. I have
used this before to various effect. But you could create your own. You could go through
every available colour thread, buy them all, take a picture in a white box room with the
exact same lighting in the exact same environment and from there determine what the best colour
is in RGB to represent it. If you have a consistent photo shoot, this is fine, but there is differences
between dye lots, variations in the warmth of the lighting that you use and a whole bunch
of other issues if you were to go about and actually take all these pictures. Thankfully
DMC has done this for you. On their website, they have all the colours available for all
their threads. The names aren't referenced anymore, but those unique identifying codes
are. The other thing, though, this is the list of all the pinks available in tapestry
wool now. There are no longer any cranberry colours. In fact, according to the website,
as of this year, they only sell 100 different colours of tapestry wool and yet nearly 500
colours of floss. Both these numbers are problematic. Back to this page, we can see that they have
featured both the swatches and the full skein or spool or widget of thread and we can use
these images to work out what the average colour of these yarns are. How? Using Pillow.
We can use image stat dot stat and get the median, the average colour for each of these
pictures. How do we do that? In our terminal that we have previously pip installed Pillow,
we can import both image and image stat, load our colour swatch that we have downloaded
from the website from our local file system and run image stat dot stat and then get the
median which comes out as a list of three colours, R, G and B. Even though this projector
has a lot of issues because projectors also have issues, this is a pretty good match on
average of what that colour should be in real life. Because visualisations are fun, I have
gone ahead and done a 3D plot scatter map of all the colours that are available for
the floss palette. The three axes here are R, G and B. And comparing this image to the
image that is coming up on the next slide for wool, you can see that there is a little
bit of an issue with the complexity of the palettes here. I mean, they have both got
red and black and blue and white and green, but there is a whole lot of nuance that is
being lost here. So we only have 100 colours of wool to work with. So we need to ensure
that when we get our images out, that we are only using those 100 distinct colours because
they are the only colours that are physically available to us. And if you want to go dye
your own colours, then that is good for you. But for me, I prefer to keep things a little
bit simpler. Thankfully, we can reduce the exact colours that are in our image using
Pillow. Again, using image.putpalettedata. What we can do is we can provide the exact
palette that Pillow uses to identify each of the exact colours in an image. Again, in
our terminal, we want to import image. And then we need to provide a 768 length list
we want as a flattened list of 256 RGB value triples. So in this particular case, our palette
would start with 000 black, 255 white and continue on. We then need to create a new
image to serve as our platform to store our palette data. The size of the image doesn't
count but the type does. The mode in this is P. P mode in Pillow is the palette mode
where instead of having specific RGB values, the palette data is a list of indexes that
point to your own custom palette. From here, we use our list and we set that as the data.
When we then load our image from source and tell it to convert to use our custom palette,
all of the colours in that image are converted to only use the set we specify. There is a
complex algorithm to work out how best to combine these colours into the one set and
work out the smallest distance and the math is interesting. But the fact that we can do
this in Pillow out of the box is really great. Then we need to convert our image back into
RGB and save it as an actual Python image, as a Pill image. You may see that I'm using
some Dunder methods in here from private use case. This is because the public API in Pillow
doesn't actually allow me to do this. I need to dive down into the C level constructs in order
to make this happen. But this particular algorithm does mean that I can specify any colour palette
I want and convert my image to only use colours from that palette. Now, that 256 number is a
little bit special. You have a range of 256 integers that you can use to specify your RGB.
Pillow also defines the length of the palette as being at maximum and at exactly 256 colours.
We have 100 colours in our wool palette. So that's fine, right? We only define 100 colours in our
palette. Well, no. See, this is the part of the talk where I was going to mention the fact that
I was getting this really weird bug in Pillow. What would happen is I define my 100 colours in
the palette, load up my application, run it, and I would end up getting all these colours that were
coming back that were greyscale. All these really light colours that were not available as DMC
threads that I couldn't stitch were coming up and they were always the same integers in the RGB.
It turns out that by default a palette mode image in Pillow has a greyscale palette. And because I
wasn't overloading this entire palette, some of these initialised values were coming through in
my final product. So the solution here is to define your palette as exactly a length of 256
triples. And what I did was take my last triple and just copy it all the way until the entire array
was reinitialised. And that works. But on the other end of the scale, we have a problem where
there are too many colours in our floss palette. We have nearly 500 colours to work with, but only
256 spaces in which to store that in our palette. So we need to somehow truncate it. So how do we
choose which colours we remove? Now, for any cross-stitches or fibre-arts people in the room,
this is the part where it may be a little bit controversial, but I'm working with computers here
and I have to make a compromise. All floss colours are different. They are so unique and so close in
some of the browns and the creams that you can make entire tapestries where you cannot tell where
the colour is changing and it makes for some beautiful artwork. Unfortunately, I'm constricted
by computers and I acknowledge this and I am sorry. To reduce the amount of colours in our palette,
we need to prune the colours that are closest together. And to do that, there is an algorithm.
There is math. This is an algorithm put out by the International Commission for Illumination
which is to do with their experiences based on automotive paint on smooth surfaces. This algorithm
is designed to kind of replicate human perception. You put in two colours and it will show the
distance between those colours. The bigger the number, the further they are apart. The smaller
the number, the closer they are. And thankfully, because we live in a Python ecosystem, I don't
try to have to implement this by hand. I can just import it from scikit image. They have made
available the algorithm where if I provide two colours, it will give me the distance. And again,
in my terminal, I can import both NumPy and scikit image, load up my Python interpreter,
import this particular formula, give it the two colours and it will give me the distance.
For my entire floss palette, I can then go through and compare every single colour with each other,
store that result, sort it by smallest distance and come up with a list that shows just how
close the colours are. This project are notwithstanding, these colours in real life
are so ridiculously close together that if I had to choose, I can take my list and just go full
Thanos on it. Again, not the best solution in the world but I have my reasons. If we were to use the
same visualisation as before, this is our original floss palette and then if I reduce it to only 256,
we still get the complexity of colours. But we can work with that 256 more easily because reasons.
Next problem, cross-titch charts. Third problem, this one should be easy, right? We can just use
Pillow. Well, that's been the solution of every problem so far and I did try using Pillow. I've
used image draw to try to replicate this system where I was building up a chart and I was making
tables and concatenating squares together but the results weren't what I wanted. I had weird
default system fonts. I couldn't get Unicode characters to work. I was sitting there thinking
there's got to be a better way, a way of being able to typeset any character with whatever styles
and tables and oh yeah, that's just HTML. Using HTML and whatever CSS styling I want, I can build
up a page of divs and spans, the odd table here and there for my legend and I can make my chart.
Finally, I have these three problems solved. For image manipulation, we're using image.getpixel.
For colour setting, we're using image stat, put palette and then the scikit image formula that
we described earlier. Then for the cross-titch charts, we're using HTML. The result of solving
these problems is a Python pip installable package called IH. Why is it called IH? It's a
cross-stitching app. There's a Disney movie called Lilo and Stitch. There's a character in Lilo and
Stitch called Stitch. There's a scene in which Stitch is able to convey to another main character
a complex persuasive argument by saying IH. Plus it's a super short name that was available on
PyPI so why not? The work in progress for all this stuff that I've done is also under a repo
called experiment 626 for similar reasons. Now I can generate a chart that looks exceedingly
familiar to those closed source Windows only applications that I used five years ago. It
also has some really nice features that I like including the exact amount of stitches that I need
that I can then use my own estimations to work out how many physical skins of wool I need.
I always have blank white as the tiniest little dot that I can to make it look as normal as I can
if I was to see this as a rendered image. Here's something I prepared earlier. This particular
logo you may recognise. It's on every sign including that one. The Twitter logo is a similar
format. Now this image itself doesn't work well for this particular medium mostly. It's too big.
Also there's a gradient going on in the skyline and for my particular medium I prefer pixel art
where gradients are annoying. So I've recreated the PyCon logo in pixel art. Now I'm no Paul
Robinson but that kind of looks like the logo I guess. So in my terminal I can pip install
I and I can run it on my tiny PyCon dot image and I get a HTML out which is a cross stitch pattern
that I can use to then sit on a nice sunny Saturday afternoon in Australia on my couch
with some YouTube channel happening on the TV and then slowly but surely build up my image on my
little tiny chart and tweet about this on Instagram and then have my final image be this.
You know what that's too small.
And what is now tradition this will be auctioned off tomorrow night at the PyLadies charity
auction. If you already have a ticket I hope to see you there with your wallets out.
It makes me really happy that as a community we can really embrace the stuff that's not tech.
We have a arts festival on tonight. We have other skills lightning talks at conferences. We have
people who have brought their knitting. We have people that are crocheting in the front row which
is amazing. And I think there's like acro yoga somewhere later and I'm all about that. So
this is now up on the warehouse but if CLIs aren't your style I've also wrapped this up
in a docker container which I've hosted for you on Google Cloud Run. If you go to ich as a service
aah.glazent.com you can use this give it a URL to a particular image and that will generate a
chart for you. One thing it also does is it shows the rendered estimations of what's going on. So
this kind of looks like a parrot. The hacky way that I got this to happen is to have each of those
little squares as a semi-transparent image that allows the CSS colour to shine through.
And if I just copy that across and have all the colours come in it looks like a rough estimation
of what the result will be. If hosted stateless containers as a service is something that
interests you come talk to me at the Google booth afterwards. We have a service for that.
Practical applications. So you can actually use this for techy reasons if you wanted to say
if you wanted to create a scanable QR code for your home Wi-Fi you could pip install QR code,
give it a string, save that as an image and then import that image into ich and render it. Now
you do need to set the scale on this because the QR code is big. So if you want one pixel per square
you need to set the scale to ten times reduction. And we're also setting the flag R here to render
it. And we get a scanable QR code. And if you stitch this and put it on your wall in a frame
it works. And you can scan this rendering now and it should work. Did it work?
What does it say? Yes! It says in French this is not a password.
I'm not going to put my home Wi-Fi password on a screen are you silly?
So I clipped together these particular bits of Python about 18 months ago now and tweeted about
it saying that I had this thing that would make cross-chatch charts of your QR code and that was
a little tiny bit popular and it got a little bit of attention. And because peer pressure is a thing
I made it into a CLI. And then because peer pressure is also a thing I've also hosted that
up on Google Cloud Run as QR.Glazon.com. You give it a string it will give you a cross-stitch chart.
So I've extended the functionality of this project over the years based on what I wanted five years
ago into a system that is now hosted that anyone can use. It supports various palettes including
floss and wool and alpaca because I gave this as a lightning talk at LCA 2018 and one of the questions
was do you support other palettes? What about alpaca? I said yes but you would need an alpaca
farm and be able to get all the different colors. They had an alpaca farm.
It also supports Lego. It also supports perler beads because those are palettes that are also
available that I've been able to import into the system. I've also got some twitter bots that are
using this similar system. Come talk to me at the Pie Ladies booth afterwards if really silly twitter
bots that do cross-stitch charts of tiny care bot is something that would interest you. And that's
all I had for those of you with a ticket to the auction tomorrow night. I hope to see you there
and thank you for your time.
And if once I get off stage I will be taking my lovely tapestry to the Pie Ladies booth.
Please follow me there. Thank you.