All right, should we do this?
Good morning.
How's everybody doing?
Awesome.
A few quick housekeeping tasks.
If you have a device that makes noise,
please make it so it doesn't make noise.
Please hold your questions till the end of the talk.
If there's time, we will take questions then.
And if not, catch these guys afterwards.
So please welcome Moses Schwartz and Andy Cullen.
They'll be giving the talk, A Snake in the Bits,
Security Automation with Python.
Thanks, everyone.
Thank you for being here.
Thanks to all the volunteers and organizers.
Super excited to be here.
So I'm Moses.
This is my coworker, Andy.
We've also got Jonathan from our team watching us here.
We work at Box on the security automation team,
which means we basically write software and manage
infrastructure that supports our incident response team,
our application security team, and even going and building
stuff for compliance and other groups that are all
under that security umbrella.
So we're going to talk about kind of a DIY approach
to building automations to support these teams in Python.
This isn't a talk about what Box does,
rather it's a general introduction.
But there are a lot of parallels with how we've actually built
out our infrastructure.
So one of the first things that's really important
to understand is sort of what the infrastructure looks
like for an incident response or like a security monitoring
team like your SOC.
So essentially, you've got all of these things
that are creating logs, whether they're individuals' laptops
or your servers or network hardware, things like that.
And so you need to feed all of those logs into some sort
of centralized aggregation system.
From there, most of those systems
will allow you to build some kind of alert.
When an alert triggers, you'll create a ticket.
And then you've got some analysts
that has to take a look at that ticket.
And so a big part of an analyst's job
before you automate things is opening up browser tabs,
copying data from the ticket, pasting it
into these web-based tools, getting information back,
putting in the ticket.
Lots of just kind of repetitive back and forth there.
As engineers, we see this and we're like, oh, we
can do something about that.
However, we have to start at the beginning.
Splunk is a really popular example
of a log aggregation system that'll let you create alerts.
So just super briefly, you start out with a search.
And the search criteria will then go through the logs
and return you any relevant log information.
And from there, we can develop an alert.
So Splunk lets you take your search, put it into an alert.
You set up a timing.
In this case, it's a cron-style time.
It's going to run every 15 minutes.
And then we set a 15-minute look back.
So it only looks at the last 15 minutes of logs
to determine if it should trigger an alert.
And that's really important, because otherwise, you're
going to get duplicate alerts.
So then after you have the alert,
you need to actually do something with the data
that it surfaces, right?
So a really popular way to handle the next step
is to send a post request out to some API that then does
ticketing or enrichment or whatever you need it to do.
So in this case, it's going to this sketchy Digital Ocean IP
address that we use for our demo purposes.
And so it just sends a webhook to the post request.
It sends a webhook to this API that we've set up.
So we're going to jump right into writing the code
to actually receive that webhook.
So we're going to start just by writing a bit of code.
We're going to use Flask, super popular micro framework
for building web apps, super commonly used for APIs
and similar use cases.
We're going to import Flask, instantiate it.
And the first thing we're going to do
is set up a status or health check endpoint.
That's super useful, because first off,
we can stop right there, run that,
and that's like our hello world to make sure we actually
did this thing right.
Later on, that's going to be super helpful
because we can check that endpoint after we say,
push an update to make sure things are back up and running.
And that makes it super easy to integrate into status
monitoring systems where they'll basically
do a heartbeat kind of thing, send a request to this endpoint
periodically, and let you know if your service goes down.
Then we're going to jump into the code to write this Splunk
webhook receiver.
So in there, we're going to just go into the Flask request
object and grab the JSON payload.
And right now, we're just going to write that out
into a JSON file.
That bit of code is not going to persist
to the end of the example.
But I want to kind of give insight
into how we go about developing these things.
So I'm going to jump right up onto that server.
It is sshn run python automation server.py.
This is going to spin it up in Flask's development server.
And it's just going to sit there listening,
waiting until we receive that Splunk webhook.
Now, if you're doing this in practice,
you're probably going to want to make Splunk fire
that alert every minute or so.
You really don't want to wait 15 minutes to test your code.
But when we finally do get it, it's
going to print out basically a log entry to the screen.
We will have received this webhook.
And then I'm just going to Control-C out and print
the first few lines from that JSON file
so we can see what Splunk is sending us.
And in there, we've got a search name, some metadata, the owner.
And then we've got the raw results.
So I'm going to take a brief detour.
Before we go back to automation server.py
and add more functionality, we're
going to start needing to use usernames and passwords
and other configuration things.
So a quick and dirty way to keep that stuff out of our code base
without going all into secrets management
is just to have something like a settings.py file
that you don't check in with your repo.
So in the next few slides, you'll
see settings.username and things like that.
That's what it's referring to.
So back to that automation server code.
Here, we are going to go write a new function
to create a JIRA issue.
That's going to be our ticketing system.
We're just going to use Atlassian's SDK.
Connect to JIRA.
You just need a URL, username, password.
And then it's literally one line,
although broken up to be readable, to create an issue.
Just specify project.
Name what we want the summary or ticket name to be.
And then we're going to dump the entire JSON result
into the description field.
So we can now go back into our Digital Ocean Droplet,
start up this new code, and just let
it sit until we get the next Splunk webhook.
When that fires, we're right away going
to go reach out to JIRA and create a ticket.
This almost starts to be kind of cool.
We at least have a ticket.
We've got some information there.
But it's an ugly raw JSON blob.
This is actually kind of the default state
for a lot of SOCs and incident response teams
before they start doing automation.
They create a ticket based on an email or a webhook
or something.
And it really just has that raw information.
But we can do something to make that a little bit more useful.
So I'm actually going to go into the JIRA configuration
and set up a webhook that's going to fire
when those tickets are created.
So we're going to come up with a name.
We're going to call this a mock scan alert,
because the faked up beta we're using was called mock scan.
And we're going to give it a URL.
Again, we've got our IP address and super verbose name,
JIRA mock scan created webhook.
And then down at the bottom, we're
going to specify a JQL or JIRA query language, I think,
query to let it know what kinds of tickets
we want this webhook to fire on.
So you can actually filter based on anything
that you can search for in JIRA.
If you scroll down further on the page,
you can also choose to fire webhooks on ticket creation
or closing or other cases.
But right now, we're going to focus on just creation.
So once that's set up, the next time Spunk fires a webhook
and we create a ticket, JIRA is going
to reach back out to our automation server
and try to call that endpoint.
So we've got to write code for that now.
Going to add a, first off, a new function,
this JIRA comment function.
It's really similar to the ticket creation one.
I'm just going to connect to JIRA,
grab the issue based on the key, and then we're
going to add a comment.
And that's basically just to take string and post it
in there.
Then we're going to write the endpoint to actually handle
that webhook, calling this mock scan created.
We specify the route up above.
Say we're expecting a post call.
And then again, we're going to pull the JSON out
of that request object and then do a bit of ugly JSON parsing.
We could have simplified this maybe,
but ended up deciding not to because dealing
with ugly JSON blobs is like half of the job
that we do day to day.
So we're going to pull out the results that
was in that description field.
And that was actually JSON that we wrote in there.
So it's double encoded.
We've got to load that JSON again.
But finally, we can pull out a few fields.
We're just going to grab a user, an MD5.
And then we can go call our JIRA comment function
and comment on that ticket with that information extracted
from the JSON.
That's not a whole lot more useful
than just having it in that JSON.
But if we were to go and do a lookup,
say take that username and look them up in Active Directory,
then that starts to be useful.
So to do that, we're going to write another script.
And this is not tied to Flask or the rest of the application
at all.
This is just plain Python using the LDAP3 module.
We're going to write a little function to search Active
Directory, given a username, and just return a dictionary that
has the results.
So this is what this looks like when you look at my username.
And then we can go back to our automation server
and set up a new function that's going
to go call our new script, that function in it,
do a bit of string formatting, pull out the fields
that we think are most interesting,
format a comment string.
And then we're just going to call that JIRA comment function
again.
And that'll post that information.
Then in our mock scan created endpoint,
we just have to add a call to that function.
Now when the webhook from JIRA fires,
it'll be handled in here.
We'll do that lookup, and we'll post the user's information
straight to the ticket.
We can do the exact same thing with the MD5 hash that we had.
We can go look it up in VirusTotal.
It's a really popular service that basically runs
a whole bunch of virus scanners against files
and puts everything into a database.
And you can query it and say, given either this file
that you uploaded or this hash, what do the virus scanners say?
This is the hash for an empty file.
So it's actually got zero positives out of 60 scanners.
And we've also got a permalink to take you to their web page
where you can view more details.
Those are the most useful fields.
So the code to actually call VirusTotal here
was pretty much copied and pasted
out of their public documentation.
It's really quick, just a little get request,
and then we're going to return that JSON.
Now, to integrate this into our automation server code,
we're just going to go back in there,
do the exact same thing we just did for Active Directory.
We'll write a new function to do the comment formatting.
We'll call VirusTotal, pull out the useful fields
and put them into a string, and call that gira-comment function
again.
Then we'll put that VirusTotal fileskin enrichment function
call right after the Active Directory lookup.
And that's pretty much all it takes.
The next time we have a ticket created,
it will get all of that information
extracted and posted.
So if you look again at this graphic
that we showed at the beginning, our SOC analyst,
Freddie Mercury there, looks at a ticket,
copies and pastes usernames and hashes into other systems,
and then makes his decision as to whether this is malicious
or what he has to do.
Now, things are looking up a little bit more for him.
We have all this information automatically
posted to the ticket.
And to recap, the way it works, because it's
kind of a weird cycle of webhooks,
Splunkfire is a webhook to our automation server.
We create a ticket.
When the ticket's created, gira calls a webhook back
to our automation server, and then we
start doing these enrichments and add information right there.
And this is actually a really simple but also really cool
model, because now we can run any arbitrary code we want
when a ticket is created.
So anything that you can write a program to do,
we can kick off automatically when a ticket comes in.
There's some low-hanging fruit that is really easy stuff
to do in an IT or security ops group.
A lot of the time, the first thing
you do when you open or close a ticket
is spend a minute going and setting appropriate fields
for the ticket type so that your metrics look good.
That stuff is super easy to automate.
We could also go a little more in-depth.
We could run another Splunk search and post the results.
You could even do something like kicking off an Ansible playbook
if you wanted to do something a lot more complex
and build up workflows.
And really, anything that has an API
or any kind of programmatic interface we could do.
I've been looking for use cases to actually get
a Roomba to do something when we have a certain ticket type.
That's the dream.
So now that we've started building this automation
server and all of its endpoints, we
need to start thinking about how is it going to scale?
What's the future of it?
When you have two endpoints, fine.
But when you're starting to write 10, 20, 100, 200,
you start to see a lot of the same patterns being repeated
in all of your Flask endpoint code.
So as developers, we want to make our jobs easier, too.
We want some sort of framework or middleware
that does this for us.
We're probably going to want authentication on everything.
We obviously want uniform logging
so that we know if our automations aren't working
properly.
Input validation is like the biggest boilerplate ever
when it comes to building APIs, because you
want to make sure that if somebody gives you bad data,
you tell them about it instead of just breaking.
In terms of breaking, you also don't
want to send a stack trace back to your API client.
You might expose sensitive information.
It's just generally not very useful to the average API user.
Things like that.
So how can we improve this?
Well, probably the easiest way is just
go get an open source plugin for Flask.
In this instance, we used Flask REST+,
which is pretty well known.
And it's also built to function very similarly to Flask.
So as you can see, we're still building a Flask app.
Then we just pass that into the REST+, API objects.
And you still set up your routes just like you did with Flask,
except now you're operating on classes.
And those classes define functions
that directly correlate to the HTTP method
that you're making available, so a get or a post.
But as you can see, we still have essentially
the same meat and potatoes code within the endpoint itself.
So this gives you, we'll get into it,
but it gives you nice error messages.
But one of the things that's really cool that it does
is it automatically generates Swagger documentation
or a Swagger specification for your endpoint.
For those that aren't familiar, Swagger or OpenAPI
is a JSON or a YAML definition of an API.
And a lot of people will write that spec
and then use generators to generate their code.
This goes the other way, and you write code,
and it generates the spec for you, which is really awesome.
Because there are JavaScript libraries called,
or a library that I know of called Swagger UI, which
will ingest that specification and build you a cool website.
And this is great, because now you
don't have to build some other documentation.
You have documentation that is built for you
based on your code.
And if you're being a good developer
and writing doc strings for all of your functions,
those get pulled into the specification too.
So your code documentation is literally
documenting your endpoint for you, which is awesome.
It also allows you to interact with your API
through the browser.
You can actually drop down those endpoints
and send test data to your endpoint,
and it'll actually send it, show you their curl requests
to do the same thing on your command line, which
is pretty awesome.
So one of the things we mentioned that we wanted to use
to elevate our RESTful API is we want to do input validation.
And that's something that's built right into Flask REST+.
So you can see here we've added a section of code
to our endpoint that is defining the API model.
And so in this case, we're saying
that we have a search name, and it needs to be a string,
and we have a result that is just
going to be a raw JSON blob.
So what this will do then is if we get data
and those fields don't exist, it'll
return a useful error message to the user,
and we don't have to worry about it in our code at all.
Our code knows that once we get to the actual post function,
we're going to have those fields in our result.
So we mentioned the swagger docs.
Another cool thing about defining those models
is it informs our documentation as well.
Because we've told the code what we expect as input,
now we get documentation that says, hey,
this is what you need to send to the endpoint
if you want to get good results.
So it's just this great back and forth
of informing the documentation from the code
so we don't have to go write the documentation
and make sure it's all still up to date when we make changes
and all of that fun developer stuff.
So we keep talking about these error messages.
So this is just a brief example.
Our first curl request there is when we were just using Flask.
And so you get back that awful 500 error
when you request something that's not there,
or there's an internal server error, your code breaks.
And for an end user, that's not helpful.
If you're calling your API programmatically,
that's not helpful.
It might be helpful if you were in a browser, maybe,
but still not helpful at all.
So the same thing with Flask or S+,
you get a nice JSON message with internal server error.
Still not necessarily helpful to the end user,
but it's something that they could parse very easily.
And then as we mentioned with the input output validation
stuff, you can see at the bottom there,
they called the webhook and their input was incorrect.
And they got a verbose error message telling them
that you can't send us a none type for this.
So that's the off the shelf solution.
But as developers, a lot of times, we're like, oh,
let's build a framework, right?
And sort of in our defense, we started
building this around the same time that Flask or S+,
initially came out.
So we weren't necessarily reinventing the wheel,
but maybe a little bit.
So we built a framework that we called Funnel.
And we built a little bit of a little bit of a little bit
called Funnel, because it's putting things into Flask.
And developers are super clever.
And we are working on getting it open sourced.
It's just there's a lot of hoops to jump through for that.
But it does a lot of the same things
that Flask or S+, just in a slightly different way.
You still define the allowed HTTP methods.
It's all based on an endpoint class.
You then have attribute classes for inputs and outputs.
You define them the same way.
There's built-ins for strings and integers and all of that,
as well as base classes for doing
like regex-based types, enum-based types, dates,
all those sorts of things.
We also do output validation, which
can be nice because it'll strip off additional fields so that
you're not returning a bunch of data
that you might not want to.
Of course, standardizes the logging.
But one of the big things we wanted
was a code-defined API, as I kind of alluded to before.
We're developers.
We don't want to write a JSON spec all day.
We'd rather write a class and have it generate that for us.
And so much like REST+, Funnel will generate you the open API
spec.
And then you can ingest it with Swagger UI or some
of the other open source tools that process those specs.
Also does all the exception masking, as well, which is nice.
And so really the main difference for us
is we don't use decorators.
If you see at the bottom there with the register function,
that's how we map routes to classes.
And then the before and after, I guess
most people can probably see it.
It's kind of near the bottom and dark.
But it allows you to specify a list of plugins.
So for instance, in this example,
there is an auth function listed there
to do authentication in the before plugins.
The after plugins are cool, too.
If you're dealing with potentially sensitive data,
you might want to scrub out credit card numbers
or social security numbers or anything like that.
And those plugins get the full request object
so they can make determinations based
on anything in the request.
And then if they throw exceptions or anything like that,
it just kills it and doesn't give data back.
So when you actually go to build one of these things
and get it deployed to really support a team,
first thing you're going to have to do or deal with
is Murphy's law.
Everything is going to break.
You're going to have ephemeral errors, all kinds of things.
And so we wanted to just talk a little bit about some
of our tips for keeping things manageable.
First off, I always like to remind everyone
that maintaining state is hard.
Some people see a problem and they think, I need a database.
I'd argue that now they got two problems.
I mean, a database are definitely
the right approach for a lot of things
where you need to maintain data.
But if you don't, if you could do something
completely stateless, why would you also
want to manage database migrations on top of code
updates?
And if you thought, I don't need a database,
but I can just go write some stuff to a local file
or something, well, that's how you get race conditions.
So anything that can be totally stateless
is just so much easier than if you need
to maintain anything externally.
Errors pop up for pretty much no reason at all,
like network hiccups that are just completely unexplainable
happen an alarming amount of time.
It's really amazing the baseline level of errors
of stuff on the internet.
Just adding a little wait and retry decorator
to your functions eliminates so many errors.
I always highly recommend everyone do that.
And then speaking of that, in our code,
we called our Active Directory lookup followed
by our VirusTotal lookup.
If we couldn't reach that Active Directory server for any reason
the whole thing would just throw an exception and die,
and we would never call out to VirusTotal.
So really, if you're doing all of these various enrichments,
you want them to be asynchronous and run
separately from each other.
So you could set up separate Jira webhooks for each one.
That kind of makes sense, but might end up
being a lot of stuff to manage.
Or we could go into Python and use Celery and RabbitMQ.
Or AsyncIO, I think, might be really neat
if you're willing to commit all in and do AsyncIO everywhere.
There are also a lot of DevOps tools that are basically
built for exactly this, like StackStorm, Jenkins, Rundeck.
And that's one of the big points we want to make.
Like, you can repurpose a lot of these DevOps tools,
even though they aren't marketed for security,
and they work really, really well.
If you're a cloud native, you could do something
like AWS Lambda.
Or if you've got piles of money, you
can also buy some of these commercial security automation
platforms called SOAR.
And they have similar functionality.
They actually have similar functionality all around.
But you can also write your own code to interoperate with them.
But at the end of the day, getting something up and running
and then iterating is always, always the best way to go.
Done is better than perfect.
So we'd like you to have a few takeaways from this talk.
Basically, first off, security automation is not magic.
It really is a series of webhooks and Python glue.
And that's true for the code we just showed you.
It's true for all of the commercial platforms.
It's really just how you tie these systems together
a lot of the time.
So I'm going to go ahead and show you
these systems together a lot of the time.
But if you've actually implemented something
like this, if you're automating tasks for a team,
start counting the number of times those endpoints are
called.
And assign a number of minutes to each one,
minutes saved that it would have taken to do the lookup manually.
And add those all up to see what kind of real impact
you're having.
This little graphic is similar to something
that our team actually sends out every week to management
and other teams saying, here's how many calls we got.
Here's how many hours we estimate we saved.
We make it green because management likes colors.
And if they care to take that and multiply
by an average hourly rate, then that
can directly correlate to amount of dollars
saved, which is a pretty powerful proposition.
We've been talking about security
because that's what we do specifically.
But most of what we talked about could
apply to any kind of IT or development workflow that's
oriented around tickets.
Even if you're just purely development,
one thing that we've been setting up
is GitHub webhooks so that when we make a pull request,
we also create a code review ticket, things like that.
So these automations are not like a thing
that you can build once and then forget about.
And you also can't replace people.
It's not like a factory where we are
trying to automate and completely take over
a human's job.
In this space where we have security analysts, IT analysts,
developers, we're just trying to eliminate the busy work that
takes up their time so that they can actually
spend their time doing security or doing development.
And there's a lot of low-hanging fruit.
Filling out ticket fields, adding links to that pull
request, that kind of thing.
It's super easy to do.
And it really adds a lot of value.
And then at the end, I just want to make a pitch for basically
our job.
Security automation is a super neat field to be in.
I wouldn't want to be anywhere else.
Our job is working with the rest of the team.
They're our customers.
But they're also sitting next to us.
We write code for them.
We develop software.
They can use it the next day, get us immediate feedback.
It's a really cool kind of hybrid of software development
and other operations work.
If anyone is a developer and wants to get into security,
it's also a really cool niche to look at.
Next time you're looking at jobs,
consider those security engineer positions.
A lot of them actually have a really heavy development
component.
And by the way, like everyone else, we are hiring.
So that is everything.
And I think we are at time.
So thank you, everyone, for your attention.
Thanks a lot.