of Python 2019. We are presenting on account security patterns. Please make Philip James
and Ashish Laroia welcome. Hi. We're Philip James and Ashish Laroia. We like giving talks
together, but right now you need to know that we have worked on a lot of websites, web applications
in Python and back-end API infrastructure things, often in Python. Some of them have been pretty
good. Some of them haven't. We've spent a while staying on top of the best account security
techniques because we know we've done it badly. This talk is a letter to our past selves.
We're going to get right into it with the bad news. People who use your website are
going to lose control of their accounts and it might become your problem. Let me define
using control of an account. If a sheesh here has an account on your website and someone
else can log into it without a sheesh's permission, something has gone wrong. If a sheesh permits
someone else to use his account, that's out of scope for this talk.
Hi. Who are you? Hi. My name is Ashish. I'm a systems engineer at Reduct and I've worked
on the security team back when Philip and I worked together at Eventbrite.
If Ashish permits someone else to use his account, that's out of scope for this talk.
With that said, I want to define account security. It's all the techniques that go into making
sure that Ashish is the only one who can access his account. We're going to focus on
techniques that relate to that specifically. You're going to have to make sure your app
doesn't have other really big problems like remote code execution or cross site request
forgery or whatever. This talk could kind of be considered the precursor to the Django
security page because all those things are great, but if people can get access to your
users' accounts, they don't matter quite so much.
And if you want to learn more about the Django security tips and tricks, Philip and I gave
a tutorial along with a bunch of other people a few years ago and Jacinda Shelley gave a
new tutorial based on that this year at PyCon. But yeah, account security. We want you to
get three big pieces of advice from this talk. Make it costly to take over an account. Help
your users stay informed and empower your users to defend themselves. The reason to
do these things is that it's a pretty scary place out there.
The amazing thing about this montage, if you're looking carefully, is that all of these breaches
happened in just the past year. And all of them involved account information being compromised.
Each of these breaches increases the chance that one of your users' accounts has been
taken over because people reuse email addresses and passwords for accounts. The main thing
you can do to protect your users is to make it hard for other people to take over their
accounts. Ashish is going to start by talking about passwords.
So I've put here a list of the most popular passwords. Honestly, if one of your users
uses 123456 as a password, their account is public. But it's still a really popular password.
And to avoid these kinds of passwords, security people created the idea of password rules.
Here's some special characters. Here's some numbers. These rules, the most common rules,
are inspired by a publication from the National Institute of Standards and Technology in 2003.
And I recently read an interview with the guy who wrote that 2003 publication.
Bill Burr is sorry. He was on a tight deadline in 2003 when he published that advice. It's
okay, Bill. We can all get over it now. There's new rules out from NIST published in the past
couple of years. And they're primarily about picking passwords that aren't in common use.
My favorite way to do that is to use a JavaScript library published by Dropbox. So here is the
Python package index account creation form. I've entered three of those top 100 passwords.
And the Python package index has a password strength meter at the bottom that prevents
you from using them. They're using Dropbox's open source library called zxcvbn. And by
the way, if you're curious where this name comes from, take a look under ASDF on a QWERTY
keyboard. So zxcvbn checks if a user's password is in the top 30,000 most common passwords
based on websites that got broken into. It's JavaScript so you can stop the user before
they even submit their bad password to you. There are some other goodies in that NIST
publication. I actually met someone from NIST earlier today at the conference. Anyone from
NIST here? Okay, well, that's fine. But there are some other goodies in that NIST publication
and I really recommend searching for it. The most important aspect is asking users to use
uncommon passwords and zxcvbn can help in the JavaScript front end. I also want to talk
about back end password strength validation. So Troy Hunt runs a free website and API called
have i been owned.com. He publishes a list of SHA-1 hashes of passwords that he has found
in breaches along with email addresses of the accounts involved. So there's an email
input right there on this website. In a perfect world, your users are searching for their
email address in this box on this site. But chances are they are not. There's also an
outrageously good chance that they're using the same password across multiple sites. Since
Troy only publishes SHA-1 hashes of passwords, you can't really loop across your user database
checking people's password against Troy's data set. I'll show you something you can
do. You can send the password to the have i been owned API. When the user is setting
their password, you have the raw password and you can check then. Have i been owned
operates a security conscious API for free where you can send the first five characters
of the SHA-1 hash of the password to them and they respond with SHA hashes of passwords
that have showed up in breaches. If you don't want to query an API, you can also download
the full database for free which is about 11 gigabytes compressed. PyPI and other sites
use the have i been owned API. By the way, Django's built-in user system uses the same
approach in an offline way. It bundles a list of the top 30,000 passwords as of Django 2.1.
If you want to use the have i been owned API, there are two options for integrating with
Django. Here are the two projects. And a third thing you can do is read the source code to
the Python package index. It uses Pyramid and it integrates directly with the have i
been owned API and it should be straightforward to figure out how to map that to Django. So
strong passwords are a factor in account security but they're only one factor. You can add more
factors to account security and Philip will tell you about that.
I love this picture. If I were in a caption contest for this picture, I would say this
is a picture of two factor authentication. Most of you in this room probably already
know about two factor authentication. It's where you as the application maintainer tell
the user they need something more than their password to log in like an access code from
a phone. I'm going to talk about different ways people set up multi factor authentication.
Before I proceed, I want to briefly know that MFA is harder to fish but is still fishable.
MFA is not a panacea against advanced phishing attacks. Sad but true. So the two main ways
people set up multi factor authentication is SMS or with an app. With SMS, you send
them a short term code and they type it into your website. SMS is not free of cost to send
as anyone who has accidentally left a Twilio account running will tell you. This is Google
Authenticator. It's an app that implements a standard alternative to SMS for two factor
authentication. Actually, how many people have used an app like Google Authenticator
or Duo or Okta? Amazing. Great. Okay, good. How many people have set up an integration
with it? Okay, so not that many. That's okay. There are packages that can help you. The big
thing to know is that app based MFA is really just your server and the user's device agreeing
on what number is going to be valid at what time. The app can generate the same number
as the server and you don't need to send an SMS. So that's pretty good. If you have users
who want two factor security, then you can set this up for them and not pay anything
to Twilio. Sorry, Twilio. There's something else you can support for free, too. This is
a picture of a security key by Ubico which supports a standard called universal second
factor or U2F. I bring it up because it's an alternative to asking people to pull out
their phones and either get texted or open an app. Google has eliminated corporate account
takeover using U2F devices. The main thing to know about U2F is that the browser sends
the domain name to the U2F device and it's therefore more resistant to phishing attacks.
Setting up U2F involves creating a certificate so it's a bit more hassle than TOTP which
is the app-based method but it's still pretty doable. Also, you have to buy a security key
or send them one so you have to take that into consideration. At this point, I'm going
to give you a list of resources. You can write these down if you want but we'll also be posting
the slides online. U2F is the coolest and it's resistant to phishing but it requires
your users to buy a little hardware token or you to buy one for them. Two factor authentication
is one way to secure accounts even if the password isn't super secure. Ashish will
now talk about another way. So here's how Slack asks users to log in. A user gets an
email, they click a link, the app finds an unforderable token in the URL and the app
logs the user in. Slack is betting that their users and their users' email providers care
more about their account than their Slack passwords. And I think this is pretty interesting
because Slack is really leaning on email providers to help prevent account takeovers.
For all the Slack users with Gmail accounts, they're asking Google to be the first line
of defense against Slack account takeover. Slack is betting that the Google security
team is really good at protecting Gmail and that's probably a pretty good bet for you
to make too. To me, this fits into the pattern of make it as costly as possible to take over
an account. The attacker's not cost now includes the cost of breaking into the user's email
account. Slack does also have a username and password prompt. I think they don't want you
to use it though. I think Slack wants to be sure that you control your email address at
the time of login. So I'll talk about how to implement that. If you use Django, there's
a Django package that does this for you. You can just use it. It's called Django token
off. If you want to implement this yourself, I have a fancy trick we used at Sandstorm
that I want to tell you about. You can store the, when you're generating a random token,
instead of storing the random token you emailed the user, you can store a hash of that token
in the database. This gives you one tiny useful thing, which is that if somebody runs off
with your database, they can't use the data from the database to log in as people. One
thing to know about data storage, if you're going to be querying for these, and you are
because people are going to be logging in with those links, you might want to know that
the database, databases do fancy tricks to save space in their indexes, and most of those
tricks won't work for random data. So you might end up with an index that's the same
size as your database table. That's just life. By the way, does this approach, does this
approach freak anyone else out? I used to be really bothered by this email address,
email login thing, and then I realized it's basically the same as doing a password reset.
So I guess it's okay. Besides, you have to remember that your users, by and large, have
pretty bad passwords. There's a lot more we can say about making it costly to take over
an account, and it could be a whole talk on its own, but there are other aspects of account
security that I want to make sure we cover. So once you've done the first pass on making
accounts hard to take over, your next step is to help your users help themselves. This
section could also be called building your users' trust in you. Here's a login alert
from Facebook. How many of you have seen one of these before? Cool. Most of the room. Facebook
and Google are really good at proactively letting the user know when something weird
is happening. They send emails. They also show in-app notifications. Here's a web notification.
When I get these notifications, what I feel is a big ball of trust that Google or Facebook
are at least paying attention to what's going on with my account. Google and Facebook don't
always send you a notification. They try to detect when it's most likely that a new login
is a bad one. So here's some code to check if the user is logging in from a new IP address.
It's based in Django. It's pretty simplistic. You're using the Django signals here, and
we're also checking that the user's last IP address is the one that they normally log
We've added that to our user model in this case. We can send an email when we detect that
there's a login that seems suspicious. You could detect instead of at last IP, you could
detect the user country changes or when they're on a new web browser. Anything that you know
about the user or the session, you can use to detect if it's a bad or at least a suspicious
login. Once you've unlocked the power of comparing information about logins and sessions, the
world is your oyster. This pattern we've just implemented can be reused for all sorts of
events that your users would like to know about, like, for instance, password changes.
If an attacker broke into a user's account and changed the password, it's going to be
really important for that person to get the problem resolved fast. Since we still live
in an age where there's no common replacement for passwords, you as the app maintainer should
do everything you can to let your users know when their password changes. Slack-style email
login makes passwords less critical, which is good, but it doesn't negate you needing
to protect the user's password and letting them know when it's changed. So here's some
example code. I'm not going to explain it line by line, and again, we're going to publish
these slides later. We haven't tested this exact code in production, so your mileage
may vary. But the Django model, which is a replacement for the user model, saves the
password at the moment that the object is initialized from the ORM and then compares
that to a password being changed and then sends a notification if the password is changed
from when it was initialized from the database. Hopefully that's straightforward. If not,
feel free to come talk to us afterwards. As an aside, here's a picture of Mint.com asking
me for my bank password. I bring this up because if you build a useful website, others might
want to integrate with it. Users are going to hand out their password if you're not careful.
This is why people make OAuth APIs, so that a user can hand over an API token instead.
If the API token gets compromised, it's easy enough for a user to revoke it or for you
for them. There's something else you can do that shows users you're looking out for them.
You can notify them of breaches in general, even if they aren't necessarily related to
your site. So remember all these breaches? Troy Hunt's Have I Been Owned database lets
you query users' email addresses to see if they show up in any of these breaches. And
we've talked about Have I Been Owned earlier. There's one other thing you can do to integrate.
If you have the account details from the other site's breach, you can check for a match for
email addresses that have accounts on your site. Letting users know when they could be
affected by another breach is the highest level of informing and enabling them. But
it's also potentially the riskiest. And if you're not sure why that would be, you can
ask Phil about it in the hallway track. Check with your legal team. We've talked about a
few ways to present information to users to help them know what's going on with their
accounts. And I want to close with some specific ways you can help your users act on that
information. So here's a picture of what it looks like when I change my Facebook password.
Facebook gives the user the option to log out the other devices that are logged in.
You could create a session database table, create a web interface for letting the user
invalidate sessions one by one, and that will let you do something similar. But that feature
can be hard to implement, and users might not go looking for it. There's a simpler approach.
If the user changes their password, they might be worried somebody else has the old password.
So it can be a good idea to log the attacker out. And in 2012, Dourly Rodriguez asked on
the Django user mailing list how to invalidate active sessions after a password change. Dourly
implemented it himself and shared the code. Then Albert turned it into a reusable Django
app. And for Django 1.7, Tim Graham implemented the same algorithm that Albert and Dourly
used. The idea is to store an HMAC of the user's hashed password in the session. Since
Django doesn't always have a database table with all sessions, Django can use this algorithmic
approach to make sure that past sessions are invalid in the future. That is, if the
user's current HMAC password doesn't match what's in the session, then you should log
out this session. So being able to muck with sessions is a pretty powerful security tool,
and there's an advanced technique that builds on it. But first, let me ask you all a question.
How many people here are logged into GitHub on your laptops right now? Yeah. Okay. Cool.
Now how many people have ever intentionally logged out of GitHub? Okay. Okay. Good. And
I said that I want to help limit the amount of damage that can get caused when an account
gets compromised. And if you logged into your GitHub account, let a friend use your laptop,
when a friend visits GitHub, they can probably do a lot of damage. So here's a picture of
what GitHub calls pseudo mode. They ask you for your password again when you're doing
something sensitive, like adding a new SSH key. And I want to talk about how to implement
this in Python web apps that you all might have. So there's the question of what your
code might look like. Let's say you have a Django view that does something dangerous
like this. You've got this giant account upgrade button. You might want to let the user click
it to get an upgraded account of some kind. And maybe it requires log in. So here's the
Django view code for that. Now, this might be a thing you don't want to let them do unless
they've logged in recently. And so I'll enhance this code in a pseudo code kind of way to
check. What that will do is when the user clicks the button, it will make a post request
to slash upgrade and the server will detect that the user needs to re-authenticate. Here,
you can see in our made up page that we ask the user for their password and we explain
why we're asking for it, this pseudo mode thing. We'll need to store the URL they need
to go back to once they've confirmed their password in the URL. I think we should send
them back to the account page so they can finish their upgrade thing. And we also add
a query string parameter reason so that you can add some template information to the pseudo
mode page. So that's what it looks like from the user perspective. Here's some quick pseudo
code for pseudo mode. I'm skipping some decorator magic here. And I'm assuming you have a session
system. Django works fine. And here's how it goes. You check when the user was last
authenticated and if it's in the right amount of time, you let it happen and otherwise you
redirect them. So to wrap up, pseudo mode, also known as elevated privileges mode, lets
you limit the damage if a user lends their laptop to a friend or other situations where
someone loses control of their account. You can find an implementation of this in an open
source package called Django Elevate if you want. And basically the reason you're doing
this is you don't trust your users to log out. There is a permanent log out, however,
that Philip will tell you about. A funny thing about popular websites is that people start
asking for their accounts to be deleted. Sometimes people want their personal data to be visible
online in fewer places. Other people want to know no one is going to break into their
account. Whatever the reason, if an account is deleted, that's pretty secure. You don't
have to hard delete the data depending on your jurisdiction and some GDPR stuff. If
no one on the internet can log into the account with its correct username and passwords, that's
pretty good. And that's the most secure account. So with that, we want to close. Remember the
three big pieces of advice that we want you to get from this talk. Make it costly to take
over an account, help your users stay informed, and empower users to defend themselves. If
you remember these three things, the techniques we described are hopefully easier to remember
and you'll find it easier to come up with techniques that work best for your app. And
with that, we'll open it up to questions in the form of a question. You can either ask
questions now or you can find us in the hallway afterwards. Thanks.
If people have questions, there are microphones in the aisles here. Otherwise...
We blew them away. We answered every possible question about account security.
Oh, no. Okay, great. Oh, there's one.
Testing, testing. So do you have any thoughts on login methodology around like point of
sale systems where you need to log in very quickly at very short lived, unprivileged
session or something like that? Thank you.
I can tell you one specific thing that I've seen. I'm blanking on the company name right
now, but there's a company that makes tools for children. And to log in... The children
are often like four, five, six years old and need to log in to a computer thing and can't
necessarily type or read very well. And so they have a... The teacher puts out a list
of QR codes in the classroom and the student grabs theirs and puts it in the right place.
This is to say... I think you even mentioned swiping something. But you can have a random
token that is a QR code that a person actually does keep secret, unlike in the classroom
example. And then they could put it in front of a camera, for example.
Well, you mentioned point of sale systems. And what I've observed, and we've also kind
of worked for companies that have helped power point of sale systems to some degree. The
way that I've seen them solve this problem, which I think is pretty reasonable, is every
user of the point of sale system has like a password or an access code or some unique
identifier for them that lets them access kind of the basic functionality that they
need. But if there's advanced functionality that the business wants more protected, then
someone who is a supervisor has like the... Effectively, the pseudo mode password comes
in and has to like put in their password to do the operation. And so if you have a system
where it's like, I know that there's going to be lots of users using this same terminal,
this same computer over and over again, I think the answer is there is like limit how
long a logged in session is valid for and like carefully evaluate all the actions for
which ones might need like pseudo mode. Question?
Do you have any suggestions about what to do when the user loses access to the email
address?
Oh. Capture... So I've seen some companies and credit card companies are actually kind
of great at this in a roundabout way. They have the, you know, the what's your call in
password? But another way they can kind of verify that it's you is they can ask you about
like recent transactions. And so if you really think that your user has like lost their
account, your support rep probably can see details about their account that theoretically
only the user would know, right? Alternatively, valid second factor, right? Like if they've
lost control of the email but they still have access to their phone and the phone is still
connected correctly, I would say that a valid second factor input is worth a password reset
email, right? Like if they can prove that they have the second factor, then sending a password
reset email to a new email system is probably no less secure than what you had previously.
Cool. Any other questions? Or questions?
Great.
So much of your discussion focused on passwords. But with WebAuthn finally getting adoption,
one of the promises of that is to eliminate passwords completely. Just curious your thoughts
on that.
As I understand it, so I haven't been paying a lot of attention to WebAuthn. Can I actually
keep you at the mic for a second? As I understand it, WebAuthn is a more standardized version
of U2F, is that right? And so the idea there is you can use something like the security key
by Ubico that we showed. And then basically we love it. There's this quote we have from this
Google PR person about account security and how they've eliminated corporate account takeovers.
I really think that this story by Google is part of what's rocketing WebAuthn and U2F and
Ubico to success. One other thing I'd say real quick is if your goal is, and we think this is
a very valid goal to get rid of passwords, then a combination of Slack style login through email
plus second factor authentication is at least as secure as password plus WebAuthn and probably
more secure than password plus WebAuthn. And then the user doesn't have to remember anything.
Yeah, it is two things they have instead of one thing they know and one thing they have. But it's
still multiple factors.
The thing I love about it is it's invulnerable to man in the middle attacks, right? Because if you
are, or I shouldn't say invulnerable to man in the middle attacks, although I think it is in some
respects. But if you're phishing attacks in particular, right, it's strongly tied to a particular
endpoint. And so you know that if you go to a site that looks like that, it's going to present a
different credential than if you go to the real site.
Totally. Thanks so much.
Hi.
So what about the third factor?
Well, so Philip carefully transitioned in the wording in the talk from saying this is a photo
contest of two factor authentication. You've all heard of second factor or multi factor
authentication. So like there's a point of diminishing returns, right? And like a thing that
you can add to that. So like the thing there is biometrics are a user name, not a password.
Just in case anyone was under the illusion that a biometrics like your eyeball or your fingerprint
should be a password, no, that is a user name. There are other factors you can add. At some point
you have to find that right balance between how much do I want my users to be secure and how much
do I want my users to be annoyed?
So you and then you.
Just a question about multi factor authentication with single sign on. I wonder if there's any
implications that come with doing that or if you treat it the same way as a user name and password
login.
I mean the standard that I've seen a lot of companies adopting in terms of software, I know
that both of M-PRIGHT and Patreon, which I currently work for Patreon by the way, I forgot to
mention that in the talk. We use Okta, which is single sign on for all of the sub apps but is
two factor multi factor authentication to get into Okta. Once you're inside Okta, there's kind of
this web of trust that you're in and therefore they almost never make you do a second factor into
the sub app. But if you're going to do single sign on, doing second factor is also still
recommended.
Thank you.
I'm still confused from the first moments of the talk and wondering how I can establish that this
is in fact a sheesh.
Well, so I'm wearing this jacket. It has my name on it except the H lost a bit of a fragment there.
As a sheesh.
Yeah. I guess maybe I'm still failing that authentication check. It's my corporate uniform for the
company I work for, Reduct.
We could go through his pockets if you want.
We can talk more afterwards. But it is impossible to know.
Okay, thanks. I think we're done. Feel free to come talk to us afterwards.
Thanks.