Hello everyone. Hello everyone. Next up is Erin Allard who is a platform support
engineer at Heroku and will be presenting a technical interview using
Python.
Hi thanks so much for coming I'm Erin. I see some friendly faces in the audience
so thanks very much for being here. Without further ado let's talk about
technical interviewing with Python. If you'd like to follow along with the
slides there's a bit.ly link there for you. So is this talk for you? Probably.
It's geared more towards candidates who are going to be interviewing less
towards interviewers but if you're an interviewer there will still probably be
things from the talk you can take away. So if you're a kind of candidate who's
rendering oh my god what should I study or how can I feel more confident because
I feel really nervous or how can I do all of this interview stuff using Python
I will answer a lot of these questions in the talk. In the next 25 minutes we'll
talk about briefly the overview of what a technical interview process looks like
all the steps, some personal qualities and non-technical skills that hiring
managers are going to be looking for when they interview candidates. Importantly
probably why most of you are here the computer science concepts that you
should probably know and how to implement them in Python. And finally I'll
wrap up with some general advice about mindset and how to stay positive because
let's admit interviewing sucks it's emotionally very draining. All of that to
say this is going to be a whirlwind of things you should probably study. There
will probably be things up here that you don't think should be and maybe things
you think should be up here that aren't. There's a lot of different ways to
approach interviewing. I'd love to hear your ideas if they're missing so feel
free to send me an email I'll give you my email address at the end. So that's me
as of this past Monday I am on the Heroku support team as a platform support
engineer. Prior to that I spent just over a year at a company called Numerator
building out their Django SAS product for which is was their flagship product
and I'm also a LinkedIn learning instructor. I have three courses up right
now all relating to technical interviewing using Python. I'll link to
two of them later on in the slides as they relate to the material here. I am a
software engineer from a non-traditional background. I actually studied economics
in college and then later went to Hackbrite Academy in San Francisco and I
continue to be involved there and do a lot of mentoring of folks who are also
trying to transition careers and so a lot of that experience has colored this
presentation. This is also my first time speaking at PyCon so again thank you
very much for coming.
Okay so this is a crossword puzzle obviously. I want to give you just a few
seconds. Can anyone think of why this crossword might be important?
Okay I'll tell you. So this crossword appeared in January of 1942 in the Daily
Telegraph newspaper which is published in Britain and I am cheekily and only
half-jokingly going to propose that this was the first technical interview in the
history of computer science and the reason I say that is that this crossword
puzzle was the one that folks from Bletchley Park used to sort of initially
try to find cryptanalysts and people who are good at problem-solving to come join
their efforts to crack the enigma code. I watched the imitation game last night
for like the fifth time and realized how well this fit in with my talk and so
added it at the last minute. We've really come a long way since technical
interviews like this and I put this here just to remind you to keep it in
perspective. We're going to talk about some very technical things but really it
goes back to things that a crossword puzzle are fundamentally trying to help
those Bletchley Park people find which is can you solve problems? Can you
recognize patterns? Can you stick with a thing until you finish it? So a brief
overview of the technical interview process in case some of you haven't yet
had a technical interview. It usually starts with a recruiter phone screen. I
call this a pulse check. The recruiter will talk to you for 20 or 30 minutes
and ask you all the general questions like why are you applying for the role?
What do you know about the company? What have you been up to for the last year or
two? And if that goes well, you know, if you can convince them that it's fun to
talk to you for 20 minutes, they'll move you on to the next step which is
typically a technical phone screen with an engineer. And I forgot to mention that
there will of course be some variation in all of these steps across companies.
But typically this is the flow. The technical phone screen with an engineer
might or might not have a web collaborative coding component but
typically it's 30 to 60 minutes and they'll ask you questions maybe about
your preferred programming language. They may kind of poke at your knowledge
about different concepts within that language. And then depending on the role
they may ask you some domain specific questions. If you're applying for a back
end Django role, they may ask you some questions about Django, things like that.
If this call goes well, typically the next step is something called a take home
assessment which is a mini self-contained project that the recruiter will probably
email you some instructions for. And it's your job over the next two to seven days
to put together some response or solution to whatever the prompt is. There is a bit
of debate about whether or not these are effective or fair. Some companies
unfortunately use them to get a little free labor out of people which is not
right. But when done well and when structured well, companies can get a good
sense of how a candidate might fit in on a team in terms of skill. And the last step
is usually the on-site interviews. This is the part that I always get really
nervous about. Typically there are at least four hours you meet anywhere from
three to ten people, most of whom will be on your team. And a lot of the interviews
are technical in nature, meaning you're white boarding or pair programming and
I'll explain what those are in a minute. Also a lot of behavioral questions where
people will ask you things you've probably heard before like what would you
do if or how do you approach conflict, those kinds of things. White boarding, you
may know, is when you and your interviewer are standing in front of a big
white board instead of a computer screen and working through what is usually a
coding problem, writing it out. Pair programming is when you're doing
effectively the same thing, working together on a problem but actually coding.
Pros and cons to both, won't get into the disagreements about which of those are
better but there's a lot of conversation about that online. So let's move into the
skills part. First I want to talk about the non-technical skills. People often
call these soft skills. I don't like to call them soft skills because
non-technical skills are hard for some people. Interpersonal stuff can be really
hard but it really matters. And the first one of those is problem-solving. And we
hear this phrase a lot as software engineers. Everyone wants to work with
people who are great problem solvers. And to me the phrase problem solver is a
shorthand for a much longer description. To me it means using what you already
know to solve a specific problem that might not be well defined. And for those
of you with a little more experience you know that this happens all the time in
your work. So this is a skill that your interviewers are going to be screening
for. Another non-technical skill that has been really important in my career
growth is the ability to ask good questions. And I've linked here to a blog
article by Julia Evans called How to Ask Good Questions. This is a fantastic
article. I mention it anytime I'm talking to anyone who's early in
their career or going through the interview process. The main thing that
I've pulled out of it is a framework around how to structure a question so
that it's most useful to you and most useful to the person you're asking it of.
And that is something like this. I'm trying to do this thing but this other
thing is happening. I already tried X and Y. Can you point me in the right
direction? For me when I use this format it's really effective because I am able
to show that I've already tried doing something on my own. It didn't work and so
I tried other things. I can set a baseline level of knowledge for the
person who I'm asking and then I make a specific ask for help. I do also want to
add here that asking a good question should be asked of the right person. And
for me the right person is usually who knows the most about this topic, who is
also the least busy. Typically you'd, well actually nevermind, I was gonna start
talking about slack but I'm not gonna go down that rabbit hole. The third
non-technical skill that I wanted to highlight is about understanding
assumptions. And this goes for both code and people. You know we're probably very
familiar with both actually but when you kind of combine them in the context of a
software engineering team we can talk about it a little more differently. We
know about understanding assumptions about a problem but I kind of go a level
deeper when I talk about understanding assumptions. I think about what things
about this problem do I think are facts that I haven't actually taken the time
to prove or ask about. And within that could also be things like bias or
expectations. So when hiring managers are interviewing candidates this is something
that they may be looking for. Same goes with people right. A hiring manager may be
very interested to know if a candidate can you know kind of get inside their own
mind and make fewer assumptions about their colleagues through the use of
asking good questions. An example would be, hey when you said this in a meeting I
wasn't quite sure how you meant that. Could you explain a little more? Checking
assumptions about people helps your team run more smoothly. So now we'll move on to
the code part. Code obviously matters a lot in a technical interview. And I wanted
to start us off by talking about collections. So when I think about approaching
a coding challenge for example I like to keep in mind what are all of the tools
that I have in programming that can help me solve a problem. And in my mind
collections are the most powerful tool because they help me store and organize
data. These would be tuples, lists, dictionaries and sets. I'm purposefully
not going into syntax or methods or things like that because I know you can
all go check the documentation. But knowing these like the back of your hand
will save you so much time in coding challenges. If you can immediately
recognize which one of these collections to use when, that'll save you time. If you
can memorize a few very helpful methods that are associated with each of these
collections that can save you a lot of time. For example with dictionaries if
you can remember oh there's a keys of values and an items method or iter items
method that can save you a lot of time.
And this is a link to the Python 3 documentation. So time complexity in my
experience comes up pretty much at the end of every coding challenge. Like
probably many of you I was baffled by this at first I like to think that I'm a
lot better at it now. But basically time complexity is referring to the amount of
time it takes to run an algorithm and the worst-case scenario compared to the
size of the input. And there's a link here in case you need a refresher this
goes to a free code camp blog post. Probably most of you have seen this
ubiquitous chart here showing all of the various time complexities. This I do want
to note is on a logarithmic scale so o of log in is that red line that you see
all the way down on the x-axis. And the important thing to pull from this chart
here is that the closer the line is to the x-axis the more optimal the runtime.
You really want to stay away from runtimes that are closer to the y-axis.
The most common runtimes that have come up in my experience as someone who's
early in my career when I do coding challenges for interviews are these four.
So constant time which is o of 1, linear time which is o of n, log n which we
just talked about that often comes up with binary search and o of n squared.
We don't have time to go into what all of these mean and how you get them but again
check out that link that I provided on the first slide if you need a refresher.
There are actually a few more as well so it would be good to know how those work
but these are the ones that I come across most commonly.
Okay, recursion. How many of you have ever been afraid of recursion?
Yes, me too. I put off learning about it for a very long time.
Recursion is at its core an elegant method of solving a problem where the solution
depends on solutions to smaller occurrences of that same problem.
And recursion when you write a recursive function it has to have two components,
a base case and progress.
And the base case just means how will I know when I'm done recursing or how will my
function know when it can stop calling itself.
And the progress portion is to continually reduce the problem until you get down to the base case.
Al Swigart who spoke at North Bay Python last year did a fantastic talk on recursion.
I wish I had listened or watched this talk three years ago when I was just getting started.
I really, really encourage you to watch it.
Again, you'll have access to these slides with the bit.ly link.
So click on this link. It's 20 or 30 minutes.
And he just does a really good job of breaking it down and also high five Al for a really fantastic talk title about recursion.
Object oriented programming just comes up all the time in interviews because Python is an object
oriented language and classes and objects are absolutely everywhere in production code,
at least from my experience and from most of the folks who I've coached.
I've again linked to an external resource here. This one's from real python dot com.
If you need an OOP refresher I highly recommend checking out that resource.
Really at its core you need to know about defining classes and attributes and knowing the difference between class
attributes and method attributes.
And likewise knowing the difference between class methods and instance methods.
And if OOP comes up in an interview you are also most likely going to be asked but why do we like OOP?
And your answers should include each of these three keywords.
Encapsulation inheritance and polymorphism.
Again we're not going to go into great detail here but that link I provided at the beginning is a good resource.
So I really really recommend knowing how to talk about each of these three things.
Data structures and algorithms.
There's a free book available online called Problem Solving with Algorithms and Data Structures Using Python.
I shortened that in the rest of these slides to PSADS up and it's written by Brad Miller and David Ranham.
I highly highly highly recommend this book.
I'm going to be linking to it on almost every slide from here on out.
I won't be telling you that I've linked to the slide you can at this point read it for yourself.
But all of the data structures and algorithms that I'm going to present in the next 10 minutes are in that book.
So while we don't have time to go over the Python code in this talk all of the Python code is there waiting for you.
So first we'll start with the linear data structures.
Stacks which you can think of like a stack of pancakes in the sense that it's last in first out.
So whatever pancake we put on top of the stack last is going to be the first one we're going to take off to eat.
You can add and remove items or pancakes from a pancake stack in constant time.
And it preserves the order of items it preserves the order in which we cook those pancakes.
In my experience with these data structures you're commonly asked to just implement like a vanilla version of them.
Sometimes you're asked to then manipulate them.
But knowing at a base level how to code them and how they all work is really really helpful.
We also have the concept of queues which you can think of as a line in the grocery store if you're waiting to check out.
First in first out meaning the first person in the line is going to be the first person to check out.
You can add items to the back of the queue in constant time.
But it's linear time while you wait your turn to get out of the queue and buy your groceries.
And queues also preserve the order of items.
Another linear data structure are called linked lists.
We differentiate between singly linked and doubly linked lists.
And linked lists are represented by a Python class which we typically call a node.
And we are able to make those nodes kind of point to each other in memory.
And that's how we represent this list structure.
In a singly linked list you can only move through the nodes in one direction.
But in a doubly linked list each node can keep track of what the node after it is and what the node before it is.
These two data structures are actually very similar.
There's a lot of overlap in the code.
So while it may feel overwhelming, okay there's like two different types of this.
I'm going to have to learn two different data structures.
The code is pretty similar.
I did mention that I'd share the link to my linked and learning courses which are all or these two are about Python data structures.
So if you need a much more in-depth treatment of stacks, queues and linked lists you can check these out.
Again you'll have access to this link in the slides and this will get you a free trial for those courses.
Nonlinear data structures.
So trees.
Binary search trees which are a subtype of a regular tree.
And graphs like social networks for example.
And hash maps.
You can think of Python dictionaries as very much like hash maps.
And so if you're asked questions about these in particular hash maps what you're being asked about essentially is how do dictionaries work.
So knowing about these nonlinear data structures is important.
I'd say at a high level know what they are, what they do and what they're useful for.
In my experience I have not had any coding challenges and interviews come up yet about these.
But again I'm early in my career so if you're more mid-level probably the expectation is that you would have a higher understanding than someone with my level of experience would have.
And all the code for these is in that book I mentioned.
Sorting algorithms.
These are commonly used to assess foundational computer science knowledge.
There's quite a debate around should we even ask about data structures?
Should we even ask about sorting algorithms and searching algorithms?
I think it really depends on the role.
So they're in this talk because I think they are important although it may be your experience that you go quite a few years of interviews without having to be asked about any of these things.
So it just depends on how the company approaches their interview process and what they value when they're looking for candidates.
So I'll highlight three sorting algorithms here.
There are actually a lot more.
These three to me felt like a pretty good place to start.
The first one is insertion sort which is a pretty simple algorithm that does not have very good runtime.
O of n squared.
This type of sorting is best on shorter lists or lists that are already sorted.
Here's a diagram.
You can see a little bit about how it works.
The next one is merge sort which has a much better runtime.
It looks a little quite a bit more complicated.
There's a lot more boxes on that screen.
But really what it does is it breaks a list down into the smallest individual component which is an item.
And then it reassembles those items in ordered pairs until it eventually reassembles a sorted list.
And the third one I wanted to highlight is quick sort which is a really efficient general purpose sorting algorithm that's commonly used.
So again in my experience it has been enough to know how these work.
I have not been asked to code them or implement them yet although it is my intention to dig into that more.
And then finally we'll wrap up with searching algorithms.
Linear or binary search. I love this one. It's one of my favorites. It's just really cool.
I love the idea that every time you do an operation you're reducing the universe of possibilities by half.
And that's why this is very efficient. O of log n.
We can also search through binary search trees. So the binary search of trees is done most effectively on binary trees.
And then we can do breadth first search and depth first search.
So I'll go through each of these. And breadth first search you're going through each hierarchical level of the tree before moving on to the next one.
So in this example we start at the root node which is labeled one and then we go down to the next level.
And then you can see two three and four and then five and six and so on.
And you can contrast that with depth first which is where you go all the way down as far as you can go a leg of a tree.
Once you reach the bottom you go back up to the most recently visited node and then back down again as far as you can go.
And you keep doing that until you've visited the whole tree.
There are kind of guidelines around when you might want to use one of these methods over the other.
We won't get into that here but there is some science around choosing which one to use in which situation.
So that's it for the really specific you know data structure and algorithm stuff that you should probably know.
Let's talk a little bit about coding challenges. My approach to coding challenges has always been quality over quantity.
I think it's really easy to tell yourself oh just just 10 more challenges and then I'll be ready to interview.
Or the other thing I've seen happen is people will just continually do coding challenges that that they can do that they can finish.
And they don't go on to ones that are more complex.
So a myth that I have seen a lot is this idea that I need to spend all of my time doing coding challenges.
Since I won't get an offer unless I can solve them perfectly during a whiteboarding session.
So reality number one is that just studying coding challenges alone is is not sufficient.
Studying coding challenges is necessary but if you combine that with also studying other computer science concepts.
Ultimately what you're doing over the long run is learning how to approach a variety of problems.
And since you never know what's going to pop up in an interview the more types of problems you have seen.
The more likely it is that something will trigger your memory when you're in an interview.
The other reality is that you can get offers even if you don't finish a coding challenge.
And the reason is that well there's many reasons.
Sometimes the hiring manager might purposefully and knowingly give you a coding challenge that's too hard for you.
Because they want to see how far you get or they want to test how you handle frustration.
Or they may want to suss out how good you are at asking questions when you get stuck.
In a situation like that where you're not able to finish a coding challenge.
You can still get an offer but you have to demonstrate a lot of the other skills that we talked about earlier in this talk.
The more non-technical skills because it's often a balance of comparing technical skill to.
Who you are as a human being.
There are lots of ways to practice what I call interview Python.
Which is a Python that you would type to fill out a coding challenge.
And I make this distinction because at least to me coding challenge Python feels a lot different than production Python.
That I was writing you know over the last year.
So I've linked to a number of different websites and platforms you can go to interactively solve coding challenges.
And then there's also good old pen and paper.
Or if you have a little mini whiteboard at home.
You know the physical act of writing things out can also really help solidify concepts in your mind.
So I recommend that you do work on coding challenges that actually challenge you.
And don't get into this rut of only doing ones that feel comfortable.
And then use the internet when those coding challenges cause you to get stuck.
I would also encourage you as you're choosing which coding challenges to do.
To be realistic about what your interviewer might be expecting from you.
If this is your very first role out of a boot camp or out of a computer science program at college.
And you're going for a junior level role.
Your interviewer probably is not expecting you to know machine learning algorithms.
Unless it's like a junior machine learning role.
In which case you probably shouldn't spend your time studying those algorithms for your interview.
You might be much better served studying a different set of coding challenges.
So we're coming to a close.
I wanted to provide some final thoughts around mindset.
Failure and rejection are part of the process.
I think this is something that we have probably all heard from people who love us.
As they have watched us struggle through the interview process.
It sounds great but for me it has been so hard to absorb.
But I guess a bit of progress that I was finally able to make for myself is that okay fine.
If it is part of the process I'm going to have to deal with it anyway.
I would rather deal with it upfront.
And incorporate what I learned from that rejection into my next interview.
And incrementally make my interviews more and more successful.
Until I finally get an offer.
So I'm kind of going to twist this a little bit and say yes.
Because it's part of the process I would encourage you to front load it.
Apply for jobs before you're ready.
Get as many phone screens as you can.
Fail and fail and fail.
And just recycle everything you learned from those failures into your next interview.
And your next interview.
Next one.
I love this one.
I made this one up myself.
You don't need every company to want to hire you.
It feels good if every company wants to hire you.
Maybe for a small sliver of people every company does want to hire them.
But most of us don't fall into that category.
You only need one company to want to hire you to get a new job.
And hopefully it's the right company.
But if that is true you don't need to beat yourself up if a company decides not to move
forward with you.
It just means that they for whatever reason were not the right company at that time.
So I want to bring it back to the crossword puzzle from 1942.
Just to remind you that we have come a long way and while it may feel really overwhelming
to think about studying data structures and algorithms and knowing all of these collection
types and having to also remember to be a good human.
It boils down to these essential things around problem solving and recognizing patterns
and being curious.
And also you got this.
Go forth.
Interview.
Get offers.
Accept offers.
There's my email address.
If you didn't get the slide link at the beginning you're welcome to email me.
I can send you the link.
Feel free to reach out and share any successes you might have.
And again thank you for coming.
I really appreciate it.