Okay, so once more, good morning.
Just like the introduction, so much has been discussed here,
and I'm really overwhelmed the way Python has actually gone.
The last time I attended the PyCon was in 2012 at Silicon Valley,
and within that six or seven years, so much has actually happened.
So I'm going to say what we are trying to do,
because all these nice things, some people are not going to benefit from them.
Like Meg said this morning, he said we need to be able to empower everybody,
to be able to shied adults from all diverse culture and geographical background
with data structure and see what the problem they can solve.
This is quite interesting, and as I go on this talk,
you are going to see that there was an effort to do so in the past, but it didn't succeed.
So my talk is on how this particular using QPython smartphone will help us in accomplishing that.
So first I would just thank the Education Summit Committee for accepting my abstracts.
Then I thank the organizers of PyCon, then the PyTorne Software Foundation for the invitation,
and of course the funding, because without it I wouldn't be here now.
I have been an active member of the PyTorne community,
and as I said I was at PyCon 2012 at Silicon Valley, and my talks are there.
The first thing I want to say is why computational approaches.
I don't need to explain that to an audience like this,
because it is now established today that we need computational physics.
Why in developing what? Computational physics is restricted to maybe university programs.
Here I hear that high-grade already taking computational physics and learning programming.
This is overwhelming.
But there is one aspect I want to add.
I'm not going to go into the details of why we need computational physics and all that,
but there is an aspect that is really motivating me here.
Today in research what we do is that we have so many numerical software for solving diverse problems.
My area, I'm a condensed matter physicist, so I work on a strongly correlated system.
In that place we have all kinds of software today,
and from solving things like density, fortunate theory, dynamic feed, mid-feed theories, they are all there.
This software when new post-graduates come in, you want to introduce them to some of this software.
If you introduce them, fine enough, they will work with it,
but then they need to understand the software for them to be able to manipulate it to suit their own personal problem.
Isn't it? That is it.
There are so many of these software that are now implemented in Python.
I just gave an example of this one that was published recently.
It's a very good software, efficient Python implementation of the continuous time hybridization expansion quantum impurity solver.
It's a very good one. Then there's this Trios.
Of course, that one comes both in Python and in C++.
So the students need to understand this software, at least the programming language of this software,
for them to be able to manipulate them.
Then of course one thing we also do is that you have a software in another language.
If you want to bring it to Python, which is open source and free,
you can also do that like this particular app pack, which is a Fortran package.
Very beautiful for solving eigenvalue and eigenvector problem, but today they have already imported it into SciPy.
So these are some of the reasons why we have to do computational physics.
But at large, we know that computer-based activities have pervaded our teaching-learning process,
as well as research, so much that in addition to theory and experiments,
as we all know now, they now constitute a third pillar in science and engineering.
Now, but how do we do this? There is a big question.
The question has been answered here by different speakers.
The first thing is the desire to ease the learner into programming
and to give them the opportunity to develop a conceptual model of what a program is and what it does.
Okay, but how do we, what is the strategy to achieve this computational physics?
The first thing is accessibility to computer devices, especially in developing countries.
Here you have a computer science lab or a computational physics program.
You have a computer lab because if you are taking a computational physics class for three hours,
you need to be able to have an equivalent three hours in the computer lab.
In 2008, I attended the conference of, organized by the American Physicist Teacher,
a branch university, and at that point, I think at that point,
there were about five universities that were offering computational physics in the U.S.
I was told then. I don't know if that has increased,
meaning that all those universities have computer lab,
but this is not the case with those developing countries.
You discover that I was teaching computational physics,
and the only lab I have access to was the computer lab, so I have to share with them.
For a computer science lab that has just one lab from 100 level to 400 level,
it was not easy for me to get in computer time,
so this was one of the problems I faced for so many years.
Then this idea of using the Q Python came in as a version of Python in Android,
and so when I saw it, of course, it's something you download the entire Q Python into your smartphone,
and once you have done that, you can now begin to use it anywhere, anyhow, and anytime,
and that is the beauty of what we are talking about,
and I hope with that, Dr. Schatz, you talk about taking the Python everywhere,
so I see that maybe you will also help us in writing a good book on Q Python
so that you can spread the message everywhere.
Now, I just made sure that there is an attempt in the past to actually have people have access to the computer.
This was what we call the War Laptop A Shied program.
It started in 2002 when Professor Likula, the group member of MIT,
he went to Cambodia, a small village, and he was able to see that by letting these young kids there have access to computer,
connected computer, they were able to do wonderful things,
so he came back to MIT and told them that, look, if we can make, I'm just summarizing,
make the entire world that every child should have access to a laptop,
then we won't believe the kind of potential they will have,
and we can't even imagine what kind of problem they are going to solve.
So the program kicked off. Many governments actually came into it.
Unfortunately, the project failed, and one of the reasons, apart from many problems,
one of the reasons is that they actually produced rugged computers at a very cheap rate,
but unfortunately, they did not include maintenance and repairs of this computer when they were planning.
So as a computer, they got bad. The kids, they could not repair them, and this became a very serious challenge.
Now, the question is, will QPython not suffer the same fate?
And my answer is broadly no, because it is not going to be government-sponsored.
Smartphones are acquired, maintained, repaired by who? By the individuals.
And we already have an increasing global penetration of smartphones into our homes.
So smartphones belong to the individual, so we are not going to have issues of repair and all that,
as we have with the one laptop kit.
Of course, this is just a statistic showing that in Africa, the numbers of smartphones are growing.
The reason is this. With $20, I can get a smartphone in Africa.
With $20, I can get a smartphone in Africa, a good one.
And with that one, I can install my QPython. That is the beauty of it, which is not the same as a laptop.
So our goal is to introduce them into remarkable QPython computing capabilities in smartphones.
But how do we do it? The philosophy is simple.
We want to be able to guide the learners, the students and the learners, such that, of course, that is what we are doing,
such that the transition from QPython to Python is straightforward.
So once you are able to learn whatever you want to learn in QPython,
if you have a laptop or any other computer device, it is straightforward.
There. But how are we doing this? I'm still on the philosophy.
We tell you how to install the QPython. Yes, we'll be having issues with this.
First, we started with QPython 2.72. Unfortunately, it does not come with a default indentation.
So you have to start teaching your student how to use the tab and all that, and it was not funny.
Good enough, we now have a higher version, 2.715. That one comes with a natural indentation. That one is for education.
So the problem, in fact, it has many of the functionalities as your normal Python.
So another problem we are having is third-party libraries. In the QPython 2.72, we are able to install NumPy.
But this one will be having issues installing NumPy into it, and we are not able to overcome it.
But when I was coming, I was also having the confidence that I would meet somebody who would be able to tell me that,
look, this is how you can easily do it. Please, if you can, please advise.
Then we teach our students how to use QPython as an advanced calculator.
Yes, before, students in the, maybe in your, what you call your high school here,
they were not allowed to use calculators for some years, but I think for about four or five years now, they now use calculator.
But we are now telling them that, look, your calculator is almost the same size as your smartphone,
and you can actually use your smartphone as an advanced calculator. It can do much more than that.
Then basically, we are coming in as this QPython, using it as an elementary, for elementary programming.
First, we were able to let our students know the difference between Python 2 version and Python 3.
Then we said about the problem we taught third-party libraries and, of course, the NumPy issue and in short.
Now, when we teach, what we let our students know, the difference between smartphones and computers,
we give them the value, of course, of Python in Android emulators.
When we started, of course, in a classroom, we have laptops.
So I said, no, it's going to create problems for me.
Because one of the things where I just make sure, let me just make sure, why I prefer this QPython is that
before when I teach my students, sending assignments is always difficult.
It's not like here, where the internet is free and all that. Sending an assignment is difficult.
But with the QPython now, because with very little amount of money, you can get your phones connected.
So with the QPython, what we are doing now, my student can send the assignment to me easily.
So when I have started this on students thinking with their laptops, okay, no, I want to teach you QPython.
So what we did is that for social data, we use the Android emulators.
We installed the Android emulators into the answer so that it can still work with QPython.
Now we teach them the interpreter, of course, the difference between the interpreter,
the QPython console, the editor, the syntax, and the various statements, Python variables.
These are the key things you want to learn in any Python language.
So the important thing here is that of being for science and engineering,
the model we require is the math model. That is what we use.
So most of the teachings we have been doing is based on this math model,
and how to use it to solve different problems.
So we have the control statement, we have the functions, the data structures, and of course the class.
But even as simple as this, I started a project which we have done before with Python,
before I introduced QPython, and that is how to use the QPython to be able to take an inventory of a lab.
Like you have a lab and you have various equipments.
The ones for mechanics, the ones for electricity, they were all there in the inventory.
So when you go to the small app, you say, what is your name? I'm this. What do you want?
Okay, I want this instrument. Then we say, this instrument is available,
these are the numbers that are available, and you can find it in so and so shapes.
So with this simple thing, our students over the years are able to repeat this simple project.
Then, the focus on the math model, as I said before, we encourage our students to apply their QPython skills to Python codes.
Like, I've taught you QPython now, but there's a difference between using the QPython and the Python.
For example, when we say solve quadratic equations, I'm just taking this simple example,
we use Numpy. Where we use Numpy? We use the polyone deforestation.
The polyone deforestation is a natural thing in Numpy. It will give it a function.
But it's not there in the math lab, in the math model. So how do we do this?
We now ask the students, go and find that. And from there, they were able to see after some time that they can use the lambda expression,
which is for arbitrary function. So without Numpy now, they are able to solve problems,
which of course they use to use just Numpy. They find a way now that they can now use the math lab to solve them.
So the things we do, because it's for science and engineering, we solve things like linear equations, interpolations,
and we also look at ordinary differential equations with Roche-Coutre, and other methods.
What we do here is this. There is a way here. For us to really motivate the students,
there's what I call the paper and pen approach. What is the paper and pen approach?
Allow the students to first solve this thing manually, so that they see the way the computer works.
Sometimes you see a problem that will take you three, four pages. But after developing a code with a touch of your keyboard
or a touch of your smartphone, you see that you can solve the problem.
So the students are able to appreciate what programming is all about.
So these are some of the things we have solved with what? With QPython in our smartphone.
And all this, you can solve them with just the math model.
So what is the outlook here? The outlook is we want a stable version of QPython
with easy means to install scientific third-party libraries like Numpy, SciPy, Simpy, and MathPlotlib.
There was once a situation if we can add the visual Python, because I miss that a lot.
Of course, when I used to teach with Python, one of the things I used to really inspire my students was
look at this program, as simple as it is. You go to Visual Python, you just put sphere with your bracket.
And you see a sphere come. You put color, and it gives you the color. So it used to be fun.
I like what Jeff said. He said he has not seen a program that is radically advancing in such a way that it's possible
he's going to take over other programs. And I'm happy that I'm going to do something with Jeff.
We've already been discussing even before I came here. We hope we'll be able to move that collaboration,
because he's also doing something in Africa.
Another thing is that can we have QPython with compound languages like C++, which is widely used for scientific computation?
Can we have various versions like the Piper and the IOPython?
Can we possibly develop very elegant websites designed to develop various QPython apps on smartphones?
I think these are things people have been asking. And I want answers. If you can provide answers to me,
while I'm around, please, I'll be happy. Because one of the things that is motivating this student is that they say,
can I develop my own application with my hands? I say yes, because Python is multipurpose.
It is used for every purpose. It's not used only for the teaching of physics, as we are doing here now,
but it is multipurpose. So you can begin to develop your own app. And this actually is attaining their interest.
So as part of the outlook, this year, because it's a project I've started the last one year,
and this year I've already been negotiating with the Niger Institute of Physics,
where they will have their conference in September. And in the Niger Association of Mathematical Physics,
they will have their conference in November 2019 on how to have a pre-workshop conference on teaching the teacher.
Here, those who are teachers at this conference, we have two or three days pre-workshop conference on how to teach them
on how to use the handset that is smartphone, QPython. I did a training like that before with the Niger Association of Mathematical Physics,
but I used Python. That was two years ago. So this year now, when we had it, we had issues of having a north space,
having a north space then. But with this one now, I think we'll have that kind of issue.
All they have to come, they come with their smartphones. And as I said, smartphone with about $20,
you can have an Android version that is compatible with the QPython. And that is the beauty of what we are doing.
Thank you very much.
Do you have any time to reach out to the QPython?
No, though I'm on their Facebook, but I've not been able to reach them. But I know they have the opportunity to ask questions, but I know I'm going to reach them.
I'm still having the feeling that if they did, usually at PyCon conference we meet other people. So I will look for them. Yes.
Yes, Jeff.
To follow up on that question, because I'm a big time free software person. So I don't run Android, I run Lineage OS and Ubuntu on my phone.
And so when I tried to install QPython Free on your crack, that was like a showstopper for me after you told me about QPython and I tried it out.
So I'm wondering if we can reach out to the QPython community and see more about fixing problems like that.
Yes, they have QPython 3.6. QPython 3.2, QPython 3.4, they are all working, but they don't have the usual default indentation.
So the educational QPython, that is the 3.6, that one is having issues. And of course the developers, they've come out to see that they have a lot of bugs which are trying to fix.
But the one, QPython 2.7.15, is working perfectly well. Yes.
I have a question. I am from Nigeria.
Oh, yes.
My question is, how are you going to integrate QPython into your
science and technology?
So I did a project in Japan 20 years ago about the EAMC meeting on COVID and I installed it on the QPython.
So how do you, somebody that wants to study in your science, maybe Nigeria, or what do you do out of your project in the U.S.
Okay. We have the National Mathematica Center, Abuja. I hope you are well fit.
And around 2008, I started a conference there. We call it the International Seminar on Theoretical, Physical and National Development.
The thing was to honor one of our very senior professors, Professor Emeritus who taught in many universities in the U.S. here.
Before going back to Nigeria, he has produced a lot of people. So when he was 70 years, then I was in Germany.
I was at Mas Planck Institute of Physics and Complex System where I was in my post-doc. So I decided to organize a conference for him.
After the first one, the second one, in 2010, I added a foundational postgraduate course to it. And that postgraduate course was on Python.
So I have been teaching Python as a part of that seminar, which we have been holding annually since 2008.
And many of the, when I say teaching the teacher, the National Mathematica Center was actually made for teaching the teacher, the teachers.
And I have been teaching Python there. And I think each year people come back. Do you know how people come back?
They will say, look, I met somebody who said he learned Python and he's now using Python for his work, especially the math plot leap.
They use it in plotting their graph and all kinds of things. And it's quite beautiful.
So since 2010, I've been teaching Python at the National Mathematica Center. And I think it has been an overwhelming result.
One last question. So one of the reasons I have been skeptical about the Python community is that both of you know that the students in the Moscow conference,
that way, for the last 30 years, I have a very different view from some of the other students in the faculty.
And there have been some problems because coming from the workforce and there are tech companies where it's very, very difficult to sort of employ your recipe for the complete plan.
So the thing is how do you think that you can suggest for sort of the plans to build a measuring government, to sort of change the curriculum of your project and things like that,
to try to bring things like Python as like, to develop a new design for Python?
You see, what I said is teaching the teacher. That is the first place we have to start from.
Because as you said, yes, many of them, the program they know is what they will stick to. So we tell you they are used to foot-fan and all that and they will stick to it.
But from our past program, we've seen that when you teach them, many of them, they go back and pass a message around that this programming language is good.
And the beauty of it is that they download the whole stuff. I always teach them how to download the whole stuff, you know, without pain and all that.
And this is it. And as you have said, I have had the opportunity of firing a number of people.
Like when I attended this conference in 2012, I attended with one of my students, okay?
And the good thing here is that when you see brain at once like that, you let them have access to the computer. They can do wonderful things.
The young man came here and he got here late. And because of the kind of training I have given to him, they gave him an assignment when he was there and he was the first person to submit.
And that was the first day in the class. So the professor said, wow, so look, how can this young man coming from Africa be the first to submit and he got it correct?
And so this young man has gone on to obtain his master's and his PhD at Sharpman University. So this is the kind of thing.
Then let me just make sure this again. Even within my investing now, I just got an approval from my vice chancellor to organize a workshop on this QPython.
As you know, it's not easy driving these things there. But because anything that has to do with spending money, they will avoid it. This is the problem.
But the beauty of QPython, why I am so excited about it, you don't need to spend a cobol.
The handset belongs to the person. My own is to show them what to do, that there is power in that handset.
You can use that handset to do your programming, to learn your programming anywhere, anyhow, anytime. Thank you.