What about more once we start?
All right, we're gonna get started now.
Yeah, it's been two minutes.
Hi everyone, thank you for coming.
This is the tutorial for analyzing census data with pandas.
If it's not the tutorial, you sign up for it, you can leave.
You don't need to install anything beforehand.
We're gonna be using my binder.
So we're gonna I'm gonna show you the link. It's actually that link up top and then it's gonna send you to
My binder which is distribution binder hub distribution. You pointed it over a github repo
They take all the requirements install it and then you're gonna have a jupyter lab interface on your browser
So you don't need to install anything
I'll show you the the
info for the github repo in a bit if you want to download this stuff and follow along in your own computer
Before we start I got
Some housekeeping notes. There's gonna be a survey link email to you afterwards
About this tutorial how I did
And and there's gonna be a
Snack break at 3 and if you see that I'm not slowing down by like 250 or 245
You can let me know that you're gonna have to go on the fact break soon
So
Let's get started. So who am I? I my name is Sergio Sanchez
I'm a research associate at the Public Policy Institute of California in the higher ed center. So I do
Objective independent nonpartisan research
Mostly on higher ed public policy in California and a lot of the work that I that I do
our work is
Covers developmental education reform, which is which is huge in California right now in community colleges
some stuff about economic mobility and
some stuff about immigration and immigration patterns and people coming in and out of California a
lot of this is based on
Census data, especially the e-com mobility stuff the immigration stuff. There's a lot of data the census collects and
So we're gonna learn some of that
I'm also on my free time
Very interested in data visualization. I am one of the facilitators
the newly formed data visualization society if you're in Twitter on
Looking into the hashtag data is you might have heard of them
I also have a personal project
Called tacos de datos or data tacos where I where it's what I'm doing right now
But in Spanish and try to expand this knowledge and best practices to Latin America and Spain
Some housekeeping you don't need to download anything we're gonna use my binder and also this is like the best room
To be to be in if we're gonna need Wi-Fi at all
So we should be good
But the github repo is here. You can clone it and just CD into it. All we need is
Jupiter and pandas and you can I'm gonna be using Jupiter lab and when we go on my binder
We're gonna be using Jupiter lab, but you can follow along on a jupyter notebook if you're more comfortable doing that
What I just said we're gonna be using Jupiter lab
We're gonna be using my binder like I said, this is
Binder allows you to create custom computing environments that can be shared and used by many remote users
So what I did was put together a github repo I added a directory there with our requirements
Txt file or environment that yamo file for a conda environment
And then you go to my binder dot org dot org you point it at your github repo
They're gonna take that grab all the materials there install the dependencies and then you can have a
Jupiter interface a jupyter notebook a jupyter lab
They have our studio now too and even shiny apps
But you can have a lot of stuff and it's free movie free it's a great resource
So census data this is gonna be I'm gonna do a quick
Presentation talking about census data and when we when we what they have and some packages in Python that are
Very popular to to download and access this data and then we're gonna get started on the tutorial
So the US census conducts more than 130 surveys every year
They have household surveys with data on education employment health
migration income levels
Just a lot of stuff facilities how if you have access to the internet if you have access to
running water
Just all types of stuff is it's a lot and I'm just gonna show you real quick
So under census on census gov you can see all the information about their data
These are some of the household surveys and you could spend a lot of time going through every single one of them
They have stuff on education and children's health college graduates
fishing hunting wildlife
So it's just a massive amount of information the census has available for you for all of us for free
They also have
They also have business surveys they go out and survey retail
All types of businesses and they have statistics on entrepreneurship
The important export stuff on the microeconomic level which is kind of like what's more commonly known when you hear about in the news
Oh, we have a trade deficit with X and X country
But they also have like monthly retail sales
So if you want to
If you're thinking about starting a business in certain part of the country and you're like, oh, I don't know if I should have here
I'm cutting next over and you can you can find a lot of information about
the market
Where you might want to start business
One of the most popular household service is the American commuter survey they do it every year since
2006 I believe and it's one of the
And it's one of the the best sources of information when it comes to population
in the US and it's
You can you can look at this data up to all the way down to like census tracts in some areas
Depending on how many people live in some parts of the country, but you can get like very fine
Data out of out of this and this is all completely free completely open
And we're gonna this is actually what we're gonna be studying we're gonna be analyzing today a subset of the American community survey
So, how do you get this information how do you get all this data from the census
I'm gonna show you two or three ways to do it. They have what's called the American fact-finder and
This is a curated website. You can you can shop here
And they have tables already prepared for you and a lot of statistics
Again age business and industry from the business
surveys
Poverty levels there's poverty measuring poverty can get really complicated
So they have a lot of different measures
race ethnicity
veterans and
You can click on any of these
I have a
A lot of information and you can you can modify this table move it around and just like I'm not interested in
In this one variable or this other variable
And you can start curating your own tables if that's
You need it for any type of research that you're looking for
I
Am going to faz you can tell me slow down if you have any questions just raise your hand
They also have tables
Pre-populated pre-computed tables kind of like American fact-finder American fact-finder just puts them all together in one nice
place, but they have
These pre-populated tables that are very common
in
journalism or in certain certain research
areas where you all you need to do is
Find out like the median income of X County or X
Are you going to compare?
historic levels of income and
Every single county of the US and they have
They have them ready to go and because they because these are computer by the census they have access to
The whole census data when we're looking at things like the ACS and stuff that we can get
They obviously for privacy reasons you cannot get access to to the whole data file you can get
What's called a sample a public use?
micro-sample
pumps
And but these are calculated from the total
Data so these if what you're looking for is
Can be found in one of these tables this could this would be more accurate, and I'm just going to show you
One of them so you can see
Detail
I'm not gonna open it
But all these tables are also found in American fact-finder. That's that's what they're doing instead of you downloading an excel file
you can just go to American fact-finder and if you know the
The table that you're looking for the information that you're looking for
You can just
Even just Google it and by that by by that I mean these tables don't are not named
gender
Statistics by state or they're not named educational attainment by
County they're called like B
15003 e
underscore L and
Then underscore underscore 2l and underscore 3l for all the variations
Another place which is actually my favorite place to get this type of information it bumps or I pumps
They provide census and survey data from a world around the world integrated across time and space
Which is huge they they harmonize all these surveys and
They make it so you can just choose
one variable for internet access for example, which is what we're gonna be looking at later on today and
If the census changed the way they ask the question or if they change the answers that you could give
And they started grouping one
All these answers like back in 2005 they didn't ask much about
If you have if you access the internet through your phone a lot
So that eventually changed because the census wants to keep an accurate kind of all this of all this information
And it pumps what they do is harmonize these variables
So you can get one variable and you know, that's the variable that you want
The change the answers might change a little bit but they make it so you can handle the data
This is kind of how it looks and I
Recorded this as a gift just in case I couldn't show you but I see that the wife is doing great
So I'm going to show you a little quick what this looks like
on their website
which is
I pumps that org
And they have I
Cannot stop talking how amazing these people are they have a lot of surveys not just about census data
They have health data
This one I have not had I don't have an excuse to use but they have geographical data and
You can make a lot of cool maps and you can find they have all these shape files for
Whatever you might want to look at not just for the US but other countries around the world across time
so I was just they have
another resources and webinars and I was I was just
Watching the webinar they did on
Ipams international and they they they mentioned
Just like oh, yeah, we also have
harmonized shape files for countries
like Kenya and they showed the example how they put it together and then Kenya has run through some political changes and
They'll take care of they'll take care of all that for you so you don't have to
do some data all the data
Magic to do to find out a way
To harmonize all these variables across time
So this is kind of how it looks like and this is how I got the data set that we're gonna be working on
today
You can you can send this section select harmonized variables you can look at person level statistics
Look how many sections we have and each of them have
Like nine at least
Um
Variables there's a lot of information here. I'm always here on the education and you can see that I'm always happy
This is what I do. I work it
But and they'll show you here for example
You can see the years they have it for some of these years though. They just stopped the question and it just there's no way you can
Have something equivalent for today's
Age but this is a great resource if you're interested in and census data and they everything is free
And they're really great if you have a question you can just email them
So, how do you get this data using Python
There's a few packages at PIPI related to census data
There's more than I thought it was just gonna be like one someone like me. I was just like I'm tired
I'm going to have them so all the time. I just want to get it
But no, there's there's many
Packages on PIPI you can just pip install any of these I'm going to show you four
Notable ones and two of these actually got from a newsletter from the census they they
I'm not saying they're promoting them or that they
Then they are pushing those packages, but they they know they exist and they're okay with
sharing them in their newsletter
So the easiest one census
Is
Literally just PIP install census and then you can get access to
The Census Bureau's API and
It has it provides access to ACS, which is what the American Community Survey
SF one is a summary file and summer SF three are so many files for the decennial
censuses and
You can spend a lot of time just talking about the different ways the census
Summarizes their their findings, but most of the time for high-level stuff
You just look at the ACS which is the most accurate. It's every year
And not every ten years
This is as easy as it gets you just pip install census you you get an API key from the census
Website and then this is what I was talking about if you know the name of your table
be 25034
Underscore zero one zero e which is obviously something about education
You can tell her
Then you can just ask for for that table for
The states for example, this this is what's asking for
You can do that by County by congressional
district
They have what what are called Puma's public use micro area. I think
Which are like tiny tiny area geographical areas where you have like 10,000 people I think so in big cities or
States with high populations you can get like really
Granular data and you can see almost like block to block
differences
but
obviously everything
They do a great job at keeping things private and in this answer so they'll you won't be able to find anything
Too crazy hopefully senpai, which is another
Another wrapper which is is based on an R package ACS
And now I'm gonna the github repo has a link has this presentation show. This is a jupyter notebook
so you're gonna have access to all these links and
I'm just gonna show you they have an intro notebook
So
It's as easy as again you
You ask for the decennial census file summary file or the ACS
I think they do ACS and the cool thing about this one is that it returns
Pandas data frames, which is always nice. I think census might return
like a list of dictionaries
which you can still read into pandas fairly easily, but
You can just get a pandas data frame done
That's great
Next and we're almost done with this and then we can get started
Census data downloader. This is actually a CLI a command line interface by the Los Angeles Times
Data disk they they're doing a lot of cool stuff with Python and open source and open data
All you need again is a an API key from the census and they're pretty quick if you go to a website use if you
Request an API key you're gonna get one
Most likely in the next five minutes. They'll just gonna email you one
All you need to do for this one. Just export your census API key as an environment variable and then you can then start using
their CLI
Tool just off your terminal and what this does is download it downloads
That ugly name
Table be three to underscore something something
And then they'll reformat it so the columns actually make sense and the name of the table makes sense and you can actually read it
They it's it's a version like 0.05. I think it's very early and they have but they have a lot of tables already
Put together so you can just ask for median age or educational attainment
Not just in states but in counties in the counties of just one state
Etc and the last one which is
one of my favorites who it's called census data and
This is the most
Pythonic one. I would say out of all of them. They they really make it
So that it's very Python friendly if you don't Python on any other
Much work in any other way before I'm doing data analysis with pandas
They they have a class
for census geographies you can create
These queries and it gets it's really great
if we have time by the end of the
workshop, we're gonna
Do an example of how to use census data to get to recreate what we what we did on
The workshop
This is the last line that was supposed to be the last line. This is laughing. This is very last thing. Let's analyze some sensitive
but I
Okay, so now we're gonna actually start get started with the workshop you all you need to do is go on this link
It's all caps
bidley census
Census-data-pycon 2019
I'm gonna write it over here just to make it easier for everyone to read and that's gonna send you that's gonna take you to
My binder so we can get started
Analyzing some census data
And you have any questions
Is it working for everyone yeah, okay
And this is how this is how my binder looks like you
I
Get this is already pointing at my the the github repo I put together beforehand
But if you go to my binder or it's gonna ask you
the link for the github repo and you can even point it to a
Specific notebook file or any file and you get a repo and it's gonna open it by default
Which is what you should be looking at right now. It's gonna be it should open to the
first notebook
prepping data
to do perfect
Presentation you don't need to do that. I'm doing this because I'm
Okay
So if you're not familiar with the jupyter lab interface over here you have a
Your files and you can go all the way to home. This is what the github repo looks like
These are folders you have the readme file
Maybe double click on the readme file is gonna show you the the raw text
But you can right click on any file and then it's gonna actually give you the options on how to open things
This works
for notebooks to if you want to open a notebook in
Editor way, I'm not gonna do that because I want to set up
But you could see the actual Jason representation of your notebook
Here are your your sessions we have open a
Kernel for our notebook
Over here you have some other stuff that we're not gonna be looking at today
But it's
So let's get started we're gonna be
Trying to recreate this fact sheet some of my colleagues at PPAC put together
specifically this one
There's one chart and these three bars
Because I didn't want to put like a huge data file and
But what we what we're looking at what we're looking to recreate is this
part
How many households in X state and you can choose your own state the data is for all the US but
I've set it up. So you choose whatever one and they should all work the same
how many households in a certain state have access to
broadband
high-speed internet, which seems to be
very important nowadays and how does that
vary across racial ethnic groups
We can even look more into
What we're gonna start you see but we can even divided by
How many
House households with school-aged children have access to the internet they need internet for school now
So as a policy person
To be very useful information
Okay, so let's get started
any questions so far
you want to hear me can anyone see the
Screen
Okay, so this is pretty much how I set up
Notebook where I'm gonna start I usually divide it into a data prep
notebook and an analysis notebook because if I
Start analyzing something and I'm gonna figure I messed up something in the preparation of my file
I would like to just fix that and
Have to rerun everything so modularizing your your workflow is always great
I've set up these research questions
For us to answer what share of a household in X state have access to high-speed internet and
Does this not mean number of area cross demographic groups and in this case, we're gonna be looking at race ethnicity
and
I usually and these are some tips and these are personal tips
You don't have to follow this if you have a better workflow
The it's up to you, but this is something I found to be like the very basic
standard
Good way to organize myself. I'll have a notebook. I'll set up
The project or the project name that I'm working on
What is this notebook doing prepping? What am I doing? If I'm researching anything? These are my research questions
What's the goal of this notebook?
This notebook I want to explore my
Master file the raw data file that I got from the census and I'm gonna create a working data
So I'm gonna grab whatever I think is useful from that
Create another data set. That's the one I'm gonna be working with because I don't want to touch the raw data
I don't want to modify that in case I mess up and I need to go back to it
The context is I this is huge and even if you don't put this in your regular workflow
I would suggest that you do this because in three months or in three even three weeks
I'll go back to a notebook all back to the work that I was doing and I have no idea why I was doing anything
that I have here and I
might look at
like some cool thing that I figure out how to do and then it's just lost forever because I
Remember what I was doing it why I was doing it that way
So just putting a little bit of context at the very top of your notebook is always nice
So again, so we're gonna get started and I've set up a
Lot of the code and as we as we progress through the notebook
There's gonna be less and less code that I have put there for you
and you're just gonna have to
Type it yourself
But I wanted to set this up because
I'm doing
This is something that I do on every notebook
And this is essential to the rest of the notebooks to make sure that we all are working in the same place at the same pace
and we get the same
variables and
The same
Workflow sorry
So the very first thing we're gonna do is obviously set up our environment import whatever we're gonna need
We're gonna use obviously pandas that's in the title of the tutorial
We're gonna use path live has anyone worked with path live before
You it's it's a great tool because when and I'm sure there's other ways
But I use it because I have this my personal computers at MacBook
My work computer is a Windows and they use different
slashes
Yeah, so it just if I write if I write something and that has to do with paths in my regular computer
And my personal computer might not work on my work computer or vice versa
And path live what it does is it creates these path file objects and they just work on
On unix I mean on Linux on Mac OS on Windows they just they just work
Which is great
also this daytime tip of importing daytime and
Then creating a today variable so you can tag your your data files
Is great tagging your data files or tagging your your work with just the date is not I mean we have version control
But when you're doing data
There's still version control systems for for big data files
But this is a great first step. Just make sure that that you can differentiate
Between the files that you're you're working with
and
I did not come up with that daytime tip. I found it online and I forgot to save the link
So if you know
Someone posted this
From daytime import daytime as DT. So you're not confused with so many daytimes
Call daytime calls on your code
Find on Twitter. Yeah, I saved me a ton of time and confusion
So if you're that person or if you know that person you can give them a high five for me
So I'm gonna give you two minutes and I want you to try to figure out what's happening here. You're gonna import the
The the libraries
You're gonna create a today variable
Which should change from April 27th to May 1st?
And you don't have I mean I'm using
if you haven't worked with daytime that I just put that together for you, but you if you know what you're doing with the
daytime object with the
string f time
You can change it however you want the first the percent D is giving you the 27 and then I added the dash
Percent B is giving you the month with the abbreviated way with the with the actual name of the month
Dash percent Y is giving you a two two digit year
If you do capital Y you can get four digit year
I
Am gonna give you two minutes to work on that and then I'm gonna stop talking I keep talking
Okay, so if you don't have a kernel you can over here and the refresh
Symbol you can restart a kernel and if you don't have a kernel it might ask you to
To choose a Python 3 was the only one that we have if not you can refresh the page my binder will like
Will stop working for you if you have ten minutes of an activity and I'm sure I've been talking for more than ten minutes
And these are not the actual names of the paths you you you need to change those
You don't want a path name called xxx
You can name is something intuitive like be three zero four underscore, yeah
You
Yeah
Our is he and if you go on the
Okay, I'm gonna start working on my version over here you don't have to follow exactly what I'm doing
You don't have to name them the same thing
But that's what the rest of the notebook kind of assumes you're gonna be doing so if
You don't want to think too much about it you can just copy these
And I got this structure from again not me I did not come up with this
Cookie cutter reproducible science
Someone put together a basic structure for reproducible science
Projects
MK rap and this is the basic structure which has worked great for me a
Lot of this I don't need because I for example. I'm not using at work. I'm not producing a lot of
Code is really just a few pandas
Notebooks. Oh, yeah, sorry
But this is this is a great resource
This is this is a cookie cutter repo, but this is by MK rap cookie cutter dash reproducible dash science
and
You can just once you pip install cookie cutter you can use it from the command line
Cookie cutter and then you can you don't have to do this if you don't for some reason my computer never works for this
HTTPS that github.com
Slash MK rap slash this is gonna ask you a bunch of questions. Who are you? What license do you want to use?
What's the name of the project all that stuff and then it's gonna create this for you
So this is why I'm using the external interim processed and raw
Structure in this project. It's it's worked out great for me
Especially this part just having
A directory with raw files that I know I should not touch look I got this from I pumps I got this from the census
this is
Original immutable data
What if I do something to it? I'll save it on interim or processed if I'm done processing it and
Yeah, so just another tip
You speak different
Yes, okay, so external what the way I've been using this and this is obviously all
For whatever you think works best for you. This is just a template. But what I've been doing for external is
I use
Now national
Center for education statistics data and then I'll get it from another place that kind of pre-process it
And then puts it in a nice format for me
So I know it's not raw data that I got exactly from them or if a colleague put together
Like an extract of something else
So I know it's not raw data because it's not directly from the source and it's been processed but not by me
So I don't have it. So I don't have a notebook over here that
Created that or over here in source
But then again, this is all whatever you think works best for you
Let's go back to
This
All right, I also included this tree function
From in this script over here. All it does is displays the tree
This place a tree a directories tree so you can see what files you have there
You could do the same going over here going on your exercises you go on data
You want to see what's in the raw file and the raw folder? Oh, here it is
So all I'm gonna do is from tools
Which is that script that I have in my same folder with my notebooks over here exercises
notebooks
I'm gonna import that function tree
so I can then use it and
And then I want to see the raw
Data path and you should be able to tab autocomplete
They're not just run this oh I did not run it
Another way to check that if you're doing the right thing is
Yeah
Oh
Tab autocomplete if you spell if you start spelling your variable tab autocomplete should
Know there you go you click tab
It gives you the variable if you have not declared the variable if you declare it a different way
You know, you're doing something wrong if the tab autocomplete is not working
So this is the data we have we have ACS data and I have it in DTA format and CSV format
And they're both compressed
It booms will give you
compressed data files by default
Which is what you want. You don't want to it's just easier
Step two we're gonna load the data into a data frame into a variable
I've provided you here the code, but this is just markdown
So I have this here and blank so you can type that up
The main lesson here is that
CSV
Format pan this is really good with CSV format format files
And you don't need to give it any other parameter if you're working with a compressed CSV file
Just hand you just give it the path. Oh and this oh, this might be confusing the raw data path and
Then slash and then the name of a file
And then the name of a file
Ultimately, I'm gonna give you an example here it joins them. This is how you join. There's one way to join
Yes, this is why it's so awesome
No, no, that's the thing it just it just knows
It just knows it's the magic of path loop
So that's that's a that's that's what's happening there if you
Which is why I was included this tree
Object this tree function because you want to know what what's going on here pandas by default if you want to
If you start giving it a path if you start giving it a path you can start you can tap autocomplete
and
It just knows but if you're like just to make a more reproducible across platforms
It's better if you use path live
But if you're using path live you don't get that tab auto complete and you're in your file path right away for with pandas
So I'm gonna start
So if you over here you couldn't go ACS tab
It just doesn't work with with path live like this
but
They did that head and what data that I mean
What that head is doing to your pandas data frame is asking you for the head of the pandas data frame
Asking you for it's gonna display the top five elements the first five rows
It might take a while because the file is like 20
20 20 gigabytes 20 megabytes
You can put 20 gigabytes
And you can I mean I try to make this as
Independent have this workshop be as usable as it can by itself
so I that's why I have so much text and
Trying to describe what I'm repeating here what I'm saying out loud here and it should match more or less
What's written in the notebook? So if you want to go back later or?
Tomorrow or in a few days, or you want to send it to anyone this should more or less
Stand on its own
Yeah
This one this one
Okay. Yes. So what exactly so has anyone tried the first one loading up CSV? Yes. Oh
You're okay. Sorry
Okay, so we're gonna move on to the next one so
Ipams like I said it gives you
data in G zip format it's
Compressed and it's very easy to to work with special in Python Python has G zip
in the center library so you can just import G zip and
open a G zip file just load it up and
You're completely right this code it might be confusing if you mess up
This very this first one or if you change the name over here
Because for the rest of the notebook I'm gonna assume that your data is saved to a variable data
And what this is doing is overriding the last one
So
Let's make sure that we get we get this one right
And here I have a little explanation on why we're using the the DTA file if you go to a pumps
When you're selecting your data at the very end you can choose what format you want it in
You can get in CSV format you can get in its data DTA you can get it on SAS and
SPSS
Which path pandas has functions to read to?
But I've worked with with data
I started economics and this is what a lot of people use and if you're doing anything with census data or any
Social that anything that people in the social sciences might be working with state. Is is very common
So a DTA file is very common and I mean it's coming up that pandas has a just read it's data
function to
Okay, so I'm gonna get
Going over here. We have 50 minutes to finish this one hopefully
Import GZ this is important because I I
Kept doing this practicing this notebook, and I always forget to import GZ
Yeah
Which is about signal but time because I wrote this and I still forget to do it
But just make sure that you're importing
GZ before
Then data equals PD reads data
And then you're passing it that file
Object that you're creating you're
Starting with this
And then I'm gonna ask you to display the first five rows like we did just a few cells above
I
We're gonna be using the DTA file for the rest of the notebook so that it's more important to get the state of file working
Ready to load it and we display it first five rows ahead. Yes
I noticed that there's a PD dot reads data
Yes
For this for this one oh
For the right if you do it directly to
For this one yes this one you cannot direct you can you cannot read a
GZip compressed file directly because the read state of function just cannot do that
but
Yes, they have a reads data and have a to state
So even if you're working with CSV files, and then eventually you want to just save it as a DTA file
You can just instead of saving it that PD to I mean data to CSV you can use data to state
And
This is
One of the main benefits of working with a state of file from a pumps if you go up here
This is what your CSV file looks like
One zeros
Once 20s just numbers for the codes in your data
Which you can then match with the data dictionary you can just grab those and then just rename all your your values
so they match something but a
state of file
has embedded
What they call it value labels, so pandas will read those as categorical variables
categorical columns which under the hood are also are still
Zeros and ones but it will display them as
their actual value
Which saves you a ton of time because if you save this
column state fit as
a
bunch of strings
That would take a lot of memory
I mean maybe not a lot but it will take a lot more memory than
It would if you save it as a categorical in a state of file or as just a bunch of int
Or floats and then just have your data dictionary somewhere else and just working with the state of file and puts it all together
But it is a different type of data so we just need to be aware of
Of that we can still compare it like it's a string and we'll see some other ways we can compare stuff in the category
categorical
variables later on so now we're moving on to step three
There are three functions that I am suggesting here that you use
But you're deducing them yourself, I'm not telling you what the functions are
So I'm just gonna give you two minutes to to fill out these two these three steps, and then we can talk about what?
What each of those is doing?
I'm gonna be walking around if you have any questions you can just
We say
I
Will do this info
Describes over here and shape
All right
As I knew as everyone done these three at least as some people going ahead
So what do you think info?
Is giving you
From from your data frame. What are these?
Yeah, this is giving you the columns the total of your columns and the type
Each of your columns is and you may notice
Things like age here
It's still a category and
Not an int which is a little weird, but we'll see that later
There in the notebook even year two is a category
So sometimes it has its ups and downs and you just got to be aware
It's always good to run info on your data from just so you know, you're aware what each of the types of your columns is
Describe what do you think describe is doing?
Exactly and is and because you cannot run a standard deviation or get the mean of
Not a number
So you only get the the quantitative columns that you have here
So if you go up here, you'll notice serial is in 32
Household weight which is what this represents. It's also an int
county FIP
Per num, which is persons number and persons weight
These are statistical weights not the actual person's weight that'd be weird
And it will run basic statistics for you on all the quantitative variables if you want to
Just grab one. You can just pass one column here and just be like, oh, we'll just give me
HHW
Yes, okay. I wasn't 100% sure
And what do you think shape is giving you?
Yes, it's the shape of your data frame and rows and columns and if you these
Pandas is built on non-py and non-py
You can have like a lot more
Dimensions in your data and it will give you instead of just rows and columns
They can give you if you run shape on a non-py array of like many dimensions. It will give you all those
dimensions
All right. So we now know more or less what our data looks like
What its types are?
we can start moving on to
Cutting off all the extra that we don't want or what we don't need
And that's exactly what what's in the text so you can try this try the following
That's my suggestion. That's what I'm gonna be doing up here, but you can choose whichever state you want and if you choose any other state
You're gonna have different
Oh
Statistics and different numbers for the rest of the notebook
But it should all the mechanics should be the same and you should be able to to run the code the same just
Just choose a different state
Or district of Columbia yet
You spell out a district of Columbia not just DC
I
Shouldn't have run that actually it's gonna be a surprise
You
I'm gonna get going because we have 35 minutes for snack time
When you run this code when you
Compare two values
What on a column in pandas which is
What pandas calls a series which is a long array?
You non dimensional zero dimensions. All right, so when you're comparing it or doing
math on a upper adding a comparing to an operator
Was if you're comparing like this you get you're gonna get
Oh my god, sorry it will return an array of the same size of
Booleans and it's gonna tell you true if it matches the condition that you passed or false if it did not
Like this because I'm using Ohio which is right in the middle, let me see if I try all about
Oh
So if I try Alabama it's gonna grab the because Alabama's all the way to the top isn't on the zero index you can see
This array starts with truth. So each of these
rows
Their state fib column matches the word Alabama and
You can use then this array
as what
I think it's this is in the pandas docs. They use they call it a mask
So you're gonna you can use then this mask of trues and falses
I'm just gonna keep it out
Trues and falses as a mask to grab certain rows of your
Full data frame. So if you if you pass something like this
You can use this array
to get the same size data state fib
Alabama
This I'm just saving what all this array that I got over here
We're saving it to the variable mask state and I like and I like starting on my
variables that I'm gonna use as masks or filters
Or if I'm gonna be filtering out on the household weight
Variable or any other variable like the age or
Gq which are group quarters
I'm going to
Name each of those variables mask underscore
Gq condition or mask underscore age
To keep track of that and because once later on if I want to use it I can just mask underscore
Tab and I'm gonna see all the filters that I've created all the masks that I have created
I'm gonna use head to look at it and this is just an example of what's happening here
Actually, Alabama is not a great example because this is the first five rows anyways
So this is what's happening I'm grabbing that array of
Booleans and I'm passing it to my data frame
with these square brackets and
That tells pandas
Match the in the these the indices
The index here and then just grab me the rows that that are true
I'm using Ohio. So this is slightly different than over here
But all is this is doing is go to the zero index on both the data data frame. I'm not my mask
All right, if it's true, give me the row
It's not
Then don't show it to me
So that's one way to filter out to slice data to they call it Boolean indexing
So we're gonna save it to
I'm gonna save this same thing that I got here mask state data with a mask
I'm gonna save it to another variable
And over here I go into a little bit of a description of why you should add this last part that copy
when you're assigning a
subset of a data frame saving it to another data frame when you're actually
Saving
From the pandas doc documentation is what they call a view of the other data frame
So to save memory is kind of like pointing at the same thing and that can have unintended consequences later on if you're then if you then
Yeah, if you start modifying your data on the second data frame or on the first one
I have not found a bunch of I
have not found a lot of
Trouble doing this when I forget but you will get a warning every single time if you if you try doing this
Just state data give me the data mask
Right now it saves but then if I do state data
Then you you can add a new column
Oh you see this I use data too much
Another column equals five
This is the type of stuff this this is what what I try to do here is create a new column and then assign a 23 to
all of them
But you're gonna get this
warning
You're trying to set it on a copy of a slice of a data frame of another data frame
try
using .loc
Because this is gonna actually assign values to to the data frame
so when you when you got
Something like this when you have a data frame
Called data you pass it a mask and you're gonna you create in a subset from that data frame onto another
Just make sure you use copy and sometimes you don't even need it
We're just talking
Over here you might get
If you're doing state state state data and instead of data you have already something
Set up and you're creating a subset of that's of its own thing and then just overriding the first variable
You don't necessarily need to to add copy
Because you're overriding and you're completely
Forgetting about the first one, but it's always good practice and it doesn't it doesn't hurt it doesn't
Make panda slower or anything
So we're gonna save
That data
With a mask state
Save it as a copy
And then
Now let's see what columns we have in our data frame and how do you think we would do that?
Anyone how would you ask that column?
You could just do
state data that had
But a lot of the times especially I mean, this is a very small subset of the American Community Survey and sometimes I want to have
race ethnicity educational attainment age
What else can have
Merital status
Nativity status
So it's gonna have a lot more columns that you could show in the data frame
Just in a cell here
So you can just do dot columns and it's gonna give you a list
Oh
Perfect this is the type of stuff that you
Just learn working with the data it bombs has this thing called these are the harmonized variables race
hispan for hispanic and
relate as it for the relationship between the person in the observation
to the household to the head of the household and
related race
raised and hispan
Are the detailed variables so you can see let me show you super quick
You could see
State data
Raised
I
Show I'm just gonna show you
Head if you if you pass a parameter to the head
Call it's gonna show you that many
Rows by default. It will show you five if you want to see
15 for example, you just pass it 15 and and it will show you 15 rows and here we can see
Oh
Okay, so this one this one works you can see in the race
column you're gonna have something like three or more major races because
There's a lot of combinations that would satisfy three or more major races. But if you're going to race D you can actually see
The three or more races that that person identifies us a lot of times. We'll just work with race
Hispan because you don't want to I mean this could get really granular for race that you can have a lot of different combinations
same thing with relate
Let me see
Other non relatives 1990 employers
Challenge. Okay, you cannot really see on this one, but you can get
children for child there's many definite there's many
Detailed definitions and they'll they'll get like very specific especially because old censuses
had like very weird ways of asking for stuff and they'll they'll be like
Adopted adopted child from previous marriage or adoptive child from somewhere else and like all different types of of children
But you don't really need that to differentiate their own
children here
Okay
Okay, so here I gave you a space to show you how you can drop columns
It's as easy as just dot drop and then you give it the columns you give it a list of columns
So if I wanted to drop those race the
Hispan D
Related
No, it's columns and
This will return
your whole data frame
But without those columns, so if you want to save this you would have to save it to another variable
But you don't have to do that yet just yet because well unless you're completely sure of the columns that you're dropping
And this is why I
Might be on the next one
Yeah, you can sometimes and some of these you can always do
Not not in everything you can do in place equals true and it's just gonna save it to itself. I saw a talk by I
Don't remember his name, but he's one of the core developers in pandas and he said not to use in place because it just has some
unintended consequences sometimes
So that's why I'm not included here, but yeah, you could just do in place
for some of these especially a drop or
in reset index is kind of
common
What do I have in I mentioned here that you should drop columns only if you're
If you're over like 90% sure you're not gonna need it
Especially because this data set is not particularly huge is not gigabytes and gigabytes of data
So you don't mind just having an extra column that you might ignore just down the road
If you're dealing with gigabytes of data, then you might just be like, okay
Well, there's no way I can have an extra column because it's gonna take an extra hour to run this
But just just in this
I would just drop those if I'm 90% sure and this is the value of having
the raw directory and the process or interim directory
because sorry again
because if you drop those columns and then you save it back to the original file and you just lost those and
The and it's just good practice to have to keep in mind. This is my raw data directory. There's the original files. I'm not
modifying those
Ever I got these and then whatever I do. I'm gonna save it somewhere else
Okay, so now we're gonna explore
GQ which stands for group quarters
Which are
Group living arrangements is what they call so such as rooming houses or military barracks
dorms and colleges
certain institutional living arrangements
We go more in depth over here but essentially if there's like five or more people
unrelated to each other
That live in one place. It's considered a living quarter
by census standards
But we want to see here is the unique values of your GQ variable
This is gonna return a list of the
The unique values in that
Array and some extra information. So now you can see here
We knew that it was a categorical variable
This this tells you
That you can see here
That you can see here that you can see here that you can see here that you can see here that you can see here that you can see here
This this tells you
Yeah, these are the unique values this is these are the categories that GQ has and if you look further over here
You can see this this is particularly interesting
This means these are ordered
Categories so you you you can then ask for comparison as like give me
a state data where GQ is less than
Additional households under 1990 definition and that's gonna that's gonna run
Because this is a categorical variable if it was strings
There's no way you can say oh this string is greater than this other string
but because it's categorical variable a category categorical column and
Because it's an ordered categorical column
Not all categorical columns can our order but this one is you can then have these greater than or less than
comparisons between
strings or values
And they're super
Optimized because under under the hood these are just numbers. These are like one one two, three four five and
It's just you that can see the value labels
So it's like comparing two two integers
We can also use this over here value counts, I'm kind of rushing because we have snack break in 15 minutes
But I can slow down if anyone needs me to
You can also do this value counts on the same on a on a column
state data GQ and what do you think is gonna give you
If you ran it you can just tell us
What do you expect is gonna
Yes, exactly it's gonna give you the counts for each of the values in your series that you're passing
So this
Just counts everything all the about it has we already know they has five values. So it just counts
each instance of each of those values
So now we know we have
112 thousand households under the 1970 definition of household which I included here from the impums documentation
This can get a little confusing sometimes when we're working with weighted data
we're working with a sample of the Americans Community Survey and
Each observation has household weights and person weights. That means each observation
Actually represents more than one person. These are not
112,000 households
These are 112,000
Observations and that's one of the main differences between between weighted working with weighted data
Working with census data because we never really get access to the whole data file
So this because because our data is a sample of the total
You
See this over here
HHWT
That's a household weight that tells me that this line is
representing five fifty five households
So each observation each line in my data file is not one household and it's not one person
This person is a head householder. He's a male. He's 79. He's white and
He has no internet access and his host and his house apartment or blah blah
Which falls under the household on?
definition from 1970
He's in Ohio on a I think zero means like we it's not
It's like no and this person is
representing
55 people
So instead of having 55 the same of fairly similar
Observations they just group them all into one
Because also they don't want to give you like each person's actual answers for the community survey
So this so if we wanted to find out like the share of
Households that have access to internet we could just like and in each of those was already one one observation was one household
This could just give us the numbers and then we can just run
Well, I have this many
Just add them up and then give me the ones that fall under X
Value over here. It's a high speed or sineth
the internet access one
But because we're working with weighted data, we have to do other stuff
And then we're gonna
So anyone with me everyone with me so far
We're gonna have break in like ten minutes and you can
Get snacks and then come and talk to me
You have more questions so what we're gonna create here
Is another mask just like we did earlier with the state. We want to create a mask with two conditions
so
in for our data what we want to do is
grab the households that fall under the 1970 definition and
Those that fall under the 1990 definition and here is the explanation if you're interested
In the 1970s the limit was five or more if you have five or more people living
unrelated people
Living in one place your group quarter your your
building slash house slash
Apartment is a group quarter in 1990. They bumped it up to ten people. So if there's ten people
Living in a housing unit and they're all related to each other
Then it's a group quarter
but starting 2000
They stopped the limit now. They have a list an actual list somewhere in the census
where they where they that's continuously maintained by the Census Bureau and
if you if your
Housing unit which would be considered a group quarter under under these other definitions is not in that list
they're gonna count it as a household and
It's not a lot as you can see here that it's only 20 observations in our data
But if we want to be as accurate as possible, we just wouldn't count those
Under what we what we think of a household
so I'm gonna give you two minutes and
I'm gonna set up the first one
You're doing the same thing state
You you you're creating a comparison that's gonna return something
And you're creating another condition for another value this looks pretty much the same
Yeah, that's the thing about categorical data if it's a long definition you have to type out
the whole thing
Oh and don't read ahead because that's the answer that's a tip to make it
You
Okay, and I'm just gonna give you the answer for this one because it's a little confusing what I'm suggesting you do here is
Create a copy like we mentioned earlier
This is that
Example I gave you earlier because we're
grabbing state data
Passing in a mask so it's gonna be a subset of itself and then we're saving that to the variable state data
Which means we're overriding it. We don't need to add the dot copy at the end
Because we're just completely forgetting about the original
But it doesn't affect it and it's just good practice is there something I try to do myself
So I won't forget when I actually have to do the dot copy
Oh
Yeah, I get it sometimes but I didn't this time I when I did it in my my earlier
I got the same thing, but all it's doing is
Just matching the index and the indexes and the C's
These are the index
They're meaningless to us. So it doesn't doesn't really affect it and all it's doing is just
Making sure they match like we're changing one of these I think the mask household because it's gonna be trues and falses
Let me see
On state data, I mean you you
You could let me see
You
You can if you do that index is gonna give you the index
Tweeting
Yeah, no, I'm not a conclusion what's happening I got the same morning earlier
And if I if I find out I'll add it to the repudging just add a note but it's not I'm not getting it. Yeah
Yes, that's exactly right the
this serial
Means is the serial number of the household under the census standards on the American Community Survey standard
So if you see here
These two have the same house they have the same serial
so there is a head householder male 79 and
his spouse female 79 in
This one household
That's that's all he's doing and the serial number is what we're gonna we keep that we need that
That's why I mentioned though, if you're not 90% sure don't drop it
If you dropped it
We're just gonna have to get it again because the serial number is what keeps that tells you which household is which
Yes, so these are not like
It's not an actual house somewhere that has a serial number that the census have saved. This is just the way to track
Same household throughout like for different observations and a lot of the times when we're working with
Individual level data we might just drop all that like we don't care the house
All we care is the person's weight and how many people?
Count but because what we're looking at today is how many households have
Access to the internet to high-speed internet
We keep these
This household level variables
We have this that's good the serial number is is what but we're gonna need later on
Okay, so we created this we created a copy and now we have
A
Working data set our state underscore data
You might you might have saved it as something else now. We only have one state
We dropped all the other 49 and or the district of Columbia, Columbia and
We kept we dropped all the group quarters. We kept only households
So now we can actually if we look at our equation
We want to see how many households have access to high-speed internet over the total households in the state. We got
The denominator easily now we have all the households in the state that we care
That we consider households
And I think this is subjective though
You could just not include the 1990 definition and say just like if there's six people living in one house
It's not a house. It's a group quarter and just drop it
All you got to do is make sure you defend it or put a note in your analysis
So when people try to recreate it, they know that that's what you did
But now we have only the households that we care about and only the state that we care about
So now we have a working data set now we can just save it
We're gonna use data again, so we're gonna use the to state up
function
And what I'm doing here what I'm suggesting you do is use an f-string which started in 3.6
Python 3.6
To include this
Tag to include this tag this today tag that we created at the very beginning
Over here zero one
dash may dash 19
You don't have to do it this way. You could use
any other
way of string interpolation
This is just suggested and because we're in my vendor if we're you're following through
On my vendor, I think we're using three seven
So you just let's save that to our interim data path, whatever you name that
And I would suggest I highly encourage to pass this
write index
Equals false
Because by default is going to write the index and then you're going to have an extra column. That's meaningless to you. It's just going to be like
What is it?
3,000 218 5099
Which means nothing to you
And two two two two two state
Save that
To stay down
And if you want to see what other things you can pass to stay down on jupyter if you
Use the question mark at the end of the function
It's going to give you the
the doc string
So the file name is what we're passing here
Is interim data path
And it's going to expand it to include
interim data path slash
state underscore data dash zero one dash may dash 19
dot dta
Do we need to convert the dates we don't have any dates we don't care write the index it's set to true
But we don't want the index because it's meaningless to us in this analysis
Encoding by default is latin one. That's what's data uses still
Um by order all these other things we don't really care about
Uh, but well here are some examples. This is just to show you what you can do if you in case you didn't know
question mark
It will give you the doc string
Which is very useful if you do two question marks
It'll give you the actual code
Do do do do
Which is a lot
If you know what you're doing then you want to make sure you like
Um, this is exactly what you want. This is another way to look at it
Okay, so we're doing this interim
Data path f string state data dash
Today
And you could just write the date yourself
If you wanted to
but this
Workflow has worked pretty great for me. I'll just
If i'm running something and I changed just a little bit of the code earlier on
And i'm running it the next day
I don't overwrite the data that I that this subset of the data that I created the day before
So it's just you might you could end up with a lot of copies of the same data if you're running it every day
But you just gotta it's it's still a nice nice tool and you could get more more
Detailed here, this is just the day
The month and the year, but I think it goes to like nanosecond
So if you really care about the time like I I I ran this at 359
You should save it like that
saves
And
Let me see if we still have time. No, it's 302. Sorry. You were two minutes late for snack
But this is a good a good time to stop
Uh, we have saved the data and when we come back, we'll talk more about what what we've done so far. Thank you
You
Yes
Okay, yes, sorry, um I forgot about that
You
Yeah, I lost mine too
Rookie mistake
You
Oh
Yeah
You
One more minute
Yeah, that's that's why it doesn't work
Yeah
You
Okay
As a time
Okay, we're gonna go ahead and get started
The second part of
Our analysis we're gonna so when we left off before the break
We had just saved our data if you're using
my binder
to follow along your
session might have
Finished if you don't do anything for 10 minutes, they'll kind of like shut it down
What I just did right now was go all the way to the top here
I just refresh to restart my kernel
And I just run every single cell again
If that happened to you, you can
Just refresh the page and then we'll start
You're not gonna have that saved
but it's great that we finished all the way to save it saving the data file because you could just
Go here to the solutions
And just run this code until all the way to saving a file
all the way to
Step five when we save the file does that make sense if if if you're running my binder and your session didn't
expire
Uh, if you're not seeing any errors, then you're good to go. This is just in case you try running something and it tells you
Kernels that or your session has expired or something
So
Okay, so I just wanna
We can just go over what we have done so far we have
At the very beginning
We have put together our environment all the libraries that we're going to need we set up the path file the file
paths
So this can be run on any platform because of pathlib it will figure out
Yeah, go up one directory find the data one find the raw one
the raw directory
Um, this is going to work even with the forward slashes
and windows or macOS or linux
We have this little function that's going to give us the
Tree of a directory tree so we can explore
The same path it doesn't have to be raw data path you can pass interim if you if you're working on something else
later on
We have
loaded up
um a compressed file so we know how to load up
either csv compressed file gz gzip csv files
gzip compressed csv files directly onto pandas
or
using gzip
loading up more
different formats like .dta
We saw the
Quote-unquote value of having a dta file it comes with value labels
Which can then be interpreted as categorical columns in pandas which allows us to do
comparisons even between strings on the categories if those
Categories are ordered
We know how to do some basic
Statistics and
basic descriptives of your data frame
We know how to find what type of data you're working with
We know how to find like the basic statistical descriptive analytics
of your quantitative variables
We know how to find the shape of our our data frame and this is particularly useful in
If you think you have like 300 million observations and then you happen
And looking at the data it looks like you have three million and if you look at the memory you might or might not notice
Those size difference you see a big file and it's a big file
But if you expect it a lot more this is you're going to see it right away
Over here or if you have a lot less columns that you thought than you thought
So we started out
From then we we moved on and we started modifying our our data set
We we loaded up the master file and then we started looking at slicing and
grabbing just subsets of that data set
We we dropped
The rows
That we did not want in this case. We looked at the states
And then we chose one state that's what that's the one we're interested in drop everything else
Is what they call boolean indexing
We created we create we learned more about this little work
Two step process of creating a mask
Passing that onto a data frame to create a subset
And then saving that onto another
Data frame
We'll learn about copy if you're if you're
Pointing it if you have a master file and you grab a subset
And then you're going to save that to another variable. You want to create a copy of that
Otherwise, you're you're creating a view
Or a copy of a slice of another data frame. That's what another way pandas documentation
Looks at it
This is then this is good practice because you don't it might have unintended consequences down the road
Uh, we learned how to look at the columns
Of a data frame
We learned how to drop columns
We learned how to find the unique values of a specific series or a column
It's a pen pandas data frame column
Uh each of these a column is also a series a pandas series, which is another object
We learned how to find the unique values of that
We
Learned how to find the count of those unique values
And then we learned that that does not help us a lot when we're working with weighted data, which is most of
The the way you're going to be dealing with census data for privacy reasons
Um, we created another mask in this this time we use two conditions. So now
uh
This is going to return a true
or false
a series of booleans truths or falses
and
It's going to compare it to another series of truths and falses
Another boolean series and then
We're gonna from those we're gonna compare them to each other and if if either or oh no
I lost everything
It's fine. We have the solutions. Uh if we if
Once we have that two two condition
those two conditions
we will get um
one series of
Booliants that satisfy either or I mean they satisfy or one of those conditions
Uh, just as a note. I added here that because we know gq is categorical
Because we looked at it over here in our info
gq
Is of type category
uh
and because we saw also in
Here that it is
An ordered categorical
Which means some of these even though their strengths are greater than another value
we could uh
Do this we can just look at gq
and grab me all the
the and just tell me if each of the values in gq is less than or equal to
additional households under the 1990 definition
This doesn't work with strings because you cannot compare strings like this, but because it's a category and we know cat this category comes
is greater than
the 1970 definition
That's what we can do that type of analysis that that type of comparison there
We learned about the uh, we created a subset and from there we got a working data set. So now we have
a
state underscore data dash
Today whatever today's date is that dta
in our interim data path
Um, i'm not going to go over this extra credit part
But what I wanted to show you here is that
Because age is of categorical variable
It's a categorical variable which we saw over here again from info
With the age is category
even though
When you look at age, it looks like their numbers
Oh, this is not going to work because I didn't run it
Even though let me see if this works
Even though you see here age 79 79 28
78 and 52 those look like numbers, but those are actually the labels of
the age categories
and
You can you can run into some
Issues if you try to compare them as numbers
So what i'm trying to do here, so this could be
I just want to give me the households that have children of over five
I run this
It's going to tell me can I compare categorical?
With a scalar which is not a category because this five is not a category
category
category the category for five years old is the label five
This is going to work
and this is because age again, it's it's a category and it would try to
Um, let me show you something
Age uh in pandas. There's this other thing that would it's not super common
Uh
In in general, but you can just try to read a
Column as type something else
For example, this fib codes over here
There we saw that those are integers in our data frame, but they actually
Mean something else in geographic
Analysis and the county fib codes have to have three digits. So this zero actually should be 000
Or this 49 should be 049 because that means something
and and geo
gis
analysis
So you could uh, we could just grab this county fib
Here and then as type string and then just change that whole thing string, but I just want to show you what happens when you try
To read this as int the age which we would think I was like, oh if the label is five
Just make it an actual five, right?
It's not gonna work and the reason why it doesn't work
Is because this you have one value in in your series
For kids less than one year old and instead of
Using the the number zero to to denote that it's less than one
They use the label less than one year old and they don't and you don't know how to change that
Look, uh pandas doesn't know how to um doesn't want to assume what you want to change that to
What you would like to change that to um, there's other ways
uh, I wonder
Errors it raises errors you could just say errors
Errors
Ignore and then it works but then all the errors are just going to be
Are still going to be there or you could try to coerce
Is it course oh, it's just raising Chris and another uh another pandas
Further in the in the second notebook we might look at that
But there's other ways right now because we just know that it's a category we can just use
Quotations around the number and we'll that will denote that it's the number five
Um
This extra credit part was just to
To trim our data set even more if you wanted to look at households with school-aged children
Which could be something of interest to to people?
Making policy decisions
Maybe you find that
kids in
Latino households are less likely to have access to broadband internet and you want to do something or your politicians want to so
Well, you find out that you go talk to your politician and then
Tell them to do something
So now we're going to move on to zero one the next notebook
By this time you should have on your on your data
Folder on interim a data set
state data
underscore
and today's date
I have this other one because I ran the solutions notebook
All the way through so working data is actually
Saved there if you run the solutions
I think it's only if you run solutions and that is actually the one with
Just school age
Households with school-aged children
Okay, and then we have so we're going to move on to zero one digital divide
The analysis and I have set up pretty much the same thing. I have the project name
What i'm doing now instead of data prep i'm doing data analysis
Which is just a reminder for me. I have this to remind me that this is what i'm trying to recreate
I still have my research questions
I updated my goal because the goal of this notebook is now that we have the working data set
And I have a link to the to the notebook
So I can just look at that if I want
I want to answer the research questions now that I have the data that I want to look at
From the from the master file
Now i'm going to run the analysis and a lot of the time you're going to spend you you're going to spend most of your time
prepping the data
and then the analysis is going to be
slightly faster, but the
Data preparation is not only what takes the longest it's usually the most important part, too
because when if you want to publish this if you want to write something up
You need to be able to defend what you did and you you need to be able to say
actually, I did not include households under the 2000 definition because
x y and z or I am only looking at this definition of households or i'm only looking at school-aged children
And i'm and i'm defining school age as five to eighteen
or fourteen to eighteen if I want to look at high school or
Not eighteen because then turn then technically they're technically adults. So only at seventeen, but you need to be able to defend that and you need to
Um, so that's one that's why the data preparation part is essential in every project
Um, I have left this
Up to you to write the context
um
You you I suggest that you write the context of this notebook
uh, you can say something like
run data prep notebook
Uh, now I have a data set with only households in
these two definitions
It's for this state is using this year's data
Blah blah blah. It's just something to remind yourself of what you have done
in case you come back
In six months and you know like hey
What is untitled 34 supposed to do?
Oh also, please name your notebooks every time you start
You start a new one
So i'm gonna give you a minute
So
Yeah, so when I left it gave me this i'm not sure how to get back on the page from here, oh if you
Uh, yeah this session left so you need to go back
And then it's gonna
Oh, yeah, it's not so you're gonna have to start a new session
Um, I would just run the solutions
Okay notebook all the way to saving the file
So
Okay
And once you're done with the context
You can then
Start working on setting up your environment. This is pretty much the same thing
Within the first notebook you import the libraries
You put together this today tag that you might use later
And you set these path files up
the file paths
So
And I just want to take a quick detour
Um
If you
Think this is annoying
Um putting writing all your imports every single time, especially if they're the same
Setting up your data paths every single time
This is pretty much the same to me every time I do it so I'll have like
project the
Data analysis part maybe our cues goal context and these same
First like the first two three cells
There's this great tool called jupyter lab templates
If you're using jupyter lab, you can create a template and it will
You you have your template saved somewhere
And it will create a copy of that so you can get started from that and you can have
It's not going to run the code automatically, but if you have
Um, you see this part it has inserted inserted code already there
So if you're using the same if you're typing the same three or four cells every single time
You can just create a template save it somewhere
um
And then set up jupyter lab templates
Let's just pip install it
installing the extension
enable it
and then in your
dot jupyter
Directory in the config file
You just add the path to your template and instead of just sample here, it's going to show you this
And you can then
Have something with all your your path file
your file paths
Set up every single time. This is what I do
in my work computer just
Create that and then I have the first cell says something like project name and then just in big
I mean, it's already in h. I mean just one
Pound sign and says I have the name of the project
And just add the date here
and then I have
These already set up
So I can just run them and not type
every single time
These 10 lines of code
Which is not even a lot, but it's kind of annoying
So jupyter lab templates, it's a great tool
Okay, so we have we loaded up the libraries we
Declared the file paths
Here I just put three interim data paths so I want to see what what's in my interim data folder
This might be different
in your hand I have the working data file
Because I run the solutions and all the way through at the very last one when we're looking at school age children is just
I saved as working data instead of state data
I loaded up the the data
And then this one I haven't ran. It looks like I ran it because I copied it
I ran it first and then I deleted the code. What do you think goes here? What do you think? What gives you this type of output?
Yeah, this is the shape of your of your data frame
And this and this changed because the first the first time I ran it was with
School age children data set which is a subset of this
um
This one what do you think is going to give you this output?
What goes here head yes
And again, it might change a little bit if you you if you chose a different state
If you didn't do the extra credit part where it's not extra credit, but the bonus part with
School age children only so this might look a little different, but the mechanics
Should be the same
Um, what does this look like?
Do you remember
Oh, yeah, sorry, yes it is info. Thank you. I'm gonna close this one too
Can you see plus
Yeah, this is info info
Info
It's really nice about info too is it will give you the memory usage
um
For for your data frame, maybe you're working with a lot of data. You don't know what as long as your computer
Info is going to tell you that you're using like 500 megabytes or something
So
We have looked at the descriptors we loaded up the data we kind of know how it looks like
um
Now for the real enough for the analytical part of this
We want to look at households that have access to broadband internet to broadband to high-speed internet
But our data right now is one observation per person
um, and like we mentioned earlier you can
You have the serial number for each of the households so you can track how many households you have by just looking at
the unique number of of cereals of serial values
But we still need to change our data a little bit because we don't
need
person level
data we need a household level and
This this information comes from from ipums
It is generally a good idea to use household weight when conducting a household level analysis of any ipum sample
To use household weight is optional when analyzing one of the flat or unweighted ipum samples, which we're not using we're using a weighted sample
um
uses
Users should also be sure to select one person from the household
From the household person number equals one to represent the entire household. So if we look at our data over here
Um
Do you remember how these two are in the same household?
You see that this
Household weight is the same for both of them because you could just grab one of them
Uh, it's better
It's good practice I mean you should from ipum's suggestion you should grab the first
The pernum equals one which is usually the first it is the first person that shows up in the household
and it is
the head or
the head of the household
So that's as simple as it gets all we got to do is
Is drop every observation in our data every person
Um that is not the household head
So I set up the code here and then i'm going to give you a minute to run this
So
Yes represents more than one person
And that's a confusing part.
Well, that's a confusing part.
Yes, sorry.
Yeah, the one I was thinking of is, OK, so I see we have three
records all with the same serial.
So this is our sample household.
Yes.
So the household setup of these people.
And then the household weight is how many of those?
Yeah.
And the household weight will be the same
for each of those observations.
That's why you don't want to run your analysis,
like add up all the household weights on everything,
because you're counting one household multiple times,
if that makes sense.
If you did want to do that, if you
didn't want to calculate the total number of households,
you select all the records where per number is one,
take the sum of the household.
Yes, exactly.
Now it's going to be that.
So I'm grabbing the first two of my data set,
which is for Ohio.
And this is one household.
Each person has a different weight,
because they're representing a different amount of people.
But the household weight is the same.
And so if you were to add up the household weights
of all your whole data frame right now,
of your whole data set, you would
be counting multiple times the same household for however
many people there are in that one.
And if every single household was just two people,
you could easily just, OK, we'll add it up,
and then just divide it by half, because I'm
counting every household twice.
But that's not the case, because some households
have more than one person, I mean, more than two people.
So this is why we do it this way.
We grab all the observations that
were per num, the person's number per num, is equal to 1.
And we're going to keep those.
And then I'm just running this.
This is not saving to anything.
I'm just going to look at the shape of that.
So now we only have 48,564 observations in my data set
in Ohio.
It might be different if you're doing a different state.
But this is 48,000, 49,000 out of 112,000.
So we dropped quite a few observations, which makes sense.
If most households have more than one person,
you're going to be counting by more than half, usually.
So we're going to save this subset of data
to an appropriately named variable.
It's good practice to name your variables something
that is very descriptive.
Data, mask per num.
And you could approach this in at least two different ways.
You can just keep all the instances
where per num equals 1.
So you're keeping the household heads.
Or you could look at those that don't match the household head
and drop those.
But that's a little bit more complicated.
And it's just easier to think about it like,
look for the ones that I want and grab those,
and then just drop everything else.
But there's definitely another way.
You could just do the opposite.
You save it.
And I did not add it here in the template of the notebook.
But remember to use copy, because we're
going to be using state households later on.
And we're going to be modifying it.
And you're going to keep getting those warnings.
The analysis and the code might run just fine.
Sometimes it might have some unintended consequences.
But I think warnings are annoying.
So if I could just not get any warnings, that's great.
So I keep doing this.
All right, so step three.
You'll notice that I have a lot less code already written here
for you.
I think the better way to learn is you typing out the code.
But I wanted to set up as much as I could
without giving you too much.
But now what we're doing here is just running value counts
on, in this case, CNF, CNF, HHH, right?
Yeah, series.
And say high speed.
So grab from your newly made data frame, state households,
grab this variable, CNF, and run value counts on them.
So let's find out what we can about it.
State households.
CNF.
And there you go.
Another way of grabbing a data frames column
is by using dot notation.
It's not recommended.
But you could just write like dot psi high speed,
dot value counts, and it will run just fine.
But when you're dealing with administrative data,
you just don't know what they're going to name their columns.
And it might start with a number,
or it might have spaces in between,
and then it's just not going to work.
So this is why we're using this way.
Psi high speed.
And it runs just the same.
I'm going to keep going, but if you need me to slow down,
just let me know.
Value counts has a parameter normalized,
set to false by default. This is what
we did last time, which is question mark at the end,
and I will show you the doc string.
This is very useful if you're dealing
with what IPM's called over here,
flat, quote unquote, or unweighted data.
If each of your observations represents one person,
in this case, or one household, then you
could run this code, state households, tab, sine.
Value counts, just like we did earlier,
but then you set normalized to true.
And you're going to get the share of each of those values.
Which, if this was an unweighted file,
again, if each observation was a household,
represented only one household, then we won't have our answer.
We'll just be like, oh, well, yeah.
Out of, sine represents people that have access.
I'm going to leave this here.
I'm not going to go.
But it's people having access to internet services, right?
So we can see if this was not a weighted sample,
if this was an unweighted data set,
you could just get your answer.
This is not the variable we're looking at.
But you could just run value counts,
normalized equals true.
Now we know that 83% of, in this case,
the observations in our sample, in our data set,
yes, have access to internet service with a subscription.
And we can do the same with state, households,
side head speed, value counts, normalized equals true.
And this is the variable we're interested in.
And you can see it up, just up in the notebook,
you see from IMPLM's their descriptions.
This is the variable we're interested in.
We want to see how many people have access
to high speed internet.
And that's what this variable is calling.
High speed internet, anything that falls under cable modem,
fiber optic, or DSL service.
And this is the power of IMPLM's.
In 2016, the census started asking,
do you have access to high speed internet, yes or no?
And by yes, I mean cable modem, fiber optic, or DSL service.
In 2015 and before, they would ask you,
do you have access to internet?
Yes.
Do you have access to it through DSL?
Yes, no.
Through fiber optic?
Through cable modem?
Yes, no.
So if you look at the variable, IMPLM's high speed codes,
you can't see it because it's in full.
If you look at the description, this size.
Oh, look.
I looked it up already.
This is great.
The documentation from IMPLM's is great.
So if you're working with census data,
and especially if it's across years,
this is a great resource.
I'm going to put it in full screen.
So this will describe what the variable is actually reading.
And in the notebook, I have the description.
It's copied from here.
If you look at the codes, you're going to see this.
So starting 2016, you only get NA, GQ, yes,
through cable modem, fiber optic, or DSL, or no.
But before 2016, so 2015, 14, 13,
you could find how many people have access to the internet
through DSL service only, or fiber optic only.
It's useful if that's something that's
what you're interested in.
But if you wanted to look at trends, 2013 to 2017,
IMPLM harmonizes this into 0, 1, or 2
in the regular, in the not detailed version.
And then you could go deeper into it
and then find out these other categories for the answers.
If you want to learn more about this, the comparability tab
is great, because it will explain to you,
this is what happened.
In 2016, you could distinguish whether site high speed values
were allocated due to server responses for blah, blah,
blah, blah.
And it will explain to you.
And then site speed is only five years
that they've been doing that.
But when you look at, for example, birthplace data,
some countries just don't exist anymore.
So it will explain this here.
We used to call it this, and now it's this.
We used to call it USSR, or we used to call it India.
But now it's all these other countries.
So it's always good to look at the description, and the codes,
and the comparability.
And for example, the birthplace variable,
that would be one that you would want
to keep the D version of it, just
like we had raised his band and relate, at the end,
the detailed version.
If you're doing anything with immigration, like I have,
you want to keep the detailed version.
Because sometimes you'll have something like Pakistan labeled
as India, still.
Because at some point, it used to be just coded as India,
not anymore.
So you want the detailed version.
So again, here I'm just describing to you
that if this was unweighted data,
this would be the end of our analysis.
We find out, oh, look, 69% of people
have access to the internet.
But it's not, because it's weighted data.
So 69% of our observations have access to the internet.
So to find out how to get the actual number of households,
is what you were saying, is you find the households that
match this condition, that yes, they have access
to the internet data, to high speed internet.
And then you add up the household weight variable.
Because that's the actual count of households.
And to do that in Pandas, you do what
it's called grouping and aggregating data.
So to group data, you have to just use the group by method.
And to group by, you're going to pass it a column,
or a list of columns.
And Pandas is going to create this group by object
that you need to apply a function to.
And this is all from the docs.
And I'm speeding up a little bit,
because we don't have a lot of time left.
Or battery.
I'll fix that right now.
But if you wanted to group by, let's say,
psi high speed, because that's the variable we're interested
in, and you want to group by, let's say,
that's the variable we're interested in.
We want to group it by the values of this column.
And then you get this object, which is not very helpful.
What you got to do is apply a function.
So try this.
And instead of sum, try it with mean, max, min.
And this is standard deviation.
And you'll see what it looks like,
what a group by object looks like once you
have applied a function to it.
I'm going to charge my computer.
Or not.
Didn't I bring a charger?
Do you have the USB-C?
Not sure.
No, it's a Mac.
No.
Yeah, it's a Mac.
Sorry.
Thank you.
What is this?
Yes, could I have my Mac?
Thank you.
Oh, no.
My computer's too old.
Yeah, this is not.
Sorry.
Yeah.
I'll be forever.
Oh, shoot.
I'm going to do that.
I just want to see.
OK, we'll see.
OK.
I actually have another computer.
We'll just switch midway through.
OK.
How much do I have?
4%?
OK.
So this is, I'm going to show you some households.
Group by.
I'm doing county fit, but you'll see later on.
So this is what it looks like.
It's creating another data frame.
Its index is going to be the column that you passed,
or the list of columns.
You could pass county fit, side high speed.
And it's going to create what is called a multi-level index,
multi-index, I think.
You can tell that these are the indices,
because they're just lower than the rest of the columns.
And when you apply something like sum,
which is a mathematical function,
it's going to apply to only the quantitative columns.
Same with mean.
So some of these might not mean anything, like per num.
The average per num is one, because that's the only one
we kept, right?
The average person's weight is going to be this.
Doesn't mean anything.
We're not looking for the averages.
If you pass something like count, does that work?
OK.
Count, because it's not a mathematical function,
it can apply to every single row,
every single column in your data frame.
And all it's going to do is count the number of instances
any value is in it, I believe.
So yeah.
So you'll see this.
Everything is the same, because every row in your data frame
right now in your data set has a value,
because we got it from the census.
They won't give you missing value data.
OK.
Let me see if we can get it moved on to.
OK, so just like you would grab any column
from any other data frame, you can do the same here.
Just square brackets, pass me the column.
So if we want to group by sine high speed,
and you want to grab the household weight,
and then I'll give you a minute to play around with that.
But we have already spoken about what
we need to do with the household weight.
Oh, no.
The cave wasn't supposed to show.
Ignore that.
Oh, wait.
It's probably in your computer.
OK.
So we could try the mean of the household weight.
So the average household weight represents 95.
So we can try the mean of the household weight.
Households.
But if we run the sum, like we mentioned earlier,
these are the actual numbers.
Now you have found there's, in Ohio, 3,223,198 households
with access to high speed internet.
And these are households, again, from what
we define as the household we're interested in,
under the 1970 definition and the 1990 definition,
which is up to 10 people.
If there's 11 people living in a housing unit,
and they're not related to each other,
we don't want to know anything about them.
Drop them in the data prep file.
And I want to show you something here.
And I might go later in the notebook,
you'll see something else, the same here.
But just like you passed just one column,
if you wanted to pass multiple columns,
you pass them as a list, household and per weight,
for example.
This should be pretty much the same,
because you dropped every other person.
So per weight is meaningless right now.
But did you notice the change in the look of this?
When you have just one column, pass it as this,
household, no, hhwt.
This is what this looks like.
This is a series.
If you pass it, even if you pass it just as a one element list,
because you're passing it a list,
it's going to look like a data frame.
And most of the things that you can do to a series,
you can do to a data frame.
But there are some things that you cannot do to a data frame
that you can only apply to series, like value counts.
Value count, drop duplicates.
There are certain methods that only work for series,
and not data frames.
So you need to be aware of that.
And I usually like this, because it's more readable.
It looks nicer.
And a lot of the time, I'm not doing anything with the data
that it has to be a series.
I need it as a series, and there's no other way.
So if I can, I'll just have it as a data frame.
It's easier to read.
So now we have the actual numbers.
This code I put together just so it will match
what you have in your.
If you're using a different state, this is going to change.
But this is the same thing as this over here.
We have, wait.
Oh, this is no.
No.
Python is zero indexed.
So now we see three million households in Ohio
have access to high speed internet.
But how many?
That's our research question, number one.
So to make this a zero follow, we
can save this same thing that we did over here.
Save it to a variable.
So all we're doing is typing this onto this.
And while you do that, I'm going to switch computers.
Hopefully it works.
Moment of truth.
every day.
Actually, I'm going to...
Yeah, I'm just going to go to the solutions.
I'm not going to do this whole thing.
Okay, so we are...
Here.
So we have this.
I saved it with just one, so I didn't pass the list, so this is a series.
So we have already a series, and we already have the number of households.
So how do we find the sum of the elements of a series?
How do you think?
That's a cool thing about pandas is most...
A lot of the times it's very intuitive.
You could do CUM sum, and that's going to keep adding more and more,
because we want just the sum of every element like this, we just pass that sum at the end of it.
And then you... There you go.
It's like this.
Because I'm in the solutions notebook, I'm going to try to keep the answers below,
so you don't see the rest of the answers.
Does this tutorial...
We have eight minutes left.
So this was the revelation.
So now we have households with high speed Internet here.
We have each of the valleys.
We have households that answer N, A.
We have households that said yes, I have access to Internet, to high speed Internet.
And we have households that said no.
And now we also have the total households.
So we now have the denominator of our equation.
When you apply a function just like we did dot sum to a series,
all it did was add up every single element of it.
Series are NumPy arrays, which are not like list.
So if you apply comparison like we did earlier,
or if you apply... If you add something or multiply it by something,
it's not going to do... It's going to apply that operation to every single one of its elements.
So if you have your households with high speed Internet, with high speed access,
which is this series of three elements,
and you were to multiply it times a million,
it's going to grab each of those elements and multiply it times a million.
It's not going to add it up and then multiply it that times a million.
Or it's not going to do it to just the first element or something.
It applies to every single element. It's vectorized, I think is the term.
So now that you have this, now that you know you can do some math to a series,
and it's going to apply that to every single one of its elements,
how do you think we can find the share of each of these?
How much each of these make of the total?
Over here.
Yeah, as simple as that. Just like over here we divide by a million,
and it divided each of those elements by a million.
Instead of a million, we can just pass the total of our households.
And then this is the actual number.
This is different from what we had over here.
Sometimes it might be very similar, but not usually.
When we did the normalize, we saw 80% of our observations said yes,
had a value of yes, I have access to the Internet.
When you actually account for the weight and you weight it correctly,
it's 78%, 78.7. So 79 versus 80%.
Sometimes they get very lacking, but this is the actual accurate number.
And this is for Ohio, it's higher actually than, not that I'm surprised, Ohio's great.
But this is, oh, I don't have it.
The California one, the one that we're trying to recreate,
for California the number is 74%.
Only 74% of households in California have access to high speed Internet.
And I completely overshot.
I thought we were going to have time for part two,
but I think we're finishing in four minutes.
The mechanics are the same.
The only thing that you need to do now is instead of grouping by just side high speed,
by their value, you want to find these numbers for each of race ethnicity group.
So to see if certain households, certain demographic groups have less access to high speed Internet.
And I try to be as thorough as I can in the notebooks and you have the solutions here.
So if you follow this through, you should be able to do it on your own
and you can find the answer for whatever state you want.
And you can learn a little bit more about pandas and deriving variables from another column
and creating groups out of another column, aggregating data in multiple ways.
I added as many examples as I could over here.
You can do other stuff, not just the group by method.
You can find, you can do a group by and then slice it.
So it just gives you the answer that you want after you have done the math.
So you can get this.
You can do cross sections. You can do cross tabs.
I really wish we got into this one because this is the fun part.
The data preparation is not the fun part most of the time.
But yes, everything is going to be on the link.
Thank you so much. There's going to be a survey at the end.
Don't mention that I didn't finish. I'm just kidding.
They're going to mail you a survey.
Thank you so much for coming. And it was great. Thank you so much.
Thank you.