.
!
have existing APIs that you would like to maintain and innovate on them without
breaking anyone that depends on them. This is that talk. So everyone, please give a
warm welcome to Jesse.
So I'm Jesse and I work for MongoDB in New York. I've worked with some very
popular open source libraries for many years and seen them change and evolve
over time. I've learned a lot in that process and I want to teach you some
shortcuts to learning how to evolve your APIs the right way. So imagine that you
are a creator deity and you are in charge of designing the body for a
creature. If you think of ways to improve the creature's body over time so
it's better evolved, you should make those changes. It would really appreciate
it. It shouldn't be stuck in the same body forever. But at the same time you
can't just go changing its scales or adding wings willy-nilly. You need some
sort of process for it to adapt its lifestyle for changes in its body. And if
you are a responsible creator deity, you have to balance these two obligations to
your creature. It's the same for library maintainers. We are in charge of
responsible evolution for our libraries. We have promises to our users. We
promise to fix bugs, add features, maybe delete features if that's the right
thing for the library's future. But at the same time we can't break code that
our users have written that relies on the way that our library works today. How
do we fulfill all of these promises at once? By the way, I'm going to go fast
because the talk is too long, but I'll share a link at the end to a written
version of this talk so you don't have to memorize everything at the speed that
I'm saying it. So the first thing for a responsible creator is that if we think
of features that would make our library more useful, we should add them if we
think that adding wings would improve the library, we should go ahead and do it.
But adding features comes with risks. I'm going to show an example of a feature
that was added to the standard library and what went wrong. Yeah, so we should add
features. That's what I meant to say. All right. So here's an example from the
Python standard library. From early days it had this datetime.time object and it's
got a special dunder bool operator for converting it to bool and 9.30 in the
morning converts to true. What do you think about zero? Well, depending on the
circumstances, it will evaluate as false. This is a very surprising quirk. I've
been coding Python for more than 10 years. I only recently found out about
this. You can imagine what sort of bugs might arise if you don't know about this.
Say that you're writing a calendar application and you have a create event
function. It might take a day and also the start time and the end time. And it
doesn't make sense to have an end time with no start time, so you write a check
for that. What can go wrong here? What about an event that starts at midnight?
Well, this should be allowed, but it's going to fail the check because of that
quirk. You could code defensively. You could say that if end time is not none
and start time is none, then that's okay. But this is a really subtle point. If you
wanted to design an API that would bite people by surprise, this is the kind of
quirk that you would add. But we're not those sort of designers. We are
responsible creators. We want to make our libraries easy to use correctly. And
that's what the core developers eventually did is that it took years, but
in Python 3, all datetime.time objects evaluate as true. How do we avoid making
these sorts of mistakes in our own APIs? As responsible creators, we must obey the
first of the ten covenants, which is to avoid adding bad features. I don't want
to be too critical of this midnight quirk. It was actually coded by Tim
Peters, who is one of the founding coders, one of the most brilliant Python
contributors ever. If even he can make such a mistake, how do we avoid it? Well,
we can do it by just minimizing features overall. Don't add a public class or
method or attribute unless there's a really good reason for it. Remember that
adding features is fun, but they're kind of like children. They're conceived in a
moment of passion. You're enthusiastic. You're not thinking. And next thing you
know, you've got something that you have to maintain for years. Let's say that you
as a responsible creator, you've decided that it's time to add a feature. You want
to make your library better. How do you choose the right feature for the job?
I'm going to look at another example from the standard library. So this one's in
async.io. So a little bit of background. You know that you can create a coroutine
with this async.def syntax, but when you execute this coroutine function, which
you get is a coroutine object. The coroutine is not actually executed until
you await that coroutine. It's easy to forget to do, and so the async.io
developers, they wanted some way to catch the mistake of deleting a coroutine
without ever having awaited it. So they wanted some sort of wrapper around a
coroutine that in debug mode could warn you if you've never awaited the coroutine.
What they introduced to solve this problem was this incredibly powerful hook
called setCoroutineWrapper. What you pass in there is a function which takes a
coroutine and returns something. The intention was that this something would be
a thing that would warn you if you've never awaited the coroutine, but you could
throw anything in there. You could set up a hook that replaces all coroutines with
a string high. This is unbelievably powerful as a customization. It changes
the very meaning of the word async throughout the program globally. This is
much too powerful for the job. As Nathaniel Smith wrote in the Bug Tracker,
sys.setCoroutineWrapper is a problematic API. It was added to solve a specific
problem to track where coroutine objects are created so the warning they print can
include a traceback. But to do this, it adds a very generic hook to replace all
instances of a built-in type with an arbitrary new type. This is more power
than we need for the circumstances. It's too easy to misuse. We can avoid these
sorts of mistakes by obeying the third of the ten covenants, which is to keep
features narrow. This actually contradicts a lot of what we learn in college or OO
textbooks. We're encouraged to come up with these very general and universal and
powerful customizations, but in my experience, it's better to give users what
they actually need to get the job done. That's what the async.io developers
ended up doing, which is that they replaced that overpowered hook with
something that is specific to the actual problem they're solving. It's set
coroutine tracking depth, and it's just a way to say how many lines of traceback
do you get if you forget to await a coroutine. It doesn't change the meaning
of async. It just prints out the line where you created the leaked coroutine.
This is a success story because the async.io developers, they thought ahead,
and they had marked that overpowered hook as provisional. We can learn from their
example as well. If we're not sure about a feature, we can release it in order to
gain some user feedback. Let's say that you think that this snake would be cool
if it had a couple of horns and a quadruple forked tongue, but for some reason,
you don't have a good way to ask it its opinion. You release these features as
provisional. Maybe the snake says, the horns just get in the way, but the tongue
is awesome, so let's keep that. This opinion that releasing features as
provisional is a good way to do user testing. This is controversial. In the
language summit the other day, the async.io developers came under some fire for doing
this, for marking features provisional and changing them, so be aware that not
everybody will love you for it, but I think that this is a reasonable way to get
some feedback. All right, so despite all of your best efforts to make narrow
features, sometimes you release a feature that it turns out that you need to delete.
Like, let's say that we've got a lizard here with long spindly toes. You want to
delete them and turn it into a sleek, modern python. There's a couple of reasons
that you might need to delete a feature. One of them is just if, you know,
you discover that it's dangerous. We saw this with that quirk of the midnight
bullion value. Another thing that can happen is just that your ecology changes
around the library. Maybe another creator deity has invented tasty mammals,
and they live in these narrow burrows. You want your creature to be able to slither
down in and eat the tasty mammal filling, but in order to fit, you've got to lose
the legs. We can look at another example in async.io where a feature was deleted
due to a change in the ecology around that library. So from early on,
async.io had this lock class. It acts a lot like a multi-threading lock.
It introduces a critical section. But you have to remember to release the lock,
even if you throw an exception, so you need to release it in a tri-finally block.
A couple of versions later, the ecology changed. The language itself introduced
this async with syntax, which makes it far more reliable. Now you are guaranteed
when you leave the block, no matter how you leave it, to release the lock.
This is much better, but what about this old API that's sort of been left behind
by ecological change? It's dangerous, and besides, in Python, there should really
be only one way to do it. So the old API has got to go. If you are a responsible
creator and you're in this situation, you've decided that you've got a feature
that you might need to delete, you need to kind of weigh the pros and cons of making
this disruption. Some contraindications might be if your users need to change a lot
of code in response to the deleted feature, and especially if those changes are,
they require thinking or logical changes that users might get wrong, maybe you
should just leave the feature in place. On the other hand, if the changes are just sort
of mechanical, a big search and replace, or if the feature you're deleting is
dangerous, then you should go ahead and delete it. Given that you've decided that
you're going to delete a feature, how do you actually do it? Let's say we're
deleting the legs so this creature will no longer be able to walk. It will only be
able to slither. Do you just replace the walk method with a slither method and
release a new version of your library? No, right? Because there's still all of this
user code out in the world that depends on walk, and when they upgrade your library,
that'll be an error. So how do we gently move the library along and gently delete
this feature? There are a couple of steps to gently deleting a feature. In the first
one, we introduce the new API while keeping the old API in place so that people can
transition, and then we mark the old API as deprecated. The warnings module is
really interesting. It's very configurable. The main thing that I want you to notice
here is that stack level equals two parameter. That's going to come up again
in a minute. So you mark this method as deprecated, and the first thing that your
users will notice is that it appears differently in their IDEs. In PyCharm and
in other IDEs, they can actually parse that deprecation warning, and they'll render
the method call with a strike through. When users run their code, by default, they'll
just see these warnings printed to standard error. You'll see that the script, it still
completes. It still prints step, step, step, and has exit code zero, but it prints out
the line that the user needs to change. That's what that stack level argument did, is it
says how to render the trace back so that users know what line in their code they need
to change. Notice also that this is a, come on, that this is an instructive error. It
doesn't just say that walk is deprecated. It says what to do. It says use slither instead.
How do users actually test that they have migrated away from all of those deprecated
APIs? In this case, a test won't catch the error because it's just a print to standard
error, but there's this cool command line option you can pass that will change the warning
into an error, and so that way your users can test their code and ensure that they are
not using any deprecated errors at all. Deprecated methods at all. So once you've done this step,
you've deprecated the old method, what next? Can you just delete it now and release a new
version of your library? You're still not ready because consider how your users are
deploying their code that uses your library. They might have this requirements.txt that
just has a bare requirement on the reptile library, and so the next time they deploy,
the latest version, and they might get reptile 2.0, it lacks the walk method, and your users
have an error again. You need to teach your users how to upgrade your library safely,
and there are three covenants that we're going to follow that are related to this. The first
of these is responsible creators maintain a changelog, and the changelog, the main point
of it is to talk about new features that are introduced, features deprecated, and when
they are removed. So this says version 1.1 adds slither, and version 2.0 will remove
walk. Why am I choosing these particular version numbers to make these changes? Version numbering
is a language for communicating the pace of change of your library, and a responsible
creator has to use version numbers consistently. So the seventh of the ten covenants is to
choose a versioning scheme. There are two mainstream choices. Overwhelmingly, people
use semantic versioning. This is throughout the software industry, not just Python. Some
libraries time-based versioning is better suited, and again, I'll share links to all
of this stuff at the end, but I would really recommend twisted versioning policy here,
even if you don't plan to use time-based versioning, it's a really good read for a good compatibility
policy that works for lots of people. But I think overwhelmingly, libraries should choose
semantic versioning. The syntax for it is defined for Python and pep 440, and it would
go something like this. Your first stable release is called 1.0, that's where you start
to make API promises to your users. In minor releases, you can introduce new features and
deprecate old ones, and then you have to wait for the next major release for the first number
of increments before you can actually make any breaking changes like deleting a deprecated
API. Tools like pip understand semantic versioning, so your users can update their requirements
to say, my code is prepared for anything in the 1.0 series, but don't upgrade me to 2.0
until I'm ready. This is great, but you're still not all of the way to helping your users
upgrade safely. We need one more step, which is to actually write an upgrade guide. This
is the eighth of the ten covenants. An upgrade guide, it might look something like this,
where you say, here's how to upgrade to reptile 2.0. First of all, you need to read the change
log so you know what's changed, and you remind your users about that command line switch
for how to test their code to make sure they're not using deprecated methods. You tell them
to upgrade to the last minor release before the next major release. In that case, it's
version 1.1, and I call this a bridge release. The purpose of the bridge release is to
raise deprecation warnings for every deprecated method that will be removed in the next major
release. It's sort of like the last body that the creature has before you delete its legs.
They're just still barely there. So if we follow these covenants, our users can safely
upgrade from version to version, and we can add or remove methods safely. There's another
level after this, though. Methods aren't the only way that you add and remove features.
We can also do the same with parameters. So let's talk about how to change your parameters
safely over time. Let's say that you've added wings to your reptile, so now it has a new
way of moving. It doesn't only slither in a given direction, it also has the option
of flying. So we want to add a new mode parameter that allows the creature to choose between
slithering and flying. This is great, but again, think about all that user code in the
world. It's only passing the first parameter. So now this is an error. What we need to learn
how to do is to add parameters safely, and this is the ninth of the ten covenants. The
way that we add parameters compatibly is every time we add a parameter, we need to give it
a default value, and the default value must preserve the old behavior. So in that case,
this preserves the slithering mode, and over time, as you add more parameters, it becomes
like a history of the function's evolution. They appear in the order they were added,
and each has a default that preserves the old behavior. This is great in Python because
it means that users can write their applications to choose by name which of the defaults to
override. But there's still a potential risk here because users can also write their code
like this, passing parameters by position. And in this case, they have chosen by position
to accept a certain number of defaults and then only override the one at the end, moving
extra sinuously. The problem here will arise if in the next major release I decide that
I want to delete one of these parameters. Maybe I think that turbo sounds sort of outdated
to me these days, so I want to delete it. Now, user code will still run, but it's no
longer doing what's intended. It's no longer moving sinuously. Instead, it's hailing a
lift. So we need to go through an explicit deprecation cycle for a parameter like this,
and I kind of like this pattern. So we create a sentinel value. I'm going to call it turbo
default, and we swap it in for the previous default for this parameter. Then in the body
of the function, we can check if the user has overridden this default. If they have,
we print a warning because it's going to be deprecated. Otherwise, we just accept the
old default. Once we've done this, we can in the next major version delete the parameter.
It's still though it's only a warning. Users can ignore warnings. The even better style
is in Python 3 to use the star syntax. When you use an asterisk this way, it means that
all parameters after it can only be passed by name. And this means that if you later
delete a parameter, you know that this will either cause errors in your user code or
it will not affect them at all. So you know that there's no user code out here like this
that uses the positional style instead. And so you can safely delete the turbo parameter.
The kind of underlying message here is not just to add parameters compatibly, but to
very, very loudly if users are doing the wrong thing. Reptiles, their hearing is not very
good. You sort of have to shout at them. Warnings are easy to ignore. If you use the star syntax
instead, that will make your users much safer. But you've got to think ahead because you
can't add the star syntax in a later release. That's a backwards breaking change. So use
the star as soon as you anticipate that you might change any of the parameters that come
after the star. So that's how to change parameters safely. We've got one more challenge here.
And it's changing behavior without changing the API. So let's say that our creature here
is a rattlesnake and we want to give it a new means of moving, which is sidewinding.
This is amazing because it's a new feature with no visible change to the creature's body.
We can see an example of a behavior change without an API change like this in the standard
library. This story is an oldie-bittie-goody. So once upon a time, Python introduced the
OS.stat function for getting file statistics. And statistics like the modification time
here were integers. Now, most systems can provide a lot more precision. So the core
devs wanted to turn this integer into a floating point number. But they were concerned that
people were not prepared for that change. So they made it configurable. In Python 2.3,
you have to opt into the new behavior by saying set stat float times. And in 2.5, they swapped
the default. So now you don't have to call this and you'll still get floating point statistics.
If you want to preserve the old behavior, you can. Or if you explicitly opt into the
new behavior, then you get consistent behavior in Python 2.3 and later. This is getting complicated.
I will share a link at the end, I promise. All right. So years pass, oceans rise, empires
fall, Python 3 comes around, and the core devs decide it's time to remove this setting
entirely. So they deprecate any usage of it, whether it's true or false. More years go
by. It's been more than a decade since the story began. And finally, we're at Python
3.7 and the option is removed entirely. So these are the steps again. If you want to
change behavior gradually, do this. First, in a minor release, add a flag that allows
people to opt into the new behavior. Its default is false, but the default is also deprecated.
In the next major release, you swap the default and you deprecate any usage of the setting
at all. And then in another major release after that, you are finally allowed to remove
the setting entirely and only allow people to use the new behavior. So that's it. Those
are the ten precepts, ten covenants that a responsible creator upholds in order to responsibly
evolve our libraries without breaking user code. And I think that these kind of are categorizable
into three big buckets. First, to evolve cautiously. Minimize features. Don't add them unless
you know they're useful. Scope them narrowly. And if you're not sure, mark them provisional.
We also want to maintain a rigorous natural history of our library's evolution. Choose
a version scheme, maintain a changelog, and write an upgrade guide so that users know
how to test their code and upgrade safely. And finally, change gradually and loudly.
If you're going to delete features, go through a deprecation cycle before removal. If you're
going to add parameters, do it compatibly. Think of the star syntax first before you
even reach version 1.0. And if you're going to change behavior without changing API, do
that very slowly and do it over the course of three releases. So here is the promised
link. This will take you to a written article version of this talk. It's got links out to
more information about all of this. If you read it to the end, your reward is that it
will tell you the source of all of the silly old snake pictures. I don't have time for
questions right now, but I'd love to talk with you in the hallway. Thank you very much.