One, I think we can start now.
We still have some people coming in.
I think we can start.
Most people are here already.
So yeah, let's get started.
This talk is, I don't remember the title.
I know it's about NLP.
I choose a title that probably is something related to NLP.
But this will be a talk about NLP and how
to use something like PyTorch for building NLP models.
That's what we're going to do in this tutorial.
So if you're in the wrong tutorial,
you're free to leave now if you're in the right one.
Let's go.
This is the GitHub address.
Here you can access all of the resources.
We have slides.
We have something like this.
We have a slide, which is a website.
You can access it, and you can ask questions,
questions that are not so urgent.
You can just ask them there.
But if you have more urgent questions
that you need some clarification or answer,
you're free to ask.
We have a mic here.
So we'll just pass it to you, and you can ask.
Yeah, and we have a hashtag, please, if you use Twitter.
Just tweet it, and we'll make sure to retweet it
later during our break.
So just a bit about myself.
My origin is Belize.
So Belize is located in Central America.
I was doing a PhD for six years.
So I did a master's and a PhD in Taiwan,
PhD related to data science field.
And I focus a lot on NLP.
So most of the stuff that I did for these six years,
this is what I will use to present today.
And I gave talks in some of these developer conferences.
So I'm a really active speaker at some conferences.
And my job is I do education at Elastic.
Elastic recently went public.
It's a company that deals with distributed databases.
So I help to basically come up with,
help develop curriculums, and teach some of the things
that the great programmers are doing at the company.
And then this is my Twitter account.
You can get access to it.
And this is my son here.
So he's a three-year-old.
And we can see that he's like with the Jabiru.
Jabiru is a very popular bird in Central America and South
America if you are from that region.
And the special thing about the Jabiru
is that we have it on the, we just recently put it
on the coin.
So our official coin, official dollar has the bird.
And we replaced this bird with the Kill Bill Toucan.
The Kill Bill Toucan is a bird that's,
it's our national bird.
So that's cool that the Jabiru, although not a very famous bird,
but got some recognition.
So some housekeeping.
We have a survey that we need to fill out from the organizers.
And we also have a break-it tree.
So initially, I didn't have the break-it tree.
But we will take the break-it tree.
We'll see how we can modify part of the schedule today.
So I just want to clarify, usually when
I do a presentation, I usually have this slide.
I like to put the slide.
It's important to know what the tutorial is about
and what it's not about.
So this tutorial is a very easy guide
to understand Pytorch and its concepts.
It's a very practical approach to NLP.
We're going to focus on the nitty gritty of applied NLP.
And this tutorial will be student-oriented,
which means you'll be the focus of this tutorial.
We have a lot of exercises.
And we have a really packed tutorial for today.
And we expect exercises, question session, and group work.
So if you have questions that you
would like me to ask during the small breaks,
please do so in the website I shared before.
And this tutorial will be very little theoretical explanation.
So I won't focus on that boring part.
So mostly it will be about application.
This is not a deep learning course, very important.
We will do some deep learning, but it's not
a deep learning course.
There is very little use of external libraries.
And there is a purpose why I designed the tutorial
this way.
I think in order for you to get the idea of how
to build NLP models, you have to know
how to build the components of the model itself from scratch.
So that's going to be the focus of the tutorial.
And from there on, I believe that once you
have this background knowledge and you know how to use it,
too, like PyTorch, it will be easy for you
to go and see a tutorial and adopt things quickly.
So that's kind of the idea behind the tutorial.
So more formally, the objectives of the course of the tutorial
is to provide a quick overview of PyTorch high level APIs.
So I'll be using the documentation on that,
especially during the exercise.
And it is intentionally built like this
so that you have that hands-on practice.
And the idea is to introduce the important foundational
knowledge to apply modern NLP and to inform students
about the latest deep learning techniques for modern NLP.
So we will do cover some deep learning stuff
and to engage students and test knowledge acquisition as well.
Just formally.
So just a quick survey.
I assume that everyone uses Python here.
Is that correct?
Maybe raise of hands.
Perfect.
How about PyTorch?
Have you used PyTorch before?
OK.
That's great.
That's great because the tutorial was designed like this.
I knew that maybe because PyTorch is a recent tool.
So I knew that there's high demand for it.
And that's perfect.
It is designed this way.
How about TensorFlow?
Do you have experience with TensorFlow?
Yeah, we do have some hands.
Yes.
That's good.
That knowledge will come in handy.
And especially when we do form the groups,
I would expect that people that have that experience
could maybe become group leaders and help out the rest.
I do believe that would be a great way
to share your knowledge as well.
So the journey will be something like this.
We have a very brief introduction to NLP.
I'm not going to spend too much time on it.
I'm just going to say what's the idea behind it.
And there is a five-part tutorial.
Feel free to interrupt me if you have any questions, by the way.
I'm just talking here, but you can interrupt me
if you have questions.
So part one is introducing the concept of tensors.
Most of deep learning and LMP now and modern LMP
is about tensors and how to manipulate and operate on them.
And part two will be PyTorch core functionalities,
very important part of the presentation.
So Dask is in charge of background.
And then we have part three, which is NLP basics and things
like preprocessing, tokenization,
creating vocabularies, and this kind of thing.
And part four is apply deep learning to NLP.
So each one of these is a notebook.
And I shared some instructions before we started here.
Like a week ago, I shared some instructions on how
to use something like Google Collab
to be able to do all the data science stuff.
So hopefully, you got that email,
and you have set up an account, and you have
access to Google Collab.
I hope that that's the case.
If not, then you'll have to maybe form groups
and just help each other.
The part five is best practices for deploying and training
NLP models.
So this part is optional.
This will be more like what you do
if you want to do research in NLP,
is like how to properly evaluate models,
things like confusion matrices and this kind of thing.
Not really important if you only want to apply NLP,
but I think it's kind of a critical part of the NLP
as well.
So that's just the core of the tutorial.
So what is NLP?
Very brief introduction.
My definition is there are so many different definitions,
and it's because it's a really new field.
We have so many definitions.
So I just made a very simple definition,
which is a computational approach
to understanding language, teaching machines
how to understand language.
So it includes some ubiquitous tasks
like the following, tokenization,
word sense, system integration.
I will explain more later during the notebooks
what these things mean.
Name entity recognition, part of speech.
You may have heard about these concepts.
Sentence classification, language generation,
question answering, and machine translation.
So all of this is included in NLP.
And there is like a little Venn diagram here.
Maybe not the most accurate Venn diagram,
but I think it gets the idea.
So NLP, you can see that it's part of the whole AI movement.
So traditional NLP versus modern NLP.
So usually traditional NLP is you
learn features from data versus human engineering features.
So a traditional way is just engineering features.
And the modern way is to learn features from the data
automatically using some tool like RNN, LSTM, or CNN.
And each one operates very differently.
So we will learn more about these later on.
And some of the weaknesses and strengths, well,
I only listed two, but there could be a whole list.
So the advantage is that these models,
you can learn efficiently from data, learn features.
And the disadvantage now is that it requires large scale data.
That's a disadvantage.
So me working six years in one field, in one topic,
I realized that large scale data was always the problem.
I was a bottleneck, especially because I
deal with real world data sets.
I could never get access to those large scale data sets.
So using something like CNN or RNN,
I always had that difficulty.
It's quite challenging.
So this is just a high level overview
of what an NLP framework covers.
So we have a database over there.
That can be anything, anything related to language, of course.
Then you have some data preprocessing,
data transformation, modeling, and inferencing.
So at a high level, this is what it looks like.
But each one includes very key components,
very detailed components.
So we will go through each one at all phases.
And that's why I have initially designed four segments,
four notebooks, each covering each one of the components
here.
So let's just jump into the demonstrations.
So some instructions.
If you didn't get the link that I shared,
I have a folder here with a data set that we're going to use.
And you can get access to it now if you
have access to the slides.
So you can get access to the slide using the following link.
I'll just share it here.
So this link here, you can use that link
and you can get access to the slides.
And you can get access to all the notebooks this way.
So first thing, slides.
Then you can get access to all the notebooks
if you're using Google Cloud.
Because that's the main thing we're going to use.
And if you don't have access to Google Cloud,
if you have your own environment set up, that's perfect.
You can use that as well.
But I expect that you would already
have installed something like PyTorch and other tools
that we're going to use today.
So how many of you guys have Google Cloud set up?
OK, yeah, a lot, it looks like.
How about your own environment?
OK.
So we can just start with the first part.
You have any questions before we proceed?
Because now the more exciting part of the presentation
is going to start.
But you'll feel like at times this
will go super fast because there's so much thing
that I wanted to put into this tutorial.
But we only have three hours.
Three hours is a very small amount of time.
But we will do as much as we could today.
And I hope that each one of you get at least something
that you can take away with you.
That's the main goal.
So let me know at the back if you can see the presentation.
If you can see the notebook, no.
Let's see.
I'll try to change it.
How about that?
It's better.
Let's see.
I think we can go one level.
I think we can do fine with this.
So the first part is mostly like cover
The first part is basically a primer on tensors.
I wasn't going to do this part.
But I realized that most of you guys
are actually starting to use PyTorch
or maybe have not used it before.
So I think it's a perfect time to introduce it
and just get the idea of what kind of features
and what kind of tools you have access to with this ecosystem.
So this is just a bunch of things that we'll do.
What is a tensor?
Building tensors.
Everything is about tensors at the beginning.
But slowly we will transition into the NLP material.
But this part is super important.
And we only have roughly, I planned it 20 minutes.
And I do have some exercises at the end.
So I will time this just to make sure
that we are on schedule with everything.
So let's see.
So what is a tensor?
That's the first question.
A tensor is just define it.
I would define it as just like a data structure, basically,
that you use in deep learning a lot.
That's how I would define it.
Very simple definition of it.
And basically, it's the core data structure
that you use to build models from the beginning to the end.
So that's what you're going to do.
And you do transformations in these tensors.
And that's just basically what you're doing all the time.
So this snippet here is just you see here.
And I will teach you how to use Google Cloud.
Because if you're not familiar with it,
it's pretty simple to use.
If you have used Jupyter Notebooks before,
I think you'll be OK.
So I basically imported Torch here,
which is the main library.
If you have access to the notebook, please,
just follow along.
But you will get an opportunity to do this
once I cover this part.
So building tensors, constructing tensors.
So the first thing is how to build a scalar.
That's kind of the most primitive way
of defining a tensor.
It's just building a scalar.
It's basically like a number or maybe a letter
or something like that.
It's just one element.
So we have one element there.
We print it out.
And that's it.
So after that, we have a 2D tensor, which is a vector.
If you're familiar with these terms, it's OK.
Just bear with me.
We'll move pretty quickly here.
So you'll get a chance to also, if you
are not familiar with it, you'll get a chance to explore.
Yes?
Can you just follow along?
Not really.
The way how I designed it is because we
don't have a lot of time.
So what I will do is I will just go over it pretty quickly.
And then I will give you guys some time
to just go through the exercises and go on it by yourself.
So like I said, most of the tutorial
will be I want it to be student-oriented,
so you've got the hands on.
And you can ask your questions.
You can ask me, and I'll be happy to support.
I think we'll find the right way to create one.
Maybe you can create a copy of it.
Yeah, you'll need to create a copy of it.
But I'll show you how to do all of this.
So just bear with me.
I will just go through the tutorial pretty quickly,
and then we'll do this all together.
So we have a 2D tensor.
We created it.
Actually, that's not a 2D tensor, but anyways.
Yes.
Something happened there.
I'll fix that.
So a 2D tensor will only be, oh, sorry.
So a 1D tensor is a vector.
The 2D tensor is a matrix.
So we have that there.
And then we have a 3D tensor, which
is just another dimension added to the data structure.
And then we can also build a tensor using
some other data structures, using another format.
So usually, you can build tensors using NumPy,
if you're familiar with that.
I think most people that do data science
are familiar with this, too.
So you can also build out of a NumPy array,
also build a tensor.
It's pretty flexible and very dynamic in that way.
So I have an exercise here.
Like I say, I will just give you time to do all of this.
And if you have questions, we'll definitely
do all of this together.
Special tensors.
There are some special tensors offered by PyTorch.
And the community is very heavily involved
with this library.
So you'll find that some people use things
like a matrix of full zeros.
Some would use matrix of full ones.
And then you have all these special cases.
And once it's popular, then you will
see that there's a function for it automatically.
And that's pretty neat.
And yeah, you have very special tensors
like this one, which is a diagonal one.
And then we can also build tensors using
some random information.
And you can also build another tensor.
So what I mean by that is you build one tensor.
It has some properties.
You want to preserve that property.
And you want to build another tensor
with those same properties.
And properties, I mean dimension.
So when you create it, you create it like that.
So B copies the properties of A. And you
have a matrix full of ones.
That's neat.
It's so dynamic and so flexible that you can do all
of these kind of things.
Yeah, the data type is also copied along too.
So we have Linspace, which is a function to create a range.
Usually, sometimes we will need a range,
especially when we are dealing with batches of data.
We will need a range.
So we have a function for that.
We just recently found out this one.
I would usually use NumPy for it.
But the library is growing so fast
that you always have a new function every time building.
So one of the things that you will find out
from this tutorial is that you'll
be referring to the documentation pretty heavily.
That's pretty normal.
Even for someone that is using PyTorch a lot,
you will just reference that tutorial.
And the tutorial is pretty cool.
It's well-built.
And it has a lot of examples, which is neat.
And you'll definitely learn a lot using the documentation.
Even for experts, you always find
that you are referring to that tutorial all the time.
So we have some exercise here again just to construct
a tensor.
I'll give you time for that.
Tensor properties, how to check what type of tensor.
Someone asked what type.
We have what the type of the tensor is.
What's the size of the tensor?
Sometimes it's really good to probe that
before you're going to train a model.
And you have tensor slicing, how to capture a specific row,
a specific column of the data.
That's pretty standard data science stuff here.
And we have tensor operations and transformations.
So how to transform?
We have a tensor of ones.
How do we convert the first two rows into zeros
and now the rest one?
So you can do that pretty easily.
And how to transpose, which is a very important functionality
in deep learning.
How to transpose a matrix.
OK, so we have here we print out the.
So you notice that when we do a tensor here,
the tensor looks something like that.
We have the zeros and ones here.
And when we transpose it, you notice
that it changes the shape.
So not the shape, but you notice the values, they shift.
So the thing is, when you do the transpose, it's not in place.
Which means it's not going to be applied to A here.
Because we're using a notebook, the transformation appears.
But usually A would not be preserved.
So what I mean by that is, let's say I print A again.
It's not preserved.
And that's very important, especially when you are
using that functionality a lot.
I always remember that it's not in place.
And if you want to make it explicit in place,
you'd have to use something like this,
which is a special character.
So in this case, the method will be transpose underscore.
And that preserves the transformation.
So now you see that it's preserved here.
So the transpose of what we wanted is here.
So some simple maths.
We have built two tensors.
Do a plus here.
It's pretty simple.
If you're familiar with that, this
is basically what you do with every deep learning library.
And how to add.
Also, if you want to add in place,
you use that underscore again.
So everything that is in place, you use the underscore.
So power and sum also, you can have a tensor.
You can do lots of different operations in it.
You can do power of 2.
And then you can sum all the elements.
And you have some final output.
That's a very basic math you can do with those tensors.
And you have element-wise multiplication,
which is also a very important operation in deep learning.
So you have that element-wise.
You're going to times the i by the 1s.
And you have that spatial matrix,
which is basically just the i itself back again.
So I have some exercise here.
It's a very tricky exercise.
I would say that if you go through the notebook,
if you form groups, if you don't understand some part
and you want to capture what it is, just ask the question.
I would say that if you do this exercise on your own,
you're in good hands.
For a beginner, you will be good using this tool.
Because it actually will challenge you to think a bit
on how you can use those functions.
So CUDA tensors.
So this one is a little bit more advanced.
So if you're using a lot of GPUs,
this is where all these functionalities come into play.
So you have some functionalities here,
like checking whether a tensor is existing in your GPU
or if it exists in the CPU.
So you can check all of those.
And you have all the different methods to do that.
So here, it's pretty simple to check whether after you
have assigned something to a CPU or a CPU,
you want to know later on where is that stored,
where are you operating on, what kind of device.
So you can actually check like that with this very simple
method.
So we have like, so you can see that if you use GPU,
you know that the difference between CPU and GPU
is pretty significant, especially
when you are multiplying really high dimensional tensors.
So in this case, for example, I have one here.
1000 is not so huge.
But when you're doing 10,000, for example,
that's pretty heavy already on the CPU.
So you can see that this is 103 milliseconds.
But if you use something like a GPU,
and the cool thing about Google Collab
is that you already have access to some GPU
to play around with.
So you will see that the difference here.
Well, here it took a little while.
That's because it has to first connect to the GPU.
But if we do it again, it's pretty fast, right?
It's like two times faster.
So you can see 20.6 milliseconds.
It took a lot shorter time.
And you see that the difference between the two operations
is that we have that .cuda.
.cuda means that we want to operate,
want to assign this tensor into the GPU.
And you don't really need to know all the GPU stuff,
all the low level stuff.
All you need is just that function itself,
and then you assign it.
And it's so flexible for a programmer that's
want to leverage both CPU and GPU
and use some form of parallelization.
This is so easy.
It's pretty easy to use these functions.
And that's, yeah.
Yeah.
So that's a great question.
So the question was if you can use all the different functions
that you have in NumPy, right?
And if you can use them in PyTorch as well, or CUDA,
you say it, right?
Yeah.
So yeah, so PyTorch is basically built on top of NumPy.
So you have access to all the functionalities.
And once you have that tensor, you can just assign it to a CUDA.
So it's a pretty straightforward library in that sense.
So one thing that I do notice from a lot of tutorials
is that they teach you how to have a similar tutorial
like this.
You may have seen it online.
So you have that tutorial where you do element-wise multiplication.
You do a transport.
That's good.
But one of the fundamental things about this library,
and in particular, tensors and deep learning,
is that you will usually have a chain of operations.
You have to think of data like in a chain of operations.
And that concept is called competition graphs.
So what you do is basically have a function
being applied on top of a data structure.
And you keep applying different functions on top of that.
And it transforms a tensor, a data structure, into different values.
And you keep doing this transformation.
So the concept of chaining is super important.
But I don't see that it's pretty like for many people that do tutorials
and do blogs and this kind of thing, they're not focusing on that.
I think it's really fundamental to be focused on that and how to leverage it.
So I have a basic example here.
If you can go through this example, you'll definitely
understand how to chain different operations.
And you will see how that makes sense when you're doing deep learning
for MLP.
Later on, you will see.
So I just have some example here that you can go through on your own.
We'll give you a chance to do that.
These are just more operations, transformations.
Yeah, and that's it for this part.
So what I would do is basically, I don't know how you prefer.
If we can do groups, I think it would be better if we can do groups.
We can go or just stand up behind someone.
And we can just quickly go through these exercises,
just so that everyone gets something from the tutorial itself.
So any volunteers for leaders?
We need at least, I would say, at least seven.
Any volunteers?
We just quickly go through the exercise.
Is that OK?
Or how do you prefer we do the exercise?
By table?
OK.
How much time do you think you need to finish all the exercises?
We have, like, let's see.
Oh, you were working on it already?
Yeah, it'd be cool if at least everyone gets
to do at least part of the exercise.
Anything that you are not comfortable with here, please ask.
And we'll go over it together.
And I will actually provide some.
I will go over some of the solutions also myself here,
so that you can see on the screen.
So maybe five minutes.
Five minutes.
We don't want to spend too much time on this one,
because we have all the other core material that we need to cover.
And we don't have a lot of time.
So yeah, let's just start.
Please, if you have any questions, just raise your hand,
and I will come to you.
OK.
Ok.
So we'll try to do it.
Otherwise, we wouldn't be able to finish today.
So I hope everyone got a little bit of a taste of what
PyTorch is about, and you understand
some of the strengths of it.
That's basically the idea of the tutorial,
just for you to familiarize yourself.
You don't need to know everything in this notebook.
It's not important.
As we dive deeper, you will see that these are just
basic operations that we're doing.
But you won't need all of this.
There are more important operations
that you would have to familiarize yourself with,
but just the idea of PyTorch.
So let's just move on.
OK, so we have part two, which is what I call getting started
with PyTorch.
So the reason why the previous tutorial isn't the starting
point in PyTorch, in my opinion, is that PyTorch is usually,
the strength of it is not really the tensor operation.
The tensor operation is basically
what you get from non-Py, what you get from TensorFlow,
and all these other libraries.
I think one of the strengths of PyTorch,
initially when it was built, was that it has this thing called
automatic differentiation, which is just a very complex concept
for what we do in deep learning, which is just having
a bunch of operations, doing some forward propagation,
and doing some backward propagation,
if you're familiar with those terms,
and you will get some output in the end.
So that's just basically the idea
of the automatic differentiation, which
includes the backward process.
So here, just to make this concept a lot much easier
for someone that's beginning to use PyTorch, what I did
is I captured this from a book.
I don't remember which book.
I'll put the source later on.
But I have, so there are a lot of these type of, like,
graph.
But I like this one a lot, because it actually shows,
we have a tensor here, a scalar.
And you see some transformation being done.
It's pretty clean.
I like this.
I use it for all my presentations.
But it shows exactly what is going on at each step, right?
So if you understand the basic math,
how to do the partial derivatives of a variable,
you will see that that's the answer.
So what I did was, so in the book, you only see this.
And they explain what it is, what the concept is.
But I would just take it a step forward
and actually implement it using PyTorch.
So what I did is just implement it here.
You have some implementation here
if you have access to the notebook.
It's a very simple implementation.
But it's, how should I say, it's pretty powerful.
When you actually implement all these lines of code,
you will see exactly what the strength of this tool is,
which is all the other stuff, all the crazy stuff going on
behind the neural network is being done automatically,
behind the scenes.
And all you need to do is just make an explicit line
like that, and you should be able to do
a lot of different operations behind the scenes.
So I can go on and on and talk about what the strengths are
and what are some of the wonderful parts of PyTorch.
But the idea of this tutorial will
be just to make it explicit, try to build your own graph,
your own competition graph, and you get the idea of what it does.
And from there, I think you'll be
able to extend this into a neural network
and even to a deep learning model.
So I have some example here.
And then there's an exercise here
in which you compute some derivatives of some variables.
Don't pay too much attention to this complicated stuff
if you're not pretty familiar with math.
And so I think it's pretty easy to understand.
Once you go through the code and you code it yourself,
you will see what it does.
And these figures really help out a lot.
So each component, each important component,
so we know that the most important component,
as I mentioned, is a competition graph.
But every competition graph has to have an input.
So in this case, it's just a scalar.
And you will see that I have some block here
talking about what the input is and have
some explanation in your time.
You can always go through the brief explanations
I put there.
And you have an explanation here that says, OK,
in order for you to have a sample,
you need to have some kind of dimension.
And usually in NLP, when you're doing NLP deep learning models,
you have some kind of dimension.
So you have a batch size, max sequence length,
times the vocabulary size.
So that's usually what you use.
In computer vision, you use something different,
some different size.
If you use videos, it's completely different dimensions
you're dealing with.
So that's just the point of this full lines of code
here, just to show that you can create some random information
of that size.
And you can use the properties to get access to it,
just to see what the size of it is.
And you can do some sample also, just with random information.
You can reduce it to 100.
You don't really need to do the 10,000.
So you have that there also.
And the point was that in order for you to have some kind of,
usually in NLP, what we do is you
don't want to work with those dimensions above 10,000.
That's going to be crazy.
That's going to be too intensive for your CPU
if you only have a CPU.
So what you usually do is we want to reduce that
to something like 100.
So with that idea and that need came these things
called word embeddings.
So now we're not really dealing with that 10,000 dimension.
Now we need something like 100 dimensions.
So if you have heard about word embeddings,
that's the whole idea behind it, just
to have something more efficient to work with.
I explained it there in some paragraphs.
And I just gave some exercise here
on how to the kind of things that you need.
You need to use something like permute.
Sometimes you will need to change.
Usually some models would want or require a certain dimension.
So usually sometimes they would have something
like SequenceNet at the beginning and then Bash Size.
So we need to transform the tensor itself.
So I would use something like permute.
But there are other functions you can use as well.
So that's just a method.
And then so we have the competition graph.
We have the input.
Then there's something called linear transformation.
So what is that?
Linear transformation is just I think we saw a bit of it here.
Actually not.
That's a very simple figure.
So linear transformation is something like this.
So there's a mat here.
It's a weight times the input plus bias.
So that's kind of the basic component of a neural network.
And how do we put this mat into code?
So you can imagine there's a lot of things
that you need to know.
But basically what we're doing is we just need some input.
And I have the input here already.
I just specify my input.
And then I have some transformation
that I want to do.
So I have my input, and I want to transform it
for it to give some y value.
And the Wx plus b is actually encapsulated
in this object here.
So all you need to do is just pass in your dimensions.
And all of that is taken care of.
By the way, when you do something like this, what you do
is you have to initialize.
If you are familiar with neural networks,
you have to initialize your weights.
You have to initialize your bias.
And then you have to do the transformation later on.
But with these objects here, with these classes,
you already have those things going on behind the scenes.
So you don't need to explicitly do it.
All you need to do, or you'll find out,
all you need to do is you just need
to specify the dimensions.
Because it's the same transformation
you need to do anyways.
So you don't need to explicitly say that.
So you have an output here.
And then there's nonlinear transformation,
which is what's called the activation functions.
So after you have some linear transformation,
you want to apply some nonlinear transformation on that output.
And so you have a different function for that.
Usually we use sigmoids.
We can use tanh, ReLU, all those concepts in neural networks.
I'm not really going to go deep into those concepts.
I think you can read about them later on.
It's not so important in this tutorial.
OK, so any questions so far?
Anything that you would like?
Yeah.
You used the variable fc.
Yes.
So yeah, so the idea is just that it's a fully connected
layer.
And you would achieve that just using that line of code.
I didn't get the question, sorry.
How does it match the dimension?
Oh, yeah.
Why do you like to do that?
So usually what you do is that's something.
So I struggled with this when I was initially
learning PyTorch.
That's one of the things that I think
was lacking at the beginning.
You didn't know which dimension you needed to put first,
or what dimension goes second, and so forth.
So usually what you do is you have
So usually what you do is, since it's a chain of operations,
usually what you do is you put the last dimension.
If you don't know which size to put,
you would put the last dimension coming in.
That would be the first here for the fully connected layer.
So when you're designing neural networks,
that's something that you need to be aware of.
That if you put a different size there,
it will be incompatible.
And usually it throws an error.
So yes.
So you could put the one that's the second size
tied into the same parameter.
So it's already encapsulated using this one,
using the linear object here.
It's already packaged.
But if you wanted to do it explicitly, then you
would have to do it on your own, like create your weights.
So I just put a layer that's using the linear space here.
Yeah.
So it's set to 90% by putting a 10% to it's call
where you're including the key.
That's why I tried to explain.
That it's already done behind the scenes for you.
It already knows which dimension, what's the size of it.
And it just uses some initialization already for you.
Oh, that's different.
Yeah.
What value do you choose?
Yeah, what values do you choose.
It's a good question.
And you can see in the documentation
that it has all the different choices.
You can change.
Yeah.
Yeah, it's a default. Yeah.
Do you use more attention when you're doing things like this?
No, you don't.
Yeah, this is like, I forgot to mention,
but everything is just eager execution.
So yeah, everything is done automatically.
Yes.
Yeah.
Sure.
So we have an input of that size.
And so we have 64 by 60 by 100.
Right?
So this is like a range three times the length.
Yes.
It's hard to picture, but you can just imagine this.
It has a lot of dimensions here.
Yes.
OK.
And let's say you wanted to build a neural network,
a very simple neural network that only has one layer, one
fully connected layer.
Usually what you do is basically that is what is represented up
here in the equation.
And what you do is you have to explicitly define
what the weights are, what the biases are, and all of that.
But what I was saying is that once you have this line of code
here, this linear, and you specify the dimensions of it,
you have already everything done behind the scenes.
But the most important part is someone.
Sorry, I didn't.
You have to use the
So it's just like, as I said, it's just like a transformation
on x, right, that we're doing.
But we're just applying weights and biases, right?
Yeah.
You have to use the weights.
You have to use the weights for all of the weights.
Yes.
So 50 would be the size of the layer, the number of units.
So I don't have a figure here, but if you know neural networks,
when you have some input, you would have some layer,
fully connected layer, but you have to specify a dimension for it.
It could be one, it could be two, it could be,
how many neurons do you want, basically?
That's the question.
And in this case, we just choose 50.
It can be any.
Oh, you want to see?
OK.
We have it.
We're going to actually, let's see.
Yeah, we can do that.
That's not wrong.
Right.
So we want x.
Let's see.
Yes, just random information.
It's just for illustration purposes.
It's not really anything important or special about it.
Yes, that was a sign.
That was a sign.
Yeah, that was a, yeah, that was an exact information.
It's an exact information.
It's an exact thing.
So do neural networks take non-sensory,
or are they all non-sensory?
Yes.
So it's really hard to specify.
Yes, exactly.
Yeah, and I printed out the sample.
It looks, all right, it's crazy.
This is random information, yeah.
I just wanted to have an example here.
I'm sorry.
I'm trying to go a little bit faster, because I could say,
this is just spider stuff.
We're not even touching the NLP stuff yet.
So because of time, we need to move.
All right, so other component is softmax classifier.
Another type of transformation here.
It's just, I have some explanation here.
It's just a normalized representation of the output.
The output would be basically what
I'm outputting from the linear transformation.
So just another transformation.
You apply some function again, and you keep doing this.
So you can see that it's just a chain of operations
that they're doing.
And you're just calling a function,
and everything is just being done behind the scenes.
And if you ever need to change what softmax do,
you can actually change that behavior of the softmax
function.
So yeah, that's basically what it does.
And the softmax, of course, is just a distribution, right?
The range 0 to 1.
You see how the values are from 0 to 1.
So and then I have some exercise here,
just to get some more practice on how
to chain those linear layers and nonlinear layers also.
You can practice that.
So I think it's a good time to try to go over the notebook.
I didn't go over this part so much.
I think this one is very important in this notebook.
Let me just take two minutes to explain it.
So we have two tensors, right?
We have two tensors.
And I want to do some forward transformations.
So what I do is just define layer 1, and I have two tensors.
And I say, OK, I want to require gradient equal true, which
means I want to apply.
I want to apply some kind of some gradients
transformation on that.
So I say true.
If this was false, I cannot really
obtain those values from this.
And you have to explicitly say.
So and then layer 2 is, so again, it's more visually
more clear here on the figure.
And that's why I didn't want to go over it,
because I think it would take a little while
to go over each part.
What do you mean by gradient equal true?
So gradient is just like some values
that you get from an equation.
So the equation is just specified here.
So let's try to do the exercises.
I think that's a better choice here.
Just to get you more familiar with how
to do more tensor transformations,
I think the other exercise was on how to change linear layers.
So try to combine five linear layers.
Just use different dimensions just
to get some practice.
You saw that I just used one.
We tried to change some of them just
to get the idea on how you would chain all these operations.
So just try that for now and maybe five minutes or so.
Always, if you have questions, just let me know
and I will come to you.
I know this is going pretty fast,
but I have to keep up the pace, because we have a lot more
content to cover.
Sorry, I'm just going to.
OK.
OK, so I'm going to move on.
So I'm going to move on.
Sorry.
So these two notebooks, basically,
I just want to say that in your time, you can go through them.
Try to understand them.
I have long descriptions.
You can go through them.
If you need any more information,
you can always search for the terminologies
that I included there.
It'll make it much easier for you to understand.
I would say that if you want to do the rest of the notebooks
that I have here, it'd be really important to go
through those two notebooks.
I don't want to really emphasize too much
or put too much time into it, because I believe
that you can do this on your own.
I truly believe that.
I think the more unique part and the more important part
of this tutorial will be the other segments that we will cover.
And you will see that we're not going to do all the tensor stuff anymore.
You will see that everything is just very high level.
So let's just continue so that we make it for the break,
because we have a break at 3 o'clock.
So let's go.
And for this, I will take my time.
I will explain parts more in depth.
It won't be so fast like the first two tutorials.
So in NLP, we have different kind of tasks that we can work on.
These tutorials that I prepared here are more specific to classification,
because classification is something that's much easier to explain.
If you have something like language generation,
that would definitely be something more advanced.
But I think classification is something you
can use to easily explain concepts.
So the first thing that we want to do is load a data set.
In that folder I shared, there's a data set that I used.
Actually, that data set is part of my, I wasn't supposed to make it public,
but I made it public for this tutorial.
I think it's really nice to have a real world data set.
The only thing I would say is that don't try to make it public.
Just try to use it for your own purposes and educational purposes.
That's the only thing I ask.
So we have a data set.
So here is just some functions.
I can just, we have some functions that I declared here.
Not so important.
But when you're doing Google Collab, how do you connect with your data?
So you have a data stored in a Google Drive, right?
How do you get access to it?
This is not your local machine.
So what you do is you have these two lines of code here.
If you have the notebook in front of you.
And if you try to run those two cells, you
would see that there's a message here with some URL here.
So basically, it's asking for authorization
to get access to Google Drive.
Obviously, this one, you cannot access my Google Drive.
If this was the case, then that would be really bad.
But yeah, the cool thing is you can make a copy of it,
and then you can access your own Google Drive.
So if you try it, so it asks you for signing.
If you sign in with your Google account, you give it access.
It's perfectly safe, by the way.
It's your account, so you should be fine.
So then you paste that code.
And basically, what I'm doing is just mounting the drive.
Like you would mount your local drives.
So now it says it has mounted the drive.
This is very important, because most of the time,
we need a data set anyways.
You won't want to work with random information.
So this part is very important for Collab.
So you have the drive mounted.
And my data is stored in the folder in my Google Drive.
So it's like merge training.
It's a pickle file.
It's already stored there.
And you have access to that already in your Google Drive.
If you made a copy of it, you should have a copy of it.
If you don't, don't worry.
We will have enough time to make a copy of it
and go through all the different steps.
So I will load the data.
And notice that for those people that are familiar with Pandas,
it's basically a data frame that I'm using here.
One thing I found when I do a lot of research,
I would always want to use a data frame.
Every time, I would use a data frame,
because it has those nice functionalities to render
a plot or something like that.
I wouldn't initially just go jump straight
into working with the tensor.
I want to know more about my data.
So usually, I would store it in that kind of format.
And so you have access to that one in a data frame.
And yeah, I just plot here the distribution of the data set
classes.
So it's an emotion labeled data set.
So you have six emotions here.
It's not the entire data set, because my real data set
has more emotions than that, more emotion classes.
But just for this tutorial case, I just used these six emotions.
You can see also the distribution here,
how many records are for each class.
It's a pretty huge data set when you think about it,
compared to what you have access to.
So it's a bunch of tweets.
Basically, what you get is some tweets already
pre-processed for you.
So you have it something like that.
There's a data.head, render 10 samples.
You can see the 10 samples here.
We have text.
And we have the emotion class.
And it's not so important how I got those emotion class.
If you really want to know, I have a paper for it.
All those details are there.
But it's just important that it's just the emotion of that text.
And then there is some pre-processing
that you need to do.
You have it very nice in a very nice format.
It's already shuffled and everything for you.
You want to do some pre-processing.
But you notice that the text is already very clean, right?
Usually tweets don't come like that.
So I already did a lot of the heavy work, right?
If you want access to that, all of the real data set,
and you want to know how to do this kind of pre-processing,
I also have a notebook for that.
But I thought it would be so time consuming.
So other information, I would definitely share it.
I have an extended thing that I will do.
And I will share everything on the slides.
Yes.
You're welcome.
So after the pre-processing, which there's
no pre-processing here, we have tokenizing and sampling,
right?
These are two very important parts of the transformation
that you're going to do to your data set.
And tokenizing part is basically splitting your text
into the word components, right?
So that's basically the idea of tokenizing.
And sampling is just sampling that data set all over again.
So in this case, because this is a huge data set,
and I say that after 10,000, you will
see that you will start to face some challenges
with the competition part.
So what I do is just sample 50,000.
I don't want the entire data set.
And in fact, if I try 100,000, I think the notebook will break.
So that's about your free to play around
with the entire data set and find ways to make it run.
I'll be happy if you can do that.
But I didn't get to do it, so.
OK, so we have a sample.
And we have the tokens.
So let me just print out what I mean by tokens.
So let's see.
Right, so you can see that it's the token size, right?
Not really the token itself.
I didn't store the token itself.
I think, yeah, it didn't store.
So you only have the token size, which
is the number of words in each sentence, right?
But why do I want that information?
So that information is very important
when you're doing batches.
You want to put the batches in terms of the token size
together.
So that's something that you would want to do.
So like I say, it's just part of the preprocessing step.
Sorry?
So usually, depending on what kind of task you're working on,
for this classification task, it's not so important.
You can actually just do it random.
But because I had designed this notebook for machine
translation, I had to do something like this
and get that information so that I can put batches together
of similar size.
Because that's usually very good for machine translation.
But for this one, we won't use that information.
I just had it here just to show.
Sometimes you would need this information,
depending on the task you're working on.
So we have a, now I think this is very important.
So we want to construct a vocabulary out of our data set.
We have all our text here, very nicely formatted.
And we want to create or construct
a vocabulary and some indexing.
Why is that important?
Because the next step would be to establish features.
What kind of features are we going to feed into the model?
And usually what we do is, in NLP,
usually we use word embeddings.
That's the first thing that we're going to use.
That's like a very typical use case, use word embeddings.
So we need to construct a vocabulary first.
Before we even talk about embeddings,
we just need to construct a vocabulary.
Because we need to tell the model what we want to embed.
What kind of words do we need to get those embeddings for?
So that's just basically the vocabulary.
And this class does that.
I don't want to go over the details
in what this class does.
You can basically tell what it does,
but it's just rendering the vocabulary itself.
So after I do, let's see, just run it.
So there's some strange word here.
I hope that doesn't break the code.
I never saw it before.
But anyways, so you can see.
Yes.
Yeah, you're right.
And usually that kind of words, as a best practice,
usually you would have to normalize that kind of word.
You remove the A's, remove all the repetitive R's.
But it just so happens that in this case, I missed that one.
Something happened.
It happens.
So hopefully nothing breaks later on.
So after we have that vocabulary,
you would use that information.
You have that information accessible
to transform your data.
Now you have all the words that you need.
And you need to convert each sentence into a tensor.
How do we do that?
How do we convert each sentence into a tensor?
A tensor of values.
And each value in that tensor would be basically an ID,
an index, into that vocabulary.
So what I mean by that.
So let's see.
So we have two sentences.
I select two sentences.
And notice that when I print it out,
some weird numbers show up.
So we're not dealing with text anymore.
We're dealing with numbers.
We have done all the transformation already.
So this is a sentence.
No one can say with the sentences.
No one.
I can bet on that.
No one can.
But you can see that it's an ID, an ID into that vocabulary.
And each ID represents a word in that vocabulary.
So far so good?
OK.
So after that, let's say we want.
So there's some exercise here.
You can try it on your own.
We'll do that after I finish the notebook.
Or you can try it.
So after that, we have to do some padding.
Notice that some sentences are longer.
Because you can see the first one is a lot longer
than the other one.
It's longer.
See?
The size, right?
So what you do in that case is you need to pad it.
Because if you want to do something
like a standard neural network or a deep learning model,
you have to have those data of the same size, the inputs
at least.
And that's very important when you're dealing with models
like RNN.
You'd have to have that already normalized already,
the same size, each input.
So that's basically the concept of padding.
I do a padding.
First, what I want to find out, what's the max length
of all the sentences?
Just collect the size of all the sentences
and check what the max length of the longest sentence is.
And in my data set, it's 69.
So we have a tweet of 69 words.
At the beginning, when I started at 69,
I thought that was wrong.
But after Twitter changed their policies,
now you have longer texts.
So you have some sentences with 69 words.
So now you have some padding that you need to do.
So this function takes care of that.
So let's see.
OK.
So what I did here is I padded the inputs.
So now you have all the same size, all the inputs
of the same size now.
And you can see the padding was done just using zeros.
So that's standard.
Your data is standardized now using the padding.
I know it's hard to understand what it means,
but just think of it that it's just a sentence.
So after that, we have a binarization step.
And this one is going to take care of.
So we took care of our sentences, our input.
Now we have our target classes that we
need to take care of.
We cannot train a model if we don't have classes in this case,
because this is supervised learning.
So we need classes.
So all this code takes care of.
So this is like Scikit-learn.
If you're familiar with Scikit-learn, I hope you are.
So Scikit-learn is just have a lot of utility functions
that you can use to just transform your data,
do some kind of special operations in your data,
and you get a lot of functions there.
So what I did there is just to obtain my target values.
So my target looks something like this.
Again, we're dealing with numbers.
Everything is numerical values.
So now it's something like this.
The classes are like this.
So for example, let's say this was anger, and this was,
I don't know, disgust maybe.
I don't remember really the label number,
but each one is a different class,
because it's a one-hat encoding.
And these are just two records, two different classes.
So our data looks like this again, just to refresh.
I have a text, a motion, and a token size.
That's the Pandas data frame.
And now we want to, so as I said at the beginning,
what was the, I didn't know what was the emotion class here.
So I just created a function here just
to get access to what was the emotion label,
just to keep track of it.
These are just things that you do
to just keep checking that you're in the right direction.
Not so important for this tutorial,
but it's just something that you need to keep track of.
And I have some more additional code
that I use just to run more checks that I'm
in the right direction.
So you can see here that I'm looking at the first sentence
just to make sure.
Yeah, I'm there, the same sentence.
So after binarization, we have the input represented
in numerical values.
We have the target represented in numerical values as well.
What do we do next is we need to establish batches in order
for us to do a training.
So these are more functions that I use here.
So you can see that I'm using this train test split function
that's provided by CycleLearn, another very helpful function.
And that just splits the data into a training, test,
and validation data set.
So we have three portions.
And each one has a different intention.
So the training data set is for training the model.
Testing data set is for basically testing
the model on the go while we train.
And the validation is a held-out data set
just to check whether the model really generalized well
or is doing well in the prediction.
So that code takes care of that.
Let's see again just to make sure.
It's divided like this.
So remember, it was 50,000 records.
So our training data set is 40,000.
Our validation, 5,000.
And our test, 5,000.
Why do you see a bunch of numbers?
Because I actually printed out together with the tensor
the target and the input.
So you saw that those are just pairs, right?
So now I think this is the core thing.
The thing that I really like about PyTorch
is that initially it was built with these very nice classes.
So usually when we work with training data sets
and validation data sets, we have the data set
in a really nice format.
But you will notice that even if you have your data
split and everything, you still need to do extra stuff.
So you can see that the data sets are really nice.
Just like extra steps on that data.
A lot of things that you need to do to get it right
in the right format before you feed it into a model.
And PyTorch provides very good support for that.
There are a lot of nice classes that you can use
to take care of a lot of the things that you need to do
with the data.
So I will just show what I mean by that here.
So I just have some parameters here like the batch size,
which is 64.
And then there is the different sizes of the trained,
validation, and the testing data set.
And then I would import those classes that I want access to.
So why do I want to do all of...
You have my data in batches already.
But I don't have them in batches.
I have them training, validation, and testing.
No batches yet.
How do I make sure that I have my batches
and that this is done very efficiently?
How do I do that?
Usually what I would do is before what I did is use NumPy.
I would just manually do it, manually do my batches,
and then I would feed it into the model.
But what I realized is that I did a lot of mistakes
while doing this.
Usually I would have some error.
Usually I don't know if you have faced this before,
but sometimes I would even feed the same batch again
into the model, and this would create a lot of problems
during training.
So there are some efficient classes provided by PyTorch
to take care of all of that.
So one of them is a data set class.
So what I did here was just provide a class
that specifies how I want to set up my data.
So here I have this very nice class,
and I'm specifying how do I initialize it.
I want the self-laid data to have the input,
then I want that to be the target,
and then I want the length of it.
I want that information.
So this is going to encapsulate all the information
that you want to use during training time.
And when you specify to get that item function,
what do you want to get from it?
So you want to get something that's like in a tuple, right?
You want it to be the input, the output,
and the length of the text.
So just like the data frame I showed,
that's the same thing that you're seeing here,
but now we're using just tensors.
We're not using the actual real text.
So just imagine it that way.
And I can establish more functions,
and I can create various kinds of functions,
and everything is all taken care of here.
So let's say this is a very simple class that I built
with the data set module,
and I would just try it here and see what it does.
And that's the best way of showing, right?
So let's see what this class does.
So we have it here, and we provide the input tensor train.
We have the target, we have the pairs, right?
Input, output, pairs.
And we pass it to this as object here.
And now we're supposed to have something here
in the train data set.
But what's in that train data set?
What's encapsulated there?
So let's try to print that out and see what happens.
So let's try to print data set.
What you would expect to see is the tensor again, right?
The tensor, the input, the target, and the size.
But what you get is something like this.
It's an object.
All of that is contained already, self-contained.
So let's see.
What's in this object?
So we have different functions in that object.
Let's see.
How about batch size?
Sorry.
Right, so we have that.
Whoa.
Yeah, I never got this open before.
Yeah, it's too much.
Yeah, so that's the reason why I never had it there
in the first place, right?
But so, let's just continue.
So we have all that information encoded already,
and I would like to print something out, right?
So what I do is I want to establish those batches.
So what I do is use this other class here, data loader,
and say, okay, I want to establish batch sizes of this size,
which is 64.
I specify that.
And I want to drop the last.
Sometimes you have batches that are not the same size,
usually the remainder, so you have 64.
Maybe you have 63 in the last batch.
We don't want that.
We want to discard that.
So we say drop last equal true.
Then we want to shuffle again.
Okay, that's very important.
So now we have, again, train data set.
So let's just try again.
So the validation data set, what's the batch size?
This is 64.
Now everything is encoded here, and I can even print it out.
Let's see.
Let's see how I would print that out.
So I have all these different functions.
Let's see, data set.
Do you see some object?
Right?
If I try to print the data, do you think it will crash?
Great.
So now when I try to print it out, it prints, right?
So you can see that all the different steps what you're doing
is just have that very efficient way of encoding your data
and making sure that you have it in the right dimension
and size that you want.
Okay?
So you have access to all the different methods from that class.
Yeah, it's a whole, yeah, because I never specified.
Yeah, I never specified the batch.
But I can do that as well.
Let me just...
I don't want to print that out.
Right.
So again, let's double check that the number of emotions is six, right?
That's the number of classes.
Again, I have some utility functions here just to convert to pickles
because I work with pickles.
I prefer to do that.
And that's the end of the tutorial.
So what I did here was just encode the data, having a batch.
Now this is just ready to be used, right?
Ready to be used, train a model with it.
That's your input, right?
That's what we did.
That's why I labeled this as NLP basis
because you're not doing really NLP.
All you're doing is just a lot of preprocessing and encoding.
But that's a very important part of the whole framework, right?
So I just stored my data here.
And this should store into Google Drive, right?
If you run those lines of code, that will start to go into your Google Drive.
So I have training, validation, and testing data set.
So any questions before we go to a break?
I think we have a break.
We have 10 minutes more.
There are some exercises here, I believe.
Did I have some exercises?
Yeah, I did have one.
So maybe just you can go back and review it if you have any questions.
Just try to do this exercise here just to review the code
and understand the different steps that I took to reach the last step.
But this one is just for doing the encoding itself,
getting the vocabulary and indexing it
and have that input tensor in the format that I showed.
So just try to do that.
And I think you can just reuse the code at the top here to get that answer.
So just try it.
If you get that, I think you should be okay.
And if you have any questions, just ask.
So I think it's just 10 minutes to the break.
Yeah.
No, not yet.
Not yet.
That would be the other step.
Okay.
Let's see this.
Let's, I guess we can start to try to wrap up with our notebooks here.
Okay.
Then you can just store those pickle files to your folder and then access them.
You need to change the code later on.
Right?
So just be aware of the permissions of that folder.
Okay.
So, let's move on to part four.
So, here we're going to, like, do the deep learning that I have been talking about a
lot.
So we already did the basics, which is the preprocessing.
Here what we're going to do is we're
going to build a model, train a model,
construct a model, train it.
And we're going to use this RNN.
It's a very popular deep learning model that's
commonly used for NLP tests.
And you will see that we can use RNN, LSTMs, GRUs.
You can use any of those models.
You can see how easily later on you
can see how easy you can use those.
So the first thing we want to do is load a data set.
In the previous notebook, we had all the data sets stored
in the proper format.
So what we do now is load it again.
So you can see that each notebook is just
a continuation of the previous one.
So now we load it again, the same.
So let me just try to do something here.
Because at some point, because I don't have access,
well, Google Collab only gives you access to 11 gigabytes
of RAM.
So at some point, because I'm working on 50,000 records,
at some point it's going to break
because I'm using one machine.
So what I would do here is I would just close this runtime.
I'll just interrupt.
And you would need to do the same as well,
because you're running multiple notebooks on the same data set.
You can imagine it's using a lot of memory already.
So it's good to always.
OK, so load the data.
Let's see.
Right, it's the same steps.
I have to mount my Google Drive all over again,
because I deleted the session from before.
And that's how you will give it permission.
I didn't show the step, but now you can see it.
Right, and then you can see it.
So I'm going to close the data set.
So I'm going to go back to the previous notebook.
And then I'm going to go back to the previous notebook.
Right, and then you would enter that code again.
OK, so it's mounted.
And then again, I would use the same class all over again
to load the data set.
This is just redundant, because I just
want to make sure that we are just doing the steps right.
Yeah, so the core part of this tutorial
is the implementation of the model.
So we're going to build this model here.
Let's see if I can get that on the screen.
So that's what we're going to build.
So we have an input.
We have the input, which is x.
And then we have a layer here.
We're going to use the GRU unit for that layer.
And that's just a variation of RNN, a very efficient variation
of that.
And then we have a fully connected layer at the top.
And then we have a SAP master to do the classification.
There's very standard things that we do in classification,
very standard model.
And so now I'm going to jump into the implementation,
the actual implementation of it.
So here we have some code.
It's pretty small over there.
So we have a model that we want to build here.
And we have a name.
It's M-O-G-R-U, which almost stands for emotion.
And GRU is the type of RNN that we're using here.
So we have an init function here.
And notice there is a super class here.
What we're doing here is we want to inherit from this module,
which means we have access to all the different classes.
We inherit all the different methods in this class, this
module.
So the first thing we want to do is establish what
goes into the init layer.
Sorry, the init method.
The init method is basically where you specify the
parameters of the model, which is the batch size, the hidden
units, the number of hidden units, the embedding
dimension.
And now we're going to use embeddings, the vocabulary
size, the output size, all of those different types of
information that we need for the model.
And that's where you would put that information.
And also for the layers, we're going to specify what kind of
layers we're going to use.
So here we're going to use an embedding layer.
And I'll explain more in detail what that means.
We're going to use a dropout layer.
It's really good for regularization, which is
allowing our model to more efficiently train.
And then we have a GRU layer.
And then we have a linear layer at the end here.
So you can see it's like a chain of different operations
going on here.
So a lot of things are hidden here.
But the most important thing to know here is that you can
see that it's just a chain of operations.
And that's how you would build your deep learning model here.
And another important part of when you're using RNN is that
you need to initialize the beginning of the training.
So what you do is a hidden state.
It's called a hidden state.
And what you do is initialize those to zero.
So it's not so important what goes here.
We just want to initialize those to zeroes.
But there is a tutorial.
I would strongly recommend.
There's a Python tutorial where you can go and read more
about what this function is doing.
And this is the forward.
This is where the input enters the neural network.
So here we have first we want to embed the inputs, which
means that we're going to get embeddings from both inputs.
And then we have a hidden state that we're initializing.
And then we have the GRU layer here.
And then we have some outputs.
After the transformation, we have some output.
And then we have an extra dropout layer that we added.
And then we have the fully connected layer.
So when you look at it, it's basically this, right?
That's what we're building here.
The only thing that was missing here is the softmax.
We didn't specify the softmax here.
So typically it's like a common practice
to have the softmax being executed later on,
like in a separate function.
So I'll show later where that is.
So that's basically your model here.
That's your basic GRU model.
And it only takes a couple lines of code.
I actually have extra lines of code
that I don't really need here.
I could have just made one line.
It's pretty simple.
And that's why I said at the beginning
that the chaining was the most important part,
because you basically add more dropout maybe,
or add another fully connected layer,
or whatever you want to add here.
Yes?
So if you follow up to the feature of the model,
you have four GRUs, right?
Yes.
So I guess one question is, there's a solid line
and then there's a dashed line.
What's the difference between them?
And also, what's the difference between x0 to x1?
Yeah.
What's the difference between x0 to x6?
OK.
So x67 means it's just the size of the input.
Is 67 units?
Yeah.
Yeah, 67 is the size of the input.
So imagine the tensor that I showed
with the numerical values without the padding
and everything.
So the max size was 68.
That's what we have from 0 to 67.
That's what the figure explains.
Although the figure is pretty high level,
so you won't get that information from here.
And I'm glad you asked, because yeah, it's a clarify.
And then the GRU, of course, is just
like the whatever you want to make that layer, whatever size.
Here, I only have each input going into each unit.
Because at the end of the day, when you're doing an RNN,
you have to do it for each input.
You would have to have a unit.
Other transformations have to happen for each component
of the input.
That's just how the RNN is designed.
But if you were using something like a standard neural network,
then the unit size doesn't have to be of that same size.
It should not be consistent with that.
It could be a different size.
So when you find the model, it seems
like you have GRU only listed once,
rather than multiple times, or in dynamic.
Right.
So here, you saw that.
So let me just explain a little bit more on that.
So we have this, which is a GRU.
You notice that the GRU, the first dimension
is the embedding dimension, which should be the input.
And then the other one is the hitting units,
the number of hitting units.
So these two are separate things.
So the hitting units can be any size you wish,
just like a fully connected layer can be any size,
like what we said.
But the embedding dimension is very important
that it's very consistent and represents the input dimension.
Is that right?
Yeah.
OK.
I mean, I think the documentation
does a pretty good job of explaining it very well.
That's why I always recommend that if you really
want to know more of what it's doing,
because this is just very high level,
if you want to know more, I really
recommend that you look at it.
Right.
So then we have, let's see.
Let's just try to run the block of code.
And one of the things that I really
like to do when building a model is pre-testing.
It's something I call pre-testing.
So what you usually do after you implement your model
is just go straight into training.
That's the typical thing that you would do.
But what I want to know is exactly what's going on,
what each transformation is doing.
I just like, I'm very curious what's going on, right?
So I like to pre-test the model.
So what I do is just generate some code.
So these are just the parameters of the model,
like the batch size, the embedding dimension,
the number of units for the layers.
Yeah.
Do you need to say that it's 6A or something?
Because the maximum size of the model is 6A?
No.
So one thing I didn't explain.
So we have the inputs, and the max length of the input
is 67.
But after that, after we have that input,
then we have to generate embeddings.
So embedding, that's why we call it, is like a layer.
So here we're going to generate embeddings for each one
of those tokens.
So now we don't have that max length, which
is going to be the 67.
Now the max length is going to be 256.
That's going to be the vector for each word.
So all of that, you can see that it's hidden here.
It's not really, it's not explicit.
You can see that it's just a line of code that's
doing all of that.
From how we went from the tensors
with just the numerical values into the embeddings.
And it's just line one of code that takes care of that.
So we're taking, you have a vocabulary,
and you want to embed in a space all these words.
And you want to have these words to have some kind of relationship
with each other, some kind of what we call a semantic
relationship.
What's the relationship between king and queen?
So in an embedding space, these words
would probably be closer to each other.
And so in order for us to do that,
we need to encode these words.
We have to have some kind of encoding.
And that encoding is basically like what we call Latin features.
It's just features that the model just
chooses automatically, because it's a deep learning model
anyways.
So it chooses some Latin features,
which basically explains the semantic relationship
between words in that space.
So we have the king and queen having some kind of relationship.
And so you have that the distance between king and queen
will be much closer to what it is to maybe say something
like dog, that will have a further relationship.
So that's basically the concept of embedding.
I mean, there's a lot more information about embeddings
that I'm not sharing here.
But the point is that we need to have an efficient way of encoding
that input.
We're not going to use just the basic indices.
We can use those features as just the basic indices,
but we want to use something more efficient.
So that's why we use word embeddings.
So yeah, and I mean, I didn't mention at the beginning
that I'm really not going to go into the theory of all
of the different options and design choices that I use here.
The whole point is that you can get an idea of how
to use all the building blocks that PyTorch offers
to get the LMP task done.
That's the idea.
So sometimes it may feel like I'm going a little bit fast,
but I'm just trying to share some of my experience
and the kind of things that I do building LMP models.
So after that, we have everything.
We have the model.
And now we want to do, we have the batches, right?
I spoke about the batches earlier on.
We have all the different batches
that we're going to feed them all.
And we have this function here.
Now, this function, I don't really use it here,
but this is a very useful function for in case.
I remember earlier on I said that sometimes I
would want the batches to be of the same size.
So for some tasks, that works.
So I would want them to be of the same size.
So this function takes care of making sure
that some of those batches are consistent,
like the size is consistent.
So that very simple function does that.
And also what it does, it transforms
the dimensions of the batches.
But we won't use it here.
This code is more useful for when
I'm doing something like machine translation.
But when I was preparing this tutorial,
I just kind of borrowed some code from there,
and I just adopted it to the classification test.
So I show it here.
Maybe it could be useful if you want to ever try that.
So I'm not really going to explain that, no, exactly
what it does, and I'm not going to use it.
So yeah, I did have some example on what it does.
So I have code for here.
So now let's explain the details of this block here.
So we have a device.
Now, the first thing you want to do before training
is what kind of device you want to use.
You want to use a CPU.
If you have only access to that, then you use that.
But if you have access to GPU, then you want to use that.
So typically, what we do is we choose the selected device
that we're going to use, and then we have the model.
Now we'll create an instance of the model here.
Remember, the emoji here represents this one, right?
And we're specifying all the different parameters
that we need here.
And those parameters are specified here.
The target size, batch size, the number of units,
the embedding dimension, and the vocabulary also.
All this information that we collected already previously.
And then we say, OK, we want to put that model
into the device that's available.
In this case, we have access to GPU
because the Google guys are very generous.
So they provide GPU for us.
Why not use it?
So we use it.
Then we have a sample here.
I just generate the sample.
So notice that there is an iterator here.
An iterator, which means that I want to just select
an example of the training data set.
So that means I want to collect one batch, at least.
And we want to check what that batch has.
So now we have that batch.
And I'm going to sort that batch.
I have that batch here, and I sort it.
And so now, let's see.
So the size of it is this, which is the 69 again.
Again, it's 69.
Not consistent, right?
Because this is 68.
No, it's 69.
But 69 because we added a padding, which is the 0, right?
So we have that extra element that we
didn't talk about much.
So that's the size of the batch.
So it's 69 by 64.
Notice the dimension, right?
So it's not batch size first.
It's max length first.
So that's key when you're going to train,
because we want to make sure that those dimensions are
in the right places.
So that's why I say it's good to always do the pretesting,
what I call the pretesting, because just making sure
that before we train the model, that we
have everything in the proper dimensions,
in the proper sizes.
And then here, we set up a training.
Again, I'm just noticing I'm creating another instance
again, and just repeating the instance again,
because again, this is separate.
Pretesting is separate from the training.
Now we're going to do the training.
And we have two things here, which is the cross-entropy
loss, which is basically just computing
what the loss of the model is after a couple iterations
of training.
Now, the details of it are not so important.
You can read about what each loss,
because there's so many different losses that you can use.
Just go ahead and read up on the tutorial,
on the documentation, and see what each one represents.
But we need a loss.
We need to compute that loss, because we
need to know if the model is optimizing well.
And then we have an optimizer.
An optimizer is just what takes care
of the training, the back propagation part.
Again, you have a lot of options on what kind of optimizers
you want to use.
There's several of them.
And then these are the functions, loss function
and accuracy, just to check what the loss is.
The accuracy is just the accuracy of the model.
So two separate values that we want
to collect after training, after each round of training.
So we have the training now here, finally.
And you see it's a lot of code here.
So the most important thing is that we want to do accuracy.
We want to collect loss.
Those are the two things we want to keep track of.
We're going to run this for 10 epochs, which
is 10 iterations.
So we do that.
So notice a for loop here.
That's going to be 10 iterations.
And then we have the training, finally.
So here we have the training data set instance here.
And now we can just iterate over each batch
and start to do the training.
Now, before, what you used to do with this one
is you have to do all the preparatory batches here
in this code.
So it's pretty messy that you have
to do all the batches here.
And then this code can get pretty long
if you are doing all that code here.
So while I was saying that the data set classes and the data
loader makes it so easy because now I'm just
using that train data set iterator
and I'm just getting the batches that I need to train.
Right, so there's more code here.
And then we have the model, of course.
Then we're passing in the input, passing in the length,
and the kind of device we want to use.
If we want to use a GPU or a CPU,
in this case we want to use a GPU for faster training.
And then we're just collecting loss,
computing the loss properly here.
And then we have this code here that we say,
OK, now it's time.
We have done the forward.
Now we want to do the backward part,
specify what the optimizer is here, the backward part.
And we want to do this.
So this is just pretty standard code
that you use when you're training models with PyTorch.
So this is not something that I made up.
It's just very common.
If you go to the tutorial, you will
see that these three lines of code are always there.
You always need them.
They're always there.
It means that you can write lines in one of the code.
You can do it in the new code.
If you want to do the code, you would have to write
the same three lines.
I get it.
That's a great question.
I guess.
You can narrow the pair of code and do it better.
Yeah.
I think that would be something that they
would want to work on, because yeah, it's just something
that you need to put in there.
Very standard.
And if you're missing one of these,
you're probably not going to get the training done.
Very important.
So you have accuracy as well.
The collected loss, we have accuracy as well.
It's not very important to know all the details,
but you'll have time to go over it.
And then we have, yeah, we want to have some just,
we don't want to do it for every iteration,
but we want to every 100 batches,
we want to know a good track of the loss and the accuracy.
And notice that here, I'm using some special functionality
here.
So the batch loss, I need to put it into the CPU.
It's more efficient to do that, because it's just a number.
Why would I want to put this into a GPU?
So you can see that I put it in the CPU, and then I detach it,
and then I just convert it into NumPy, and it's just a value.
So I have the flexibility to do whatever
I want doing training with my data.
Then we have validation, the same code.
It's almost the same code that you use.
The only part is that you would see this missing,
because we are just checking what's the accuracy of the model.
We are not going to do training again.
We're not going to do it backward again.
We cannot do that in validation, because that's just
typical things in deep learning.
So I have it already.
I don't want to run it, because I'm just
suspicious that it will break.
So I have trained it already.
So you can see here that the training accuracy is 93,
and the validation accuracy is 92.
That's pretty good, I guess.
For this kind of task, this is a multi-class classification.
This is not a binary, so it's a pretty complicated task,
I would say, in my opinion.
But you can see that a very, very simple model,
like a GRU with dropout, a fully connected layer,
and a softmax layer, can achieve this accuracy
on that very complex data set.
It could show you the power of deep learning here for MLP.
And you can see that after each epoch,
you can see that it stays relatively the same.
And at some point, it will overfit at some point.
Overfitting means that there is some huge difference
between the validation and training accuracy.
So see that.
And then you need to stop it.
But I just have 10 iterations here,
and you notice that we have a very high accuracy.
At some point, you want to stop it.
And there are methods that you can use, like early stopping.
I'm not going to go into that details.
I have another notebook that talks about this,
so I will share that with you later on.
And the other thing that we want to do after we have trained
the model, we want to store it.
Sometimes we want to do some inferencing on the model,
and so we store it.
So there's a very convenient function that we can use.
PyTorch offers this one.
So it's just like torch.save, and we have the model.
And now everything is saved and serialized properly.
So the model name is just emoji.ru here.
I know if I want to use that or share it with someone,
I could just use that.
And then that person would just need to load the model,
basically, and do inferencing on it.
That's basically what would happen.
So that's the end of the notebook itself.
And the other part is how to load this model
and how to properly evaluate it.
That's kind of the last segment of the tutorial.
I think let's see how much time do we have.
So the end of the tutorial is 420, right?
420.
OK, so we have roughly 440.
OK.
So I do have a special group exercise
that I really want us to work on,
just to put everything together that we have discussed today
and that we have learned today.
So one of the things that I really
wanted to try with this model, because I showed
a very simple model, a GRU.
You saw in the figure it's very simple.
But you can do extreme deep learning.
You can do many layers of GRUs.
You can use LSTMs.
You can use all the different components
that are offered by PyTorch.
So what I would like is that we can just join,
make some groups.
I would say large groups, because maybe I'm
thinking something like seven or eight groups.
And then I would like that you guys can come and present
your model.
And what I would suggest you to do
is use the same model that we have here,
the same model that I showed here.
And look, I could just show you how easy it is.
Let me show you.
So we have the model here, right?
All we need to do is just go back to this function here,
and then you can add whatever you want to add.
So you can add another fully connected layer if you want.
You can do that.
You can just copy, paste.
Then you can just continue building on top of that.
So I would really like that if we can get into some groups
and try to go into the documentation,
just read up on it a bit more, and just have that practice
that you can go read up more on the documentation.
And you can add more GRUs if you want.
You can change it to LSTM if you want.
The documentation will tell you exactly what
you need to change when you're using different components.
So I would really like you guys to try it out.
Just change it.
Don't be afraid to change the code,
because you will have access to original code here.
And then see if you can improve that accuracy.
This is 97.
Maybe you can improve it.
I believe you can improve it.
All you need to do is just change that model that I showed.
So do you want to try it out?
I think that would be nice.
And I would just want you guys to just share what you learned.
Just share whatever you learned so far, and just try it out.
Can we do just groups?
I mean, just I'm thinking like seven groups or eight groups.
And we can just share what we have made.
OK.
Sure.
So do you prefer that, before we move on to the other?
OK, perfect.
Because I have the other one.
So.
Yeah, so I would definitely have to change forward,
and then add it here.
Yeah.
So here, I would say FC2.
OK, so we can just do port 5, I guess.
The initialize couldn't state a function in that model.
That's something that's overwritten from base model,
right?
Like you didn't implement that in the model.
No.
Yeah, I just use the standard thing that's using RNNs.
OK, let's jump into part 5.
And part 5 is why I had it hidden here, optional,
is because it's more like what you
would do when you're doing research.
It's very important.
OK, so you have an accuracy, but you don't really
know why you got that accuracy, right?
How do you explain why that accuracy is so high?
So something you want to do is properly evaluate the model,
and that's just the part 5.
So I'll go over it.
Definitely want to share that as well.
OK.
All right, so part 5, evaluating NLP models.
So I stored the model the last time, right?
And then now, again, I'm just doing the necessary steps
to make sure that I'm loading the model.
Notice that one of the things that a lot of these programmers
are working on these tools is just
trying to make sure that we have tools that you can properly
use for sharing models.
OK, we have a model that I train,
and I want to share with someone,
and I want that person to just load that model
and quickly use it.
That's something that I would love.
I think when we were working in teams,
that's something that would be perfect.
But it's so hard to get these things right
when you're building these deep learning frameworks.
So one of the things that PyTorch offers is just, OK,
you have all the model, but you still
need to do some extra work in order
for you to use that model for inferencing or evaluating
later on.
So you'll notice here that I'm using, so I unloaded,
so here I have to declare again what the class is
and everything included in the class.
Notice that there is no code before that.
It's just the same code that I used to specify the model.
I just basically copy and paste it here.
And then I have this special line here,
this important line here.
Let me just try to make this a little.
Right.
We have this line here where you load the model.
So now you have the model stored again,
and you can now use to do inferencing.
Yeah.
So you load the model, and you have to know
that it's actually a model.
Yes.
That's kind of like a drawback.
Yeah.
That's kind of a drawback.
And there's so many reasons why it's designed that way.
So many reasons.
What do you have to know to load the model?
So you would have to know the properties of the model.
You can see embedding there.
Probably put your name in there.
Yeah.
And then you can find it.
Yes.
Yeah.
The other ways you can store the model and load it,
I just find that this is, for me, the easiest way
to get things just running fast and easy.
But there are other ways that PyTorch offers for you
to store and load the model.
There are other practices that you can use.
This is just one way you can do.
All right.
So let's see.
Right, so I have that model here.
And now I want to evaluate the model.
What do I mean by that?
So I want to know why this model does so well.
Like, it has a high accuracy for a multi-class problem.
Why does it do so well?
So one way you can do that is do some inferencing on it.
So I have a validation data set, like a held out data set
that I can use to test the model.
And one of the things that I'm looking forward to do
is, so you can see again, this is standard code again,
all over again.
I'm just repeating the code here.
That's something I do when I'm doing experimenting a lot.
I like just to redo things, just making sure everything is
right.
So you don't have to do all this code repeated again.
You can just use one notebook and do everything in one
notebook.
OK, so here again.
So now we have noticed that I want
to inference on a set, like a part of an entire validation
data set, right?
Sorry, the test data set.
So what I do is I don't need to do training.
I don't need to do like, OK, epochs and other stuff,
because I just want to do one shot.
I want to just check the accuracy of the model
at one shot, because this is the inferencing part.
And one key thing is, notice I have the model running
on CUDA, on the GPU, right?
But do I really need it to be in CUDA or a GPU
when I'm doing testing?
That's something that you may want to ask yourself, right?
So in this case, I would just use it,
because I have access to it.
But if you are paying cloud services,
and you don't have that amount of money to do that,
you just want to make sure.
Because initially, this model was trained on a GPU,
so you want to make sure that you change it to CPU,
like that, right?
You're doing inferencing on that one.
And this is very useful if you are sharing models
with someone, right?
In this case, just leave it as that.
OK, so I didn't want to do this.
I missed out on some of these.
Other stuff I'm not explaining again,
because it's just repeated code.
OK, yeah, at some point, it told me
that I need to get rid of all the,
because I'm just overusing the stuff, right?
I just need to do it all over again.
OK.
There we go.
Valuating.
Oh, wow.
This one, actually.
I think I've done something wrong.
I got the same value?
Yeah, yeah.
I may have overwritten the model itself and the weights,
so you would see that it would change.
But yeah, if you do it right, if you do all the notebooks right
and you run them in that sequence,
you'll get a high test accuracy, for sure.
And one of the things that I want to show
is it probably won't work so well here.
So I have a lot of code here that I
show that I typically use when I want
to evaluate a classifier.
So just a lot of code.
And basically, what I want to do is just
plot the confusion matrix.
So a confusion matrix looks something like this.
So you can see that that model didn't do so well, right?
But generally, what you want is that you want all these values
to be super high.
And then you know that your model does well.
So you can see that the accuracy is not so good.
Because I did something wrong with the one
when I executed those notebooks.
I did something wrong.
So the model wasn't stored properly.
I used a different model, probably.
And I stopped training maybe at some point.
So it's probably not a really good model here.
But yeah, you wouldn't get a high accuracy if you did right,
if you run all the notebooks right.
And yeah.
So you have access to all that code here,
all that code that you can generate the prediction,
and you can do the inferencing and everything.
And it's just a good way when you're
doing research in NLP just to properly evaluate your models.
You just don't want to focus too much on the accuracy
or the loss, but you want to properly evaluate it,
especially for a multi-class problem.
That's really important.
Yeah.
Can you just show that?
I think you can do it in the middle.
OK.
Here.
I'm sorry to hear that.
So if you have a better one, you can
see that something is going wrong.
The system is really bad.
You can find one that's good, but what can you do?
Yeah, so what I would do is, for this kind of problem,
it's a good question.
For this kind of problem, what I would do
I know, for example, in my case, it was like I had love and joy.
There's some overlap in the language used for joy and love.
That's very common.
So something I would do, and I think someone brought it up
already, I would definitely want to do a lot more preprocessing.
I would definitely want to try to see if I, or even
obtain more data.
For deep learning cases, I think it's
really good to have a bigger data set just
to make sure that the model has enough data to properly learn
those features and weights.
That's one way when you're using deep learning,
but when you're using the classical way of machine
learning, then your engineering features,
and I really like that because you can use some domain
knowledge.
For example, I know love and joy will have a lot of language
overlapping, so I would probably want
to inject more of the language that's
going to distinguish those two classes.
What I mean by that is get more instances, for example,
in this case.
Definitely it would be more clear if I had all the steps
that I did for collecting this specific data set.
Because here I'm just showing, OK, this is a clean data set,
but I actually cleaned the data set
and reprocessed it already with many different steps.
And as I said earlier, I have that notebook
that I want to share because I think
it has a lot of information that can help you answer that question.
But for every case, you need that domain knowledge.
So yeah, there are many ways you can do that.
But since now we're only focusing
on deep learning in notice, I guess a bigger data set
would be able to help with the classification accuracy.
So didn't you say in the deep learning case
that you didn't do things like release the software,
and then you kind of did it again?
Yeah.
Did you comment on that?
Yeah, so for this kind of task, I
didn't have to do a lot of that, if you notice,
because the data was super clean.
I mean, if you analyze the data more in depth,
you would see that the data has removed stop words.
It has emojis removed.
I think emojis are removed as well.
Emoticons were kept.
Some emoticons were kept.
But I just kind of specified what I want to keep
and what I want to move, to filter.
Yeah.
I already did all of that already with the data.
That's why it's so clean.
But you would have to do all of that yourself.
It would change for every use case.
It would be different, I guess.
Yeah, so the labels were like, so it's a Twitter data set.
And each label has, yeah, it's very important.
So it's connected to your question as well.
Because for my case, I just had to collect
like a series of hashtags.
For example, like surprise.
I would have like hashtag surprise or hashtag wow.
And I would use that as a weak label, like a noisy label,
to basically determine the class of the record.
Yeah.
Can we see the things that we want to see?
Is it an eye?
Yeah, you definitely want to see that diagonal, that eye
that I showed.
But yeah.
We don't have the time, I guess.
I guess we can try to fix it.
So let me just try to rerun this notebook.
And while it loads, maybe I can answer more questions
and see if it works.
Yeah.
So on the data collection side, I
don't know how many changes you have.
But you said the more you have, the better.
What if you don't have a lot?
You have something that you want to do.
And you want to be kind of a label.
What are some values or techniques
to know about a data set?
Yeah.
There are some techniques, like in LMP.
Data augmentation is one of them.
It's not so clear.
I've been following this research space a lot.
It's not so clear how you can generate text,
keep generating text.
So for computer vision, it would be much easier.
Yeah.
Shift, the CAD.
Yeah, definitely.
So that's something that's not so clear in LMP,
how you go about doing that.
Because everything is discrete.
So yeah, so that's the kind of challenge.
But I've heard some people working on using embeddings
to do that.
I think embedding is the key thing,
to properly be able to auto-generate text,
synthetic text.
So basically, yeah.
But for my case, why I didn't focus on that
is because I have that domain expertise, which
I can use to collect larger data sets.
But it's a lot of tedious work.
In my case, I have to do more hashtags,
find out from people manually what people are texting
or what people are tweeting.
And if that is related to emotions,
and I have to do some evaluation,
and I have to use Amazon Turk to ask people
if those hashtags are really what they are.
And so I have to get a lot of that domain expertise
and evaluation from others.
So it takes a lot of work.
But yeah, there's no clear way how
you can go about generating larger data sets.
How do you know if you have enough data?
Maybe somebody's doing something like, OK, I mean,
like you're doing this thing on a kind of a curve, right?
So when do you stop?
1,000 instances, 10,000?
When do you stop?
I guess it depends on every task, I guess.
This is not a very simple question to answer.
I guess for me, it's like, OK, I tried with a sample, by the way.
I didn't try the entire data set, right?
And you can see how good the classification is.
I guess that's an indicator that I can stop,
because we have a high accuracy.
We have a low loss.
That's a good indicator.
But what do you do in cases where
you don't have such a clean data set,
don't have good accuracy?
That's your question, right?
What would you do in that case?
Yeah, like I mean, when you say, like, hey, I'm good, right?
And you can always get more, right?
But if you're starting with a small amount,
at some point, you can use a hey.
Yeah.
I guess, yeah, like I say, it's properly evaluating it,
I guess.
Doing the confusion matrix for me helped.
That's the indicator for me.
If I do have something.
So again, it's like, you need some kind of domain knowledge
at the end of the day.
That's my opinion.
You need some domain knowledge.
Because if you're going to do something in computer vision,
you have to explain why that model is doing so good.
You have to be able to explain that, right?
I mean, you can apply it if you like,
and a lot of people can't do that.
But if you really want to go to the extreme
and be innovative, you would have to just learn exactly
what the machine learning model is doing.
So on the vision side, right?
Some people might do some kind of segmentation, right?
Right, right.
You can find out a kind of cap of things.
Right.
Even a feature that they're using to recognize
that this is a cap.
Right.
Like, each map that shows you the elephant in there.
Yeah.
Is there any kind of de-tapping applied with like NLP?
Like, these are the features, and these
are the words that it's using to recognize joy or sadness?
Yeah, we do.
Let's see.
Let me try to show you like a notebook here.
So this notebook here, that I have this extra notebook here,
is basically text summarization.
So it's just another NLP task.
And what I do in this notebook uses the same code, by the way.
Model time is just different.
So it's a lot of code.
Let's see.
So I have this really wonderful visualization that I can use.
In this case, it's basically visualizing the same thing
you're talking about here.
Here, you can see that.
So this is like an attention weight.
These are attention weights, or we call it attention weights.
And it's basically indicating to you
what parts the model is looking at that are
important during training.
So in this case, you see that here, it's
focusing a lot on Bush-Argy.
So those words are important for this summary.
And so here, you see, original summary, and then
the predicted summary is this.
So what the model used to make that proper prediction.
So that's what it means here.
Yeah, I mean, there's a lot of information
that I can share here.
But I guess, just to answer your question,
there are techniques.
They're not fully developed, I guess, in my opinion.
You can use them to get an idea of what
the model is doing, like interpret
what the model is learning, what areas are important.
In computer vision, I guess it's easier to do that.
But in NLP, we're still struggling with that area.
So yeah.
Yeah, I will share all of it.
I have a series of notebooks.
I have may have up to 20 notebooks that I worked on.
And the good thing is all of them are consistent.
Use similar code should be very easy to understand, I guess.
Just a data set changes.
Right.
And I have another one here for neural machine translation.
And this one uses the attention mechanism again.
And it's the same code, the same functionality,
it's just a different data set.
I will also share with this if you're really interested in it.
Yeah, I will share this.
It takes a lot of time to explain all of this stuff.
But I think these notebooks were pretty
helpful for a lot of students.
I shared them over the past.
I really got a lot of good feedback from the,
because I spent a lot of time trying to explain,
you know, write a paragraph about it,
and try to explain it in a very intuitive way.
These things are very complicated.
But it's important, like I say, to always start
from the beginning, and just go step by step.
Just don't rush into just building that model.
So let's see if I can get that model running,
and see if I can get that accuracy.
Let's see.
I think it runs, so let's just try.
So I might have to.
Let's see.
If you have any other questions you want to ask,
or maybe after the session, feel free to approach me
and ask me.
I'll be really glad to answer your questions.
Wonderful, got it to work.
Okay, so, yeah, so I guess that was a very important
question, the one you asked, because I was gonna speak
about that here when I was showing the confusion matrix.
So you see here for joy and love, there is some overlap
there in the language used.
So you can see that the model is confusing those labels
here, so that's the true label and the predicted label.
And for surprise, usually it doesn't do so well.
And one of the reasons is that there's a lack of examples
for surprise, and let's go back to see the distribution.
So for surprise, you will see that it's 78,
and for love, it's 84.
So let's go back and see what the distribution
of this dataset was.
So you see surprise is like the class,
like with the lowest examples, right?
So small, it's like maybe less than 10,000 records
compared to all the rest.
And love also is the second, this class.
So you can see that the training time,
it will affect the model at some point.
It's something that I try to always try to do,
and I think that's the reason why I'm doing this.
At some point.
It's something that I try to argue when I wrote my thesis.
I try to argue this a lot, and I try to run
a lot of experimentation to make sure that
what I'm claiming is right,
because there may be other things that I'm not considering.
But yeah, this stuff that I'm sharing here
is just part of my PhD thesis,
so this stuff that I properly evaluated.
Yeah.
So when you change the model,
surprise is very low relative to some of the others, right?
Would you sum the examples together,
or would you add more if you did?
In that case, just try the examples, right?
That's something you can try.
You can definitely do that.
For our methods, for sure that help,
trying to balance all the datasets.
But in that case, you would lose, right?
You would lose some, like,
if you really wanna focus on some emotions,
some people, what they do is just reduce
the number of classes as well.
So instead of having the surprise and love,
maybe merge it into one, or something like that.
In this kind of task, you can do that.
Yeah, there are many ways you can try to fix it.
Any ways to fix it.
Sorry, the.
A testing library.
Yeah, another great question.
I guess for most people that use PyTorch,
that's the number one thing they would complain about.
There are not a lot of good functionalities for testing.
It's because PyTorch was actually built
for research purposes at the beginning.
And so most of the things you only have access to
are just the fully connected layers, the RNN,
and the other stuff you have to do it on your own,
which is the evaluation part.
So I have all that code that I have to, you know,
implement myself to properly evaluate them all.
I think that's done intentionally.
I mean, at some point you have to have the responsibility
to actually evaluate them all yourself.
Yeah, but there is some tool that they're working on.
I think it's called PyTex, I believe.
So it's a relatively new part of the ecosystem
that they're trying to address these issues,
like how to evaluate them all easily with PyTorch.
You don't have to use an external library to do that.
So any more questions that I can answer for you?
So the other part I really wanted to share
were those three, machine translation,
which is I think machine translation,
if you're really interested in NLP,
this is one area I would strongly suggest
for you to explore.
It is really challenging and interesting
because the whole setup is so different from classification.
There are a lot of techniques
that you need to be aware of using,
and some of these techniques, you know,
you can use them in different types of NLP tasks.
Like I said, most of the things that I share here
are actually machine translation stuff that I just use,
and I use it for classification.
So it's a very interesting field.
I guess you can learn a lot from it.
So yeah, if you don't have any other questions,
I guess it'd be good to stop it here.
Yes.
Okay, thank you for reminding me.
Okay.
So, do you have to learn other models
that you need to learn how to use?
Do you watch other models?
I didn't get your question, sorry.
For which kind of models?
Like what do you have?
Yeah, so there are definitely a lot of the things
that I didn't really talk about here.
You mean like GRU?
So, yeah, so GRU is just like a very simplified version
of an RNN, and then LSTM is a lot more complicated.
It does things more efficiently.
It adds actually more components to the RNN,
the standard RNN, so it's just a lot of things
that are changing in the model.
And I didn't really focus on that here
because like I said, it wasn't like a deep learning,
you know, deep learning course or tutorial.
But yeah, those things are very important to know,
especially if you wanna use them here.
But yeah, I would suggest like the,
if you're really interested in it
and you want a good place to start,
that documentation for PyTorch,
I think is the number one thing I would recommend.
I wouldn't even recommend books.
I would just recommend go to a documentation
because the documentation actually has like explanations.
It has like references, like the proper references
of where you can, of what was used,
what paper was used to implement that model, for example.
And it has like a really, really nice explanation
of what the model is about, yeah.
Yeah.
How do you use the machine learning
to kind of understand the value of the model?
Yeah.
So for me, it's like, initially I started
in machine learning, basic machine learning,
like doing like hand, I still enjoy that.
I still enjoy like establishing my own features, you know,
because I have a lot of domain expertise in this space.
So I just, you know, try something like an SVM
or try something like a naive Bayesian classifier.
It does well.
It actually does well for the task.
There was no need for me to do deep learning.
But as you can see that one of the things
that I showed here was that if you have a lot of data set,
you can actually achieve it without having
to do that tedious work, right?
If you're all interested in accuracy and this kind of thing,
you would get that kind of result.
It took quite a bit of time.
Most of my work was basically trying to combine
like traditional methods with deep learning methods.
So I have some papers in that I managed
to publish this year, past year I mean.
I discuss a lot about that, like what are some
of the drawbacks, because I use, I don't know
if you're familiar, there are a lot of trending models
like BERT and OpenAI, GPT, and all these new models
that are coming out from these companies.
I compare all these models with this kind of task
that I showed here today, and I show the differences.
And it's unbelievable that something like an OpenAI GPT,
which was trained on a Wikipedia data set,
can actually all perform all the other models that I trained.
Even models that I trained on like data sets,
like domain-based data set, like a Twitter data set,
even those models were performed by a GPT,
OpenAI GPT, which is outstanding.
It means that deep learning is actually working,
because you can see, right?
But it raises questions as well,
because what is a model learning, like you said, right?
Like you pointed out, but the model is learning.
So that's an area that we are working a lot in NLP,
trying to understand.
Because I think that's a very important point,
very important part of the work that we do.
I try to explain it.
Otherwise, we are just coding, coding, coding,
and just combining GRUs and just doing that,
but it's no fun if you don't understand it very well.
Sorry, sorry.
No, I did it.
So I did my thesis in like three years.
Yeah, three years.
I was very fortunate, because I can say,
I was working in a task that not a lot of people
are working on.
I'm not sure if you have ever seen like
emotion classification, maybe you have heard about it.
But not a lot of people are working in this space.
Thank you.
Yeah, so I was fortunate because of that.
I mean, when I built my models,
there wasn't a lot of papers to compare with,
so it was good for me, I got lucky.
But yeah, I know if you want to get into this space,
and you want to do this kind of work,
you will see how competitive it is,
because companies have a lot of GPU power,
and deep learning is working, so it's pretty tough.
Any other questions?
Yeah.
Oh, not too sure of that.
Maybe contact me after, I'll definitely answer.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, definitely.
I definitely would like to chat to you more about it.
Let's check that again.
Yeah, that's the one.
Doesn't work?
Well, they shared the wrong one.
Maybe someone can help me double check.
Double check, see if they're right.
Ha ha.
Wow.
It's gonna be small.
Yeah, so there was an R missing.
Yeah, so one more thing that I wanted to share with you,
let me see, one more quick thing.
Just quick advice is, I would say,
I always say this, I was fortunate, like I say,
that I got to do a PhD in LLP,
and I get to teach like this, I'm very fortunate,
and I'm really happy, and I really like the turnout of today,
and I really appreciate you being here
and trying to learn this stuff.
One thing I would say is don't rush,
there's plenty of time to learn.
A lot of the exciting results, as you see today,
are just stuff that, you know,
it's just like a lot of repetitive stuff that's going on,
and companies have a lot of GPU power,
so they're able to get those good results,
but there's a lot of things you can work on and improve.
And enrolling courses, but be sure to practice on your own,
that's something that I try to highlight
during this tutorial.
Enrolling math courses, most people would tell you
don't worry about the math,
but you can see that Python actually makes it super easy
to go through the math, do the derivations,
yeah, do the computations in that computation graph,
I think that it's really helpful.
Try to implement papers on your own,
that's the way I started, I just went and I started
with something like the word embedding paper,
like a skip gram, I have like a notebook for that
where I implemented myself,
and like CBO algorithm for word embeddings,
I implemented that myself as well.
There's a lot of like cool stuff
in the Python documentation,
which you can use also as a really nice guide
to know that you're going in the right direction,
because sometimes that's kind of like a challenge, right?
Where to start, that's a big question.
So I guess these documentations really help for that.
There are many books, here is good to learn as well.
It's also nice to combine these different learning resources,
if you're only learning from videos,
it's pretty difficult,
for me, in my personal experience, it was difficult.
I try to go to meet-ups a lot and talk with people
and try to understand the use cases
that they're working on,
and I appreciate the questions that you ask
about the data sets, you know, and the kind of challenges,
because all these things really help me
to understand the problem better, so I appreciate that.
For me, future work is like, I want to extend these notebooks,
eventually I want to make it like a book,
so feel free to just keep up with me,
I have a Twitter that I constantly use,
I'm always trying to help students
to learn this stuff from the beginning,
so I'm always trying to adventure into a new task,
for me, it's just exploring the area.
Yeah, and there are other sophisticated techniques
that I didn't discuss here, like GANs,
which someone raised earlier,
like what do you use for doing natural language generation,
so you can use those generative models,
so that's a really interesting area as well.
These are just some references, so these are just some books,
I don't usually recommend books, that's not my thing,
but I would say that these books really help me
in my learning,
in my learning.
This is a recent one, NLP with PyTorch,
that's a recent book, I haven't really read this book,
but I heard it's good, I guess you can try that,
and Deep Learning with PyTorch from Chalet,
it's a really, really good book,
if you want to learn deep learning,
I would strongly recommend this book as a starting point.
There are other really good books here,
for learning theory, this one is really great,
neural network methods for NLP,
it would help to answer questions like why,
what's the difference between LSTM, GRU,
which sometimes you want to know,
that book will really help you
and create a really solid foundation for your theory.
Yeah, and there are some websites I share here,
one more last thing I want to share before you go,
so I partnered up with another researcher
to create this really nice website here,
and basically it's the foundation of all the stuff
that I'm doing here, I'm trying to teach things about NLP
and using deep learning techniques,
so this is, if you ever want to know where to start,
we created this project, it's like an ebook,
where you can basically know where to start,
so we start at word embeddings, and character embeddings,
then we go to CNNs, then we go to recurrent neural networks,
then we go to recursive neural networks,
and all these models, right, it's a step by step,
learning the theory, eventually we plan to incorporate
all these notebooks into this,
so we have like a full-fledged learning resource
that you can use, that you don't have to go all over
the place to learn this stuff,
so that's kind of the intention behind this project,
most of the things are thought, yeah.
So it's in the, so it's here?
Yeah, the last one, yeah.
So it's pretty useful for that,
it has some of the equations I use here,
let's see, and it has like, what of the state of the art,
models used for what kind of tasks,
it's a really intuitive, like ebook,
definitely check it out if you're interested in this space,
if you ever have questions, please email me,
you have access to my email, you have my Twitter,
just feel free to have a discussion with me,
I'm always free to ask, it's my job, educating,
so I'm always free to, and excited to always
answer your questions, thanks a lot.