Our next speaker is Jacob Kaplan-Moss, and he will be teaching us about assets in Django.
Please make him feel welcome.
Howdy, folks.
So I started this talk with a hypothesis.
I've always been super frustrated with managing static assets in Django.
It's been one of the parts that I feel like, you know, I'm supposedly the Django creator,
and I ought to know it, but I really, it never felt easy, it never felt smooth, and so I
had this idea, okay, I'm going to propose a talk for PyCon, and if it's accepted, I
will be forced to figure it out.
I'll get to write.
It's called conference-driven development, everyone.
I'll be forced to figure it out.
I'll be able to finally come up with a good answer, and it will no longer be hard again.
I am sorry to report that my hypothesis was incorrect, and the title is somewhat misleading.
It is, in fact, not possible to handle assets in Django entirely smoothly and entirely easily,
and that's because while the simple things are simple and easy, the hard things are actually
hard, unfortunately.
So the title is a bit of a bait and switch, but hopefully by the end of this talk, you'll
at least have a fairly good framework to move forward and handle things with a little less
head scratching and some good ideas for best practices around this area.
Before we dive in, I want to share a couple of terms and terminology just to make sure
we're all on the same page about them.
So when I say assets, I'm talking about the non-code parts of your app.
Sorry, the non-Python code parts of your app.
I'm talking about CSS, JavaScript, images like logos or icons, you know, anything that
you're using that's part of your app that isn't sort of interpreted, it isn't part of
your Python code.
Now, Django uses the term static for these things, and that's a historical wart.
Like there wasn't a best practice name for this stuff back 15 years ago when we were
inventing some of this, so you'll see most of the places around Django, you'll see the
term static.
I will try to use the word assets throughout this talk because I think it's clearer, but
you will still see in a lot of the settings and a lot of the Django documentation the
term static, and these are the same things.
Django also uses this term media, which specifically refers to stuff that is sort of dynamic and
uploaded, and so these are things that users will upload.
These could be admin users uploaded through the admin interface, or these could be end
users of the site, but the point is it's not part of your code base.
It's not checked in.
It's not distributed.
It's not part of your app.
It's something dynamic and uploaded.
Images, PDF files, whatever all else you're letting your folk, your users upload.
And Django uses the term media for all of that stuff.
So I'm going to cover four scenarios.
The first scenario is the sort of simplest version.
You've got some JavaScript or CSS, and you're fine with that living on the file system.
This actually covers probably 80% of the use cases, and the good news is this is very simple.
If there's a theme of this talk, it's don't overthink it, and this is the don't overthink
it model.
Like you just need to write some JavaScript.
JavaScript's really good now.
You probably don't need a JavaScript precompiler unless you're doing pretty advanced stuff.
Likewise CSS is really good now.
You probably don't need any sort of fancy CSS stuff until you do.
The second scenario is the cloud storage scenario.
So at a certain point, having your assets being shipped along with your code starts
to fall apart.
This is sort of large scale in terms of traffic, but also large scale in terms of development
team, large scale in terms of a lot of assets to be compiled and shifted around.
So at a certain point, you probably want to start storing your stuff on a cloud storage
service like S3 or the Google equivalent, et cetera.
This is also a prerequisite in my mind to doing media uploads correctly.
In most deployment scenarios, uploading, having media uploads go to the actual web servers
is a bad practice for a variety of reasons, from scalability to security to sort of just
best practice development.
So when you come to media uploads, you kind of need to have the cloud stuff worked out,
and the good news is those things work well together.
And finally, the last sort of most complicated scenario is you want to do fancy stuff.
You want to use JSX.
You want to use ES Next.
You want to use post CSS.
You're building a big React app.
You've got all the sort of heavy front end tooling, and you want that to work well with
your Django app.
So the simple scenario.
Most of the time, this is where you should start.
And everything in this scenario kind of gets built on in the later ones, so there's no
downside to kind of starting here.
I always try to get away with this for as long as I can and only start to get more complex
when I need to get more complex.
This will scale for most like, I don't know, like medium-ish web apps.
Actually it's like fairly well.
I would say 80% of what I develop is suited just fine with this scenario.
This doesn't support any sort of fancy compilations.
If you want to use post CSS or less or Sass, you're out of luck here.
And it's relatively slow and inefficient, as we'll see in a bit.
So you're going to want to use White Noise.
White Noise is a static file server that lets you use Django to actually serve these static
files.
Back in the day, this was discouraged.
We used to encourage that people use an external third-party web server to serve static assets,
something like NGINX.
That's no longer the case.
White Noise is really quite good.
It integrates super well with Django and it means that you can just have one server out
of the box that serves both your dynamic stuff and your static stuff.
As a bonus, White Noise sets all the correct headers on your assets so that if you use
a CDN like CloudFlare, it kind of just works.
You just point CloudFlare at your Django site and you've got caching of all your static
stuff.
No configuration needed.
It's real nice.
So here's what setting up this stuff looks like.
There's really two key settings to pay attention to when you're thinking about static files.
When you think about assets, excuse me.
There's the static files DERS setting, which tells Django where your source files live,
where the static files that you're writing live.
And then there's the static root setting that tells Django where all of the static files
from those directories are going to be served by your web server.
And so when you run the collect static management command, what's going to happen is Django's
going to look at everything in those static file directories, suck it all out and drop
it into that directory pointed at by static root.
And then you would then point your web server at that static root directory.
Now White Noise does this automatically so you don't need that extra step.
But if you wanted to use something like NGINX to serve your assets, you could just point
it at that directory.
And the reason you need this level of indirection, by the way, is assets can be collected not
just from the directories specified in that static files DERS setting, but also from installed
apps.
So that's how, for example, the CSS and JavaScript associated with the admin get collected and
put into that same directory so that when your admin is served, it has styles.
If you've ever deployed a Django site, turned debug off and suddenly discovered your admin
doesn't have any styles, that's what's happening here.
You haven't properly configured static files and so the admin doesn't know where to find
its CSS and so you don't get styling in your admin.
The last bit of this scenario is making sure that you're correctly referencing those files
in your templates when you need to include a script or a CSS file.
So that's the first step.
The second step is to make sure that you're using the right file.
So you're going to have to use a static file.
So that's the first one with the green checkmark.
Everything just kind of works.
So in this scenario, your best practices are to use white noise.
Pay attention to your static file directories and your static root.
I would just like, these are my common ones.
I put my static files in a directory called assets,
and I have static root called static root so that I know exactly what it is.
Reference your files with the static tag, and just run collect static at deploy time.
Don't try to be fancy about when you run collect static.
Just run it every time you do a deploy, like as a post deploy step.
If you're using Heroku or another cloud library that uses the same build packs,
collect static will be run automatically for you for this reason.
This isn't like the best practice in a global sense.
Running asset compilation on your production servers is kind of a code smell,
but for this sort of simple scenario, it's fine, and don't overthink it.
Okay, so at a certain point, instead of just having stuff on your file system,
you want to put them in cloud storage.
This might be you've got a bunch of images,
and so blowing out your file system on all your app servers is a problem.
This might be because you've got a bunch of different developers,
and you're starting to separate front end and back end development,
and so the process of deploying assets is a little bit complicated.
You might have high traffic, so you want the sort of efficiency
and lower cost of something like S3.
There's a bunch of reasons why you might want this.
You also might want to be doing this as a prerequisite
for allowing users to upload media.
At this point, DevProd parity, having equivalency
between your local development environment and your deployment environment
starts to be a concern, and I'm going to cover that in a minute,
but start thinking about it now.
So the library you want to be looking at here is something called Django Storages.
Django Storages provides built-in asset and media storage engines
for basically everything.
It even supports FTP, which I don't know that anybody's using anymore.
If it doesn't, there is an API to write your own that's part of Django,
and it's actually not that complex.
If you look at Django Storages source code,
it's actually not particularly complicated,
but most of the time you can just install Django Storages
and it will just pass whatever other third-party prereq like Bodo you need,
and stuff will just work.
You'll end up needing a bunch of settings.
This is my settings file.
So the stuff on top is basically all the sort of AWS preamble
that you need to set up to make these files work right.
The key is the stuff in bold.
So there's a couple of good practices here that I'm showing off.
The first is that the static file storage setting is the main setting
that controls what Django's collect static command uses to actually store the files.
And so here I'm switching away from the default and saying I want to store stuff on S3.
The other thing that I'm doing is specific to the S3 backend,
but I'm giving a prefix to everything that I upload.
And that lets me, that means when I run collect static on my laptop in debug,
I upload my assets one place.
So I can test that uploading step.
I can make sure that AWS is working correctly and all my creds are good
and getting everything right, but it also won't stomp on my production files.
There are a bunch of other ways you can do this.
And once you start adding staging servers and review apps,
this can get a little bit more complex.
But it's a good practice here to start having sort of separation
between where your assets upload so you don't accidentally upload testing stuff
into your production server.
Now a big downside of doing it like I've done here is if,
at this point I can only develop online, right,
because when I run collect static or when I run my web server,
I'm getting files served off of S3.
I think this is probably a good idea because you want your local development
environment to be as close to your production environment as possible,
but that may not work for everyone.
And so if it doesn't work for you, you could add some additional conditional logic
in your settings file to when debug is on,
fall back to the white noise local file system storage
like I presented in the previous one.
That's just another line or two in your settings file.
And it's okay.
It's a trade-off I want you to think about between having good parity
between development and production or making like coding on a plane
something that you're able to do.
So what collect static actually does that I skipped over the first time
I showed you this slide is it actually consults this static file storage setting
to figure out what to do with your assets.
So it still is going to look in those static file directories,
but what actually is happening is it's saying, all right, storage engine,
I found app.js.
What do you want to do with it?
And so in this case, in my example, the S3 storage says,
okay, I want to stick that over on S3 instead of sticking it in that static root file.
And so now when I run collect static, my files get pulled from wherever they are
in my source repository and pushed up to S3 or Dropbox
or whatever else you're using for your storage engine.
And this is why you want to be using that static tag,
because once I switch my storage engine over,
it's actually going to ask my storage engine, hey, what's the URL for app.js?
And my storage engine is going to say, oh, hey, it's this particular bucket URL,
and it will actually get a full reference to my S3 bucket.
So if you want to do cloud storage, Django Storage is your answer.
It basically just works.
It integrates well with all the rest of the stuff that we'll see later.
The key setting to look at is your static file storage setting
plus whatever other settings you need to configure that engine.
The Django Storage's docs are good.
They'll tell you what you need to do.
Just find your preferred engine of choice and walk through it.
Remember to reference static files and templates with the static tag.
And finally, this is probably the point that you should think about a different way
of actually deploying your assets to production.
Doing it as part of the deploy step is going to slow down substantially now,
because you're pushing a bunch of files to an external storage engine
rather than just copying them on disk.
So this is a good time to start putting your collect static command
into a CI task somewhere or some other post deploy hook.
That's kind of out of scope for this talk,
but there are probably other talks here at PyCon about continuous integration,
and you should be able to figure that out with a little bit of head banging.
All right, so media.
The use case here is where you want people to be able to upload files.
And the good news here is if you've done step two, if you've done scenario two,
this is super, super easy.
I do really want to encourage you to take the added time to get a cloud storage engine
set up before you allow file uploads.
That's for a couple reasons.
One is safety and security.
Although the file upload code in Django is pretty hardened and pretty hammered on
and hasn't had security vulnerabilities in a long, long time,
it's still dangerous to be letting people put stuff on your web server.
And that danger is not the same as letting people put stuff in an S3 bucket
you've set up specifically for letting people put stuff there.
It also performs significantly better.
You know, the speed of a user downloading a file from S3 is probably going to be faster
than from your web server.
It's going to scale better, and it's going to scale with your team better,
as I mentioned earlier.
So I really, like, it's worth the extra time to figure out the S3,
Azure, whatever stuff, before you start letting people upload media files.
So like I said, to upload media files, you want a storage engine.
You should be using Django Storages.
If the media files you're allowing people to upload are images,
Django also requires Pillow just to handle images at all,
and so you'll want to install that.
But that's all you need, and from there it's pretty simple.
You can use an image field in a model.
If you do it like that and use a model form, it basically just works.
Uploads to the admin are going to work automatically.
They'll land on S3 as configured beforehand.
Basically, it just works.
If you want to be doing custom stuff with files, you want to be doing streaming uploads,
you want to do some pre- or post-processing, consult the documentation.
It's pretty good in this area.
You should be able to figure out some more complex tasks without too much trouble.
One best practice that I'm showing off here is the uploadTo function.
Image and file fields take this argument.
It's a callback that determines the file name to upload to.
It's not like a big deal, but it's going to make your life a lot easier
if you've got a nice, clean URL there rather than some auto-generated hash
of something that you can't really figure out what that file refers to.
So I recommend taking the extra 20 seconds to figure out a good file.
And from there, you just set your default file storage setting
to whatever storage you want to use, Azure, S3, what have you, and bam, you're done.
You can actually, file fields and image fields take a storage argument too.
So you could use different storages for different types of files.
Like you could put images in one S3 bucket and video in another.
I've never actually run across a need for that, but maybe you will.
For models, referencing stuff in templates is pretty simple.
You just get whatever your image field or file field is named,
and you have a .url, and that will automatically expand
to get to the correct URL for your thing.
Now you have to start thinking about how you want to handle this in development.
So you're running things locally, and you want to test it out,
and you want to upload an image file from your local laptop.
So you kind of have to think about how you're going to handle this in development.
So this is that same sort of dev prod parody question.
You have two options.
One is to use S3 just like production does,
and to use something like the AWS location setting
to separate your development uploads from your production uploads.
So this means that your sort of testing scenario
is as close as possible to your production scenario,
but again you can't hack on an airplane.
Is that something you need to be able to do?
I don't know, it depends on your company and your organization.
You can fall back to using file system media.
There's a couple of settings to look up, media root and media URL,
and you can serve them with a built-in server designed for debugging.
So this gets offline development at the cost of being different from production
and potentially introducing bugs.
I can't tell you which is best for you.
It's going to depend on your team.
There's some more documentation about how to use uploaded files
in development at the link there.
So to summarize, use Django Storage as in Pillow,
set the default file storage setting,
remember to define upload to,
and think about local development options.
All right, let's get to the good stuff, asset compilation.
So this was the part that I was hoping would be really easy.
It's not, sorry.
Maybe if I was a better JavaScript developer,
but I don't even, I've found it hard to do.
but I don't even, I've talked to a bunch of them
and they've told me not.
So look, there's some really cool stuff in the front-end world.
I mean, I can joke about JavaScript,
but the fact is it's an incredibly exciting space right now.
There's some really, really cool stuff.
If you haven't played around with TypeScript,
you owe it to yourself to check it out.
It's like MyPy, but way better. Sorry.
If you haven't played with ES Next,
it makes Java, that's what will be the next version of JavaScript.
It's very cool. It has list comprehensions.
It has generators.
It feels like, it feels really familiar to Python users.
It's like putting on jeans from a different brand.
They fit real well, but they're a little,
some parts are a little different, but they're still real comfy.
Post CSS is super cool. I'm mildly obsessed with it.
This is a cool area.
And if you're using something like React, you kind of don't have a choice.
You need to get into this, need to get in this area.
The problem is it makes my head hurt.
If you're like me, it might make your head hurt too.
Okay, so the best asset manager right now is Webpack.
I know there are a bunch of Python asset managers.
There's Django Pipeline, there's Django Compressor,
there's I don't know what all else.
The problem is they're not really that much better.
You think, okay, if I use Webpack, I need to install NPM,
and I need to install a bunch of JavaScript stuff.
But so something like Django Pipeline seems a lot simpler,
but the fact is that the Python ports of these compilers
are not the same as the JavaScript versions
and will confuse people who are doing JavaScript front-end development.
And things like Babel, the JavaScript transpiler that converts ES Next
into JavaScript that browsers will understand
just don't have an equivalent in the Python world.
So you almost always end up installing NPM anyway,
and now if you're going to go to that step,
you might as well use Webpack, which is just better.
Now, every time I talk about front-end development,
because I know high people in the future,
you're watching this video and it's three years from now,
this is probably wrong.
My guess is that within a year,
Parcel is going to replace Webpack as the best practice.
My guess is if I give this talk at PyCon 2020,
I'm going to be talking about Parcel here.
It's not there yet.
Maybe play with it, but it's probably not ready for production.
Webpack is significantly better right now,
but as we'll see in a bit, Webpack frustrates the heck out of me,
and I think that Parcel is on its way to replacing it, but not yet.
So what do you need to make this all work?
You've got to install NPM, you've got to install Webpack,
plus a whole bundle of plugins.
There's two very specific bits that make Webpack and Django play nice together.
If there's a secret to this talk,
if there's one big thing I learned about how to make this less painful,
it's these two things.
Webpack bundle tracker makes Webpack generate a metadata file,
and then Django Webpack loader will read that metadata file
and do the necessary to integrate it with your Django site.
So this is how I got it all working.
I used a package manager to install a package manager,
to install an asset manager, real simple.
I installed a bunch of NPM packages.
Specifically, these are the ones that I installed to get SAS and Babel working.
If you are wanting to use other ones, consult the Webpack docs.
I don't really have time in this talk to really talk through
exactly how Webpack works and what it does.
The documentation is good, but it's complex.
I'd recommend giving yourself a good day or two to really sit down with it,
work through a bunch of options, figure out how everything works,
and kind of get all the details fleshed out.
It's not particularly difficult, but it is a bit time consuming.
So Webpack is organized around this config file, webpackconfig.js.
It's just a JavaScript file that specifies a few different things.
It starts with an entry point,
which is the beginning of your asset compilation chain.
The way that Webpack works is you say,
hey, index.js is the start of my app.
Then index.js will import a bunch of stuff.
It can import other JavaScript files.
It can import CSS files.
It can import SAS or post-CSS files.
Webpack will figure out based on those imports
what sort of translation and compilation need to happen.
When it's all done, it drops that off in a bundle file.
One of the keys to doing this right with Django
is making sure to include a hash in the name of the bundle file.
That way you get versioned assets,
so it's easy to deploy a new version of your front end
and then a new version of your back end
without having to synchronize that in a particularly tight way.
You give it some rules, which say,
hey, JavaScript files I want to compile with Babel.
Then you've got to make sure to use this plugin.
That's the little key bit that makes it spit out that statistics file.
At that point, you add some stuff to your settings file.
You install the Webpack loader app,
and you give it a little bit of configuration.
You can consult the docs for details here,
but this is the minimum, and this will be enough to get it working.
Then you run two commands.
First you run Webpack, which follows that index.js
and brings all your things and puts it in a bundle.
Then you run collect static,
and that takes the bundle that's now been generated
and pushes it to S3 or does whatever else needs to happen with it.
That's the cool little magic that Webpack loader does,
is it makes sure that when you run collect static,
collect static knows how to find your compiled bundles
and shove them in the right place.
There's some other cool stuff in that library too,
like support for live reloading and those sorts of things.
You can take a look.
Now in your templates, instead of using the static tag,
there's a new one, render bundle,
and you say, I want to render my main bundle.
This is what would let you have multiple different types of bundles.
Say if you have different parts of your app
that need different prerequisites, different JavaScript files.
So this is how this whole thing works.
It's going to look at your index.js,
it's going to compile everything using Webpack,
spitting out that bundle, and then collect static
and push it off to your cloud server.
Now it's real tempting at this point to try to automate this more.
We're running two different commands,
it feels a little manual, like can't I just automatically reload stuff,
I just want to edit my post CSS file and have my CSS be spit out
and automatically uploaded to S3 and happen all automatically.
You actually can do that. That will work.
However, I started to go down that path
and I very rapidly got very, very confused.
I recommend actually leaving it pretty simple and doing it by hand,
maybe using a CI server for this,
because otherwise it can get real hairy, real quick,
and you can end up with a lot of confusion about what's doing what
and what's watching what and what's listening.
I didn't really understand what was happening here
until I threw out all the fancy stuff and got super simple with it.
So my recommendation would be to do the same.
So Webpack is the best practice here right now.
I think that may change in the future,
I predict it will change in the future,
but for right now that's the one you should be using.
There's really nothing that compares to it that's as flexible,
that has as many options, or that will do all the things
that you might possibly need to do.
The key connection bit is that Django,
that should read Django Webpack Loader on that slide.
That's the key connection bit.
Again, I recommend using a CI task
and be very careful about premature automation.
Thank you all very much.
Thank you, Jacob.
I think I have time for maybe one or two questions.
I think we have time for one question.
All right, who's going to be the lucky one?
Russ isn't here, so someone else has to do it.
Yes. No, go for it.
Thank you.
I was thinking on the thoughts of faking your cloud storage
for your local development,
when you were talking about the option one, option two,
and you're on the airplane.
Faking, so running something that pretends to be S3 locally,
but isn't actually?
Yes, sir.
I'm not aware of anything that does that,
but it's not a terrible idea,
because now your Django app is just speaking the same old APIs,
but you're faking it at a different point.
So if there's something that runs locally and works there,
yeah, that could be cool.
If you know of something, let me know after the talk.
I'd love to play with it.
Thanks again, y'all.
Thank you again, Jacob.
It's now lunchtime.
Enjoy your lunch, and we will see you after the break.