Okay. Thank everybody for coming. Today we're going to be hearing about attracting the invisible
contributors with Charlotte Mays.
Thank you. So before I start, I want to give a little bit of context to this talk. I am
one of the co-organizers of my local Pi Ladies group. In that context, I spend a lot of time
talking to people who come to the group asking them what they want out of the community.
Not just the Pi Ladies group but the community general, what their goals are, that sort of
thing.
I hear a lot of people saying that I want some sort of place where I can come and actually
get into some coding. So of course there are a few things that already exist that I'll
often point them to. Existing groups that do supportive coding including our local Python
group that isn't the Pi Ladies group. And that sort of thing. And I get a lot of people
talking particularly when the subject of open source comes up about, well, I tried. I went
to this project and I hit X roadblock. So I had a lot of that. And then from there,
I am also a core committer on a project and have contributed to a bunch of projects. And
I work at Red Hat where project maintainers kind of grow on trees. And so I'm in a situation
where I see a lot of both sides of this. And there's a lot of things that I think project
maintainers and contributors don't necessarily think about that are actually chasing some
people away. So who are these invisible contributors that I'm talking about? A lot of times they're
students. They may be current students in a traditional bachelor's program or they may
be students at a boot camp. They also can often be self-taught coders where they don't
have much structure that they're coming from to know where they should be looking. And
then also sometimes they're just users who want to contribute. Users of a project who,
you know, found a bug that they would like to help fix or have a feature that they would
like to see exist and they feel like they maybe have enough knowledge of programming
to be able to help out. So these are often the people who, they're not well versed in
the open source community. They don't know all of the default assumptions that most people
in this room probably already have. So these are what I call the invisible contributors.
They may come look at your project and go, this looks overwhelming. I'm going to not.
So how can you use the content that I'm about to give you? Because I'm going to warn you
this is going to be a bit of a fire hose. One thing is just simply for insights into
diverse viewpoints. So a lot of this has been accumulated not just from people I've interacted
with locally and directly, but I've actually reached out and kind of tried to go, okay,
I know this little piece of this, what other things are going on that are pushing people
away and really tried to collect a bunch of this stuff together. So this ought to give
you some insights into the different people who may come to look at your project. If you
maintain or contribute to an open source project, then you're obviously very much my target
audience. Do not, when you get this fire hose of information, assume that it's a lost cause
and just ignore it because there will be a lot of things that I'm going to tell you.
There's probably for the majority of projects going to be a whole lot of things that you
look at and go, yeah, we don't do that. Don't assume it's a lost cause and ignore it. Instead,
make small changes at an appropriate pace. Pick up a couple of things. These talks are
all recorded. You can go look at it later online and once you've made a couple of small
changes, go back and make a couple more small changes. As long as you're continuously improving,
you're going to continuously get closer to that goal of being able to attract more and
more contributors to your project. Do not, especially if you have a project that's going
at a steady pace, you've got contributors, just sit there and declare unilaterally, okay,
we're going to change a bunch of things. We're going to do this, this, this. It's great if
you want to make changes based on this, but you're going to get people pushing back. When
those people push back, do ask them for alternative suggestions because sometimes you'll have
people who say, well, I like, for instance, the chat system that we use and you're telling
me that we need to change it for X, Y and Z reason. Ask them for alternative suggestions.
Say, okay, well, here's the problem we're trying to solve. All the suggestions I'm going
to give you, I'm going to tell you exactly what the problem is that we're trying to solve.
Present this and let it be a conversation within your project. If somebody objects to
a specific change, ask them, okay, well, do you have another alternative to solve this
problem? Do not completely disregard the opinions of your existing contributors. They are still
important. But do stand firm that existing contributors should also be welcoming to new
people. So, you know, hopefully everybody is going to be on the same team in terms of
we want to have the most thriving open source project we can and have that be your approach
that you take to all of this. And the last thing I want to mention about how you can
use this content is as a framework to help a company be more attractive to a diversity
of candidates. It's not directly put together with companies in mind, but all of the same
principles apply. So think of it, you know, when you are within a company situation trying
to think about how to be more diverse and inclusive, these are also principles that
you can think of and think how would that apply to those situations as well.
All right. So I'm going to define a couple of terms that I'm going to use in this talk.
I'm calling projects sticky versus slippery. And I'm not trying to define this as a binary.
This is a spectrum. So projects can be anywhere from the sticky end of the spectrum to the
slippery end of the spectrum. A sticky project has multiple long-term contributors. They
see communication when people look it up. Even if those people don't end up contributing,
they at least say, hey, I'm interested. What can you tell me about this? A slippery project
may only have a few long-term contributors, maybe just the maintainer and a couple of
people who might drop in a PR blindly every now and then. And it sees minimal or no communication
from people who look it up. Nobody comes and says, hey, I want to help with this. And so
the goal of this project or the goal of this talk is to help your project go from the slippery
end of the spectrum to the sticky end of the spectrum. So what makes a project fall on
one end or the other of the spectrum? There are five things I'm going to break this down
into and I'm going to go into each of these in more detail. But in brief, communication,
they need to be able to communicate with you. Documentation, we all know the importance
of documentation, but I'm going to go into some more detail about how that relates to
this. Kindness, basic human trait, very important in this context. Terminology that's used in
your project. And the ever popular code of conduct. So when we're talking about communication,
you want to make sure that you make it easy for people to communicate with your team.
I see a lot of projects that the only thing that they have for communication is maybe
a mailing list or an IRC channel. These are not great for communication. They're great
to have. They're better than nothing, especially the mailing list because that likely will
have the archived interactions so people can go look back and see how the conversations
went over time. But it's not good for real time. IRC is good for real time but has no
archive. Nobody can go and look and see anything that happened before they joined that IRC
channel. And it can be really not accessible to new coders. It's something that there's
not a whole lot of information about how to set it up. You have to kind of read through
a bunch of different things, that sort of thing. So these are the kinds of things that
you want to think about when you think about how are people going to communicate with my
project. And this should be on the front page of every place a person might land. Your documentation,
your GitHub repo, any place that you have a presence, how people can communicate with
you should be front and center. You want to make sure, like I said, that it's accessible
to non-technical people, that there are archived interactions. Archived interactions are important
because that way people can see how did people interact with other people. Are they going
to be nice to me when I come and ask my newbie question? Because that's the people we're
talking about. We're talking about people who they have no idea if their questions are
intelligent or just incredibly naive. They want to know how are you going to react, are
you going to be dismissive, et cetera. And then we want minimal downloads or installation.
If you want to use something like Slack, most people probably already have that installed
or are used to using it just because of how prevalent it is. But then, you know, something
that has a web accessible version, which Slack also does, you can log into it from
a web browser, helps minimize that friction of people trying to communicate with your
project for the first time. All right. So documentation. We all hear all the time about
how much you need documentation. But I want to kind of pin down here a difference between
user-focused and developer-focused documentation. So usually when we're talking about documentation,
we're talking about user-focused documentation. How do you use this project? How do you use
this library or app? But what we're talking about here in terms of attracting the invisible
contributors is we want to make sure you've got developer-focused documentation. Something
that's going to, for instance, tell people how to set up their dev environment. You know,
just having documentation of this is how you use it does not tell me how I need to
set up my virtual environment for development, for running your tests on your project, all
of those components that may be part of the process of developing. Especially if you're
working with a library or something like that, it may not be something I can run directly.
I may need a sample project, that sort of thing. Any of those environment set up steps
need to be spelled out. And you should spell those out for all the major operating systems
because you never know what operating system your invisible contributors are using. And
if the set up doesn't work on their machine, guess what? They're going to disappear on
you. You also want to make sure your documentation includes the PR submission process. This doesn't
have to mean here is how you do GitHub, although it's great if you want to include that. But
in particular, once you submit a PR, how long should you expect to wait before somebody
responds to it? What kind of response should you expect? What are the standards for PRs
that people are going to look at? And that sort of thing. Anything that you feel like
is an assumption, if you have any question about whether it's an assumption or not, maybe
you should link out to somebody who explains it. I mean, there are already plenty of people
who explain the basics of GitHub. You may not want to reinvent that wheel and explain
that in your documentation, but you might want to link to if you're new to GitHub, look
at this. Here's a guide. That sort of thing. But then, you know, this project specifically,
when you submit a PR, this is the kind of person who's going to come look at it. This
is the kind of comments you're going to see. Here's an example of a PR. That sort of thing.
And then expectations after submission. Are your tests going to automatically run? Can
they look and see what test results happened? Can they see if there were failures and go
ahead and start fixing that without your project having to interface with them? Those are all
good things to have documented what people can look for.
So I want to take a minute to talk about kindness. We all know what it is, but how does it relate
to your open source project? One thing that I want to really put in context here is to
be kind to all questions or submissions. You hear a lot, and I don't want to minimize,
that project maintainers deal with a lot of abuse. There are a lot of people who just
have high expectations. They expect a maintainer to do everything for them. All that sort of
thing. Yes, those people are going to come along. And yes, it's easy to go, yeah, go
away. You are expecting way too much of me. I am doing this on my own time. But you want
to be kind to them even as you tell them, hey, we are not going to do that. We don't
want to maintain that. The thing is, those invisible contributors are going to be coming
along and reading what you wrote to those people who are expecting too much of you.
And the invisible contributors, since, remember, they are the people who are not familiar with
the open source process, they don't know that maintainers deal with this kind of abuse all
the time. So they don't, if you have a snippy response to them or dismissive response to
them, to these people who are abusing the process, the newbies, the novices, they don't
know why you are being snippy or dismissive. They just know you are being snippy or dismissive
to somebody and they are going to worry you are going to do that to them. And remember
that you can reject without being unkind. If somebody offers a PR and it's for a feature
that doesn't work with your project, it's not going to integrate well, you can still
say, hey, I appreciate that you did this work. We are not going to integrate it but maybe
you want to fork and maintain this yourself. They are going to know what that means. But
those novice contributors are going to look at that and see you being polite and they
are going to understand that you are going to be polite to submitters. You can also,
if somebody submits something that just isn't good code quality, then you can do the same
thing. You can say, hey, this doesn't meet our standards. Preferably, hopefully you have
that documentation of what your standards are. And you can point them to that. You can
point them to your communication channels, wherever it is that your team communicates.
And say, hey, maybe somebody over here can help you clean this up a little bit before
we try to merge that in. So keep in mind ways that you can kind of be kind while you reject
things that are maybe not appropriate. Also remember, again, with the whole burnout thing,
you don't have to respond immediately. If you don't have it in you in this moment to
be nice to that person, just don't say anything at all. Come back to it when you have a little
bit more space or ask somebody else, hey, can you go respond to this person? I just
can't deal with this right now. So there are ways to handle this without getting that snippy
and dismissive tone into the indelible stuff that's going to sit around in the closed PRs
of your project and that sort of thing. So I want to talk about terminology a little
bit. First of all, you want to make sure that you minimize your jargon. I mean, of course,
there's going to be jargon that's used. But make sure that you're not using jargon just
for the sake of using it, just for the sake of hitting buzzwords on search engines, that
sort of thing. Because the more jargon that's there, the more likely it is that this new
person is going to come along and go, I don't know what this is talking about. This is clearly
above my level. And they're going to go somewhere else. So use the jargon that you need to be
clear. And anything that isn't necessary, try to use plainer language. You also want
to make sure your terminology is nonoffensive. There's a bunch of stuff out there in terms
of discussion around the terms master slave. So I'm going to use that as an example because
you can find a lot of discussion around that. Master slave has been used to discuss servers
and processes for a long time. It's been out there for ages. It's ingrained in all kinds
of things. But it is not welcoming. No, not everybody is going to be offended by it. No,
not everybody in the X demographic group is going to be offended by it. But there are
a good number of people who are offended by it, who just don't feel comfortable in a context
where that terminology is being thrown around. So there's a lot of discussion out there about
what are appropriate replacement words that are maybe even more descriptive of the process
that's actually being done. Primary replica, primary secondary, leader follower. These
sorts of things might explain what's actually happening even more than the terms master
slave do. So that's one of those things where because it's going to offend some people,
you probably want to kind of pull that out. And you want to think of these things as being
kind of technical debt, things that you can kind of chip away at as you have time, that
sort of thing. And I do want to mention, you know, that one has a lot of press. But there's
a lot of things in this category. Think about so easy your mom could do it or so easy your
girlfriend could do it. How are people going to think if they are a middle-aged mother
of four coming and wanting to contribute to your project or if they are a 22-year-old
girl just out of college and they see that language and they're like, oh, you think the
women can't do this. Okay. You know. And it's something where everybody knows what you mean,
but the tone is underneath that. Things that have to do with mental health. Don't say our
project is going to be very OCD about the syntax here. OCD is a mental health disorder
that people have. And when you say that, it trivializes what their experience is, what
their lived experience is. And that's just not necessary. You can use different language
that doesn't other them. So think about these things. If people tell you there's a problem,
pay attention. Don't go ask five of your friends, hey, do you think this is actually a problem?
Because your friends are probably going to be the people who think similarly to the way
you do. Even if those friends are from the same demographic as the person who told you
there's a problem. That doesn't mean that every time somebody says, hey, I don't like
this term you use, that you have to immediately change it. But take it seriously and give
it consideration. So the last thing I want to spend time on, and I'm going to spend a
good chunk of time on this, is code of conduct. You hear a lot about this, and it can be difficult
to parse out what's important in this process. The first thing I want to say about this is
don't reinvent the wheel. There are a ton of codes of conduct out there. You can borrow
one almost wholesale. You might need to make a couple of tweaks, but not a lot. So, you
know, start with something that's already built for you, that's already been vetted.
There's a lot of nuance in a code of conduct. So don't try to build it from the ground up.
You're going to probably miss a lot of that nuance. The next thing is, you know, you hear
a lot of people talking about, oh, a code of conduct limits what you can say. You just
can't say things that you would otherwise say. That's not actually really true. First
of all, a good code of conduct should not limit anything you can say about the actual
project itself, because the project itself, it's the code, it's the technology. Most codes
of conduct don't say anything about what you can say about the technology. They talk about
how you can say it. So keep that in mind when you hear complaints, and a lot of established
contributors might complain about, oh, you know, this is going to tell me that I can't
say blah, blah, blah, blah. Well, maybe you can't use those words. But think about what
you're trying to say, and maybe you can say it in a nicer way. And concordant with this,
your project is not your living room. So expect to behave professionally when you're working
on your open source project, when you're communicating in official project channels. If you want
to go and cut loose and just shoot the shit with your buddies, that's great. Even if your
buddies are also on that project, that's fantastic. Go do that. Don't do it in your project's
chat room. That's not the place for it. And then finally about codes of conduct is that
enforcement is absolutely critical. So many places adopt a code of conduct, slap it on
the website, maybe put links to it a few places and go, okay, done, and step away.
The problem is if you don't enforce it, then nobody is going to believe that it's going
to do anything. People are going to behave how they want to behave. If there's no enforcement,
it means nothing. It means somebody thought enough to say, eh, we should have this thing.
And then nobody thought enough to say, because people need to feel safe. So all of the prior
points, communication, documentation, kindness and terminology apply at least as much if
not more when you're enforcing a code of conduct. It's a tricky business. The first time you
have somebody who asserts that somebody violated the code of conduct, it's a mess. It's going
to be something that you have to think hard about how to deal with. It's going to be a
headache. Absolutely. But dealing with it well is going to compound the rewards for
your project. Because once people know that you're going to deal with this well, they
will go tell people they know, hey, this is a project where you can count on being treated
well. So make sure to be kind and don't accept attacks from any source during resolution.
One of the things you'll see is somebody who has been hurt, you know, person A says person
B said something that was really awful. Person B might take that as an attack. If person
A is saying, ah, person B is always rude to me, okay, that's an attack. But if person
A says person B said X, Y and Z that made me uncomfortable, that's not an attack. That's
a legitimate accusation. It's something that should be addressed. If person B comes back
and says they're making stuff up, they lie all the time, that's an attack. If person
B says I didn't say X, Y, Z, that's not an attack, that's an accusation, deal with that
appropriately. But make sure that you don't ever tolerate anybody just casting aspersions
and trying to broadly categorize what's going on. Keep things focused on individual incidents.
Be prepared to remove or ban people from your project if necessary. I know this is a painful
thing to think about and especially if you're dealing with somebody who maybe has done a
lot of code contributions, maybe even as a really good coder, it can be really painful
to think about maybe having to ban them from your project. But keep in mind there's grades
of this. You can ban someone from the communication channels on your project without banning them
from being able to contribute code. They're not going to like it. But if they're a continuous
problem in terms of making other people unwelcome, then maybe that's what needs to happen. And
if they decide they're not going to contribute anymore, that stinks. But what's going to
happen is that having removed a harasser, you might get six, seven, eight new people
coming along who wouldn't have made contributions otherwise. So keep in mind that yes, reject,
ban, these are final solutions, but don't consider them off the table. Remember that
that is something that needs to be considered. So that's all the content that I have. I do
have a QR code up here that links to a copy of my slides that has a bunch of examples
in it. So examples of how to look at the pros and cons of communication tools, how
to look at the pros and cons of different documentation, terminology, links to example
codes of conduct, all that kind of stuff. So if you want to go and look and have all
that extra material, that's all in there. It's just these slides plus some extra example
material. And I will be happy to take questions out in the hallway. I will be around the conference
Saturday and Sunday as well. If you see me, feel free to come up and say hi. That's what
I got.