Okay.
So
if everyone could pass around, you could take one sticky of
each and pass them around. We'll use these to say when
you're done with an exercise and when you need help and that
type of stuff. So we'll get all of those sent around.
So now we'll get into the
next question.
Who's been using Python for more than two years? Cool.
Who's been using Python for more than five years? Who's
been using Python for more than ten years? Yeah. Who loves
Python?
Yeah.
Okay. What's that?
Anyone else less than a year? Fantastic. Yeah.
Appreciate that.
Who considers themselves somewhat proficient with the
SciPy stack?
No, I don't.
Who's been working
around the clock?
We're getting the
stickies passed around. Where are they at currently?
Okay. Great.
Awesome.
Mm.
Oh, man.
Yeah, it's incredible.
And I'd really, yeah.
And I would encourage you to reach out to the Binder team
as well and tell them how great you find it.
And if you have any issues, raise issues on the repo
or pull requests or better.
But yeah, it's very cool.
I wouldn't suggest doing this now,
but I just found out in Binder, you
see it ends with tree notebooks.
If you change that to lab, it launches a binder session
of JupyterLab.
We're not going to do that now for a reason that may become
apparent downstream, but it involves IPY widgets.
So we'll start in a minute.
Eric, did you want to say anything to start or?
Yes, actually.
OK, so just like with the network analysis tutorial
that I was just in, if you have a question,
I'm going to ask you to raise your hand.
And I will come to you with a mic
because we want to record your questions for posterity
on YouTube so that those who are listening to the tutorial
and following online, believe me, people do it,
and I've done it before.
They can know the context of what Hugo is going
to be blabbering about.
So please make sure if you have a comment or a question,
raise your hand.
I will come to you with a mic, and that way
we'll have it recorded.
And I will be blabbering consistently.
Firstly, I just want to thank PyCon
for accepting this tutorial.
Both Eric and I are really excited to be teaching it.
Eric and I have been talking about this type of stuff
and teaching this type of stuff for several years,
for three years together now.
And we first taught, I suppose, what
is a foundation of this workshop last year
at SciPy in Austin over the summer,
which was really exciting.
So I'm really happy to be here teaching with Eric again.
And I also just want to thank all of you
for coming and taking an afternoon
to learn this stuff and be interested in this stuff.
I really appreciate all of you being here.
So we're here today to have an introduction to Bayesian
inference, essentially through the world and lens of simulation
and telling stories.
And we're at a very interesting point in time
where we have a lot of fantastic computational tools
to think about probability, which
weren't around 20 years ago.
Definitely weren't around 100 years ago
when people were developing all these frequentus tools.
And so it's actually a very exciting time
to be thinking about these things.
And one thing that we're going to do today
is think about how to talk about probability,
how to think about probability, not using calculus
and equations, but using random number generators,
numplized random number generators,
and telling stories of probability distributions,
which I personally find very, very exciting.
So we're going to start off with a bunch of probability
via simulation and random number generation.
Then we'll move into conditional joint probabilities
or using a lot of different data sets.
And in the second half, we'll wrap up the first half
with Bayes' theorem.
And then we'll start thinking about Bayesian inference
and how to compute these types of things and answer
data-centric and scientific questions using
the formulations of Bayesian inference.
We'll be doing that via simulation once again.
And time permitting, and I'm pretty sure we'll get there,
we'll wrap up with an intro into the wonderful world
of probabilistic programming languages,
which I find very exciting because as opposed
to most programming paradigms where
you have first-class citizens such as ints and strings,
or in data science, data frames and arrays,
in probabilistic programming, your first-class citizens
are probability distributions.
So we get to work with them directly, which is super cool.
So maybe to get started, I suppose
the other thing to mention is that there's
going to be a mixture of live coding, which
we'll see how that goes.
And oh, no.
OK, sorry, yeah, this is the wrong direction.
OK, so we're just going to execute the first cell
to import all our packages.
We'll be using some NumPy, some Pandas,
Seaborn, which is data visualization for a few things,
Matplotlib, which is data visualization.
This Matplotlib inline command allows plots
to appear below cells as output of cells.
sns.set is, you see I've imported Seaborn as sns.set,
makes figures look nicer, essentially.
So we're going to start with part one, although I really,
because it's PyCon, we should start with part zero.
That's a zero indexing joke if nobody got it.
So part one, if you have to explain a joke,
there's a problem there.
So we're going to develop an understanding what probability
means in both Bayesian and frequentist terms.
We're also going to start simulating probability
distributions, that model real world phenomena.
Then we're going to look at how probability distributions relate
to data generating stories, so the data generating processes
and how can we describe them in words and some numbers,
but not a lot of equations.
Then we'll look at joint probabilities
and conditional probabilities.
And then we'll understand Bayes theorem and its utility.
OK, so the first thing, and I want to say,
there's a bit of conceptual overhead here,
but it's worth going into.
People think about probability in a multitude of ways.
And pioneers such as Bernoulli, Bayes, and Laplace
thought about probability as a degree of belief or plausibility.
How much do I believe this thing to be true based on the evidence
that we have at hand?
That seemed like a vague notion at the time,
and there wasn't actually a lot of computational power
to figure out how to formalize this that we have now
and we'll see now.
So what happened is the statisticians of the time
redefined probability as the long run relative frequency
with which an event occurred, given a lot
of repeated experimental trials.
So you experiment, you get a lot of data,
and then whatever proportion you get there
is a probability of some sort.
You can think about error bars or uncertainty around that.
But it's something that can be measured, is the point.
And it was then seen as an objective tool
for dealing with random or stochastic phenomena.
This book, which I got this quotation from,
by Sivya and Skilling, is a must read
for anybody interested in this type of stuff.
It's a really beautiful, short, and more comprehensible,
more understandable book than a lot that's out there.
So when we're talking about this type of random phenomena,
we can be talking about so many types of things,
such as click through rate on a website.
So this is a nice example, because if we
know that a website has a click through rate of 10%,
we can then calculate the probability
of having 10, 9, 8 people click through it
upon drawing 10 people randomly for the population.
But that's not the type of question we usually ask,
in science, right?
In science, we usually say, given the data of how many people
click through, how can we calculate the click through
rate?
And then how certain can we be of this calculated click
through rate or this estimate?
Or how likely is a particular CTR click through rate?
So I've written this here, but I'm actually
going to write this on my makeshift whiteboard.
Pull this over here so I'm still close to the microphone.
Oh, that's great.
This is embarrassing.
Thanks, man.
There we go.
That's why they call us a team.
So essentially, what I've told you
is that we're quite good at computing the probability
of seeing data, seeing how many people click through,
given, and all this line, this means conditional,
and we'll see what that means a bit more later on.
But given a model, we're pretty good at calculating
the probability of the data.
But in science, we're very often interested
in the probability of the model, given the data
that we've collected.
And moving between these two is essentially highly nontrivial.
But Bayesian inference provides a really
robust and interesting way of doing that.
OK?
So we'll start thinking about probability
by exploring questions of the first kind,
so the probability of data given an actual model.
And to do this, we're going to start writing some code, OK?
Random number generators.
So the framing of this question is,
let's say that a website has a click-through rate of 50%.
All that means is that 50% of people click through, right?
So if we pick 1,000 people at random from the population,
how likely would it be to find that a certain number of people
click?
I'm just going to edit this slightly.
OK?
And what we can do is we can simulate this.
We don't necessarily need to use equations right at this point.
We can simulate this using NumPy's random number generator.
OK?
So before we do that, though, I'm
going to say we're first going to use NumPy's random.rand
to randomly select floats between 0 and 1.
This is known as the uniform distribution, OK?
So we're going to do this.
So this is code along, right?
OK.
So np.random.rand.
And how many did I say?
Let's do 1,000.
And now I want to plot a histogram.
The reason I've got the semicolon after this,
you may be aware, is there's some text output
that we want to avoid, OK?
OK.
So there we go.
Now, I'm sure a whole bunch of you who work in science
have been like, label your axes.
And I totally agree.
We're not going to do that for the sake of time currently.
But I totally admit that this is like bad practice to not
label axes here.
OK?
So we've got a uniform distribution.
But how does this tell us about how many people click through?
Right?
We can actually use this random number generation process
to figure out how many people click through,
given a particular rate.
The way we do this is, as we've got uniform numbers between 0
and 1, to simulate sampling from the population of people
clicking, we check whether each float was
greater or less than 0.5, OK?
If it's less than or equal to 0.5,
we say the person clicked through.
And this is generalizable to any click through rate, OK?
So let's compute how many people clicked.
So what was the original variable?
It was x.
And I said less than or equal to 0.5.
Can anyone tell me what clicks will be?
So x is an array.
What will clicks?
It will be an array of true or false, of Booleans, right?
Now, the cool thing about Booleans
is they've got arithmetic operations,
so we can add them together.
If someone clicked through, it's going to return true.
If someone didn't click, it's going to return false.
So if I sum together that array, that
will just give me the number of people who click through,
right?
That's pretty handy.
So sum, the number of clicks is the sum of clicks.
And then I'm going to print it out using f strings, which,
so let's do that.
So the number of clicks was 518 out of 1,000,
which isn't quite 50%.
But remember, because we're simulating a phenomenon,
we wouldn't expect it to be exactly 50%, right?
A little note about f strings.
f strings, it's pretty cool.
It was introduced in Python 3.6, I think, right?
And it allows you to include variables
within strings very nicely.
I joked once that it was the best thing about Python 3.6.
But I'll never joke about that at PyCon ever again,
because people are pretty opinionated.
OK, so we've got the number of clicks.
Now I want the proportion of clicks, right?
OK, so to get that, we're going to get number of clicks
and divide by the total number of people.
And I could divide by 1,000, but just in order
to have it generalizable, the code, I'm just going to,
by the length of clicks.
OK, so up for discussion.
I always do this.
The question I had, did you get the same answer as your neighbor?
And the answer is probably no, because I've already
told you why, because we're simulating a random process,
and there'll be some variation with respect to that.
OK, so let me ask you this.
Let's say that all you had was the data.
We didn't know what the click-through rate was.
We didn't decide it a priori.
All you have is this data, and you
want to figure out the click-through rate.
So that's really the probability of the model, given this data.
What would your estimate for the click-through rate be,
given the data that I have up here?
I'd estimate it to be 1 half, 0.5.
Well, would it?
Because look at the data.
The proportion is actually 0.518, right?
So wouldn't the estimate be 0.518?
So all we have is the data, not the data generating process.
So what's the probability of the click-through rate
being 0.518?
It would be whatever each of us sees on our screen,
given some error, right?
Yes, so that answers my second question.
My first question is, what would your point estimate be?
What would your estimate be?
And it would be what you have on your screen?
Now, how confident?
What would your error bars or confidence
interval around this be?
My error would vary by my sample size,
so smaller the sample, bigger the error.
Yeah, exactly.
Standard on the concept.
And essentially, what we'll see at some point,
well, maybe not today.
It depends how far we get, is that the error
will vary with respect to the square root of the sample size,
one over the square root, in fact.
But the issue is that doing it in a way
that it's not going to be a big problem.
So what would be the error?
Well, the error would be the error
of the sample size, which is the error of the sample size.
But the issue is that doing it in this fashion,
we have no idea what the error is.
What we'll see in a Bayesian framework is that we get out
this estimate, and we actually get a distribution of all
the possible click-through rates.
And from that, we can actually draw out
any information we want about this particular value,
which is really cool.
Now, just as a note, I've called it a note there.
I think I called it a keynote last time, which doesn't
make sense at a conference.
So we've described probability in two ways,
but we haven't described it mathematically.
And we're not going to do that today.
We're going to think about probability
as a way of thinking about data-generating processes
in the world and use random number generators
to simulate them and see how that corresponds to our data.
If you're interested in the mathematical descriptions,
essentially, what I'll say is that probability defines
a function from the space of possibilities,
possible values.
In the above, it's the interval 0, 1.
That describes how likely it is to get a particular point
or region in that space.
Michael Bedancourt has an elegant introduction
to probability theory that I can recommend if you're interested.
So all that having been said, it's time for hands-on.
I'd love to take five, maybe five to 10 minutes for you
to use random sampling, as we've done above, to simulate how
many people click when the click-through rate is 0.7.
How many click is one question and what proportion?
So get coding on that.
And when you're done, put up the green sticky.
And if you have a question, put up the red one.
Yeah.
OK.
And if you're done with the exercises,
feel free to move on.
This is a habit that Hugo and I have had.
You can always go beyond us.
But please do remember to put up the sticky just so we have
an indication of how many people.
Just make sure you put up the stickies.
And actually put it on your forehead, not the computer.
No, I'm joking.
That's a ridiculous idea.
OK.
Got it.
We'll have one more minute.
I see a bunch of green stickies coming up.
And if you're having any challenges, Eric's going around.
I'll also say that it's quite similar to the solution
for the 0.5 that we went through together.
OK.
Great.
This is exciting.
So let's see if I can do it.
Good.
So use random sampling to simulate
how many people click through.
You can sample from the uniform distribution once again.
I'm going to be slightly lazy and use the same random numbers
that I generated before.
So because the click-through rate is 0.7,
we're looking for all those that are less than 0.7.
Number of clicks was the sum of clicks.
Remember, because we have that Boolean.
So I got something in my throat.
Number of clicks.
And then once again, how do you get the proportion?
Can someone tell me?
It's not a trick question.
What's that?
Exactly.
So it's the number of clicks divided by the length,
the total number of people.
Perfect.
Whoa.
I'm not into that.
I'm definitely, there's a very low probability
that you will get this, right?
Wow.
OK.
Cool.
I like it.
It's an omen of things to come.
OK.
Great.
So now we've generated the proportion.
OK.
Great.
So now we've generated some stuff.
I just want to discuss some similar principles
with real-world data.
You can calculate these types of proportions or proxies
for probability with real-world data.
And we're going to look at the Galapagos Finch Beaks, which
several people went over many years to measure the length
sum to the islands of, I think this one is the island of Daphne
Major, but I need to confirm that.
All the data is here, this hyperlink.
So these are measurements from 2012.
So I'm going to call it DF underscore 12.
OK.
So and we're just printing out the first five rows here,
which I would urge people not to do.
Do it now.
But I think someone asked the question a while ago,
like how many mistakes do you think
are made in data science just as an artifact of people looking
at the head of a data frame first?
Right.
Worthwhile question.
Don't have time to think about it right now,
because we're here for probability.
OK.
So I just want to take out the lengths.
And this is B length for beak length.
Right.
And just we'll see, band doesn't matter.
We'll see the species.
There'll be two species.
We have the beak length and the beak depth.
So we're going to do that.
Now the question is, what proportion of birds
have a beak length greater than 10?
So we can do exactly the same thing
as we did before, where the proportion will be,
we'll look at the lengths that are greater than 10.
And I'll need to divide that by the total length of so
many lengths happening.
Whoa.
What have I done here?
Yeah.
Yeah, I do.
Thanks.
Lucky I got you here.
OK.
85.
Just over 85% have lengths greater than 10.
I am.
I have a question.
Sorry.
I think it's green on the browser.
Oh, I guess.
Yep.
Absolutely.
How is that?
That's better.
OK.
If you just give me one.
OK, we're going to keep going and then I'll
figure this out in a second.
So what I want to say is that this
is the proportion of birds in your sample,
in our sample that have a beak length greater than 10,
in the empirical data, not the probability
that any bird drawn from the population
will have this beak length.
So always remember, sample is different from population.
But we can use samples to think about proxies for probability.
And one way to do that, which we'll mention now,
see a bit more later, is via resampling.
So essentially, what we do is we look at this data set
that we have and draw, treat it like a population
and draw new data points from it.
So thanks.
We'll simulate drawing random samples with replacement.
So we'll draw one, put it back, then from the same set,
we'll draw again to see how many lengths are greater than 10
and calculate the proportion.
And this is something known as, well,
it's been dubbed as hacker statistics
because we're essentially using computational hacker
techniques to think about statistics.
And you can get distributions out this way, et cetera.
So we're going to, let me get this right.
Yep, so what I'm going to do is I'm
going to draw 10,000 different data points out
of our sample, which is actually quite smaller.
So we're going to take the sum.
Now, to randomly sample from it, we're
going to do np.random.choice.
Now, we're sampling from lengths.
Now, how many do we want?
The next argument is the number of samples.
And we want to be able to do it with replacement.
So we're going to set the keyword argument replace
equal to true.
Now, this will give us 10,000 samples.
And we want to see how many of those are greater than 10,
and then divide by the number of samples.
And once again, we see something quite close.
Now, the reason I wanted to mention this now
is now we've got not just a proportion,
but a proxy for probability.
Now, the really cool thing is, what we just
did and what you just did, I just
love that you've got a green sticky on your head still.
It's awesome.
It's really, really positive.
What we can do is we could do this procedure 1,000 times
and get out a variety of different results.
And that will give us a distribution.
So we'll know more about uncertainty in that sense
as well.
But we'll say a bit more about that later.
Now it's time to get to some really fun stuff.
Not that that wasn't fun.
It's just going to get funner.
That's an Australian term for more fun, by the way.
I don't know if people say funner in this great nation.
So in the above, we've used the uniform distribution
to sample from a series of bias coin flips.
But some of you may know that these bias coin flips
or click-through rates are actually
called a binomial distribution as well, right?
We've got a question up back.
Just wait for the mic.
So I have a question to the validity of the method above,
the resampling thing.
So would you say that if we resample and do it many times,
we know more about the probability now?
We used the data set, which had just a very limited sample
size, right?
Now we resampled it, and I did many times.
Do we know more about standard deviation, standard error?
I mean, what do we know actually now?
Yeah, you can get out.
Once you do that a number of times,
you can get out standard deviation.
You can get out standard error.
Also, notice that we're not presuming any model.
So it's actually a non-parametric technique
for getting out the distribution.
You can get out percentiles.
You can get out a lot of different things.
And for this to be reliable, does the sample
have to be of a certain size?
That's a good question.
Yeah, there are certain.
I'd suggest checking out Efron's original bootstrapping
paper to figure out the actual.
There are very few assumptions, but sample size is important.
Great question.
Thank you.
So let's think about the binomial.
So with the click-through rate, I'm
not sure that I mentioned that this can also be thought of
as a biased coin flip.
But this is kind of the more abstract model
that people think about is flipping a coin with probability
of heads being 0.7 or 0.5, as we've seen.
Just as a click-through rate can be modeled as that.
Incidence of disease also modeled as that.
So it's quite an abstract model that's used in a lot
of different places.
More generally, the binomial distribution,
it has two parameters, n and p.
And it's defined as the probability distribution
of the number of heads seen when flipping a coin n times
with the probability of heads being p.
And that's the story.
That's the story of the binomial distribution.
I could write out the equation for you,
and you could work with that.
But now we know the story, and we can simulate it.
We can actually work with it in a lot of different ways.
And as I wrote here, this distribution
tells the story of a general model in the following sense.
If you believe that you're collecting data in the world
that has an underlying data-generating process
with a binary outcome, and that one of the two outcomes
occurs with probability p, then that story
is the binomial story.
So you can model your data using the binomial distribution.
And what you can do, as we'll see,
is not worry about equations or fits
or anything along those lines.
You can plot what the binomial distribution would look like.
You can plot your data and just eyeball and see whether it
seems like a good fit initially.
And we're going to be doing that time and time again.
I'll reformulate this slightly and say
that any process that matches this is a binomial process,
as I said.
You'll also see individual coin flips referred to as Bernoulli
trials in the literature.
This is because this was discovered or created
this theory by, I can't remember if it was Daniel Bernoulli
or Jacob Bernoulli.
But whichever one it was literally sat there flipping
coins for date.
Like, no, he did what we're doing, but flipping coins
and writing down the results like tens of thousands of times.
So we should all be grateful.
Formulating this story in terms of Bernoulli trials,
the story of the binomial distribution
is the number r of successes in n Bernoulli trials
with probability of p of success is binomially distributed.
So we're now going to use the binomial distribution
to answer the same question as above.
OK?
And what I mean by that is we used the uniform distribution
before, and we're going to see it as binomial.
First, I'm going to set the seed.
We're randomly generating numbers.
Our computers use something that's
known as a pseudo-random number generator.
And what that means is that once I can set the seed,
it's pseudo-random because once I set a particular seed,
the random number generator starts from that point.
And setting that seed will give the same random numbers
after the fact.
So if you and I set the same seed,
then we'll get everything the same.
And this is very important, of course,
for reproducible science.
So I'm going to set the seed.
What am I going to set the seed to be?
Feel free to set the seed to be whatever you want, essentially.
I'm going to set it to be my birthday, the way that we write
birthdays and dates in general.
It's weird that you all know my birthday now,
but feel free to reach out on July 16
with wishes of prosperity and happiness.
So the cool thing about simulating stuff
is we did np.random.rand.
Or you can also do uniform, but we did rand before.
np.random.
If we're doing a binomial distribution,
does anyone have an idea of what the function's
going to be called?
Binomial, yeah, definitely not a trick question.
And that's pretty cool.
And we want to flip the coin 10 times.
And p is 0.7, so that's the second argument.
And look, come on, seriously.
I really didn't want to get seven there,
but this is some black wizardry we have here.
But OK, what we'll see, though, is
so that's if we do this binomial trial once.
If we flip a coin 10 times, now we've got seven heads.
Unlikely, but cool.
And as I write here, in the above,
we've simulated the scenario once.
This only tells us one potential outcome.
So let's now just simulate it 1,000 times.
Or let's simulate it 10.
I don't even care.
We can simulate it like a million times and see
what happens.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to, once again,
and this is one of the great things about NumPy random,
is that I can do the same as I did before.
So I've got 10.
Let me just get this right.
10, 0.7.
And now I can just choose to do it as many times as I want.
So this will be the size.
This is the number that I get out.
And then I'm going to plot the histogram.
I'm going to plot it normalized.
We get a density.
We get a fraction, a proportion, essentially.
We'll see what that means.
OK.
Cool.
This is nice, right?
So we'll see.
And I'll just, I'm actually, just for clarity's sake,
I'm going to just print x here.
We'll see x.
Before this just gave out one number.
Now it's actually going to give out 10,000 different results.
So x is an array of all the 10,000.
We're plotting a histogram of that.
And what do we see here?
I mean, we see pretty unlikely to get anything down here.
But as we get more and more, we'll
see 7 is the most likely, as you'd expect.
And then it goes down and down and down.
And 10 is the maximum you'll get, right?
OK.
So that's pretty cool that what Daniel or Jacob Benouli,
I mean, they were brothers.
They probably flipped coins together.
That was a weird remark.
You know, we just got to do 10,000 sets of 10 coin flips
using our random number generators
and getting out this normalized histogram, which
is pretty cool, OK?
Once again, I answered the group chat.
What do you see in the above?
And the point is there's a peak at 7,
and it goes down on either side.
So having said that, it wasn't so unlikely
that we got 7 there.
Got 7 there?
I mean, it was the most likely.
OK, all that having been said, I think
what I'd love for you all to do now
is to use the tools that we've just developed
to start flipping some bias coins
and answer these questions.
So the first one is, if I flipped a bias coin with
probability of heads 0.3 20 times,
what's the probability of five or more heads?
And then there's a similar question,
and then I'll get you to plot something.
And I'll give you 5 to 10 minutes to do that.
So take down your green stickies, please,
if they're still up from before.
And then get coding.
OK.
So if you get stuck at all, just go back and look through some
of the stuff we've done together.
Remember, there are clues everywhere.
That's my new mantra.
OK.
All right, we'll take a couple more minutes.
And then as a teaser, things are about to get really fun.
We're going to have a battle between histograms
and empirical cumulative distribution functions.
Spoiler, ACDS win.
All right, everyone, I'm going to get moving on this.
So I'm flipping a coin 20 times, probability 3.
So once again, I'm going to be doing NP.random.what?
Binomial.
This is great.
It's like a colon response.
How's that?
I don't even know if that was a hip hop reference or what that was.
And look, I'm going to do this experiment 10,000 times.
You can do it as many as you want, essentially.
And I want to know when that's greater than or equal to 5.
That will give me the Boolean, so I want to sum that up.
And then I want to divide that by the number of times I did it.
OK?
OK.
Good.
That's the probability of getting five or more heads.
OK?
Now similarly, calculate the probability of five more heads
for p is equal to 5.
I'm going to get a bit lazy here and just copy and paste, right?
If you copy and paste three or more times, what do you do?
You write a function.
Thank you.
Great.
Eric will tell you that as well.
OK.
So if you flip a fair coin 20 times, the probability of five or more heads
is 99.5.
And that makes sense.
I mean, OK.
So plot the normalized histogram of number of heads,
flipping a fair coin 10 times.
OK.
I think I can do that.
Really embarrassing if I just couldn't for a long time.
The rest of the workshop was me trying to do that.
So doing that, 10 times fair coin.
Now I'm going to plot the histogram of x.
Because I want it normalized, I'm going to do density equal true.
And I'll set the number of bins equal to 10.
OK.
Probably need to close that out.
Cool.
Did most people get something like that?
Quick question.
Does this look like anything to you?
It's a binomial distribution.
But does it look like any other?
It looks kind of normal or Gaussian-y.
And that's telling.
And we may not get to this in this workshop, unfortunately.
But in certain limits, the binomial looks like something else.
You can prove that in a number of ways, one of which is the central limit theorem.
What we will see soon is the limit in which the binomial distribution turns into the Poisson
distribution, which is really cool.
OK.
So this is a key point now that I don't want to spend a lot of time on.
But you may have noticed that the binomial distribution can take only a finite number
of values, whereas the uniform can take only a finite number of values.
The uniform can take any number between 0 and 1.
And these are different enough to make mention of them.
The former is called a probability mass function.
That's where you have a discrete number of possibilities.
And the latter, a probability distribution function, or PDF.
Going on, we may discuss this a bit more.
But I wanted to make that very clear.
And once again, severe and skilling is a great reference for this.
I'll also provide a link maybe in the next iteration.
A lot of the work of Alan Downey, who will probably see some of his stuff later on.
He does a lot of incredible work on this stuff.
So I have a question for you.
Looking at this histogram, can you tell me the probability of seeing four or more heads?
Can someone easily read off that histogram?
So you'd like the way I'd do it.
And if like this is my naive way of doing it,
I'd like add up the proportions across four or more or three or less
and then subtract that from blah, blah, blah.
That seems like hard work to me.
And it seems kind of counterintuitive.
I'm just wondering if there are any other types of figures that could help us with this.
And lo and behold, enter the empirical cumulative distribution function,
which is one of my favourite plots.
And empirical and we're going to be building a lot of these actually.
It's an alternative to a histogram.
It's a way to visualise univariate data, so data of one variable.
And the eCDF is super rich in information.
So it allows you to visualise all your data.
There is no binning bias.
And some people think binning bias in histograms is a very archaic or not relevant problem.
But in terms of even thinking about multimodality of distributions
or where these things occur,
you can tell a lot of lies with histograms by choosing bin sizes inappropriately.
So you avoid binning bias with an eCDF.
So you plot all the data.
You can also plot controls and experiments.
You can plot data and models, which really means many populations.
You can see multimodality, though it's slightly less pronounced.
And if you think, what we'll see is that for the more mathematically inclined,
an eCDF is the integral of...
Is that right?
Yeah, integral of the PDF.
And what happens when you integrate,
modes or peaks become points of inflection.
So you see that there.
And you can just read off so much stuff from eCDFs, such as percentiles.
I would really advise you to see Eric Ma's great post on eCDFs here
and this Twitter thread, thanks to Alan Downey.
And Eric, like, I'm telling you, I love eCDFs.
If you speak to this guy about eCDFs afterwards,
you'll come away with a different worldview, I think.
I just want to show you one thing that happened recently.
I saw a really bad histogram in a paper a few weeks ago
on Friday afternoon before lunch.
And so before going out to lunch, I just tweeted out three words.
I tweeted out, stop plotting histograms.
And I went to lunch and came back to, like, essentially a lot of abuse.
So, yeah, this is...
I don't know what time... why I thought I was in that time zone.
Maybe it's because I set up Twitter in Australia.
But, you know, stop plotting histograms.
Someone wrote, can we stop Brexit first?
Fonsbeck wrote, plot several histograms.
Michael Bencourt, good friend of mine, threatening me with fighting.
And then they... it keeps going on.
Then I start swearing and saying, let's teach people more broadly.
You're the guy who, you know...
And it just goes on and on and on.
Andy Muller called dev of psychic learn.
You know, like it's... yeah.
Essentially, I just left it alone
and saw the whole Twitterverse explode, attack me.
And I left it for a day.
Then people started defending me.
Then people started attacking again.
And it's just...
Twitter's a beautiful place, isn't it?
Enough about that, though.
OK, so to define...
Please, Eric.
Sorry, Hugh.
I just wanted to make one point of clarification.
It's that it's not the eCDF
that is the integral over the PDF
of a probability distribution.
It's just the CDF.
Yes, the cumulative distribution function
is the integral of any continuous probability distributions PDF.
All right?
So if you take the derivative of the probability distribution
and the derivative of the cumulative distribution function
which runs from 0 to 1,
you will get back the probability distribution function.
And we'll see that.
And I suppose the point is that
the empirical cumulative distribution function
is from data,
whereas the cumulative distribution function
is from a probability distribution.
OK?
So to define it,
in an eCDF, the x-axis is the range of possible values
for the data.
And for any given x value, the corresponding y value
is the proportion of data points less than or equal
to that x value.
OK?
Now, that's a bit of a mouthful.
But we're going to make one now.
What I'm going to do first, though,
is define a handy eCDF function
that takes in data and outputs the x and y data
for the eCDF.
So what we do is we compute the number of data points,
then we sort the data,
and then we take the y data for each data point.
So we'll just get you to execute that cell.
Now, what I want to tell you
is that I'm going to get you to do this now.
Actually, no, I'm going to do this,
and then you can plot eCDFs later on.
That's great.
I think the first time I should demonstrate.
So we've got...
OK, this has to be the, not he.
OK?
So we generate x and y data for the...
So this is for the following,
for the previous question, I'm sorry.
Please read the answer to the following question.
Is that what I wanted?
Yeah, so I want the previous data, OK?
So to do that, remember this eCDF function
just takes in the data,
so I'm going to do eCDF,
x, OK?
Now I'm going to plot it.
plt.plot
Now the x data is x flips,
y data is y flips.
Now I'm going to add a few more
little quags, keyword arguments.
It'll create a line,
and I don't necessarily want a line per se,
so I'm going to have dots as markers
and I'm going to have line style
equal to none, OK?
Let's just do that again.
OK, beautiful.
Once again, I haven't labelled my axes, but that's OK.
So what we actually see,
the question is, what's the probability
of seeing four or more heads?
So these are the number of heads in these trials
and we'll see that the probability
of seeing four or more heads
is 80%.
OK, the probability of seeing
less than four heads is 20%, right?
So the probability of seeing
four or more heads is 80%, OK?
Yeah, 80%-ish.
Yeah, it's actually just like,
it's probably 82 or something like that.
You can do that calculation.
But having said that, you can read off the median,
you can read off all types of percentiles,
your 95 percentile,
your 25, your 75,
you can read off all your percentiles
and do all of these types of calculations as well.
And I want to add one more piece.
So for those of you who are in the network analysis tutorial,
whatever I said there, Hugo has just repeated.
And there's, looking at this,
there's even more information that you can get
for the case of a discrete probability distribution,
which is what we have here.
If you look at all the points stacked up,
the height tells you the amount of credibility
associated with that number,
so which is the most probable number?
The one that has the highest amount of height.
Try reading that off a histogram, fighting words.
Yeah, I like it.
See, that's what I'm talking about.
I'm the good cop.
I took the full amount, yes.
At that point, we'll, yeah.
I guess you could also use just the histogram
and add the cumulative equals true parameter
and you would get the same thing, right?
OK.
Yes, but you would still have the binning bias
if you didn't bin correctly.
So if you're, yes, exactly.
And there was a question behind?
OK, great.
And so the one thing I want you to notice here,
let's say I had 10 different populations.
I could plot them all in different colors
or different transparencies here.
Try doing that with, I mean, you see histograms
of people plotting like all of these overlapping things.
But I could plot a model here as well
and then control and experiment.
But OK, I want to move on to really,
we've talked about probability distributions
and some of their stories.
I really want to get into this now.
Before I do, though, I want to thank Justin Boyce
who is a very old friend and collaborator.
He's appeared several times on a podcast that I host
called Data Framed that I'd all urge you to listen to
to help me meet my KPIs at work, essentially.
I know they're OKRs,
I know they're OKRs now, whatever.
But Justin and I have spoken,
it must be for 100 hours, about this type of stuff.
So he's a lecturer at Caltech teaching this type of stuff.
The material he's developed
has changed the way I think about probability simulation
and telling stories.
So I want to shout out to him.
I also want to say I think some of this
I actually just directly plagiarized from him.
But I think the license he used allows me to do that.
So it's all good.
OK, so once again,
we saw we can match data-generating processes
with binary outcomes to the story
of the binomial distribution,
given another characteristic of Bernoulli trials.
Now I want to tell you about the Poisson distribution,
how we can think about the Poisson distribution
by telling stories.
So there's a great book by David McKay
called Information Theory, Inference and Learning Algorithms.
He tells the story of a town called Poissonville
in which the buses have a very odd schedule.
OK, so if you stand at a bus stop in Poissonville,
the amount of time you have to wait for a bus
is totally independent of when the previous bus arrived.
So what this means is you could watch a bus drive off
and another arrive almost instantaneously,
or you could be waiting for hours.
Now this seems like it probably wouldn't happen.
I live in New York City,
and the subway system does operate like that,
I feel, a lot of the time.
Having said that,
there are a lot of natural processes
which follow Poisson processes.
So natural births in a given hospital, OK,
is one.
There is a well-defined average number of natural births per year
and the timing of one birth is independent
of the timing of the previous one.
Why is it important that I said natural births?
You can't schedule them.
If you had to schedule births in general,
it wouldn't be true,
because induced births actually happen
with respect to certain schedules
of doctors' availability, nurses,
a lot of different things play into that.
So they're not Poisson processes.
Landings on a website can follow Poisson processes.
Media strikes, molecular collisions in a gas,
aviation incidents,
and any process that matches the buses in Poissonville story
is a Poisson process, OK?
So what then is a Poisson distribution?
A Poisson distribution
is the number of arrivals of a Poisson process
in a given amount of time, OK?
And it has one parameter,
the average number of arrivals in a given length of time.
So to match the story,
we could consider the number of hits on a website in an hour
with an average of six hits per hour,
this being Poisson distributed, OK?
Now, what I'm going to do
is I'm just going to generate that data now
so we can see what it looks like, OK?
So what I've said is
the Poisson distribution
has one parameter,
the average number of arrivals in a given length of time.
So I'm going to generate
np.random.
So if it's a Poisson distribution,
what do you think the next...
It's not a trick question.
It's Poisson, but lambda will...
Yes, so lambda is the variable.
But the name of the function
is Poisson.
And I can just use a positional argument.
I don't need to use a keyword argument.
I'm going to use the size
equal 10...
Let's just say 10 to the power 6.
Now I'm going to plot this.
Samples, and I'm going to choose
21 bins.
Yep, didn't work.
OK.
Bins.
Cool.
So this, if I take this many samples,
is what our Poisson distribution looks like.
And you'll see that the average is
around 6,
the average of 6 landings on a website
in 10 minutes.
So what we've done, we can write down
the equation of the Poisson distribution for sure.
But we've actually
rigorously defined it
using a story
and able to simulate it now and understand it
without using the math or the calculus.
And I actually think this is incredibly powerful
and it will allow a lot more people
to kind of...
It reduces the barrier to entry for people who don't
necessarily have a serious background
in calculus.
Question, does this distribution
look like anything to you
that we've seen before or you've seen before?
It's kind of normal.
It's not quite because it's definitely not symmetric
but I can see why you'd say that.
What's one we've seen earlier today
that was kind of normally but not symmetric?
Binomial, right?
It's kind of binomial-esque.
OK, that's a new term.
OK, and in fact
the Poisson distribution is
the limit of the binomial distribution
for low probability of success
and large number of trials
and I've written this here but I actually want to go through it.
So let's think about
this is one of the greatest things about telling these stories.
You can show that in
the limit of low probability
and large number of trials. You can show mathematically
that the binomial
and the Poisson converge or they're approximate, right?
But you can also do it just by telling the stories, OK?
So think about the stories.
You're doing a Bernoulli trial
once a minute for an hour
each with a success of probability
of 0.05
you do 60 trials
the number of successes is binomially distributed
and we'd expect to get about three successes, right?
So this is
the same as the Poisson story of seeing
three buses on average arrive
in a given interval of time.
What this means is that the Poisson distribution
with the arrival rate equal to
n times p from the binomial
distribution approximates that binomial
distribution, OK?
The reason this can be useful, practically
is the Poisson distribution can be simpler
to work with because it only has one parameter
instead of two.
So what I'd love for you to do now is
just have a quick hands-on.
You get to put your first ECDF by yourselves
not coding along. So please
put the ECDF of the Poisson distribution
that you generated above. And I'll give you a few
minutes to do that.
.