Hello, everyone.
How's everyone doing?
Awesome.
All right.
This talk is Beyond Two Groups, General Bayesian Testing
by Eric Ma.
He has an open space later today that he'll
be telling you about.
And that is where you can go and ask questions.
So please hold your questions for the open space later.
And Eric Ma.
Hello, everybody.
How are you all doing?
And how has PyCon been?
Pretty awesome?
Yeah.
Cool.
I've been on staff for a few years myself.
PyCon's one of the highlights of my year.
And it's really amazing that we were able to get
so many people here.
I'd also like to thank you all for coming to my talk today.
The title, you can see it on the screen, Beyond Two Groups,
Generalized Bayesian A, B, C, D, E, F, G Testing.
At the end of it, I hope it's pretty clear to you
that this is basically my rant against canned
statistical procedures.
We do not want canned statistical procedures.
We want to do our statistics in a more principled fashion.
And Python can be a great part of that.
A little bit about myself, just so that you
have a flavor of who I am.
Currently, I work for the Novartis Institutes
for Biomedical Research.
We do data science.
I'm on a team called Scientific Data Analysis.
My official title is investigator,
which sort of means I'm allowed to do researchy things.
Scientific Data Analysis is basically
one of the most generic names you
can think of for a team that's embedded
in a company whose bread and butter is science.
All right?
Prior to that, I was an Insight Data Science fellow.
And prior to that, I did my thesis
in the Department of Biological Engineering at MIT.
It was a journey for me to go in through the back door
and out the front door.
And then if people want to hear it,
open space is open for that.
All right?
Finally, a little bit about me and Python.
Python, for me, has been a very productive language
because it's been the language in which I've
been able to learn a lot of math, things from Bayesian
stats to machine learning to network science.
Without the programming language as a tool
to aid in my learning, it would have been much harder
because this interactive nature of programming
really aids in the learning.
And beyond that, a little note about Python.
It's one of those things where I've
heard people say that Python is just
like the second best language for everything.
And the keyword is not second best.
The keyword is everything, right?
There's rarely one language that lets you go from the web
to data science, to munging data, to DevOps, to SysOps,
et cetera, et cetera, et cetera, all while sticking
within one language.
So it's great.
And I hope you all have the same sentiments.
OK, so why did I make this talk?
I made this talk because I saw a gap in the data science
so-called talk literature in which most talks tell you
how to do an A-B test, Bayesian style or frequentist style.
And they show you two groups.
And they tell you about the T test.
Then they tell you how to apply this to your business case,
et cetera, et cetera.
So in response to that, I basically have three messages.
The first message is you don't have to be stuck with two
groups.
And more importantly, you don't have
to be stuck with the assumptions of the T test, which are
basically normal distribution assumptions.
The second message I have for you
is related to the language.
Python, and more specifically, PyMC3,
is a really great language for probabilistic modeling
and for doing your stats in a principled fashion.
And that's the third point, that with Bayesian modeling,
we can move away from these canned statistical procedures
that have been handed to us in our university classes
and our university stats education
and finally start doing stats in a more principled fashion.
OK, so this is a talk that is a statistics talk disguised
with Python.
And so I am assuming a few pieces of knowledge here.
And I'm putting this out here for the benefit of you,
the audience, so you can make an informed decision as to whether
you would like to continue in this room
or if you'd like to move to a different room.
And I don't mean this in a way to exclude people.
I just want you to have an informed decision.
So first off, I talk a lot about probability distributions,
and I name them in passing in this talk.
So I am assuming that when I name a probability
distribution, you're able to conjure up in your mind
what its shape roughly looks like, what it's
used to be modeling, what it's used for in modeling work,
and what values for which this probability distribution are
valid.
Probability distributions, by the way,
as a working definition for today's talk,
we're just going to call it credibility points assigned
on the number line.
And so when I talk about strong belief or weak belief
inside a strong or weak belief for the value
of a particular parameter, a strong belief, all I'm saying
is that I'm willing to assign very few, a small range
of numbers, credibility points.
So we have a narrow distribution.
And a weak belief says, I'm willing to assign
a large number of, a large range of numbers, credibility points,
and therefore we have a wide distribution.
So the distinction between continuous and discrete
is also important because the two examples that I will show
involve one continuous and one discrete data.
Now, because this is a talk on Bayes,
we have the obligatory Bayes rule slide.
And so what is Bayes rule?
Bayes rule is a neon sign that lives on the, on the,
oh, sorry, no.
Bayes rule is a mathematical routine
for working definition for today.
that lets us update our beliefs about a particular
parameter having seen new data.
All right?
That's all it is.
We don't need to worry about what the mathematical routine is,
thankfully, because PyMC3, which is the package in which I have
implemented all of these models, PyMC3
does all of the fancy math for lazy programmers like me.
All right?
So PyMC3 is a great language, a great package
written in the Python language for doing that.
And I will assume some familiarity with Python,
with PyMC3 syntax.
Now, this isn't to say that if you don't understand
PyMC3 syntax, you shouldn't be here.
It just means I will go a little bit slower
during the code portion for the benefit of those who need it.
That said, if you've never touched PyMC3 before,
my hope is that by looking at the PyMC3 code,
you'll intuit how we've told the data
generative story of our models in such a plain language way
that we can just intuit it from the code.
All right?
All right.
So comparison.
Comparison is the basis of how we do science.
And this video here shows the late Hans Rosling,
a statistician who's great at storytelling.
And in one of his books, he wrote this quote.
When I see a lonely number in a news report,
it always triggers an alarm.
What should this lonely number be compared to?
Implicitly, what he's saying is, what is the baseline?
And what is the baseline that we're
comparing our intervention against is basically
what we're doing whenever we're doing science
and when we do the statistical analysis of that data?
Typically, we're thrown it.
We're thrown two groups.
And it's my hope to tell you, we don't have to stick with two.
So I'm going to tell you two analyses that are lifelike.
I'm clearly not showing real data here because
of confidentiality issues or because they're borrowed
from a different source.
But I'm going to show you two analyses that are lifelike
and will simulate for you what they look like.
The first vignette will tell you how
we do an analysis that moves beyond two groups.
And the second vignette will tell you
how we move beyond two distributed,
t-distributed data in addition to that.
So let's look at vignette one.
This story comes from a paper written by John Kresge in 2013.
And it's a paper that talks about the intervention where
we give participants in a trial a drug.
And then we measure their IQ post-intervention.
So we get data that looks something like this.
Just a quick poll.
How many of you have seen a chart that looks like this?
This is a cumulative distribution plot.
Great.
So I don't really need to explain too much
about what it says.
Just very quickly for the benefit of those
who haven't seen it, the x-axis, we
have the values that we've measured.
On the y-axis, we plot what cumulative fraction of samples
have that value or less.
And so the tails of the distribution
are on the left and the right.
The meaty part is in the middle.
And we have two groups shown over here.
We have the placebo group, which is our control group.
And then we have the drug-treated group,
which is our intervention group.
Marketers call this AB testing.
I don't know why we have to invent yet a new term
for case control testing.
But yes, that's the alternative term that people will use.
So when you look at this, you think, well, yeah, OK.
What kind of statistical procedure could I use here?
So we go back into our university textbooks,
flip back our notes from college, find stats 201,
and they tell us, use the t-test.
So we run a t-test.
And how many of you see that p-value, that juicy, juicy
p-value of 0.025?
Things are statistically significant.
It's awesome.
We can publish this paper, right?
This drug can go to the trials, right?
No.
As it turns out, we missed out that there
were two other groups.
And if we were a dishonest scientist,
we'd stop there.
But we couldn't mask the fact that we've got four groups here.
So now what's the canned statistical procedure
for four groups?
So we go back to our textbooks, go back to our notes.
Stats 201 didn't teach that, so we go to stats 211.
Stats 211 says, there's this thing called an ANOVA.
And you might be able to do a post-hoc t-test.
So we whip out SciPy.
And then we do the ANOVA.
Oh, no.
That p-value is 0.09.
This thing is not statistically significant.
What are we going to do?
The whole thing has gone crumbling down
in front of my eyes.
Well, it's OK.
Even if this thing is not statistically significant,
that's fine.
Let's just do the post-hoc t-test anyways, right?
And so how many post-hoc t-tests do we have to do?
Well, we have four groups.
We do pairwise t-tests.
And so we have four choose two number of tests, right?
And so we put this in.
And since we have more than one test, one hypothesis testing
going, we do the French Revolution thing.
We bring out the guillotine.
And we start chopping out hypotheses
that are not significant.
And we tremble before the guillotine,
asking, when will we get a significant hypothesis test?
Oh, my.
What an emotional roller coaster.
Is this the right way to do stats?
Is this the right way to do science?
Do we really have to bring out the French Revolution
guillotine in front every time we have multiple groups?
Moreover, think about the case where we don't have just four
groups tested.
We have 50 groups tested.
Suddenly, we have more than 1,000 pairwise tests.
And that guillotine is going to have a field day chopping out
hypotheses, pairwise hypotheses tests
that are not significant.
There's got to be a better way.
And when I see a scientific article that says,
or someone says that science has proven this and proven that,
first question I ask is, what have they disproven?
Second question is, how did they do the stats?
Was it a p-value that they calculated?
I don't quite believe that just yet.
So there's got to be a better way.
In particular, let's think carefully about the assumptions
that we make every time we do the t-test.
Every time we do the t-test, we are assuming a bunch of things,
these three being the key.
Firstly, that our data are normally distributed.
IQ, you probably could make a case.
But what if you had other things?
Not necessarily true.
Why would we throw the canned statistical procedure
at non-normally distributed data when we're assuming
normally distributed data?
Secondly, we assume that the standard deviations
between the groups are equal.
What if that's not true?
What if we need a way to flexibly model that?
Thirdly, what if our samples were not independent?
Now, in a randomized controlled trial,
hopefully someone checked.
Otherwise, our drug trials by our company would be done wrong.
Hopefully someone checked.
But what if that assumption doesn't hold true?
We can't do the t-test.
So what canned statistical procedure is there?
So I propose we stop assuming things
and stop implicitly violating these assumptions.
And instead, we do it Bayesian style instead.
So let's carefully model the key components of this problem.
What are the key components of this problem?
Well, we got data.
We need to know what its likelihood is
under a particular model.
And then we need to find out and compute
what the key parameters of this model are
and what their most likely parameters are.
And then for each group, do the same thing
and compare those key parameters.
That's all we need to do.
So we go in.
We write some PMC3 code.
PMC3 code is written like this.
You'll notice, first off, there are these things
called PM.normal, PM.halfKoshi, PM.exponential.
And there are all of these great first class citizens
called probability distributions.
So we can assign them to variables
and we can do math with them.
So for example, I'll model our data,
maybe as a starting point, with a student t distribution.
Because there's a case that multiple factors affect your IQ
and so as a result, the resultant IQ may potentially,
in a hand wavy way, be t distributed.
The student t distribution has a few key parameters.
It's got a mu, it's got a standard deviation,
and it's got a degree of freedom parameter.
Remember that point that I made about having
non-equal, not necessarily equal standard deviations
per group?
Well, as it turns out, we can model standard deviations
on a per group basis using PMC3.
All we have to do is specify that it's
a vector of standard deviations, one per group,
and then pass that into the student t distribution.
So those are the key things.
We can explicitly encode what we are assuming about our data
inside the probability model.
In other words, lay out all the cards on the table.
And if you're not happy with those assumptions,
bring me a different distribution
and a justification for that.
How do we analyze the results of a Bayesian model?
Well, first off, there's no K choose 2 pairwise hypotheses
test that we need to do.
All we have to look at are posterior distributions.
This is one particular representation
of how we look at posterior distributions.
This is essentially what we call a forest plot.
And in a forest plot per group, each of the groups
are the horizontal, are the rows here.
Per group, we can plot out what the median of the posterior
distribution is, what the interquartile range is,
and what a percentage credible interval would be as well.
And those are the dots, the thick bars, and the thin lines,
respectively.
And all you have to do is look at that and say,
yes, studying turned out to be the better intervention.
And actually, I don't even know what this drug is doing.
Is it making you stoned or something?
Because compared to drug plus studying compared to studying,
you actually have lower IQ, right?
So I don't know if this is the thing that was most recently
legalized in Massachusetts.
So all we have to do is compare posteriors.
And compare this, by the way.
And look at this versus that.
Would you rather kneel beneath the guillotine,
waiting for a hypothesis to be proven true,
or would you rather just look at the posterior distributions?
And moreover, what's really interesting,
what's really neat here is the posterior distributions
tell you the credibility assigned
to the particular values.
Plain and simple, nothing fancy.
So two key lessons from this particular analysis.
Firstly, all you need are posterior distributions.
You didn't have to do the multiple hypothesis
correction procedure.
Could we still be wrong?
Yeah, of course, because our data are
assumed to be generated by a random process.
And so if we, by chance, had the wrong sample,
a non-representative sample, well, we
wouldn't have the correct inference.
But it's harder to be wrong when you go with Bayesian procedures.
Secondly, there should be nothing that
stops you with two groups.
PIME C3 code basically lets you write these things called
a vector of probability distributions
in which you can use each slot in the vector to model one group
and do all of your inference in a nice, principled fashion.
Cool.
So I sort of gave you a semi-cheating example
in which IQ, there's sort of a case
to be made that it's maybe normally distributed.
But what if our data were not t-distributed?
t-distributions and normal distributions
are in the same family.
Well, that's when we come to the second vignette.
And this is one where we're talking about clicking on websites.
And this is an example that came to me last year
after I did my tutorial with my co-instructor Hugo.
I was holding office hours in the Tejas room in the AT&T
center in Texas.
And this guy comes up to me and asks, hey, I got some data.
Turned out to be his company data.
I got some data.
And I need some help looking at it.
Would you have some time?
And they're like, yeah, sure.
I got half an hour.
We can totally sit down and look at it.
Three hours later, we were satisfied.
And the process was very illuminating.
So let's take a look at what that data looks like.
The data looks something like this.
This is a company that has a website.
They're helping with booking of hotels.
I won't say which company it is.
There's basically things that they
did to the website to try to improve customer engagement
and clicking and revenue.
So they have the control, which is don't change anything as is.
Then they have a first intervention,
which is let's sort all of our results by price by default.
By default, we sort them by price.
And the second intervention was completely independent.
Let's just put images of the hotel rooms
on the search results, like little thumbnails
that you can see.
And how do we measure customer engagement?
Well, there's a way to do it.
We will measure how many times they click
before they stop clicking.
And so basically, we want to know
which intervention helped our customers find
what they're looking for, and that's how we measured it.
So what are you going to do with that data?
Are you going to do the t-test?
Are you really going to do the t-test?
Does the t-test stand here?
Firstly, I don't think so.
Firstly, we have zero inflation in the data.
Look at the data.
There's this big bar on a log scale
that says that there's a bunch of stuff with zero clicks.
So the t-distribution completely does not hold.
If you did the t-test, you are wrong.
Because the t-distribution assumes
that you can take values from negative infinity
to positive infinity, and that you are continuous.
What are these data?
Zero to positive infinity and discrete.
So again, if you did the t-test, you're wrong.
We need a model that allows us to account for this thing
that we call zero inflation, and we
need a discrete distribution model for this data.
All right, so three hours of modeling later,
we arrive at the conclusion that the zero inflated negative
binomial distribution, that long mouthful name,
is actually the right thing to describe the data.
And why is that the case?
It's because the zero inflated, the ZinB model,
the ZinB distribution is a distribution that
lets us model two processes.
The first process is the group of customers
that have no intent to click whatsoever.
They're just looking around.
The second process is the process
that describes the customers who are looking around.
Sometimes they see the result and they make the purchase
straight away, so zero clicks.
And sometimes they need a first and a second and a third
and a fourth, clicking around before they actually
make that purchase.
So the zero inflated negative binomial distribution
turns out to be the distribution that models this process.
Now, our friend here was not convinced.
He said, we really got to try the T distribution
and I let him try it.
It didn't turn out well.
But he needed to see it in order for him to be convinced
that this was true.
So in PMC3 code, it turns out, look,
we have the zero inflated negative binomial distribution.
A lot of probability distributions are first class citizens
and this particular so-called mixture distribution
is also one of them.
And in fact, you can make a mixture distribution of your own.
Moreover, here's what's really cool.
Because of the data generating process,
there are two very interpretable parameters
that we're interested in.
Firstly, we're interested in knowing whether the intervention changes
the probability of a customer just searching around
to actually being intended to click.
Click around and make a purchase.
And the second thing that we're interested in
is whether the clicking process is affected
or the probability of making a purchase is affected
each time the customer clicks.
And those are calculatable
and I'd invite you to take a look at the code.
I won't dwell too much on it.
But that's modelable if you know just a little bit
about the math behind the equation,
the negative binomial distribution.
So what did we find?
We found that putting images of rooms
actually increases the probability of your customers
clicking on anything at all, right?
So they're moving away from this mode
where they're just looking around into this mode.
We're capturing more customers
that are actually actively seeking to purchase things.
And that if you put an image of the room on,
compared to sorting by price,
you actually increase,
you maintain the probability of purchasing an item.
So it actually reveals something interesting
about the customer behavior.
These are not your price-sensitive people.
These are your value-sensitive people,
the people who want value for money
more than the best price, right?
And so we would not have been able to do this
if we just stuck with the t-test
and blindly assumed all of the things
that the t-test assumed.
Instead, because we sat down and we did the hard thing,
but the right thing,
and carefully modeled the data-generating process
and did our checks to make sure
that it was modeling it correctly,
we're able to arrive at this new insight onto his data.
And this insight on his data
was illuminating for the business and valuable.
And you can actually tag a loss function on top of that
and calculate how much this is tied to dollar amounts
and make that interpretable for executives.
You couldn't do that with the p-value, could you, right?
Okay, so the key takeaways.
Firstly, from this example,
three or more groups are possible, totally possible.
There's no reason again to limit yourself to two groups.
Secondly, all we're doing is comparisons.
And who said that t-tests
were the only way to do comparisons?
As long as you're comparing the consistent quantity,
that works fine.
Finally, this was a neat insight for me,
sitting down, carefully constructing the white box model
lets us tease apart the interpretable things
that are important to the business.
And me coming in as like an outsider
and not even knowing any of this,
this for me was an epiphany.
Now this might be a bit more obvious
to the guy who I was working with,
but for me, wow, this is powerful.
This is really powerful stuff.
All right, so back to my three messages.
I hope it's clear.
From this talk, you can totally do your analysis
without needing to be stuck with two groups
and normal distribution assumptions.
Secondly, PiMC3 is a great flexible language
for probabilistic modeling.
There's a wealth of tops that are out there
and tutorials even on how do you use PiMC3
to do your probabilistic modeling.
I encourage you to check those out.
And finally, when we go base,
we can move away from canned statistical procedures
and instead now do statistics in a principled fashion.
The bonus message here
is you can better interpret your data with Bayesian methods.
Thank you.
.
..
So the first way of picking distributions is to make sure that you pick a distribution that has the correct support
That is the values for which it is valid
So if you got something that can never take on negative values
If you got data that can never take on negative values
Don't pick a distribution for which you can the distribution actually can take on values negative values
The second way to do this is to know the probability distribution stories
And so there's this instructor at Caltech who have met at the sci-pi conferences
His name is Justin Boyce Bo is and he wrote this really great resource online about
probability distributions and their stories
So he tells us what the story is for the binomial distribution the negative binomial distribution the exponential distribution
the normal distribution etc etc etc and
Once you know the distribution stories it becomes really easy to pick out the appropriate distribution for the problem at hand
Now finally there is some model checking that's involved and I've glossed over that over here
You got to do that model checking to make sure that the model is correct and sometimes it's not a single distribution
It's a mixture distribution. We got to do the right checks to make sure that's correct
next question
Quick disclaimer, I'm not trying to start a frequentist Bayesian war but
My question is if if you're doing multiple hypotheses at once
Isn't some sort of correction still needed because
Just by chance you'd expect that you know one of your hundred or two hundred or whatever different high
Categories just happens to be an outlier in what sample you assign to it. And so it will
It will perform it will appear to perform better than the control and you might spend a lot of work trying to implement that
When really it is the same right it speaks to the point that I had made earlier on that we might be wrong
About our inferences because the data as you mentioned just came by random chance from a non random sample
Non-representative sample so I actually had that question when I first made my first notebook with three comparisons
and I went online and asked Alan Downey professor of computer science and
statistics and data science at the Olin College of Engineering and
I asked him do we need multiple hypothesis correction?
and his answer was no because
And he didn't give me the rigorous answer and I'm unfortunately not able to give you the rigorous answer either because I don't have the necessary
Requisite training. I'm I'm a statistician midway through grad school
But but the the answer there the reasoning there was because we've summarized everything that we need to know having seen the data
In the posterior distribution and so the posterior distribution
Tells us everything and there's no hypotheses that we've constructed that we're explicitly testing all we're doing is looking and comparing
What the what the data tell us?
Conditioned on our priors conditioned on the data and I'm happy to talk about it more during the open space
So there will be a I have Bayesian open space or Bayesian office hours as an open space
Later in the day and I'm happy to talk with more of you if you'd like to talk about it
And please don't bring your data to me
Thank you