All right. Good morning, everyone, once again. This talk is break the cycle, three excellent
Python tools to automate repetitive tasks. Session chairs can sometimes have a little
bit of a stage fright, too. So the speaker is Thea Flowers, and she has requested any
questions that you may have. Please hold them off until the end of the talk, and you can
see her outside in the hall where she will be more than happy to answer any questions
you may have. So without further ado, Thea. Hi. There are a lot of you. I'm very nervous.
I'm Thea, and I'm going to talk to you today about three excellent Python tools that I
like to use to automate repetitive tasks. Before we get started, I want to tell you
what to expect from this talk. We only have, like, 30 minutes together here today. It's
a very short amount of time, and there's a lot of things that I want to tell you about.
So we're not going to do any, like, super big deep dives into any of these tools. My
goal here is to kind of give you a taste of these tools, to give you an idea of what they
are, how they look, how they work, and inspire you to go check them out. I'm also going to
be pretty focused on tasks related to working on or maintaining a Python project. There's
at least one tool out of these three that can be used outside of that context, but it's
going to be largely focused on that sort of thing. Another thing to keep in mind is that
I'm going to show some code samples, and I'm going to show some output from these tools,
but my goal here isn't to, like, teach you what this code does or have you fully understand
it or anything like that. Just to give you an idea of what it looks like to use these
tools. So don't sweat it if you can't, like, read all the code, if you're all the way in
the back standing up there because this room is very full, which isn't scary at all. Just
know that the slides will be published online. You can go dig into them later. They're all
pretty straightforward samples. Cool. And also, some of you will probably be familiar
with the first tool I talk about, but I promise that later two are going to be really interesting
for you. And like I mentioned, what I want you to take away is just this inspiration
to go check out these tools and maybe automate some of the things in your life. So I want
to start this talk with story time. So not a fun story, though, unfortunately. A story
of frustration. This is one that's really common to me, and hopefully it will resonate
with a few of you. Let's imagine that you have just come back from work, back to work,
not from work, back to work, from like a long weekend or a holiday or you've decided that
you want to contribute to an open source project for the first time. Really cool stuff. You're
excited and you clone the code, you have it locally, and you're like, cool, before I go
breaking stuff, let's run the test. It's a great idea. Always make sure things still
work before you go breaking things. The problem is you can't just do that. The world that
we've made for ourselves means that we can't just simply run the test. So this story, this
scenario I'm going to walk you through is what goes through my mind when I have to run
the test for a project. So the first thing we have to do, step zero, is create a virtual
environment. Because you don't want to run all this project stuff in your global Python
environment and install its dependencies and mess up all your versions and end up with
version conflicts because that's never fun. So virtual environment. The problem is I haven't
used virtual environment in a few days because I've been on holiday and I forgot the commands.
So let's Google the virtual commands. So this is the virtual environment. And this is the
top Google result for virtual environment. And it's really dense. You'll notice there's
not any commands here. This is wonderfully useful if you want to know what virtual environment
does under the covers. It's completely useless if you want to know how to use virtual environment.
Thankfully there's a user's guide on the left side there. And that has the two commands
kind of spaced out a little bit that we need. So cool. I can do that now. So let's make
a virtual environment. Cool. So in this sample I've made a virtual environment and I've activated
it. It's two steps actually. Step zero has part A and B. Cool. Now what were we doing?
Oh, we're running the test. Let's run test. But how do I run the test again? I can look
at the readme. I can look wherever I could guess. I think it's PyTest. So let's just
try running PyTest. That makes sense. Oh, man. PyTest isn't installed. And I also would
like to point out this is an error message from Ubuntu. It tells you to install this
completely unrelated package. So don't do that. But we're not in trouble yet, right?
We know that PyTest is a Python thing. So we can just pip install that, right? Sounds
like a good plan. Pip install PyTest. Yay, there's green finally somewhere in this. So
we installed PyTest. Yay, another step. So let's try running it again. We have it now.
We can run it. Oh, great. More red. So it seems like I'm missing a dependency. I'm missing
flask is what it's called out here. But I'm almost completely certain that if I just wouldn't
install flask, that I would be missing some other dependency and some other dependency.
Thankfully, I think this project has a requirements.txt. So there can't be any traps there, right?
So let's just pip install requirements.txt, right? That's easy. We're Python developers.
We know how to do this. Oh, crap. What did I do? See, this happens to me every time I
pip install requirements.txt. If you know the problem, raise your hand. I forgot the
dash R. So it's pip install dash R requirements.txt. And at this point, my excitement over working
on this project is quickly waning. Like, fine. Okay. So kind of dependencies installed. Let's
try third time's a charm. Let's try running PyTest. Yay! It finally worked. But I'm not
at what cost. We had to do a lot of stuff to get here. Like, lots and lots of steps here.
We had to go and do all this stuff. And it might seem like to some of you folks who are
like super advanced Python developers, you're like, this is trivial stuff. I do this 17
times a day. Sometimes more than twice an hour. And it may seem trivial, but for people
who are either newer to Python or coming from other languages or whatever, just coming into
your project, these steps are potential points that you can lose people. And people are the
most important part of software. So let's try to be kind to people. This stuff is toil.
Toil is all the nonsense that you have to go through to get to what you actually want
to do. Which was run PyTest. Which is the Macbeth mentioned toil and trouble in the
same breath. And I promise you want nothing to do with what they're cooking up. So this
whole talk is about being kind to yourself and to your teammates and contributors and
trying to reduce some of this toil in your life. This is what I'm about. So let's talk
about how we can fix this. The first tool I want to talk about is TOCS. And it might
be very familiar to a lot of you. It's been around for quite some time. And it's basically
the gold standard for this use case. TOCS aims to standardize Python testing. Which
is a very lofty goal, and they've kind of succeeded at it. It uses an any file at this
configuration. And it makes this scenario really, really simple. Because if you're a
Python developer and you check out a project and it has a TOCS.any, you know immediately
you can probably just run TOCS and you'll get to what you want to do. That's one step.
Let's take a look at what that looks like. So, okay. This is a simple TOCS.any file.
Again, like I said, don't try to digest this whole thing. It's an any file. It just tells
TOCS to do some things. In this case, it tells TOCS to do the same steps we did all those
manual steps. I'm going to highlight some things here. So, this first highlighted section
is where it installed those dependencies I talked about earlier. And this second highlighted
section is where it runs PyTest. You can see at the bottom there's green. And green is
good. So, yay. It took all of those toylful steps, got rid of them for us, and made just
one step. That's wonderful. It's a huge win for everyone involved. But this isn't TOCS's
real strength here. Automation is power. Because TOCS makes all of this stuff trivial, it actually
makes it possible for you to test multiple Python environments, which is really, really
cool. So, imagine, just imagine, I know this is going to be difficult for you all. Imagine
it's 2019 and you're still dealing with Python 2 and 3. Well, TOCS can help. I've highlighted
a one line, not even really a one line change, a four character change in the TOCS.ini file.
And now when you run it, this is going to be very hard to see, but you'll notice there's
two green stripes across the screen. That means it ran PyTest twice. It ran it once
for Python 2.7 and once for Python 3.7. And this is wonderful. I didn't have to do anything
extra really to get that. You kind of get it for free. That's the really powerful part
of this tool. Another scenario you might be able to imagine if you write plug-ins or packages
or anything like that is that you need to test against multiple versions of a dependency.
Especially those of us who develop Django extensions and Flask extensions need to do
this. So this little example tests against Python 2.7, Python 3.7, Flask 0.12 and Flask
1.02. I really couldn't find better version numbers, I'm sorry. But this actually does
four runs of PyTest because it multiplies it. It runs the two different versions of
Flask in both Python 2.7 and 3.7. That's really, really awesome. So this is a really cool
tool. So Tox is everywhere. You can throw a rock and hit 17 or 18 projects that use Tox.
You throw a bunch of rocks, you'll find hundreds. It's been used for a long time and if you
decide to start your automation journey with Tox, you'll find lots of examples, lots of
support, lots of resources. So it's a good thing to keep in mind. However, Tox is a really
focused tool. It is very, very good at what it does. It is mostly intended for automating
Python packages and that is things that can be installed. So things that have a set up
.py or a project .toml and it can be used for things like web apps but it takes a little
bit of telling for that. You have to tell it how to deal with that. But it's really
good at the package idea. You can use it for things like building documentation as
well but the further you stray from Tox's intended purpose, the more inflexible it becomes.
So that is to say, if your automation is like hammering nails, Tox is a pneumatic nail gun,
it will make it happen real fast with very little effort and that's awesome. So Tox is
wonderful. But what if you want to do more? What if your automation needs to deal with
all kinds of stuff? So next tool I want to talk about is Nox. I know it sounds really
similar. It definitely wasn't intentional. Full disclosure, I am the original creator
of Nox but I love Tox and Nox and the last tool that I'm going to talk about too. So
they're all my loves. So Nox aims for flexible test automation. It is a spiritual sibling
to Tox. They are sort of intended to solve similar problems. Like Tox, it uses a configuration
file. But unlike Tox, its configuration file is Python. So let's see what that looks like.
Let's see what that looks like. Easier to show than tell. This is a simple Nox file.
If you've used Flask and Flask is a sort of use of decorators to define view functions,
it's very similar to that. We have a Nox session. This session does the same thing we did with
Tox before. It creates a virtual environment, installs requirements, runs PyTest. Boom.
Pretty much the same stuff. Easy peasy. Just like Tox, Nox can handle the whole matrix
thing of testing multiple versions of dependencies and different Python interpreter versions.
Nox calls this parameterization. It borrowed that term from PyTest. So if you're familiar
with PyTest's parameterization, you'll be right at home with this. And just like with
Tox, it spits out four different invocations and all that stuff. So I know what you're
thinking at this point. So does the same thing as Tox, why would I use it? Well, good question.
But I have an answer. Python as configuration is magical. Being able to just use Python
as configuration for your automation is a really, really freeing thing. Like I assume
that you're in this room because you have some vague interest in Python. So you already
know basically 99% of how to use Nox. You just need to learn very small things, a very
small API. So let me show you some more examples of things going beyond this. Imagine you're
working with protocol buffers. Or don't. I don't care. Just imagine that you're dealing
with something that has like a source file, a proto file in this case. And it needs to
be compiled into a Python file. And you could sit here and add an entry to your Nox file
or Tox file for every single proto file you have. And that's probably going to become
really tedious really fast. Or you can use Python's glob module, which does pattern matching
like shells do. You can find star.proto and find all the proto files and then just pass
them into the compiler all at once. So this one just does two files because I didn't want
the output to be crazy. But it's much easier that way. This next sample is one of my favorites.
This is in every project I have that uses Nox. How many of you build docs have used
Sphinx? Cool. All right. A little less than half. That's fine. Sphinx is a tool that
builds documentation. You run it. It spits out a bunch of HTML files. And then you have
to go and like serve that. And then browse to it in your browser. So what this example
does is if you just run Nox as normal, it will do that. It will build the documentation
to build slash HTML. And then what you'd normally do is you'd go and you'd cdn to
build slash HTML. You'd run Python dash HTTP dot server, I think. And then you'd browse
to localhost 5000, I think. So steps involved. But Nox has a super power because it can do
Nox docs serve. And what it will do is instead of just using Sphinx, it will use Sphinx auto
build which does this magic of building the docs, starting a web server, opening your
browser for you automatically, and then watching for changes and automatically reloading your
browser. That is awesome. Like that's the kind of experience I want people to have when
they're trying to contribute to my documentation. It should be really, really easy. So Nox is
for automation of Python projects. It is more flexible than Tox but also less focused. So
it has pros and cons. It's a really great choice for things like Python applications,
especially web applications that tend to have a lot of peripheral tasks that need to be
done. I've seen Nox use it in some really interesting ways. For example, Google Cloud
Platform has like 200 odd sample applications. And it became pretty tedious for them to maintain
individual test configuration for each one. So they actually use Nox to discover the sample
applications and generate sessions for each sample and run them all. So instead of having
200 odd Nox or Tox configuration files, they just have one, which is really, really cool.
So what if Nox still isn't enough? What if you're like, Fia, that's cool, but I have
way bigger needs than that. What if you are not actually working in a Python project and
you want to use Python to do the task? Okay, cool. We can use Invoke for that. Invoke is
a really, really cool tool that I discovered about a year ago. It's been around for longer
than that, but it's really, really great. Invoke is a task execution tool and library.
It takes inspiration from things like GNU Make, Ruby's rake, and like other stuff that
I forgot. Fabric, because it's from the same creator as Fabric. It's really, really flexible.
And it makes a lot less assumptions than the other tools that I talked about, so it lets
you do more. So I'm going to show you some really simple examples really real quick.
So Tox has this thing about environments. That's its high-level concept. Nox has this
thing about sessions. That's its high-level concept. And they're very interchangeable.
But with Invoke, you have tasks, which is a much more general thing. So you have task-based
workflows. These are two simple tasks that basically clean the docs build, so they delete
any old HTML, and then build it. And the two separate tasks, where they have dependencies.
So when you run them, it actually cleans the build output first and then runs the thing.
I mean, you could definitely do this with Nox and Tox. It's just illustrated. Don't
worry about it. We'll get into some really cool stuff here in a second.
So Invoke is this tool framework. It's kind of superficially similar to the other tools
here, but it's kind of a horse of a different color. You could write tasks that do the same
thing as Nox and Tox, sure. But it's really better for things beyond that. What I find
myself doing is using Tox and Nox for the Python testing aspect of my projects, and
then using Invoke to handle the maintenance minutia. So let's talk about that.
So this is from PIP. Are you all familiar with PIP? Yeah? We talked about it earlier
in the presentation. PIP, they have a lot of contributors. And they used to have this
problem where they'd ask contributors to manually add themselves to the author's file so they
get attribution for their work, which is really a nice thing to do. The problem is we kept
forgetting to do that. What this does, and this is super simplified, PIP's actual task
is a little bit more complicated. This uses Git to just find all the authors by their
commits and then compiles an author's file for us. So this is an example output. But
this way we can run this as part of a release process, and we don't have to worry about
leaving anybody behind. That's really cool. Another one that I use all the time is I release
a lot of packages, and when you release packages, it's nice to put together a change log to
tell people what changed between the versions. I mean, you don't have to, but it's a nice
thing to do. So what this task does is it uses Git to actually figure out the difference
between the last release and the current release and prints it out in a nice format that can
be easily copied and pasted into a change log. Of course, you could take this concept
even further and have Invoke actually update the change log file for you. There's an idea.
Or even further and have Invoke just automate the entire release process for you. That's
an idea, but that's for a different talk, I think. So you can also do really fun stuff.
Don't try to wrap your head around this. Please don't. This is an Invoke example that compiles
a C program, and it does actually compile. I actually pulled this from my personal experience
because I do a lot of Arduino stuff, and I hate using make and I hate the Arduino IDE,
so I can build them with a command line using Invoke, which is great, so I don't have to
write make scripts and I don't have to deal with the Arduino IDE. So you can do that.
You can even build C projects with it if you really want to. Invoke is for everything,
basically. It's a tool that lets you build any variety of task-based workflows. It's
super awesome. It's not going to do anything for you. It's not going to make assumptions.
It'll do argument parsing and stuff, but it'll just give you the primitives to build whatever
you need to build. Cool? All right. That's a lot. I threw a lot at you real fast. Showing
you three tools that I like to use, but let's wrap it up. I like to think of these tools
as a gradient of sorts. On one end, you have really opinionated, focused tools like Tox.
Towards the middle, but still not really, you have less opinionated and more flexible
tools like Knox. And then towards the very other end, you have really, really flexible
tools that don't really make a lot of decisions for you like Invoke. So hopefully these have
inspired you to go and reduce some toil in your life. Hopefully one of these tools is
useful to you in your day-to-day life. If not, I'm sorry. I don't know how to make you
happy in that case. Finally, thank you for coming to my talk. If you would like to learn
more about these tools, please go check them out on GitHub. If you'd like to learn more
about me or ask me questions about these tools or how I use them or talk to me about synthesizers
or whatever, you can get in touch with me. You can go to my website. You can stalk me
on Twitter. That's cool too. But thank you.