Hello, Pythonistas.
This is a welcome to the last session of the day.
Here is Kushal Das.
He's going to talk today about building reproducible Python
application for secure dev environments.
So the stage is yours, Kushal.
Thank you.
Hello.
Can you hear me?
Well, OK.
Before I start talking, I want to give a shout out
to my friends at Chicago Python User Group.
Hi, all my friends there.
And let's start.
Before anything else, a little bit about myself.
I'm a public interest technologist
with a small nonprofit called Freedom of the Press
Foundation, where we try to protect, defend, and empower
public interest journalism.
So we mostly work with different kind of media orgs.
We do digital security training.
We write software.
We help them to make their security better.
I'm also heavily involved with various other nonprofits
and open slash free software projects.
One of them is something we all know here,
Python Software Foundation.
I'm a director at Python Software Foundation,
also a co-developer of the CPython, the programming
language itself.
And I'm also a core member of another nonprofit slash project
known as Tor, where we try to make sure
that our human rights can get defended
and we can maintain our privacy.
So I'm going to start the actual materials of the talk now.
So I'm going to guess that many of us
are here, Python developers.
But you're going to learn about one thing,
that this whole talk, we're not going
to talk about anything new tools or new systems.
We're going to make sure that we're
going to reuse whatever is already available to us
from the community.
So a very simple Python application.
I'm going to just use it as an example.
And as developers, we always think it works on my laptop.
And job done.
But as we know that organizations and companies
do not work in the same way.
So for the same Python application,
we may run it on one server.
We may execute slash run it on different servers,
or this magical thing also known as Cloud.
There are different ways these applications get
into this server slash computer slash cloud.
One of the easiest step is to use the source code management
system itself.
I'm going to mention git, because that's
one of the most highest used these days commonly.
Then if you're on a Debian slash Ubuntu world,
you may want to use .deb, Debian packages.
If you are coming from a Fedora slash CentOS slash Red Hat
world, you may want to use RPM to deploy
your final application.
At this moment, many of you must be
thinking that there is another way of deploying
in the modern world.
Sadly, this is not the right talk for the.
I'm going to talk mostly related to things on the Python world.
A little bit about the actual project.
So I'm a maintainer for a project known
as SecureDrop, which is an open source whistleblower platform.
It means anyone can securely and privately leak information
to different media orgs so that they don't get caught by,
let's say, their respective governments or any three
or four letter government agencies.
SecureDrop is deployed over 75 media orgs,
including New York Times, Washington Post, Guardian,
Intercept, and various other orgs.
So this is what the sources see when they go and try
to leak any information over to our browser.
The journalists in those organizations,
they have to get into a locked room inside their org
and boot a Tails operating system based laptop where
they will see something like this.
You can think like this as an inbox, correct,
where you can see different random names, where
you can click and download any of the material or messages.
But the part of the story is these all documents
are encrypted with a key, which is not
available on the same laptop, which
is there in a second computer, which is air gapped.
Means now the journalist has to somehow take those documents
using either a USB key or write once CD-ROM slash DVD drive
and then bring it to the next computer
and decrypt those files and then view the documents.
And this whole process is kind of taking time.
It takes almost like 40 to 45 minutes for every journalist
to go through the documents.
They want to view.
So it brings up a question between security
and usability.
In our case, the nature of the kind of post or project
secure drop works.
Nation state actors are always a pretty good advisories
for this project.
So we have to choose between two.
And in this particular case, we should always
try to get some help from professionals.
Luckily for secure drop project, we
got someone named Nina who really helped
us to build the next steps.
And we have something like this, which
is in the alpha level, which is a desktop application
for the journalist.
And from the look and view, you can understand
it's just another normal application.
But that's get deployed on a special operating
system known as cubes.
Cubes-os.org is the website.
Cubes is a reasonably secure operating system
which uses Fedora slash Zen to build up such a system where
each and every application may run in different VMs.
And within the same laptop or desktop,
you can actually have air gap VMs where you can store
your private keys and details.
So this really brings in both worlds a little bit nearby,
the security and usability.
And that's the future we're looking at.
And we particularly deploy this application
in using Debian packages.
So for the rest of the talk, when
I will say Debian packages or Debian,
that means a Debian VM inside of Cubes-os in a computer.
Now the question is, what all things can go wrong security
wise?
I'm sure all of you have different ideas
and different stories.
I'm going to take a few of those which recently came in my mind
to share with all of you.
A few months ago, Asus figured out
that their signing keys were taken over by some attackers,
and they managed to sign some malware
and pushed across to multiple millions of people's computer,
I guess.
There is another example in another programming language
where is a really important used library got malware.
And in our Python world, if we see,
last year in 2018, there were some tries
to put in malwares using some typosquatting,
where people wrote a project which is almost similar name
of a known project.
And they tried to put in some malware, which in turn
tried to steal Bitcoin wallet addresses and details.
Those are the three examples I put in here.
But this is not the end of our attack sites.
A few years ago, this particular gentleman, Mr. Edward Snowden,
also talked about a document, iHuntSysAdmins.
That particular document is about few,
let's say, three letter government agency folks,
who loves to visit different conferences.
And at the same time, try to find sysadmins
to various infrastructure and get their credentials,
so that in turn, they can own those infrastructure
and figure out and decide whom to kill next, part
of the mission.
I don't know to make you paranoid,
but it might so happen that such people may be sitting just
beside you or behind you.
The threats.
So all the points I mentioned one after,
we can summarize them into four simple points.
The source can contain malware.
Let's say that someone got access to the developer's
laptop and changed some code which developer never noticed
of our dependencies.
Or the source is totally changed.
Binaries can be replaced with malware.
If the address is not there, the source
can be replaced with malware.
If the adversary is powerful, they
can do man in the middle attacks while you are downloading
the source of binary.
The storage of the web server, or in case,
let's say, the whole infrastructure
can be compromised.
Correct?
And we all know some stories about these things.
So we're going to see how we can mitigate these issues.
The simplest solution to that starts with one point.
One point, review your dependencies.
It's important.
I'm going to get into that more.
So as I said, we are a Python project.
We use PPNB a lot.
So PPNB can help us, or P-Pen, whichever
way you want to pronounce, P-Pen helps
us to create a requirements.txt, which
will look something like this, where
we mention the project or slash dependency name and the version.
But we do not want to use this.
Instead, we want to use something like this.
Sorry for the size thing, because it will not
fit in one line.
So it's basically the project name, the version number,
and a SAR256 sum of a binary wheel.
Wheels are the binary package built from the source
ter evolves.
In our case, we want to make sure
that we can use only the wheels which are built by us.
That's the end goal part of it.
Now, to do so, as I mentioned in the beginning,
we never created a new tool.
Instead, we have a make file.
You can understand long-time Linux users,
and also a few bash slash Python scripts,
which help us to create all of this.
One of the steps there is called build-wheels.
And wheels.
This is the step.
You can see that it has four different commands,
different scripts it's actually running.
The last script just creates a URL
of all the ter evolves and the source,
sorry, binary wheels we created.
The first script, verify hyphen SAR256 sum hyphen signature,
that verifies that it exactly matches with our signatures
or not.
And the build and sync wheels, now we
are going to go in depth to see what we do there.
So we also have a separate file known as pfile.lock.
It has the source hasses and all the recursive dependencies.
So what we do is that we create a temporary requirements.txt
with only source ter evolve hasses.
And then in our script, we execute this pip3 command,
which only downloads the source ter evolves.
You can see that we are telling it,
do not download any binary wheels.
Get me all the source ter evolves.
And then we re-verify that.
And because we are passing hyphen hyphen require hyphen hasses,
it re-verifies that all the hasses match.
Then another pip3 command helps us to build this into wheels.
These are standard commands from pip.
And we rebuild all of those ter evolves into wheels now.
At this moment, because we have freshly built wheels
on the system, we can now create this requirements.txt file,
which has the SAR256 sums of the wheels which we built.
And the maintainer of the Python project, that is us,
we can create a source ter evolve of our own,
setup.py sdist.
This will have a requirements.txt
with our own wheel signature.
At this moment, many of you may have the question,
we never check the dependency source code, correct?
We just happily assumed whatever came from pip is valid.
So to actually rectify this step, we have a rule.
And to follow on the rule, we use a tool called diffoscope,
which helps us to create a diff between two
different ter evolves.
And then at least two human beings, two developers,
manually go through the diff of the whole change
to verify that this particular source code ter evolve doesn't
have any malware or any code which
is connecting to random sockets on internet
or tries to download code or, let's say,
doesn't have base64 encoded lot of data,
which is not supposed to have.
So we verify all these steps and then only
allow any changes in the updates or the dependencies
for each and every dependency.
And we actually stored those dependencies
in a file called Sa256sums.txt.
You can imagine from the name that it's just
names of all ter evolves and wheels.
At the same time, the Sa256sums.
And then we sign it with our keys,
which are not on the system.
All are always either on air gap computers or on hardware
tokens.
And we keep the same file, signed file,
there so that anyone can verify.
And our tools verify the same couple of times.
At this moment, we have our source ter evolves.
We have the wheels.
Now we have to make sure that we can consume those wheels.
There are different amazing technologies.
But luckily for us, in Python world,
we can just use a simple old technology also
known as HTML files.
We can create some index.html files,
which can enable us to create a private repository,
or says our own repository, which
will provide the source ter evolves and binary wheels.
And PIP will work.
If you want to know more, later at home,
you can search about this PIP 503.
This has all things in details.
Here are two examples.
This is the index, top index page.
You can see it has just links to different projects.
And if you go into any of the projects,
it will have URLs to each ter ball and the wheel file.
Static files, which we can verify, commit to GitHub,
and deploy anywhere we want.
Static files, correct?
Up to this, we managed to get source code.
We managed to build them into wheels.
Now let's talk about deploying the actual application.
How do you want to do this?
You can raise your hand about how many of us
already saw this before in life or did this.
And we can always say that this is dangerous,
because a Python dependency will change things into your system
Python libraries.
And this may go very bad or sad at the same time.
So for a remedy, we know about virtual environment, correct?
We use it to develop our applications.
What about just packaging the whole virtual environment
instead?
And then we figured out in the last PyCon
that we are not the only people who are thinking about this.
And Donald Stubb actually pointed us
to a project named dh-virtualenv,
which is coming from Spotify, an open source project which
modifies and adds some extra layers on top of Debian
packaging so that you can install, build, and package
a whole virtualenv for your Python application.
In that way, you can actually now control all the Python
dependencies of your application.
And you can install it easily in a virtualenv,
and you can still package it automatically.
Here is an example of the rules files.
There is too much of text, but if I just
try to click this line, you can see
that we are saying we are using Python 3.5, setup.tools.
And the index, this is the index we use at SecureDrop.
So you can actually open it up in your computer later on
and find it out.
And you'll also find that this particular Mac file
has four separate commands at the end, a couple of finds
So using those things, we try to achieve the next level,
that is reproducible builds.
This is actually enabled from Debian stretch
onwards, all Debian versions, where
it will help us or anyone else to be
able to produce the exact same artifact from the exact same
source code.
So it doesn't matter if I'm building the Debian package
today in my laptop or in our production system
or if I'm building it in my laptop or in our production
system, or if tomorrow you want to try to build
the same package again, we will get the exact same final output.
All of these things together help
us to create a secure, usable, reproducible builds.
The things it has are authenticity.
You can actually check who made those builds.
Those are signed with our keys.
You can have auditability.
You can have reproducibility to have
exact same build and outcome that whatever
software you are installing for your secured environment
are exactly what it's supposed to be, not anything fancy.
Now, these steps together can help
us to mitigate those threats we started from.
The first threat, source contains malware.
So this is the step where we do the human review
to make sure that the source tarball is what it should be.
And then we store and sign the SAR256 sums with GPG keys.
Now, that also helps us because we also
store the SAR256 sums of the binary wheels.
That means binary cannot be replaced.
And throughout our build process,
there are many places where we double check or triple
check the same keys and the values of the SAR256 sums.
Man in the middle attack, it's taken
care by two different things.
Again, HTTPS, which is the standard thing everyone
should now use, plus the SAR256 sums,
so that the final thing which comes down to a computer,
and Debian packages also, they make sure
that it's the exact same thing.
Because none of the signing keys are there on a network
connected box anywhere, we also make sure
that just in case our infrastructure
slash web application slash web server gets compromised,
that no one will get access to those keys,
that they can replace the actual any of those signed files.
This is the way, correct?
One can try to push a new malware or new source
into our system.
And on top of it, using the reproducible builds guidelines,
we managed to create the reproducible builds, which
at the end give us a certain amount of secured idea,
where we can really say that these reproducible builds
helps us to verify what we are finally running.
And I can tell you one thing honestly,
that it sounds a lot of steps, but it's not.
But even before this talk today at PyCon, for the last few days,
I was showing the slides and the ideas
to various other people in this conference, who actually
are much more better experts than me on this.
And all of us actually agreed that this step looks much more
centered to make sure that we can reduce those threats.
Here are a few links.
Freedom.press is the website of our organization.
Securedrop.org is the primary website for Securedrop project.
Those URLs, where you can find those scripts and all
the other scripts slash make file.
And it also contains the update policy on us.
And because this is available only for Debian,
I wrote a similar thing for RPM packages,
just in case any one of you want to deploy
the similar thing for RPM-based operating systems,
say Fedora CentOS REL, you can use the same thing.
Thank you.
I'll be open up for questions now.
[?
Applause. ?]
Any questions, anyone?
Yep, here.
I'll repeat.
I can repeat.
You tell me.
Have you ever heard about the NICs package manager?
Because didn't he incorporate some of these verification
process and it's not a part of the OPM?
Yes, we know about NICs.
But the idea is that because we are so much depend already
into the whole idea of using Debian slash Ubuntu-based
systems, and the kind of small team we have,
we cannot make a lot of changes at the same time.
So the idea was like, let's try to do what we can do or achieve
within staying the same operating system level where
we are, and something which just works out of the box.
That's why we chose to add all of this inside the Debian
package we installed.
Any other questions, anything?
Yes.
Hi.
So first, [? cure drop. ?] I'm curious as to what went
into the decision to set it up the way that you did,
as opposed to considering things like a blockchain
or trusted execution environments.
OK, number one point, I'm not a blockchain expert at all,
number one.
Number two, our idea was, again, as I said,
we want to use the tools and technologies already
available to us, which is being consumed all
across the Python environments.
And as I said, we found this is the most common thing
which we can use.
And there are a few times where people came and told,
I know me personally, that, oh, you
can use blockchain to solve all your security problems.
And my general answer to them is,
why don't you come back with a PR?
So I don't know anything about blockchain
other than it's a database, some sort of.
Sorry, that's my answer.
Next question, please.
You have, you're hosting your own PyPI server.
So you're building a virtual environment
and you're packaging that up.
So the end user is receiving a Debian package,
but they're not actually from installing that,
interacting direct with that PyPI server.
Is that correct?
Correct.
So the virtual end already has all things installed.
Your PyPI server is just internal at this point, right?
Are you exposing that as well, such that people can,
for transparency purposes?
Yes.
So this is the URL of the server which we are using now,
dev-bin.ops.secure-drub.org.
And any one of you can actually open that URL,
slash simple, I mean, that URL.
So it's public, but it's only used
while building the Debian package instead of end users.
So end users just use the Debian package, which is already
ready for consumption.
But everything is public because the idea is
you should not have to trust us or what you get from internet.
You are supposed to be able to verify and audit
what you are using.
Yeah.
Yep.
And then just one more quick question.
You're doing PGP encryption on the text file containing
all of your checksums.
Was there kind of a process where
you experimented with signing the tarballs
or signing different portions of it,
such that putting all the checksums into a text file
and signing that was the most efficient or simple?
Yes, because we stored that file inside our Git repository.
And we trust the standard HTTPS thing we are doing.
And instead of trying to reintroduce or redevelop
anything new, and because we trust also our GPG as a tool
for the whole project, we just go with GPG.
Thank you.
Next.
OK.
So great talk.
Thank you.
So I just wanted to give a suggestion
that there's a tool called FPM that you
can use to specify the type of package that you want.
And when you run it in any folder,
it packages up the whole thing into an RPM or a DEP
or whatever you want.
So we at work, we basically do the same thing that you do.
But instead of using different tools for different types,
we just use FPM that gives you a lot of flexibility.
Thanks for the suggestion.
That's an open source tool, so you can check it out.
Yeah, I mean, I am coming from a Fedora packaging background.
I spend my life with the Fedora project.
And I also package things for Debian and Ubuntu
in a different capacity.
My personal finding as a packager,
I found having separate package builds for every system
works really well.
Next question, this side.
So when you're making your builds for Debian,
do you have a separate process to make the builds for Ubuntu?
Because I use a DH virtual env to create builds for Ubuntu,
and they never work on Debian.
Or I can create them on Debian, and then
they don't work on Ubuntu.
Have you run into that?
Or are you trying to support both?
So the idea is that you make sure
that your build environment matches
with what you are running in.
So if you are running, say, building for Debian 9 stretch
and latest Ubuntu, whatever version number,
you have to build two separate packages,
because they will not be compatible with each other.
And if they contain ASO files, that is, like, binaries,
it will not work, basically.
So that's the way to work.
Thanks.
Hi, thank you for the talk.
I've noticed that you consume from PyPI on the source packages
intentionally, which means that in your Debian build
depends who will be required to provide
all of the build dependencies of all the PIP packages
that you have, all of the C extension packages
that you have.
Has it been a problem in any way?
Was it a concern?
Did you have to have a build depends
of the C extension packages that you consume from PyPI
to be in your build depends list?
The question is, did you get into any kind of trouble
while building any kind of C extensions?
Till now, no, because the biggest C-based thing,
we have two.
One is cryptography.
And I think PyML also has now C extension.
And no, so I think we required only one of the dependencies
which we added as a build requires for the package.
Make sure that it exists.
Thank you.
For DiffaScope, have you found anything interesting
while reviewing all those changes?
And a second question, in reviewing all of those changes
in your dependencies, do you run into review fatigue?
And how do you deal with that?
Correct, so the question is about DiffaScope.
Have we noticed anything special?
No, it's just that a long set of text one has to go through,
which creates the problem.
And we're talking to more and more projects, less people.
We found that many other companies also
do the same internally.
So one of the things I'm planning to work on,
maybe just after sprints or during sprint,
is we'll try to create a way where different projects,
less people whom we can trust can publish this information.
Right now at SecureDrop, we are publishing it in our GitHub.
So github.com slash freedom of the press.
In the Debian packaging, the actual repo,
I am signing the whole change with my GPG keys
and putting it up in the wiki, which is not working right now
here, network.
But yeah, it's going to create a lot of pressure.
But the more people I talk to, everyone
says manually reviewing the source code
is the only way to make sure that the source is clean.
So we have to find out a way as a community
so that we can actually start trusting it more.
Thank you.
OK, I guess no more questions.