So, for example, I work with your class, I guess, that are able to participate in the
class. Okay, I think it is 1.20 now. Can everybody hear me okay? I'm okay on the mic. Awesome.
Housekeeping type stuff, basically this is the 2D platformer tutorial, so if you were
looking for a different tutorial now is a good time to go find that. The survey link
for this tutorial is up there. I will try to also show it near the end if you're the
type of person who likes to give your opinion after you actually watch the tutorial or you
can jot it down now. Most important, the snack break is from 3 to 3.20 by what I've got up
here and help us watch the clock because I'm told if we don't get out right at 3.20, all
the good snacks are gone and we don't want that to happen. Please do share outlets as
well as there are only some outlets here and not everybody's computer can run the three
hours that we've got. In order to get started, a lot of this is online. In fact, there's
some stuff that you hopefully will want to download for this and if you go to that website,
arcade.academy, there's a platformer tutorial link if you haven't already been there and
that has all the notes for the presentation that I'm giving today, so if you would please
go there now, that would be great. Okay, how are we doing? Anybody who need more time?
Everybody got that link? Arcade.academy and then once you are there, you should be able
to see underneath the example code, there is a platformer tutorial right here. You can
see the link to the platformer tutorial. You can see the link to the platformer tutorial
right here. See underneath the example code, there is a platformer tutorial right here.
That link is the one that we want, so click on that link and then that should take you
here. Okay, so that's the platformer tutorial. Now, if you have any questions, please feel
free to ask them. Okay, anybody need help finding this? And for the people that just
came in, arcade.academy, if you go to arcade.academy, there is a platformer tutorial that has the
example code and the download links on it. Okay, this particular tutorial I'm going to
work to make sure that everybody can get wired up a 2D platformer game using Python in the
arcade library. The tutorial I've got divided up into multiple parts here into a total of
nine different steps and each one of these steps at the end of it has a blue note to
it and down here like at the end. This note, basically if you're the, you're the developer
if you happen to get ahead or working a little bit ahead and you want to do further exploration,
this has a lot of sideways areas that you can go in order to learn more, but I want
to make sure that everybody gets at least through the core part and once you've gotten
through the core part, if there's extra time, take a look and explore some of those different
areas or you can work ahead too if you so desire. Our first step here that we're looking
to do is basically make sure that you've got the library installed that you end up
needing and also that you've got the downloads, the supporting image files as well to get
this up and going and a basic window open on your screen. So the first step, I'm hoping
that basically I'm looking for Python 3.6 or greater to be installed. You can, I got
the download link there although I'm guessing here at a Python conference, hopefully most
of you have Python installed, but I do need 3.6 or greater in order to get this to work.
There's also a zip file with code, images and sounds from this presentation. If you
click on that and download it, you should be able to expand your library and get a lot
of that and download it. You should be able to expand it into a zip file that will look
close to like that directory structure that I've got there on the screen. And the images
are from Kenny.NL. He's got a whole lot of really cool images available for doing 2D
games that are license free and it's pretty cool if you want to check out that stuff.
Anyway, so the basic directory structure should look like that once you get it downloaded.
And then you need the arcade library, 204 or greater. Everybody has different ways they
like to manage libraries, but for most people you should be able to type in pip install
arcade on the command prompt or you might need pip 3 install arcade in order to download
it. I've got longer instruction, official installation instructions there. Once you
have it downloaded, you should be able to open up a window with the code that you have
in the code that we've got up here. This particular code, the primary thing to note
here is we are creating our own subclass of the arcade.window class and we will basically
override functions that are part of the window class in order to add additional functionality.
There's not much functionality going on right now, but we want to make sure that we at least
get everything downloaded and installed and can get a window to pop up on the screen.
We're setting the background color right here. There are a lot of pre-programmed background
colors and you can take a look at the blue note at the end so you can actually click
on the documentation for this and see what all the different colors are that are available.
The CSS colors basically mirror the standard CSS colors you would get for Cascading Style
Sheet on the web. Then there's another package with a bit more color in it called the color
package. Right, at this point basically then, if you have extra time, play around with changing
the screen size, the title, and the background color. I'd like to pause here and then try
to make sure that we get everybody up and going to have the libraries installed and
up and working. There are some scattered Post-it notes around if you would like additional
help, if you want to put the red Post-it note or something on your computer or otherwise
just raise your hand. Then I want to wander around trying to make sure everybody's up
and going at this spot. Any general questions? All right, have at it and we'll go from there.
Okay, thank you.
All right, how are you doing? Who has yet not worked on the party yet?
Okay.
Okay, I'm going to look. I'm going to go from here and hit towards the next step. The next
goal is to, can you hear me okay? Okay. The next goal is to add in sprites and the sprite
is any sort of interactable object on the screen. The whole history behind that terminology
is kind of cool but anyway that's time for like a totally different talk. So we want
to get the graphics loaded and on the screen. We'll get the interaction going on later.
The aspect of putting this on and getting the setup, normally it is a better practice
to not actually create the sprites in your init method of your window class but actually
in a separate method. The reason being if you want to restart your game, you can easily
just recall the setup method to recreate all the sprites and set up your game. It also
makes it easy if you want to add multiple levels then basically you have a setup level
one, setup level two and so forth. Therefore we're going to end up creating the variables
basically in the init method and just set them to blank, zero or none and then actually
initialize them and set them up in a setup function.
The main way of creating a sprite for your game is up there on the screen right there
where I've got the player sprite being created. We end up using the arcade sprite class and
the use of it is really straightforward. You just need a reference to the image that you
end up wanting. In the case of the package that we've downloaded, everything is in the
images folder. I like to keep things separated out and there's a player one sub folder and
there's a player one standing. If you don't like this particular player, there's a few
other images that you could quickly swap out in that folder as well.
Character scaling is simply a constant number. It's optional. By default the sprite if it's
128 by 128 will appear as 128 by 128 on your screen. You can scale that up and down by
giving it a number there in character scaling. If the image is too large, you can simply
do a 0.5 and that will take 128 by 128 and actually scale it down so that it's 64 by
64. The 0.5 is what percentage of the width and height, not total percentage area of the
player sprite. Anyway, this creates a sprite. You won't see it yet because we'll have to
draw it but this will actually create the instance of the sprite. Next up we have to
position the sprite. Sprites have attributes for center X and center Y. These are the most
common attributes to use to position it. You just set them equal to whatever you want.
There are also attributes for top left bottom and right if you want to control the sprite
based on the top bottom left or right edge instead which can be rather handy at times.
You can set both X and Y using the position attribute if you want. That right there will
actually move a sprite to exactly 64 and 120 for an XY location. Once we've got the sprite
created, we've got it positioned, the next thing we need to do is add it to a list. All
sprites are managed by lists. This makes drawing them a lot easier. It makes also managing
and updating them a lot easier. To do that, I'll show you how to create a sprite list
in a bit but we simply append it to the sprite list that we've got. The code, in order to
actually do this, is right here. I've highlighted the important parts. I've created scaling
factors. In this case, my tiles that I've got are going to be scaled down by 25% actually
but half the width and half the height of the original sprite. The character will be
its original height. If you do much scaling, it is advisable to make sure that everything
is evenly divisible. You don't want to scale a sprite that's 35 by 35 down by half because
the pixels don't line up straight on pixel boundaries and then you end up getting blurring.
It's a good idea to try to keep everything evenly divisible when you put this together.
Next up in the init, I've got the lists themselves that I'm going to end up working with and
the player sprite that I have individually pulled out because the player sprite needs
to be moved so we're going to work with it individually. We're going to have a list for
walls, basically anything that the player can't walk through. We're going to have a
list that's going to have just the player in it. It's not much of a list. We're going
to have a coin list, basically anything you want the user to actually pick up along the
way. We'll end up adding that in here in a bit. We're just going to initialize those
to none and then down in a setup function, we're actually going to create the entire
level. So lines 39 through 43 create the sprite lists. It's pretty straightforward. All you
need to do is a constructor on sprite list and that will set your sprite list up and
get it ready so that you can add sprites to it. Then we're going to create the sprites.
There are basically three main ways that you can easily create and position sprites. The
first way I've got up there from lines 45 to 49. If you look from 45 to 49, I've got
the standard four lines of code where the first line I create the sprite. Next two lines,
I position the sprite. Fourth line, I end up appending it to the list. That's one way
of creating a sprite that's pretty darn straightforward. Another way of creating sprites, a whole set
of them is from lines 51 to 57. You can easily create these sprites in a loop. I've just
simply used a for loop here. I'm going to set the X value going from 0 to 1250 and every
64 pixels because my sprite's actually 64 by 64 once I scale it. Every 64 pixels, I'm
going to put in a sprite and I simply set the loop up that way, which is a whole lot
more convenient than simply doing four lines for every single sprite you want if you want
to create a border. That will give you the basically bottom row of blocks that I've
got for the example that I'm showing. The third and final way I'll show you right now
on creating sprites is to actually list a set of coordinates and then add the sprites.
Rather than four lines for each sprite that I create, I can do it in one line per sprite
with a little bit of additional overhead. Line 61 through 63, I'm going to create sprites
at those XY locations, so 512 and 96, 256 and 96, and 768 and 96. No idea why those
aren't in numerical order, but I never noticed it before now. Then I'm just going to do a
for loop and I'm going to create the sprites and then I'm going to pull the individual
coordinates out of that coordinate list and simply add them. Those are three main ways
of creating sprites. Once you've created the sprite, it does not automatically appear.
We actually need to draw the sprites. There's an onDraw method inside of your code that
we want to go through all of the different sprite lists and draw it. The ordering does
matter so the first sprites that you draw will appear behind everything else. The last
sprite you draw will end up appearing on top of whatever you've drawn before. Keep in mind
the ordering on that if that particular what sprite appears in front is important. That
should give you basically that window that we've got up here for the graphics. Way up
here. There we go. You shouldn't be able to move yet, which will be the next step. If
you've got extra time, I would spend a little bit of extra time adjusting the code, put
sprites in new positions, search through those images folder and see what you can find and
practice placing those sprites in different locations. Then I'm just going to go around
and make sure everybody's up and running for this point.
I'm going to go ahead and open that up.
If you install Homebrew, that's with Pygame?
Yeah, mine was with the downloaded version when I tested out and that's supposed to
work. Is yours installed Homebrew or is it?
Yes.
For that reason, I don't think the 60 Otherwise, if you have a smaller
system, you actually have a larger display than the 140 it's also relatively large
than those and it doesn't help with the Saud самой files that will just make
Is yours is yours installed home brew or is it?
Okay, next up I'm going to talk about adding user control and if we want to move a sprite
around we end up needing to progressively change its center x and center y values. We
can do this but we need to not only keep track of where the sprite is, we need to keep track
of a vector of where it's going. In addition to the center x, center y if we keep a change
x and change y this is how many pixels are we going to move per frame for our particular
character. If change x is one then 60 times per second we should move one pixel over
and that will cause our character to move to the right. If change x is negative it will
move to the left. With graphic systems, some graphic systems flip the y value, don't know
if you've run into this before but in this particular library zero is at the bottom for
y and whatever your screen height is is at the top. PyGame actually works opposite of
that if you've used PyGame but this is sort of more of a standard OpenGL and the graphics
coordinate system that you actually learned in math class type of thing. So zero zero
is in the lower left corner, a positive value for change y will move you up rather than
down. There's an update function and you can call that on a sprite list which will
actually move the sprites according to their change x and change y and eventually we will
factor in a extremely simple physics engine class which will just keep you from moving
through walls. And the additional code that we need for that, I've got a constant here
that I've declared on line 17 for the player movement speed. So if you want your sprite
to move faster just make that a larger number, if you want it to move slower just make that
a smaller number. The next set of code that I've added in, I've created a very simple
physics engine and it takes two parameters. It takes the item that is moving which in
this case will be our player sprite and then it takes the list of things that you can't
move through which will be the wall list in this case. If you want to move other items
like enemies or that type of thing then you can create physics engines for them as well,
you're not limited to that. So if you want to move a lot of things you can create physics
engines for them as well, you're not limited to one simple physics engine, you can have
one for each item that's actually moving. This simple physics engine will actually update
the player's location and prevent the player from moving through walls. So we put that
inside of the setup function here. Then we need to respond to keystrokes if the player
is moving by the keyboard and in this case there are two events for the keystroke. If
you're not used to working with game type of work you might think of hitting the key
as one event but there are actually two events. One is when you press the key down, the other
event is when you let the key up. This will basically change our changeX and changeY depending
upon what key you hit. The up, down, left and right correspond to the arrow keys on
the keyboard and the WSAD respond to those characters just depending upon which you prefer
to move your item around. This will actually work with both and when you let up the key
then it will actually set the player's velocity back to zero. Then we've got an update method,
this will be called about 60 times per second and it will then update via the physics engine
which will cause our player to actually move around. Delta time if you want to take it
into account is the time that it took since the last time we actually called this function.
It should be about 1-60th of a second by default but you can actually then adjust how fast
the player moves if you want. If there's a system slowdown then the player can actually
keep moving at the normal speed if you want to take into account delta time. In this case
we don't and most of the time we're pretty reliably being called every 1-60th of a second.
So with that you should be able to move the player around the keyboard or around the map
and you should be able to not run through boxes. If you're coming from a computer
you should be able to not run through boxes. If you're curious there's a better move by
keyboard example which is a little bit more complex but responds to the keystrokes better
than the simple example that I've got up there right now. So work if you could at making
sure that your character moves around by keyboard and give me a shout if it's not moving around.
So that's the first one. So the game is going to be a lot of fun. And then the title after
the start is not going to be accurate. The higher the level the more accurate the game
will be. So that's the first one. And then the second one is the last one. And then the
third one is the last one. So that's the fourth one. And then the fifth one is the last one.
So that's the fifth one.
Okay.
Okay. Next up is a really fairly simple addition. Adding in gravity. If you are working with
a top down map where the player can basically scroll all around then you don't want to
add in gravity but if you're working with a side view scroller then adding in gravity
is basically the next step for that. And I've added two more constants on this. I've added
the gravity constant which is how fast your character is going to accelerate down and
a jump speed which is whenever you jump how fast is it going to move up. You can play
around with these. If you've got low numbers your character will be very floaty. If you've
got fast character or if you've got pretty high values then your character will jump
up and down really pretty quick. It's a nice one to explore around with to see if you get
the mechanics that you end up liking. Once you've got that then instead of the simple
physics engine we're going to end up using the physics engine platformer which will allow
you to add in the gravity constant. And there on line 82 I've added gravity and on line
80 I've actually switched from simple physics engine to the physics engine platformer. And
you can also create multiple ones of these if you've got enemies in your platformer game
that you want to move around. Next up taking a look at the on key press. The important
part here in particular is on line 99. Line 99 there's a check in the physics engine to
see if there's actually ground underneath the player. If there's not ground underneath
the player we don't allow the player to jump. You can modify this and work with it a little
bit to allow double jumps if you wanted but this particular update is necessary otherwise
then you've got more of a flappy bird game where you can just keep hitting the button
and float around. And then on key release we do not set the player's Y speed to zero
when they let up off of the jump because then that just won't work at all. We actually end
up taking that out. And that is basically all that's involved in putting in gravity.
And if you play around with the numbers on that then you can get it to be floaty or not
floaty. So work a little bit with the gravity, play around with the numbers and let me know
if you've got questions.
So yeah, go to the program and you need your editor to edit programs. And then you have
to go to the program and you need your editor to edit programs.
I'm going to get the issue on the right for you.
I think it's roughly one of the six that you're scanning out.
You need to keep it countered so that when you...
A pull request figuring out the...the problem with that though is you've got to be able
to...you could reset your double jump. You have to make sure you have some mechanism
that when you touch ground again you reset the double jump counter.
You'd have...anyway, it'd be totally doable but you'd have to think about it a little
bit.
Okay, anybody need some extra help for step four before we go on to step five?
Okay, step five is to add the ability to scroll. With step four, if you went off screen, you
just plain went off screen, you couldn't see what was going on. If you want a larger map,
if you want the thing to be able to scroll from side to side or up and down if you've
got a large 2D map, then the ability to add scrolling is rather important.
The new parts with adding scrolling. First off, we're going to set up margins so that
if the user gets close to the edge, the camera will scroll. This particular case, if the
user gets within 150 pixels of either the left or right edge, it will start scrolling.
You can up that or downgrade that depending upon how you like it. The bottom viewport
margin is 50 in this particular example, which works okay for platformers, although actually
50 is a little bit low. If you're up high and then you try jumping down, you won't really
be able to see what's down below you very well, so you might want that to be a bit higher.
Again, that's totally what you end up wanting. And the top viewport margin basically then
covers the top. We need to keep track of how far we've scrolled. In this case, I've
created two variables, view bottom and view left. This is basically the lower left corner
of your particular screen so that if I've got a huge map like this, whoa, that's a big
pen, hold on. So if I've got a really big map like this, and I am not drunk, honestly,
then you might have a screen that only shows this part. The view left and view bottom is
going to be what point is this? This would be zero, zero, and then this would be like
200, zero. I don't think turning off the mic helped there at all. Anyway, we want to be
able to scroll this smaller window around. View left and view bottom are going to be
your lower left corner of where that is. The next thing that we add in is this part,
which is inside of the update method, and this will actually manage our scrolling. First
off, I create a Boolean variable. I don't want to scroll if I don't need to scroll,
so I just set it to false. If anything that I encounter here leads me to need to scroll,
then I'll go ahead and do the scrolling. I just check the left boundary, the right boundary,
the top and bottom boundary. I take a look at where the player is. I see if they are
within whatever the boundary number is, like 150 pixels. If they are, then I need to figure
out how far do I need the player to move, which in this case would be like line 146.
It basically figures out if you're at 140 pixels and the boundary is 150, it's going
to figure out that you need to move 10 pixels over to the left. That will basically trigger
the actual scrolling, and then I'll set the changed value to true. Then if I actually
need to scroll on line 167, I will go ahead and do the scrolling. Line 170 and 171 are
rather important. You can actually set a viewport where you don't have the people line up on
individual pixels, but it looks terrible. The computer trying to figure out how to draw
a pixel at one and a half pixels, it sort of blurs it and tries to do its best guess.
We really want to make sure that every pixel on the window lines up with an actual pixel
on the screen. Therefore, in line 170 and 171, we go ahead and convert it to an integer.
Then the key command here, we set viewport. We set the left side of the screen. We set
the right side of the screen. We set the bottom, and we set the top. You can actually stretch
the screen out larger. You can compress the screen if you want, but this will keep the
screen according to the screen width and screen height dimensions in the particular
example we've got here, but it will allow us to scroll around the screen.
Most of the time when I end up doing games, this logic is pretty well left unchanged,
and all you end up needing to do is managing the viewport boundaries. This should allow
you to create a much larger world and scroll around in it for your particular game. If
you want to make sure that you've got that up and going and give me a shout, if you've
got any questions on getting it working, that would be great.
I'm going to go ahead and put that here and change the one on the right to 120. I corrected
it last time. Now it's 11. Yeah, it won't be back in the wallet.
It's basically the scaling of what's going on.
It looks like scrolling is a pretty easy addition. Anybody have extra questions or
need more time for scrolling?
You could still use it with basically viewport, like your viewport margins would be basically
huge. I have to think about how you could quickly do that. You would just keep the
character at that single spot, and then you'd need to just keep continually adjusting the
viewport.
Next up, basically jumping around is all great, but we want to end up adding some sort of
coins and sound to this for you to be able to pick up. You could do coins, gems, keys,
whatnot. In order to do that, basically we've got two things. We need to be able to figure
out how to work with sound. Number two, we need to figure out how to work with another
list and figure out when we've actually collided with a coin, because we're not going to let
the physics engine manage that for us.
The new parts. Lines 55 through 57 load in the coin. The new parts are the ones that
are going to be in a sound. Cross-platform sound is really hard in Python. It's one of
those things that I wish there was some magical solution for. The easiest way of getting this
working is with the WAV sounds, and then you don't have to worry about decoding OGG or
MP3 type of items.
For many platforms, particularly Windows, you can get it to work on the Mac, although
it's a little bit more difficult. The FFMPEG library will allow you to decode OGG and MP3
sound formats as well. For the sake of trying to make sure that this works, we're going
to just stick with WAV files. You need to load it here, and then once you've loaded
it, you can actually play it later on, which we'll hit here in a bit.
Next up, I've got another list. In this case, I'm going to create a coin list. All the coins
are going to go into the coin list. That allows me to keep them separate from the walls.
Then I need to place the coins. What I've got here on lines 99 through 104 is my coin
placement. You could adjust this, place the coins wherever you want, and that will get
you up and working with your particular coin placement. You could also end up subclassing.
You could create your own coin class and subclass the sprite class, and then easily add in another
parameter. You could have some coins that are worth 1 point, 5 points, 10 points, that
type of thing, to create some items that are more valuable than other items.
Then as far as the sound goes, I've added a play sound on line 128. Every time the player
jumps, I already have the trigger for that. Therefore, I can fairly easily add to that
trigger the ability to play the sound. I just use that same sound that I created up
above. Then the other one I end up working with is down here. I am playing the sound
on line 158 when I figure out that I've run into a coin. How do I end up figuring out
that I've run into a coin? There's a function on line 150. There's an arcade check for
collision with list. This allows me to take a particular sprite as the first parameter.
As the second parameter, I can take a list of sprites. It will then give me a list back
of every single sprite that I am actually in contact with. Most of the time, this will
be an empty list. You will still get a list back. It will simply be an empty list. Then
I can loop through each coin that I hit and process it. Therefore, I am doing that on
line 254. I've got my list of coins that I hit on line 50 in coin hit list. I loop through
each coin that I hit on line 154. Line 156 will actually remove it from all lists that
exist. It basically destroys that coin. Then I go ahead and play a sound. Later on, I've
got the comment in there. Later on, I will go ahead and add one to the score at this
point when I start tracking the score. Once you've done that, then you should have a game
where your player will actually... This should be Coins and Sound. I should be able to right-click
and run this. Any day now. Wake up. Right-click and run. I'm going to go ahead and add one
to the score. Once you get sound effects going in, your game is 100% better. Definitely.
There are some other sounds in there as well. I teach college class. The day I introduce
sound is one of my favorite days when I do that. Anyway, go ahead and play with some
of the other sounds. Play with the coin placement, the coin pickup. There are other things in
there. If you don't like picking up coins, you'd rather pick up gems or keys or whatnot.
You can play around with that and get your game put together the way you want it. Then
the next step we'll talk about is being able to display the score.
I'm going to go ahead and add one to the score.
Next up, talk about how to get something to actually move around the screen with you.
This is particularly useful if you want to display the score, how many lives a person
has left, if you want to keep a frame, any sort of stat that you want to actually have
move around with the player.
There are functions which I've got over here that basically, well now I can't get to it.
There's a draw text function which will draw text on the screen.
These two lines that I have here.
This particular, it's a little hard to see without me getting it bigger, but this particular
line says, arcade draw text, whatever text I want to display, tells me to draw it at
location 1010 on the screen in a white color with an 18 point font.
If I do that when I actually run the game, it works fine at the start, but then as I
move, the score actually scrolls with the rest of the screen instead of staying where
I want it.
It is a pretty easy fix in order to get anything to have a solid position on the screen.
In order to do that, switch back to the easier to read version, in order to do that, you
need to add in the viewport margin.
That's a key point here where I've got the location that I want the text to appear, an
X of 10, I then add in view left so that if I scroll to the left or right, it will adjust
that 10 based on it, and likewise here, I add in the view bottom so as I go up and down,
it will move the text and keep it at a relative location of 1010.
That will allow your score to basically scroll around with it.
The other important parts of this particular example, up here in setup, I set the score
equal to zero, then further on down, I display the score, and finally here, every time I
encounter a coin, I go ahead and add one to the score.
That allows me to do the score tracking.
There's a lot of other stuff that you can add for stats.
You could use the length of your coin list and display basically how many coins you have
left to pick up in a rather easy fashion.
There's the ability to keep an onscreen timer, which is a fairly popular thing that people
end up wanting to have.
You can also keep a frame per second counter if you want to keep track of how fast the
game is running.
There's just a fairly large host of different things that you can do with that particular
case.
Really, at this point, I'm kind of hoping to give you a bit of a more extended break
and talk about some of the other things that you could end up doing and playing around
with.
If you want to add a background image to your screen rather than having a solid color, I've
got an example that shows you how to do that.
If you'd like to have a platform that actually moves around from frame to frame, so a platform
that you can jump on, ride it up, ride it down, or across, then you can take a look
at the moving platform example.
If you'd like ramps, I've got another ramp example here.
The collision box for any particular sprite is the entire rectangle that the image takes
up, which can be problematic in several cases in that if you have something that's not a
rectangle, if you've got a sprite that has a lot of white space around it, you could
trim the sprite or you could set up a hit box that way.
The ramps example shows you how to do that.
This is, though, a lot easier if you use the Tiled Map Editor, which we'll show here eventually.
I'm kind of thinking maybe that'll be the after break one.
At any rate, the ramp, you can graphically then set up your hit box using the Tiled Map Editor.
If you would like to have your character face left or right, depending upon what direction
that they end up moving, that's a fairly easy add-on.
There's an example that shows you how to do that.
And adding in instruction in Game Over screens is a little bit more complex, but that enters
into a sort of state mechanic for your game so that your game is either showing an instruction
page, the game is over, or your game is actually running.
Anyway, you can rotate your game through multiple states that way.
My suggestion here is to get the text up and working and then take a look at some of the
different examples that are there.
You might also want to take a look at, if you actually go to Arcade Academy example
there's about 95 different code samples total, but the ones that are most interesting would be
the sprite area.
It shows you how to actually move the sprites.
So if you want the coins just not sitting there for you, but you want them to move around.
If you want the coins to bounce around, follow the player, that type of thing, then that shows you
how to do it, how to do levels, how to shoot things.
Anyway, there's quite a few different examples there that you can also take a look at and ask
questions about, and I would be more than happy to discuss with you on that.
So that's what's up next, alright?
I think on that one, if you go to where the player is, I think the player is on the lower
left.
You can add code, check the Y value if you want, and in fact later on in the example
I would probably do like a player one sprite.
So in this case you need to make sure that you have an auto-replacement.
So let's just go up to the view and the sprite area.
Okay.
All right.
As we get closer towards break time, basically after break time I would like to work with
the Tiled Map Editor which allows you to basically then paint your level.
And in order to do that basically we need to have downloaded the Tiled Map Editor.
And if you go down to the step eight for the Use Map Editor program, if before break or
during break if it takes a little extra time, if you go to the Tiled Map Editor and make
sure you have that installed right there, you should end up with a program that basically
Tiled Map Editor and you can download it up there.
Make sure you have that up and working on your particular pro on your computer.
And then the other thing is if you have eight examples instead of nine examples, I added
a ninth example later on, you might want to re-download files.
There's the ninth example and map files that go along with that that might be useful
to have as well.
So if you have eight examples you might want to re-download those image files in the example
code and get that last ninth example and have that ready by the end of break.
So the Tiled Map Editor and make sure you've got nine examples and you've got like about
seven minutes or so before break time starts and we don't want to miss out on snacks.
So make sure you've got plenty of time for that.
So that's it.
Thanks.
And as a time check it is 2.59.
We will reconvene with the Map Editor at 3.20.
So you might want to now take your break.
Thanks.
declined
Heh.
hasn't
Yawned
Yeah.
No.
Yawned
Well, for me it was kind of disappointing in that I did some pull requests and stuff but nothing was happening with PyGames.
And then it was very much a Python 2, I mean they didn't use new Python 3 things, which I get, there's a lot of backwards compatibility.
And then there's weird, just language things that I would have to explain to students.
Okay, here normally with lists you use a pin, but with PyGame you want to add it to PyGame list as an add.
And then all the students would like the image scaled down. There's no easy way to scale down the image there.
The list went on and on and finally I was like, I just start with something.
Yeah, and then I tried playing around because PyGames is backed by SDL1 library and there's now a 2, but even the 2 wasn't that great.
And I couldn't do basic drawing commands like draw a line with a width of greater than 1.
So that took some, and then basically I just was like, oh, why not just use OpenGL?
What I ideally would like out of a platform like this is to not, like one of PyGames' problems I think as you mentioned is that they're so focused on maintaining backwards compatibility
that they're afraid to do anything new where they don't want to accept it for it.
I would like for the opposite, I would like for at least over a major burden help or something like that to not be particularly worried about breaking backwards compatibility in favor of doing things like that.
That's generally how I work. The idea that somebody doesn't want to fix a bug is that they rely on that bug.
Especially in like a game room.
Yeah, I get both sides of it. For the education, if you're using this for education, just simple better naming conventions that are more consistent really help out a lot.
And then it's been nice with the type-hinting and some other items with the newer editors with students to allow them to catch errors that they wouldn't have easily otherwise caught.
And simple quality of life improvements like f-strings and stuff like that just make general Python variable better.
Python 3.6 at least is what I want to use at this point.
Yeah, the f-strings.
I'll try to use f-strings with Python 2.
The f-strings are big for me.
Okay.
Yeah.
I could see doing that just on a default basis.
I mean, you usually add a reset function in there.
I'm trying to think. What's the biggest hint normally goes with on Python? It's a huge number though.
Yeah.
So you're not going to overflow anytime soon.
Is it just held by a decimal? A decimal? Classes, I'm sorry.
The biggest one that I haven't really found an easy way that's a very common pattern is the scrolling.
But it would be, you still want to be able to control the camera somehow.
So yeah, that one, I think of the chunk of the most repeated code.
Yeah.
So the intention for a game just an educational rule or whatever?
I've seen some pretty decent 2D games made out of it by people.
I mean, just not advances of regular game engines, but I'd like to see it developed into a lot more potential, quite frankly.
Adding in the ability to do lights and a bit more on the whole shader aspect of things would be nice.
It's pretty quick, but it runs into problems in conversion between Python's floats and native floats that whole mapping.
If you take it over to the graphics card, that's a big time crunch that I would really like to figure out something better on.
Yeah, basically right now it uses numpy to do the native transfer over to the graphics card.
It's not fast moving numbers from a regular Python number to a numpy number.
I mean, one number is not bad, but if you're doing thousands, 60 times per second, then you start noticing the difference.
If you don't move them at all, then it's like super fast.
You can take a look at the history on it.
I picked up on a number of people doing bugs in Fork Web.
Yeah, it uses PyTest.
There's basically two folders of testing.
One's more mocked out.
The other one is a little bit more complete and actually using the OpenGL.
There's another one that's not actually a PyTest, but it just runs every bit of example code to make sure that the examples all work.
Yeah.
All right.
So if you have a jump speed of 15 and your gravity is one, it'll take 15 frames then to get to the top of the jump.
And then you can end up calculating how many pixels that would be.
I couldn't do that in my head on hand.
Actually, that wouldn't be too hard because then you just have to do it.
15 frames, you're traveling to 15 per second.
You just do 15 divided by two.
Now I have to switch into a better thinking mode.
But anyway, yeah, then you can calculate that for the top of your jump.
Yeah, then your speed goes to zero immediately.
It'll actually set that for you when you hit the top because otherwise it just looks wrong because you stick there.
Yes, then it also gets reset.
I don't think you're used.
I have to look again, but I don't think your speed changes at all.
And you just simply don't go through the item and just keeps resetting you back.
Okay, so keeping the time here.
Mike's working, right?
All right.
Mike is sliding off me.
Hold on.
Okay.
Please make sure you've got the tiled editor down and working.
And while we're just double checking, make sure that people have got that done and had enough time to make sure that's working.
Just as a bit of history, there are, as you may or may not know, several graphics libraries out there for use with Python.
The arcade library was actually sort of born out of, I taught using Pygame for quite a few years.
And eventually Pygame got to the point where it wasn't being updated.
Thankfully, that's not the case anymore.
It is being updated now on a more frequent basis.
But it was still very much a Python 2.
Didn't take advantage of the Python 3 items.
Used an old SDL library for the back end.
And this basically, after I taught with this and spent so much of the class working at trying to teach people the oddities of the Pygame library instead of programming,
I wanted a library where I didn't have to do that and it used the new type hinting features and allowed OpenGL use for some faster graphics and eventually some more advanced support.
So that's kind of where the arcade library ended up coming from.
So did anybody have issues getting tiled, the program to work?
Everybody got that set up?
Okay.
Tiled itself is not the most intuitive to get started, but once you're started, it isn't too bad.
So to begin with, you'll probably need to create a new file.
I'll go ahead and close this one.
And you can either open a file that's already there or you can create a new file.
So I'm going to create a new map here and then to actually expand that out and make it easier to read, I'll bring up the website.
And you need these particular settings in order for the map file to work.
There are some other settings that work, but these are basically optimal settings.
The map file itself is just sort of an XML file.
You can actually open it up in XML and see it.
This says how large the tiles are.
That's really probably the most important part.
All the example tiles are 128 by 128 pixels.
And then this also sets how large you want your map.
So in this case, for this example, I've got a height of 20 tiles, which is actually kind of tall, and a width of 25.
If you've got more of a flat top down map, you want it a bit more square.
But if you're doing a side scrap platform scroller, then you probably want it a lot wider.
And you can change this rather easily underneath the map settings once you create it so you're not really committing to too much there.
But the tile size, you want to end up making sure that you've got it right.
And you want to make sure that your graphics really are pretty much all the same size or else a tile-based layout just does not work particularly well.
Then once you've got that done, so I'm going to go ahead and create this.
So I've got 128 by 128, and I'll just kick the default.
Hit save as.
And then wherever you end up saving this, you want to try to make sure that you save it in the same directory as your Python file.
If it's in a different directory, it's going to have a really hard time finding it.
Therefore, I want to make sure that it's in the right same folder.
In this case, I'm already there, but make sure you select that same folder.
I'm just going to call mind map to, and the extension on these files is TMX.
At which point you end up with a screen that looks similar to this.
You can use the control wheel.
You can zoom in and out.
If you're using it on a laptop, you can probably just use two fingers.
And to see how much of the map you actually end up wanting to look at in a single time.
The map by itself doesn't do a whole lot of good without something to add to the map.
So if we want something to add to the map, we need to create a tile set for us to actually then paint onto the map.
In the lower right corner, there should be a button that says new tile set.
If you find that particular button, we can end up creating a new tile set.
I'm going to flip over here where I can zoom in on it.
I suppose I should make sure I follow my same bit here.
Maps are usually generated into layers.
If you double click on the layers, you can rename a layer.
I usually use platforms as a layer that's anything I can't move through.
So any type of wall.
You can call it whatever you want, but the example code that I've got assumes that you are using platforms as the layer.
So double click on that, rename it platforms, then click on this new tile set button.
And you should get a screen that looks something like this.
Anybody have trouble getting to this spot where we need to double check?
All right, we're good.
Okay, the new tile set, you can actually call this just about anything.
We're not really going to end up using this name anywhere.
So just type something in there, and then there are different types of tile sets that you can have.
In our particular case, we want a collection of images.
Using a sprite sheet is not supported right now in the arcade, so we definitely want a collection of images.
And then it's a lot more convenient if we just embed the tile set in the same map that we've got.
So set your new tile set up box like that, and then you'll get the option basically to work with the tile set.
So I'm going to go ahead and do that in my program.
New tile set, my tiles, great, click okay.
And then it seems like pretty much nothing changes.
What I've got in the lower right corner are all the tiles that I can use to paint my screen with, except I have no tiles.
And in order to get those tiles, I need to click on the right icon, which actually looks like it's grayed out.
This takes a lot.
This took actually me quite a bit of time to figure out.
But if you click on that little wrench icon, you'll actually get taken to a screen that will allow you to specify your tiles.
So find that wrench icon, which would be in the lower right corner of your screen.
Click on it, and then you should get a new screen to pop up that will allow you to add in your tiles.
Looking something like this.
Once you've got that set up, we need to hit the plus button.
So these are basically two kind of hidden buttons that you just have to magically know to hit.
You hit the plus button, and then you can add in tiles.
And then you can find the images and add all of those images into your particular tile set.
So I'm going to go back over here.
I'm going to hit the plus button.
I'm going to go into the images folder for my particular examples.
Let's see, examples, platformer, tutorial, images.
And I've got multiple directories.
The first directory that I want to add in is the tiles directory.
So I'm going to double click on it.
You should be able to quickly select every single tile there so you don't have to individually add them,
which would get really monotonous by hitting Control-A or whatever the equivalent is with the Mac.
This should select all of the different tiles, and then you can click open on that.
And I also usually hit the plus button, go to the directory with the items,
and select all of those and click open.
You can get a tile set with all sorts of tiles that you can actually end up drawing your particular map with.
So go ahead and do that, and let me know if you have any problems getting this set up.
Okay.
All right.
Once you've got these different tiles set up, you can flip back to your map editor,
and the tiles are in the lower right corner, and you can paint out what you want for world.
To begin with, I'm just going to throw something down there at the bottom to make sure that I can actually end up loading it.
And it's not a bad idea to make sure it works before you spend a ton of time putting together your particular world.
Then don't forget to save it with a Control-S. By default, it doesn't automatically save behind the scenes.
Then once you've saved the game, you should be able to use the sample code in number eight.
And I'm going to flip back over here to the web where it's a little bit easier to see.
This code should be able to load up a map, and the map...
There we go.
On line 90 that I've got up here, the map name is here.
So if you save your particular map with a different name, you can change the map name to whatever your file name is.
And then I actually go through and have two layers that it's expecting, a platforms layer, which is the first one that I would try.
You don't have to have a coins layer yet just to make sure that it's working.
And then at this point, it should be able to load up a map, and then it should be able to load up a map, and then it should be able to load up a map.
So if I run... Let's see, I'm going to go ahead and switch this to map two.
And then you can see if it works.
So try to get to the point where you're at least able to see the map.
And then you can see if it works. So try to get to the point where you're at least loading the map.
And if you've got the map loading, then you can expand it out. Don't put coins in the map quite yet.
I'll show you how to separate out the coin layer here separately.
But put in the platforms that you want and make sure that that's working. And let me know if it's not.
Oh, right.
So this is what we have here.
And then you can see if it works.
Although those look like huge tiles.
I won't get into that part.
That part is usually large.
That part is probably not.
So I'll just show you how to separate out the coin layer.
So we have a map.
And then you can see if it works.
I don't think you're supposed to be separating the map.
And then
I'll just do
that.
And I'll just
do that.
So
.
Okay, if you've got this working,
you can add in additional layers.
If you right click on the layer over here, you can select a new tile layer.
And then I'm going to create one here called coins.
That will allow you to add separately things to pick up.
It is extremely easy to select the wrong layer and then have your coins act as blocks that you stand on top of.
And then if you want to add them to the right layer,
you can simply flip them over to the right layer.
You can also add a block of coins that you accidentally end up picking up.
Make sure you select the right one here.
I've got platforms and I've got coins.
There's also a little eyeball thing here on the side, so if you want to make sure you
know what's in what layer, you can select those two.
And then once you've done that, you should be able to save it and then rerun this particular
program, see the new items, and pick up the coins.
So that's the next step.
Add in those different layers that you've got.
Okay, so you can use your fileware.
So, yeah, right click on the form and then you can use that.
And then add in the fileware.
Yeah, now you can do it right after.
Oh, you've got multiple filepads?
Yeah, it's like a computer map.
Oh, yeah.
Right now the program's set up to always put the person in the same spot, so don't
worry about putting down the person.
Okay.
A couple things that you can add in to your particular map.
If you go underneath the map menu, there's also a map properties.
So underneath the map menu, there's a map properties, and you can specify the background
color that you want for your map with that.
So I am clicking on map, map properties.
There's a background color, and you can click this and just do whatever particular color
you want.
Although keep in mind, when you do the color picker, by default it has things as dark as
possible, so no matter what I'm over, it's actually still black.
You need to grab this side thing and pull it up and then get your color.
And now finally I've got my color.
So I can get whatever I want for a background color.
I'm going to make this a bit more pale.
Awesome.
And now you've got your background color set for the map.
The other thing that is really useful is if you've got a particular tile and you don't
want it to act like a huge rectangle, such as I've got ramps in here, I can go to the
tile editor.
I can click on the tile that I want, and then over here, it helps if I zoom in, over here
on the right side, you can draw a polygon that will act as your hit box for that particular
tile.
Zoom out.
And you can do that polygon by clicking, and it needs to be actually on the polygon tool.
So if you click on the polygon tool, which is the one that looks like a triangle, you
can then start drawing around your particular item.
If you hold down the control key, it will actually snap you into a corner.
And I'm going to click on this, move this over here.
Click right here.
And then I can finally click up here.
Now this will actually act as a ramp.
You can put a hit box around the coin so that you don't actually have to get, you actually
have to touch the coin.
These particular items right here where you just have part of the item being as a tile,
if you put a, again, you need to use a polygon around it, but if you click on this and draw
yourself a box around it, then that bottom part, you won't actually hit.
You'll move through it instead.
And once you get your tile set up with all of these different oddities, like this has
got a bit of an under slope on it, then your hit collisions will work way better.
So...
Yeah, basically as soon as you do that shape, it just saves it, but you do have to save the
entire file, so don't forget to hit file save.
And then it should just plain work from that point.
So give that a try too.
Yeah, that doesn't happen automatically, unfortunately.
You have to add a code.
It would be very cool for it to automatically happen.
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah, there you go.
You want to do it basically with a loaded texture, and then once you load a texture,
you can draw the texture.
Yeah.
Oh, there's not an easy way of representing that file.
No, not yet.
Okay.
Yeah.
So wherever you saved it, is that where you saved it from right here to get to a good load?
If you want, I'd love to do it.
Oh, it just worked.
See, I was just thinking that you didn't have to do it in the last year, but you did it in the last year.
So you didn't have to play around with it.
Yeah, it would be better for its load.
It just doesn't fit.
That was actually a good one.
Yeah.
The other
example I would add
and it's going to be a good one.
So if you want to animate that.
Yeah, there you go.
That's another one.
Oh, right.
Right.
You know, there were parts of it.
The half tile doesn't work?
And it's too good in that order.
There's two, one has my name on it.
Yes, that one.
Draw with that one.
Right, right.
Hit the erase button right here.
And then you can be able to provide.
Are you going to write later?
Okay.
Is that how you do it?
If you don't mind, if you don't look at the most bad
and short corner, you're definitely on the right layer.
And then you're getting the right eraser there.
So I know I'm stuck on the left.
It's actually in the wrong.
I don't understand.
I understand it's not working.
Yeah, that's what I did.
Oh, good.
If you do it a different way,
then you make it work.
I do it a different way.
You can use the flat, you can use the flat.
This is my theory.
I have another one.
Do you want to go ahead and show me?
It's weird.
It's like coming walking.
I think that's...
It's in the middle.
The point on it?
As much as it is a line there.
I have it.
But you can save it.
I don't know if you have it.
You have it in the middle.
I don't know if you have it in the middle.
Okay.
Thanks.
I don't think it is, but earlier down the road,
it was a much bigger problem.
So,
that's a good one.
Um,
um,
I, let's see.
I have to spend more time looking it up.
You basically want to take the sprite and then see if it has points that are not corners.
So, you can go to get points, not that it's on sprite.
And basically you need to find one of those sprites and then call getPoint5
and see what it actually has.
See if it's different than what a rectangle would be. And it's different than what actually loaded it.
And then you need to figure out what the right to steal is going to be.
So, my guess is that somebody's going to stop loading that.
The other thing you can do is go into
maybe you like PyTorch or some other program, go into that
program load and then you can access it.
And watch as it pulls in the points
for that.
Alright.
As some additional
items that one can do. There's a step nine.
If you don't actually have a program that's like number nine,
you might want to re-download the items as I just recently
put this in the chat.
So, you can go to the next one.
And you can access the items as I just recently put this in.
But this expanded example has different layers
that do other items. It has a background layer
which the player doesn't interact with, but if you like have a plant or something
in the background that you want to add that's just for visual reference, then the background
layer will draw the plant and the player can just basically move in front of it.
You can also have a foreground layer. This is also for objects that you don't interact
with. And this will actually be drawn in front of the player
instead. And I'll show examples of both of those here in a bit.
You can add a don't touch layer. This could be anything
like lava or spikes that if the player encounters
that, it'll just reset them back to the beginning. You could add additional
code to it like subtract a life, do a game over, or basically
anything that you want you can add extra layers for.
I've had questions on like if you wanted a ladder layer where people
have the physics basically moves different so you can climb a ladder. You could add
all sorts of layers that act differently depending upon when the player
encounters them. This code example
also has
showing you basically how to reset the player if they end up falling off the map.
And if the player gets to the right side of the
map, then this will attempt to advance the level to
level two. So if you go all the way to the right and
get to that far, then it will try to load a second
level. And it will try to load a third level and fourth level. I don't actually have a third and fourth
level so it will error out in that case. You could add extra logic.
But this will show you how to have multiple levels and
be able to load your code that
way. So the key items to this that are new,
I have additional layers.
And the pattern is
so similar it's really nice to be able to set things up like this. All you need to do is add in
the additional layers that you've got. So I've got my foreground, background, and don't touch list.
If only my kids could respect that.
And then I also have
a level number.
And this level number
I will use to figure out what map I end up loading.
And I've got a game over,
which really isn't game over, it's just whenever the user hits something that
they're not supposed to.
Then what's new is
I'm going to do play by play for football.
I can't figure out these on screen drawing things. I've got a level here
that you can end up doing.
And this will change the map that I end up
drawing. Therefore I can call set up with a one, two, three, four, five
and it will bring that in as a parameter. And then it's just incredibly
simple in that down here
I
okay, by now, great. I use
I give up.
I just use my favorite F strings.
I hear they have stickers this year.
And I can easily select what file. So in this case it's going to do map two,
level one, map two, level two, map two, level three and so forth.
And then I load the layers. Basically I set up the layers here to load.
And then down below I end up loading the layers into
the particular level. The keep in mind levels are case sensitive
so you don't want to call it background with lowercase b
if your level name is actually background with an uppercase b inside
of your program. That can get to be fairly confusing if you don't do
that case match. And then down
here I just end up loading the levels. The code's really the same
for each one. We just do a different variable for
what layer I'm at and I specify
which map I want. This
takes a look at how large the map
is, the length, how far across it goes and
I know where the end of the map is which is what I need to figure out
when I want to advance the level
and I get to the end of it. Anyway that's basically just an expansion
of stuff that we've already done before. Then when I draw
it I want to make sure that I keep in...
I want to make sure that
I draw it in a proper order. You'll note that I have the player here
and the background is drawn first so those
that whole background layer will appear behind the player and the
foreground layer will appear in front of the player and that's really
all I need to do with adding the background and foreground layers
in order to allow my player to basically pass in front of and behind
items. Then the don't touch list
is
handled down here
in this section.
I simply restart
the player back to the beginning. The second half of this
the view left and view bottom, it's also important to reset the camera
back to the beginning. Otherwise you'll reset the player back to the beginning but the camera
will stay where it was before which will
make playability a little bit more complex
if they can't see where they are. So you basically reset the player's location back to the beginning
you reset the camera back to its original spot and that
works really well for a don't touch. In this case I also have a
sound that it plays in addition to that.
Then
when the player's X location, so the player I can figure out
where they are by center X, I can get self dot player sprite
and I can figure out the location of that player sprite at any time by using center X.
If it's greater than or equal to the end of the map make sure to always use
the greater than, don't do equals end of map because the player could easily skip over
that last number, that's a really common mistake I've had people do
when working with these games. Then I simply add one to
my level number and recall the setup function.
That will load the next map and the player can move forward from there.
If you've only got three maps in here then you could basically add in extra game logic
so that if they hit layer three and the end of it
then you can place a game over on top of the screen. I didn't do that in this
example but it's pretty straightforward to add in.
This then allows you
to do a lot more
with your particular game. So I'll run this.
The player passes in front of this background item
and behind this foreground item.
Pretty straightforward.
And like no pressure here.
And I've got a lava level here.
Which will just reset the player back.
Which I probably shouldn't have done.
Cool. Then when I hit the end here
I've got the exit and
now I'm on level two. So I've got a background object there, I've got spikes.
I can add anything I want to the coin level and have it pick up.
So you can even use those samples. This is a ramp so I've used the collision editor
to make this into a ramp. This is the foreground so
I'm just drowning. Help, give me some air.
And another ramp back down to show you that in action.
And if you run off the end of the map here it will error out because I don't have a map three.
But pretty straightforward. Not a lot of extra code
in order to get this closer to a full fledged
game.
Yeah, question if you wanted like a
continuously jumping type of game.
Right. You could generate it all at
once. I mean at some point basically if you just
wanted it to go infinitely you could
as the player goes up the ramp you could
just go up the ramp and just go up the ramp and
infinitely you could as the player gets near the top trigger the creation
of new random tiles and it would not be hard then
to once the tiles at the bottom fall off remove those
from play just like you remove the coins. And that could
allow you to infinitely basically move upwards.
The arcade library itself
can actually, depending upon the graphics card, you can have about
400,000 stationary sprites at a time before you start getting slow
down. Your computer will turn into a heater before then.
But you can have quite a few sprites actually created even if they're
off screen. But
it's totally possible to dynamically put those sprites in and out
at a time.
Other questions on the library?
Right, so to figure out
the logic behind if you should remove it into a continuously
upward jumping you'd look at the player center X and the player center
Y coordinates and then basically
you could loop through every sprite that you've got in the game
for wall in wall list and if that
sprites center X you could loop
sprites center X is so far below the
player's center X then you simply just do a remove
on that sprite and then it goes away. And that will keep you to a
very manageable number of sprites. And you could
do that going up, you could do that going down. There are
procedurally generated examples in
the example list. So let me get over there.
Example code.
And
right.
These can hold quite a few
different sprites. We particularly consider each one of those as an individual block.
But this shows you an example of creating mazes two
different ways. A recursive maze uses a recursive algorithm
in order to divide up the maze. A depth first search
type of maze. They produce very different types. One has really
long passages and the other one doesn't. If you
use the cellular autonomous type of algorithm you can create
cave type items. This is the, if you've ever played Terraria
where you've got this style of layout they use a very similar
logic and procedurally generating their item.
Binary space partitioning. I love doing procedural
types of layouts. But that's if you have more of a dungeon
and you want to make sure all of the rooms are connected up. You can create
quite a few games or quite a few randomly generated
levels that way. Other particular items to make
sure to sort of show or talk about. Adding
in enemies is not too difficult. There's an example for how to
do that. How to,
yes, if you want to shoot things there are, all you need is
a bullet list basically. So another sprite list that manages bullets.
And then there are a whole series of examples. One, the simplest one
is just to have bullets always go upwards and
shoot coins. Then a slightly more complex one
is to aim the bullets. This is where you actually end up needing
to use a little bit of trig because you've got to use sine and cosine to figure out
what your vector is in order to get to that final location.
Or you can use the programmer's favorite three keys of Control C and
Control V in order to just copy the code rather than
remember your geometry. Having the
enemies shoot and having them randomly shoot.
A common pattern is to actually keep a frame
counter. So you've got an attribute inside of the game
class that's simply an integer. You start it at zero and then every time
you call update you add one to it. If you use the
modulus to see if it's operated, see if it's evenly divisible. So
if you do frame count modulus 60 then every time it's evenly
divisible by 60 that's going to equal zero. And that will allow you to
have something shoot one time per second. Or 120 would be
two seconds since it's 60 frames per second. That's a nice way of doing
periodic shooting. Or you can use the random number generator and just
randomly one out of every 60 see if they end up
shooting if you don't want it to be as predictable.
The have enemies aim at the player example again uses a little bit
of trig. It's very similar to the one up above. And sprite
explosions shows you how
to basically animate items frame by frame. So you've got a sprite
and then you're going to flip through a whole bunch of frames. There's actually a really cool
website out there. I forget the name of it but it's in the example
that will allow you to generate explosions. I mean what more could you want out of
a website, right? And then it will
let you download each of the individual images that make up the explosion.
And you just simply flip through those different images.
And another very similar example
right here
covers some of the
basics on actually having the user move around
with a little bit of animation in it.
And I need to get an example with the physics engine
as well as I've been told.
So we've got those as particular examples. Tetris is always popular
so you've got to have Tetris. If you really want a full fledged
physics engine, the physics engine that we have is incredibly
simple and straight forward. PyMonk is
a wonderful library that does a full 2D
game engine, basically a 2D physics engine inside
of it. And I can kind of show you that a little bit.
So I'm going to go ahead and show you the PyMonk examples.
So you can basically, this example lets me grab
a box and move it around. I can toss things over, I can shoot
stuff. So anyway, I love PyMonk and it's very
straightforward to implement with the
arcade library. It is however physics, so you have to
think about mass, weight, and a bunch of other particular
items on friction when you put this together. But you can
create some pretty interesting items.
You can also create
joints. I think I hit the wrong
button. I don't know what happened. Try again.
There we go. I can
do a,
and I want circles.
So I can join these together.
Oop, don't hit that button.
So you can join multiple items together.
Let me try this again. Pin joint,
one, two, two, two.
Then I can drag them around
as well.
Anyway, you can do fun stuff. It can add motors, that type of
thing. There's a lot that's possible. The simple physics engine
is good enough to get started with, but if you want to create something
really advanced, PyMonk is an awesome library to
join up with this.
There's a start of a particle system.
There are some different stress
tests if you really want to play around with items. You can do
full screen as well. There's an example that shows you how to do
that. Doing a background image. So if you don't want a solid color,
you can do a background image. There are examples showing you
how to do a timer on screen. There's also a full-fledged
asteroid example if you're not interested in doing a platformer.
Then that example
shows you a little bit on how to do fade out.
This, when you shoot it, it actually ends up creating
additional sprites for the smaller
rocks.
Anyway, there's a lot of different examples on that particular website to give you an idea
of the things that you can do and building blocks to go
from there. Any general questions?
Goal in the future on the library?
Basically, I'm hoping that
more work is done on shaders so that you can have lights as well. It's not
all particularly lit up. Performance improvements
right now. Stationary sprites
draw incredibly fast. The moving sprites you're limited to about
I forget what it is, like 2000 or so before it starts to
slow down. The other thing is sound support is
the, probably McKeeley's Heel that I would really like to see
improved. But just Python in general. Pygame uses
a really old library called AVlib that hasn't been updated in forever.
This is using FFmpeg libraries, which can be a little bit problematic
from system to system to make sure that they end up loading. There are some other
libraries out there that are sort of on the research queue.
That would be a huge load to try to figure out
better overall sound support, particularly with callbacks so that you can
play background music in the games and then when it's done playing background
music you can queue up the next song as well. That would be
a big improvement. So, I don't know, we'll see.
It depends on what people contribute to. The whole particle system was contributed
by somebody else because they cared about the particle emitters
and being able to do that.
Is there anything
regarding fluid mechanics?
Is there anything regarding fluid mechanics?
I would think probably not. You'd need to look
at the Pymunk library and
see if they've got anything like it. They might
actually, because then, my recollection is that you kind of end up
creating a whole bunch of circles with some soft bonds between the two and then
you just kind of draw over it.
For the arcade library itself, no, but take a look at the Pymunk
library and see if it's got something fluid-like
on it.
Any other questions?
Okay, at this point I will
stick around for as long as people want to stick around and take a look
at that other ninth example that's a little bit fancier. You can edit the maps that are
already there. You can create your own maps. There's quite a bit
that you can do with that final example and the multiple layers that it's got.
So, thank you very much.
Applause