Hello, everybody.
I'd like you to welcome Alex Landau.
And today, he's going to be talking about building
a culture of observability.
Hi, everyone.
Thank you very much for coming to this talk.
This talk is about some interesting work
we've been doing at Rover around observability.
My name's Alex Landau, and I've been
at Rover for about two years on our site reliability
engineering team.
So I just want to start with some quick facts about Rover
before we begin.
You can kind of think of Rover as like the Airbnb
for pet sitting or Uber for dog walking.
Basically, we connect pet service providers
with the needs of owners.
So we're the global leader in this space,
the biggest competitor.
We just launched in Europe last year.
And I think that we have a strong collaborative
engineering culture that encourages experimentation
and creative problem solving.
And I think that that led to some of the work
that we're going to talk about today.
I want to start with defining how we define observability
at Rover, like how we think about it,
and talk about why we thought it was important to focus on it,
why we thought it was worth investing engineering resources
towards it.
Then I want to talk about our particular approach
to a few major pillars of web apps
and doing observability in web apps,
in particular, logging metrics and dashboards.
And at the end of the talk, I want
to wrap up with some higher level philosophy about how
we actually built observability into our engineering culture.
So this is a tweet.
And it's kind of a tongue in cheek tweet
from Cindy Street-Harrin, who wrote a book on observability
and distributed systems.
And it's basically like an overheard tweet
where someone was saying that observability is just
a new fancy word for monitoring to make it
more palatable for developers.
And I think that it's true that observability encompasses
monitoring in a big way.
But at Rover, we take the definition a little bit further.
We think observability is all about knowing exactly what's
going on in your web application.
And when something does go wrong,
knowing very quickly what went wrong and how to fix it.
The metaphor that we like to use is
telling the narrative of your application
or the story of what's going on.
And we think a culture of observability
really empowers developers by removing
uncertainty and speculation and making it easy for developers
to feel comfortable working at all levels of the application
up and down the stack, especially as the application
grows in scale and complexity.
So complexity is something of an abstract term.
And I want to make it more concrete with an example.
And I want to take Rover's web app as an example of what I
think is a fairly complex Python web app.
We have about 600,000 lines of Python code
in a single monolithic Django application backed by MySQL.
We have about 100 developers committing code
to that on any given day.
And we're deploying changes between 15 and 30 times a day.
We have thousands of individual views, celery tasks,
management commands, cron jobs, basically lots of places
where we execute code and lots of places
where things can go wrong.
We care about observability because observability
has a real tangible impact on our business
and on our engineering culture.
It helps us wrangle the complexity of this web app.
Some examples include bugs being much easier
to identify and localize.
When things go wrong in production,
it's much easier to quickly detect what went wrong
and then fix it.
And then when we have a root cause analysis
after the fact or a postmortem, it's
a lot more efficient and productive.
That process gives us the action items
we need to prevent the issue from reoccurring in the future.
Basically, observability gives us the detective tools
that we need to eliminate mysteries and black boxes.
We think these are bad things to have in an application.
And it becomes a lot more common to have these
as your application grows in scale
and your engineering team grows.
And we think a culture of observability
really helps us eliminate those.
So we've defined observability as we see it at Rover
and motivated our focus on it.
So the question then is, how do we actually
enact observability into our engineering culture?
And as I mentioned before, I want
to go through three pillars, so logging, metrics,
and dashboards.
And in each pillar, we're going to talk about a problem
that we faced and a solution that we
built in Python and Django.
I'm going to focus mostly on tools for Python, Django,
because that's what we use at Rover.
But I think that there's some learnings that
are widely applicable.
And then at the end, we're going to talk about the philosophy
that we use to unify these tools as part
of our engineering culture.
So we'll start with logging.
Logging is fairly simple conceptually.
It's just writing down things as they happen.
It's a very standard way to keep track of what's
going on in your application.
But it starts to get more interesting at scale.
So the standard best practice is to just log things
to an output stream and then aggregate all your output
streams in one single centralized place
where the logs are structured and searchable.
Loggly is a third party service that does this.
You can also use the Elk Stack, which is Elastic Search
logs-kibana.
And the idea is you have a centralized stream that
developers can search.
And they can search on different facets, like application
or whatever other things you think are important.
And this is really useful for developers
because you can have logs coming from all over the place
in your infrastructure.
In fact, even on a single application server,
you could have logs coming from NGINX if you're using that,
your application, like your Python app, system processes,
lots of different things that are emitting logs.
This is an example of 10 minutes of logs from Rover's production
application.
This is from a Saturday last June, I think.
I think it was noon.
And so we had about a million log
events in that time, which is around 300 per second.
And I think that this is relatively moderate scale.
I think there are places that have much higher scale than this.
And it's certainly not our peak traffic during the week.
And so you can imagine these logs are coming
from all over our infrastructure,
from different applications.
They're all centralized in a place we use Loggly.
And it's a searchable, structured stream.
But the problem is, at a certain scale,
it becomes really difficult to focus
on one particular workflow, so seeing the logs
from one workflow.
And when I say workflow, what I'm talking about
is one execution of your web app,
whether that's a request response cycle or an async
workflow.
There's a lot of components that are probably
important to see in the logs of a workflow,
request response metadata, like status code, anything
that your application is logging.
But then there's a lot of other parts
that could be equally important, like if you're using NGINX
and you want to see the proxy jumps,
or if you're publishing async tasks from your requests,
or in a service-oriented architecture,
if you're calling into your other services.
These are all things that you want to see
as part of the components of a single workflow,
like request response cycle.
But at scale, it becomes really difficult
to find these in the logs.
You can't rely on timestamps.
First of all, timestamps are not always
reliable in a distributed system.
You can have clock drift.
But even if they were reliable, a lot of things
happen in the same instant.
And trying to correlate all of the logs
for a particular workflow becomes this needle
in a haystack problem.
So the common approach that a lot of APM and tracing tools
use is to inject a tracing ID into the logs.
So this is basically a string that is unique per execution.
And it's generated by something.
And it's injected into all of the logs.
And the idea is, if you search your logs
for this particular ID, you get all of the logs
for that workflow and only those logs, nothing else.
And the idea is, if you can find one log,
you can find all of them for a particular workflow.
It looks something like this.
This is just an example to illustrate
what I'm talking about.
I've highlighted the tracing ID here.
It's xyz.
Of course, in production, it would be like a UUID
or something that's actually globally unique.
And the idea is, if I search for xyz,
I would see only these logs.
So we have like nginx logs.
We have some application logging, some celery task
logging.
And this is really useful because it
allows you to just dig into a particular workflow.
Well, we don't actually need any APM tooling to do this.
We can just do it with the Python standard library.
We'll use a logging filter and thread local storage.
Logging filter is a tool that the standard library
provides to optionally filter out logs
from reaching your handler or to alter log records
as they come through before they reach the handler.
And we're going to use the latter functionality.
And then thread local storage is basically
just like an attribute bag that you
can use that is safe to access within a thread
and specific to a thread, which is important for web apps.
So our production implementation looks almost identical to this.
It's very similar.
This is the logging filter that we use.
So the tracing ID is being retrieved
from thread local storage.
And then it's being added into the log records dunderdict.
And that makes it accessible in the formatting string.
So you just have to have tracing ID in the formatting string,
and it will show up there.
And it's really simple to do this.
And it creates a ton of value for when
you're looking at logs.
Now, the only complexity here is really managing
the thread local storage.
But you can do that pretty easily in a web app.
It kind of depends on what you're using.
We use Django.
So we have a middleware that sets the tracing ID
as a request comes in and clears it as they come out.
If you use Flask, you already have this with the request
object that you can import.
But thread local storage works in all frameworks.
So one interesting extension to this
is if your web requests publish celery tasks, which
is pretty common, it gets a little tricky
to get this ID passed down into your celery workflows.
We wrote a blog post about it.
I don't have time to get into all the details now.
But the basic idea is to put the tracing ID as part
of your celery task IDs.
If you can find me after the talk,
I can tell you all about how we did that.
So once you've enabled this tracing behavior
for your logging, it makes it very useful
to understand at a granular level
how your application is behaving per execution.
But logging isn't great for looking
at systemic or aggregate behavior.
You can kind of get some of it from structured logs.
But logs tend to be really hard to monitor.
You end up with a lot of false positives, trouble
with parsing log formats that change.
There's a lot of issues with it.
And another kind of thing that people don't really
think about as much is logs are very expensive.
And the cost model of logs sort of roughly scales linearly
with your volume.
As you get more requests, you're going to be storing more logs.
And it's not great to rely on that just for monitoring.
So to fix these issues, we have metrics.
And metrics are also pretty simple conceptually.
It's just a measurement of something that you care about.
Where metrics get interesting is when
you go past the basic metrics.
Now, the basic metrics are basically these three.
These are the big three that most web apps are
going to be collecting.
So you have error rate.
How many 5XX responses are you sending back
to your clients?
Response time.
How long does it take to actually respond to requests?
And volume.
Do you have a giant spike in volume or a drop in volume?
If any of these metrics are going out of whack,
then someone's getting paged.
And people are seeing pages like this one from Reddit.
At Rover, these metrics were not quite enough to us
to understand some of the problems
that we were seeing at scale.
In particular, we were having a lot of issues
with our interactions with our database, which
is a shared resource.
So it's very important that we utilize that
in an effective way.
And this is kind of a common problem
in frameworks like Django.
Django uses an ORM, or an Object Relational Mapper,
which allows you to interact with Python code
and have SQL queries issued on your behalf.
It's basically an abstraction over SQL.
And it's common in those frameworks
to introduce suboptimal interactions
with your database layer.
We were seeing a lot of this as we scaled.
It's a problem that's pretty pernicious,
because we have lots of places where we execute queries.
And we have a complex web app.
So it was really important for us
to understand how we were issuing queries.
So we collected a class of metrics, query metrics.
And in particular, we collect in production
the distribution of the number of queries issued
and the total time spent querying the database
per request for all of our views
and per execution for all of our celery tasks.
So this provides us a really useful granular view
of how our application is behaving and performing
with respect to our database all over the place.
We use statsd to do this.
Statsd is a common metrics model
in a lot of Python applications.
Basically, you pre-aggregate metrics
on all of the servers or containers in your infrastructure
and periodically flush them to a backend,
which is Datadog in this case.
In a moment, I'm gonna show you how we use these metrics
to power some dashboards
and achieve some big performance wins.
But first, I wanna talk really quickly
about the implementation,
because I think it's kind of interesting.
The high level idea is really simple.
You just need to wrap your database queries
and you need to have a hook where you issue queries.
In Django 111, we do this by extending
the built-in MySQL database engine
and just overriding the execute method on the cursor.
In Django 2, this gets a lot easier.
It's supported as a first party API
using the connection.execute wrapper.
The interesting part of this implementation
is really around how we get the per request granularity
or the per execution granularity.
The way that we do that is,
instead of omitting a metric after every query,
we actually remember the total number of queries
across the request
and the total time spent querying the database
across the request or task.
And then at the end, we emit a single histogram,
which is Datadog's version of a distribution, basically.
And that gives us the distribution of query count
and query time per request.
And we'll see an example of that
on some graphs in just a second.
I should also mention that we thought
this was a pretty common use case
to have this capability to do that level of granularity
for metrics.
So we wrote a library to make it helpful.
It's a library that's specific to Datadog,
but it should be easy to extend
for any protocol of stastity
that supports tagging your metrics.
So we talked about this particular set of metrics
that have been really useful to us.
So I wanna talk now about how we put these into dashboards
in a useful way.
So our high level dashboarding strategy
is we wanna make dashboards very easy to visualize
and look for visual diffs or trends over time
that make it clear what's going on
for whomever is actually looking at the dashboard,
even if they weren't involved in making it.
Another philosophy that we have is
we think that documentation should live as closely
to the tool that's being documented as possible.
So we actually put on our dashboards,
what are you looking at in each of these charts,
and what are the things you should be looking for
in terms of what the lines are doing.
So even developers who weren't involved
in making the dashboards can get an understanding
of what they're seeing.
And lastly, when we're talking about dashboarding,
we like to share examples or case studies
of when the dashboards have been useful for us.
And so that's what I wanna do right now.
I wanna go through a few examples.
And in each of these examples,
we're going to look at what were we looking for
on this particular graph,
like what were we graphing and what were we looking for?
What did we see that made us take an action?
What action did we take?
And then what was the result?
So this first graph is a graph
of the median number of queries issued per request
for a particular view.
So this is that query count metric I was talking about.
So for each of these time slices,
basically it's saying within that time,
the median number of queries that any request
to that view issued was this number.
So about 200 in this case.
Now for this particular view,
it wasn't really supposed to be doing much.
And so what we were looking for is views
where there's a very high number of queries per request
or a variable number.
That's usually indicative of the N plus one query problem,
which is a common problem in ORM frameworks.
The idea is you end up issuing N queries
to fetch N rows instead of one query.
Very common, easy to introduce in frameworks like Django.
So we look for this on the graph.
We see a view that is not supposed to be doing much
that's issuing a lot of queries.
And when we were able to find the N plus one query
with our local debug toolbar, and we eliminated it,
you can see about a 75% drop in queries per request.
So that was a big win for us.
Another common problem in any framework
that's using MySQL or anytime you're backed
by a relational database is if you have a query
that grows in time linear with the growth of a table.
So that's bad.
That's usually an indication that you're missing an index.
So what this graph is showing is very similar
to the last one, but this is the median amount
of time spent querying the database per request
for a particular view.
So it's query time per request.
And when we look at several months of data,
if we see this trend of query time per request going up
kind of at a linear rate, that's an indication to us
that there's like a missing index.
And in this case, there was.
And when we added the index, we saw that the query time
per request dropped very significantly.
And most importantly, it's no longer trending up
at the same rate.
So this was really important for us.
And then one last example, this is a little bit different
from our previous metrics.
Once we had a hook where we were emitting
these query metrics, we started to think about
what else might be useful around the context
of a query to emit.
And one of the metrics that we thought was useful
was anytime there's one slow query,
we emit a metric, a counter,
and basically some metadata about it.
So what you're seeing on this slide is a graph
of a total number of slow queries, basically.
So queries over a threshold amount of seconds.
I think it's two in this case.
And you can see that there are quite a few of them.
And it's broken down by all of the views
in our infrastructure.
So you can see that we have like kind of a,
I don't know how easy it is to see on this graph
with the colors, but basically there were a handful
of views that were issuing a large number of slow queries.
And when we dug into it, we actually found
that it was all coming from one slow query
that was on a very hot code path.
And when we eliminated it, we saw not only a huge drop
in the total number of slow queries,
but we actually saw our database,
master database CPU utilization
and our IOPS drop like very noticeably.
So this one code change was really significant for us.
So I wanna wrap it up with speaking,
taking a step back and talking about
some higher level observability points.
So there's a saying that goes something like,
if you build it, they will come.
And the idea is like, if you build tools that are useful,
people are going to use them.
And I think that that only captures half the battle.
The other half is you have to document
and evangelize those tools in some way.
People aren't just going to use a tool that you build
just because it's really cool
and you know that it's really cool.
So one example at Rover that we have is a venue
for doing this where every two weeks
we have an informal gathering of the broader tech team
where anyone can present on some tech that they're working on
or some tools that they have.
And that's been a really useful venue for us
to evangelize these tools internally.
So as an SRE team, whenever we think that there is a metric
that would be widely applicable to all of our developers,
we actually go and we go out of our way
to emit this metric in a way that we don't have
to have our developers go instrument their code themselves.
So we find a way, for example, with these query metrics
where we don't have to have all of our developers
go instrument their code in order to get
the metrics submitted.
This is really important
because it makes the observability culture frictionless
and it makes developers much more likely to buy off
on the tools that you're making
and it empowers all of your developers as well.
We also think that it's much better to have a metric
and not need it than need one and not have it
because you can't retroactively measure something
that you didn't realize was going to be useful.
So we budget a lot for our custom metrics
and we err always on the side of granularity
in terms of whether we think a metric
is going to be useful for us.
And the last thing I wanna say is you can think of SRE
as this reactive harm reduction team
where you go shake your fist at developers
for introducing performance problems
or have these kind of confrontational
or antagonistic standoffs, which sometimes is what happens.
But I think it's much more productive to think of SRE
as a developer tooling platform,
which means that you're building tools for developers,
you're building tools to empower developers.
The developers are like the customers
of the things that we're building.
We think that not only has this made our engineering culture
like more friendly and inclusive,
but it's also helped us scale the SRE tooling we have
with a pretty large organization
while having a fairly small SRE team.
So that's all I have, thank you very much.
We have some time for questions.
If anybody has any questions,
there are microphones set up in the back.
If you go to those microphones
so that everybody can hear you, that'd be great.
Thank you for the presentation, that was wonderful.
I'm curious if you have any advice for how to make sure
that these tools that you create age well.
I'm not sure if you have any advice
for how to make sure that these tools that you create age well.
I found that when we create them,
they're really useful for the team
that we introduce them to,
and then the team changes or a new feature is added
and it breaks and then they lose faith.
Yeah, that's a great question.
I think it actually boils down to a similar question
about APIs that you develop.
When you develop an API, how do you know
that you're solving for the right problem,
that the API isn't going to solve for a problem that,
or like you have a problem in the future
and the API doesn't cover it.
So I think treating the tools like an API platform,
so when you're developing,
trying to make things generic, as generic as possible.
For us, queries is fairly generic for Django
because we issue queries from many different contexts,
but it all breaks down to interaction with the database.
So we try to avoid building any tools
that are only solving one problem
by spending a lot of time upfront thinking about
how do we build the tool in a way
that it might solve and other problems
that are in a similar space in the future.
It's a hard problem, there's no set answer to it,
but so is building a good API that ages well.
So I think it's a very similar problem.
So this might be out of scope for your talk,
but in a lot of cases,
the problem might be a result of an exception.
And I'm wondering if you've found principles or cases
where to ensure that when an exception occurs,
you have enough context available.
Yeah, so one of the tools I didn't talk about
that we use is Sentry,
and I think Sentry is a pretty widely used tool.
So these tools are not the only ones that we have.
Sentry covers the cases where you have
an unhandled exception
and will automatically kind of log a bunch of context for you.
And then Sentry also includes the tracing ID.
We make sure that all our Sentry contexts
have that tracing ID,
and we can use that to go into the logs
and kind of dig deeper and see what was happening
around that exception.
Thanks.
You mentioned when collecting the metrics
for database queries,
and how you would send basically state to Datadog,
like a histogram to Datadog.
How do you guys control if something crashes
or something like that and that state gets lost?
How do you not interfere with the actual query
that's gonna be run or anything like that?
How do you keep the tooling both out of the way
but still useful, I guess?
Yeah, that's a great question
because when we first rolled out the query metrics,
of course, that's the code path that everything goes down,
and we had an issue with it,
and so of course, you broke all queries, right?
Like, in a certain sense, it's unavoidable
if you introduce a change to a code path
that is like the hottest code path
in your entire application.
We try to avoid having things,
we try to avoid doing dangerous things in that code path.
So we keep it as simple as we can.
We unit test extensively,
and then we also do some integration testing.
So we have like a staging environment
where we're running Datadog,
and we can run some passes,
making sure that that stats-de path that we're impacting
is not going to be destructive to our code base.
But the short answer really is that it does happen.
Like, there are times where we've introduced problems in that,
and it's a production outage,
and there's a trade-off of how deeply
you extend the internals of something
and how much you alter hot code paths.
For us, the trade-off was worth it.
Thanks. Thanks.
Yeah.
Has your work helped to debug things
that are problems with the ORM,
and work around those problems with the database views?
Yeah, absolutely.
Actually, one of the biggest ones was,
Django has this kind of issue when you do unions in SQL,
and I don't remember the exact nature of the problem,
but it's something like if you apply any modifiers
to a query set after you do a union,
they don't get respected.
This comes up when we, especially in a slow query metrics,
when we go dig into those slow queries
and look at where they're being issued from
and what the query actually is.
We log kind of the templated version of queries in that case,
and one of our engineers actually developed a library
to fix that problem,
so it's absolutely led to some ORM improvements.
Sweet.
It's called Django Delayed Union,
I think is the package name.
Can you just talk a little bit
about how the workflows are actually created?
Are they spawned from your engineering teams,
or they spawn as a consequence of the application
from your team?
Percentage-wise, how is it divided up?
Can you talk about how the different workflows are created?
I think you mentioned they were workflows that you'd request.
Yeah, so I'm using workflow kind of as a model
for any request that comes in
or any asynchronous task that gets kicked off,
and then everything that happens after that.
To give an example, we might have a request come in
that kicks off a celery task,
that kicks off three more, and so on and so forth.
For me, that's what we consider it as one single workflow.
So the moment that the code starts executing,
to kind of like, if you think of it as a tree,
the end of that tree.
So that's, for us, one workflow,
and that should all be unified by a single ID.
So even if that workflow goes on and on and on
for a long time,
we think that the tracing ID should be part of all of that.
So requests coming in is one.
Django management commands is another,
so like a one-off command, and then cron jobs.
Those are sort of the three where we start workflows from.
Okay, yeah, I come from a highly variable,
large enterprise environment
where not all the workflows are auto-discovered.
So I was interested to see
if you had come across something like that.
Yeah, one way you can deal with that,
if you have that scenario,
is if you have in your middleware a header or something.
That's how a lot of tracing tools do it.
That's like a shared library
that all of your services use, something like that.
You can accomplish the capability fairly easily that way.
Thank you.
So as a pet-focused organization,
was Datadog a thematic choice?
No, it was purely a wonderful coincidence
that we joined that way,
and that their logo also happens to be like a dog.
Also, serious question.
Do you have a monolithic backend,
or some sort of shared library,
or how do you go about making these tools
very available and consistent?
Yeah, so we have one large shared code base right now.
There are certainly advantages and disadvantages to that.
We can talk all day about the disadvantages.
One advantage of it, though, is that you don't need to...
Versioning is whatever is in the app, right?
So when we roll out these tools,
it's all in the same shared code base,
so people can take advantage of them right away.
And of course, there are problems with that as well,
but that's where we are right now.
Thank you.
So my question is about asynchronous tasks,
and I want to read your celery blog post,
but we have a JavaScript front end
to the Ndjango backend,
and it's gonna be fun to trace the requests from the client.
Yep, like I said, I'll be outside or something,
and I can tell you all about how we did that.
And we are at time, so I'm sorry, last question rejected,
but there'll be open spaces on this topic.
Yeah, I'll be outside.
You can find Alex outside.
Thank you, everybody.
Thank you.