Hello. Oh, hello. Welcome everyone. It's super loud. Thank you. We're starting a bit later
to accommodate for all the folks that were in the registration, but I just realized that
we have a full room now, so I assume that we can start. I just want to introduce myself.
My name is Tanya. I live and work in Manchester, UK, so I did a long trip yesterday. And I
Microsoft as a developer advocate, but for many years before that, I've been working
as a research software engineer, as a data engineer, as a machine learning engineer,
pretty much everything across working with data, data pipelines, and reproducibility.
You can have a lot of means to be contacted if I need to be contacted as a follow-up for
the tutorial. I know a lot of you have already mailed me for different troubleshooting issues
and stuff. I just want to start with a reminder that we have a code of conduct for all PyCon
stuff, so everyone in this room has to be, well, has to be aware to the code of conduct.
And if you feel that anyone is not aware to it, please let us know or let the PyCon volunteers
or PyCon organizers know. Also, all of the materials for this tutorial are CC by, so
if after that you want to use them, remix them, you're free to do that. I'm going to
be adding some bits later on just to extend on some things. And I'm going to go over just
some general information about the workshop. We're going to be talking about fundamental
or basic concepts of data pipelines and also present a couple of practical use cases of
Python for data pipelines. Mainly, we're going to be focusing on ETL, but you can then adjust
that if you want to be more on the patient learning side or models retraining or more
analysis focused. Some of the requirements or some of the assumptions that we've made
about you is that you have some experience using the command line, whether the command
line is for you, if you're using Mac, Windows or Linux. And you're also expected to have
some intermediate Python knowledge and be able to use it for intermediate purposes.
And also because we're going to be having a top view of the stuff instead of going into
very, very technical details or very in-depth explanations of everything. You should be
able or one of the ideas is that you have enough understanding of what we're doing
so that you can then take it back home, take it to your work or read your research or whatever
you do and apply whatever you've learned here. I also assume that you're interested in data
and systems a tiny bit, even if you like more data than systems or the other way around.
And I imagine that a lot of you are either aspiring or current data engineers or work
in research or research software engineering. And ideally you also know, have a tiny bit
knowledge of systems and databases because we're going to be working with databases mainly
to move our data around. So at the end of the day, I hope you have a better understanding
on how to apply pipelines using Python tool sets. We're going to be starting with pure
Python, well, more vanilla Python and then eventually move on to the use of our flow
to have DAGs and schedule tasks. And we're going to be focusing much more on the concepts
as I said before, instead of going very, very deep onto the knowledge. And this should ideally
give you some building blocks for whatever you want to do afterwards. As we follow the
tutorial you're going to see that there are some little traffic lights and different examples
or different tasks that we have. And these are going to be either tasks that you have
to complete on your own or that I'm going to be doing and I expect you to follow along
or that you're going to be doing pair programming. So at the beginning I gave you two post-its,
everyone got their post-its. And this is going to help me to understand how fast or how slow
you're going through examples or if you need extra time or if you need extra help. So if
you have, well, it's not purple, this time it's blue. If you have gone through, well,
as soon as you see a traffic light and you start with a task, I want you to put the orange
post-it here on your laptop so I can see. As you finish the task or you complete whatever
we're doing, you'll take this off and replace it with the blue post-it. So that way I can
ensure that everyone is following along and I don't leave people behind. Questions? Yes?
Is that better? And this one, is that better? Or do you want to do it again?
It didn't work. Is that better? Is that too big? Bigger? I'm going to have to put it on a separate thing probably.
But we'll see. Is that right? Fabulous. If at any point there is something that is not very clear or you need extra help or extra time,
feel free to ask me. We have a scheduled break at 10.15. Well, it's going to be 10.15. And we're going to be finishing instead of 1.20, 1.30 because of the 10 minutes that we accommodated at the beginning.
You know that some of you didn't email me on time or email me this morning about your passes, so I have not replied you back. And someone emailed me because I double-assigned a pass. That was my bad.
So during the break, feel free to reach out and I'll sort them out because we're going to be using that in a second. Cool. Are we all ready?
And I want you to put your purple post-it if you all have your installation and your environment and all of your prerequisites met.
I can see some oranges. OK, for most of it, I can see blue. I see a couple of oranges. If anyone is missing their Twitter, who's missing their Twitter approval? Oh, quite a few. Did you fill in your application?
Last night. Oh, OK. I'll have to figure a way to share this with you privately so that it's not there. And then everyone that goes to the videos will see my keys. Fantastic.
So we're going to start with pipelines, and this is a very appropriate meme these days. And the central, and every time I talk about pipelines, I have to talk about automation because when you build a data pipeline or a processing or analysis pipeline, basically what you're doing is focusing on automation.
And the great thing about automation is that it helps us to automate or speed up those tasks that are manual, that are quite boring, and it allows you to spend much more time in the things that you like most or that are actually going to add much more impact to your projects or to your company or to your research, whatever you're doing.
The one downside of having automation is that it also forces you to add certain monitoring and logging steps. So once you automate your tasks, then you have to ensure that you have processes and tools in place so that you can actually continuously monitor how the task is doing or if your system is failing or dying a bit every day in here.
So whenever you want to automate a task, you have to understand what kind of tasks are easily automated. For example, tasks like regular release schedule reports or something that you have to deliver every month or every week or every quarter, that is easy to automate.
If you have something that you only do once, probably after a meeting or it's a one-off task, then probably the effort of automating a task is going to be too high as well as cost.
Also for you to be able to automate anything or any task, you need to have very, very clear understanding of very clear outcomes of what success and failure looks like.
If you know, for example, that you're going to be sending an email to your 100 customers, then success more than likely is going to be that your email contains appropriate information and is sent at the appropriate time.
If you have unclear success or unclear failure rates or metrics, this is going to be very, very tricky because you can't monitor the state of your task. It just becomes very, very complex.
Also, if you have tasks that can be easily manipulated or the input can be easily manipulated by machines, let's say that you have data in the database that you can port around or that you can query through an API, it's going to be much easier than that data.
For example, you have to do surveys on paper and then translate or transcribe everything.
So whenever you want to automate anything, I suggest everyone to start following a checklist or answering this question because this is what is going to determine first how you're going to automate your task and what tools are you going to use for this purpose.
You have to have a clear understanding on when your task starts and when your tasks end. Let's say I have to generate report every month and it goes out every first Monday of the month or the first of the month.
So I know when I should trigger this.
Does this have a time limit? For example, do we have to cover a certain span of time as well? And also, what are the inputs of the tasks? This is essential. You need to understand what your task is going to consume and where it's coming from.
Again, what is success or failure? And how can we early identify these outcomes? How can you early identify that your task is failing? How can you easily identify that you need to do some remedial work or that your database or your systems are encountering problems?
And then when you face these problems, you also have to think about what afterwards. What is going to happen when there is a failure? Who should be notified? What remedial actions or what fixings do we have to apply?
And also, we need to understand what is the final output or the final outcome of a task and who should be made aware or who should receive all of these outputs or final products.
And once I have completed my task, whether successfully or unsuccessfully, what is going to happen then? Is this report going to be sent to someone? Do people have to receive a Slack message? Or what is going to happen? Do we have to purge databases or what? So that's the first thing.
So if when you're trying to automate or establish a pipeline to automate a certain task, you struggle a lot to answer these questions. More than likely is that you'll have to go again and redefine your task or probably it's not easily automatable.
And the same thing happens when you have a very, very large project or that is very loosely defined.
Mainly in data engineering, you'll have, for example, a task that collects your data, then it does some cleaning or runs some analysis and then sends the results probably to your head of marketing or to your head of data science or to your head of enterprise structure if you're doing monitoring, for example, of your resources.
So from the very, very point of view, this is what a data pipeline looks like. There are many, many variants, but generally you'll have some sort of data engineering that is data acquisition, transportation of the data, then prepare that so that it's actually consumed in an appropriate manner and then however does the analysis.
Or in machine learning or analytics in your company will have to have access to this already cleaned and already formatted data.
Now, because the data follows a very, very specific flow, every processes upstream and downstream are very, very interconnected.
So the quality of the data that goes from an upstream process will permit downside in your downstream processes.
And the reason is that for us pipeline and data workflows matter a lot because now they power pretty much every single data.
They are mission critical. If you didn't have enough pipelines that are well monitored or that are robust enough, we can't guarantee the validity and integrity of the data.
And therefore we can't guarantee that the data is well monitored or that it is well managed.
So the data that we have is not going to be a problem.
And also for those of you that already have a machine learning process, we can guarantee that the data is well monitored and that it is well managed.
And therefore we can't guarantee that the data is well monitored or that it is well managed.
And also for those of you that already work in data engineering or in companies that do all data intensive works, you will have realized by now that we spend a lot of time monitoring.
Doing a lot of logging, understanding how things are working, why they are failing.
And if you are not doing a lot of monitoring already, probably you should be doing a lot of monitoring.
And that's probably where we spend more of our time. Well, most of our time.
I certainly have spent a lot of time understanding where to improve our pipelines.
And I think this is also something that you have to understand when you are working with data pipelines.
Although you might have static ones, they are not static because then the data streams as well keep continuously changing.
If you are using APIs, APIs will continuously change.
As new packages or packages apply patches, again, everything is continuously evolving.
So you also have to schedule time to actually maintain and maintain your databases, migrate them, ensure that everything is working.
And how do you know that a pipeline is good?
Basically, a good pipeline is reproducible.
And this in very, very crude terms means that if you have the same code, the same data, the same environments, you should always get the same outcome.
So that shouldn't change because you are basically pinning down the three pillars or the three bases for your code, your data and your environment.
Also, a good pipeline should be easy to productize. It should be easy to take from an R&D or an exploratory environment into production.
And this means that we will need minimal modifications from one environment to the other.
In many cases, this will mean that probably you are changing the database from a development database to a production one.
Sometimes if you are running on Kubernetes, you are probably going to just change from a small cluster to a higher cluster with a security lockdown or with higher security configurations.
But in general, they should be easy to productize. And most of the time, this productizing process is done through continuous delivery and continuous integration.
So again, you have to liaise a lot with your DevOps or your infrastructure people to figure out how to, again, automate the automation of your pipelines.
And another characteristic of good pipelines is that they are atomic.
Basically, every single unit or every task is very, very well designed.
Every task is almost independent and can be run independently.
So that makes it easier to understand what code can be easily reduced.
It will make it easier to maintain them as well.
And also when working with data pipelines, there are two things that you have always remembered.
Your data is dirty. You always start with the assumption that your data is dirty.
Unless you can put your hand on the fire and say, I know it is not.
So the excuses are, it's already in the database, so it's already good, it has good quality, we don't have to do cleaning and validation.
That's a lie. I'll tell you, that's an absolute lie.
And second, all your data is important.
Unless you're 100% sure that that client is not going to come back and ask for a retrospective report from the last three years, you keep your raw data.
You can keep it, you can transform it, don't get rid of your raw data.
Don't touch it. Don't touch it, even when it's sick.
And the better you want to get at your data quality, at your data engineering processes, the downside again is that the complexity of the processes increase.
Because you have to increase your tool set, you have to increase the tasks.
And as you encounter yourself doing more automation, more pipelines and having to monitor how these workflows are going, then more than likely you're going to get a lot of data.
And if you're going to have to monitor how these workflows are going, then more than likely you're going to end up needing a workflow manager.
And in this case, you can use things now like Airflow, that is what we're going to be using here, but there are other alternatives like Ligee, for example, and PackageRM.
And in very, very simple terms, a workflow manager is like having the best of make, Unix pipes, because everybody loves pipes.
I love pipes. They're my favorite part of Unix.
And some sort of steroids. You have also a bit of cron jobs there.
So are we ready to start writing our first ETL pipeline?
And we're going to start with a Vanilla Python pipeline to understand how this process is going to go.
For those of you that don't have a Twitter API, I'm going to have to figure out how to share the keys with you.
And I'm going to have to burn those keys to the ground after we finish the tutorial as well.
Oh, I fixed that. I merged it yesterday. Was it like the two tiny typos or so?
Yes, I think so. Was it yesterday?
Oh, okay. I'll merge it later. Yeah, that's fine.
Because someone found two typos that I typed cdch instead of cd. Oh, that was you. Great.
Probably less.
Yeah, I know.
So I'm going to have to find a way to do that.
Probably less.
Cool. So the first thing that we have to do is setting up our local database.
And this is because we're going to be doing streaming.
So eventually, when you're working with large volumes of data, moving CSV files or that kind of type delimited or text files becomes very, very tedious and very, very inconvenient.
So if you follow along, we're going to start creating from your common line our setup.
And this is going to be our database that we're going to use throughout the whole tutorial.
So with that code, it's going to request you to enter your password.
If you have a password and if you don't have it, it's fine.
You know that you're in SQL because you get this very beautiful message saying that you're in SQL.
And you can see your databases using the directive show databases.
In my case, I already have an Airflow database, but this is a very fresh install.
So it only comes with the defaults or MySQL.
And you can also see your user's.
You can see your users and I have obviously an error there.
There you go.
And that is going to show where your users have their normally you only have a route and the MySQL infoschema decision and the system.
We're going to create an Airflow user for this tutorial because eventually we're going to need to grant privileges to our flow to access our databases and store data in there.
So let me clear my screen so you can all see.
And the next step is going to create our databases.
So for this we use create database and then you give your database name.
I like to remember what it is.
It's called create database Airflow DB.
Now for those of you that are not familiar with SQL, you don't have to use capital letters all the time, but it makes it much more understandable.
And then set we're going to use UTF for our encoding.
And then we're going to collate.
And it will tell you straight away if uses that panini code or even use c vertex.
It's just an array that we're probably a little bit different if you didn't have so familiar with SICOH ..
And it will tell you straight away if your syntax was correct.
It's going to tell you I created one database.
So you can again use your social databases command.
And you're going to see that you have your Airflow,
your newly created Airflow database
and the default databases that MySQL comes from.
Now, because we don't want to use our root passwords
and our root privileges for everything,
especially when we're doing things in our indeed
that are then going to be taken into production,
we're going to create our specific user
that is only going to have access to both the Airflow
and the Airflow DB databases.
So again, we're going to use a directive create user.
And we have to use single quotation.
This is very important because MySQL goes crazy.
Add local host because we're running our local database.
Our host is going to be a local host.
And we're going to give it a password.
Here, I don't care much because I'm going to burn this again.
So I'm going to call it, give it a password, Python 2019.
It's easy for me to remember.
It's not going to cause a lot of problems.
For me, it's going to fail
because I already have an Airflow user.
But for you, it should work.
So again, if I do a select user host from MySQL,
you should see your newly created Airflow user.
And once you all have your users and your databases put your,
or no, your blue stick is on.
Cool.
Great.
So now the next thing is going to be granting privileges
to our user and this is that our user has
write and query access on the database.
As with Unix, the star wildcard
will identify like anything.
So we don't want to grant access to this airflow user
to all of our databases, we're gonna just do it
for our newly created airflow database.
And we're gonna for this use,
the grant all privileges.
And this means read, write and admin privileges.
So they can create new tables, they can delete the database,
they can query, append data, add data, remove data.
They can do basically everything.
And we have to say on what database.
So it's airflow database and this dot,
whatever is gonna be my host.
In this case, I only have local host tied to this.
So it's okay.
And then I'm gonna grant this to my airflow.
Sorry, this is the different tables
and the children of the database.
The same local host that we have.
So we have grant all privileges on airflow database
to my airflow user.
And now it tells you that it's fine.
And we need to then do a flush privileges.
Fantastic.
So if we go again,
now we have a database,
we have an airflow database database.
And we're gonna create as well
a secondary airflow database
that we're gonna use later on with which is airflow.
If you use your up arrows,
you can go back to where we created this airflow database.
And instead of calling it airflow DB,
it's gonna be called just airflow.
So for me, more than likely it's not gonna like it
because I already have a database.
So we need to have two airflow databases now.
And again, repeat, they grant all privileges,
but instead of being airflow DB
is gonna be the vanilla airflow database.
Good night.
The biggest one, perfect.
The ones at the back,
you see better with that super big font?
Cool.
Yes.
And now that we are ready with our databases, we can exit.
And it's going to take you back to your regularly beautiful
command line.
And I'm going to make this bigger as well.
Fabulous.
If at any point, I don't know, later on,
did we finish the tutorial?
Or if you made a mistake typing and you need to remove a user,
you can use the drop user.
You replace the username into localhost.
That's going to remove it.
It's the same directive.
If you want to get rid of database or a table,
instead of using the keyword user,
you're going to use drop database, Airflow, for example,
or drop table, airflow.mytable, whatever you want.
And in this case, SQL is a very intuitive language.
And basically, the directive tells you exactly what it's doing.
No.
So you have one user that is Airflow, two databases,
an Airflow and an AirflowDB.
Has access to both.
No.
The users that you create are global users.
So they're not inside the database.
They're global users.
The thing that we do with this directive,
with the grant privileges, is just giving them permissions
to do things with the database.
For example, your root user, by default,
will have access and all level access to any database
that you created, your localhost.
Any other user need to be given explicit privileges.
We're using all privileges.
So after you created your Airflow database,
well, the Airflow one, not the AirflowDB,
you have to do again a grant all privileges on so
that your Airflow user can access it.
Does that make sense?
Cool.
So now we have our database.
We have our environment.
And the next bit is for those of you
that have never connected to a database from Python
is to learn how we're actually going to do this.
So I'm going to go to my documents
and create a directory called Documents Demo PyCon.
You can call it whatever you want.
Oh.
Why?
OK.
So I have now a brand new directory.
And I'm going to start my ID.
I use Visual Studio code because I really like it.
And it makes life easier for me.
And just let me change the color of my bar
so I can actually identify which one it is.
And this is not a commercial.
But if you use VS Code and you end up
like myself with 30 windows at all time, use Peacock.
And it's amazing because it just changes the color.
I'm going to say it surprised me with random color.
So that is great.
And you can see that I have my other VS Codes here.
Fantastic.
So I'm going to create a folder called Database.
Just so that all of my little snippets that refer to,
do I need to make this bigger?
That refer to managing databases or accessing databases
are in the same place.
They're happier if they're together.
I'm going to create a Python MySQL.
I'm going to have to select my interpreter.
So now I am using my Airflow environment.
That is the same environment that we are all using.
We should all have the same libraries, hopefully.
And we're going to start by importing into the libraries
that you have to install.
We have a library called MySQL Connector, MySQL Client.
And this is a library that allows
you to hook up whatever you're doing in Python
to the SQL databases that we created before.
And it's very nifty because that way,
you didn't have to do batch scripts that
will do your SQL things and then call them
through some processes.
But everything is Python native.
So it makes it much more efficient.
It's easier to debug sometimes.
So we're going to check that we actually can access our database.
For this, we're going to import the MySQL Connector as MySQL
because I don't like typing.
Then I'm going to create an object called dbconnect.
And this is actually going to be my connector object
or my connection object to the database.
It's going to be MySQL.
And you'll see that as you start typing,
you have a lot of methods.
So we're going to use the connect method
because we want to actually establish
a connection between our Python interpreter and the database.
And this is going to take three arguments by default, your host,
your user, and the password.
And then the database, sometimes it
depends whether you have a default one.
So I'm going to copy this across because I'm a bit lazy.
Can you see what this syntax highlighting at the back?
No?
Would you rather have it black, like a dark one?
Is that better?
OK, so let me make this.
So this is going to return a connection object.
It's not very exciting because when you start it,
it doesn't give you anything.
So I'm going to do a print of the dbconnect
just so that I can actually see the location of memory
of this object.
And after I'm done with whatever I'm going to do with my database,
I always have to close my connection.
This is mandatory.
So we have this little snippet that is actually going
to help me now to connect.
And I have my host, my local host, my user.
In this case, I'm using the user airflow
that I created before.
The password now all the world knows my database.
So if I start my terminal here, I am in the right space.
If I do a Python, ETL, no.
Sorry, my terminal goes crazy when it's such a big font.
So it's not very exciting, but at least we
know that we are able to connect to my database.
If I call python database slash python mysql.py,
I'm executing this little snippet,
and it tells me, hey, here is your connection.
Here is your connector.
And it gives you the allocation in memory for this object
in true Python experience.
Now we have a database.
We know how to connect.
We know that we always, always, always
have to close our connection.
And this is because if you forget
to close your connection later on when we're doing streaming,
and we are not only opening connection,
but saving data and then querying data,
our threads will just get clogged,
and we won't be able to access anything.
Then comes the nice things of streaming Twitter
into the database.
Well, in the meantime, while I give everyone a set of keys
that they can use, the ones that don't have
your own personal keys pair up with someone that does.
Can you make sure that you're sitting next to someone
so at least you can speed up, and then I'll just
find a way to give you a set of keys.
We're going to be using a library called TweetPy.
Going to be using a library called TweetPy.
And it's, in my opinion, is probably the best Python
library, the best Python wrapper around the Twitter API.
It's very intuitive.
There are other around, but this one is very, very intuitive.
It gets you up and running in very little time.
And we're going to be doing the next two things.
We're going to first create a class, an object,
well, a Python class, sorry, to connect to the Twitter API.
And this is going to allow us to identify ourselves
and do this handshake with the Twitter API
and say, hey, my name is Tanya, or my username is Shik.
I can access the data.
Then we're going to hook up these Airflow DB database
that we created so that we can start streaming Twitter
data into the database.
So we're going to go and look at how a Tweet object actually
looks like, what kind of data it has.
It has actually a lot of data.
That is why I like doing things with the Twitter API,
because it gives you so much information from a single Tweet.
It's beautiful.
I'm going to open the Getting Started.
Getting Started.
And it gives you a very, very nice introduction
on how to actually get up to speed
or how you can get started.
So for those of you that have your keys,
I'm going to create a new directory in my demos
called ETL Basic.
This is where we're going to put all of our ETL Python scripts.
And then I'm going to make a new file called config.config.
It's going to be empty, but now I
can edit it in my ID or my editor.
We're going to have to create a copy and paste
during Twitter keys.
In the setup, you are given information
on how to set up your account and then later on how
to create an app.
If you gave your app read access,
you should have been issued with a consumer key, consumer
secret, access token, and access token circuit.
Now, you have to be very, very, very, very, very careful,
because if you commit this to Git or GitLab or Bitbucket
or anywhere, it's going to be out there.
So the only thing that you can do
after committing your keys is to burn those keys to death,
kill your apps, delete them from your repository,
and then create a new set of keys.
That's the only thing you can do.
There is no way to safeguard them after that.
So you have to be very, very careful.
So I'm going to just give you five minutes to do,
folks, to create your config file to get your keys.
You're going to have to replace them here
with whatever Twitter gives you.
And I'm going to sort out the ones that don't have.
So put your red sticky, your orange sticky,
while you're doing this, while you're getting your keys
from your Twitter API, creating your config file.
And I'm going to unplug this so that people don't see my keys.
And then when I'm actually getting
contact and I get noticing, I just know what you're doing.
Did you activate?
Hello.
Yeah.
OK, folks.
So I have created a Google Doc where
we have a couple of links.
There is a final survey that you have to fill in.
So please do it.
I'm not going to read them.
The results are going to be in the chat.
So I'm going to go ahead and read them.
And then I'm going to go ahead and click on the link.
And then I'm going to click on the link.
The results didn't come to me.
So feel free to write whatever you want.
Here is a link to the docs, well, to the tutorial docs.
And I have created a Google Docs.
So if you go to bit.ly slash airflow dash tutorial,
that's going to take you here.
And for those folks that don't have
their Twitter API keys, write your email.
And I'm just going to have to send you an encrypted email
with keys and then bring them alive as soon as we finish this.
Cool.
The rest of you, have you created your config file?
Yes.
Oh, it is bit.ly airflow tutorial.
Capital A, dash tutorial.
Everything looks huge on my screen, but it looks tiny there.
There you go.
Thank you.
Blue sticky, who's got their config file with their keys on
so I can now have an idea?
Yes.
Can you not?
OK.
Can edit.
There we go.
Does it work now?
Yes.
I can see a few of you there.
And I'm going to get your emails off the way.
Cool.
So it seems that most of you have your config file now.
So we can move on, and we can start getting with the scripts
and then get your your keys.
Fabulous.
So you should now have your config file there.
Going to put it in there.
You have your config file that looks like this
and has to have that call to Twitter,
because that's how we're actually going to extract the keys
later on.
We're going to start creating the actual script.
So now I'm going to create inside the ETL Basic
something that is called Connect Twitter.
You can tell I didn't have a lot of imagination for naming.
I'm going to use from config parser.
And I'm going to import config parser.
This is going to help me to actually get information
from the configuration file.
And then I'm going to use pathlib,
because I like pathlib to manipulate paths.
It makes everything easier.
And I'm going to use import my library to a pi,
because this is going to make it easier for all of us to access.
The next thing is to create my global variable that
is going to point to the config file.
And I do this using path.
For me, it's the current directory,
because I know that I'm there.
Config.cfg.
You can also use, for example, path resolve or path of the such.
Cool.
So that's going to generate the path for myself.
It's very nifty, because you only
have to append whatever subpaths you have.
Then we're going to create a config object that
is a config parser.
And the config then is going to read the actual config file.
And then comes the nice bit.
We're going to create an authentication object
from tupi.
And we use for this an OAuth handler.
And we have to pass our consumer key and our consumer secrets.
This is a way we actually authenticate into a pi.
And then the second bit of authentication
is your access tokens.
And then we're going to create a new object.
So after it has done that, it will return an authentication
object.
But you still have to create another object that
is going to be the actual API wrapper.
So for this, we're going to use the API.
And it inherits from our authorization handler.
And now what I'm going to do is I'm
going to collect some tweets that are in my public timeline.
So we're going to see what my friends are tweeting about.
And for this, I'm going to use this directive
called home timeline.
It has a lot of things already built.
That's why tupi is so easy to use.
And then it's going to print the text.
So find Guggen, Python, ETL, basic,
and then connect to Twitter.
I miss my parentheses.
So now what it's going to do is it's
going to connect to Twitter if it wants to do that.
This is a very simple connector.
There you go.
Because I didn't pass any information
on how many tweets I want to collect,
it just goes with the default. You can then
pass something in here that is the number of tweets
or for how long the connection is going to keep open
and things of the such.
But this is a very simple connection.
But it already tells you whether you
have connected successfully to the API or not.
And now the next thing it's going to create
is now that we are able to connect to the Twitter API,
we need to create a table that is going to actually hold
the different tweets or the different data that we're
going to be gathering.
And this is going to be living or this
is going to live into our SQL database or SQL data table.
So I'm going to look into the Twitter developer.
Object.
I almost forget to link.
But I just want to show you what we actually have in here.
There we go.
OK.
So by default, it's going to give you,
inside the Twitter object, it's going
to give you information of the user and the tweet itself.
And it comes in the format.
Well, you can parse it straight away into JSON object.
So if you're familiar with JSON parsing,
you'll know that you can access the different elements
inside it as you access a dictionary object.
Never mind.
So we're going to create a table.
We're going to create a simple stream listener.
And this is going to save the username of the person that
is tweeting the tweet content that is the actual text
inside the tweet, the time of creation
when that tweet was created, the retweet count,
if there are half any, and all the other things.
And then we're going to create a table.
So we're going to create a table.
The retweet count, if there are half any.
And also, each of the tweets that you create
have a unique tweet ID.
And this is very, very helpful sometimes
to do some sort of things.
In SQL, this is going to correspond to five columns
and an additional column for the primary key.
And these primary keys, if you're familiar with pandas,
is very similar to the index.
So it will allow you to uniquely identify
each of the entries.
You can think of it as a pandas, as a pandas index stuff.
So I'm going to create a stream Twitter.py script.
And again, I'm going to do from my SQL import connector
as my SQL.
I'm just going to walk you through here
and then copy and paste.
I don't have to tape anything.
As we did before, we're going to create our global environment,
our global variable for our database.
That is a dictionary.
We have already seen this.
Then we're going to create a database-related function.
This first database function is going to first connect me
to a database.
That what we did before in the script.
We're going to wrap it in a function
so we can actually reuse it a lot of times.
And we're going to wrap it around a try-accept
just to make sure that we catch any errors.
Because sometimes we can have errors with different stuff.
For example, if we didn't close our connections
or if we burn our user or the password and things of the such,
you might want to have a try-catch
and print the error for debugging.
And this is the nice thing that we're going to do
is create a function to create the table.
So inside the Airflow DB that we have,
we're going to create a new table.
And for this purpose, we first need
to connect to the database.
We do a dbconnect object.
And then we're going to create a cursor.
And this cursor is the actual instance
that allows us to do all of the extractions and queries
and insertions of data.
Sometimes, especially in Mac, MySQL gets a bit dodgy.
And it forgets that you're using the database
that you're logged into.
So it's always safe to have a cursor execute
use Airflow DB.
It's just for precaution, just to know that you're always
inside a database.
And in this case, because I don't
care very much about persistence,
I'm giving also this directive.
After you've connected to the database,
after you've recognized it, I want
to check if this table that I'm requesting already exists.
And if it does, just delete it.
Just drop it.
You can change that directive for if table exists,
then do nothing.
If table doesn't exist, then do actually create it.
And then we're going to create the columns where our data is
actually going to fall into.
And because the SQL queries are very, very, very long strings,
I just wrap everything in parentheses.
And I use f strings because I love f strings.
And then this also allows reusability
because you don't hard code stuff.
But you can actually pass a parameter
or the name of your table or your database.
Or the name of your table or your database's parameter.
Gives you much more flexibility when constructing stuff.
So I'm going to create a table.
However that table is going to be called,
I'm going to call it tweets.
And the first identifiable, the first row that is my primary key
is going to be called ID.
And it's going to be an int 11.
You have to specify what type of data it is.
And I don't want it to be empty.
So I say no, no.
And it's going to auto increment.
It's going to start from one downwards.
Then I'm going to add the user.
And this is going to be the username on Twitter.
And it's a bar chart because it's
going to be a variable character or bar query.
I'm also using timestamp for created
because I'm going to parse them later on with the date time
library so that they're in a useful format.
The content of the tweet, the retweet count, and ID string.
And then I bind my ID to my primary key
to be my identifier.
And then I take a cursor, execute this query,
close my connection, and close my cursor.
And just because I like seeing stuff,
I just give a print stuff.
OK, so you can go for a break.
Let's break up here.
And then we'll come back to put this together.
We're doing OK for time.
And during the break, I'll sort to you folks
that don't have their Twitter API keys.
Oh.
OK, the Twitter team are keeping an eye on your applications
because I pestered them a lot.
So check your inbox because some of the folks
are receiving approvals now.
If you've not received an approval,
go to the Google Doc, write your email,
and I'll send you the keys in an encrypted email.
OK.
Have, oh, you should all have, the ones that send me emails,
I reply to your emails.
The one that wrote your email on the Google pad, Google note,
I send you Twitter API keys.
Just ready to copy and paste into your config file.
Cool.
And just a recap.
So now we created our function to create a table.
So I'm going to copy this into.
So I already have all of this to make it easier.
Note that I added async true.
Python, well, 3Py should be updated.
Well, it says that it supports Python 3.7.
So if you have 3.7, it's going to complain.
And you can just remove the async.
So that means that it's just going to be single-threaded,
and it's fine.
Cool.
And then the next thing is we have created now
our database functions.
The first one that is going to allow us to connect,
and then the second one that is actually
going to create a table where I'm
going to put all my tweets in.
Now the next thing and the most important thing
is to collect the tweets.
And Twitter has a rate limit.
You can read more about that.
So that means that it's basically
to prevent bots and folks from downloading too much data
too fast.
And also to prevent you from connecting
to from 30 different apps or in different places.
So I hope my app doesn't get blocked.
Now the nice thing about TweetPy is
that you don't have to worry about it,
because TweetPy handles this rate connection limits
very nicely, very swiftly.
So that function that we created originally, that
is the connect Twitter, well, that little snippet
that we used before to connect to Twitter,
we're going to transform it into a function again
so that we can reuse it.
We're going to import a JSON library
to parse the tweets, to parse the JSON data.
And we're also going to transform that.
So I decided to call my function connectTweeter.
So it's the same usual.
I have my config file, parse the config file,
create my authentication.
The only difference, and you have to notice,
that in the TweetPy API, I not only pass the argument off,
but I also pass wait and rate limit equals true,
and wait and rate limit notify equals true.
So that's going to first, what is going to happen
is as we create our stream listener,
it is first going to issue a warning if we
are approaching rate limits.
And then when that happens, it's going to wait.
It's going to wait and wait to our requests.
Because I like, again, having intermediate stuff that
tells me that I'm doing stuff, I'm not adding logger
because we didn't have to do that.
I'm just adding a simple printf connected us.
And once I am connected, the Twitter object
should be able to extract me because I'm authenticated
as a check.
So people are going to be authenticated as a check.
The ones that have my keys.
But you only have read access, so you can't tweet on my behalf.
So I'm going to extract Twitter, me, and my screen name.
And that is my Twitter username.
Then it returns the Twitter object.
We're going to be using this a lot in the next stuff.
And the beautiful thing that is going
to connect the data, that is actually
going to collect the data, is the stream listener.
And Tupi has a stream listener class.
And we're going to inherit from that one.
Basically, it's going to keep our connection
to the home line open for as long as it has to.
And I modified.
I added a function that is called onError.
And this 420 code is actually the rate limit code
for the Twitter API.
If I hit that, it's going to complain.
And it's going to tell me, hey, what are you doing?
Then you also have two options to process your data.
You can choose using the onStatus.
And that is only onStatus stuff.
So that means that it's only tweets
that people are putting on.
Or you can use onData.
And that gives you much more width
of the actual collection of data.
So that not only includes statuses,
but it also includes direct messages
that you receive, or mentions, or taggings.
And you can also see your gifts there.
So because we already created that SQL database,
we already know what we're going to be extracting
from the JSON object.
And hopefully, yes, it loaded.
So now we can actually have a sneak peek
of what it has inside.
A tweet has, this is the basic information.
It tells you when it was created.
This is how the ID looks.
How the ID string.
They're the same.
Just in numerical or string format,
we're going to use the string one to make it more annoying.
The text, the user, and the entities.
But then inside the dictionary, we have more stuff.
So you have very interesting things,
like in reply to followers count.
If you look at the user part of the tweet.
Yes.
Bigger.
It's super big here.
Can you see better?
If you look at the user part of the tweet,
you can get the screen name, the location, if it's enabled,
whether it's verified, the count of followers.
So it's very, very rich.
The amount of data that you can get from the API is amazing.
And whether people have geolocation enabled,
you can also see the coordinates.
And there's another geolocation object called place.
And this is nice because it not only gives you the coordinates,
but it also gives you the country and the place type.
So depending on the currency, it will tell you,
I can only pinpoint this person to a country level
or to a city level or something else.
Don't use it for surveillance because that's
a prohibited use of the API.
So you can get a lot of information.
But for these purposes, we're only going to extract on data.
Again, I'm going to try to collect the raw data that
I get from the API.
And then I load it on JSON.
This is going to take your object,
parse it in JSON format so you can actually manipulate it.
There are many ways in which you can then
extract data from that.
But I just went for a very simple one.
And it checks first if text is present in raw data
because I'm not interested in tweets that are just a GIF
or that are just an image.
I actually want to see the text coming from it.
So if there is text, I'm going to first extract
the screen name from the user when it was created,
the text, the retweet count, and the ID string.
So if you look at the same columns or the same data types
that I created in my SQL database,
so they match one to one, I'm going
to create another helper function that
is called populate table.
And this is actually going to pass the data
from the populate table from this Twitter object
into my SQL database.
So I'm going to give you five minutes
to discuss with whoever is sitting next to you,
how do we create a populate table?
If you have any idea how you would actually,
once you have your streamer on, once you have collected a tweet,
how you're actually going to pass that into or persist
it in your database.
You have this example.
And it's missing the actual implementation part.
So I'm going to give you five minutes,
so you can discuss how you would do it.
OK.
So I think some of you, oh, this one is streamed to error.
So let me go to where I have this solution.
OK.
So we have this bit, and then we have the create table.
Then the next part is to populate the table.
So we created our connection, our recursor.
And the next thing is to create a SQL query.
In this case, it's going to be an insert into tweets.
And we're going to pass, again, the arguments in the same order
that we declared them first.
So we're going to be using user created
at tweet, retweet, count, id.
You have to make sure that they match the columns
that you created.
And then we pass the values with a percentage s.
Again, we have how many columns we said?
Five.
So we have five columns.
We're passing five values.
And then we pass the cursor execute to execute the query,
and we pass the values.
And then we do the commit.
If the commit is successful, meaning
that everything went to right is going to be committed
and is going to be persisted.
If it's not, we're going to have our database
is going to roll back and print an error.
Now, because it's too much to type for you,
if you go to flow tutorial, you're
going to see that there is a solutions directory.
And that has all of the solutions for the tutorial
plus more examples.
So if we go to ETL Basic.
Oh, nice.
People are fixing my typos.
I love them.
I pass them through stuff still, but cool.
So if you go into stream Twitter,
you can see the actual code.
Now, let me run it myself so I can actually
show you what it is.
If I do Python ETL Basic, then stream Twitter.
Oh, didn't like it.
OK.
Somehow it doesn't.
Oh, OK.
This is the async thing that I was telling you about.
I forgot to remove it from my code.
So if we are running in Python 3.7,
it's going to complain because it doesn't like it.
Remember that in 3.7 async, we became a keyword.
I'm going to remove that async.
So now I have my function that connects to my database,
my function that creates my table in my database,
then my function that opens my stream list in order to Twitter,
my function that drops my data into my database.
The way you would normally do it in a Python script
would then be create a function.
Well, put it inside your main function.
So if you have ifname equals main,
first you're going to create your table.
And I decided to call it tweets because it's easy.
We authenticate Twitter before we actually
start our stream listener.
We create our stream listener, and then we stream to 2Py.
So we pass our authentication.
We have to pass the stream listener.
And I'm going to give it a timeout of 30 seconds,
just in case if it's trying to connect or redo a lot of retries.
Then after 30 seconds, it just stops doing it.
So it doesn't take my bandwidth.
Once you have your stream, you can either stream everything
or you can filter specific words.
For example, I am only interested in filtering things
that are contained in Python, PyCon, Jupyter, and PyCon 2019,
because we're in PyCon.
So what is going to happen when I run this script?
It's first going to tell me that it was connected to my database.
Then it's going to create a table.
And then it's going to connect to me as whoever I am.
If it successfully finds a Twitter that has those search
terms, are they PyCon, Jupyter, because I love Jupyter,
Python 2019, it's going to grab it, call that populate table,
and insert a new row.
And you can see that it's actually telling you
tweet collected at and that it actually has been committed.
So that's a new entry in your database.
Then it will also give you some warnings or errors
like incorrect string value.
And that comes a lot when you have special characters
or other languages, when it can just parse stuff,
weird data formats, and basically all the niceties
and weirdness that you get when you're processing text data.
Because this string listener is going to be open.
Once you run it, you only stop it with Control-C.
This is the only way we have to.
Cool.
So now we have a full extraction part.
Now the next thing that we're going to do
is once you have your extraction part,
do you care about what we're going to do with the data later?
You're not just storing the data in a database
for the sake of it.
But you're actually transferring it
to downstream processes.
And there are different mechanisms to do that.
You can either use files like CSV files or text files.
You can use databases like the one we have or use cues.
For example, you can use things like Celery
to create your cues and have your workers
and your consumers.
So then the next step would be to create a transformation part.
And this is going to consolidate your ETL part.
So we have our stream Twitter one.
And we're going to modify it so that it also
contains language for our account and country.
Again, the solution is in stream Twitter out.
And you're going to see that it's the same structure.
What changes is the database construction.
So I just expanded it so that it holds more columns.
So it's now going to hold the columns that we extracted
before, but it's also going to extract the country
the followers sent the language because we're
going to be doing some plots in language.
So naturally, you also have to update your stream listener
to add this additional stuff.
Now, there is only one thing or one gotcha
because all of the places or all of the place entries
in the tweets depend on the user having their geolocation
services enabled.
And funny enough, if it doesn't find that,
it's going to be a problem.
And funny enough, if it doesn't find it,
all of the parsing is going to fail.
And then all of your downstream processes are going to fail.
So we have to add, again, an if else or a gotcha
or a try or a catch.
So if that exists and it's not known, then it extracts it.
Otherwise, it's just going to return a known value.
And when we transfer this into our database,
it's going to keep the known value.
So then it'll make it easier for us to process later.
It's exactly the same thing.
I added a start stream function because then this
allows you to disconnect from the stream
if there are any fatal errors.
Again, instead of you having a failure
and then trying to reconnect or your API or your app
or whatever you have, trying to reconnect multiple times,
once it finds a fatal error, it's just
going to disconnect automatically.
So that's going to save your threads as well.
And in this case, I'm going to create a new table.
So I don't overwrite the table that I have.
So I'm going to call it tweets long.
And again, it has a timeout of 30 seconds.
And I have to get rid of the async.
So I'm going to run this for you so that you actually
see what it's doing.
It's going to be a very small database, but that's enough.
So it's the same process.
Again, creates the table, connects to the table,
opens the streaming, and then starts populating the database.
So the next thing that I want to show you is I'm going to open
a JupyterLab so you can actually see
what the next transformation process is going to be.
And I have already this little notebook that
has an analyzed Twitter part.
It's a very, very simple script because we
don't have time to start doing NLP things or tokenization.
But Twitter data is very, very good to do tokenization,
well, all of text analysis.
So I'm importing the usual libraries.
And in the meantime, I'm leaving my database there to populate.
So in the meantime, I'm going to load.
I'm going to use the traditional libraries
that you would use to do transformations
and cleaning and filtering.
So again, I have OS.
I have path.
I have ref or regex.
I have my SQL connector again because I want to connect.
I have non-pine pandas.
Again, we have the database that we already know this.
But I'm going to create two functions.
The first one is imagine that after you
have created or cleaned and filtered all your data,
you want to persist them somewhere.
It can be in your Azure Blob storage
or if you use other services, it could be S3.
Or it could be your local database or local place.
Doesn't matter.
So it's going to take my database, whatever
that database is, find a table that I want to persist,
create a connection, and again, create a query.
Because I want to extract all of the tweets,
I just select everything from whichever table.
And then it verifies whether I have a directory called data.
And if not, it will create it first and then
save that into CSV file.
So I'm going to run this.
And then I have a data processing part.
So once I have my SQL, pandas also
is very nice because it can read SQL and interpret it properly
immediately.
It has these nice rubbers.
So this one, what it's going to do is, again,
the same connect to my database, create a cursor,
select everything that I have in my table,
start in a data frame.
So we have read SQL query.
I create a query that is all the thing here from the database
and collect the index.
OK?
So it connected nicely to my Airflow dot tweets.
Now I'm going to do a simple query.
So if I look at the database, how it looks,
it's going to be very small.
But you can see that I have, because I passed,
that the indexes I did, that primary key that I created,
it's properly indexed now.
So I have the users.
I have my timestamps, the data, the retweet count.
So let's imagine that you don't care about the retweets.
So you can get rid of it.
So you can say, well, clean that and extract all of the rows
that do not contain a retweet.
I only care about tweets that are original tweets.
And also, probably for parsing purposes,
you want to make all of your user names lowercase
or get rid of a special case, special cases
or have the actual encoding for certain characters,
depending on what your application is.
So I call this on my data frame and that does some cleaning.
But this data is not very exciting.
It's quite small.
So I'm going to call it on the tweets log,
the extended database.
And here we have more data.
We have on top the country.
The tweets don't have country, but we have number of followers.
We have language.
And then we can start doing plots, for example.
Probably I want to plot.
It doesn't like my path.
Probably I want to plot how many of the people
that are talking about Python come from the states
or from different countries or have a lot of followers.
So then you can go and talk to those
and have a lot of followers or two followers,
whatever you're interested in.
And then you can save your DF or your data frame
directly into a CSV file.
So if we look here, we're going to have our data and stuff.
And this is very useful because this now
gives us the whole idea of how an ETL pipeline would
look like using Python.
Now the next thing is, how would you normally
put this together?
If you were given this task, how do you
tie these scripts that do the extraction?
These scripts that do the extraction and the listening
and database creation and then the analysis?
If you don't have a workflow manager,
how would you normally do it?
Cron.
What else?
Bash.
Nice.
What else can we use?
I'm late.
Oh.
Yeah, you can use Lambdas.
Yeah.
You can use things like make or snake make.
All right.
So but the thing is, more than likely,
what is going to happen, and I'm going to just show
the simplest of examples, which is going to the basics.
I know, and it's creating a lot of different things.
The basics that I know, and it's creating an ETL.bash.
And it's as easy as calling the script that does the stream
and let us know when the extraction is started,
when the extraction was completed,
and then it started cleaning.
There is one caveat, because if you remember,
the stream listener is open until you interrupt it.
It's just going to stream forever.
So you're never going to get to journalized Twitter.
What there is, you can time it.
You can add an additional stuff.
Let me find it.
If you remember, we're filtering the data
as they come in their own data stuff.
So what we can do here is set a time.
So get the time when that starts and say time, time.
Use the library time.
And then subtract the self-start time.
But we can assign itself at the beginning here.
We can create an initialization function
inside my stream listener.
So you can do a def done.int.
And I can give it whatever time limit.
In this case, I gave it 60 seconds.
But you can give it an hour, two hours, two days, whatever.
And then you define your start time,
which is as soon as it enters that part or that queue.
And then assign a time limit.
Now, for those of you that are not very familiar with this,
we are going to do a time limit.
For those of you that are not very familiar with this,
we are using the super method.
So we can actually wrap around our custom listener.
And it initializes using not only
the default stream listener initialization or variables
or methods, but also this one that we are extending on.
So that way, it allows you to do this.
If the self timer is bigger, then it
will shut down immediately.
So that way, I can now call it homage
and then do an ETL basic.
So again, it's going to start.
I only gave it 60 seconds.
So as soon as those 60 seconds finish,
my stream listener is going to be killed.
It's going to do the analysis and cleansing.
And that is OK if you have one pipeline
that you need to look after.
But what happens when you have a problem?
So let's say you have a problem.
And you have to do an ETL basic.
And then you have to do an ETL basic.
But what happens when you have 100 pipelines or 20 pipelines
or, I don't know, 20 APIs?
Then that's when we have to start using things like Airflow.
And that's what we're going to start doing now.
Now, the beauty of Airflow is that it not only
allows you to define your workflow,
but it also takes care of all the scheduling
and running the jobs.
You still have to write CRUN, I'm sorry.
And you still have to understand what it's doing.
But it also ensures that everything is sorted,
that it's also based on your dependencies.
So you know what part of your pipeline has completed
and which not, and which do you retry.
Oh.
Oh, it doesn't like my back end.
OK, so you see that it actually completed the collection.
And then it should do the analysis part.
The correct solutions are all in that repo,
so you can follow along later on and then spend more time.
Also, the nice thing from Airflow
is that if your DAG fails, like in this case,
it's very easy to retry them or re-trigger them
so that you can actually do whatever is missing.
Now, when we talk about Airflow, we
have to have a short understanding of what
things are in Airflow.
The first one is a task.
And this is a unified unit of work.
In this case, for example, the task is going to be,
I don't know, stream tweets.
Then the other task is going to be clean data.
Then the other one is going to be saved to CSVs.
And a task instance is when one of these tasks
is actually running.
But it's not only when it has run,
but it has attached metadata on the status of that.
And it tells you whether it succeeds, a failure,
a skip, or to retry, or if it's queued.
And the way we organize things in Airflow
is through directed acyclic graphs, which
look something like this.
They have a start and an end.
It's very well-defined.
And they don't have loops.
That's why it is acyclic.
But it makes it very easy to track
the dependencies between tasks.
So you can say task A completes.
Each node of this is going to correspond to a tag.
And then that corresponds to a part of your data processing.
For example, in our case, node A is the polling data
from the API.
In this case, it's the Twitter API.
Then node B can be the code for anonymizing the data.
For example, if we don't want to know who the person is that
created the tweet, sorry, but we're only
interested in the text, we can do that.
Then node C can be checking that there are no duplicates,
checking that there are no retweets, that I
don't know if we're only doing analysis on Polish language,
that we only extract the ones that are in Polish language,
and so on and so on and so on.
So going back to good ETL architectures is idempotency.
Again, it's very tied to the sense of reproducibility.
And if I were to run a DAG today on the same data tomorrow,
and the same DAG on the same data tomorrow,
it should give us the same result.
And Airflow gives you very good options to do that.
It allows you to understand and keep track of when
your DAGs are running, what they're doing,
what are the intermediate dependencies
and the final dependencies.
And before we actually spin it up,
you're going to see that it's quite convoluted.
Airflow is very nice and very easy
to start working with in the sense of you can create
a simple DAG very easily.
But the actual architecture can be a pain,
because you need, on one side, your queue,
something that is actually going to send the messages
to your workflow manager and say, hey, you need to run this.
You need to collect the results from this.
We also need a worker.
And we also have a scheduler and a work server.
So a scheduler is basically CRUN.
So the work server, it has a very, very nice UI.
We're going to be playing with it.
It makes it very intuitive.
It's all built in Flask.
And the advantages, as well, is that it comes by default
with Ginger.
So you can create your own templates for your stuff.
It's very flexible.
Then the scheduler is actually what
tells you you can't schedule on run days every Monday
at 5 o'clock, or your report is going to go every other month.
We have our executor that is the actual unit that
runs the task.
And in this, we have a lot of flexibility.
We have a sequential executor.
Its name means that you can only run one task at a time.
We have a salary executor.
Kubernetes executor.
So it really, really allows you to scale
from running things in your local computer
to at a much larger scale and better managed infrastructure
like Kubernetes.
And everything is a code.
That's the most beautiful thing of Fireflow.
Everything is code.
Your whole workflow, all of your dependencies,
all of your parameters, everything is a code.
So you can version control it.
You can do it so that you have, for example, a Git repository.
And then you change something in your configuration.
And it will auto sync with that repository.
So you can almost imagine having your CI or your CD pipeline.
When you push code there, it will do some tests,
deploy automatically, or update your Airflow instance
wherever it is.
So that gives you a lot of flexibilities.
And we also have things called operators
that allows you to identify or run a task.
Again, the more atomic everything is, the better,
because you can run things in the most appropriate operator.
You have things like bash operator, Python operator,
email operator, simpleHTB, MySQL operator.
So they will do tasks that are native to their structure.
So bash, you can do all the things you do with bash,
with Python, so you can leverage the main advantages of this.
And when it comes to alerting and monitoring,
having the email operator, and now there is also integration
with Slack, it allows you to have real time,
or almost real time, notification and monitoring
capabilities.
So it's very straightforward to get started with simple DAX.
We can start, for example, with something
that will print a context.
And say, you create something, you pass an argument,
and that's going to be immediately printed out.
It doesn't have a console as such,
but it does have its standard output,
that is the Airflow logs.
And then the way you call that into Airflow
is by wrapping it around the operator.
You assign a task ID, and this is
one of the most characteristic things of Airflow.
Everything is identified by the task ID, and you define this.
The thing is that you have to be really good at naming
your tasks, because otherwise, if you have duplicate tasks,
the newest one will override the oldest one.
And a lot of folks use Luigi.
The most notable difference now is that Luigi,
well, that Airflow has been since 2016.
Yeah?
You were saying that it's really important to see
the integration and naming of tasks.
Is there a standard maybe for past lectures,
or for example, like in general?
Yeah.
I'm also wondering if you think that there's
some possibility that there's a thing in the case
that there's a similar pattern.
I don't think there is a standard convention.
People normally use just the same convention
that you use to create a function, so that's snake case.
But I don't know.
Do you just need to make sure that you have a function
that's similar to that?
I don't know.
You just need to make sure that it's very explicit in what
it does.
So it will depend again a lot on your company.
For example, where I was before, we
used to have a lot of DAGs.
And it would start whether we would have an identifier,
whether they were just for internal consumption,
client consumption, and then depending on the team,
and then just the name of the tasks.
So that is easier because then you can track
where the reports go to.
So if you have client, whatever it does, blah, something.
Also because you can't have a date because you're
setting recurring tasks.
But we're going to see it.
As soon as you open the dashboard,
you see when each task is due or when it's scheduled for.
So we're going to explore that in a bit.
But yeah, I don't think there is a well-accepted convention
anywhere.
I'll think about that.
Well, there are a lot of differences
and a lot of similarities.
The thing is you have to, again, find what works best for you.
What is your best option?
And what is going to satisfy your needs?
Again, it depends on your workers' needs
and your scheduler needs.
But generally, the scheduler, you
have to be careful because their scheduler in Airflow
is centralized.
So that means that it's self-aware of every single task
that is due to happen at all time.
That makes it easier to assign the load and the workers.
In Luigi, you have to create all of your tasks through the CLI.
And then what is centralized are your workers, not
your scheduler.
So I think that's a bit different.
So now we're going to be setting up our Airflow locally first.
It's well-involved.
It's well, well-involved.
Make sure that you're in your environment to start with.
So either you have a source-activate Airflow
AMP or a PIP AMP shell or whatever you're using.
And now we're going to start Airflow locally.
When you install Airflow by default,
it creates an Airflow home directory.
So if I go, for example, to here,
I see an Airflow directory.
And I'm going to show you how it looks like.
When it's started, when you do PIP install Apache Airflow
or PIP AMP install Apache Airflow or something,
it's going to create this.
So the very top is going to be your Airflow configuration.
We're going to modify some bits.
It also has logs, which is the logs for the whole stuff
that you have in there.
So that's every single dog that gets run, every single failed
dog, every single success is there.
And it also has the unit tests, the configuration
for your unit tests.
So I'm going to go to Airflow.
And because we're going to start our local Airflow instance,
you have to create a dogs folder because it will automatically
identify the dogs there and pull them in.
So if you go to wherever your Airflow home is
and create a dogs folder, then the next step
The next thing is we're going to be creating a lot of dogs.
So they're going to live inside dogs here.
But then we're going to have, as you run to different dogs,
different logs for each of them.
You'll also have a database.
And this database is basically where everything
is going to store it, all of your logs.
So it's also good practice to have something or a dog itself
that will do cleaning and maintenance
just to make sure that your databases are not growing a lot.
If you have XCOMs or mechanisms to communicate from one dog
to another or one task to another,
also those get all stored in that database.
So they can become very bulky.
So the next thing is going to be open from our Airflow home.
We're going to do some changes in our configuration file.
So if you open error, you should see the Airflow CFG.
You can change the location of your dogs folder.
But for this example, we're going to leave it in Airflow dogs.
You can use anything else, a specific location,
as well as logs.
You can also change the time zone.
But that is going to determine the time
with each of your single dogs is going to run.
So you have to be very, very careful
because you can't have multiple time zones, especially
if you have a cross time zones at work.
They can be problematic.
So you have to stick to just the one.
And then here is where you change the time zone.
And then here is where you choose the sequential executor.
For local experimentation, we're just
going to use the sequential one.
And remember, that only allows you to run one dog at a time.
You can have task executor if you do task stuff
for distributing data.
You can also have Kubernetes and the celery executor.
We're not going to use the celery now
because otherwise we would have to set up celery and rabbit
MQ, and it's too much fun.
Yes, so if you go to your Airflow directory,
it is all in there.
So you should see your Airflow CFG.
So actually, we need to make some changes.
By default, it uses SQL Alchemy.
So remember that at the very, very beginning of the tutorial,
we created an Airflow database.
So we're going to replace that with our, oh, sorry,
not this one, but another one that is down there.
It also gives you the option to change the concurrency.
You can tailor all of this to your needs.
You can create plugins if you want to create a plugin.
But it also has the URL, the endpoint.
When you go, when doing start it, it will always go to 8080.
But if you have something else or another app that
is running on the port 8080, you can remap it to another port.
This is one of the nicest things that it has,
but it's in very, very, very, very experimental stages.
And it's lineage.
And it allows you to track your data lineage.
And this is, well, I find it very exciting.
Because that means that not only you're doing your tasks,
but you're actually keeping track of every single change
and every single process and how one version of your data
differs from the other one.
It's fantastic.
Data.
Yeah.
It's very similar to have you, well, if any of you
have ever used PacketDorm or heard about PacketDorm,
that they keep like a data change log.
It's similar to that concept.
OK, cool.
So we have to modify here so that it actually
uses our Airflow database that we created instead of using
the default SQL alchemy.
So you need to find this broker URL
and change it to Airflow at Airflow,
well, Airflow Airflow localhost plan.
And then that ensures that it uses your, how's it called?
Your database.
Fantastic.
So we did this at the beginning so that we
didn't have to do it again.
The first step to get Airflow working
is we're going to start up the database.
So we do this using Airflow and a DB.
I don't know why I don't like it.
Oh, OK.
Sorry, I already have my database initialized.
So you can do Airflow upgrade database.
And actually, it's better if you have initialized your database
before and then you only want to get it running again.
It's better practice to do an upgrade DB.
So that's the first step.
Once you've done this, if you do an LS wherever you are,
you should be able to see your Airflow database there.
And this is not the SQL one, my SQL one that we created,
but it's the actual Airflow where all of our result logs
are going to be.
We're going to skip this celery bit,
but if you want to use celery in Revit,
that should be enough to get you up and running.
And now we're going to start the web server.
If you do Airflow web server and bind it to the port 8080,
you're going to see that it comes up with a lot of stuff.
And I don't know why it keeps saying about that.
OK.
Whoa, this is too big now.
Is that better?
So once you have your web server,
get your web server on and get familiarized a bit.
By default, it has a lot of operator, a lot of examples.
And for example, you can see the bash operator.
So you click on it.
Each of these represents a dog.
So it gives you the tree view, and it gives you
the understanding of how each of these tasks
is related to each other.
You can also see the graph view, which is the more, yeah, bigger.
Is that better?
So you're going to start your web server on your laptop
and start familiarizing yourself with it.
I'll probably make it easier.
There we go.
Oh, OK.
Yours is going to look different.
In my case, it already has been run before,
so it is marked as successful.
You're going to see that the changes are different.
For yours, the rim outside is going
to be white if it's a fresh or flow instance.
That means.
Oh, yes, of course.
So if you go here.
Give me a second.
So half that one.
There is another one.
So I don't know if it matches that already.
Because 3306 is where MySQL runs.
OK.
Yes, so the worker URL, and we have an SQL alchemy.
There you go.
So we have an SQL alchemy.
There are a couple of things that we can do.
So we can go to the SQL alchemy.
So we have an SQL alchemy there.
And it's going to point to the newly created Airflow database.
In the tutorial, there are details
for you to try with the salary executor as well.
OK, cool.
I forgot what I was saying.
Oh, so we have this.
And something else, it has a new function.
And something else that it has is a lot of connections.
So if you go to admin and go to connections,
you're going to see a very, very, very, very big list of things
that it can be connected to.
I have, for example, a custom Airflow DB there.
You can connect it directly to AWS,
to Azure Container Instances, to Google Cloud, Hive.
So you can actually connect it to a lot of databases
straight away.
Now, we're going to need to update this as well.
So we'll have to open the MySQL default.
And that is the SQL database.
So the connection ID is going to connect to MySQL default,
whatever that is.
And then we're going to use connection type, MySQL, local
host, and the schema.
So the schema for MySQL is a database.
It's another way to call a database.
So for this purpose, we're going to be using the Airflow schema
that we created at the very beginning.
We're going to log in as root.
Or you can log in as your Airflow user.
Either are fine.
And then your password, you have to type your password here,
whatever it is.
So you can log in as root.
And then your password, you have to type your password here,
whatever it is.
You can fill or not the port, because by default,
if it doesn't have a port, it's just going to default back to 3306.
So you can leave it.
If you wanted to be in a specific different port,
because that's how you've configured your SQL instance,
you have to update it there.
So we have MySQL, default, MySQL, local host, Airflow.
That is the database that I'm going to connect to, root, and password.
And I'm going to save it.
But you can do a lot, a lot of things.
You can connect to a lot of stuff here.
It's very interesting.
Cool.
So we've already done this.
And we're going to get started with some commands that we can do from the
common line.
Well, some things that we can run from the common line.
And there are a lot of things that you can do from the common line and so
many other things that you can do that are probably better off from the UI.
Let me make this super huge.
Is that OK?
So at the moment, I have not created any personalized DAG.
But if I run, for example, Airflow list DAG, it will deploy all of the DAGs
that you have.
For you, you're going to have all of the example that is example bash,
example branch, blah, blah, blah, example XCOM.
In my case, I'm going to have the generate Twitter DAGs that we're going
to be doing in a bit.
I have also a Hello World and Twitter links.
So that's how you can see all of the DAGs that you have registered in your
Airflow instance.
Let's take, for example, the tutorial task.
So if we use Airflow list tasks, tutorial, and then we use the argument
dash, dash, three, it tells you about bash operators.
So it tells you in that same tree graph that we saw before in the UI,
it's the same way that it gets displayed but on the common line.
I personally prefer looking at it on the UI because it makes more sense.
Now, imagine that you have a DAG and you don't want to yet commit to start
running it actually in production.
You can test your UI.
So you can do Airflow test tutorial, print date 2019, 05, 01.
Okay.
But I'm going to show you first the code for this DAG so you actually
understand what is happening.
So if we go onto tutorial, you have these notes.
And you can click on code.
And I'll tell you the code.
So it imports libraries and then it creates the default arguments.
We're going to create our own DAG in a bit so we can actually explore what
these default arguments are.
And then we can see that it's actually going to create a new DAG.
So you can actually explore what these default arguments are.
And then what is going to happen is you can define a lot of stuff.
Normally you can define who the owner is.
In this case, is there a flow because you want to give Airflow as much
autonomy as possible.
You can say whether it depends on past or not.
In this case, it's false because it's a completely independent task.
So you can set the start date.
And this is very important because it has to exist in the sense that you
can't run DAG before the time exists.
So you have to, let's say if you're going to be doing a task that runs
every week, you have to at least leave a period of time before the task
actually starts.
Because otherwise it's going to complain that the time didn't exist.
And I'm going to show you a better example of this.
Then you can set whether you want to receive emails on failures, whether
you want to receive emails on retries.
And this is very important, how many retries you're actually going to
allow.
If your task fails, how many retries are you going to give?
And then you can also specify the time between retries.
So if you have some complex infrastructure that needs time to consolidate
and to reconfigure itself, you might want to extend this time.
If you don't have any other scheduled task or task in the queue, it's very
easy and you can reduce this to, I don't know, 60 seconds or one minute,
two minutes.
You also have things to define your queue, how your queues are assigned,
how your pools are filled, your SELAs, and you have a lot of things that
you can configure.
And here you create your DAG object.
And this name is the name that is going to be displayed in the UI from
Matter.
And you can also add a description.
The description doesn't get seen at the beginning, but it's good to have.
Another way we define this is creating individual tasks.
So in this one, you have a bash operator that is going to print a date.
And then you have, after that has completed, a bash operation that is
going to apply a bash sleep for five units of time.
And then it's using ginger templates.
So here it is doing ginger templating here.
And finally, display the parameters that you run.
So now it's going to make more sense if I run this.
And then it tells you that it runs the command date, what was the input,
when was the date, and what was the exit code.
And the important thing is that when you run your tests, your air flows,
your DAGs tests, they don't get whatever the status is, if it's failed or
passed or whatever, they don't get persisted in your data.
So you can run as many test runs as you want.
So that is the template.
So if you do the, that was a print date.
But what about if we do the template of worm that is the one using the ginger
syntax?
So it's actually filling in the dates that you passed, the parameters that
you passed, and they're being directly replaced into the ginger template that
you had.
Okay?
So if you go to our flow, you're going to notice, for example, if I start
this task, okay, if I go here, it doesn't tell you when it is next scheduled for
you.
And that is because we've not started the scheduler yet.
So we've started, we have an initial time, and we have an initial time to
start the test.
So that's the time that we're going to start the test.
So we're going to start the test.
So we haven't started the scheduler yet.
So we've started, we have initialized our database.
We have our web server, but we still have to initialize our scheduler.
So you have to do this from another terminal or another common line.
So you have to do airflow scheduler.
And it's going to keep streaming out, on your standard route.
Okay.
And because in this case, we're using the local executor or the sequential
executor, it will tell you that actually you can only use parallelism as well.
You can't do multithreading or any of the such.
And behind the scenes, these schedulers are actually going to make sure that
things are up to date.
So we can now call go back to our terminal and do our flow run.
Oh, I have two.
Example bash.
Operator.
Run me.
Oh, why do I have that weird day?
I'm going to say 2019 05 01.
So when you do that, it actually tells you what executor it is using.
It then tells you that it's feeling the dog and that it's running the dog.
If we turn it on, it will tell you when is the last run.
And you can start it.
It's similar to doing this.
It has a little bit here.
Sorry.
It has this little trigger dog button so you can press it directly.
And hopefully, you'll straightaway see that it's running.
So the status of that is going to change to green.
I personally like this better.
Okay.
I'm going to have to plug my laptop.
I find that better because it helps me visualize much more where the tasks are
taking place.
Sometimes take a bit to fill in.
And then if you click on the task, you can also see when was the last successful
one.
And follow a traditional cron to do this.
I killed it.
There you go.
Now, you're going to notice as well that it has some nice syntactic sugar.
There are some very nice things.
And you can have this decorator style things.
So you can do daily or this is only going to run one.
Or for example, I have this generic Twitter dogs that we're going to do later.
And it's daily as well.
We have this hello world that we're going to create.
So you can use more traditional approaches like cron stuff.
And you can go to crontab group and that will help you.
Or you can use the decorators.
The decorator style.
So I'm going to give you five minutes so that you can try and check some of the
example dogs.
Familiarize yourself with how you actually run it, how you're scheduling it,
and getting them up from the UI or using the CLI before we start actually
writing tasks.
So I'm going to give you five minutes.
So you can see that I'm going to give you five minutes.
So you'll lose the cron.
Well, the scheduling.
Yeah, you'll lose the cron.
Yes. So when you turn them on,
that's enabling it.
So the scheduler keeps monitoring
because it has a heartbeat.
So that is the thing that it does.
It has a heartbeat.
So every so often it checks whether a task is due,
whether a dog is due.
So it's constantly checking,
and when the time comes, it'll spin it off.
It'll start it off.
Oh, it tells you if they were started manually.
So...
So if I go to the bash operator...
Where is it?
Tells...
No.
Task drives.
Let me check where it is.
Oh, here it is.
There is a part where it actually tells you who...
There is a part.
I can't remember exactly where it is,
but...
Oh, there it says.
Yeah.
So if you hover over those little buttons
that indicate a state,
if you hover, you'll see that it has a scheduled manual.
Could you see it?
Where is the verbalized schedule?
So if you click there...
In the run...
Yeah.
So you can differentiate
if they were manually triggered.
So you have scheduled, and then you have manual.
So if I run it in A,
it would be a...
If I run it in A,
Airflow run,
bash operator,
manual...
Yeah, that would be a manual.
Yeah, so it does...
Very equivalent if you go and press a button,
or you just start it from the CLI.
Yes.
Oh, you mean the web server?
You could do everything manually.
You could do everything from the CLI.
So if you didn't have the web server,
it doesn't give you the graphic interface,
but you can do everything from the CLI.
So you can see Jerry Dog's,
you can test them from there.
You...
I'm not sure if you can set the connections there.
That's what I'm going to do.
So you can set the connections there.
That's what I was wondering,
because I was just like,
Airflow is a wireless system,
and I may not want to...
I may not want to be able to...
So you're able to give them any other way.
You're able to...
They're all...
They're all encrypted.
Well, everything that you have in your connections,
and we have also a variable section,
they're all encrypted,
and you can only access them through
the Airflow models.
So that's a secret ball now?
You can have... Yeah, you can have a secret ball.
Yeah.
So it's good to know that there's a kind of parity
between the command line and the...
Yes. Yeah, there is.
That's the only thing...
That's the only thing that I don't know if it's
the connections.
You can do
when you're
running on Kubernetes,
because you have your... You can create your Helm chart,
and then you can extend
your configuration.
So that's where you
can very easily add new connections.
I've never tried doing them from the command line.
Yeah, we can check that.
Yeah.
The thing is that also
it gives you... If you're using
Celery,
when you have the web server,
you can also use
Flour, that is the Celery
debugger.
And that exposes on
78, 78?
So it's another port. Yeah.
Yeah, we're doing sequential right now.
Yeah.
The Flour.
Well, you get Flour.
But also the thing is
the capability of the things that you can do,
because with a sequential, you can only have
one queue.
Basically, you get the one queue.
With Celery, you get up to
16 queues.
I think.
Queue.
Queues, yeah.
With Celery, you get up to 16.
Which is quite good.
Yeah, exactly. Yeah.
So that is a nice thing.
Airflow takes absolute care
of the workers.
For you.
That's probably one of the main differences
versus Luigi.
Because the scheduler is central.
So it just finds the first
available worker and assigns
it to a task.
In Luigi, your worker is tied
to the task.
Does that make
sense? Yeah.
Yeah.
The nice thing
that you can do if you have
your Airflow on Curinet is
auto-scaling.
Because you can use node pools and stuff.
Yeah.
If you want to take it into
production, it becomes
more convoluted.
To get the infrastructure right.
Security and
authentication.
The other thing that
we didn't want to do
with the
algorithm is
to have a
range for
adding and dropping.
Okay, yeah, yeah.
It depends a lot on your needs.
Yeah, it depends a lot on your needs.
For example, I very rarely
run Airflow locally.
Because of the nature
of things that I do,
I can't run it here.
I always have it somewhere else.
But what I do is
I don't have a permanent Airflow now for me.
Not now.
Before I had.
But now
I just have it and spin it
up and down as I need.
Because I already have
the deployment template.
So it's easier to turn it
up and down.
Well, on and off.
For, I don't know,
if I need it for a month or two months.
Yeah.
So now I have it there.
I'm going to show you
a simple way to do it.
But what I can do is
I can add the tutorial to get it working
on Kubernetes.
On the AKS.
If that's something that
folks would be interested in.
Cool.
Sorry, we're talking too much about
stuff. But yeah, that's a good question.
Pretty much,
if you didn't have access to the web server,
whatever you have
in the web server and what you can do
from the CLI are
paired up. So you can do
everything from the CLI. You can start
the server, you can start a
DAG, monitor it from there,
test it from there.
Cool. So we're going to now
create our first DAG.
We're going to have to
because in your configuration file
your DAG's folder
is in airflow slash DAGs.
Unless you changed it intentionally,
which is fine as well.
We're going to create a simple DAG
.py file.
We still have
make sure that you still have
the web server on
and that you also have the
scheduler on.
So we're going to create
where is it? This blue one.
Cool.
So we're going to create
inside my DAG's folder
a simple DAG.
And we're going to
create a simple DAG.
So we're going to
And we're going to
create a simple DAG.
And we're going to start
with loading the operators.
Sorry, loading libraries.
I'm going to use daytime
and time delta because
it makes it easier to
work with time and time
sums. Sorry.
And from our airflow
operators, dummy operator,
we have to import the dummy operator.
And as the name says, it's
an operator basically
that does nothing on its own.
It has no
kernel, no
many things.
And then airflow operator is
Python operator. We're going to import
the Python operator. If you do a lot
of Google, if you do some googling
around and look at
the workflow and examples of DAGs
on there, you're going to see that
a lot of folks import
from airflow operators,
import dummy operators, they do direct imports
that is
I think that changed from
1.8 or 1.10
at some point in airflow.
You're going to get a lot of errors,
a lot of warnings if you do that.
Cool. So our first
function is going to be the traditional
hello world. Yeah.
We're going to see why we need that.
That's fine.
So we're going to create
our
traditional hello world function.
So we define it as
def print hello return hello world.
And we're going to pass the default args.
I always use
default args because that prevents me
well, I'm lazy again
and I don't have to rewrite stuff.
So we're going to pass
the default args.
I don't have to rewrite stuff.
So the owner is going to be airflow again.
It doesn't depend on past.
And this is very important because when it depends
on past, you have to backfill.
So we're not going to be doing any
backfilling.
For me to start date
is 2019-4-30.
So it's just
going to increase.
It's just going to go from there.
I don't want emails.
I just left that email as an example,
but I'm not gonna receive any emails or emails on retry
because we've not configured the SMTP or server.
And I only want one retry.
And my time delta for my retry is gonna be two minutes.
So I'm gonna start it to my DAG,
and I'm gonna call it hello world
because it's easy to identify and describe it.
Then we're gonna do a schedule interval,
and how often is this gonna run for those cron?
12 minutes?
No idea.
12 minutes.
So it's 12.
12.
Okay, so it's every 12 hours.
Every 12 hours?
Yes, at 12.
Like every day at 12 o'clock.
So remember that in cron, I'm gonna maximize this.
So in cron you have minute, hour, day, month, day, week.
And then if you fill in again,
you have jury wildcard, so there can be any.
So the next time is gonna be tomorrow at noon at 12.
Cool.
I forgot where I was.
And now I'm gonna define my tasks.
So I'm gonna start with my dummy operator.
So it's just gonna be a task ID that is called dummy task.
Basically, it's gonna do nothing.
It's just gonna wait there.
It's like a sleep there.
And once that has completed,
it's gonna instantiate that Python operator.
And the task that it's gonna call is hello task.
You have to be very careful
because then we have to do a Python callable print hello,
and this has to match the name of your function.
So be very careful because we don't call the function
as or the method as we normally do it in Python
that we have to append the brackets,
but we only call it by the name.
And then this tag is gonna belong to that.
This task is gonna be part of tasks of the tag,
of this tag object.
So now I have two tasks,
and then we have to determine
the order of these tasks to be run.
So I have T1 that will precede T2,
which is equivalent to write T2 setup stream T1.
These are equivalent options,
so you can have one or the other one.
And an easy way to think about this is,
do you remember that node graph?
So this is the arrow.
Where is T1 going to?
Here you can say T2 set upstream T1
or T1 set downstream.
Okay.
So if you save this,
if you've typed this into whatever your,
your dog houses, you save it.
As long as your web server is up and running,
as well as your scheduler,
you should be able to see it straight away in your dogs.
Where is my hello world?
So I'm gonna turn it on.
Okay.
And you see that there has been two successes.
The last time it was running a worried hour,
but I'm gonna trigger it anyway.
Mm-hmm.
So if I go to the graph view,
you can see that very clear graph,
or that very clear resuccession.
Cool.
And then if I leave it as such,
if I leave it on, then the next time,
if I leave it like so,
then tomorrow at noon or at 12 o'clock, it's gonna run.
Okay.
Because I have UTC, well, because I have UTC enabled,
it is 1613 actually here.
But this is the start date.
It counts the start date
when you actually activated the dog.
Cool.
So if we click here, you can see the logs
either from your comment line,
or you can click on the task and then click on view logs.
And it tells you how many times.
Remember that we gave three retries,
so it's attempt number one of four.
If it failed, it would have started again.
It would have waited for two minutes and then started again.
Cool.
And then once this is completed, this one is queued.
Because again, remember that we're using the sequent anyway,
it has to be queued, because this goes afterwards.
And then this is attempt.
This one only has two retries,
because that's what we specified.
Not one retry, sorry.
Now, so you can, if you define in your default arguments
a global retry, then when you actually specify the task
inside your dog, you can modify or overwrite
any of those default arguments.
So T1 has three retries,
whereas T2 has the single retry,
because I didn't pass it.
It's just the default ones that I defined before.
So once this is completed, again,
sorry.
These changes to green, that indicates the success.
So it's gonna be automatically added.
So let me see.
Let's say that I have another dummy operator, right?
So if I do two, three, and I have a dummy operator,
I'll create a task ID called finale.
And then I don't care about retries,
and it belongs to that.
Oh, okay.
So you have that.
And then I said that it goes after E3.
After two.
Now, remember that the scheduler has a heartbeat,
so it's not gonna be automatically.
But you can go here.
What is that I have here?
This is a web server.
Oh, here is the scheduler.
So here it has been filling the duck box.
So it was a minute ago, so it'll take a bit to update.
But you should be able to see,
depending on how often this is updating.
So it should refresh at some point.
You should be able to do that.
But then the new task will only be run
when the next schedule run is due.
It doesn't run on update time.
Does that make sense?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Yeah, so even if you do an update on the dog,
they should be persisted in there.
Yeah, it's just gonna take a while.
But yeah, you can update your dogs.
But then again, it depends on how you have them
in production, how you actually are
updating them or uploading them.
So if you have something like blob storage,
it'll depend on how would you push them
or how would you update them.
This isn't gonna be served locally.
But it's gonna be pretty much automatic
as soon as you push it.
Yeah, for that, it's more like all of the full
this Python content, does that matter, right?
Everything is Python, yes.
But that's why you have also the bash operators.
So if you look here at the bash operator,
you have another one.
The HTTP.
We'll look at the code, for example.
Yes, so in the HTTP, like you're sending a HTTP request.
Well, you're using the simple HTTP operator.
So you have your headers, your requests, and your endpoint.
So it's still a Python wrapper, but you can use it.
The structure itself, whatever operator you're using.
In that case, you can use, that's why you have bash
and soft, but also you have a lot of overflow hooks
that hook to other self-like SQL
to actually extend the capabilities
without you having to add more operators,
if that makes sense.
Cool.
So now we're gonna, if you remember that Twitter pipeline
that we created, the goal will be to try
and get it on Airflow.
Instead of having all of that, that we had a Python script,
we'll have to do a lot of refactoring
to actually put it in a form of a DAG
so that every day you can choose an hour,
two o'clock in the morning.
I choose random hours, like three o'clock in the morning
where there is very low volume of stuff.
So that one that we did, to extract the tweets,
then do a bit of analysis, how would you do it
so that it becomes a DAG?
You'll have to do a bit of thinking.
And I want you to do it in pairs,
to do a lot of pair programming.
You can start with something very, very simple,
like just do, start with a Twitter query.
How would you would do the Twitter query
so that it runs every day?
And then start, how would you do the Twitter query
plus the database saving and stuff?
Does that make sense?
And I'll be helping you, well, I'll be around.
I have the solutions, but I want you to try
and start thinking about how you would refactor it
into a proper DAG.
Oh, yeah, no, that's not in the GitHub.
But I've not, the only changes,
if you don't have your database by default now.
That's fine, there you go.
Okay.
So.
Oh, yes.
Sure, cool.
Something that you might want to look at
is this thing called my SQL hook.
Air flow.
And I can't find a documentation.
Oh, here it is.
So if you think in terms of tasks,
let's just start breaking that ETL in number of tasks
and then that will make it easier for you
to start refactoring the code.
So what would be the first task?
The listener, yeah, creating your listener,
whatever it looks like.
But then you're gonna have to have a different approach.
For example, it'll have to be a timed listener
or have a maximum number of pages
or a maximum number of queries that you can run.
Okay, yes, yeah, so the first one will be the listener
and then the second one will be.
The cleaning, yeah, whatever you're doing.
Cleaning, filtering, whatever it,
then you can do, for example, a plotting bit
and a reporting bit or something of the such.
I wanted to work in Paris to try and get
some sort of listener, a listener of some sort first.
Working.
I've only done like four or five.
I have my Airflow running here and it's on the local,
like here, can I go?
Sorry.
I thought we still had 10 minutes,
but now it was a 10 minutes on top of 12.20.
So on there, if you go on the repo,
that is the one that I shared here,
if you go to solutions, I have two more docs.
It's just so that you can follow along.
And here is the Twitter Airflow
that will do a more refined version
of the Twitter ETL that we did.
And it includes everything and collating tweets,
but instead of using a stream listener,
it's using a cursor and it's based on number of tweet pages.
So that'll make it easier because you don't have to time
your stream listener, what actually you fill in a page
of tweets.
And then there is another example with so dogs
so that if you have your dog with a parameter,
let's say I'm looking for the hashtags,
PyCon, Python and tacos, whatever.
So for each of those parameters, you have a base tasks.
I am actually going to show you here.
It's gonna be super quick and you can go for your lunch.
And then it creates sub dogs depending on how
your parameters are defined.
So if you look in the graph view, it looks like this.
So you have your initial filter
and you generate your search terms
and then it expands into as many dogs.
So this is very useful, especially if you're using
Kubernetes or Celery because you can run
all of this in parallel and then they'll go back together
to finalize your dog.
So those things are very, very useful as I said,
if you have tasks that you can actually run in parallel
and then bring back together.
I have the instructions for you to run a experimental,
well like an R&D, Airflow on Azure
and you can use your credits.
It's very, very simple.
But if you want, if you're interested in actually having
a Kubernetes powered Airflow instance in Azure,
I will be writing a mini tutorial or a mini walkthrough
so I can always add it to the read docs
that I already have if that's something
that you would be interested.
And you can follow along.
You have $200 of Azure credit
and those are gonna last 90 days.
So you already have them, make sure that you use them.
Because otherwise, they're just gonna die.
And I'm gonna be around if you want to ask any questions.
Remember to fill in your survey.
And I have some nice Python stickers
if you want some stickers.
I have Clippy stickers as well if you like Clippy.
Thanks for spending all your morning with me
and hearing me talk all the time.
Thank you.