All right, good morning everybody.
Thanks for waking up early to come nerd out about APIs today in our tutorial this misty
morning.
My name is Dave Anderson.
On Twitter I'm Dave Anderson without the vowels.
Our tutorial today is called building evolutionary API in Python with GraphQL.
Before we get started, a little bit about me.
I'm a lead developer consultant at Stride Consulting based out of Manhattan, New York.
I'm also cohost of the definitive developers podcast, the rabbit hole, where we talk about
human vectors of software engineering as well as fun new tech like GraphQL.
That's episode number 52.
Have a listen, like and subscribe and all that.
I've worked with GraphQL for almost two years now on several projects helping various companies
rebuild their stack with similar technology to what we'll use today.
Python with Django, Graphene, JavaScript, Apollo and React.
Stride's hiring for software development consultants to co-locate with clients in New York if you're
interested so feel free to chat me up.
I also wanted to talk a little bit about you guys since this is a conference, we're here
to network.
I really appreciated you guys taking the time to respond to my survey.
It was great hearing about your interests and backgrounds.
People were enthusiastic about all kinds of things from medieval times to westerns and
APIs of course.
People were coming from such distant locales as Boston and Taiwan.
Software engineers working in all kinds of fields like finance, construction, materials
and all kinds of different angles of the technical spectrum.
Lots of experts in Git, but some newcomers, both newcomers and experts in Django and unit
test.
All kinds of people today in this tutorial.
Before we get started, I just want to take a couple of minutes, maybe two minutes to
meet your neighbor.
One of my favorite things about coming to conferences is getting to meet people.
So given the crowded room, it might be a little more difficult for me to meet everyone, but
we can meet a couple of people and it might be good to find out what we're looking to
get out of the tutorial, what they might be unfamiliar with being Django, Git testing
or some other technology and if there's a way we can help to meet each other's goal.
We're going to be collaborating together on exercises, so hopefully this will be helpful
and know where everyone else is out and we can move through the exercises quickly working
together.
So yeah, just take like maybe two minutes.
All right.
So I know we're having fun chatting up.
We're going to collaborate a little bit more later.
So yeah, let's get back to it.
Why are we here?
We're here to talk about...
Oh, focus.
GraphQL.
What is GraphQL?
That's the first thing, right?
Some of you guys may be familiar with it.
GraphQL is a query language for your API, basically meaning much like SQL, you can specify
the fields that you want to get out of the API and get exactly what you've asked for
in response.
So GraphQL is a specification.
It's implemented in many languages and frameworks.
The ones that we care about since we're at PyCon is Python and Graphene particularly.
GraphQL provides a system of constraints that help us drive a constantly evolving API.
So one of the things that we like to focus on today is how these constraints that Graphene
and GraphQL put us in help us safely evolve our API over time.
So our focus today is going to be on answering questions like what is GraphQL and what are
its benefits?
How do I get started with GraphQL and Python?
What does it mean for an API to be relay compliant?
What kinds of changes are safe to make my API as clients begin consuming it?
How can I ensure my GraphQL API performs well?
How should I design mutation responses for my GraphQL API to serve client needs?
And why GraphQL?
So this is a lot of stuff, so let's keep moving on.
So if you go to graphql.org, you'll see six bullet points that kind of describes talking
points for why GraphQL is a helpful framework.
Let's dig into those one by one.
So the first bullet point is ask for what you need and get exactly that.
So like I mentioned before, it's a query language for your API.
You can avoid data overfetching by clients.
You don't have to worry about sending too much data over the wire.
It may be expensive to commute because a client may not actually need it.
It's easy for clients to express precise field-by-field data requirements which are lazily evaluated
on the server.
So if something's expensive, like I mentioned before, you don't have to worry about that
getting sent down to the client if they don't need it.
This also encourages concentration of business logic and the domain model and the API in
the back end.
So that means that our clients can be lean and focused on presentation of data.
And if we need to pivot or make a new platform in the future, like a mobile platform or a
public API platform, it's a bit easier because we're not as committed to it.
An example of that, recently, Facebook had a complete rewrite of their platform using
GraphQL.
And the client that they're using is very lean and mainly focused on presentation of
data.
How they were able to do something like that.
The next bullet point, one request for all your data needs.
This basically means that we can avoid n plus one for resources and clients.
An example of an n plus one resource, if you have a really structured rest endpoints, you
might have an endpoint for author and you want to get the publisher's address.
And so you would need to request the author and then the stories from the author, then
the publisher and then the address.
So that helps us to have more structured requests for data that can be all co-located together
for one page load or specific components and user interactions.
Basically a more declarative way to describe what data we're going to be using in our API
and the components in the front end.
The single endpoint also increases discoverability and avoids versioning more endpoints than
a squid has arms, which is nice.
The next selling point is that we can describe what's possible with a type system.
Everything in GraphQL is statically typed.
The specification requires a schema with every field defined and typed.
We can introspect our GraphQL schema in real time, provide documentation and powerful tooling.
And it's also a contract with our clients.
Clients themselves actually request the data using static queries against the static schema
ensuring that we have a safe contract.
And that's something that we can use to validate for breaking changes in our API, which can
be very useful.
We can also evolve our API without versions.
So GraphQL schema provides a safe guide for evolving over time.
The next point is about making changes and encouraging building only what you need now
and embrace the you ain't going to need it or Yagny and evolve as our needs become more
clear over time.
We also have first-class tools for deprecation and control changes to APIs in case we can't
evolve safely.
The next point is about moving faster with powerful developer tools.
So static schema typing and runtime introspection allows tooling to help you move faster.
An example of this is powerful IDE-like editors for rapid prototyping of queries and clients,
like GraphQL, a tool that we'll be using today.
And also you can have a robust client in your front-end web application to manage concerns
like caching and asynchronous actions, which let you focus on code that matters.
So an example of that is Apollo, which we'll be using today.
Can bring your own data and code.
So there's broad support across languages, starting with JavaScript, and over time more
clients are available, including Python.
The Python community is growing also, which is pretty exciting.
We've had Graphene, which is a very established and fully featured client or server that we
can use.
But there are also newcomers like Ariadne and Strawberry, and more people are getting
involved in the community.
So it's kind of an exciting time to be involved.
Lastly, GraphQL can be a unifying API for any kind of data source.
So basically that means we can leverage that as glue for other data sources and APIs because
it has that static type.
It's very easy to provide a back-end for microservices, other data sources.
It can also be a back-end for front-end for almost anything.
So GraphQL can be a gateway that allows us to cater to the needs of mobile, web, and
outside clients.
So let's talk some logistics before we get going.
I think some of this may be a repeat if you've reviewed the references and stuff, but I'll
try to get through it for anyone who may have missed those.
So the general schedule for the workshop, I'm going to be trying to follow Pomodoro
25 minutes on, 5 minutes off, where we can get some water or ask some questions.
Have a handy-dandy clock running right now, so we have about 12 more minutes on this pond.
We'll also be doing lectures and exercises, going through GraphQL and Graphene basics,
CRT, XLA compliance, schema evolution, performance of APIs, and mutations and client side concerns.
General principles with designing this tutorial, I would definitely encourage you guys to pair
on exercises to share your expertise and help each other move through the exercises, and
also have a little bit more fun, hopefully.
The tutorial code kind of tried to follow these general coding
practices where the API code is very simple.
Most of the logic is in the models and service layer.
We drive solutions for the exercises in all these
with tests that are already prepared for you,
so you'll know when the solution is right.
And we model our API and coordinate the code.
So each chapter has at least one branch in the Git repo.
We'll start with the branch chapter one.
And some chapters have multiple branches.
We'll indicate which branch should be checked out
for the exercise.
The project set up is in the readme.
There's a pretty self-explanatory invoke script
that will help you get set up quickly, I hope.
There are some compatibility issues with Windows.
So running the check and start commands
may not work properly on Windows.
But you can just use the pipen script that's
listed in the readme instead of that.
Also in the repo is a references file
that some of you may have seen already.
This kind of has some basic commands
that you will need to do.
Pretty much for our purposes, we just
need to check out chapters and make our working tree clean.
So either save the work in progress
or reset or stash the work that you have.
For our Python environment, anything above 3.6
should work fine.
But I'd recommend the latest Python.
We'll be using pipen for the virtual environment
and also using pipen script's functionality
to centralize all the useful commands that we will be using.
Like I mentioned before, using invoke as a task runner
and pipen script for our build scripts.
So there are some nice tasks that you
can use while you're going through the tutorial.
I'll call them out in the exercise explanation as needed.
But if you want to poke at it a little bit,
you can list the tasks using invoke-l.
And each of the tasks has some corresponding pipen script
that it's deferring to.
So for this code base, we're using unit tests for testing.
They're pre-written for each exercise.
Basically, if you run the tests, you'll
know if you're implemented properly or not.
We're using pilant and mypy for linting and type annotations.
Type annotations hopefully are useful for folks here,
even if you've haven't seen them before.
Basically, we have the argument here, which is root,
and then the type that that argument is.
So in this case, our root is a story model from our Django
RRM.
And this info is from Graphene.
It's the resolve info.
And display is just a string.
We also have the return type here, which is a string.
So hopefully that demystifies some of the weird arguments
that you might see flying around in a GraphQL resolver, which
we'll get to a little bit later.
We're also using Django.
You'll have to write some Django during some of the exercises.
But the key commands are kind of here
and listed in the references.
So hopefully your neighbor is familiar with Django
if you're not.
So finally, getting to GraphQL and Python.
Graphene is our focus today.
It's a code-first library, meaning
that we will write Python code instead of defining the schema
through the GraphQL schema definition language, which
a library like Ariadne, which is another newer GraphQL library
in Python, uses.
So in Ariadne, you would write a special GraphQL syntax
for defining the schema and then write Python
to bind that schema to your Python models.
Ariadne also supports asyncIO.
There are other newcomers, like Strawberry,
which is code-first as well as Graphene, asyncIO
and uses data classes under the hood.
So yeah, it's an exciting time to be involved with GraphQL
and Python.
So let's get into the actual material.
So to start off with, let's just have a simple API, just one
resource, listing stories.
So how would we get a list of the titles and authors
for those stories with REST and GraphQL?
So with REST, to get the stories and authors,
story titles and authors, we don't really have a schema.
It may be documented in something like Swagger.
We may have some other generated documentation or a readme.
We may ask somebody which endpoint to use on their team.
But eventually, we'll find our endpoint.
So we'll get our API V1 stories.
And we'll pass an argument for how we want the name to display.
And then we'll get a response, which
may be a little bit more data than we really need right now.
So with GraphQL, we have a schema that's defined.
With Graphene, we don't write this schema,
but we can generate it from the code that we've written.
We'll get into a little bit about what
these different parts of the schema are.
It's useful to know generally what the GraphQL STL syntax is.
So that way, if you are interested in using
or JavaScript library, you can read the documentation,
understand it.
When we have that schema set up, we'll send a query.
And we'll get back some data in the same shape that we asked for.
So let's pick apart each of those pieces now.
The first piece is the schema.
So as I mentioned before, this over here
is our schema definition language
that describes our API, the fields that are available.
We have a root query, which is basically the entry point
to our API.
We only have one field on the entry point, which is stories.
And it is of the type story type, which we define over here.
So that's a custom object type that we've defined.
And that object type has fields using
scalars, like strings and ints and floats.
We can indicate required fields with a bang, an exclamation
point there.
We also have arguments that we can define on any field at all,
which is incredibly useful for describing the data
requirements for our front end.
So in this case, we have a name field.
And we pass an enum to indicate the display format, which
in this case is first or last.
We also have array fields.
So just like in Python, those are the array fields.
So just like in Python, those are
indicated with square brackets.
And we can also define enums, lists of related values
that we can use in the API.
So next, we are writing a query against that schema.
So here we have the optional query keyword.
In most cases, that's understood.
But it's useful to include that sometimes.
We also have an optional operation name.
So we can call our query anything we want.
It's just a convenient thing for our clients to use.
So we could call this query pants if we wanted to,
and it would be fine.
This is our field on the root query.
So we have stories on the root query.
That's our first field that we're fetching.
We have a selection set of fields on the object, the
fields in the selection set, and the arguments and values
for those arguments.
So when we send that to the server, we're going to get
some JSON results back.
And those JSON results are going to be exactly in the
shape of what we asked for.
Only the fields that we've asked for in the selection set
are evaluated.
So if we need to change data, we can write a mutation.
So in REST, we might write a put or delete or a patch.
In GraphQL, it's only a mutation.
So in this case, we still define a schema.
We send the mutation, which looks very similar to the
query, except we have a mutation keyword instead of a
query keyword.
We pass some input variables in our arguments.
We do some operations.
So we create the story.
And we get back the data using this story type.
So this is exactly the same story type that we defined
earlier for our queries.
So it leads to some good code reuse.
We don't need to re-implement the wheel.
And the user has a lot of flexibility as to what data
they fetch from that.
Like if we had other connected types, we'd have
on that story type, we could keep fetching all day.
Cool.
Yeah.
Actually, we have a mic for questions.
So I was just going to ask about questions.
In both the two slides here, you mentioned create your
schema.
That's on the server side that the API developer would do,
correct?
That's right.
The schema will be defined on the schema.
Or the server side.
OK.
And the other queries that you're doing are pulled from
the schema.
The queries are sent by the client to the server.
And they'll match up with the schema that we provided there.
Cool.
Any other questions?
I think we've got one more minute.
Yes.
The slides will be available.
So the question was, are the slides available?
I can make you want to follow along or something?
Yes.
It's kind of a small way back here.
The idea there is not that it's one slide, but that might
help.
OK.
Cool.
That's good feedback.
Well, we have our first palm break coming up.
And I'm going to try to make that available.
Sure.
So yeah.
Let's just take five minutes.
I'm just going to grab some water and make that available
for you guys.
OK.
So I made those available now.
So if you look in the Read Me in the repository, you should
be able to click the link and follow to the slides.
Just let me know if you're able to access it.
Yep.
Locking data packets.
Anything?
It won't be running forever.
And then you can know where the data is other than the
other side of the point.
My partner also had the same problem.
Yeah.
It was just saying locking.
And just, that's it.
Cool.
We will eventually come back.
I think I have one more point.
It's the data connection.
It's very hard to know.
And use your phone to help.
It's a profile.
OK.
All right.
I have many Windows.
If you could hear something, it would be really nice.
I'm not a robot.
I know Windows is long.
I got it.
OK.
That was part of the reason why I put that tutorial out.
I was like, how many people are using Windows?
No, but these are the only people.
Oh, are you?
OK.
I think it's probably the Wi-Fi.
The download speed is 0.3.
There's too many people in here, I guess.
Yeah, it's not even the main day.
That's not a good sign for Windows.
Yeah.
Any other questions or setup problems?
I'm getting an error on the Windows setup.
I'm not sure what it's saying.
It seems like it's saying it's not
part of the version that Mac has expressed.
OK.
It seems like that's a similar thing with the dependencies.
Well, it's not that it's changing.
It's that it's not changing.
It's on Mac.
And you're on Mac?
Mac.
I've got a minute.
I'm back.
OK.
All right.
So let's keep moving forward.
So hopefully most of you guys have everything set up
properly and there are a couple of issues.
One of the tools that we were using today
is called GraphiQL.
GraphiQL is a very helpful tool for exploring your API.
Basically, it's like an ID for prototyping queries.
So on the left-hand side here, we
have a query editor where we can write queries.
And it has like autocomplete and all kinds of helpful features.
On the right, we have the query results,
which is the data that comes back from our server.
We can also pass in some variables
into our queries when we're sending it to the server, which
we'll get into a little bit later in this talk.
But for now, don't worry about it too much.
So GraphiQL provides some powerful features
for rapidly prototyping queries for your API.
So we can run multiple operations.
So we have multiple queries here.
Each have their own name, their own operation name,
and we can pick them to run.
We can prettify our query and make it look nice
or check that it's valid against that schema.
We can also check the history of queries that we've run.
And probably most excitingly, you can actually
browse the documentation.
So you can search the documentation,
see what the description of all the fields are,
and really discover what kinds of things
are available in your API.
So some power user tips.
You can hit Control and Space to do an autocompletion hint.
In the query editor window, you'll
get that automatically when you start typing.
But it can be nice to hit that before you
start typing to know what you can even type to begin with.
You can also hit Control and Enter to run under the cursor.
So if there's multiple queries in your window,
Control and Enter will run that query
that your cursor is on right then.
So let's do an exercise.
So we'll try to pair up.
Ensure you're on the chapter one branch.
Open up this file, API Queries.graphql,
for some sample queries and instructions
on how to get started.
And run some queries in GraphiQL.
Just copy over those queries into GraphiQL.
Spin up your server.
And try to add some new fields, change some arguments,
explore the documentation.
Just get comfortable with using GraphiQL.
Yep.
Sure.
So if you start your server, you can go to localhost 8000
slash GraphQL.
And if you open this API slash queries.graphql,
there's some more detailed instructions in there too.
So let me actually pull that up.
Can I go to the white line?
Yeah.
OK.
So what exactly are we querying?
Is there a database locally?
Is there another one?
Sure.
So the question was, what are we querying when we run this?
So there's actually a database locally.
There's a SQLite database.
There's some Django models.
And next step, we'll dig into how that's implemented.
We take another four minutes or so
just to get set up and comfortable with that.
Happy to answer any questions people have to while we're
working through that.
Can we try the mutations file or does it need a variable?
Yeah, you can try that actually.
So there is a mutations.graphql file.
So if you're comfortable with the queries,
feel free to open up that mutations file
and take a look at that as well.
So let's see.
So that's a similar path to the queries file.
And yeah, you can just paste it in there.
And also, if you're curious to poke at something that's a
little bit more meaty than this right now, you can check out
this URL here, developer.github.com.
And then you can go to the next one.
And check out this URL here, developer.github.com.
v4-explorer.
So if you sign in with GitHub, you can actually query anything
about yourself on GitHub.
I have a sample query here.
So here's some comments that I had on GitHub.
And this API, the GitHub API, is actually one of the most
robust and gold standard APIs for GraphQL that's out there.
We have a couple minutes.
So this is the kind of craziness that you can have
with a GraphQL schema.
So this is GitHub's schema from their root query.
So they have organization, repository, repository owner,
resource, and all of that.
And then you can actually query the whole thing.
Repository, repository owner, resource.
Those are the root things they make available.
And from that, we can go take a look at repository,
see what fields are there, what kind of issues
are on that repository, what kind of users edited that,
so all kinds of stuff.
And this tool is driven by that GraphQL schema
that I was talking about.
OK, cool.
All right, why don't we move ahead?
Any other quick questions before we move on?
On the back?
Yeah, let's do that.
Well, let's move on to the next section,
and I'll explain that to you.
So now let's actually get to the Python part of this.
This was just like kind of a surface level GraphQL
explanation that we went through.
So there's increasing diversity in the GraphQL Python ecosystem.
So there's both code-first and schema-first approaches,
like I mentioned.
Graphene is a code-first implementation of GraphQL,
and it's one of the most established ones.
So that's what we'll be using today.
There's also bindings for Django and pretty much
any other popular framework like SQLAlchemy you could think of.
So we'll be using Graphene-Django bindings as well.
So kind of like to go to that question about what happens
with the server side of things, how does this query get
resolved?
So it kind of starts from the URL route.
So if anyone's familiar with Django,
we have this urls.py.
We define all the routes that our application
is going to serve.
In this case, we just have one endpoint
for processing GET or POST requests,
and it's just GraphQL.
That's the endpoint that we were using for GraphQL.
So Graphene provides this GraphQL view
that we can use as the view for that route.
We pass it the schema, which we'll define in code,
and we tell it that we want graphical enabled.
But you can disable it for production
if you don't want people poking at your API.
So the schema is defined through Graphene.
So we have our schema here, which we passed into our view.
We define a route query object, Graphene object type.
And on that route query, we define fields.
So we have stories, which is a list of story type.
And we define that custom story type up here.
So this is all analogous to the SDL on the left
that we talked about earlier.
We have our fields, ID, title, and subtitle.
We have an author name, which is camel-cased by automatic
with Graphene, so we don't have to worry about maintaining
consistency with Python's standards
and the web standards of camel-casing.
We'd also define some arguments as well.
So this is our display argument, where we have an argument.
Display takes the enum with the default value.
So each field in our schema has a resolver function.
So a resolver is a simple function
that returns the data for a particular field, which
will then be passed through to the next type in a graph.
So in this case, we have a field author name
that has provided data from the function resolveAuthorName.
So here's our field author name and the function,
our resolver, resolveAuthorName.
So the value object that we're resolving
is always the first argument of that resolver function.
So here we have root as the first argument,
and it's a model object.
It's our story model.
That's the same for all of these things in the story type
Graphene object.
So the root is the story model for resolve subtitle,
and it's the story model for resolveAuthorName.
Graphene allows us to have implicit resolvers
if the field name matches the attribute of the root value
object.
So in this case, the field is called subtitle,
and the attribute on our object that we're resolving
is also subtitle.
So we don't need to write that.
Query context info is always the second argument.
We'll get into that a little bit later.
You don't really need to worry about it
until you have some more advanced use cases.
Any further arguments that are passed into this function,
like display for resolveAuthorName,
are from our GraphQL arguments from the field
passed as keywords.
So any arguments on the author name
will be passed as keyword arguments too.
AuthorName will be passed as keyword arguments
to resolveAuthorName.
So in summary, resolver functions
help us answer queries.
So let's trace through a query and see
how those resolvers are connected together.
So queries are first parsed and validated against our schema.
So all these fields need to be in our schema.
The resolver function is cascade data from the root query
to individual fields.
So we'll start from resolveStories.
We'll get all those objects, all those story objects.
And then on each of those objects,
we'll resolve the author name and all the other fields
that we want from that.
So finally, we get that value, that string value
for author name.
So kind of like more diagrammatically,
like following the flow of that data through.
We start from the root query.
Initially, our root is none.
Then we resolve the stories, that story field.
Then our root value is all those stories,
which is then passed into each of the resolvers for story type.
So resolve the author name, the title,
the ID for the first story.
And the same thing for the second story, the author name,
title, and ID.
Yeah, if the attribute on the object
is the same as the field name, then it'll
just do a default resolver.
Cool.
All right, so let's do another exercise.
So this time, we'll be making a modification to the schema.
We'll add two fields, description and published year.
So ensure you're on the branch chapter 2.
If you open up API query story.py,
there'll be further instructions on how
to make changes to the schema.
And you can verify your changes through prepared tests
and running sample queries in api-queries.graphql.
OK.
I'm just getting an error when I try to run the query
suggested in chapter 2.
I think there's something wrong with that.
What is the data model?
Sure.
Let's take a look.
OK.
How's everybody doing?
Any questions?
Green build.
Yeah.
It's a little goofy.
I put the errors as a string.
But trying to write a resolver.
OK.
All right.
So yeah.
Let's take a look at a solution for this guy.
So our problem was to add description and published
year fields to our schema.
So the amount of code we have to actually add to this
is pretty small just to get the schema going.
To add the field to the schema, we
can just add description as a graphene string
and published year as a graphene string as well.
It's going to automatically camel case
so we can stick with Python conventions
and use published year.
A feature that I haven't really gone in here,
but we can actually add description string over here.
And this will actually go into our GraphQL documentation.
And then for the resolver function,
since published year doesn't match
with the story model field, which is published date,
we need to write a resolver function.
So basically, we pass through.
We have the root as our first argument, which is a story
model.
And we pull off the published date
and then take the year part of that and return it as a string.
If we don't return it as a string,
our graphene will coerce that value into a string,
so it's not a big deal.
But yeah.
Let's just take a couple minutes.
If anybody has any questions, I'd be happy to answer them.
Yep.
So the question was about performance and concerns
about this quickly becoming inefficient.
Because I'm sure your experience with Django,
you've spotted the n plus 1 query right here.
So yeah, we'll address n plus 1 queries in a little bit.
But yeah, if you don't address that,
then it can get out of hand pretty quickly.
So in this code base, we're actually using Django ORM.
So the question was, where is the integration point
with a back-end data store?
And let's just take a quick look at that.
So basically, we have these models that are defined here
for our Django ORM.
So all this is already set up with the fixture data.
So here's our story model.
And it has all these fields and relations defined on it.
And if you haven't used Django before,
it has very nice migration capability
to manage the database changes.
But that concern is kind of separate from the GraphQL part.
So if you want to dig into that, feel free to look at the references
that were provided for this tutorial.
Yep.
So this is a little code first, where you define the Django code
and the schema comes later.
I noticed that you do a schema file.
When do you do a schema file?
Every time?
The schema.py?
There's a pretty fantastic one in the JSON file.
Oh, yeah.
So this file is just for your reference.
Normally, you don't need to include the queries.graphql in your repo.
Yeah, in the back?
This bigger.
OK, it's not global.
I'll keep that in mind.
This is good, though, right?
A little bigger?
I understand you're back here.
Yeah, maybe I should...
Yeah, there are a couple seats up here, so if you're having trouble.
OK.
All right, so let's move on to the next chapter.
So a phrase you'll hear pretty often when you start digging into GraphQL
is this phrase, relay compliance, or relay standards compliance.
And it can be a little bit confusing about what exactly this is
and why you might want it.
So relay compliance is a set of standards created by Facebook
that are required by their relay client library that's used in JavaScript.
So it's not required by other popular client libraries used in JavaScript, like Apollo.
So you're not required to implement these standards.
But the standard does include some useful patterns,
so it's good to understand what they mean and how they're used
so you can make an informed trade-off about whether you want to adopt
relay compliance for your API.
The GitHub API that we were looking at before is relay compliant.
So they have that flexibility to let people use either Relay or Apollo as a client.
So what does it actually mean when an API is relay compliant?
So that basically means that we provide a mechanism for refetching the object,
a standard way to page through connections of lists of data,
and a structure around mutations to make them more predictable.
We'll dig into each of these requirements and how we can pretty easily satisfy them using Graphene.
So the first requirement from Relay is a mechanism for refetching an object.
So you may have noticed that our simple API right now only has the ability to fetch a list of stories.
So as our list of stories grows, as we get more data in our database,
obviously we won't be able to send all of the stories to the client if we have a million stories.
We need a way to page through those results.
Oh, sorry, skipping ahead.
Sorry. So we'll get to connections in a little bit.
But for fetching a single object going the other way,
if we just want one story, a particular story, what's a good pattern?
We could add a single story field on the root query and pass the ID to that.
Or we could follow Relay standard.
So Relay requires a node field and interface at the root query
that allows us to fetch any object that implements that interface.
So let's dig into that a little bit more.
So what exactly is a node interface?
So an interface in GraphQL defines a set of fields that is shared across types implementing that interface.
So in this case, the node interface just provides a single field to the type that implements it, an ID.
In Graphene, we just need to use this metaclass pattern,
like an interclass inside of our Graphene object
that has an attribute that specifies the interfaces that we're going to be implementing.
So this is pretty similar to a pattern that's used by Django and other popular Python frameworks,
so you may have seen it before.
So when we have an interface that we're resolving,
we need to know which type this particular object is that we're resolving.
So if a node can be either a story or an author or a passage or any number of things,
we need to know which of those things it is so we can pull off the fields from that.
We can apply our GraphQL schema to it.
So in Graphene, we write this function isTypeOf.
So that basically helps us determine if the object can be resolved with this type.
So we have isTypeOf, and in our case, we return a boolean
if it's an instance of the story model from our Django ORM.
If it's a story model, then we can resolve it using the resolvers
that we specified in story type, like those fields apply to it.
So when we want to query that node field,
this is what a query might look like.
We can pass in variables into our static query.
So here we have some variables that we might put in our query editor down here.
And we pass them through as these references,
this ID reference into the value here for the node ID.
We can alias a field to something more meaningful.
So node is pretty generic sounding,
so we can rename that in our results to story,
because that's what we're expecting back.
We can also have an inline fragment,
which only fetches these fields, the title and description,
if the node matches that story type.
So that's when that isTypeOf comes in handy.
The node ID value is meant to be human readable and globally unique.
So GrapheneBase64 encodes these ID values under the hood,
that encodes to the story type and the ID,
so the GraphQL type and the ID.
And it's going to be using that ID under the hood
to resolve which particular type should be used.
So the node field returns any type that implements the node interface
matching the providing ID.
So we don't really need to write much code for this.
Graphene provides a pretty good interface out of the box.
The one thing that we do need to write, however,
is a method that tells Graphene how to get that particular node
when it matches on it.
So it'll match on that name of the type, the story type,
and then it'll pass in that ID value into the getNode class method.
Oops.
So basically we'll get the ID through here,
and then we'll pass that to our ORM to get the story that we want
for that primary key.
All right, so let's just take a couple minutes
to try out a query on this node field.
So this is a little more complicated query.
We're using the variables.
So when you open up this queries.graphql file under chapter 3,
you'll have some variables here.
Just paste those into the variable editor in your graphical.
So you can see here I forgot to paste those variables in there,
so I'll just take those variables,
try to make this bigger for people in the back,
and I'll paste them right in here.
So we need to get the variable into the getNode class.
So we can get a list of all of the different IDs,
copy it from there, and get a different story back.
So let's just take a look at the list of all of the different IDs
that we have here.
So we have the first one,
and then we have the second one,
and then we have the third one,
and then we have the fourth one,
and then we have the fifth one,
and then we have the sixth one,
and then we have the seventh one,
and then we have the eighth one,
and then we have the tenth one,
and then we have the last one.
Just need one more minute.
Any questions?
in the make.
Sorry, I can't hear you too well.
Is there anybody who use IDs without base64 encoding?
Yeah, so if you don't use Graphene's implementation of node, then it won't use base64 encoding.
Not use the node interface, not use relay.
There are reasons to do base64 encoding that I'll get into a little bit later.
So there's some, it is a little bit weird, but like there are some good arguments for
using it.
You should get rid of display right there.
It doesn't need that.
Yeah, it should be good.
Okay.
Yep, one more question.
Okay, so the question was if you're using node, do you have to write get node for each
object that you have?
So if you're using something like Django, you might be able to write like a generic
implementation of get node.
I think with the SQL alchemy bindings, there is a default implementation.
But with like user access and things like that, there's often like specific concerns
that you might want to handle for each model individually.
But yeah, you would need to get node for each one.
Okay.
All right, so the next bit about relay compliance is the connection.
So like I mentioned before, we have a large, we have an array of stories here.
And as that list grows, we need a way to page through the connection.
Since we don't want to send a million records back to the client, we need them to tell us
how much they want.
So we need pagination.
So relay connection provides a pretty easy to implement solution for pagination using
Graphene.
So what does that look like in practice?
So this is an example of a query for doing pagination forward through a list of results
using the cursor API.
So first, we have this first parameter here, which is basically our page size, saying that
we want 10 records.
We have a variable here, the after cursor.
And basically that's saying we want all of the records after this cursor.
So the first 10 records after that particular bookmark.
We have a page info object here, which tells us what the last cursor or bookmark is for
this particular set of data and a boolean that tells us if we have the next page of
data.
We also have edge and node for each record, which is like a graph-like metaphor.
So basically the edge, each edge has a cursor, which is like a bookmark that you can use
for pagination, and the node, which is the actual data that we're looking for.
So everything inside of node is our story record.
So really connections use a cursor-based pagination API.
You might compare that with a limit and offset-based API, where you would tell it you want 10 records
offset from 100 from the first record.
The cursor API is opaque to the client.
It's again like base64 encoded, and it contains all the information needed to paginate the
results.
So you can have a very specific implementation of the cursor that is encoded for maybe doing
a more complicated query than just limit and offset, which can have some performance implications
if you have a large set of data.
So Graphene basically uses limit and offset under the hood for the cursor, even though
we use that cursor API.
The connection arguments first and last determine the limit, and the cursor is base64 encoded
again.
So the cursor itself determines the offset.
So here we have like an array connection, zero.
So that's the pagination style and the offset.
So you can write a custom cursor if you need to, but that's out of the scope of this tutorial.
So the connection API for cursor-based pagination provides us with a lot of things out of the
box.
So for us, we just need to write a very little amount of code.
So we write Graphene.connectionField, and that gives us all of our pagination parameters
first, after, last, and before.
We have to write a story connection, which inherits from Graphene connection, and that
gives us all of our page info and edges.
We give it a meta with the node type, and that will actually resolve all the nodes for
each record.
So just from three lines of code we have, or four lines of code, we have like a pretty
decent pagination implementation right out of the box.
We can use these arguments first and after with the end cursor and has next page for
paging forward, and these arguments for paging backwards.
So moving from list to connection, like we just did, that's a breaking change for our
API consumers.
And in fact, like adding pagination on any list is really going to be a breaking change,
so we want to consider carefully which fields require pagination up front.
And using connection instead of list doesn't require that much effort with Graphene, so
something to consider.
All right.
So again, let's try out some new queries.
So check out chapter 3b this time, and your API queries, GraphQL, should have some example
queries and more specific instructions about how you can page through these.
Okay.
Let me come over.
Yeah.
So one thing to remember when working with variables in your query, like we have here,
so we have this variable after cursor.
If we try to run that without specifying the value, and it's not nullable, so in this case
if we try to run this query here, that works because we have our variable specified here.
But if we get rid of that, we're going to have a problem because that's a required argument.
So we just put the value for story ID down here, and then it'll work fine.
For this query, we haven't specified that the after cursor is a required parameter,
so we can write fine without specifying that.
If we give a little bang right there, that'll become required, and it will complain.
But really, it's fine if our after cursor is null in this case.
So if I want to page through a random part of this data set, or if I want to page through
the next page, I can take this end cursor, use it over here, and then run it again.
So right now I have these three stories.
If we run it again, we get some other stories.
I can also just pick a random cursor. I can pick this one.
And now this next page will start with this result here, Raven Tower.
All right, so let's keep moving on to the last piece of this about GraphQL.
Did you have a question?
Oh, okay, back there.
Yes, you can definitely... So the question was, is it possible to have a lookup
not just by ID, but by a name?
So GraphQL is very flexible, so you can actually specify any arguments on any field.
So you can just arbitrarily specify argument on a field, and then that can be used in your
resolver to get the data that you want.
This is just one standard way to do it.
Any other question?
So the question is, do you have to implement node to be able to lookup by any other thing?
No. If you're implementing by node, this is just an interface that you can use to fetch any arbitrary record.
It's totally possible to use a slug or something like that to lookup a record as well.
But you're basically implementing a custom interface at that point.
Relay interface is standard for that Relay client library.
So the last bit here is structure around mutations to make them more predictable.
So from our perspective, this is actually pretty straightforward.
Graphene does most of the heavy lifting with this again.
So there's no big changes to the structure or behavior of mutations to comply with this part of the specification.
We still receive some arguments and an input.
We still change data in our mutation function, and then we send a response.
The big change that Relay needs is that it wants to have a standard way to receive the input or send the input in.
And it also wants the input and the payload to send back this client mutation ID without changing it.
So in practice, that'll look something like this.
This mutation is Relay compliant.
It has this client mutation ID, which is just whatever we want it to be as a client.
So I might call it like mutation one.
And when we send back the data, we just say, hey, this is the result for the mutation that you asked for, this mutation one.
And internally, that's used by Relay for tracking purposes, but not really important for most clients.
So in Graphene, the code is pretty simple.
We just inherit from client mutation ID in Graphene, and we get this for free.
So client mutation field is automatically added and sent back in the payload.
We specify the input that's passed into the mutation in this inner class, the input inner class with some fields that we want to send to the mutation.
So a title, subtitle, and description will be arguments that we can send to create a new story.
And that will be sent to the keyword argument here, the input data.
So to sum up, Relay compliance is just a standard with some good GraphQL practices.
It's pretty easy to implement with Graphene.
And you might want to consider carefully if you don't want to adhere, because adding connection or client mutation ID later will be breaking changes for your API.
So let's just take a couple minutes.
And yeah, if anyone has any questions, I'm happy to answer them.
I work with a lot of APIs on network devices and firewalls.
Do you think guys like those, all names work just kind of like that?
Would all of them have like the rest of the APIs?
They would have to change, they would have to add, they graph too well.
Wait, so the use case is like you have some third party APIs?
Yeah, I use a lot of third party APIs.
Yeah, so there are a lot of first party, or there are a lot of people who are building out third party GraphQL APIs, like GitHub, for example.
But there are also people who are doing like API gateways for third party APIs.
So like I mentioned in the beginning, you can kind of wrap a third party API in your GraphQL endpoint and then receive the result back.
So yeah, even with like microservices, like in internal services, people use it as a gateway, consume all of the data, and then send it back.
Okay.
No worries.
Well, the material is all there, so you can feel free to go for it or email me with any questions.
Really appreciate that.
Thank you.
No problem.
All right, so we should go another like 30 seconds and then we'll get started.
All right.
Let's get back to it.
Okay, so let's talk about schema evolution versus versioning.
So making changes to public interfaces can be hard.
With an API, there can be multiple consumers and your single page front end application or an Android or iOS app.
The information that tells you if a change is safe to be made is spread pretty thin across all those different places.
And if your API is public, then there are even more considerations that need to be taken in order to avoid breaking any consumers that you may have.
But there's some general rules of thumb that we can follow to help us evolve the schema without breaking changes.
And GraphQL provides some constraints that make adhering to those rules of thumb a bit easier.
So what does it look like to evolve without having breaking changes?
So given some query with a selection of fields, arguments, and variables, if it returns the same types to the client before and after the change, then we can say that that's not a breaking change.
So types help us make that promise more easily.
The schema is a contract that isolates the client from the implementation on the server, so we're free to refactor how that data is fetched and provided to the consumer as long as the types don't change themselves.
So there are ways to do this with REST and any other API standard like RPC or what have you.
But particularly having a schema is very helpful with implementing this contract.
Additionally, like Base64 encoding tokens like ID and the pagination cursor also encourage client safety.
So a change to the implementation on the server shouldn't affect clients like we were saying before.
By Base64 encoding our tokens like ID and pagination cursor, we're discouraging clients from parsing and interpreting data that's used by the server internally.
So basically, if they start messing with our tokens, then it's their own problem that they get burned.
But the interface of how these tokens are used won't change as we evolve the internal implementation.
So if we decide to go away from a connection that's paginated through offset like the internal implementation of Graphene does and do a more efficient database based cursor, we can do that without worrying about breaking all of our consumers.
They don't need to change the API in order to benefit from the better performance of our internal implementation.
So if we add a new field, in GraphQL we have confidence that when we add that new field, it's not going to have an impact on existing queries that use that type that we've added the field to.
And that's because new data is only exposed to the client when it's used in a query.
So until we add that into the world, it can't be used. So we know it's not going to be sent to the data.
Even with REST, we can make that kind of change safe as long as we maintain the schema for the other fields.
But if the new field is expensive to compute, we don't really have any guarantees about performance impact to the clients with REST.
With GraphQL, we know that clients are not going to be impacted by adding an expensive to compute feature to our API because they'll only fetch that if they need it.
So we add a new argument to one of our fields. As long as it's optional or has a default value, we know we can add it fine.
Same as evolving an API in a method or any other object.
Even on clients for GraphQL with statically typed systems like Android or iOS, they're typically only impacted by changes that affect the return type of queries because that's really what they're typing in the API itself.
It may break RPC-style generated code from specific libraries, but that's not common with GraphQL. It's more common with like gRPC and things like that.
So in general, the same principles for evolving GraphQL APIs apply to REST APIs and any other public interface.
Google's API design guide really codivized this very well. It's a reference that I would encourage you guys to check out if it's something that you're interested in.
The guide is written with REST and gRPC in mind, but the concepts are broadly applicable even in GraphQL.
Especially given that gRPC, similar to GraphQL, has a schema for all of the responses that are sent.
So in addition to the schema, the GraphQL community has developed useful tooling and techniques to safely evolve APIs.
So for clients with known queries, like if it's a client that we control our API, or if it's a client that we control like our web front end or a mobile client, we can do contract testing by checking the types of static queries against the static schema definition.
We can also do like resolver-level middleware to track API usage from live production queries on a per-field basis.
This is the kind of tool that Apollo Server provides and is broadly used as a technique in the GraphQL community.
With REST, it's a little more difficult to get per-field level information about what is being consumed and know how things can be changed.
So inevitably, we're going to need to make a breaking change to our API. GraphQL's built-in deprecation reason can be used to communicate changes to consumers.
GitHub does a really great job of this. We can take a look at that in a little bit.
They have all of the changes that are going to be breaking into their API scheduled months out without ever having a version of their API.
Introspection can also warn clients about using fields that are marked for deprecation. So that can be helpful as well.
In REST, versioning is often the default option. So we might add another endpoint that versions a particular schema of our API.
In GraphQL, it's not the first choice, but it can still be done. It's still an option as a useful escape hatch if we really need to do some vicious refactoring.
Shopify, which is a pretty big proponent of GraphQL, has recently added versioning to their APIs because they have a special use case where they're providing a platform for people to build consumer products.
So they want to have a stable API.
Cool. So let's consider adding a new record related to the story author to our API.
In REST, we might add a separate endpoint, V1 authors. We might add links to related records as URL, which may lead to N plus one on the client side.
Or we might embed the author directly into the story request, which might lead to overfetching for some clients.
Do we need to bump the new version for stories endpoint? Will that have an impact to clients? That's a question.
With GraphQL, adding fields is a safe change. We don't need to worry about it.
So here we have we're leveraging connection and node from our previous talk.
So we have an author connection that we're adding to the root query and our author type is implementing node so we can fetch a single one.
In terms of graphing, like how should we structure our project as we grow?
As with any other project, we want to have like small modules that keep like things together.
In this case, we've organized the project with a package for query and mutation separately and a separate module file for each of the different types.
So trying to keep the module files pretty short and focused.
You can also invert this and have author as your package and query and mutation as your module, but either approach works fine.
For our base query, we combine these using multiple inheritance.
So basically we have some root query here and we inherit from story query and author query.
And same thing for the mutation. By inheriting from all those, we get all of the fields.
There's a risk that you could like have the same field, but that'll break your schema anyway.
So let's let's try to do a meteor exercise now.
So let's try to evolve our schema, write some more graphing code and add this author's type.
So the connection and the author type.
So you want to be on chapter four branch, pair up with somebody, open up API query author.py and follow the instructions there to implement changes to the schema.
There's also some sample queries over here and API queries dot graph QL.
So I'll pull that up here and we can go through it.
Okay.
So we're running a little bit ahead in this section, but let's check in and maybe like 10 minutes and see where everyone is.
If you have any questions, feel free to raise your hand.
Okay.
Yeah, it's just a.
Yeah.
Okay.
So, let's take a look at the next part.
I know a lot of people are still working on this one, but try to get through all the
material.
So, okay.
Let's take a look at a solution for this guy.
So, I will check.
All right.
So, just really quickly, let's take a look at the solution for this guy.
So, let's take a look at the solution for this guy.
Set this guy in the string.
Should we be using public string?
We should call the fullName method with the display argument.
For is type of, we just check if the root that is being resolved
for is type of, we just check if the root that is being resolved
to get the author object using this key that comes from our base64 decoded ID.
For connection we just specify the node type as the author type.
And we add authors and node as connection field and we resolve authors using Django.
So let's move on to the next thing.
So we can also add fields that connect two different types together.
So the author and the story are related.
Each story has one author.
So we have the author defined on the story type as a field.
And the author also has a list of stories for each of them.
And we can paginate across that list of stories because there are some authors out there who
are quite prolific.
So adding this kind of connection makes it a more flexible API.
We can navigate from any single node to any connected type, which is very flexible for
our clients.
In Graphene we use field and connection field with Python module string.
So we can use this Graphene.field for API query module type and connection field API
query module connection type.
We can also pass in the thing itself as we have over here.
So we have a connection field with the author connection that's defined right here.
This is just a little trick to avoid having a circular endpoint in Python.
So we can also deprecate fields that are no longer required.
So author name is no longer required on our story type because we have a more rich way
to describe that relationship.
The user can just fetch the author full name instead.
So we can give it a deprecation reason.
Similar to how we can specify description on any Graphene schema object, any field,
we can also provide a deprecation reason keyword argument with the reason text and that will
become available in our graphical documentation explorer.
So if we go over here in our documentation explorer we can look and see if a field is
deprecated it will show up over here.
So as a further evolution of the schema let's try to add this connection between author
and stories and story and author and specify a deprecation reason for author full name.
So this will require the branch chapter 4b that will have the solution of the previous
exercise there as well.
And you can open up author.py and story.py and implement the changes to the schema.
There's also some new sample queries in queries.graphql.
So that's the new sample query.
How's everybody doing?
Yes?
Is
in
.