Good.
Okay.
Welcome, everyone.
We're going to go ahead and get started.
So thank you so much for being here.
My name is Kevin Markham.
I'll be your instructor for this tutorial.
This is Data Science Best Practices with Pandas.
Very happy to be here.
It's my privilege to be teaching you today.
So before I talk about the tutorial, I'm just going to tell you some setup instructions
if you haven't done them yet so that you can get caught up with that.
And then I'll introduce myself and what we're doing.
And then we'll get started.
So you'll want to go to the GitHub repository.
And I snagged that sweet bit.ly link slash PyCon 2019 if you want to go directly there.
And there's some instructions here on downloading a CSV file, checking that Pandas and Matplotlib
are working.
And that's about it.
I'll link here to the TED Talks dataset.
You're welcome to pull that up.
We'll use it just a tiny bit.
But yeah, go ahead and open your Python environment, whatever environment you're most comfortable
with.
And put that CSV file into the same directory or wherever you usually open files from.
And that's that.
If people run into problems, I've got two backups, backup solutions.
One backup is I have some flash drives with the data file on them and some flash drives
with Anaconda installers if your machine just isn't working and you want to install Anaconda
right now.
The other backup is that if at any time you are having problems with your machine, just
go to the top of the repo, click Launch Binder, and you'll be running Jupyter Notebook in
the cloud with the data file and with the libraries you already need installed.
It takes a couple minutes to open, but it's a great solution if you're having big problems
with your machine.
Okay.
All right.
So while anyone's getting set up that's not already, I'll just tell you about myself.
I live in Asheville, North Carolina with my wife and my son.
And I used to live in Washington, D.C.
I'm the founder of Data School.
I teach data science in Python.
I teach in person at General Assembly in D.C.
I have a lot of YouTube videos.
Anyone seen one of my YouTube videos on something?
Cool.
Awesome.
Thanks.
Cool.
Well, I have taught a couple tutorials.
I taught a machine learning one at PyCon 2016 and one on Pandas at 2018.
That was a lot of fun.
And since I'm online only, it's a real pleasure for me to be in the classroom these days.
So this is great.
What we're going to be doing today is my goal is to help you become more fluent at using
Pandas to answer your own data science questions.
So I do expect you know some Pandas.
We're going to be doing a lot of exercises.
Basically, we're going to have this single data set.
I'm going to ask you a question or give you a task.
You're going to try to answer it using Pandas.
And then we'll discuss the answer together.
We'll spend a good amount of time on that where I'll kind of walk through a solution.
We can talk about it.
And at the end of each section, there are just some takeaways, some best practices that
I'm trying to communicate.
In terms of the pacing, this is intermediate level.
So if you feel beginner to Pandas, it might go a little fast.
If you feel like pretty advanced, it might go a little slow.
But I'm aiming for that middle ground.
If you do finish an exercise early, I've in most cases got a bonus written down that
I can give you.
So always let me know if you want a bonus exercise to work on, if you're just sitting
there and I'm happy to give you something.
Alternatively, just help your neighbor or just explore the data set on your own, make
up a question and start trying to answer it with Pandas.
And I can help you.
Yeah, please.
Yeah, I might.
Oh, please.
Okay.
So the question is about using a Conda environment for running the Jupyter Notebook.
So if you're in a Conda environment and you have installed the Notebook in that environment,
you'll have access to it.
That sounds good.
Yep.
Let's see what else.
If you are struggling to keep up at any point, don't worry so much about that.
Most of the exercises are independent of one another, so you won't get too far behind.
Don't worry about the red and green pieces of paper.
Final thoughts, if you're not used to using the Jupyter Notebook, that's what I'm going
to be using, but you should use what you're most comfortable with.
Questions are welcome at any time, but I've kind of timed this out and it's a lot of material,
so if questions are too far off topic, I'll probably just save it for a break or to talk
with you one-on-one and I'm happy to help.
We will break from 3 o'clock to 3.20 and we will end at 4.40.
All the code I'm typing will be posted on GitHub, so you don't feel like you have to
type everything if you're trying to keep up.
That's it.
Any questions for now before I jump into the first exercise?
Awesome.
All right.
What I'm going to do, this is all live coding, and this first exercise we're just going to
do it together, so I would encourage you to just type along with me.
We're just going to do an introduction to the dataset.
This is really just kind of a warm-up.
Go ahead and follow along.
In terms of ... This is a dataset of TED Talks.
Has anyone ever seen a TED Talk?
Yes, everyone.
Can someone just define quickly what a TED Talk is?
A talk about technology, entertainment, or design, or that was the original idea.
They're short talks, very popular.
They've been around for a long time and they have kind of a message they're trying to communicate.
This dataset, actually before I start typing, there's this page on the Kaggle Datasets website,
which by the way is a great way to find and explore datasets.
This is a description of the TED Talks dataset.
If you don't have this open, it might be useful.
The thing that may be useful is there's some metadata here about the dataset that might
be useful for you to understand, so I would keep that page open.
This was scraped from the TED.com website.
That's where this came from.
I just wanted to set the context for the dataset, but let's go ahead and just import pandas.
Sorry, it's harder to type and talk than it seems.
I'm using, I think, .24, .2, but you can use any modern version.
Should be just fine for today.
We're just going to import matplotlib.pyplot as plt.
If you're in the notebook as well, matplotlib inline.
If you're not in the notebook, that's largely or completely irrelevant.
Then we're just going to read in the dataset, and we're just going to read it into a dataframe
called TED.
It's in my local directory, so I'm just going to read right from TED.csv.
Let's just take a quick look at the dataset.
If you're falling behind, definitely feel free to ask your neighbor if you missed a
line of code.
Is it okay if I take the font size down one notch, because I want to get a little more
on screen?
Is this okay, or is that a little small in terms of reading the code up here?
Bigger?
Pretty small?
Okay, I'll go back up.
Each row in this dataset represents a single TED talk.
We're just going to check the shape, just the shape attribute.
There are 2,550 talks, so those are rows and columns.
Then we'll just take a quick look at the D types.
This is just what I do when I get a new dataset and want to be vaguely familiar with what's
in it.
We'll just take a quick look at the D types.
It's just a blend of integer columns and object columns.
Object columns are usually strings, but what else can an object column contain?
Just go ahead and raise your hand and I'll grab someone.
For categories, it'll actually say category, I believe.
There's something else.
What else can an object type contain?
Other than strings, other things?
Yep.
Object data types, though they usually have strings, they can contain arbitrary Python
objects such as lists or dictionaries.
That is something useful to keep in mind, that they're not always strings.
But yeah, the most important thing, we have a bunch of int columns and object columns.
I'm just going to write this and not explain it and then show you the result.
Can anyone tell me what this code is checking for?
Right there?
What I did is .isna.sum.
I'm checking for missing values.
That's another useful thing to know when you open up a data set.
Isna, which is the same as isnull, isna outputs a data frame of Boolean values.
Then when you sum it, sum sums along the zero axis, the rows axis, which gives you column
sums.
True values are treated as ones.
False values are treated as zeros.
A lot happening in that line.
The bottom line is that speaker occupation has six missing values.
I'm not going to take any action at this time, but this is something you should know about
any data set you're working with.
There's lots of different ways you might deal with missing values, especially if you have
a lot of them.
But we have very few, so there's not much to say.
This isn't really a big best practice, but the documentation has been migrating over
to using isna and notna rather than isnull and notnull for consistency with dropna and
fillna.
That's why I've switched to isna.
You might, I don't know if they'll eventually deprecate the isnull and whatnot, but that's
what I'm doing here.
Anyway, that's just a brief intro to this data set.
We're going to jump into the first exercise, which is going to be very short.
Does anyone have any questions up till now?
I'm going to call this.
This exercise is the following question.
Which talks provoke the most online discussion?
That, you don't have to type that, you can if you want.
But that's the exercise.
You're going to have to decide which column or columns are relevant to answering this
question.
Some of the columns are self-explanatory, but you can check out the Kaggle website for
descriptions.
I will give you about three minutes on this, so that's just because it's not that deep
of an exercise.
But if you've already got an answer, maybe think a little bit beyond the surface as to
what I'm trying to get at.
But I'll be walking around during every exercise and you can ask questions.
But go ahead and take three minutes and try to figure out which talks provoke the most
online discussion.
Okay.
All right.
Subcomments?
Subcomments on other forms?
There's a lot of data we do want, but we don't have, and that's an example.
How about there?
Right.
How long it's been online, right?
Because that's really relevant.
Some of these talks have been online for 20 years.
Others have been online for a day.
And so it's relevant how long it's been online.
The way I was thinking to correct for this bias is to normalize it by, anyone want to guess?
Views.
Views is what I'm thinking.
So if someone watches a talk, the number of views, if someone watches a talk and they
do comment or they don't comment, that would seem to indicate how provocative, if you will,
a talk is.
So I'm going to create a new column called comments per, per, per, per.
View.
And it's going to be Ted.comments divided by Ted.views.
Okay?
And I'm creating a new column.
I always use dot notation when I can, which I'm using on the right side.
You have to use bracket notation when you're creating a new series in a data frame.
Thus, that's why I use bracket notation.
I put underscores in my, in my column names because I like to use dot notation.
So you need underscores there.
So we, I do that.
And then let's go ahead and sort by comments per view instead.
Use comments per view.
And we'll look at the tail again.
So now we actually, so that Richard Dawkins talk is still up high.
But now we have a different talk we're defining as the most, sorry, I'll scroll over all the way to the right because when you add new columns to a data frame, they end up all the way on the right.
And here's the comments per view column.
And all the way at the bottom, we've got our number.
This is the greatest number in the data frame.
So this talk, called the case for same-sex marriage, is a different way you might define, you know, the number of people you might have in your life.
So we would interpret this number as for every view of this talk, there are .002 comments.
So that's the greatest number.
Though that number is a little bit tricky to kind of put into real world context.
How might I make this more interpretive?
So we would interpret this number as for every view of this talk, there are .002 comments.
So in real world context, how might I make this more interpretable than what I've got?
How might I make this the same information but slightly more interpretable?
Views per comment, that is a great idea, that is exactly what I was thinking.
Is we can just reverse the calculation, invert the calculation.
And change this to views per comment.
Views per comment.
And then it will be Ted.views.
Maybe the copy-paste wasn't the best idea.
Ted.comments.
Sorry, I should have just typed it, that was silly.
All right, views per comment.
All right, looks good.
And then we'll do Ted.sort values, views per comment.
Views per comment.
And then this time we'll look at the head because we want the lowest number.
It's the opposite.
So now I will just scroll over all the way over here.
And views per comment, it says 450.
So it says that it takes 450 views to generate a comment or one out of every 450 people who
watches the talk comments on it, which to me is a lot easier to interpret than comments per
view with that small decimal number.
So the bottom line for this exercise is this is how I would probably measure with the data
we have, which talks provoke the most online discussion, but it would be great to have
other data.
All right, I'm going to show you, I'll just show you on screen a couple lessons I took
away from this, but any questions about this exercise before I do that?
Yeah, please.
All right.
When I created this self-explanatory thing for them, I'm interested in, I believe that
the views come from the rating test.
Okay.
I'm thinking about the view from the rating test.
Right.
Oh, okay.
So you, yeah, no, that's fine.
So she basically filtered out a lot of the columns that were irrelevant to the question
before doing kind of a similar process.
So yeah, you can always, the problem with kind of like sub data frames is if you create
them and then you do any manipulations to it, you haven't affected the one you created in
the original one, so it can be easy to lose track, but sometimes it is nice to create
a smaller data frame that focuses on the columns you're interested in.
Okay.
So I'll just show you the lessons, the lessons I was trying to get across from this exercise.
And these are lessons or best practices.
Some of these will be data science lessons.
Some of them will be pandas lessons.
But number one, consider the limitations and biases of your data when analyzing it.
So the limitation, as someone mentioned over here, is we only have the first level comments,
whereas actually having those nested comments might actually be even more useful for which
talks are most provocative because people are saying things and then other people are
replying to them.
But we can't really correct for that without gathering the data ourselves.
And then the bias that we tried to correct for was that older talks have had a lot more
time to accumulate comments, so we tried to correct for this by normalizing by views.
So that was the first lesson I was trying to get across.
The second lesson is just to make your results understandable, regardless of your audience,
regardless of whether it's just for yourself.
And that's why we used views per comment rather than comments per view.
So those are just a couple lessons.
I hope you found that to be useful.
I'm going to move on to the next exercise unless there are any final questions about
this one.
Okay.
All right.
So the next exercise is visualize the distribution of the data that you're using.
Visualize the distribution of comments.
Okay.
And we're going to talk about this one for just a few minutes before I let you loose
on this one.
So let's just make a plot real quick with pandas.
So we're going to do ted.comments.plot.
All right.
And here's what we get.
What kind of plot is this?
A line plot.
A line plot, that is correct.
So what do the axes represent?
What does the X represent and what does the Y represent?
X is the index.
And what does the Y represent?
The value of the comments field.
Right.
So it's basically plotted out 2,550 points and connected them by a line.
That's what a line plot is.
Line plot is not what you would use here because a line plot is for measuring
something over time.
So if there's not a time component to it, in what you're showing, a line plot is
usually not the right choice.
I just wanted you to know how to plot using pandas if you haven't done it before.
We can learn some things from this plot.
We can see that many talks have a low number of comments and a small number of talks have
lots of comments.
But that's about it.
So this is not the plot I want you to create.
But you might know, and in a Jupyter Notebook you put your cursor in the parentheses and
shift-tab and I'm going to do it four times to pull up the signature, essentially the
doc string in a lower pane.
And you'll see, and it'll be different depending upon which editor you use, but
you'll see that there's this kind of thing that you can do.
But you'll see that there's this kind argument, okay, the default is line.
But if you scroll down, you'll see that there are also other options like bar, bar H,
hist, box, KDE, density, area, and pie, okay?
So there are many different plot types supported by pandas.
So the exercise is really, again, I want you to visualize the distribution of comments.
So the first step is I want you to figure out what plot to do that.
And if you don't know the terminology, you're looking for a plot that summarizes how often
particular values are occurring.
This is called the frequency distribution.
And when you've made this, it should be easy to see are there a lot of low values?
Are there a lot of high values?
Okay?
So that's step one is pick a plot type.
And step two is once you've picked a plot, I want you to modify the defaults to make it as
informative as possible.
So let's pretend you've got one shot to pick the perfect visualization to visualize the
distribution of comments.
I want you to make it as informative as possible.
You don't need to add labels, but I want you to modify how it looks so that it's as
informative as possible, okay?
So I'm only going to give you about four or five minutes on this, but I'll be walking
around.
I'll leave this doc string up just in case it's helpful to anyone.
And then we'll be back up in a couple minutes to talk about it.
And I'll...
So in the Jupyter Notebook, if you put your cursor within the parentheses, you can hit
Shift-Tab once, and it will pop it up here.
A second time to get it larger, a third time to do I'm not sure what, and a fourth time
to get it to appear at the bottom of your screen.
And then you can hit this X to close it.
So that's how it's done.
Great question.
And I will do that again so that everyone can have it.
All right.
So...
We're going to go ahead and go through this one.
Hope you had some fun playing with some visualizations.
So...
What plot type did someone choose?
Tell me what plot type you used.
Histogram.
So that's kind of when you talk about a frequency distribution, that's kind of the natural thought of...
Usually, so a histogram, if you're not familiar, it shows the frequency distribution of a single
numeric variable.
And the way it works is it creates 10 equally sized bins by default between the minimum value
and the maximum value, divides those into 10 bins, and then it counts how many observations appear
in each bin.
So this isn't kind of the end point, but what have we learned so far by looking at this visualization?
Where was that?
What have we learned?
The bins need to be a much greater number of bins.
There's only 10 bins there.
So it's going to be by default.
If you're going to spread it out, you're going to see basically smaller things.
So there are two thoughts I want to get at.
One is adjusting the number of bins, which we'll get to in a minute, that many of you may have
thought about already, and if you haven't or are not familiar, you'll see that.
The other thought, which is just to make sure we understand this, this is a bin that starts at zero
and ends at about 600 and something.
So this bar represents a lot of talks with between zero and 600 comments.
It's not a lot of talks with zero comments.
So it's not what's at the left.
You have to think about the bin itself, which is zero to 600 and something.
And we only know that because the max number is 6,000 and something, so when you divide it by 10,
you get 600 and something.
So that's the first thing we've learned about the distribution, is that most talks have a lot
fewer than 1,000 or 600 comments.
Now, what does this not tell us that we might want to know?
Right.
So how are the, what does the distribution look like within that bar?
How does the distribution look like within that first bar or within that subset?
So we've got, the reason we have this kind of weird looking histogram, well, weird in the sense
that you've got a lot of what looks like empty space, is because there's a talk with 6,000 and
something comments, but that doesn't really tell you anything, and it's artificially spread out
this histogram.
So the vast majority of our data is at the left side, and so my thought is that we don't know
whether most talks have 5 comments or 500 comments, we just know that most talks have less than 600
comments.
So I thought it would be nice to modify this to be more informative by filtering it down.
So we're actually going to filter just like this.
Ted Doug's comments is less than 1,000.
Okay?
So we're just filtering out everything above 1,000.
So all I did is filter the actual data frame before selecting the comments series, and we've
actually only lost a little bit of data, and I'll just show you in a cell above here.
So if we do Ted.comments is greater or equal to 1,000, sorry, and we do that dot shape, we can see
that when we filter out the ones with 1,000 or greater, we're only losing 32 talks out of 2,500.
Okay?
So this is my way of getting at a little more, like this to me is a much more informative plot
because it tells me about most of the data.
It doesn't focus on the outliers.
Okay?
Any questions about like how this line of code works or what's going on here?
Okay.
All right.
So before I move on and show you a few more things, I do want to mention that there are
different ways you could write this code that would produce an identical plot.
So did anyone use the query method?
Anyone use query?
So it's a different way of writing, of filtering your data frame.
So you pass it, actually pass it a string, and dot plot kind equals hist.
I think I got that right.
So this does exactly the same thing using the query method.
Some people like using query.
And then a third way you can write this, and it's the way I like, and sorry to move things off
screen, but that's kind of the nature of this, is I use loke a lot instead because I think it is the
most flexible and the most, well, to me it's the most readable way because it's very explicit
about which rows do I want and which columns do I want.
So this is not really about plotting.
This is just showing you a couple different ways to do the same thing.
So this is with loke.
So with loke, I select which rows I want, which columns I want, and then run the, sorry,
which rows I want, which column singular I want, and then plot it as a histogram.
Okay?
Yeah, please.
Right, yes.
So loke is great because you can select multiple columns.
You can pass it a single column.
You can pass it a list of columns.
You can pass it a range of columns, literally column A colon column C, and it will select A, B,
and C, or a Boolean series, and that will at least work for the rows, and I'm actually not sure
about that for the columns, but anyway, yes, there are different ways you can select with loke,
which is quite nice.
Okay.
So the final thing, or well, there's two things left I wanted to show you about this, is what
someone over here has already suggested, which is maybe we should increase the number of bins so we
can see a little more fine-grained detail, and so instead of sticking with the default of 10 bins,
we're going to change it to 20, and now we get a little bit more fine-grained picture, and what
we've learned, so now we have 20 bins, each represent, like the first bin is zero to 50
comments, the next bin is 50 to 100 comments, et cetera, et cetera.
Now we've learned that the most popular, at least in this context, is 50 to 100 comments,
that's more common in this data set than zero to 50.
Yep.
Right.
Right, right, right, yes.
So, and a lot of folks, when they were trying to research the documentation, were like, I don't
see all these things I want, and if you did like ted dot something dot hist instead of dot plot,
you would get, you would have more information about the data set, and so that's what we're going
to do, and if you did like ted dot something dot hist instead of dot plot, you would get, you would
have more information about that.
So, very briefly, and we can talk about it more after, but briefly, pandas is always calling
matplotlib to draw its plots, there are different, there are many different ways to call pandas
plots, there are the generic, like, dot plot kind equals, with a lot of options for keyword
arguments, and those keyword arguments ultimately get passed, I think, directly onto matplotlib,
but if you want to know what all those are, you unfortunately have to go to the matplotlib
documentation.
The flip side is you can use things like ted dot comments dot hist, which allow things like
grouped histograms, but the downside is most plots don't have a, you know, dot hist, I mean,
there is dot hist, there is dot box plot, but there's not, I don't think, like dot kde, and
there's so many types of plots that there's not a specifically named one, that I like to teach the
dot plot generically because it has most of it, but the downside being you have all these kind of
hidden keyword arguments that you don't know what you can put in it, and you end up at the matplotlib
documentation, like, kind of guessing, like, okay, I think this one will work here, and then you try
it, and it usually does work. So, that answer your question? Okay, great, great, great, great, great.
The final thing you might think about using here is did anyone try a box plot? So, some box plots,
yep, so that's another good way to do distributions, and it's kind equals box, and unfortunately,
it doesn't, it's not quite as informative because of what are all the black dots?
Outliers, so anything that it defines as an outlier just gets a black dot. There's a ton of things that
it shows you, so you can think of this kind of like a, in a sense, it's like a histogram that's
been turned vertically, but it's just showing you your quartiles, and then, but it's got so many
outliers that it's not the most informative plot. So, I don't like the box plot in this case,
but sometimes the box plot is kind of what you're looking for.
All right, before I jump into some lessons, any, some lessons about what we just
walked through, any questions about this exercise?
Okay, and I will say that after the next exercise, which is longer, I'll take a pulse on how we're
doing in terms of is this too fast or too slow or somewhere in the middle, but I want to have one
longer exercise before you kind of gauge that, so I will be asking just not quite yet. The lessons
that I take away from this, from this exercise, number one is you choose your plot type based on
the question you're answering and the data types you're working with, so histograms are good for
distributions, bar plots are for comparing categories, line plots are good for time series
data, scatter plots are for comparing multiple numeric variables, so yeah, you have to choose
based upon the type of data you're working with, and pandas actually has a lot more plot types
than are represented in that kind equals, so if you're really interested, I would encourage you
to read the visualization page of the pandas documentation because it has tons more plots and
you call them, unfortunately, in an array of different ways, but there are actually a ton of
supported ones, so that was my first lesson. My second kind of takeaway is I like to use pandas
one-liners to iterate through plots quickly. As I said, pandas is calling matplotlib under the hood,
but it's generally faster and easier to write pandas plots than matplotlib plots, the downside
being that this advice is mostly relevant for exploratory plots because there are limits to
how much you can customize it without using matplotlib directly. The third lesson I wanted
to impart is just to try modifying the plot defaults because it's rare that the default
settings are going to give you exactly the plot that you are looking for, the most informative plot,
and the final takeaway, especially for anyone who is uncomfortable with the idea of like,
let's just cut out these 32 observations, which is what I did, creating plots involves decision
making, in fact a lot of decision making, because you can't show everything on a visualization. A
visualization is inherently a summary, so you have to accept that you're not going to show something.
There's no single correct way to visualize a certain piece of data, so there's no right or
wrong visualization, but there are certainly misleading visualizations, and it's very easy
to create a misleading visualization even accidentally, so your decision should be guided
around how do I accurately answer this question and not mislead folks as to what's going on in the data.
Okay, so those are the takeaways there. I'm going to jump into the next exercise,
and this one is going to be, as I mentioned, is going to be longer, and hopefully you will like
kind of, if you found those to be easy, then hopefully you'll struggle some, a little bit at
least. So this is number four. Plot the number of talks that took place each year. Okay, number four.
Plot the number of talks that took place each year, and I choose my words very carefully, so
look back at that if you're unclear. I'm not going to give you any advice this time. I do have a
bonus for anyone who finishes early. I will just raise your hand and grab me. I am going to give
you about 12 minutes for this exercise, okay, and again always grab me while I'm walking around with your questions.
So we're at 12 minutes, but I'd like to just see, just a quick show of hands, how many folks would use more time if they had it?
Oh, okay, almost everyone. So at least a couple, we'll do at least a couple more minutes and then
I'll kind of make a decision, but yeah, ask a neighbor, if you're stuck on one part and you're like,
I just can't get, ask a neighbor and see if they can just tell you and then you can move on to the next part, okay.
So
yeah, I've gotten that,
I've gotten it to group by year, but
I think so.
So I got it from the film date.
So I think it's a UNIX time stamp.
So yeah, I think the UNIX S should be, I don't know why, but I realized the question very quickly in my little program.
So
yeah,
so
I can't figure out how to
know
You got these things.
There's two of them.
This is the first one starting in 1932.
A lot of the movies and others.
But it's also like, this isn't, I don't think it's the sword.
Yeah.
All right.
This is, I think I'm going to go ahead and cut you off on this one,
because there are some sticking points that a lot of people are running into,
and I don't know if you'll get it even if I give you like a really long time.
So I don't want to just spend all day.
No, and that's not, I mean, this is hard.
Like, this is hard.
If you, you have to know, I mean, I have to guess what you might know,
and that's what I'm using when I create these exercises.
So if you don't know certain key things, this would be very, very hard.
So anyway, with that being said, let's go through it.
Okay?
Let's see here.
Okay.
So what is wrong first with using the event column?
Did anyone try the event column, and then they got stuck?
Why did, did it work or did it not work?
Well, I was able to extract years out of that field.
You were?
I mean, it's just the last four characters in the field.
Okay.
Meaningful.
Now, in what cases would that all, did that always work?
And the answer is no, but can someone tell me why the answer is no?
Some of them work.
Some of them don't have the year.
So this is, if you're not familiar with, like, the random sample method,
that's useful.
So, you know, I just want 10 randomly selected events,
and you'll see that some of them end with a number that obviously represents the year,
and some of them don't.
So if you go to that column, you are going to get stuck.
You're going to have at least a lot of missing values
because you're not going to have the year.
So what I was hoping you would do is go over to the TED Talks dataset website,
and you would scroll down and you would see Film Date,
and you'd see it's the Unix timestamp of the filming,
and that sounds like, well, that's when it took place.
So that sounds like the right column to focus on.
So let's take a look at it.
Film Date dot head, okay, and we've got our Unix timestamp, okay.
So I look at that and I think, well, I don't really know much about Unix timestamps
or what to do with them, but my, you know, pd dot to date time,
which was a key function here, if you did not get to pd dot to date time,
that was like a big, something you needed to make this easy.
So pd dot to date time converts a series to the date time format,
and it does a lot of guessing as to what format it is and produces pretty good results.
Now, unfortunately, these don't look like good results,
which is disappointing because usually you stick in whatever
and out comes the real dates, and you're like, wow, that's magical.
But in this case, it did not work, okay.
So here's what I was hoping you would do, and I know this is a stretch
because you'd have to happen to follow this same sequence,
but if it was me and you know what to date time is,
you would Google pandas to date time, do to date time,
and you might go looking to Stack Overflow and you might stumble upon a good answer.
But in this case, I would get here because I know I want to use this function.
I would search for the word Unix, whoops, Unix,
and I would get down at the bottom, I would find this,
which is an example of using it to convert something that looks like our timestamps
to something that looks like what we want.
And all they did was say unit equals s, and magically they got the right thing.
So my thought was, well, let's just add unit equals s.
And then you get these dates that look like, hey, that looks like the right date.
And so what I did, and so if you didn't know about two-day time,
getting to this step would be very hard, but if you did,
then what I'm hoping you did is created a new column,
because it's best not to overwrite your existing column unless you're sure you don't need it.
So I'm going to create a new column called film date time with this data.
And then they looked like the right dates,
but I would want to verify that these are, that this is like, that it worked as we had hoped.
So what I'm actually going to do is just pull out two columns, event and film date time.
So I'm pulling out the two columns that one is the one I just created,
and the other is one that has a name that often includes the year.
And I'm just going to randomly sample.
And when we do that, you're going to have a different random sample.
But you're going to look at it and you're going to say, okay,
the 2012 event has a 2012 film date time.
Same thing with the 2007 and the 2008 and the 2015.
And so you think, okay, that probably did work.
So we don't want to assume it worked just because some rows looked like they were correct.
It's good to use a random sample to kind of verify your results.
Okay. Now, the thing it's done, the we're going to check the D types again of the entire data frame.
And the thing it's done is create this new column called film date type.
Okay. Sorry. It's created the new column called film date time,
and it's using the date time data type.
So that's a special pandas data type that is automatically output when you use PD.2 date time.
Okay. And just I'm just curious, like how many people this is completely new to them using the okay,
at least half of them. Okay. Okay.
So the neat thing, so basically, if you want to get a, I'll show you,
you'll see why you want to have date time data types.
But any time you use PD.2 date time and pass it something, it will output a date time column.
And that's useful for a lot of reasons.
And I'll show you one reason right now, which is Ted, if I select film date time,
then I have this little DT namespace and I can select convenient attributes like year.
Okay. I can select day of week, I think is one.
I can select day of year.
And all these convenient attributes are available under this little .dt namespace
because it's the date time data type.
Okay. So this is the easiest way to get the year.
There are other solutions to this exercise, but this is a good one.
So now we've got this .dt.year.
Now, if you're like, wait, that looks kind of familiar.
This is the same as like string methods have this little str namespace, like str.lower.
So if you want to do string methods on a series that's a string,
you do column.str.string method name and it will do it.
In the same way with date time data types, you have this little DT namespace
with a variety of convenient attributes you can pull out.
Okay. So I've got this year data.
How, so I've got everything I need in this column, year, which is what we were going after.
How do we count the number of talks per year from where we are here?
Value counts, whoever said that.
The value counts method is good anytime you want to count values.
Okay. Now we've got our value counts.
And now that we've got the data that we're looking for,
which is the number of talks that took place each year,
what kind of plot do we probably want to use?
Bar plot is one suggestion. Anyone want to offer an alternative?
Someone said histogram, someone said line plot.
Okay. So a bar plot is okay, but there are two things, well, let's just, okay, let's do it.
And then we'll talk about it for a second.
And whoops, obviously I need to actually dot plot.
Sorry. Value counts dot plot.
Okay. So we get this and yes, we can fix up the sorting.
But the thing, there are kind of the main issue here with using a bar plot other than sorting,
which we can fix, is that it's excluding all the years that did not get, that are not in the data.
So there was no talk in 1973, but there was in 1972.
But a plot that misses those time spans is a little bit misleading because you can't see the jumps.
Now bar plots are best for categorical data.
And technically you could consider years to be categories, but they're not really, and, or it's not optimal.
And a line plot is better because line plots are four things that are plotted over time.
Okay. So a line plot is better in this case.
So what I'm going to do, the line plot is the default.
So I'm just going to run this.
And I want you to tell me what went wrong here.
So this is not the answer, but what went wrong?
Someone, something about sorting and who can tell me more?
Tell me a general principle about why this plot looks the way it is.
Like what is it doing that is non-optimal?
Yes. Why is it doing that is the question.
It is, yes, it is forming a continuous line, but there's something more to it.
That's actually not the case. Over here.
It's not plotting along the wrong axis.
These are great. Obviously this is a great question because I'm not getting the right answer.
Right. Okay. So it is a sorting issue and let's look at the data.
Okay. Let's look at the data.
If I take this and I give it to dot plot, which produces a line plot,
pandas will plot them in the order in which they appear.
So it will first plot 2013 to 70.
Then it'll plot 2011 to 20.
Then it'll plot 2011 to 70 and connect it.
Then it'll plot 2010 to 67.
And if you actually follow this, you'll see that that is why it produces this plot.
So it plots things in the order you give it to them.
Okay. Now if we want to fix this, we're just going to do sort index.
Okay. So we're going to throw in sort index.
Actually let me show you that before the plot.
Sort index sorts the index, which is the thing on the left,
not the values, which is the thing on the right.
So you want to sort the index because the index is going to become the x-axis
and the values are going to become the y-axis.
But because it's connecting the points, you need those points to be in order.
So when we do that, we get the plot that I was actually looking for.
So this is one way to go about getting this particular plot.
And there are others, but we could talk about that all day.
I do have one question though.
Is the number of talks on a sharp decline?
You say no, and why do you say no?
Probably just the last year in the conclusion.
Right. So there's some incomplete data.
So you don't want to draw a conclusion that there is a big drop
just because there's a drop in the plot,
because it turns out that if you use film datetime.max,
so you can use things like max and min with your datetime data types,
and you see that this data ends in the middle of 2017,
which is why we have incomplete data for this particular year.
Yeah, please.
Sorry, say that one more time.
Okay.
Good question. In this case, it would not.
And there's a different way, so there's multiple ways you can go about.
There are, if you're familiar, anyone familiar with resample?
Resample? Okay.
So I won't go into it because I don't want to stray too far,
but resample is another way you could solve this problem.
Essentially, you resample it by year,
and then you do a count of observations of any column,
and you'll end up with roughly the same plot,
except it will handle zero years slightly differently,
which is probably slightly better,
but it depends on what exactly you're trying to show.
Oh, interesting. Okay.
So there aren't any missing values in this case,
so a zero isn't a missing...
There are no observations 2010.
Right.
In that series.
Okay, got it. Got it, got it, got it. Yes.
So I don't know how plotting...
I think plotting would just...
I'm actually not sure how plotting would handle a missing value
in that case, but it's a great question.
I just don't happen to know.
Other questions about this particular exercise,
and then I'll go through some lessons. Yeah, please.
So I'm a little confused.
See, this is a plot that I had before,
and I'm doing a plot for 2006.
Right.
So I created that by mapping the daytime function to that row,
and I'm a little confused about why those two things
didn't get different results.
When I looked up the doctrine of meaning for what I did,
I was learning a unique timestamp for the same object.
Okay.
So your question is essentially you're wondering why yours ended up
without anything below 2006.
Yeah.
Okay.
Let me take a look at your code during the break
and see if I can figure it out, but...
I was going to say I had the same issue.
Okay.
Publish date instead of...
Oh, you use publish date.
Okay, that might be it.
So publish date and film date are actually different,
though I don't know how far back the publish dates go.
Oh, okay.
Well, that solves it.
So that is a tricky little piece of...
It's why I phrased it as the number of talks that took place each year
so that you would kind of choose a certain way,
but it's an easy mistake to make.
Other questions?
Yeah, please.
What's the name of it from...?
Okay.
Got it.
So it is probably...
So most things in Pandas,
as long as you're calling them directly and not through apply,
which we'll talk about later,
are going to be more efficient than anything else
you can just pick out of a different library
because Pandas overall is well optimized.
So it's probably less efficient,
but it's more that the functionality in two-day time is really nice,
and I know it works really well, and there's a ton of options.
Now, there might be more or less options
in the library you're mentioning,
so sometimes you might need to use it,
but in this case, all we needed was to say unit equals second,
and we got what we needed.
But great question.
Other questions about this one?
Okay.
So a couple lessons, and then let's see.
A couple lessons I wanted to go through as to some takeaways.
And first takeaway is read the documentation.
So in this case, the documentation for the data set
as well as the Pandas documentation would both be useful to you,
so it's a good resource to use.
The second lesson is to use the date-time data type for dates and times.
So number one, it works well with plots.
Number two, it provides convenient attributes.
And Pandas actually has extensive, extensive functionality
for working with time series data,
but that functionality depends upon you using these specialized data types.
So the takeaway here is if you have date and time data,
it will serve you well to use the date-time data type.
Lesson number three is check your work as you go.
So hopefully, you know, I use the random sample method
in order to spot check that certain conversions are working properly
rather than just looking at like the head or the tail.
I like to use a random sample.
And then the fourth point here is to consider excluding data
if it might not be relevant.
So as we saw, we only have partial data for 2017.
You might want to consider excluding that.
It depends on what you're trying to show.
It turns out that some of the talks from the TED website,
which is this is it was scraped from the TED website,
some of the talks on the TED website actually were not TED talks.
They're just like talks that they uploaded
because they thought they were really TED-like talks.
The TED conference was actually founded in 1984, not in 1972.
So you might want to consider, like,
if someone asked you this question for work for some reason,
it might be a good idea to research,
oh, are all the talks in the data set actually TED talks?
And do I want to include data that is non-TED talks on the TED website?
And that would depend on what question you're trying to answer.
So, yeah, that's really all I want to say about that
is sometimes the data you have, you should exclude certain things
depending upon what you are trying to get across.
Okay?
All right. Yeah, please.
Question about H time conversion.
Is there a way to do the dot notation on the arbitrary integer
treated as an epoch time dot the as type of H?
Oh, he's asking if you can do conversion using, like, as type
in the same way that you have a column of strings that says,
like, it's a string of the number 3,
you can just do, like, as type int,
and it will become an integer column.
I think it would be a good thing if there was, like, as type date time,
but as far as I know, that does not work.
There's no, like, as type does not support that particular conversion.
So you have to use this PD.2 date time, which is this top level method.
It's not like a series method or a data frame method.
It's just this top level function, actually.
Other questions?
Okay.
So let's see.
I think what we're going to do...
So we've got 12 minutes till the break.
So I'm going to start you on the next exercise,
and I think I'll just let you go to the break working on that,
and then we'll talk about it afterwards.
It might put us slightly behind,
but I may start talking about it before if I feel like it.
So anyway, you're going to have at least eight minutes for this one,
and let me go ahead and type it out and let you get started.
Okay, this is number five.
Oops. Five.
What were the best events in TED history to attend?
Okay. What were the... Sorry.
And I'm not asking about the best individual talks.
I'm asking about the best event,
that event column that's like TED 2006, TED whatever.
So what was the best event in TED history to attend?
And it's your job to figure out how to define best
and then use that definition to calculate which event was best.
Okay?
So I'm going to give you at least eight minutes,
but I will more likely give you until the break at three o'clock
and then we'll discuss it after.
And if anyone finishes early, I have a bonus you can work on.
But yeah, go ahead and get started.
Okay.
Let me give one quick piece of advice.
Is start with a simple-ish solution.
If you have multiple ideas, try to execute a simple one first
and then increase your complexity just in case you're heading down
a path and you decide you don't want to be there.
So just start with simple and then add on complexity if you like.
Yeah, I'll just leave it at that.
Okay.
Just give you a preview.
So it's 2.57 right now.
So the break is from 3 to 3.20.
I'm not going to talk before 3.20, but at 3.20 sharp,
I'm going to start and I'm going to start explaining this exercise.
So if you need still more time on this,
then feel free to work on it a bit during the break.
But you're welcome now or in two minutes at the start of the break to head out.
But we are starting back at 3.20 promptly.
Okay.
Created this black than e
.