Hopefully you all have maybe got some of these.
I've never used these before, so I'm just going to try it out.
The idea with these is if you need help, put up a little red thing.
If you're good, put up a green one.
There's a lot of people and I don't have any mentors to help out, so I can't guarantee
that I'm going to be able to spend too much time with anybody.
Ideally, if you finish early and someone else is struggling next to you, we could try and
help each other, but I will try and respond to the stickies.
I guess we'll get started.
If you haven't already, please load up the binder link.
Show of hands, who has already loaded the binder link?
Let's do it the other way around.
Who has not loaded the binder link?
Of those, who is having trouble loading it?
Who is having trouble with it?
No one yet?
Let's just assume that it's going to be okay and by the time we actually need it, the last
stragglers will be fine.
All right, great.
I'm just going to start quickly with just a little overview of how this material is structured.
On the repo link, actually, and in the binder, there's a lot more material than we're going
to cover in this tutorial.
I can pretend that it's because I wanted to give you guys extra material that you could
but it's really because I don't know how long it takes to go through material.
I just wrote twice as much as can be covered in three hours.
There's plenty of extra bonus material.
That may mean that we're going to be skipping some workbooks and some exercises are going
to be just bonus exercises, but no worries.
The material is also written to be done well.
It works well in a self-paced manner.
If you go through later, if you missed something today, or if you were like, oh, I really wanted
to learn this particular thing, you should be able to just go into the binder link, into
the materials and read what I've written and work through the exercises.
The things that we are going to be covering are three things.
The two big ones are going to be time zones and recurring events because those are kind
of complicated and we'll have a little light fare, which is working with the serializing
and deserializing date times.
Unfortunately, the way it works out is that the fun exercises come at the end, so I'm
going to try and make sure that we get to those more fun exercises by the time, with
enough time for us to actually spend a good amount of time on them.
It's going to be a mix of lectures and exercises, and it starts out a little lecture heavy and
ends up a little exercise heavy.
Before we do any of that, I just wanted to get us all on the same page about date times
because when I've done this in the past, people have said that...
Actually a little background about me, which is that for the past four or five years, I'm
afraid to calculate it because then I'll realize how old I am and then that death comes for
us all.
But for the past four or five years, I've been maintaining the library DateUtil, which
is a date time library, does parsing, time zones, things like that.
We'll use it a lot in this material.
But what that also means is that I've been kind of steeped in the world of date times
and I have no problem talking about calendrical arithmetic and all kinds of other obscure
date time terminology.
So if I kind of use unfamiliar terminology or a concept that you're not familiar with,
feel free to stop me and ask because I actually don't know, I don't remember which things
that I learned while doing this and which things I can assume to become a knowledge.
So feel free to stop me because there's a lot of details involved.
But I know there are a couple of things that people have in the past had trouble with.
I just want to establish the terminology.
So the first thing, a very critical notion is the difference between absolute and civil
times.
And I don't know that there's a great standard terminology for this.
So I call it absolute and civil times.
Sometimes you can call it timestamps and wall times.
But absolute times are a specific moment in time.
So 15 minutes ago, 20 years ago, one minute after the beginning of the eunuchs epoch,
those are all absolute times or timestamps.
Civil times are kind of a related concept but what they are is the time it says on the
wall.
So civil times are not necessarily, they don't necessarily reflect how much time is elapsed
between two events or anything.
They're really more what a human would expect the time to be.
So if we're going to have a meeting at noon and then all of a sudden the meaning of noon
changes because like daylight saving time gets cancelled with two days notice.
We're not going to start having that meeting at 11 o'clock because we agreed that our meeting
is in 75 hours.
We're going to have our meeting at noon because we're humans and we get to work at 9 and we
have our meetings at noon.
So I guess maybe people go to lunch at noon.
I'm sorry, I'm actually not a human.
I'm more of like a robot.
So I don't really understand lunch and human breakfast.
So with absolute times, they're usually the right choice for things in the past.
So like logs, logging events.
Sometimes they're used for things in the future like astronomical events or like chemical
processes things that don't that where you care about the elapsed time.
Civil times are usually the right choice for things in the future.
So like meetings, events, alarms, things where what really matters is that you get there
when everyone agrees that it's noon, not when a certain amount of time has passed.
With absolute times, you can store them as UTC or as a fixed offset.
And with civil times, you generally want to store the local time and sometimes you want
to store the time zone that it's in.
It depends.
Okay.
So with regards to and this is the slides a little bit with regards to so now that we've
established that I'm going to talk about the Python's representation of daytimes.
So Python has a standard library module called daytime.
There's a class in there called daytime that represents a given daytime.
Daytimes are immutable.
So that means that if you try and assign one if you try and change the values of a daytime,
it will not work.
You know, this is useful when you so that you can use them in as the keys for a dictionary
or something like that.
But what that means is instead of if you want to get basically the same daytime but with
something changed, you need to construct a new daytime.
There's a convenience method for that called replace.
So if you you can pass it any number of the keyword arguments that would be passed to
the constructor.
And that's essentially the same thing as saying give me the constructor for this daytime but
with some of the arguments replaced with this.
And this will construct a brand new daytime.
So then there's also a time delta time.
So normally if you think about if you have two integers and you subtract one integer
from another, you get an integer back.
And if you have two floats and you subtract two, you know, one float from another or add
two floats together, you get another float.
These are different in that the class that represents a difference in daytimes is not
a daytime.
It's some elapsed time.
It's time delta.
This represents the difference in the like wall times.
It does not represent a difference in the elapsed time.
So these are this is a difference in civil times basically.
So we can look at that by saying, all right, here is November 2nd at noon.
If I add 24 hours to that, what I get is November 3rd at noon, even though the daylight saving
time has ended and now the UTC offset has changed.
If I convert these both to UTC and then subtract one from the other, instead of getting 24
hours, I get 25 hours, right?
So that's just something to know.
There's a whole workbook in here that we're not going to cover that covers some of the
more complex aspects of arithmetic semantics.
But I just wanted to get just the baseline settled there.
And then another big thing is aware versus naive daytimes.
So a naive daytime, that's just what it's called, is when it has no time zone information.
So the time zone is set to none or it's not specified.
And that just represents a daytime, basically local time.
You can consider it local system time.
You could also consider it an abstract daytime, right?
You're just trying to do calendrical arithmetic.
Basically if you want to know, November 4th is always more than November 5th in the abstract,
even if there's some weird time zone where that's not the case.
And then an aware daytime is one where you've attached a TZ info to it, right?
So this is a daytime that is aware that it is in Eastern time.
And we'll have a whole section on time zones where I go into all the implications of that.
Okay, great.
So now that that is covered, do we have any questions?
So we're all on the same page and we will open up the first workbook.
So the workbooks, if you've loaded a JupyterLab, I want to make sure this is in presentation mode.
And all right, show of hands, who is having trouble seeing if I do this and like that?
Is anyone having trouble seeing it?
Okay, so a little bit bigger then.
How about now?
Anyone having trouble?
Sure, does anyone in the back know how to do that?
Or is this?
All right, I'm just going to start pressing switches and let's just find out.
No?
I think I heard a fire alarm.
Is that good?
All right, great.
Okay, so all right, now show of hands, anyone having trouble seeing this?
Yes, the binder is here.
Okay, so if you have the binder loaded up, you should see here, it probably started you
in materials or it started you here.
So you go into materials and then 01-time underscore zones and then load up the first
workbook which is called Python underscore time zones.
Okay, great.
So now we'll start on working with time zones.
And the first thing I want to address here is that sometimes what you'll hear from people
is like, oh, I don't like to deal with time zones, I just convert everything to UTC as
soon as I get it and then I work with that and it makes everything super easy, right?
This is a fairly common refrain.
It's probably a refrain that may be that may jive with your experience if you're like a
Python admin or something who actually works with absolute times all the time.
But if you're, say, working in like business where you care about market closes and actual
human times or some kind of recurring events, you'll find that that is not actually the
greatest advice because so for example, here, I've constructed an R rule and we'll spend
more time on that later, but this is a recurring rule and what it's going to do is it's going
times during the weekday at five o'clock in New York and that's basically market time
for like market close time for like the New York Stock Exchange, right?
So if I just look at this, you can see it says five o'clock on each of these days and
at some point it switches from being standard time to daylight saving time, right?
And that was just a smooth experience.
Now, if I wanted to just use UTC, what we would get is something where here I'm just
going to convert all those day times we just generated into UTC.
You can see at some point, the market close time stops being at 10 o'clock and it starts
being at like nine o'clock, right?
So if you wanted to just use UTC, you'd have to kind of know what the rules are for that
and then figure out all the kind of aspects of that and there is actually something that
does figure out all those rules and that's the time zone objects.
So unfortunately, as with far too many things with day times, there's not really simple
rules.
I'm not going to be able to just say like here's a little slogan that you can go and
you will be a master of day times.
What's going to happen is I'm going to say, oh, it depends on your use case and, you know,
do really good job testing, I guess.
But hopefully I can give you some ideas of what to look for and how to understand this
problem so that you can identify when you need to understand the shades of meaning between
things.
In Python, the TZInfo class is an abstract base class and all the concrete implementations,
they implement at least these three methods, TZName, UTCOffset and DST.
I'm not going to go into too much detail about exactly what they do, but basically the TZName
tells you what the localized name is at the time that you request it.
UTCOffset is the offset and then DST is actually the difference between standard time and the
current offset.
I would say if you ever find yourself trying to use this DST method, you're probably doing
something wrong.
This concept is not universal enough that I think you can rely on it for all time zones
and you can almost always get away with saying like I don't care whether it's daylight saving
time or not.
I just care about what the name is and what the offset is.
But you'll notice that these all take DT as a parameter, right, and DT meaning daytime.
That's because what happens is if you, what these are is they represent a mapping from
the local time to the absolute time, right, or to the information that you, the information,
the time zone information that applies at that time.
So here I'm going to show you, I have this little function and this function, all it
does is it invokes TZName, UTCOffset, and DST.
And you'll notice that I'm actually invoking these on the daytime.
That's because the TZName, the TZInfo methods are invoked by the daytime itself.
So you only have to know that they're on the TZInfo if you're implementing a TZInfo and
you should probably not be implementing a TZInfo.
So here I just have this thing.
It's going to invoke them, it's going to print these out and I'm going to create a single
time zone object.
This is like, represents Eastern time and I'm using DateUtils TZ module for that.
And then I create a daytime that's in the standard time zone and if I execute that, you can see
that it says Eastern standard time, right, that's what applied on March 1st.
Minus five, no daylight saving time.
And then if I attach the exact same TZInfo to a daytime one month later, which is in
daylight saving time, the offsets change, right?
So this is something to note is that generally you're attaching the exact same Python object
to more than one daytime and these map and it's just a lazily implemented mapping to
get the time zone offsets.
All right, so I have this example.
This was originally an exercise but to be honest, I really don't want to be encouraging
people to be implementing their own time zone classes just because really the answer is
like use a third party time zone provider.
But I can show you how it works which is like def tzname self dt return utc def utc offset
self dt return time delta zero.
I don't know if I imported time delta so I'm going to say from daytime import time delta.
And then I'm going to do def dst self dt.
So this is one thing that you should, that may be worth knowing.
So reasonably speaking, you could return time delta zero here as well because it's always
zero but sometimes for these fixed offsets and in the standard library they do this,
you return none and I think that's useful for certain third party libraries if they
want to detect whether something is a fixed offset or whether it has rules that just aren't
in effect.
I don't rely on it because I don't know that people consistently know about that but there
we go.
That's our UTC thing and these tests, I don't know, that's not a great visual spectacle
but behind the scenes I tested it against the standard library tzinfo.
Okay, so let's get into something a little meatier which is what you probably should
be doing which is working with third party time zone providers.
So there's a little more complexity than we would hope because of historical reasons but
I'm just going to go through, I'm going to be talking about dateutil which is the library
I maintain is also the best library.
That's a completely objective opinion.
And I'm also going to be talking about PyTz which is a legacy module that you should never
use but no honestly it served its purpose very well and there's probably a lot of code
out there that is working perfectly fine that's using PyTz and it is a little dangerous so
you may, I'm just going to try and go through a couple of edge cases so if you see something
like this in production you can fix it.
Okay, so we'll start with our eastern time zone again.
You can see that if I attach it to this date time we have our standard thing, this is 2
o'clock eastern daylight time, right?
So the way I've used this is I've taken the eastern object and I just attached it to the
date time by passing it to the tzinfo argument of the constructor.
I'm not sure if you can pass this positionally, I never do it though.
I always pass this as a keyword argument just, I don't know, it makes things a little clear
just because there's so many positional arguments for date times.
So if I have this thing that I've constructed, if I want to reinterpret this as being in
another time zone, right?
So say we have some meeting that's in New York and then everyone from the meeting all
goes to San Francisco all at the same time and so the meeting is still at 2 o'clock but
we need to just shift the time zone.
I'm just going to use dt.replace, oh and I accidentally pressed capital Z there, and
you can see now here I have 2 o'clock UTC minus 4, the second one is UTC minus 7.
If I want to reinterpret the original meeting, right, so for example in the original meeting
everyone was in New York, maybe instead of everyone moving to San Francisco, someone
from the San Francisco office is now calling in and so we want to know what time they should
call in and the answer is 11 o'clock and we got that from using as time zone.
So replace is saying, just reinterpret this, as time zone is saying kind of do a unit conversion,
give me the same absolute time but represented in a different local time.
Okay, so with PyTZ if you use as time zone it works exactly as expected and in general
PyTZ works well with these methods where you're taking something where you know the absolute
time and converting it to another absolute time.
But if you use a constructor or the replace method which is equivalent, it actually fails
horribly.
So if you notice now what I've done is I've tried to put this in Los Angeles time but
instead of getting what we were expecting up here which is Pacific Daylight Time we're
getting this thing called LMT and its offset is 7 hours and 53 minutes or 7.88 hours so
that's obviously weird, right?
The reason for this is that PyTZ does not use the standard Python time zone model and
I think it's a little beyond scope of this talk to explain exactly why that is but I
do have a blog post on that.
Needless to say it was a good idea at the time and it is no longer really applicable
but what that means is that you can't just attach PyTZ zones either with replace or with
the constructor, what you need to do is you need to call localize on the zone itself because
what PyTZ does is instead of acting as a mapping it just is a factory for static mapping objects,
it's just like when I made that UTC and I hard coded what the TZ name is for all the
date times, PyTZ does that for everything and it decides which offset to attach when
you call localize on the date time.
So here if I use localize and actually I'm just going to change this to Los Angeles so
if I call Los Angeles now we get what we were expecting if we're using localize instead
of just using the constructor.
The same thing will happen if you use arithmetic because if you add 180 days or 6 months or
something what that's basically doing is it calculates what the new date time is and then
attaches the same time zone object to the result.
So what that means is that for date util it works fine because if we add 6 months now
we're in standard time.
Now we're in standard time.
Now I have to change this back.
So now we're in standard time 6 months later but with PyTZ because the same it's hard coded
and doesn't actually pay attention to the date time argument then what that means is
that you're going to see EDT even though this never existed, it was never Eastern Daylight
Time in February.
To fix that you have to call the normalize method which will give you what you would
expect by calling normalize on the result.
So generally my advice is if you see something using PyTZ see if you can use date util instead
and if not you just have to be aware of making sure that you're very diligent about using
localize and normalize.
There are also alternate constructors not the main constructor so there's datetime.now
and datetime.fromTimeStamp.
Both of these take a TZ argument so if you call datetime.now or datetime.fromTimeStamp
both of these are going to take basically an absolute time.
Right now is an absolute time, it's a specific moment in time and they're going to represent
that in your local system time.
Time stamps are also an absolute time, they're Unix epoch times or whatever so they're always
denoted in, they're just numbers, this number of seconds after the Unix epoch so that's
also an absolute time.
Both of these will give you naive datetimes that are represented in the system local time
so the result of this from time stamp will depend on what system you're on.
So here it's 20-20-1-1 I think on the binder because this is running on my laptop which
is set to eastern time.
On the binder this will probably give you a different result like 10 o'clock or something
like that.
So I generally prefer if possible to attach a time zone to it unless you really just want
the local system time that's fine but you can attach a system time to it and it will
work just fine with PyTZ and with datetil.
So here if I take from time zone and I want it in eastern time in both cases I'll get
I'm not sure why those are different.
It doesn't really matter.
What I said is true so I think I may have done something funky here but in any case
you'll see that this is the local time that corresponds to that absolute time in that
time zone.
So generally speaking if you want the local time like now in UTC use datetime.now and
then pass tz equals tz UTC or whatever UTC object you're using.
There are these sort of semi-deprecated methods in the standard library UTC now and UTC from
which will give you a naive local time that is basically the same as passing UTC to the
tz argument and then removing the time zone but honestly I don't recommend using these
because there are other parts of Python that treat naive time zones as local times and
it will cause confusion.
So generally if you want the local time in UTC use the tz argument.
So this brings us to our first argument and I'm sorry that I talked for so long.
And here we're going to work on getting the current time in multiple time zones.
So let's practice using time zones by implementing this function and this function is going to
take as an argument a list of strings and you can pass to get time zones from those
strings if you have from datetale import tz you can do say tokyo equals tz dot get tz
this is the best way to get a time zone from a string.
And that will give you the time zone that you want.
So here just implement this function and what we'd like to do is we'd like to see the current
time printed in all the time zones that are in the list and you'll note that these are
all the exact same time they're not like milliseconds or microseconds after each other that's because
I only use datetime.now one time if you call datetime.now like five times you'll get slightly
different times because it has microsecond precision.
So yeah so go ahead try and implement that and try and use exactly one thing.
If you're having trouble getting started put up one of the red post-its I'll give you a
couple minutes.
Let's take like 10 or 15 minutes for this.
Oh and when you're done put up the green one.
If I start seeing a lot of green in five minutes then we can just move on.
Okay.
you
anyone else having trouble okay
if you're still working feel free to continue working or I can I'm just
going to run through it real quick do a live code and then you know if you want
to try and if you're having problems still and you want to try and see how I
did it hopefully this will help okay so I'm going to show you how I would do
this there's like basically a bunch of slightly different ways that are we'll
all have the same effect so the first thing I'm going to do is I don't really
want to worry about the edge cases with the lists and stuff so I'm just going
to say from date time import time zone I could use it also I could also use date
utils UTC but I'm just going to show you this because then you'll know that it
exists and then I'm going to say dt equals date time dot now time zone dot
UTC that'll get me the daytime in UTC this could be any aware daytime I just
picked UTC because it's a nice reference time and then we'll say for TZS in TZ
list DT say DTL equals DT dot as time zone TZ dot get TZ TZS print DTL and
then there we go oh and if I wanted to have this thing I have to have some more
complicated formatter right so I do something like TZS colon I'm not going to
bother with the other part where it gets them all aligned to the right at the
same time but that is in the answers oh there's also answers for all of these as
well like it's in a Python file that's sibling to the to the exercises forgot
to mention them okay great so does anyone have any questions so far on just
working with time zones by TZ versus date util anything like that time zone
dot UTC is a time zone object which is a subclass of TZ info time zone and time
zone time zone dot UTC is a singleton it's a single instance of time zone
which is fixed offsets and that was added in Python 3.2 so if you use Python
2.7 you you won't be able to use this time zone dot UTC but all of that stuff
is in date util so if you use TZ dot UTC which is another UTC singleton that will
work just as well okay any other questions
yeah is this visible now it's all right even bigger well you should oh yeah here
we go so yeah also pretty I don't know if I did exactly the same thing but I
probably did a much more correct version of it in the in this sibling directory
so if you go to TZ answers you can you can see what you know how I implemented
it there if you if you're having trouble reading the screen okay all right so I'm
gonna move on to the next case which is this is our first interesting edge case
which is ambiguous and imaginary times so obviously and you're always talking
at the water cooler like oh did you see that ambiguous time like so ambiguous
and then they'll be like yeah at least it wasn't imaginary right am I right okay
so but no obviously this is not water cooler gossip this is this is a specific
daytime terminology so an ambiguous time is when you have in a given zone two
different absolute times that map to the same local wall time right so this will
happen anytime you set your clocks back so here I guess it was like Halloween
2004 was I guess a Sunday so the way it worked was that at two o'clock so first
it was 130 and then it was 149 and then it was one o'clock right and the only
difference was Eastern one is Eastern daylight time the other is Eastern
standard time for a long time Python could just literally not handle this
because there was no as we talked about before the TZ info is a mapping from
wall times the naive portion of the daytime to the information that applies
at that time right but these daytime are actually distinguished only by the
offset information so the the only it needs to be an input to the function but
it's also the output that you're trying to calculate so there was just no way to
express this you couldn't round trip anything like this this is in fact why
pi tz has its weird interface because it can handle this but in Python 3.6 pep
495 was accepted and what that does is it introduces a fold attribute to
so what it does is it just adds fold if you set fold equal to one if you set
fold equal if folded defaults to zero if it's zero then it just represents the
first occurrence of the daytime if it's one it represents the second occurrence
of the daytime and zero and one of the only valid options so now we have this
solved and detail can handle this one but of course there's only ever using
Python 3.6 or greater but there is a there is a backport for this so in detail
here I guess what I'm oh so I'll tell I'll talk about the backport in a second
sorry right so if you're dealing with these ambiguous times as time zone will
just always work both for date util and pi tz right because again this is
another one of those situations where this is another one of those situations
where having an existing having an existing absolute time makes these much
easier right so pi tz is always able to calculate the right offset given an
existing absolute time using and date util is always able to calculate what
fold should be given an absolute time because it knows how to do the mapping
pi tz obviously also knows how to do this if you have a sort of naive time if
you're doing replace or wall time or something and you need backwards
compatibility for Python 2 detail also provides an in fold method so what this
does is that on Python 3 it just is like replace fold equals 1 with a little bit
of logic to not do any replacement if the fold is already 1 right but on Python
2 what this does is that if the fold needs to be set to 1 then it will give
you a backport like a backported object which is called date time with fold and
that just adds fold back into the into date time generally speaking you don't
like print these the wrappers of these things but essentially in any case that
I've ever seen you can just use tz dot in fold for all backwards compatible
cases and then when you go to Python 3 only you just replace it with just
regular fold equals 1 okay so that's one side of the story right which is sort of
working with it if you already know that something is ambiguous and you want to
choose one or the other if you want to detect ambiguous times detail will will
has a function for that generally speaking if you just want to always
default to STD you can just pass fold right so if you just pass fold equals 1
then the fold is actually ignored in any case where it's not ambiguous so you
don't really have to know this information too much the one time that
you would want to like call this function is if you have a situation
where you as the developer don't actually know what you want the user to
do or something right so it's actually an ambiguous case and you're saying this
is out of scope or I need to query for for what to do in this case I need a you
know I need a policy or something so you would do something like raise an
exception if if there's an ambiguous case or maybe you just log it right you
say this was an ambiguous case I defaulted to the daylight saving time and
yeah if you just set fold equals one it'll always it'll always it'll just
ignore it if you're not ambiguous okay so the next step is thinking about
imaginary times so the conjugate of ambiguous times where there's two wall
times that have the same nominal value is imaginary times when a nominal wall
clock never even exists in a zone so I mean for some examples you could say
like that example where pi tz was attaching EDT to something in February
that is a kind of ambiguous time or a kind of imaginary time but the more
common one is when there's a gap because you've you're switching your clocks
forward so in this case here it was you know in March of 2004 it was what it was
159 and then it was three o'clock right so nothing about Python will stop you
from constructing an imaginary time right because Python is very lazy about
its time zone handling you only get that information if you need it so if I go
through and I just add one hour or or just do a replace you can see it'll
happily construct imaginary times that's why that detail has this tz dot daytime
exists function so you can check if it exists and then do something with it
whatever you want to do with it right if it doesn't if the time zone doesn't if
the daytime doesn't exist in that time zone you can you know make your choice
there's also this thing called resolve imaginary that I added and that
essentially just skips you forward so if I think you know a lot of times this is
what you want so you're going one you're adding one hour at a time and then
there's a gap right and if you fall into the gap a lot of times you're just like
instead of going from you know from 1 30 to 2 30 just go 130 to 330 but if that
gap is some other weird amount of time that's you can't always just add an hour
so resolve imaginary handles that so here's a case where in Kirboss in like
1994 they wanted to switch which side of the international dateline they were on
so there was just a missing day and I think I guess the missing day was all of
December 31st so it was like December 30th and then the next day was January
1st so an interesting story about this this was in my test suite in date detail
and then someone was like digging through the like South Pacific news
newspapers or whatever and they're like you know in the time zone database this
is saying that January 1st was skipped but in the newspapers it says that
December 31st was the one that was skipped and then they're like oh that
was our mistake and then they updated it and now I have this weird check which is
like oh is this imaginary well maybe a little check if the other one's
imaginary so even like the past is sometimes the mappings in the past are
sometimes not super stable okay so again I recommend using date
detail but if you have to use pi tz I'm going to just give you the information
that you need to understand it so with pi tz they use the localize function and
if you localize something it defaults to the if you localize an ambiguous
daytime it will default to the to the the standard side which was what the
Python standard library originally said to do if you want to get the first
occurrence or the daylight saving time side you pass to localize is underscore
DST equals true and I think that's ignored if it's not ambiguous so here
if I want to localize these you can pass is DST equals false or nothing and it'll
give you the standard side passes DST equals true and it will give you the
daylight saving time side but if you want to detect ambiguous times then you
pass is DST equals none and what it'll do is it will throw this ambiguous time
error so if you want to recreate the date detail version of the daytime
underscore ambiguous then you would just do this try catch for imaginary times pi
tz will happily create a an imaginary daytime and then it'll just assign it
like an offset based on what you say for is DST which again I think defaults to
false and if you pass and if you pass it none then it will raise this pi tz dot
non-existent time error so basically you can get you know other than the fact
that pi tz uses weird localized method they have they have a method to handle
everything you can do with the date util with pi tz though again I don't
necessarily recommend it so here's another exercise which is hopefully we
have yeah I think we have time for this what I'd like you to do is say that you
have some system you can you can see where my bias is here right let's
imagine that you have some system and we're gonna call it a legacy system
that's using pi tz and someone's like well we have all this behavior based
around pi tz's localized stuff and you say well you know what I am a big
proponent of date util so what I'd like to do is I would like to write this
compatibility function for you it's going to be called localized and it
basically does exactly what pi tz is localized does it takes a daytime a tz
info and then is DST and it recreates pi tz's functionality about raising errors
this is something you may actually legitimately want anyway in terms of
again you know if you want the is DST equals non behavior okay so let's take
15 minutes for that again put up the the red if you have a problem and the green
if you're done and I'll come around
you
behavior of pi tz that I neglected to mention but I actually am testing for is
localized can only be used on naive time zones and normalized can only be used on
aware time zones so you may have implemented this and then it's like
you're not raising value error just note that that's because if if we're
actually trying to build a pi tz style exactly localizer then it wants you to
raise value error if you get a time zone if you get a daytime with a tz info
attached so if the tz info is not none so was that clear is anyone unclear on
that okay so
unless you're naive maybe I'm maybe yeah sorry yeah localized tz info has to be
none normalized tz info cannot be none so you're to me that's like localized
normalizes is the same as localized except for aware date times so let's just
focus on localized localized has to be called on naive date times if you call
it on a on an aware date time then it will raise an error
you
feel free sorry I keep messing with this microphone after this please do send me
feedback because I realized that some of these am error messages are probably
ambiguous I could probably do better so I'm very much looking forward to
adjusting this tutorial for future people so just saying that by the way I
think we're at 15 minutes do we have one more question let's take one more
minute how many how many people are have something that works even a little bit
just like a couple okay I'll give you like one or two more minutes
you
Okay, so it's been 15 minutes. How many people finished? Show of hands. Like one. Okay. All
right. Well, I'm just going to go through it. Just, and I realize now, all right, how
many people were like 70% done? All right. And how many people were like 50% done? And
how many people just didn't know how to start? Okay. Yeah, that's what the red sticky is
for, guys. Like, I'm surprised, given that there's 50 people, I'm surprised at how little
I've had to, like, walk around. So feel free to, you know, I hope I don't regret saying
that, but feel free to, like, make extra use of that red sticky. Because I want everyone
to get something out of this for sure. All right. So I'm just going to show you how I
would do it. It's that, but I'll say, okay, so the first thing I'm going to handle is
I'll check the case that we, the edge case that we mentioned about the value error. So
if dt.tzinfo is not none, raise value error, localize can only be used with time zone,
time zones. And, you know, I really hope no one hears on the Unicode standards committee
because I did not use the dioresis in naive. I'm just, I'm so sorry about that. I just
don't know how to type it. So then what I'm going to do is I'll handle the isDST. So there's
two ways you can do this. One, you can just set the fold one way or the other, and it'll
just, it will work. So I'll show you how to do that. I'll show you that way, right, which
is just to say dt.fold equals int. I mean, you don't really have to do the int part,
but not isDST. I'm not sure if the semantics of this are exactly right because I suppose
there are possibilities, there's possibilities where you're like in Ireland, this might cause
some problem. This might be slightly different, but those are very hard to detect. But they're
not in the test suite either way. But just to note that the fold has an inverted sense
of isDST because the standard, usually you're going from daylight saving time to standard
time when you're setting your clocks back. So that means standard time is the second
occurrence, which means fold should be one. And then we'll say if, oh wait, actually first
I have to say if isDST is none, we'll say, now this is the case where we have to throw
an error. So we'll say try, actually we'll say if tz.datetime.ambiguous dt.replace, oh
wait, I can just do this. Raise, oh and also I can't do that. I'm sorry. Raise, ambiguous
time error. Okay. And then I'll say lf tz.datetime. sorry, datetime underscore ambiguous. I don't
know why I thought this should be datetime exists and not datetime imaginary. Dt tzi
is nonexistent time error. Dt does not exist in tzi. And then finally we'll say fold equals,
actually I'll say fold equals zero. Else fold here. And then finally I do dt.replace tzinfo
equals tzi.fold equals fold. And we're going to return that. And let's check the tests.
And it passes all the tests. Another way to do this would be instead of setting, here
I'm just setting the fold like indiscriminately, which means that if I do like localize datetime.now
tz.get tz America New York, then it's going to set fold equals one even though this is
not an ambiguous time. So if I want to fix that, I can say, I mean, fixed. It doesn't
really matter. But if I say if tz.datetime ambiguous dt tzi, that'll still pass all
the tests. And when I localize it, it won't have the fold. So there we go. And that works.
Great. So I'm going to, at this point, I'm going to skip the last two workbooks. The
first one is about handling local times. You should be able to read through it. And
it's fine. One thing I will note is if you go through this, if you go through this locally
and you don't have time zone information, some of these demos won't work. Like I noticed
the demos didn't quite work when I tried it on the binder originally and I had to install
the tz.data. Windows, it will definitely not work because it turns out that this is something
you may want to know. If you change the system time zone during the course of a Python run,
like say if you wanted to demonstrate what it looks like to do some Python things that
take place in different locales on Windows, it will just not do it. Like you have to restart
Python to get the new local time zone information. And there's pretty much no way around that.
You can get different local time zone information if you use datetil.tz.tzwinlocal. But I was
trying to demonstrate something else. So go ahead and work through these two. Probably
do the local time one on the binder if you're on Windows. And frankly, I haven't tested
any of this on Windows, so it might all be broken.
Yes. I mean, there's datetil.tz.tzwinlocal, which actually queries the registry whenever
you construct it. And the registry will get updated. You have to call this tzset function
in time in order to get datetil.tzlocal to work. So generally speaking, try not to change
your local time zone while a Python run is happening. It doesn't happen too often. But
yeah, there's a lot of edge cases around that.
Okay. All right. Let's see. All right. So I think the break is probably at 3 o'clock.
So we're going to go through the serializing and deserializing. So you can go, if you're
in the time zone one, just go up one level to materials and then go down one level to
02-serializing underscore deserializing. And we'll open the first workbook. We may not
get to the other workbooks, but at least the first workbook is a good start.
So yes.
Yeah. So not is DST. Fold has the opposite sense of is DST because, well, I mean, they
just map to different concepts. So is DST is like, are you on the daily saving time
side? But there are other situations that could cause folds. So for example, like Portugal
at one point canceled the saving time and they wanted to do it with a minimum of problems.
So what they did was they just waited until daylight saving time or they shifted their
base offset. So they shifted their base offset. So instead of being UTC plus two during standard
time, they switched to being like UTC plus one or UTC plus three. I forget which one.
And they were, I think they were also canceling daylight saving time or maybe not. I don't
know. But they.
Oh, no, it's going to be true, false or none. Yeah. Yeah. So like if you were going to write
this, it would be, yeah, sorry. I misunderstood that. It would be like bull and then none
or something or optional or actually. And I think this would have to be. Yeah. So false
means choose standard time if it's an option. True means choose daily saving time if it's
an option and none means throw an error if you're uncertain. So that's exactly what
Pytz does. You can see it up here, right? Where here true does one thing, false is the
default. It does another thing. And then none throws errors. Yeah. Okay. So any other questions
on this? Okay. Great. All right. Let's jump to workbook one strings. All right. So, no,
go for it. Yes. Is DSC kind of has the inverse sense of false. I mean, yeah. Yeah, they
are. But I cast it to int. I mean, you don't like you don't have to. Oh, yeah. If you pass
true or false, it will just get cast to int like automatically. I think I mean, you could
I'm not even sure you may be able to pass the string zero or one. I don't I don't I
don't know. Yeah. The reason why it's zero or one I think is because the underlying representation
if you add just an unsigned character instead of like a Boolean, it wouldn't make the times
take up any more space because of the alignment the padding for alignment in the C structure.
So like I think they were like very specific that the only valid values are not like Python
objects. They're like zero or one. Yeah. Okay. Cool. So let's jump into serializing and deserializing
date times. And then I think there's well, we can stop for a break at three o'clock. I think
that's also when there's going to be like tea and stuff outside. Okay. So serializing and
deserializing date times. So I have a couple workbooks on here. The second two are probably
going to have to be just do self-paced. But this is a fairly common operation that you're going
to do, right? Because you need to represent your date times in some format that's either going to
be independent of programming language or you're going to have to transmit it to something that
you really shouldn't be transmitting like Python binary objects or maybe you're just sort of
serializing it by writing it to a log file that a human being is going to read. Generally speaking,
if a human is going to read it, you're going to want to use some sort of a string representation
that's unambiguous and compact. If no human is going to read it, we would jump to workbook two
and probably just represent it as like a number because that can be easier. And then workbook
three, I don't have time to go into it, but I deal with JSON because JSON, as with many other
programming language and such, including Python, frankly, don't treat date times as a kind of
first class type. You know, they're not primitive types, but they're so common that it causes a
lot of problems when people just have to create all their own different standard ways to represent
them. And so the JSON standard does not have any way to represent date times. So you just have to
represent it as a string and then have a schema that says this is a date time, convert it from a
date time, or you have to have some sort of self-describing superset of JSON where it's like,
oh, if I have a little curly bracket and it says object and then date time and then string or
whatever. So the last one at least lets you add hooks for JSON, but you have to work out all the
stuff that goes around that because it's not standardized. YAML, on the other hand, does
standardize date times but has other problems. Okay. So, oh, and one other thing I'd like to note
before I go on to this deserializing and serializing of strings is the difference between what I'm
calling deserializing and parsing. So deserializing does involve a parse because it involves taking a
string and then turning it into the actual core values and turning that into a date time object.
But that's really a subset of all parsing tasks, right? Because a lot of times when you think of
parsing, you're thinking of things like maybe parsing user input, right, where they're going to be
typing a date time as a string and it might be in one of 16 million different formats or someone
from the business team gives you an Excel spreadsheet and they've got a column with half the
date times are like year, year, year, slash month, month, slash day, day, and then the other half are
like year, year, dash month, month, dash day, day, or some other weird thing like that. And you as a
programmer are not able to be like, well, I really only support this one format, right, because you
don't control what your users do. And if you make that mistake, you're going to be making the same
mistake as whatever programmer is making it so that someone named John Null is unable to get on
airplanes, right? Oh, John Null, that's just some fake thing. It's probably test data. Let's just
throw it away. You don't get to choose how people are going to give you their date time formats
necessarily, and you also don't get to choose what people's names are going to be. But when you're
deserializing, and that's why I was very specific about that's what we're going to cover here,
that's because it's either you're reading it from a serialization format, which is standardized,
right, so you're saying part of the standard is that we use ISO 8601, which itself is actually quite
ambiguous. And then, or it's maybe something you generated yourself, right, so it's like you're
writing some sort of microservice kind of operation, and you just have some interchange format, and
maybe you want to be able to read the data in packet captures or something, so you want it to be
strings, but you don't have to worry about arbitrary date times because you're controlling both sides.
So we're going to be talking about the latter case, the case where you control both formats, but, you
know, this is a refrain I go to a lot with date time, and with a lot of things, honestly. It depends
on your use case, and try and be careful about not mistaking one use case for another.
Okay, so when you're going for a string format, you want something that's going to be unambiguous,
something that's going to be easy to parse, preferably fast, and ideally fairly compact, right, you don't
want it to take up a huge amount of space. So probably there's two ways to do this. One, you can use
strf time, and in that case, it will be, as long as you know what the format is, the format string
you choose, it will be unambiguous, but it may not be unambiguous to people who don't know what that
string is. If you use iso format, which does a very specific subset of iso 8601, though it's also
able to generate a superset of iso 8601, so, yeah, things are complicated. There is an easy way to
invert iso format, and then there's, and mostly people looking at iso 8601 day times, they will just
be able to look at it and say, that's what this is, right. It's unambiguous that it goes year, month,
day, because, you know, the only middle Indian people are like the Americans, and we usually
represent it day, wait, day, month, day, year, yeah. Sorry. I mean, yeah, I'm Canadian. I didn't just
say TZ a million times. Canadians say Zed. Sorry. Anyway, yeah, so we have this datetime.iso format.
It has two arguments, sep, which specifies what the separator between the date portion and the time
portion is going to be. It defaults to T, which is what the standard says you should do. And then
time spec, which determines the amount of truncation. And you can tell that I was putting off
writing the rest of this talk because I spent like an inordinate amount of time making this ASCII
diagram. So we're just going to bask in that for like a couple seconds. Look at this. Yeah. All right.
So this is all the formats that it can generate. Basically, the default is that it will generate
this much if there are, if there's no microseconds. So if the microseconds are zero, it'll, the auto
will generate this. And if the microseconds are anything other than zero, it'll generate that. If
there's a time zone attached, it will generate as much of this portion as is necessary. So usually
it's HHMM. If you're in some weird time zone, like one of the Pytz LMT zones, you'll sometimes get
seconds. I don't know of any times when you'll get microseconds, but there is support for that. So
like we can take a look. You can see if I have microseconds, it looks like that. If I have, if I
don't have microseconds, it'll auto truncate. If I want to specifically make sure that I have
microseconds, I can just specify any one of these things to say use all of that. There's no way to
specify this. You can't always get microseconds for the time zone portion of it. You can also specify
more truncation. So you can say hours, and then even though I have stuff in minutes and seconds,
it'll just get truncated. If you want something that's more like what you print, like the statement
for printing a daytime, you can change the separator to a space or change it to whatever you want.
That can actually be any Unicode character. Like I think even like weird non-supported, like things
not in UTF-8, like surrogate characters and stuff. And then for aware daytimes, you can see it'll
just have this offset. And then, right, it supports all of these things. So before Python 3.7, there
was no way to invert this. Like literally no way to cover all the use cases. Even STRP time wasn't
able to handle it because STRP time only supported the inverse of STRF time, and STRF time does not
have this colon, and there's no way to specify it. Python 3.7 brings two additions. One is STRP time,
if you use the %z directive, it will now parse it correctly even if there's a colon. And then the
other thing it brings is from ISO, which is the same thing as Python 3.7, is the same thing as
Python 3.7. It will now parse it correctly even if there's a colon. And then the other thing it brings
is from ISO format. And I know all this weird stuff about the separators and stuff because I actually
added from ISO format to Python. So what this does is, and I also am like super specific about the
guarantees, like most people will be like, oh, it just parses ISO 8601 time. So I'm like, no, you're not
going to parse it correctly. Because what it actually does is it inverts the output of ISO format.
It's a subtle difference, but it's a difference in the contract, right, which means that there's not going to be a
z at the end. Like you can't take any ISO 8601 date time and parse it with this. You can only take things
out of the output of ISO format. If you want something that parses ISO 8601 date times and only
ISO 8601 date times, dateutil has dateutil.parser.iso parse. And that will work for a wider array of date
times. And yeah, so that will work. And that will also work before Python 3.7. But this is much faster.
It's an interesting thing to note is that from ISO format, if you pass it a data.py, it will
pass it a string literal. It's actually faster to do that to get a date time than to create a
date time literal. Like it's maybe twice as fast. And the reason for that is this is just on CPython,
and I wouldn't rely on that because we might optimize other things. But it turns out the reason
for that is CPython spends a surprising amount of time parsing the arguments. So if you
pass a string to a date time, it's like, oh, turn that into a C string and then the parse takes like
10 nanoseconds and then it spends most of the time constructing the date time. So anyway, that's some
weird optimization thing that you probably shouldn't, it's like dangerous knowledge, you probably
shouldn't even know it. So great. So that brings us to our exercise, which is write a function to
parse a log message. We have this bonus exercise down here that I'm going to tell you about now
because we're not going to get to it, which is this is some logger format, and we're going to use
an ISO 8601 date time because these are absolute times. And we're going to be time zone aware, we're not
going to make it UTC because when you're reading logs, you prefer to see things that are at least kind
of in the ballpark of what your local time is, right? And if you want to configure your parser to
have something that from ISO format can understand, you have to reconfigure it. So that's the bonus
exercise is to actually change the logger to work this way. And it turns out that if you want to
ignore the microseconds part and you also don't want to be able to like, you know, and you don't
want this colon, it's like trivial to do this. And it's like a nightmare to do if you don't want
that because you have to like subclass formatter and then like do all this weird stuff. So feel free
to try your hand at that if you're going to be like the logging guru, but otherwise it's probably not
worth your time. So yeah, so we're going to say that someone like slaved over this and figured out
how to generate this output just to make it easier for you to do the log messages. And we'd like to
write a parser that will take this, it'll break it apart, and then it'll have some structured
JSON object that has the field's date time, which is the date time, and then level, which we'll just
keep it as a string if you want to map it to an enum, like if you're super fancy, you can do that,
but don't waste too much time on it. And then the name and then the message. In the test suite, I
don't have anything where like the message contains a colon or anything, so that's fine. But if you
want to handle that edge case, you could just use split with like, split takes a second argument, and
if you pass it four, it'll be fine. Okay. Great. So let's take like 10 minutes for this.
And I think that brings us to the break, so you can work into the break or whatever. I'll be around
and make sure I can help. So green when you're done, red if you need help.
Okay.
So it's three o'clock now. I think three o'clock was like the schedule break time. I'm not
entirely sure, but maybe, like, refreshments out there. Should I just go over the answer real
I'm sure a lot of you are probably still working on it,
but I'll just show it to you,
and then you can pay attention or not,
and I'll be around during the break
so you can ask me questions
if you just wanna keep working on it.
But the way I would do this is I would say,
let's say DTSTR level name message equals line.split,
name message equals line.split,
splitting on a colon with two spaces on it.
Stay on page for sure.
And then I'm gonna put four
because I want at most four of these.
And then I will say, or I want,
like yeah, at most four I think.
And then I just have to convert the DT string into a,
into a date time.
So date time from ISO format DTSTR.
Then we can return date time DT level,
level name, name, message, message.
And there we go.
And we'll check the tests.
There we go.
So that's how I did it.
So we'll do a break.
I'm gonna lose some of the message
if the message contains Facebook.
Oh no, actually I won't.
See here, look.
Blah, blah.
Two, wait.
Sorry, this should be a three.
But I'm gonna do a break.
So I'm gonna do a break.
But the second argument to split
truncates how many,
it's like if you find this three times,
once you find this three times,
like stop, yeah, just like keep going for the end.
So yeah, I always forget if it's like the number
of values you want returned
or the number of separators off by one.
Okay, yeah.
So we'll start up again at 320.
Head out there.
If someone like starts yelling at you,
like get back in the room,
like just let me know, I guess.
Yeah, I'll be here for your questions on this or anything.
It's 323 and someone asked me a question about leap seconds,
so my ire is up.
So I think we'll jump right into something soothing
and talk about recurring events.
So, right.
So just a reminder,
we're skipping the other two workbooks
in the serializing and deserializing.
Those will just be self-paced.
So if you're interested in that,
you can go to the link in the description
in deserializing.
Those will just be self-paced.
And we're gonna jump to section 03-recurring-events,
workbook 01, introduction.
So the first workbook just has one example thing.
And as you're going along,
you can feel free to run some of these,
I have some little bonus exercises you can play around with,
but I wanna make sure that we definitely get
to the second workbook
because I think that's a more fun exercise.
It was fun for me,
so I don't know how well that generalizes.
Okay, so we're gonna talk about recurring events.
You would hope that it would be easy
to express a recurring event
because it's like this just happens every day
or it happens every five hours or something,
but I think we all know where this is going.
That's obviously not going to be terribly simple
because we have a lot of overloaded terms in daytimes
and we have a lot of colloquial meanings
like what is the length of one month
or even one year, right?
There's not a fixed amount of time that elapses in one month.
So we need some kind of better way to clearly
and in a standard way express things that recur.
So I think the best standard that we can get for this
comes from RFC 5545, which is the iCalendar spec.
And this is actually like some kind of string format
that is used for interchange
between different like calendar systems.
I think maybe ICS is based on this.
And it's like this long spec.
This is the second version.
There's another version that this displaced.
And then there are addendums to this
and it's like 170 pages of like iCalendar stuff.
And we are going to represent all our recurring times
using the data type that's defined
in like subsection 3.3.10.
So it has like all these different types
and of this 170 page spec,
the next two workbooks will be devoted
to a type defined in these eight pages.
So I try and be as compliant with the spec as possible
with my date util implementation of this.
But some of the things are a little dicey
and there were some non-compliant stuff
that was already there before I took over date util.
Another note is in date util,
the way this worked out was that RFC 2445
was standardized in the IETF
and then date util was written.
And then it was updated with RFC 5545
at like five or six years later
and date util never got totally upgraded.
So I have some support for 5545.
If you're interested in making open source contributions,
I would love to see more support.
The code in here is kind of tricky,
but I would love to see someone go in there
and take a crack at it.
Okay, so the type that we're talking about
is called an R-rule, which is a recurrence rule.
It describes a recurrence.
There are three fundamental elements.
There are required elements.
There's DT start, which is the start date of the recurrence.
And if you're a physicist,
this is kind of like the phase of it.
This has some consequences.
Basically, anything that doesn't recur,
it picks up its original elements from the DT start.
So that's something to note.
And then there's freak,
which is the fundamental frequency
and that can be yearly, monthly,
weekly, daily, hourly, minutely, or secondly.
And then there's interval,
which is basically the multiplier for freak, right?
So if you have, so let's work with these actually.
So first I'm gonna import all these like
weird constants and stuff.
And then I'm gonna describe this rule,
which is an hourly rule.
So hourly is an R-rule.
Its frequency is hourly.
Interval is one,
and it starts on this day in 2016 at 9 a.m.
So when I print this,
you can see that it does what you would expect, right?
It generates a daytime at nine,
and then one at 10, and then one at 11.
And these things are also like at least semi-immutable,
but instead of mutating them,
you really should, even if it's possible,
you should use replace to generate a new one.
So now I'm just gonna take that original rule,
and I'm just gonna change DT start, right?
So if I change DT start to 10 o'clock,
we get the same hourly rule, three occurrences,
10, 11, 12, right?
Straightforward.
And then interval, if I change that from one to two,
the multiplier on hourly changes from one to two, right?
So what that means is that I'm gonna get nine, 11, and 13
instead of nine, 10, 11.
I'm not sure, like this is a very redundant spec,
so generally I would say go with the simplest possible rule
that you can, and I think try to minimize
the number of dates that are filtered out.
Well, I'll get to that.
Okay, so normally, if you'll notice,
I have this count argument here.
Normally, if you just take an R rule,
and you don't limit it in any way,
you don't put count or until,
that's just kind of a more abstract thing,
and it says generate recurrences indefinitely.
Indefinitely just means until the year 10,000
when the daytime class can't represent it anymore,
and then it throws an error.
So generally, these things are just like,
they lazily generate your datetimes,
so it's pretty easy to generate them,
but then as long as you don't call list on it,
it'll be fine.
But if you wanna clearly limit it,
there are two options, there's count and until.
Count says give me this number of them.
I want, in this case, I was like, show me three of them.
There's also until, so you can imagine,
oh, I have bar mitzvah practice at Hebrew school
or whatever every Saturday at 12,
but then when you turn 13,
you're gonna get bar mitzvahed,
so then that is no longer necessary.
So you would generate a rule that happens every Saturday
and then it stops on your 13th birthday.
So that would be an example of our rule.
And then you can also, as I mentioned before,
if you have one of these things that is indefinite,
you can also just get a subset of them.
So there's no natural number that you want.
You just really want, okay, I want the next occurrence
after next Friday or the last occurrence of this
before some date.
So there are three options.
There's after, before, and between.
After and before generate just one daytime
and then between generates a list.
So here I have this monthly thing.
It says every four months starting in 1995.
And I can just say, all right, so given this rule,
I wanna know the next thing,
there's an even number of months,
an even number of four month intervals after this time,
after 2015, like February 2015.
And you can see that it's March 10th.
And then the last one before 1997 is in November of 1996.
And then all of the recurrences in 2001
is between 2001, January 1st and January 1st, 2002.
And we get these three occurrences.
Okay, so I'm not gonna pause for this,
but feel free to like, if you can listen
and do it at the same time to just play around
and generate something that does every day at 1.30
or like every other week for six weeks.
Or and then play around with like,
what does after do after the last recurrence?
I think it probably returns none.
Oh, and the other thing is, I forgot to mention this,
but count and until are mutually exclusive.
So you can't use both.
You can implement something that will use both
in a sense, which is to say like you specify one
and then you just generate dates and then throw an error
or stop iterating over it once you reach the until.
But the spec says that you can specify one or the other
and not both.
So I think right now it's just a warning,
but it will eventually be an error in detail.
Okay, so that's fairly simple.
That's something you could basically do with time delta
other than with the yearly and stuff.
But then it gets a little more complicated
when you use these by rules.
So by rules are rules that modify the base recurrence.
So for example, and they have like by month,
by month day, by year day, by week number, by weekday.
And then these like exotic ones like by set pause.
This by Easter is the only thing that's not in the spec
that's in date util.
I think like this since the beginning of date util,
it's had support for calculating Easter.
And I don't know, like maybe the original developer was like,
well, we got these Easter days around,
like we might as well.
But I can imagine it being useful if you schedule something
that has to happen on Good Friday or something, right?
So the way these are interpreted
is a little counterintuitive.
And I wish I had like an intuitive explanation
of why it works this way.
And I'm sure there is one like based on the Nyquist theorem
or something, but I just haven't come up with it yet.
But when the by XXX rule,
or like when the by rule specifies component
whose like duration is greater than or equal
to the frequency, then it's a constraint
and it's gonna reduce the frequency of the occurrence.
So for example, here, I have this R rule and R rule,
it's daily, so it's gonna generate every single day.
It's going to generate it.
And then I'm gonna use these larger components
by month of 11 and by weekday, Tuesday,
that's equal to, it's like roughly equal to a time, right?
And so what that means is it's gonna start,
it's gonna generate a bunch of daily,
it's gonna generate one instance every single day.
And then if that day is not in November,
or if that day is not Tuesday,
then it will ignore that and move on to the next one, right?
So I've set a count of five and I have this restricted,
but I'm starting in January of 2015.
And if you look, I get, just with my count of five,
I get four dates, four Tuesdays in November in 2015
and one in 2016.
So you can see how like the count interacts with this
where you're generating a specific number of days
that have these rules, right?
So the by rules for larger components, they're filters
and it'll just filter everything out except for this.
Oh, and these accept scalars and they also accept
like pretty much any container type.
So tuples, lists, things like that.
If the rule is less than the frequency,
then it increases the number of occurrences, right?
So here's another rule.
This is a monthly rule and there are more,
there's more than one day in a month, right?
So the by month day is a lower frequency
or is a higher frequency.
The duration is shorter than a month, right?
So these by month days are gonna increase
the number of occurrences.
So what I have here is I say every month
on the first 15th and 30th of the month,
I want recurrences.
So you can see, even though the DT start is not a recurrence,
it's gonna give me the first,
it starts with the first one that is the 30th
and then it gives me the first 15th.
And you'll note that at the end of the month,
it didn't like fall back to January or to February 28th
and it didn't like jump forward to March 1st.
Well, I guess you could imagine that it did,
but I'll tell you it did not.
So, because if I change this to the second of the month,
you can see that it went, it goes to March 2nd, right?
The rule is that if a date time does not exist
in the calendar system, then you skip it.
And there's no way to configure this in DateUtil.
There is a way to configure it
in the more recent specs, but it's like,
it's a little complicated to implement
and I haven't done it yet.
So I've used by weekday a couple times.
This is kind of one of the more interesting ones
and it has kind of a little complicated use case,
like the way it interacts with the other components.
Weekday is one that you'll use a lot
and it just says that a recurrence will happen
on a specific day of the week.
And normally I just use the constants directly,
like Tuesday, Friday, something like that.
But occasionally you want to use,
you want something like the first Friday of the month
or the last Friday of the month.
So you can pass an argument and this is an index
and it's an index into the number of occurrences
of like the Friday or of that day of the week
within the period of the frequency.
So if the frequency is anything less than monthly,
it will just give you every Friday
no matter what number you put there.
If you use a monthly rule, then it will give you just,
in this case, the first Friday of the month
and the last Friday of the month.
So this is the first Friday, that's the last Friday.
If the frequency is, oh sorry,
this one is first Friday, last Friday,
first Friday, last Friday.
If the frequency is yearly,
then it will give you the first Friday of the year
and the last Friday of the year.
So this interaction I found out about
when I was writing these slides.
So it's not super well known.
Yes.
Is the onset based off of the painter's definition
that it is the onset that first opened
and then it was merely the onset in the beginning?
I mean, this is not a Python thing.
It comes from the iCalendar.
So yeah, I think it's a one-based index in both directions.
So the first and the last is minus one, the first is one.
Right.
So yeah, and for the small ones,
this is every Friday.
But yeah, so generally speaking with these,
unless you actually need a very specific frequency
for the reason that you're using these weekday things
and it actually matters what the frequency is,
try and keep the frequency.
Basically think about what it would look like
without, what the rule would look like
without filtering anything out
and try and pick the thing that generates
the least number of daytimes that get filtered out
because under the hood,
that will actually make things much slower.
So if I had a secondly rule
that generates every single second
from like with DT start of like 1970
and then I'm like filtering by day
and by hour and by minute and by second
so that it's actually just like a specific time of day
once a year, it will generate like thousands
and thousands of daytimes
and then most of them will get filtered out.
So I mean, maybe it doesn't generate actual daytimes
but it does a whole lot of math that it doesn't need to do.
So try and keep the filtering to a minimum
for performance reasons
but don't jump to that until you're starting
to see performance problems probably.
I mean, it's like a good baseline thing to do
but it may be that in six months
I find some way to like normalize these things
and there will actually be no performance difference.
So I'm just gonna show an example
of how you can use this to generate something
that may be hard to express otherwise.
Martin Luther King Day is a US holiday
and it's always the third Monday in January.
And its first observance was in 1986.
So let's say DT start equals date time 1986, 1, 1
and we'll do our rule will be frequency equals monthly
frequency equals monthly because it,
we need the third Monday of the month.
And then by weekday equals Monday one.
I guess I don't need this.
And then it needs to be in January.
So we'll say by month equals one.
And then I think that is it, right?
The third month, oh, you're right.
It's the third Monday, not the first one.
Yeah, but this is a monthly rule.
So otherwise it would generate January, February.
Yeah, I mean, you could use this if you had like a meetup
every third Monday of the month or something, right?
And then we need DT start, DT start.
I think by default DT start will be just like
the current date time.
So always specify your DT start interval defaults to one
frequency is required.
Okay, so we'll test this and I guess it just passed.
Sorry, I need more, I need more flare with these
or it like prints some amazing thing.
So yeah, so you can see how this would be useful.
There's also something related to this for things like this
which is called relative delta.
And that's a workbook we're not gonna get to
but it's materials slash zero four.
And there's like another 20 minutes worth of material there.
Okay, so we have an hour left.
I'd like to take this, we're gonna do this last workbook.
This is like a very interactive one.
So I think we're gonna do 10 minutes per exercise for this
and then depending on when we're done,
we can either jump back to one of the workbooks we skipped
or we can just do like 20 minutes of Q&A
or something like that.
Or we won't even get it done by in the next hour.
So let's see how it goes.
All right, so so far, honestly,
the things that we've done with our rules are,
well, sorry, the things that we've done with our rules so far
can get you very far, right?
They can do things like most holidays,
they can get you most kinds of meetings and things like that.
But there's kind of also more complicated things
like for example, every Sunday of the year,
except for Mother's Day, right?
And there's no way to express that
because it's actually like kind of an overlap
of two different rules, right?
And that's what our rule set is for.
Our rule set is kind of like a set of recurrences.
And the way it works is that you can combine
basically anything that generates,
you can combine basically anything that generates date times
to make just a set of recurrences.
And the interface looks like this.
Each one of these our rule sets is mutable,
so you'll construct one and then you'll just sort of
add things to it and subtract from it.
It has our rule which adds a recurrence rule to the set,
X rule which cancels out recurrences,
our date which is like adding one off dates,
and then X date which cancels one off dates.
So let's play around with this.
Right, so we'll start with our rule.
When you have two our rules and they can be combined
to make one set of recurrences.
So for example here, I have two rules.
One is the end of the month and the other is like
the last Friday of the month.
So you can imagine maybe you have some kind of event
that happens at the end of the month
and also the last Friday, like you have an alarm
and you want it to happen on the last Friday
because the developers are in,
it's like the day before they're gonna go out
for the weekend and then maybe you also want an alarm
for that anyone who's on call will actually see.
During the day that it's actually possibly
gonna be a problem which is like
some monthly transition or something.
I don't know why I spent so much time on this flavor text.
So here's what I have, right?
I have expressed these two things
and I kind of snuck in this end of the month rule
because this is actually a kind of hard thing to express
without that skipping back thing.
So this uses by set pause which I did not spend any time
talking about and you can like read the spec
and if you do that you'll probably understand it
even better than me but it's basically saying
like generate like this monthly thing generates
four day times in its set or up to four
depending on which ones exist and then by set pause
it's saying filter that down to be the last one.
So that's how this one works.
Yeah.
I think no.
I suppose it's, I don't know.
Let's see.
Oh, then maybe it does work.
I don't know.
Maybe, yeah, honestly I didn't even realize
that this one worked and then I like was reading something
and I was like oh my goodness this works
and then I like found myself talking about that
a year earlier like oh my goodness this works.
So I like learned things about this
and then immediately forget it.
So yes, I suppose it's very possible
that if by month they worked when you checked it out
then either there's an edge case that I wasn't thinking
about or I was just being stupid when I made these slides.
I think both of them are well within the realm
of possibility.
Okay, so no matter how we've constructed it
I can now combine these two and I have my R rule set.
I add one R rule, I add the other R rule
and then we're gonna print them out.
And so you'll notice I have two entries in March
and I have two entries in April
but then in May I only have one entry, right?
And the reason for that is that the last day of the month
in May is a Friday.
And the sort of set part of this is not really,
that's not just like,
it actually has properties like a set has
in the sense that if more than one recurrence rule
is generating a given daytime
it will only show that recurrence once.
So in this case both rules generated the last day of May
and so it said, okay, we'll just generate the last day of May
and ignore all the other rules that are also generating
the last day of May.
So that's something.
So now we're gonna start the exercise.
And this exercise here, it runs through the whole workbook
and it's essentially, so they build off of one another.
So if you end up messing things up
you may have to end up using kernel restart
and run all cells a couple times just in case like,
cause you know how Jupiter has state that can persist
in a way that you don't realize it.
So the exercise is that we're gonna build a bus schedule
and bus schedules can be complicated.
So hopefully we can see some of the complexity.
So the way it works, what we're gonna do is
we're gonna start with the base schedule
and the base schedule says that on weekdays,
Monday through Friday, the bus comes once an hour,
37 minutes after the hour, starting at 6.37
and running until 10.37, right?
So that's one recurrence per hour
and that's the total of, I don't know, however many,
23 minus sixes.
And then on weekends it has a different schedule.
It's like reduced schedule or something
from 8.07 to 7.07 at night.
It comes every hour, seven minutes after the hour.
So you can, if you don't wanna bother
like the two R rules for generating the schedules,
there's not anything terribly interesting
about like making the same thing twice.
So you can make that schedule,
feel free to like either make the schedule
for the weekday or the weekend
or you can just use the like weekday schedule
and then you write the R rule for the weekend schedule
and then you combine them.
And when you're done with that, you just run this,
you uncomment this and run our tests,
test basic bus schedule.
All right, so let's take 10 minutes
and that goes until four o'clock
and then remember, Red, if you need help
or raise your hand or something.
So, we're gonna do 10 minutes of this.
Okay.
Oh, one thing I forgot to mention.
If you want to see this, I guess I didn't put it here, but there's this thing helper.
So I have a helper function that makes it easier to see this.
It's called display underscore bus underscore schedule.
And you can see your progress.
Like, this is just the weekdays.
So this is maybe like a convenient way to look at your progress instead of parsing some
complicated list of date times.
It's four.
And I think whether, if you've done or not, let's just...
All right, so how many people are still working?
Okay.
That's a good fraction.
I think it's probably best to move on, but you can still work on it, work and listen.
But obviously, since these build on each other, you'll need the output of the first one for
the second one.
So if you don't end up getting it before it's time for the next one, you can just do weekend
schedule.
Well, yeah, you can do weekend schedule equals rr underscore answers dot get weekend schedule.
And now you have the weekend and weekday schedules.
And then you do bus schedule dot rrule weekday schedule, bus schedule dot rrule weekend schedule.
And that adds them both.
And now...
What's happening here?
Oh, I put weekday schedule.
I meant to put bus schedule.
Now I have these.
Okay, but I'm going to go through quickly how I would do the weekday schedule one.
So we'll say weekday schedule equals rrrule.
And you can use a daily rule or a monthly rule.
Or an hourly rule or whatever.
It doesn't really matter.
I'm going to use a daily rule because there will be less things filtered out.
Freq equals daily.
And then we know that we want to start.
It goes, let's say, oh, we already have our DT start at the top.
And the rule is that we need to do it every hour on the hour between 6 and 10.
So I'm going to say by hour equals range.
And again, you can use pretty much any iterator here.
6 and 23.
And then by minute equals 37 because I want it to be on the 37.
And then I need to filter it by weekdays.
So I'll say by weekday equals weekdays.
And I've helpfully defined that above.
And then for weekend schedule, it's basically the same thing.
Except instead of weekdays, it's weekends.
And instead of 6 to 11, it is 8 to 20.
And instead of 37, it's 7.
And now if I run these three right here, then I get, oh, this is wrong.
Oh, it's because I named this weekday schedule.
My mistake, my mistake.
There we go.
So you can see we have our schedule.
It should look like that.
OK.
And if I run the tests, hey, it works.
All right.
Let's move on next to discussing X rule.
So X rule is just like R rule, except instead of adding date times,
or adding recurrences, it just takes them away.
So what happens is under the hood, it's going to just generate one recurrence
from each of the different R rules and one recurrence from each
of the different X rules.
And then it's going to pop them off in order.
And if an X rule matches a recurrence, matches any of the R rules or R dates,
it's just going to obliterate that and then keep moving down the line.
And if it doesn't match anything, it just keeps moving down the line.
So this is, again, very similar to the diff behavior of a set.
If you have a set that has 1, 5, and 7 in it, and then you subtract 7,
you get 1, 5.
And if you subtract 9, you get 1, 5.
So here, I'm going to use X rule to implement that rule that I said
we couldn't do with just a pure R rule, which is every Sunday,
except Mother's Day.
And Mother's Day is one of these, huh, I'm going to just make this monthly,
is one of these second Sunday of the month kind of things.
And it says, so if I do this, you know, that's weird.
I guess yearly works, right, because that's actually when Mother's Day is.
So maybe I misled you about this Sunday thing.
Maybe if you have a bi-month, it's equivalent to being monthly.
This is so confusing.
So yeah, but in any case, let's just do it the other way.
So I have my every Sunday rule.
I have my Mother's Day rule.
I will create a rule set.
I'll make that the basis of the, I'll make the every Sunday rule the base
with R rule.
And then I'll exclude every Mother's Day.
So if I combine them together, you can see Mother's Day is May 12, 2019.
And then if you combine the two, you get, you know, Sunday, Sunday, Sunday,
and then a gap, and then Sunday, Sunday.
So that's it.
One useful trick that I found for limiting some rules, right, is that you
may have some kind of complicated rule, and then you want to, like, cut out a
certain, like, you want to cut out a certain subset of it.
You can use R rule.replace to do this by generating, you basically take an R
rule, you take the exact same, you create the exact same R rule, but modify it in
some slight way, right, and then you add that as an X rule.
So it's going to be generating based on very similar rules.
So for example, here I have a rule that generates every single Friday.
So it's a weekly rule Friday, and it generates it at nine and five.
Every Friday, nine and five.
And then Friday, and then say I want to exclude from that rule anything that's
on Friday the 13th.
You can't just kind of have, like, a filter lambda or whatever that's, like,
anything that matches this, filter it out.
So what you have to do is you have to generate the same date times, and you can
do that by just adding the by month day, which to 13, right?
So we want this rule, but only when it falls on Friday the 13th.
And if I add one and then subtract the other, then I'm going to get, you know,
nine and five every Friday except for Friday the 13th.
Okay.
So now we're going to go with the next exercise, which is to reduce the evening
bus service.
So, you know, after rush hour or whatever, we'll say that the buses, instead of
coming every hour, they come every other hour.
So we're going to take our original bus schedule, and we want to drop the, all the
recurrences that occur after, every other recurrence that occurs after 6 p.m.
So the seven o'clock and nine o'clock buses, they just are not in the schedule
anymore.
So go ahead and we'll take our original bus schedule object and modify that with
like an X rule or, I mean, I'll be, I'm just being suggestive, but yeah, an X
rule.
And then uncomment this for the tests.
And then we'll look at the answer at 418.
So someone just mentioned that I actually made a mistake here.
This is not supposed to be, like this will just pass this test because it's, this
is test basic bus schedule.
So you're going to have to change that to evening.
So test evening base schedule, bus schedule, and that will actually throw
errors until you fix it.
Of course, it's a totally uninformative error.
It's like, oh, this is wrong.
So again, sorry about that.
So it's 418.
So I'm going to take a crack at this.
All right.
So here we have, so now what we have so far, I'm going to display the schedule,
display bus schedule, bus schedule.
Right.
So what we have so far is we have our regular rule and what we need to
eliminate is this occurrence and this occurrence.
So that's a rule that can be deleted.
So we're going to use X rule for that.
So now what I need is I need the subset of, I need a rule that generates only
these occurrences and these occurrences.
Right.
So what I'll get is I'll have evening reduced equals our rule, freak equals,
actually, I can use that replace trick.
Right.
So I can say weekday schedule dot replace.
So I want to generate the exact same rule as we use for the weekday schedule.
But now instead of by hour being like six, seven, eight, nine, ten, I only want
the ones that are seven and nine in the evening.
So I can say by hour equals 19 and 21.
You can probably be, you know, you can also maybe do like range 19, 23, 2,
something like that, but it's only two elements, so it's actually less typing
to just specify all the hours.
So now I have that and I'm just going to see if it's exactly what I want.
Right.
Evening reduced.
You can see, yep, that's exactly what I wanted.
I just want the ones on the weekends or, you know, I mean the weeknights.
Okay.
So then I will take my bus schedule and I will add this as an X rule.
Evening reduced.
And when we check it again, here we go.
It's looking good.
And this is no longer failing.
Okay.
Great.
So now we've covered adding rules, we've covered subtracting rules, and then the
last thing is sort of one-offs, right?
There's no specific rule that generates these things.
It's really just, you know, this subset of it is, this extra thing is happening or
this particular date, it just gets canceled, right?
So, you know, you can imagine there's a meeting that's every Wednesday at 2 o'clock
and the person who organized the meeting is on vacation on June 12th, right?
That's not something that's recurring.
It's not every June 12th, it's just June 12th.
So what we do is if we have our rule for a meeting, we create an R rule set and we
add the meeting as the basis and then we say, let's just take the recurrence that
happens on June 12th, you know, and we could get that from dot after or dot before or
whatever or we can just manually put it in there.
And then we'll add that as an X date, right?
So it's just like cancel it out.
And so then what happens is we have, you know, it'll just skip the one on Wednesday.
But then you can imagine the meeting organizers, they're just out for that one
day because they have like a dance recital or something.
And so they just rescheduled for the next day.
So instead of it being June 12th at 2 o'clock, it's June 13th at 10 a.m.
So we can just do our, again, one-off exception.
We'll use our date and we'll just add a specific example.
So June 13th.
So normally this rule is, you know, every, what is it, every Wednesday at 2.
But here it's missing this one Wednesday and it's adding a Thursday.
Okay, great.
This is how you do like a stock exchange holiday calendar?
Yeah, depending on what the holiday, like, yeah, like certain bank holidays or like
Memorial Day, Mother's Day, those things like those, those ones are going to be,
you can use a rule for it.
But yeah, like certain hard-coded days like July 4th, December 25th, things like that.
Yeah, you could like, you would do hard-coded X dates or R dates or something like that.
Okay, all right.
So now we're going to do the last exercise in our, in our bus schedule, which is that you can,
you know, so far we've been in this idyllic town where buses all run on schedules and things.
But maybe it's getting a little like, it's getting a little more real.
Like this is like the wire stuff, right?
Because in our hypothetical town, the politicians are like, well, you know what?
We really need to do a lot of improvements to this bus line on, let's say, I don't know,
like November 3rd, 2020.
I'm like, wait, is that election day?
And they're like, yeah, how strange, like, that you guys can't get to the polls
if you take the bus.
Oh, well, anyway, I guess it's canceled.
So, you know, if you have ethical issues creating like this R rule set that actually cancels it,
like let's just imagine in our scenario that it's not that you're actually making the schedule,
that you're like documenting it and you're going to send it to FEC and be like,
we got to get these guys.
So, yeah, so let's just be descriptive about it and say, let's imagine,
let's use X date to cancel just one day's worth of bus schedule for the day of November 3rd, 2020.
And then we'll take, remember to use the green, like you guys may be getting the hang of this,
so put the green ones on if you guys are done early,
because once a good number of people are done, we'll just jump to the Q&A.
So, otherwise, we'll finish here at 4.32, something like that, like say eight minutes from now.
All right.
So, it is 4.32, we have eight minutes left.
So, I think I'm just going to show you guys how I'm going to do this,
and then we'll kick it into just some Q&A, and then you can always feel free to like,
you know, email me some questions, you know, later if you have them or if there's a little bit of time after,
I'm happy to answer some quick questions.
Okay.
So, show of hands, how many people finished the exercise before this?
And of those people, how many finished this exercise by now?
So, a smaller fraction.
Okay.
I'm just trying to gauge like this.
I know that I've stacked it, so like the people who are a little slower on the earlier ones,
like they are falling further and further behind,
but I thought it might be nice to have a kind of theme running through the thing.
Great.
So, there's a bit of a trick to this one, I think, in that you can make it much easier.
You can just try and figure out what the recurrences are and then hard code them in.
Another way to do that is we already have a rule that generates all the bus schedule times
during this, during this, during that day, and that's the R rule that we're about to modify.
So, if I say recurrences on election day equals bus schedule dot between date time 2020-11-3,
date time 2020-11-4.
Oh, some of you may have tried to like just do an X, an X date on the, just the 2020-11-3,
which, you know, again, it would be nice if you could just sort of arbitrarily be like cancel everything on this day,
but that's just not how the standard works.
So, and this represents actually November 3rd, 2020 at midnight, right?
So, if there's not a recurrence at midnight, which there's not, it will cancel nothing.
So, we have, now we have recurrences on election day, right, which is a list,
and so we can just like iterate over this.
So, like forward DT in recurrences.
Oh, in recurrences on election day, bus schedule dot EX date DT,
and then we'll just like cancel those all out.
And you can see, like if I run this again, it will do nothing.
I mean, it'll probably make that bus schedule object a little bit bigger, but it doesn't matter, right?
So, what this did was it, the bus schedule dot EX date, it generated all the,
it generated all the recurrences on that date, and then we just went through one at a time and canceled them.
If you want to do R date, you could, you know, in the, there's this bonus exercise
where you can use an R date and just manually add in two more, and the flavor text is there like,
oh, we're bowing to pressure, so we'll give you a bus at 432 in the morning and one at 8 in the evening.
But don't worry, you can vote if you just get there at five in the morning.
So, all right, so that's done.
We have our test passing, and then at the end of the day, we can, oh, uncomment this,
and then actually name it the same as we named it in every other thing.
And we get our thing, oh, it's Tuesday.
Oh, I thought that it would have a Tuesday in there.
I guess I messed that up a little bit, but there should be a Tuesday, and it's empty.
But you can see it goes Monday and then Tuesday.
All right, so that's our bus schedule.
Again, there's a bunch more workbooks in here that you can go through.
Also, all this material is public domain, so if you want to take it back to your work
and show it to people or whatever, that's totally copacetic from a licensing perspective.
So, thank you very much for coming to my tutorial, and I would be happy to take some questions.
Oh.
So, the question is about serializing day times.
I think daytime works fine with pickle.
The time zone stuff, PyTZ and dateutil will do different things based on using them with
pickle.
I think dateutil's zones will like pickle all the information and then give you the
exact same TZ info back, even if your system date time has changed.
PyTZ, it may be different, but it's still a good way to get your data back.
So, I think that's all I have to say.
I think that's all I have to say.
So, yeah, but other than that, I mean, generally speaking with pickles, I think you really
only want to use that from like one process to another process that are both the exact
same python on the same machine or maybe on a couple different machines that are all in
the cluster.
So, I think it works well enough for that use case.
And then, as for databases, I don't know too much about how it works with databases.
I think Postgres does an okay job.
There was a talk here last year.
last year, it was like a 45 minute talk on time zones, and he had a whole section on
different databases and how they handle time zones, and it was pretty good. So I think
his name was David Guden or Goulden, something like that. Okay. So other questions?
What? Which test? Oh, it's checking. Oh, so you want this to say 39? Oh, okay. All right,
yeah. So thank you. I will fix that. I'll either fix that or the test. All right. Any
other questions? Yes?
Okay. So the question is, could we use plus and minus operators for our real sets? I think
that that's fine. I think maybe I would want to override the bar and like the binary or
and binary and or it might be minus either way. The equivalent operation is in sets because
it's closer to what's happening. I'll have to think about that. I'm not sure that I really
want to be playing with the interface too much because there's plenty of people, like
there's a lot of other things to fix. I think that's fine. I think that's fine. I think
there's plenty of people, like there's a lot of other things to fix. But if you want
to jump on the issue tracker and come up with a little prototype of how it could work, I'd
be interested in discussing that. I want the software to be easy to use. Okay. Other questions?
So it's 4.40. Feel free to leave or feel free to stick around.