Good morning, everyone. We're going to get started here. Please welcome Angela and Brian.
They will be talking about dependency hell, a library author's guide.
Yay.
Good.
Ah, good.
Perfect.
So I'm the Brian one in the pair.
So this is a talk about compatibility issues
that can occur when you're packaging Python libraries,
like for distribution on PyPI or internal repository,
if your company has one of those.
This might be useful for people who
are just kind of interested in packaging
but not doing that explicitly.
But if you are not really familiar with packaging,
this talk will probably move a bit fast for you.
So that's just a bit of a warning.
So we're going to talk about just do a bit of an overview
about the problem.
Then Angela will dive into some of the technical details.
We're going to talk about all the packaging dependency
problems that can happen.
And then finally, end with some best practices.
So all the examples that we're going to show you, by the way,
are real ones, or at least they were real at the time
I was making these slides.
So let's imagine that I'm going to do some data science stuff.
I'm going to use TensorFlow for my machine learning stuff.
And I'm going to use Apache Beam for my kind of data flow.
So I make my new virtual environment.
And I go pip install Apache Beam, TensorFlow,
wait a couple seconds, and then I get this crap.
I'm in dependency hell now.
And the reason this is hell and not just another minor little
inconvenience, like you hit all the time when you're programming,
is I seriously do not understand this error message at all
as a user.
So let's see what it says.
So it says TensorBoard.
So it's good that it starts up with a word
that I don't understand, because I don't know
anything about TensorBoard.
I didn't ask for TensorBoard.
It's not on the list of things I asked for.
And it says a version number that I don't care about,
because I didn't care about TensorBoard overall.
And it talks about protobuf, which I also don't care about,
because I didn't ask for protobuf.
And then it falls out.
It'll say I have protobuf version 3.3.0,
which is incompatible.
But incompatible with what?
I didn't ask for it, and I didn't ask
for anything that uses it.
So as a user, I have no idea what this is telling me.
And even as a packaging expert, OK, let's imagine
I fully understand what this is saying to me.
What am I supposed to do about it?
So this isn't a syntax error I can fix.
My choices are I can assume that someone on the Apache Beam
team or the TensorFlow team is just a liar,
and that this is a bogus error, and just ignore it.
And that would just be yoloing the entire situation.
And hopefully, it won't explode on me.
Or I could just say, look, I've heard
TensorFlow is kind of good, but I just
can't use it for this project.
I just can't use it.
It's incompatible with this other thing I need.
So yeah, we're just done with this.
And so neither of those solutions
is at all reasonable for the user.
And this isn't some theoretical thing.
This is an actual problem.
And Angela and I actually both work for Google.
And we started looking into this because our customers were
complaining, hey, we get errors like this,
but we don't know how to fix them.
And this isn't just a Google project.
If you look at the top 100 Pi PI downloads,
seven out of 10 of them have a dependency conflict
with another top 100 package.
And this is actually super surprising
if you think about it, because most of these packages
are foundational and don't really have dependencies.
But even though a good chunk of them
don't have any dependencies at all, still seven out of 100
of them will conflict with at least one other top 100
package.
And the big problem here is this is one of the few things
where a user can encounter an error
and be totally helpless to fix it.
So our job is library packagers to take this problem seriously
and try and make sure this doesn't happen
to other Python developers.
Off to Angela to explain why this actually happens.
ANGELA LIU, M.D. Thanks, Brian, for talking about the introduction
and motivation part.
Next, let's look at the technical details
behind the example that Brian just talked about.
In this diagram, it shows that this application uses
Apache Beam and TensorFlow.
And both of the two packages, depending
on a shared dependency called protobuf.
But as we can see that they are requiring different version
ranges of their shared dependency.
Apache Beam is requiring protobuf less
or equal to 3.3.0.
And TensorFlow is requiring protobuf greater
or equal to 3.6.1.
So when the user is trying to pip install these two packages
together, they will see a warning message
saying that the dependency requirements for the two
packages installed do not agree with each other.
And that's why the dependency conflicts occur.
And if we look at the shape of this diagram,
it looks like a diamond.
So that's why this kind of dependency conflict problem
is called diamond dependency problem.
And in here, let's look at a setup.py file of the Apache
Beam package and TensorFlow package.
Using setup.py file is a common approach for Python library
authors to set the dependency version requirements.
And in the install requires part,
we can see that that's where the protobuf dependency
requirements is set.
And that's how the dependency conflicts
comes for that example.
After knowing about the technical details,
let's talk about the two common reasons that often lead
to diamond dependency problem.
As we all know that package owners often
use a three digits version number to represent the version.
And a question comes here.
Who thinks that it is problematic to release
a breaking change that only bumps the third digit
in the version number?
OK, thank you.
Next, I will explain why it's not OK to do that.
Actually, releasing breaking changes in the minor release
is the most common reason that often causes
a diamond dependency problem.
And here, I will use an example, the all-usk-to-client library
to explain that.
In version 4.1.2, it removes an API that previously
existed in version 4.1.1.
And this is definitely a breaking change.
And it is bringing three kinds of problems to the users.
The first problem is that the version number
isn't communicating the changes accurately.
As it only bumps the third digit in the version number,
the user may still assume that the latest version is
a backward compatible change.
And if they just migrate to use the latest version
without doing any code change, their code will be broken.
And the second problem is that it makes it hard for the users
to depend on the latest version of that library.
Because the API was removed, the user
will have to find the replacement
or implement the replacement for the removed API, which
could be a nontrivial amount of work.
The third problem is that it makes it hard for the users
to specify dependency ranges.
Imagine if every future version of all-usk-to-client
releases some breaking changes and just bumps
the third digit in the version number.
The user will have no way to figure out
whether the latest version is backward compatible or not.
So they will need to test each single version
between the dependency version range
to make sure every version in that range
can work well with their code.
And the testing part can also take
a significant amount of time.
Speaking of using version ranges to set the dependency version
requirement, breaking changes in the minor release
can also cause trouble to the user.
In here, this graph shows that my package,
depending on three dependencies, we
use ABC to represent the dependency name.
And at the beginning, the user is
using version painting, which points to an exact version
number to set a version requirement.
They are using version painting because their dependency is
always releasing some backward incompatible changes.
And using version painting can make their code safe
and won't be accidentally broken by the backward incompatible
changes in the dependency packages.
But later, the user will find out
that using version painting isn't that good,
because that can make their package incompatible
with any other packages that require a different version
number of the same dependency.
And also, their dependency can get audited very soon,
so that they decided to change to use a version range.
At this point, the user is actually
doing all the right things, but they are still having trouble.
The first kind of problem is that the user
will have to use a very narrow version range.
For example, greater than 1.3, less than 1.4.
This is just slightly better than use version painting.
But as soon as a version 1.4 release comes out,
their dependency will get audited.
Even if the user changed to use a broad range,
there are still problems, because there will
be too many versions to support.
As we just mentioned, the user has no way
to figure out whether the latest version is backward compatible
or not, so that they will need to test
each single version between that broad range,
and that could be a lot of work.
If the user decided to exclude the newer versions,
a third problem will come, that they are not
supporting the latest version.
And this is actually the second most common reason
that caused diamond dependency problem,
because nearly all the newly created packages
will use the latest version of their dependencies.
And if your package doesn't support the latest
version of the dependency, that means
your package won't be able to work well with almost all
the newly created packages.
And also, the latest version of the dependencies
can contain some important bug fixes or security fixes,
and you don't want to miss out that kind of maintenance
updates.
Back to Brian to talk about the best practices to avoid diamond
dependency problem.
So everything isn't hopeless, though.
There are some things you can actually
do to minimize the chance of your users getting dependency
problems.
The first one is the easiest, but potentially the most
controversial.
So Angela asked you this question
before about whether bumping the least significant digit
in a virgin number is reasonable when you have a breaking change.
We all had this intuition that it wasn't.
And there's a specification called semantic versioning
that kind of describes what you should do instead.
So the specification is really short.
It's like nine points that are like three sentences each.
And I have the link there.
But I'll give you the TLDR version.
So you divide your version number
into three numbers separated by periods, the major version,
the minor version, and the patch version.
So when you make a breaking change,
you increment the major version, and you
reset the other digits.
So in Angela's example, you would
have gone from 4 point something point something to 5.00.
And then I think kind of intuitively,
we would all think that that's more reasonable to introduce
a breaking change.
If you add a backwards compatible functionality,
you bump the minor version.
So that's like adding a new feature
or adding some new optional behavior.
You can bump the minor version.
And finally, if you do some sort of security or bug fix
without breaking the API, then you
increment the patch version, so the least significant digit.
And the nice thing about doing this change,
supporting this with your packages,
is you don't have to coordinate with any one.
You just decide the versioning scheme for your package.
You just do it.
You don't have to talk to coordinate
with any other packages in the Python ecosystem.
And it also, if you advertise that you're doing this,
it's also a clear signal to your users
what the guarantees you're offering are.
So you've probably seen on some, like,
PyPI and GitHub pages, it'll say, like, we use semver.
And that's just telling the user that they
can count on this behavior.
This is an old joke you can just read.
So there's something called the Hiram's law, which is basically,
if enough people use an API and you change it,
it doesn't matter what the change is.
It's going to break someone.
Because people will start depending
on every bit of behavior that you offer.
And a lot of people object to semver because they say,
oh, you can't really be backwards compatible.
And if you think that way, I think
you're just letting the perfect be the enemy of the good.
So if your API offers one function
and you change its name, that is clearly
a backwards incompatible change.
You will break every single user of your package,
and you should bump the major version.
If you change some documentation string in your source code
and that breaks people, I think that's on them, not on you.
So just try and do the right thing.
Be reasonable.
And I think things will normally work out OK.
Back to Angela.
ANGELA LIU, CHIEF EDITOR, CREDITS, CREDITS
ANGELA LIU, CHIEF EDITOR, CREDITS
Although we semantic versioning, we
can safely bump the major version number
to release some backward incompatible changes.
But it is still not recommended to do that,
because that will create an API churn.
API churn is the backward compatible changes
that includes removing an API, renaming an API,
or changing the parameter list of an existing API.
All these three kinds of changes will require the user
to do some extra work to refactor their code in order
to, depending on the latest version of your package.
In here, this diagram used TensorFlow as an example.
As we all know that there are tons of users using TensorFlow.
And imagine if TensorFlow decided
to release a breaking change.
And if the user just upgrade to use the latest version
without doing any code change, their code will be broken.
And they will need to refactor their code in order
to use the latest version of TensorFlow again.
And if the owner of TensorFlow keeps releasing backward
incompatible changes, this cycle will
happen over and over again, which
creates a lot of extra work for the user.
So package owners should avoid creating API churn too often
and try to minimize the cost for the user
to use the latest version.
For example, if a package owner is going to rename an API,
they can still keep the old name of that API,
but mark it as deprecated.
So if the user continues to use the old name,
they will receive a deprecation warning.
That can allow some time for the user
to migrate to use the latest version instead of just
break their code.
Back to Brian to talk about using version ranges.
So this is plowing on with the machine learning example
I was using before.
So let's imagine I'm doing some machine learning stuff,
and I'm using this nice Adanet package.
It's a Google package, and I'm using it.
I'm building my model, and I'm just
showing you the setup file just for no particular reason.
And I developed my model, and now I
want to export it to Core ML, which is Apple's machine
learning framework, because I want to use this library
on my iPhone.
So I install Apple's Core ML tools.
But Apple and Google have conspired
to screw me over here.
So they both demand a very exact version of 6
that it's not possible to satisfy that constraint.
And this 6 is a very compatible package.
There is no reason why anyone needs
to depend on an exact minor version number.
So what you should try and do, or what they should have done,
and what you should do when you're doing your own packages,
is support a reasonable version range.
So as far as I could tell, 6 does not
support semantic versioning.
So I actually had to go and look at their release history
to see what kind of compatibility
6 provides with versions.
And it looks like they basically never
released a breaking change.
So in this case, we can just say, look, I need this version,
but any version after that is also fine.
And if both packages had done that,
now they'll be mutually compatible,
and they'll probably be compatible
with any other software that uses 6 that doesn't make
the version pinning mistake on the previous slide.
Now, it would have been even better if 6 had used SemVer,
because then we can just add another condition.
We can just say, I'll use anything after the version
that I need, but I don't want to support
I don't know that I won't be broken with the next version
bump, so I'll explicitly not support that.
And then if version 2 of 6 ever came out,
it would kind of be depressing if that ever happened.
Then we could upgrade.
We could change the we would locally relax this condition,
test, make sure that everything works,
and then we could start supporting the greater
than 2 version.
Once you stop pinning versions, you
do have a bit more of a testing burden, but it's not a big deal.
This might look like goop if you don't use
Knox for continuous integration, but CircleCI and Travis
also support this idea.
And the idea here is I want to test
with every supported Python version of my package.
That's the top line.
And I want to test with the earliest version of all
the packages that I depend on.
So by default, if you pip install a package,
it will install the latest versions
of your dependencies, which is great.
But for testing, you also want to make sure
that you don't introduce a breaking change
with an earlier version of your dependencies.
So if you look at the first line there,
I have like, Jinja 2 equals 2.9.0.
That would be what I want to explicitly test
with that version, because my setup file has greater
than or equal to that version.
So I just basically, in my, I've called this compatibility test.
In my compatibility test, I just install that early dependency
version, and then I just run my test as normal.
So this will ensure that I don't accidentally
introduce regression with a version
that I claim I support, because I don't develop
with old versions typically.
Back to Angela.
ANGELA LIU, CHIEF EDITOR, CREDITS, CREDITS
AND RANGE
Brian just talked about using version ranges.
Using version ranges is good, because it
can prevent the dependency version get audited very soon.
But we will still need to update the upper bound
of the version range to include any future version
number that isn't included in the version range before.
So let's talk about the relationship between the Apache
Beam and Google API Python client.
They have a common dependency called HTTP lib2.
And in here, it shows the relationship
between the two version ranges of the two packages.
The blue part represents the Apache Beam's requirement,
and the orange part represents the Google API Python client's
version range requirement.
The blue part represents the Apache Beam's requirement
for the latest version of HTTP lib2, that 0.12.3.
And the latest version falls into the orange part,
but isn't forced into the blue part.
That means the upper bound of Apache Beam
isn't including the latest version.
And there's a question.
Will PIP install a version in the overlapping range?
So if you have a version of the Apache Beam and Google API
Python client, the installation can happen successfully.
And PIP freeze shows that the actual version of HTTP lib2
get installed is 0.11.3, which is
the upper bound of Apache Beam.
And it satisfies both the two packages' requirements.
But what will happen if we switch the install order,
API Python client, and Apache Beam?
There will be a warning message saying
that the version of HTTP lib2 cannot satisfy
the requirement of Apache Beam.
And PIP freeze shows that the actual version of HTTP lib2
get installed is 0.12.3, which is the latest version.
And this is because PIP is resolving the dependency
version on a first-come, first-served basis.
So whether there will be a dependency conflict
depending on the PIP install order.
That's why, as a library author, we
should support the latest version of the dependencies.
Because as the example shows, the users
will be very confused if they see a dependency
conflict in that case.
Because most of them don't know that PIP
will resolve the dependency version on the first-come,
first-served basis.
And also, as we mentioned in the previous part,
newly created packages will certainly
use the latest version of the dependencies.
And that's important for your package
to work well with all the newly created packages.
And also, it's important to pick up the bug fixes and security
fixes in the latest version.
Here is a summary of the four best practices
we just talked about, which includes
using semantic versioning, avoid API churn,
support as large as a version range as possible
for your dependencies, and also support the latest
version of your dependencies.
That's all for our presentation.
Oh, sorry.
Thanks.
I was going to ask if there are any questions,
but it looks like that's being handled for us.
Is this on?
All right.
So we have some time for questions.
Please, if you have a comment, wait.
Meet them in the hallway.
If you have a question, now is the time to ask.
Yeah, if anyone wants to fight over
whether semantic versioning is a good idea or not,
we can talk in the hallway.
Not in the back.
I just had a quick question.
Does that pip install order matter in a requirements.txt file
as well, or is that only on the command line?
In the requirement.txt file?
Yeah.
Actually, if you use the requirements.txt file,
the actual install order is arbitrary,
and you don't have enough control for that.
OK, that's what I was saying.
Thank you.
That's actually pretty mind-bending,
if you think about it.
So the order that your dependencies are installed
if you use requirements is arbitrary.
So theoretically, you could install the same requirements
file twice and get a different set of dependencies installed.
That's what the docs say.
It's not true in practice, but that's what you should rely on.
Hi.
So I was wondering how automated dependency management tools
like PiUp fit into this framework, I guess?
Are they still useful?
You might have to be a bit closer to the mic.
We can hear you.
Sure.
You didn't get that.
OK.
I was wondering how automated dependency management tools
like PiUp fit into this.
There isn't really a tool for dependency management,
but if you want to check the dependency version
in your virtual environment, you can run pip check.
And if there are any dependency conflict,
there will be some warning message printout.
Can I add one thing to that?
If the user made a so if you're thinking about this
is what you should do as a package author, it doesn't really
if there is a tool that will do fancier dependency management,
I think you still shouldn't rely on that
because most people are still going to use pip
and they're still going to hit these issues.
Hi.
So you talked a little bit about how
pip isn't the greatest at dependency resolution sometimes.
But do you think there's anything
about the way Python does dependency management
and packaging that makes the impossible conflict more
common?
Yes.
So one problematic thing in Python,
and I'm not a packaging expert, is source distributions.
So you don't know like in general when
pip is downloading a package, it
doesn't know its transitive dependencies
until it's downloaded it and run the setup script that's in it.
So at the time that it's doing dependency resolution,
it could have already downloaded the package,
had to run it to check what the next level of dependencies are.
If you had, say, wheel only, like if Python only
supported wheel, then you could just, you know,
like the PyPI API actually will tell you
what the dependencies of wheels are without running any code
because that's just known at package creation time.
And then you could have more sophisticated tools
that just, you know, they make some API calls
and then do this resolution.
I actually was kind of an advocate of that
until I started talking to other people who
hate wheels for other unrelated reasons.
So I don't know what the path forward here is.
A lot of people aren't.
Oh, sorry.
I'm afraid we're out of time.
So if we could move all questions out to the hall.
Thank you very much, Brian and Angela.