Yes, thank you. Okay. So this is the wrap-up session for the mini sprints. We had, I think,
like, one, two, three, four, like, seven different clusters of people working on stuff. I'm going
to report out first because I was in one as well. And then we have a line of people who
are going to do one to two-minute report outs of what we did in our cluster. So in my cluster,
we had two mini sprints. One was mine on making worksheets around Python syntax and other
sort of drill education things that we need from a language standpoint. And then we also
had Mason Eggers. Did I get that right? I hope I did. Cool. Got a thumbs up. Can you
yell the name of your website? Unlockededu. Unlocked.edu, in fact. Unlockededu.edu. And
unlockededu.org is the correct version of there, where you're trying to compile up multiple
choice questions into a website where you can access them and compile them together with
an API. And so we all worked together to try and create questions. And we had a great time
kind of coming up with a format that would work for these worksheets and brainstorming
a lot of what should be inside of these workshops and worksheets and questions and trying to
come up with what are the concept model of misconceptions that can happen in things like
functions and for loops and using that to drive some of the content. And we have repos
going, or at least I do for my project. We have repos and style guide and license and
contributor guide and a couple completed worksheets at this point. And templates worked out. So
I'm really excited. All right. Name and one to two minutes.
I'm Dylan. And the thing I was working on was DocTest quizzes, which is essentially
we're allowing students to take quizzes using the DocTest module, which is a standard library
in Python. We, our project changed a lot in the last VRs. Initially, it was going to be
a web app. And now we're going to be integrating, probably going to be integrating Jupyter Notebooks
as a plugin to Canvas, which is a learning management system. And I'll let you do the rest of it.
I'm Adrian. What we did was we worked on kind of creating questions for the Python certification
that Jeff talked about and that like the MTA 98 whatever, 81 or I don't remember, but
93 or whatever. But anyway, that Python certification that people found very challenging, very difficult,
like it was long and just like tedious. So we started creating questions. We have Sphinx
running RuneStone so that we can just run RuneStone build and have those questions out
and just rewrite the questions and then we can just check the questions. So yeah, that's
what we did.
My name is Alex. I was working with the SensorCraft group over there, like the Minecraft game.
One of the biggest things we worked on was we thought about making an installer. One
of these things we thought of was a mutex editor implementation to make it a lot easier
because some of the people even in that group had a hard time downloading it and getting
everything working. And so we can't really expect kids to do that then. So making it
easier for kids to download. We also encountered a retina screen issue with Mac OS that the
game would display at a quarter of its actual size, which obviously won't work. And so we
got that fixed. We also learned about PyGame Zero, which is like a Python-based game creator
that lets you create really robust code to create games. And we thought about that and
took some examples and thought of how we could apply that to SensorCraft because we have
about 900 lines, but we're trying to condense that as much as we can, again, so it makes
sense for younger kids.
We also talked about Blocky, maybe making some way that there's like an introduction
that teaches you with Block-based programming and then you kind of transform into text-based
programming. Again, even younger kids can understand it and they kind of have a less
steep learning curve. We also talked about explicitly defining prerequisites. So we used
some big words like algorithm mapping, that type of stuff. So just going through and making
sure that the kids actually understand what we're talking about and they're not just
going to lost and sit quietly in the back of the classroom and not raise their hand
because they don't want to look stupid. So we went there and defined some of those things
that we assumed that the kids would know.
And finally, we also talked a lot about integrating into a school setting. So we had some teachers
in our group that really wanted to use this in their classroom, but they have to use Common
Core. And so we went through each tutorial and thought about what Common Core standard
would this be hitting? What programming activity would this be teaching the students? And kind
of made it a lot easier to integrate into a school curriculum, whereas before there
wasn't explicit lessons for each tutorial. But thank you.
Hi I'm Gabrielle and I led a mini sprint on creating Jupyter notebooks to help high school
students analyze scientific data sets. So we had a great group of sprinters. We had
mathematicians, physicists, biologists, grad students, professors, coders, so a great group.
And we split into three subgroups to work on three different notebooks. One on a coral
reef data set, one on an earthquakes data set, and one on a very difficult to work with
plant archeology data set. So thank you for dealing with that one. And there are now three
new Jupyter notebooks in a GitHub repository that are open source. Anyone can feel free
to use them. I tweeted out the repository if you're interested in it, just let me know.
And there are still works in progress, but they all have a lot of great examples of exploring
a data set, getting some questions you can ask about them, making data visualizations.
So I'm really proud of what we came up with and look forward to seeing where it goes.
Hi I'm Shlomi. In my group we work about developing learning activities for teaching programming
problem solving. Think about the challenge students have after getting syntax and basic
of the language, how I take problem and solve it end to end. So basically we are using a
Jupyter notebook that starts with a problem and guides the students through solving the
problem, like getting what is the problem, making design, code, testing, and debugging
and reflecting about its work. Writing a work through is really tough because you need to
really design well the path you want the student will go through that. So we took one advent
of code problem and make a design and make a break it into an outline, what is the path
we want the student to go. It's include for example reasoning explicitly about a data structure
you want to use. It also includes strategies like simplification. I don't know how to solve
the original problem, so I'll try to solve a simplified one. So we make all of that explicit
and embedded with activities in the middle for the students. And I'm very happy and
think it was very successful. Hi, my name is Ariel. I was leading a sprint, many sprint
on pair programming, effective pair programming with students. So we spent most of the time
actually working on pairs so that we could have experience first hand. There were five
people in the group and well I decided to team with one of the other person so that
we could actually have three teams in total. So we spent most of the time solving a group
of problems that I originally proposed. Some issues happened on using the tool that we
were basically utilizing. We were using an online judge to solve certain problems and
getting a hang of the online judge was a little bit of an issue in itself. But at the end
every team actually solved at least a few problems. So they were able to have first
hand experience on actually working with somebody else doing the corresponding roles in pair
programming which is the driver and the navigator. So at four o'clock we stopped and we had the
opportunity to fill in a survey, an online survey so that we could actually have quantified
the experience. And then we had a small discussion on the personal experience that we had using
pair programming. We can see that there are still a lot of questions that we need to answer
but hopefully we should be able to have these issues solved or at least we'll explore them
a little bit in the coming months or the full year in the future. Thank you very much.
Hi, I'm Ariadna and I was working with the Raspberry Pi group and I believe initially
we were trying to work on a template that would help educators kind of set up like more
of a simplified way to set up a Raspberry Pi like an introduction just like very basic
stuff and I think we decided on a template that is on DocuWiki that would allow educators
as well as developers to contribute but kind of bridge the gap so that educators aren't
overwhelmed with like the tech language but also be able to pull lessons and be able to
translate them for their students but without getting intimidated by not knowing how to
use GitHub. That kind of thing. I think that's pretty much it. Okay, thank you. Great, can
we get a round of applause for all of the Mini Sprint organizers and another round for
all of the participants as well providing awesome help. So yeah, this was an experiment
to run this year and I was really excited to get down to business and get some stuff
done. I think we got a lot of really cool stuff worked on and some new experiences and
you know, do you want to have some final comments and then we can all go and get prepared for
the lovely opening reception. Yes, so thank you everyone for attending and it is very
good. Something new this year has been pretty successful so we are quite happy about that.
We will now be sitting down and preparing for next year's summit. I would really appreciate
feedback. Please feel free to send it to PyCon Edu Summit, the email address that's on the
website and if anybody is wanting to volunteer or wants to know more about the programs or
the talks that were mentioned today, please feel free to reach out. Hope to see all of
you next year in 2020. Thank you.