Hello everybody. Welcome to the third talk in this afternoon block. First, well, third
up, we're going to have Nicole Cisneros, trying to get that right, speaking about AITA, why
internationalization and localization matter. Please welcome Nicole Cisneros.
Hello everyone. Can you hear me fine? This is okay. So my name is Nicole, and I'm here
today to talk about internationalization and localization and why these concepts are important
for your applications in general. Oh, does anyone here know what AITA means? That's in
the title? Oh, yeah, okay. So don't worry, it's not a bad language. I know that the standard
for learning a new language is to learn the curse words first. That's not the case. Don't
worry. So it's a Portuguese expression, actually, and it's used when something unexpected happens.
By the end of the talk, you will understand why AITA is in the title of this presentation.
And why do I have a Portuguese word in the title of my presentation? Well, because I'm
Brazilian, and actually in Brazil, we speak Portuguese, not Spanish. Shocking, I know,
but it's Portuguese. I'm a full stack developer at LabCodes. I work with Python in Django.
In the backend and the frontend, I work with JavaScript, some Angular, some React stuff,
and I'm a huge fan of the Python community. I'm part of the Python users group back in
my state. I'm also part of the PyLadies group in my city. Brazil is very huge as the US.
So I flagged my city over there in the map. It's a very sunny place. We have a lot of
great beaches, so feel welcome to visit in time that you want some warmer place to be
because he is very cold for me. And as I said, I work at LabCodes, which is a software studio
based in Brazil that designs, implements, and scales digital products. We deliver great
experiences and build web applications that fit our customers' needs using Python, Django,
JavaScript, especially React. Our projects are centered in creating unique solutions
and bringing value to their users and therefore to our customers. We have been partnering
with the US clients for almost five years now and helping a big variety of companies
from one-person startups and Y Combinator startups to well-established companies throughout
the US. Our team is very talented and recognizes worldwide giving talks like this one and many
conferences and mentoring people. And this is actually my second PyCon. Thanks to the
support of LabCodes, they are very helpful. They help me to bring these talks together.
They finance me to come here, so it's great. And I will be in the conference until tomorrow,
so if you want to talk about LabCodes, ping me. My contact information will be in the
last slide. And this year we are sponsoring PyGotham, which is going to happen in October
in New York. So I hope I can see some of you lovely folks over there, too. I will be over
there. So this is the agenda for this presentation. First, we are going to discuss the definition
of internationalization and localization and why does it matter? Why is it important for
your application? And then we will go over some of the internationalization tools that
the developers have available to work with their Python and Django applications. Last,
but definitely less important, I will present to you what we were able to do when managing
localization, especially translations in a multiplatform system. Okay. So let's start
by addressing the difference between localization and internationalization. Fun fact, I didn't
know what I 18 N and L 10 N means until very recently. They are numeronimous, which means
that there are 18 letters between I and N in internationalization. The same for localization.
And to be honest, I didn't even know that numeronimous was a thing, but apparently it
are. Localization is the process of adapting an application, a product, or even just a document
to be more user-friendly to customers from different countries and different cultures.
On the other hand, internationalization is the process of making the localization process of
a product and application possible. So this is a step of design of development process. You need
to make sure that your application is able to support localization. And as the Django documentation
perfectly summarizes, localization is done by translators, while internationalization is done
by developers. So here we are going to discuss some tools to help us internationalize our apps
and make sure that it's able for translators to localize our apps. However, this simplified
definition of internationalization and localization may give the wrong impression that this is just
about translations. This process actually entails other adaptations needed in order to make your
users more from different countries, from different cultures, to feel more comfortable using your
product. I will go over some examples here to illustrate these adaptations. So here is map usage
of different date formats that's used around the globe. The countries colored with cyan use the
format day, month, year. The ones colored in yellow, they use the format year, month, day,
and the green ones use both those formats, like the interchange between them. And only the USA
uses the format month, day, year. This is another map usage, everything that I'm talking here I took
from Wikipedia. This is another map usage, but this one is about number format. So the countries
colored in green over there, they use comma as decimal separators and dots as thousand separators.
And the countries in blue format the numbers using the other way around, like here, like dot for decimal
and comma for thousand separators. So how are you going to show to your user, to your final user,
these type of values? Like how do you know when to format one way and when to format another way?
Another example of localization issue is currency conversion. If I'm browsing through Amazon back
in my place, I want to see the price of products in Brazilian real, that's our currency, not in dollar,
it doesn't make sense for me. So it's important to provide prices and other values converted to your
local users. They should be able to know what they are paying for. Another interesting adaptation is
bidirectional text and unicode character support. It's a very common issue and when bringing your
application international, in this example, we can see how the Wikipedia page adapts to different
languages. So here we have the common Wikipedia page for English language, and we can notice all
the basic elements of the page, like the navigation sidebar is on the left, as we usually see. However,
if you change the same page for Arabic, we can notice that the navigation bar migrated to the
right side because this language is reading from right to left instead of left to right. So you can
see that all the elements in the page had to change to mutate in order to adapt to the culture
of people that speak Arabic. There are several other aspects that they need to take into
consideration when localizing your apps. Coverage of measures between metric and imperial systems,
for instance. Legal requirements that may be different from country to country. Sorting and
presenting a list may be different. The way addresses and personal names are formatted,
like family name goes first or last. Depends on the country. Time zone, calendar, and special
holidays too. You need to take this into consideration. Yes, I know that we as developers
are so used to code, to write code and documentation in English that we may not realize that
there are only like 360 million native English speakers people in the world, and that only
represents like less than 5% of the world population. And I know that it's very useful
to have a common language for the communication between developers, but regarding your final user
of the products that we are developing, English may not be that useful after all. And in fact,
from the top 10 countries with most people using the internet, like only one is a native English
speaker country. This is from 2017. So if you want to grab that share of the market,
you need to go international. You need to be able to internationalize your app.
Okay. So I hope that at this point I have convinced you how important it is.
And now I'm going to show you how we can do that with Python.
Okay. Let's go to review some tools that we can use that can help us with this task.
It starts starting with the new get text package that's from the translation project. This
package offers a runtime library that supports the retrieval of translated messages.
A set of conventions about how programs should be written to support message catalogs.
And a library supporting the parsing and the creation of files containing translated messages.
So how does it work? Let's say that we have a simple hello world app here called eta app.py.
Where we are using the get text Python module to create a text domain for our app over there. Like
we are creating a text domain. We are saying where the translation is going to be held. The
locale folder. And down here when we are saying our greeting, we are flagging that string as
translatable. So if you run this code, it's going to print hello world as expected.
It's not going to break because you don't have another translation for this code.
So after you flagged your string to be translatable, the new module, they offer a
tool that can collect all the strings that you marked as translatable in your code and generate
a PO file containing all the strings that must be translated. So this is the method that we use to
generate the text. It's a command line tool that you can run saying what's the domain that you
created, which is our eta app, and what's the input file. The PO file that this method is going to
generate contains a list of all the entries that you created. And the list of entries that you
created is the list of all the entries that we flagged as translatable. And this is the basic
structure for an entry in the PO file. We may have some comments for the translator trying to give
some sort of context for them. Like the word may. We can say that this is may the month or may from
the verb. It's a verb? Yeah, it's a verb. We can also add some references, some flags for the string.
Then we have entry ID, which is the untranslated string that's going to remain untranslated.
And we have the entry string that's going to be the translated string.
So when we run the command x get text in the command line passing our eta app.py file,
this is the PO file that comes back. At the top of the file, we have some metadata about the file.
We have some information about the project, some information about the translation process.
The idea of the PO file is that it should be readable for both developers and translators.
So we have that meta tag information over there. And down here, we have even a reference for where
the code, where in the code the string came from. It's in line seven. And then we have our entry.
Once we have our PO file done, we can start now. We can start translating our terms for different
languages. In this example, I'm translating the simple Portuguese. So I copied the PO file
generated by the x get text command and started to translate my terms. And then I followed the
recommended structure for my domain and my different languages that I want to support. So I have a
folder for all the English domain PO files that I want to support. And then I create another one for
the language, Portuguese. If I want to give support for French, I would need another folder and yet
another PO file for French language. So I have a folder for the English domain. And then I create
another one for the English domain. So, okay. Now I have two PO files for the two links that I want
to support in my app, organizing this specific directory hierarchy as recommended by the new
module. So in order to use now the translated strings in my code, I need to compile the PO
file that's a portable object file into an MO file, which is a machine object file. And this is
done by this tool in the new module, which is the message formatting tool. I pass what's the
output, like what's the output file, which is going to be the MO and the PO that I'm compiling.
When I run this for all my PO files, now I should have this structure for each language.
I should have my MO and my PO file. Now, with my PO files compiled, I can now install the translation
for the desired language in the get text tool in our Python code. So the translation method is able
to find the correct MO file based on our directory structure, the domain text, that's eta app, and
the language that I passed as parameter. So now if I run this code passing the language
Portuguese from Brazil, I'm able to get ola mundo instead of hello world. That's the translated
string. Another useful internationalization service in the Python module is the local
module. This module has access to the POSIX local database and is especially handy for
formatting dates, numbers, and currency. Let's take a look at this example where we are trying
to translate to format a date, number, and currency using the local library. Here I'm
importing the module. I'm changing all locale settings to English from the U.S. and retrieving
the locale conventions. This locale convention is an object that contains all the conventions
for the language in that country, such as decimal separator, thousand separator, currency symbol.
We have all this in that object. Then I proceed to format my given date and price. Let's say it's a
price application. I don't know. And using the locale format method, I can format my number
without worrying about the decimal and thousand separator symbols. The same effect, I can
accomplish the date format by passing the percent X directive to the date format function.
This is the output. If I run that for English in the U.S., I have my date
in the format that's used here, month, day, year. And the decimal separator is a dot,
while the thousand separator is a comma. And also I have the dollar sign representing the U.S. dollar
currency. Now, if I take the same code, but just changing the locale to Portuguese Brazil,
just changing that parameter passing in that set locale function over there,
I already have a different output. Now I have my date and my number and my currency
following the conventions of Brazil. The date is formatted as day, month, year. And we have
a, we have comma as the decimal separator, dots as the thousand separator, and we have the R
plus the dollar sign, which represents our currency. Okay. Now, since I'm here to spread
the word about internationalization, I want just to give, like, a tiny overview on how we can
accomplish this on Django. With the framework, we are able to serve our content, to serve our web
content based on, in different languages based on the accept language header that the base of the
browser adds to our request object. So we are able to change depending on the end user. We need to
know that language in order to return what they are expecting. For translations, we can flag
translatable strings in both Python and template code. In the Python code, we can use the standard
get text function and all the other get text module related functions that we already saw for
Python code, for the Python part. It works in the Django part. One interesting feature of Django,
though, is that we can have lazy translations, which is great because we can flag a string
that will only be translated when the value is used in a string context, such as in the
template Henry. So this is especially useful for translating help text and variables names in our
modules, for example. On the other hand, we can use some special tags in our template code once you
load the internationalization tag. We have the trans tag that translates just a single string.
While the block trans is able to mark as translatable a block of strings in your template.
To be honest, this slide covers only like 10 per cent of the features available for translation
in Django. It's not the point of this presentation. I just want to give you a highlight. And you can
check the documentation. They have everything explained there. It's very good. So go check it
out if you want more details on how to use these features. The Django command line already has
some facilitations for the whole process of generating a PO file and compiling the PO file
already puts everything in that folder structure as recommended by the new project. So it does
everything for you automatically. It has some comments that does this for you.
Another support that we have from Django is related to time zones. When time zone support is
activated in your Django settings, that means that Django will store date time objects in the UTC
format in the UTC time zone and in the database and uses only time zone aware date time objects
in the code. So because these date time objects now are time zone aware, Django is able to format
the date and the time according to the time zone of your end user. So that's great.
Okay. Now that I presented some tools that can help us internationalise our apps, I want to share
with you a challenge that we came across back at LabCodes last year, which was to support localisation
in a cross-platform system. To illustrate what I mean by cross-platform thing, I put together
this diagram. Basically, we have in the front-end part of the system native apps for iOS and Android.
We also have a web-based app, Actin, and Actin as a controller for those native mobile apps,
we have a middleware that's written in Java. And this middleware consumes from some services from
the API and also this API powers the data for our web app. As you can see, we have different
technologies powering each piece of the whole system. And believe me, Java, Swift, the Android
SDK, they don't use PO file to translate their messages as their message catalogue. Each one of
them has their own file format. So that's the part where we came as a group, as a team, and we said,
ATA. Yeah, we were in trouble in this part, like, how are we going to manage all this? It's all fun,
it's all cool, and you have just your Python code over there, you work with Django and it's doing
everything for you, but this time we were in trouble. So our goal was to collect the translatable
strings from all those parts and send them to be translated by a team of translators.
These translators would use a localization platform to translate the terms. Yeah, let's face it, that
PO file to change a lot of strings wouldn't be the most fun thing to do. But we have several
localization platforms. This is just like the top six that I got back from the Google search. And
they usually have, like, all of them, I'm not sure if all of them, but they usually offer a nice API
integration with the system in order for you to automate your process of sending all those terms,
getting back the translations, and doing the whole flow. So I don't really have any preferences.
I worked with TransFax for this project, but, like, just pick one, like, it's not, I don't have
many opinions about this, but choose one. We have several.
So in order to do this, in order to send everything there, and we came up with several
different API services that would parse the different formats of message catalog files.
So we have our PO file from our web-based platform. We also have PO file for the API part.
We have the strings.xml for the Android native app. We have the localizable.strings file for
the iOS app, and the messages.properties for the Java middleware part. So the API services
had different services to handle and parse each one of those since they have different formats,
so we have to deal with different parsing methods. And then the API would then aggregate these terms
once we parsed everything and store it in a local data store. In this case, we are using Redis,
just for performance sake, but it can be any data store, actually. And why we use a data store for
this is because we don't want every time that someone sends a file to send all the terms to
the localization platform. We want to avoid this bulk process, and if we are not sending only the
different things that are being added or updated. So with the local data store, we are able to
control this better, and only send actually the terms that need to be updated or added to the
localization platform. In the API, we are also able to kind of aggregate the same terms
that have different platforms. So, for instance, a button that says cancel,
that's in every front-end platform. So that cancel, we will only send one cancel string to the
localization platform, and the translator would need to translate cancel three times. It's useless.
So the API also does this cleaning process in the terms. And once the aggregation is done,
the API now sends the terms to the localization platform using the API integration. And now,
all the terms are available for the translators to do their magic and translate everything.
Also, these integrations, they also allow to send all those comments and all those context
information that we can pass along to facilitate the work of our translators.
Okay. Now we have the terms over there. Now the translators can do their job, they translate,
and once the translation is done, our job now is to make these translated terms back to the
platform. So the API does the same process, but in reverse. Now we get the translated terms from the
API, we format them into the correct file format for each platform, and make them available for
each developer, for each core team that's responsible for each one of them. There are some
localization platforms that have a web hook that they can actually signal your API to inform you
that the translation is done, and you can do this automatically. And you can look for something
similar. And yeah, now we have this basic flow work, like we have all the way to send the
translations to the platform, and to send the terms to the platform, and get the translations back.
But this is not all. We also needed to review our deploy process, because now we needed to adjust
our process to accommodate the translation process in between. So each platform now has to update
the terms, send all the new terms that they want to send to the platform when they go to QA.
We use the process of QA our system. So whenever they are ready for a QA deploy,
they send all the terms to be translated. And the QA team now has to perform integration
tests for different locales. And all these features are approved to go to production
once they are tested, and once also all the strings are translated. So this is a slightly
difference in our deploy process. Now we have to take into consideration not only our team to be
ready, but also the translators team to be ready to translate everything.
And this solution that I just described, they have been placed since last year,
and so far it has been working. The team seems to be adjusted with the whole process of deploying,
signalizing the translators, and the communications is well established. So it's working so far.
Not a big deal, not many problems. However, now we have a new challenge coming.
Something that I omit from the presentation of the platform is that about 60%
of the data presented to the user actually comes from different data sources over there.
And I'm not going into too many details about our ETL process of extracting, transforming,
and loading this information into our API. However, it's important to notice that
this data is constantly changing. So yeah, our next challenge is how we can manage these terms
in an organic and performatic way. But this has to go to another talk because we are still planning.
We have a huge question mark in our heads right now. We are in planning stage, and maybe next year
I can come here with another talk and tell you what's the result of this huge plan.
And yeah, that's it, folks. I was able to show you, I hope that I was able to show you
how important localization and internationalization is.
And I believe that the main lesson from this is that internationalization is a fundamental step
in design and development process. Don't do like we did. We took months to flag all the strings
and to internationalize each one of those platforms. The whole team was a group effort
that took months until we came up with the solution. And don't do this. If you are in the
beginning of your development process or if you are thinking of starting one, take internationalization
into consideration. Even though you don't have big plans of going international, believe me,
you want to go. And it's better to be ready now when the opportunity comes and you can do this
without being a pain in the neck as it was for me. So be warned. Hope you do this. And
yeah, thanks a lot and obrigada.
Hey, great talk. Thank you. Did you ever have to deal with the migration of a Django app from
Python 2 to Python 3 at any point? And how did you deal with internationalization with that?
With that, yeah.
Actually, we were already working with Python 3 when we did the internationalization process.
We did that process before. I'm trying to think if we had like this was also like it was very close
the transformation that the parsing. I'm trying to think if we had any apps that were at the same
time. But I don't think so. I think I had everything in Python 3 before doing the
internationalization process. Yeah, so it was okay. Okay. Were there any issues that you faced during
internationalization? Oh, yes, actually, there is one that didn't get into the talk. It was
the IDs. Because when you generate the PO file, the string that you flagged comes as an ID. And
we actually had to use well formatted IDs like KMLKs or something like this. Because we would
have like collisions of terms that didn't mean the same thing. So we had to go over all the IDs.
That was a challenge, too. So when it comes to internationalizing an application, I imagine that
maybe getting the last 5 to 10% is the hardest part because there might be different edge cases
to handle. Like for example, one case you can imagine is maybe the translations aren't just
single string replacements, but maybe they're strings that have like substitution areas for
like a number or something like that or plural or singular. And I'm wondering if you can talk
about some of these harder edge cases to completely internationalize an application.
Yeah, like we had to do this for pluralization as they called. Like we had to treat these edgy cases
on like feminine and masculine terms, prurals in our text. And in those different,
and each of these cases is treated differently in the PO file and all those other files for all the
other platforms. So it came down to sitting and establishing how we are going to handle those
edgy cases for translating. Yeah. Okay, thank you. Thanks.
Hi, thanks for the talk. It was really cool. I wondered if you could talk a bit more about
about the QA process that you use to sort of like make sure that what's coming back from an
external service is legitimately what you wanted to translate. Is that people internal who speak
the language that are going over every line and how do you sort of make sure that there's not
English strings sneaking through and that kind of side of things?
Yeah, kind of this like because our QA team is not that big and we don't have people that speak
both languages for this project. We were supporting Canada, French, French Canadian,
but like our QA team didn't know French because it's based in the US. But like we looked for
English terms when we were doing the QA process and overall we trusted the translators because
like we had to separate our concerns if we were able to check everything we couldn't trust our
translators. So we trusted them but like testing everything like we look for English maybe some
terms that didn't get translated. But yeah that's basically it and it's quite a pain to do this at
first but as I mentioned the team seems to be adapted well so far. So now we already know how
French works and then when we change we are able to spot on any
errors quickly more quickly than before. Cool, thanks.
So I was curious about like the CSS styling and how you handled that like when things need to show
up on the opposite side of the page. Did you guys have any of those cases and like how did you end
up handling that? Yeah we had a special case for CSS translation and we actually didn't translate
in the CSS file. We actually got back to JavaScript. So there was something that we had in a before text
in the CSS file that we were like okay we can't do that and I actually didn't spend
we didn't spend much time researching. We are just like okay let's change back to
JavaScript for this part since we already had JavaScript enabled and doing a lot of things for
CSS and then worked with that and we already worked with JavaScript translations in our front end.
We had Django. Django also supports JavaScript. They have a catalog that they send back
and also in Angular this project also had a tiny bit a little bit in Angular. So we also supported
that so we ended up shifting from CSS to JavaScript. And I just want to make sure I understand
your whole flow here. So you have like translation tools that you're using kind of in all these
different languages and then you're passing the config files like from your back end like through
your API to these different services in different languages is that correct? Actually we only have
one platform for the translation process and what we do we grab all those files and compress
not compress but aggregate them and pass to a single platform. So the translators they only
have to work in a single platform. Translator supports several languages for the same set of
strings. So we have the French translators but at any time they could add another like I don't know
German translator team to work in the same platform. So we don't need to have a different
platform for different translator teams. We only have one. Okay so it's like you're really
dependent on like the back end to translate? Is that right? Yeah yeah like okay. But we have these
services that's kind of an isolated service is in our API so we can now we may migrate to another
platform. So now we just need to change that to communicate to integrate with a different API.
But like they are very similar. So like the API is responsible for generating that file that goes
to the front end applications. Yeah for each one of them. Okay thank you.
How do you determine your user's preferred time zone?
How do I sorry can you repeat? How do you determine your user's preferred time zone?
Preferred time zone. I don't think that we do because I know that we take from the accept language.
But since we store everything in UTC because we don't work with with date that much. So we
store everything in UTC and we do this based on the location. Sorry we have we do have a time zone
part of the process that we use moment.js in the front end and we are able to get the location of
the user in the front end in the browser from the moment.js library and then we format that data in
that. So the API is able to get the location of the user in the front end in the browser from the
that. So the API sends everything UTC and then in the front end part we do the conversion using
that information. Yeah I forgot about that moment.js part. Why do you do that?
All right well thank you very much.