Okay.
So welcome back.
I guess those coming in, welcome.
Those continuing to come in, please come in, find a seat.
Try not to stay in the back.
For those who had stayed from the last session, hi.
So today we have a new speaker.
His name is Vinayak Mehta.
And he will be talking about extracting tabular data from PDFs using Camelot and Excalibur.
So please help me in introducing him and welcome him to the stage.
Am I audible?
Yeah.
Hello, everyone.
Is everyone having a good time so far?
Like, who all are first-time attendees?
Nice.
It's my first PyCon 2.
Let's give it up for PSF and the volunteers for organizing such a wonderful event.
So wait.
Why isn't this moving?
I think I'll go there.
Yeah.
So hi.
I'm Vinayak Mehta.
You can follow me on Twitter here if you like.
I work at Grofers as a data engineer in Bangalore, India.
If you'd like to work, if you'd like to know about the things I'd like to, I work on every
day, you can catch me afterwards.
So I'm here to talk about how you can extract tables from PDF files very easily.
I believe each one of us has interacted with a PDF file at some point in our lives, maybe
through resumes or research papers.
In this talk, I'll briefly go through the history of the portable document format.
I'll touch upon some problems I faced while extracting tables from it and then finally
show you some code using which you can do this very easily.
So let's begin with a fun fact.
Why is Python called Python?
Yeah, Monty Python.
So while he began implementing the language, Kwedovan Dawson was also reading the published
scripts from Monty Python's Flying Circus, which is a BBC comedy series from the 70s.
And he thought that he needed something which was short, unique, and slightly mysterious.
And thus we have Python.
There are numerous Monty Python references written throughout the Python ecosystem.
I'll also tell you about some of them today.
Cool.
Let's quickly go through the history of the portable document format.
PDF was born out of the Camelot project to create basically a universal way to communicate
documents across various machine configurations, operating systems, and communication networks.
This is a memo by Jay Warnock, who is the co-founder of Adobe, where he outlines the
Camelot project.
You can check it out at the link below.
It's a PDF.
The goal was to make documents viewable on any display and printable on any modern printer.
It hints the portable document format.
It was built on top of PostScript, which is a page description language that had already
solved this view and print anywhere problem.
So a PDF package is components required to build a document, like text, fonts, vector
graphics, and raster images.
And these components travel with the document wherever it goes.
And a PDF contains instructions to place these components in precise X, Y coordinates relative
to the bottom left corner of the page, which is the origin for a page.
So they're just placed at specific coordinates.
So words are simulated by placing some characters closer than others.
And sentences are simulated by placing words relatively far apart.
How is the table simulated, then?
By just placing words like they would appear in a spreadsheet.
So the portable document format really has no internal representation of a table structure,
which makes it difficult to extract tables out for analysis.
Sadly, a lot of open data is stored in millions or possibly billions of PDFs, which wasn't
designed for tabular data in the first place.
Unlike a CSV, which is very structured, or a JSON, so you guys must be wondering why
are you so obsessed with PDFs?
So here's a short intro.
I joined Social Cops in New Delhi as an intern in January 2016.
It was my final year of undergrad.
And as a student, I had come across various types of PDFs, which were basically resumes,
research papers, software manuals.
It makes sense for those types of documents to be in a PDF, right?
Because you want them to look similar on a variety of machine configurations.
So initially at Social Cops, I worked on escaping tabular data from open data sources, which
were primarily PDF reports, to extract data that could be then used by analysts for the
analysis basically.
So these are some types of PDF tables that I worked with.
Each organization that wants to release open data as PDFs comes up with a bizarre and colorful
table structure.
There isn't any set standard for this.
So what is the first thing you do when you want to solve a new problem?
You look for existing open source projects that might have already solved it.
So similarly, there are already existing PDF table extraction tools.
Some of them are open source, some are closed source, like Tabular, which is open source,
and PDF tables, which is closed source.
So let's go through the problems with existing tools.
This is a table, this is a page from a weekly disease outbreaks report released by the Ministry
of Family Welfare and Health in the Government of India.
It basically contains weekly data about the number of cases and the number of deaths that
were recorded in various Indian districts, along with a comment on what action was taken
to afford those outbreaks.
Looks like a very easy table to extract, right?
Only seven rows and ten columns.
But when you pass it through Tabular, which is an open source tool, you just get this.
So you can see that the header is broken into multiple rows, and the comments column is
shifted into separate columns.
Tabular has a very nice interface, but it either works or it fails miserably.
There's no in between.
This is the output of PDF tables, which is a closed source tool.
It works slightly better, but costs money.
And you're either there or you're nowhere, which is the worst place to be.
It also either works or it fails miserably.
to get even 80 or 90% of a table out, which is not helpful since most of the things in
the real world, including PDF table extraction, are fuzzy.
So a solution that I tried was PDF to text, which just extracts a text from your PDF file
into a text file while preserving the layout using white spaces.
But there's a problem with that too, because the output that you get is a text file, and
there's a post extraction step required to make sense of the underlying text data and
convert it into a table.
You have to write custom code for each different type of table structure, which can become
expensive and time consuming, and that is not scalable.
A solution that we came up at Social Cops was Camelot to overcome the problems of not
having a generic PDF table extraction tool, which had knobs included with it.
So let's take the example of the same table and let's go through a short demo.
Let me just launch a Jupyter notebook.
So you can import by typing it correctly, I can't really see it.
You just import Camelot.
You do a tables is equal to Camelot.readpdf in the name of your PDF.
The API is very similar to pandas, like a read CSV or a read HTML, and then you can
see that the table, is it visible?
Should I enlarge it?
Yeah, I can see it now.
So the tables is basically a table list object, which just tells you that you've got one table
on the PDF page.
You can access the table using the index of the table, which will tell you the shape of
And then you can finally access the table.
There's a .df attribute which will give you a pandas data frame for that table.
So here you can see that it's all extracted very nicely.
All the headers are preserved.
There's a, I can't really see the comments column, but oh, here it is.
So all the comments are intact.
Yeah, let's get back to a presentation.
Yeah.
I can't really change it.
Oh, it got out of present mode.
Yeah, so it's just a screenshot that I put there if the demo didn't work.
So why Camelot?
Camelot gives you complete control over table extraction with some tweakable parameters.
You can override the table areas and columns that were detected by the library itself.
And you can tweak the resolution of the image that would be used to do line recognition
on a PDF page.
And there are some other things that are built into the library itself.
So each table is a pandas data frame, which can be easily integrated into ETL and data
analysis workflows.
You get a parsing report for each table, which tells you the accuracy with which the text
was assigned to a table cell and the percentage of empty cells in a table with which you can
discard back tables.
And there are some other things like you can flag superscripts and subscripts.
So here the superscript is not really a problem because it occurs after a decimal.
But if the decimal wasn't there, then the number 2491 would become 24912.
That would be a problem in your analysis.
So you can just use this keyword argument, and you'll get the superscript flagged with
those tags.
You can strip unnecessary characters, like those dots aren't really required in the text
that is inside that PDF.
You can just use strip text and pass in the characters that you want to strip, and you'll
get a very nice table out of it.
You can shift text in spanning cells.
You can also copy text in spanning cells because, yeah, it's just a nice feature to have.
And there are multiple output formats.
You can export your table to a CSV or JSON or an HTML or an Excel file.
There's a command line interface too that you can use.
So as you can already guess, the library was named after the Camelot project.
Fun fact, Camelot is also the name of the castle in Monty Python in the Holy Grail,
which is a movie by the same comedy group.
Another fun fact, the Python package index was initially called the cheese shop based
on the Monty Python cheese shop sketch.
You should check it out.
You can install Camelot using a very simple pip install.
I've put a comparison with other open source PDF table extraction libraries on that link,
so you can check that out too.
So Camelot is built on top of PDF minor, which is a Python library that lets you access the
text lines in a PDF along with the coordinates at which those text lines occur.
Camelot has two parsing flavors built in.
Lattice, you need to choose between one of the two.
You can use lattice if your table is built using lines and steam if your table is simulated
using white spaces.
The names for these flavors were taken from Tabula, inspired from Tabula.
But what if you don't want to write code?
You can use a web interface that is built on Camelot.
And it is called Excalibur.
You can just run the web interface using Excalibur web server and go to localhost,
colon 5,000.
This page will load up when you go to that URL.
You can access the PDF that you uploaded earlier underneath the upload button.
You can auto detect tables on the PDF page.
This is the same PDF that we were using earlier.
If the table is really buried inside the text inside a PDF, you can specify the table areas
and columns to make your extraction even more accurate.
Excalibur supports all the different tweakable parameters that Camelot comes with.
So you can just enter them here and finally view your data and download it in any format
that you want.
So why Excalibur?
It's a web interface.
It's much easier to use than Python library.
You can save your parsing rules, which were your tweakable parameters, and then use them
on similar tables in the future.
You get to work on your data from the safety of your own home.
Your data is safe on your machine.
And Excalibur can be configured with MySQL and Celery to make your workloads parallel
and distributed.
So again, following the same Arthurian theme, Excalibur was named after the legendary sword
of King Arthur.
Here's another fun fact.
The meta syntactic variables inside the Python literature are called spam and eggs instead
of the default foo and bar.
You can install Excalibur using a simple pip install.
So this is the road ahead with these projects.
Right now you have to choose a parsing flavor.
I'm working on having an auto detection algorithm built in which automatically chooses your
parsing flavor.
Right now Camelot only works with text-based PDFs.
So there's also a plan to add OCR support so that it can work on scanned images.
And there are a couple of minor speed optimizations that can be done here and there.
Since you looked at the web interface, it looked very simple since I'm not a frontend
engineer.
So if any of you know a little bit of frontend, you can help me out there, I think.
These are the links where you can find out more about me and about the projects.
You can check out open issues on the issues tab on GitHub.
And all your peers would be very welcome.
Awesome.
So this is a picture of Team Social Cops.
I want to thank Rishabh Raj, Deepu Thomas-Phillip, Ankita Mathur, Shilpa Rohra, Varun Banka,
and all of the team who gave their inputs and feedback during multiple iterations of
Camelot.
And I also want to thank Jacob Singh, Manoj Tiwari, and Deepu Thomas-Phillip for their
feedback on this talk.
So yeah, I think we can move to questions.
Yeah, so open the floor up for some questions.
So if you do have questions, please come up to one of the mics and we'll go from there.
Hi.
So I've tried to do some PDF parsing.
Some of the libraries I've used are like PDFminer, PyPDF2, and I've noticed that you can feed
it different PDFs from different PDF generators and get different results.
And one thing I recently was surprised by was that when you view a PDF in Chrome, it's
always perfect.
But if you do the Google cache operator on a web PDF, even Google can't convert it into
HTML perfectly.
So how could that be that the browser displays a PDF perfectly, but we can't convert it to
HTML reliably or accurately?
It's possible that the PDF that you're trying to convert is a scanned image instead of a
text-based PDF.
So that could be a problem with the PDF.
Because any tool needs to have access to the internal text to convert that into an HTML
in the first place.
And if it's an image, you can't really access that text without running some sort of OCR
operation on top of that PDF.
Yeah.
Is there some sort of intermediate format that you can get back from Camelot?
I know you have the data frame, which is awesome.
But is there a way to get back some sort of table object where you could merge cells and
do stuff like that before putting it into a data frame?
What sort of format are you looking for?
I'm just, I have dealt with a number of kind of mangled PDFs where I've had to do splice
cells together and stuff like that.
I think you can easily do that on a Pandas data frame.
If you just need to split cells or merge them together.
Right now you can only access that table as a Pandas data frame inside Camelot.
Okay.
Thank you.
Hi.
Kind of adding to the question he had, how successful is Camelot in extracting a multi-index
PDF?
What if a couple of rows are clubbed together?
Can I extract it to a multi-index Pandas data frame as well?
What do you mean by multi-index PDF?
Let's say a few rows in between here and there are merged together and I want to preserve
the exact same format.
It's actually two separate blocks of text which is, in Excel you can do it straightforward.
You can just merge two blocks of text.
But if you are converting an Excel document straight to a PDF, it doesn't look so neat.
But if I try to parse out the data from a PDF, it's not necessarily a straightforward
extract.
If you're talking about those text lines lying in maybe different tables, then you'll get
them as separate tables.
But I think we can talk later.
Maybe you can help me understand it better.
You can take a look at it.
Well, first of all, I can help you with your question, so find me two.
Thank you for building this package.
Much needed.
So everybody here I know is probably really pleased.
Is it possible to extract a list from the PDF, i.e. a table with one cell, because often
that's what we need to get out?
Yeah, it should be possible to extract a table with one column, you mean.
Right, yeah.
Yeah, it should be possible.
Thank you.
I'm curious if you have any, worked on any examples where there are multiple tables in
the same file, if it confuses it, or if you have to reprocess it over and over?
No, so if there are multiple tables on a PDF page, it would extract those as separate tables.
I can send you a link for that example.
It's on the documentation.
Okay, thank you.
Yeah, I wanted to echo the earlier comment that the tool is awesome.
A couple months ago I had a challenge at work where someone said we need to find if this
thing has a table or not, and so we looked at a bunch of different tools and we used
Camelot heavily.
I have a question.
If I recall correctly, there was a feature in Camelot that allowed for a sort of visualization
of the structure of a table.
Okay, I was mixing up the ones and I thought it was Camelot.
Yeah, that is in Camelot.
I didn't include it in the slides because it would have made it longer, but there's
an option for visual debugging where you can visualize the text lines that are lying on
a table in the table that the library detects.
We found that really helpful.
I wonder if you could speak a little bit to how that works.
Maybe I can show you the documentation for that.
Let me see if I can escape this.
So the documentation is on Read the Docs.
You can go to the advanced usage.
There are multiple examples here which you can use.
So there's this whole section on visual debugging where you can basically, let me magnify this.
So you can basically plot all these components that were found by Camelot on a PDF page,
which is text, the table boundaries that were detected by Camelot, the lines that were detected,
the line intersections that were detected in text edges is something that is, I can
explain it to you later maybe, which will just show you the text that was on a PDF page.
It can help you identify the coordinates for table areas and columns that you need to pass
into Camelot.
So this just generates some at plot lib for each of these different types of components.
This is the table that was detected.
This is the table boundary that was detected.
Similarly, lines, line intersections.
So you can play with the different knobs that the library gives you and see if maybe the
intersections were detected or not and tweak them to maybe improve your results.
Yeah.
Is it able to union a one table that spans multiple pages?
No, you will have to write logic to do that yourself.
So each page gets converted to a one data frame and then you would union all of them?
So each table is converted into a data frame and if a page has two tables, you will get
two data frames and then you will have to stitch all those data frames together using
some logic.
Thanks.
Hello.
Have you noticed any functionality differences when you have a scanned and OCR PDF with tables
in it versus a text-based PDF that's generated electronically?
What sort of functionality differences?
Well, a lot of times when you have a scanned PDF where you have to OCR it, the tables come
across differently, at least in that text layer.
So I was curious if you've found that with CamLot, if it works pretty good with those
scanned and OCRed?
No, right now it doesn't work with those scanned tables.
There's a plan to add that as a feature.
Right now it only works with text-based PDFs.
Gotcha.
Okay.
Thank you.
Do you have any interest in generalizing to text extraction as well as tables?
What sort of features are you talking about here?
So if you're interested in data in the PDF beyond just what's contained in tables?
Okay, that way.
Yeah, initially I was thinking about it, but right now it's mostly focused on tables.
But I can add that as an issue and we can talk about it on GitHub.
Did you have a question?
It was more of a comment to the last gentleman.
I recall when we were trying to sort of solve the problem we had, I can't remember if it
was CamLot or Tabula, but one of the libraries had, for some of the things we used OCR on
my PDF and then we passed those things to CamLot.
But either CamLot or Tabula had a method for giving you a probability or a likelihood
that this thing was correct or not.
If that was CamLot, can you speak to that?
I can't remember which one it was, but that may speak to the gentleman's question.
Are you talking about the parsing report that I showed?
Could have been CamLot, I guess.
Are you talking about this parsing report?
Yes, sorry, yes.
Yeah.
Cool.
Thank you all for coming out today to this talk.
So in the next few minutes, I believe there will be some sprints.
I don't believe they're happening in this room, so you can check the schedule.
And I'd like to thank Mr. Mehta for coming and giving his talk.
Thank you.