Good afternoon, everybody. After lunch, the second tutorial of the day. Faster Python
programs measure the own guess. This is the tutorial. If it's not your tutorial, you have
to change rooms. So, again, please make sure to install all the required software and also
download the material. First, I would like to introduce myself a little bit. So, I've been a
Python user for now about 20 years. I still remember buying my first Python program in 1999.
First Python 1.52. It's a bit newer now. And also work as a Python trainer since 2004. I've trained
people in Python. And since 2006, I do it full time. And I'm the CEO of Python Academy.
They're a Germany-based teaching company. So, I teach in Germany and other countries in Europe.
I'm also involved in the communities. I've been chair of a bunch of Python conferences you can
see here. And I'm still involved in organizing PyCon DE and EuroSciPy and maybe some other
conferences. And also the chair of the Python Software for Bunt, which is something similar
to the PSF, but a bit smaller in Germany. Okay. Maybe a few words about you. So, there's quite a
few people in the room. And it would be good to have a little bit of feedback who you are,
what you know about Python. So, who has less than one year of Python experience? Please raise your
hand. Okay. It's about 10%. Between one and two years. Okay. Between two and five. Yeah. And more
than five. Good. So, it's a pretty nice kind of even distribution. Of course, at the time of the
usage of Python, it's not a good measure, but it's some kind of approximation how well you know
Python. So, who of you has to still use Python 2 in production or for their job or something? Okay.
So, quite a few people. So, this tutorial, I've been using this for a while. So, I updated it,
but it works with Python 3 and also with Python 2 mainly. So, you should be able to get something
out even if you have to still work with Python 2. But remember, end of the year, Python 2 is dead.
So, we probably should speed up a little bit moving from Python 2 to Python 3. So, who of you is doing
number crunching or something that has to do with numerical computations or something? Okay. A few
people. Who of you has CPU bound problems? More or less? Yeah. Okay. Who has more memory bound
problems? Okay. So, there's also distribution. And who has more IO bound problems? Okay. So,
kind of even distribution, all kinds of problems are here. Good. Thank you. Just what you're gonna
do is if you have about three hours here, and this will be hands-on. So, just have a few slides,
and then we go do kind of, I do kind of live coding more or less, and you're encouraged to
work along. Then you can also go to the material. Everything, it's in the material, so you won't,
hopefully you won't get lost. You can do copy paste, but typically it's not that efficient. So,
it's not too much to type. You may try to type along. I'm gonna use iPython notebooks. Actually,
it's called Jupyter notebooks. Who of you is familiar with Jupyter? Most of people. So,
it will give you a very quick introduction. If you want to use some different tool, you can use
some different tools, but a few things, some timing and profiling things work much nicer
than in notebooks. Then if you don't know this, you have a handout. This is about 78 pages PDF
handout in the download. Also, example code is also downloaded. We do some exercises a little bit,
so you have to do something yourself. Not a lot, a little bit. And there will be a break at three
o'clock, so that will be some new coffee, hopefully. And also, you can go to this link there after the
tutorial and give you an evaluation how you like it or didn't like it, some suggestions or something.
That would be nice. I will show the link again. It's here. And maybe I also, during the break,
I'll upload it so you can have it. Just need to click it. You don't have to type it in. Okay. So,
the first few words, introduction. Because everything is about making things fast in some way. So,
as you know, Python's a pretty high-level language, very interesting language, actually,
that makes programming easier. But Python can be slow. Python's not necessarily slow,
per se, I would say. But for a few things, it can be slow. Typically, it's pretty slow. If you do
heavy numerical calculations in pure Python, that's not going to work out well. But there
are quite a few solutions to do it in a different way. We're going to look at some of them. This
may or might not be a problem. Sometimes it doesn't really matter too much. So, if you program
something and you're waiting for something like a database or so, then there might not be a problem
with Python at all. And before you start optimizing, you try to make Python faster,
very often it comes with a cost. So, you have to pay for it in one way or the other very often.
And we're going to look at this a little bit. Because once you optimize the code,
you might need to spend more effort not only writing the code, but also maintaining the code.
It's more complicated. So, you need to find some kind of a balance. And of course, this is very
different for each application. Sometimes if performance is very important, then it makes
sense to do it. Sometimes it's not so important, it might not make sense to do anything at all.
So, optimization, guidelines, premature optimization is the root of all evil. You might know this. It's
not really clear who came up. This is the first time to say Hori, but maybe somebody else. But
it doesn't really matter too much or Knuth. But this has something true. I have a lot of people,
sometimes I work with people that say, we have to use Fortran to program this because all of us
would be slow. That might be a little bit hasty decision. Very often, you might need Fortran for
only a very small portion of the program actually, not for the whole thing. And then you have to
write the whole thing in Fortran. That might not be the best choice for some problems. Very often,
you have to make it correct first and fast later. So, it doesn't make sense. You have a very nice
fast program, but the result is not what you want. So, you have to make sure the program works
correctly. And you can also think before you start about optimization, but it's typically a very bad
idea to optimize on the way. First, you have to make it work right, have tests. And then once you
have the tests, you know the test works right, then you can make it fast. That's a good way to do so,
correct before fast. So, otherwise, you might not be very successful. So, as I said, optimization
often comes with a price. It can make your code less readable. There are other cases where the code
actually gets more Python-ic, as you might call it, more readable. And I tried to show you some of
these sweet spots where the code gets easier to read, but I understand simpler in one way or the
other and still faster. But sometimes, that's not possible. And you might end up having, putting
more effort in maintenance of your code. The readability, which is a big feature of Python code
typically, may suffer if you put something in there that makes it faster, but not as nice and
Python-ic maybe. Because Python typically puts a load on the machine and not so much on the
programmer. And if you reverse this process a little bit, then you might lose some of the advantages
of Python. Sometimes you have this kind of different thing, and then you have to find some kind of
compromise between these different goals that are not, you cannot solve for both of them. So, general
guidelines. So, I have to have just, this is pretty much common sense. But even though it's common
sense, you have to just keep this guideline somewhere when you do optimization before you spend a
lot of effort, just go through there. And then, of course, you have to apply this common sense to
your actual use case, which is different pretty much every time. So, do you really need, it's kind
of a strange question, do you really need more performance? Maybe you don't need it. It's just an
exercise to do something faster. It can be okay, but maybe you don't, if you need to make it faster.
Also, you have to figure out if Python is actually the cause. And that's pretty much most of the
tutorials, actually figuring out what's going on. And this is a very, very important basic step,
which is rather general, to find out what the problem is. Then how do you really solve it? That's
something I cannot really teach too well in the tutorial, because my every case is somehow
different. But if you have some general guidelines, then you can apply them to your special case. So,
there might be other things, network traffic, whatever, that are slowing down, it's not Python.
So, I always say, it doesn't matter if you wait fast or slow, you still wait. It doesn't help if
you may use C or some other fast language when you don't have anything to do. And does it hurt if
your program runs slowly? If something runs two hours or six hours, and it runs overnight anyway,
and it's finished in the morning, it might not matter. So, this is something you have to answer
yourself. So, as I said, don't optimize as you go. So, you have to make it work right first, and then
look at the speed later on. Because you very often don't know if this really matters what you're doing
right now. So, you have to measure that's something I will hammer on quite a bit. And I do this for
a while and have some experience, but very often I'm wrong. I have an assumption what it is, but
when I measure it's wrong. In the aftermath, it's very clear, but when you start, you often have
wrong assumptions, and that can happen. Use realistic use cases. So, what is a program for? So,
if something runs overnight, then you don't have to make it very interactive typically. So, how many
people are going to use it? So, if you know your small company and you only have 10 people,
then there will never be more. You don't have to scale up to a thousand. So, sometimes it's
very difficult to predict how this thing is going to develop in the future, but just spending a lot
of effort for something that might never happen, maybe not a good idea. How often it's used. This
is one time thing, and then you throw it away, then it doesn't make a lot of sense to spend a
lot of time to make it faster, because it's just way till it's finished and that's it. So, again,
external courses can be, typically kind of gets like network connections, everything goes to the
network can be much slower than anything you do in the programming language. So, you have to check
this one. Database access is a typical case. System functions. You might find some other things,
depending on your use case, that can be other external sources that make your program slow.
Architecture. So, architecture can be thought of a kind of a higher level algorithm, like how do
you set up the whole thing, maybe have a floor on the whole idea you have. This is really difficult
to tell, and I don't have an example, because typically it's like the bigger picture. And
typically simple tools work, so if you have a big piece of paper and write boxes and arrows and see
how they work out, and if they all cross each other, then it's typically assigned something
wrong. Most of the time, simple tools are good to give you an idea. Complicated tools are not
necessarily better. Sometimes you need them, but something like just to have a general picture,
how the program is set up, and maybe there's a problem somewhere in there. So, general rule.
Box. Yeah, forgotten to print in the inner loop, or something like this that slows your thing down.
So, print can be very slow, especially in Windows, if you have a print on a console,
on Linux typically. And debug might be the problem. So, if you make your program work right,
then you might not have a speed problem in the first case. So, and now, once you're through
these six steps, step number seven, now you say, okay, I have a case. It's too slow, I have to make
it fast. Very often, not the whole program is slow. Typically, you have some bottlenecks. Actually,
hopefully you have some bottlenecks. If really everything is equally slow, it's really hard to
make it faster. But fortunately, in many cases, you have one or two or three bottlenecks somewhere,
and you have to find them. Yeah, you have to find them where they are, and then you can focus on
these bottlenecks. And that's what we actually do. You have to be finding the bottleneck, and if it's
your domain, you know what's going on. Maybe if you found the bottlenecks very clear how to solve it.
Maybe you cannot solve the bottleneck, because you have to do these computations anyway, or
something. And it's very different for each use case, but very often we have bottlenecks, and sometimes
they're even easy to solve. Of course, you need to check after your optimization if it makes things
faster, you still have the same result. Yeah, so use unit tests. PyTest is a framework I was
being in talk here to draw about PyTest, which is highly recommended because it makes it very
easy to get started with tests, actually, but gives you a lot of sophisticated features later on. So,
it grows with you, and you should try to cover most of your code. So, even if you have 100%
coverage, it's not guaranteed that your program is correct, but it's one more indicator that things
are going well. And then, we will go for the algorithm first. So, if you apply the right algorithm,
you can, if you have a certain problem, easily speed up your program by many orders of magnitude.
No switch of programming languages can do this. So, if you switch from Python to C, you can get a
speed up between 10 and 100, depending what type of thing you solve. That's probably what you can
do. So, a lot of numeric code, it can be up to 100 times faster, with highly optimized compiled
code. But if you use a different algorithm, and Python has advantage, it comes with data structures
that have very powerful algorithms behind it, and if you use the right one, you can be 10,000 times,
100,000 times, a million times faster. No compiler will give you this one. So, this is something you
can do. Actually, I gave a talk in 2012 with Europe Python. I said, Python is faster than Fortran,
which is a kind of a provocative title. And I just did something like, we have two files,
this is a million coordinates, x, y, z, and find out which ones are on both. And in Python,
it's a nine line program, open both files, read them into sets, do an intersection, write it out,
everything. I tried to reprogram this in Fortran, took me 168 lines, and I did a, I couldn't find
anything like a set in Python, and I made a neat, naive quadratic algorithm, and the Python program
ran like two minutes, and Fortran took two hours. Of course, you can say, you do a binary search,
but if you do binary search in Fortran, that will take you a few days to program it and get it
correct. In Python, yeah, I can do this in half an hour, or a few minutes, actually, the whole program.
If you have the right algorithm, you take advantage of Python built-in structures,
that can make things faster. And as strange as the science, sometimes it's just the easiest way to
throw hardware into the problem. So nowadays, hardware is really cheap compared to programmer
time, and maybe just put more memory in. So putting more memory in is always, most of the time,
it's possible, and putting memory in is pretty cheap, comparable. Getting a faster CPU, it's,
you can get many CPUs, many cores, but of course, then you have to change a program that it can take
advantage of it, and Python has some problems with that sometimes. Some libraries do this,
but if it's a memory problem, or some input-output problem, just replacing a hard drive by SSD,
or something might be very useful already. Yeah, and of course, you can, whatever you can buy,
it's typically cheaper than optimizing. Of course, if you have something simple to do,
and change the algorithm, that's still, we can still do it on top of it, but more hardware will
help. Good. That's my slides. Now, let's go and do some work here. So I'm going to go through
some examples, and we work with the Jupyter Notebook. So I created a new environment here.
You don't have to do this, but if you're familiar with Conda or some other, or if you can use
PIP virtual amps or something, whatever you feel comfortable, it's fine, or if you work in your
main environment, I use Python 3.7 here for the tutorial. If you have a question about 2,
so it should work with 2. A few things might be slightly different, but for the most part,
it should work with 2, and I activated, and I installed the software, and actually now,
I'm starting a JupyterLab here, and I need to specify a port here, otherwise it's not going to
something like this. See if this works, and then it should start a Jupyter Notebook in this
directory, and that's what it does. So, and I made a mistake. I have to go to the directory
first, because otherwise, it's always recommended to go to this directory first,
and then to do the same thing again. Then all the notebooks will be automatically stored in
this directory, and I can get rid of this one. I have a problem with using a different port for
some reason. It has something, complaints about workspace if I use the same port.
Okay, so this is actually the download, the examples, and I make a new notebook,
and I will spend most of my time in a notebook, and typically I rename it. So, if you want to
use some other tools, that's fine. The advantage here, I will develop this notebook, and I will
upload the notebooks, and you will get the link to the notebooks, I'll send them out. Later on,
you get all my notebooks, because yours might look a bit different. So, I don't have any
prefabricated notebooks. You have the handout, it's a PDF, so you have all the information there,
but I don't want to just show you something, you have to press shift and or shift and so on. This
is not typically a good way of doing it, because you want to do something yourself, and therefore,
we spend some time in a notebook. So, it is big enough. Everybody in the back can read this? Yeah,
okay, great. So, let's go through. So, I'm pretty much following the material. Of course,
you're always free to ask questions, so raise your hand, and if I don't look at it, just make
some noise, and you can always ask questions. I will answer directly or just say, okay, we're
going to cover this later. And we start with measuring. So, most of this tutorial will be
about measuring, and then I have in the second part some hints looking at some algorithmic things
and some suggestion what you can do. Since there are many different types of problems in terms of
performance, I cannot cover all of them, but I can give you some suggestions. But the main thing is,
you need to measure. And once you measure, you might solve your problem already. If not, at least,
you have something, then you know, I could solve it, I could not. It was a time-versed spending.
Okay, the first thing is timing. So, timing can be done in different ways. There's a library called
timeit, which is part of the standard library in Python, so you can import timeit. So, this has
advantages always there, but it's not really comfortable to use. I would say it's not too bad,
but you'll see that will be a more comfortable way here in the notebook. But let's do this. So,
I can do something. I just use my example. So, I define two variables, a and b, and I just want
to measure how long it takes to add a and b. And to do this, I can say total time, yeah, and I can
use a timeit module, which offers you something. So, measuring time is always kind of tricky,
can be pretty tricky. That's why you should use tools, because people that develop the tools,
they thought through, and they tried to make it robust in one way or the other. There can still
be problems, so you can still measure something strange. And now I can say measure a plus b. So,
I use a string. So, I have to have a string. And then I have to specify a few things, like I say,
the global namespace is, I can say local to global here in my notebook is the same. So,
I can use locals, and I can supply this namespace. So, now that defined a and b end up in locals in
the dictionary and feed this dictionary there. And I can say, I can specify how many times I
want to repeat it. If I want to have a million times, so I'm Python 3, I can do something like
this. If you might know, so you can underscore that's easy to read for a million. In Python 2,
you cannot, you have to type it out or do something else to get to your million. And once I do this,
and then I can look at the total time and I get the total time in seconds. So, it took 0.063 seconds
about to do a hundred million loops. And of course, now I have to divide it. And that's why
actually what I said here, I can say repeat if you want. And then you don't have to repeat or repeat,
so to speak. So, a million and you use the repeat there. And then you have to divide the time by the
repeat. So, and then you get the time for one. Yeah. So, now the total time for one run is about
this much. So, this is the time. But when you're in the iPython notebook or the Jupyter notebook,
you can actually use this magic command. This notebook has this magic amount of percent time.
It is not a Python thing. This is a Jupyter notebook thing. And I can do the same thing here.
And I can say A plus B. And then it's using time it. It's actually using this machinery in the
background, but it gives you a much nicer interface. You will see this because you don't have to do a
lot of things yourself. And now it tells me it takes 45 nanoseconds to do this. Yeah. So,
nanoseconds 10 is minus nine. It's about five times minus eight, which is about the same time.
It's the same result. But you see what it did. It came up as a number of repeats itself. And the
number of repeats actually, if you check here, it's about 10 million, if I'm not mistaken here.
Yeah. So, it repeats it 10 million times. And it divides the time by 10 million, obviously. And
then it does some statistics. It repeats the whole process seven times, seven runs, and then gives
you the mean and the standard deviation. So, this is good because if the standard deviation is small
compared to the measurement, then you have, you see, okay, they have seven times pretty much the
same result. And this is useful. If the standard deviation is big, you have a problem with something,
caching or some kind of thing. Yeah. So, this is some indication. Again, there's nothing 100%. When
you measure something, you always make mistakes. Just the question how big they are. Are they 3%
or 300%? That's the thing. So, 3% is to be okay. So, it won't be that big. But 300% is obviously not
okay. Then you have to do something with the measurement. Maybe you cannot do anything because
you have so many moving parts and every time you measure everything is different or so. That can
happen. But this is one way to measure the time and you can do this. So, let's, we can also say
percent time it. One plus two, yeah. So, you can use literals. And you see when I use literals,
instead of A and B as names of my objects. So, typically I don't say variables. I say objects.
And you see now the time goes down to about nine nanoseconds, which is more than four times as fast.
Here I can still calculate. So, but you can actually use a small, actually if you say time
it question mark, then you get the help. And you see this time it takes several arguments. You see
the other time it was 1% and the other time it was 2%. 1% is just valid for one line. The 2% will be
valid for the whole cell. The cell is this gray thing here. Yeah. And you can have several options.
You can determine if you don't like this automatic calculation how many repeats you want. You can say
I want to have 10 repeats, 10 million, whatever many repeats and so on. All the things can be
used here. And one of the interesting one is O. And this dash O here returns a time result instance.
And we want to do this because this time result instance has way more information than just what
is printed out. And this is in as Python objects. You can access them later on. So, if you say this
one is pretty useful. So, I like it. So, I say dash O. Okay. So, A plus B. Now this returns this object.
And I can retrieve this object. I say time this. Okay. Let's call it variables. I use variables here.
This would be this time. And I can do the same thing as a time literals. So, if I type in my literals,
let's time it. Time it. O. O. One plus two. You see. Now, you still get the output. You can suppress the output
if you don't like it. Actually, it has an old switch for this. But now you get the output.
Then this output does have several attributes. You see. Type. You get all these attributes.
The interesting one is average. And average is exactly the same we just saw here. Just not in nanoseconds,
but in seconds. And now I can do an easy calculation. This is kind of okay. But if you have different units,
you always have to calculate in your head the units or do something like this. So, this is typically nicer
to do something here. And you have average. And you see the factor is about five. I said four.
More than four. It's about close to five in this case. So, if you repeat the whole thing,
you will get slightly different. Yeah. Yeah. So, are you sure you have the same version?
So, if you say import IPython and then check the IPython version. So, that might be something because
the older version, do you have seven repeats or three repeats?
Yeah. Best of that, then you have an older version. So, best. There used to be a best of three.
And a few versions back, they changed it to seven repeats. And then they always have the standard
deviation. So, if you're typically the version, as you know in Python, typically, ah, it's not there.
So, there's a version. So, you can just go and check up here, help about
JupyterLab. And then you see the version. And this is a version 0.35.
Maybe the IPython version. You maybe figure out the versions. And I'm not really sure where the
versions are right now. But if it says only three repeats, then you have an older version. You have
like three or four versions back or something like this. This is the IPython feature because
JupyterLab has several parts. But I'm surprised if you install the newest version of JupyterLab,
it should actually get the newest version of the IPython also because of the dependency.
Maybe for some reason it doesn't work. Maybe you have some configuration options or whether
they set it back or so. There's a lot of configuration things you can do with here.
But if you make a new install and try it again, everything clean sheet and try from beginning
to see if it works. So, I'm not sure where the version is here. But it just looks like an older
version to me. Okay. The two percent sign, as I said, you can use this one. Now I can say A
equals one and B equals two. If you stay with our simple example, say A plus B. And now it's
measuring the whole cell. So, it's measuring the assignment as well as the addition.
If you don't like this, if you don't want to measure the assignment, you can actually move
this assignment in the first line and make it a precondition which is not measured. Here we have
to use the semicolon. Actually, yes, because we want to have two lines there. So, now if you do
this now, it does measure the assignment. It should be hopefully a bit faster. Yeah, it is faster.
Yeah. So, assignment is not expensive compared to this
resolving with the names. But it gives you some clue how things are sometimes interesting to get
a feeling. So, if you have a different machine, a different operating system, you might get
different readings a little bit. Yeah. So, good. This is the first thing. Timing can be interesting
and using this notebook is very nice because the overhead doing it, the effort is pretty low.
You don't have to do much and quickly just check is that difference if you do it this way or this
way and if it's pretty much the same, it doesn't matter too much, at least for my use case. So,
all this timing and profiling can depend on many things. And one big thing is like the size of the
data structure you use. If something works for a small data structure, it might be very different
for a bigger data structure. And what's smaller and biggest depends also on the machine, on the
CPU you have, caches and all kind of stuff. Yeah. So, if you do measure, you always need to measure
for something that's kind of more or less realistic. If you just use a list of three elements also,
obviously you don't see any difference in looking up in a list. If you have three million elements,
might be very different. Or 300 million might be very different. Okay. This is, so actually I can
here develop my notebook. The first one, this is, I can use markdown. You see I changed the cell to
a markdown cell up here and now I can use markdown and then do markdown. So, how did I insert a cell?
Escape A and Escape B. So, if you haven't used the notebook yet, you can open this site here
and then you go to the palette which gives you help and you see a lot of these help things.
You can even search them and some of them have keyboard shortcuts. And if you do things often,
then you should, keyboard, this is a control B to turning off this left pane, one of the left pane.
And these are here, if you press escape on one of them, then you can wrote a cell.
And so, if you say escape one, I make a cell and markdown cell is header one. If you say escape six,
it puts six of these hashtags in there. It makes it, this makes it easier. Yeah. And also, here's my
insert. We can also delete a cell. Yeah. Since the deletions, you destruct the cell that have
repeated DD. So, for the user here. And then there's a escape A somewhere. Must be escape A here,
insert cell above and B insert cell below. These are pretty common. Good. That's what I did here.
And if I turn this off, then you get more screen real estate and see more. So, the next thing would
be actually profiling. So far, we just time something and timing, you can only time a whole thing
and that's it. That's it pretty much. And here, I can say profiling. And profiling means
looking deeper inside. So, profiling is if you have a program that's a bit bigger and you want
to find out which part is actually consumes how much time. So, this is now CPU profiling. Later on,
we'll do memory profiling, which is we can be even more complicated. Memory is not that easy
typically. And there are no built-in tools here. In profiling, you can use some Python standard
library tools. We'll see there are some other external libraries on top of it that use information
the profiler gives you to give you a nice graphics and something, which is typically helpful.
You can also find some other tools with your other machines, but the principle should be
saying you need to measure something. And also, once you do profiling, you might want to automate
this profiling in the way that fits your project. So, that's typically useful to automate
things here. Okay. So, if I say actually percent, that's nice what to do. I have this
sub-directories from the download. And if you go to measuring, then you will find
as it is from the download zip file. Everybody download zip file. Yeah, good. So, there's a few
things in here. A typical is very small programs. You could type them in, but it takes too much time.
And they are all toy example programs. But I tried to make them as simple as possible,
but still to make a point how to do it. Of course, in reality, this would be way more complicated.
But then it would be kind of a disturbing what you're doing. So, I can load this here. So,
you can open an editor if you like, but you can also open it here. Profile me. You see,
when I start typing, it gives me call tips. It loads a file. And this is a very simple file.
So, I see I still have some pure man's Python 2s, Python 3 compatibility in here. So,
Python, of course, it's important to use the Python 3 type of range. In Python 2,
you have X range. It's not exactly the same, but for our purposes, okay. So, Python 3 range
can do things like you can use a long in range. X range is limited to 64 bit integers or something
like this. There are some small differences, but for our purposes, they don't matter.
When I have two very simple functions, I use the built-in function time,
I built a module time, sorry, and use sleep. So, this sets your processor to sleep for that
many seconds. The typically tells operating system, please wake me up after this time.
Okay. You have to be careful with sleep. Sleep is not very accurate,
especially in Windows. It's very inaccurate. So, if you sleep a million times, a millionth of a
second, you end up not with one second, but 10 seconds or something. It's totally off. Yeah.
Sorry, I think I missed the command to do this.
Yeah. So, I go up again. So, always raise your hand if I'm too fast. So, I unzip the file,
and in the directory measuring, there's this, LS gives you all the files, and then I use
percent load, which is gone. So, actually I type percent load and then the file name,
yeah, profoundly, and then I execute it. It will turn my command into a comment. Yeah.
So, if you go to the schedule and to the nodes, and if you are logged in, you will see the link
there. I sent a message last night, and there should be the zip file. Yeah. So, then the zip
file can download from there. But you have to be logged in, otherwise you won't see it, because
you have to be. But since you're registered, you should be there, otherwise you wouldn't get
registered in the first place. Good. So, this is a file, and there are some very simple functions.
So, this is actually Python 2, Python 3, comparatively, if you're in Python, if you're
in Python 3 or Python 4, so not there yet, it wouldn't have any effect. Then there's two functions.
This waits at a thousandth of a second, and this waits at tens of a second. Yeah. So, there's two
small functions, and then there's two more functions that use this function loop. So, I repeat something
100 times, and since I don't use a loop variable here, you could use X or something, use underscore,
which is typically a pattern of Python 2, if you want to have an anonymous name, so to speak,
which is kind of strange, oxymoron, then use underscore typically. And I just repeat it 100
times and see what happens. So, this is just a very simple example. It doesn't do anything useful,
it just waits so many seconds. So, if I actually execute it, it takes a while, because now, if I
wait 100 times, tens of a second, it takes about 10 seconds. So, it should take about 10 seconds.
After 10 seconds, you should see that it returns. So, as soon as the number is here, then it should
have returned. Good. And now, I can profile things. First, I'll show you the slow way to do this in Python
standard library modules. So, I say import zprofile. So, this module has a name, which
it's not supposed to have. So, according to PEP 8 naming guidelines, it should be all lowercase, but
the capital A P made it from Python 2 to Python 3 for some reason. I don't know why. But in there,
so it's supposed to be lowercase, but you have to type it even on Windows.
Windows is not case sensitive, but case preserving. Even Windows, you have to type the right case,
otherwise you're going to find the module. It's kind of strange. Good. And so, I make a profiler.
So, I make an instance of the class. So, it's the long, winding way of doing this. So, I say
module zprofile.class profile, and I make an instance of this class. And then, this instance
provides a few methods, and I say I use one of them. It's called run call, and then I feed my
function, and I can give it the arguments. Since it doesn't take any arguments,
I just give it a function without anything. So, I don't call the function. It's called like I give
this thing my function. It's calling the function on my behalf. And this is very fast. And then,
I say profiler.print stats, and then it prints the statistics. It looks like something like this.
I have to make it a bit shorter so it don't get line breaks. I hope it's readable. So, this is a
very simple statistic. This is very simple. You see, it's just a full function calls. In reality,
there can be hundreds and thousands of calls in your program if you run a function under this
profiler. And you get an output. And you see, this is, there are 202 function calls in 0.12
seconds. And this here is a number of calls. The total time that is spent here, the time per call,
which is, since it's very fast, is zero here, you don't see much. And then, the cumulative time
here at this one. And then, actually, the time per call. So, this is the cumulative time of the
outermost function is the total time. This is this time up here, obviously. And then, the other ones,
the time accumulated. And you see, this is here, a function that lives in the notebook has a strange
kind of name here. This is a file name. And I use fast first from outside. It's called once,
which calls fast 100 times. That you see the 100 here. And fast actually calls the time sleep
method in turn. And of course, the profiler measures itself. Yeah. So, this is all. So,
when you measure something, the tool measures itself. Like, if you're in a room and count the
people, you count yourself or something like this, some kind of strange thing. But this can happen
that the measuring has an overhead and somehow impacts the measurement. It's kind of unavoidable.
But if the impact is small, it's okay. If the impact is a main thing compared to a measurement,
then it might be a problem. So, typically, measuring something very fast is much more
difficult than measuring something long. If something takes 10 seconds, it doesn't matter
what my overhead. 10 seconds. If something takes one nanosecond, then my measurement consumes 10 or
20 nanoseconds. And that can be a big problem because I might measure something that's not there
and measure some kind of a ghost effect. And then if you try to make a ghost effect going
fast, you won't be very successful. Those things can happen. So, now you can do a lot of things
with this profiler and can get... So, actually, I can use the same... I can make a new instance
or can use the same instance. So, I can use the same instance or make a new... Yeah, I can make
a new instance. Profiler two here and do the same thing, make a new instance. See,
profile, capitalized profile. And now I can just do the same game again with my profile
profiler two, run call. And, of course, now I use my run slow. And then you will see...
No, no, no. Use, use, slow. And then run call. So, run takes a string. Run call takes a function.
So, that different ways of doing this. And, of course, it takes longer now. It takes my 10 seconds.
So, I have to wait 10 seconds to see your result. And then we need to do the same thing as here.
Instead of profile log, we say profiler two. And then we see the output of this call. And you see...
I called run. That's why there's one more call there, I guess. And then you see the time
it's spent in sleep. And the sleep time is now 10 seconds versus this 0.1 second. Yeah.
Yeah, yeah. You have to load this file and then go in there, press shift enter. Otherwise,
it's not executed. So, if you load it, it doesn't execute for security reason. You have to look at
the file, just code first, and then go in there, shift enter. Otherwise, it's not defined. You can
also import it. It's the same directory. You can import it and use the import, normal Python import.
That's also fine. Good. So, now you see the difference. And here's very obvious. Sleep takes
all the time. And we have to do something about the sleep if you want to make it faster. Yeah.
Here, threads would help. Of course, sleep is input output. And you can use threads and it would
go away, so to speak, if you wanted to. Yeah. So, when you have input output and you have a
clear case, threads are not too bad, actually. If you don't use any shared objects and any locking
and so on, threads are fine, I would say. If you have shared objects, threads are typically not
recommended. You might find a better way. So, this is input output bound here. And the sleep
takes the time. And if you know a little bit about sleep, then you will solve the problem. Yes.
What is the built-in snake? I don't have that in my house. Maybe I have a different version,
but what is the built-in snake? Like, the method? There's one called that.
Which method? Yeah. The third one.
Yeah. This one? Yeah. This is a measurement itself.
The third one. The one in the middle. The built-in snake thing.
Yeah. Yeah. Because I used run up here. First, before I used run call, and run uses a string,
and it calls the exec. That's why also I don't have two runs, so I have 204 calls. Yeah. So,
actually, if I want to do this, this would be a trick, because now I have some artifacts there.
There's still a memory, but don't show up in the notebook. I deleted the run to call, but the effect
is still there. So, trick. It takes a while, but I can say kernel, restart, run all cells,
which now would restart my kernel, and does all these things from the beginning again,
and reruns all my cells. Does it do it? Did I say yes? So, you say kernel, restart, run all cells,
restart. And it doesn't do it? I know it doesn't. Okay. I did it. Now you see,
now I have to wait here, because now it takes so many seconds. I have to go to the whole game
again. We have to wait a minute or so. But then this would be a thing now, you would delete
everything in memory that's there you don't see anymore. You can still access it, but this would be
wait this while, let everything restart, and do all these things. But I have all this timing in here.
So, it's now doing all this timing. We have to wait seven seconds, seven seconds, seven seconds,
and it's recalculating. So, the star means it's busy doing something. And now it's doing this one
here. So, it's still busy. And then once everything is through here, we have 202 here.
I should see 202. Yeah. Actually, it's 202 now. So,
this is a fast one. And this is now it's 202. Now it's done. Yeah. You see, instead of 204,
now the exit is gone, because the run call is not there anymore. This can happen if you work
interactively. You do something, you delete the cell, you don't see it, you forgot that you did it,
but the effect is still there, and you measure the effect in one way or the other. So, always
make small notebooks. If something is strange, restart the whole thing, do it new. So, otherwise,
figuring out what happened, it's not worth it. Just redo it. Yeah. Very often. Yeah. You remember
this? It doesn't have effect. You change the file, you change the file, just to remember there's two
files with the same name, with different directories. Those kind of things happen, and then you have to
make a step back, go drink your coffee, and come back on any solution. That you do something
strange here. Good. Now, we have this statistics, and then you can do a lot of statistics and work
with it, so you can sort it, you can limit the printing, and so on. There's a lot of these output
things. You can also actually do the following. You can say, say, cprofile.run. Yeah. And now,
run will take a string, and the string uses exec. So, you type in the Python source code that actually
is supposed to run. So, I can say, use fast, and actually call use fast here. So, I type the code
in literally, and then I can also say that I would like to store this. So, I say fast.stats,
and this stores the result. And I did something wrong. Yeah. This is a file name.
Yeah. So, now it runs it through, and then you have this file in your file system.
This is a binary file. I think it's Marshall or some kind of persistent thing, but it's
standardized, and a lot of tools will be able to read this. So, you can do this profiling your
code somewhere, and then post-mortem can go through the results. And it's a kind of simplified format,
and there are quite a few tools that are able to read it and do something with it.
Yeah. So, you can write your own tools if you want to. So, you can put some decorators in
somewhere that actually save these files for different versions, and so on. Yeah.
Yeah. So, the notebook saves everything in the directory I started from. I can also change the
directory, but it saves the notebook, saves everything in my current working directory.
This is exactly what... These numbers actually are stored there. These numbers are a bit more.
This information about CPU profiling. Yeah. So, if you do memory profiling later,
that there are no built-in module in the library that does memory profiling to my knowledge. I
couldn't find any. So, we have to use third-party libraries to do memory profiling. So, you can
measure the memory of one object. This is GetSizeSurf, but that's pretty much it. Yeah.
Can C profile take the average of multiple runs like timing?
As far as I know, you have to do it yourself, I think. So, you have to run it yourself, and then
you can write some tooling around it. You will see we use prun. The next one is one of the notebook
tools that gives you much more higher level and much less effort approach to do these things.
Okay. Now, you can do some of things. You can sort it. So, you can say...
So, my statistics. Import a tool that's also part of the standard library.
Pstats. Sorry. I forgot. Import Pstats. So, if you have Pstats. So, Pstats is,
as you can see here, this is part of the standard library. I'm using miniconda here, and this is
just in the lib. Python 3.7 directory. So, it's part of Python. There's always a way to find out
what module it is. It's something that's part of Python. Now, you can do quite a few
investigation steps on it. Just a few examples. So, I can say stats, and I can read my statistics.
Okay. That's equals. And I can say Pstats. Make an instance of the class stats. And feed this file
fast to file which I saved, and then it reads your file. So, you can do your profiling somewhere,
and then the next day you can do the analysis, which can be helpful. So, you can also save
multiple files for different things somewhere, and then do the analysis later on. Because when
you do profiling, you might slow down your program quite a bit. So, it might take a while. So, if
something takes a few minutes already, that might take a few hours or something. And then you don't
want to wait all the time. You can do this and then later on analysis. Let it run overnight or
something like this. And now stats offers again a lot of things. I just show you a few. You don't
need to know all of them, but you can print a lot. A lot of different types of things. And print
statistics will do exactly the same we just seen. Yeah. So, we just seen this one. We can do
this. Of course, now you can sort this. You can select something. So, if you want to sort it by,
this is sorted by time, by default. And you can also say I would like to sort it by calls.
Then you can feed in calls and then it sorts it by calls. And now you get this and then you have to
say print stats on it. Print stats. And you can also limit the number of lines you want to print.
The print is only the first three lines. Yeah. So, you can limit the number. This is a short
example. If you have a big assembler, it might be hundreds and thousands of lines. You don't
want to see all of them. And you just see which one is interesting. Yeah. So, you can also go
through materials. So, if you cannot follow, you should be able to catch up, go into the PDF. So,
print stats prints just the way we had. And now there are multiple options to sort this and do
some kind of investigations on this one. You can also find out who's calling whom. So,
there are some things in there you have to say can stats. Print callers. There's callers and
callees. So, callers in one way. And so, who calls fast? And you see, okay, that you have this
connection here that use fast actually calls fast here in this direction. And the other way around,
you can say print callees. And then you get the other. Use fast. Yeah. So, just ask the question
a different way. And say use fast. And you get this information out of it. Yeah. Those kind of
things you can find out. Okay. This would be doing things with the Python C profiler. Now,
we're doing it with Jupyter. So, Jupyter uses this library in the background but gives you again
very similar to the percent time it denies the interface. There's no new functionality per se,
but everything is much easier to use. And typically, if things are easier to use,
you might get people to use it more easily. So, use fast.
Why doesn't it come? Is it use fast?
Okay. It's just the call tip didn't come. So, you see now, it's doing the thing. So,
instead you don't have to make instance of something you call the method. You just say
p run use fast and it's doing the stuff in the background. And this is the same output here
sorted by calls. And you can also give it a lot of options. So, if you say p runs, if you don't
know what to do, put a question mark and then you get the very long help. Run a statement through
Python code profiler. So, it's using exactly the same thing we just did but gives you a nice
interface. And again, you have a 1% version for one line and a 2% version for a whole cell.
And then there's explanation. And then you have a lot of options what you can do. So, if you don't
want to have many lines, you can limit how many lines you want to actually display.
It also can return this instance of the stats object we just seen. If you have something ready,
you can use it. You can also sort it by all kinds of things. You can say sorted by this key and then
you can provide a key and it gives you a list of keys you can sort by call and so on. So, you can
sort by all kinds of criteria here. You can also save it. Save whatever is printed. It will be
saved in the file. Or you can save it with D which saved this in a different binary file version and
you can read it with some tools later on. Yeah? If it's to talkative, you can suppress screen output
and so on. There's a lot of things you can do here and it makes it really, really useful.
And you cannot remember all of these but it's in the help and a few important ones.
So, I can use my p run and I can use one of these.
So, yeah, p run. I don't know what that's to. p run. And I say here my stats again
and I can now use the option return. Returns this object and I can say use
slow. And I have to call it actually. Now this will take 10 seconds again because we have to
wait so long. I don't think there's a way to speed this up. And then once we have done this,
we can look at this object. Since I didn't suppress the output, you still see the output.
But now we have the stats slow object which if I use it and say print stats as we did before,
then you see this output. Yeah. So, you can combine it now with existing tools. If you have
something there, then you can put it in but it makes it easier to work with it. So, again,
you can use some of the other options. So, p run. P run. Capital T option gives you writes
everything in a file. And I can say stats slow.txt. And I say use slow. So, if I say use slow and have
to wait again. Now it writes it instead of an addition, I think. In addition to write it to
my notebook, it writes it into a file. So, you know, if you copy and paste it in a file,
it will be in a file. So, if I now say ls, you can use the ls without percent but it's nicer to do it
with. Ls stats slow and you see it's there. And you can look at it with less. Yeah. And you see
that exactly the output we have. This would be one option. The other would be
doing it instead of the t with a d option. So, instead of the t, we use a d option. And now we
use our extension stats. So, you can make up any extensions. But this would be another binary
version and then you can load it again as we did before. But this is something that can be
interesting. It can be useful and gives you a lot of information and doing things. Good.
This would be basic profiling with a profiler here. Now the problem is when you measure something,
you might not measure the right thing. And we have to distinguish two types of
times. We have war clock versus CPU time. So, war clock time and CPU time. The war clock is
the time that actually the time that expires which is not necessarily the CPU time. So,
typically the war clock time is longer than the CPU time. Unless you have a multi-core machine
and use multi-cores, then that might be more CPU time because CPU time is more CPU core typically.
That's something interesting. But what do we measure? And unfortunately, that can be a bit
different depending on your operating system. And we load this file. Load. Load clock check.
So, this is this file here I wrote that does some interesting testing. So, we import a bunch of
things from the standard library here. This is again making Python 2 compatible with Python 3.
And this also. And now I have three different ways of measuring it. It's not very accurate,
but see what I'm doing inside here. I have two. I get three start time stamps. I use
OS times. This gives you a tuple. And the first entry is a timestamp. Then I use time clock.
And I use time at default timer. This works in Python 2. Python 3, there are some changes.
Python 3 has time. The time module.prov counter. It's a bit different. But if you use the time
it, then you don't see a difference between 2 and 3. So, I do something. I do a million times 1 plus
1. And I say sleep for the duration which defaults to 1. So, this one uses CPU. This one doesn't use
CPU because it tells the operating system to wake me up after one second. And then I do the same
thing. And so, that's not totally accurate because I measured this also here. But compared to this
one, it doesn't matter too much. And I measure the second. I do the same procedure here. And I just
get the second timestamp and measure the difference. So, I measure three differences between timestamps.
And then I print them out. And if I do this, I get a warning which I haven't seen before.
So, that's something that will be removed in Python 3. Yeah. So, time it.
Time clock. Yeah. So, time clock. And now we get a warning. I didn't have this warning before.
Must be the newer Python 3.7 version. I get this warning. So, that time clock will be removed
which is a good thing because it can be confusing. That's my point actually. And you see, now you get
here I'm on my Mac. I get OS timer and time clock being essentially the same. This is pretty coarse.
Pretty obvious. It should be pretty much the same. But they're essentially the same. And here, when
I use default timer, I measure my second of waiting. So, this is the CPU time. So, the CPU
time is approximately 0.03 seconds. Where the wall clock time is one second plus the CPU time, more or less.
Yeah. Anybody is on Windows? So, if you're Windows, you should see something different. Yeah. You see
the difference. Then time clock, it's a different thing. Yeah. Because time clock here gives me
the CPU time. When Windows, it gives you timestamps since the start of the process.
So, if you don't look at the timestamp, the absolute value of the timestamp,
you need a difference, then you don't see this. So, in Windows, you have something different.
And that can be tricky. So, if you have a nice script that works and you give it to a single colleague
and has a different operating system, all of a sudden the readings are very different.
That's why the recommendations use time into default timer, which abstracts us away. Yeah.
So, what's again the difference between the OS time and the time clock and in which case will they significantly diverge?
Yeah. You see, I do two things. This one consumes CPU. This is about 0.03 seconds, million times.
This one doesn't consume CPU, but it waits. It waits for a second. That's a different. So, one of this
timing, in my case, is one second longer than the others. So, the first two are pretty much the same.
And the last one is a second longer because the last one also measures the walk. But this one
is the walk clock time and these two are CPU time. If you have Windows, this one will be
CPU time and this two will be, that will be one there also.
And even in the first two ones, again, it's a multi-freted application. Would they also give the same thing?
It depends how you measure. No, no. If you have, what you measure, if you have,
if Python has a GIL, the global interpreter log, but it releases a GIL when you do input-output.
Sleep is input-output because you say operating system call me back and this means it's input-output operation.
So, if you sleep in the thread, the other thread can keep going. It doesn't wait.
So, it depends where you measure. You measure on the main thread or on the thread that waits.
Of course, if you measure the thread that waits, you still measure this waiting second.
If you measure outside, you don't measure it. It keeps going. Yeah. So, depends where you measure.
This is, sometimes can be tricky. And even in a simple application, it might not be clear what
you actually measure and where you measure it. And if you have a complex program, it can be,
you have to really make sure that you measure what you think you measure.
And typical solutions doing it, doing the two or different, two or three different ways.
And all the results agree, it's a good sign that you measure the right thing.
If they disagree, you have a problem, you find the problem. That's really how I do it. I try to,
like, I can excel. I do the sum this way and the sum this way. And if it's the same thing,
seems like I have all the cells to sum up. It's not guaranteed, but it's a good sign that
you might miss the same set of both ways could happen. Something like you have to find two
different ways to measure it, kind of independent ways, and then they don't make the same mistake,
hopefully. Yeah, something like this. It's kind of, it's a, it's a culture. It's not really good,
but it's better than nothing. So, and this is interesting to see that there can be differences.
And if you use a different function here to, to calculate this. And actually I wrote a small helper.
Yeah. That's not really good, but it gives you, actually I can load it here. Load CPU time. Yeah.
This is my small function here that measures CPU time. And I just distinguish if I'm on Windows,
I use this function. If I'm on, not on Windows, I use something else. So this works in Linux,
it works in Mac. I have no idea if it's a different operating system, but the case is there. Yeah.
Let's say I want to get rid of the defecation warning. What is the proper replacement function?
Don't, don't use clock. Right. But the warning say there are two different options.
Yeah. Do you can actually hear you can use, um, there's still a deprecation warning here.
There's no, there's still a defecation warning. I can use perf counter, perf counter. That's a
new function in a process time, process time or perf counter. So perf counter is a
war clock time and process time is the process time. So let's check. So always don't guess,
check it. Time, time, perf counter, which is a new stuff now that there's also nanosecond version.
It's the final version in Python three. So, um, and putting a question mark tells you,
yeah, performance count for float. That's not very, not very talkative, isn't it? Yeah. And the
other one was, uh, what was the other one process time? It just must be the, uh, the actually CPU
time. Yeah. This is CPU time. The other one is war clock time. Now you have it and now it's
they do this abstraction away. So if you're in Python three, seven, you don't need this thing
anymore. But if you have all the version of Python, then you have to be careful. So things
improved over time. So Python three is clearly better as always. Yeah. And they get away,
but you still, you have to make sure to do some experiments and some simple experiments. So take
something, you know what the result is and measure it and see if this agrees what you're measuring.
And of course this approach you can apply to other problems. You know what it is? Of course
you have some different tools, use your tools, measure. And if your tools agree with some,
like if, like if I have Linux and you have some operating system tools to measure something,
use your tools and try to reproduce the results. And if they don't agree, do you have to find
the reason why it is? Yeah. That's, that's important. And you have to be a bit skeptical.
If you measure something and especially if it's a strange result, say, can this be true?
Where's the problem? Maybe I'm the problem in my measuring, messing everything up for some reason,
which is not that obvious. Yeah. Good. So this is what I did here. And now actually you can
supply this, this function. This is my CPU function I did here, or one of these functions. Now,
if you fail in Python three, you can use these functions and you can
do the profiling here and supply this
this function. Yeah. So I can, I can do the same thing with p run, by the way, I can say p run.
And if you look at it, p run also takes, if I'm not mistaken, key, doesn't it take it? D.
Should be an option to take a different function to measure it. Maybe I just overlooked it.
No, it's not here.
I thought because this Python, this is a Python profile run, you can supply actually
runtime functions. If you don't, if you want to measure the, so you can say c profile,
c profile dot profile. You make an instance and then I specify the function. I say my CPU time here
or time it process time should be the same. We can try this in a minute. And then, yeah.
Then you get this result and you say print
stats, I guess. I can remember right. Then you see it get, no, it doesn't print stats.
Did we say print stats? Forgotten already. Did so many times.
I have to,
I run.
Yeah, print stats.
You have it in your loaded file.
No, I still get this one. This one works. Of course, this returns an instance.
Yeah, I haven't, I haven't executed cell.
I loaded the cell and didn't execute the cell. So.
No, that's CPU time.
No, I gave it. It must be there.
No, that should be the same because the function is there.
Thank you. Run call. Yeah.
Run call with underscore.
Run. So, and now I messed it up because I wanted to do it everything in one line.
Profiler, run call without.
Yeah, that's, yeah. Good call. Okay.
Sometimes then you're too close to the problem, even the simple things. So.
Okay.
So I make an instance and say run call and it works and it complains about this as a warning.
It gives me back the time.
Make an instance.
Yeah. And after this, I say profiler. So I have to make an instance and then.
No, that's a P.
So I make an instance and I call instance. Why is it difficult? Good. And I get the same
thing back and I have to supply.
My function is because I can change the function. I don't want to measure the walk clock. I want to
measure this one when I made it. And I have to give us this one here. That's a whole thing.
No.
Yeah.
So.
Okay. Now this works and now I can say P.
Run call.
Yeah. I have to feed TPU time there. And then once I, once I do this now,
it works. And now I have my, my P and I go step by step. That's easier. And now I can say,
I can say run call and now feed the function. Yeah. And then I have my,
I get my warning because I use this function and now I can say print starts. So.
Sure. It was better to do it in one cell. Now you have this and you see now the timing. I measure the,
the CPU time. And actually I can say even slow.
Yeah. This will take a while, but if I do the printing, it should be,
shouldn't take, you have to wait 10 seconds for the measurement because this is still the time it
takes, but the 10 seconds shouldn't show up there and they don't show up. Yeah. There used to be 10
seconds here. There's no 10 seconds anymore. Of course, now the measurement doesn't take this into
account. Okay. So once you figure this out, we're doing exactly the same steps we did before.
One step after the other, you get the warning because I do this. If I, instead of using this one,
I use time. I use time, the time module and I use the process time in Python stream. So in Python two,
you won't have this. Then you should get the same results. Again, after wait 10 seconds. Now you
should see the process time. So you can feed a different time measurement. That before that takes
a wall clock time, but you can also have process time. You see no 10 seconds here.
No 10 seconds here. Yeah. So in this case, it doesn't really matter what the absolute numbers are.
You have this 10 seconds. Good. This is a very simple function. Let's do a bit more complicated
function. I always have my, uh, uh, pi function and I have to go to a different directory. So we
go up one, we go up one directory and then we see there's a pie. So this is a very stupid way to
calculate pie. So it doesn't really matter. Um, but then numerics do so I can just import this,
load this file. And this is a simple way to calculate pie. It's using a Monte Carlo approach.
It's just a little bit numerics that we don't have to go in there. And then once you run it,
you get actually here, uh, value that's kind of close to pie. It's not even there. Yeah. 3.14,
159 or something like this should be the value. And we are pretty off here,
but this is a very simple numerical calculation. And then I think is when, once we do this,
because we calculate run the numbers, you can parallelize it. I use it as a simple example
for a lot of things making faster. So that's goes way beyond using all kinds of ways to make it,
to make it faster, to get it, get it going. Yeah. And, uh, for this one, you can also use numpy.
So if you have, this is a version, the simple version, and then we have a numpy version,
which is doing exactly the same thing. But if you use numpy, anybody who knows numpy,
they use random random, which doesn't give you one value, but gives you a whole array of values.
And this will be much faster. Has one disadvantage. It calculates all the values of memory at once.
So if you keep all the memory, the other one has one number at a time. So it might be very slow,
but it's not memory bound. Numpy will get memory bound sooner or later, because in this way I do
it. It calculates all the values. It wouldn't be necessary. You can do it stepwise, but the way I
implemented there, but it gives you also, uh, yeah, I haven't installed numpy. That's not good.
Forgotten to specify. So you need to install numpy, see if it works. You should be able to
do this right here. So, ah, uh, kernel interrupt. You have to say install. Yes. Otherwise it asked
me to do it and then there's no way to enter it. Yeah. So if you do it from the command line,
it asks you, uh, by the way, if you hear, you can open a new, uh, console terminal right in here and
you would get a terminal and then you can do it. I would need to activate my environment here because
doesn't activate. You can store it from there. This is a bit tricky here because now it would block,
but if you say yes, then it doesn't ask for confirmation. Otherwise ask for confirmation,
but I cannot type in the confirmation, which is not that good. Yeah. So you can install me,
if you install numpy and see if it, if it works out, but it doesn't really matter too much.
Um, here you, you will see numpy as the same algorithm and you can, you can work with it. Good.
Let's wait if this is works here and the next one actually would be a snake with. So now we want to
do some visualization and one to visualize, um, things. And actually this would be now a good way.
You can do this on the, on the console.
And maybe, maybe I do the installation of the console. They are making a new console
here and activate, activate my, uh, environment and I can do my content store here and I don't
have to do this. So I can activate it here and say, come to install numpy. I see maybe it's not
got you to do it twice. Cause here there's still interrupt. Yeah. It's interrupting. So you can,
can install here if it works. And now we can also make a new tab. I activate my environment again.
And now we want to look at a snake with, so snake with is a tool that allows you to visualize
the results of the run. So so far we only saw numbers. It was kind of okay, but if you have
hundreds and hundreds of line of numbers, it's really difficult to see something.
And snake was takes these numbers and puts it in nice pictures and you don't have to do it yourself
and that different ways of doing it. So you can, uh, do it from the command line. So there are
different ways of doing it. So you can run Python, uh, dash M anybody knows the dash M actually,
this is recommended. If you say PIP install, you shouldn't use PIP. You say Python dash M PIP.
Then it runs PIP as a command line tool, but it uses the library version because if you say PIP,
it takes one of the paths and might take a different PIP. Depends how you set up your system.
Yeah. If it, they dash M, it will take the PIP that belongs to the Python
because it runs a module like a standalone program. Yeah. That's what I'm doing here. Uh,
and I say, okay, run C profile because you got it from the command line. Actually one C profile.
We write the result to the file. Um,
PI dot stats, which is this binary file and run our simple program. And now I, I'm not in the directory.
Yeah. I'm, I'm, I'm not sure where I am.
Okay. Oh, and the directory. So, so now I do the same thing for Python, uh,
run as module C profile again, with the spelling profile, with the spelling,
write the outputs to PI dot stats and run the file simple PI. So, uh, and Python missing an N
and then it should run this one and produces this, this output file. Yeah. It does a print
on the way. And now I can use snake with from the command line and I can say snake with,
if it's installed, I should work snake with, uh, um, PI dot starts. And then it opens the result
of snake with right here. And why doesn't show anything? It should be a nice picture.
Always used to be a picture. It takes a while. Okay. Now this is icicle to typically sunburst
this one. This is now, uh, the result of this one. And there's a lot of stuff here,
which we don't want. And this, you see, you will recognize this table. There's quite a things going
on. This is a table of the calls here. Yeah. So this is the same thing we saw. The nice thing is
here. You can actually sort it. You click on it and sorts it by whatever you want. Otherwise it's
the same result, but not just plain text. And then you have a picture here and this picture is
interesting because these are the calls. And if you go in here, it shows you the function. You
might not see it, but, and there, that shows you the function. And this is the main function from
inside. It takes a hundred percent of the time. And then you go outside this function called this
function that takes, spends most of the time in this function and it'll be in this and then the
next and the next and the next and the outermost. Actually these ones, this, this here is a random
function. So it's how much time you spend in a random function. And then this is how much time
you spend in the function, a pipeline in general. So this is a time you spend in the whole function.
That's like the time that's in the main loop in the function. These are the other function. This
is a function, uh, the built in square root. I'm using the square. This is square root and this is a
random function. And this is the time that you spend in the loop itself. So that's this one.
Yeah. So this is this part. So we have the random function rent and no, sorry here, random function
and we have a square root function and the rest is a loop and this calculation here.
This gives you some results here. And if you don't like this, you can change sunburst to icicle,
which is the same information, but instead of a circle, you have square. Now the inner circle,
there's an inner circle, the next circle, the next circle, the same thing, just here. And then
it's easier because now you can read the names. There's no space to put the names, but there's a
lot of stuff here, a lot of small helper functions you're not really interested in. But it's very
obvious which function takes the most time in this case, where the time goes and where you might be
able to make it faster if you do it. So that's something you can do from here. But of course,
since you're in a Jupyter notebook, we can do the same thing in Jupyter notebook and we have to
load an extension, load extension, snake with, and you can do the same thing from here just by
calling snake with and say plain. What's the function name? Pyplane? Did not execute it?
So the call tips don't work, pyplane, and they have to give it a value, yeah, one million.
Something like this. And I used a double instead of a single, and now it does the same thing out of
my, it opens a new tab and shows me the result and I don't have to go to the console. Yeah, so you can
do it directly from here just by using this snake with command. You have to load it first, an extension,
so you can extend the notebook. There are many extensions. The extension has been installed
automatically when you install snake with. Yeah, so you get, and this is really useful because now
you have this information here and you see now just all these extra startup functions, all those
little noisy things are gone because they're not measured here. Yeah, good. Okay, this is snake with
and snake with allows you to measure a few things. That's the profiling. So far all the profiling
is restricted to functions. So the most fine-grained level you can see anything is in the function
level. Sometimes that's not good enough. If you want to go final and you will do a line profiling,
then you need to install the line profile and go line by line. This is interesting. The problem is
with line profile, it adds a lot of overhead, so you cannot line profile your whole program typically
because it would take ages to run. So typically you do profiling first and if you find one or two
interesting functions you want to go into deeper, they can use line profile on these functions and
you can do this. So again, line profile you need to install and then you can run it and you have two
options. So you can run it from the command line or you can run it from the notebook as always.
So this is because notebook has an extension. So let's do both. Both of them, both of these
methods can be useful. And now finally we found NumPy to install. So let NumPy install and I can
kill this one here. Yeah.
Because there are small things going on. All the startup process.
The Jupyter notebook is running already. When you saw the new Python process, a lot of startup
functions, all the startup functions are measured also.
Everything. In the notebook everything is loaded already and then you do from the command line you
have a lot of noise there that happens which actually not really interested because you
don't have you have to start the process anyway.
Because we did this C profile on the whole program, if you generate the C start file in
a different way then snakewiz will show the same result. Just the way how you how you
generate. Since we use this dash m function and run the whole program, if you just use your C
profile from within everything's loaded and you shouldn't do this one you can try then all this
little noisy thing should go away. Yeah but good question. So why is this noise there?
Okay line profile you need to install it and once you have installed it then
check where we are. We are now in the py measurement and let's go up to measuring.
Yeah and now I can use Kernprof which is the name. This is by Robert Kern. That's called Kernprof
and you can say verbose and if you use Kernprof on profile me then you won't see any anything
special. This is just using normal profiling and you just see the normal results here after a while.
You need to fortify this program. Now this is just a normal output. Again now you see all this noise
because it runs a whole module and you have all the startup crap in here so to speak. If I look at this
if I load now
profile me line profile. So I put a decorator here out of the blue. I didn't import. If you look at
this, if I run it from here I would say there's no such thing. So I just run it from here.
So I just run it from here. So I just run it from here. So I just run it from here. So I just run it
out of blue. If you look at this, if I run it from here I would say there's no such thing as profile
because Kernprof is ejecting this decorator in their namespace. I don't know if it's a good thing
but that's what it's doing. You have to actually explicitly mark the functions you want a line
profile with profile. This is deliberate. So you typically don't want a line profile or your
functions. You don't want a line profile 100 100 function because it takes very long. So you have
to explicitly say I want to use these ones. These two. And now once I go to my here go to my
line profiler and I profile this one and I also have to give the option that is supposed to do this
when I say dash L for line. So I turn on line profiling otherwise I wouldn't do it actually.
And then now it takes longer and after a while it will show you everything line by line. So it takes
a while but once it's working we can look at the version that actually works in.
Ah yeah. See now you have this line by line when you see here if it's fast you can still something
by 0.6 percent. This is a time percent and this is the total time here with units there.
How much time it spends here and how much time it spends here and here in slow you see this would
be 0 percent because this is so slow that there's nothing left. If you run it to one digit in percent
you don't see anything. So it is a very simple it's a very simple function and you you have this very
simple result. So let's do some small examples that make a bit more sense with line profiling.
The next one would be actually accumulate where I wrote this very simple function
that hopefully makes a point about line profiling. Accumulate you see now I do this this does nothing
else but adding up numbers in the list and keeps all intermittent result. Yeah so if you use NumPy
then you use might not accumulate. Does this profile decorator is it can we import it from a package so that it actually.
Yes you can do I will show you typically I do it from the notebook because this is something
you do only once and then you don't have to put it the decorator there. Yeah.
Accumulate yeah this is this is a use line profiler so profiler use line profile everything the directory measuring.
You see this one just calculates if you do this you see I say accumulate.
It's.
I can run it I can run it because it's decorated I need a decorator take a decorator out when I take a
decorator out then it accumulate accumulate it and if you had because I don't have a printed result accumulate
you see that adding numbers from zero to nine gives you 1445 and this keeps all intermittent results.
Okay so I did this one now we can do line profiling here and run it for 10 and 100 so we do the same thing.
But instead of using profile may use accumulate and then it works a while on it and then you see
the difference between these. These function calls when you see if you run it here.
This is the time is pretty even distributed between these four steps this one doesn't take a lot on this one
not of course but they take about more or less 25 percent or so around it.
So that's something you know there's no one line that consumes all the time.
But you can see something you have this breakdown breakdown line line by line.
A few more examples for line by line so you can always do some experiments load the list and then you can
do experiments load some calculations some different types of calculations.
So I do here a loop and I add 10 to a number I multiply a number by 10 I use to the power of 10
then I use the power function is doing the same thing I use a square root mastered square root and
also set square root to mastered square which saves me a lookup and do this again and adjust excess
square root and so a few things here and then I run it through my my line calculator again and
see the differences. So it will show you the code also and then you see what takes how much time
and you see here then you then you have plus and multiplication takes about the same amount of time
very similar power is more expensive and the power function takes a little tiny bit more time than this
double star here and you see square root mastered square root and square root there's a difference
here in our this over is relative to the total time you should be careful yeah so if something
else takes a lot of time everything gets to zero because it's but you can also see the absolute
time but there's a small difference doing it this way and this way if you repeat it so many times
yeah as you see if excess mastered square root and just square root as it is there's a difference
of course there's an extra lookup so that's something you can can investigate here you can work with it
good so three o'clock is break it's it's five minutes to three so maybe it's a good thing
if you make break now then you have a better chance to get a coffee so we have 20 minutes break I
think so then we meet back here 15 past the hour which is 20 minutes so we break 15 minutes and
we continue with some more of these a little bit profiling memory profiling in algorithms
so we meet here 15 past the hour and continue with our tutorial
so
good
but
.