Good morning, everyone. We're going to get started. So today we have David,
pardon, we have David Wollever. He is the founder of PyCon Canada. He will be
talking about floats, our friends making the most of IEEE 754. We will not be
taking Q&A. If you have questions, he will be outside the door after the talk.
Please give a warm welcome to David.
Yeah, hey folks. So my name is David Wollever and I am super excited to be
here today to talk to all of you about floating point numbers. I'm really
curious though, what the heck are you doing here? There's lots of other great
talks. Why do you want to hear about floats? If you don't mind sending me a
tweet right there and just letting me know what brought you to this talk as
opposed to any of the other great talks, I'd really like to hear it. The second
small thing for the folks up front, if you don't mind grabbing a photo or two of me,
I'd love to have something to show my mom. Thank you. And finally, I need to
apologize for the artistic license that I took with the talk title. 754 can be
exactly represented in floating point. I'm sorry. So over the course of this talk,
I'd like to tell you a bit more about what floats are, how they work, and why
they do the weird things that they do. Because they definitely aren't the best,
but also they're not the absolute worst. And regardless of any of that, we are
absolutely stuck with them. So hopefully by the end of this talk, I don't expect
you to like them, but at least I hope you'll understand them a little bit
better. So to understand floats, we need to take a step back and look at why
floats exist. And to understand that, we need to look at how numbers are
represented in computers. So whole numbers, integers, those are pretty
straightforward. We take a chunk of memory, and within that chunk of memory,
there's a nice one-to-one mapping between the binary numbers we can represent there
and the whole numbers that we're used to dealing with every day, our ones, our
twos, our fives, et cetera. And the way we do that representation is more or less
what you're used to if you've done any reading on binary notation. Now, one thing
you'll notice is in this example, I'm not including any negative numbers. And
those are done with a representation called twos complement. Twos complement is,
in my opinion, an absolute thing of beauty, and I'd really suggest you go look
it up after the talk, but unfortunately, this is about floats, so we can't get
into that here. Anyway, whole numbers, integers, and computers, those turn out
to work pretty well. With a 32-bit int, we get to represent numbers between about
2 billion and negative 2 billion. And then if we pump that up to a 64-bit long,
we can go up to 9 quadrillion. And it turns out that for the integers, for the
whole numbers that we deal with data programmers, the numbers that occur in the
real world, that range is actually really sufficient. We don't often need to go
bigger or smaller than that. When we start moving into fractional numbers,
though, things get a little bit more difficult. To understand why, imagine how
you might implement fractional numbers. Well, we might say we got that chunk of
memory, and let's split it in half, and we'll say, okay, the first half is going to
be the integral component, and the second half is going to be the fractional
component. And that might look a little something like this. So we could have, if
we have a 1 in the fractional component, that's 1 over 2 to the 8, so 0.125. If we
have a 2 in the fractional component, that would give us 1 over 4, 0.25, and so on.
But one of the things you'll notice here is with this representation, we don't
actually get a very large range of numbers that we can work with. If we're
only using 32 bits, the smallest number that we could represent is 1.5 times 10
to the negative 5, so that's like a decimal place, four zeros and a 1 and a 5.
And the largest number is a measly 131,000. We could go up and use, say, 64
bits instead, where we have 32 bits before the decimal place and 32 bits
after the decimal place, and that will buy us quite a bit more space. We can go
down to 10 decimal places of precision, approximately, and we could go up to
numbers as big as about 4 billion. But, I mean, the first caveat there is this is
completely ignoring negative numbers. And the second caveat is in the real
world, it turns out that when we're representing things with real numbers,
the things we're representing tend to be on a much larger scale. You know, we have
to deal with things like the distance to Pluto, that's 7.5 billion kilometers, and
we might want to represent things that are really small, like the size of a
water molecule, three-tenths of a nanometer. And in this naive system that
we had just talked through, this system where we're taking a certain
amount of bits and we're fixing the position of the decimal place, a fixed
point number, if you will, we're going to run into some problems because that
range we can represent is fixed, and it's not going to, in practice, be able to
handle a lot of the numbers that we have to deal with in the real world. So I'm
sure you're all smart programmers, your brains are worrying figuring out how
you're going to fix this, and probably what you're coming up with is a system
that will look a little bit like this, where we say, okay, we've got the number,
and alongside that number, let's store a scaling factor. So with the distance to
Pluto, that's going to be 7.5, and we have a scale factor of 10, which is going to
push that 7.5 all the way off to the left. And then for the very small number,
like the size of a water molecule, we'll use a negative scale factor that'll push
it off to the right. So this would be a system you could say this moves the
decimal place around, it floats the decimal place around. It's almost like
we've got a floating point. And lo and behold, this is what floats do. Internally
in the computer, floating point numbers have three different components. The
first bit in them is the sign bit that controls whether they're positive or
negative. The second set of bits is the exponent. That's basically the shifting
or scaling factor we had just talked about. And finally, the third portion is
called the fraction. That's the actual number portion. It's also called the
mantissa if you're trying to sound fancy. So you calculate the value of the
floating point number by taking the sign, multiplying that by 2 to the power of the
exponent, and multiplying that by the fraction. If you've ever worked with
scientific notation before, this is exactly the same thing just in base 2.
This is just base 2 scientific notation. So to get concrete with an example here,
let's say we want to represent 0.5. 0.5 is a really nice easy fraction to
represent because it's 1 over 2 or 2 to the power of negative 1. So we're going
to have a sign of 0 because it's positive and an exponent of 4. Now the
exponent of 4 is a bit weird here and that's because exponents are what's
called biased. Since we need to represent both positive and negative exponents,
there's a fixed bias that we introduce. In this case we're going to use 3 and
that shows up pretty well. And we deduct whatever exponent is stored in the number
from that bias to get the actual value. And finally, we just want half so we
multiply it by 1. A couple other examples. 3.25, that would be 2 to the
power of negative 2, so 0.25 times 13. Or a negative number, we have a 1 in the
sign bit. We're trying to represent negative 88 so that the exponent is going
to be 4, which is 2 to the power of 4, 8, and multiply that by 11. Sorry, 2 to the
power of 3, excuse me. 4. Anyway, this is neat. So we've got this number system and
you can see how we can scale to represent numbers that are either very
small or very large. And to give you an idea of the actual practical range of
that system, 32-bit floats, so these are the kind of older-school floats that
systems used to use in the past. They've got an exponent that's 8
bits long and a fractional component that's 23 bits long. And 64-bit floats,
doubles, these are the default whenever you have a float in just about any
modern computer or programming language. They've got an 11-bit exponent and a
whole 52 bits of a fractional component. So they can represent numbers that are as
small as a decimal place with 300 zeros behind it and as large as a 1 with 300
zeros behind it. So this is pretty good. We've got a pretty large range of numbers
we can represent there, but as with everything, there is a trade-off here.
And the trade-off that floating-point numbers make is between precision, so
that is how small can our numbers get, and magnitude, how big can the numbers get.
So for instance, we can measure the distance to Pluto, but that measurement
won't necessarily be accurate and precise down to the meter. And we can
also very precisely measure the size of a water molecule, but we're going to run
into some trouble if we need to, say, measure a billion of them at the same time.
So to give you a concrete example of what that precision error might look like,
let's say we have a smallish number, a 1, and we have a very large number, 1e20.
Just the exponential notation there, the 1e20, means a 1 followed by 19 zeros.
And if we try to add 1 to a 1 with 19 zeros after it, you'll notice that the
magnitude of that large number just completely overshadows the precision of
the small number, and the 1 is completely lost. In fact, it's as if it never existed.
So what do you, as work-a-day programmers who don't want to get a degree in
numerical analysis just to add some numbers together, what are you going to do about this?
So the first rule of thumb that I want you to remember is that with a double,
so that's a 64-bit float, you get 15 significant decimal digits. That means 15
of the digits in your floating point number are generally going to be reliable.
But you're going to lose precision if you try and add or subtract numbers that are outside of,
that have different magnitudes. So for example, let's say I want to add 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 to 1e15.
So 1e15 has 15 digits. That's safe, and you'll notice that we get an exact result.
But as we move up, as we move up to 16 significant digits, we're going to start losing some precision.
And that problem only gets worse as the large number gets larger.
It is important to note, though, that multiplication and division are just fine.
They're not affected by this. And finally, if you are in the unfortunate situation of having to sum
lots of floats together, there are very good libraries to do this. And to show what they do,
consider first this naive sum. So we're going to take a very small number, like a very large
negative number, add 1 to it, and then add a very large positive number. Ideally, we'd get 1.
But because of that floating point rounding error, using Python's built-in sum, we get 0.
However, if we go and we use math.fsum, we're going to get the exact result. And this is because
math.fsum is doing something really neat under the hood. What it's doing is each time it performs an
addition, it's keeping track of the precision that was lost of that roundoff error and storing
that in a separate list. And then once we've summed up all the numbers in the main list,
we go back and sum up all the numbers in this roundoff list and add that in. So it's going to
get very precise. The tradeoff there, of course, is a runtime one. You're doing many more additions
and it's more computationally expensive. The other interesting one to look at is numpy's sum.
Now, in this case, numpy's sum actually gets it wrong. And that's because it's using an addition
algorithm called addition by parts, where it's going to take chunks of the list and sum them up
at a time. And then sum those sums and sum those sums kind of a divide and conquer type algorithm.
It doesn't have the strong guarantees that Python's fsum has, but it does have the advantage
of being much more efficient, which is why they use it by default. And finally, if you truly need
to do a lot of these, A, my heart goes out to you, and B, you might want to take a look at the
acupy library because they do this very fast and very accurately. The second tradeoff that I want
to talk about here is the fact that every real number can't be represented by floating point.
In some cases, it's kind of obvious why. We have real numbers that are infinite, like pi or e,
and obviously we just can't represent infinite numbers in a finite amount of memory.
The second more tricky kind of number, though, is the fact that since floating point uses a binary
fraction, there aren't binary fractional representations for all of the decimal
fractions that we expect, like common decimal fractions, like 0.1. 0.1's a good fraction.
But I'm sure this is a thing you have all run into. And just if you're curious and playing
along at home, when I'm showing these floating point numbers, I'm rounding them to 20 decimal
places, and this is the code you could use. So to understand a bit more why that, what's going on
here, consider this number line. The horizontal line is the continuous line of all the real numbers,
and each of the white vertical lines represents a single floating point number that can be
represented. So for instance, we might have 0.5, 1. Forgive my scale, that's way off, but hopefully
you'll understand the idea. So when we get a real number coming in, and we need to figure out
which floating point number is nearest to that number and use that nearest floating point as
an approximation. So in the case of 0.1, we can't represent that exactly, so we fall over to the
nearest float, which is 1.0005. Or if we're representing pi, that might have to round up
a little bit to like 1.146. And if you're curious to dig into this, the difference between that
real number and the nearest number that's being represented is measured using a technique called,
it's measured using the relative error, and you can go and look that up, and it's very interesting.
But again, to give you a really concrete example of what's going on here, let's say we have 0.1.
And 0.2. When we add them together though, notice that the floating point number we get by summing
0.1 and 0.2 is different from the floating point number that is nearest to 0.3. Similarly,
if we try to add 0.1 to itself 10 times, we don't actually get one. We get a number that's very
close to one, but it's definitely not one. Although fortunately, multiplication does typically work
a bit better. So what are you going to do about this? Well, the first thing that's important to
remember is each time you perform a floating point operation, some error is being introduced.
You do have that small roundoff error, and it's just going to accumulate. The only thing you can
really do about that is judiciously round your numbers, and that's the thing I'm going to be
talking about in a second. The second thing that you need to remember is to be really careful when
you're comparing floats to other floats. And instead of using a double equals equality,
use something like numPy is close, or even just write your own is close. That becomes especially
relevant when you're comparing numbers to 0. So for instance, if you're taking the dot product of
two vectors to figure out if they're perpendicular, the number you get back might not be 0. It might be
a very, very tiny number, but it's distinctly non-zero.
And the third and the very most important thing, if there's only one thing you take away from this
talk, this is the important one. It's that any time you're working with floats and you're displaying
them, so after you've performed computations, they need to be rounded. You need to have some notion of
how many decimal places are relevant and appropriate to show for your application,
and any floating point numbers need to be rounded to that number of decimal places. I was even
talking with a friend just over lunch yesterday, and he said, well, you know, I'm going to show
you a bunch of things that I've been doing with my friend just over lunch yesterday. And they were
telling me about a whole bunch of caching errors they were having. They were getting a bunch of
cache misses because they had a system that was caching based on a time code, and the time code
was being stored as a float, and that float was having exactly the kind of computational errors
that I've just talked about. So that's some of the more mathematical parts. Now, I want to get
to the next number of the most weird parts. The first weird part of the floating point standard
that I want to talk about is infinity. So the floating point standard does define a representation
for infinity and negative infinity. That's where all the exponent bits are set and the fractional
component is zero, and it's actually a really neat and kind of useful number. It does what you expect.
Infinity is larger than any other number, and I have actually used it a bunch if I have a loop,
say, that needs to find the smallest or the largest item in a list, and I need a good default
initial value. Infinity makes a really good default value. It'll also pop up if numbers that are very
large overflow or very large negative numbers overflow negative. And the last kind of exciting
thing about it is at least according to the standard, you get infinity or negative infinity
if you divide by zero. Now, fortunately, Python's got our back here, and they do,
Python does something a little bit more sensible. But this is important to know when you're working
in other languages that aren't quite as careful about raising exceptions. And to understand why
it might make sense that dividing by zero gives you infinity, I want you to consider if we were
writing a function that evaluates one over x. So as x is getting smaller and smaller and smaller,
the value of one over x is getting larger and larger and larger, and that is in math terms,
you say, converging to infinity. So if you imagine we're calculating this x and getting it smaller
and smaller and smaller, at some point, that value of x might underflow, and it might underflow to zero.
And it would be, when you squint it the right way, natural for that underflow to result in infinity
as opposed to a math error. And that brings us to the second interesting part of floating point.
We have negative zero. So if you remember the binary representation in memory, we have
all zeros is going to be a zero, but we still have that sign bit floating around. And if that sign bit
is set, we get a negative zero. It basically only comes up when you underflow a sufficiently small
number. And it can be actually kind of useful, again, when you squint things the right way,
to have the distinction between negative zero and positive zero. Because again, if you consider that
one over x function, as x is approaching zero from the negative side, it's going to be converging to
negative infinity. And when it underflows to negative zero, it's kind of useful to have the
result be negative infinity as opposed to positive infinity or something else.
And otherwise, negative zero behaves just like our good friend normal zero.
Now, finally, I want to talk about NaN. NaN is probably my favorite part of floating point.
NaN stands for not a number. And it's a number that, just like it says right there on the box,
is not a number. It's defined as being the result of mathematically undefined operations. So for
instance, dividing infinity by infinity, you'll get NaN. It's also defined as being the result of
operations like the square root of negative one. Although again, Python has got us covered here.
It's going to do something potentially a little bit more helpful. But NaN is really important to
know about because it's wild. It just breaks everything. It's the only value that is not
equal to itself. And this is true in every programming language, in every computer system.
It doesn't make any sense to compare it to things, so every comparison will return false.
And every mathematical operation that you try to perform with a NaN is going to give you back NaN.
It's kind of infectious, like a SQL null if you're familiar with that.
Although the one interesting Python tidbit that you can bust out to have fun at parties
is that in some situations, testing to see if NaN is in a list with a NaN will return true.
But that's left as an exercise to the reader. And actually, I kind of like NaN. It can be pretty
useful if you have, say, a large data set. Maybe you're taking measurements from an external system
or something like that. And you need to have a value in a particular place, but no value makes
sense. Using a NaN as a placeholder, kind of like a null, is actually kind of useful. So in this case,
imagine we have two lists of numbers that we want to divide by the number of values that we want to
divide by each other and then take the mean value of the result. Because one of the numbers will be
NaN, it will just be ignored when we use NumPy as a NaN mean. So NumPy as a NaN mean is like mean,
except it ignores NaNs. And it's also got NaN sum and so on. So this is really important to know
about, though. Because especially if you're building web systems that accept values from a
JavaScript front end, if any of you have worked in JavaScript, you know that it coughs out NaNs
all over the place. And now you know just how badly it's going to wreck all of your numerical code.
So the two best ways to test for it, either using math.isNaN or just checking if a thing is not
equal to itself. Because if a thing's not equal to itself, guaranteed it's going to be NaN.
So okay, pop quiz time. How many NaNs are there? One? I've heard one. I'm sorry, you're off by 52
binary orders of magnitude. There's actually two to the 52 NaNs. And that's because they're defined
as being any floating point value where the exponent is fully set and the fractional component
is just not zero. And you know, there were some smart programmers at one point who kind of realized
that's a bit of a waste. We've got all these values that are doing nothing. So why not just stuff some
pointers in there? And this is actually what happens in every modern JavaScript implementation.
Under the hood, when you're passing around a pointer to an object, that pointer can actually be
two things. If you mask it properly and the mask returns true, then it's interpreted as a double.
On the other hand, if the mask is false, then it's a pointer, which means that you can write
actually very interesting, efficient code. So this is a completely fictitious implementation, but
it's close enough to true where if we're adding two JavaScript objects together,
the first thing we need to do is if we can run this quick bit mask to check and see if they're
both doubles. And if they are, we can add them with just one machine instruction. So this is now much,
much more efficient than Python, say where we'd have to go and unbox those numbers.
And so on and so on. So, okay, we've talked about how the precision can be lost when numbers of
different magnitude are added and subtracted. We've talked about the problems that come when
we try to stuff binary decimal numbers into binary fractions. But I do want to offer you some hope.
The decimal module.
Per the documentation, the decimal module provides support for decimal floating point
arithmetic. And hopefully you have a bit of a notion of what those words mean now.
Because it's doing decimal arithmetic, we have exact representations of decimal numbers.
We're still going to have problems with that nearest number rounding problem. We still can't
represent pi exactly. But at least the representations will be more sensible.
They'll follow the same grade school rounding rules that you're used to.
And we still need to specify precision. We don't have unlimited memory.
But the default in decimal is 28 decimal places. And that's probably going to be enough for most
folk. And of course, if you need more, you can just turn it up. So to give a really quick example of
what decimal looks like, we could import it. We'll create a decimal value of .1.
And notice that when we add .1 to itself 10 times, we get the precise exact result of 1 as we'd expect.
Now, one interesting consequence is that when you load a floating point number into a decimal,
it will faithfully try and read in that entire number. But at some point, I don't know how well
you know pi. You'll notice that it does diverge. And that's because the floating point number can't
precisely represent pi. Now, there is, of course, a drawback. There is a tradeoff here.
And that's that decimals are significantly slower. In a quick test that I did here,
multiplying a number by itself, comparing a decimal to a float, found the decimal was about
10 orders of magnitude slower. It's a lot slower. Also, unlike floats,
floats are going to be the same size. They take up exactly 64 bits, no matter how big or small the
number is. That's not true of decimals. The size of a decimal is going to grow as you get more
decimal places or as the number gets larger. But that all said, decimal is great. And if you're
doing computations that need precision, so this is things like math, if you're doing math,
you need numbers. If you're doing math with money, for instance, it's absolutely a thing that's worth
using. So thank you for coming out and listening to me rant about floats. If you've got any
questions, I'd love to come chat with you in the back. After this talk, I'll just be hanging it
outside the hall. Thank you all so much.