Hello, everyone.
This is from Minutes to Milliseconds with SQL Alchemy by Leo.
If we have time at the end of the presentation, there are two microphones right in the middle
of this corridor right here.
If you have any questions, please form a line and we'll take questions one by one from there.
Thank you.
Leo.
So I'm here to talk about ORMs.
I'm Leonardo or Leo.
I'm a technical lead at Jiru, which is a financial services company in Brazil.
I'm by no means an expert in either SQL or SQL Alchemy or ORMs, but I'd like to pass
on some lessons I learned while optimizing some really little processes we found out
while using SQL Alchemy, in particular the ORM.
So Jiru, as I said, is a Brazilian fintech.
We do loans without collateral, completely online.
You don't have to visit the bank or anything like that.
Our backend stack is pretty much all Python.
We use mostly Postgres for storage.
We use Pyramid as a Python framework for almost all our projects.
Since we do Postgres with Pyramid, SQL Alchemy is a nice fit.
There's really great integration with Pyramid that integrates the request cycle of the web
framework with the transaction, with the SQL Alchemy transaction, so it's really nice.
Of course, when you talk about SQL Alchemy, there are two aspects.
One is the expression language, which is just a fancy way of writing SQL using Python.
And then there's the ORM, the object relational mapper, which is where you get classes mapping
to tables and records of these tables mapping to instances of the class.
In SQL Alchemy, the ORM is built upon the SQL Alchemy DSL, but you mostly can use them
without ever thinking about the other.
I really like SQL Alchemy.
I think it's awesome.
But as Martin Fowler said, frameworks still require you to make decisions about how to
use them, and knowing the underlying patterns is essential if you're to make wise choices.
So we're going to talk about the ORM trap.
Using an ORM is really nice.
You barely remember there's an SQL under that at all, and that's actually a problem, because
the database is an external system.
You treat it like you treat an external service, like you treat an API from a service provider.
Because if you don't, what happens is you do bad access patterns, you do things that
are inefficient, and the ORM doesn't help you write good performance SQL.
Things that look perfectly sensible in Python translate into bad SQL access patterns.
Worse is that this is unnoticeable at low data volumes.
Everything just works and seems happy enough.
And this happens, obviously, when you're developing and early in production.
So you're babysitting your system.
It seems to be doing fine, and you start to relax.
Everything's doing great.
And then when you're actually getting some success on your system, then things start
slowing to a crawl.
Because SQL alchemy is so good, and ORM from SQL alchemy is so good that the metaphor rarely
leaks.
You don't see bad SQL blowing in your face while using the ORM.
Things just start getting really slow.
So how do you fix that?
You need to be mindful of the work that the database is doing while you're operating with
what looks like just Python.
You need to be especially mindful of the amount of round trips that the access to your instances
do, the attributes that you look up.
What kind of queries does it do when you access that attribute?
Is that a relationship to another record?
Is that triggering an SQL statement as well?
You need to be mindful of those things, especially when you're looking at relationships, especially
when your ORM is mapping relationships into attributes.
You should try as much as possible to reduce the proportionality of the queries that you
emit during a transaction.
It should be ideally a fixed number of queries per, for example, an API request or a background
job.
You should, as much as possible, avoid looping through model instances.
You have this class that's mapping to a table, and it's tempting to go to a query that pulls
a bunch of those records and starts making calculations.
But you should avoid that.
Instead, you should let the DB do it for you.
So I'm going to be talking about one case that we got in our company, which was a report
that took more than 24 hours to run, and now it takes a few minutes.
So for that, I need to talk a little bit about how Jiru works.
This is a model of how my company works that simplifies beyond any sense of closeness to
reality.
But it's kind of like this.
There is a securitizing company, I don't know the correct term in English, that sells the
ventures like company loans.
With that, it acquires funds.
It uses those funds to grant loans to borrowers, and as those borrowers pay back their loans,
usually once a month, at the end of the month, or at the beginning of the next month, we
collect everything that was paid and pay it back to the debenture holder.
The contract for the debenture is such that the debenture holder knows what we're going
to do with the money, and he knows that if the borrowers don't pay, that's going to come
out of his premium.
So the company is not in any danger if the borrowers default.
It actually is in danger of investors not wanting to buy our debentures anymore, so
we have a really nice credit model to select the right borrowers.
But anyway, the thing is, this last arrow down there that says pay back debentures,
we run a report at the beginning of every month collecting everything that the borrowers
paid, contrast that with everything we ever paid to the debenture holder to make sure
that rounding errors don't leave anything behind, or also to make sure that payments
that were only registered after the last time we ran this report, regenerate payments for
things that should have gone in the previous month.
So we have this kind of relationship diagram here.
This kind of represents the models in our database.
We have a table or a model for the debenture holder, one for the debentures it owns, so
each debenture holder has one or more debentures.
The arrows here indicate which record points to the ID of each other record.
And then to the right side of this diagram you have the debenture series, which is a
collection of debentures that were sold to a number of debenture holders.
And the loans that go out, they pay money into this account, and each payment becomes
an operation into this account.
So a debenture is associated also with the debenture series, which points to the account,
and every month we do a series payout.
We collect everything that was paid, everything that was left behind that should have been
paid before, contrast with everything that was paid, and calculate the records that represent
the debenture holder.
For Texas purposes sometimes we don't actually distribute everything immediately to the debenture
holder.
We sometimes create a reserve of the principal amount so that we can pay all the principal
first, and then we reserve some of the principal, because the principal is not taxed, only the
premium is taxed.
So we try to pay all the principal first and pay the premium later so that the debenture
holder doesn't pay as much tax.
So we have this payout reserve that we do at the end of the price of each debenture,
and after that we pay only premiums and then we pay the reserve at the end.
So how does that look in code?
Well we have a base class for all the model classes, which is that class called base.
It inherits, because of the SQL alchemy declarative base called over there, from this ORM class
which has a property that makes it convenient for us to query models in a property called
querying the model itself.
So for example, one model is this debenture, which has a relationship with the debenture
holder, like I showed before.
So we also model an attribute for the relationship.
So when I access this attribute in an instance of debenture, I'm looking at an integer.
When I access this attribute, what SQL alchemy does is it goes into the database, does a
query and pulls a record for the debenture holder and wraps it up in an instance of
the debenture holder class.
And I then get access to that instance through the holder attribute in the debenture instance.
Same thing for series ID and the series relationship.
One important part here is this back ref here.
This call describes that the debenture holder class will in its turn have a debentures attribute
which represents all the debentures associated with that debenture holder.
And this lazy equals dynamic here means that what this attribute will be on the ORM class
is a query, just like model.query is.
The debenture holder.debentures is a query which allows me to then apply filters and
order by and things like that.
And it will only go into the database to fetch records when I iterate over it.
If I just access the debentures attribute in the debenture holder, I get a magical query
object.
It doesn't go into the database immediately.
So the thing is when this report was first running, it had to run in two parts.
One it was going over a bunch of calculations and caching them in a MongoDB somewhere and
then running the proper distribution using these values that were cached.
Why was it doing that?
Why did it need to do this thing?
And this caching run, it took four hours.
And then we had like five debenture series already emitted and each one of those was
taking an additional four hours.
So we had like 24 hours of reports to run this thing that run at the beginning of every
month.
And people just let it there for a while because, well, you know, it just runs once a month.
What's the problem with letting it run for a whole day?
Well the problem is if at the end of the reports the numbers are wrong and we need to debug
why they are wrong, you're facing another 24 hours of running it all over again.
So what we did, what I did, let me explain this function.
This function here that I wrote in the code.
So this function called SQL.
What is it doing?
It's using the sum SQL function from SQL alchemy over a column that I passed as parameter.
If there is a filter, it applies a filter on that and I will show the SQL of that what
it looks like later.
And it wraps that into a coalesce.
Why?
Because sum, if you are summing over an empty set of records, instead of getting zero, you
get a null.
And for our calculations we wanted a zero.
So you coalesce a null into a decimal zero when there is nothing to sum over.
And if a label is also passed, I, this function adds a label to this column and returns a
column.
This is just a way of assembling a piece of a query in SQL alchemy.
And it's used in this other function here, get column sum for query, by taking a query
just like the one from model.query or the one from a relationship and a definition of
a column.
And this definition of a column is exactly the class attribute that defines a column
in the model.
So for example, the bencher.sale price.
And it drops the order of the original query because if we are going to aggregate we don't
need to worry about the order and replaces everything that was in the query with a single
column which is the coalesced sum of the column that I'm interested in.
What uses this?
I'm going to show you it in a bit.
So you see here I imported those functions that I declared.
And this is the diff of the changes that I made, of some of the changes that I made.
And you can see here that what the code was doing before was looping in Python the code
for each payback operation between a start and an ending period and summing a few attributes
of it.
Then it was calculating another sum over the principle of operations also within the same
period.
But you see this is payback operations while this is, yeah, it's payback operations as
well.
It's doing two queries into the database, fetching a huge amount of records, fetching
all the columns of those records just to get a few sums again and again.
And then there's earnings operations which is another method but which also uses the
same period start and period end and so on and so on.
And I replaced that with a method called calculate operation summary.
I named it like that because just like bestiary is a collection of beasts, a summary is a
collection of sums, so I thought it appropriate that since I had a bunch of sums I would have
a method called calculate operation summary.
This operation summary is a record with attributes, with names that match the variables that I
had before.
So how did I create this record, this one single record that has all these things, all
these sums already calculated?
Ignore this part for a little bit.
So I refactored out the method that queried the operations in a period because you saw
that various methods there were accepting start and end period and all they were doing
were filtering self.operations between start and end date, all of them individually.
So I refactored that out into a method that calculates the query with these filters.
When you run this method you're still not running the SQL, it's just assembling a query
that has these filters.
And I then refactored out all the rest of the filters into attributes of a nested class
called operation filters.
And finally I rewrote the original methods that were using those filters to use the filters
that I factored out.
But I also implemented the calculate operation summary which gets the query for the operations
in the period, order by none because I'm just going to aggregate them all, and I replace
the columns that it was going to return.
Actually it was not going to return the columns, it was returning instances of the class operation.
And I asked Keolo Okumi to throw that away and instead return me the operations summary
columns.
You see here I used the Python operator for exploding a tuple into parameters, the star
here in the beginning of the method.
And what does this self get operation summary columns do?
It calls col-s-sum on operation value for several filters.
And these filters they are being applied not in a where clause of an SQL but in a filter
clause of a column.
And in the end because of this I only need to return one result set.
Each of those columns is looking at a set of operations, selecting some of them that
they are interested in and summing only the value of those records it is interested in.
But these records are a subset of a bigger set of records which I'm only fetching once
in the database and asking the database to aggregate it all for me in a single step.
So in the end I get a single record and you can see here that I pass labels here, g-r-u-f-e,
earnings, earnings taxes and those labels they match with the attribute names of the
record up here. So let's see how that looks in the code.
Where is my... Okay.
Is that readable back there? Okay. Now. One more? It's okay? Okay.
So here is the same piece of code that I showed in the function down there. And one
nice thing about SQL alchemy queries is that if you print them without iterating over them,
it prints the... Okay. So not that. It prints the SQL query for you. So it's all jumbled
up, but I have a SQL query for you. So I'm going to print the SQL query for you. So I'm
going to print the SQL query for you. So I'm going to print the SQL query for you. So I'm
going to print the SQL query for you. So it's all jumbled up, but I have the same thing
nicely formatted somewhere here. And that's unreadable. So not that. Actually those are
the slides. So you see, remember I called the coalesce. So I'm going to call it coalesce.
On top of sum, on top of the principle of an operation. Other... One of those functions
was calling operation.value. And operation.value is a hybrid property in the declared in SQL
alchemy that expands to a sum of other properties. So it's usable not only as a column, but also
as a query, just because I declared it as a hybrid property. So the ORM is really powerful.
We don't want to throw the ORM away, but we need to know how to use it to write well-performed
SQL queries. So what it does here, applying filters to the columns, it filters at the
column level instead of at the where level. At the where level I have other criteria like
selecting a specific dimension series that those operations belong to. And the timestamps
here are filtering for the range of operations that I wanted to. But I got all those columns
to do themselves their own filters so that I don't need to do many queries with different
where clauses into the database. And I did that without actually having to write SQL
on the Python side. I used the column definitions from the models themselves to assemble the
query for me. And this was just one of the changes, and there were many other changes
like this that caused a reduction from the four hours of the cache plus four hours for
each of the adventure series to 15 minutes for a single, for the run of a single adventure
series. Actually, it went from, first it went from four hours caching plus four hours of
running reports to just four hours running the reports because most of the time in the
second part was inserting payments. And they were inserting one by one the records in the
payments. And they had already optimized that to write raw SQL inserts to make it fast.
But they were still inserting one by one the records. So instead of doing that, on a second
phase of optimizations, I had, let me see if it's here. No. So on a second set of optimizations,
I asked SQL Alchemy itself to calculate the insert for me. Let me see if I can locate
the code here quickly because I had a little panic about 10, 30 minutes before the presentation
because my slides stopped working. And it's like, it got stuck in the first slide and
it wouldn't advance and I didn't know what was happening. But I managed to fix it in
time. So anyway, before I go to that, let me show another optimization. This one brought
a page that was rendering in a few, in one and something minutes to milliseconds, which
was not this one. All right. I just got it because I might have lost theAlexander. I
So, we had this, one nice thing about Pyramid is that it allows you to encapsulate the logic
for authentication and the lookup of the request object they're interested in the route itself.
Because most of the times when you write a route in a web framework, you take the parameters
and then you go look up the object and then you check if the user that is authenticated
is allowed to see the object.
And Pyramid allows you to delegate this part into separate routines that are called automatically
for your view so that when you get to your view, your request object has a context object
which is the object you're interested in and you only get there if the user is actually
allowed to see that.
But sometimes you also want to do permission checks manually.
Actually this admin, the banchor holder factory is exactly the code that's checking the permissions
before the view runs.
And what it was doing before, it was taking the user, taking the admin object which is
this property, it went to look up the admin role in the database and checking if it had
permission to do something or some other thing.
And by itself this was already doing many queries which were optimized away when I pulled
up the has permission method.
But the biggest benefit actually came from telling SQL Alchemy to, when it was time to
get the user to actually load with it all the profiles and from the profiles load all
the permissions.
Because of this, the SQL Alchemy would then issue not just a query for the user but a
query for all those objects where they were joined to the user and joined to the roles
so that they were already loaded by the time the piece of code that did the authentication
was going to do these checks here.
So instead of going into the database to check if a user had a certain permission, these
permissions were already loaded directly in memory.
So I got about 10 minutes.
I'm going to try to locate the code that calculates the inserts to show it to you.
In five minutes I will open for questions.
Oh, okay.
Okay.
So this was the final pass of optimizations that I did.
And you can see here that I ripped off what was essentially raw SQL being written to insert
into the database.
And it was written to insert one by one each record that was needed.
And instead I asked SQL Alchemy to generate the inserts for me because when you look at
the model declaration, the model declaration it has a Dunder table attribute which maps
to the DSL for writing SQLs that an SQL Alchemy has and then you can ask it to do an insert
to return to you the query that does the insert.
So here we have it.
A payout insert is a debenture payout dot Dunder table dot insert.
And the insert method has a from select which does an insert from select and you pass it
the list of columns that you're inserting from the query, the names of the columns,
and you pass the actual columns or constant values or whatever you need to insert into
the database.
So instead of looping on Python side inserting a lot of objects, I asked Postgres to loop
on his own side over the objects that he knew existed and insert values calculated according
to what I needed so that I didn't have to insert on my end each one of the objects.
So that brought down the whole report from four hours down to 15 minutes.
The other optimization I showed before about authentication, there were some pages that
were taking over a minute to render and they were rendering down to a few milliseconds.
So going back to our message, in order to write good performing ORM code, no matter
how comfortable the ORM code is, you need to understand SQL even if you're not going
to write it by hand.
Even if you're just using the DSL from SQL Alchemy, it's already a really good way to
refactor the common parts of generating SQL, but you need to understand what the database
is doing when you access an attribute or when you do an insert or when you access the attribute
of an attribute of an attribute and you should know how to do things in a well-performant
way in SQL so that you can map that to idiomatic SQL Alchemy.
So I recommend highly that you read the select documentation for your database and try to
understand which part of it it does and look up in Stack Exchange what does it mean, how
group by interacts with aggregation functions to reduce the number of rows that you get
back and why you need to have a column either in the aggregate or in the group by clause.
Understand the window functions of SQL which is another way of calculating aggregates without
reducing dimensionality, read about sub-queries with statements that allow you to calculate
a part of SQL, then calculate another part based on that calculation all going in a single
round trip to SQL and then study SQL Alchemy and understand the underlying queries that
SQL Alchemy is generating when you do attribute accesses. Try to push as much work as possible
into the DB but not too much. Sometimes you're going to be generating a very complex query
and it goes only one time to the DB and brings a bunch of information but then you don't
need all that information. Be careful of the amount of information you need and if for
some reason you're bound to a loop on the Python side because you need to do some Python
calculations, doing a very complex SQL query before entering the loop is kind of useless
so you might have to do a few round trips to the database but be mindful of the queries
that you're generating and try to reduce the amount of queries that you're doing and the
amount of volume of data you're trafficking. And that's it. Thank you very much for your attention.
Thank you, Leo. If anyone has questions, they can come to this microphone and ask them. I
request that you keep the questions objective and if you have more detailed questions or
want to, or comments, please see Leo outside in the interest of time. Thank you.
Thanks for the talk. I guess when we do optimizations nothing comes for free so you bought yourself
a lot of speed ups. What do you see as the costs of the optimization? What did it cost
you? And I guess if you have time there's a second question which is did you ever consider
giving up on the SQL Alchemy DSL and just writing SQL as strings? Thank you.
I did but most of what I needed to do as I showed you were trivial changes from summing
on the Python side to summing on the DB side so there weren't that many things that were
I was lucky that I knew about the filter where clause for columns that allowed me to do a
single round trip to the database and when I showed that to my colleagues they kept asking
me how do you know about this? It was pure luck. I was curious. I was reading the SQL
long before doing this optimization I was reading the select manual from Postgres and
I was curious why does it have a filter where here? And then oh that's what it's for and
things like that. Unfortunately there isn't much documentation either on Postgres or SQL
Alchemy on why certain things exist. They are there. If you're looking for them it's
easy to find how to do something but if you're not you have no idea what to do so my tip
is always study what the select can do, what insert can do, what update can do, go into
little corners, what does window mean here, what does over mean here, what does filter
where mean here and try to find examples of these things working so that you have baggage
to optimize these things later. And then I had not much difficulty in convincing SQL
Alchemy to do those things in a Python idiomatic way but the point is the Python idiomatic
way without thinking about SQL is going to lead you to generate bad SQL but if you are
aware of it it's easy with SQL Alchemy to generate good performance SQL from idiomatic
Python accesses.
Do you have a favorite way to review queries when they come out? I saw the text blob up
there and I've had a similar problem where it's like oh great it gave me this query and
now I need to format it in such a way I can actually read it. Do you have a tool or a
script you run for that?
There's a Python library called SQL format that you can run it through. There is a Perl
script called PG format that does that as well. The query that I showed was formatted
with PG format actually. Talk to me later and I'll show you the URLs for those.
Excellent. I had one more question that filter on column. I found that interesting too. How
do you do that in SQL Alchemy? What's the call to that?
How to do filter where?
Filter on the column as opposed to on the query?
You just do a column. If the column is an aggregation like a sum or something like that
it will have a filter attribute. You do sum of my column or average of column or count
of column, func.count, func.sum, close parenthesis, dot filter and then you pass the same things
you would pass into a filter clause of the SQL.
Excellent. Thank you.
Hi. Great talk. I have a question about where you decided to do your optimizations. How
did you identify that you needed to optimize that particular query or that particular function?
Did you do that through manual code review? Did you use some sort of profiling library
in Python or did you review the SQL queries running on the actual database and then traced
it up that way?
Yeah, actually there's something that I realized now that is missing from my talk. I should
have emphasized how important logging is. So if you configure the logging level of SQL
Alchemy to info, it will show all the queries. And then if you're running a report and you're
getting spewed on by gobs and gobs of queries, you know there's something there that should
be optimized.
I also use, well if you're using some service like New Relic, you usually nail down, for
example, in the case of the authentication there, it will show, oh this function here
that's doing this query is being called a lot. But also there's a WSGI filter called
slow log that dumps tracebacks of your request if you're using a web framework that's written
on top of WSGI. You can use slow log and point it to a file and every request that takes
more than say two seconds, it starts dumping every second the traceback of the thread.
So if you see that you're hitting SQL a bunch of times, you say, oh either this query is
very slow or this query is being called a lot. So you know how to optimize it just above that.
But that's mostly it. Of course nowadays I see a sum over an instance of a model. I ask my
people on my team to rewrite that. So it's like please don't sum on the Python side.
If we don't have any questions. Thank you so much Leo.
Thank you.