Hello, Python Insta.
Now we are ready for our next session,
getting to 3 million lines of type and audited Python.
And the presenter for the session is Michael Sullivan.
Michael is, as he says, a recovering academia.
Please welcome Michael.
Hi, everybody.
I'm Michael Sullivan.
I'm going to be talking, like she said,
about getting to 3 million lines of type and audited Python.
I'm here from Dropbox, where we're a very big user
of both Python and type annotations.
So sort of the way this is going to look
is I'm going to just give a lightning-fast overview
of Python typing and how MyPy fits into that.
Then I'm going to talk about how Dropbox
got much of our code base in Python.
So I'm going to start with a quick overview
of how Python is going to look.
How Dropbox got much of our code base annotated.
And then I'm going to talk about what we did
to keep up with our success and make sure
that performance stayed acceptable,
to make sure that the performance is also lightning-fast.
So, okay, that overview of MyPy.
So what MyPy is is an optional static type checker for Python
that allows you to write type annotations in your Python code
and have a tool, before you run it, check it
to make sure that those types make sense,
and it helps you prevent a lot of bugs,
and in a lot of cases makes it easier
to reason about your code.
So here's sort of the basic example of typing in Python
straight from the MyPy website,
which defines a function that computes
the first n Fibonacci numbers.
And so it takes in an integer for how many to compute,
and then returns an iterator of ints back.
You know, it yields all the numbers and gives integers.
The sort of style of typing that Python uses
was defined in a Python PEP called 484.
So if you hear that mentioned,
that's sort of the definition of Python typing.
Now, this example here is using sort of syntactic type annotations,
which were added in Python 3,
but like a lot of people,
Dropbox hasn't gotten rid of all of our Python 2 yet,
or honestly haven't gotten that close.
So MyPy needs to be able to support Python 2 as well,
and it does that through this workable,
but not beautiful technique of type comments,
where you write sort of a comment at the top of your function
saying what the type of the function is,
and the type checker will be able to figure it out from that.
It's not beautiful, but it works.
So that's what we do.
So what's an example of things that the type checker can do for you?
Here's a pretty simple one.
We define some function called foo,
and say that it takes a parameter that's a string.
Then we try to call a method on it called eggs,
but strings obviously don't have an eggs method,
so the type checker will complain at us.
It'll say, you know, stir does not have attribute eggs.
Or let's say we try calling that function with none.
We will then say, okay, but this function wants a stir,
and we're passing it none.
That doesn't work.
This is nice because it gives sort of a level of checking
that a lot of sort of more traditional statically typed languages don't have.
For example, in Java, basically any object you could pass a null in instead,
and something breaks at runtime,
but the sort of Python equivalent of that none will catch.
Importantly, all of this is done statically beforehand
without ever running the code.
MyPy does all these analyses.
Importantly for the sort of MyPy type checking process,
you don't need to type everything all at once.
It's very important that you be able to mix typed and untyped code,
which allows you to gradually add type annotations to your code base.
If you had to do it all at once, that would be deeply intractable,
because we have five million lines of Python or something.
We can't add types to it all at once.
That would be sort of one, impossible to do,
and two, sort of too big of a change to land all at once,
even if you sort of could do it.
So here we've got functions foo and bar,
and foo has a type and bar doesn't,
and they work together just fine.
So that's sort of the basics of type annotation.
Now I'm going to talk about what we did at Dropbox
to sort of advance this, to get it into our code base.
And so the first question about how to annotate legacy code bases is,
why even bother?
That sounds like a lot of work,
and it's work that we're doing maybe instead of writing new code.
Why not just annotate new code
and leave the old code that works unannotated?
And the main reason for that is that interactions
with untyped code can't be type checked.
If you're working with code that doesn't have type annotations,
MyPy just has to assume that it can be anything.
You sort of can't make any assumptions about it,
because you don't know what it is or what it does,
which means that any new code you write,
if it's interacting with old code that doesn't have type annotations,
you lose a lot of the benefits of typing.
The more of a code base has type annotations,
the more benefit the typing gives.
It's sort of a nonlinear payoff.
Like once you get a ton of your code base typed,
then it's really good,
whereas if you only have some of it typed,
it's just kind of good.
In MyPy itself, which is written all in Python
and type annotated Python,
we have basically 100% type coverage.
Every function in MyPy has a type annotation,
and this allows us to rely on type checking
to support a lot of aggressive operations in the code base.
We can do major refactors, renaming things,
changing the types of things, like large changes,
and when we do it, we expect that the type checker
will tell us most of the places you need to change.
If you add an argument to a function,
before we even run tests, the type checker can say,
like, okay, here are all the call sites you need to update.
So then what do we do to get this done?
How do we get old code annotated?
And to quote Mike Solomon,
a senior principal engineer at Dropbox,
when we asked him for some advice,
he said, show value, reduce friction,
encourage the general virtuous cycle,
and when all else fails, move them out in yourself.
Well, okay, so what are some of the ways we did that?
One of the first things, one of the core things
we've done a lot of is trying to talk to our users
to make sure what they want out of MyPy typing
and what's causing them trouble.
So we do about twice a year a regular MyPy survey
where we ask a lot of questions of our users
about, you know, how much do you like MyPy?
Would you recommend MyPy to a friend?
What are your biggest complaints about MyPy?
And sort of gratifyingly,
the biggest complaint that we get these days
is that not enough code is type annotated.
People want more MyPy, which is great.
We'd love to give them that.
And then something we got a lot last year
but stopped getting this year is performance.
We'd like MyPy to be faster so we can use it more
and have it be less invasive in our workflows.
So as part of trying to get more typing,
we've had a lot of meetings with teams
where we sort of try to figure out
what's keeping them from typing their code
and push them to, you know, get things working.
So one common thing we've heard with teams is like,
oh, well, you know, we'd love to use MyPy types,
but we don't understand how.
We've got some complicated library
that has some sort of typing behavior
that, like, we don't know how to express with MyPy.
There's just not a good way.
And, well, MyPy has a plugin API.
We can help people build plugins to make their stuff work.
We've built a plugin for SQL alchemy
and adders and data classes that are all public,
and then a couple for internal Dropbox libraries, too.
You know, even old code can sort of be worked into the model
with our plugin system,
even code that doesn't sort of naturally fit a type system.
Another thing we get told a lot is we're asking teams like,
hey, maybe you should annotate your code,
and they tell us, well, you know,
we'd like to annotate our code. We like types.
But the thing is, you know,
we have, like, our quarterly goals, our OKRs or whatever,
and typing code isn't on them,
and it's not clear that we can put,
get more of our code annotated,
because none of the teams using our libraries
have been asking us for it.
Well, we know that a lot of teams want this,
so, you know, we can sort of make sure
that their users know who to bother about it.
Like, if Web Platform doesn't have type annotations,
we can make sure that all of their consumers know,
like, hey, look, ask them for them.
They might be able to do it.
As part of figuring out what's worth annotating,
one of the big things we've sort of needed to figure out
how to tackle is that not all annotations are equal.
Not everything has the sort of same value to annotate.
If something is called 1,000 times,
it's more important to annotate than something
that's only used in one or two places,
because if it's only used in one or two places,
the sort of impact of not having type information
is very small, because there just
isn't that much downstream of it.
But if something is used 1,000 times,
then every single place that calls it,
even if all of those have type annotations,
they aren't getting any information.
They don't know what it is.
Whenever they operate on it,
we can't find any mistakes there.
So a missing annotation
reduces how useful type checking is
in all the code that uses it.
And so anything with lots of uses
is a big, valuable target for getting annotated.
But there's sort of a dark corollary to that,
which is that the most important functions
to get type checked
are often the hardest to type check.
Not because they're sort of anything fundamentally hard
about giving them a type,
but because if they have lots of uses,
then it's much more likely that they're going to be
then it's much more likely that lots of those uses
will have errors.
If something only has one or two places that call it,
and 20% of the call sites are wrong,
that's 0.2 call sites on average you need to fix.
That's not bad. But if it's got 1,000,
and now you've got to fix 200 bugs,
you'll very quickly decide,
like, oh, maybe it's not worth fixing this,
because it's going to be super tedious,
even though it would help a lot.
And so that's something we actually
still struggle to find a good trade-off for,
because it's hard,
but something worth tackling.
As part of the sort of getting teams to do the work for us
and to sort of encourage the cycle of type checking,
we send out weekly email reports to about 50 teams at Dropbox,
sort of giving them information about the state of type annotations
in their code bases based on sort of our notion of ownership.
So teams get emailed saying,
hey, you know, like, 40% of your code is typed.
Maybe you should try to type more of it.
Here's, you know, like, what you've gotten typed recently.
Here are the good things, here are the bad things,
and here are some functions that we think
are very important for you to type,
the ones that have lots of view sites that are typed,
like we were talking about before.
Now, unfortunately, it's sort of hard for us to tell,
like, how much these emails help,
because it's hard to track sort of a direct correlation
between any changes, and, you know,
the emails we're sending out.
So we don't, it's hard to, you know,
get an exact metric on that, but as a bit of signal,
shortly after we started sending out these emails,
we got contacted by a bunch of teams who were like,
hey, these emails are great,
and we'd really like to use this reporting information
to sort of directly decide how to change our code.
And so could you give us sort of a self-serve way to do it?
And so we built that, and it's become, I think,
popular at least in a few teams.
We also had sort of a very gratifying bug
discovered in this reporting,
where the first team at Dropbox
to reach 100% coverage on their code
sent us a sort of very satisfying email saying,
like, hey, we found a bug in your report generator
where it gives nonsense information
if you have 100% code coverage.
We're like, huh, yeah, we didn't think anyone
was gonna get there for a while.
We never tested that.
And the sort of more...
I've been talking a lot about sort of the social pressures
we do to try to get annotation done.
Now I want to talk about some more
of the technical measures we do.
And this is here sort of at the intersection
of, you know, technical measures that we're doing
to sort of apply the social pressure to get things working.
So one thing we have is we have a linter that complains
whenever you add a function that doesn't have an annotation.
And we recently sort of turned up
how annoying that linter is.
At Dropbox, we have different linter, you know,
complaining levels, and previously it was a notice,
and we've now moved it up to a warning.
And whenever a linter gives a warning, you have to...
In our system, you have to type in an excuse
for why you're ignoring it.
And so it's not hard to ignore, but it takes, you know,
just like an extra five seconds
and one more step in the process.
And so you do it, and you're like, oh, okay,
maybe I'll just fix it.
It'll take a little longer than, like, writing out a good excuse,
but not that much longer, maybe.
And as part of that sort of...
We're trying to gradually ratchet up
the default level of enforcement
by when we want to introduce some new check we do,
we'll make it the default,
and then sort of automatically opt out code that doesn't check.
So pretty soon we're going to be making...
You must annotate your code be the default,
and anything that doesn't, you know, will be able to opt out,
but setting the right defaults is a big part of this.
Now, sort of moving into more explicitly technical measures,
things that, you know, are just a technical device
for getting code typed,
sort of one kind of clear observation is, you know,
these types should match Python runtime types.
Like, if something's an int,
you know, that's a Python thing. At runtime it's an int.
And Python has pretty deep introspection facilities,
so you can at runtime check what types things are.
So you can imagine, and we did, building a library
that sort of dynamically at runtime records the types
of all the inputs and returns from a function
and sort of outputs that to a tool
that can add those annotations to the code.
So we built a tool called PyAnnotate to do this.
But honestly, it didn't help us that very much.
Like, we have not had a ton of luck with it.
This is one of our losses, maybe.
And a couple of the problems we had is the loads in test cases
are pretty unrepresentative of real types.
Like, instead of some real object being passed in,
like, probably it's a mock.
And so you sort of don't get the data you need.
And so really you need to sort of run these on, like, real loads,
like maybe live site loads,
but like some, you know, like, one out of every 100,000 requests
or something and sort of gather the data from that.
But unfortunately, our team itself sort of lacked the expertise
or the confidence to go insert sort of this invasive monitoring stuff
into, like, live Dropbox site loads.
And we had some troubles getting buy-in from the parties
that did have that expertise,
partially because we didn't want to push that hard.
But there was some nervousness about it.
So it sort of never got off the ground.
And so because we sort of never had those bulk data collections,
it couldn't really be done in batch.
It produced output that usually required tweaking,
and we had troubles getting engineers to do much uptake for it.
That said, other people have had success with this.
I know that there are some...
It's an open-source project, and we have open-source community users.
And Instagram has reported success with a different tool
that they built called MonkeyType
to dynamically monitor Python types
and generate type annotations from them.
And my understanding is that they did have...
They did set up the sort of live site type recording
that we never got around to.
So if dynamic inference of type annotations doesn't work,
maybe the other thing, right?
We've got a type checker, so we might just be able to look at the code
and sort of via program analysis figure out what can happen.
And so that actually works okay.
So as a really simple example,
here we've got a function called foo that just adds one to its argument
and some other module B that calls it.
And so we can look at the program and say, like, okay,
every place that calls foo is calling with an integer.
So I guess that probably means that the input to foo is an int.
And then once you've assumed the input to foo is an int,
you say, like, okay, x is an int and 1 is an int,
and if you add them together, that's also an int,
so the return type must be int.
And once you've computed that, you can sort of check to make sure it works
and that it doesn't produce errors and then say, like, okay,
I guess that's the type of the function.
We can write that in there.
And, you know, sometimes it's trickier because there might be different functions
getting called and you need to...
And there are, like, different options for how you can combine them.
So, you know, we'll make up a couple different possible function types,
see which works, pick the best.
But this is a reasonably productive approach.
And so we have just, in the last couple weeks,
started automatically adding statically inferred type annotations
to our code base.
It's still a process that requires somebody to sort of shepherd it through
to generate a diff and put it up and get approvals.
When I first tried this, I generated a diff that was way too big
that, you know, added, like, 3,000 annotations all over the code base,
and I put it up without thinking as hard about it as I should have,
and then I go look, and it's emailed half the engineers at Dropbox
asking for code reviews.
I was like, okay, well, this was a mistake.
Sorry about that.
One of the next steps, because we don't just want this to be a tool
for me to add type annotations, we'd like other people to be able
to leverage this too, is to build a user tool that fits into this,
maybe with some IDE integrations that'll say, like, hey,
here are, like, the best guesses we have for this function.
We haven't found anything that's perfect, but, like, here's what works well,
maybe here's what you have to tweak.
So I've talked a bunch about what we've done to get our code base annotated,
and so there's the question, like, how's this working?
Are we getting it done?
And the answer is, yeah, it's going great.
Here is a graph over time of how many lines we have annotated
in our server code base, and it's, you know,
this nice up-and-to-the-right graph, right?
We started off with nothing back in 2016, and now we've got, you know,
like, half a million lines in just that repo.
There's a catch to this, though, which is that here's our performance graph.
Here's how long we take to do a total type check of the repository,
and it is also this very clear up-and-to-the-right kind of graph.
So now I'm going to talk a bit about what we did to keep up with our success.
Just going back to that graph, because I just, like, love this graph.
I mean, I don't love it,
but I love just how, like, nicely clear of a linear relationship it is, right?
It's like, this is how much code we're checking,
and this is how long it takes to check,
and every so often you can see, like, oh, yeah, we messed up,
and it started getting nonlinear, and then we fixed it,
but it's still going up.
And so, I mean, this is obviously a problem,
and it's been a problem for this whole time,
doing things to mitigate it that aren't reflected in this graph
that I'm going to talk about a bunch.
So at its worst, MyPy was the long pole sometimes,
about 20% of the time, in our continuous integration system.
The long pole being the slowest part,
the part that, you know, when you've parallelized things,
you can do a bunch of things at once,
but there's still no way to be faster than the slowest thing.
So if MyPy takes 25 minutes to run
in order for something to get landed into our repo,
then nothing can land faster than 25 minutes,
which is real bad.
On top of that, this is obviously really painful to use
as part of interactive development.
Not only can you not, you know, reasonably use something interactively
if it takes 15 minutes, honestly, if it's at 2 minutes,
that's way too bad.
So, and on top of that, fear of making this problem worse
sort of limited how hard we could push on growth.
There was always sort of this trade-off, like, okay,
we could go sort of do a bunch of stuff
to automatically add annotations,
but if that makes MyPy take twice as slow,
maybe we need to focus on performance first,
which happened a bunch.
So I'm going to talk to them about the strategies
we've done to approach this.
And two of them are pretty straightforward,
doing incremental type checking and using caching.
And then one that's maybe a bit more off the wall,
which is we built a new compiler for Python
and for type annotated Python in particular.
So, okay, first the incremental type checking.
There's sort of a trivial idea that the easiest way
to compute faster is to compute less.
If you have less computation to do, it obviously will go faster.
So the idea is instead of checking the whole code base
whenever we run, we should only check what we have to.
So the idea then is we store type information to disk.
When we run, we store sort of a cache
of what all the different types we've seen
and what modules have what functions and all of that.
And when we run, we check just the files that have changed.
And then once we've checked the files that have changed,
we check any modules that depend on modules
that have had interface changes.
Here, when I say interface changes,
our idea of interface for this is actually kind of cute hack,
which is we generate these cache files saying,
like, okay, here is all the relevant things about a module,
all the functions in it, all the types of those.
And so the interface we check is actually just a, like,
hash of the cache file.
If the cache file we generate changes,
then we know the module's changed in an important way,
and we need to recheck anything that depends on it.
So this works pretty well.
There's an unfortunate snag,
which is that for annoying technical reasons,
if you have an import cycle,
like modules importing each other in a circle,
those need to be checked all together.
So if one module in an import cycle has a dependency change,
you have to check all of those.
And if you have, like, a nice, elegant, beautiful,
well-factored code base, this isn't a problem at all,
because you shouldn't have big import cycles,
because that's a pretty major code smell.
We have some pretty big import cycles.
Like high hundreds of modules.
And so whenever you had to hit anything
that needed to check that, it got bad.
Okay, so here was supposed to be a graph
of how incremental mode improved the typing,
but instead this slide is intentionally left blank,
because I was having troubles
finding our historical data for it.
But this helped a lot.
It ends up being a pretty substantial speed-up.
If thing like 4 or 5x for the typical case.
And when we were doing this incremental mode,
it got this sort of...
At the time, MyPy took about eight, nine minutes
to check the whole repository,
and with this incremental mode,
it would get down to one or two,
which was solidly usable in most, like most interactive cases,
just not good, but it was not as bad.
But it was not impossible.
But there are still some bad things.
So the thing about, like, doing stuff incrementally
is you still need a starting point,
something to increment.
So you need to, at some point,
generate that initial type information, that first cache,
which requires doing this full check
that takes maybe 10, 20 minutes.
And you could say, like, okay, that's fine.
Every developer runs that once when they start at the company,
and that's where you get some place to start from.
But that's bad, too, because the changes
when you switch between branches
or when you pull all of the changes
that other people have made can be pretty big.
And you don't want people to have to type check,
like, everybody else at the company's changes.
You really want them to only have to waste time
sort of checking their own code.
So there's sort of a joke that, like,
the only two systemsy ways to solve problems
is to either add a level of indirection or to add a cache.
And here the trick is to add a cache.
So we have our continuous integration systems.
Every time a commit lands in master,
it runs MyPy on it and generates sort of this cache
of all of the type information in the code base.
Then when users run MyPy,
it will download this cache information
sort of whenever they've done anything
that we think might be a big change,
like a branch switch or a rebase.
So this gives us a cache that's sort of shared
between all developers at Dropbox
that's generated with a short 10, 15-minute delay.
And this ends up being huge,
because it means that nobody ever needs to run these,
like, full type checks.
So this is great.
Unfortunately, it isn't sort of released.
Like, the infrastructure to do this isn't released,
because it's much too dependent on the minutia
of the continuous integration system
and the build system and source control.
Like, we have a homegrown continuous integration system,
and then we have sort of homegrown scripts
for running MyPy and Git.
And if you have any sort of different combination of those,
the way you'd set this up is different.
That said, it shouldn't be too hard,
and our documentation does have pretty good instructions
for how you might want to set this up.
And if anyone's done that, I'd actually be really interested
to chat with you to see how it's worked for you.
Now, this whole cache warming also,
there's a lot of sort of fun, very fiddly
performance engineering we had to do,
and what we were able to do to sort of improve it.
One of the things that was sort of an easy win
at one point where we were getting stressed out,
like, oh, man, it's taking, like, six seconds
to download the cache information.
Or, like, if you're in, you know, the Tel Aviv office,
it's taking, like, 25 seconds just to download the cache.
We were able to just switch the compression algorithm
and get a good speed up.
Another sort of dumb one was,
originally the cache was just a tarball of little JSON files,
but the Mac OS file system is very slow
at creating lots of little files,
so if you switch to it just being one file,
then it gets a whole lot faster again.
We've done a lot of investigation on that sort of thing,
like, how to optimize all the details of those.
Now, there's still some downsides
to this incremental type checking stuff I've talked about.
There's lots of data to load from the disk
every time you run,
because all this stuff is stored on disk in these caches,
and the module is sort of a pretty big unit of rechecking,
because modules can be big,
and there's sort of a lot of work to do with them.
You have to parse it, you have to, you know, reanalyze it,
you have to do all this type checking.
And so whenever something's dependency changes,
you need to do this full module reprocess,
and actually worse than that,
this full module reprocess of this entire cycle of modules,
which, at its worst, would be, like, 500 modules
at Dropbox, which is real bad.
Like, you'd hit that, and it suddenly just gets very slow.
So our solution to all of this is what we call
our, the MyPy daemon,
which is an incremental type checking daemon,
which is to say, like, a background process.
It runs in the background and does type checking for you.
So instead of needing to load all this stuff from disk
every time it runs,
it tries to keep a lot of this information in memory.
It stores syntax trees and the types of everything
it's encountered sort of in memory,
where you can access them quickly,
instead of having to wait to load them.
And then the way it works is, as we check the code,
we compute what the dependencies are
of every function in class that we encounter.
So here, in this example, we've got a function eggs
in module B that's calling into a function foo in module A.
So we track that B.eggs depends on A.foo.
Then, if foo changes,
so here the types changed from returning an int
to returning a stir, we know that we need to recheck B.eggs.
So we'll go recheck eggs, and we'll see that,
oh, there's an error.
We're trying to add a string and an integer.
And we can do that without needing to sort of reload
the rest of B.py.
We don't need to parse it. We don't need to check spam.
We can sort of just, because we already have it in memory,
check eggs.
So sort of the full story here is,
we compute the dependencies of every function in class.
Then, when run, we figure out just which files have changed.
We recheck those files, and we figure out
what functions and classes and type definitions
have had an important change.
And important basically means that the type has changed.
If you change something about the implementation of a method,
callers don't care, but if you change what type it returns,
it's important.
So from that, you then go and recheck everything
that sort of depends on it.
So anything that's changed, you recheck anything
that depends on that, and then sort of push that outward.
Like anything that those changed, you go recheck,
and you repeat until you hit a fixed point.
This involved some pretty exciting engineering,
because MyPy was really deeply not designed in the first place
to allow this sort of rechecking and reprocessing.
So there's some very fun, subtle code there,
where fun is maybe a euphemism.
But it works very well.
And it is like a pretty cool engineering achievement
to get it to work.
And then like with the coarse-grained checking,
we also use a remote cache so that you don't need
to ever do a full check of the code base.
Now, how well has this worked?
Well, when combined with what I'm going to talk about next,
we get on average, or sorry, 75% of the time
when our users run it, it takes less than 700 milliseconds.
This is for like a three million line code base.
When you need to start the daemon from the first time,
it usually takes 75% of the time, 50 seconds.
And really gratifyingly to us,
when we started rolling this out,
and in the first place it wasn't this fast,
it was maybe five seconds, six seconds,
down from a minute and a half,
users started using MyPy a lot more.
Like as soon as we had this five second type checking,
the amount of times people ran MyPy,
according to our telemetry, went up by like a factor of three.
So as soon as we made it cheap,
people started buying a lot more of it.
It was great to see.
There's a downside here though,
which is that it's still kind of slow
for non-interactive workloads.
It's still like full runs,
which we had to do to generate those caches,
which would still take 15 plus minutes.
And so it only checks about two or three thousand lines of code a second,
which when you're not managing to do this incremental stuff,
isn't great.
And so every so often,
we'd have to disable incremental mode
because there'd be some sort of bug.
We'd have generated a broken cache and needed to fix that.
So we'd need to temporarily turn off incremental mode.
And sort of our SLA ended up being for that,
like, okay, whenever we need to turn off this incremental mode,
it would usually take about one and a half to two hours
before the head of the developer effectiveness team
would come over to my desk and be like,
hey, Sully, when is MyPy going to stop being slow?
I was like, okay.
That was rough. We wanted to avoid that sort of thing.
So then the question is like, okay, well, why was MyPy so slow?
Why would it take, you know, 20 minutes?
And there are a lot of answers to this.
I mean, one is just it had a lot of work to do.
But the biggest answer is because it was written in Python.
And obviously everyone here, we all love Python.
But Python does not have a reputation as being a speed demon.
And that's for a bunch of different reasons.
One of them, though less of a big deal than you might think,
is just the interpreter overhead,
the cost of having to look up sort of what the next bytecode to run is
and dispatch it and sort of go through this interpreter loop.
But that's definitely part of it.
One of the biggest things is that attribute and method access
is multiple hash table lookups, at least two, sometimes more,
like lookups in a hash table, just to access an attribute on an object.
And that's rough because accessing attributes on objects is very common.
And Python has like a very well implemented hash table,
but it's still not super fast.
So why is this?
And why do we need to do all these hash table lookups and indirections
to do everything?
And the answer to that is sort of because Python doesn't have types.
And so as maybe a history lesson of sorts,
in sort of back in the 70s or 80s when languages like C were built,
they're statically typed,
but the static types in C were basically all about helping the compiler.
They weren't really there to catch bugs or provide safety.
They were just there to tell the compiler how to lay out data in memory
and what operations to generate.
It was really about helping the compiler and not about the programmer.
So as an example of that, if you have some C structure
with a tag in the data field,
the C compiler just turns that into a structure in memory that has a tag,
and then eight bytes later it has a pointer.
And then on an Intel processor at least, if you write, you know,
P arrow data and try to access that field,
that compiles into one instruction, just one MOV instruction.
And now instruction count isn't a direct proxy for performance
because modern performance is very complicated,
but an attribute access in Python takes over 200 instructions on my laptop.
And so, again, that's not a direct proxy for performance,
but it's still quite a lot slower.
And so there are lots of things that are sort of conspiring to make it slower,
but this is really one of the big ones.
So C types were designed just to help the compiler,
and the types in Python as envisioned by PEP44
were mostly not about helping the compiler.
They're basically just designed to help safety checking.
But that doesn't really need to be true.
There's nothing fundamental about that.
And in fact, PEP44 actually specifically says,
using type hints for performance optimizations is left as an exercise to the reader.
And I'm like, okay, well, I'm a reader.
We can try this.
So MyPy itself is, like I said earlier, basically 100% typed,
which means we have all this type information that we could use to try to do this.
And so the idea then is maybe we could write a new compiler for Python
that takes advantage of all this type information.
And now there's sort of this question of, like, okay, wait,
you're like a bunch of language and compilers people,
and you think that the only way to solve a problem is by writing a new compiler.
Like, should we trust you?
And well, I mean, yeah, yes, I think so.
Because just because all you have is a hammer
doesn't mean that the problem isn't a nail.
And it turns out this one was.
So this was started by Yuka, the tech lead of MyPy,
sort of as a side project, as a hack week project,
that was essentially unfinished business from his PhD thesis,
which was designing a Python-like language
that was going to sort of compile to native code,
but eventually Guido convinced him to turn it into a type checker for Python.
But so the solution here then is we've built a compiler called MyPyC.
It compiles a subset of Python with what we call strict semantics,
which means that the type annotations need to be accurate,
and we can report runtime errors when they're not.
So this ends up being basically a Python language variant,
because it doesn't run exactly the same, but it's very similar.
And it uses MyPy itself sort of as a front end to do type inference
and to generate the sort of input to the compiler.
We then compile specifically to CPython extension modules,
which are C programs or C libraries that get dynamically loaded by CPython
to provide code that interoperates with Python but is written in C.
And this is sort of the standard way to write Python libraries in C
for either performance or to talk to system libraries.
And one of the things is this sort of interoperates very cleanly
with regular Python code.
And so some people might notice, like,
hey, this isn't the first time I've heard about this sort of thing.
So what makes this different?
Or to put it more colorfully, what about all the bodies
of all the projects that have tried to do this and either failed
or maybe not had as much of an impact as you might hope?
And so Cython works pretty well, but to get really good speedups,
you sort of need to translate into their dialect and type system,
which sort of thinks more about C types than it does about Python types.
And we wanted to think in terms of Python types.
PyPy is a tracing JIT that works very well for some programs,
but the sort of program that MyPy is, it didn't fit very well.
It doesn't have any sort of tight loops.
It's sort of big, branching, very large.
And we never had that much luck with it.
Sort of more traditional JITs like Piston and Unladen Swallow
sort of chose the full language support hill to die on,
which is they wanted to be basically fully compatible with Python.
And so then you spend all of your time trying to be fully compatible with Python
and not enough of your time making it fast,
and then your employer stopped paying you to work on it.
So we're not aiming for exact compatibility,
though some of our gaps right now are kind of embarrassing
and we're working on fixing them.
But so sort of as an example of what kind of code we generate,
the big thing we do is try to provide good data representations.
So if we have this class foo that, like our C example earlier,
had a tag that's an integer and a data that's a string,
we'll turn that right into sort of a C object that's a Python object
and has sort of just laid out in the structure as C attributes,
a tag and data field.
And then sort of as a, like in the traditional compiler technique
for doing method calls, we sort of also include a virtual table
of function pointers that includes all the methods on the function.
So you can call those without doing dictionary lookups
just by indexing into that.
To avoid sort of the trap of having every integer object
be sort of allocated on the heap and require lots of operations,
we try to store integers unboxed without an allocation of a pointer
using sort of the traditional language runtime hack
of using the lower order bit of a pointer
to indicate whether it's really a pointer.
And that works pretty well.
So then the question is, how well did this work?
And sort of if you go look at this MyPy runtime graph we made,
it worked pretty well.
It was pretty slow and then it got real fast.
So this was a big success.
Here in this graph, this shows this happening in April,
we actually turned on MyPyC for most of the stuff we do
about six months ago, but not this particular report generator.
So really this crater was back in October.
So what's the future of MyPyC?
It was sort of originally built to be a pretty narrow accelerator for MyPy.
And when we were designing it, we really wanted to make sure
that building it would be justified just by the wins
that we would get from MyPy, that just the speedup we're going to get from MyPy
is worth building this.
But it doesn't really need to always be just a MyPy accelerator.
So we definitely imagined a lot of other typed Python programs
that would maybe like a 4x speedup.
So sort of the next thing on our roadmap is we'd like to try to get black
working under MyPyC, and I think that's what I'm going to have my intern do this summer.
We're also going to be working on MyPyC during sprints on Monday and Tuesday.
So if anyone is interested in hacking on code or documentation
or trying to get their own stuff to compile with a typed Python compiler,
come chat with me on Monday or Tuesday.
And MyPy is also going to be working on sort of usability error messages
documentation those same days.
So as the sort of TLDR for this talk, I've talked about how we've gotten
to checking 3 million lines of annotated Python code in a few hundred milliseconds.
Thank you.
Questions?
We actually have five minutes.
I'm sure people might want to ask something about MyPyC to Michael.
Great talk. Thank you very much.
My question is on the adoption side of things.
Have you had any luck?
So at Instagram, we occasionally, we have a lot of developers
very happy about type annotations subjectively.
Occasionally someone asks, so can you demonstrate to me using some data
that adding all of these type annotations has improved something?
And I'm wondering if we usually respond with an awkward silence.
I'm wondering if you've got anything better.
No, that's exactly what we do.
We have anecdotes.
But the thing is it's very hard to prove anything about the site outages
that didn't happen.
But every so often we have a great example of there's a site outage
that wouldn't have happened if that function had had a type annotation.
If this had been type checked, this bug would have been caught.
And so we can sort of point to those anecdotes, but we don't really have data.
And if you figure out how to do that data, let us know.
And if I do, I'll give you a call too.
Yeah, well, we have the survey, but that's just that we can prove
that our developers subjectively like it.
But we don't know how to prove that it prevents outages or something.
Thanks, Michael.
When you talked about static type inference, is that part of MyPy
or is that a separate project?
Yeah, so it's sort of a tool integrated with the MyPy daemon.
Then also in practice, when we use it, it's sort of like a bad shell script
I wrote and some daemon code.
So the code is there for other people to try,
but it's not quite a push button solution yet.
And kind of a follow-up, do you have a sense of at what percentage
of annotations something like that becomes practical or productive?
That's a good question.
I'd say just guessing, you probably want at least 30 or 40 percent
or there's just not going to be enough to start with.
Starting from an empty code base, you won't get a lot
because it won't know where to start with for most things.
Very interesting talk, thank you.
I have a related question to the type inference.
So if I understood correctly, then I would say that the type inference
is a very important part of the process.
So if I understood correctly, then you run the inference process
to then annotate the source code.
I'm kind of wondering why if you can infer statically,
then just keep that knowledge in the type checker
and you won't need the annotations in the first place.
Yeah, so one, the inference system we're doing is this big,
bulky whole program inference that's slow and sort of requires
looking at everything.
So it isn't really something that we can plug well into the type checker
because it's not like a traditional, like,
it's not the traditional type inference algorithm
that you'd use in like a functional programming language or something.
It's much more sort of let's look at all the call sites to a function
and figure out like, okay, here are the things it's calling it with,
let's just call it that and stuff like that.
So it's not sort of built in a way where it could really integrate with that
and if it was, it would probably be too slow.
So if I wanted to use MyPyC for like the typical,
your code has one hotspot, so write that module in C,
like how well does the tooling support that?
Reasonably well as long as right now the big thing is that you can't
subclass compiled classes from interpreted ones.
And so if you've got some class that you need to subclass from other code,
you're out of luck right now.
But we definitely support that. You don't need to compile everything.
In fact, there's parts of MyPyC that aren't, or of MyPy that aren't.
Given your experience with MyPyC, given a 100% type coverage code base,
how difficult do you think it would be to target something like LLVM?
You mean instead of generating C?
Yeah.
The answer is that it wouldn't be that hard, it would just be work.
Like if you told me that it was important and it needed to be done,
I could have it done in a month or something.
But we sort of don't think it is.
There's sort of nothing fundamental, it's just work.
I see, thanks.
All right.
Thank you, Michael.