Hello.
This talk is going to be getting started testing in data science, and this is Jess Ford.
Hello, everyone.
Thank you so much for coming to one of the last talks on the last day of PyCon.
My name is Jess Ford.
I'm really excited to be talking to you about getting started testing in data science.
So I'm Jess.
I am a data scientist currently working at a company called Recursion in Salt Lake City,
Utah.
We do AI-driven drug discovery, and we are hiring kind of across the board.
So if that interests you, check out our careers page at the bottom there.
My backstory is I'm originally from Alaska.
My first passion in life is for snowboarding.
So I've lived kind of all over the West Coast trying to balance my academic and career pursuits
with snowboarding as much as possible, which is how I ended up in Utah.
I did a PhD in astrophysics and a postdoc in data science after that, and that was where
I was first exposed to actual software testing.
Like a lot of data scientists I've met, I don't have like formal background training
in software best practices, and a lot of data scientists that I've met have never written
tests or have no idea how to get started.
So that was kind of my motivation for the talk today.
So the plan for my presentation, I'm going to start off kind of motivating why you would
want to test.
I'm going to introduce how to get started at a really basic level writing your first
test using PyTest, and then we're going to talk data science specifics.
So we're going to talk about workflows that are kind of unique to working in data science,
and we're going to talk about and go through some example actual bits of code, for examples
of ways and tools that are useful for testing in data science.
Okay.
So why test?
Testing gives you evidence that your code is working as expected, right?
It gives you confidence to make changes without fear of breaking anything, and it can give
other people some more trust in your code.
So that's great, but why wouldn't you want to test, right?
So a variety of reasons, but I think the main thing that people will say is that it takes
time, and that's true.
And so this is my struggle.
So as a data scientist, I'm constantly trying to balance these competing interests of getting
results to my stakeholders as quickly as possible, but also obviously trying to be as confident
as possible that I have the right answer when I do that.
So trying to balance these interests in the optimal way, I think testing gives you a tool
to be able to do that.
So in this talk, I'm not going to insist that you should always write tests, but I'm going
to talk about different scenarios that I find myself in as a data scientist and how I try
to be confident that my results are correct.
I'm going to show you how to get started and some tools for data science testing.
The disclaimer here is that I'm not a testing expert or a software engineer, and there's
a lot of things I don't know.
And data science itself kind of covers a laughably huge range of actual day-to-day job duties,
as I'm sure many of you know.
So formal testing is more important in some of those than it is in others, and we'll talk
about that.
Okay.
So we care about our code getting the right answer.
So how do we know when our code is correct?
There's kind of three levels of this.
You can do some manual sanity checks.
So you run your function, and in your head, you kind of know what you expect, and you
look at the answer.
And in your head, you decide this looks right.
The next level up is defensive programming.
So this is adding checks within your code itself to make sure that things are working
as you expect.
And then there's the third level of having a standalone test suite that can be run automatically.
So let's talk about defensive programming first, because this gives us the building
blocks that we're going to be creating tests with.
So defensive programming is just adding assertions within your code.
So as a kind of silly example, I've got this function hello to all.
It takes in a list of names, and it prints hello to those people.
But before it does that, it actually checks that there are things in that list, and if
not, it's going to raise an error.
So I can print hello to some of my friends, but if I give this function an empty list,
it's going to raise an assertion error.
So these assertions are the building blocks of what we're going to test with.
So I do want to emphasize this before we jump into actual testing, that these are your best
friend as a data scientist.
This is your middle ground.
If you don't have time to go and write the tests that you maybe know you should, this
is your middle ground of checking that things are working.
So check that you don't have duplicates in your data set.
Check for the types of your data columns, things like that.
So this is your takeaway if you don't go write tests, is to at least start adding assertions
all over the place.
Okay.
So let's go to our actual first test example.
So I'm going to start off with a really, really simple toy example, and we will get more advanced
later, I promise.
So here's a simple function backwards all caps.
It takes in a text string, and it just reverses that string and uppercases it.
Okay.
I can write a test for this, or sorry, just to manually check things here.
I'm going to run this on Python.
I get back no teep.
And I can write a test for this function by just defining a function that starts with
test, and then I just add some assertion lines in here, and I just check that running my
function on some known input gives me some known output.
And this is really, really simple.
This is how easy it is to get started writing tests with PyTest.
PyTest is a great framework.
It has much less boilerplate than things like unit test, and it takes care of a lot of things
for you.
There's a lot of stuff you don't have to worry about and a lot of really powerful built-in
features, and we're not going to cover very much of that today, but you can pip install
it and get started.
So I'm going to go through a little demo just to kind of show you what it looks like when
you have like how you actually run your tests and what it looks like when they pass and
they fail.
So let's say that this example I was just showing you is in a file called demo TDD.py,
and I could run these tests on the command line by just saying PyTest, name of the file.
So if I do that, if you can read this up here, it tells me that the test session started,
it prints some information about my platform and the versions, and it says it collected
one item, which is my one test, and then it shows me the name of the file, and there's
this little green dot right here that I'm not sure if you can see, but there is a green
dot, and this symbolizes my passing test.
I could also run the same command with a verbose flag, and this will tell me the name of the
actual test and print passed in bright green letters, and if I had a failing test, this
verbose flag would give me a lot of useful information to figure out what went wrong.
Okay, so let's say that we want to add a new feature to our test function, and we want
to, let's say that we want any white space in text to be actually removed.
So we're going to do this in test-driven development style, so instead of going and adding this
feature right away, we're first going to add a test for this.
We're going to run our test to make sure it fails, then we're going to add our feature
and make sure that our tests pass.
Okay, so I have added a function, testLettersOnly, and I'm testing that giving it Salt Lake City
should return that reverse of that with no spaces.
If I run my test, I'm going to get one green dot for my passing test that I had previously,
and then I get a failure.
So testLettersOnly has failed, and it shows me that I tried to assert that the output
of my function here with spaces was equal to the thing that I hard-coded with no spaces,
and that's not true, so I have a failure.
Okay, so we're going to go in and add this feature now.
So I'm just using the dot replace string method to replace white space with empty string,
and if I run my test again now, I get two passing tests.
Okay, so that's fine, that's how easy it is to write tests and practice this test-driven
development workflow, but you're probably thinking, okay, so these examples were pretty
dumb, right?
So a couple of things here.
These examples don't really seem very applicable to data science work, right?
We do not often, you know, doing simple string manipulation, and this test-driven development
workflow, which I really love and I think is helpful for writing good code, it's not
always a really reasonable way to be working in data science.
We are often kind of exploring things and seeing what new directions you might take,
and it's not, you know, it's not like these well-defined problems that are easy to do
this, like, software best practice with.
Okay, so we're going to talk about each of those pieces.
So data science domain problems, instead of working with a lot of those, like, native
Python data types, we often have pandas data frames, numpy arrays as the inputs and outputs
of our functions.
We might be reading and writing to databases quite a bit, and then, of course, we're generating
these machine learning or probabilistic models that don't necessarily have deterministic
outcomes.
So we might want to think about what are the acceptable tolerances on our results or testing
for properties of these things instead of exact values.
And workflows, right?
So I can kind of break down the types of work I do into roughly three buckets.
There's the one-off analysis that I put in quotes because, you know, you think you're
doing something once and you end up having to come back to it.
And there's the exploratory phase where I spend a ton of my time, you know, maybe you
have a new data set and you need to see what's in it, see what's available, or you're exploring
a new type of model you might apply to some problem.
And then finally, there's the well-defined problem, the elusive thing that comes up occasionally
but is probably a smaller part of our actual workflow.
Okay, so for one-off analysis, I don't write tests.
This is probably something that I'm just doing in a Jupyter notebook and I try to focus on
clear documentation.
Having good documentation is going to save me work in the long run if I do have to come
back to this.
And that's going to be, I think, more effective than writing tests for something that I don't
know I'm going to need again.
If I do come back to this, then I'll consider maybe breaking this out of the notebook, maybe
writing some tests, but that's for down the road.
Exploratory work.
It's definitely impossible to test when you are exploring and going in all different directions,
right?
But the challenge here is I spend a ton of my actual time in this phase of work and I
think nearly every time there's some code that I write while I'm doing this that ends
up being useful down the road.
And so this is this challenge of, as I continue writing more and more functions or bits of
code that are useful in this exploration, I have to decide, you know, when do I think
parts of this are becoming useful enough that I might want to consider writing tests for
them?
So this is challenging.
And finally, the well-defined problem.
This doesn't come up a lot, but when it does, I try to practice test-driven development
here.
This is when I can actually have a chance to write tests while I'm developing my software
and usually end up with some nicer designed code.
And I'm going to add on a fourth bucket here.
As it pertains to testing, there's this issue of working with legacy code.
So this could be code you inherited from somebody else at work or it could be stuff that you
developed yourself while you were in this exploratory mode of your project.
And when I'm in this kind of scenario, you know, you don't want to get overwhelmed thinking
about writing tests for everything that's there, but I try to think about when I modify
that code, adding tests at that time.
And this is inspired by a really good talk from last year that I would encourage you
to look up.
So PyCon 2018, this talk by Justin Crown on testing legacy code bases I thought was really,
really great.
Okay.
So let's get back into some actual code.
So examples of tests for common data science problems.
Well, we'll start off pretty simple here.
So pandas data frames.
There's some really useful things built into pandas that will help you test.
So here I've got a toy data frame of customer orders that were recorded through coming through
different marketing channels.
And some of the simple things you want to do with your data frames is you want to check
for missing values.
You can do that in a few different ways using some built in pandas methods like not null
and is null.
And you can check for duplicate data using the built in duplicated method.
Duplicated will by default check across the entire row of a data frame and you might only
care about a specific one.
So here I've got an order that was recorded twice as coming through different marketing
channels and I might want to assert that I only, that I don't have duplicates just within
the order column, for example.
So I can do that with the subset parameter.
Pandas also has a lot of useful built in tools for testing.
And the one that I use by far the most is assert frame equals.
Assert frame equal lets you compare two data frames and assert that they're equal given
a whole bunch of other qualifying things.
So the ones I use the most are check like.
So check like, if that's true, I'm saying I don't care about the rows and columns of
my data frame being in the same order.
I just care that all the content is there and that that matches up.
Check D type is whether or not you want pandas to really strictly compare the data types
to your columns.
And this is, I find this useful to set to false in some scenarios where I do a bunch
of manipulations on a data frame and I end up with two different kinds of floating points.
The numbers are the same but the data type's not technically the same.
So it can be useful sometimes to set this to false.
And then you can set the precision that you care about comparing things with.
And then finally, assert frame equals handles the nan or none comparisons as you would expect.
So in Python, nan is not equal to nan.
But in the context of comparing an entire data set, what you probably care about is
that the nans are in the same places in both.
So assert frame equals will handle that as you would probably hope.
All right.
What about working with databases?
So let's say that I have a function load data.
It takes in some SQL condition and then it actually queries the database.
So it queries my database and returns some data frame.
And then I apply some transformations to that.
So I do some one-hot encoding and then I set the index of the data frame and return it.
I could test my load data function by defining a test load data that actually runs that function,
passes in some sample condition that I've defined and then checks that the output is
matches some output data frame that I've defined.
But the problem here is that we probably don't want to be querying our database as part of
our tests.
So for a few reasons, it might take a long time to run the query.
You might have different data that exists in your table at different times.
It might not be consistent.
And if you're running your tests as part of a continuous integration, you probably don't
want that system to be hitting your database as well.
So one solution to this problem is to use PyTest mock.
This is a PyTest plugin that you can pip install and it basically lets you kind of patch or
swap out one piece of code for another.
So to show you how that might work, here I've now changed my test load data function so
that I'm pulling in this mocker object and then I call mocker.patch.
And I'm basically saying any time that you encounter this query database function, instead
of doing that, do this other thing and return my sample data input, which I've defined to
be some data frame here.
So what's going to happen now?
I'm going to call my load data function and it doesn't matter anymore whether I actually
pass it a query string because when load data runs and it gets to that query database line,
instead of running that function, it's just going to pass in that data frame.
And so then what I'm doing is I'm basically testing these additional transformations that
I was running in my function.
And you can imagine, obviously, something much more complicated that just has some SQL
query in there and you want to test everything else in your function but just not that one
piece.
Hopefully that should be tested elsewhere.
All right.
Cool.
So in this example, I kind of threw in a couple input and output data frames here but I didn't
actually in this slide include all the boilerplate code for how those data frames would be defined.
And the reason is that would take a lot of lines of code.
Hard coding input and output data frames to your function is extremely verbose.
Even just for a couple example inputs, outputs with, like, you know, really toy data frames,
few rows, few columns, that's a lot of lines of code and it takes a lot of time.
So a really useful library to handle this is called hypothesis.
And you're going to hear a lot more about this in the next talk.
But the idea for my purposes is that this is a way to automatically generate data for
I don't have to hard code things.
So hypothesis has this idea of strategies for different types of input and output data.
And so for the integer strategy, in an interactive session, you can ask hypothesis for examples
of things.
And here I'm just printing out a few different integers that hypothesis might generate if
I were to pass this to a test function.
And going back to our really simple toy example from the start of the talk, I've got my back
all caps function.
So now I can use hypothesis to generate examples to run my test on.
So here I'm using this hypothesis given decorator.
And I'm saying that given some text, according to a text strategy, I'm going to run backwards
all caps on that text generated by hypothesis.
And then I'm just testing that that output, when reversed, is the same as the uppercase
of the input.
So I'm kind of reverse engineering and doing a similar thing in a different way and testing
that that matches up.
And so if I run this now, to run a test using hypothesis, you don't have to change anything.
So you're still just running PyTest, name of your file for running on a specific file.
And here I'm including this extra hypothesis show statistics option here.
And that's going to show me that hypothesis ran 100 different passing examples.
So one line of code here, it ran hundreds of different input text strings.
And they all passed.
It spent about 75% of its time actually generating the data.
And it stopped because it got to the settings max example was 100.
So this is fully configurable.
You could run thousands of examples or fewer examples if it takes a lot of time.
So what's really useful is not just being able to generate text, but being able to generate
pandas data frames and NumPy arrays.
And hypothesis has support for both of those.
And we're just going to talk about pandas.
So you can import the data frames and the column strategy.
And you can build up data frame strategies out of columns.
So here I have a data frame that has three columns, customer, price, and probability
of return.
And the customer column is made up of an integer strategy with values between 0 and 100,000.
And the values have to be unique.
Price is a floating point column.
And probability of return is floating point with values between 0 and 1.
So like a probability.
And I'm asking hypothesis here for one example of a data frame it might give me.
And here it prints out something.
And you'll notice that it's a hypothesis tries to kind of push at the corners of your
code and give you like test cases or examples of code that you might not expect and look
for edge cases in your code.
So it's trying some really large values in the price column.
And it's experimenting with what happens if you don't have unique values in a column.
And so you can configure that.
And you can say you can give bounds on the numbers and things like that.
By default, it'll give you some weird stuff.
Another example, same code here but a different example, is an empty data frame.
I could specify how many rows I wanted to have or a minimum and a max number of rows,
but I didn't.
So hypothesis will see what happens if it gives your code an empty data frame.
Okay.
So as one last example, let's say I have a data frame of customer attributes.
I have the days since they last placed an order for customers who ordered in the last
year.
And I've got the total number of orders that they've placed with me.
And this is a toy data set that's not a seasonal business.
The days since the last order is pretty flat.
A lot of customers have made one or two orders.
Very few have made a lot of orders.
And let's say, just for the sake of argument here, that I think I knew how to calculate
the probability that a customer is loyal to my company.
And let's say, for the sake of argument, that I think applying a logistic function to the
number of total orders and normalizing the days since last order and multiplying those
things will give me a probability that this customer is going to come back.
So here's my distribution of customer probability of being loyal.
And let's say I want to test this function.
And I want to make sure that this function is always going to give me back a valid probability.
So what I could do is I could define a test function that takes in a data frame.
It applies my probability loyal customer function to that data frame.
That gives me back a Panda series.
And here I'm just asserting that all the values in that are between zero and one.
So they're valid probabilities.
Then instead of actually hard coding those input and output data frames, I'm just going
to use hypothesis given to say, given any data frame that has these two columns, integer
values for days since last order, and total number of orders, which is an integer between
say zero and a million, I just want to make sure that this always gives me back probabilities.
So I'm going to run this test with hypothesis.
So I just run py test, name of the file, and I get 100 different passing examples that
pass through my test.
It took a few milliseconds to run.
It spent half its time generating data.
And it stopped at 100 examples.
So this is a pretty huge time-saving tool for me to be able to just specify the types
of data that my function should expect to see and then things that should be true about
the output.
Instead of saying exactly what the output should be, saying stuff that should be true
about it.
All right.
So to wrap up here, data scientists should not always be writing tests, but we should
always be practicing defensive programming.
So those are the assertions within your code.
Any reused or shared piece of code should probably be tested, especially if you're putting
things in production.
And of course, we're trying to strive for this balance between speed and confidence
in our results.
And testing is one tool.
Testing at the right time can help you achieve that in the long run.
Some aspects of data science code are really hard to test.
So machine learning results, probabilistic outcomes.
You want to think about testing properties of your data.
What are things that should be true of the distributions of the data you're getting out?
Is missing data allowed?
Are there certain data types you're expecting?
Testing properties can be really helpful here.
And I'm just going to throw up some of the really useful example resources that I came
across when I was researching this topic.
There's a ton of resources online for general software testing and testing with PyTest,
but this is the best stuff I could find for testing in data science that's really kind
of specific to our use cases.
So there's also a link to my slides in this Jupyter Notebook on GitHub.
So yeah, that's it.
Thank you very much for coming.
Thank you.
Yeah, first time I can take some questions.
Yeah.
Okay.
We have a few minutes.
I was faster than I practiced.
So if there's any questions, I'm happy to talk to you now or afterwards.
Thanks so much for an excellent talk.
The data frames one was particularly useful.
The question I had, do you have any recommendations or resources for testing perhaps the output
of scoring one of your models or even the training process?
Scoring the, sorry, the metrics?
So like for example, let's say you had a model and you wanted to make sure it didn't get
really funky after you retrained it or introduced some new data, something like that.
Yeah, I mean, you could use hypothesis if you had bounds on the types of output that
you expect.
You could code that up and pass in different types of input data that you think you might
see.
Yeah, I mean, you can always get funky stuff depending on how funky your input data gets.
So you have to set your own mental limits on what you think might be reasonable to get
or you want to make sure that your code handles really funky data.
That might be a case really where you want to add the assertions in the code itself to
make sure your input data isn't crazy.
Cool, thank you.
I have a question about the PyTest.moc library that you mentioned.
Are you familiar with the UnitTest.moc and is the PyTest variant set up about the same
way, have the same capabilities?
I have not really used the UnitTest framework so I can't really answer that question.
Someone in the front says they're identical.
Jesse says they're identical.
Hey, thank you for that.
It was a great talk.
I was just wondering if you had any ideas for teams wanting to leverage a shared testing
toolkit across both Python and R?
Oh, I don't have much experience with R so I can't really speak to that, I'm sorry.
Towards the end you made a comment about testing properties rather than testing specific items
of data.
One of the issues I've come across is that some of those properties are themselves inherently
statistical.
They will only be 95, you can only have a 95% confidence that they will be greater than
a mean or greater than a whatever.
Do you have any suggestions of how to manage that in testing?
You can't be guaranteed that your 95% confidence test will always pass, 5% of the time it will fail.
Yeah, that's a tricky question.
Thank you, Russell.
I mean, I guess if it's not something that you're sure should always be true then maybe
that isn't something you hard code in your test but you could...
I'm not going to recommend you run that test 100 times and make sure it passes 95% of the
time, that's not the right approach.
I don't know.
You don't know.
Thanks.
Hi.
What are your thoughts on integration testing in the data center environment?
So like testing all your workflow from processing, collecting the data, processing the data, then
training your model, testing you have a model.
So what are your thoughts on this kind of workflow?
Yeah, yeah.
So that's a good point.
I was really focused here on unit testing, testing like basic units of code and the question
is about doing integration or larger scale tests across many functions or whatever and
I don't really have any experience doing that.
I've kind of been focusing on the little building blocks.
Thank you.
Thanks.
This is in some ways a callback to the first question I guess but it's a slightly different
detail with it.
I work in machine learning as well and I will train models and there's a couple issues with
that.
I can train a model and find that it has low success, whatever metric I'm using, but that
can actually be kind of two things.
One is I made a mistake in the way I set up the features or something dramatically wrong
with hyperparameters.
The other thing is just this isn't a good choice of model and it's not going to be effective
because it was a poor choice.
But if I could somehow test that difference, that would be enormously useful and I wonder
if you have any insight in what approaches might be relevant.
Yeah, so I think when you're talking about trying to choose the right model for your
problem, I think you're not quite in the testing phase yet.
You're really exploring your data and trying to figure out what the best model is.
So I wouldn't use testing to make that choice.
Alright, thank you everyone.