Hey, everybody. Welcome today. If you're coming in, please take a seat. You can sit closer
to the front if you want. Today, Max Belanger and Damian Deville are going to talk to us
about migrating from Python 2 to 3 on Windows, Mac OS, and Linux. So please give them a round
of applause. Welcome them.
Hi, everyone. This is going from 2 to 3 on Windows, Mac OS, and Linux. My name is Max.
I'm an engineer at Dropbox.
Hello, I'm Damian. I'm also an engineer at Dropbox.
All right. So why are we here? Well, the first part of the answer to that question is we
love Python. So Dropbox has been using Python actually from the very beginning. The very
first lines of code ever written at the company by our CEO, Drew, were actually in Python
for Windows. And we use it, obviously, not just for servers, but also for our desktop
clients. We use it on Windows, Mac OS, and Linux. And that's really just from the beginning
all the way to now. We include, in fact, we include our own custom fork of Python that
we ship to our users with a whole bunch of fun patches. And really, over the years, we've
just become Python fans. We've kind of used it all. We've used async core. We've used
multiprocessing. We just love Python. So that's part one. Part two. So for almost a decade,
Dropbox has been using Python 2. This actually ended late last year. So in late 2018, we
actually made the jump. So we made the leap from Python 2 to 3. And so today, what we
want to talk about is the sort of abridged story of our four-year journey from Python
2 to Python 3. The main takeaway here is that migrating client software has some pretty
fun and unique challenges. You may have heard stories of other Python 3 migrations, but
we hope ours will be a little bit more interesting because of the crazy things that we've had
to do. So without any more delay, let's get to what we're going to talk about today. So
we'll start with the why and sort of what led us to finally decide to make the jump.
Second we'll go into the how. So we'll talk about how we laid out the problem that we
were facing and how we actually started to solve it. Then we'll do a deep dive into sort
of two of the major efforts that made this project happen. The first one was Project
Hercules where we migrated our entire code base from Python 2 to a hybrid Python 2 and
3 syntax. Then we'll talk about Hydra, which was our hybrid runtime, so the ability to
run both 2 and 3 on a user's computer. And then finally we'll go into how we combine
those into actually executing the transition, so how we made the rollout happen. So why
would you even want to switch, right? Like why would you want to make such a giant transition?
Isn't Python 2 working just fine? The answer was it was relatively working just fine. But
there were two primary reasons why we wanted to do this. It was in a way a pretty straightforward
cost benefit analysis. So Python 3 had huge benefits that we valued and Python 2 had huge
costs that were becoming difficult to bear. So let's start with Python 3. Python 3 is
actually genuinely exciting. It represents the actual evolution of the language and it
shows when you compare the two. So let's start with the Gill. So if you're not familiar,
the Gill is this measure that the runtime user is to maintain consistency when you
have concurrency with multiple threads, but it does that at the cost of parallelism. The
Gill is actually really important in a client-side app because it affects responsiveness. So it
affects how quickly your UI can respond to the user's requests. Now, we've been growing
the amount of UI that we have in our app, and so Python 3's Gill having all these improvements
actually made a difference, and I'll get to why in just a second. Second, native type
annotations. So we love type annotations. We're huge fans of MyPy at DrawBox, largely because
this is huge if you have a large code base. So we have hundreds of engineers working on
this. Being able to know exactly what's going to happen when you call a function is a big
deal, and so being able to do that natively in the syntax is just fantastic. Next, generally
just syntax improvements, things like f-strings. There's a long list of those, but when you
combine them, you get much greater developer productivity, and that's something we wanted
to take advantage of. As you might be able to imagine, we use the OS module a lot. So
DrawBox's job on Windows, Mac, and Linux is to sync your files, and so we use the OS module.
We use POSIX module quite a bit, and there's been so many improvements there, so many enhancements
over the years that we really wanted to be able to take advantage of them. Pathlib is
the best example of that. And finally, coroutines. So the whole async IO effort, that's just
a great leap for the language. To us, it opens up an entirely new way to think of concurrency,
and we see a potentially much better way to implement a bunch of patterns that occur very
often in our code. So really, there was no shortage of excitement around Python 3. And
for the second part of the reason, Python 2 became an issue. It became difficult to
maintain it and to keep it running. We're going to consider Python 2 for Windows as
an example. That's a good example because Windows is our most popular platform. There's
been a lot of amazing work done in Python 3 to improve Windows support, but we weren't
able to take advantage of that work. If you consider how old the compiler requirements
are for Python 2, then you see the sort of core of our issue. Python 2 requires Visual
Studio 2008. Let that sink in. That is an 11-year-old compiler, right? And there's a
good reason for that. It means if you download something from Pippi, you get a binary that's
going to work the same way regardless of where you download it or where you install Python.
But that's a bit of a problem. Thankfully, we control our own Python, so we decided to
fork Python 2, and we actually manually patched it all the way up to supporting Visual Studio
2013. But the more we did that, the more painful merges were becoming and the more kind of
undocumented behavior started appearing. And this came to a head when some of our key dependencies
like Qt or Chromium just started requiring the very latest and greatest in compilers.
And then on top of all of this, we realized we were starting to spend considerable time
taking features from Python 3 and backporting them into 2. So, for example, we actually
backported Python 3.2's Gill into 2.7 specifically for the native responsiveness issues that
we were seeing. So the point of all this is Python 3 basically became a blocker to a bunch
of our initiatives. We realized in order to build what we wanted to build, we needed to
upgrade, and the more we waited, the worse this would get. And to talk about the how,
Damian?
Cool. All right. So we knew that we had essentially upgraded Python 3, and this talk is about
how we actually did it. So we have a problem at first, right, which is Dropbox is not a
small application. We have hundreds of thousands of lines of code with hundreds of engineers
that push code every day. We support a large number of configurations. So we don't just
run on the server. On client, we run on Windows, we run on Mac OS, we run on Linux, and we
support pretty old OSes. So making sure that our code runs everywhere is not just super
easy. Also, as Max said, we have a custom fork of Python, which means that we have pretty
much like a decade of patches that we need to kind of try to migrate and maintain and
all of that. And finally, the last thing is we like a desktop application, which means
that shipping code doesn't just happen overnight. Releasing an app happens every couple of weeks,
but we go through a series of channels, which means that the time it takes between I learn
the code now, essentially you will be able to run the code that I learned in six weeks.
So you kind of just flip a switch and change all your stuff to Python 3 or things like
that and just make a switch and everything is available everywhere. So that's a bit essentially
of like a sort of complexity on the scope of the issue here. So how would we even start
with that? Because there's not like a perfect time to just go ahead and oh, yeah, let's
go ahead and migrate to Python 3. So where did we begin? And really it came out of Hack
Week. And if you're not familiar with Hack Week, it's basically we have a couple of weeks
a year where engineers can work on whatever they want and try to do the things that they
probably wouldn't either have time or sort of bandwidth to do in the rest of the year.
So in 2015 and 2016, like a bunch of us just met and we're like, yeah, what if we just
tried? And it was super important to kind of build like a sort of momentum and getting
a lot of folks excited. So there were folks that were excited about like the language
itself. There were folks that were excited about like sort of challenge and we met all
these folks and we kind of set a little team during Hack Week and worked on that. And most
importantly, we showed the rest of the organization that, hey, this is doable. Like we are small,
we can make it work. That's something that we could do. And basically, yeah, it was really
the perfect sort of setting to like start the work and bootstrap it. So as part of Hack
Week, we also like got a chance to discover what would work and not work. So like a great
example, the first thing that like we tried to say, hey, we got a code base there, let's
just feed it into a 2 to 3, get code and just like everything is going to work, right?
Well, we figured out it's not that easy. So we kind of looked at, yeah, five options and
realized that. But what really came out of Hack Week was we put a system in place, like
we had a way to start a Python interpreter in Python 3 and feed our code to it. Nothing
worked. It was like doing nothing. It was just crashed. It crashed like at boot. But
at least we sort of unblocked other engineers after Hack Week to like work on it and just
iterate and try to make like, oh, yeah, we'll fix a bunch of tests and make sure they run
on Python 3 and things like that. So like it was super, super important. So that's the
graph. That's like a histogram of basically a number of, it's not a number of commits.
So it's basically additions and deletions of code that like touch Python 2 and 3 across
the years, like the last five years. And you can see the kind of two exploratory attempts
in like in 15 and 16, which is really Hack Week. And then like bulk of the work was like
spent in 2017 when we actually staffed the team and decided we all in into that and we
just made like the work. And we shipped that in 2018. So all the work that happened in
2018 was mostly fixing bugs and try to stabilize the thing and make sure that everything worked.
So yeah, most of the work was really a year, but it was kind of spread into a bunch of
initiatives early on. So like the thing I really want to kind of take out of that is
the transition of Python 3 will very like force it had to be a gradual process. Like
it didn't happen overnight and it took a while and we really, really rated on that. So let's
start actually a deep dive into how and what we specifically did. I want to talk about
like the syntax and the basically hybrid. So we had a project called Hercules and given
that we had to gradually move to Python 3, it basically meant that we had to support
both 2 and 3 at the same time. So what did we do? From the future we just import Python
3 and everything worked. Not quite. It was not that easy. This would have been great.
But it was not that bad. As in there are like there is a rich set of tools that can really
help you there. So we've used a bunch of modernize and 2 to 3 really selectively rather than
throwing the whole code at it. Mostly fix the sort of obvious issues. So like syntax
has changed, like exception, you cannot have a comma here and there and things like that.
Like obvious issues that work on 2 to 3. So we fixed that. But first like really the key
was 6. So if you're not familiar with 6, it's essentially a model that lets you import things
that will work on 2 and 3 at the same time, if that makes sense. So you don't have to
write a lot of if clauses. If on Python 3 import that. If on Python 2 import that and do this
other way. So we used a ton of that. And basically our code was like we didn't want the code
to look a lot worse because of the migration. We still wanted to have a code base that looked
good and that was easier to work on once we were on Python 3. So that was super key to
us. And finally we wrote a bunch of like small helpers. So in nature if any of you have used
a future.utils function, it's similar. It's mostly a deal with strings. And these helpers
are like, hey, when I'm fed a string, just give me a unicode. If I'm fed a string or
a unicode or things like that. Just to make sure that you're dealing with the right type
of string. And finally we used a typing module in MyPy. There is a type annotation called
text that's simply unicode in Python 2 and stir on Python 3. And we really used that
where it made sense. And it was super important for us to have our APIs adder to a contract.
Hey, I will never be passed bytes. I'm dealing with a unicode string everywhere. So we used
that a lot. And that was super, super important. So on types in general, as Max said, we still
are super fan of MyPy. We use it a lot. And it's really, really, really helpful on a code
base that is pretty large, right? And as part of migrating, we have annotated our code quite
a lot. We reached like a 60% as part of the transition. I think we're like a bit above
now. And that was just, yeah, it was just very important for us to kind of verify the
compliance with the new APIs or contract to making sure that the code was actually correct.
And for all these issues where you don't really know what sort of type you're passing or what
you work across, you know, sort of run times, this was important. We even found like a bunch
of bugs that were just in Python 2 bugs that we've had forever. And that's the classic
engineer thing. You stare at your screen and you're like, how did that ever work? And
so we found these bugs. And that was cool. However, there's one little thing you won't
be surprised. It's strings. It's just not that easy. And even if you type your code
super, super well, ideally you would say, yeah, so stir become bytes. And now your unicode
is stir and everything is good. But the problem is really Python 2 is very permissive with
strings, like more than happy to sort of coerce them and things like that. So in order
to kind of explain that, I want to go in detail. In a couple of little bugs that we've had,
that just show you what we mean by that, right? So we've all done that. That's basically an
authorization header that you want to send to HTTP and you pass and you generate a token
from like a value that you had and you base 648 and put it in there. You run the code
on Python 2 and things like that's good. That's what I expect. Nice. You run the same code
on Python 3 and suddenly you're like, wait, that's not what I want. And you go through
server logs and why can't I authorize everyone? And the problem is, well, this is not a token.
This is a representation of a token. So what's the issue here, really? We're trying to interpolate
a byte string into a unique string. The essential person test is like, okay, I need to get a
string representation of that thing, so let me just call stir on it. In Python 2, a byte
string is a string. That's what it is. So it just gives that one back and that goes into
there. In Python 3, however, a byte string is not a string anymore. And it needs to call
a reaper to get a string out of that. And the representation of a byte string happened
to contain this like a prefix and quotes. So this was a fun one. And a second one that
we kind of... So this is more like of a kind of a scary bug, I would say. So when you deal
with like Python versions, there is the code, but there's also anything around the code
that you might write a disk or get from a server that might be different across the
versions of Python you get. So in that case, that's like a simple little thing. You've
got like a database with a table that basically has like a bunch of hash and size. And the
idea is you want to know the size of a file and you compute the hash of the file and you
get it. That's like simple. On Python 2, you will just... Like you compute the hash of
the file, you put its size and you just insert that in SQLite. And then back on Python 3,
you execute a query where you basically bind the hash and hope to get the size back. But
unfortunately, if you run that code on Python 3, you will get nothing. The reason for that
is... Well, as we saw earlier, in Python 2, bytes string, it's a string. So what happened
on the third line is basically SQLite is just trying to insert a string. So we like insert
a row as text. On Python 3, it says, oh, yeah, I'm giving bytes. So that's a blob. So let
me just bind it as a blob. So it bytes in the statement as a blob. And basically the
query doesn't match anything because there is no blob that match that. So this was a
fun one. So that's kind of like issues with like strings in general, a lot of little things.
So now that we can actually write code that works in Python 2 and 3, how do we make this
sort of lasting improvement? So making sure that code works and we avoid a bunch of regressions.
So what we did is we made sure that our tests always run in Python 2 and in Python 3. And
we made sure that we type checked on Python 2 and 3 all the time. And basically we made
it like, hey, if you break Python 3, you break the build entirely. And that's just breaking
the build and that's not acceptable. And a better yet, we like even set a git hook that
would just run all unit tests on Python 2 and 3 and mypy in Python 2 and 3. And you
couldn't push any code unless it worked on both. And yes, so basically we were like preventing
anyone from writing code that wouldn't work on either. So we really tried to make it easy
for our engineers to write code that would work on Python 2 and 3 from day one. And yeah,
that was quite important for us. So I'm going to give it to Max to talk about the runtime.
Okay, so let's go into the second part of our deep dive. So now that our code is compatible
with Python 2 and Python 3, how do we get it to our users? So let's take a step back
for a second. So if you're using Python from the client side, that means you're actually
shipping three things. One, you need to ship a native app that's compliant with the platform's
app model. Now, that's a complicated way of saying that on Windows you need to ship a
.exe and on Mac you need to ship a .app. Second, you need to ship a Python interpreter, so
something to run Python with your app. And then third, you need to compile your Python
source code to byte code and then you need to ship that too. So we view our app as being
this sort of Russian doll of all of these three things. Now, on desktop, this is usually
done by popular tools called freezers. Shout out to PyInstaller or Py.app. Those are the
ones we've used before. Now, as part of this project, though, now, so we used our freezers
for a decade, but we actually decided not to do that anymore. We call this project antifreeze.
So why would we want to do this? Well, first, in the beginning, Python 3 support was not
actually very widespread in the freezer tool, so PyInstaller at the time didn't support
it, though it does now. Shout out. Second, we actually rely quite a bit on native tool
chains now. So as you can imagine, Dropbox integrates pretty deeply with each operating
system and if you take Mac as an example, there's some features now on Mac OS that require
you to use Xcode to take advantage of them. But since the freezers hide all of that from
you, it can become difficult to tap into those features. And for some of those features,
they were very important to us. And finally, Python's not alone in our code base anymore.
So where the first version of Dropbox was just Python, we now have a whole bunch of
Objective-C and Rust and C and C++, and since freezers are very deeply embedded in the Python
environment, they're basically setup tools. And setup tools isn't quite good enough as
a build system to wrangle all of these things together. So to us, it was just more advantageous
to control our native entry points. Shout out to the Py installer. We think it's really
good. Dropbox kind of became too complex for that. The way we actually implemented this
is we just used the C API directly. So even there, actually, Python 3 made improvements
and provided generally better isolation from other Pythons installed in the system. Like
Py set path comes to mind. So back to our problem. So we want to be able to get Python
3 in the hands of our users, but we need to do this gradually. We can't just turn it on
for everybody at once because there would be a whole bunch of bugs and people would
be angry. So how do we do this? Well, we need to enable Python 3 for very specific groups
of users. And how do we do that? Well, now that we control the main function, now that
we control the entry points, we can actually do whatever we want. We can now ship more
than one Python runtime. And that's exactly what we did. We actually shipped two. So we
had a Python 2 runtime and Python 2 bytecode and a Python 3 runtime with Python 3 bytecode.
And then what we would do is we would choose at runtime which one to use. We called this
project Hydra because multiple snake heads. So the point here is that to get the granularity
that we needed and to target very specific user populations, we needed to ship a hybrid
application. It wasn't just it wasn't good enough to just have hybrid source. So let's
look at the last step. So how do we all the pieces are interplaced. How do we bring it
all together and actually complete the transition? So there will be bugs. That's we fully expected
we didn't know about and that we would discover halfway. But we needed a process to deal with
them. Now, we know that we can actually give selectively Python 3 to some of our users.
We need clear criteria to grow that population. So we can't just how do we add more people
to that group? And we knew that we needed one capability. And that's to recover very
gracefully if Python 3 breaks. So in a way, we'd want to be able to try Python 3. And
if something breaks, bail out. And that actually means that you need to be able to move back
and forth between Python 2 and Python 3 seamlessly. And that's important because of what Damian
said earlier, especially when you persist data locally, you need to make sure that you're
writing and reading consistently on both versions of the language. Otherwise, you'll corrupt
the state. So how do we do this? We designed a fail safe initialization process. So basically,
we'd always start out in Python 2. And if we would check in with our servers, and then
we'd say, hey, am I allowed to run Python 3? No, yes. If so, we would restart ourselves
in Python 3 mode. And that actually was implemented through a command line flag. So you would launch
literally draw box.xz slash Py3. That was the flag. And then if an app crash would happen,
because the normal initialization is without any arguments, you would always just restart
in Python 2. So the default was always Python 2. And that ensured that users never remained
in a broken state. We also had a logic to detect if we crashed repeatedly and then just
stop trying for a little while. Okay. So now that we can introduce new users, that we feel
relatively confident about that, how do we actually release? So we decided to do that
in three stages. And those roughly matched how we released draw box itself. We would
start with something we call internal alpha. And that's for draw box employees. So we basically
ate our own dog food. Then we would move on to the beta stage. And the beta stage is for
users who explicitly signed up for bleeding edge. And they're generally okay with a little
bit more instability. And finally, we'd go to stable. And stable is just the entire population
of all draw box users. What we'd do is we'd slowly kind of move the dial within each stage.
And we would never move from one stage to the next unless every last Python 3 bug or
crash or exception was investigated and marked as being green. This was very conservative.
And it actually took us nine months to fully roll this out. Because remember, every commit
takes six weeks to make it to a user. So let's take a look at how the rollout actually
worked. I don't know if you can see this well. But green represents the Python 2 population.
Orange represents Python 3. And then we moved in increments of 10%. The longer pauses show
places where we had tougher bugs that took a longer time to investigate. But we would
never grow the population until the bug was resolved. And we never went to 100%. Can anyone
me why we never went to 100% here? Want to hazard a guess? That's good. No, the actual
reason is we didn't want to regress Python 2. So this whole time we were paranoid and
we were thinking, what if this goes, it's like a catastrophe and it goes horribly wrong
and we want to undo all of this tomorrow? The worst thing we could do is send everyone
to Python 3 and then regress Python 2 because then we wouldn't be able to go back. And so
we always kept at least 10% at each stage running Python 2 just to be sure. And this
is a stable rollout. This one is a bit more abrupt. And what we did is we initially went
to 10%, gave it a bunch of time, looked out for all of our metrics, all of our exceptions,
and when no bugs appeared, we then made a release that removed Hydra and only shipped
Python 3. And then we were basically done. So this conservative approach basically meant
that the vast majority of migration bugs were actually found in the first stage. In fact,
there was one bug we found afterward and that was where we briefly broke proxy support,
but that was fixed really quickly. So dogfooding works. Now, in conclusion, so all of this
to say that client software can be unique here, we think we succeeded because we gave
ourselves complete flexibility to migrate users because we made it really easy for developers
to join in, we made it hard to actually regress the winnings that we'd get, and we very conservatively
left any stone unturned. In fact, exclusive, we just moved from Python 3.5 to 3.7 and it
took one engineer two weeks to do so. Many of the processes we actually came up with
are still in place today. And with that, we'll open it up for questions. Thank you. All right.
So I'm told we can do two questions. So anyone want to hazard a question for us? Hi.
ianr enough attention and content with trying to take your time and work with your client,
So, if you just got bugs and you didn't even go,
you could have just gone to the Pop Box
because they would actually use it as a site
and they would be off the way.
So, we're lucky in that way.
So, the question was, how do we detect bugs internally?
Like, did the population at DrawBox
actually use the software?
And the answer is yes.
So, all DrawBoxers run the desktop client.
That's kind of pre-installed on all of our machines.
And so, the population was really good.
And yet, we were lucky in that way
in that everyone used the product
and so we were able to get most of the bugs that way.
Yeah, so, do I?
Yeah, it's working.
So, the other thing is like,
is DrawBoxers add DrawBox,
but they also get the same build at home.
So, for example, that's how we got a lot of Windows issues.
So, most folks use Mac at work, things like that.
And we have a lot of very old Windows machines at home.
So, that's how we caught a bunch actually of these issues
is at home.
Okay, I think you were in line, yeah.
So, you said you had a lot of issues
when you were working in Pi 2,
which caused you to migrate to Pi 3.
Why did you, well, did you decide to move to Pi 3
before checking out other Pi 2 interpreters like Pi Pi?
Oh, that's a good question.
I think it was less about,
so, language features did play into it,
but it was primarily a compiler thing.
And so, I wasn't extremely aware of,
I'm not super aware of Pi Pis
or the other sort of compilers tool chains
and those requirements of other interpreters.
But we had used CPython for so long
and we relied on it so deeply.
We had made a bunch of changes to it
that it didn't seem,
it seemed like it would be another extra step of migration
to try another interpreter.
And we weren't sure whether we could sort of maintain
the same sort of compiler tool chains as before.
But that's a good question.
I don't know that we very deeply explored that option,
but we kind of assumed
that we wanted to keep using CPython.
All right.
We can catch up.
I'm sorry.
I think we have to run, but thank you.
All right. Thank you.
Thank you.