Good morning, everyone. Or afternoon. It's still morning. I live in California, so my
brain still thinks it's morning. Hi, I'm Jacinda Shelley. If you're not completely
set up with Slack or anything like that yet, don't worry. We can take care of any logistical
issues when we get to the practical portion. The first part of the tutorial is me blathering
on at you for a little bit to give you some background on security. I'm really excited
that you're all here. This is the second time that I've been the instructor for this
tutorial and I was an assistant for it the first time it was presented. Talk a little
bit about that later. As I mentioned, I think a few of you were confused why I actually
had to ask for your email. It's because PyCon takes your privacy very seriously, so I can't
actually, well, I can see a list of the names of everyone who is attending and I can check
a box to send an email via a form. I can't actually invite you to Slack unless I request
your email. If that seemed a little confusing because PyCon has your email, then that's
why. So as I mentioned, the history of this tutorial, it was originally given in PyCon
2015 and it was titled Getting Comfy with Web Security. I was asked if I would be interested
in assisting with the tutorial because I was giving a tutorial on a different topic at
the same conference and he wanted some extra help. I was actually giving a tutorial on
the Django admin and I randomly emailed him last year because I thought the tutorial was
so cool and he hadn't updated it and I wanted to give it again. Last year he was like, oh,
sure, it's all under Creative Commons and I was like, you sure? I'm going to take all
you did and update it. It took a lot of updating. Thankfully I did most of that last year when
I presented it at DjangoCon 2018, but going from Django 1.4 to Django 2.1 was a lot and
in fact some of the exploits became a lot more difficult to pull off with that update.
So that's good news on the Django front. They're getting more secure all the time. So a little
bit about me. I was the first engineer at Doctor On Demand. I was promoted to CTO a
couple of years ago. We are a sponsor. You can come find us at the expo. They do pay
for me to come to the conference. I feel okay giving a little bit of a plug and we're
hiring. I also have an adorable little two and a half year old who you might see running
around at the conference because PyCon is very family friendly. And she's come to this
is her third PyCon. So a little bit about what this tutorial is and isn't. I like to
start this off with a quote from James Mickens who I don't know, it doesn't matter if you've
heard of him or not, if you are at all interested in extremely nerdy humor, I recommend reading
anything he's written or watching any of his talks. But he has a small paper called This
World of Ours that says, sometimes when I check my work email, I'll find a message that
says talk announcement, vertex based elliptic cryptography on in-way bojangle spaces. And
the thrust of this paper is that essentially if you're relying on really, really advanced
security to keep your website secure and you're only concerned about simultaneously shared
party, that's not actually how attacks happen in the real world unless you are getting hacked
by the NSA or another nation state. In which case you might as well just throw up your
hands because they're going to get in. But this is about protecting your website from
the most common attacks, the ones that are most easily scripted and that are most practical
and they're also, in Django they're not as easy to mess up but they are pretty, they're
pretty common. So order of operations, I talk a little bit about example attacks in the
real world and you get to see examples of some big names who have gotten this wrong.
We do a little bit of what used to be called Google dorking. They now call it like Google
hacking or something. We have a little bit of a group discussion which you may have already
initiated about what you're trying to protect. Lab time break is at 3 p.m. and I've been
instructed to let you out right on time because the snacks go quickly. We do more lab time
and then we do a wrap up lecture where I walk through all of the exploits that we did during
the lab. And then I give you a survey link so you can tell PyCon whether you loved or
hated the tutorial where I can improve and all of that good stuff. So getting to know
you, obviously there are too many people in this tutorial to have everyone go around and
introduce themselves, but if we have a few brave volunteers who want to stand up and
share why they're here at this tutorial, that would be great. All right.
Thank you. Anyone else want to share? All right.
All right. Anyone else? That's fine. You'll all get to know each other in your groups.
From the survey you completed, you might be interested to know there were questions about
familiarity with web security, Python and Django. The average in the group is about
2.5 for Django and for web security. So if you feel like you don't know that much, then
you're in good company. And then it was about a 3.5 for Python, which made sense to me given
that we're all at a Python conference. The next step, this is some examples of real world
exploits where we talk through and these mirror the exploits that you'll be doing in the lab
exercises. So it's good to pay attention. Some of these may look a little dated because
the websites and the examples are from a few years ago, but the attacks are still relevant.
So I don't know how many of you are familiar with TweetDeck. This is the first example
that we're going to talk about, which is cross-site scripting. TweetDeck is a kind
of if you are a pro-expert user of Twitter, like a celebrity or you're managing a Twitter
account on behalf of someone else, then you might be a user of TweetDeck. It used to be
quite popular. So one day someone went and they wrote this test. And that says in German
that this shouldn't work. And this was the raw tweet. But what got displayed was this
message down here in TweetDeck. Now, just offhand, for those of you who are more familiar
with cross-site scripting, this is who are less familiar with cross-site scripting, this
means that instead of displaying the raw HTML, it means that TweetDeck was actually interpreted
in the HTML. So the next thing that someone did not too long after this tweet went out
was they wrote this little script. Because what happens generally speaking on a website,
if you write HTML and input it in your client, and then another site that's interpreting
the HTML doesn't escape it properly and actually executes that HTML, then you can script basically
anything you want. We'll walk through exactly what this tweet does in a minute. And then
TweetDeck tweeted out this. We've taken down TweetDeck temporarily while we investigate
the security issue. And as we will walk through each thing. So the first part of this is it's
embedded in a script tag, which means it's JavaScript. It's throwing up an alert that
there's a cross-site scripting vulnerability in TweetDeck. The next line in there is clicking
the retweet button. So if you opened this up, all of a sudden you would retweet this
to all of your followers without actually hitting the retweet button yourself. Set the
class to XSS. And what this kind of obscure line is doing is it's finding the heart button
and also favoriting this tweet for you. So this tweet rapidly garnered 83,500 retweets
and almost 10,000 favorites. I think because in some of the clients, the clicking the favorite
action didn't actually work correctly. So what else could this exploit have done? Like
if someone hadn't wanted to do just something funny, what else might they have been able
to do? Yes? Yeah, potentially. Other things they might have been able to delete all your
tweets depending on what authorization is required to do that. Essentially anything
that the user is authorized to do that can be executed by JavaScript, your attacker can
now do to you. Now what can't they have done? Yeah? Probably not. Although it's possible
that that would require another vulnerability in terms of best practice. Right. Also anything
that that particular user wouldn't have access to. This doesn't change who you are authenticated
as. This just performs actions on your behalf. So if you opened up this tweet, like I could
potentially delete all your tweets. If other security measures weren't in place, I might
be able to change your password, take over your account. I could upload any of your user
data but I couldn't do things like access what's on Twitter's servers that doesn't belong
to me. That would require another vulnerability to be in place. So we can pause there if anyone
has any questions about cross site scripting. Okay. The next example is around why defaults
are not always good. So this, as I mentioned, Ashish was the original presenter of this
particular tutorial. He was doing a different talk about setting up Django and was using
a particular person's version of the Django tutorials app that had the database built
in and the user was able to use it to create a new user. So this is a very interesting
tutorials app that had the database built in. So all you had to do was clone the repository
and it would run and lots of things were set up for you. So he had this up during his talk
and he was asking what is the most awesome. It was Django, Chewbacca, and caffeine here.
He then, the next part of the slide was LOL Chewbacca caffeine. He quickly realized that
someone, instead of voting on his poll, had hacked his website. Any guesses how they might
have done this? It requires access to not necessarily the database itself but a way
to access the database. Yes?
Maybe, but not in this case. This was in 2014 but you could still do it this year.
Yeah.
Exactly. So it was forward slash admin and the default was set by the particular repository
that he was using. So he was using someone else's repository that already had the database
set up that said the password for the admin account is admin. So someone went in and they
changed the model. This was the actual tutorial that he was using and you notice in the readme
that this is the mysite.polls tutorial. The database has a super user with name admin,
password admin. So they could have done something much worse than just change the poll. But
because it was a Django talk and Ashish is a security engineer, it was pretty hilarious.
So default passwords and URLs. He also did not change the slash admin which is something
that I recommend is a best practice. It's really easy to change the URL from being slash
admin to slash something random or something easy to remember that is not admin because
it's just one fewer attack vector. I'll talk more about that after the lab exercises.
The next exploit that we're going to talk about is one that often I think confuses people
the most and it's cross site request forgery. So if you've ever tried to think about cross
site request forgery before and your head exploded a little bit, don't worry, that's
not uncommon. If we break it down a little bit, cross site means that you are making
a request from another website. This is becoming increasingly common in a world of additional
REST APIs and there are often valid reasons for doing this. But if you're using strictly
a model view template relationship within Django or in Flask you're just using standard
routing, there is no reason that you should turn off any of the security defaults in terms
of same origin because Django has good defaults for those and you should use them. In fact,
one of the things that you'll take away from this tutorial is that most, the vast majority
of the security related defaults for Django are sane and you should not change them unless
you know exactly what you are doing and why. Another note on that is that I saw in some
of the responses that people were looking for API specific security recommendations.
It's not something that we'll do hands on in this tutorial but if you talk to me afterwards
I can point you at resources and things like that. So Google Web Accelerator is really
old. It was one of the early things that Google shut down in 2008. It was back in the days
when a lot of people still had dial up, the internet was slow and Google Accelerator was
a product that was around I think from about 2005 to 2008 and they were trying to make
the web faster. That was the goal of this project. It was a client that often ran on
Windows machines and things like that. One of the things that it could do to make your
web browsing experience faster was click on all the links in your search results for you
ahead of time. So this is a screenshot of Basecamp which was built by the same people
who created Ruby on Rails. One of the things that you could do in this admin interface
was there's that little trash can. What do you think it does? Deletes the user and it
deletes the user with a get request. So in general get requests should not change server
side state for this reason because if I am authenticated as this user and I send a request
to this website that says get slash delete slash one for user one then bye bye Jeremy.
So this would come up in Google search results. You were logged in. It would try and click
on all of these links and all of a sudden you lost all of the users except for yourself
because there's no delete button next to you thankfully and this caused heartache. So anytime
that you have a get request that is modifying server state that isn't just returning information
this is an opening for the easiest form of cross site request forgery. There are also
ways to do cross site request forgery over post. Those are more complicated and as long
as you're using Django's defaults and don't add like at CSRF exempt to your views you
are protected from those but don't do it over get. Pause there before we go to the final
example of our me talking through some of these exploits and see if you have any questions
about that. All right. The last example exploit that we're talking about is directory traversal
and this is a subset of improper authorization checking. So moin moin was a very popular
wiki engine at one point. Wiki.debian ran it. So did wiki.python and it allowed you
to put in a lot of plug ins. This is an example of one of the plug ins where you could draw
diagrams and then they would be populated within the wiki and people liked this plug
in a lot. We'll talk through exactly what that plug in did. So we have this get request
here. The action that's happening is you're using the plug in to draw something. You're
modifying the requests or you're modifying the diagram and you have a target which is
just the name of the file that is the drawing. The response is you get an authorization ticket
saying this is your authorization ticket for this particular, pardon me, for this particular
file. Then what you do is you post. So in the first request you're not modifying any
server state. It's just giving you an authorization token to perform an action on this drawing.
Then in the post you actually save the file with the auth ticket that you were given in
the first request. So here we see get where the target looks a little odd. And then the
post here lets you, so what this is doing is it's going up a few directories and actually
accessing the plug in directory for moinmoin and the moinexec.py and replacing it with
whatever moinexec.py file you wanted to load. So this is the post. So this is the post.
So what would you do if you could put arbitrary code on someone's server? I won't, to spare
anyone future criminal allegations, I won't have anyone volunteer. So to briefly go through,
we have the get action is whatever. These are some examples. Delete the entire server.
That's one example. And this happened because this actually did happen. And the people working
on the Python wiki and the Debian wiki had a fun, I forget if it was a couple of days,
going back to backups and rebuilding everything. So that's another important component of security.
It doesn't seem obvious as a security measure, but unless, until you think about it a little
bit more, but make sure you have backups and that your backups are stored somewhere
that your primary application server does not have access to. Because if your backups
have the same kind of authentication that your server does, anyone who accesses your
server can then also access your backups and delete them. So best practice is to put your
backups somewhere that is under an entirely separate account or in an entirely separate
place within your account that has extremely restricted permissions. Also, as a side note,
make sure that you practice restoring your backups periodically because if you don't
practice restoring your backups, what you have is not a backup. You have a potentially,
you just have a file. You have no idea if it actually does what you think it does. Case
and point, GitLab, last year or the year before, they have an excellent writeup that you can
go look at in terms of they were doing backups, but they had never tried restoring from those
backups or hadn't in a while, and then when they actually needed to, it didn't work. So
in summary, the exploits that we've covered are cross-site scripting, and we walked through
TweetDeck and what that looks like. Looked at security misconfiguration, so default passwords.
Cross-site request forgery, so using get to delete on another site. And then code injection
and directory traversal. And these are all within the lab exercises that we're going
to be doing. So the next piece that we're going to go through is a little bit of a warmup
where it just starts, we just want to be thinking in the security mindset because a big part
of defending your website is thinking like an attacker. So I'd like everyone to go to
this URL up here and give everyone a minute to type that in and take a look at what you see.
I'll pull it up here as well. So this used to be called Google dorks, they changed it
to Google hacking database because it sounds nicer. I have a little slide about the history
of why they're called Google dorks. There's an original page that is no longer up, but
you can find some information on Wikipedia and this is in the way back machine because
Johnny I hack stuff took it down, but he had definitions of various things that people
would do and find on Google dorks. So what these are, and they're put in here in terms
of categories, these are all Google searches. So if you click on this, it shows you the
way to do how you would actually do the Google search. And oh, it's a good thing this is
not accredited for processing or storing classified information. And what I want people to do
within your groups as a way to get to know each other is look around these. So this for
example is a login portal files that you might find, advisories, and these are ones
that people have recently posted. So take a look around at these, talk within your groups
for about five minutes and we'll circle back and talk about what people found and what
they thought were the most interesting. Yes. Right there.
Doom
Oh, you're employers are preventing it?
Yeah.
Can't provide us, oh.
Yeah, my employer is blocking the exposure.
Oh, you should definitely share that.
You should definitely share that.
That's hilarious.
I don't know which group I am, so I don't think I just...
Uh, yeah, we'll figure it all out later.
And you can hang out with them.
And maybe you're short, I don't know.
So you could just hang out in the group.
I think group two was a little short.
I'm sorry, I didn't really follow exactly what this is showing us.
So these are like advanced Google search terms.
And so if you click on that, it'll actually pull up Google.
And so this is telling it like...
This one is showing if there are publicly exposed profiles for Garmin Connect.
So for example, you were trying to target like where...
So if you click on one of those, I think that one's going to show you
like where people have been running.
There was an interesting security vulnerability disclosed where
one of Garmin's competitors, another big running firm,
was by default publicly showing all of the lat-long information
for runs people had done.
And someone went and looked at this map and they found...
There's nothing here on the map, but there are all of these people running around.
And you can imagine that was actually a military base that was classified.
So that would be a good one to share with the group.
Nice. Yeah.
Thanks.
All right.
We...
So I talked to a few of you.
Some of you had some relatively interesting finds.
I clarified with a few.
So a few people asked about what this is doing in more detail.
And what it's doing is using advanced Google search terms
to find websites that may have vulnerabilities.
So hackers will often use this as a springboard to things that have known vulnerabilities.
So one of the things that...
The first link we clicked on when I was going through the example
was looking for cold fusion login pages.
If a cold fusion zero day had been discovered yesterday,
that search would be really useful to an attacker
trying to see if they hadn't updated their cold fusion site yet.
So we'd love to hear some of the funny things that people found.
Or interesting or concerning.
So he found someone's Steam game library.
Yes.
Yes, someone's running history in Japan.
Someone else mentioned that they'd found that as well.
And that's actually really interesting from an exploit perspective
in terms of accidental information disclosure.
I forget if it was last year or the year before,
but there was another one of these running companies
that by default published all of your running maps to be public.
And as you might imagine, there are a lot of people in the military
who are pretty fit and like to use these tracking devices.
All of a sudden someone goes to the map of all of these trails
that people have taken and finds that there are an awful lot of people
running in this place that doesn't have any buildings on the map.
And there was a base that was accidentally disclosed
because of information that was made public by default.
All right, what's another example?
One more thing by the way.
So Garmin, if you try to log in,
you're using Tor to access them, it'll just block you.
But if you're not using Tor, it won't block you.
So I don't know if it's just optimization I think.
Interesting.
So he said that if you're using Tor to access the profile,
it will block you.
But if not, then it won't block you.
Which I would imagine is probably a default firewall setting.
Might be something else.
Who else?
Yes, or actually in the back.
Yes?
We have a printer controller in China.
Oh, so are you going to start printing off random pages for them?
Say hello.
Yes.
In URL is very common.
And then I know there were at least two people
whose employer laptop configurations were blocking them from accessing this site,
which I also find quite funny.
I'm not sure if that's actually improving the security or not.
All right.
So moving on.
So what was the point of going through all of that?
Mostly to have you start thinking like attackers think,
which is like, what kind of exploits do I know about?
How can I find them?
What are the most common?
They're generally not, again, unless they're employed to do this full time,
they're not looking for something that's going to be really difficult to attack.
They're looking for things that were misconfigured or you didn't follow the checklist.
So doing 80, well, the 80-20 rule sort of applies here in that if you do the most basic things,
like 20% of the security work, you will get 80% of the results.
Another aside that we won't really go into in detail,
but what Google is to port 80 and 443, Shodan is for all of the other ports.
So if you ever want to get into the wonderful world of IOT hacking,
Shodan is your friend because it will show you how to search for webcams,
Ufinet, we'll leave that one off, Netgear routers, lots of Cisco stuff, FTP servers,
everything that operates that's not on web ports or HTP or HTPS ports, Shodan will help you find.
So what is at risk for you?
Normally I do a small group discussion here.
I think that we've talked a bit in your groups beforehand enough that you don't necessarily need to do this in here
or you can do it in line with some of the exercises.
I really want to give you more time for the exercises.
So I'll pause here and ask if there are any other questions before we go to the practical portion of the tutorial.
Nope. All right. Great.
I'm going to go break some websites.
And I will be talking a little bit more before we break the websites.
It's part of my job here.
And then for any of you who haven't gotten on the Slack workspace yet,
once I'm finished talking through the first part of the lab material,
then I'll go around and make sure that everyone has access to everything you need and answer any individual questions you might have.
So we're going to look at the lab material here.
This is the student handout that you need to go through all of the exercises.
I'll go back to the...
This is the website that you can go to for this, PetTwitter.com.
There is no association between PetTwitter and RealTwitter.
To be clear, please don't sue me.
To a certain extent, you can work at your own pace,
but the tutorial is designed for you to be social and talk amongst your groups and learn from each other,
which is why I set up the Slack channels.
I'll be stopping around the groups to see how everyone is doing,
and I'll be monitoring the Slack channels and helping everyone out.
So you can either flag me down or at me on Slack, and I'll come by.
So we want to make the most of lab time.
You have 90 minutes to get some hands-on practice.
Most of you already went there.
The attacks are structured such that when you complete an attack,
if you are the first person in your group to complete the attack and you want to confirm that you did,
send me a direct message with a link to your work and the number from the slide heading or the type of vulnerability it is.
So like, attack one is a cross-site scripting vulnerability.
And once I say, yes, you got it right, you can announce this in your group's channel,
and then other people in your group will then send their links to you to make sure that they found the correct vulnerability.
And if you find other vulnerabilities, like this is supposed to be fun, so attack things.
If other people don't know something, don't treat it like a failing.
I feel like this is generally obvious to most people, but I like to state it explicitly because it's part of,
it's in line with PyCon's code of conduct.
So too long, didn't read. Be kind.
This is one of my favorite XK CDs.
I try not to make fun of people for admitting they don't know things because for everything that everyone knows by the time they're adults,
every day there are on average about 10,000 people in the US hearing about it for the first time.
So if I make fun of people, I train them not to tell me when they have those moments,
and I miss out on all the fun of having someone share a discovery of something new.
So in the comic, it's diet coke and Mentos thing? What's that?
And the response is not, oh, I can't believe you never saw that.
It's, oh man, come on, we're going to go to the grocery store.
Why? You're one of today's lucky 10,000.
Each slide in this student handout has a category of web app vulnerability that we covered in the initial lecture portion.
Each slide has hints, which you can access by hitting S on the keyboard.
And you can look at the progress bar on the bottom, although it may not show up in all browsers or it may be kind of hard to see.
You can see it here just at the bottom, this purple.
So it'll show you about how far along you are in the handout.
And we already talked about being social.
Do fun things, but don't be malicious.
This is mostly you can treat this as black box testing if you want more of a challenge.
So if you are more advanced, then feel free to treat it as though you are black box testing.
The GitHub URL for the source code to this is both on the website, pettwitter.com, and shared in Slack.
So you can also do white box testing, which would simulate being an engineer at pettwitter.com and looking for vulnerabilities.
At this point, I will leave you all to your own devices.
I'll make an announcement just before 3 p.m. when we'll have a break.
And you can all step out and get some snacks, coffee, tea, whatever you fancy.
And with that, I'll leave you to it.
One minor note in this slide.
There is a space between script and slash script.
That's just because of the formatting in reveal.js that it did weird things if I didn't put the space there.
So it won't work if you leave the spaces there when you're using that sample attack code.
So keep that in mind.
All right.
Have fun.
And I'll go around and find anyone who, if for whatever reason you're not in a group or on Slack, raise your hand,
and I'll come around and we'll get all of those things fixed.
Yes.
Please only attack your own group's environment.
You were.
If everyone should be part of a group channel, a private channel for your group, if you are not,
it's because of Slack oddities and when I could add people.
And so depending on when you were invited, you might not be in the channel yet.
All right.
It's just about time for us to wrap up and talk through all of vulnerabilities.
I had a great time seeing what everyone did.
I heard a few comments about people saying that they had never actually performed real exploits against a website,
which was the whole point of this.
So I hope that was worthwhile.
I would love to take a few minutes and do a share like we did before of things that you found particularly clever
or anything that surprised you or that you learned.
So if a few people want to volunteer something that they found interesting, I would love to hear it.
Yes.
CSRF exempt is not your friend.
Now, I did have some people come up and ask me about cases in terms of APIs where there are cases where you legitimately need to turn it off.
But if you find yourself just turning off CSRF for your whole site and you don't have a primarily API-based site,
and even if you do have an API-based site, there are generally ways to leave it on.
And there's articles that you can find where if you're using a REST API, sometimes it's debatable how much that keeps you secure.
You should have other factors in place.
Like I said at the beginning, this is not an API-based security tutorial.
But it sounds like there would be an opportunity for one.
So if anyone would like to come up with that, please submit a proposal.
Anything else anyone found?
Yes.
Yep.
We'll get to that in more detail.
And that is actually particular to the way that this site was set up.
One more person?
Did someone do something that was particularly funny?
Well, besides the David Hasselhoff thing.
No, that's fine.
All right.
Let's talk through each of these.
So cross-site scripting.
In a previous version of this tutorial, someone made the astute comment that safe is not very safe,
and that it should perhaps be renamed.
I have not seen that pull request against Django.
I think there would be backwards compatibility issues, but really safe should be named unsafe.
If you're putting safe into your code, probably not a good idea.
So if you looked in the templates, anywhere you found safe was a place where you could perform a cross-site scripting attack.
Oops. Apologies.
So the theory is to escape content in a context-appropriate way.
So there are cases where you want to show italicized text and bolded text and allow people to do formatting,
but you don't want them to write scripts.
This is really hard to use, so use Django templates.
And there's a library called Bleach where if you are taking user data in
and you want to make sure that absolutely everything is stripped out of it, Bleach is a good way to do that.
We talked about defaults.
So clearly the default password on the super user account was not particularly secure.
Other things that we mentioned earlier were that it would also be good to change the default admin URL.
So that's an easy thing on your sites.
Just go in, change that from slash admin to something else that is specific to your site.
Security through obscurity by changing URLs is not a defense in and of itself,
but there is also no reason to make it easy for attackers to find your admin site.
If you are able to, in fact, putting it behind a VPN or some other form of security
so that only authorized users can get to the login pages is useful as well.
Two-factor authentication.
There are libraries that will help you add two-factor authentication, and it's configurable.
There's one called Django two-factor auth that adds a nice set of views,
and it supports YubiKey and Google Authenticator and SMS, which is not particularly secure.
So don't use SMS unless you have to for some reason.
And there are other talks about why that is.
But that is another relatively easy piece to put in.
So the next one was authorization checking.
So what's wrong with this bit of code here?
Why were you able to modify other people's pets in certain views?
Correct.
So it's not enough to just have a login be required.
You also need to check that someone actually has access to the thing that they are requesting.
There are a variety of sort of built-in methods in the Django documentation for how to do that,
such as get model for owner that will do some of that checking for you.
This is the other one that we had where we got a question of whether it should be a 403 versus a 404.
At this point, here you're checking that they're actually the owner.
So this is another way.
It's not the way that I would necessarily recommend,
but it is one way where the user has to be the same as the requesting user.
If it's not, then it will fail to find it.
404 versus 403 is kind of debatable here.
So 404 would mean that the pet doesn't exist.
403 means you're not authorized for that pet.
What would people argue either way in this case?
Yeah.
I would say 404 is more technically correct,
but it would mean that 403 would correct the leaked information.
So then, oh, this pet does exist, but you can't access it.
That's what I would say as well.
So in security, and that's a great answer,
there's a principle where you want to leak as little information as possible,
which is often why when you're going to websites and you do a password reset email,
they don't tell you whether or not that user exists on the system.
They just say, if this user exists on the system, an email was sent,
because they don't want you to go through and be able to enumerate
the email address of everyone on the system.
So I would say in this case, a 404 is more appropriate
because a 403 leaks information.
Yes.
It might depend on your particular use case.
If your user base generally always has access to things.
It's also somewhat accurate in this case to say that it is a 404
because there's no pet that belongs to that user.
And in this case, the query is more specific.
Where previously it was only checking that that pet ID existed,
in this case, the query is now checking that the pet ID with that user exists.
And this is what I mentioned.
Previously, there's an at-login required decorator
that is typically not enough on your views
if they're actually fetching any type of data.
There is a model.objects.filter.
Just check that the user is the request user.
And Django has a little helper here that makes it just a little bit shorter.
So on the next one, we have our SQL injection.
So what's wrong with this picture?
Yes.
So in a sense, well, I think ID in this case, yes,
that could be more specific as an integer.
That still is quite vulnerable to an injection. Yes.
Correct.
If you ever see a case where the SQL query is just constructed out of a string,
like massive alarm bells should go off in the SQL query,
and you should probably, depending on the exact circumstances,
consider educating the responsible party,
alerting your security officer if your company has one.
I hesitate to say resign because there could be extenuating circumstances,
but maybe update your resume and fix it.
So I think that's a good example of how to do that.
And fix it.
So the difference here, this is one way that this could have been avoided.
Where here the query string is constructed,
and instead of passing actual strings and constructing the whole string,
this is performed by the library itself,
and you pass in pet ID and user ID, and then the library parameterizes those.
That is not actually my preferred method of avoiding this.
My preferred method, and this is an older slide.
My preferred method is to just use the ORM.
This is by far the safest solution.
The bottom line is don't use raw SQL.
Use an ORM.
Jango's ORM is actually really, really good as of 2.0.
It supports subqueries and all sorts of fancy filtering.
James Bennett gave a tutorial at this past JangoCon,
which unfortunately wasn't recorded on video,
but it basically talks through why if you're using especially Jango 2.1, 2.2,
you would have to try really hard to need to go down to raw SQL.
If for some reason you must use something outside of the ORM,
which I acknowledge there are cases,
maybe you're using Jango and your database has tables that aren't part of Jango,
and you have to interface between those, there are cases where it's valid.
But use parameterized queries.
But read all of the ORM documentation before you think you have to use parameterized queries even,
or especially raw SQL.
The next kind of note is a lot of Jango is secure by default,
where most of the settings will keep you safe,
as long as you don't actively try and override them.
I think that actually got out of order.
This is talking about CSRF tokens.
I'm going to skip this diagram because I don't find it very helpful.
If you find it helpful, you have links to all of the items.
So in here you can, I'll just go through it anyway,
You have action delete, user ID, and a CSRF token, which is set on the cookie.
If you don't have CSRF protection set up correctly,
then it won't pass the CSRF token and the server should not accept it,
but if you mark something as CSRF exempt, it will instead.
We talked about why you should use post to change data,
and you want something that only a user on that site can have.
So cookies, unless you override a lot of settings,
the cookie will only be possessed by a user on that site within the browser.
That means that you can then take that cookie and pass it back to the server,
and the server will be like, oh, okay, you have that.
This is what the CSRF templating is what you should put at the top of every Django form
that you create in a template, and this will automatically set that cookie and bring it back.
The next one we went through was session data stealing.
If you looked in the settings, many of you noticed that the secret key was in the GitHub repository itself.
So to start with, what is wrong with that?
Any takers?
Yep, and it's supposed to be private.
Even if it's in a private repository, you should consider it to be a public key.
Why do you think that it's not okay to put this in the settings file even if your repository is private?
Yeah, if someone removes it, it's still in history.
But say I have a private repository on GitHub and I'm being lazy,
and my company has all of the security settings locked down on GitHub.
Why shouldn't I put it in the code even in that case?
Or why is it less than that? Yes?
Yes, because people don't stay in organizations forever,
and you probably don't want to be rotating that every time you have someone leave the company.
That's not really scalable.
There are better ways of storing secret keys.
You can set environment variables.
There are some newer vault-based methods that are even better than setting environment variables.
We can talk more about that in detail at some point.
The method that Heroku still basically uses if you're using that by default is it sets an environment variable.
But if you're setting up something internally, you want to use a vault to store all of your secrets
and have those only be accessible at runtime.
Yes? Was there a question?
Oh, okay.
I will not ask you to divulge any organization-specific secrets as funny as they may be.
Session data stealing. Don't use pickle. Just don't.
Pickles are for delis, not for software.
Session stealing.
If you got this far, you can have Session Cookie be on the same site.
This is the warning in the Django docs about using cookie-based sessions,
which the reason that you would want to is a performance reason,
where if you don't want to be checking your database every time to check for sessions,
then maybe a cookie-based session makes sense.
I would say start with a database-backed and then put caching on top of it,
both of which Django has first-class support for.
You probably don't need to use cookie-based sessions.
It goes through all of the things that we talked about here.
The secret key is not kept secret, and you are using the pickle serializer.
This can lead to arbitrary remote code execution on your server.
So, one, don't use pickle.
Anyone in possession of the secret key can generate falsified session data,
which your site will trust.
And the session data is signed but not encrypted.
So the session data can be read by the client.
So if you had, for instance, a rootkit or something,
then they would be able to read that data.
And as many of you saw, the vulnerability got trickier in Django 2.2.
If you didn't get this far, that happens a lot.
This was one of the more challenging vulnerabilities.
It was also the vulnerability that when I was updating this tutorial from Django 1.4
to Django 2.1 last year and then Django...
I didn't have to do anything going from 2.1 to 2.2, thankfully.
But one of the things that changed was in Django 1.7, or prior to Django 1.7,
all you needed was the user ID and the secret key,
and you could sign whatever you wanted.
And you would believe it.
Now you need additionally the hashed password of that user
in order to masquerade as someone else.
But as I was explaining to a few of you one-on-one,
we can get that if we have a dump of the database.
So if they've somehow acquired even the hashed password,
which is normally not going to help you as an attacker,
but you're also using signed cookie-based sessions,
you're not going to have a great day.
Oh.
And that's just what I was showing right there.
Testing.
How many tests did this project have?
None. None is the correct answer.
How many tests should it probably have had?
I hear one or two.
Presumably at least as many as security assertions
as I was making in the comments in the code.
So the comments in the code that said
users such and such shouldn't be able to access that.
Testing.
There are limits to how much you can test.
You should also assert that you get a 404 or particular response status codes.
You want to make sure that both you cover the happy path
and that the unhappy path is unhappy in the way that you expect it to be unhappy.
For example, when we were...
And then, sorry, to continue with that, when we found bugs,
so for example, when we found that another user could modify someone else's pet
just by being logged in,
it would have been good to create a test that first failed
and then fix it so that at least from that point forward you're covered.
So keeping security in your testing and in your continuous integration pipeline
as much as possible is another good first step.
The last kind of note that I'll touch on in terms of best practices
is remember that libraries run with full privilege.
So if you're using a dependency from PyPI,
make sure you're only using trusted sources,
pin your dependencies, get up-to-date versions,
read the diff, subscribe to appropriate security newsletters,
and turn on GitHub security vulnerabilities.
These are super useful,
and they are turned on by default for any open source project.
You do have to go in and manually turn them on for private repositories
or organization repositories,
but for example, when I went to go update this repository,
it said I had potential security vulnerabilities in my dependencies.
And I was using a...
I think it was on 2.1.2 for Django,
and there had been a security vulnerability that was patched in 2.1.6.
And GitHub helpfully links to the actual description of the vulnerabilities
and makes it really easy for me to see why it was vulnerable.
It will also send you an email every week,
so it's a great way to keep up-to-date on all of your dependencies,
at least at a very basic level.
It also works for Ruby and NPM,
and GitHub is doing the community a great service by having this available.
A couple of other resources like pyup and requires.io
are services that you can...
I think they have free versions.
You can also pay them a small amount of money,
and they will look at your requirements file
or wherever you're defining requirements,
and whenever there are updated versions,
they will even submit a pull request to your site if you configure them that way,
so it's a pretty easy way to keep track of what dependencies are
and aren't out of date, at least for your Python dependencies.
Resources.
This is a laundry list of various resources that are related to security,
and I mentioned most of them earlier.
You'll have a copy of these slides.
They're actually in a hidden URL on the website.
You had access to them the whole time.
You just didn't realize it.
Are there any other resources that people have found
that they'd like to recommend or call out?
Yes.
A lot of them open source, both on ZetAttackProxy
and the other ones on WebM.
Yes, that is absolutely true.
ZetAttackProxy.
There's also a checklist that Django helpfully provides.
For those of you who are asking,
what are some things that I should know in terms of basics
when I'm deploying my web app with Django?
Django has great documentation and has been very helpful in terms of...
This is a list of things that you can go through
to make sure that you're setting things up for best practices.
It'll tell you about check, dash, dash, deploy.
It tells you about certain critical settings, like secret key and debug.
A few of you noted that our web app had debug set to true,
which in older versions of Django would actually dump everything
in your settings file at one point, even including the secret key.
It used to be even easier to exploit websites.
In 2.2, debug equal true will not dump all of your settings necessarily.
It definitely doesn't output your secret key.
It knows to redact that now.
They've done a lot of things to help protect people from themselves.
There used to be crawlers out there that would go looking for sites
with debug equal true.
I'm sure there are still old versions, deployed apps out there
using old versions of Django,
where if you left debug equal true turned on,
you probably had been hacked and didn't know it.
This also goes through a number of other settings.
It's quite useful from just a,
am I doing the bare minimum to make sure my site is up and running?
A few other resources that you can run yourself against your own site.
We talked about GitHub security vulnerabilities.
Metasploit and burp suite are both in the vein of the attack suite
that someone in the audience mentioned that OAS provides.
Google dorking, make sure that your site doesn't show up in those queries.
InMap is a way to check to see which ports are open on your site.
Unless you're doing something really fancy,
it should probably just be 443 and 80.
80 should just redirect to your 443 site.
Jack the Ripper is a tool that will run through common passwords
and attempt to crack passwords in your database.
This is the GitHub link, which is poorly formatted.
But you already have this.
Finally, I just want to give thanks to all of the following people
who contributed to this tutorial in one way or another.
It wouldn't be here without the work of a lot of people.
I really appreciate you all coming today.
I'm happy to pause at this point and answer any questions
that may not have been answered thus far.
Yes?
I did. I had to change the same site.
I think I glossed over that.
Yes, the overarching middleware is still on.
I did have to change this setting.
The default of lax still makes it more difficult to perform CSRF queries.
I think I changed it to none. I'd have to go back and check the code.
Yes?
How do you check that no one can do a post from an iframe?
How do you know if your website is not vulnerable?
The very short answer is it's really, really tricky to know
that your site absolutely isn't vulnerable
because it's a cat and mouse game.
What you can do...
One, you can get penetration testing done,
which I recommend if your company doesn't do penetration.
That will give you a little bit more assurance.
The second is to be wary of changing defaults
unless you understand why you're changing them or what the need is.
Yes?
Yes.
Is this the CSRF token?
Oh, okay. Let me see.
The question was, is there something in the code
that tells you about the CSRF token?
How do you turn it off?
The CSRF middleware is activated by default in settings.
It's one of the things that's turned on.
The first thing is that by default,
all of your views will use Django's CSRF protection.
The second thing is you would want to check
that any forms in your templates have that CSRF token tag.
Then the last thing you would want to check
is to disable CSRF explicitly.
You would use that at CSRF exempt decorator on your view.
If you're not using that and you have CSRF middleware turned on
and you're using the CSRF token tag,
then you'll be using the default for Django security.
You can also set, if you wanted to,
you could set the same site session cookie to strict,
and there are a bunch of other cookie settings
that you can set in Django.
The deleting, so how could you delete everything?
There was not a, because that view for deleting everything
had the at CSRF exempt decorator on it,
so it was not doing CSRF checking.
Okay, yes?
Is there a way that your framework can default
requiring the CSRF token?
Not that I know of, which I find annoying as well.
If you find it, please message the entire group and let me know,
because I don't think there is.
Yes?
Yes, that is great.
I should have added that.
Ponycheckup.com.
I will add a note to send that out after the tutorial.
And the last thing that I've been asked to do
is give you the survey link.
So this is a survey that, as far as I know,
I don't see the results of.
This is purely for the PyCon organizers,
so they know what people got out of the tutorials
that they went to and ways that they can improve.
I think they may send me, like, in the past,
they have not shared any of the results with instructors.
I think they may send, like, rolled up results to help us improve,
but all of this is entirely anonymous.
It won't be associated with you in any way that I can see it.
So I know this would help out PyCon's organizers
and would definitely appreciate if you have the time to complete it.