Welcome everyone.
I just want to give a brief introduction.
So my name is Marietta and I'm one of the Python core developers.
I come from Vancouver, Canada and I work at Zapier building web applications with Django.
But in the past few years I've contributed to open source and I've built various web services with AIO HTTP.
I think it's a cool library that we all should know about.
So that's why I wanted to give this tutorial.
I'm just going to introduce my co-presenter, Andrew Swetlov.
Hi, I'm Andrew from Kiev, Ukraine.
I'm also a Python core developer.
I work mostly on async.io part of Python and I'm an author of AIO HTTP and current container.
I'm a Python trainer.
To help today I have two TAs, Stefan and...
Do you want to introduce yourself?
Alright, yeah, they are Stefan, Python core developer and...
Svetl... Svetl... Svetl... Sorry.
Svetl... Svetl... Sorry.
Yes, he's been building some GitHub bots together and he uses AIO HTTP so we're all in good hands.
Before I start I just want to mention about this postage.
So the green ones, if you are going through as we go through the tutorial and you're doing good, you finish the exercise, you can put that up so I know that you're done.
But if you have troubles you can put out the red one and one of us will look into it with you.
So if you don't have one I think we have them at the front there.
Alright, so let's talk about AIO HTTP. What is AIO HTTP?
It is a web framework for async.io. If you're familiar with Django or Flask this is another of that kind of framework.
So what is... Oh, before I start again.
I just want to make sure everybody has Python 3.7 installed. Yes?
Alright, and you have all the requirements installed. There is an update to the requirements file.
A couple hours ago you might need to reinstall. Sorry about that.
And you can test if you have Python 3.7 by running this code.
This portion down here is just a list of documentations that you might want to refer to but we're not going to go through this in details but it's there if you need them.
And again the URL of this is in the class notes. You can check them out.
Alright, now let's go back to async.io. What does it mean to be asynchronous?
I just want to give a brief example just to get ourselves quickly familiarized with async.io and then we can go into the web service web framework.
Suppose you have a long running task and you need to run them multiple times.
Traditionally when you run Python code you will start one task, wait for it to finish and then run another task.
Right? And this is a small code example to demonstrate that.
So suppose I have this task that can take time. I would have to run them one by one.
And you can see the output. That's an extra one. The correct output is down here.
You will see that start a task, finish, start another task, finish and then start another task.
And the total time, it takes a while.
Now how is async.io different? With async.io the different tasks will be started simultaneously and then finished at different times.
So the total time takes, it's shorter than if you are to run that synchronously.
So I'm just going to show an example like how to get started with async.io.
So suppose the regular, the user function will look like this.
Start time, begin, sleep time.
Sorry.
Awake. And you would run it like this, right? Say two seconds.
And it's kind of small but that's how it works. And if you have more than one, you would call it multiple times like this.
It takes time so I'm not going to run too many.
So now how do we convert this into async.io?
So the first step is adding the async. Just like that.
Now this is called a coroutine. But you can't, the way you run it is not by just simply running the code.
It does not work. It will complain like that is coroutine, was never awaited, this is not how you run it.
So to run this, you have three options. One is by using async.io.run.
And then async.io.run that. I'm just running it in here.
What's my async.py? So that's the output. So now it's running. You see the code is being executed.
That is one way to execute the async coroutine.
Another way to execute the coroutine is calling await.
Like that.
Right? That is the right way. But it will complain that await outside of function.
That's still not right. So basically you will need to do async.io.
You will create another coroutine.
Run task.
Something like that. This is just to show you how you would execute, like call another coroutine from another coroutine.
Maria, for correctness you have to replace time sleep with...
Oh yes, that is right. Sorry. Async.io.time sleep. Yes, await. That is a coroutine. Thank you.
So now it's running. So that's just a brief example. And it's not exciting.
So the next one. This has a more complete example. You can take a look at that.
Now, again let's go back to AIO HTTP. Now we know about async.io. It can help us save time. You can run things concurrently.
But what can we do about it? What can we do with it?
The web frameworks like Django and Flux, they do not support async.io. So if you need to use async.io with those web frameworks, you can do that.
So this is where you might need to use an async web framework like AIO HTTP.
And I want to give a brief example like how using AIO HTTP to do web scraping.
Because it seems like everybody wants to scrap data from the internet and use it and analyze.
This is just a fun little example. Say I would like to scrape web 8010.
First I'll show you how it's done without AIO HTTP. Usually you would use request library.
Client.py. Import request. And with request is easy. Request get.
Whoops. Is that content?
Client.py. So it's going and it's fetching data. It's straightforward.
Now let's try to do this in AIO HTTP. Remember we need to have a coroutine that does things.
And the code to do that is...
So is AIO HTTP run app.
No, no, no. Just async.io run for client.
With AIO HTTP.
Client. Session.
With...
Async please.
And square brackets to create a class.
You need instance of client session.
I like it.
I mean just this one.
So it will look like this.
So it looks similar except you will need to have coroutines to do that.
Wait.
URL.
Maybe.
And text is a function.
So that is...
It's not text.
What's going on?
Please switch back.
Wait. No, no, no. That's fine.
Return back.
Wait.
Data text.
It's okay but get is also a coroutine.
So...
Thank you.
Alright. So now we got the data.
So that is AIO. That is fetching data with AIO HTTP.
And let's go to the next section.
I showed... I provided some right up here.
So you can take a look.
But it shows similar to the previous example.
Well, fetching data one by one takes longer time compared to if you were doing this with AIO HTTP.
Where it would start downloading about at the same time.
And then this short one will be completed first.
And so on. So it takes much faster.
So I think it's useful if you need to do web scraping or lots of long running tasks like this.
And the reason why AIO HTTP is nice is because it provides the framework for both client and server.
Whereas with Django it's mostly a framework for building a server.
Usually you would use it with request library as well to fetch data.
That's what we do at Zapier.
So with AIO HTTP you get both. So it's less dependencies to be installed.
Yeah. Any questions so far?
Let me read a couple of words.
The real difference is...
The real reason why do you want to use async server.
When you have pretty good libraries like Django, Flask, whatever.
It's a responsibility.
Because if many users ask your server and server should do some relative long tasks.
Like go to another server, ask Facebook, GitHub for something.
If your architecture is built on microservices, you have many network communications.
And with Django you can do it for sure.
But Django starts, I don't know, 30 workers for a node.
It means that 30 parallel requests can be processed and 31st is blocked.
It's wait for a free node.
In async AIO you can start tens of thousands, hundreds of thousands of parallel requests.
And if one request processing is waiting for response from GitHub, another one, all other responses are working.
It's fine.
It also allows to avoid a very popular problem.
When almost all your requests are processed very fast.
But if one request per 10,000 is slow and load is high enough.
You can quickly overload server.
Server will be busy on processing that slow responses.
It's not the case for async frameworks.
And next reason, it's pretty interesting by the way, is a memory.
Because in Django you fork 30 processes.
Typical web server consumes, I don't know, 300, 500 megabytes.
So you very quickly go to memory limit.
And you cannot fork 100 workers on the server.
The server is not very powerful.
In IO-GTB and in any async framework in general, you can use less workers to handle giant amount of requests.
And a worker when it process hundreds, hundreds of thousands of requests consumes a little more memory than processing one request.
So your limit is still close to a tray of 500 megabytes.
But you can run much more.
You can process much more users with the same memory.
If you have extra memory, leave it for radius, for caching, for everything.
It's better usage than just clone, Python process in classic way.
So this was the reasons.
That's great. Yeah, thank you for the explanation.
Any questions so far?
Yes.
Looks like question for me.
First, client session use async IO internal objects.
So lifetime of session should be shorter, should be inside of lifetime of running loop.
This is the reason why you cannot create session on import time.
It's not limitation of synchronic code.
Technically, you can create a session inside constructor.
But you should create object with this constructor from asynchronous code.
So violation, this rule is, for example, on import time loop.
Well, it doesn't exist, event loop, Python event loop, async IO event loop.
If you ask for loop, async IO creates an instance if you are in the main thread.
But if you go async IO run, async IO creates a new loop.
So session is coupled with async IO loop inside.
If you run another loop, then was used on session creation.
Program just hands, nothing happened.
That's why I added such protection.
Another question is, how many client session should you use?
It's interesting.
Client session is an abstraction which contains cookies, client cookies, and connection pool.
So simultaneous request for the same session from different async IO task reuse this loop.
It's a very handy feature because opening connection takes time.
If you want to connect to Google, Python, or whatever,
connection is not established, is not for free.
And IHTP allows to not shut down connection just after getting a page.
It keeps it active for a while and close only after some period.
So using a session for several requests makes sense.
How many sessions do you need?
Maybe, this is a suggestion, start from using only one session.
Or maybe you can manually split your outcome in request to big groups like
those requests are for Facebook and those are for Google.
Having two sessions, one for Facebook, one for Google, maybe makes sense.
Maybe you don't need it.
It's, again, depends.
Session has a parameter like how many parallel connections it supports.
Default value is not too big, it's about 100.
Because without additional steps, a limitation for amount of open sockets for process is 1024.
You can increase it, but it requires additional steps on server setup.
So you should keep in mind also this one.
Also if you use session for scraping the whole Internet, you probably get too many cookies.
It can be also a problem.
Session saves cookies inside.
It keeps cookies sent by server.
If you use for everything and touch too many files, cookie storage can grow in memory.
And again, maybe you need it, maybe not.
Again, depends.
But better to try from a single session for everything if you can.
And after that add new ones.
Or use a new session for any new request, but it's not the fastest way to work with Internet.
It's not how TCP sockets like to communicate.
That's it.
So the next section, so that's brief introduction.
And thank you, Andrew.
I think this is the fun part at least for me.
Let's all start writing our own AIO HTTP session and server.
And I will start by showing different pieces of building up a server.
But at the end of this, we have provided some kind of an exercise where we will be building a server
where you can create blog posts, retrieve the blog posts, edit them, upload the files.
And the full example, full working example is in this link.
But maybe we'll go through, try to create one of this at the end of this section.
So, all right.
Now we have the requirements.
All right.
A simple web server.
Start by defining the request handler.
Server.py.
And feel free to follow along or just watch.
So this is a request handler.
It's a coroutine.
It accepts a request and then returns a hello world, just a text.
And next we need to create the application.
So we created the AIO HTTP web application.
And we're telling it we're going to create the root URL, the slash URL.
And that it will be whenever somebody hits the slash URL, we'll execute this handler coroutine.
So we will see hello world.
And then just run the app.
Okay.
And then just run it.
Now server is running.
We can open it in the browser.
And you'll see hello world.
I'll give people some time to just try along.
Deal.
One point to the address of the server.
I know that now zero person is going to be.
For zeros works on Linux, on Mac OS, as I see.
But if I recall correctly, Windows does not resolve this address.
But you can use localhost or 127.001.
Like this, 001.
I got the same thing here.
Just put out the green one if you're done.
Just so I know, have an idea how many people are trying it.
Okay, that's easy.
That's straightforward.
Seems like you all got it.
Next.
That's fine.
Right.
The other way to define URLs.
So when you define URLs, notice this is a list.
So you can always, if you need another URL you want to create,
you can just put it in the URL.
And then you can define the URL.
So you can define the URL.
So you can always, if you need another URL you want to create,
you just add another URL.
And it will, and the order matters, right?
We will process from top to bottom?
Yes.
It matters when you start using variable URLs with placeholders for variables.
But that I will show right now.
So that is how you would create another URL.
The other way to create URL is by adding decorators.
So this is, if you're familiar with Flask, they have the same feature there,
but not Django, I think not Django.
So like that.
Another.
So instead of calling add routes, we just do routes here.
Restart the server.
And run it.
Hello world.
Another.
There it is.
So if you want to try it out.
The difference from Flask is in Flask you create an application or blueprint first,
and then use application instance to add URLs by decoration.
In IOTP we decide to use different way.
Routes is basically a list with helper methods like get, you see.
A list with additional methods to add objects to this list.
And when you have a route table filled with your URLs,
you should explicitly add it to application.
The reason you can separate route tables, list of routes, from application creation.
You should not create an application on import time.
You can do it from inside an async function.
You can do it later.
And for async IOU it's important because application is async IOU object.
It has a loop inside also.
And the same reason as for session exists for application.
Lifetime of application should be inside of lifetime of loop.
So you have to create application from async code.
Well, it's not 100% true.
You see, in this example we create an application early.
But again, it's a good practice to use function,
initialization function for application creation.
And probably we will duplicate this usage later.
Who knows.
And examples from our tutorial site demonstrates
you need app async function usage.
So this is recommended way.
Okay, I will just copy paste that.
Okay, next.
Sometimes you want to have arguments and parameters to your URL.
For example, having say you want to have a username parameter in the URL.
Like dynamically instead of hard coding the URL.
You can use that like curly braces here.
And it's the same way if you were to do this without the decorator.
I like to use the decorator.
So the code examples here are using the decorator.
So let's try this.
And to retrieve the value of this parameter,
you will get it from the request, match info and get the username.
That's the variable here.
So let's do that.
And try it out.
And there you go.
And you can type any name.
So another way to parameterize URLs.
If in the get request you might want to have the request, the get parameters.
Like if you're familiar with the URL, this part of the URL, you can do that too.
And then the code looks like this.
Instead of the match info, you'll get URL query.get.
Let's add that in.
So now this thing works page one or something like that.
So that's a brief example.
I'm sure you'll use it for more complicated situations.
Any questions so far?
So far our server only handles get requests.
But you will probably need like post or put and all that.
And you can definitely do that by simply changing instead of get, you will do post there.
Actually I will do it here.
So now the grid user only accepts post requests.
We cannot simply go through this URL on the browser anymore.
You will need to use a client to fetch this resource.
And you will probably want to retrieve the data from the post method.
So you will call await request.post and get the data like that.
Nice question.
Because in the post you can send a huge HTTP payload.
So you can send 20 gigabyte files.
Maybe it's too much, but megabytes is pretty common.
You can send a picture from your cell phone.
And reading it takes time.
Maybe you want to get it instantly.
Maybe you want to get it by chunks.
Or one chunk by next to other.
Say reading only megabyte chunk, process it and do next.
In case of HTTP forms, HTML forms, you want also maybe to process it in a stream order.
Not to load everything in memory like we have in post.
But use more complex code and process field by field in sequence.
All these reasons are for adding await here.
Await is a sign of some IO, input-output operation.
And how HTTP works.
You can read a header which contains path and HTTP headers.
And you are ready to start processing request.
Next you can read a body.
Two different operations.
The same in client.
Remember client example.
You do client head, await client get.
Get response object back.
And for getting response content, you should use await response text.
Or await response JSON.
Or work with multi-part encoding.
Whatever.
Use the streaming content.
All these operations require additional input-output.
And every input-output is awaitable.
It's an asynchronous function.
We explicitly want to do it.
It would be design decision to fetch the whole content of request before starting processing web handler.
But it's obviously easy to lead to memory leak.
If you want to do it, do it in application code.
If you want to have all requests in memory, we cannot forbid.
But you do it on your own.
Not on our library.
So this is the reason.
Another question.
Yep.
Are you able to stack the message from your REST API from users?
Stack?
If I have a...
This is what you're thinking about, right?
You see.
Just decorate twice.
Register your handler twice.
Request has method property.
If you want to, if your code is organized in this way, you can do it.
Sometimes it's convenient, sometimes not.
But you can.
How do you retrieve the method from the request?
Request.method.
Method that will give you get or post.
Request is a relatively big object with many methods and properties.
You can open HTTP documentation for full description.
Also, HTTP has a lot of narrative documents describing how to work in different cases,
how to operate with it.
This is a reference.
This is the documentation here.
Yes.
In Quick Start and Advanced Usage pages, we describe some requests and response aspects and usages.
All right.
Great.
Let's go back.
Okay.
Where were we?
We were doing a post.
Because we made this a post, we can no longer access it from the website like this.
You can try out your post request by doing the client, from the client.
Basically, if you put in the ad user.
Whoops.
Let's restart my server.
I need to put before that because the other man.
Yes.
While Marietta changes code, let's see why the order is important.
User name, greeting user, has a variable in URL.
And it variable matches any text in URL path segment.
So if you push ad user after getting user name, ad user will never match because its request will be swallowed by former handler.
So if you have a variable URL and just constant one, usually you have to put constant first.
URLs in HTTP is a list logically and it iterates hour and hour looking for first match, not for best because there is no good definition for best matching.
HTTP doesn't decide.
You have a variable, you have a strict string and if request URL matches to string, use this strict.
No.
No such complex logic.
Go from top to bottom and select the first match.
So I just want to give example like how you can do the post using the AIO HTTP client.
So what I did is I added the URL here pointing to my local server and passing in the JSON object user name.
And that's because my ad user.
It's not JSON technically but it will be form.
Yes.
Yeah, multi-part.
It's expecting the user name here.
And let's try that out.
So I have my server running.
So I received the response from my server.
So give that a try if you like.
All right.
The next example I want to show is returning a JSON instead of a plain text like that.
And the only difference is just you replace the web response with JSON response.
It's pretty simple and straightforward.
But internally data are encoded completely differently, you know.
JSON looks like Python dictionary, pretty close.
And post data, it has two encoded forms, as it is, ampersand and equal.
Like in parameters, query parameters in get and another one is multi-part encoding.
We will show you how it looks like after next session.
Right.
So whoops, go back to my server restarted.
And the get JSON URL.
What am I doing wrong?
Did you use JSON in URL?
I think you in browser, not get but just JSON.
Of course.
Yes.
Okay, now it returns JSON.
All right.
Yes.
To my code.
Terminal.
Yes.
That's a request, yeah.
Ah.
Looks weird.
Okay.
When I started to write web framework, I learned a lot.
And technically get can have a body.
Maybe you're surprised, but it can.
Also delete can have a body.
So I agree, looks strange.
But better to use post for this example.
But yes, it's a polyquest body.
All right.
Maybe we should remove this to confuse people.
Later.
All right.
What's the next one?
Do you think you can give this example?
Yes.
Let's use this laptop.
So in web application, usually you need to use a database or another long-living object.
And in IOTP, the best place for initializing and closing objects like database connection is cleanup context.
Let's call it signal.
So you see, we have a neat application.
Okay.
I'm not good in Mac, but at least pointer works.
So we have an application.
We add routes here and we register a coroutine.
Actually, it's asynchronous generator with yield inside to create a database connection.
And we use asynchronous library for SQLite.
Usually in your real code, you want to use MySQL or Postgres or real big databases.
But for tutorial, we choose SQLite because it's already present.
It doesn't require installing a server on your laptop and good enough for demonstration.
So we connect to SQLite database.
This is file name where database live.
Initialize the connection and store in application.
Application works like a dictionary.
It has square brackets or operator.
So you can push everything what you want into application on initialization stage before your server ready to serve requests on time of server starting.
Then we have yield.
Many Python libraries use this approach.
So before yield is initialization, but after yield is finalizing.
You can avoid closing database connection, but usually I want to be accurate.
If you create a resource, please close it.
So this is how it looks like.
There are different ways to do it for sure.
You have good and recommended example here.
In web handler, you can get a database from request config.
We used DB for storing in application.
We get the value back from request.
And use standard DB functions to execute some SQL query, get result, commit it and so on.
And add JSON.
We have an example.
Full example here.
Click and learn.
It has methods for working with REST API.
List posts, create new posts, get detailed information about specific posts by its number, delete it and update.
Every method is really tedious.
But you can learn it.
Our database structure is here.
We have integer post ID, title, post content, and owner and editor fields.
We will use these fields later in session part.
The idea is owner is the person who creates a post and editor is the last editor, last updater.
Full example.
It's really not very long but still sizable.
And I recommend to learn it yourself to briefly read this code.
We make a database if it doesn't exist.
We use a DB path in the root of our repository to share the same database file between this section and next one.
And what else?
Time for questions maybe.
Is everything clear?
Yep.
No.
This one.
Middleware is a wrapper around requests.
So when a server has a request, it can execute a code before request handling and after it.
But DB is just a single function for establishing connection to database and closing it.
It's called not for every request but only once at server startup.
And last part after yield is called server shutdown.
Does that work exactly?
It works like context manager decorator.
Maybe showing the code is too much but let's go to standard Python documentation.
There is a context lib standard library.
What's up?
Yes, we are here.
I'll increase the size.
Not too much.
And we have a context manager and example.
Yes, like this.
You have an initialization part, then yield something and finalization part.
And you can use it with managed resource.
It's a very, very common way to organize code in Python.
And HTTP uses the same technique but it yields nothing because returned object cannot be used by HTTP.
You just create a connection and push it explicitly into application under some your name.
And how to make it work?
Initialize, call a next function, then get an iterator, iterate asynchronously, iterate one time.
And on shutdown, I think iterate next step.
Any other question?
Good question.
First, I suggest try to find asyncIO library.
Maybe you want to use it.
If not, I think I still can execute synchronous code in thread pool.
Again, for image resizing later we will have a demonstration how it works.
But briefly it looks like you say execute this function, this code with that argument in a thread pool.
And the call returns object which is awaitable.
So you use result is equal await run in executor synchronous code.
And when synchronous code result is ready, you get control flow back and you can do it.
Sometimes it works very well.
It works always. It doesn't fail.
But using synchronous request library this way is not a very good choice if you have IOGDP client.
If you have asynchronous library, usually it performs better in asynchronous.
I think I will. But you have a backup plan anytime.
Another question?
Okay, let's go to the next section.
The next section is client.
Client, yes.
A minute.
Sure.
Server.
Oh, no, sorry.
It's not a tutorial.
This is our guy.
And we have a client.
So we have a REST server.
REST is a programming API.
Our server accepts JSON requests and returns JSON responses back.
It's for programmers, not for end users.
We don't write fancy pages with images, animation, whatever.
So usually if you have a REST server, you want to have a REST client for it to work with.
Client is a set of handy helper methods.
So at first, we are working with a simple blocking engine.
We have a post entity.
We send post to server and get post or list of posts back.
We can use for sure dictionaries for post data.
But I have several reasons against plain dictionaries.
Mainly because dictionary is not structured well.
It can have any fields.
You have no idea what fields are.
It has no typing information for type checking.
It's just everything.
That's why we use post data class.
A brief description.
Data class is a class which is decorated with data class decorator.
Frozen means post cannot be changed after creation.
Post fields cannot be updated.
It's immutable class.
I prefer to use immutables if I can, especially for data classes.
It has several fields and a method to print post content.
Nothing really interesting.
Client.
So we have a client for our REST API.
Client is initialized with URL to our server and username.
Username is used for owner and editor fields.
We save URL, save user and we create client session here.
The next thing is a handy helper.
It raises an exception if returned status code of response returned by server is not in 200 area.
200, 201.
If server returns 400 bad request or 400, 3 forbidden, 400, 4 not found, 500 server is in trouble.
All these responses are converted into exceptions by Ioctp.
You should not check it yourself.
We also have a close method.
Usually if you have some async Io object, you should close it sometimes.
You can avoid it, but it's not a very good idea.
We have a client.
Client has a close method, IoctpClient.
That's why we in turn add a close method to our client, not to Ioctp embedded object,
but to our REST client, which closes embedded object.
This is an example for list method to get a list of our posts.
Type hint in here.
The idea is pretty simple.
Using our internal Ioctp client session, make a request, return, get response back,
convert this response into a list of post objects.
Make URL is a helper function.
It's private because usually nobody from outside wants to use it.
User code of your client calls, lists, get update, whatever.
Do not call, make URL method.
But what it does, it constructs a real URL used for this call.
Let's assume our server is started on localhost 8080.
To list our posts, we should call localhost 8080-API here.
The idea is pretty simple.
Also, sometimes you need to return headers, for example, authorization headers,
to sign your request to different things.
But we avoid this complexity.
You got my idea how to make it more robust and satisfy your requirements.
Usage.
We have a client now, not an Ioctp client, but our client wrapper around Ioctp session.
We initialize it with URL and username and use await client list to get posts and print them.
It can be improved.
People usually don't like to use try finally, but the real situation is even worse.
Many people cannot use it properly.
I personally made such mistakes several times, like pushing client inside a try and it's a perhubung error.
So, this statement is much more handy.
For asynchronous world, we have async with.
The difference is in old good with statement, you cannot do asynchronous code in enter and exit dunder methods.
But I think with... Sorry, forgot to change this example to fix it.
I think with can do it.
So, I think with client do everything on exit from this block, client will be closed.
And I really sorry, should be a enter and a exit to work with async with.
It's a new asynchronous magic method.
There are async def.
This code is used to enter the context and async def a exit, sorry again, closes our client.
So, again, full client is much more complex.
The beginning is pretty same.
We have a post data class, we have a client with all required methods like get, delete, update.
But we want to provide not only a class, but command line interface.
Like... Sorry.
Give me now.
Write and code client.
So, we have a command line too with POSIX standard command line interface with help, with bells.
And we had it using click.
So, let me make a full example.
Let's start a server.
Yes, we have a server here.
REST server and client say list.
It's empty.
Let's use create command from here.
Create.
What is create API?
I should provide title and content.
Like this.
Sorry.
Should be text.
We created a post, then list says we have one post.
Also, get.
Let's see the full information about the post.
You can try delete and update on your own.
What is the tricky part of it?
It's integration of synchronous click.
Click is awesome library.
I love it almost.
Except some parts.
But click is a synchronous one.
So, this is standard click usage like we have a base group for main command.
You have commands in name and group to get create and post everything.
I want to use asynchronous code from this command.
So, I think dev create to call my client, REST client.
It's achieved by this decorator.
Which, see, this decorator may be a little complex, but this is the idea.
We provide a wrapper which runs our internal asynchronous function and return result back.
Also, click has a context.
Context is a global object for click.
We can push into this context our own class.
So, in the root click command, we create a root object passing URL user here.
And this root object from here has an asynchronous method.
Async context manager.
Like just context manager I showed you before from context sleep from here.
But Python has also async context manager.
The same, but you can use await from async.
So, we have a helper which creates a client, returns it, and closes after the usage.
And in our click command handlers, we use for async with client, do something, and go away.
So, that's it about client.
Do you have questions?
Do you need time maybe to try yourself?
I'll just mention that there's a break at 3 o'clock, so we'll try this out on your own and then take the break at 3 o'clock and come back after 20 minutes.
I can.
Let me switch to code editor.
I use Mariata's laptop and sorry.
Let me switch to my own.
Because I don't know how to type properly on Mac.
I prefer Linux.
Linux and Emacs.
Doesn't anybody use Emacs?
Good.
So,
I recall how to change font by command, but
this is a problem.
No, sorry, too long.
Let me use simple editor.
And where is the font size here?
Small to small, properties, preferences.
Yes, here we are.
Not default, but something really big.
Enough, no?
Yes, we'll do.
Okay, so, you know, thank you, Seth.
We want to use, I think, this statement.
Let me save it as Python to enable colorizing.
Yes, looks better.
But still colorizing, don't like async vault.
I cannot solve it.
So, we have a class which has an init constructor.
Just as placeholder, that's fine.
And we need to implement async enter.
Return self.
And need to implement async exit.
Exit self.
Well, xtype, xvalue, xtraceback.
We don't need all of them, but do something.
Closing.
And it's async function, so we can use await.
Awake async, you'll sleep.
Just for example.
It works pretty well.
But you have to write a class.
You have to split logic between a enter and a exit.
And it's not very convenient if you want to quickly just initialize something.
Return control flow back to the callee.
And close.
So, what can we do?
We can write async function which do initialize part.
Then yield something.
Like, well, to be more concrete, client is iohtp client session.
Then yield client.
Then use await client close.
The problem is this function, it's generator.
It's pretty readable, simple.
But cannot be used with async with statement.
I think with func does not work as client.
We want to do something like resp is...
Let's use canonical way.
Async with client get URL as response and print response status.
Our function has no a enter and a exit.
But we can make a decorator.
Decorator is pretty easy.
Should I display it? Maybe not.
Maybe yes.
So, it's projects.
Let me open Python context lib.
And go to async context manager definition.
Not format 12 to this screen size.
Scroll down, scroll down, scroll down again.
So, basically, what do you need?
You need to create this function object.
We have function.
We have generator is function.
We should to get async iterator from it.
Now we are ready to iterate our function.
We should call first iteration.
Await it a next.
Here.
It runs our asynchronous generator to first yield.
And we get result here.
So far so good.
And this part, these two lines could be pushed inside a enter function.
Next part is again it a next to execute await client clause.
Real code has a little more checks, for example, to make sure that our function has only one yield and finished after calling second a next part.
But that's it.
And everything is done by context lib async context manager already in Python 3.7.
Yes.
Again, like Python had already synchronous context manager for many years.
Good idea.
People like it.
And we created asynchronous context manager for it.
Because class writing is not always fun.
People like short code.
Any other question?
Okay.
So let's make a break.
Good.
Okay.
Jaa.
Juhh.
Call.
It's
jiii
joi
no
Jadi, biar saya buka dokumentasi kita.
Tidak di sana.
Ya.
Jadi, rendering HTML.
Menciptakan HTML dengan string concatenasi, itu menjengkelkan.
Dan itu berbahaya.
Biasanya orang menggunakan mesin template.
Dan yang paling terkenal dalam dunia Python adalah Ginger 2.
Oh, sekarang harus lebih baik.
Ya.
Saya mencoba untuk menyelamatkan mata.
Jika Anda tidak memiliki mata, silahkan mengelak.
Jadi, Ginger 2 tidak memiliki pengetahuan tentang IHDP.
Dan IHDP tidak memiliki mesin template yang dianggap.
Tapi kami menawarkan library tertarik.
Ini library tertarik, tapi saya menerima sokongan.
Saya menulisnya, saya menerima sokongan, dan juga IHDP.
Mengapa library yang berbeda?
Karena dekomposisinya adalah ide yang bagus secara umum.
Karena dengan ini, kami menikmati jika IHDP bagus dan cukup selesa untuk membiarkan memasukkan,
untuk contoh ini, mesin template tanpa memubah kod IHDP sendiri.
Jadi, ia berada untuk beberapa alasan.
Kita menuliskan Ginger dan IHDP, dan kita memiliki server yang mudah, dan kita memiliki folder untuk template.
Template di Ginger terlihat seperti kod HTML, dengan yang Anda lihat,
dan juga untuk pembantuan varian.
Ginger juga memiliki sintek untuk flow yang lebih kompleks seperti if-block, 4-block,
template inheritance, dan lain-lain.
Tapi sekarang, kita memiliki template yang mudah.
Selanjutnya, kita harus menggunakan plugin IHDP Ginger 2.
Biasanya plugin ini disiarkan dengan cara ini.
Mereka memiliki metode set up yang mengisinya aplikasi dan parameter-parameter.
Parameternya bergantung pada third party.
Di sini kita memberikan file system loader, yang mengatakan,
menggunakan subfolder template dan melihat templates di folder ini.
Dan kod kita, yang sudah diketahui dari snippet pertama,
disiarkan untuk render template.
Ginger diperbuat dengan cara ini.
Anda membuat diksyonari, menyebutnya konteks.
Diksyonari adalah nama variable konteks, dan nama value diksyonari adalah nama.
Jadi, Anda memiliki konteks, dan Anda meminta template Ginger untuk render.
Ini adalah nama template.
Anda memasang request, dan Anda memasang konteks.
Dan Anda mendapatkan result yang dikoreksi.
Mari kita lihat bagaimana ini berfungsi.
Ini harusnya ada di sini.
Kod 06, templates.
Bagus.
Sekarang, buka link.
Apa?
Maaf.
Mungkin saya harus menyatakan sesuatu.
Jadi, Anda lihat, ini menggantikan nama saya.
Dan, nama page adalah hasil rendering template.
Dan, diubahkan, date dan username.
Anda lihat, date, apa?
Menarik, karena saya tidak menjadikannya.
Dan, username.
Bagus.
Jadi, mari kita menambahkan...
...sebuah sisi pengganti untuk bekerja dengan blog.
Kami memiliki API.
Sekarang, kita memerlukan sesuatu untuk menunjukkan kepada pengganti.
Sekarang, kita memerlukan...
...sebuah page untuk menunjukkan.
Untuk menciptakan baru, untuk menunjukkan yang berada, untuk menerima...
...menjelaskan informasi yang terperinci.
Apa yang saya lupa?
Untuk mengubahnya.
Yang saya ingin menunjukkan juga.
Ada dua cara yang berbeda untuk menggunakan HTTP Ginger 2.
Ini adalah fungsi eksplisit.
Call, render, template, with passing, name, request, and context.
Dan, satu lainnya adalah menggunakan dekorator.
Dan, silahkan, pesanan bergantung.
Pertama, Anda harus menggunakan dekorator, template dekorator, dan kemudian menggunakan route.
Mengapa?
Karena...
...signature web handler terubah.
Anda melihat...
Pertama...
Pertama, kita memiliki fungsi async yang menerima permintaan dan menerima objek respons.
Tetapi, dengan template dekorator, kita memiliki fungsi async yang menerima permintaan.
Pertama, ini menerima...
...diksonari string pada objek.
Ini menerima konteks Ginger.
Dan dekorator mengambil konteks ini dan menghasilkan template.
Ini seperti gula.
Tidak ada apa-apa yang menarik, tapi menyimpan...
...seperti beberapa tali.
Tetapi, kedua-duanya adalah...
...alternatif, mereka melakukan yang sama.
Jadi...
Sekarang saatnya untuk bekerja dengan blog kami.
Kami memiliki page indeks yang menerima semua dari database.
Kami membuat konteks, yang dipanggil RET.
Di conteks ini.
Ini adalah list dikonteks.
Dan kami menerima konteks ini ke template.
Template harus dikendalikan.
Template indeks sedikit mengerikan.
Saya menggunakan template inheritance di sini.
Ginger template inheritance.
Anda bisa membaca lebih banyak tentang site Ginger sendiri.
Tetapi idea ini adalah...
...page index kami menerima base HTML.
Base HTML...
...sekejap.
Di bawah.
HTML dengan dua blok.
Satu blok untuk titel dan satu blok untuk konten.
Dan dengan inheritance kami mengubah...
...blok yang benar di page inheritance.
Mengapa orang melakukannya?
Untuk...
...menyiapkan...
...site styling...
...CSS...
...basis layout, apapun.
Di template base.
Dan menerima template base ini dengan konten benar...
...yang bergantung pada page to page...
...dengan page inheritance.
Jadi...
...dapatkan...
...4 loop.
Ini cara 4 loop terlihat di Ginger, jika Anda tidak tahu.
Dan kami menerima pos di sini.
Seperti...
...referensi A.
Hyperlink.
Jadi...
...itu saja.
Sama untuk...
...menyeditasi.
Tapi...
...menyeditasi sedikit mengerikan.
Biar saya lihat bagaimana terlihat.
Kami memiliki server template.
Dan...
Kami memiliki list pos.
Maaf untuk...
...terkumpulkan titel.
Saya tidak sempurna saat menulis database.
Jadi, ini...
...page dikondisi oleh Ginger.
Menurut saya, ini agak mudah.
Tidak ada colorizing, tidak ada styling.
Anda mendapatkan idea.
Kami memiliki...
...page untuk menunjukkan...
...list pos.
Sekarang saya ingin...
...bicara bagaimana untuk menunjukkan pos.
Untuk menunjukkan, kita perlu...
...menulis yang berikutnya.
Kita harus menunjukkan...
...form HTML.
Menulisnya dengan...
...valu-valu yang berada.
Dan...
Biar saya...
...menunjukkan.
Kami menunjukkan form.
Kami memiliki titel baru.
Kami memiliki konten...
...fancy...
...konten.
Dan ketika saya tekan...
...menulis boton...
...form konten...
...dia akan dihantar ke server kami.
Sekarang kita berada di...
...page yang menunjukkan form.
Sepertinya agak mudah.
Kami memiliki...
...post-edit...
...path.
Kami menulis...
...post dari database...
...dengan post-edit.
Dan...
...menulisnya sebagai...
...konten ginger...
...dan menulis form ini.
Template untuk form rendering...
...ada di sini.
Anda lihat...
...ini form.
Action adalah...
...url untuk menghantar data form.
Kami menggunakan method-post...
...yang dikonsumsi dengan cara yang dikonsumsi.
Jangan menggunakan get jika...
...kalau Anda tidak yakin.
Dan kodin-kodin adalah...
...data form yang berbagai bagian.
Kami memiliki beberapa...
...pada bidang untuk edit...
...submit button.
Itulah.
Ketika saya tekan...
...submit...
...saya menghantar...
...request untuk servis.
Biar saya lakukan.
Klik.
Ya.
Kami memiliki titel yang diubah.
Dan database juga diubah.
Bagaimana itu terjadi?
Data post dihantar dalam form ini.
Anda lihat...
...kodin-kodin yang sedikit kompleks.
Ada dua bagian.
Yang pertama dan kedua.
Ini separator antara...
...bagaimana...
...kalau kami...
...menyelidikan...
...kodin-kodin yang diubah...
...ke...
...tex...
...dan...
...di dalam form kodin-kodin...
...kodin-kodin itu sangat besar.
HTTP tahu bagaimana...
...menyelidikannya.
Jadi, post kita...
...webhandler...
...reit data post.
Semua itu dalam memori, maaf.
Menyelidikannya.
Memori konsumsi.
Tapi saya...
...tidak ingin membuang...
...tutorial ini.
Mari kita simpan...
...secepat mungkin.
Jadi, kita memiliki...
...data post baru.
Kita mengelakkan...
...database...
...kodin-kodin SQL...
...untuk mengubah...
...title dan teks.
Di sini.
Kita harus mengumumkan...
...atau mengubah...
...bagaimana...
...library ini berfungsi.
Dan...
...kita tidak...
...membuang...
...konten baru...
...segera.
Tapi...
...kita akan...
...menerima...
...penggunaan.
Dan browser...
...akan pergi...
...ke lokasi ini.
Tapi dengan...
...metode GET.
Sangat komen...
...di perkembangan web.
Sangat komen teknik.
Yang...
...yang...
...sangat...
...kita harus melakukan...
...penggunaan.
Semua orang...
...seharusnya...
...menerima...
...data post baru.
Jadi...
...kita...
...memiliki...
...seberapa...
...pengetahuan...
...untuk...
...sebarang...
...menunjukkan...
...forma...
...forma baru...
...dan menerima data...
...menerima ke database.
Menunjukkan post, edit post,
menerima data...
...menerima...
...post.
Tidak...
...di REST...
...kita bebas untuk menggunakan...
...patch...
...dan...
...menerima...
...menggunakan...
...browser...
...tanpa JavaScript.
Tidak hanya...
...tentang menerima dan menerima.
Jadi kita butuh...
...lebih...
...menerima...
...menerima.
Dan...
...kita butuh...
...2...
...webhandlers untuk...
...post-edit lagi.
Untuk alasan yang sama.
Satu untuk menunjukkan...
...forma HTML...
...dan...
...salah satu untuk...
...menerima data.
Lihatlah...
...ini adalah...
...fungsi...
...yang dianggap...
...semuanya berhasil.
Saya ingin...
...menyebutkan...
...kita tidak...
...menjadikan...
...menyelidikkan tes untuk tutorial ini.
Dan itu menakutkan...
...sikit.
Biasanya saya...
...menyelidikkan dengan...
...menjadikan tes unit yang bagus, tapi...
...tapi...
...menjadikan...
...tutorial ini...
...menjadikan tes yang bagus.
Mungkin...
...ada yang salah.
Tapi...
...kita coba.
Saya mencoba secara manual.
Text...
...submit...
...seperti...
...text...
...anonymous, karena...
...kita butuh sesi untuk...
...memanfaatkan login, logout...
...teknik...
...text, text...
...new text...
...submit...
...seperti...
...new one...
...dan kita bisa...
...tukar delete...
...postnya hilang.
Mungkin ergonomik...
...tidak...
...tidak sangat bagus, tapi...
...berfungsi dan...
...kamu bisa memperbaikinya jika kamu mau.
Seperti biasa...
...kita punya...
...teks penuh untuk contoh ini.
Sebenarnya...
...menampaknya cukup dekat...
...ke dalam server...
...tapi...
...tidak menerima...
...JSON...
...tapi render HTML page.
Terakhir.
Pesan template Ginger...
...sudah selesai.
Pertanyaan.
Petani
Oh, the other!
atau 302, saya rasa.
Bukan 200.
Ini kode redireksi.
Jika Anda buka tutorial
untuk Django,
untuk Flask,
Anda akan melihat kode yang
kelihatan sangat
serupa dengan yang ini.
Tapi tanpa asing weight syntax.
Semua framework web
di Python
yang bekerja dengan templates,
menciptakan konteks,
mengerjakan,
menerima bentuk,
menerima data baru
ke database,
dan itu saja.
Sebuah bahan selanjutnya adalah
imaj.
Database kita
sebenarnya memiliki
imaj
di
pos
SQL table
dengan jenis bytes.
Ini adalah
blop field.
Biasanya,
Anda ingin menyimpan
imaj Anda
pada CDN
atau Amazon S3,
apapun.
Bukan di database.
Tapi untuk sebab
tutorial,
database itu
sudah cukup baik.
Bagaimana
kita menangani
imaj?
Kita butuh
jenis yang lain
yang dipanggil post-image,
yang dikirimkan dengan nombor
post,
image content dari
database,
dan kembali ke respons
dengan jenis image jpg.
Content itu
image content,
hanya bytes jpg
representasi.
Jika formnya
tidak memiliki imaj,
kita cepat menyerang
kecil
untuk
menunjukkan sesuatu.
Kita memodifkan
template kita
untuk menunjukkan
imaj
dengan
EMG
HTML tag
dengan
source image
yang menandai pada image web handler kita.
Itu saja untuk
menunjukkan.
Saya tidak melihat
imaj di sini,
karena saya harus
menjalin server
lain
dari
section baru.
Jadi,
ya,
lihat,
ini
imaj kecil
dengan sesuatu.
Sesuatu
dengan
teks.
Oke.
Jadi,
konten ini
dimulai dari database.
Untuk menerima
imaj,
kita menerima
form
baru
yang
menolong
meneliti file
dan
klik butang
menerima.
Imaj itu sudah diubah.
Saya tidak
menyiapkan
cat yang
meneliti,
tapi, Anda bisa melakukannya.
Bagaimana
untuk menerima
imaj?
Form mudah.
Langkah selanjutnya
sedikit lebih kompleks.
Lihat,
kita memiliki
form,
kita
mendapatkan
imaj dari form,
dan jika imaj
ada,
kita menerima,
menerima dari database.
Imaj tidak
ada jika saya tidak meneliti file.
Lihat,
jadi,
sekarang,
kita
menukarkan titel,
tapi bukan konten imaj.
Jadi, titel
diubah,
imaj sama.
Dan,
yang juga
saya ingin
tunjukkan,
benar-benar,
imaj
yang diubah,
diubah
ke server,
itu cukup besar.
Imaj
dari dokumen saya,
yang saya
hanya memakainya
dari
telefon saya.
Dan,
saya tidak tahu
berapa banyak megapiksel,
tapi, ukuran itu besar.
Saya ingin mencetakkan
gambar
sebelum menyimpan di database.
Itulah kenapa
saya memiliki
satu lagi corotin
yang menggunakan
imaj
yang menggunakan PIL
untuk mencetakkan data imaj.
Lihat,
kita mendapatkan
konstruksi PIL,
PIL,
Imaj Library,
Imaj Library.
Kita memiliki objek imaj,
kita memiliki
kecil-kecil
menggunakan
alias
yang sangat kuat
aliasin
metode,
mendapatkan imaj baru,
dan menyimpan di database
konten kecil-kecil
imaj.
Dan saya menggunakan run in executor
disini.
Run in executor
itu
untuk alasan yang berikutnya.
Imaj resizing,
terutama resizing dari imaj besar,
mengambil waktu.
Ini adalah
operasi CPU yang berat,
yang dipanggil
operasi CPU bound.
Tapi,
dalam async IOU world,
Anda harus mengelakkan
operasi seperti itu
dalam fungsi async Anda.
Karena resizing
bisa mengambil
waktu,
dan pada waktu resizing,
server Anda
tidak bertanggung jawab.
Ia tidak
menjaga
pengguna lain.
Ia mengambil
waktu,
dan
memanfaatkan
pengguna-guna
yang berat.
Jadi,
async IOU
bisa
menggunakan
CPU bound
atau
operasi sincronis
untuk
mengambil
pengguna-guna
yang berat.
Dan
pengguna-guna
memiliki beberapa pengguna-guna
yang berat
pada async IOU
untuk mengambil
waktu resizing.
Atau 8?
8.
Jadi,
laptop
laptop memiliki 8
pengguna-guna yang berat.
Kami menggunakan kerja baru
untuk pengguna-guna yang berat.
Dalam
pengguna-guna yang berat,
image
resizing.
Kami menunggu
di sini.
Menunggu
berarti server kita
sudah
mengganti
ke kerutin lain
dan menghadapi permintaan lain.
Ini
tidak sejatuh.
Tapi, ketika resizing
sudah selesai,
image baru
yang berhasil resizing
telah dikeluarkan
dari thread pool
dan kita bisa
bekerja lagi.
Sebenarnya, mungkin
saya tidak bisa
mengekalkan
pengguna-guna
seperti image
open, image
save,
tapi bergantung.
Bergantung dengan berapa banyak
waktu yang diperlukan
pada
pengguna-guna ini.
Saya akan bilang
bahwa
membuka
image
yang tidak dikenali
dengan ukuran
yang dikeluarkan oleh klien
mungkin lebih baik
dikeluarkan
ke thread pool.
Mencetakkan
image kecil 64
yang berbasis 64
cukup cepat.
Setiap
waktu, harus memutuskan
apakah Anda ingin
menulis lebih banyak kode untuk
mengekalkan pada thread pool
atau
Anda percaya
bahwa operasi ini cukup cepat
tidak menghalang
loop,
hampir segera,
jadi, lakukan saja di tempat.
Terima kasih.
Jadi,
sekarang
kita
memiliki
image, ya.
Pertanyaan yang bagus.
Anda
lihat
bagaimana
saya menggunakan kode ini.
Kita memiliki Python 7.
Kita bisa menggunakan
pilihan ini.
Ia memenuhi
mod debag
untuk Python, bukan hanya untuk
async.io, tapi juga
beberapa debag yang
berguna.
Dan jika
operasi ini
mengambil
kebenaran,
saya tidak tahu
apakah
saya bisa
memproduksi sekarang
atau tidak, tapi biarkan saya mencoba.
Wow, ini
file yang sudah dikunci.
Sangat buruk.
Masih
semuanya
sangat cepat.
Tapi jika
kode
antara dua awet
async
menghalang
event loop
lebih lama dari 100
millisecond,
kamu akan melihat
keputusan debag untuknya.
Ini
sebuah tanda baik
yang harus
Anda letakkan. Biasanya Anda harus
letak kode berlenggak
dalam executor.
Apakah kode
yang berlenggak
dalam executor?
Ini kode berlenggak.
Ya, jika
saya letak sleep
kemudian saya akan melihatnya
di sini. Anda bisa mencoba.
Jika saya akan
menggunakan
library request
biasa
untuk mendapatkan laman dari Python
atau saya akan melihat
kewarnian.
Saya tidak tahu.
Sangat besar file dari
local file system juga
berlenggak.
Setiap kode
yang berlenggak
adalah
berlenggak.
Saya pikir
ini bagus. Saya pikir
kode ini harus dihidangkan.
Python
saya pikir
ayo debag
environment variable
berlenggak
sama.
Tapi dash x dev
mudah untuk menyatakan
dan saya suka ini.
Juga
maaf, saya
lupa kode
yang berlenggak.
Kode selanjutnya adalah
middleware.
Middleware adalah idea yang
saya pikirkan.
Ini fungsi
yang mengambil
request dan next handler
dalam chain handle.
Jadi ketika kamu pikir
middleware, kamu bisa
bayangkan onion
dengan middleware,
middleware di dalam
dan web handler
dalam core.
Jadi
ketika
request
diproces
top level
middleware dipanggil
inner middleware
atau web handler
dipasang sebagai
handler. Middleware
bisa melakukan sesuatu sebelum
pengelan
ke inner handler
atau
bisa melakukan
sesuatu
dan bisa melakukan sesuatu
setelah pengelan.
Menurut saya
sangat teoretik,
tetapi
ini adalah contoh yang berguna.
Jika kita
dapat
kelebihan yang tidak dikenal
dari web handler kita,
kita render
sebuah
page yang istimewa.
Sangat mudah.
Kita harus mengurangi
web HTTP exception karena
ini bisa menjadi redireksi.
Kita lepaskan
istimewa
untuk kancelasi tugas.
Jangan berbicara terlalu banyak.
Tetapi semua exception yang tidak dikenal
dikancelasi
oleh page ginger euro.
Bagaimana ini berfungsi?
Kita mengelakkan kode
dari middleware
dan mencoba
memperlihatkan
post yang tidak ada.
Di sini
maaf
Anda tidak bisa membaca,
tetapi ini hanya
sebuah nombor yang besar.
Post tidak ada.
Saya memiliki
exception dari
dalam mesinari
dan teks ini
dikancelasi
oleh page euro istimewa.
Tidak terlalu susah.
Kita memiliki middleware,
kita memiliki
template ginger
untuk mengurangi teks ini.
Kita perlu
menginitialisasi
untuk menceritakan
HTTP
di mana middleware
yang saya gunakan.
Saya lupa untuk menetapkannya
di website, tetapi
idea ini
disini.
Kita membuat aplikasi
dengan
list
middleware yang dikancelasi.
Ini satu cara
untuk melakukannya.
Dan juga
client max size.
Ini karena saya memuat
besar, benar-benar besar
gambar
dan default
HTTP
limit
tidak memungkinkan
gambar besar
dan saya ingin memperbaikinya.
HTTP
mencoba
mengawal memori
untuk tidak
memiliki
gambar memori besar.
Apa yang middleware
juga bisa melakukan?
Ia bisa
memodifikasi permintaan,
sebenarnya mengklonkannya dengan
nilai.
Pemintaan nilai
tidak bisa
dimutasi.
Anda tidak bisa memodifikasi
mereka di tempat
tetapi Anda bisa
klon
permintaan
dengan
pasang
dan memasang
remote dan schema.
Anda bisa
memusik server
di belakang Nginx
untuk contoh.
Dan untuk mendapatkan
IP pengguna
Anda tidak
bisa menggunakan
IP IP
tetapi harus
mendapatkan
X forward
untuk HTTP
ini. Ini saja
tapi
apapun, Anda dapat idea
Anda mengklon
permintaan dengan nilai baru
dan memasang ke
pengendalannya.
Anda bisa
menggulung pengendalannya
dan mengelakkan
database
transaksi
komitif jika
semuanya berjalan baik.
Jika
sesuatu yang buruk terjadi, jika kelebihan
adalah kode, Anda
bisa mengulang
database transaksi.
Mungkin
berguna.
Anda bisa
mengikuti jika
pengguna dikodokkan
dan
ini adalah
fungsi yang tidak terdapat
ayo kita mengingatkan
jika pengguna
dan
bagaimana
pengguna
akan kembali dari
penggunaan informasi
dan jika pengguna
tidak ada
penggunaan
penggunaan sebagai aplikasi
adalah objek yang
seperti dikodokkan
tetapi jika
penggunaan tidak ada
dan pengguna
sebagai pengguna
memerlukan
logit di pengguna, tidak berfungsi
dengan anonimus
mari kita kembali ke
login page, jika tidak
bekerja seperti biasa
ini adalah contoh
contoh untuk
memperlihatkan
percobaan
selanjutnya
adalah
session
dalam konteks ini
adalah storage
untuk menyimpan
data terkait pengguna
storage
tidak besar
biasanya
tapi Anda bisa menggunakan
username
beberapa
informasi
HTTP
search plugin
library
yang perlu
dikodokkan
dan Anda melalui
jenis storage
untuk session
kita menggunakan
untuk menyimpan
memperlukan storage
kukus
seperti ini
ada
kukus
yang kita sokong
2 dari kotak
Anda bisa menggunakan
session storage
idea ini
setidaknya
data ini
dikode
browser kukus
memiliki
sekitar 8 kilobit
biasanya
untuk single record
jadi Anda tidak bisa
menyimpan kukus
gambar Anda
atau kadang-kadang
kukus
memiliki
ID
identity key
untuk mencari semua
data yang lain
data session
di database
apa yang Anda gunakan?
sesuatu yang tersebut
objek session
adalah dikodokkan
dengan beberapa
kualitas seperti
session baru
tidak penting
dan
kita memiliki
beberapa pembantu
lihat, ini adalah dekorator
yang menandakan
fungsi yang
memerlukan login
sangat mudah
kita memiliki middleware
dari contoh yang sebelumnya
yang
pertama
menandakan
apakah ini
proteksi
atau tidak
dan jika
login yang diperlukan
dan endpoint yang diperlukan
dan
pengguna tidak di login
maka redirect
jika tidak
terlalu
terlalu terlalu
terlalu jauh
dan penggunaan ini
untuk
endpoint yang diperlukan
seperti
kita memutuskan
yang
penyelidik
bisa melihat
list blog
konten post yang tertentu
dan harus log in
jadi
endpoint editpost
diperlukan dengan
login dekorator
kita menandakan
middleware
di registren
untuk log in middleware
dan
hampir itu
bagian terakhir
kita harus
mengurangi
login page
login dan log out
untuk
completeness
login
seperti
semplifikasi
post edit page
kita render
dan
kita
memiliki
post route untuk form ini
dan
menyimpan username
ke sesi
lihat
sangat
mudah
log out lebih mudah
untuk log out kita
mencuci sesi username
bagaimana
books
sessions
session
jadi
mari kita ke
route
saya akan menulis
nanti
menunjukkan
saya log in
log out
saya bisa
lihat
post
tapi saya tidak bisa menunjukkan
tidak bisa menunjukkan
untuk pasti
untuk login
saya harus
menunjukkan sesuatu
menunjukkan password sangat mudah
tapi
tidak perlu menunjukkan
saya akan
menunjukkan
password
sebagai
latihan yang berbeda
jadi sekarang kita
lihat saya log in
dan
saya bisa menunjukkan
post
menuliskan alamatnya
ini
saya menunjukkan
post
semua
bagus
terakhir
saya
Jinja
ada
konteks prosesor
adalah cara
menggunakan
varian
untuk menjalankan konteks Jinja
tapi tidak
untuk
untuk menjalankan
dalam contoh kita
username dalam
web handler
maksud saya
saya bisa
menukar kod
saya
ini adalah indeks
saya bisa menulis
username
adalah
sesuatu
tentang
username
dan
kopi
ini
di mana-mana
di sini
new post
edit post
dan Anda memiliki ide
tapi saya tidak mau melakukannya
saya lelaki yang lemah
saya ingin menggunakan
template base
untuk menggantikan di sini
adakah pengguna anonimus atau tidak
dan menunjukkan login
atau login
atau log out
link
dan saya bisa
melakukannya secara otomatis
dengan menjelaskan
konteks
yang menyebabkan
bagian dari konteks
sebenarnya
diksjenya yang dikosongkan
ke konteks utama
dan
untuk fungsi asing yang menerima permintaan
menerima
konteks
dikosongkan
saya harus
menyiapkannya
dengan jenja middleware
sangat mudah
secara basic
jenja
dikosongkan
saya menambah
versi asing
untuk
mendukung
kekosongan
ini
jadi kita
sekarang
versi middleware
contohnya
untuk mereka
hampir selesai
jadi
ada pertanyaan
ya
saya pikir
mungkin itu menurut Anda
apakah ini
untuk ORM?
saya
akan bilang tidak
ada
ada library
untuk
PVORM
saya pikir PV
dan itu mungkin
untuk
beberapa library seperti
IO-PG, IO MySQL
Anda bisa
menggunakan
SQL ALGIM
untuk menerima tabel
bukan objek
tidak ada
map
tapi definisi tabel
Anda bisa menggunakan definisi tabel
untuk membuat
kodik
lebih baik dari string concatenation
full ORM
sangat
sulit
dan besar
kerja
sebuah
SQL ALGIM
tidak disediakan
untuk membiarkan
asingan
inget
tidak mungkin untuk
menggunakan
tabel untuk SQL ALGIM
asingan
jadi
situasi sekarang
itu
Anda bisa melakukan
sesuatu
tapi tidak full
full-ledged ORM
dan
mungkin tidak begitu
buruk karena
sekarang
kita memiliki
database relasi
tidak
dominant
biasanya kita memiliki
kompleks
sistem heterogen
dengan
data secara bagian
di database secara bagian
terutama
di tempat lain
saya tidak tahu
key value storage, blob storage
apa-apa
data
tidak normalisasi
jadi
sebab
bagus ORM
tidak hilang
tapi menjadi
lebih
lebih tinggi dari 10 tahun lalu
saya ingin menanyakan
soal
apakah
kita bisa memiliki
Mongo
dan Elastic
ada
asingan
untuk Mongo dan Elastic
hanya
gunakan Google
dan cari sesuatu
apakah kita bisa memiliki
data secara bagian
yang terutama
static
seperti TSM
atau
apa?
bagus
saya harus memilih dan menjual
file static
kamu bisa
bilang
application router
dan
untuk menjual
tapi
biasanya
kamu meluncurkan
aplikasi
di belakang
reverse proxy
di belakang Nginx
di belakang
Elastic Cloud Balancer
di belakang sesuatu
dan
server depan
server
biasanya
lebih baik
untuk menjaga file static
jadi
mereka tidak
bisa
menjaga
AIO?
mereka bisa
tapi
Nginx menjaga file static
lebih cepat
HTTP masih bisa
mereka bisa melakukan itu
tapi
bukan kompetitor
dengan kode C yang sangat
teroptimis
untuk menjaga file static
juga
Python tidak
terlalu cepat
jadi
saya mengesankan
keputusan
jika kamu
menggunakan kode
dan logik
itu mengapa kamu menggunakan Python
bukan C
itu mengapa kamu menggunakan
HTTP
tapi sama
dengan Django
untuk Flask
tidak terlalu baru
saya pikir
dengan Django
Flask bisa menjaga file static
HTTP bisa melakukan itu juga
jadi
ada waktu atau tidak?
kita ada sekitar 15 menit
15 menit
oke
saya
ingin
sangat sederhana
mengenai cara mencoba
tes
asingkronos
ini
sangat
serupa dengan
standard
asingkronos 1
tapi
ini
juga
fungsi asingkronos
saya tidak ingin
bercerita tentang
unit test
karena
bisa
untuk unit test dengan
third party library
tapi saya lebih suka pi test
dan
apa yang harus kamu lakukan?
kamu harus
menggunakan pi test
ihtp plugin
untuk pi test
dan tolong
perhatikan pi test ihtp
ini tidak bisa dikongsi dengan pi test asingkronos
itu cerita yang panjang
kenapa?
dengan
pi test ihtp
kamu bisa
menulis
pi test style
bukan
hanya dev test
tapi asing dev
dan plugin akan
mengangkutnya secara automatis
jika plugin melihat
fungsi test
asingkronos
itu menciptakan loop
loop instance
per fungsi test
run
untuk membuat
istilah di dunia
untuk
mencetakkan
dan
terkoneksi
kelihatan mudah
tapi tidak penting
untuk mencetakkan
aplikasi kita
kita perlu memodifikasi
sedikit
lihat, saya melalui
db-path
ke database
ke kod kita
dan
dengan ini kita bisa menggunakan
satu database untuk
kita panggil produksi
dan satu lagi untuk mencetakkan
dan
saya
bisa
menggunakan
untuk menciptakan
fitur untuk
menciptakan database
di lokasi
sementara
setiap
waktu, database baru untuk
mencetakkan
untuk mencetakkan
jika saya mau, saya bisa
menceritakan database
jadi saya memiliki fitur untuk
menciptakan database
saya memiliki
fitur lain, fitur isinkron
lihat, Anda bisa menggunakan
await untuk fitur
untuk
menghubungkan database
untuk mencetakkan
pengendal
untuk menghubungkan
untuk mengakses database
kemudian
kita perlu
fitur untuk
menciptakan klien
HTTP menciptakan
fitur
yang menciptakan
klien tes
apa maksudnya
kita memiliki
aplikasi initialisasi
kita menyebutkan
ke klien HTTP
dan klien HTTP
untuk mencetakkan
fitur tes
klien
dan mencetakkan
server
untuk mencetakkan
dan menciptakan
semua
jadi
secara dasarnya
kita bisa membuat
server instance
per tes
dan ini berfungsi
dengan cepat
dan sangat mudah
jadi kita memiliki
klien tes
seperti klien
klien sesi
tapi berfungsi dengan
FML
server, dimulai dari port random
dan
kita tes API kita
kalian lihat
ada respons
cek kode, cek
konten JSON
setelah
secara default setelah
kreatif database itu kosong
kita bisa
menyimpan sesuatu
ke database, bukan menggunakan
rest API kita, tapi
langsung
langsung mengemaskan data
ke database
dan kemudian menggunakan
klien HTTP untuk mencek
bagaimana API
rest kita
berfungsi
dengan ini
kita bisa
tes semua
semuanya di server kita
jika kalian ingin
tes bagaimana
template
rendering
berfungsi
bukan
API post
tapi
nilai
dan
tes respons
dan lihat bagaimana
terlihat
seperti
tes
biasa
klien
ingat, kita juga
ada klien dari
seksyen 5
rest klien
jika kalian punya kode untuk server
cukup mudah
mari kita gunakan
lain
toolkit HTTP
feature
disini kita gunakan klien HTTP
untuk mencek
klien
sekarang kita ada server HTTP
untuk
mencek server lagi
di random port
sebenarnya klien HTTP
menggunakan
server HTTP
secara internal
dan
kita ada
server instance
di random port
kita ada
URL server
make URL
terserah
root
endpoint
dengan host dan port
host sebenarnya
localhost dengan port yang benar
untuk server yang dimulai
dan kita bisa
hanya mengunjungi
URL ini
tes user
menggunakan klien rest
instance
menangkut
saya pikir konteks manager
dari
kita berbicara sebelum
berhenti
tentangnya
dan
lakukan sesuatu
tes
yang memiliki
klien rest kita
database connection
kita
menulis
post baru
menggunakan klien rest
API
dan menggunakan database
untuk mencoba
apakah
post diambil
database
jika kamu tidak
ada server
mungkin server
berseparasi
kita bisa
menggunakan
GitHub repository
dan memiliki project berseparasi
kamu tidak bisa memiliki server
kamu tidak bisa memulai server
ada cara
untuk
kita melakukan
aplikasi
hanya satu endpoint
hanya satu handler
dan di handler
kita melakukan
cek
yang
endpoint diambil
dengan test
yang bagus untuk kita
dua asursi
dan menulis
beberapa data yang gagal
dan cek data kembali
terlihat seperti
berbicara
tapi tidak, lebih baik dari berbicara
kenapa?
karena
kamu membuat
server yang benar
dan kamu mencoba
lebih banyak
bahan bergerak
kamu menghantar
permintaan dan menerima
respons menggunakan
protokol network
menggunakan sistem
network benar
lebih baik dari
monkey patch
kita cek
bagaimana monkey patchnya
berjalan
HTTP
oh, maaf
HTP
secure
sedikit
sulit untuk tes
karena kamu membutuhkan
sertifikat
dan kamu bisa memasukkan
sertifikat untuk tes
tapi masalahnya
dengan namanya DNS
kamu harus memulai
dan mungkin
ini gagal
selain
kamu memutuskan server produksi
tidak sangat handa untuk
tes HTP
di laptop lokal saya
tanpa namanya DNS
terkumpul dengan ini
tapi, Nathanial Smith
yang
sangat bagus
task me library
dan terima kasih
Svetoslav untuk mengadoptikannya
untuk tes HTTP
jadi, idea ini
bukan menggunakan
sertifikat
dari
sistem operasi kamu
untuk tes saja
kita membuat
sendiri
secara temporary
root
sertifikat
kita menyebut
sertifikat untuk lokal
untuk tes saja
hanya untuk waktu
menggunakan program ini
atau
untuk tes spesifik
sebenarnya, dalam kes ini
kita membuat
konfigurasi server
konteks SSL
dan konteks SSL klien
dan konteks ini
bisa dikonsumsi
ke HTTP
atau async IO
teknik, konteks
bisa dikonsumsi
ke socket
ke request
library, by the way
dan kamu memiliki
dua panggilan
konteks yang bisa dikonsumsi
untuk menciptakan
koneksi HTTPS
dan kedua
bagian, kondisi
satu sama lain
jadi, ini
cara paling konvenient untuk tes
HTTPS
jika kamu ingin
bagian terakhir
jika kamu masih
ingin
atau harus
menggunakan mocking
ada respons
dengan mocks session
itu menggigil
internal representation
dan kamu bisa bilang
jika kamu pergi ke example com
kemudian
kembali tes body
dengan status 200
terlihat
lebih mudah
saya tidak suka
tapi
kadang-kadang
bisa jadi mudah
jadi, ini sangat mudah
overview tes
jika kamu yakin dengan
tes by test
saya percaya
kamu akan dapat idea
bagaimana untuk bekerja dengan tes
di HTTP
di dunia terorong
jika tidak
maaf
tes
berbeda
3 jam
mungkin tidak cukup
tapi, apapun
saya sudah selesai
pertanyaan
saya
tidak bisa
mencoba
untuk mencoba
kelihatan seperti
semuanya bersih
terima kasih
itu bagus
terima kasih semua yang datang