So, good morning, everyone. We'll be starting now. So, we need Anaconda Navigator and the
Jupyter Notebooks for this particular tutorial. And this is the survey link. I will show this
again at the end of tutorial. And there are some announcements from PyCon. So, the first break
will happen at 10.15. It is mentioned that snacks go quickly. So, if you haven't had a break fast,
then decide accordingly. Lunch will be at 12.20 to 1.20. Food trucks will be at the grassy area
of the East Mall Drive. And please share the power sockets. Okay. Okay. So, this tutorial is
Hello, World of Machine Learning Using Scikit-learn. Here is the expectations from this tutorial. This
will not make you an expert in machine learning, but it will cover enough things to acquaint,
enable, and empower you to understand, explore, and exploit the concepts and idea behind it.
Might be feeling that it's too much of a material, but these are the basic steps that are needed for
you to start your journey with machine learning. If you are absolute beginner, fine, you will be
at home. If you know some things about machine learning, still you will learn something new.
Okay. So, let me introduce myself. My name is Deepak K. Gupta. Also known by my pet name,
which is Dutch. I'm programming pretty much since the time I was a teenager. I got my first full-time
software development job in the year 2000. Still doing that. And I've, over the last 20 years,
I've worked with many programming languages and many domains. Just a recommendation that if you
know only one or two programming languages, try to explore two, three more. It just helps. I'm also
a technical content creator. I write blogs on Medium and create YouTube videos. And if you want
to reach me on Twitter, this is me. And this is the place where I put all my technical contents.
Okay. Here is the agenda for this tutorial. We'll be exploring some of the acronyms. Then,
we will talk about machine learning algorithms. We'll introduce to scikit-learn. Then, we will
learn some prerequisites of machine learning using scikit-learn. Some things like NumPy and
Matplotlib. We'll also see Hello World dataset from scikit-learn for machine learning. Then,
we will explore supervised learning and unsupervised learning algorithms. So,
I'll be explaining at least three algorithms. That is linear regression, KNN, and K-mean clustering.
After doing all those things, we'll be also exploring how to explore real-world machine
learning data using pandas. Then, we will take one real-world example and apply the
machine learning algorithm on that. We will finish with a mapping application exercise.
Okay. So, let's start. So, what is AI, ML, and DL? These are the terms being used interchangeably.
AI means artificial intelligence. Artificial intelligence means any decision that is being
taken without the direct intervention of a human being. Okay. So, if someone else which is not
perceived as intelligent like our laptops, if it is taking some decision without asking me,
it's called as artificial intelligence. If I display artificial intelligence as a big oval,
where does machine learning come into this? So, machine learning is part of artificial
intelligence. Artificial intelligence is built on top of machine learning. There is another
thing called DL which expands to deep learning. DL is considered as part of machine learning.
Now, this is this picture, AI, ML, and DL. As of now, it's the most acceptable picture across
the board about DL, ML, AI, and the relationship between these three. But in reality, you know,
these fields are still evolving. DL and ML are more overlapping in nature as compared to being
part of each other. But again, this is the most acceptable picture. And if you are going for a job
interview, this picture will help you at this point of time. Now, we will explore what is machine
learning. We will not look into deep learning, but let me tell you what is deep learning. So,
machine learning, what happens that we tell machine that, okay, you learn something about
some aspects of data and tell me the result. What deep learning does is that it's a combination
of machine learning. So, machine learning, you give some data to machine learning algorithm,
it gives some output. That output is again used for learning, which gives another output,
and that output is again used for learning. So, this is a chain of sequence that builds up. So,
then it is called deep learning. So, it's learning, result, learning from result, then learning from
result, and it goes on and on. It's clear, right? What is AI, ML, and DL? It's just a basic
introduction to what it means. Any question? So, at any point of time you have any question,
just raise your hand, I'll try to answer that. Okay. Okay. So, let's talk about the need for
machine learning, why machine learning is there. So, machine learning feeds on data. There can't
be anything called machine learning or data science without the availability of data. Data
is fuel for machine learning. Okay. So, if someone asks to define machine learning in
simple terms, here is how we can do that. So, machine learning is all about extracting valuable
information from the known data so that it can take appropriate decisions for the unknown ones.
So, if I have some data, I take valuable information out of it, okay, so that I can take some decisions
based on those data for the unknown ones. And in today's world, some of the problems can't be
solved without the help of machine learning. Okay. We will see some of them. Now, before I go ahead,
I want to explain one thing that what is similarity or difference between mathematics and machine
learning. You can come here, please. Now, all of you know that machine learning is based on
mathematics, right? You see lots and lots of calculus-related things when you talk about
machine learning. But what is the difference between mathematics and machine learning? Why
don't we use mathematics in its pure form and why do we use machine learning? Let's take an example.
Let's assume that airport is around 10 miles from this place and it will take you 20 minutes to
reach there. Just an assumption, okay? And if I ask a question, okay, it takes me 20 minutes to
reach airport, which is 10 miles. How much time I will take to reach the fifth mile? What will be
the answer? 10 minutes, right? Okay. So this is mathematics. Mathematics tells you that, you know
what, if you are taking 20 minutes to reach 10 miles, you will take 10 minutes to reach fifth mile.
But what machine learning does is that it tells, okay, hold on, you will reach to the airport in 20
minutes, but you are starting from downtown. There are lots and lots of traffic over here. There will
be traffic lights. You will start at different point of time. So you will reach the fifth mile
on 14th minute and you will cover rest of the distance in six minutes. This is what machine
learning is. Understand the difference between mathematics and machine learning? It's clear, okay?
So let's talk about a scenario to understand why machine learning is required. Let's assume that
some of you come up with a great startup idea, which is about building an e-commerce startup,
and you intend to sell consumer electronics, okay? Now once people come to your website and
buy something, you want to recommend also that you can buy this also, something like Amazon, okay?
All of us use Amazon, so we know that it recommends us something when we buy anything. Now in the
beginning, you analyze some data and come to a conclusion that you basically have two types
of customers. One is younger ones, less than 25 years of age, and rest of the people greater
than 25 years of age. Younger ones prefer iPhone and not so younger ones prefer laptops, okay?
So you decided that, okay, you know what, I'll go ahead and code that if the person which is
currently browsing on my website and the person is less than or equal to 25, I'll recommend iPhone.
Otherwise, I'll recommend laptop. Good, and you are doing fine. But after some time,
you analyze some more data and you come to a conclusion that, oh, you know what,
I have another category called greater than 35 years of age, and they are the people who don't
like to spend money just like that, okay? So I will come up with a new category and say that,
you know what, if the people is 35 or more, I'll recommend budget option, budget laptops.
And now your startup is doing fine and you want to expand to another country,
and you decide to expand to a country like India, for example. But what happens that
in India, people like Android phones more than iPhones. What will you do? You say, no problem.
What I will do is that in younger generation, I'll create another category called North American
Market or India Market. In North American Market, I'll recommend iPhone. In India Market,
I'll recommend Android, as simple as that. So far, so good. You launched your startup in India.
It's working fine. But now you get some more data, and you came to a conclusion that, okay,
hold on a minute. India has lots and lots of middle class population. It's as good as
overall population of United States. So it doesn't mean that they are not buying iPhone.
They are also buying iPhone. And you come to a calculation that, okay, out of 10 phones
that are being sold there, 7 is Android, 3 is iPhone. It's not a real data. I just make it up,
okay. So what you will do is that, okay, you'll come up with another condition saying that, okay,
in India Market, what I will do is that I'll generate a random number. And 3 out of 10 times,
and 3 out of 10 times, I'll recommend iPhone. 7 out of 10 times, I'll recommend Android.
I'll stop here. But just wanted to check. Do you see the problem in this particular scenario?
Correct. So, you know, if you go ahead on and on and on and on, the permutation and combination
of conditions will be huge to manage, right? And other thing is that, you know what, if you
decide to write some code with these conditions, by the time you pass your emperors sitting in
quality control department or somewhere else and your bills are passed, your product is actually
shipped, and by the time it is actually coming to the market, this might be changed. The condition
might have changed because a new phone is being launched and people are quite enthusiastic about
it, so on and so forth. So these kind of problems can't be solved with static programming. And these
are the problems where we should use machine learning. So machine learning is not an answer
to all set of problems, but it is an answer to these kind of problems, where you have lots and
lots of conditions and things are very dynamic in nature. It's clear till now? Yes, okay. Are
you getting the point? So let's take a brief on machine learning algorithms and then we'll move
further. Okay, so machine learning algorithms are generally categorized into three types.
Supervised, unsupervised, and reinforcement learning. Let's talk about supervised learning.
So in a nutshell, supervised learning is very similar to what we want our kids to learn when
we send them to school. Okay, for example, we tell them, okay, this is history, this is geography,
this is friendly country, this is enemy country, and many other things, right? We know the result.
We want them to learn the result the way we want. This is called supervised learning,
where we say that, okay, this is the result. If this is this, then this is the result. You learn
this. That's all. You don't apply your mind. I am telling you, this means this. You just learn it.
So supervised learning is actually of two types. One is called classification. Classification is
easy. I mean, you can classify things into one of the available categories. For example, all of us
over here can be categorized into one of the 195 countries. There cannot be 196,
unless a country is created tomorrow. And regression is all about coming up with a continuous data.
So it's beyond classification, but what it does is that it gives you a continuous set of data. We
will see one example of it. Now, unsupervised learning is all about giving data to machine
learning algorithms and don't tell them the results. So it is just like I gave you the data,
you find out what it is. So let's take an example that if I give a high school data to unsupervised
learning algorithm, it can come up with a set of clusters, like people who are staying nearby,
people who are consistently getting lower grades, people who are consistently getting higher grades,
and so on and so forth. It can come up with any number of these kind of clusters. So we don't
tell them the result. So difference between supervised learning and unsupervised learning
is that in supervised learning, we tell them the result. This means this, but in unsupervised
learning, we don't tell them the result. We ask machine learning algorithm to find out
interesting facts from the data. Now, third is reinforcement learning. It is also called
semi-supervised learning. It is a reward-based system. So all of the things you have heard about
games like somebody is learning chess, AlphaGo, any other thing, these all things are reward-based
system. So let's take an example for reinforcement learning. Let's assume that this is my cell phone.
This is just a simple robot. I want this robot to just roam around here, not to fall down.
What I will do is that I will give this guy a reward if it is not falling down within a minute.
So what this guy will do, this robot will do, is that this will generate a random number.
Random number will generate some random behavior, and random behavior will lead to some random
movement. So if it moves here, it will fall down. If it moves here, it will fall down. But
over a period of time, sooner or later, it will not fall down for one minute. And as soon as this
happens, this will learn it. Now, once it learns that, okay, I'm not falling down for one minute.
If I do this, it tries to maximize that. And over a period of time, it will never fall down.
That's the way reinforcement learning happens. Any questions? Because we will not be covering
an algorithm for reinforcement learning. So that's why I wanted to explain it very clearly.
Okay. Make sense?
How do we use that for reinforcement learning?
Okay. Reinforcement learning actually happens with the reward. So it collects the data which
leads to the reward. So these kind of movements leads to this kind of reward. For example, chess,
these movements lead to reward. It will remember that movement. That's the way it keeps on
accumulating all the data which leads to reward. And when it has lots and lots of data,
it finds the appropriate data for a particular situation the machine is put into. Okay.
So if you have seen pictures from Boston Dynamics, some dog, robotic dogs, and other things are
running. It's reinforcement learning. Okay. Let's go to chapter three.
We'll just introduce ourselves to scikit-learn. Basically, if you open the scikit-learn web page,
this is how it looks like. And you can see lots and lots of algorithms over here.
But the important thing is this. It is just as Python libraries for data mining and data analysis,
not only for machine learning. We will see one of that. And it is open source. It's built on
NumPy, SciPy, and Matplotlib. And we will see NumPy and Matplotlib. And if you go to scipy.org,
this is what it looks like. SciPy consists of these core packages in which includes NumPy,
Matplotlib, and pandas. We will see pandas from SciPy. Okay. So scikit-learn is just a helper
library to help you start with machine learning. Okay. It just takes away all the complexities
of machine learning. So you can concentrate on data. Okay.
So you can just open the first Jupyter Notebook in Chapter 4.
Till now, anyone has any questions? Yes. Okay. So machine learning and data science are actually
a bit different fields. But data science is all about getting the valuable information from data.
Machine learning is learning from that and expanding that to take decisions where data
is not available. So machine learning uses data science to extract valuable information from data.
But data science can be a totally separate field altogether where we are just using different,
different methodologies to extract valuable information from data.
So data scientists just extract valuable information from data. There is a job for
data scientists because you know what? In the real world data, it doesn't come in the form of,
I mean, it's not decorated where we can just take it and dump into the machine learning
algorithms. It needs to change into a proper shape before we can do that.
So that's where data science comes into picture. You have this notebook open with you.
Introduction to NumPy. Yes. Okay. So what is NumPy? NumPy is also called Numeric Python.
And it's the first step towards your journey on machine learning with Python programming language
because everything that scikit-learn uses is based on NumPy as of now. If you are not aware
of NumPy, you can't use scikit-learn or for that matter any other machine learning algorithm.
So to use NumPy, you have to import NumPy as NP. You can import it as any name, but just like
self in Python, this is a kind of de facto standard. We use NP for NumPy. Okay.
Now what is NumPy used for? NumPy is used for creating N-dimensional arrays. Okay.
And to create N-dimensional array, what we will have to do is that we will have to call a function
called array and pass something similar to Python list over here. Okay. And my NumPy array is created.
Now all of you might be having a question right now is that if it is very similar to Python array,
I can create a Python array itself. Right? I mean, there is no difference between these two.
If I go ahead and print these two. Okay. Other than in Python array, I can see comma separated
values. There is no difference between these two. From the look of it, from the look of NumPy,
it may look like that creating array is an overhead. Because if I want to go ahead and
create Python list, it's very easy for me. I can just create the list. But in NumPy, I have to call
a function called array and pass the Python list into it. But there is a reason why we should use
NumPy. And the reason is there are two specific reasons. Reason number one is that NumPy array
takes less memory. If I say less means it's considerably less, much, much less memory than
Python list. And second thing is that NumPy is meant for mathematics. Okay. We will see how it
is different over here. So let's first see how memory usage are different. So I have created a
Python array called parr with the same 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 as NumPy array narr with the same 1, 2, 3,
4, 5. Okay. So if I say length of parr, it will give me 5. Number of elements is 5. And if I want
to see how much memory in bytes occupied by each individual elements, in Python, I'll have to just
import this and I have to say get size of a particular integer because I am using integer.
Makes sense? This is correct, right? You must have used in Python, right? Checking the size of it.
How much it comes? 140. Okay. Let's check the same thing for NumPy arrays. So if I say length
narr, it will say 5, which is same as Python list. But NumPy array also provides us some
of the data members which can be used to find the size. So if I use dot size, it will give me 5.
If I use dot item size, it gives me the size of individual elements. Okay. Which is 8.
And if I go ahead and multiply these two, you can see it's 40.
So what is happening over here is that for the same amount of data, Python list took 140 bytes
and NumPy array took 40 bytes. Does it makes the difference? Think about it. When you are
giving your data to machine learning algorithms, you must be giving lots and lots of data,
hundreds and thousands of rows, okay, if not millions. And if you combine all of those,
the amount of memory will explode if you use Python list, not with NumPy. Not only this,
there are further optimizations which are also possible with NumPy array. So we know that 1, 2,
3, 4, 5 can be stored in a single byte, right? If it is signed, 127, if it is unsigned, 255 can
be stored in a single byte. Okay. So I can actually provide a data type in the NumPy array. Okay.
I have 1, 2, 3, 4, 5. By default, you are taking int64. I don't need int64. What I want is that
int8. Okay. If I go ahead and do that, and then I check the size, it's just 5 bytes.
So 140, 240, 25. And that's the reason we should use NumPy. Okay. You must have heard about
something called a sparse matrix or dense matrix. It's extremely useful to create NumPy arrays
because it saves lots and lots of space. Are you getting the same output in your Jupyter notebooks?
So NumPy wins hands down over here. Yes, no, maybe. It's right. Because, you know,
it takes really less amount of memory. But there is no magic behind reduced size. Unlike Python lists,
NumPy arrays are homogeneous in nature. Okay. Which means that all the elements are
the same type. Now, if I can create a Python list like this, with integer, floating point,
string, and some number, I can do that. Okay. If I try to do the same thing with NumPy array,
can you try that and see what happens? Remember, I said that NumPy arrays are homogeneous in nature.
Yes. It works, right? So it works because what NumPy array does is that if it finds different
type of elements, it tries to find out the data type which can accommodate all of them. In here,
the string type. So if you go ahead and see NumPy array and the data type of NumPy array,
you can see that it's Unicode 32-bit less than sign means it is stored as little Indian.
Okay. So if I multiply NumPy array, 0th element, 10 times, I'll get
repetition of 10, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1. But if I do the same with Python array, I'll get 10. Because
Python array gives me first element as an integer, not NumPy array. NumPy arrays will always be
homogeneous in nature. And it makes sense because mathematics is all about numbers.
Whether you have a string or any other data type, internally, it is all about numbers and machine
learning. Just use numbers. Makes sense, right? Okay. There is a simple exercise you can just
try out in 30 seconds maybe. Create a NumPy array with floating point and integer data types and
see what is the data type that is provided by NumPy arrays.
I mean, 30 seconds should be fine. Just try it out and let me know.
Okay. This is how it will look like. Just see what is the output of these two.
Okay. So you can see that if I provide both integer and floating point data types, it stores
by default as a float64. So NumPy arrays are homogeneous. That's very important. Okay.
Because whatever we are going to look right now, it's based on this particular principle.
Now we talked about two reasons to use NumPy. One is memory. Right? We have seen that it takes
very less amount of memory. What is the second reason?
Okay. It is made for mathematics. Okay. Now let me create the Python array and NumPy array together.
And if I multiply Python array by two, what will happen?
It will just duplicate the array. Right? 1, 2, 3, 4, 5. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5. Right? But if you multiply NumPy
array by two, here is what happens. It actually multiplies every element by two. So if you go
back to your mathematics days, if you say vector two before that, what does it mean? It means that
I want every element of the vector to be multiplied by two, not gets repeated. Okay. And that's what
is being taken care by NumPy array. Similarly, if I create a two-dimensional array,
both in Python array and NumPy, if I multiply Python array, it will repeat it. If I multiply
NumPy array, it will actually multiply each element by two. You can see one by two,
two multiplied by two, and so on and so forth. Remember matrix multiplication? If you just put
two before that, that means each element will be multiplied. So NumPy takes care of that implicitly.
If you use Python array, you'll have to do it explicitly. So there are two reasons to use NumPy.
One is that it takes less amount of memory. Second is it is made for mathematics.
Makes sense? So it's very important to know more detail about NumPy, but I am not combining
everything in one notebook. What I'm trying to do is that as we move further, we will explore
new functionalities of NumPy. Okay. Now, one thing about representing data in machine learning.
So no matter which programming language we use, whenever we create an array, we use to create
bracket one, two, three, four, five. This is the way we used to create the arrays in any
programming language. Right? Okay. And this is how it looks like. But in machine learning,
we generally represent numbers in column format, not in the row format. So if you consider this
as a vector, single column is called vector. So if you are creating an array for machine learning,
you will have to convert it into a column format. You will understand the reason once we go and see
the data later on, but it has to be converted into column format, not in the row format. Okay.
Now NumPy array provides a way to do it. We can just reshape it. Okay. So right now I have seven
elements. Okay. Right now what is the way it is arranged? One into seven. I want to arrange it
at seven into one. So if I do that, I'll get it in the column format. Now this reshape function
is intelligent. You can skip one dimension. You can just give minus one. The meaning of this is
that it says that, look, I want one column rows you decide. So end result will be same.
Or if I just say seven and minus one here, this means that, look, I want seven rows column you
decide. Same result. Okay. But we can't give minus one, minus one. We have to specify at least one
dimension. Okay. So if you go ahead and see the shape, it's seven one. If you go ahead and see
the dimension, it's two. So the number representation in machine learning is generally column vector,
not the row vectors. Okay. Make sense? Is it clear till now over here? Okay.
Okay. Now let's create a two-dimensional array with actually more than one column.
So once you have more than one column in terms of data science, mathematics, or machine learning,
it is called matrix. And let's generate more than two columns. Sorry. Two dimension.
So what we did till now is that we just passed the static values in numpy array.
We don't need to do that. There is a chair over here.
Okay. So numpy has various utility functions which can be used to generate some data. So there is a
function called arrange. It is similar to Python range. Right? If I say for loop x in range 10,
I get zero to 10. Right? So by default, it generates a number in a step of one. I can
provide a step which is a by default thing. I can provide a step as two or even I can provide a step
as 0.25. Okay. So arrange is inclusive exclusive, which means that zero is inclusive, 16 is exclusive.
So if I say zero to 16 in one, I'll get number zero to 15. Okay. Now let me use the reshape function
to convert this into a three-dimensional array. And here is how it will look like. And if I check
the shape and dimension, it will come as three and four to two. Okay. Now in terms of mathematics,
data science, and machine learning, anything which is beyond two dimensions is called tensor.
Okay. So vectors are called tensors of rank one. Matrix are called tensors of rank two.
And this is called tensor of rank three. And it goes on and on. Okay. You must have heard about
tensor flow. Right? So you know what it does, right? It's just a manipulation of numbers
in form of tensor. Even PyTorch does the same thing. So that's all about beginning of NumPy.
Okay. So you let's repeat. There are two specific reasons to use NumPy. One is that it takes very
less amount of memory. Second, it is meant for mathematics. Okay. These are some of the utility
function of NumPy. Like if I want to create an empty array of five, row vector five, I'll get
some empty. I can also create two dimensions. You might get different numbers over here. Okay.
Like this. So in terms of machine learning, many times you need to create data in a particular
dimension. So this NumPy functions will help you to create a structure where you can fill the data
later on. Yes? Which? Okay. The internal implementation generates anything between
zero to some random number. Okay. It can be anything. It's not actually empty. It takes some size.
So can you do one exercise for me? It also takes 30 seconds to convert this two-dimensional array
into one-dimensional array using reshape. Just 30 seconds. Just try it once.
So if you want to add some cell over here, you can press A in Jupyter Notebook to create a cell
before the place where you are. If you say B, it will create a cell below your cell.
Okay. You'll use something like this. Okay. So this is converting the two-dimensional array
into one-dimensional array. This is reshaping it to two-five. Okay. And this is like 10 row,
one column. Okay. So the only condition of reshape is that the multiplicity factor should
match. We cannot say three into five. Everything should come to 10. As long as it is matching the
multiplicity factor, reshape will work fine. Okay. So you're good with NumPy, right? At least
basics of it. Okay. Now, you know what? I wanted to give you an exercise as a homework. I guess
this is the right time to talk about it. Once you go back after this tutorial, let's do one thing.
You start collecting data about yourself for a month, actually. Right? Things like what time you
wake up, what time you go for bed, what was your fooding habits on that day, whether you were happy
on that day or you went somewhere out, something like that, whatever you can come up with, number
of times you took coffee or anything like that. Even if you miss for one or two days, please keep
on collecting this data for at least a month. Okay. Once you do that, apply whatever you are
going to learn today on that data. Two benefits. One, you will really understand what is the meaning
of machine learning. Second, you'll find some interesting facts about yourself.
You can keep on doing that for second month, third month, and apply the same thing again. See?
As long as it's between you and your husband. I guess it should be fine.
Okay. There are some utility functions. You can see it in the Jupyter Notebooks. Let's go to 4.2,
which is introduction to Matplotlib. Human eyes are very bad in judging the text or numbers,
but very good in visualizing the pictures. Right? So, Matplotlib is a 2D plotting library.
We'll just glance through it, how we can use it. It is used for plotting. While you are doing
something, you can plot it. Okay? So, you will have to include matplotlib.pyplot. Again, as PLT,
you can name it as anything. And you import numpy. I just create a x and y numpy array.
And this is how I can plot it. Just say plot and x and y. And this is what you will get.
If you open your Jupyter Notebooks, you can just press shift enter. You'll get this. To execute
a cell, you need to press shift enter. Talking about 4.2, notebook chapter 4, 4.2. Okay.
And we can also do customized plotting, right? I didn't like the blue line. I want a red line
or a green line. I can also give RGB as a short form for red, green, and blue. Okay? We'll be
using this Matplotlib to understand our own data. So, that's the reason I am explaining this.
You can also use color symbol like red color plus symbol. You can see that plus symbol is
there of red color. Green color is star symbol. And blue color circle. Okay? Or triangle, red color
triangle. Or you want a dotted line in different, different color. This is the thing which you may
end up using is like dotted line with markings where the data are or triangles where the data
are. Simple different, different choices of how you want to plot your own graph.
Okay? Once you plot that, you can actually set X and Y axis labels.
You can see the X axis, Y axis. Okay? You can even set axis values. Right now, the values are
dependent on the NumPy array I gave. You can set axis value as X mean X max, Y mean Y max.
And if I go ahead and do that, you can see that axis values are being set. So, this much is good
enough for 80% of the requirement. But, again, Matplotlib is quite complex. And it has various
functionalities. But this much should be good enough for this tutorial. Is it executing? Are
you able to plot in your system with using notebook? Anyone having any issue?
Can you try to do it in a different cell?
In 3.7, I don't think you need inline. If you're... Okay.
If you have latest navigator, you don't need to use Matplotlib inline.
Last thing about Matplotlib is that you can actually plot multiple values together
in one graph to compare. Okay? And you can even select the style of two graphs, how you want to
plot it. This is very easy. Just you need to know what you need to provide.
So, if you're not getting the plot, maybe you can try this.
This comma. Okay? If you have downloaded the latest Anaconda navigator, this is not required.
Old one, you have to put this in the top of the line. Okay?
Okay. So, now let's actually start the tutorial. So, let's start with the
machine learning. Okay? Okay. So, now let's actually start seeing some data for machine learning.
So, whenever we learn programming, we start with Hello World. Right? All of us started with Hello
World. Similarly, there is a Hello World dataset for scikit-learn for machine learning. Is it
visible to you guys? At the back, is it visible? Okay. Now, I'm showing this Hello World dataset
of machine learning from scikit-learn to make you aware about the fact how the data is actually
stored. So, there are two things which you need to know. One is feature. Another is label.
So, feature is a set of data representing specific characteristics,
and label is the result of those characteristics. So, let's see this picture. Can you see this picture?
Okay. What does it look like? It's a result sheet. Right? So, it's the marks on first,
second, third, and fourth semester for different, different subjects. Science,
maths, English, social science, and the result. So, these marks in individual subjects are called
features, and results are called labels. So, in machine learning, especially with scikit-learn,
whatever data you get, you get some features and then some labels. Feature can be anything.
Right? And feature can be 10, 20, 100, 200, 1000, anything like that. Okay.
So, right now, yes?
I guess this one is not. PNGs are not there yet. There are some issues with upload. I'm not sure why.
So, can you see it now? Okay. Got it? What is the meaning of features and labels? So, you know what?
I told you about supervised learning algorithms. Like, we tell what is the result. Right? So,
here I'm saying that if you get at least 40 in science, 30 in maths, English, 20 in English,
or 33 in social science, you are passed. This is what I'm telling my machine learning model.
But if you get 32, 21, 20, 22, you are failed. So, my machine learning model will identify
who is passed, who is failed based on features. So, any data that you use for supervised learning
algorithm contain two things, features and labels. Okay? Features and labels. Clear? Right? Any questions?
So, there is a data called Iris data and it contains four features and a single label.
So, this dataset is used for differentiating three types of species of a particular flower.
And this is how the flower looks like. This is an image from Wikipedia. Okay. There are three
species of the same flower called Iris centosa, Versicolor and Virginica. Okay.
So, these three species are identified by four features and the features are called
sepal length, sepal width, petal length and petal width. Okay. You can see that these
sepals and petals are a bit different. I think the top which is there is called petals. Bottom
small one is called sepals. These are different. So, based on these characteristics, length of
each sepal and petal in centimeter, we will identify which flower species it belongs to.
Make sense? Okay. So, let's see how we can import this dataset. Okay.
So, scikit-learn datasets has lots and lots of datasets. One is Iris. We can import load
Iris. Okay. And we create the instance of load Iris. And this is how Iris DB looks like. Okay.
You can see there is something called data.
Target, target names and description. Okay. So, let's see them separately.
Okay.
This is what data looks like. So, data contains four features.
What are those? Sepal length, sepal width, petal length, petal width. So, these are sepal length,
sepal width, petal length and petal width in centimeters. And what is the target?
Target. Whether it is a particular species of flower, what 0, 1, 2 represent, we can get to
know by using target names. 0 represents centosa. 1 represents versicolor. 2 represents virginica.
Okay. And these are feature names. Sepal length, sepal width, petal length and petal width. Okay.
Now, let's see the type of all these data. You can see that all of them is actually given to you
as numpy and dimensionary. None of this data will be provided to you as a Python list here.
Okay.
No. Target, yes, target is the label. Okay. Data is the feature. Target is the label.
So, in the terms of machine learning, it is called features and labels.
Here it is data and results. So, target is the result. It can be called as labels. Okay.
So, I would like to tell you that everything that is happening in scikit-learn is actually a numpy
array. Okay. So, we can use numpy array data types to understand various things that number of rows,
column, number of data and so on and so forth. Okay. So, this is the hello world data set
from scikit-learn. We will not be using now. What we will do is that we will generate our
own data set for better understanding. Okay. And then we will use iris data set.
So, you know what this data set is all about. This data set can be used for supervised learning
or unsupervised learning. It has features and labels. Supervised learning, right? Because
we tell what is correct, right? And it has to learn from it.
Okay. Let's open chapter 6, our first machine learning algorithm.
It will take some time over here, but it will be worth it, I guess. So, linear regression,
all of you have heard about, right? It's a supervised learning algorithm for regression
values based on learning prior data. So, what we will do is that we will not use a readymade
data. We will generate our own data and here is how the data will look like. Okay. Let's assume
that a farmer is producing some vegetable and the farmer sells the same vegetable in a local
farm market, which is four miles from the farm. The farmer sells it for $10. In the village,
which is 12 miles from the place, the same thing is being sold for $28. In the town, which is 25
miles from the farmer's place, same thing is being sold for $54. In a city, which is 52 miles,
same thing is being sold for $84. Downtown, which is 60 miles, same thing is being sold for $90.
Just five data points. Okay. So, we'll have to plot this in x and y axis. Okay. So,
how to decide what will be x and what will be y?
Okay. So, what you want to know is y. So, in here, I want to know that
what will be the price at 30th mile? The data is not here. Okay. So, that will be x axis,
miles will be at x axis, actual value in dollars will be y axis. Make sense? So,
this is a very simple data and we can actually analyze the result. And that's why we are just
taking five points. Okay. This data is clear, right? It's a single farm product. You may consider
that one lb of something is being sold at the local place for $10. Same thing is being sold
in downtown for $90. This is, again, a made-up thing. It may not be true. Okay. So, what I do
is that I create a numpy array first and create a distance and price. Okay. Because I have to use
numpy array. So, distance is miles, price is dollars. Okay. Now, remember what I told you
that single row of number has to be represented as column vectors in machine learning. So, we'll
have to convert x distance into column vectors. Right? If I do reshape, I get the same thing
as a column vector. But what will happen if I just try to print x distance again?
Can you try that? What happened? Huh? Yeah, it's unchanged. You know what? So, what happens is that
when you call a reshape function, it gives you a new numpy array. Okay. If you want to use it
in place, you will have to change the shape manually like this. And then you can see that
it is changed. So, reshape implicitly doesn't change in place. Same for y price. So, I have
converted both the data, distance and price, as a column vectors. Okay. Let's plot it using Matplot
lib. We know how to plot it. So, if you plot it, this is how it will look like. These are dollars
and these are miles. Okay. Till now, things are clear, right? Which data we are looking into right
now? Okay. So, let's use linear regression. What we will do is that first we will use linear
regression provided by scikit-learn. Then we will decode it piece by piece. And to understand how
it actually works. Okay. So, to use linear regression from scikit-learn, we will have to
import linear regression from a linear model. And we will also have to import matrix. And we will
have to import from matrix mean squared error. We will come to know in a moment why we need these
two things. But let's import these two. Now, as I said that scikit-learn makes things very easy for
all of you. Because it provides a unified machine learning interface in just three lines.
Everything is done. Okay. No matter whether you are creating an instance of supervised learning
algorithm, unsupervised learning algorithm, you just use three lines. Okay. So, what you do is
that you create the instance of the algorithm. Okay. And pass some algorithm specific parameters.
You call the fit function. Fit is the training function, right? I pass x and y in fit. My
machine learning model is trained. And I use predict function to predict the data. That's all.
And if I change this linear regression to logistic regression, KNN, anything, it's the same thing.
Create the instance, call fit, call predict. As simple as that. So, it takes away all the pain
of doing things manually in case of machine learning. Okay. So, this is a unified interface
provided by scikit-learn. Okay. So, here is how we will be using it. So, let's create the instance
of linear regression. Create it. Call the fit function with distance and price. Done. Okay.
Now, we have our machine learning model trained. Actually trained on the data we have provided.
The data was distance in miles and the price at a particular point. Okay. Now, we can predict the
value. Let's predict what will be the price at 45th mile. Okay. Now, I am putting this 45 mile also
as a column vector even if it's a single data. Okay. And if I go ahead and predict, it gives me
$73.26. Okay. So, let's predict it with the original data points. From the look of it,
at least, from the visual look of it, this looks to be correct. Right. What will be the price at
45th mile? It says $73. And $45 is between $25 and $52. At $25, it was $54. At $52, it was $84.
And $73 comes in between. So, from the look of it, at least, it looks correct. Right. Yes, no, maybe.
Looks correct. Right. Till now, it makes sense. Right. Scikit-learn provides a unified machine
learning interface. What we do is that we create the instance of a class for a particular algorithm.
We call the fit function. We call the predict function. In fit function, we provide our X and Y.
Okay. I can also predict for multiple values. So, here I have close to nine values. Okay. This is
how it looks like. So, just consider this. I trained my machine learning model with just five
values. Right. Distance were five distances, 10 miles, 25 miles, and so on and so forth.
But I can use predict for predicting even 100. It will work. It's not that my training data was
just five points. I can only predict one or two points. I can predict any number of points.
If I go ahead and predict that, you can see that it is predicting things. And again, from the visual
look of it, it looks to be doing really well. Okay. These greens are being predicted. These red
are the original data points. Okay. So, till now, it's clear how we can use Scikit-learn algorithms.
Create the instance. Call the fit function to train. Call the predict function to get back
the predictions. We'll have to provide column vectors. Clear? Okay. Now, let's understand linear
regression. So, it's not needed to understand complete mathematics behind all the algorithms,
but it's actually useful to know what it does behind the scene. If we can at least understand
one mathematics behind linear regression, it actually opens up lots and lots of opportunity
for us to explore the algorithm. Now, what linear regression does is that it attempts to generate
a best fit line, which is generally a straight line in these x, y cases, but it need not be a
straight line. Okay. It can be a quadratic line also. Okay. Just for simplicity purposes,
we are using a straight line. Now, when we say it generates a best fit line, what is the meaning of
best fit? Best fit means that align with least mean squared error. Okay. So, you remember we have
imported two things from Scikit-learn, linear regression as well as mean squared error.
And mean squared error is imported to check the mean square of best fit line. Okay.
Now, one very important thing. I know all of us during our childhoods would have hated one or two
subjects, right? So, what we do is that we just mug up things because we have to pass exams on
those subjects and just give the exam. If the same question comes, okay, I pass with flying colors.
Okay. So, we don't learn, but we mug up things. Machine learning doesn't do that. Okay. It doesn't
mug up things. It learns from it. What does this mean? This means that if I said that at 10th,
let's say at 4th mile, the price is $10. Okay. And at 90th mile, the price is $80.
And if I ask my machine learning algorithm that, okay, what is the price at 4th mile?
It will not necessarily give me the same what I have provided to it. It can give me, okay, 10,
which was what I have provided. It can give me 9. It can give me 13. Because it doesn't
mug up anything. It comes up with a best fit line and learn the algorithm. And that algorithm
may give you different results. Okay. So, never assume that if you provided something on your
training data and you are asking question based on your training data, it will give you the same
answer and always correct answer because it was there in your training data. That assumption is
wrong. Okay. That assumption is right for us because we mug up things. Okay. You said this,
then this is the value. No. Machine learning doesn't do that. This has to be remembered.
This has to be remembered because whenever you use it, you will say that, okay, you know,
it's not giving the value even if I provided it with the training data.
So, let's see the mean square error value. Now, as I said that my machine learning algorithm may or
may not give me the data which I have provided in training set. So, let's see. In the predict,
I am passing the same distance what I have provided in my training set. And let's see what it
gives me. It gives me something different, right? For all of you, it will give you something
different. It gives 16, 27, 45. None of them is what I have actually provided in the machine
learning training. Right? So, let's plot it to see the difference. Okay. These red points are
my original data. And this green line is what is being provided to me by my machine learning
algorithm, linear regression. You can see that only two points here and here are approximately
closer. Okay. So, it may or may not provide you same data even if you have provided the things
with the training data because it learns from all the data you have provided. It doesn't remember
each and every point. Okay. Now, let's calculate mean square error. What is the meaning of mean
square error? I know the correct values of these five points, but you are giving me something
different. What is the sum square difference between this point, this point, this point,
this point and this point? This is called mean square error. Sum of square difference between
original point and predicted point. And we don't need to do the mathematics because
scikit-learn provides a function called mean square error. And if I just go ahead and use it,
it will give me the mean square error as 26.07. Now, what my machine learning algorithm is saying
that this is the best fit line for your data. Okay. So, let's understand the maths behind linear
regression and how it works. Okay. This is bit text, but I think it will be important.
So, all of us know that the equation of straight line is y equal to mx plus b. Somebody says that
m alpha plus beta m alpha plus alpha one or something like this. So, this is y equal to mx plus b.
So, if I have x distance and I have to find out y, I have two missing values over here.
One is called m, one is called b. m is called slope and b is called y intercept.
Okay. So, slope is calculated using this formula like y end minus y begin divided by x end minus
x begin. So, this is our data. y end is 90, y begin is 10, x end is 60, x begin is 4. If I go
ahead and calculate slope, it comes to 1.42. Right? So, slope is y two minus y one divided
by x two minus x one. So, we used only two points when we learned mathematics. That's why we say y
two minus y one is in fact y end to end between two points. It's y end, y begin, x end, x begin.
Okay. Now, let's we have m. So, we have x, we have m, we need to find y. y intercept means value of
y when x equal to zero. There is a different equation called point slope equation which is
defined as y minus y one equal to mx minus x one. We can substitute x one and y one over here.
And so, y one is 10, x one is 4. We just go ahead doing the basic mathematics
and we will come to a point where it is represented as 1.42x plus 4.32. Okay. So,
if we substitute the y equal to 1.42x plus 4.32, m will be 1.42. We already know b will be 4.32.
That's intercept, right? This is what we get from mathematics. Now, you must be wondering
that what is the value of m and b provided by my linear regression algorithm. So, let's see.
It says 1.39 is m and 10.55 is b. What we got it 1.42 and 4.32.
Just by using mathematics and this is what my machine learning algorithm gives me. Okay.
As I told you in the beginning that there is a difference between mathematics and machine
learning, right? So, the same difference can come over here. Now, let's understand how we can get
this particular m and b value because my machine learning algorithm says this is the best fit value
which means this is the m and b values. Okay. I will not like you to do the exercise because
we are running out of time. So, let's put a let's use m and b to get the y value.
Okay. This is what I am getting if I am using my m and b which I have calculated using pure
mathematics. Okay. And let's see what is our mean square error is. It's coming as 55.89. So,
in your notebook this might not be there because I wanted you to do this exercise. But again,
so once this session is over I will upload everything including the PNGs and all those
things. So, you can just reuse this notebook once again. Okay.
So, our mean square is 55.89. Okay. So, let's plot all three of them. Okay. So, this green is what
comes when I use pure mathematics. This is blue is what provided by linear regression algorithm.
Okay. And these rates are the original points. Okay. Make sense? So, till now are you getting
the sense what is happening over here? Right. I use linear regression algorithm. I find out
that m and b values are somethings and I use mathematics to find out that they are different.
Okay. Now, the idea is to get the best line and the mathematical term is called gradient descent.
Okay. Just a note that you don't need gradient descent to come up with the best line. You can
just randomly generate some number and keep on trying, keep on trying. Sooner or later you will
come up with the best line. But with gradient descent mathematics you will get it sooner.
Okay. That's the only reason why we use gradient descent. Okay. So, mathematics behind gradient
descent is derived from calculus. So, we do partial derivative because in gradient descent
what we do is that we want to change m and see what happens. We want to change b and see what
happens. Okay. So, this is the sum mean squared error formula is original minus predicted whole
square of all. Right. Sum of mean square error. So, this y predicted can be substituted with mx
plus b. Okay. So, if I want to do a partial derivative with respect to m, this will come
as minus 2x y minus mx plus b. This can be simplified as minus 2x y minus mx plus b.
Y original is what we have provided with our data set. This is predicted. What we are predicting now.
Original is original dollars at that particular distance. Predicted is what we get when we apply
our m and b values. Okay. If you simplify this, this will come as y minus mx plus b.
Mx plus b can be substituted with y predicted. Okay. So, basically y original minus y predicted
minus 2x is what happens when you change m. Similarly, if you change b. So, there are many
online calculus things where you just put this formula. It will tell you step by step how it is
being done. This is simplified as minus 2y minus mx minus b which is simplified as minus 2y minus
mx plus b. So, this can be simplified as minus 2y minus y predicted. This y is original. This is y
predicted. Okay. So, once we have the gradient, gradient descent is a mathematical way of finding
the proper value, proper minimum. Okay. Beyond which you cannot find the best value. Okay.
So, once we have this gradient, we can apply this formula to our
m and b and get the new values. Okay. So, let's do this. Okay.
So, I start with m and b value with zero. Iterations is 100,000. Let me put it thousand first.
Number of iterations are called epochs in machine learning. So, if you create a neural network
instance using Keras or any other things, wherever you encounter the term epochs,
its number of times these things will be done. I said learning rate, it has to be very small.
Otherwise, there are chances that things will escape. You will not be able to find the local
minima. And n is number of elements. Okay. So, what I am trying to do is that 1000 times,
I calculate the new y value. Okay. And I am getting the gradient. Like you can see that sum of
2x into y predicted minus y original minus y predicted. 2x y original minus y predicted.
For b, 2y original minus y predicted minus 2y original minus y predicted. Okay. And I multiply
each of them by learning rate. And if I do that, my bn m value changes to 1.6 and 0.72.
And my original values are 1.39 and 10.55. Of course, this is not great. So, we have to increase
the iterations. So, let's do it for 100,000 times. Star means still calculating. It will take some
time. Come on. Okay. You can see that it came very near to the original value. 1.39, 10.54.
Okay. And this is what our linear regression algorithm does internally.
Okay. So, linear regression algorithm, it takes the gradient descent and tries to find the local
minima. Okay. We can do it any number of times and we can have any starting values. Okay. Let's say
starting value is 2000 or 300, for example. Sooner or later, it will find this value.
But you should either start with 0 or mn b value you get from mathematics. Why is that?
Any reason you can think of?
Okay. So, if we don't provide either 0 or mn b we got from mathematics, we don't add any biases,
which means that if you provide random values, it will take more number of iterations to come
to local minima. If you use 0, it will take less number of iterations to come to local minima.
That's the only reason we use 0. Otherwise, you are free to use any number you want. Yes.
Correct.
Well, you care about those decimal spaces if it actually impacts your result. So,
right now what we are seeing while we are learning is very simple small amount of data set.
For example, if you are getting data for, let's say, black hole data,
even small changes in those decimal points can give you a different result.
So, if you have that much data and that much precision is required, it is required.
But in normal terms, it is not required. It's only for scientific reasons it is required.
If you are doing scientific computing, yes, you have to take care of those precisions.
Because a small amount of difference means a lot if you are considering the distance
between galaxies and so on and so forth. Yes.
Okay. The learning rate is that, okay, I have to change. Let's say you change,
M and B says that you change with, let's say, 10 steps. I said that don't do 10 steps. You might
skip the door. Just do very small step. That's what learning rate is. It has to be very small.
Otherwise, our intention is to find local minima. If we give bigger learning rate,
we may keep on just rotating around and skipping the door. Okay. So, I guess it's 10, 15.
Okay. So, 15. Snacks will be over. So, you can go for snacks and come back. Then we'll continue.
As soon as possible. 10 minutes should be good enough. Okay. You can bring your snacks.
In the meantime, anyone has any questions, I am free to answer.
Yes.
Yes, you can use.
Okay.
.