All right. Hello, everybody. Let's get started. Our speaker today is Ferris. He is the founder
of the Salt Lake City Python meetup and the head Python janitor at team. He's going to
talk to us about meetups. Take it away, Ferris.
Hey, how's it going, everybody? Everybody have any good PyCon? Yeah. So welcome to the
biggest meetup of them all. PyCon 2019. I'm hoping everybody is having a good time today.
Yeah, this is my little talk. I have a quick poll before we get started. Who here has attended
a meetup? Yeah, like pretty much everybody in the audience. I dig it. Now keep your hand
up if it was a Python meetup. Still a few. Okay. And then now keep your hand if you've
helped organize a Python meetup. Excellent. I want all these people who are still raising
their hands after this, give them a pat on the back because this stuff is hard, okay?
This is the human side of stuff. So, yeah, let's get started here. First off, who am
I? I started the Salt Lake City Python meetup group accidentally. I think that's how a lot
groups accidentally. I'm a big fan of the Django meetup in Vancouver. That was one of
the ones I used to go to a lot. Anybody from Vancouver, Canada? Yeah, up in here. And then
the bad old days of the Salt Lake Linux users group, they were good old days. Yeah, I started
the meetup group in a coffee shop when I saw a couple individuals sitting there with their
Django admin tools open up. I was like, hey, is that Django? Are you guys doing some Django
programming? Let's talk about this. And we realized there wasn't a meetup group that
was that close to us. So let me show you a little bit of Utah's geography. So this is
Utah right here. We're the one that's not on fire at present. So this is pretty much
what the summer looks like. No, we get lots of fires, too. If you're trying to avoid burnout
in the valley in Pacific Northwest, you can literally avoid it by going to Utah sometimes,
it looks like. But yeah, we're this state over here. A little bit about our first Salt
Lake City meetup. Oh, dear. It's the wrong slide for some reason. Yeah. My apologies
here. Okay. That slide's not showing up. So I'm going to point it out over here. So the
original meetup used to be all the way down here. And here's downtown Salt Lake City.
So our first meetup, we decided to restart in a little lovely named neighborhood called
Sugar House. Yes, that is literally the name of the neighborhood. Utah's quite a fantasy
place. And now we're at the University of Utah. We just call this the U. They're very
picky about calling it the U. And then I have to give a few disclaimers. So I've been thinking
about this talk for like three years. And I finally submitted it. And then I ended up
getting bought by WeWork. Like our company was bought by WeWork. And as you might know,
WeWork also owns Meetup. So this is my legal disclaimer. I'm not speaking on behalf of
WeWork or Meetup. This is Ferris right here talking to his fellow Pythonistas. So only
giving my personal experiences. You might have your own ideas. And we're going to talk
about that in room 16 at 16 o'clock after this. So we're going to have like a there's
a secondary thing. If you're an organizer, I encourage you to go. If you go to Meetups,
I encourage you to go. And we can have more discussion about that. So who here has ever
gotten this email right here? Anybody? Yeah. Yeah. You're like, my Meetup group's going
to shut down. All those people, all that Python, all those lessons. I'm going to have to drive
four or five hours away to go to another Meetup group if that. And who knows if that's going
to work out. So you do what anybody does. And you click that giant red button to keep
the Meetup going. And you're going to keep this group going. And you know what? It's
just going to be easy. You just have to find a space and pizza. And you have to keep track
of money. Uh-oh. You're going to need some help. Because guess what? You're now the organizer
of a Meetup group. And this is exactly what happened to me almost or more than five years
ago. And I have some like number one thing that you should get out of this talk. Guess
what? It's going to be okay. Okay? You're at this presentation. So let's go over a quick
checklist. So first things first. If you're taking over a Meetup, you should do these
three things. Okay? First thing you should do is you're going to ensure that your Meetup
group is not scripted. Sorry. Ensure that your dues are paid, obviously. But you're
also going to chat with the old organizer. Why are they stepping down? It could be the
case that there's just a glitch. They're changing their email or they click the wrong button
and then they immediately hop back on five minutes later. But good for you for clicking
that red button anyway and trying to snatch that Meetup. And yes, this did actually happen
to me as well. It was like, oh, I'm going to do this other Meetup. No. They were just
doing something. They still wanted to run the Meetup. Make sure your dues are paid.
And reintroduce yourself to the members. So once you click that button, you're going to
get a bunch of Meetup tools. One of them is email your members. Email them. Let them
know who you are. Let them know that, hey, this Meetup is going to keep going. And that
last point could be tricky. Okay? Because you're putting yourself out in the world.
And if you're not really ready to do that, maybe don't organize a Meetup quite yet, but
keep going to them. That's my advice there. And one more thing, you've got to plan and
schedule your next Meetup. Make sure that is ready to go. Don't do it immediately. Give
yourself like four weeks. But you're going to have to plan. And we're going to go through
how to do that as well. And again, seriously, it's going to be okay. And you know why that
is? Because Python has a superpower. Does anybody know what it is? Is it the interpretation?
No. Is it the ubiquity? Kind of. But what's the greatest superpower of Python? It's the
community. Yeah. Who said that? You said that. Yes. Thank you. So you being here today, right
now, it shows that you recognize this. Okay? It's the second best language for everything,
but the community. It's the number one in community. I've been to other conferences
where they reference PyCon and the Python community as an exemplar community of what
they want for their standards. So here's a picture, by the way. This is our soiree we
hold every year. This is our community. This is our little Salt Lake City Python community.
We have a once-a-year anniversary. I have to tell you, these 27 Pythonistas who made
it, we made it through a foot of snow. This was some of the worst snowfall that we had
that day. And it just happened to coincide with our fifth year anniversary. And they
all made it. So the Python community is awesome. And what that means is that if you're part
of a community of programmers, that means that programming isn't the thing anymore.
Programming is just a tool. We shouldn't call ourselves programmers. We should call ourselves
whatever we're doing. You don't call somebody who pours cement like a cement pourer. You
call them a landscaper, right? The cement pouring is just a tool in their tool belt.
It's the same thing. We have lots of examples now. Katie Bowman, you know, she did her continuous
high-resolution image reconstruction using PatchPriors, aka the Chirp project. And now
we're able to see a black hole. How cool is that? And that's Python and that's the community.
Right? There's also an art scene that's coming up around Python. This was a commissioned
piece of art for our meetup. There you go. Beautiful is better than ugly. 801 is our
little area code. There's a little snake. And this was commissioned art. And this is
a shout out to at dead binky on Twitter and Instagram. She does a lot of work involving
So we just had to have her do our T-shirt logo. And the other thing, Python's awesome.
And Pythonistas are awe-inspiring. So the people part, that's the hard part. And that's
what your job as the organizer is, is to make sure that Python keeps going. So to do that,
you have to make sure that humans keep going. And Python wouldn't be the language today
if it wasn't for the community. We said that enough. So one thing that people have, I feel
like people have started to forget in this age of social everything all the time, like
I'm literally getting a notification because I forgot to mute it before the talk. Software
is for people, right? It's for people, not computers. And you probably are going to hear
this a number of times at this conference. When we're thinking about software for people,
this is how you can get that exchange of a diverse set of ideas. And now you get to orchestrate
a community experience. Now, what's a community experience? It's any gathering of people.
And all of you pretty much have taken place in a community experience of PyCon. But what
are some other ones? Airports, rodeos, you've all been to a rodeo, right? Well, you should
go to a rodeo, okay? And PyCon, of course. This is a community experience. And what you
should take from that is that your meetup is just a small-scale PyCon. It's just a small-scale
community experience that you get to facilitate. And remember, community defines Python. So
how do you run a successful meetup given all that? First thing you're going to do is you're
going to go to meetups or go to PyCon. And guess what? You're already here. Isn't that
great? So now what you need to do is absorb your experience. Seriously, it's just like
how when you practice the same thing over and over without trying to improve, without
studying what you're getting wrong, you're never going to do well with that. So what
you have to do at this PyCon, if you want to start your own meetup, absorb your experience
right now. For example, I'm a speaker, right? But before I came up here, I was coached by
our awesome session chair over here. And this is the result of a lot of people coming together.
We have our cameraman, we have our sound, we have somebody interpreting the words coming
out of my mouth right now. Thank you very much. And you should think about what's your
favorite experience at PyCon and what do you want to copy from that? And you're going to
copy it because that's what we do. We copy that experience and we make it better. And
isn't that all we do with code? I mean, who copies code from GitHub? Come on. Yeah. Or
Stack Overflow. It's the same thing. You're going to be doing the same thing but with
a community experience. Now, I'm going to give you a bunch of advice right now that
are my personal advice that I think makes a successful meetup and will keep that meetup
going. So the first one would be you want to keep a consistent date. Okay? You're going
to start with no more than one meetup a month and be sure it's at the same time every month.
So for example, it should be one sentence. Salt Lake City Python meets on the first Wednesday
of each month at the University of Utah. Great. That's your one sentence pitch to everybody.
And this is my chance, even though this is a very, you know, it's a softer, less technical
talk, I'm going to do some live Python right here. Yeah. So the date utility library learned
a lot about this at the tutorial. Render that. And there we go. So this is how you would
interpret in Python when our meetup group meets. I just thought I'd nerd out a little
bit with everybody and with my people. Venue. So venue is one of the trickiest things that
you're going to need if you're going to have a successful meetup. This is probably one
of those hard problems that you don't think about until you realize that a meetup is like
a fourth dimensional space and, oh, I need a time and a place. It can be really hard
to get. So here's some ideas. First one that everybody seems to forget about in our field
for whatever reason is your local library. Okay. Libraries. Who's been to a library in
the last three years? Okay. Okay. I'm digging it. Just with my people. But what I'm saying
is that libraries, they're not just about, you know, books anymore. They have 3D printers.
Ours has a telescope checkout system. So you can literally check out a telescope. They
have lessons for kids. Lots of summer coding camps for kids now. And you can involve yourself
in that. That's just one more community experience that you get to enrich it. Your local college
or university. We were very lucky to have the University of Utah actually reach out
to us and offer a space every month. Another potential one is to reach out to local companies
with the intention of maintaining that consistent location. So for example, there's the new
startups that are always going on. We have a data engineering meetup in Salt Lake City.
And they decided we're going to be based out of Pluralsight. It's a consistent location.
Great for their venue. And it works. Another one is the WeWork community associate or community
lead of hospitality. And here's the disclaimer, though. There's no WeWorks in Salt Lake City
yet. So I've never run one out of there. But I know that WeWork is pushing this. So this
might be a nice ticket in. If there's a WeWork next to you, go talk to their community associate
or community lead of hospitality. They'll give you some good advice on that. So the
next thing you're going to need is somebody like me who can just talk, apparently. You're
going to need presenters. By the way, this is Ken Myers. This is one of the individuals
who is sitting on the Django toolbar. He focuses more on ETL and database stuff. But he was
still able to give a really good talk about data modeling in Python. And to find those
speakers, you need to realize every meetup that you host, it's an opportunity to find
those speakers. You need to encourage your members to step up and try giving a talk.
I didn't just come to PyCon all of a sudden. I've been giving talks at my meetup and other
meetups. And it's the same with most of the speakers here. They started at a meetup. Okay?
The last point, you're likely going to be the first speaker at your meetup. Sorry, not
sorry, because it is a fun experience to do that. But at the same time, it can be a little
bit intimidating. Next point, sponsorship and money. This is something that I didn't
realize would actually be kind of important to keep track of, who would have known. Running
a good meetup is the key to getting that sponsorship. If you run a good meetup, that sponsorship's
easy. I have three guidelines for this. And it's going to solve 99% of your issues. The
first one is you're going to want to make sure that you have a specified time slot for
your sponsors. Because they're going to want to take over the meetup, whether it's a recruiter
or something. We all love recruiter calls, don't we? Recruiter emails. No, nobody loves
those. So what you're going to want to do is make sure that you tell them the rules.
You tell them, hey, we're going to give you three minutes to do a spiel. Don't let them
dominate the conversation. And use open accounting. This is our open accounting right here. If
you go to meetup.com, slash SLC Python, slash money right now, you can see all of our accounting
up through February. Yeah, I fell behind on this because I was working on this talk. But
that's where it is, all of the accountings on the books. On top of that, I'm happy to
report, I didn't know this until a couple days ago, because I have some awesome members
working on it. As of Monday, we're a 501C3. So that's where you can get, if you keep track
of the money right, yeah, thank you. This gentleman over here. Another thing, most important
thing is you need to be human. We're all bags of meat trying to make our way through this
world. Get rid of that robot side of you for just a second and realize this one thing.
A good tech meetup, it's 20% tech and 80% networking. Another thing you'll need to do in order to
remember that, keep going to other meetups. This is something I personally neglected to
do when I first started. Just a little bit burned out by trying to maintain a brand new
Salt Lake City Python meetup. We went from 80 members to 2,500 members in the course
of five years. So yeah, you can get a little burned out. But at the same time, there's
some other meetups that you can check out. They don't have to be tech meetups. There
was a skeptic society meetup that I found fascinating. Different group of people, different
format. But I still got some ideas and I was able to port them into our meetup. One
thing, another thing, there's lots of things I'm talking about today. Never ever forget
that everybody starts out with the ability to use tech. Okay? One thing that's amazing
about this community, the tech community, it's their passes, race, gender, creed, it
welcomes everybody. And we know this. We're at PyCon. But make sure that your meetup is
also an example of this. Make sure that your meetup is a place where somebody can become
a better human being. So given all this, what's a basic agenda look like? An agenda is key
to a good meetup. It looks kind of like this. So here's a link. For some reason, bit.ly
didn't work for me today. So the link's up here. I also linked these, I pinned these
slides to my Twitter profile. So we can catch those later. But let's go through our meetup
agenda. So first thing I like to do is we do our networking and pizza. This is a great
time to introduce yourself to new members and introduce them to other members. While
you're doing these intros and sponsors, you're going to talk about other local meetups. Because,
again, you're trying to get that network effect going. This is also a chance to do a, this
is also a chance for your sponsors to have their plug. And you can give their spiel for
example, X missions, our local friendly, organic ISP. They've been sponsoring us for the last
two years. So we always give them a quick shout out. And it's just like that. There's
their shout out. And that's the next thing you're going to want to do while you're doing
introductions. You're going to be looking at who's hiring. This is another opportunity.
Once you start this meetup, you're going to get a lot of meetup.com messages. And take
that opportunity to say come to the meetup. That's where you can start advertising for
jobs. Things like that. Again, this is just a slice of PyCon. We're just taking that slice
of PyCon. We have a job fair coming up Sunday. So we have our job fair on Sunday. It's the
same thing. We're just taking a slice of something that works. Put it in your meetup. Next thing,
who's looking? This is a great opportunity to get those Pythonistas to give their spiel
about themselves. One kudos that I like about our tech community in Utah, we tend to have
more people who are hiring than looking, which is phenomenal. And then you talk about community
news. So for example, you can talk about local community news. This isn't actually happening.
Guto's not coming to Utah. That would be awesome if he was. But it's just an example. And then
you can talk about global community news like Python 4. This is happening. No, I'm just
kidding. It's not happening either. Again, both of this is fake news. So much fake news.
Talks. Again, this is just PyCon but smaller. There's some differences, though. What you're
going to need to do is you're going to have to give that first talk, as I said. And I
believe in you in giving this talk. And you're also going to make sure that your first talk
is a beginner talk. So what we've changed formats in the last 18 months, where our first
15 to 20 minutes, myself or one of my colleagues, we'll just sit and answer general Python questions.
We'll show you how to install VS code and Anaconda and things like that. Because we
have a lot of Windows users. I'm just a Mac user. But I used to be a Mac user. Sorry.
I'm a Linux user. And we have a lot of Windows users. And I could never answer for them,
how do they get started? How do they learn Python? I said, well, let's just do a beginner
talk. And we'd work through that stuff. Your members' first talks, you're going to coach
those. So once they say, hey, I'm going to be your speaker for June 3rd or whatever the
next meetup is, keep in touch with them. Touch base with them every weekend to make sure
that they know that, yeah, this stuff's hard. But this is what they can improve on with
their slides. This is some other things that people have talked about. And it'll come easy.
Another piece of advice that I like to give to everybody, take a chance to record and
stream your meetups as soon as you can. We neglected to do this for our first year. So
this is a lesson that we learned. And in retrospect, it would have been very handy to be able to
interact with more than just our local tech community. Another example of why this is
important, Nina, who is going to be our keynote speaker, she actually did one of her first
talks at our little meetup. OBS is a great program for this, by the way, OBSproject.com.
If you don't know how to use OBS, just find any 12-year-old who likes to stream Fortnite
and they will teach you how to run OBS for your meetup. Next thing that we do, well,
at the very end, after the talks, is we'll do raffle prizes. So here's an orange pie.
An orange pie, it's just like a raspberry pie, but you can buy more than three of them
online. So that's pretty awesome. Next thing, this isn't part of the agenda, but this is
something that we do every year. Once a year, we need to come through and celebrate your
members and their community. What's really great about this is it's a good opportunity
to do fundraising, to do network building, but also it's an opportunity for your meetup
members to bring their spouses, people who normally wouldn't go to a technical meetup,
and realize, oh, this is what you've been doing every month? Like, what is this? It's
just a lot of cake. And yes, there's a lot of cake during our S4As. So this is our very
first one. This is last minute, can you tell? It was a cookie that had some whipped cream
slapped on top. This is our first year anniversary, and, you know, as the years go by, our cake
gets better and better. And for some reason, I'm missing all my other cake slides, but
that's okay. Yeah, and that's what I was going to talk about with that. Another place, as
I said before when I started this talk, we're going to have an open space at PyCon right
after this talk for more involved questions. I want to hear from you what's working. It's
going to be room 16 at 16 o'clock. And there's some more resources and inspiration. This
is the Python wiki on starting your users group. I've taken some advice on that. I've
tweaked a bit of the advice on that because I found it didn't work. But it's another good
start, another good place to look. I'm nearing the end of my talk now. Let's give a special
thanks, though. This is Dylan on the left. So he's run the last two meetups. So I think
what I'm talking about kind of works if he was able to take this and keep our meetup
going, even though I'm at PyCon this year. I can't count the number of times that Dylan
has also stepped up and given a talk when one of our speakers just dropped or we didn't
have enough to speak about that meetup. And, yeah, so thank you, Dylan. And we can do an
AMA perhaps in the hallway. How are we on time? By the way, my clock just stopped on
this thing. So seven minutes? Okay. Yeah, we'll do an AMA after this. But one thing
real quick, if you're ever in Salt Lake City, I encourage you, be my guest. Please come
to a meetup. Meetup.com slash SLC Python. We're more than happy to have you. And thank
you for coming here and listening and trying to improve the Python community. And I'm more
than happy to answer some questions at the microphone if somebody had some.
Five minutes for questions. So please step up to the audience microphones if you have
any questions. Hi. Hello. So great talk. Thank you. I had a question about platform for how
you organize these things. Everyone seems to use meetup.com, which is a really handy
site. But it's not the only game in town. And I know that there's another site called
get together.community, I believe, which is meant to be like an open, federated version
of meetup. I don't know if there are other options out there as well. Do you know anything
about this? And do you have any thoughts about alternate platforms? So again, I'm speaking
for myself because technically I'm an employee of the same ones as meetup. I personally have
enjoyed using meetup because it's been around since forever. I mean, I used meetup before
So that's why I knew about meetup. Facebook is another place to go, but I don't have an
account and a lot of people don't. I don't know about what was the...
Get together dot community. Get together dot community. I will need to check that out.
No, platform-wise, meetup, the number one feature I like as an organizer is it gives
you some tools to grow, gives you ways to print name tags, and it lets you do open accounting,
which is just a killer feature for me. But if get together has that, I'll definitely
check it out. Thanks for the question. Sure. Are there other questions? Oh.
Do you have any resources on establishing a code of conduct for a new meetup?
That's a good question. So the question was, are there any thoughts or resources for establishing
a code of conduct? To which the answer is, we literally link the Python code of conduct.
We say you follow this one and you're good. When it comes to enforcement of that code
of conduct, we've only had to do enforcement action once, and in that case, it was just
a conversation the next day. Literally, I bought the guy lunch. I went through, hey,
what you said to this person, it can be misconstrued. I'm going to ask that you don't go to this
meetup for the next one, but after that, things worked out. So that's what we do, is we follow
the Python code of conduct. But that's an excellent question. Yes?
Thanks. Appreciate the talk. I was wondering if you could comment on finding presenters
and the challenges there, because that seems to be one of the big challenges as a person
organizing conferences. And another question, as you're organizing this, a lot of people
organizing this, would it be valuable to have a space where people who organize meetups
could get together virtually to share stories or even like an onboarding process to be a
meetup leader? So your second point is a fantastic idea,
I have to say. Perhaps after this, we can look into making a Slack group or something,
because Slack is literally here, so we can just beg them for a free workspace or something.
To your first point, finding presenters is difficult. A lot of the time, they will end
up coming to you as you get going, but that initial hurdle, it's tricky. A lot of my initial
presenters were coworkers and people I knew from other meetups. So that's why I encourage
you to go to other meetups before you get started. This gentleman over here, and then
we'll go back. Is this on? Yeah. So sponsors for meetups,
oftentimes the sponsors want the meetup to be in their space, because it's often a hiring
tool and getting people into the space is a huge boon to recruiting. But that kind of
consistent location principle. What are your thoughts on that and how have you handled
that when it's come up? So we consider the University of Utah to be
a sponsor. We have looked into the fee that they would normally charge for the use of
a room, and we just do, in our accounting, we will do plus minus. And we put the University
of Utah, they get the same spiel time as anybody else, and we just give them kudos. If the
company that is looking to sponsor in their location wants to do more than that, arrange
it ahead of time. But I honestly think that as long as you're focusing on your participants
and Pythonistas, the rest will come naturally. Again, this is a rule of thumb. Your mileage
may vary, but that's what's worked for us. Yes?
What was like, do you have any big shocks from going as a meetup participant to a meetup
especially if you start a meetup from scratch and not take it over from someone else?
That's a good question. On Wednesday, I was missing a meetup, and Dylan was really nice,
and he set up a video chat. And what was phenomenal to me, the big shock, was it was the first
time I had organized something that didn't rely on me, on one individual. That that community
could keep going, and they set up a video chat. So I could keep chatting from a hotel
in downtown Cleveland and say, hey, everybody, we got 501c3. Isn't that great news? That
was one of the biggest shocks. That's a good question. Thank you.
You mentioned Dylan is your co-organizer. How deep is your bench of co-organizers? I
travel a lot. Is that just not suitable for someone who travels a lot to organize a meetup?
Or do you just have a deeper bench and how deep that needs to be?
That's a good question. This year, I've traveled more than I have, I feel like, in my entire
life, and Dylan has stepped up. My bench right now is probably there are two people I could
rely on other than myself to run this meetup. But that's a good question. It's something
I'll personally need to think about. Hello. What do you find most effective for
communicating to the community for turnout, like frequency, initial kind of messaging,
like, hey, this meetup is happening, and reminder, we have a meetup tomorrow?
So the most effective one, initially this doesn't work, but the most effective is having
that consistent date and time and location. But if you can make sure that your meetup
is that slot, the first Wednesday of every month. And the other thing is we accidentally
bumped up against the big data user group in Utah is also the first Wednesday. So I
don't know, we've been stealing from them, but not intentionally.
I guess what I mean is on messaging, communicating out to the audience. Like, let's say you have
an established time, and then where, like, what we do is I communicate out a week before,
I open up the meetup a week before, and then I switch between either two days before or
the day before, remind people, hey, we have a meetup in two days or we have a meetup tomorrow.
Okay. We're really lucky. I don't have to do that. There is a Twitter bot in Salt Lake
City that will find meetups that are tech, and it will automatically tweet a week before
saying, hey, are you going to this meetup? It's going to be about this. Sometimes it
gets it wrong. Like, this meetup is going to be about the fifth anniversary soiree.
It's like, no, that doesn't make sense. And then it will also tweet the day before. So
a number of our members follow that bot. In addition, whenever we have announcements,
I try to every quarter do kind of a state of the meetup email to all of our participants.
Good question. Thank you.
All right. That's all the time we have. Let's give Ferris another round of applause.
Thank you very much.