.
Buddy, welcome everybody. We are here with Victor Stinner to
discuss how to, I lost the title of the talk. We're talking
about Python contributors for Python projects. Take it away,
Victor.
» Hi, everybody. I'm Victor Stinner. I'm working for
Red Hat.
I'm here to talk about how to engage Python contributors in the
long term.
Or say differently, tech is easy, but people are complex.
I hear many people saying that Python is all about code.
Nope. Liar.
I'm here to talk about Python.
I'm here to begin my journey with an event which happened last
year for me.
It was a burnout.
So, what does it mean, a burnout?
Last year, I decided to unsubscribe from seven different
Python mailing lists. I also closed all my pull requests.
I used my filters to ignore all notification coming from Python
and I decided to do something related to Python. This is
something really huge for me because Python was like, I was
doing that like all the time and suddenly I stopped to do
anything related to Python.
It's like a giant change for me.
So, I went to the doctor who asked me to stay at home for one
month.
I also decided to stop to work on Python for three months and a
month and a half, which is, I think, the longest period of no
activity from my side on Python.
To give you an idea of my involvement into Python, this
was my typical inbox.
So, you can see that there are many folders like the Python
billboards, the bug tracker, the mailing list for core
developers, the mentorship mailing list,
the notification from GitHub, there is also mail and
emails from my customers.
There is also the security and a mailing list from users.
So, I was doing many, many different things.
And I'm trying to read all my emails at the end of the day.
So, try to read all emails was more and more difficult for me.
So, what I understood from the burnout is that maybe, maybe
it's time for me to step back a little bit from Python because
I'm just doing way too many things and it's not going to be
fine.
So, to explain you why I'm doing so many things in Python is
that I didn't decide one day to take all the responsibilities
in Python.
It's more than I decided to pick one more responsibility every
six months.
And after a few years, I was just responsible of too many
things.
And I was working something like 30 hours in average per day
which is way too much for a human.
But I will not elaborate all reasons for the burnout because
it's also something very personal.
And I prefer to not elaborate here.
So, I decided to take one more responsibility every six months
because I'm not going to take all the responsibilities.
So, to come back to the open source, the problem is that I
don't scale.
Even if I would like to work more hours per day, it's not
physically possible.
And I also see an increase of the workload in Python.
There are more and more things to do in Python in general.
And there is a decrease of the new core developers per year.
And there is the number of open issues over the last seven
years.
And you can see that it's a straight line.
We are getting more and more open issues.
It's just increasing.
And to give you an idea of the pull request, today we are over
1,000 open pull requests.
And almost 7,000 open issues.
And we are getting more and more open issues.
So, we are getting more and more open issues.
But if you look at the bottom, it's the number of new core
developers per year.
And you can see that the trend is more and we are getting less.
So, the workload is increasing and the new core developers is
a little bit more.
And also, as you saw, we are getting more and more open issues.
And we are closer to 30.
And I like this comment that I found on the
commit strip.com website.
It shows how people expect that open source is done.
So, what can we see here?
is a manager saying that, oh, I have assigned a team
to blah, blah, blah, which means that even outside
this picture, there is even more resources to do the work.
There is someone bringing coffee.
And we can also expect that they are working during the day.
And you can compare that to the reality.
And this is how open source applications are really
maintained.
So here you have a single person working, obviously,
in the middle of the night.
There is a cat waiting on the couch for these people
to stop working.
And he says, hmm, maybe just one more
ticket before going to bed.
So it means that in practice, open source
is done by volunteers.
And they are doing that in addition to their work.
You often hear the sentence, we are all volunteers.
And I would like to elaborate the sentence a little bit.
Contributors are giving their free time to Python.
So what is free time?
It means that it can mean evening, weekends, maybe
also part of the night.
And you have to understand that a day
has a fixed number of hours.
And if you remove the time used to sleep,
you don't have so much time per day.
So each time that you spend off Python,
you are taking it from something else.
So it means that people who would like to contribute
to Python as a contributor have to trade this time
between friends and family on Python.
And sadly, few employers allow their employee
to contribute to Python upstream.
But there are a few of them.
I'm feeling very lucky because I'm working for Red Hat
and I'm paid full time to maintain Python upstream
but also downstream.
So to fix issues in a rel on Fedora.
From Microsoft, there is Brett Cannon, Barry Warsaw,
Eric Snow, Steve Dower, who have one day per week.
At Dropbox, Guido Van Rossum has more or less
50% of his time on Python.
Kotlsoft, we have Emily Morehouse,
who also have one day per week.
And there are also Neil Shimenowa and Inada Naoki
who have also one day per week.
But if you put all these people all together,
at the end you have almost three people,
three developers paid full time.
And honestly, that's not a lot of developers
who are paid to work on Python.
Especially when you compare the popularity of Python.
It's according to the Tire Index,
which is a website which measure the popularity
and usage of programming language,
Python is just the third most popular
world language in the world.
The first complaint about contributors is that
they succeed to produce a pull request
but nobody wants to merge a pull request.
And Brett Cannon found a good explanation for this issue.
Maybe you can think of a contribution like a puppy.
You may view it as this cute, wonderful thing
you are giving me, while I'm looking at it
as an over decayed of feeding, walking on wet bills.
So to explain to you what it means in Python,
is that when I would like to click on the merge button,
if I click on it, I will be responsible for the change code.
So if anyone complains, if there is a regression,
if it's causing more troubles,
I will be the one responsible for this issues.
And sometimes I don't want to get these responsibilities
because I already have enough of them.
We already did some actions in the past
to try to work on this scalability issues.
For example, we now have a developer guide
to explain the workflow, how to create a pull request,
where to find the information.
We migrated from Mercurial to Git on GitHub
and the purpose is to simplify the creation
of the UFORCE pull request,
but also to simplify the workflow.
We now have a CI running on Linux
and another one running on Windows,
which is run when you propose a change.
And this is really helpful for the core developers
who click on the merge button
because they can be more confident in the change.
But even with all these actions,
the core developers are still the bottleneck of the workflow.
And to explain it differently,
you cannot solve people problem with software.
So now let's see the diversity problems.
First of all, I commonly hear,
oh, there is no complaint about diversity,
so there is no diversity issue.
And Marietta Vigiaia shared a tweet saying that
when women speak out about diversity in the community,
they get penalized, branded as non-technical.
Some women chose not to speak out because of death.
We will not be silenced.
So there are different issues in a community like Python.
It's a set of things that I would call
the toxicity of the community.
For example, when someone proposed a change in Python,
some people, instead of arguing at the technical level,
they tend to attack directly the outer of the proposal.
And this is not a good way to behave on the main list.
And we really have to stay at the technical level,
especially because when you are involved in a project
like Python, it can be difficult to handle this criticism.
And the attacks can be in the public space,
but sometimes it continues in the private space,
and sometimes it even works,
even only happens in the private space,
which means that we are not aware of it
and we cannot take any action.
And this is also why some people consider
that there is no diversity issue,
is that these issues are hidden.
Toxicity can also be bullying, misogyny, or racism.
To give you a concrete example of the diversity issues,
I noticed that some project decided to get rid
of the master and slave terms
because they are badly connoted as slavery.
And sometimes it's not really appropriate,
not the best term that you can use.
So what I did is to,
my computer is fine.
What I did is just to replace the terms
in only the documentation and in comments.
For example, I replaced master process with parent process.
And for the networking, I replaced client and master
with client on server.
For the build bot, I replaced build slave
with build bot workers,
because build slave was the old term,
but in the newer version of build bot,
it's build bot workers.
But I think that the worst term was client slaves,
which has been replaced by helpers.
So a journalist became aware of this change
and decided to write an article about that
on the news website called The Register.
And from that point, many, many other website
decided to discuss this topic.
There were articles in Russia Today,
Breitbart, develop.com, Hacker News,
Motherboard VS, slash.forshan, West China,
Twitter, Weibo, and many others.
And people commented this issue in English,
Russian, Japanese, Chinese, German, French,
Czech, and many other language.
And all these articles mentioned not only my full name,
but also my employer.
And to give you an idea of the volume of the discussion
just on Slashdots in two days,
there were more than 1,200 comments.
And to give you an idea of the quality of the discussion
on how people like this change,
I just chose two examples from Forchan,
which is a website where people are anonymous.
And it says, fuck you, Victor Stienaer,
you are the enemy of Slashdot now, eat shit.
I will probably make a video about this gay shit.
And someone else is even more direct.
I would like him dead.
Okay.
Honestly, I did not expect this violence
and this amount of communication and debate.
I did not expect anything
because it was only a change in Python.
And many people who don't know anything about Python
started to discuss this thing.
But it's just to give you an example of the diversity issues.
Okay, we saw the problems, so let's see the solutions.
First of all, as I said, it's not a technical issue,
it's a human issue.
So you need a different tool.
You cannot use a debugger,
but what you can do is, for example, psychology.
And there is something called the unconscious biases.
They are social stereotypes about certain group of people
that individuals forms outside their mind
outside their own conscious awareness.
So it's a little bit tricky to understand it,
but the key point is that there are biases
and you are not aware of them.
It means that even if you are trying to not be racist,
to not have stereotypes, you still have stereotypes.
And I found a good example to explain you that
today we have more and more machine learning
and some people decided to apply machine learning
to the justice to help to take decision.
And a study has been made on the machine learning
used to predict future crime.
And the study says that the machine learning
is biased against black people.
So this is just one example of two people
who have been arrested because they possessed drug.
And the white person got a score of three,
which is low risk.
And the black person got a score of 10, which is high risk.
But the machine learning failed
because the white person has been arrested three more times
and the black person has not been arrested after that.
And machine learning, to try to simplify
as much as possible, you have data, you have the training,
and from that you get prediction.
So if the prediction is racist,
maybe the issue is coming from your input data.
And what I'm trying to say is that thanks to software,
we can look at ourself inside a mirror
and we can see that we are racist.
It's part of us.
It's just that the software is telling us that we are racist.
Something else which is helpful to understand
the human relationship and how people behave
is called the imposter syndrome.
It's a psychological pattern in which an individual
doubts their accomplishments
and has a persistent internalized fear
of being exposed as a fraud.
So again, it's not really easy to understand what it means.
To explain it differently, I would say that you consider
that you don't deserve what you get.
And I think a good example of the imposter syndrome
is that nowadays more and more people
are using the social media, social networks.
And the thing is that when you go to these websites,
people are only sharing the best of themselves.
They try to share photos of their latest amazing travel,
of their beautiful children, of their children,
of their funny pictures of cats.
And when you look at all of this, slowly you consider
that your life is less interesting
than the life of your friends
because you compare your life to the life
of people using the social media.
And because of that, some therapists started to say
that the social media are making us more depressed.
And the thing is that this is one example
of the imposter syndrome because you consider
that your life is less interesting.
It's just because social media are designed
to make people only share the best of themselves
to only share the positive message.
When someone is sick in your family,
if you get a very boring day,
nobody shares this kind of information
because it's boring.
And I think that we can also make the parallel with work
because it's common that as war people just show
the best of themselves and they try to hide their defects
just because we want to get a promotion,
we want to show that we are very good at what we are doing.
But when you compare yourself to your peers,
you consider that your work is less valuable
just because of that.
Now let's talk about the code of conduct.
So at the beginning, there was no code of conduct.
And it was fine at the beginning
because Python was quite small with a few people,
but slowly Python becomes more and more popular
and we started to see some conflicts between people.
And we say that maybe we need some kind of agreements
of what is a good behavior
and what is an inappropriate behavior.
So code of conduct has been created
and first it has been applied on the mailing list
to continue with the bug tracker and also the websites.
Now the code of conduct is also applied to conferences
like back in US.
And last year, the back in US even used the service
of a company to help to manage code of conduct incidents
because the worst thing that you want to get
in case of code of conduct incidents
is to make the event even worse.
So you have to be able to understand what is the issue,
how to provide the best action
and to be able to react quickly.
So this is not something that we are used to do
and we need some training for that.
And by the way, the Python Software Foundation
even requires a code of conduct
for all conferences called PyCon.
And now the discussion is more about
how to handle incidents and bans
to be blocked on our community.
Some people propose to maybe write down some rules,
but it's a little bit tricky to agree on that.
To come back to the diversity,
the diversity means different things.
And for example, you can see that
as a diversity of point of view
because in Python some people cares more
about the documentation,
some others about the reference counting in C
or the backward compatibility,
the API, the language consistency,
ability to find the simplest solution,
to care about corner cases,
performance, security,
other Python implementation like PyPy.
And if you take a small group of people
who are only experts on certain area,
maybe Python wouldn't be as good as it is today.
We really need this diversity of point of view
to make Python as good as it can be.
It can also means the diversity of use cases
because some people are using Python
for command line interface.
And in that case, what is important is a startup time.
And some people are using Python
for several running for multiple days.
And here what is important is more the memory usage
because you don't want to have to reboot your server
because it's out of memory.
Some people are using the graphical interfaces
for machine learning, develop rest servers,
games, and many other use cases.
To give you a very concrete example of what I said,
Naoki Inada has been promoted as a core developer
three years ago.
And he has been selected as a BDFL delegate.
So the one to take the decision on a PEP.
For the PEP 538, which is a C local question,
and my PEP 340, which is a UTF-8 mode.
And what we can see is that in fact,
English speakers are just satisfied with ASCII
because it's plenty enough to write
whatever you want in English.
But maybe people from Japan are more used
to Unicode issues.
So it's something which are really bugging them every day.
And for Naoki Inada, it's really important
to make sure that Python is working in all cases
for any kind of encoding.
Okay, now let's see the mentoring.
And I would like to begin with the positive actions.
So three years ago at the SpyCon,
Willow Van Rossum encouraged women
to contact him for mentoring.
And he mentored Marjata Vijaya,
who became the first woman core developer
in January 2017.
And after Marjata, other women have been promoted,
Carol Winning, Lisa Roach,
Emily Morehouse, and Sheryl Sibala.
And you can see that thanks to positive action,
we moved from zero woman core developers
up to five woman core developers.
So it's still not 50-50, but at least it's growing.
And to explain you the mentoring,
I would like to come back to the beginning of my journey
about the burnouts.
I say that I don't care.
So the idea of mentoring is that instead of fixing an issue,
you have to explain it to how to fix it.
Or say differently, give a man a fish
and you feed him for a day.
Teach a man to fish and you feed him for a lifetime.
For example, I mentored Pablo Salgado
between January and June 2018.
And he became a core developer in June.
And usually it's way, way longer to become a core developer.
So what I'm trying to say is that thanks to mentoring,
it was possible for him to become a core developer.
Or maybe without mentoring,
he would just move to another project
or stop contributing to Python.
And you have to understand that the development
of an open source project like Python
is really a matter of trust.
To be able to give the keys of Python,
to give the commit bit of Python,
you really need a very, very high level of confidence
in someone you have to trust
as the person that you are promoting.
Python is also about communities.
You have, for example, PyLadies.
And their module is women who love coding in Python.
They are organizing events all around the world.
As there are events in Australia, Brazil, France, India,
Netherlands, Nigeria, Taiwan.
And their website is PyLadies.com.
This is the kind of thing that they do,
is to organize events to teach Python to women.
But you can see in the audience
that it's not only for women, it's also for men.
There is trans or code.
And their module is the event that aims
to help draw attention to transgender issues
through a topic-focused Ag Day.
And for example, the latest events
was PyLondonium at London, UK.
And their website is transcode.github.io.
That's the kind of event that they organize.
It's the creation of the trans.tech,
the previous version of the website.
And I think that the most popular community
is the Django Girls.
And their module is we inspire women
to fall in love with programming.
And I will not give you the full list
because they made a lot of events,
more than 700 events in Cameroon, Finland, France,
Ghana, India, Japan, Spain, Switzerland,
and many other countries.
Their website is DjangoGirl.com.
So you can see that all people enjoy programming,
so it's very successful.
And to conclude,
I would say that we are aware that there is an issue,
and we are aware that the core developers
is a bottleneck of the development of Python.
We are aware that Python has a people issue.
And we saw that the mentoring is efficient
to train contributors of future core developers.
And also that the code of conduct
reduces the toxicity of a community.
According to Grido Van Rossum,
increasing the core's diversity is a very important goal
to ensure the future health of Python.
And I like the quote from Brett Cannon,
also Naomi Seder, which is,
come for the language and stay for the community.
So what's next for the diversity and mentoring?
We are working on a process to promote people,
to make it more, to write down things.
We are working on a mentoring guide
to explain what is mentoring,
how to mentor, what does it mean.
And there is also a work in progress contributor tutorial,
which is a C by Tor,
which is a way to explain what is a mentor.
Tutorial, which is a C by Tor.score.tutorial.readthedoc.io.
And that's it, thank you.
So he'll be taking questions out in the hallway
and give it up again for Victor, yeah.