Hello and welcome to this afternoon's session which is basically actually the last one for
today here.
And now we're going to be listening from Jill Kate how to build clinical diagnostic model
using Python.
There's something in this presentation won't have Q&A but she will be available in the
corridor for any questions that you have after the talk.
Let's give a let's give a welcome applause to Jill Kate.
Thank you.
Hi everyone.
My name is Jill Kate and I'm a data scientist at a company called Biosymmetrics in Toronto,
Canada.
This is my first time in Cleveland and my first PyCon so I'm really excited to be here.
Today I'll be talking about how to build a clinical diagnostic model in Python.
Before we get into the details though, what is a clinical diagnosis?
The formal definition of a diagnosis is the process of determining the disease or conditions
that under underlie a person's symptoms or signs.
So it requires expert knowledge of the physician and years of medical training in order for
them to assess all of the patient data and make an informed decision on what the patient
has before proceeding to treatment.
But what if we could replicate this complex decision process using a machine learning
model?
Recent efforts in machine learning have focused on building tools like these to triage low
risk versus high risk patients, identify early onset disease, and also reduce the risk of
misdiagnosis with the end goal of improving patient safety.
So diagnostic models can save time and money allowing doctors to see and treat more patients
on the job.
In this talk we're going to be building our own clinical diagnostic model and we'll use
sepsis as our case study because it's an extremely expensive and deadly condition that can actually
be treated with a good prognosis if identified early on.
So what is sepsis?
Sepsis is a life threatening condition caused by the body's response to an infection.
It's typically caused by an inflammatory immune response and can be triggered by pneumonia,
the flu, or even an infected pimple.
Sepsis is a leading cause of death in the intensive care unit and it's responsible for
one in three hospital deaths.
It's very expensive.
It costs around $20.3 billion each year and it's also very time sensitive.
So each hour without treatment increases a patient's risk of death by 4 to 8 percent.
So clearly detecting sepsis early on can save lives.
That being said, early stages of sepsis can be hard to detect and while there are some
risk factors for sepsis, it's very difficult for a physician to predict who will get sepsis
and who will not upon admission.
In this case study, we propose a model that predicts a patient's likelihood of getting
sepsis during their stay in the intensive care unit.
If we can reliably identify which patients are at high risk versus low risk, the hope
is that these clinicians can make more informed decisions in their practice.
Here's a big picture view of our pipeline, which can be broken down into three parts.
So we have data preparation, data modeling, and post-processing of results.
A big part of this talk though will be focused on data pre-processing since medical data
is very messy.
As some of you probably already know, healthcare data is known for being fragmented and decentralized.
There are hundreds of electronic medical record systems out there.
And while all of these systems store the same type of data, their interfaces and data schemas
can be extremely difficult, or extremely different.
To make things even more complicated, electronic medical records contain disparate data types,
including unstructured text from clinical notes, 2D and 3D medical images, time series signals
such as EEG and ECG, as well as genomic data.
These discrepancies across EMRs need to be taken care of, and they can be taken care
of through a process called data harmonization.
So data harmonization involves mapping data from various EMR sources into a common data format.
There are a couple of different data models out there, but a very popular one is the OMOP
Common Data Model, which was developed by an international group of researchers called
OHDSI, or Odyssey.
The OMOP Data Model has a predefined schema with a set of standardized data tables,
and is currently being used to harmonize all data across UC hospitals in California.
This whole process that precedes the pipeline is called ETL, or Extract-Transform Load,
because we extract the data from its source, we transform it into a common data format,
and then we load it into a clean centralized database.
All right, now that we have all of our data in one place, we can start cleaning our data.
I'm going to be covering two types of data cleaning in this walkthrough.
So the first one is handling missing values, and the second one is standardizing inconsistencies
in medical terms.
To assess the amount of missing values in our data set, we can use a package called
Missing No, which gives you a big picture view of which features are sparse versus
which features are dense.
So as you can see in this figure, the outer columns are very dense, while the inner columns
are very sparse, which means that there are a lot of missing values.
There are many different ways for us to handle missing values.
We can do case deletion or some form of imputation.
But in order for us to choose the right imputation method, we first need to identify the data's
mechanism of missingness.
So there are three possible mechanisms of missingness.
The first mechanism is missing completely at random.
In this situation, there's no reason for the data to be missing.
It's just totally random.
An example of this is when a nurse forgets to record a patient's blood pressure.
The second mechanism is called missing at random.
There might be differences between the missing and observed blood pressures, but these can
be explained through other variables like age, gender, or a patient's history of cardiovascular disease.
So in this example, younger patients with no risk of cardiovascular disease tend to
have blood pressure missing and will tend to have lower blood pressure than older patients
with cardiovascular disease.
So the data here is missing and it's conditional on age and whether or not the patient has
cardiovascular disease.
The third mechanism is called missing not at random, which is when there are differences
between the missing and observed blood pressures, even when all of the other variables are
accounted for in the patient population.
One way to deal with data that are missing completely at random is to just drop all
observations with a missing value.
So you can do this using Panda's drop NA method.
If you're dealing with time series data, you can use the approach of last value carried forward,
where essentially you're backfilling missing values with the last observed values.
Panda's also has a method for this and it's called fill NA.
There are many more robust methods for handling missing values.
You can use a package called fancy impute to perform standard imputation methods like
k nearest neighbors and matrix factorization.
Stats models also has an imputation method, which lets you perform techniques like Bayesian
multiple imputation and MICE, which stands for multiple imputation with chained equations.
And these are much more robust than the previous examples I showed.
A very important part of cleaning patient data is standardizing all of the medical terms.
Each clinician has their own naming convention when writing prescription drugs and diagnoses.
For example, when doctors write some doctors write Tylenol while other doctors write a
scene a medifin.
But these are essentially the same drug.
Intravenous normal saline is commonly given to patients in the ICU.
But some notes say NS, which stands for normal saline, while others say 0.9 percent sodium
chloride, which is essentially the same thing.
Another example is morphine, which we can see in this table here.
There are all these different variations of describing morphine.
So you can say morphine sulfate, morphine S, morphine all caps.
And as part of our pre-processing, we need to standardize all of these drug names.
Two common drug naming standards are RXNorm and the National Drug Code, or NDC.
So sticking with the morphine example, we can map all variations of morphine to a single
drug code, as shown here.
You can use open source APIs like OpenFDA and RXNAV to map drug names to their appropriate
codes.
Inconsistent terms, though, expand beyond drug names and can be found in clinical notes
describing a disease or symptom.
Here are some examples of medical synonyms that can be used interchangeably.
For example, myocardial infarction is another term for heart attack.
Bruise can also be described as contusion.
And Lou Gehrig's disease is commonly referred to as amyotrophic lateral sclerosis, or ALS.
We can standardize these terms into common unique identifiers using the Unified Medical
Language System, or UMLS.
This is a metathesaurus framework supported by the US National Library of Medicine, and
it's extremely powerful for doing any type of NLP project involving medical data.
Once we have our clean data, the next step is to engineer our features.
We can use classification systems like MeSH or ATC to extract properties from drug names.
So, medical subject headings, or MeSH, is useful for categorizing drugs by property.
You can think of them as hashtags or descriptors that describe a medical term.
In this example, morphine has three MeSH terms, so analgesic, opioid, narcotics, and it gives
us a general sense of what morphine is used for in a medical context.
For our sepsis model, we need to know if a patient was given antibiotics, which we'll
get into more details later on.
So, identifying all prescriptions with the MeSH term antibacterial agents is going to
be very important for us.
ATC is another drug classification system that categorizes drugs by anatomical, therapeutic,
and chemical use.
So, here's an example of morphine's ATC code, which can be parsed into four sections, and
each section represents a different property of the drug in increasing detail.
All right.
So, to standardize diagnoses, we can use the International Statistical Classification of
and health-related problems, also known as ICD.
At the end of a patient's stay, the physician will typically report the patient's primary
diagnosis, as well as relevant comorbidities in the form of ICD codes.
These also get used for billing purposes, so the more complex the ICD code, the higher
the bill.
Here's an example of some ICD codes.
It's a real-life example of a patient with severe sepsis.
So, at the top is their primary diagnosis of severe sepsis, but we can also see a long
list of their comorbidities, for example, acute kidney failure and urinary tract infection.
Ideally, we'd like to include these comorbidities as features in our model.
However, it doesn't make sense for us to do this with raw ICD codes, because there
are thousands of them.
So we need to collapse our ICD codes into more descriptive comorbidity groups.
And we can use either the Charlson or Alexhouser Comorbidity Index, which buckets an ICD code
into its appropriate category.
For example, all of these ICD codes fall under liver disease, which can be represented as
a feature in our model.
So let's assume we have x-ray images in our patient data set.
We can do some processing of these images and generate new features that identify whether
or not an x-ray has a lung opacity.
Having a lung opacity is a sign that a patient might have an infection.
And if we want to create more granular features, we can also identify or predict what the
infection size is, assuming that the size could be correlated to the severity of infection.
Note that generating these features from images is an entirely separate model in itself that
requires its own pre-processing, modeling, hyperparameter tuning, and evaluation.
Another very important data type in the electronic medical record is clinical notes.
So these notes are dictated by the treating physician and contain very helpful information
like symptoms and past medical history.
A single hospital admission can have dozens of different notes from the admission note
to a consult to a discharge summary.
The biggest challenge with clinical notes is converting the unstructured data to structured data.
So let's say we want to include symptoms as a feature, and we need to extract them from
our admission note.
We can use a named entity recognition model to do this, which classifies medical terms
in unstructured text and to pre-define categories like symptom, anatomy, medication, so on and so forth.
This particular example, as you can see on the slide here, comes from the AWS Comprehend Medical API,
but I also recommend checking out open source packages like spaCy.
We need to be very mindful of ambiguous medical terms when we run our named entity recognition model
because there are some terms that have multiple meanings.
For example, Lou Gehrig's disease, which is commonly known as ALS, could be interpreted as a patient name.
Dermatome could mean an area of the skin, or it could also be a surgical instrument for skin grafting.
And pelvis, believe it or not, has two meanings.
It can mean pelvis as in hip bone or renal pelvis, which is a part of the kidney.
When we train our model, we need to account for the many medical abbreviations and ambiguous terms
that could be misinterpreted for something else.
So now that we have a clean data set and we've constructed some features,
we're very close to being able to start training our model.
However, there's one crucial step we need to do first.
We need to define our target variable.
There are three approaches that we can take.
So the first one is to look at the explicit diagnosis of the physician from the ICD codes that they list at the end of the stay.
The issue is that we're trusting that diagnoses were accurately reported, which might not always be the case.
There's a phenomenon called up coding and down coding in health care,
where ICD codes are intentionally left out from the report for billing purposes.
So the second approach is to look at clinical notes and try to interpret whether the clinician said that the patient had sepsis.
We can't rely on naive parsing, though, because even though a note may say sepsis,
it's possible that it was described in their past medical history or perhaps it was explored but then ruled out.
So we'll need to apply assertion classification to these notes to identify the context surrounding sepsis.
So was it a positive assertion? Was it a negative assertion? Or was it speculated without a concrete assertion?
Lastly, the third approach is to use severity scores, which are calculated from a patient's vital signs and laboratory results.
So these scores include the sequential organ failure assessment, or SOFA, the systemic inflammatory response syndrome, or SERS,
and the logistic organ dysfunction system, also known as LODs.
For our particular sepsis model, we're going to be using the SOFA score.
SOFA looks at vitals, blood test results, and urine test results to calculate the degree of dysfunction of six major organs in the body.
A patient's SOFA score can range from 0 to 24, with 24 representing maximum organ dysfunction.
Using this score, we define sepsis as an acute change in SOFA by two points or more upon suspicion of infection.
And here we say that suspicion of infection is assumed when two things happen.
So first, a lab culture is ordered, and second, antibiotics are prescribed within a specified window.
Our recent studies showed that regardless of a patient's baseline SOFA score, it's really their delta in SOFA score over time that's the strongest indicator of sepsis.
So we're now ready to select our algorithm for our clinical diagnostic model.
There are two approaches that we can take with our model.
So the first one is a global binary classification, where we're basically asking, did patients get sepsis during their hospital stay?
Or we can do a more detailed time series approach, where we ask, at what point during their hospital stay did the patient get sepsis?
So for the first approach, we can use a classic binary classification algorithm, like random forest or logistic regression.
For the time series approach, we might want to consider using a fixed or random effects model or a multivariate LSTM or Bayesian networks.
While there are some algorithms that are known to perform well, it's really important to keep in mind the no free lunch theorem.
This theorem basically states that there is no best model that performs well in everything.
It really depends on the type of data that we have.
So while there is some intuition behind choosing which model to use for our particular data set,
we should definitely test out several models and choose the one that gives us the best performance.
Speaking of performance, we also need to choose an evaluation metric.
There are a variety of metrics that we can choose from.
So the ones listed here are options for binary classification.
The metric that we choose, though, depends on what we want to optimize.
So for example, if we want to optimize the number of patients who are incorrectly classified as having sepsis,
this means we're trying to minimize our false positive rate.
And if you can see in the precision equation, we can see that having a lower false positive rate can result in a higher precision score.
So precision would be a good metric to use.
If we wanted to minimize the number of undetected patients with sepsis,
we could choose recall, which is good at optimizing false negative rates.
All right.
When we're building models with patient data, it's really important to assess the diversity of our data set,
which is usually done in the exploratory analysis phase of our project.
So let's say that our data set represents a patient population that was 70 percent white male.
Our model will be very good at predicting sepsis in white men,
but it might not actually be good on women or other ethnicities, assuming that their physiologies could be different.
Demographic bias is especially prevalent in clinical trials.
So in 2004, there was a study that analyzed the patient recruitment in over 100 trials,
and they found that on average, 25 percent of clinical subjects were women.
So under-representation of women in these drug trials is very dangerous,
because while a drug may be considered safe for men,
we don't actually know how it will behave in women and what the side effects might be.
We also need to be cautious of what our ground truth is.
So our model is only as good as the data that we feed it.
If we're working with annotated medical images,
we're relying on the opinion of the radiologist to know whether that patient has pneumonia.
But different radiologists have different opinions.
So while we may have a pretty good pneumonia prediction model, or we think it's good,
it could be complete garbage if our labels were incorrectly defined.
A scary phenomenon of machine learning is something called adversarial attacks.
So a couple of years ago, OpenAI showed this example of a neural network
that could correctly identify a panda and an image.
But if you overlay an adversarial input, which looks just like noise,
it could fool the machine into thinking that the panda was actually a gibbon with 99 percent confidence.
So the adversarial input may look like an array of random pixels,
but it's actually been optimized to find small manipulations that can fool the model.
Adversarial attacks can also happen in medicine,
which is a particularly vulnerable industry with competing interests in healthcare
and billions of dollars at stake.
For example, a group of researchers at Harvard and Harvard University
showed that making subtle transformations to an image of a mole
changed the classification label from being benign to malignant.
So to mitigate the risk of these attacks, we should make sure that our data is secure.
And also, we can periodically retrain and reevaluate our model on a validation set
to see if there are suspicious changes in the performance scores.
Lastly, to build a clinical diagnostic model,
we need buy-in and collaboration from clinicians.
When artificial intelligence became a hot topic,
there was a lot of talk about doctors versus robots
and clinicians someday being out of a job.
But it's important to note that clinicians are the end users of our model,
and it's the doctors who are the end users of our model.
So getting doctors involved in the process and getting their buy-in and validation
are so crucial for implementing our models in a real-life clinical setting.
So that's the end of my talk. Thank you everyone for coming.
If you have any questions about how to pre-process medical data
or how to build your own clinical diagnostic models,
feel free to send them to us at the end of the session.
Thank you.