All right. This talk is how to JIT, building a simple JIT compiler for Python from principles
by Matt Page. Now, Matt has requested that you hold off all your questions until the
end of the talk, and Matt will be outside and be more than happy to answer any questions
that you may have. So, with that, here's Matt.
Hey, everybody. I'm Matt Page. So, we're going to talk today about building a simple JIT
compiler for Python from first principles, but we're going to do it in Python.
Okay. So, a quick outline of how the talk is going to progress. First, I'll give, I'll
introduce myself and then go over some of the motivation for why we want to do something
so crazy. Then we'll go through a high-level overview of what we're going to build. Then
we'll transition into talking about some supporting runtime infrastructure we need, and finally,
we'll close out with building a bare bones compiler.
Okay. So, who am I? Well, I'm a husband and a dad of two amazing daughters, one and four.
They keep me super busy. In my free time, I'm Moonlight as a software engineer at Instagram,
and I've been there since 2017. And I've worked mostly on Python-related projects. So, initially,
I worked on bootstrapping types into our code base. We have about two million lines of Python
code that were initially untyped. So, we built this open source project called monkey type
that collects types at runtime, and you can use those to generate static type annotations.
And then for about the past year, I've been focused on Python performance work. So, specifically,
how do we make Python go faster for Instagram? All right. So, why would we want to build
a JIT? Why would we want to do something crazy like this? So, first off, it's a learning
opportunity. For me, the best way to really understand something and to really understand
how it works is to build it. I'm not a compiler expert, so I'll probably say some wrong things
here. But I've always been curious about how JITs work, and even more so with the recent focus on
performance work. And so, in learning about that stuff, trying to dive into production quality JIT
compiler is pretty hard. They're large, complicated pieces of software, and that's not intended as a
criticism. They're kind of that way out of necessity. So, it can be easier to start from
something small. I also think it's really fun. I like understanding how things work, and I also
like being close to the metal, and you can't really get much closer to the metal than this.
And finally, you actually start to see opportunities for special purpose JITs once you kind of
understand at a baseline level how they work. Depending on your workload, you can actually
see large constant factor speed ups with pretty low effort. So, a couple examples of this are
like the PCRE regex library actually has a JIT compiler, so it can compile your regexes into
machine code. Graphic shaders are another great example of this. So, you kind of start seeing
places where if you have access to data at runtime, you might be able to generate more
efficient code. All right. So, first off, kind of let's go over at a high level what we're going
to build. You know, like, what even is a JIT compiler, right? Let's break down what it's doing.
So, for the purposes of this talk, it's something that translates Python code into machine code at
runtime. So, it's compiling while your program is running. This is where the JIT comes from. That
stands for just in time. So, you take a Python function, you stuff it into this magical black
box and out pop some native code. There are lots of different kinds of JIT compilers, but we're
going to focus on a simple method at a time template JIT. We'll see what that means as the
talk progresses. Hopefully, you'll leave this and have a good understanding of what that means.
So, breaking this down into subcomponents. So, we have this JIT. First, we said that it needs
translate Python code into native machine code. So, we're going to focus on x8664, on UNIX-like
systems, so, like, Mac OS and Linux. So, we're going to need a compiler. This is the thing that's
going to take Python and spit out machine code. So, we have some machine code. We're going to need
a place to put it and it's going to need to be executable. So, we need a memory allocator.
And, finally, we need to be able to integrate it with CPython so that we can call it. So,
we're going to need a foreign function interface or an FFI that will let us call native code from
Python. And we're going to say that this sort of foundational layer, that's our runtime.
That doesn't deal directly with translating Python code into native code, but it's required to sort
of wire everything together and make it all work. Okay. So, let's look into how we might implement
a runtime. So, we're going to do that. I like to learn by doing. So, we're going to do that
by implementing the world's simplest JIT compiler. This function, we're going to JIT a function that
computes the meaning of life. So, it's just going to return 42. Okay. So, diving in, first off,
we import the C types module. And that's part of the standard library and that gives us a way to
call native code from Python. So, that's our FFI piece. Next, we're going to import the M map module
and that gives us access to the M map system call. And we can use M map to allocate executable memory
from the operating system. So, this is our memory allocator. If we were going to do this for realsies,
we would need to worry about limiting the amount of memory we've allocated and freeing it. But for
now, since this is slideware, we'll just free it when the process executes. Or, sorry, exits.
Okay. So, then we call M map and that gives us 4K of readable, writeable, executable memory.
And the map private just says, hey, operating system, if a child process tries to write to
these bits, create its own mapping. And the map anonymous just says, hey, operating system,
we don't have a file backing this mapping. So, then we write out some code into the memory we've
just allocated. We expose it to Python. So, here we're saying, well, using C types, here we're
saying, hey, Python, treat this address as a function that returns an integer. And finally,
we call it. And it prints out 42. Awesome. But taking a step back, we didn't talk too much
about this magical binary string. So, this is the X8664 encoding of the assembly shown here.
Move 42 into the register racks and then return. So, racks is special. That's where return values
go. And then we had to translate that into some machine code for the CPU. So, this means we're
actually going to have to do instruction encoding. And this is something we'd rather not have to
focus on. We'd rather focus on the high level task of translating Python into some higher level
representation. Say assembly code, for instance. Okay. So, we don't want to deal with manual
instruction encoding. And to avoid that, we're going to use a library called PeachPy.
So, PeachPy is an awesome open source library that was originally designed for writing
hand-tuned highly optimized computational kernels for numerical computing applications. So, think of
things like math applications where you as a human might actually have a higher chance of writing
something more efficient than a compiler would produce. It handles all of what we just went over.
So, instruction encoding, allocating executable memory, exposing it to Python and more. And it
exposes a high level DSL that lets us write that assembly what we wanted to in Python.
So, this is great. So, let's revisit the world's simplest JIT using PeachPy. So, this looks already
kind of a lot shorter and hopefully a lot more clear. So, walking through what this is doing,
first we're wild card importing everything we need from PeachPy. Normally, we'd probably want to
avoid doing this. But this is what lets us use it like a DSL. We'll see that in a second.
Then we declare our function. So, we say, hey, we have this function. It takes no arguments. And
it returns a 64-bit integer. And then we get to use the nice PeachPy DSL. So, we're actually
writing assembly code, but we're doing it in Python. So, we're moving 42 into the register
axe. And then we're returning. And this is where PeachPy I think really shines. So, we can actually
just dump all of that C types instruction encoding work off into PeachPy. So, there's a lot going on
in this line. But PeachPy is taking that assembly code we wrote, lowering it down into machine code,
allocating executable memory, and then exposing it into Python for us. Under the hood, it's doing
this using C types and M map. So, we at least kind of know how that works. But we don't have to think
about it anymore, which is great. Then we call the function. And boom, we get 42. Awesome. So,
we've now figured out the runtime bits. Let's dive into the compiler. But before we get too deep,
we're going to go over a bit about how the CPython VM executes Python code that we write. So,
here we have a simple function called add. That just adds its arguments. And on the right,
so that's what we write. That actually gets compiled by CPython into byte code that you see
on the right here. So, this is byte code for a stack-based virtual machine. If that doesn't make
any sense to you, don't worry. We're going to walk through this byte code on the next slide.
So, here we have the byte code we just saw. And the blue arrow is going to represent the instruction
pointer for the virtual machine. And the empty space on the right is going to house the contents
of the stack. So, initially, it starts out empty. After we execute the first instruction,
this first load fast instruction pushes the value of A onto the stack. Then we execute the second
load fast instruction. And that pushes the value of B onto the stack. And then we execute binary add.
And this pops two values off of the stack, adds them. And so, for whatever that means,
because this is Python, if it's two integers, it could be doing integer addition. If it was
two strings, it could be concatenating them. And then it pushes it back onto the stack.
And then finally, return value pops the stack and returns the result.
Okay. So, under the hood, Python implements this pretty much as you would expect it to.
The interpreter loop is basically just a giant switch statement. So, for every opcode, there's
a case statement. And then it's just constantly going over the byte code doing this fetch,
decode, execute cycle. So, grab an instruction, decode it, figure out what to do with it,
then execute the corresponding case statement. Okay. So, this kind of begs the question,
if CPython already has C code for every opcode, can we compile a function by looping over the
byte code and just emitting the equivalent native code? So, we basically would just take
the assembly code for the case statement and we spit it into an executable piece of memory.
So, as you probably anticipated, the answer to that question is yes. And this is the essence
of a template JIT compiler. So, instead of a fetch, decode, execute cycle, we have a fetch,
decode, emit cycle. We just walk through the byte code and we go boom, boom, boom, boom, boom,
and we emit some assembly code. Okay. So, what does that look like in code? This is the basic
skeleton of the compiler. It's pretty straightforward. It's not really a lot more code than we saw
in our world's simplest JIT example. I've omitted imports for brevity. So, we have a function that
takes as input now a Python function and it produces as output a JIT compiled version.
So, we have to emit a prolog. We're executing code on the... We're executing native code now,
which means we're going to be running on the machine stack. So, our prolog is going to need
to handle things like saving the base pointer, copying arguments to the stack,
and then some CPython-specific stuff like grabbing the gil. After we've omitted our prolog,
we can just iterate over all of the instructions like we said before. We can emit some assembly
code for them. And then finally, we get into our epilogue. And so, here we see another feature of
peach pie, which are symbolic labels. So, we emit a label for the epilogue and that lets us
reference it from jump instructions throughout the code. And then we emit our epilogue,
which is just emitting some assembly code to pop the stack and clean it up and then return.
Okay. So, now that we have the skeleton in place, we're going to
fetch out some basic primitives. Once these are done, we're going to have a solid foundation
in place that we can take and we can extend as desired. So, to start off with, we're going to
walk through how we'll emit some assembly code for a couple of opcodes. This will just kind of
help us get some intuition and see how simple things are. So, first off, let's take that meaning
of life function again. That compiles down into two opcodes, load constant return value. So,
we're going to implement the emitters for this. Once we're done with this, we'll actually be able
to compile our first Python function. Not super useful, but a cool milestone. Okay. So, to develop
some intuition here, we're just going to look at the case statement from the interpreter loop.
And this has been simplified for brevity, but I think this captures the essence of what's going on.
Load const just loads a constant value out of a code object for a function
corresponding to the argument for the opcode. Then it increments its reference count and it pushes
it onto the stack. So, what does our generated or what does our emitter look like for this?
This is pretty straightforward and is not a ton of code. So, this is the first one we're seeing. So,
we'll just go over the function signature. It takes as input the function being compiled
and the instruction. We grab the constants for the function. Then we move the constant
into a register. So, here you'll notice we're calling ID. This is just a C Python implementation
trick. ID returns the address of its argument. We're putting it into a register. Register doesn't
matter. The choice of register doesn't matter here. We increment its reference count and then
we push it onto the stack. So, our assembly generation code looks pretty much like what we
saw in the interpreter loop. Now let's look at return value. Return value again, super simple.
We just pop the stack and then we exit the interpreter loop. The emitter code looks
correspondingly simple. So, we're popping into a register. Here the register is actually important.
So, this RACS register is where return values go. Then we jump into our epilogue,
which again cleans up the stack and returns. Okay. Awesome. Moving right along. We can look at
local variables. So, keeping in this theme of simple pieces of code, we have an identity function
that returns its argument and we have its corresponding byte code. We only have one new
opcode here, which is load fast. So, if we look at the interpreter code or the case statement
inside of the interpreter loop here, we see that we're fetching an argument from the locals array
in the frame and that's specified by the argument to the opcode. We increment its reference count
and then we push it onto the stack. Awesome. So, it's pretty straightforward. Before we can dive
into the emitter, though, we're going to have to talk a little bit about stack layout. So, we said
that we're going to execute on the C stack now and we're going to use that for local variable storage.
So, when we enter into a function, our prolog is actually reserving space on the stack for
local variables and then it updates RBP, which is the base pointer, to point at the first local.
So, to load a local variable I, we compute its offset relative to RBP and on x86-64, the stack
grows from higher memory addresses to lower memory addresses. So, we need to subtract from the base
pointer. And then finally, we're going to have to scale it by the size of the things that are on the
stack. So, we're just pushing pointers here, which are eight bytes on x86-64. So, we just multiply
that index by eight. So, now that we have that, the emitter code is really straightforward.
So, we just load the argument into a register. We increment its reference count. And you'll note
here that we're no longer using the peach pie DSL. We've abstracted that away into a helper function.
This is a great feature of being able to write assembly code in a high-level language like Python.
You can do refactoring and it actually makes sense. And then you can just, then we just push
it onto the stack. So, again, this is all pretty straightforward, which is really, really cool.
Okay. So, we're almost done. Now we need to talk about calling into the C API. So, we want to be
able to call back into CPython from generated code. It turns out that a lot of core CPython
functionality is actually written in C and it's exposed through the C API. The interpreter loop
often delegates work to these functions and we'd like to be able to do the same thing from our
generated code. So, here we're going to revisit our simple addition example. And we have the
disassembly on the right. We've covered everything so far except for binary add. So, let's dive into
that. So, this looks pretty familiar. We're popping our arguments from the stack. But then
we have to call this helper function pi number add using the arguments we popped. And so,
this is where the interpreter loop is actually calling back into CPython.
So, we'd like to be able to do the same thing. So, we need to figure out how to do this. And
this basically amounts to just being able to resolve the address of a function at runtime.
So, to do that, we lean on C types again. Here we import it. Then we import Python API. And Python
API just exposes the C API as a shared library. Then we load a helper library for resolving
symbols. Then we expose DLSim, which is just the function we need to resolve a symbol in a shared
library. And now we can finally look up a symbol inside of CPython. So, now we have something
that we can use to build on top of. Once this is in place, the emitter looks pretty straightforward
again. So, now we're popping our arguments. And the registers here now are important because these
are the registers that arguments or the first two arguments, to be precise, are expected to be in.
So, we pop those. And then we call our helper function to resolve the address of pi number add.
And we move it into a register. And then we call it. Okay. Great. We're almost ready to wrap up.
The final piece I want to go over is how we represent control flow. So, up to now,
we've only dealt with straight line code. How would we want to handle something a little bit
more complicated? So, we're going to look at another helper function again. In this case,
we have this max function that just computes the maximum of its arguments. And the disassembly on
the right is a little longer. But we've implemented everything except for these two op codes, compare op
and pop jump if false. So, we'll walk through how those work. So, compare op just pops two values off
of the stack, compares them using a predicate, and in this case, it's greater than. And then it
pushes the result back onto the stack. Okay. So, pop jump if false is probably pretty straightforward
if you can read. So, we pop a result off of the stack. And then we jump depending on that result.
So, in this case, if it was false, we update the instruction pointer to point to 12.
And if it was true, we fall through to the next statement. So, what happens here if we wanted to
modify the bytecode of a function? Say we wanted to optimize it. We could end up invalidating the
offset that's used in the jump. How would we represent this more abstractly and in a way that
lets us not have to worry about that? To do that, we're going to reach for control flow graphs. So,
a control flow graph is a directed graph where nodes are basic blocks which are just sequences
of straight line code with no branching in the middle of a block. You can only branch at the end.
And then edges represent control flow. And this allows us to edit the graph without worrying about
invalidating jump targets. Once we have a graph, we can transform it back into linear code just
by performing a graph traversal. So, how would we want to build one of these things from some
bytecode? The first step is to identify basic block boundaries. So, an instruction starts a
new basic block. If it's the first instruction, if it's the target of a branch, or it follows a
branch. So, in our example, zero starts a basic block because it's the first instruction. Eight
starts a basic block because that follows the branch instruction. 12 starts a basic block
because it's the target of a branch. And then we're done. Okay. So, now that we've got basic
blocks, we can build a mapping from offset to basic block. And then finally, we can add edges
by going through and mapping offsets to the corresponding basic block. So, integrating this
into the compiler is pretty straightforward. This is the updated compiler. Again, not super different.
Only now we're going to iterate over basic blocks instead of just iterating over instructions.
For each basic block, we emit a label. And we saw this earlier. And this, again, lets us emit jump
instructions using symbolic labels rather than offsets. And then we can delegate fixing up those
symbolic jumps into absolute jumps to peach pie. So, then for each basic block, we go through and
we iterate through the instructions in it. And we emit the assembly code for it. So, that's pretty
straightforward. And then that's it. We're done. Now we've pulled an entire control flow graph
into our compiler. So, takeaways. First off, Python is awesome for exploration and prototyping.
At this point, we have the basic structure of the compiler in place. And we can compile real
functions. So, we can't compile a whole lot yet. But we actually have a fully fledged working
compiler here. And we have the structure that we can build on to make this into something more real.
And that's really awesome. We did that in like 25 minutes. It's an incredibly small amount of code.
It's like 200 or 300 lines of code. And it's just, yeah, I think it's pretty amazing.
Low level work doesn't have to be scary. We did all of this from Python. And we generated
native assembly code or native machine code, sorry. And we executed it. And now we have a JIT that
has a REPL. Which is, I think it's pretty cool. Okay. So, future work. What is there to do?
The answer is there is a lot to do. You can add emitters for more op codes.
CPython has about 120 op codes. And we really only covered three.
Exceptions. So, we didn't talk at all about how we deal with exceptions or how we represent them in
the control flow graph. This is tricky, but it's doable. We haven't talked about generators or
async functions. Those need to be able to suspend and resume at arbitrary points of execution.
Which means we need to figure out how to save and restore the stack and register state.
And then finally, the big one, which is optimization passes. So, the generated code,
or the code that we've generated now is going to be pretty slow. It's going to be, at most,
a little bit faster than CPython and maybe even a little bit slower. We've really only compiled away
the interpreter loop. But with a little bit of work, we can actually start producing something
that is much, much faster than what CPython can do. And the name of the game here is type
specialization. So, if we go back to the example of addition, if we can generate specialized code
and we know that the types of the arguments are integers, we can instead just emit machine code to
add integers as opposed to calling out into the CPython API. All right. Thank you. I hope you guys
thought that this was interesting. If you want to go play around, the source code is up and available
on GitHub. I'm here all week now. Thank you for your time, guys.