All yours Tracy. All right. Well, thank you so much
I am super excited to be here and I really appreciate the opportunity to speak with this group as Meg says
This is such an amazing crowd of people who are already excited about this
And I think what's really great about the people that are excited about education is that teaching is leadership at the front of the room
So we have a bunch of teachers and we have a bunch of leaders
In this group that are interested and excited to make an impact in their communities
Whoops, okay. So yeah, so this is what I'm going to talk about today and I work with the Carpentries
But I used to teach swimming
And so when I taught swimming you actually can learn to teach swimming. It's a 40-hour course through the American Red Cross
And when we learn to teach swimming, you know walk through there's certain things that everyone needs to know about swimming
Like put your face in the water put your head under the water
Kick your feet move your arms the kind of core skills are not overwhelmingly complicated
So what we talk about is how to introduce those skills what order to introduce them how to work with the people
in the pool adults to children and
So when we talk about learning to swim this is never how we approach it
Where you walk someone to the edge of the pool and you push them in the deep end, right
Does this person obviously this is not that scenario come back to swimming lessons the next day
Would we expect that to happen if we took someone who didn't know how to swim and threw them in the deep end?
probably not
Instead what we're taught is that we want to support people in their learning
We want to be there with them. We want to provide guidance. We want to introduce things at an appropriate level
But yet somehow when we move into the computational realm
We forget some of these things that we know about learning
And we sort of throw people in the deep end not because we think that that's
What we should do necessarily, but maybe we've forgotten what it was like to learn to swim what the deep end looks like
Maybe we don't know how to introduce things in the right order how to create the environment for our learners
And so in swimming we're really motivated to do it
This way rather than the other way because actual drowning has a lot of bad implications
It's not quite as obvious when we're teaching someone coding
So what we see is that how we teach is as important as what we teach
right same things in swimming, but one person is never getting in the water again and
another person can go through the steps to learn to swim and
So we talked about bringing compute to data
Maybe in this conference will have a lot of that compute to data or data to compute
But what we need to do is we need to bring people to data and to software
Because we want to empower all people culturally and linguistically diverse students to use data in software to answer
Questions that are important to them by having more people who have these skills and these perspectives
We have more opportunity to answer questions in science and society and for these people themselves
Most of all to feel empowered to do the things that they want to do and I took Meg's statement here
I like the access counts
Right access for everyone to be able to learn these things is important and when we're thinking about that framework
And this is what Meg was saying too. It's really important that we consider how we teach if we want to bring these to everybody
So I'm going to be talking about
Some of these elements from the perspective of the Carpentries the Carpentries is a nonprofit organization
And we're an open global community teaching researchers and librarians
The skills and perspectives to turn data into knowledge and we do this through our curriculum our instructor training program and our community
And so what we realized in the Carpentries we started out teaching the skills of the Carpentries
and skills and
more we taught the more we realized that the most important thing to select for is
confidence and self-efficacy
Do we teach short format workshops two days in two days?
We're not necessarily going to be able to see we definitely can't teach everything
But at the end of the two days is not as important if you know exactly how to write a line of syntax
Then if it's you have now the confidence to continue learning that you have some ability to keep learning yourself
That's the thing that's going to keep you going on your exciting coding path
and
So what's really great is in having this mentality?
There's already a lot of work done in this space and educational pedagogy and culturally responsive
Teaching that can help guide our practices so when I talk about the things that we're doing these are things that come from
From the literature from research that can help guide our practices so we still have more to learn
But this is where we are right now. So these are two great resources. I would highly recommend both of these books
And the other amazing thing is that in the Carpentries we have about 2,000 volunteer instructors
And so these instructors to are contributing to all the ideas that I'm going to talk about today
Through their teaching through their learning they're contributing to our instructor training to our materials talking to each other in the community
So we have a really rich resource that contributes to these ideas and people passionate about teaching people
and learning coding skills and
So all of this is incorporated into our instructor training program
It's also a two-day program that highlights a lot of these things that I'm going to talk about
And all is this is all open source or CC by so you can check out our materials to and if it's some of these things
seem interesting
Okay, so I'm going to focus on when I talk about how we teach three
Sort of concepts and then some of the things that we do within each of these concepts
So the first is creating the classroom community
the second is talking about productive struggle and
Then finally assessment for learning
So creating the classroom community or a container for learning so sometimes you hear the phrase we need to create the container for learning
What space is someone walking into where they're going to learn so if someone is walking in feeling insecure?
Maybe the first way they learned it is being pushed in the deep end of the pool if that's how they're feeling you need to create
A space where they can feel safe to learn to try to fail
So every person needs a place that is furnished with hope you want people to be hopeful when they walk in that room
Okay, so just as an example so who in this room has been in a course or workshop where they felt like they didn't belong
And then how many people then left that topic for a while or maybe even forever
So
That space that sense of belonging
Impacts that content you can think to yourself if you've now come back to that subject is it because you were incapable
Or was it because it was your first that your first experience with that topic
So how we are taught has such an impact on what it is we decide that we can learn
So what do we do in the carpentries to create this classroom community
So I'm just going to highlight five things and so the first
Introductions is connecting with your learners so
When you're creating this space the learner wants to know that they can trust you that they're you're an advocate for them
So we have a whole sort of introductions to introduction
So how you'd introduce yourself as an instructor has a big impact
And I'll do a quick example so I could introduce myself two different ways to this group or let's say your classroom
I could say hi. My name is Tracy. I've been working in bioinformatics for 20 years
My favorite thing to do is work out the Linux command line and computers are awesome. So let's go
Do you feel like I'm gonna connect with you necessarily or I could say hi
My name is Tracy. I've been working in biology for 20 years
I've been able to use some computational approaches and I really was exciting what I what that let me do
And I'm really excited to be here today to share some of those skills with you and so that we can all work together
to learn
computational approaches in biology
Which one thinks has you thinking that I'm on your side, right? So it does start the second
I hope maybe the first
Depends on the audience, right? So that's something to know right? Who's your audience?
What's gonna help you connect with them? What part of your experience?
It's gonna help you connect with them
And I think that's actually a really great and amazing thing about being a teacher is that you bring your whole self
To that teaching makes you a better teacher
So sharing that parts those parts of you can be really powerful
Our code of conduct so Carpentries has a code of conduct and enforcement guidelines
So we always share that upfront that we have a code that we have certain
Expectations for how the teacher is going to interact with the students and how the students should interact with each other
And then we make those expectations clear
We also give the students an opportunity to connect with each other
This isn't just a dynamic between the person at the front of the room
And the people sitting there
It's a dynamic between the students as well, so we say we don't like a quiet classroom
We like the students learning from each other
Partly because they can see each other struggle a little bit
But they can learn from each other and they can teach each other
Sometimes they may think they don't know something but they actually teach the person next to them
So we have students just take a minute and introduce themselves to each other and just you say
What's your name?
Describe your research in three words or less and name one thing you're proud of that you made
So it just provides something a little bit interesting
That's that's one example for a quick introduction and that makes a really big impact on the feel of the workshop
Accessibility highlighting up front how people can
Accessibility is a very important part of the process
How people can
Access the materials in a variety of different ways
So in terms of accessibility, this is a place where we have improvement and it also reminds me that I forgot to turn on the captions
Here, let's see there
Telling people up front see i'm using the google captions. We're going to see how it goes
So but telling people up front how they can access materials instead of having to have people ask for them
Because sometimes people don't necessarily know
that they
Have different ways of learning or access challenges and so being up front with the way different ways that people can access the materials is important
and then finally setting expectations for learning so
We're going to be in this course
You're going to be learning a lot of new things things are going to be challenging. You might not get it right the first time
That's okay. We're working through this together. Here's where we're starting
Here's where we're going to end up
So it's not a mystery around what you're going to learn and also setting the stage for the idea that you know
That they're going to struggle and that that's expected and that's part of the learning
Okay, so
Productive struggle so we're in the workshop. Everyone's excited to be there
And so this I think I can a lot of people that walk into training around coding are disempowered
They feel like it's something they can't do
So it might be that we're not rebuilding we're just building in the first place
But a lot of times I am talking sorry about adult learners throughout this rebuilding that
I think I can attitude begins with helping the students achieve small incremental success on important tasks and both of those things are important
success as small successes and important tasks if people are having successes on things they view as toy problems
They don't feel as accomplished
So how do we embrace productive struggle in our workshop first in that introduction by saying you're going to struggle?
But we have the active learning so you have to try it
As a part of the struggle you can't just hear it
Like also in swimming you don't teach swimming by having everyone sit on the pool deck and show them a powerpoint presentation
Right that would not be very effective
So same thing here get them in the pool get them in their computer
And so when we teach when we're at the front of the room
The instructor is coding and the students are coding along with the instructor
And so it gives people an opportunity to try things out together. So we're not just showing
We're working together
We use an I we you model of teaching so I introduce the topic
We work on it together and then you try it on your own
So again that has that incremental element to it where you see it
Then we do it together and then you get to try it on your own
and
Also meg highlighted this as well reframing mistakes as learning so we say the mistakes are the pedagogy
So when you're the instructor at the front of the room and you're live coding you make mistakes
so many mistakes
And um, so it's a real opportunity one to show that you are human and that you make mistakes, right?
And it's also an opportunity to show how you recover from those mistakes
So we want people to be able to learn how to recover
And so the mistakes are the learning for the instructor at the front of the room when they tell you that you forgot
Whatever it is. You forgot
Or type the same thing wrong for the third time
Um, but they themselves have that process of seeing where they make a mistake and using that to learn
Rather than thinking of it as a failure
Um relevant examples, so in software carpentry data carpentry library carpentry
We are primarily working with researchers in librarians
And so all of the examples that we use are relevant to the people's research
Context so they're working with a system. They're already familiar with so they already have a
Framework that they're interested in and understand and so the examples come from that
So they're building coding onto a framework that they already have and then it's also
Motivational because those are problems that they want to solve they want to go back to their lab back to their library
And solve those problems. Um, and so using relevant examples helps them feel it is productive
They're doing something that they would do in their daily work
And then finally immediate feedback and help
So struggling on your own is not very valuable
You do need that someone to be able to step in and say oh here, you know
Here's where we could do something differently. So it does need to be immediate
And so in all of our workshops, we have two instructors and then we have helpers in our workshop
So we have about a five to one ratio
So the helpers can come and help people individually when they're struggling with challenges
So
Finally assessment for learning so often we think about assessment as sort of taking a test and it's very stressful
But we actually can use assessment as a way to think about learning
And so our favorite version of format assessment is formative assessment. So assessment during the workshop and we use sticky notes
So if you have our
We do an exercise we say when you're done with the exercise put up a green sticky note on the front of your computer
And if you're having trouble put up a pink sticky note and someone will come help you
so that helps the learners see that
They can get some help and also helps the instructor know when the class is having challenge
So if you see a sea of pink sticky notes, you know, you need to re-explain that concept
We have the exercises as I mentioned
And then our survey designed to build confidence
So we did put some questions in our survey around skills
And the feedback was that people had a great experience in the workshop
and then they went and took those questions at the end and they felt like they failed
And was it most important that we knew whether or not they had learned exact syntax?
Or was it more important around that self-efficacy and that confidence? So it's influenced how we do our survey design
So what we believe about belonging
That community our effort that productive struggle and the value of the task leads to the engagement and the motivation
So
This is just a big recap of all these things and I did highlight some of the things that we do
But the concept is really important. What's so amazing about our community is they're always exploring
And learning about different ways to implement these things in the classroom
And so actually how many carpentries instructors are in the room?
Yeah, so feel free to reach out to any of these folks too to learn more about some of these things
Okay, so i'm going to quickly go just through some outcomes. So does this work?
So one it scales we have a lot of instructors. I talked about our instructor training that gives a lot of people the
Ability and interest to go teach workshops. So we teach them all over the world
But mostly does it improve confidence?
So when we see just a pre and post workshop of two days
We can see that things like confidence and programming and at the bottom and overcome problem in the middle
There's a full point difference in just two days and people's perception of their comfort their feeling of whether they can do this work
And these are the kinds of things they say about the workshop and this confidence persists long term
So when we do a survey six months more after the workshop
Almost a hundred percent of our respondents say I am more confident now
Which is surprising to me because the more I use python the less confident I feel actually
And that people have seen this as value they highly recommend these workshops is something they see as having a positive impact
And then they go on to continue learning
Which is the other thing that we want to see right that they have that self-effort cda going on to continue learning
Um
So these are a few different ways that we continue to learn and I think as we talk about the sprints
We'll see that there's lots of opportunities
um
So just kind of as a bit of a wrap-up
When we talk about how we teach it's how people feel
And so Maya Angelou i've learned that people will forget what you said people forget what you did
But people will never forget how you made them feel
And that's what we have the opportunity to do in our workshops to inspire people
To use these skills and keep using them in
In their work and in their lives to do amazing things and feel awesome about their capabilities
So and I thank the amazing carpentries community that does all of this work
And the opportunity we have here in this summit something we take to heart is if you want to go fast go alone
If you want to go far go together
And this community is great at coming together to work towards shared challenges, so thank you very much
You