Thank you for joining us.
Up next is Simon Willison, a co-creator of Django,
inventor of Ticker, and presenter of the next talk
on instance serverless APIs powered by SQLite.
OK.
Well, good afternoon, everyone.
Thank you very much for coming along.
I know there were some incredibly good talks
in this slot, so I feel honored that you chose to join me here.
So I have a bit of a confession, first of all.
I called this talk Instance Serverless APIs
Powered by SQLite.
I've actually submitted it to regional Python conferences
under a different name, and it wasn't accepted.
So for PyCon, I thought, sod it.
I'm going to throw in a buzzword.
I threw in the word serverless, and it got accepted.
And so now I feel honor bound to give you
a definition of serverless that isn't complete claptrap.
So my preferred definition of serverless,
the one that actually means something useful to me,
is scale to zero.
It's the idea that you only pay for the computing
resources you use, which means that you can run a web
application, and if no one visits it,
it doesn't cost you any money.
And as a investor at Tinkerer and somebody
who loves churning off new side projects,
this is a very useful capability to have.
And the serverless world got even more interesting
this month with the release of Google Cloud Run.
This came out, I think, just at the beginning of April.
And it's a fascinating thing.
It lets you define an application as a Docker
container, and then Google will run it when it gets traffic
and turn it off when it doesn't.
So it should ideally be incredibly inexpensive,
if not free, if you're not getting a lot of hits.
But if you look at the web page about Google Cloud Run,
it does say stateless in two different places
just on that home page.
And this is a very important characteristic
of most of these serverless offers, is they're stateless.
You can run code on them, but if you
want to have a database with stuff that changes,
that's going to cost you extra.
That's a whole new level of complexity,
which if you can avoid it, these things can
get really interesting.
So one of the questions that one of the techniques
that I've been experimenting with a lot over the past couple
of years is, OK, if I can't have a regular database,
what about if I ship static data as part of the application
itself?
We're dealing with Docker containers.
What if my Docker containers got a bunch of data
inside it already?
It turns out the SQLite database is the perfect tool
for bundling up data and shipping it
with the rest of your code.
But before we get into that, I wanted
to talk about some of the use cases for this.
How is a web app that doesn't accept rights at all,
how is that an interesting thing?
And for that, I'll dive back into my own career history
and talk a little bit about data journalism.
So data journalism is when programmers work for newspapers
and help analyze the data and discover facts about the world
through data analysis.
It's a really exciting field.
And I was lucky enough to get to do this back in 2008
through 2010 at The Guardian in London.
And so when I joined The Guardian,
they have this fantastic onboarding scheme
where you get to have coffee with random people
from around the company.
And I was expressing my interest in data stuff.
And a bunch of people said I needed to talk to a journalist
called Simon Rogers.
And Simon was the journalist and the person in the newsroom
responsible for the data behind the infographics.
If a newspaper publishes a map or a chart or a graph,
they'd better have good numbers behind it.
And so Simon was a dab hand with Excel.
And he knew who to call to get data about basically anything
you could think of.
And I got kind of excited talking to him.
I said, OK, so what do you do with all of these data
sets that you've collected?
And he said, oh, they're on here pointing at the desktop
underneath his desk, which had hundreds of beautifully
categorized Excel spreadsheets describing all sorts of facts
about the world.
So we started scheming together about how we could best
publish this data online, like share this data
and let people derive their own insights from it.
And in the end, we went with the simplest thing
that could possibly work, which is a blog.
We started The Guardian data blog.
And when The Guardian published a story against data,
they'd publish a spreadsheet of the underlying numbers.
And the tool we chose for publishing the data itself
was Google Spreadsheets.
Again, easiest thing that could possibly work.
It didn't cost anything.
And you can publish data in it.
Now, this worked.
It worked fantastically well.
The Guardian actually built up a community
of people around this data blog who
would do their own visualizations of data
that were published in Guardian stories.
But I was always left a little bit frustrated by this.
Is Google Sheets really the best possible way
to be sharing data with the world?
And so time passed, and I transitioned out
of data journalism into startup things
and kind of lost connection with that world.
Then a year and a half ago, I was thinking about this.
And I realized that the technologies
that you would need to do a better job of this data
publishing were now openly available.
And so I started building this open source project
called Dataset.
I describe it as a tool for exploring and publishing data.
But basically, it's the thing I wish
I'd had when I was at The Guardian working on these data
journalism stories.
And Dataset is best illustrated with a demo.
So I'll try and give you an idea of some of its capabilities.
Now, FiveThirtyEight are a blog that is basically data
journalism through and through.
Every story they publish is based on top of a Dataset.
And if you look closely at their stories,
you'll see there's this fascinating link that says,
get the data on GitHub.
If you click through to that, they've
got this giant GitHub repository full of CSV files.
And so this is a story about the number of charges
and convictions that came out of the recent Russia
investigation compared to Watergate
and a whole bunch of other things.
So this is 195 lines of CSV data on GitHub.
And what I've been doing is I set up a Travis CI automation
job, which once a day grabs everything from FiveThirtyEight,
like 450-odd CSV files, converts it into SQLite,
and then hosts it under my Dataset project up online.
So I'll actually pull up a demo and show you
what that looks like.
This is tethered off my mobile phone,
so I'm hoping this works well.
So this is every Dataset that FiveThirtyEight have created
converted to run under my Dataset application.
And if I click through to this Russia investigation CSV,
here's that raw data.
But I can start doing interesting things.
Like I can say, show me this by the current American president.
So there were 20 charges when Ronald Reagan was president,
72 for Nixon, 45 for Clinton.
I can say, show me the type of charge.
Was it a guilty plea, an indictment, or a conviction?
And then I can start digging in and say, OK, well,
under Bill Clinton, there were 18 guilty pleas.
And those 18 guilty pleas were these people.
And I can say, show me the investigation.
And this was 11 for Whitewater, four for Cisneros,
and three for eSpy, I guess.
But you get the idea.
This started life as a CSV file on FiveThirtyEight.
With zero configuration at all, I
converted that into a SQLite database.
And then Dataset is providing this interface
over the top of it.
But I promised you APIs in my talk title.
That was one of my other buzzwords.
If you click on JSON here, you get the same data
that we were just looking at back as JSON.
And in fact, you can also get it back as CSV.
This is quite fun.
This means you can slice and dice your data in any way
that you like, and then get max CSV subsets of just the things
that you're interested in.
And because this is running on top of SQLite,
and SQLite is a SQL database, there's
a link here that says View and Edit SQL.
And if I click that, I get this interface,
which is actually showing me the underlying SQL query that
was run to generate that page.
And I can even edit it.
So I can say, you know what?
I just want investigation, comma, name
from bloody, bloody, blah.
And now I'm getting back that subset of data,
which I can also get back as JSON or as CSV.
This seems kind of insane, because everyone
knows you don't allow random people to run
SQL against your data.
But there are two things in this favor.
Firstly, this is all public data.
It's not like they're going to select my password file.
And secondly, SQLite allows you to open files in read-only mode.
So if you tried to do an insert or an update,
it just won't work.
It'll be rejected.
So these are read-only SQL queries.
I put a one-second time limit on them, too.
So if you try to do something crazy expensive,
you'll just get an error after a second.
And it means it's shocking enough,
it's safe to expose data with SQL as your query language
and make that available through an API.
A really fun detail here, if you look at the JSON URL here,
you can see it's something.json?sql equals.
And I'm literally passing a SQL statement in as a parameter.
People get really excited about GraphQL
these days because GraphQL lets you specify exactly one.
SQL's GraphQL from the 70s, right?
It turns out it works great.
So there are a whole bunch of handy features.
You've got filtering and faceting.
So you have that interface where you can
facet by different columns.
You can filter by things where something is
greater than something else.
You can run these custom SQL queries.
And you've got this JSON API on top of everything that it does.
And really, the secret source to this whole project
is SQLite.
SQLite is this amazing little public domain licensed database.
It's absolutely tiny.
It's an embedded library which everyone in this room
has access to because it ships as part of the Python standard
library.
But it turns out it's ubiquitous to the point
that it's in mobile phones, it's in desktops.
My Apple Watch has a SQLite database on it
that records my steps, which I haven't
managed to get access to yet, which is really infuriating.
And one of the nicest characteristics of SQLite
is everything is a single database file, which means you
can back it up by copying it somewhere.
You can email them to people.
It's a really nice archival format
for any piece of data that will fit in a relational database,
which is everything.
The catch is SQLite famously doesn't scale well for writes.
That's why you wouldn't build a high traffic
interactive website with it.
But we're not dealing with writes.
If our data is read only, the one limitation of SQLite
just disappears.
And if you want to scale to handle millions of hits
a second, run 30 copies of the SQLite database
and load balance between them.
That's going to work just fine.
So what this lets you do is it lets
you ship both the data and the code in the same Docker
container or in the same environment, which
means all of these serverless platforms
are suddenly available for you to do all kinds of exciting
things with them.
So I'll show you another demo to illustrate quite
how ubiquitous SQLite is.
Dataset is Python 3 only, I think, in 2019.
That's not even something I need to mention anymore.
But what I'm going to do is I'm going to run a command which
searches my hard drive.
This is going to search my library folder on my hard drive
for any file ending in star.sqlite.
So it's a find command looking for names, star.sqlite.
And then I'm going to sort them with the biggest first.
So hang on.
Let's run that again.
Here we go.
The largest SQLite file that my computer has
is this mystery file called clsbusinesscategorycache.sqlite.
It's something to do with Apple photo analysis D.
So what I'm going to do now is I'm going to run Dataset
against it.
So Dataset, once you've installed it,
it's a command line tool.
You can give it a port, because I'm
thinking I'm already using the port it normally runs on.
And I'm going to give it the path for that file.
And it's going to start up.
And now if I visit this URL, here is that database.
This is now me browsing this mystery database
that I found on my computer.
It's got 189,000 rows in zbusinessitem.
They've got zlatitude and zlogitude,
which is suspicious.
So one of the things Dataset does
is it has plug-in support.
So you can write plug-ins for it.
And one of the plug-ins I wrote is one which says,
if there's a latitude and longitude column,
render them on a map.
Now this isn't latitude and longitude.
This is zlatitude and zlongitude.
So I'm going to do select zlatitudeaslatitude,
comma zlongitudeaslongitude, comma star from this.
And I'm going to get rid of the limit and hit Run SQL.
And so this is kind of creepy, because these are places
that I have been in the last couple of years.
I've been to South America, London, the East Coast,
the West Coast, and Mexico City.
In fact, if I order by this descending,
it'll show me the most recent places I've been, presumably.
So I've been in San Francisco.
And oh, look, Cleveland.
This is interesting.
Siri seems to have cut in.
So this is kind of fascinating.
There is a database on my computer
containing all kinds of locations
that I have been recently.
And so I searched Google for CLS business category cache.
And I got two hits, one of which was from the computer
forensics subreddit, where somebody's saying,
does anyone know what this thing is?
And if you zoom in, it says, one of the GPS coordinates
is the crime scene.
And to my utter frustration, there's no follow-ups on this.
This is all I've got to go on.
So I don't think anyone even replied with anything useful.
So there's a mystery for you.
I can't tell you any more than that,
but it's a fascinating thing.
I found by digging through my laptop looking
for SQLite databases.
So that's SQLite databases.
Turns out they're everywhere already.
The thing that we're going to want to do
is we're going to want to create new ones.
So I'm going to show you a couple of the tools
I've been working on that help create SQLite databases.
And the first one is a tool called CSVs to SQLite.
The reason I created this is about 10 years ago,
a whole bunch of people were really campaigning
for open data from governments.
We were saying, hey, governments,
you've got all this amazing data.
We, the taxpayers, have paid for you to collect it.
You should release it somewhere.
And to my utter surprise, it worked.
This is a map of open data portals around the world.
And this is from a year ago.
And there were 2,600 of them crossing
basically every country.
And when you actually start digging into this,
it's amazing what you can find.
The city of San Francisco publishes a CSV file
of every tree in the city, which is 190,000 rows of trees,
each with a latitude and longitude.
I found parking meters, data from a tiny little town
in Morocco.
There's all of this amazing stuff out there.
And the standard format that people
are publishing this stuff in is CSV,
which is it's good in that we can work with CSV.
It's bad in that it's easy to mess up your CSV files
and get escaping and such and like wrong.
So for today, I thought I'd have a quick look
at what's available around the state of Ohio
and Cleveland.
Ohio, I have to admit, is not great at open data.
San Francisco has 400 CSV files for the one city.
Ohio is a little bit further behind that.
But I did find this file, which is interesting.
This is the state properties.
It's properties owned by the state of Ohio.
And it's a CSV file, which you can
download from that website.
And luckily, it has those latitude and longitude columns
in it.
So let's actually, hang on.
Let's hit this thing up.
So I've got a file.
Oh, wrong folder.
Dropbox presentations, PyCon 2019, PyCon.
OK, so here's one I downloaded earlier, sorp2012.csv.
So I'm going to CSVs to SQLite that.
And I'm going to call it ahio.db.
So it's created ahio.db.
Now if I run data set on another random port, ahio.db,
here we are diving straight into that data.
Oh, again, we've got lon and lat.
You know what I'm going to do?
I'm actually going to edit that file.
What was that file called?
In fact, you know what?
I'm going to switch to a more exciting way
of working with this.
So there's this amazing product called Glitch,
which is a sort of learn to program environment
with live recoding and the ability
to remix other people's projects.
And it's a very interesting thing.
And I built something a couple of weeks ago on it
called data set CSVs, which is a demonstration of how
to use data sets and CSVs to SQLite to convert CSV files
and host them online.
So if anyone goes to glitch.com slash tilde data set
hyphen CSVs, you can click on remix
this to create your own copy of my project
and start editing it.
Glitch has a text editor in your browser.
It's running a container with your code in.
And it's automatically previewing your code in here.
So this is a live code environment
where I can start editing things.
And as this read me says, you can drag and drop a CSV file
into this project, and it will be converted
into a SQLite database.
So let's see, where did we put?
Here's that SRP thing.
I'm going to drag and drop it in here.
So now we've got sorp2012.csv.
And then the edit I was about to make in my editor,
I'm going to find the longitude and latitude columns
and rename them.
So that one I'm going to call longitude,
and that one I'm going to call latitude.
And note that this right hand pane is already
showing that data.
This right here is, oh, there we go.
This right here is that CSV file running inside of data set,
but with those two changes made.
So longitude and latitude are running there.
This is all powered by a file called glitch.json,
which knows that to install, it has to pip install data set
and CSVs to SQLite, and then run them.
And then it has to start.
It has to run the data set server.
And I actually want to add an extra thing to this.
I'm going to install that plug-in, the cluster map one.
So I'm going to say pip install data set cluster map.
There we go.
And there's a little log file here
that will show what it's actually doing.
So it's already done it.
It's installed that new library.
It's loaded up here.
And now if I click on this thing here, I've got a map.
Let's do show in a new window.
This is a URL right now that anyone can go and visit.
And this is a map of all of the 36,000 buildings
owned by the state of Ohio.
If I click the Load All button, did I click that successfully?
It's actually going to load all 36,000 points onto the map,
because it turns out JavaScript's kind of fast now.
So yeah, this is loading up.
And this is now a interactive map of every property
owned by the state of Ohio.
And literally, all I had to do to get this
was download that CSV file, drag it into a window,
and here it is.
I think this is a really, I'm absolutely
fascinated by Glitch as a sort of tool for rapidly prototyping
things.
And part of my goal with this project
is to make this kind of tooling more accessible to journalists.
This is a pretty exciting way of giving journalists the ability
to start messing around with code
and with these kinds of projects without having to completely
talk them through how to program.
So did that map finish loading?
There we go.
This is 24,000.
It's loading over my phone.
That would explain why it's taking a while
to load 36,000 data points.
But anyway, you can see this is, these are,
oh, it's going to zoom in and out while it's loading.
I'll come back to that one later.
So that's an example of using the CSVs to SQLite command
to convert open data released by government
and then using Glitch to actually host that data
and start interacting with it, installing plugins,
playing out with this whole ecosystem.
Amazingly, Glitch doesn't even require you to have a login.
If you, without logging into the site,
go to my project and click that remix button,
it'll give you an anonymous session
and give you a project that will get deleted in five days time.
But it's still enough for you to start playing around
and trying out the tools.
But let's talk about a slightly more sophisticated example.
Because CSVs to SQLite works great
if your data is a CSV file.
But a lot of times, you want to pull data
from multiple sources and do something
a little bit more comprehensive with it
before you start trying to serve it up.
So I've been working on a library called SQLiteUtils,
which is mainly designed for running in Jupyter Notebooks.
I'm a huge fan of Jupyter Notebooks.
If you're doing ad hoc data analysis,
screen scraping and so forth, they're
a fantastic environment.
And so what I'm going to do is show you,
talk you through how I built a database of the most popular
PyPI packages using that Jupyter Notebook and this library.
So I'm going to jump over to that now.
Again, this will be fun watching it work over my phone,
but I think it'll be OK.
OK, so is that readable?
There we go.
So there is a fabulous project run by who?
Oh, what happened there?
I lost track of who built this.
But this project here is running a Google BigQuery once a week
to figure out the 5,000 most downloaded packages
from the Python package index.
And handily, it makes all of that data
available as a JSON file.
So if you want to start interrogating Python statistics,
this is a really good starting point.
And in that JSON file, you basically
get a list of projects and their download count.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going
to use the requests library to fetch that back in.
I'm going to pull out just the top 100
to speed things up a little bit and print them all out.
So here we have the top 100 downloaded packages from PyPI
over the past 365 days.
And pip itself has been downloaded
531 million times, which is an interesting number in itself.
So now that I've done that, I'd like
to get a little bit more information
about each of those packages.
And it turns out, PyPI has this semi-documented feature
where if you go to pypi.jango, you
get the information about Django.
And if you add slash JSON on the end,
it'll give you the key information about that package.
Oh, what happened there?
Oh, pypi.jango.
So it'll give you the key information in that package
as JSON.
And you can pretty print that out and see, OK,
we're getting back the author, the author email,
the classifiers, the description.
It's a good amount of data.
So again, because I'm on my phone,
I'm just going to do this with the top 10 packages.
I'm going to loop through the top 10 packages.
And for each one, request that URL,
annotate it with the download count,
because that's not available in PyPI,
but it is available from our original data source,
and stick that in a list of records.
So shift-enter.
Here we go.
So that's fine pretty quickly.
There we have the top 10 packages.
There's 10 things in my records array.
If we look at the first item in the records array,
it's, as you would expect, it's a JSON blob.
And so now this gets fun, because what I want to do
is turn this into a database, into a SQLite database,
so I can start exploring it with Dataset.
And so to do that, I'm going to import the SQLiteUtils module.
I'm going to do db equals SQLiteUtils.database
and give it the path to a file.
I'm actually just going to make sure I haven't
got that file already.
OK, I'm going to remove that file first
to make sure this works.
So I do this.
And then I can say db packages.
This is a table that I'm about to create.
I'm going to create a table called packages.insertAll.
I'm going to send it that list of records.
I could stop then, and that would create me a database
table.
But I want to do a couple of other things.
The primary key should be that name column, which
is the name of the package, which on PyPI
we can guarantee is unique.
And I'm also going to give it a column order,
because without that, the columns
will be in a random order.
And if I say, you know what, I want
the name and the summary and the download count first,
it'll be a little bit nicer to look at.
So I'll do that, and that's created the table.
And then the last step, I'm going
to tell it I want to enable full text search across the name,
summary, keywords, and description columns.
So that's it.
That's done.
Now if we look in here again, we have a file called PyPI.db.
It's 140 kilobytes, because it's only got 10 things in it.
And I can run data set dash p.
I run out of ports a lot.
PyPI.db.
And here we go.
This is a database of Python packages.
Couple of interesting things about this.
Firstly, we can order by download count,
and there's pip sitting at the top.
If you look at the classifiers column here,
you'll notice that this is an array.
That's because the data, it was actually
a nested JSON array in that data we pulled back.
SQLite util spots when that happens,
and it creates a serialized JSON blob
in that particular column, which is handy,
because SQLite actually has JSON functions built in.
So you could run SQL queries against the contents
of a JSON array and do all sorts of interesting things
with that structured data once it makes in there.
And this is super convenient if you're working with,
if you just want to grab some data
and get it into a shape where you can start looking at it,
because you don't have to think about the fact
that some of it's JSON.
That's just handled automatically for you.
And again, we can fast it.
We can see that Amazon Web Services have two
of the packages in the top 10.
That's BotoCore and S3 Transfer, two of the top 10
downloaded packages.
What I'm actually going to do is I prepared, before this talk,
a more interesting database.
Actually, well, before this talk,
I downloaded the first, the top 1,500 packages.
So what I'll do is I'm going to load those in.
This is 1,500 packages in the same format
as those 10 that I just pulled down.
And now I'm going to add them to that database again.
Here I'm, rather than doing an insert, I'm doing an upsert.
So this is saying, insert these records.
If the primary key of name clashes
with an existing record, replace that existing record.
So I can do that.
And I'm also saying I want to populate the full text search,
which I'll show you in a moment.
So that should have worked.
I'm going to run the data set again.
And so now I should have, here we go.
This is now 1,500 Python packages.
You'll notice everything is super fast, because 1,500 is not
a lot of data, and SQLite is an incredibly optimized
piece of software.
There's an interesting thing here where data set suggests
fields that you might want to facet on based on which
columns available have less than 20 unique values.
And right now across 1,500 packages,
the only one with less than 20 unique values
is the description content type.
So we can see markdown is currently
beating restructured text.
But you can actually hack around in the URL.
So if I say facet equals author in the URL itself,
it'll show me the top authors.
Microsoft Corporation are responsible for 149
of the packages in the top 1,500 on PyPI,
which is kind of fascinating.
Google have Google LLC, Google Inc, and Google Inc.
They need to standardize their names a bit.
In terms of individuals, I'm sure people
won't be surprised to see that Kenneth Reitz has
the most packages in the top 1,500 that
aren't authored by a corporation.
But this is kind of cool, right?
We're getting insight into those top 1,500.
And we've put very little work in.
There were a dozen lines of Python code in the Jupyter
Notebook to create this thing.
And now I'm able to start exploring that data.
I'm going to do something a little bit more exciting than
that.
Let's publish it to the internet.
So Dataset has a bunch of subcommands.
Dataset dash dash help will show you what those commands are.
The most exciting of which is Dataset publish.
So Dataset publish lets you take a CSV file
and stick it on the internet.
And actually, I need to switch to my development version
of Dataset for this.
Dataset dash dash help.
Dataset publish dash dash.
So as of yesterday morning, Dataset
can now publish to Google Cloud Run.
Previously, it could only do Zeitnau and Heroku.
And the best part about open source
is that's nothing to do with me at all.
That's a pull request I just merged from Remain Primate.
So thank you very much, Remain, for implementing that feature.
But that means I can run Dataset publish Cloud Run.
And I have no idea if this is going
to work over my telephone.
So we'll see.
I can pass a bunch of arguments.
I'm going to tell it I want the title of my published Dataset
to be PyPI top 1,500 packages.
I want to install a plugin.
Dataset Vega is a visualization plugin.
I'm going to use the master branch.
So rather than the version of Dataset from PyPI,
I'm actually going to use the latest version from GitHub.
And I'm going to enable cause headers
so that I can do JSON API calls to it from other places.
And let's see what happens.
I'm excited to see if this works.
Here we go.
We'll leave this running in the background for a little bit.
Thankfully, I've got one of these I prepared earlier.
So there we go.
It's kicked off.
It's creating a tarball.
The tarball is 12.9 megabytes because it's a Docker file.
And it's that SQLite database.
We're packaging the data with the thing.
We send it up to Google Cloud Build, which will then
build that Docker container.
That upload is going to take a little while.
But eventually, we'll start seeing
it spit out a whole bunch of output of building the Docker
file, publishing it to their image storage,
and eventually launching a new instance which we can actually
go and browse.
So let's see what that's going to be like right now.
Here we go.
Unfortunately, Cloud Run gives us quite ugly URLs.
But what it will give us is this.
I haven't hit it.
There we go.
Oh, that's a bug in the latest master that I need to fix.
API.
Here we go.
So here's that database, just as we saw earlier.
But this is published on the internet.
And because I installed the Dataset Vega plugin,
I also get the option to do charts.
So I can say, you know what?
I want a bar chart where I'm going
to take the name of the plugin.
And I'm going to plot it against the download count.
And let's swap x and y coordinates
so that we can see it more easily.
And then you can also say, you know what?
I want the color to correspond to, let's do the licenses.
License in there?
Dum-pa-dum-pa-dum.
There we go.
So now we're seeing that we've got
a graph of the downloads of the top 100 in this case.
We've color coded against the licenses.
And this is something I'm really excited in digging
into further, the idea that plugins can add visualizations
or all kinds of other additional functionality on top
of the core Dataset tool.
So let's see if that's.
Oh, look at that.
It worked.
That's amazing.
My telephone just deployed a web app.
That's really cool.
And yeah, if I double click here,
I get that error, which I will have to fix after this talk.
But there's that database.
As I mentioned earlier, we've got a JSON API.
So now anyone in the world can start building their own tools
against a JSON API of the top 1,500 Python packages
with a whole bunch of useful things.
Something I forgot to demonstrate earlier
is I enabled full text search against a bunch of columns.
This means that if I search for, say, Django,
it'll return all of the packages that match Django.
I can search for ginger.
Oh, ginger.
So ginger didn't give me the right result
because it's stored as ginger2.
You can actually use wildcards in this.
So if I do ginger with a star, then I
think I'll get back ginger2 as one of those results.
So we've now got full text search running
against four columns in a database.
And the amount of effort taken to put this together
and publish it online was very, very small,
which is really what this whole project is about.
It's like, how can we take any Dataset you can imagine
and get it online in the most useful way possible
with the least effort and cost?
So let's build something even more fun.
So we've got this JSON API.
What can we build on top of it?
And again, I'm going to return to Glitch for this
because Glitch is such a great rapid prototyping environment.
So what we've got here is an autocomplete search engine
running against PyPI.
If I start typing Django, there we go.
It's returning results.
I can do AWS.
And Troposphere comes back.
Oh, and this is kind of giving us
a clue as to why we're getting different results come back
at the top.
It's a straightforward, what's it called, TF-IDF style search.
So AWS is mentioned, it turns out,
50 times in the description of this thing
because it's got all of these different resource
supports and so forth.
But the implementation of this is kind of fun.
What I'm going to do is I'll show you this in the Dataset
SQL environment first.
So what I've actually done here is
I've composed a custom SQL query for the feature
that we want to build.
So I'm saying select packages.rank, packages name,
packages summary from packages, join packages FTS,
where packages FTS match search.
This is how SQLite's built-in search engine works.
It creates a second table called the name of your table,
underscore FTS, and it lets you then join against that table
to run full-text search commands.
Another fun detail here is because I've
got colon search in my SQL query,
Dataset's smart enough to spot that and pull it out
and turn it into a form field.
So here I've got a quick interface
for starting to play around with this SQL query.
Really neat detail here is it means
you can build entirely new applications by writing
some SQL and then sending the link to somebody else.
I can literally paste this link into an email,
and if somebody clicks on it, they'll
be able to start interacting with whatever SQL query it
is I just came up with.
So there's that query.
I click Get as JSON.
I'm getting it back as JSON data.
And so if we look at the autocomplete implementation
here, this is an HTML file with a little bit of JavaScript
in it.
JavaScript literally assembles SQL
in a JavaScript backtick string, which
is the JavaScript equivalent of f-strings.
I love this.
I think there's something very subversive about embedding
SQL directly in JavaScript.
I've been trying to upset people at work with this quite a bit.
But it works, right?
And so this is assembling that.
I'm adding a little bit of code to do this syntax highlighting.
I've got a onKeyUp on the search box,
which runs the searches.
This is entirely like raw vanilla JavaScript.
There's no libraries or anything in here.
All of the work is done by a fetch.
I do a fetch against that URL, and then I decode the JSON,
and then I use innerHTML to create the search results.
Literally, this entire thing is, what, 100 lines of code,
and that's the full implementation for a very
snappy autocomplete.
The performance you get from this
is pretty decent, partly because it's SQLite on the server,
partly because there's very little bytes on the wire
for this.
I've been having a lot of fun building all kinds
of little prototypes like this.
Because once you've got SQL in your JavaScript,
it turns out you can knock out some really exciting complex
projects with very little invested effort.
And I've got an article I wrote in December
that more or less describes this technique in more detail
if you want to really get into the guts of how
all of that worked.
So I wanted to show you a few other interesting projects
that myself and other people have built on top of Dataset.
The first one, this is some sort of freelance data journalism
I did last August.
So the Russian IRA, the Internet Research Agency,
are this mysterious group in Russia
who've been buying Facebook ads to promote
various political causes.
And the House Intelligence Committee
got hold of all of the ads that they had placed
and then made them available for people
to download, which is super exciting,
except they made them available as a bunch of zip files
of zipped up PDF files, which is not quite so exciting.
But this chap called Ed Summers took those PDF files,
wrote some genius code on top of Tesseract OCR,
and turned them all into JSON.
And actually, you know what?
I'll show you his project for this just quickly,
because it's kind of amazing.
Here we go.
He has a GitHub repository, which you should check out.
It uses Tesseract OCR, takes those PDFs,
and turns them into a beautifully constructed set
of JSON.
So I took that JSON, and I used it
to build a Dataset instance that lets you search through the ads
that the Russians were placing.
And so let's search for cops as an example.
If I search for the word cops, I get back.
These are ads that the Russians paid for in cops.
I can sort by the amount of US dollars that they spent on this.
So they spent $215 on this ad here.
But you also get the targeting information from Facebook.
So they were targeting this at people who are age 18 to 65.
That one's not particularly exciting.
But the really creepy stuff is when
you look at things like the most frequent targets
that they were going after.
It's people who match interest, Martin Luther King,
African-American history, and so forth.
The Russians were deliberately targeting
the African-American voting segment
with all kinds of messaging.
It's kind of fascinating to dig into this data.
But it's also, this is exactly the kind of thing
I want Datasets to be used for, is
taking these initially sort of obtuse binary blobs of PDF
files and then turning them into an interactive experience
where people can actually start diving through
and investigating that data themselves.
The other project I wanted to show you is I built Dataset
hoping the newspapers would use it.
At least one newspaper has.
This is the Baltimore Sun.
Carl Johnson at the Baltimore Sun
used it to publish the salary information of everyone
employed by the state of Maryland.
And so you can see the, this one's quite fun,
you can see the highest paid person for each organizer.
People will not be surprised to see that the football
coach at the University of Maryland
is the highest paid person in the entire state
by the state government.
But this is great, right?
This is a newspaper used by software.
They used the theming and the templates
to put their own color scheme interface on the top.
And they used it to publish data of interest to the public.
And I believe they're hosting this entire thing on a T2 micro
because it turns out Python and SQLite,
like SQLite runs on a watch.
It doesn't need a lot of resources
to produce really good results.
So I'm going to move to questions in a second.
But I have a call to action first,
which is that it turns out the world is completely
full of interesting data.
I want people to publish it in the most useful way possible.
So if you have data, please take a look at Dataset.
If you're interested in working with me on this open source
project, I'm very keen on getting more plug-ins,
getting more publishing options to different hosting providers.
I'm trying to figure out Amazon Lambda at the moment, which
is difficult because they decided
that SQLite was not a useful module
and didn't include it in their Python distribution.
But there's a lot of scope, I think,
for developing this project in all kinds of interesting ways.
So thank you very much.
Thank you.
OK, thank you, Simon.
We have about five minutes left for questions.
So if anyone would like to have a question,
please come to the mic.
And we'll be able to get that started.
You stated early on that, first of all, thank you so very much.
This was very enlightening for what you can do with data.
Early on, you stated that because of your description
of serverless as it can scale to zero
and SQLite being in read-only mode
eliminates the problems that it comes with,
you can inherently scale that as well.
How is Dataset Deploy shipping the databases with it?
Are you shipping to two different areas that
can scale on their own?
Or is it each building a database?
No, not at all.
I create a Docker container with the Dataset app in it
and the SQLite database just in the container,
and I ship that.
And that's been working really well.
It has size constraints.
Once you get to a 2 gigabyte SQLite database,
that's a Docker container which is not
going to boot up very quickly.
So I'm very interested in looking
at providers that let you mount a persistent volume just
so I can store a 2 gigabyte database
and not have to worry about it.
But the technical size limit of SQLite is 140 terabytes,
so I'm not expecting to run into any constraints on that
anytime soon.
Anyone else for questions?
I guess that's it.
Oh, thank you.
Thank you.