Anyway, so quick introduction about myself.
I'm Grishma Jainer.
I work as a cognitive software engineer with IBM Watson.
Many people ask me, what exactly do you mean by cognitive software engineer?
It's honestly just a really fancy term for a data scientist who does a bit of
software engineering on the side.
So before we start off, I have a few questions for you.
How much data do you think is produced every year?
Anyone?
Sorry?
Infinite, okay.
Let's talk figures.
Megabytes?
Terabytes?
Hexabytes?
Hexabytes, okay.
Anyone else?
All of the data in the world, like.
Yeah, all the data in the digital universe, everything that's online.
Yeah, it's going pretty big, right?
So it's actually 16.3 zettabytes.
They had to come up with a new unit called zettabytes, where one zettabyte is
one trillion gigabytes, just because that's the amount of magnitude of data
that's there today.
Okay.
So to place this in a bit of context, how much data do you think the brain would
hold?
Depends on the day.
Depends on the day, very true.
Do you think it would be more than zettabytes?
No?
Has to be more than megabytes, right?
I mean, I would like to think we are a little better than our standard pen
drives and hard drives.
Probably gigabytes?
Okay.
So it's actually 2.5 petabytes, where one petabyte is one million gigabytes.
So the digital universe was a zettabyte, which is one trillion gigabytes, and here
we're talking about one million gigabytes.
So it's orders of magnitude lesser.
So to give you a little bit more context, 2.5 petabytes, just think of your
favorite TV show playing for three million hours.
So back in the days where everyone used to use a video recorder to tape shows,
that video recorder would be continuously playing for 300 years.
So just imagine.
And that's only the capacity of the brain.
So multiply that by orders of magnitude to get the amount of data that's there
in today's digital universe.
Okay.
So what we're going to do is, this is a small presentation to give you a gist of
some concepts, to give you an understanding of what the basic data science
pipeline looks like, and then we'll delve deeper into actually coding and using
our Jupyter notebooks.
A quick question was, everyone able to install Jupyter or able to access Google
Core Lab?
Is there anyone who faced problems?
Okay, I'll take that as a no.
All right.
So my objective behind giving you these statistics is just to make you realize
that the amount of data that we generate is way, way more than we actually realize.
In fact, there are some estimates that say that by 2020, that is by next year,
every human on Earth is going to be generating 1.7 megabytes per second.
So that's going to be your location data, your medical data, all your tracking
devices, your emails, your blogs, videos, and whatnot.
So before that, let's actually get down to the very basic terms.
What do you mean by data?
Data is just any piece of information that can be stored, that can be processed.
You can manipulate it.
You can access it.
Data science particularly refers to some algorithms, some techniques, some heuristics
that you use on that data to get some insights.
There's no real consensus on how much amount of data is considered big data.
So the only consensus is that anything that your traditional database processing
systems cannot handle, that's called big data.
Or another definition is if the data can't fit on your local machine, it's big data.
Artificial intelligence specifically talks about agents and trying to give them some
semblance of cognition.
So you're trying to develop so-called intelligent systems over there.
And finally, machine learning is a particular field where you don't try to tell the
program, you don't try to explain to the software what are the patterns, but the
software tries to understand it after you give it the data and tries to analyze what
are the different patterns.
These are the kind of different trends that you're seeing.
And that's machine learning.
OK, so data science is really good at doing common tasks, but quickly and more efficiently
than humans do because it's able to process lots of data quickly.
Another application it's really good at is predicting and forecasting results, making
customized recommendations.
So think about Amazon, think about Netflix, think about Spotify.
It's really good at making recommendations that are good for you as an individual.
Optimizes procedures and actions, of course, and really good at finding the needle in the
haystack or trying to identify patterns that are not as easily identified by humans.
OK, so this is a snapshot of what the data science pipeline looks like.
You start off with a question and the data at hand.
Then you finally dangle the data.
You clean it, you explore it, you try to get an understanding of what is the data like?
What are the different features?
What are the characteristics?
Is it text-based?
Is it sound-based?
Is it a combination of both?
That iterative, you can see that there's from explore to preprocess to model is kind of
an iterative cycle because oftentimes you might create a model and you might not get
really good performance.
So then you go back and you try to take more features from the data or try to do more of
cleaning and then start the model building process again.
And finally, when you're happy, you validate the model, you're happy with the performance,
you tell a story, which hopefully will give you some actionable insight.
OK, so what kind of questions can we use data science to answer?
So pretty basic.
All of us use Gmail or some other mail service and you see a lot of emails going to your
spam folder, right, or your junk folder.
That's data science at the back end because it helps you identify which emails are likely
to be marked as spam or which are spam and which ones are probably important emails that
you need to see.
Another really common example is oftentimes you use your credit cards and you might get
some text alerts saying that, hey, your credit card was used for so-and-so transaction.
Was that really you?
That's because in their machine learning system, it got triggered as an anomaly, something
either probably the retailer you went to was not one where you go to usually, or maybe
you stay in the US and it got used in some other country.
So those kind of things stand out as anomalies, so that's data science.
Like I mentioned, Amazon, Netflix, even Facebook, they have these recommender algorithms.
So how likely are you to engage with a particular article or how likely are you to listen to
a sound, how likely you are to buy a particular product, and it also helps in allowing you
to predict things.
For example, you're trying to predict who is going to be the primary candidate for Democrats
in the upcoming elections, or you're trying to predict which team is going to win in a
certain sports league.
So it's a lot of wide variety of applications, but the algorithms behind most of these applications
are kind of the same, and we'll be seeing them shortly.
So once we have the question at hand, when we have identified what stakeholders we want
who are involved in the decision making and who want the answers to the questions, you
obviously need the data at hand, because you won't be able to perform data science without
the data.
So data comes in a lot of different formats from a lot of different sources, but you can
categorize them into three main categories, which is structured, unstructured, and semi-structured.
So structured, think of your traditional databases where you have a tabular format, you have
the row and column format.
Unstructured is the opposite end of the spectrum.
Think about your audios, your videos, your documents, where there is no standard structure
that gets followed.
And finally semi-structured, which kind of sits in the middle of these two, where there
is some sort of structure associated.
For example, think about web pages, you have HTML tags, but within those HTML tags the
content could be anything, which is unstructured.
So it's a bit of both structured and semi-structured.
Most of the data in the world today is actually unstructured, which is kind of a challenge,
because if you have structured data you know what to expect and you know how to handle
it, how to access it.
But with unstructured data there could be a combination of data formats, combination
and becomes a little challenging in accessing and manipulating it.
Okay, so you got the question, you have the data at hand.
You start off with something that's called as data wrangling or the data cleansing, data
cleaning process, where what you're trying to do is try to make sure that your data is
in a format that makes it accessible, that makes it accessible, that allows you to derive
insights better.
So data wrangling is nothing but the process of gathering and selecting data, transforming
it to make it useful.
Examples include you would standardize multiple sources if you're trying to combine different
data sets.
Let's say for example one data set has the column name called gender and another data
set has the column name called sex.
So both of these two mean the same thing, right, but the computer is not going to understand
that.
So you can standardize it by performing, by giving the same name to both of the columns.
There is often the problem of dealing with missing data because real world data is messy.
Let's say for example you send out a survey, maybe someone fills their human age as 200
years.
Now to the best of our knowledge nobody like that exists, so that's going to be a wrong
or maybe someone doesn't want to reveal some information and it's just like blank over
there.
So you could either discard the data or you could try filling it, interpolating it, you
could fill it with the median or the mode or the maximum and whatnot.
Also you can convert categories to numbers, let's say like in the spam detection example
you have the email records labeled as spam or not spam, so you can assign a value of
one to spam and you can assign a value of zero to not spam.
Okay, so after the initial process of data cleaning you go through exploration which
is where think of it as getting your feet wet with the data and you're trying to understand
what are the different features that are present and what are the characteristics, what do
they look like, what is the distribution like, what are the different values that those features
can take and hopefully by the end of it you have some idea of what looks interesting,
is pretty obvious what is something unexpected and you've formed some sort of hypothesis
about the data.
So it'd be things like okay this looks pretty obvious, perhaps I don't want to delve deeper
into it but this is kind of unexpected, I would like to further investigate and see
is it something that is pretty obvious, is it something not obvious, is it something
surprising, I might help answer the question and this step also involves a lot of data
visualization, you try to create graphs to see the distributions of data and understand
the correlations among the features.
Okay, and finally we head on to the model building phase where you create a lot of features,
you have the features, you create some more meaningful features using a combination of
these and then finally you divide the data into training and test sets, you choose a
machine learning model or a particular algorithm that you want to apply depending on the kind
of output that you want, keep iterating, like I mentioned it can be an iterative process,
maybe you want to go back and get some more features that give you more information and
then finally you end up with evaluating the model.
Okay, so hopefully I gave you a quick brief overview of the entire process, so let's get
down to coding.
You should be able to access this by PyCon ID.
Yeah.
Is this better?
So, this is the URL, it's bid.ly slash PyCon IDS which is into the data science.
Yeah, sure.
Oh, okay.
Okay, you should be able to access it now.
Was everyone able to access it?
It's bid.ly slash PyCon IDS.
Yeah, I can do that.
Thank you.
Mr. Elliott?
So, let me just actually write it in the world.
Sorry?
Oh, okay.
Was everyone able to access it?
Okay.
What browser are you using?
So, now I have two options.
For those of you who already have Jupyter installed, you can run it on your local machine,
or you can just run it in the browser using Google Colab.
So, let me just show you quickly how you can run it.
So, this is the first cell of code.
You can click on the left-hand panel, and you will see the Play button, and just click it to run it.
And then you can see it rerun the cell.
And for those of you who are using Jupyter, you can download this notebook.
There should be a download button somewhere here.
I probably cannot see it.
Oh, okay. Yeah.
Because, yeah, it's magnified, so I'm not able to see it,
but you should be able to download this notebook and place it in your Jupyter.
Or just place it anywhere in your documents.
And then start up a terminal.
Oh, terminal, sorry.
So, just type Jupyter notebook in the terminal for those of you using Jupyter on your local machine.
And that will open up the Jupyter ID for you in one of your browser tabs.
And then access wherever you have stored your notebook.
So for me, it's here.
And then you should be able to run it using the Run button.
How many of you are using Jupyter?
Okay, I guess a majority of you. Fine.
Then I'll keep it in Jupyter.
Is the size okay for everyone?
Otherwise, you should be able to access the notebook as well.
Okay. So this has all of the code.
Feel free to run it over here or feel free to open up a new notebook and just try to run it on your own.
Okay, so I already gave you a bit of introduction about data science.
What does the data science pipeline look like?
Question to answer and of course the data.
Okay, so before we go into that, there are a few tools you can see with the heading Python tools mentioned at different intervals.
So the first one is NumPy. How many of you are familiar with NumPy?
Okay, I think some of you aren't.
Okay, so NumPy is just this really cool package.
It stands for numerical Python.
It's a part of the scientific computing or SciPy stack in Python.
And what it does is it gives you this really high-performing multi-dimensional array that you can use.
So if you're familiar with MATLAB or the way MATLAB works, it's all in matrix form.
So that's what NumPy does for you but in Python.
It gives you a multi-dimensional array and it's super fast because the operations that are taking place are on the matrix instead of the scalars.
You can use Conda or PIP to install NumPy.
For those of you using Google Colab, all of the packages should already be accessible.
You don't have to install them.
But for those of you who are using Jupyter and local machine, you might already have the package installed.
Otherwise, you can just install it using PIP and Conda.
Okay, similarly, pandas, NumPy and pandas almost always go hand in hand.
Pandas is this, let's say it's kind of a data frame or if it's an object that tries to model the data into what an Excel spreadsheet would look like.
So think of rows, think of different column headers, and that is what your pandas data frame would look like.
It came from the word panel data, which I believe is used in economics.
And again, you can go ahead and install pandas using Conda or PIP.
How many of you are familiar with pandas?
Okay, again, most of you.
Is there anyone who would like me to go through pandas in a little more detail?
Okay, a few hands.
Okay, I'll do that.
Okay, so there are a few different ways to use panda.
So you can start off with a list, a dictionary, or a NumPy array and just load it directly into a pandas data frame.
Or you can open a local file on your machine.
So think of a CSV file and you can load that into your data frame.
And finally, you can connect it to a remote database or you can try to scrape the information from a website and load that into a data frame.
So let's take a look at a quick example.
Let's go ahead and import NumPy as NP and pandas as PD so we don't have to type the entire name always.
And here I'm just creating a simple list with the first few numbers of the Fibonacci series.
So this is a list that's user defined.
And then the way you would convert it to a data frame is pandas or PD.dataFrame.
You pass the list or the data that you want.
And then you say that I want the column names to be a list of whatever column names you want.
Since we have only one column over here, let's give the name as value and see what happens.
So this is what a pandas data frame looks like.
You have value as the column, you have 0, 1, 2, 7 as the different rows, and the 0, 1, 2, 7 are also the index numbers.
Okay. So another way to load a data frame is like I mentioned, a CSV file.
So you can go ahead and access any CSV file on your computer.
Or there's one of these raw data sets on GitHub, which is a list of countries and the regions they are in.
So let's try to go ahead and read that in our pandas data frame.
So you'd go pd.read.csv and then finally give it the file name.
In this case, it's the URL name.
And you can print out the shape or the dimensions using pandas, the data frame dot shape.
And you can also print out some information about the metadata using the data frame dot info.
So you can see the dimensions are 194, where 194 are the number of rows, 2 is the number of columns.
It's an object of type pandas dot data frame and tells you some more metadata about what are the different kind of columns present, what are the data types for them.
And then you can also print the first five or the first end data points or rows in the data frame using the head function.
Or if you want the last ones, you use the tail function.
So it works in a similar way.
So you can see these are the first five rows in our data frame.
There are some more functions that you can use in the pandas data frame like, okay, very important, you access it using, if you want to access a column, you access it using the data frame name with in square brackets the name of the column.
You can also use indexing over here, pretty similar to how our arrays work, except you have to use ILOC, which is, I believe, the index location.
And then you give it zero zero as, for example, the first very first element.
You can perform some other operations like filtering, grouping, selecting.
And this is the kind of syntax what you would use for doing that.
So this gives you all of the data points where the region is North America.
And finally, you can also group by region and then see how many countries are there in those particular regions.
So this is what the output looks like.
This was the very first element in our data frame.
These are all of the countries where North America is the region.
And finally, this is a count where after you group it by regions.
OK, any questions so far?
OK.
So this is another way to access a data set.
There's another package called sklearn, which stands for scikit-learn.
We'll be seeing that in detail a little later.
But there are a few data sets that are already included in this package.
You don't really have to download any data set.
We can just work internally and try to perform some sort of model building.
So another really famous data set is called as the Iris data set, which is basically some sort of characteristics, some sort of information about flowers.
You have sepal length, sepal width, petal length, and so on and so forth.
It's just completely numerical data.
You can't see any text over here.
And the way to load it would be you give, you convert it into a numpy array.
And then you see that this is all of the data.
And then finally, target is what the label is associated with the data and the different column names, which are nothing but the feature names plus the target.
And then you can see what the initial few points in the data set look like.
We won't be using this data set, but this is just to give you an example of how there are inbuilt data sets in the package sklearn.
And that's how we can access them.
OK, moving on.
So now we have our data or rather toy data set sample data sets.
We go into data cleaning or data rankling.
So like I mentioned, real world data is often messy.
There can be points where the value doesn't really make sense.
Like I mentioned, age, human age being 200 years.
Or there are data sets where you have some missing values or null values.
You could also have categories and we would convert them into numbers.
And another important point is we must ensure that a data set is unique or at least as unique as we can make it, because we don't want the model to get a false weightage of the most frequent occurring data points.
OK, so remember we had a user defined list of Fibonacci series which we converted into a data frame.
So let's perform a few simple data cleaning steps on that.
So if you see in the initial list or in the initial data frame for Fibonacci, you'd see that the last value is any n, which is basically kind of a null value.
And I intentionally put it there so we can see how the cleaning happens.
OK, so there's this nifty little function called isNull.
What you do is you call the data frame dot isNull and then do a sum.
So you can the sum just tells you tells you that it OK.
So isNull is going to return.
Let's see what it returns.
It's going to return a series of true or false values where if the particular value was null, it's going to return true.
And internally, if you use a dot sum, it gets mapped to zeros and ones.
And you finally find the sum.
So if it's not zero, you realize that there are some values which are null.
So like in this case, the sum was one because there was one null value.
And the way you would handle it is let's say for instance, I want to fill that missing null value using the average for that particular row or for that particular column.
So I just use the mean since there is only one column in the data set.
And I'd say Fibonacci PD, which is our data frame, dot fill any fill the empty value with the mean.
And this would fill all of the any values.
Just in our example, there's only one.
So it's going to fill one.
And you can see it's filled it with 2.85, the actual average for the numbers.
So this is usually the procedure you follow when you are a little pressed for data and you don't have enough data points.
But if you do have a lot of data points or a really small percentage of data points that are missing values, you can just go ahead and completely discard them.
That works too.
And the way you would discard it is using the drop any function.
In place is equal to true just means that it's going to perform the operation in that on the data frame itself.
So you don't need to save it or you don't need to allocate the result into another data frame.
And then you can see over here the value is gone.
Yeah.
It really depends on the application that you're going for.
So in fact, while I was preparing this tutorial, I replaced one of the column names in place.
And then I later realized I actually needed the original column.
So if you do see that you might have a need for the original column, it's better to assign it to a different data frame or a different column name.
So kind of like a duplicate column.
So you're pretty sure that you don't want anything else to do with it.
Just you can do it in place.
Yeah.
Any other questions?
OK.
Similarly, let's go to the country toy data set.
And we can get an idea of what are the unique values for the region column using countries of region.unique.
So these are the different values.
OK.
Remember how we mentioned that we would want to standardize the data set or convert the categories, the string names to some sort of an integer mapping.
So this is what we're trying to do over here.
We've just given all of the different regions an integer from one to six.
And the way we would go about mapping it is let's create another column name called region category, which is the integer map integer mapping.
Let's assign it to region first and then using our mapping, we would use the replace function.
So the ones like, for example, South America would get a value of six like you can see over here.
So whenever we have any sort of categories in your data set, go ahead and perform a mapping so that it's easier to work with numbers later on.
Any questions so far?
Yeah.
Is there a way to have it do that?
I noticed these are alphabetic, right?
Yeah.
So they don't look like it's supposed to say Africa is one of the issues too.
Is there a way to just have it map that automatically?
Yeah.
You could just run a for loop and start like an iterator and have it map it that way.
But I just wanted to keep it simple over here.
Any other questions?
Okay.
So now that we have got the data, we have a question that we want to answer.
We've cleaned the data.
We start with the data exploration phase, which is just prior to the model building phase.
Think of it as getting your feet wet, where you're trying to understand what the data looks like, what are the different features, what are their characteristics,
and it involves a lot of visualizations, drawing, plotting a lot of graphs.
So another tool that comes in handy over here is Matplotlib.
How many of you are familiar with Matplotlib?
Okay.
Fewer hands this time.
So just think of it as a 2D plotting library for Python.
It helps you create graphs.
So think about line charts, your box plots, your distributions, histograms, and whatnot.
Similar to how you install the other packages, you can go ahead and use Conda and PIP.
So let's take a look at how Matplotlib works.
So before we do that, let's try to explore what the different columns look like.
We already know that Fibonacci series has only one particular column, which is value.
The data types for the different columns is you use .dtypes, and it says that there's only one column value with data type float64.
And there's another function called describe, which tries to give you all of the different statistics, the numerical statistics,
to think about your quartiles, your mean, your count, min, max,
and it gives you a snapshot of those statistics for each of the columns, numerical columns in your data frame.
So you can see it over here.
So oftentimes when you try to use Matplotlib, your graph might not show up,
in which case you would use this magic line where you see Matplotlib inline,
which says that I want the graphing to come as part of this code or the cells output.
So it has to be inline with everything else.
Okay, let's go ahead and import from Matplotlib pyplot, and let's use it as PLT so that we don't have to have the name.
And we just say plt.plot and pass it the pandas data frame.
And that gives you a line chart.
Go ahead and feel free to write the title, name the axis.
You can also change the intervals for the different axes using extx or ytx.
So this is what the line chart looks like.
But this is the index, and remember the last value was 8, which is over here.
Let's try to use a similar strategy on the country data set.
Value.counts tells you the different categories that are present and the frequency for those.
So let's try to plot a histogram for the frequency of the different regions in there.
So you can see South America is the lowest, and Africa and African countries in the data set are highest or the most occurring.
So you can also go ahead and plot distributions, box plots, trying to see if it's a normal distribution, and a lot of other things over there.
Okay. Another visualization tool that's pretty popular, that's very commonly used, is called cBond, which is built upon matplotlib.
So just think of it as advanced matplotlib.
We'll be seeing a few examples later on.
It looks a little prettier. It gives you more information, and it's used mainly in the statistical graphing sense.
Installation remains the same with PIPConda.
Okay. So we took the question, we have the data, we performed some sort of analysis on it, we cleaned it, we explored it.
Now let's get to what is considered as the meaty part of it, which is called model building.
So like I mentioned earlier, model building first starts off with feature engineering,
where you try to think of what features might help you answer the question that you have at hand, or what features, if combined together, might give you a more informative feature.
So think, for example, you're trying to detect credit card fraud, and you have a list of transactions with each of their timestamps.
Now the timestamp on its own is not going to be an important feature, because it's just going to be a series of human readable date, time, time zone.
But if you use that timestamp to convert it to maybe, let's say, days since last transaction, or hours since last transaction, that might help give you a more meaningful feature.
So let's say, you know, if you weren't using the credit card for maybe like a year, and suddenly there's a transaction, it might get flagged as fraud, because you usually don't use the credit card, and suddenly you've used it.
So that is where feature engineering comes into play. It's also helpful to have a domain expert, like let's say in the case of medical imaging data, someone with a medical background, usually data scientists, they don't come from medical backgrounds, right?
So you do need doctors, nurses, bioinformaticians to help you understand what exactly do those features mean. Is it something that's important?
Is it something that's indicative of trying to predict if a cancer exists, if a tumor exists or not?
Or is it something that another feature already represents? So you can just kind of like, you know, drop that feature and use the other feature that holds the same information.
So domain expertise is also important. It really depends on the application.
Okay. Once you have the data, we perform what's known as a training and testing split.
So remember how in school we would be given homework, so we'd be taught in the class? That is the training that's happening for us.
And then finally, the semesters would culminate with an examination or a project, which is where your performance or your testing happens.
So it's the same logic for a model. We're trying to give it a majority of data as training data or scene data on which it can learn some sort of patterns, get some insights.
And then finally, we want it to be evaluated in a fair and objective manner.
So you're not going to give it the exact same data points, but you're going to give it unseen data to see how well it has actually created a model.
Yeah, good question. So this one is random, but oftentimes what happens is, let's say for instance, let's take the example of you're trying to predict cancer.
And what you're trying to predict is a very rare type of cancer.
So you're probably going to have like maybe 90 or 95 percent of your data set where it's predicted as not cancer and five to 10 percent or a really small percentage where it's predicted as cancer.
Now, if you try to do a very simple model, you're going to get a very small percentage of data that's predicted as cancer.
Now, if you try to do a random train test split, you're probably going to end up with like, you know, most of the splits being not cancer, whereas you're trying to build a model that's trying to predict cancer.
So it's going to be difficult, right? So in those cases, you use something that's called as stratified sampling where you try to balance the data.
You say, OK, I'm going to I have a very small I have maybe 10 percent of cases where cancer exists.
So I'm going to learn to balance it and split it accordingly.
So even my training has some of these samples and even my testing has some of these samples.
Another issue that also comes with those kind of data sets.
So those kind of assets are what we call imbalanced class or because there are two classes, right?
Cancer and non-cancer. And they are really different in proportions.
The other strategy that you can take is called sampling, which is over sampling or under sampling.
So like I mentioned, if you have 90 percent of non-cancer non-cancer data points, you can down sample it.
You can reduce the number, the proportion in it and bring it a little closer to 10 percent.
Or alternatively, you can over sample the minority class where you take the 10 percent and you keep duplicating the data points so that it tries to learn a general model.
Does that make sense?
Any questions?
OK. All right.
OK. SKA learn, scikit learn, that is what forms the crux of most of our machine learning algorithms.
And it works in conjunction with NumPy and SciPy, which we have already installed.
OK. So like I mentioned in the slides, there are two main categories of algorithms, supervised and unsupervised.
Supervised is it has labels involved with the data like cancer, not cancer, spam, not spam, fraudulent, not fraudulent.
Those kind of labels are associated with the data.
So when you get the data set, you have those kind of labels already over there.
That's why it's called supervised, because you have some sort of supervision or some sort of knowledge to inform if you're trying to predict the label correctly or not.
Unsupervised is the other end of the spectrum where there are no labels associated.
You don't know what is a right answer, what is the wrong answer.
But in those cases, you're usually not looking for the right or wrong answer.
What you're trying to do is you're trying to understand what is the structure of data like.
Like, for example, you're trying to create, let's say, some sort of recommendation algorithm for Netflix.
If I know that my taste and your taste, let's say for both of us, like action superhero movies,
then we're going to come in the same cluster because the kind of movies that we've watched or the kinds of movies we would be interested in watching are going to be similar.
So that helps us cluster our group objects or people in the same same categories.
But like I said, there is no right or wrong answer.
So it's unsupervised because there's no supervision to go offer.
Any questions so far?
OK. There's a third type, which is again like how we had structured and structured and semi-structured.
The third type is semi-supervised.
Semi-supervised basically means you have a data set where you have some of the labels, but most of them are unlabeled.
So let's say for if you have an archive of photos, your images, some of them might have captions in them,
but a majority of them wouldn't have any captions involved or they might have location tags or a majority would not have location tags.
So that is semi-supervised.
And the fourth type is reinforcement learning.
Let me quickly go down to that.
We're not going to be looking at semi-supervised reinforcement learning, but since those terms are pretty important,
I just wanted to mention it and give you just of what they mean.
So this is unsupervised.
This is semi-supervised.
This is reinforcement learning.
So there was this news a few years back where they tried to teach a robot to flip pancakes.
And you can see that it's doing really bad at start.
It's just, you know, trying to go all for it and having fun with it.
So what happens in reinforcement learning?
It is quite similar to how humans have goals and it's a very goal oriented learning.
So given an environment, there are a set of actions you can take.
Let's say, for example, you have an examination tomorrow.
You can either go off to sleep and not really care about the examination or you can pull up an all nighter and, you know,
try to do your best on the examination.
So you have two options over here.
Based on past performances, you see that, OK, I am able to manage the test, the exam.
They're usually easy.
I pay attention in class.
Or you may say like, you may say that, you know, if I pull an all nighter, I'm going to really perform worse than I should
because I won't remember anything.
So you have two different options or two different actions you can take.
And on your past performance, you understand if a particular action gave you a reward,
like yes, the risk paid off where you can go off to sleep comfortably and still pass.
Or no, if you do pull an all nighter, your performance is going to be worse than usual.
So that's the penalty.
So you kind of weigh the reward and the penalty using your past information or your past performance.
And then you try to fine tune your learning later on.
So this is what the robot flipping pancake does.
See, it finally was able to do it correctly, right?
Because after a lot of trials and errors and a lot of feedback being given to it saying that, OK, if I put a lot of force
and I try to like, you know, really flip it high up in the air, it's probably not going to land correctly.
But if I be really gentle and I just put a little bit of force, it's probably going to be correct.
And those kind of that kind of feedback mechanism or that kind of reward penalty systems helps it learn what is the right way to do.
And this was like just a trial error.
There was no information really given to the robot where, you know, this is how you're supposed to flip a pancake.
OK, so that was reinforcement learning that's often used in robots.
There was another really cool link of Google had this deep learning system where it learned to play Atari video game.
So I'm just going to run it in.
So like they mentioned, there was no domain knowledge given.
All it was told was you have to maximize the score that you see on the screen.
That's it.
So you can see it's not doing a great job because the ball keeps falling and it keeps losing lives.
And then after I believe what was 10 minutes of training, it's doing a better job, right?
It's being able to balance the ball and also trying to hit the blocks.
So it realizes that digging a tunnel is the best way to do because it gives it some time to like hit the other blocks, yet not fall.
So you can see it hit that tunnel over it created a tunnel over there, right?
And that was the most optimized way to play the game.
So pretty cool applications of reinforcement learning, but they involve a lot more knowledge.
So we won't be dealing with that today.
OK, shall I continue or would you like a five or 10 minute break?
Could use a break.
OK, five minutes or 10 minutes.
OK, sure.
Let's take a break.
Hey, I'm Eshma.
Nice to meet you.
So I've been curious.
I'm not from a data science background, but I'm really interested in the field.
And you made a comment about like consulting with domain experts.
And I'm wondering if there's like a trend in the field of people like from that domain sort of becoming data scientists or is it mostly like two separate roles that collaborate?
There are both.
Both of action scenarios where both of those happen.
I think it really depends on the company or the department of the team you're working in.
Like for my work, what we do is we are a central team of data scientists and then we keep changing, switching projects.
So each of us will work on maybe a few months on one project, a few months on another project.
But if you're working in, let's say, a company that's, for example, focused on the medicine domain, then you would probably try to have your existing employees in the skills of data science because you already have the background knowledge of the domain expertise.
Right.
You can just learn a few statistical concepts, learn a bit of programming or just use data science.
Okay.
Yeah. So I work for Boeing.
And so we are involved in a project where we're basically like building tools to like try and get engineers to like figure out how to use data science.
Okay.
And so we've just started out, but it's proving a little difficult.
It's kind of surprising.
I think we tried, you know, like, for example, using Jupyter notebooks to display math that we know the people are familiar with.
And they're like, that's code. I don't want to see that.
Oh, wow.
Oh, so by the way, I don't know if you're already familiar with, there are a few lines that you can write in this part of the notebook, which hides all the code.
Well, the thing is we wanted to show them.
Oh, okay.
We were like trying to use a combination of like the markdown, the text equations with the code to try to get people to understand it.
But apparently it's scary.
Okay. I would say maybe just starting off with some sort of interactive virtualizations, get them comfortable with that.
And then once they already know, like, okay, for example, this is the clustering algorithm or the classification algorithm, maybe just slowly start to put in a bit of code.
But yeah, sounds pretty exciting.
Yeah, it's pretty neat. I hope it starts to pick up some traction and people start to be less afraid.
Cool. Thank you.
Hey.
So by all the experience with data science on this side, things that I've seen in, you know, in academics and in classes and stuff, how does this sort of sort of compare to the type of work you do every day?
It's actually pretty similar, but like, you know, slightly simplified.
I think at least one of the things that I noticed was huge differentiator.
And I think from that is a, the toy data sets are really natural.
You know what they mean. They're going to be similar to what we're working with.
Right.
You can't understand what the different columns mean.
You don't know why there's like maybe 90% of goodness and how you're supposed to perform analysis.
That's number one.
It doesn't fit in your local as well.
So you often have to use your data processing frameworks like Spark, Hadoop, Hive, all of that.
And I think the third one is because you're working in the industry or you have specific deadlines, specific milestones to meet.
Like in academics, it's, you know, like if you can improve it by one percentage point, that's great.
Like you need to publish papers.
But in the industry, it's more like, okay, this is our deadline.
Our deadline is tomorrow. Is it good enough? Is it like 80%?
And then like so the first thing you mentioned, the data isn't as clean as it's going to be.
So I'm going to say, are there techniques that you have to deal with that are taught in academics?
Or is it mainly just figured out in the situation?
I think you're given like some sort of groundwork, some sort of like you're probably told like, okay, this is what you can do.
This is what you can do. You don't know how exactly to do it or you know what does the data look like.
And another thing that you often use in the real world is humans to label a lot of things.
Okay.
You do have that human label, but it's not going to be completely automated.
You do have humans in the room for labeling the data.
So you do have humans for evaluating what the machine is having to say before it makes sense to you.
Okay.
Yeah. What, did you go to school?
No, I graduated.
Okay.
Okay, shall we begin?
Okay, how's the pace so far?
Is it okay?
Is it too fast?
Too slow?
Okay.
All right.
So, yeah.
Now we're going to get into model building.
So we'll quickly see a few more slides just to understand the different concepts and then
go back to coding.
Okay.
So, we've already covered about feature engineering where we start to select the important features,
maybe construct a few useful new ones and then divide the data set into training and
test sets.
Create the machine learning model where it could be supervised, which is classification
or regression, where you already have labels associated with the data.
Or it could be unsupervised where there are no labels, but you're just trying to understand
the structure of the data.
You tune the model parameters, just some models, the parameters, some input values associated
with the way the model works.
I'm often asked how exactly do we go about tuning them.
Honestly, a lot of it is trial and error.
And then you've trained the model, monitor against overfitting.
Evaluate the model and unseen data where you're trying to see how well it performs.
And like I mentioned, it could be an iterative process.
If you're not happy with the model performance, you can either go ahead and change the algorithm
that you're using in your models or you can go back and try to use a different subset
of features.
And you can also have an ensemble of models where you're trying to combine a lot of different
types of models with each other and create this huge, bigger model.
Let's say if we have an apple as our object or the data frame, its features would be things
like color, type, shape, so on and so forth.
We've already seen some examples of that.
There's this XKCD comic which I find really relevant where the first person says, okay,
I'm seeing this huge pile.
Is this your machine learning system?
And the second person goes, yeah, it's this huge big black box.
It's just a lot of linear algebra and all of these fancy numbers and calculations.
So you just pour in all of your data.
And on the other side, you magically get all of the answers.
And the first person goes, but how do you know if the answers are wrong?
Like what do you do then?
And the second person goes, you know what?
Just start stirring the pile till they start looking right, which is pretty much what we
do with tuning model parameters, trying model buildings, evaluating what features are good
or not.
So I guess my main objective behind all of this is saying that data science is a field
that comes with a lot of uncertainty involved.
And that's something that might seem a little odd at the start.
Lot of questions you might have in your mind, things like how much data is enough?
How do you know if the quality of data is good?
How do you know if the quality of your model or the performance is good enough or not?
And there's one constant answer to this.
It depends.
It depends on are you trying to build a production ready model?
It depends on are you trying to detect rare type of cancer?
Are you trying to detect maybe something a little more not a little less important?
Maybe you're trying to give some sort of recommendations for music.
It depends on how much data can you get more?
If you can, if it's easy to get that kind of data, that amount of data, go ahead and
do it.
But if it's really going to be difficult, probably concentrate on trying to improve
your model with different features, with different algorithms.
So yeah, there's just a lot of question marks, but hopefully it's something you'll ease
into and figure out some heuristics as time goes by.
Okay.
So we already covered this supervised, unsupervised, semi-supervised and reinforcement learning.
Now let's get into what exactly are the different kinds of algorithms and what are the applications.
So the first algorithm is classification.
Very simple example, giving the computer an image and trying to let it guess if the image
is that of a cat or a dog or maybe something completely else.
A slightly more nuanced example of this would be given a patient's history, try to predict
if this person is going to suffer from heart failure or not.
So classification is a type of supervised learning since we have some sort of labels
associated with the data, right?
We know that, okay, this person suffered heart attack or we know that this image is that
of a cat or a dog or something completely else.
So it falls under supervised and the features, let's say for example, of trying to predict
if heart failure is going to occur to a patient or not would be things like the patient's
medical notes, the kind of environment, the lifestyle the patient leads, what is the history,
is it something that runs in the family, is the patient taking the medications or not,
those kind of things would be the features.
The second type is called regression, which also falls under supervised learning, except
how in classification you had categories, in regression you have numbers or values.
So a very simple example of that would be you're trying to predict how much or how many.
Perhaps you're trying to predict your company's next quarter's revenue or you're trying to
predict future disease outbreaks where your features could be things about population
health, if there's a lot of travel, international travel going on, like the recent outbreak
of measles.
So you can look at features saying is there a lot of travel from probably New York, I
believe that's where it originated, people from there traveling or are there a lot of
people who didn't receive vaccinations, climate change, contamination of food and water supplies
for different questions.
Regressions could also be used.
So those two, regression and classification, fall in supervised learning.
The next one is unsupervised learning and the most common example would be clustering.
So let's say you have a bunch of objects and you're trying to create groups to understand
how exactly these objects are organized.
So you can see like triangle circles and crosses get separated.
Another example would be trying to use clustering for customer segmentation.
Like I mentioned for Netflix, for Spotify, for Amazon, you would have certain groups
of customers which interact with your website or with your products in a similar manner
or which would be interested in the same thing.
So those are your clusters where you're trying to segment customers.
Features would be things like what has been your purchase history or what have been the
things you've clicked on, you've tried to see if you want to buy or not or added them
to cart.
What are your demographics like?
For example, people in San Francisco in a certain age group might tend to buy something
more than someone from let's say New York and on an activity like I mentioned.
Another type is called anomaly detection where you're trying to see is this particular data
point weird or not?
Like in the case of credit card fraud detection, is the particular transaction fraudulent?
Is it abnormal for that person involved?
And features might be the amount you're spending per transaction.
Let's say you only use a credit card for probably everything less than $50 and suddenly there's
like a $10,000 charge on your credit card.
It's probably going to get flagged.
The transaction time, let's say there's a transaction that happens at like four in the
morning that could be flagged as an anomaly.
The merchant location, the code, like I mentioned, if it's something that you don't usually spend,
use your credit card on and the transaction method.
Let's say you use your credit card all the time online and not in person and then you
suddenly use it in person, it might get flagged.
So after we use the algorithms to create a model, we do want to evaluate how well the
model's performing or we want to validate if our model is giving the right answers or not.
So there can be cases where it's either false positive or false negative, which means that
in the first case it's called type one error, which says something is falsely positive.
So basically in the first picture you can see that's like an easy way to remember.
The doctor's examining a man and saying that, oh, you're pregnant.
So you're giving it positive, but that's actually a false positive.
It should have been a negative.
And the type two error is the converse, which is a false negative, where this doctor is
tracking a lady patient and she's clearly pregnant, well, in this case, and then the
doctor goes, but you're not pregnant.
So that's false negative, giving it, predicting it as negative when it in fact is positive.
We look deeper into those, why exactly we use those and how they make sense.
Some other metrics to consider are a very simple one, accuracy.
How well are you predicting or how correct are your predictions?
Precision and recall, we'll be looking at them again in the codes.
F1 score, which is just a combination of precision and recall.
So you look at the false positives, false negatives, true positives, true negatives.
True positives, true negatives are what got correctly labeled.
And you use them to calculate their precision and recall, like you can see in the example
over there.
And finally, after you have the results, you're happy with your model, you create some sort
of visualizations to summarize your model's results.
And there's another term that's another step that's come up a lot is data storytelling,
where you don't just present your results, but you try to understand the whys or the
reasoning behind why something is happening and try to give that to the stakeholders,
ideally with a recommendation for a step that they could take, an action that they could
take.
And of course, you have to tie it back to the original question that you were trying
to answer.
Another comment that I find really relevant is this PhD student who is working on trying
to get the data for three years, trying to interpret the data for two years, trying to
have some sort of documentation model building for one and a half years.
And finally, the number of slides that she presents is just one and everybody's like,
seriously, that's all you did for all of these years.
So yeah, that's why storytelling is important, because you need to explain in layman's terms
what exactly was it that you did?
Why was the question important?
How did you go about finding the answers and what were the conclusions for it?
Okay, let's go back to our Jupyter notebook.
Okay, so now we'll be seeing a really specific example for supervised learning, specifically
for classification.
We're given a data set.
Again it's a part of the SQL on library.
Please go ahead and install SQL on if you haven't already.
This data set is actually a list of characteristics that were derived from images.
These images were cell nuclei from breast masses and a lot of information about the
cell nuclei.
So it's really medical information that wouldn't make sense to people outside of the industry.
But we're going to use it for now and see how it works.
So our question is that given some characteristics about a breast mass, about the cell nuclei,
can we predict if the tumor is malignant or benign?
So it's a classification problem, right?
You're going to look at the data points and you're trying to predict if it is malignant,
that is class A, or if it is benign, that is class B.
So let's go ahead and see how we do that.
Like I mentioned, SQL already has some inbuilt data sets.
So this is one of them.
We can go ahead and import it from SQL on data sets.
You load the data in, let's say for example, raw data.
Or let's actually make this tumor data.
And remember the target over there is what forms are labeled, which says whether it's
malignant.
If it's malignant, it's one.
And if it's benign, it's zero.
And let's go ahead and run that.
So this is what the data set looks like.
The different features called radius, texture, parameter area, so characteristics for that
particular cell mass.
And finally you have the target, which is the label.
So these are all zeroes, so they're all benign.
So let's take a look at what were all of the features of the columns present in it.
You can do that using the dot columns.
And this is a list of all of the different features of the column names that are present.
Mean radius, compactness, symmetry error, texture, and finally the label of cause.
So now we have an idea of, yeah.
Yeah, I did change the variable name.
Okay.
So now we know what the data set looks like.
Let's try to perform some sort of exploration for the data.
Like I mentioned, graphing or visualization is a huge step of this process.
So let's go ahead and try to see the distribution of these two classes, the malignant and benign.
Are they symmetric?
Are they almost equal?
Or are they completely imbalanced?
And we'd be using matplotlib inline because we want the graph to show right after the
cell output.
We'd be using labels since that is the column name or that is the feature name that we're
interested in.
Value counts just tells you the frequency for that particular column.
And then we want a pie chart to see the percentage distribution.
So let's go ahead and run that.
Okay.
So it is actually the opposite.
It has malignant as the majority, which is great because that is what we're trying to
predict.
And it has benign as the minority at slightly less than 40%.
So it's not equal, but it's not terribly disproportionate either, which is good.
Otherwise we would have to use the sampling techniques that I talked about, where you
try to give extra weightage by oversampling the minority class, or you try to downplay
the weightage of the majority class by downsampling it, that is removing some data points.
Okay.
So let's go ahead and break this huge data frame into two subsets, where the first one
is all of the malignant data points and second one is all of the benign data points.
And we're using our Pandas indexing and filtering procedure over here.
So I didn't print out anything here, but it's very free to print it out.
Okay.
So now what we're going to do is, we already have these two different sub-datasets, where
malignant and benign.
Let's try to plot a few features in these datasets and see if there is any starking
difference between these two.
So it's going to be easy to see visually if the distributions is different for the two
categories.
So I'm just running two for loops over here.
That goes over the different features or the different columns in our malignant and benign
datasets, and it's trying to plot histograms and overlaying them one on top of each other
so we can see the differences between them.
So let's go ahead and run that.
Okay, bins is not defined.
Oh, because it's number of bins.
Okay.
So you can see this huge list of graphs.
Let's try to go through them one by one.
So the first feature under consideration is mean radians.
You can see there's some difference in distribution.
For malignant, the mean radius tends to be higher, almost around 75, 50, 75, and it tends
to be lower for benign.
Similarly, we can look at all of the other features and see there are some overlaps.
So let's see if we can find any feature that might be a good indicator of distinguishing
between the two types.
Mean concavity, this could be a good indicator because the distribution's remarkably different.
Let's see, another one.
Oh, it could be worst concave points since almost everything less than 0.1 is malignant
and greater than 0.1 tends to be benign.
There's a very little overlap over here.
So like I mentioned, data exploration is an initial investigation.
It helps us create some sort of hypothesis, some sort of interesting things that we might
look into.
So I guess the hypothesis that we can agree on over here is that worst concave points
might actually be an important feature, might be a distinguishing feature for trying to
predict if something is malignant or benign.
And then we'll try to verify it with our models, of course.
Any questions so far?
Okay.
So before we start model building, we should do something that's called scaling the features.
So all of these different numerical features are on different scales, right?
Probably some of them are on 0 to 1, some of them are on 0 to 100 and whatnot.
We don't want those numbers, like just because something is 100, we don't want it to get
extra weightage, correct?
So what we're going to do is we try to scale it, bring all of these features on a similar
scale and then accordingly give the values.
And the way we would do that is using a standard scalar.
And then we're transforming the data over here, so let's go ahead and run that.
So X is basically all of your column names except the last column.
The last column is the one that has the label.
And Y is just the label.
Okay.
So you can see it's a NumPy array with some numbers.
It's okay.
We don't really need to make sense of that.
Let's just take it for granted that it's working the way it's supposed to.
Okay.
So now we go into the model building.
Yeah?
So how do you scale it?
For example, if you're dealing with dry data and you want to know the transaction size
of the column, you can always do it.
No, it's not necessary to always do it.
You need to look at the different features that are involved.
And if they are on similar scales or the similar ranges, then you don't need to do it.
In this case, if you look at the data, some of them are in points and some of them are
in hundreds.
So there's a lot of degree of variation.
Yeah, it should be okay.
Okay.
So like we saw earlier, we need to divide it into training set and test set, where training
set is what actually builds the model, helps it learn, and test set is where you evaluate
the performance of the model and try to validate it.
The common two common ratios that are used for the split is you either use a 70-30 split,
that is 70 training 30 test, or use an 80-20 split.
Okay.
So this is really handy function called train test split in SQL on model selection.
We just pass our X and Y datasets where, remember, X is all of our features and Y is just the
label, the very last column.
We see that test size is 20% of the data.
So you can see that the training set is 455 and the test set has 114 rows, which is roughly
about 80-20 split.
Okay.
So now comes algorithms.
We're going to use decision tree classifier over here because it's one of the most intuitive
and most interpretable models.
Decision tree is pretty much how we also function, right?
If you're feeling hungry, you would ideally go and eat something.
And if you're feeling sleepy, you would ideally go off to sleep, right?
So we have this decision structure, the decision tree in our head where, given the current
situation, you would choose one action or one path over the other.
So that's pretty much what this algorithm is going to do.
Let's take a look at how it does that.
So let's go ahead and from sklearn.tree call our decision tree classifier, which is what
actually is going to create the model.
Let's assign it to CLF classifier.
And then all you have to do is on the model, that is the decision tree classifier, call
the fit function and pass it to your training set.
So your training X, that is all of the features except the label, and your training Y, which
is the output or which is the target labels.
So it's trained and it's given us some sort of an output.
So this is just metadata about the decision tree classifier or about the model that you're
trying to build, where it says that I don't want classes to be given any extra weight.
Since they are almost similar in proportion, we are not going to do that.
So the next one is Gini, which is a specific type of how to decide to split the nodes.
We'll be looking into that.
Max depth is where you're trying to control the tree that gets formed.
If you want to place in limitations on the tree shouldn't go up to a certain beyond a
certain depth.
Similarly for features leaf nodes, you're just trying to set bounds or restrictions
in it.
Yeah, okay.
So if you go into the documentation for sklearn, you would get a better idea of all the different
parameters that are involved and what exactly they mean.
We're not concerned with concern ourselves with them for now.
Okay.
So here we have a model that's been trained on our training data.
What we're going to do next is since it's a decision tree, let's try to visualize the
tree itself and see what features it's deeming as important and how is it exactly making
the split between malignant and benign.
So we use another library that's called pi.plus over here.
This is just a bunch of syntax for having the classifier being an input for the graphing
for the visualization.
This is what the graph would look like.
Oops.
Data is not defined because I changed the name.
So you can see this is like a huge tree.
Let's see if we can, yeah, you're not able to see it, right?
Let's see if we can zoom in.
Otherwise, yeah, it's not working.
So I hope you can see it on your machines.
So let me read all the first ones.
Oh, yeah.
So another thing about you're looking at the colors, right?
So the colors, and there's a gradient associated with the color.
It's for what class forms the majority of samples in that particular node.
And the higher a node is at the root, the root is at the top, the more important that feature is
the more discriminatory that feature is that helps you distinguish between what's malignant
and what's benign.
So over here, you can see that the most important feature is worst concave points, where if
worst concave points is less than 0.4, it goes to the blue class, which is I think it's
for malignant or benign.
I'm not sure.
Let me check that.
And the opposite is the other class.
And you can see that there are samples written over there, which just tells how many data
points fit that criteria.
So all the way from the root of the tree to the node under consideration, those are the
samples that satisfy all of the criteria over there.
And then so on and so forth, depending on the features and the values, you keep getting
additional splits.
Okay, any questions so far?
Does the decision tree algorithm make sense?
So you're just trying to see all of the different features and looking at each of the individual
features, you see that, okay, if I consider just this feature, does this show any difference
for benign versus any difference for malignant?
How much of a difference does it show?
Okay, and you're creating the splits based on that.
And then you consider the next feature and so on and so forth, and then you finally have
the tree in hand.
You can have multiple classes for decision trees, yeah.
Okay.
Another algorithm that we are not seeing over here is logistic regression, which is a type
of regression, but we're using it for classification since it can handle with zero and one values.
If you would like to try it, you can just go ahead and import logistic regression from
sklearn.logistic or .linear, and then it's the same way.
You just change this over here, what algorithm you're calling, train the classifier the same
way, and try to see the output.
If you have time, I can come back to it at the end.
Okay, so now we trained our model.
The most natural step to do next would be test how good it's working, right?
So let's go and see the model validation part of this.
Okay, yeah.
So remember we talked about precision and recall, and we have the notion of false positive
and false negatives.
Precision is the fraction of information you got that is relevant.
So for our very particular example where we're trying to predict tumor or cancer, we're
trying to say how many of them actually have cancer.
And recall is similar but different.
It's a fraction of relevant information that was retrieved where you're trying to say that
of the people who actually have cancer or have the tumor, how many have we correctly detected?
So there's a fine difference between them, but precision is how many of our predictions
actually have cancer?
And recall is how many of the ones who actually have cancer have we predicted?
There's another thing called the classification report, which gives you a snapshot of the
false positives, the false negatives.
We'll see the different details for that.
So it's a good snapshot where you get an understanding of how well your model is doing.
And finally, you have something that's called as the confusion matrix, where you have the
predicted on one hand, predicted labels, and the actual labels on the other hand.
And if it's positive and you predicted as positive, great.
That's true positive.
Similarly, for negative, that's true negative.
But false positive is where it should have been negative, but you predicted as positive,
and false negative is just the opposite.
And the way to calculate precision is recall is using this formula, where you consider
the false positives and negatives in play.
Okay.
Yeah.
You would ideally go back and try to tune the model parameters and see how, because
that might help you change the importance of the features.
Or else you might also consider using a slightly different algorithm.
Because some algorithms work really well if the data is linearly separable, but some
of them are really good at detecting mixtures of the classes and seeing, you know, like,
okay, how can we differentiate amongst them?
Yeah.
Okay.
So like I mentioned, the most obvious metric to use is accuracy, where you're trying to
understand how many were predicted correctly, whether they were false, whether they were
true, whether they were benign, or whether they were malignant.
And then finally we have the classification report being printed over here.
So let's take a look at what that looks like.
So it gives us an accuracy of 92%, which is great, right?
It's in the 90s.
I think that's good.
Let's look at the precision recall scores.
So that's for each of the classes.
For the benign class, the precision is 0.85 and recall is 0.95.
And for the malignant class, the recall is slightly lower.
So it depends on a specific use case if you're happy with those numbers or not.
F1 score is just the harmonic mean of the precision and recall.
Support is just the number of instances or number of classes in the testing set that
satisfy the criteria.
So this is for the benign cases and this is for the malignant cases.
Some more averages statistics about this.
Okay.
So oftentimes, I have a question for you.
Do you think false positives and false negatives should be treated the same or not?
Correct, yeah.
Like I mentioned, right, the answer, if you're not sure of what to answer, just say it depends
and you are going to be right 99% of the time.
Okay.
So let's try to give a bit more context to this.
Let's say if a person does indeed have cancer and you're saying that person that, no, you
are in the clear you don't have cancer.
Is that worse versus a person that does not have cancer but you're telling that person
does have cancer, right?
I mean, both situations are really bad, which is where the whole ethics in data science
and AI comes into play.
But you would ideally want the false, let's see, what would you want?
You would want that a person who does have cancer to be correctly detected, right, before
it's too late.
So there's this notion of asymmetric penalty.
Similarly, there's been this huge debate about how in airports you're screened and you're
questioned a lot.
So if a person who is not a terrorist is questioned and interrogated, although it's not great,
it's not good, but that is okay to do compared to having a terrorist actually escape, right?
So there's this notion of asymmetric penalty involved.
Okay.
So we looked at the precision and recall scores and they are probably in the high 80s and
90s, which is good.
What can happen, like I mentioned, if you're in this case, we had fairly balanced classes,
which is good.
What can happen in imbalanced cases, imbalanced classes, let's say for instance, you have
90% of the data where it is benign and 10% where it's malignant, okay?
And let's say if I were to create a model that just randomly spits out, everything is benign.
It would be correct 90% of the time, right?
Because 90% of the data is benign.
So that is the instance where, which this is the instance of overfitting happening,
where what you're trying to do is you fit your model so well on the data that it's going
to give you amazing accuracies, but it's not going to be generalized.
So if you have a completely different set of data points coming in, it's going to do
really bad at that.
An example of this was there were scientists that came up with this computer vision algorithm
to look at images and predict huskies, and they got these amazing accuracies of like
90, 95%, and they presented it in a conference.
And it turns out what they actually built was not a model to predict huskies, but a
model to predict images of snow.
Because all of the training examples that they gave were huskies with a background of
snow.
So the model became really good at predicting snow, and they were really happy with the
accuracy because, hey, the data set has just snow.
And when the model was given pictures of huskies without snow, it failed.
So this is a classic example of overfitting.
And this whole debate about how there's not enough diversity as far as training set examples
are concerned and how there are a lot of racial algorithms being used, it's not that the algorithm
is racist on its own.
It's because you give garbage and you're going to get garbage out, right?
So if your data is not representative, your data is not varied.
Like there was this instance of, I believe, all white teams were working on this, and
they failed to test out the model, the face recognition model on people with darker skin
colors.
And this is also an object detection model, and it actually was very racist, and it detected
people with darker skins as gorillas.
And this was by Google.
So if a company with seemingly infinite resources can do something stupid like this, imagine
how careful we have to be as individuals and smaller companies.
So basically, I just wanted to point out that it's really important for our data set to
be diverse and representative, especially where we have these kind of machine learning
algorithms taking judgments on really serious issues, like who to grant bail to, who to
arrest, who is more likely to commit a crime again, who is not.
And these data sets are often skewed against racially diverse people, because that's the
way the data has been given.
And that's the way data in the past has been handled, that they've not been granted bail.
So the model is going to learn that from the biases in the humans.
OK.
All right.
So now we have the models.
It's 92% accuracy, and the precisions and recalls look good.
So we know that we have not overfitted our model.
We have trained it, and it's a generalized model.
That's great.
Let's go on to visualizing the data.
So I remember after Matplotlib, I mentioned this under the package called C-Born, which
is built on Matplotlib.
So just consider it as an advanced step of Matplotlib.
And let's go ahead and try to visualize the confusion matrix in this.
And the way we would do is we would pass the confusion matrix to a heat map for C-Born,
and then we're trying to say, let's look at the actual and predicted classes.
So this is what a confusion matrix looks like.
Your x-axis is the predicted classes, and your y-axis is the actual classes.
So it's doing a great job of true positives and true negatives.
And it's doing not so bad, because it's just single digits, fours, and sevens on false
positives and false negatives, which is OK.
So this is just a visualization to look at what we were seeing in the classification
report and the confusion matrix.
And then, like I mentioned, data storytelling.
You tell a story with data.
You try to explain the why's.
And the final conclusion you're saying is that the current model is able to predict
malignant or benign masses with, it should be, 92% accuracy over here.
Yeah.
OK.
Also, if you keep running the model again and again, and you don't have a random seed
set, it's going to give you different accuracies, because the way the splitting happens is
random, right?
So the data points in the training and test set are going to keep changing, and that's
where the accuracy is going to slightly lower or increase.
Another thing that I have not mentioned here, but I'll link a resource to, is something
that's called as k-fold cross-validation.
So k-fold cross-validation just means, like, how in this case, we're just dividing the
data set into training and testing once, right?
So we could get really lucky with the way the split is happening, and we could get extremely
high accuracies, or we could get unlucky and get really low accuracies.
It's all random, so we don't know.
So the way to counteract this is you keep doing this iteratively.
So that's called k-fold, because you'll have k, let's say, if your k is fair, then you'll
have five-fold cross-validation.
So what happens in that case is, let's say, if this is your entire data set, so your first
one-fifth would become the test set in the first iteration, and the rest would become
your training set.
In the second iteration, your second one-fifth becomes the test and the others training.
So that way, you have each portion becoming the test once and becoming the training four
times.
So that way, it helps you create more of a generalized model and have generalized performances
that are not going to give you unexpected results when you finally test it out on unseen
data.
Okay, any questions about that, about classification?
Okay.
Yeah, sure.
So in the end, you're predicting whether or not the tumor is malignant or not.
Right.
It was a combination of all of the features with different weightages.
So let me just go back to the tree.
And thank you for bringing it up.
I actually forgot to mention that.
So I believe what I mentioned was the convexity or the concavity.
Let's go back and see.
Okay.
This is a graph.
Yeah, I believe it was the worst concave points, correct?
So let's go and see what is the importance that's been given to that.
So worst concave points is up over here.
So it's not the first.
It's not the second.
It's not the third.
But about the fourth most important feature.
So it's still pretty high up with a dataset of 29, 30 features is the fourth most important.
So it's still doing a pretty good job.
But if you open close inspection of this tree, you can see these are the one at the top is
the most important feature.
And then slowly as you go down bottom, it decreases in importance.
So it's a combination of all of the features involved.
You can go ahead and also try to see how well it does on one feature.
It might actually just do great on one feature.
But if you have more data and more features, it might do slightly better.
Oh, yeah, it is also at the top.
Thank you for pointing that out.
Yeah, so it's also like, yeah, it depends on it's trying to like really define the intervals.
So the first one is the biggest split.
And then the second one is the slightly smaller split that's dependent on other features.
Yeah, thank you.
Yeah.
I guess typically in the actual output of the model in terms of the interface of what's
given to the medical professional race, sort of extrapolating on this pretty far, are you,
I guess you kind of think of each one of these sort of top level leads as effectively a justification
for like this is a reason why the model is this way.
So in the output of the model, are those justifications typically given out as well?
So saying like, I think this is a malignant tumor because of these five sets of things that led me to this conclusion.
No, unfortunately not.
But if that were the case, then we wouldn't have any role to play.
Like we would just run and automate that.
But this is why in decision tree it's helpful to visualize this because as humans we can
understand that, OK, these features are pretty important.
These features are, you know, a little less important.
There's a slightly related technique that you can use which is called as feature importance,
which is where it does give you as an output, like this is the different weightages or the
different coefficients for the features.
But oftentimes it's not as interpretable or it might not even be absolutely correct.
I guess I'm also thinking about the medical professional who might be wary about trusting the model.
Right, right.
Which is why there's this whole debate on I'm not sure if you're aware of, but IBM Watson came out with
this oncology tool that helps professionals or medical professionals understand if, you know,
it is a particular type of cancer, what are the different, what are the different.
So basically what it does is given a patient's history and medical case, it gives you the top 10 approaches
or methodologies that might be successful.
And then it says that based on, you know, my review and my reading of these millions of papers in the
database, the top two are most likely to work.
The bottom two are probably like the worst, do not try them.
And the middle ones are like, you know, they might work, they might not work.
It really depends on the particular case.
And doctors are very happy because this is something that's pretty revolutionary in the medical field, right?
You have a system that can in a matter of minutes, if not seconds, read through millions of research papers
and try to find out what are the new approaches, what are the new, you know, remedies that are coming up that
might work well.
But the problem was that the model interpretability what you're talking about, it wasn't able to justify
why it selected a particular technique or remedy for that particular patient, which is where the trust
issue comes in, right?
Would you rather trust, you know, this huge, literally this huge pile of linear algebra, or would you trust
someone who has been maybe for 10 years of grad school, 20 years of experience in the field and who has
actually seen what happens, you know, like as a human?
So that does come into play a lot where the interpretability and the explanation of models is important,
which is why models or algorithms like the decision tree, they're pretty explainable, right?
You can see the snapshot of the tree and you can understand that, okay, this was rated as important and
because of this, the split happened like that.
But in slightly more complex models, especially in deep learning models, where you give it some input and
you get some output out, there is not much interpretability.
You don't know what exactly is happening in the black box, which is where all of these fears of, you know,
machines might just take over the world.
There was this experiment by Facebook a few years back where two programs were chatting with each other.
And this was a deep learning one because they were trying to look at, trying to make them speak languages
like humans and interact the way humans do.
And what happened was at the end of it, they started spewing garbage out.
So it would just be like, I, I, I, this, this, this, this, like a lot of repetitions and words and sentences
that didn't make any sense.
And the Facebook researchers stopped the experiment because clearly the objective, the outcome was a failure.
And in newspapers, it was this yellow journalism that was completely centralized, which said that
two Facebook programs were caught talking to each other in a language that nobody could understand.
They invented their own language and, oh my God, it's the, you know, humanity is at the edge of extinction.
This is what's going to happen.
Like, no, that is not what happened.
But because it's not interpretable, because we can't understand what's going on, it creates, it creates this atmosphere of fear,
which is also there in like so many other AI applications right now.
But yeah, that was that.
Okay. So we have about a little over an hour more.
Would you like another break or should I continue?
Who would want another break?
Okay. Everyone seems pretty good.
Okay, cool.
So we have two options.
Oh my God, I misspelled regression.
We have two options.
We can look at another supervised learning problem, but regression, where remember we are trying to predict
numbers or values.
You're like, for example, you're trying to predict your next quarter's revenue.
Or we can look at an example of unsupervised learning.
What would you like to take a look at?
How many for supervised, like staying unsupervised but regression?
Okay, a few hands.
And how many for unsupervised?
Okay, more hands for unsupervised.
So we'll try to finish unsupervised quickly and then hopefully we'll have time to come back.
If not, you have the code and all of the details already.
Okay.
So just to give a quick recap, unsupervised learning is where we have no labels associated with the data.
So there's no right or no wrong answer.
But what we're trying to do is we're just trying to find out the underlying structure, the distribution of the data,
and hopefully get some meaningful clusters out of it.
Okay.
The most I would say used and important algorithm as far as clustering is concerned is something that's called as K-means algorithm,
which is where K is an input that you give to the algorithm as a user, which stands for the number of clusters that you want.
And means just imagine your data points on a 2D plot.
It's just like all over.
You're trying to figure out three data points, if K is equal to three, three data points that could serve as good means for three different clusters.
So it's based on finding a mean for a particular cluster.
We'll take a look at how exactly it works in this code over here.
Okay.
So we're going to import something that's called make blobs, which is pretty much what it sounds like.
It's going to create random blobs of data on the plot from SKLearn.
So let's say we want 200 data points with two features, five centers, and that is, you know,
five clusters with the standard deviation and this random state.
And let's go ahead and see what that looks like.
So it's a bunch of.
Remember, we talked about two features.
There are two columns.
There are 200 data points, so 200 rows.
And the way they were generated was in a way where you can form five distinct clusters out of it.
So what we're going to do now is we're going to use some visualization and try to plot a 2D scatter graph of these data points that we have generated right now.
And the way we would do it, we already have the data about how they are centered, right, that there are in five different five distinct clusters.
So let's plot each of the clusters in a different color and see what that looks like.
So this is what it looks like where each of the five clusters have different color.
There's some overlap, but mostly I would say it's pretty distinguishable.
OK.
So this is kind of like reverse engineering.
We already know what the answer is supposed to be or what it's supposed to look like.
And then we'll apply our K-means algorithm and see if we're getting a similar result or not.
So from sklearn.cluster, let's import the K-means algorithm that helps us decide the cluster.
For now, let's say K is equal to five because we do know that the data we simulated or created had five clusters.
So let's keep it at five. Let's try to give it, you know, the best shot at performance.
And then as an input to K-means, you would say K is the number of clusters, which is five.
And then finally, K-means.fit pretty similar to how we use it in our decision tree classifier.
Use the model name.fit and then you pass the data that you want to it.
And these are different cluster centers. Since K is five and there are only two features,
we've gotten five rows of five data points with two features or two columns each.
So X, Y coordinates.
OK. So now we've created a model on the data.
Let's go ahead and try to see how well it's going to predict,
how well it's going to create clusters out of that model.
So these are the clusters that created. You can see with the different colors.
OK, so we see three clusters at the bottom and at the top side of the figure,
we have two more clusters with a little bit of overlap between them.
Let's go and see what our data was actually like and see how well it did.
So three more clusters at the bottom, two clusters at the top, a little bit of overlap.
Yes, it looks like that.
You can see it's a little more spread out over here.
I guess it's that because the scaling is different. No.
And it's a little more tightly wound over here. But overall, it did a pretty good job, right?
Most of the clusters would get classified as the predictions would be the same
as what the initial data values would be.
Now let's go ahead and change the value of K. Let's increase and decrease it and see what happens.
Let's make it three and see what happens.
Why did this not work?
So now it's become three clusters, right?
Where you can see the top two clusters have kind of merged and become one.
And the blue and the red at the sides are each cluster.
And the middle cluster is kind of now merged into red and blue.
So this is what it looked like. So the light green cluster and I believe that's purple, dark purple clusters kind of like a part of the other clusters now.
So what this algorithm is doing is just trying to find those center points that would form the means for that particular cluster.
And then all of the data points around it would form the body of the cluster.
Let's increase K and let's see what happens. Let's make it 10, for instance.
Oh, yeah, it won't work at 10 because I have only given it one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight colors.
So let's keep it as eight.
So we do have eight clusters over here.
And what happened was our initial five clusters got split into sub clusters with a little bit of overlap and not too much distinction amongst them.
But yeah, we do have eight clusters now.
OK, any questions about that? Yeah.
Yeah, I'll do that. Let's go to the next part of the code and then hopefully you'll get a better idea.
Any more questions?
So like I mentioned, an application of this would be if you have two users, let's say on Netflix, and if they look at similar shows, you probably have them in the same cluster.
And depending on the cluster, maybe you could have clusters, let's for example, based on the genre of the movie.
So you would have one cluster that like sci fi, another cluster that likes rom-com, and the cluster that likes maybe world cinema.
So that would be one application of it where your features would be the movies that they've seen in the past or probably the movies that they've looked at trailers on but not watched it.
The kind of ratings that they've given to the different movies that would be your features.
And over there, what you're trying to do is you're trying to find similarities between groups of users and see what kind of patterns match with what kind of users and group them together.
And then based on that clustering, you would say that, okay, if this cluster or this group of users see sci fi movies, I should probably recommend, you know, Avengers to them maybe or if they are used to superhero, maybe Avengers is also another good one.
Or if they never see superhero movies and they've downloaded all superhero movies, probably not recommend that.
So that would be kind of an example of it.
Let me post a link to a slightly more concrete coding example for k-means.
But let's go into the next one, which is also clustering but in a slightly different format.
Any other questions so far?
Okay.
So what we saw till now was all just numbers and we were trying to create models out of that.
There's another field that's called natural language processing, which deals mainly with textual data.
Right.
And how can we create some sort of predictive algorithms for those?
So the way we would go about to do this is there's a library that's called Jensim that is used for a lot of natural language processing tasks.
We won't go into the details since it's not an NLP tutorial.
Excuse me.
Okay.
So what we're going to do is we're going to use the Wikipedia API and we're going to extract articles from Wikipedia on particular topics.
And those topics we are then going to try to cluster.
Again, so we already know kind of like how we did back in k-means.
We already know what the clusters are supposed to look like.
But we'll just see how well is that algorithm working.
Is it going to give us same clusters or not?
Okay.
So what this function is doing over here, it's using the Wikipedia API and it's going to retrieve articles to random articles.
This is what this line does.
And then it's going to retrieve additional articles on music, gardening, reading, San Francisco and Mountain View.
Mountain View is another city in the Bay Area.
And then it's just going to take all of the data on those pages and use that as our data set.
So let's go ahead and run that.
Okay.
So here cleaning of textual data is a little different from numbers.
We don't just look at what are the missing values.
We don't look at what are irrelevant or abnormal values because it's all text.
So it's difficult to generalize that way.
Okay.
What we do instead over here is since we are retrieving this from web pages, what we'd like to do is we would like to remove HTML tags.
And we'd also like to remove anything that is not a word.
So things like numbers, special characters, emojis, we're just going to get rid of them.
And the way we do that is using regex, regular expressions.
How many of you are familiar with regular expressions?
Okay.
So just to fit is that you're giving it a pattern where anything that meets the pattern stays and anything that doesn't meet the pattern gets filtered out.
So W plus stands here for words.
W stands for words.
So anything that is a word stays.
Anything else just gets filtered out.
And over here we are going to make everything lowercase because we don't want there to be a difference between all caps or camel case or lowercase if the word is the same.
Then to clean the articles, what we're going to do is we're going to use a list of stop words in the English language.
Stop words are all of your filler words or words that don't carry any meaning on their own.
So think about prepositions, words like the, of, and, but, in.
On their own they don't really mean anything.
But grammatically they need to be used for a sentence to be correct.
But since they don't mean anything we're just going to filter them out.
So this is what this line of code does over here.
And then finally there's something called stemmer.
So each of the words in English language have a base word associated with it.
Let's say for instance you're looking at the words running, ran, runs.
They all mean the same thing, right?
At the end of the day they are all just different forms of the base word run, right?
So for the purpose of this, there are two purposes for doing this.
Number one is that sometimes the vocabulary size or the number of words that are in your data set is so huge that it might not fit in memory
or it might take a really long time for your algorithm to compute models.
So stemming helps you to collapse the vocabulary while still retaining the meaning of the word.
The second way is that because they all mean the same thing and I'm not really,
I'm not really interested in knowing whether it was running or whether it was ran or whether it was run.
We're just going to get it down to the base word.
Any questions so far about the cleaning processes for textual data?
We'll take a look at what it looks like.
So here is where we are calling each of the functions and let's see what happens.
So we're getting the data from Wikipedia based on the list of articles, list of topics that we gave it and two random articles.
And then it's going to process, go through the process of cleaning the entire data,
which is where you're removing your stop words, stemming it, lower casing it, removing numbers.
And then finally you create something that's called as bag of words.
So just think of a matrix where your row numbers or your rows are each of the documents
and your columns are each of the words present in your vocabulary.
So let's say for instance, it is my sentence is this is good, the first sentence.
And my second sentence is this is bad.
So there are four words in my entire vocabulary.
This is good, bad.
For the first sentence, for this good, this is good, bad.
These are the column names or the feature names.
We would have one, one, one, zero, where one says if that particular word or that particular feature is present in your sentence.
So this is good, we'll all have one.
But bad would be zero because bad is not present in the first sentence.
Similarly, for the second sentence, it would be one, one, zero, one, because good, the third feature is not present in the sentence,
but bad is present, so that would have one.
So this is just this matrix has a fancy term that's called bag of words because you're losing the contextual meaning of the words.
You don't know what exactly the word means, but you still have a collection of the words.
It's like, you know, a bag of popcorn where you have each of the kernels where the words are there.
So you have the collection of the words, but you don't know what the words mean or what the sentence means.
Okay, name clean is not defined.
Okay, so these are the articles that we have, Music, Gardening, Reading, San Francisco Mountain View, which were the ones that we used to define.
And it went ahead and selected two more random articles where the first one is the De Vinci's Challenge
and the second one is Siege of Fadrian Opel 1912-1913, some event that happened in history.
Okay.
And then we have something that's called LDA, which is a very specific type of algorithm.
LDA stands for Latent Directly Allocation, which just means that every document is a proportion of topics and every topic is a proportion of words.
Does that make sense?
Every document is a proportion of different topics.
So every document is going to have multiple topics that it's talking about, and each of the topics has different words, different proportion of words that it's talking about.
Let's try to look at the results.
Hopefully, you'll get a better understanding of what it does.
So we're going to create a model that is going to use this algorithm, LDA, and then we're going to try to pass our words or our articles and see how does it cluster them.
And over here we said that we want to look at, we want six clusters or six topics to come out at the end.
We're going to build word clouds that helps us visualize this better.
Okay, so these are what the topics look like.
So this is a form of clustering.
The first topic or topic zero is probably about San Francisco.
Remember, San Francisco was one of our topics.
It's talking about things like California State, San Francisco City.
The second one is talking about the siege command artillery battle.
If you see, you would find the spellings of the word a little weird because these are the stemmed versions.
So these are the base words of them.
So like siege, siege could be siege, could be sieged, could be sieging.
Similarly for command, it could be command, commandment, commanding.
Okay, so the second one is probably about that random event, that historical event that took place, the siege.
The third topic is about instrument, classic, form, play, music.
So it probably is the one about music.
The next one is about a game or a pattern.
And we know that the Da Vinci challenge was one of the randomly selected topics.
So it's forming a cluster of that.
The next one is probably about reading, text, learn, word comprehension.
And finally, the last one is about gardening, landscape plan.
So it's probably something about gardening.
So you won't really get the topic names directly from the algorithm.
But once you take a look at the different words that form the topic, you can kind of gather what this particular cluster is about.
If you notice, we selected seven topics and we have only formed clusters of six because we kept the seventh topic as the testing data,
which is Mountain View.
Okay.
And then we have something called a similarity where we are trying to see that, okay, all of the words that are present in Mountain View article,
how similar it is to one of these clusters.
The same way how Netflix or Amazon does, it has like, if you're a new user and you have done some sort of activity, some sort of transactions,
then they pitch you against the different clusters, different users that they've already formed,
and then see which one are you most similar to so that they can give you better personalized recommendations.
So over here, it says that the given topic, which is Mountain View, is most similar to topic zero with a similarity of point A3.
So the similarity scale is from zero to one, so point A3 is pretty high.
And let's see what topic zero was.
Topic zero was San Francisco, which is correct because Mountain View is also another city in the Bay Area.
So this is another example of clustering, and I took this example because I wanted to give you a glimpse of natural language processing
and that data sets don't always have to be numerical in nature.
They can also be text, and the way you would go about handling a textual data, the cleaning, the processing, the understanding is slightly different
and leans more towards linguistic knowledge and natural language processing,
but it does apply the same predictive or modeling algorithms.
Any questions so far?
Should I move on to the next one?
So now we can go back to our regression example.
Does anyone want to break?
Yes? No?
Okay, let's take a five-minute break.
Okay.
Hey. Sure.
I used a fraud detection algorithm to figure out if transactions are either fraudulent or not fraudulent.
And I used random forests, regression, logistic regression, and I was wondering if naive base is a good alternative to that.
Or if there's any other thing that I can...
Have you looked at time series algorithms?
That is probably something you should look at.
That is one of the first things that is really useful for detection algorithms.
And so, primarily because anomaly detection is, you know, it's like a time series data since it's dependent on time,
and that is an important metric to understand if something is anomalous or not.
Something very basic that you can start off with is just don't get into the modeling part, just do the visualization.
And see what, you know, visually for yourself, you see there's like a high peak in probably the transaction amount,
or there's a big gap between two transactions there.
And if that gap or that particular value is greater than, let's say, two or three standard deviations,
it's probably something that's anomalous.
Okay.
That's like another approach to just like...
Yeah.
So we should try what you did there with the different features.
For clustering?
No, no, the different features of the two of my data.
Right.
And you had those little...
The graphs, yes.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
You can try that.
And you can also try clustering.
Wow.
I'll use the satellite.
Oh, okay.
Is that better?
Yeah.
And you can also try clustering, because then what would happen is probably transactions with similar amounts
might get clustered into the same thing.
Like I mentioned, right, if there's a transaction with $10,000,
and everything else is probably below 50 or in the context,
then 10,000 is going to be one lone point on your graph.
So do I also have to do normalization of scaling?
Because I have transactions that are $20,000, and then you've got $5.
Right.
No, I would suggest you don't do it over there, because that value actually means something, right?
Like 20,000 is very different from $5.
Okay, so in this instance...
Yeah, in this case, you don't need it.
Awesome.
Thank you.
Sure.
Why is this not charging?
Okay.
Is the lighting okay for everyone?
Shall we begin?
Okay.
What happened? Oh, yeah.
Make sure to add price.
Okay.
So, it varies quite a bit from zero surprises in thousands of dollars, so it goes up to 50,000, but I'd say the majority is around 20 to 30,000.
We're going to try something a little different here because there are a lot of features involved and we don't have a good understanding of what each of those mean.
Let's try to create a correlation matrix where we're trying to see how each of the features are dependent on the others and how all of those influence price, which is the feature we're most interested in since we're trying to predict the price of the house.
The way you would do that is in Seaborn, create a correlation matrix using the call function on your Pandas data frame, round it up to two decimal digits if you want, otherwise it's going to be a lot of digits.
And then you have to use the heat map function, pass the correlation matrix as the data, and annotation true just says that these numbers, these labels will show up.
So, let's go ahead and do that.
So, we have a really huge matrix because of the number of features involved and it's going to be a little difficult to interpret at first, but let's break it down.
So, it's basically an end by end matrix where n are a number of features and you can see each of the features are along the x and the y axis.
And as expected, this diagonal is going to be the highest correlation because it's just correlation of itself with itself.
And correlation is on a scale of negative one to positive one.
Negative just means that they are correlated, but if one goes up, the other goes down, so they are inversely correlated.
And positive means they are positively correlated where if one increases, the other will also increase.
And the actual value is the magnitude of how highly correlated they are.
So, let's take a look at price and see what features are correlated highly with price.
So, we're going to look for lighter regions because lighter regions indicate higher correlation or extremely darker regions which indicate negative correlation.
So, LSTAT seems pretty high, negative 0.74, which is pretty high, negative correlation. 0.33 is mild, not as high, not as high.
0.7 also seems pretty high up, positively correlated RM.
And the other are more or less, they are not as important.
Let's go back to our data set and see what RM and LSTAT exactly meant.
So, let's go back to our description and see where RM is. RM is the average number of rooms for dwelling, which makes sense, right?
A studio apartment is probably going to be the cheapest with one bed and five bed probably most expensive.
And that seems to have a high correlation, which even like common sense or our heuristics also tell.
Okay, so that's great. What is LSTAT? LSTAT is the lower status of the population.
Percentage of lower status of the population.
So, I guess that tells, that depends on the location and how affordable it is in a way.
Let's see further and find out what exactly, how informative they are.
Okay, so we selected these two features, the RM and the LSTAT as our two most important features from our initial exploratory data analysis.
Let's try to plot scatter plots for these two features with price and see if we can see any more trends or any more variations in it.
So, we're going to select only LSTAT and RM and we're going to try to plot it against price and see what it looks like.
So, these are the scatter plots we created.
So, you can see they seem to be linearly correlated, right? You can see that you can kind of form a line, but this is negative correlation and this one is positive correlation.
Because if LSTAT is low, then the price is high and if RM is high, the price is high, which also is what we saw in the correlation matrix. So, it makes sense, right?
Okay, so our hypothesis for now is that these two features are probably going to be the most important or the most indicative features as far as the price of a house is concerned.
Let's try to verify those claims. Any questions so far?
Okay, so what we're going to do is, like in previous examples, we're going to have X as all of the columns except our output column or our target column or our label column, which forms the Y dataset.
So, we're going to remove price and have all the other features in X and then we're going to have price as the only feature in Y.
So, we have 506 columns, 13 features and one feature over here. This blank means one.
We're going to scale over here because these are all numerical features on different scales and again, we don't want one of them to have a lot of weightage just because the number is high.
So, let's go ahead and scale it.
And then similar to how we did in our previous supervised learning, we will split them into training and test. We'll still go with the 80-20 split using the train test split.
We passed the transformed versions.
Again, over here, like I mentioned, instead of using the decision reclassifier, we're using linear regression over here.
So, classifiers are used for classification where you want to categorize the data points into certain categories.
Regression is where you're trying to predict a particular value, a particular amount. So, we're going to use linear regression, which is the most basic model for regression.
So, we just call the model, .fit, give it your training data set, the X and Y values, so our features and our output.
And it creates similar to our decision reclassifier. It finally creates a model based on all of that data.
And we've kept aside the training data set, the 20% that was remaining. So, we'll try to predict the results on that 20% of the data and use some metrics that we can see.
So, over here, we're not going to really have false positives or false negatives since this is not classification.
So, we're going to have slightly different metrics, which are called RMSE, root mean square error, and we're going to have R-square. I'll explain about what they mean.
So, you can import those metrics from sklearn.metrics, mean squared error, and R2 score, which is R-square.
And then we look at the model performance.
So, for the model performance for training set, we had RMSE of 4.6 and R-square of 0.7.
So, RMSE is an absolute metric where the actual numbers, where the actual numbers or the actual values influence that particular metric.
But R-square is independent of the magnitude. So, it's always going to be between 0 and 1. It's kind of like a percentage.
RMSE looks at the difference between what was the predicted value and what was the actual value.
And if that difference is extremely high, it's going to be high. But if the difference is low, it's going to be low, right?
It's going to be difficult to say if this RMSE is high or not without having the data and context.
Since our prices are in thousands, an RMSE of 4, 4 is much smaller compared to thousands. This is good.
But let's say if you had to predict click rates, for example, and click rates are always between 0 and 1 because it's expressed as a percentage.
In that case, an RMSE of something like 0.7 would be extremely high because the range itself goes from 0 to 1.
So, in that case, 0.7 is extremely high. So, over here, I think RMSE looks good.
R-square talks about the variability within the price.
So, it's just another way of saying that given these features, how well can these features explain the variation in the price that we're seeing, the highs and the lows that we're seeing?
So, it's doing a job of 73% of explaining it, which is 0.73. So, it's definitely better than average, but it's not really got a really amazing.
It's just doing like 73%, slightly above average, you can say.
But this is for the training set, mind you. So, this is something that the model has been trained on and the model is good on.
We definitely don't want these to be extremely high because otherwise that would be an indication of us overfitting the model.
Remember the Huskies example where it was just predicting snow instead of trying to predict Huskies, trying to detect Huskies.
So, we don't want it to be extremely high. We want to keep it a little lower so that we can generalize the model.
So, let's go ahead and finally evaluate the model on the test set.
We're going to use the same metrics and let's see what happens here.
So, the RMSE is 4.86, which is similar to the training set, which is good. It's not fallen completely.
And the R-square is about 76%, which is a little higher than training, which is also good because it's able to explain slightly more.
The model is able to explain the features and the variability and the price slightly more.
Any questions so far? Yeah.
Yes, I definitely agree that there's a lot of confusion where people think correlation and causation are the same things, which is where your domain experts also come into play, right?
So, if someone from a medical profession comes into play and says that, yes, this is something that's proven that perhaps if the radius is extremely high of the tumor, it's probably malignant or something like that, which is where the domain expert comes in.
So, data science cannot always tell you the causations. That is left to how well you understand the context of the problem, how well you understand the data and how well the model is interpretable.
So, it gives you a good starting point, but of course, it's not going to be all end all, otherwise we would all probably be out of jobs by now.
Okay. Any other questions?
So, this is a really short example, but I just wanted to give you an idea of another application of supervised learning.
So, I know on the face of it, it seems that coding for data science is simple. You just go to SKLearn, you import some model and you keep trying it on a bunch of predefined metrics, but trying to understand what the models are doing internally, trying to understand how the metrics, are they good enough, are they making sense to you, are they able to predict it, or are they just over-fitting and over-generalizing everything?
That is kind of the tricky part of data science, I would say. And all of those skills are only learned when you practice a lot with the data.
So, my recommendation is pick up an interesting data set. It could be something about your favorite sports team. There's another really great data set about one million songs that has all of the features, the audio features of each of the songs, and you can like cluster them and see.
Or you can even look at lyrics. There's another application someone built that's a little bit on the NLP site, but it was an application where you tell the app what Beatles song you like the most, and it gives you a recommendation based on clustering, whether another Beatles song is something that you would like or it's something that you would hate, looking at the lyrics and the different audio features in the song.
Yeah, I think that's pretty much it. I can talk a little bit about the data science ethics part, since I think that's also very important and it's an often neglected portion. We already covered a bit about when we talked about it, when we talked about how our training data set needs to be pretty diverse, needs to be representative, doesn't need to, shouldn't have the biases that humans have, otherwise the point is kind of lost.
There was this, I was reading actually just yesterday we had this chat with a colleague of mine, and this person was trying to advocate the cause of introducing humanities in data science.
And a lot of people initially would be like, what humanities and science engineering tech, really that doesn't make sense, it's so different.
But let me give you one particular example, which is two examples actually, they're quite tragic, but it really shows the need of ethics in data science.
So did you hear about this instance where Target actually predicted the pregnancy of a person before the person themselves found out?
Right, some of you did, okay. I think it was a teenage pregnancy, I don't recollect, right, but Target actually predicted, I'm guessing it was probably based on her purchase activity, the kind of product she was buying and the frequency with which she was buying.
And they just sent her this coupon for some, you know, like get a discount on some baby care product, blah, blah, blah.
And this was before she even herself knew she was pregnant. So it's just like creepy. But consider the slightly other extreme of it.
So all these algorithms are really good at tracking the kind of activities we do online, right?
And if a person is going to look at baby care products, then it's not difficult to jump to the conclusion that the person is expecting or someone in the family is expecting.
But what happens if unfortunately the mother undergoes a miscarriage and you still continue to show baby care products to that person?
It's not ethical, it's going to be emotionally very traumatic for the mother.
But as engineers or as software practitioners, data scientists, we don't really consider that use case, right?
Like nobody could have even thought of that because you were just trying to give personalized recommendations and make the users happy.
But there are these kind of certain use cases where you need to take a slightly more human approach and where ethics come into play.
There was another case of someone who actually had quite an outburst where...
Have you seen those Facebook friend-worsy videos?
Like if you...the day on which you became friends with person X, Y, Z, they showed you a picture of a baby.
The day on which you became friends with person X, Y, Z, they showed you a short video of your pictures together and how many likes you've shared and so on and so forth.
So this person received a friend-worsary video.
And as part of the video on the common pictures in which both of you are tagged, there are these small graphical cartoons that are jumping around and saying, you know, like, happy friend-worsary and the balloons are going up.
This happened on someone's mother's grave's picture.
And they brought it up and they were like, oh, happy friend-worsary with your mother.
And that is just not...that's inhumane, right?
Like just imagine how traumatic it must have been.
So these are really tragic examples.
These are really tragic examples, but as you all are starting off in data science, whether you continue it personally, pursue it professionally or just, you know, do it as a hobby, I would really love it for you to be mindful of all the use cases the applications could be used in.
What are the disadvantages and how could it negatively affect humans?
Because at the end of the day, we are using machines, we're using algorithms to make lives easier for us.
They are the ones who are, you know, working for us.
We are not slaves to them.
So these kind of ethical issues definitely need to be talked about.
Another example that comes to mind is the MIT model machine.
Have you heard of that?
Okay, so it comes from this classic trolley problem, which says that...let me give you one instance of it.
If you're a self-driving car and you see that there's probably a truck in front of you and you have to swerve one way or the other, and on one side there is one person who is crossing the road legally because the green light is walking for that person.
On the other side of the road, there are five people who are crossing the road who are, you know, like jaywalking.
Who should you kill?
Should you kill that one person because it's one compared to five?
But that one person was legally, lawfully obeying everything.
So should you go kill the other five people?
Similarly, just to twist it around a little, if it was the driver's fault, would you kill the pedestrian who was walking legally or would you, you know, rather the driver?
Should the car meet an accident and the driver gets injured?
Like ideally it should be the driver who should get injured because the driver is at fault.
But if that is the case, who will buy a self-driving car?
Nobody, right?
Sorry, let me show you quickly.
So they built this app which has all of these simulations.
So you start judging what should the self-driving car do.
That's where you see like these are all scars.
Like do you want to kill them because they were crossing it illegally or do you go there and enjoy yourself and kill these people?
Sorry?
They are collecting data, yes, to facilitate conversations about this.
Yeah.
Hopefully not the train, no.
But yeah, I think after you finish all of these 13 steps, at least when I checked it last, it gives you a breakdown of how similar have people performed actions like you or how dissimilar have the majority of the people performed actions like you.
And it brings up a really interesting debate of who is the judge and how do we act in a way that is similar to the judge.
How do we actually regulate these algorithms?
How do you add the human touch?
How do you consider the ethics of it all?
Which is why humanities and arts kind of are going to play an important role in these kind of debates in the future.
They certainly don't have it.
What's the difference between self-driving cars and self-driving cars?
Yeah, I don't think they do it in this, but I wouldn't be surprised if they do it for like actual self-driving cars or something.
Because it's pretty easy to collect that data.
I wouldn't be surprised if they do.
Okay, I think I have covered pretty much everything I wanted in this tutorial.
Are there any other questions about the code that we went through?
Okay, so I'm going to update this notebook with a few more examples.
There was another example for k-means clustering.
It's actually used in image compression.
So I also found out about this example, I think, last month when I was preparing for another tutorial.
So image compression, if you originally look at a high definition image, it's probably going to have thousands, if not millions of colors, different colors.
And the way image compression works is you look at one pixel and you pick which other colored pixel is it closest to.
So kind of like how we did in clustering, we picked one center, one mean point, right?
And all of the points nearby would take that cluster.
Similarly, you pick one data point which is representative of that particular color and all of the other colors collapse to that color.
So if you have like pale white and off white and ivory, they would all probably come down to like white.
That is a way of compressing the image.
So you can see like this is the original image and this is the image compressed with just 30 colors.
So that's another application of k-means algorithm.
So in that case, they're not reviewing the number of pixels?
Yeah, exactly.
I can send a link in the resources as well.
This is my contact information.
Feel free to ask me any questions.
And just a snapshot of what are the skills that data scientists in today's world should have.
Definitely maths and statistics.
We did look at a lot of statistics today, but that was just really the tip of the iceberg.
Programming and database, of course, because you need to have coding knowledge to be able to create these models.
Domain knowledge and soft skills, domain knowledge to understand the context of the data and the applications better.
Soft skills to be able to communicate the results and the challenges with the data.
And visualisation so that you're able to tell a good story, a coherent story about what was the data, what exactly did you perform, why did it have such kind of results.
Or even sometimes it could be something like it's inconclusive or the data is not enough and we need more data.
Yeah, that's it about me.
Feel free to ask me any other questions.
So I'm going to go ahead and start with the question of the data.
So I'm going to start with the question of the data.
Yeah, that's it about me.
Feel free to ask me any other questions.
Yeah, another really cool example I wanted to mention that was slightly again more natural language processing.
So that's actually my expertise area was I mentor this group of three high school girls as part of AI for All, amazing profit that's trying to involve kids into artificial intelligence at a young age.
And they created this application that passes 911 EMS emergency medical service calls.
And based on that, it detects if where exactly should the ambulance go.
San Francisco and in the recent year, San Francisco has had a huge ambulance crisis where there are not enough ambulances and ambulances can take as long as up to 40 minutes to arrive, which is ridiculous.
So this application, it goes through the transcripts of what the you know, the audit record is of what you're seeing.
And then it detects keywords saying things like, okay, if someone had a fall, it's probably lower priority versus someone who's had a heart attack.
And it prioritizes that and then puts it all in a map, like what is the closest location and what is the high priority.
So it's like a blinking red.
And then a slightly lower priority would be like, you know, a yellow or green and things like that.
So there are a lot of really cool applications for data science.
It could be something another early important resource.
So useful resource I like is 538 by Nate Silver.
If you're aware of him, he was pretty popular for predicting the election results.
And there was this huge fiasco of how even he wasn't able to predict the last election results correctly.
But they usually publish statistical blogs, but they do a very good job of explaining why, for instance, Liverpool has a 4% chance of making it to the finals in the league.
I don't know if any of you follow soccer and watch that.
But so then they also target other sports.
They also target elections and they kind of explain how statistics informs their models.
And how when they say 75% probability of something happening, that is completely different from 70% probability happening.
And why is that difference of 5%, which might seem really negligible to us, is actually important, statistically important.
Yeah, I think that's it from me.
I'm just going to have it on now.
But feel free to ask me any questions if you have.
I hope you enjoyed the tutorial.
I will be sending out a link.
I'll be sending out a tweet with the updated slides.
It's still going to be on the same link that you accessed.
I would also love to receive any feedback.
I usually do one to two hour tutorials, so this three hour was something new for me as well.
But I hope it wasn't tiring.
I hope you all got something out of it and you definitely have the notebooks and resources to refer to.
And I hope I've sparked some interest of data science in all of you when you're going back home with Mona Lisa.
Thank you.