And I think everybody is seated, so we're going to start the recording.
And then we can go on, and we're good.
So hi, everyone.
This is a Jupyter and IPython tutorial at PyCon.
You have some instruction that we get back to the slide.
I'm Mathias.
I've been part of the Jupyter team since about 2012.
If you want to see my email, you clone one of our repository and you git log.
And as a day jobs, I'm at the University of California, Merced.
Denis would not be here today.
He couldn't make it.
So I'm going to try to fill in for him as much as I can.
But we have another Jupyter code in the back here.
Paul, who is waving to you.
Say hi to Paul.
Hi, Paul.
There's also a backstretch.
So he will be going through, helping you if you have any issues.
And maybe at some point he will come in front of the camera.
But it's not his job.
So he's just helping today.
You should have received these instructions.
We're going to make sure that everything is slow in the first 15 minutes.
If you have everything installed and you go to a terminal and do JupyterLab,
you should have JupyterLab popping up.
If it's not OK, raise your hand or put a red sticky note on your laptop.
And we're going to come help you make sure everything is installed
so that we can move forward.
If everything is good, you put a green or a blue sticky note
so that I can have a quick overview of for whom it's going well
and for who it's not going well.
So you see those people are nice.
And they put the sticky note up so that I can see that it's mostly doing fine.
We're going to do a short presentation for you to finish installation.
Some of you I know just started to download.
And then we can directly dive into Jupyter.
And if you're stuck, if you can't install it on your machine,
just don't stay quiet.
We have a way to set you up online.
We don't have hundreds of machines,
but we have a couple of machines where you can play online
if it doesn't work on your laptop.
So what is Jupyter?
Well, it depends who you talk to.
But mostly when people talk about Jupyter,
and I pay it on for some old timers like me,
it's mostly known for what they call the notebook.
We're going to monitor what is in the notebook later.
It's usually like it's a web server and a web app
that can contain code, narrative, math and results.
You probably all have seen Jupyter maybe once before.
Who has never seen Jupyter before?
Okay, good.
So nobody raise their hands.
And usually these things is attached to a kernel doing computation.
And here we're going to use Python.
If we dive more into what Jupyter is,
it's assessed as standard and protocols.
We have the notebook document format,
which is usually a file that ends in the IPYMB,
which is JSON inside.
It's relatively easy to manipulate.
It's a ZMQ protocol.
So why ZMQ?
ZMQ is a library which is available in many languages
that allows the front end you interact with
to talk with the process that does computation.
And the kernel can be local or remote,
and the front ends can interact with the users,
but sometimes not.
And we have the default implementation.
The default implementation is the one you usually know about.
It means that we have many languages
that are maintained by the community.
You can run Scala, you can run Haskell,
you can run Julia, Erlang, Ruby, whatever.
But because Jupyter is written in Python,
we're going to focus on IPython,
which is one implementation that implements the Python language
as one of the kernels that can run in Jupyter.
But you can use Jupyter only with R if you wish to.
And there are many front ends.
You can see that you can hook Jupyter with VS code,
with interact, with Atom, with a normal notebook.
And we're going to mostly focus on one front end today
that you may have heard it's called JupyterLab.
We are going to do everything using Python 3.
I remind some of you that Python 2 End of Life
is supposed to be January 1st of next year.
You can still use Python 2 after that,
but the support is going to decrease really fast.
It has already started to decrease really fast.
So there is no problem if you want to use Python 2.
You can still use Python 2 with Jupyter,
with older version of the kernel.
If you have any questions, you can come talk to me later.
I'm going to do a quick FAQ.
And at the end of the FAQ,
or even if you have question now,
be free to raise your hand
and I want to answer your question now.
So that you can be on peace of mind
and focus on the tutorial after.
How do I pay for hosted Jupyter?
This is non-exhaustive, but you can Google
and there are many companies
that pay for hosted Jupyter online.
So if you want to have a big server
with thousands of machine,
probably don't want to talk to the Jupyter team
who are mostly volunteers and open source.
Some of us know and can redirect you
to how to pay for hosted.
But you can find a lot of company doing that online.
How do I run Jupyter at scale?
If you came here to know how to deploy Jupyter
for your lab or your company,
we're not going to talk about that too much.
You want to Google about Jupyter Hub.
As soon as you have more than one user,
you probably want to run Jupyter Hub.
Jupyter Hub is one way of dispatching user
to their own servers and do things at scale on Kubernetes
if you know what Kubernetes is
or on raw hardware if you want to use raw hardware.
Those are two links.
All of that will be online, don't worry.
Tell you how to deploy Jupyter, Jupyter Hub.
So that one is the core documentation,
but if you want to just do things to copy and paste
and get a server for 20 people, that would be this one.
After that, there's a lot of customization possible.
How do I share static notebook?
You will do notebooks.
You might want to have some of your colleagues or friends
to view those notebooks
without when they don't have Jupyter installed.
For that, you might want to use nbviewer at nbviewer.org.
What happens is you give it a URL to a public notebook.
We don't do integration, we don't do authentication.
So as long as a notebook JSON file is public,
you pass the URL here and it will convert it to HTML
on the fly for the person.
It's static, so it means that they can't interact with it.
It's automatically updated.
It looks at the latest Git.
Usually this work doesn't work only with GitHub,
but it's mostly work with GitHub.
It looks at whether the commit hash has changed
and if the commit hash has changed, it will be rendered.
It means that you just have to push on GitHub
and the notebook will be refreshed.
So it's a nice way of sharing it.
And we just got one new Jupyter developer
that arrived in the back, Matt from Netflix.
Say hi, Matt, thank you for being here that early today.
So Matt is working on mostly the things
that powers NB viewer in the back,
NB convert and paper mill.
That is a nice project from Netflix.
If you want to share a live notebook,
like you want someone to interact,
you have a data set that you've explored,
but there are thousands of images
and you don't want to print a thousand page report
for your boss or your colleague.
Or you have a paper that you've published
and you only show some data sets in your supplementary,
but you want people to interact with other data sets.
You want to go to mindbinder.org.
Slightly more complicated than NB viewer.
It doesn't take a single notebook.
It tells the full GitHub repository.
And what it does, it will try to analyze dependency.
If you do the right file, it will create for you on the fly
a Docker image in the cloud, which is there for two hours
and you will be able to interact with that.
So if you have some notebook
and you want people to be able to see
how some parameters change, how the plot look like,
or which data set to look,
you might want to look at mindbinder.org.
It's hosted so far by the Jupyter project
from front from UC Berkeley.
So there are some limitation on how much compute you can do.
So please don't mind Bitcoin.
And if some of you don't manage
to install the tutorial material,
you can use binder to try the tutorial.
Or if you're on YouTube or whatever video system
is being used to record me right now.
Which language are supported?
We said that there is only Python
that we're going to see today.
There is a Wiki if you develop your own kernel
for your own language.
Some people have liked to invent languages.
You can go there and add your own kernel.
It's mostly community maintained.
You go on the Jupyter Wiki
and you look at Fortran,
where is the documentation for Fortran
and you can install the Fortran kernel.
One of the question that we often have
is starting to get better is,
what is the difference between Jupyter Notebook
and Jupyter Lab?
We're mostly going to talk about the Jupyter Lab today.
Jupyter Lab is a new front-end that we rewrote from scratch
starting two or three years ago.
Because we were Python developers
and we started to write JavaScript for the main notebook.
The main notebook still exists, can still run.
Usually when you use a main notebook,
you can only have one notebook on the page.
And Jupyter Lab is better software engineering.
You can have several notebook on the page.
You can have text editor.
You can have a terminal.
Why do you want to use one or the other?
It's more like Vim versus Emacs,
so left of the room versus right of the room.
GIF versus GIF.
It doesn't really matter.
You can work with each other.
You should be friends.
They read exactly the same file format.
So if you have a file in Jupyter Lab,
it will work in classic notebook.
If you have a file in classic notebook,
it will work with Jupyter Lab.
They can connect to the same kernel.
There is only some extensions
that exist for one and not the other.
And the classic notebooks that you may have seen
when you do Jupyter Notebook on the terminal
will probably go away someday.
So it's slowly being sunset.
And Jupyter Lab should be in version 1.0
or relatively soon.
We're going to use something which is slightly before 1.0.
So if you see bugs or think that I know you,
you can still give us feedback.
Say, this doesn't make sense.
It would be nice to change it before 1.0.
How do you get help once you are out of the tutorial?
I would suggest you go to Jupyter.org slash community.
There are a lot of channel,
and I would suggest for you to join the discourse.
You can log in with GitHub or with Google
if you deactivate ad block,
because ad block tend to remove the things that tells you
you can log in with GitHub or GitLab
or any other provider.
And of course, if you're in the room here,
you put your red sticky note or you raise your hand
and we're going to help you.
And so that's the slide about the sticky notes.
I already told you a bit how it works.
So when everything is good,
when you think I can go faster,
you put a green sticky note,
and don't forget to put a task to remind you
to remove your sticky note.
Sorry, people forget to have the green sticky note.
I think everything is fine,
and I just go faster and faster and faster,
and you will get lost.
And as soon as something is wrong,
you put a red sticky note app,
and some of the helper will come
and try to help you to install,
or I will stop and ask questions.
You can think that as a try-except in your brain,
and as soon as there is an exception,
you put the red sticky note,
and I will slow down.
Do you have any questions so far?
Does everybody has everything installed?
Feel free to interrupt me during the tutorial.
Ask me to rephrase if I have a question,
or if I forget to do something.
I know I can have a really strong French accent sometime.
So if you don't understand, it's because of me.
And so again, the install instructions are here.
PyCon 2019 branch, it should be the default one,
so you shouldn't have to do anything,
but just in case, I've put it here.
And once everyone is ready, we can go to the tutorial.
So I don't see any red stickies.
So we have about one hour before getting food.
Okay.
Is that big enough for people in the back?
No, it's not big enough for people in the back.
Say I want something bigger.
More?
Okay.
Yeah, I want me to...
Change your operating system too.
So some people want me to change PS1,
so what is written before,
and others want me to change my OS.
Yeah, I would prefer to change my keyboard,
who is starting to have keys that type two times,
and keys that don't type.
You probably have heard of that.
So I'm going to do a lot of typo.
It's definitely not because I'm not awake,
it's because of my keyboard.
So here we are in where you should have probably
gotten your material from GitHub.
You see here that I'm on the PyCon 2019 branch
because I have my terminal set up this way.
And you see that nothing have changed
because I have the green check mark.
You might not have that.
And so the first thing we want to do,
and not forget to do that,
is kind of activate PyCon 2019
to be in the environment I should have had you create.
And so now I'm in PyCon 2019,
and I don't have much space,
but we're just going to start with one thing,
which is to press Jupyter, then space, and lab.
If you have any questions, you can do dash dash help,
or it's a little normal command line, you can run things.
And once you do that,
it should hopefully start Jupyter lab,
which is kind of like Jupyter Notebook,
and open your web browser at a specific URL.
One thing I would suggest you do later after the tutorial,
if you want to use it on your machine,
is to look at the documentation
on how to set up a password.
Because this is running a server on your machine.
Normally people cannot access it from the outside,
but other processes on your machine
may try to access Jupyter unless you set a password.
There is an automatic token that is set up,
and so on and so forth, so this should be secure.
But better safe than sorry, look online,
look on how to set up a password with Jupyter.
And now you should be prompted by your password
the first time you log in.
So here we will have the Jupyter lab interface.
We're going to see exactly what is a Jupyter lab interface,
and how it works later in the tutorial.
We're just going to focus on some of the Python first,
because playing with buttons is not too interesting
at the beginning of a tutorial.
You can see that there is a bug already here,
that's weird, there is no icon here.
I don't know why.
Let me try to force refresh.
Okay, so that needs to be filled somewhere,
and figure out why, probably because I'm zooming.
So here you have a file browser
that you can expand and collapse using this
if you want to have more space in your screen.
You'll see that I have relatively few real estate
on my screen, so I will do things
slightly different than you.
But you should be able to have more space
and see more clearly what is happening.
You see that you have a menu at the top.
Here I'm full screen, so I remove the,
actually in a web browser.
So most of, some of your short cut here
you might be used to, like go to the next tab
of previous type, might be slightly different.
So if you're confused of what's happening
when you are a big keyboard user,
that's because you have two level of interaction.
You have the interaction with your browser windows,
and the interaction with the JupyterLab.
And so what we're going to do is,
well first look at that, you will see that
we always have first the notebook, the folders,
and directories of where you are.
Then we have this small orange icon on notebooks,
and then we have other kinds of file.
And so when we sort by name or by last modify,
you see that it's actually three groups.
You have the folders on top, you have the notebooks after,
and you have the other files after.
So don't be confused if you think,
well no, it's not sorted by name,
it's because the folders themselves are sorted by name,
or by last modified, and it's a transfer, and so forth.
And we're going to just start with going with
notebook number one, and double click on it,
and it should open a new panel like that.
And now I'm going to collapse that
just to have a bigger real estate.
And now we're going to directly interact with our notebook
using the JupyterLab interface,
which is quite similar to the normal notebook interface
with some differences if you use normal notebook,
or if you want to use normal notebook after.
You'll see that we have many cells,
so it's sometimes hard to figure out where the cells are.
You can see that you have the indicator here
of which cells I'm currently selecting,
which is this blue line, and you can see that
I can move it up and down with my keyboard when it works,
or click with the mouse.
And you will see that usually we have a model interface,
which means that you can either be in a mode
where you are going to manipulate cells themselves
in a notebook, so a cell is a chunk of text or code,
or you can be in a mode if I press enter,
where I edit the cell.
So that might be one of the tricky things
where you might get lost, is that if you are in a mode
where you are manipulating cells themselves
and try to type, it won't edit the cell,
it won't write things in the cells.
It will basically just do things with the cell.
Like for example, if I press D twice,
it will delete the cell.
So that's something to keep in mind.
But usually the keyboard shortcut you will use
most of the time is shift enter.
So you press shift and you press enter,
and what it will do, it will execute
or render the current cell.
So if it's some markdown, it will just display it.
If it's some code, it will send it to the kernel,
execute the things and show the result back.
So usually when you want to go through a notebook,
you press shift enter many times to go down.
Some useful things when you're prototyping,
there is also alt enter that executes
and insert a cell below.
If you have some long code and you want to add
some debug statements, and control enter to just rerun
the same thing again and again and again and again,
so you don't have to do shift enter up, shift enter up.
So we'll see that, but first let's do some Python first.
So here you have the first cell that's a print high.
I'm going to assume all of you know what that does in Python.
And if I print shift enter, it will just say hi.
And now I can go up and modify my code,
everyone, and press shift enter,
and it says hi everyone.
And you see that I have this number in front here.
In normal notebook you would see in two,
and that means that it's the second statement
I have executed in my current session.
Because of document I'm editing,
and the process that is running in the back are different,
I can restart the process without having
to destroy my documents.
And so now we're going to that normal Python,
but IPython itself, because we have IPython in the back,
who is just executing Python,
can do more things than pure Python can do.
And we are mostly targeted to all having interactive stuff
and making you interactive data analysis more efficient.
And so the first thing you should be really happy about
is a question mark operator that allow you to get help
on a large number of things,
and we try to pull more help information
than what pure Python does with a help function.
And so if you just want global help because you're lost
and you don't know how to do things,
question mark will give you a quick summary
of what you can do in IPython.
So this is question mark itself,
introduction overview of IPython features.
If you want some information about an object, any object,
you can use object question mark and then shift enter,
or question mark object and then shift enter.
If you want more detailed information,
you can use two question mark, we'll do that later.
You also have present quick ref,
and you can also call a pure Python help system.
This is quite long, so I'm not going to do that now,
and I'm going to just collapse this cell
by pressing the green, the blue button here on the side,
which is green.
We'll see more about the interface of our JupyterLab later.
And so now we're going to see how to get help on objects.
We're going to use, to look at the collection module.
We are going to import it
and look at collection name tuple, question mark.
Name tuple is a nice, really nice thing.
It's like a tuple, except you can give name
to each of the elements.
And you see that we're going to pull the signature
from the Python, the Python documentation.
So it gives you the positional arguments,
the keywords arguments.
So this means that, the star here means
that those arguments are keyword arguments only.
Then it pulls a docstring,
it tries to find where this file is defined.
So you know that if you have different version
of Numpy installed or different version of Python installed,
you can figure out that it's the right one
and that it's a function.
Let's call up that as well, but you don't have to.
And if you want more information,
well, you're going to put two question mark.
And what you should get is not only everything
you got before, but you should get the full source.
So if you ever wonder how a function was defined,
instead of going through the source of the library
and searching through it, you can actually directly see
how it has been written, which is really useful
when you do science, you want to figure out
how things are done to understand correctly
if there is a bug or not.
It does some other fancy stuff.
It will try to find if there are subclasses at the bottom.
Here there is no subclasses.
So if you want something more specific,
in something like Matplotlib, it will say,
well, here you have an artist,
but you also have an artist which are,
you have the circle artist or you have the ellipse artist
or you have the square artist.
And so you can drill down into more specific things.
Another useful things, let me re-scroll up, sorry,
is you know that there is some function somewhere
where have that name somewhere in it,
but you don't exactly remember how it's called.
You can use wildcard with a question mark
and it will try to recurse your own namespace
and find something that match this pattern.
So I know that there is something I want to use
that have int in it, where I have the ability
to get either a floating point error or is it break point
or is it int or is it print.
So then you can search in things
when you don't really remember what you want to use
because you only use it once in a while.
There is also the quick reference
that is slightly more compact than what we've seen before
with just question mark.
So it will tell you, well, yeah,
you can search for everything that have ABC
in the full namespace.
You will have many of IPython specific syntax
that starts a line with a single percent or two percent.
We'll see that later.
And you have a number of reminders of things
you can do.
We'll go through all of that in this notebook.
As any other idea, we provide tab completion.
So if you have some code and you want to figure out
what you can write after, you can press tab.
As Fernando Perez, the creator of IPython said,
we weaponize the tab key.
Tab key does a lot of things.
So we've imported the collection module.
We can press tab and it will tell you
what you can complete with that.
This is a really nice example because here you see
that only ABC has an M in front.
I'm going to just dismiss that and repress it.
It had time to compute more information
and now it shows me more information.
And it shows me that I can complete to ABC,
to chain map, to default DQ, et cetera.
And it gives me the type of each of those things.
So unlike many IDE computers, this is not statically inferred.
This is actually inspecting live objects,
which means that if you don't, if you have an API
that written on a different kind of object,
once the object is in the namespace,
you can tab complete on that.
And it will also tab complete everything
that you have defined.
So here, let's say I want to look at DQ
and can go down to DQ and press enter to get that.
And now we're going to see the second thing
that tab can be used for.
I'm going to open parentheses
and I'm going to press shift tab instead of tab.
And it's going to give me a quick help.
So if you don't remember the signature of a function,
you can press shift tab and it will show you
approximately the same things
that question mark will show you.
You'll see that it's slightly different in classic notebook.
But here you see that collection DQ takes,
so the signature is not really useful now,
but the doc string is.
It takes an iterable and then a max length
and it returns to you a DQ object.
So now I can actually do one, two, three,
and a max length of five, for example.
We're not going to look into what DQ is
and then I press shift enter and now I have my objects here.
Not going to DQ itself,
but it's just trying to go through things you can do.
A lot of things that you do interactively,
you might forget to assign a variable.
So now we're going to see how you can use
some IPython features to get back some results
you forgot to assign, especially if they're
a large computation.
So we're just going to do a dummy computation.
We added the two and 10.
We could have done that using TensorFlow,
but it might have been a bit overkill.
Well, if you want to do that, you can see,
you can see FizzBuzz in TensorFlow,
which is a nice one, an article online by Joel Groose.
And now we want to basically add 10 to that,
but TensorFlow basically computed for five hours
on our GPU and we don't want to rerun that.
So you can use a single underscore.
If you haven't assigned to single underscore,
it's automatically there in your namespace
and refer to the previous result.
So now hopefully the previous result is 12.
If I add 10, it's going to be 22.
We also have, we'll see later, we have double underscore,
which is two results before, and triple underscore,
which is three results before.
And they shift all along, so it might be sometimes
hard to follow.
You saw here that, well, you wrote something
and it was automatically displayed
in the interactive shell.
If you have a big result, like a panorama frame
or a matplotlib figure or something,
you might want to not display it.
So one of the specific IPython syntax
is if you end your line with semicolon,
it will suppress the output.
So here 10 plus 20 is 30, but it's not displayed.
And now if we look at the previous results,
because we didn't display it,
that's one of the thing you need to remember,
is it still refers to the previous one that was displayed.
So because this one was none, actually,
it skipped and still refers to this one.
So it might be useful if you want to do
some temporary computation and just refer
to what you have back.
One of the issue with underscore, double underscore,
and triple underscore is that they keep shifting around.
You don't know which ones they are.
So what you can do is actually refer either
to underscore and the number of the output,
so 10 would be this one, or directly refer to out
with an uppercase O and the number you want in it.
And so hopefully underscore 10 should be equal to out 10
and should be equal to 22.
And so they're both equal, and we are going to check
the value of 10, it's actually 22, so that's good.
So when you have a lot of things that you've done
and you want to reuse, you can refer to it.
One of the drawback of that, especially if you're working
with really large data sets, is that some outputs
will stay in memory, where in normal pythons
it will be garbage collected.
So be careful, you might use way more memory
when you use IPythons than when you use a normal python.
And we have a question here.
So my column appended that computation,
it was still done, it's just not displayed.
So, well, this computation, yes, this computation
has done, but not displayed.
So that's a good question, well, we can try.
I'm going to talk a bit about the JupyterLab interface
while I'm here, I'm going to not edit,
I'm in edit mode here inside the cell,
I'm going to press escape, so I'm modifying
the notebook itself, I'm going to press A for above
to create a new cell, I'm going to define a function
that prints, let's do double quotes,
I'm called and return result.
Really difficult.
So now I'm going to call F and put a semicolon,
and so we are going to check that the function
is actually called, but the result,
it returned was not displayed.
So it's called, but the result is not displayed.
If I remove the semicolon, it's called,
but I have a result.
You see here that there is a slight difference
between printing and returning the value,
you see that the value which is printing
doesn't have a prompt in front of it.
So you can't refer to something that has been printed.
But you can refer to the value of the last statement
of a cell, so a result.
So let's do this example, let's go create a new cell,
let's do one, two, three, so we have three statements.
Only the last statement would be printed,
which will be three, we can check that 18
is actually only three.
And one and two were executed,
but the result were not outputted.
If we print them, it's the same,
we can print one, print two,
and you see here that we have one and two,
but they don't have a prompt number in front.
Good question.
If you want to access what you've written before,
you can also do that with in instead of out.
So you saw that on input 11, I got 10 plus 20
that I had to pass output, you can also use things
with I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, et cetera.
Or if you want to have more information
about everything you wrote, especially since you can edit
what has been previously done in the notebook,
you might want to really see exactly
the command of sequence you have.
You can use the percent history magic,
we'll see what the magic is later, with line one to five.
So here I would see only the first five inputs I've done.
And you see that the first five, five times I've done
was to print high, print high to everyone,
I edited the first cell, used question mark,
worked with import collection and collection name tuples,
and then did collection counter to question mark.
And now we're going to do a small exercise,
I'm going to let you look at history question mark
to see what the documentation of history is,
and try to see if you can extract the last 10 line
of history to a file name log dot py.
And we have a question here.
So are the, in number 23, the one to five,
is that referencing those, the numbers to the left?
So the question is, in history, one to five,
what are one to five referring to?
Are they referring to the number on the left here?
Yes, they're referring to the in number.
But that's something that should be hopefully documented
when you do percent history question mark,
to give you more information.
And some of the information you will see
is that this is not related to only the notebook,
it's related to iPad on itself.
And you can refer to either this session,
the current session you're in,
or you can also refer to previous session.
If I remember correctly, if I do that,
that's going to be what I showed earlier today to Mike.
I showed him how to do some of the auto-avoid stuff.
And you see that it's my 383rd iPad on session,
and that the fifth line of the 383rd session
was auto-avoid true.
And here I used tilde to do the previous session,
but all of the syntax should be defined
in history question mark,
where you will get some information.
So let's take two or three minutes
to make sure that you're fine with all of that.
If everything is good or bad,
you can put your green sticky note and red sticky notes.
You can ask questions.
Okay.
F.
So I didn't remember everything correctly.
So the N was just printing line number.
It was not referring to the actual range.
It's its own parameter.
And so if I do history question mark
and put a percent in front,
so I have the information.
So it give me some examples.
It tell me what N print line number for each input.
I also want to have the F file name.
So I'm going to do minus F log.py.
And I only want to see,
get the last N line from all sessions.
So if you ask for any one session,
that should be that.
And so if I do, yes?
So how do you,
since the dash L is the last N lines from all sessions,
is there another option that makes it say
just the current session?
So if you don't give any,
the session are the things before the slashes here.
I think the communication might be slightly unclear here.
So here you're asking for sessions eight to six.
Well, six back and eight back.
If you don't give anything,
it will only assume it's one session.
Like if I did minus L with tilde eight dash tilde six,
it would give me the last L lines of all the session
tilde eight to tilde six.
So if you don't put any session,
it will assume it's only the current one.
If it's unclear, you can send the pull request
if you think you can write it better.
So, oh, well, I already did that.
File.log exists, overwrite, yes?
Overwriting file.
And now we're going to see,
well, that's nice because we can do that just after.
We can see that IPython have some nice integration
when you can call the underlying shell.
If you don't know how to do things in Python,
you can do it in bash.
You just prepend your line with a bang
and then you write some bash.
And now it will run bash for you in the bash.
And give you the result.
So you can see here that I have created a file code log.py
that have the last 10 items of as a history
of my current session.
And that's just what we had with perfect transition.
You can in IPython access underlying operating system
using the bang and bang bang operators
when they are in, when IPython figure out
they are invalid in Python syntax,
it will automatically try to do
all the right things for you.
So if I want to see in which directory I am,
I can do pwd and it will print it.
And we have also one other special casing
which is equaled followed by some spaces or none and bang.
And so if you do that, it will attempt
to run the command here and get the output of it
into an object that you can assign.
So basically if you don't know that in Python
you want to do os.listdir,
because it's something that you would take
like 10 minutes to Google,
you can just do bang and use your bash.
If you're on Windows,
I believe it use underlying command shell,
I'm unsure, or power shell if you use it with power shell.
So this specific syntax is a syntax
of the underlying shell.
So I assume that's just using standard and centered out.
So the question was, I assume it's using
standard in and standard out.
Yes it does.
We're not going to do exactly into the detail
of what this object is.
It's not purely a string, it's a wrapper around strings
where you can ask for each line independently
or the full bytes or something like that.
So if you want to play with that,
once you've run these cells,
I would let you play with it and do files?
And files.tab to see what's in it.
And so here I want to look at everything
which is in my notebooks folder.
Well let me just change that to ls
to see what are the current working directory.
You see that I have a notebooks folder.
I can pass option to ls if I want it to be more complete
and be as a list, you can do that.
So it's pure bash if you know, if you know, if you know bash.
And so now you see that you have those files
in the current working directory.
So now if you want to loop through those files,
it will work.
So that's relatively useful
if you want to manipulate things.
I like to match Python and bash.
Like you want to copy only the ipynb file
or only some py file.
If I want to get only my py file,
I would do star.py and I would get only my py file.
So let me remove that.
Let me rerun that.
And so now we basically got something from bash
and got it into Python relatively easily using the bang.
We might want to do the opposite.
You might want to take a Python variable
and send it to a bash command.
And so when you run a bash command
with a shell command with a bang,
when you know that the shell variables
are usually starting with dollars like that,
if ipython finds that some of that
is actually in your current namespace,
it will actually replace that by the value of files.
So if I do that, it should basically use bash
to echo the value of the list as a string.
So the value of a file as a string here
is not super useful,
but what you can do is you can actually do
some extra Python syntax inside here
by using curly brackets.
So it's curly brackets or dollar, not both.
And you can see that you can, for example,
get the file name, the first file name,
theta.ipynb as a pre-case.
And what you can do with that
is actually put it inside some Python syntax,
some Python loops, for example.
And so here, if I want to see,
I want you to number my file and remove the extensions.
What I could do is just loop through my file,
and if it's n with ipynb,
I will print a two-digit number, a dash,
and the file name, and otherwise put two dashes.
So that's not extremely useful,
but what you could do here is, for example,
do SSH or SCP or any other manipulation of file system
that you know how to do that,
or submit a job in Slurm if you're using HPC
or something like that,
directly from within Python.
So you can use the flexibility of the command line
and the power of the Python analysis tool.
Question?
Is that flexibility where the curly braces
were used in Python also present in other kernels,
so are those capabilities present in non-Python kernels?
It depends.
They are implemented in the Python kernel,
and it's a Python-specific features.
Some other kernels have mimicked this feature.
It's not Jupyter-specific, it's IPython-specific.
If you use something, I believe the Scala kernel
have some of that, the exact syntax that varies,
and one of the reason is that we use syntax
which is non-valid Python syntax
so that we can escape that and say,
oh, that's actually not Python,
but we know how to handle that.
In other languages, that wouldn't be invalid syntax,
and so the kernel cannot have exactly the same syntax.
They might want to use a different escape characters.
Like instead of persons, they will use hash,
or they will use at.
Small story before that,
before I joined the project,
instead of using percent something
that you've seen with history,
it used to be an at symbol,
and this was before Python had decorators.
So if you've used Python decorators,
decorators used to have at,
and so in 2005 or six, I believe,
was way before my time,
you used to do at history instead of percent history.
And there are some things, like you will realize
that that kind of syntax is really close
to what you have with f string in recent Python,
but this predates f string.
So we might have some conflict with newer Python features,
and when this is the case,
we'll prefer to tilt toward having the Python way
than our own way.
So some features, if they conflict with Python,
will slightly change.
So that bring us to magic functions.
So usually you have things that you want to do
that are beyond Python.
For example, you want to embed SQL,
or you want to automatically time some code
to figure out if it's fast or not.
And IPython has this percent that allow you
to escape from Python and do some things.
You will find two kind of magics,
and you see that they have more a bash-like syntax.
You will have one with a single percent in front.
When you have a single percent in front,
it means that they work only on everything
which follows a line.
So this percent magic will do the thing it does
only on the rest of the line,
which here is nothing, it takes no argument.
And you will see also things with two percent,
and when it's two percent, it acts on the rest of the cell.
Here it's in a notebook.
If it's not in a notebook,
there are some rules of to which scope it applies.
But basically this is most of the magic take strings,
so they will take the value of that as a string
and do any manipulations they want.
Most of them only accept Python syntax,
but you don't have to, you can use non-Python syntax.
And so that allow you to basically escape from the Python
to the Python syntax to do a lot of things.
So if you just do percent magic,
it will give you a nice explanation of what it does,
how it works, some of the possibilities,
and we're going to go through some of them.
So let me just go back to the top
and just compact that.
So one of the first one we're going to see is timeit.
And so timeit is really nice when you want to get
precise measurement of how long a block of code does.
So Python has a timeit module,
but it's relatively heavy to use.
We've done some open-united default things.
So if you say I want to time this piece of code
and see how much it runs,
timeit will run it a couple of times in a tight loop
to see how long this specific piece of code runs.
And you see that doing this take 10.7 microsecond
plus or minus 40.9 nanoseconds per loop,
mean percent deviation.
And we actually did seven run with 100,000 loops each.
Because this is really, really fast,
timeit decided, tried to do some experiments
and decided, well, if I want to be able to measure
precise that I need to run this one,
these things at least 100,000 times
because there is an overhead of starting the computation
and stopping the computation.
So it's going to run that, measure the time
and divide by 100,000 to get 10.7 microseconds.
And to get the standard deviation,
it did the experiments seven times.
So that's what gives you the standard deviation.
So now you have some confidence of how things are working.
And if you have a big block of code,
which is not a single function,
what you can do is put 2% and it will run all of that.
This has a slightly different syntax
that if you need to do some setup only once,
you can put a setup code just on the line
and it will run the setup code on the line only once
and then run that.
So now if I want to see how much that is taking,
taking, I can do so shift enter again.
And now I have my percent, percent time it,
which is running this piece of code a number of time.
And you see that hopefully counting to 110
is faster than counting to a thousand.
If you want to test a function on the wide range
of parameters to see how the behavior here is,
if it's N squared or N cubed or even worse,
if it's exponential,
what you can do is you can actually use the line magic
inside Python syntax.
And so IPython will be able to convert that
into proper Python code
and runs the test for this specific size.
And so you see that it's currently running for size 100.
I should run for 200 and et cetera, et cetera.
So,
I would suggest for you to look at the percent time it help
with a question mark.
You will see that there is an option
that allow you to not only print the result
but return them as an option, like as an object.
And this object has all the information
about the code you ran.
And so now if you want to make a graph
of how long it takes depending on which parameters you gave,
you can do that.
So let's do that as an exercise.
Let's do a question.
You're a time that is a little more provoked
than what I have.
So you don't have, the question is your time
it doesn't have the standard deviation.
I don't know why.
What operating system or Python installation are you using?
Three, four, five, Windows.
So Windows, okay, so I don't know why.
I know there are some codes to be careful
that the plus or minus Unicode can show.
It might be that.
So we can try to take some time as a break to,
to see that.
And another question here.
Is there any way to cancel or stop something from running?
Is there any way to stop or something
which is running in a cell?
Yes, there is.
That would be the equivalent of control C.
So let me do import.
It will work only in Python code.
Like if it's in C code
and the C code doesn't have an interrupt handler,
it won't be able to stop it.
Import slip.
Or from time import slip.
And let me sleep for 15 seconds.
And what I'm going to do is press I twice
for interrupt.
And once might be a mistake, so we have to press it twice.
And so that will send the control C to the kernel
and it will interrupt.
And so the way to, I think we're slowly slower
than my other plan, so I'm going to skip that.
And so same thing, like we've seen that single bank
can allow you to do bash on one line.
If you do percent, percent bash,
you can write multi, multi-line bash
in the middle of your script.
So that's kind of already some cross-language integration.
If you need to drop a file on disk
to do something specific
and you want it to be in the notebook,
you can use write file.
So write file here, we'll write a file
could test.txt with this content.
So you can write, I need to speed up
speed up, cause food is in 20 minutes.
And you can see that I now have this file on just here.
If you want to see all the magic
you have at your disposition, you can use LS magic.
And you can see, well, you can start to see
one nice feature here in Jupiter and Python
is that objects don't always have to be texts.
They can actually be rich representation.
So here we have an HTML thing.
And you can see that you have a two magic
or a call alias magic page, few print X modes.
We're not going to go through all of those
because it would take us forever.
You can see that we have alias,
we have alias couple of things
so that you have consistency between windows and Unix.
And you have a couple of things that work on multi-line.
So you have a latech magic, you have HTML markdown,
we have profile run that we're going to see,
we have time it if we just saw,
write file that we just saw.
And if you want to run something,
for example, on the Python two subshell,
you might be able to do that.
It's not sharing namespace, but it might be useful
if you have some specific software,
which is Python two only.
And so let's call up that and feel free to look at that.
So the other thing we can look at,
if you're writing some scientific code,
you might want to optimize your codes.
And to do that, it might be nice to run a profiler.
Running a profiler is often relatively hard.
So I have this function that's just some computation.
What I can do is I can time it.
And I see that it takes 332 milliseconds using time it.
You see that time it decided to run the loop
only once each because the function was already slow.
And what you can do is run prun to optimize.
So that's shipped in with Python
and it will tell you, well, here is the breakdown
of which functions, if it's something way bigger,
which function took how much time.
In this specific case, it's not really useful
because we only have one function.
But what you can do is you can actually ask some packages
to inject some magic into the namespace.
So not everything has to be built in in IPython.
As soon as you install a package,
when you follow the instruction, you install rpy2.
rpy2 installs the magic.
When you install line profiler in these instructions,
line profiler provides the magic as well.
And so what you can say is, well, IPython look for magics
that are available in the line profiler package.
And so if I tried before doing that to do lprun,
it would say, well, I don't know what lprun is.
Sorry, I need to do a percent first.
Say no, I don't know what that is.
Well, what I can do is say, well, load magic
from this line profiler package.
And now you have lprun, which is available.
So how do you know that lprun is available?
You have to look at the package documentation.
And now what you can ask lprun
is to run this specific function or functions
and track the performance of this one.
So that means run the line profiler.
So line profiler run, track the function to optimize.
And while here I'm running the same function,
but I might have some other code that runs that
and run to optimize with 1,000 iteration.
And if I do that, well, my code is going to be way slower,
but I'm going to have a nice breakdown
of how much time each line is taking.
So you have the line number,
how many times a line was executed,
the times a line took, the times per,
like time divided by the number of hits,
the percent of the total time,
and actually my code here.
And so here, well, you can see that,
well, my function was not super efficient.
You see, well, it's relatively good,
but I'm doing this computation
that takes about 30% of my time,
but it doesn't depend on j.
It's relatively easy, I know.
So here we were taking 322 millisecond.
Let's just try to move this one level above.
Oops.
Redefine and we run.
And if everything is fine, it should probably be faster.
It may take slower to text because if time it figure out
the function is faster, it will run more iteration.
So you see here that it ran each time,
it ran like 10 times in a row,
and my function is about twice as fast.
And now I can rerun my line profiler,
and you can see that, well, now the other
have increased in proportional time
because this one is basically now taking, well, 0%.
It's called way less often.
I'm going to skim that, but what you would see
is that it won't break down in sidelines,
but if you try to dive more into this function,
you will see that actually accessing the first
and second value takes time.
So it might be better to define ta and tb
and do ta plus equal and tb plus equal
and then we would shave a few more milliseconds,
a few more milliseconds.
Couple of nice things.
You probably work by Googling
and copy pasting from Stack Overflow.
You don't, I don't judge, I don't judge.
I'm only judging you, Paul,
because I know you answered to me on Stack Overflow,
so I'm copy pasting your code.
And so you will have some codes
that already have this prefix here
and it's sometimes relatively annoying to edit.
Well, we are going to strip that
and understand that it's actually Python code
so you can copy past.
If you want to amaze your coworker,
as that works also in the pure terminal,
if you are in the notebook, what you can do
is actually do multi-line editing.
So if you press, I believe on Mac, it's alt,
you can do rectangle selections.
You can also put many cursors by pressing command
and putting a cursor in many location
and type in three places at once.
Can you do that again?
Can you do that again was the question.
Yes, I'm going to do that, I'm going to do something else,
I'm going to replace a variable with something else.
So I'm going to use my mouse and I'm going to use my thumb
to press on the command key on Mac.
I believe on Windows it's control, I wouldn't bet on it.
And now what I can do is actually click on several locations.
So I keep command pressed and I'm going to click here
and click here and that thing, that's all.
And now I'm going to write b-r-a-c-a-d-a-b-r-a.
And now I have a variable that has been changed several times.
I believe you can also do double click
to select three variables.
So if I double click, I will select three variables
and get back to a.
And here I have four cursors,
so this one I had to get rid of.
That was fine.
Do it.
Do it again.
Okay.
You can just, you know how in your text editor
you can have one cursor.
You can actually drop many.
Like it's exactly the same interaction
as you normally have with your text editor,
except on Mac if you press command
and on Windows if you press control I believe,
instead of removing the previous one,
it will create a new one.
So if I do command, here I have a cursor here,
if I do click, click, click, click,
I will have five cursors.
So it's the original one plus four new ones.
And now if I press a key,
the value will be done at those five locations.
So whether I insert a, in which case I have a,
I mean I'm not going to do a because it's hard to see,
I'm going to do x because it's bigger,
I now have five x's.
If I press delete, it's going to delete one character
at all my cursors.
So if I want to change a variable,
I can create a cursor after the first one,
I'm going to press command and click after the first,
the second one and the third one.
So now I have three cursors, one after each A,
and I type.
It's, I mean here it's easier,
if it's something bigger you will do search and replace,
right?
You wouldn't do that.
But it's possible if you want to do some,
some editing,
but if you want to, you can also select the words.
So if I double click on Abra Cadabra, I will select it.
So if I double click here without pressing command,
I will select this one.
And if I double click here, I will select this one.
What I'm going to do is select the first one,
start to press command, double click on the second one,
double click on the third one.
And now I have that selected three times,
and now I can change it to PyCon.
And there I have PyCon three times.
Thank you.
I, yeah.
So the library,
so libraries that does that,
almost none of that was written by the Jupiter folks.
It's written by the underlying library,
which is called card mirror.
So I'm going to get the,
let me do that.
Code mirror.
So code mirror.net,
this has a number of plugins and nice documentation
on what you can do in your text editor.
That's what does the highlighting and so on and so forth.
So thanks to the author of this library
if you really like multi-line editing.
It doesn't work for me.
Doesn't work for you.
Let's see.
Because control click is the,
it's like a right click.
Is command click.
Yeah, command click.
Command, yes.
It's command or Apple for some of you
who had Mac for a long time.
Because it used to be an Apple on the key
before it was this weird clever things with for loops.
Okay.
And if you use IPython in the terminal,
you will see also those things
and it also take care of those things for you.
If you're scared about tracebacks,
you want to look at the X mode magic
which remove some of the information in traceback
to be less scary.
Or if you like tracebacks,
you can make it more verbose
and it will try to find the actual value
of the local variable.
So here we are going to create several functions
and we're going to divide by zero
which usually computer don't like.
Maybe in JavaScript they like it, I don't know.
So that's usually what you get.
You get your stake trace.
You are in mode G and you called F
and in F you called X minus one.
If you know what you're doing
and you remember all your 10,000 function,
you figure out that X was one,
so X minus one is zero.
But it can be hard to get everything in your head.
So if you do X mode plain,
it will actually give you less information.
Instead of showing you context,
you see that here I have the line before
and the line after.
Here I don't have context.
I only have where the error are.
If you have really long stack trace, it's helpful.
But in our case, we probably want to do verbose.
And you see that the difference is
it will try to say, well, what is the value of G?
And G is a function.
What is the value of F?
F is this function and also Y is equal to zero.
And if in here, if Y is equal to zero,
Y plus one is one.
So now in F, we actually have X equal one when you do this.
So we actually have figured out
that here we divide it by zero.
So of course, here is a toy example,
but in big code, it might be relatively convenient.
Of course, when you do that, it makes IPython slower
and it's not on by default
because you might write codes
that deals with password and authentication tokens.
And so it's not on by default
and you can get back to the original value,
which is context.
Let's go fast and we are going to go to break after.
If you want to, we have some magic
that allow you to run different languages.
So here we write Perl, here we write Ruby
and it works to process the same as bang.
You can also run a debugger.
So if you had a trace back just after you do debug,
you're going to be in PDB.
If you know about PDB, you can learn about that.
So you're basically stopped in the middle of the stack trace
and you can say, well, what is the value of X?
X is one.
Let me go back into G.
What is the value of Y?
It's zero.
Let's go back to F.
So you can debug interactively.
So that's post-mortem debugger just to present debug.
Don't forget to press exit once you're done.
Otherwise you won't be able to continue executing code.
You can ask the user for input.
No, it's too slow.
So you can get user inputs.
And the one that you probably see often
is matplotlib inlines that allow matplotlib
to actually display things directly inside your notebook.
You might see often sometimes other value here.
So if you want the Windows to pop up,
you can change to Qt or WX or OSX
depending on which platform you are.
We're not going to do that.
And I'm just going to stop with this one.
Something we might want to see later,
but Dennis is not here, so we're probably going to go fast.
If you want to transform a function
into something more interactive,
I would advise for you to look for what Jupyter widgets are,
and in particular the IPY widgets package.
So if you import interact from IPY widgets
and you use at interact, you don't have to put all of that
unless you want to do some modification
on top of a function.
What it will do, it will try to automatically
make a GUI for you where you can tweak parameters.
So for example here, I've just copied and pasted
the code that was above,
and it made a function with a plot,
and it say well, I want my color to be,
the value of color here to be either C0, C1, or C2.
My function is either to be a sign or a cosine,
and I saw that lambda is a float value,
so I'm going to automatically make a slider
to make you change lambda.
And so now if I want to see how this function change
when I change lambda, I move it,
and it's going to recompute it and re-plot it.
And so now I can basically say,
oh, here is a sign, here is a cosine,
and actually wants the cosine to have color C1.
So now if you want to have some interaction,
you can do that using interact.
You can build some relatively complex UI
if you go deep into this package.
But usually using a single line after a function,
you can basically get something which is interactive.
And I think it's 10.13, so we have two minutes before breaks.
We're going to stop the recording for a few minutes,
but you get some stretch your legs, get some coffee,
and get back for the second round.
So here is a rigid,
spreadable object for race.
I have some Jupiter stickers in the front if you want some.
Stickers and stickers.
Yes.
They need to be rewritten.
In Jupiter notebook you have a single instance of the notebook.
And in Jupiter lab you may have several instances.
And so you basically get assumptions or extensions that you only have one notebook.
And so you can't just...
Because everything was global in the previous one.
Yes.
But the story for extension is way better in Jupiter lab because it's officially supported.
There is actual APIs, there is stability.
There is a lot of stuff that you can do.
So I have to wait until that particular person transfers.
Or you rewrite it.
Thank you.
Two very specific questions.
One of them, for the multi-line select, the S code, there's a control T that will take
the highlighted variable.
Yes, it's there.
I don't remember how to do it.
I think it's not in the default key map, but it's possible.
Because you can...
Because one of the things is settings.
We won't see that.
Advanced setting editor.
Card mirror.
Control D is sublime, right?
Yes.
And then you can change the settings.
Card mirror.
Control D is sublime, right?
It's VS code.
I think it's originally sublime.
Are you going to highlight first, maybe?
I'm pretty sure no, but I've seen it.
But control D is already mapped to something else.
But yeah, you can do it.
You can go into the specific settings of code mirror.
I don't know how.
And yes, you can bind your own keyboard.
And then, other question.
In the spider ID, there's like a double percentage magic that is like an auto reload for imports.
Yes.
Does that exist?
I mean, it's actually come from my Bible.
Oh, yeah.
I figured.
But I never see it.
It's one of my later demo.
I can show it to you now.
Well, yeah, we're probably going to have to speed up because I'm 15 or 20 minutes late on my schedule.
So I want to show some of the latest.
But yes, it works.
And we're improving it.
The latest version of Python can do things with auto reload.
The previous couldn't.
It is limited, right?
It won't do everything.
But I think since the latest version, it's our two versions, two small versions ago,
it can actually remove and add methods from classes that it used to not do.
It used to only add or reload.
But now it's actually more.
You can always just pull up a terminal and make a new environment and have that one in the background.
Yeah.
I'm just too happy with mine.
I'm going to be representing this nation.
OK.
Thanks.
I have a few tutorials on separate things, tutorials, just trying to learn.
We just set up environments where I'm using the tool.
So I think here, I figured out some little things.
So I was able to like create a chart stream, I chose the widgets to render.
And I wanted that because I didn't do this in the virtual environment.
In other places, I've done it in the room.
So I need to install each installation of JupyterLab and the separate projects I'm working on.
I need to install the widgets in that environment, not just like...
Yes.
Well, the other thing you can do is we can discuss that later, but you can actually install JupyterLab once outside of the environment.
But after we sum up what you can do is actually you see here is Python 3.
What you can do is here select the environment.
So you can have one JupyterLab with many environments.
It's not super easy, but it's doable.
If you want to have one notebook in Python 3, one notebook in Python 2 in the same JupyterLab, it's possible.
And usually that's how I am set up.
Like basically I will have one JupyterLab or one JupyterNotebook and I just say, oh no, I want this notebook to be in this environment, this notebook to be in this environment.
And then you don't need to do the lab extension in the environment.
You can do the lab extension outside of the environment.
You still need to have the widgets, the IqI widget installed in the environment, but that's way easier because it's just bit.
I think that's the reason I didn't understand.
The extensions needed to also be in the environment every other time I use it.
Yeah, no, it's not always obvious.
Yeah, and we can work on that.
See if I can get something to drink.
Yeah.
First.
So all we did was.
It's the instruction is not working.
There is a binder.
Yeah, it's working.
Got stuck in a very interesting.
Do you dare try it again?
Double clicking something in the item.
You're stuck in.
It's depending whether you press command or not.
If you press command and click, it won't behave the same as if you just click.
Don't do it.
How do you try turning it up and down again?
That's sounds about right.
Okay.
Yeah.
Depends what people are doing.
So you speak to the friends.
So yeah, it might be that might be memory.
You probably have to talk to that folks.
So yeah, usually, usually people who use pandas and you learn stuff because pandas a lot of copy our memory down.
But do you have your own server or your own Amazon cloud?
Is it is it like your physical machine or is it it's your physical?
Is it's.
Academic research.
Company.
Okay.
So Jupiter habit itself won't take much.
What what what you might want to look at is our users living long time notebook where they don't interact.
They forgot to forget to shut down the notebook.
And if that's the case, you might want to look into some Jupiter that automatically stop the book that are not running.
If someone has not been interacting for minutes, just stop it.
And so then you will use less resources in general.
Otherwise, I would suggest to start to look at things that are not to be there have been inside using like Dask distributed and other stuff that allow you to distribute things across many computers.
And where where usually you want to set up things in a way where you have is actually a small machine.
And what it does is just a font that will start each user on a different machine.
And that's how you would say that's how you would scale to 700 users.
I'm not the best person to talk about that.
You can try to talk with Paul, but most of the developer who are doing that are not here.
So I won't be that helpful.
Yeah, but that's a great point.
And one of the questions is if one user wants to share his notebook, is that enough on the source side to make that notebook read by text?
So, yes, as long as two people don't open the same notebook at the same time.
It's basically like if two people were to open the same file in Vim or in Emacs or in the last one who writes Win.
We had a prototype. We have a prototype of real time collaboration that works with Google document.
The problem is Google deprecated that so we can't release it.
It works, but you need you need as a user for your account when you set up, you need to go to Google and say, oh, I want an API key and you can't create new ones.
So we can't we can't release it because it works, but it's useless unless you already have a key.
And anyway, I know that your girl is going to shut that down.
And so most of the work is now to actually rewrite the backend of the right.
So write some some collaboration.
And once you have a time collaboration, yes, you will have ways of saying, well, like Google document, you open a notebook, you send a URL to your collaborators and they just open something.
And they just like basically.
So it does to save.
So if you when you execute to actually change the notebook and it will auto save.
But if you set the permission right, if you set the permission to read, write for the owner and read only for the group on Unix, that's fine.
Yes, they just won't be able to save the modified version.
They will. They might get some error messages in the thing.
Oh, this is really only our X, Y, Z, but that should be fine.
Sure.
Where is he?
OK, so you can talk to him about oh, he's just there with a green shirt.
It's fine. It's OK. It's it's it's it's a sticky thing is is not sticky anymore.
On the what?
No, nothing.
I OK. Good. Good.
Sweet.
I know some people in the core team as we're working on the robot framework.
I think you should talk to Nick Bollweg.
In Google, Jupiter dash R.S. and those folks would be really happy to get to get feedback from you.
I can't. I have to to leave on Sunday morning.
Ask ask Paul and let you hear in the green shirt if they are here.
I think Paul will do will do it.
I think we are happy to get to get some contribution.
Uh huh.
Oh, you mean a lot of my frame in Jupiter?
I don't know, but probably I'm not the right person to ask.
I would ask Paul who is standing over there with a black coat.
He might direct you to the right person.
Oh, yeah, that's not too far away.
You probably mean the.
So you can also you can also display JavaScript as a probably need an extension for Jupiter lab, but you can you can display JavaScript and get the handle on the elements where you do whatever you want.
Should we restart slowly? At least I'm going to give you tips to blew up your colleagues mine.
So how many of you write math, use gamma Greek letters and stuff like that often?
We have two people that know how to write Greek.
Okay, so sometimes you want to have, you know, we are always told that don't use variable names with only one letter.
So, of course, you use, you know, you use alpha beta because it's easier.
What you can actually do in in in IPython is if you actually want an alpha, you will precede it by a backslash.
You know, like in LaTeX and you should press tab and you will get an alpha.
And if it's a if it's a derivative or actually a second derivative, you can put a double dot on it and you can say that it's equal to whatever.
And so now you can have your your variables that are that are extremely compact.
And so you can do that with many of the things like if you want to have a force with a vector on top.
Well, here I don't have the font, but you can do you can do stuff like that.
Can I use emojis and things like that?
Well, no, because they're not supported identifiers by by Python.
We only complete two things that will be actually recognized as variable names.
So you can't you can't do that. Not not all the things are recognized by Python as as actual variables.
There are a few a few gotchas like epsilon and var epsilon are actually exactly the same.
So they can look different.
But if I do if I do epsilon press tab equal one and I ask the value of var epsilon, it's also one.
So that's something like that. Same for phi and var phi.
What? So I know some people really like that.
But it was just to get your attention so that we can we can restart.
Why? Can you try to force refresh? Yes.
So if for some of you, the widgets don't work, try to force refresh because sometimes your browser will cache Jupiter lab.
The first Jupiter lab, if it doesn't, we can figure that out exactly how to install things correctly so that you have you have widgets.
We won't do much with jets. So that's a good good thing.
OK, let's slowly move forward and let make you Python experts at things that not a lot of people on Earth understand,
which is a second notebook. So I'm going to let's do things slowly.
I'm going to close this notebook, say no, I don't want to save it.
I'm going to go to these things where you have a person running hopefully on your laptop.
I don't have it. I don't know why.
So when you close the document, you have the document and you have the computation back end.
You need to shut down the computation back end as well as the kernel.
You see that I have here one which is still attached to to one beyond playing Python.
I'm going to shut that down to free some of the resources on my laptop.
You don't have to right now, but if you have tens of notebooks, they can still run in the background and use use memory and a little bit of of CPU.
And I'm going to reopen the second one.
So again, I can I can open and collapse things by clicking here.
And once you open this one, you should see here is that now you have a notebook notebook running.
Depending on what you're doing and what you're working on, you may have heard about new thing in Python called a sink and a wait.
And you most likely have heard that things are super complicated and it's hard to run.
And we tried to make that pretty easy for you, especially if you're interacting with remote resources like if you're downloading your eyes or something like that.
I think in a way it can be useful for you to make this mixing concurrent.
So not parallel. There is a slight difference.
It won't make your code magically faster, but it may make some of the tasks you're doing when you're waiting from something which is remote easier to work with.
So just as a quick introduction, I think in a way I'm trying to understand what it is.
It allows Python to interleave tasks.
And so usually the way your computer does that on a day to day basis is just stop a task in the middle of what it's doing.
The CPU does that magically and it's not another task.
And so you may have heard about threads when you do thread that you have different tasks and you have preemptive multitasking.
The CPU will suddenly say, no, you stop and you start.
So that's that's the OS level.
What we can do is move that at some point at the Python level.
But we need some kind of agreement.
And so to take a metaphor, when you're going to a restaurant and you're going to get seated to a table, the waiter will be able to take care of several people at once.
It will be able to take your orders and the order of the next person.
But you have social conventions that tell us when the waiter can move from your table to another.
It's not he's not going or she's not going to to leave your table while you're giving your order.
And at the same time, the convention is that you won't hold the waiter here if you're still reading the reading the menu.
No, no, it's fine. I'm not ready.
You can take care of somebody else.
And that's basically what I think in a way are in Python.
You basically have to say at which point Python or the scheduler is allowed to move from one point to another.
And so that's why you can have this weird syntax.
We say, well, if I have a function which is a sink, it may be interrupted in the middle.
Like basically a function going to the restaurant is going to be a sink because while you're going to the restaurant, you may at some point like the waiter can go somewhere else.
And so if you try to do that, some of what I've seen here in pure Python or a top level in the Python file and do Python dot my Python file, it might not work.
So let's let's deactivate I Python automatic integration with this magic as you can await and try to run some code.
And so let's say, well, instead of wait, importing from time, I'm going to import probably zoom a tiny bit import from as in K.O.
And I say, well, sleep five seconds.
I didn't sleep because you actually need to to await sleep because sleep you say, well, you can do something else while you're sleeping.
But if you do that in pure Python, it will just say, no, it's a syntax error.
I don't know how to do that.
Let's keep a bit about exactly how you would try to solve that.
And that doesn't work.
And so what you can do in a Python is start with auto it equal true and say, well, if you see in a wait and I haven't told you how to deal with that, do something magic.
And so now what we can do in a Python that we can do in pure Python is just have a sleep five within the wait.
And then you have before and after and it's set for five seconds.
So sleep is not really interesting.
So let's try to do some some interesting things and get fifty try to get fifty results from an API of ice and fire characters.
Let's get the fifty first character from this API.
You may have guessed where this is coming from if you're watching HBO on Sunday.
And so let's try to get like ask for the first character, get it and do a loop with that.
But you will see that in a normal Python, if you use requests, if you use request before or you are a lib, what's happening is it's relatively fast.
But you see that you start a request, get the response and start the next request after the first response came back.
So here I have only 50. And so it took quite some time.
And if you look at the CPU of my machine, it was not going to the maximum.
It was basically doing only one task at a time.
And most of the time it's pain waiting for something to happen.
And so what I think in a way it will allow you to do is to do that concurrently.
The computer will be able to start many connections at once without having to use threads and start the request for the first character and start the request for the second character before the request from the first characters ended.
If you want to really know more about how to use that, I would suggest one of this afternoon tutorial on AOHTDP.
We are just going to see how we can use that.
And so what you can do with in Python is to just import AOHTDP, which is similar to requests, except every now and then you have to await the object.
And when you object, what awaits the object, something else can run at the same time.
So this is how to use AOHTDP.
You have to create a session and then you have to manipulate this session and ask this session to get things.
So let's try to get a single result.
So here is someone who knows nothing.
Let's put that in a function async def like that.
And let's see if we can just.
So this function is async def because it uses await.
You can't use await in functions that don't have async.
That's about everything you need to know.
And now we're going to again do this client session and await getting this character.
And again, this just works in IPython or in pure Python.
It will be a syntax error.
So now if you want to speed up looking at who has died in the last season,
because everyone is dying anyway at some point in this show,
what you would do is do a for loop and you will create, you say, well, I want to have this 50 task
where I will get the character, the nth character.
And you create a list of those things that you want to do.
And what you will do after is just await from all of the things you wanted to do.
And because now they are, we can see here, they are async def.
It means that on this line, each of these functions you called can be run concurrently.
So you will have the 12th and the 23rd that will be running at the same time.
And so now hopefully what should happen is that we will fetch the first one
and start to fetch the second one before the first one is actually there.
And you see that, well, suddenly getting 50 of those characters was way, way faster
because we were able to actually start them all in a bunch.
And then hopefully if it took one second to get one character, it takes only one second to get 50.
Does that make some sense?
And so what you can see here is that, well, you might not exactly understand
how each of the library works and which call to do, but you won't have in IPython and in Jupyter,
you won't have to mess with creating your own event loop or submitting tasks or things like that.
You can just use normal syntax at top level without having to create an application and run the thing.
So that's just to tell you that if you want to touch async and await, you can do that.
It's not as scary as people show you online.
And we've been working hard on that.
If you don't want to use async IOs, there are also other libraries that do async and await that are sometimes easier to use.
And so what you can also do is tell IPython to use those.
So just to show you, if you want to have two tasks that do things like one every two seconds and one every second,
we will use this other library.
So here we will create a function that sleeps for n seconds and then print a message.
I'm going to do it only 30 times just to avoid having an infinite loop.
I'm going to tell IPython to use trio because here I'm using sleep from trio and not async IO.
And what I will do here is start two tasks.
One, I will start every task every one second to print plick and the other one every two seconds to print pluck.
Choose less.
And now everything is fine.
You have two concurrent tasks running in your notebook.
So if you're interacting with a remote service and you want to check something periodically,
you can do that relatively easily and you see that it keeps running.
It keeps working.
And you didn't have to use threads.
So that's some of the new features in IPython 7.
I don't remember.
I'm going to interrupt that.
And let you, is everyone okay?
Do you want to play with that or is it maybe too advanced?
Now I'm going to go back to the terminal because IPython is about powers running Python
and even if things are possible in the notebook, they're also possible at the shell.
So what you can do is you can either follow along in the browser.
What you can do is go there, create a new, scroll down and a new terminal.
Or if you have your own terminal you like, you can also go in your own terminal
and don't forget to activate the PyCon 2019 environment.
And let me just use the light theme because I'm going to guess you're going to see better in the light theme.
If I can zoom in.
When you launch the terminal, does it just automatically launch whatever your default terminal on your system is?
Or is it always a batch?
So the question was if you launch a terminal, does it automatically launch a terminal on your system?
It should.
I know there might be some issue on Windows where it might not be able to,
sometimes it will try to run command on PowerShell.
And it might be some issues there where we might need to work on that on some machines.
Of course, if it's trying to run batch, you need to have batch installed.
Depending on how you, with Anaconda I don't remember exactly what it does on Windows,
but depending on how you install on Windows, it may sometimes start batch or sometimes start PowerShell,
depending on how you install it.
Okay, but on Mac or Linux it would just run whatever your default?
Yes, on Mac and Linux it would run whatever your default.
Yes, on Mac and Linux it would run whatever your default is.
And it's compared to other browser terminals, this is a full feature terminal.
So if I want to use Vim and play with Vim, I can use Vim in my terminal.
You don't have to, I'm a Vim person, I can't quit.
I'm stealing Paul's jokes.
Okay.
How did you launch the terminal?
How did I launch the terminal? Good question.
We're going to see the JupyterLab UI later, but usually if you go on the folder here,
you have these new things that create those panels here.
Let me reopen that and close the launcher.
If you press plus, it will open a launcher.
And the launcher allows you to create Python notebook.
I also have a bash kernel, so I can create bash notebook if I want to.
Console, you're not going to see that.
And terminal and text file.
And if I click on terminal, it should open a terminal here, which says terminal 2.
If I go to my running things here, I still see my old terminal, terminal 1.
So here I have my two terminals.
I'm going to close terminal 1, shut down terminal 1.
And I have my terminal 2 here.
I'm going to close my notebook and shut down my notebook.
Again, I'm going to go there, click plus, and I can go to terminal.
Or if you close all your tabs, the launcher automatically appear and you can go to terminal.
What does the little red X indicate in your terminal?
So that's a custom thing that tells me that I have a Git repository and the Git repository has changes.
It's not specific to Jupyter.
It's specific to how I configure my machine.
And that tells me I am in the PyCon 2019 branch.
I need to do, I need to do conda activate PyCon 2019.
If I want to be in the PyCon 2019 environment.
And if I want to change my PS1, if that is too long, I just need to call up that.
That's more bash things, but you can do PS1 equal to H.
No space.
That's work. I don't know why. Anyway, probably did something wrong.
Whatever, that's my own configuration. Sorry about that.
Let's erase the screen and let's start IPython as a repo.
So that's a pure terminal IPython. That's strange. It's 7.2. It will be 7.5. Anyway.
So unlike normal Python repo, we have way more feature in the terminal as well.
It is a full-fledged terminal. It's not using a kernel like a notebook.
Which means that something that you can't do in a notebook, you can do in a terminal.
So for example, you've seen in a notebook that I was using cat.
And I don't remember the name of the file that we did was log.py.
So in the notebook, I did cat log.py.
But one thing I didn't tell you is that you can't run commands in a notebook that asks you to interact with them.
Like in a notebook, you wouldn't be able to do bang-vim or the notebook will hang.
In the pure terminal, you can actually call things like that.
So if I do bang-vim log.py, I remember you that bang runs something in an underlying shell.
Now I should be able to just edit my log file.
And quit if you know how to quit. Or you can use nano if you prefer to use nano if you know what you're doing in a terminal.
I can exit. It just means that you have more power when you want to run subcommands in the terminal.
Especially subcommands, we will ask you to interact with them.
If you want to do app get install and interact, you can't do that from a notebook. You can do that from the terminal.
It also means that we allow you to do some of the stuff in the terminal that is easy.
If you define a function, let's say I define a Fibonacci which is definitively wrong because it returns one.
And actually Fibonacci needs to take a number.
After some time, it's going to be annoying to write something really long.
So what you can do is you can actually configure a Python to tell it what your preferred editor is.
And use, well I want to edit my Fibonacci function.
And it will create a temporary file and now you're in your favorite text editor.
And you can edit your function.
If you like to use blind text or VS code or atom, those editors have specific flags that you need to pass to them for this to work.
But you can configure and say well open an atom window and when I close the atom window tell IPython to continue where it is.
So now you can properly define your function.
Yes.
So you see that now I saved and quit my editor.
And it brought me back to IPython and updated my Fibonacci.
Now if I do Fibonacci 3 and I will redo that again.
Now it's returning 2 which is still wrong but principal.
So you define a function. Let's say you define a function.
My function.
And you want to edit it at some point in the future.
Once you've configured properly IPython you can do percent edit which is one of the line magic we've seen.
We haven't seen but it's a line magic because it starts with percent and then you tell it the object you want to edit.
So my underscore function.
And what it will do it will squeeze error message without my system.
It will create a temporary file on this.
Invoke your editor to edit this file in a blocking manner.
Whatever.
Now you can edit that.
So if you haven't configured by default it's going to be Vim so you might want to have to quit.
So you edit your function.
So I want to write in Vim so I'm going to press I to be in edit mode.
In insert mode so you know that there is insert here.
Now you say you.
You change your function using your editor to return a value.
It's Vim so I need to press escape and it's press colon WQ.
And now my function is has been updated.
My.
Function.
I need to call it if I want to get the value.
That's not the best way to do it but it's just to show you that you can interact if you want to.
You can you will see that we already have a lot of things like Python.
We have syntax highlighting.
We have type completion as well.
Which is relatively advanced like in the notebook.
Import numpy as NP.
If I do NP dot and I press tab.
It should get it should take some time at the beginning to show up because it did inspect things.
It gives you all the completion you can do.
And one of the recent new thing is when you highlight one of them it will try to give you the type here.
And if it's a function it should try to tell you the signature of the function.
So here it didn't have the chance to complete everything when it said unknown.
When it says unknown it needs to actually get some more time to complete things.
So I re-invoke the computer.
And you see that now your functions you have parentheses because they are functions.
And it will give you the signature of the function here.
So you know that's numpy add new doc.
Well add new doc is maybe not super interesting.
But maybe maybe array is.
And you see that array is a function that take an object that you type.
Whether you need to copy which order and other parameters.
And so one of the things we have especially in IPython.
Yes.
I'm sorry but what mode are you in right now?
Is that a terminal? A console?
So that's a terminal. That's a pure terminal.
I'm doing that in my browser but I could do that in iTerm if I wish to.
I can open iTerm which is super small.
And I could do IPython in my terminal.
And now I have IPython.
Oh you're in a terminal and you ran IPython. Okay.
Yes.
So that works on a remote cluster if you're on a ssh or something like that.
Let me come back to this.
So Matt says that using IPython to write some quick Python is way better than using idle.
Not my words.
Well yeah because we have syntax highlighting.
Again we have syntax highlighting.
You will see a lot of tutorials that tell you to use a Python repel.
For quick things here we have multi-line editing.
If you do for i in range 10, print i.
Well you want to do range 12.
In the normal Python repel you can't go up.
You have to rewrite the thing.
In IPython you can.
It's a small thing but a lot of really small things that are helpful.
And so that should just work.
What was I going to say?
Yes.
But one of the things that you might want to do is develop a library next to it or have some code you want to update that you don't want to iterate over in a notebook or prefer in a file.
So I have here demoautoreload.py.
It's a small library I used that I was bad at math at the time that tried to compute the square of a number.
It's definitely wrong.
It's multiplied by two but it works with a equal to actually.
If I did a equal to and I had to square it, it works.
And I want to develop that.
So one of the things you may have learned is that you can't reload a Python module.
You have to quit your interpreter and come back if you change your py file.
We do our best to allow you to do that in IPython.
You have to opt in.
And so let's try to do the normal mode.
Let's do from demoautoreload import my class.
And then do c equal my class of two.
Well, because it works with two and like as a square of two and it's definitely four.
It works right.
If we do with four, well, c square is not right.
That's not supposed to be eight, 16, probably a factor of two somewhere.
Here, if you were to modify that and put actually square, it wouldn't work.
So let's quit IPython and restart just for the sake of restarting.
And this time we are going to do load ext.
Go back to the beginning.
Autoreload.
So that's set up something in IPython.
It's now slower, but it has some capabilities of really reloading code on the fly.
There are different modes.
You have either explicitly telling it what you want to reload or just try to reload as much as you can.
We're going to be lazy and do autoreload mode two, which is try to reload as much as you can.
And now we're going to go back and import my class.
We're going to create c, which is my class of 10, because square of 10 is relatively easy to compute.
I don't remember the other one.
And realize that c square is wrong.
But now if everything works fine, if I update my file with just a new star, I save it.
Don't forget to save and compute c square.
It has updated our thing and we didn't have to to read our code.
So here it's relatively simple, but you may have a big data set in the library where you want to run something on the data set.
And the data set might take like five minutes to load.
Same thing is if you do if you do c cube.
Well, that does not exist.
I'm going to do the same thing that you apparently liked earlier is to select multiple things and delete at once.
Question.
Does it work if a module import another module?
It depends.
It's we do it's the best effort.
Well, not in the sense that we do as little as we can and we just want to tell you that we're doing our best we can.
But we literally do as much as we can.
But not everything works.
It's it's really on a case by case basis.
If you really want to be sure you have to restart your your your session.
So I know some of the things that don't work.
I know some of that works, but it depends.
It does more.
If you use import live with a reload function, it uses that internally plus some other things.
But as for his question, if you wanted to force it to reload something, I use it reload.
Well, it's it does it does use import live reload, but it does some extra things on top.
So using import live reload explicitly will probably not do more than what auto reload does.
Maybe.
But I'm unsure.
And another question there.
So that's correct.
And that's what I'm going to show there just after is if you change some if you change in it, you would need to you have to reinstated the glass like we can attach and remove things.
But things that happen in it are not propagating.
So let's just do it.
Cube is now defined.
But if I do something like self be equal one over a.
C.B. will not be defined.
I will have to redo C called my class and see that.
So we do as much as we can, but we can't do everything.
Everything that has like all the we try to reattach method.
We try to update things.
And so you will have weird H case.
But that is extremely useful when you actually want to develop a library.
Because you can have something which is almost as if you were to completely rerun your scripts.
But it will try to update as much as possible from your name space.
I would again advise you to look at authority load question mark.
So that's that's a bit big.
So let's do that.
It tells you what are the different different things you have to do the one or two or two or zero.
To try to do as much as it can.
If you do it or reload one, you can't just import something you use.
You have to use percent auto auto reload import.
And if you do that, it will only try to reload this specific things.
It can't reload things that are compiled in C.
If some of you develop C is right.
See, but I would advise.
I think that's that's good enough.
Is there anything else I wanted to say about that?
So that's about it.
So that's I don't have a comment question.
So is there a way to say what you've done in the console in the Jupyter notebook?
We've seen one thing at the beginning of our session that was history.
And history will tell you everything you've done in your console.
And so now what you can do is actually make it to a file and.
Oops, I forgot.
Come back.
You do history to the one or two.
Oh, and you need to do one hundred.
You can get previous sessions.
I don't remember how to do that.
Yeah, there you go.
So one session ago, line one from one hundred.
Take me if you want to.
Technically, every all of that is stored in a SQL database in your home.
So don't type your passwords in clear.
Like, don't put like don't put password equal and your actual password.
Because otherwise it will be stored in this SQL database.
You can project, you can do stuff.
But yeah, everything is also you can come back in time, see when what was done.
And small result or string small result are also stored in the database.
So you can also react to some of the outputs.
But that's that's the date.
Four was Jupiter.
Yes.
Can you what?
Can you play back on history?
Probably.
I wouldn't do it because often you have like a thing that you have to back and forth.
You often have mistakes.
So you probably want to expose your history to a file.
It is a file.
And then once you have once you have a file, you can actually you question was, can you replay a history?
You can use the run magic.
So run magic allow you to in different ways or options to run a Python file almost as if you had typed it into the report.
You wouldn't get the input and outputs.
You could.
There are options.
There are many options.
But I mean, at some point, I want to discourage you for just doing that and more thinking if I have a thing that I run often, you want to make a Python module out of that.
You want to make functions and you want to call your functions.
You don't want to venture too far from normal Python.
And at some point, there is convenience.
And once you move away from convenience, you can make them into a into a PY file.
We have a sarcastic comment from from Matt in the back says that there is a nice things to track snippet of code called notebook.
Yeah.
He does help with these type of things.
He is tracking the history of course.
He can delete the things you don't care about as you go.
That's quite more of a value.
There is.
You have different different way of of doing various things.
And I have something in my head that I forgot now.
It's fine.
Plenty of things.
Look at the IPY documentation on IPY.
There is way more on that question.
So does the database also store history for the input?
It does store some of the outputs.
I don't remember the exact criteria.
But yes, I believe if they're small and purely text and less than I don't remember hundred characters, they are going to be stored.
So now I was going to go to the folder number four and going to describe a tiny bit of the Jupiter lab UI so that you know a tiny bit what you can do if you're working in the browser.
So you've already played a bit with it.
One of the features of the Jupiter lab is that everything is a plugin.
So every event, the core components are plugins.
And if you want to swap them, you can.
So that means that it's extremely, extremely flexible.
I'm going to unzoom a tiny bit to to be able to get some real estate because now the exact content of things are not that important.
You've already been familiar with the launcher.
If you install a different kernel, the kernel will allow you to run to create notebooks in different languages.
So here you see that I have to have Python and I have bash.
You can change after the fact.
So here I created a Python notebook.
You say that it says Python three here.
I can't change it to actually be bash.
And so now I'm not writing Python.
I actually do bash.
If you have several virtual environments or condom environments, there is also one way to have here Python for each of the condom environments.
I'm not going to do that today.
The other possibility and we're not going to dive into that too much because of time is if you have already a notebook with a kernel, you can attach another notebook to the same kernel.
So you're basically sharing namespace.
You're sharing your assets.
You're sharing your functions.
But you might want to have a scratch pad where you just to run some small analysis and an actual notebook that you want to do for a report.
And that's possible here again.
You just create a notebook and you just attach to.
So how do I got that?
I'm going to read it.
So here it tells you which language your notebook is in.
It's actually not which language is usually which kernel.
The name of the kernel doesn't have to be equal to the language, but it's a default.
So here you see that I have Python 3, I have bash.
I could have something called Python 3.8 or I could have a kernel called PyCon if I wanted to.
That's specific to each kernel and how to do that.
So you're just going to go to go here to the one where this is just a quick way of doing it.
There are more generic way of doing things.
You do have to have the kernel installed.
You probably don't have bash.
I have because I have it installed.
And it's across all of the Jupyter things.
So if you use Ntract or if you use integration with VS code, you will be able to see those kernel as well.
This indicator that you might have seen is kernel busy.
So when the thing is doing computation, it will be black.
So import time and not bash.
I want to actually do Python now.
Time dot sleep 10.
You see that it's actually busy running.
So that's a quick way of knowing whether computation are actually happening or if something is just stuck.
You will also see that the number becomes a star when something is running.
But this is slightly more accurate.
You have a number of shortcuts here.
Change the type of a cell to markdown if you want to actually write some markdown and then press shift enter to render.
So it's relatively similar to the normal notebook.
I'm not going to go too much into detail of what you can do in a normal notebook.
I will let you play with that.
You have the restart kernel.
So if you're not sure what's happening and what you have done and have not done, if you press that and you press restart,
then the kernel has been killed and a new one starts.
Now you have a fresh namespace on which you can be referencing one by one and make sure that your computation actually does the right thing.
The shortcut to restart is when you're not editing a cell, but when you're actually in command mode, you can press 00 twice.
And it will bring the same data.
Question.
Question about the cells.
In the notebook, there's a plug-in that you want to convert in.
You don't need to make a hard point to convert into a presentation.
Rise?
Yes. Is that the same thing we would use in the left?
So the question is, there is a plug-in or normal notebook called Rise for Reveal, JS, IPython, Slideshow extensions that allow you to convert a notebook into a slideshow.
Is there the same thing for JupyterLab?
I'm not sure it has been completely updated to run with JupyterLab, but because the files are the same and exactly the same,
what you can do is close it in JupyterLab, go to Help and launch Classic Notebook.
And now you're back to the classic UI.
And from the classic UI, then you can open your things and start the Rise plug-in if you're a Rise user.
Or for any extensions that does not work with JupyterLab yet, you can just come back to the old interface and use that.
Don't open the same notebook into interface at once because it's the last one that writes to disk that will win.
So I'm not going to go into detail on how to go to normal notebook.
But let me just go back to the tree here.
And go back to Lab.
And I should be back here.
And the command that Matt said is that there are also command line tools for all of that.
So you can also use the command line tools.
One other thing you should question.
The question was, is there a difference between starting JupyterLab, changing the, like what I did,
help launch Classic Notebook and change the URL to slash tree?
No, it's the same.
It will work in some circumstance.
It kind of is aware of JupyterLab and things like that.
But it's mostly that we don't actually want users and we should not need to know the URL structure.
So we have this nice shortcut as a convenience.
And it's actually not launching. There is nothing at launch. It's already running.
It's just like switching the URL.
One thing you should be really familiar with is this palette here called the command palette.
Here you will find all the action you can do in JupyterLab.
Regardless of whether they are in menus, in right clicks, or even not available anywhere.
Else, it's basically like searching everything you can do.
And you can see that you even have the shortcuts that are shown on the side here.
So for example, if I have a Notebook and I want to change the kernel from Python 3 to Bash,
which was one of the questions I had before, I would go to search.
I could either click here and get the select kernel, or I can Google here and do kernel,
and search for, I have restart kernel, I have clear all outputs, and I have the change kernel menu.
And if I click the change kernel, it will pop up this window here and ask me what kernel do I want.
And now I can switch to Bash.
You could do a lot of things. Let me open a bigger Notebook from before.
Let me reopen this one. I'm going to close my untitled one.
You see that I still have my prompt number of what I have done before,
but I want to basically clear everything, every output on my Notebook.
I would go to the command palette here and search for clear.
I have clear output for a person operation, and Notebook operation, I have clear all outputs.
And if I click that, well, all my outputs and prompts are now gone.
And so that's relatively useful.
And if you want to learn keyboard shortcut as well, which is at least on Mac,
if I'm here, I can press command shift C, and it will bring that.
And so now I can just look for what I want. I want to run all cells.
And now it's going to run all cells one by one until it finds an exception, and then it will start.
So if you want to run one Notebook completely from top to bottom,
you could restart your kernel to make sure your namespace is clean and then to run all cells.
And it will run them one by one until there's an exception.
And they say, oh, well, this was wrong.
And you can fix it and make sure that your Notebook is actually safe.
Because it's a completely new interface from the classic Notebook that some of you may have seen,
there's a lot of new features that were not possible in normal Notebook.
So I'm going to go back here.
I actually, oops, that's the exercise one. I want to open that.
We can render a Markdown file, for example.
So if I have a Markdown file and I double click, I will get the Markdown file.
Markdown might be hard to read.
So what you might want to do is right click here and say Open With and the Preview one.
And so now you actually have a render Markdown file, which is easier to read.
And to cut up that, and you might want to edit the Markdown file.
So that view is nice to edit. That view is nice to view.
So, well, can I have both?
Well, yes, you can drag tabs around.
So you can see that we've seen that before.
And you will have a blue indicator that shows you where on the screen you can put that.
And I'm going to put them side by side.
And they are actually different view on the same model.
Both are actually, like, if you edit one, the other one will update live.
So here is, with a few seconds of difference, some modifications.
And so now you can have the same thing open in two different ways.
So you can, for example, or even like the same one twice,
and you want to copy things over between two different locations.
So let me remove that.
So in the folder for JupyterLab UI, you should have some exercise.
And let's, well, I would suggest we take five or ten minutes to go through that
and try to play with UI.
There is some guideline here of things that you might want to try.
And so that you get a feeling of what you can do with JupyterLab.
And then we'll do, I'm going to run through that and show you all the features.
But I think it's best for you to take ten minutes to see what you can do.
Also, I'll show you some of the Python stuff you can do.
You have the sticky notes.
If you're already finished on board, you can put the green one.
If you have issues, you can put the red one.
If you want to go get something to drink, you can also get something to drink.
We have stickers in the front also, Jupyter stickers for your laptops.
Select.
It's fine.
I don't know what happened.
It seems to be enough.
And you can't run.
I don't know why.
It seems to work now.
That's relatively fast.
That's fine.
That's a normal error.
Error, yeah, this 10 is not the right number.
It seems to work now.
I don't know.
Maybe we can try to sit down later in the week and recheck everything if you still have issues.
Okay.
Right click on the tab of one.
And right click in the file itself.
Show Margon preview.
You can also in the file browser here, if you right click on the regular size one.
And you can also open it.
And you find either the editor or the Margon preview.
Sorry.
I just have a question for you.
I'm going to try to reach you.
I was making a note.
It's a pretty tricky thing.
I'm trying to do a good job.
So thank you.
Right click.
And then right click.
If you click in the middle, it will do Schumacher.
There are different ways.
Okay.
So that's it.
Thank you.
Okay.
So that's the typo for me.
We should file them.
Yeah.
Okay.
So I don't know.
So I think that's a good way to do it.
So we can use the free file.
So we can say to remind folks to find the file before with their browser.
Okay.
So that's what I wanted to find within here, but it's not yet.
So there is a typo.
You don't know Markdown?
No.
Okay.
I'm going to go through it.
So this is two star for bold, one underscore for italic.
Each side.
If you put hash at the front of the line, it's a header number.
Okay.
What about the math?
Each dollar.
Okay.
I have the example.
And single dollar is going to be nine math and double dollar is going to be display math.
Okay.
So that's the typo.
It's Jason or it's lower-case t or maybe, I don't know.
It's installed.
I don't know then.
We can try to debug that later in the world.
Maybe they can.
Yes, no, no, because the node is-
Is the node, yeah, yeah.
So it's trying to-
Okay, so it's the node, yeah.
Okay, let's try to move quickly forward.
Some of the solutions are in the example notebook here.
So some of the people struggle because I was too fast before.
So let me show again how to create these two markdown things.
You have several ways of doing it.
So if I double click on the exercise one dot markdown,
I get the edit view.
I can either right click on exercise one
and do open with markdown preview,
and then it will open a markdown preview,
and then I can put each of the preview
and the edit next to each other.
Or I can right click directly somewhere
in the markdown file and do show markdown preview.
I'm going to get rid of that,
and now I have the preview as well.
You can also try to click on the tab that some of you did.
You see that there is no way to get a preview,
but you can make a new view.
There are slight differences depending on where you click.
And one other thing that you might have seen
is create console for editor.
We're not going to dive too much into that,
but you can actually attach any file
in JupyterLab to a kernel.
And if you have here something that say print
hello, hello, hello, hello.
Hello, PyCon.
I'm just going to show you so that you know it's possible.
And close the triple quotes,
which is a way in markdown to show code blocks.
If you go there and press shift enter,
oh, missing a quote here, press shift enter,
you actually take the code block
and send it to the console to execute it.
So if you prefer to write something
more like R markdown but Py markdown,
you can do something similar.
Let's close that.
Let's reopen the app solution.
So what you see is here,
like we have some example of notebooks
that show what a few things you can do.
So here it's markdown.
If you press enter to edit,
or if you double click,
you will be able to edit.
I'll give you a quick reminder of the markdown syntax.
If you use GitHub or some other website,
you might know it.
We can have math, either display math,
when you have two dollar sign,
or in math you have a single dollar sign.
You can write a subset of LaTeX
and do shift enter to render some small differences
between when you use backtick for the language
with two Ls because my keyboard is broken.
Or four spaces, one will be highlighted,
the other will not.
One of the things that we've slightly seen before
is that objects do not need to be pure text.
They can actually be displayed as LaTeX,
or as PNG, or SVG, or interactive stuff.
We're going to see that later if we have time.
And then it's just,
how do you go through some of the kernel functionality,
like having a question mark to get some information,
how you could use,
you didn't import it so it won't work.
Import pandas as pd.
Press tab to actually complete the data frame.
Once I have my data frame,
I can use shift tab to get the signature.
We've seen that.
We've seen the shell escape with bang.
Now you can see how some object of some libraries
are already nice, represented in HTML,
and not purely text.
How matplotlib, as I was typing somewhere,
can actually render in your graphs.
If I don't execute everything, it won't work.
Let's print something long.
If you click here, you can collapse,
or if you right click, you should be able to find
how to make it scrollable.
I can't read from here.
Enable scrolling for output.
So if you have a long output,
so it don't take too much space,
you probably have read that you can,
when you see these four arrow things,
you can drag cell around.
If you have a second notebook next to it,
you can grab a cell,
you should be able to grab a cell
and move it between notebooks,
so you don't have to copy and paste.
There are a lot of small things like that
that make so many things
that I won't go through everything.
You have the shortcut here,
like undo cell operation, reduce cell operation.
And here, well, something if you want to,
to have some JavaScript, you can have some JavaScript.
You may have seen, depending on exactly how you do that,
hopefully when you load it the first time,
the things did not appear,
but on my machine it did,
because I already ran the full notebook once,
so we have a notion of trusted notebook.
There are security vulnerability
if a code you don't trust
can run JavaScript in your browser.
So once you have run a complete notebooks once
from top to bottom and saved it,
we will keep a file on your computer
that says that this notebook is trusted.
And so JavaScript that has is in this notebook,
because you were one of the last person
to completely run it from top to bottom,
this notebook is able to show JavaScript at load time.
So what you will see is that some notebook
might not look exactly the same
when you receive them from someone,
and after you have completely executed them,
if that makes sense.
If it doesn't, we can come back to us
and we can talk about that.
But basically everything which is JavaScript-based
and interactive plant-based might not appear
exactly as it does when you load a notebook
from an external source.
Any questions?
Is there a way to make it trusted?
Yes.
You go to the command palette and you can do trust notebook.
Well, in that case, when you do that, we trust you,
but if there is any code in the output,
if the notebook has been forged,
and well, that's basically the equivalent
of accepting an unknown Excel macro
or an unknown Word macro,
and you probably have heard what's happened in the past.
So it's up to you.
You can do that.
There is also a command line thing
if you do Jupyter notebook trust,
or is it just Jupyter trust?
Yep, it seems to be Jupyter trust.
Does help.
Yep, you can pass it a number of notebooks
and it will trust them so that when you open them,
the JavaScript will be displayed.
Any more questions?
So I'm used to the original Jupyter notebook experience,
but if I'm in the lab and I have multiple notebooks
and I restart, like I want to clean up the in numbers,
and I restart kernel,
will it affect the other tabs that have other?
So if you have the same notebook in multiple tabs.
You're opening multiple tabs if you work,
not the same.
Like Chrome tabs, like browser tabs.
No, in Jupyter lab, like a second notebook.
Okay, so the question is yes,
if you have several notebook and you have,
so two notebooks here,
I have exercise one and untitled.ipoinb,
and I want to clear all outputs,
and I go to command palette,
and I go to clear all outputs.
Will it affect one tab or all tabs?
So that's the question.
Or restart the kernel or clear tab.
It should affect only the current focused notebook.
So here it's discrete,
but you will see that untitled.ipoinb at top
has a blue line on the top of the tab,
and so that would only affect the one which is in focus.
And so if I restart,
it will also restart only the one which is in focus.
I don't believe there is a way to do that for all notebooks.
If you want to do restart for all notebook,
what I would suggest is go to the running tab here,
and just do shutdown, shutdown, shutdown, shutdown,
shutdown, shutdown.
And now it will say, well, no kernel for this notebook.
Let me just get rid of that one.
It says no kernel because the kernel is gone now.
You can read the Python 3, and now you have a clean thing.
You have a shutdown all,
but I don't think you have a restart all.
It's possible to add, I think it's an extension.
Let's see if there is a restart all,
but I don't believe there is.
No, there is not.
But we could add that if necessary,
because everything is plugin-based.
Other questions?
Or we move on?
We have, okay.
So let's go to reach this place.
We are already at five.
So that's some examples mostly.
So this one you won't have to change much.
It's basically explained to you that
if you know a bit about Python,
you know that Python objects have a wrapper, a dander wrapper.
So when you have dander in Python,
it means a method with two underscore before
and two underscore after.
So you will hear dander init, dander equal,
dander wrapper, dander stir.
And so we extended that in Python to say well,
and Jupyter, say well, you don't need to be text only.
You can be PNG, you can be SVG,
you can be anything you want.
And so I'm going to go slightly faster on this one.
So the equivalent of print,
but for all the formats is called display.
So if you use Python, either you can import it explicitly
on relatively recent version of Python is already there.
So if you call the display on an object,
like a pandas.frame, it will show itself as HTML.
And so that's just showcasing some of,
what's wrong?
That's okay, anyway.
Where is it?
Good question.
It's not there.
Well, a bug, I would pick that.
So hopefully the output is still saved.
So if you have an image and you do shift enter,
it should show an image or you can display it.
You can also give it a URL
and it will get the URL and display it.
Or you can use, this one is gone as well, I don't know why.
So you can have rich things in line.
When you have images, you can have either embedded
or you get the data of the image
or what's it called, not embedded or soft linked.
So here, there is not much differences,
but here is the image of
Lawrence Berkeley Lab Hall of Science.
And you see that this one is a value of the image
at the time I ran this notebook last time.
So you see it was on April 28th at 12, 13 p.m. local time.
I'm in Berkeley.
And if you look at this image,
which is about the same code except
the way I've called it is slightly different.
You see that it's actually just the image at is now.
So every time I will reload this notebook,
this image will be just soft link.
It's basically just having an image tag.
You can of course display HTML.
I forgot to import it, starting to be tired.
And so you can have your own custom object
or you can use a percent percent HTML magic
if you want to just get some quick HTML.
You can display LaTeX.
And you can have your Maxwell equations.
That's relatively useful.
So that's just showing some of the things
that can be displayed on your laptop.
You can run this one and you will have some audio files.
One of the funny one was a couple of years ago,
you've found the Lego detected two black holes
that merged together.
They actually computed, like they shifted
a frequency into the audible range
and you can actually listen to the two black holes colliding.
And you can embed videos, like for example,
having the heat equations on some system
or embed a different website if you want to add them,
have people interact with that.
So of course that ties into the security issue
that we talked about and why notebook get trusted or not
because you can actually execute things in the browser
and you should be careful about that.
For JupyterLab, we extended this notion of rich output
and so now you can basically teach Jupyter and JupyterLab
how to render specific file types
or more specifically MIME types.
In some of the instruction, you might have seen that
we did install GeoJSON extension and FASTA extension.
So GeoJSON is a way to represent landmarks using JSON
and FASTA is a biology file format
that shows some like MIME.
And what you can do is install extensions
that both teach JupyterLab and the notebook
how to render that in the browser.
So here I have somewhere
if I can make that wide enough.
I have a GeoJSON file.
If you open with a normal editor,
you will see that it's just JSON.
But because I have taught JupyterLab how to render it,
I can now view GeoJSON file directly in my browser
and if the internet connection is good,
the tile should load and now I see my,
I see directly this file as it's supposed to be shown.
And same thing if you have a specific,
like if you know what a FASTA file is,
you can have a specific renderer for this FASTA file.
Let's look at the FASTA file.
I want to have the row view.
So Zika assembly opening with editor.
Let me try to get the two next to each other.
And one of the nice things,
or let's look, the first one is a dash here,
the first one is a dash here.
If I change, hopefully it should automatically update
without having to save so the two view are synchronized.
But now that you've taught JupyterLab how to render a file,
well you can do the same in a notebook
and hopefully this works now.
You can have this FASTA.ipynb
and now here is the complete code
to display a FASTA file or a FASTA data set
without having it to actually be a file into the browser.
So here I'm defining FASTA class
and say well now I want to teach IPython
how to display it as non-text.
Well if I can only render text,
just send the data as is.
Otherwise, tell JupyterLab to render it
using the FASTA viewer that we used for our file before.
And that's it, you can actually make that in a py file,
you can actually distribute it on PyPI if you want.
And now if you create an object like this one,
like FASTA objects equal FASTA
and now do FASTA object,
it should display with my keyboard that just type to is.
It should display properly.
So now what you can do is you can write
with a bit of time an extension for JupyterLab
and say well I have this specific kind of data
that I want to see in a specific way.
Here is how to display them.
Question in the back.
Is it similar to Ripper HTML
that we used in the Ripper HTML?
So is it similar to Ripper HTML
that you have in classic notebook?
Yes it's similar in the sense that Ripper HTML,
you could actually do here,
you could do a text HTML
and then here compute HTML representation
in the kernel.
So data.
So you would actually send HTML to the front end
and the front end will say okay, oh here is our HTML.
But here it's doing something slightly different
in the sense that it's sending the data itself
and the front end is deciding how to render it.
So the HTML here is computed by JupyterLab itself
not by the running process in the back.
Which means that usually when you do Ripper HTML
that you've seen in the other notebook,
you usually, the library author is in control
of how the object will be displayed.
While here the library author just sends some data
and the users can decide which plugins
they want to use for which rendering.
Which is a slight difference
but we're not going to dive too much into that.
On the big difference also from classic notebook
is that when you register a plugin on JupyterLab
because you don't have to do a kernel computation,
it will work with a file browser.
While if you do Ripper HTML,
you have to get a process in the back
that does some computation.
And that was not possible in normal notebook.
Questions, other questions?
How did you get to write that because
you didn't represent the things?
It should be root of the repository notebook
and FASTA.IPYNB.
In FASTA.IPYNB the only thing that does
is create a dummy object that defines this.
I'm going to remove that or at least comment it.
That defines this IPYTON display things
and say well, here is a MIME type
if you know what a MIME type is
and here is a data for this MIME type.
The kernel will send all of that to the front end
and the front end will say well,
I know how to represent FASTA file,
I'm going to use the FASTA representation.
Or the GeoJSON.
So let's try to do it with GeoJSON.
If it already exists this one,
so from IPYTON.display import GeoJSON.
Let's look at our GeoJSON object.
JSONable dicts, so we probably want to do JG equal
and what was the name of our file?
The name of our file was data museum in DC.
So let's do with open dot dot slash
data museum in DC as F.
Let's try to just do that F dot read
and let's try to do G, will that work?
Yep, that works.
There's a warning, not JSON string.
And so now we are able to directly source on JSON.
If we know our JSON is supposed to represent
some geographic data, it doesn't need to be a file
if it was an API here.
I could have done something like as an example,
but I don't know, request dot get HTTPS kernel slash slash
HTTPS kernel slash slash museums dot org slash DC
slash location dot JSON.
And that would be dot content with requests
and do GeoJSON of that.
And if I had to do that, if this was an actual API
that works, I would just like directly
instead of printing JSON, it would actually print
the location of the museum.
And so how, and 5B is how to do that on your own.
So that introduced some of the display HTML
which is slightly simpler that Mike talked about.
And it shows you, like for example,
if you have a custom class which is a circle class,
that's relatively simple, how would you create,
how would you do that on your own?
And so the way to do that is to create
underscore repr underscore png or HTML
or whatever underscore methods that returns
what data for HTML or for LaTeX or for something else is.
And so here is what you would return for HTML,
what you would return for LaTeX or for JavaScript,
for example.
And one of the exercise here is to rewrite
my class circle to try to display a circle
instead of printing some text, I am a circle.
So we're going to take five minutes to do that
and then move on to the last part.
Questions?
Okay, so that takes five minutes.
Okay.
Thank you.
I have to do two more minutes, I have to produce some sugars.
I have some to do some.
It's 5B, 5B custom display logic.
Okay, sounds cool.
Sorry.
Does this work?
I just saw it.
Sorry.
Are we good?
So if you're developing your own library, you can create your object and say here is
how to display yourself as HTML.
So I've done it with repr HTML, and you have the solution.
Let's see how the solution differs while print HTML and also in LaTeX.
Or you can have several different methods like that depending on if you are going to
convert your notebook to PDF, which is one of the possibilities, say how to represent
yourself in LaTeX.
And then you can force IPython to display as a specific, or Jupyter as a specific things.
Here I haven't defined for LaTeX, so let's redefine it and now it will display with LaTeX.
If you want to do something more complicated, what you can do is define how to do it in
PNG using Matplotlib.
So you can create a Matplotlib object.
Yes?
So there must be a list of formats that are ranked somewhere.
So there is a list, the question is which one do you choose when you have several.
So yes, in the front end, the front end will decide, you actually send everything and the
front end will decide which one to display.
It stores everything in the notebook document, which means that when you reload in either
or another front end, the front end can after the fact decide which one to show.
Also, for example, if you create a display JavaScript, it's going to be a high priority
and it will display in JupyterLab.
And if you convert to PDF, well, the PDF converter will say, no, I don't know how to deal with
JavaScript, I don't know how to deal with HTML.
Oh, here is a LaTeX one.
I'm going to use a LaTeX one.
But you can force when you have display underscore PNG or display underscore HTML, you can force
which one to send.
Actually, what you can do is do display has two keyword arguments, exclude and include,
I believe.
I don't remember why it doesn't work.
And you can say, well, I want you to send everything except image SVG.
Or I want to only send those one.
And that's a slightly advanced thing, so we're not going to do that.
So the other thing that here that exercise notebook show you is what if you don't control
the object itself?
What if you want to already have your circle object, you want it to be able to represent
it as PNG, but you can't change the circle object itself anymore?
What you can do is teach IPython here, and IPython not Jupyter.
Like, no, don't use that to display the object as PNG or HTML.
Use my own function that I want, because I know what I'm doing and I want to overwrite
what the library author is doing.
So here we have the function that convert our circle to PNG.
And what we can do is get the handle on IPython itself and say IPython when you're requested
to do some formatters for image PNG.
So we're moving two steps.
We're getting the things that converts, that try to loop through object and say, oh, how
do I make things as PNG?
And so the PNG formatter, when you see something which is a my circle, to generate the PNG,
use this function.
So now we have these functions that take a circle and return a figure object, which is
a PNG.
And now if we do that, because PNG is higher on the list you requested, well, now we have
an actual circle which is displayed as PNG.
And so the typical use case is what is just after is what if you have NumPy arrays?
NumPy arrays will usually have different meaning in your domain specific.
You know that they are a map or they are actually matrices where you are interested in the numbers.
What you can do is say, well, here is a function to convert a NumPy array to a PNG or to HTML,
if you prefer HTML because you want to see the number.
And now we're going to tell IPyTown when you see an NumPy array, so here is a PNG formatter
for type NumPy and DRA, use this function to generate a PNG for my NumPy array.
NumPy doesn't have a default PNG representation because I think that it might not be the right
thing.
And so once you do that, now IPyTown says, well, if I see a NumPy array when I display
or if it's a last statement of a cell, I'm going to generate a PNG for that and send
it over.
And so now if I create a NumPy array which is just random end by end, well, I have these
things.
If I prefer to, you could use map.lib and change the color and change the size, you
can do whatever you want as long as you know how to go from a specific data to a given
representation.
And then you can force to get back for NumPy, for example, NumPy has a pretty representation
that adds ellipses and so you can force to have a pretty text representation for these
NumPy arrays if you want to skip the PNG representation.
And so here is a nice gradient to finish that.
And for the, well, not even 15 minutes we have left, we're going to venture a tiny
bit into cross-language integration.
That you will have to go to specific libraries, but I want to show you that a lot of people
think one notebook is one language, one kernel is one language.
It's usually the case, but not always.
What you can do is cross-language integration.
If you're doing statistics, you might want to mix, mix, and match R and Python.
If you're doing some high performance, you might want to put some site on or some scene
side.
And there are many libraries that provide, we've seen the LP run line profiler, Python
magic that you can load from line profiler package.
And here we're going to load some extension for Rpy2 to move data back and forth between
Python and R.
So there is a lot of explanation, but I basically just created a Fibonacci sequence.
So it goes from, it grows, if I remember correctly from my university time, it should be exponential
at some point or close to exponential.
So let's just try to plot it.
I'm assuming you kind of know how to use Matplotlib, but we can dive into that at some point.
And it does look like that.
But the question is, how can we check that?
Well, my thought is that if we do in a semi-log axis and do a linear regression, it should
be close to a line and we should be able to find the intercept at the origin and the slope,
which would give us some information about the exponential growth.
I actually am not quite sure how to do that in Python.
Actually, I know how to do that in Python, but it's an example.
So I'm going to use rpy2, which is a really nice package, which in itself has a lot of
Python API to move things back and forth between Python and R. And it has specific integration
with ipython.
So again, I'm going to do rpy2.iPython.
And what this does is it injected in my namespace several percent or percent percent R something
that can take non-Python code and do what should be done with it.
And so the first thing it gives us is R push.
And what R push does is it takes y, the value of our Fibonacci sequence, and x, the index
of our Fibonacci sequence, and sends that to R. If the variable names are not valid
R, it does its magic.
I'm not quite sure I understand what that does.
And now we have a persistent R session with x and y, which we can access from our Python
notebook.
And now every cell that we want to execute in the R process, we are going to proceed
with percent percent R. And it's going to be persisted on the R session.
We still need to manage some of the movement, but some extension on other languages will
do the time movement automatically for you.
If you write some R, that would make sense.
You do a linear model of log of y versus x.
So that hopefully should be a line if our value is long enough.
We do a summary statistics of that that we put to value.
We do plot x and log of y, which hopefully should look like a straight line, and look
at our fits.
And so one thing we will see here is that not only you can run computation, but the
computation can send results and display rich objects.
R knows how to plot something, and it displays in the notebook, which is not a trivial thing
to do.
And indeed, our Fibonacci sequence seems to grow exponentially.
We can look at the summary value.
If you've done some R, this should mean some things to you.
You should understand that better than me.
But it tells you that it looks like, sorry, on the intercept is at minus 0.77, and the
slope is that much with the standard error and the p-value.
But now you want to do more from that.
So you want to get the value out.
You can just print them or actually return them as an MPI array.
So percent R, this is a line magic.
So this returns a value.
This is a cell magic, because it just prints a value.
You can see this difference, because here there is an output, and here there is no input.
No out number.
And if you remember correctly from the previous notebooks at the beginning, if you have a
line magic that returns a value, you can assign it.
And so you should be able to do something in Python equal to something in R.
So let's look at that.
R coef variable does not exist.
So we are going to assign it from R, and R pi 2 is going to do the type conversion
for us.
And then we can basically do some Python unpacking and get the first two values into the intercept
and the slope.
And now we have our value back in Python.
So we've mixed and matched Python.
We created a function in Python.
We did some statistical analysis in R, and we are back in Python for the analysis.
R is nice for analysis, but it's not the fastest language around.
Python is not either.
Cyton does work well.
If you heard about Cyton, it's like Python plus some type annotation, and it will compile
to C, and hopefully you will get something fast.
But using Cyton can be quite challenging, because you have to write your own module
and so on and so forth.
But the Cyton developer were nice enough to write some integration with Python so that
we can just basically do things on the fly.
So what you will do is the same as with R. You will load an extension from this module
so it's not shipped with IPython.
You have to have Cyton installed.
And if you do percent-percent Cyton, then all of that is going to be compiled in C.
So you see that it looks a lot like Python, except now you say that n is an integer, but
it can be a Python integer.
But inside the loop itself, x and y are going to be integers as well, but C integers.
And now you have something that really looks like Python, but just computes your function
way faster.
And you just have to basically put percent-percent Cyton at the top, put some type annotation.
And now you just define a function which is way faster than if it was in pure Python.
And you can directly use it without having to import it or anything.
And one of the nice things also is that you can redefine it on the fly.
So here you see that it does 1, 1, 2, and let's change that.
Let's put it to 6, which is not correct.
But you see that you were able to redefine this function on the fly, which usually you
cannot.
Which means that now you can also have quick interactive workflow with a faster language
than Python in some case.
So let's go back to 2 and let's compute our two things here.
And we see that, well, we got about a factor of 10 in speedup, slightly less, between our
normal Fibonacci function and our Cyton Fibonacci function.
Here what I've done with the time-it magic is to force it to do three loops of 100 each,
just to have something to show you some extra example for the time-it magic.
And I think we have a couple of minutes for questions and if you want to play with that.
And after it will be time for lunch.
And there is one survey that they asked me to ask you to fill in.
And so let me just write that here and then we can wrap that up.
And if you have any feedback, feel free to write on the sticky notes and stick them next
to the door when you exit.
And I will be happy to take that into account for the next tutorial.
Questions?
Tired?
Coffee?
Yes, question.
What do you recommend for version control of Jupyter Notebooks?
So what do I recommend for version control of Jupyter Notebooks?
I actually put them like that in Git and just push everything, even the outputs.
It's not the best when you want to merge things.
If you try to merge things, I would suggest to install some extension of Jupyter Notebooks
that store them as plain text file.
But if you do that, you lose the outputs.
And one of the critical thing in Jupyter Notebook is because it stores the output,
you can send them to someone and they can see the output without having to rerun everything.
Does that answer your question?
Jupyter Texts, something which is relatively recent that does some of that.
UGT2TZG.
Let me see if that works.
Yeah, that works.
And so if you have some time to answer.
Make it bigger.
Like that.
Can you do multiple kernels on the same Notebook?
No, I don't think.
I mean, there is technically no limitations.
But I don't think there is any option to do that.
And what would you want to do with several kernel?
You want to move data back and forth between kernels?
And the filter cell with the batch.
So you want to run one cell with Python 2, one cell with Python 3, and one cell with batch.
I would use cell magic.
I would start a single kernel and the single kernel can talk to several languages.
For example, if I want to...
If I do...
Python 2 print high.
It works.
So here I have a Python 3 Notebook that runs Python 2.
It did run Python 2 in a super process, though.
Sorry.
That would be the same as Perl and Ruby.
And so now the magic author can decide whether the process that it's talking to is persistent or not.
So the percent-percent Perl, the percent-percent Ruby are non-persistent.
Like as soon as the cell is end-executed, it stops.
But the R author decided that the process was going to be persistent and provided R push and R pull to get and push values.
And so now if you want to write a Python 2 magic, you can overwrite execution magic.
And a Python 2 magic that knows how to serialize the parallel array, sends them to a Python 2 process, and does its things, it's possible.
The kernel is always at notebook level.
Yes, one kernel can be at many notebooks.
So a kernel is just a remote process that gets user input and figure out how to execute it.
And so there are some kernels that are made to be multi-languages.
You tend to have one kernel equal one language.
But for example, at work, I have a kernel which is on my local machine.
But if I want to run something on the supercomputer, I just switch a kernel to actually be on the HPC system.
So I can have a kernel which is a different conda environment.
Or I can have a kernel that have a limitation in memory or something like that.
So kernel switching UI.
Sorry, it's zooming, so it's hard to manipulate.
But here you can select kernels.
And so, yeah, and you can, I could attach to an already existing, like for example, let's go to the FASTA one and select.
And now this notebook, which is called, I don't remember what, if I do FASTA object, I will get my FASTA object from, because it's actually the same running kernel.
And food is there in two minutes.
If you want to be the first one to have food, feel free to run outside.
And come and talk to us for the rest of the conference and enjoy the rest of your conference.