All right. I think I'm going to start. I'd just like to welcome everybody to this. This
is the Lambda Calculus tutorial. Hopefully you read the description of this, especially
the part about nothing usefully practical being done in here. If you're expecting
something that you're going to be able to use at work, you're probably in the wrong
place. Also just a couple of little logistic things. You will get the most out of this
by typing along and trying the code out as we go and experimenting. I will also emphasize
that almost nothing is obvious in here. I want you to meet your neighbor at the table
there and feel free to chat back and forth. What is he talking about? What are you doing?
You're going to get more by trying stuff out, talking with each other. I also have an assistant,
Brian Ward, in the back with a traveling microphone. If you have a question or something, just
to make it a little bit easier for you people to maybe raise your hand and he'll come find
you and you can ask the question. A little background on the tutorial. We're going to
be talking about the Python's Lambda function a lot. You've probably seen things like this
before, hopefully. One thing about Lambda is it is a way of defining a function in Python.
It's just another way of defining a function. One kind of interesting challenge with Lambda
is how to introduce it when teaching Python. I actually teach a lot of Python classes.
This is something that usually comes up at some point, maybe with the sort function or
something. It's like, oh, you use the Lambda function. Then you have to describe this to
people. We have Stuart here who's taught a lot of classes. One question that sometimes
comes out is why is it called Lambda? Does anybody encounter this in teaching Python
to people? It's kind of a weird name. It's like, Lambda, what's that about? Then you
start answering that, well, it's called Lambda because everybody else calls it Lambda, which
is sort of a non-answer. It's just deflecting to some non-thing. Then people are going to
ask, why does everybody else call it Lambda? It's like, well, they called it Lambda in
Lisp or Scheme or something. It comes from Lisp. It's like, well, why did they call
it Lambda? It's like, well, they took it from the Lambda calculus. If somebody asks,
what's the Lambda calculus? You start running away in horror. Actually, just personally,
before doing this tutorial, I didn't even really know the Lambda calculus at all. I
think I'd crossed paths with it in graduate school at some point. At the time that I did
it, I was studying for qualifying exams and spending the other half of my time playing
Duke Nukem or something like that. My memory of the Lambda calculus was just zero. This
tutorial is kind of born out of that. It's like, what is the Lambda calculus? I don't
know. How does it work? I think it's going to be really cool. My experience with it is
this is just insane and crazy. I think it'll be fun. That's what we're going to talk
about. I'm going to step you through it in maybe an unusual way. The thing that I wanted
to start with is actually that thing that I got up on the slide, the Lambda X there.
How would you teach what's happening there to a 10-year-old? I have a 10-year-old kid.
He's in third, fourth grade. They're doing math. Forget the Lambda part of that for a
second. If you were to describe how a function works, what's going on there? How would you
teach that?
Yeah?
Yeah. But it's not even about the name. If you have a 10-year-old and you're just saying
F of four, what do you do there? Maybe overthinking it. You just replace the function with a
function. You replace the X. If you were to describe what that does, it's like you replace
the X with four. Then you do math. It's like three times four plus one. You describe the
function as, well, the whole thing that's just going on there is you just replace the
X. Function. Substitute the X.
There's some interesting things that you could get into with a kid. If you said, well, what
if you have F two plus three? How does that work? There's their issue. It's like, okay,
you're going to get 16. Do you do the two plus three first? Do you get three times five
plus one? Is that how you do that? Or do you do that? Do you just literally take the two
plus three and plug it in for the F? There are some variations there. Basically, function,
you take the thing in parentheses and you substitute the X.
You have that. Now, the thing that we're going to start with is what if you were teaching
programming and you decided right at this point to stop? You don't need to know anything
else. What if you had this thought experiment where it's like you actually do not have
to do anything else other than substituting the X? Imagine that you had Python. You're
going to do the scene from the Holy Grail on Python. You're going to start chopping
things away from Python. Non-essential parts of Python. I'll help you out here. No packages
or modules. That would solve a lot of problems. Get rid of that. What if you had no objects?
Or no numbers? Or no strings? Or no data types? You basically just start carving it away.
Or you just start stripping things down. It's like how much of it could you actually cut
away and still actually have something that you could compute with? Do anything useful?
The thing that we're going to talk about here is actually an idea which is what if functions
are actually the only thing in the universe? Not only functions, but just single argument
functions. Nothing else exists. You can write a function like you can say F of X. You can
have that. But you're not allowed to do anything else in your whole language. Now, this is
going to get a little bit mind bending because you're thinking of function like if you said
return X plus 1. No. There's no numbers. And there's no plus either. We don't have any
operator. That's a little weird. You can't do this because we only have single argument
function. This actually solves a lot of problems, by the way. If you only have one argument,
you don't need defaults or keywords or positional only arguments. If you're following that
debate, it sort of collapses. You can have multiple arguments. You could do something
like that, but it's hard to decide whether that's very useful. It's sort of under specified.
You could have a function X, takes an X and returns X. They always take an argument. They
don't. Zero argument functions are not allowed. There's no if statements. We got rid of control
flow. I didn't put it on the list, but control flow. Once you start thinking about control
flow, it's going to lead to things like exceptions and all that's evil. No. We don't want to
know. Control flow is gone. The only thing that you have is basically single argument
function. You could do things like this. That's okay. X is a function. The reason it's a function
is because functions are the only thing that exists in the whole universe. By default,
it has to be a function. I'm not clear what that does. You could also create a function.
This is technically allowed. You could do something like that. It's a little strange,
but you could have a function that defines a new single argument function only. It has
to be single argument. The only thing that you could do with a function is call a function.
Keep in mind, we have no numbers or operators or anything other than just calling a function.
You could return that. You could do this sort of stuff, but now the challenge is could you
actually do anything with that? Again, you've taken Python. You've just chopped everything
off of it except for functions, single argument function. Is there anything in the real world
of anything that you can do with this programming restriction? I'm going to let you ponder that
for a couple of minutes here. It's a little tough, I think. I'm trying to gauge whether
anybody has any thoughts on the zero. The thing that's a little weird about it is it
feels extremely abstract at this point. Keep in mind, did we just lose audio for a second?
Do you have audio back there? I think we've lost audio. Do you have audio? You're getting
audio in the recording? Maybe just the speaker. At this point, it actually feels very, very
weirdly abstract. Just to emphasize, in this system, there is literally nothing other than
a single argument function. There are no bits or anything. You can return a single argument
function. Actually, that's an interesting multiple things. That's a very interesting
thing. That would imply the existence of a data structure or something like a tuple.
As long as your multiple things is a single argument function. Functions can be passed
around. You can pass functions. You can return functions as long as they're single argument
functions. Well, as long as it's a function. It's a real brain. It's a very simple thing.
Maybe one way to think about this is like a weird escape room that I've put you in from
coding. It's like, okay, we've got this style guide, which is extremely easy to remember
because single argument functions. That's it. But the question is, how do you do anything
with it? Actually, names are not technically allowed either, but I'm going to break that
rule just to be able to do anything. It turns out that having names of global variables
is not really technically allowed either, but we're going to whiten that rule.
So in looking at this, at first glance, it's going to be like, this is just, okay, I don't
even know where to start with this. So I thought I would start you with actually something
real that you could model with this. It's going to be something really unexpected, I
think. But you could model a switch using this. I was trying to think about how to make
this tutorial go full stack down to the bare metal, basically. You've got to talk about
electricity and other things. So let's say you have like a switch like that. This is
a switch, like left, right. It has two inputs, A and B. It has an output on that. That is
actually something that you could model in this system, but the way it's going to work
is going to be a little strange. I'm going to write a function left that takes in a single
argument because everything has to take single argument. And then inside, whoa, okay, hot
audio excitement there. I'm going to define a function F that returns the A and then I
return the function back. Now at first glance, that's going to look really weird. I'm going
to write a function right that does the same thing. Well, almost the same thing. Okay,
so I'm going to have you type that in. Now how this is going to work is this is essentially
like a chaining of functions where you provide an argument to the first, like the outer function.
You say like, okay, left, A, that's five volts or something. Okay, think electricity. And
then what it is doing is returning a function back. Like it's returning this F back.
Oh, well, okay. Ignore that for the moment. Ignore that. No. Yeah, I'm breaking the rules
a little bit. But you're onto something important here in a second. Okay, so what's happening
is like two inputs are coming in. There's like an A, which is like the five volts, and
then the B is like maybe ground or something. And what left is doing is it picks out the
A basically. Like if you're in the left position, it means that you're picking the A. You're
connected to the A. And if you were to do the same thing with like the right function,
it would come back and it would say, well, you're connected to the ground. Now the thing
that's kind of wild about this is that these functions, they don't really represent like
a thing. It's not a bit. It's not a piece of data or anything. What they're representing
is a behavior basically. Like the behavior of left means that you're connected to the
A. And the behavior of the right means you're connected to the B. In some sense, it doesn't
really care what you pass in here. Like you could have left of loud, maybe like the loud
soft or something. If you're in the left, it means you're loud. If you're right, it
means you're soft. It's still a little abstract, but essentially you've got, you're modeling
again like a behavior. It's like the behavior of a switch is that if it's in the left position,
you're connected to the A input. And if you're in the right position, you're connected to
the B input. And that's what is happening here. Let me just pause for a second. Again,
I definitely want you to try typing in the code as we go and trying this stuff out. So
I'll give you a minute to try that. While you're doing that, by the way, I do want to
say, I do want to make a mention that this technique that we're doing here, this is not
part of our system, but this technique of writing single argument functions, like let's
say you had a function add, like that, where it took two arguments. You could rewrite that
in a really funny way using single arguments. And I'm going to give you a little bit of
this is not going to win you points at work doing some trick like that, but you can basically
you can take multiple argument functions and turn them into single argument functions.
This is something known as currying. If you've ever heard that term before, it's sometimes
something people will throw around that term. It's basically a way of like take, you can
take multiple argument functions and just kind of turn them into single argument functions.
Again you're going to have a lot of explaining to do at a code review if you were to show
up with something like that normally, but that's what's happening. All right, how are
people doing? Questions? Okay. Next thing we're going to talk about is could you take
that and spin it into the notion of truth? Most computers do have a notion of Boolean
values, right? Like you have true and false. Could you represent like true and false using
this scheme in some way? And the reason that I kind of did the switch example is that you
could think about it like that. Like think about your computer. What is a true value
on your computer? It's an electrical device, right? It means electricity flowing around
in there. What is true? Yeah, something. I mean it's like a bit on your computer. What
is a bit? I mean is it like, it's probably like, it's either like five volts or three
volts or something. I mean it's like there's electricity on it or it's the ground. It's
one or the other. And it turns out that maybe that switch code that we had is the same thing
that we could kind of do for true and false. I'm going to switch over to the lambda there
just to shorten the syntax a little bit, shorten the amount of typing. So maybe true and false
are kind of the same thing. Basically what true is, is it's like a behavior. Basically
true means that you're connected to the first value, whatever it is. Five volts or something.
So we're talking about computers again. And false is the opposite. It's kind of arbitrary
in a way. But if you think about true and false values, it's like you have true and
you have false and true is supposed to be the opposite of false. I'm never quite sure
with the news these days. But normally true and false are meant to be opposites. And that's
kind of what's going on here. You've got X and Y, true and false. True is one of them
and false is the other one. And again it's a little odd because we're not representing
true and false as a concrete thing. It's not a bit. It's not a piece of data or anything.
It's strictly like a behavior. The behavior of true is that you're connected to the first
thing and the behavior of false is that you're connected to the second thing. Question up
here.
I'm a little bothered by the absence of fact finding.
Fact finding?
Yeah, you know, it's like the thing where you have to report. Are you sure there's
cannibalism going on? Because no, no, we're just reporting that there's cannibalism going
on.
Right.
So the hair that stands up on my neck is that we won't in some sense be able to have the
sort of fact finding that you need to have an actual Boolean structure.
Yeah, there's like nothing concrete to really hang onto here. It's like true. No, I find
this really disturbing. It's like true is not a thing. It's just like, well, it's whatever
the first, it's whatever the x is. That's what true is.
The only thing that we know about the rules here is that technically it has to be a single
argument function. These values like five volts and ground, that's bogus. Normally
I can't do that. Normally I would have to do something like this. I'd have to say,
well, you can do true and true and false. That would be okay. Or you could have a function
of one argument. You could say lambda x is x. I mean, I could say true of f, false. But
that is making my head explode because it feels even more ungrounded than it was before
doing that.
It's very weird. It gets even weirder if I challenge you to start implementing the Boolean
operators like not, and, and, or. Let me take that away. No, here's a challenge. How could
you define not? Just to be clear about the behavior of not, not true is basically false.
And not false is basically true. At least it was the last time I checked anyway. So,
yeah, Brian, you want to try to get people to do the mic on the question here?
Yeah.
Just to sort of keep inventory here, are you cheating again here for narrative purposes
at the end or do you, do we have a universe that has identity?
I'm cheating with Python here. No, the assert statement is that that's some Python stuff.
It becomes a little bit hard to talk about if there's not, like, if there's literally
nothing but it's a...
So the question is how in the world would you, how would you do not? And this is where
things are going to, I mean, it's already probably very abstract and weird. I mean,
it's like, wait, it's like true and false are functions and like, and, and, and what
does it mean? And, and, and so like, let's think about the, the, the not for a second.
The only thing that exists in this universe is function. So one thing that we can say
about not is that X is definitely a function. Okay. We know it's a function because that's
the only thing that exists. So that we have a hundred percent guarantee that it's a function.
Okay. So we, we know that it's, that, that it's going to be a function. The other thing
that we, that we know is that if, if our intent is to pass true and false to that thing, those
are functions that have the two arguments. Remember the behavior of true is that you
choose the first thing and the behavior of false is you choose the second thing. So we
know that we can, we can do this. Like we say, return X something and then something,
something else. And exactly right. So, so common up here, just reverse it. So if X is
true, what you want to do is pick out false. Like the behavior of true is you pick the
first thing and if it's false, you pick out the second thing. So not true is false and
not false is true. Okay. So looks, looks, looks a little strange.
Leave that up there. Gets a bit more interesting if you start thinking about and and or function.
What if you wanted to have, what if you wanted to have something like that? So what you want
to do? Let me, let me let you ponder that this one for a second. I'm going to give you
a little hint on this one. One hint here is to understand how Python does and ors. So
if I were to say two and three in Python. Keep in mind this is not allowed in our system
because we have no numbers, but we're just talking about Python here. What does that
return? So that returns three, but what about zero and three? What if I were to do zero
and three? What does that return? You're kind of seeing like a hint of how to do this from
Python. Basically, if the first item in and is a true value, Python goes to the second
value and uses that to determine the result. Like if the first thing is true, the only
way you know whether it's true or false is to look at the second value. If the first
thing is false, like zero, then you're just done. You know that it's false. So what comes
back is zero. That is going to be a little bit of the trick here. We're going to look
at the first value, the X. We're going to basically look at it and say, okay, what are
you X? Are you a true value or are you a false value? Then I'm going to return some things
back. Just give her a few seconds to kind of ponder it here. What do you think you would
go in this first parenthesis here? Somebody said, I think you put Y in there basically.
If X is true, the behavior of true is you pick the first thing. It's like true picks
the first thing. If it's true, the result of and is solely determined by what Y is.
If X is true, then whatever Y is, that is the result. If Y is true, then it's true.
If Y is false, then it's false. If X is false, then what is the result? It could just be
X. If X is false, then the thing is false. You could do that. It turns out that that
exactly does that. It's kind of mind-boggling, but you can try it out. And true and true
is true. And true and false is false. And false and true is false. And false and false
is false. It is giving you the Boolean logic. Again, it's a real sneaky thing going on there.
It's like, yeah.
Doing this, how much do you think, or did you ever draw or think about a truth table
that you might make in a logic class? The syntax totally messes me up. It's very hard
to read. It blocks my thinking. But when you see a simple truth table where you write T,
T, F, F, and you do all of that, that logic becomes very simple and easy to understand.
When you think about not, you just put the little curly thing in front of it. If you
think about the and or the or, those become very simple and easy to understand. When thinking
about this, the syntax blocks me. But that idea is very easy to understand. Did you look
at something like that when thinking about this?
The answer is yes. I've seen logic from math classes. I think the difficulty, at least
for me, is how do you bridge that to this world where the only thing that you have is
a single argument function.
But then the truth table is a single argument function, right? It takes a one-piece.
Right, but how do you encode it? Yes, you get in the X and the Y, but how to take the
logic table and turn it into something that I can type within the rules of what I'm allowed
to type becomes really challenging because there's no if statement. There's no control
flow or anything in this. The only thing I can do is function call. It becomes this really
weird puzzle where it's like, how do I do this when the only operation that I can do
is call a function? You're exactly on the right track, though. If you're looking at
this thinking, that is insane. I never would have come up with that. That is totally the
correct response to that. Don't ask this on any job interview question, by the way. It's
sort of crazy. The OR operator is also kind of a similar thing. I mean, OR, what do you
think for that? Think about the OR logically. If the first argument to the OR was true.
Yeah, you just got to switch the order of the X and Y to reverse. Yeah, to do the OR. If X was true,
then you're done. It's X. The behavior of OR is like, if you're true, it's true. If X is not true,
then it must be Y. Whatever Y is, and you'll get that. So OR true and false is true. Or
false and false is false. You can build it up, but it is sort of, you know, it's tricky. I would not
claim that this is obvious. If you've never seen this before, it's like, whoa.
Yeah, so I just tried this, but OR false and true comes out with problems.
So OR false and true comes out with... Yeah, that should be okay. Debugging some of this is a real
challenge sometimes. All right, did everybody get that code entered, by the way? Just trying it out.
Again, a lot of the code in here is something that's like, try it out, and you sort of stare
in disbelief that it's like, this shouldn't be working, or it's sort of nuts. I do think it's
kind of interesting, though, where it's like, we basically started with nothing, where it's like,
you have functions and substitution, and now all of a sudden we have Boolean logic. The thing that,
again, it's a little strange is that there's nothing concrete here again. It's like, there is
no bit or data structure. It's all purely behavior, basically. Like, you know, like the behavior of
OR is that, well, if the first thing has the behavior of true, then the result of OR is the
behavior of true. It feels like sort of very kind of nebulous and abstract.
So, you can only have kind of a single argument function, right? But then you made add with the
kind of two function calls, right? So we can then infer that we could have kind of infinite number
of function calls, right? So technically, you could take any number of things, right? And so,
if you wanted to represent something, say you wanted to represent, you know, a simple kind of
three-letter alphabet, right? You could just have each bit, so to speak, be some n number of
function calls to represent a string in that alphabet, right?
You are exactly right. And you're actually on to the very next thing we're going to talk about,
which is, like, how would you represent numbers? You want to represent, like,
integers or something? Let's forget about letters, per se. But let's say you were thinking about
numbers. And one thing with the numbers is to maybe not overthink the numbers, but to go back to
kindergarten. Okay, so, like, how do they teach, like, preschoolers how to do numbers? And it's
like there's a lot of, like, finger counting kind of stuff, like one and two and three. And then they
show you pictures of, like, well, how many gummy bears are there? And how many, you know, it's
always showing, like, a visual representation of, like, a certain number of things. Or maybe you do,
like, score marks or some other thing. And if you wanted to do numbers, could you do something
like that with functions? And the answer is actually yes. We had the comment up here. It's
like, since you can have, like, an infinite number of function calls, maybe you could use that for
numbers. Let me show you one of them to give you kind of an idea. Like, maybe one is where you do
one function call on X. Like you say, F of X. I call the function once. That's the number one. It's
like a repeat. And then maybe the number two is like two function calls of X. Like you just say F
of F of X. It's like holding my fingers up where it's like two, okay? What would three be? Big quiz
time. What is three in this universe? Yeah, F of X. Now, you're gonna look at that. You're gonna say,
like, what is that? Like, I mean, okay, so it's like, again, this is like purely, it's like
functions all the way through. But like, what is going on here exactly? What the numbers are
representing, again, is a behavior. It's not a thing. It's not a bit pattern or anything like
that. The behavior of three, for instance, means that you take a function F and you call it like
three times on some, like you start with F of X and then you do F like three times in a row. Let
me show you an example. Let's say you had a function increment. Again, this is not allowed
in our rules, okay? So this is like we're, okay, legal in the rules, but this is just purely for
like demonstration purposes. Basically, what the numbers are is if I said Inker of zero,
that's like the number one. I did Inker one time. If I did Inker Inker zero, that's two times. I did
Inker two times. And then if you said Inker Inker, like if I started doing it like a whole bunch of
times, I mean, essentially, it's like repeating that function basically a whole bunch of times.
Essentially, what we've got up here at the top is an abstraction of that idea where instead of
writing out like Inker Inker Inker Inker like that, I could just say three Inker zero, and it would
do it. It's like three basically you give me a function and a starting point and it will just
like turn the crank like that many times, like three times. The thing that's really odd about it
is it's all extremely abstract. It has, like the number three does not actually care what the
function is or what the X is. It's like, again, it's like a behavior where it's just like, I'm
going to turn the crank three times. I don't really know what it is or I don't even really care
what's going on. I'm just going to turn the crank three times on it. I mean, just as something
wildly different here, I mean, I could have a function P that maybe this thing takes a, we'll
introduce like Python tuples or something just to do something really radically different here.
Like here's a function where you give it like a tuple like zero zero or something and it increments
the first value and so forth. You could start, you could do that. Like you could say, well,
what's three of P applied to the tuple zero zero? And it comes back with like three two. I mean,
essentially it's just like turning, like the numbers are basically just like turning the gears
without any regard for what the actual function is. As long as it's a function with single argument.
Okay, we're still in the single argument case here. Let me put the code back up. Let me ask,
see if there are questions here. Let's pause for a second. I do want you to enter that code and try
it out here. So if we're, you said there were no exceptions in there, right? But seeing as how
you're starting to do math, right? If you get to divide, what happens when you divide by zero?
We haven't even gotten there yet. We don't even know how to add yet. We don't have to divide. I
mean, are you like, that's like in the next version or something. No, but like, like all we, all we
have now is just like a representation of numbers. Like, like, okay, the number three and four, you
know, like, I mean, we can type them out. We're actually, actually hitting a bit of a problem here,
which is like, how do I get more numbers into my system? I mean, you got to, or we just make like
a big file with like the first million numbers in it and then like type it out. I mean, that's a
little, so that's, that's a little bit weird. There are some other kind of interesting things going on
as well. Like, like, let me, what if you were to do something like this? Like four times, like four of
three. I don't know, like what if you were to do that? Remember that a number means that you've
repeat something a bunch of times. So what I did here is I just said, well, I'm going to do the three
function four times. No, let's try it like a increment zero. No, no, no. What do you think the result is there?
Any 12?
81. Yeah.
What that's doing is it's doing, it's doing exponentiation. It's doing three to the fourth power.
Like three means do something three times. So if you do three times three, that's nine. Times three is 27. Times three is 81.
Yeah, at some point. Yeah, but that the, but, but already like just from that, you're maybe getting a little bit of a hint of some,
of like some math, mathy stuff where it's like, huh, okay, this is weird. Like, okay, like the, like the behavior of four is to repeat something four times.
The part of this that I am following is when I see the one, the two, the three, and the four is those things are creating function objects in Python.
And they're unique objects and they represent unique things, which we've happened to name three and four and two.
Yeah. So is that helping me or making it harder for me to understand the rest of this?
And we have names too. Yeah, I, it's, I have to name them something just to even refer to it at this point.
I mean, the thing that I, that I want you to focus on is that, that they are functions.
Okay. So lambda defines a function and this is a function that returns another function.
I'm going to, I'm going to be stretching you on the syntax a little bit here, but it's like, this is a function that returns another function.
And then what it's doing is it's, it's, it's just doing like F of F of F of F of F like a bunch of time.
And then the number of times that you do that is what the number is, how you're representing the number.
It's like, and again, it's like, think like it's like finger counting, like from kindergarten, just in a really horribly gone astray, basically.
So it's, but it's the same, same idea there.
I was thinking until we typed in four, three that you could make some sort of a ten and hundreds kind of a thing.
And then you could do ten of three and it would be like thirteen.
And that's how you get more numbers in. But I haven't quite figured out how to do multiplication yet because I thought four, three was going to be twelve.
Right. I thought it was going to be twelve. So I'm lost.
But.
So in, in, in the syntax that you use where we do like the one, two and three, you have a lot of kind of nesting going on.
It looks a little clearer to me when you write things with just, you know, kind of a, where you did a, a, zero.
Right. So where you have like the single argument in each of the of the parentheses.
Right. So if you took something there and you just had some long, like if you wanted like you created the bit earlier.
Right. I mean, you could create, you know, like a four bit representation of something with four of those kind of parentheses in there.
If you passed in true in the first one and zeros and the others, you represent some binary number.
Right. You could do one in each block. And right. You could combine them in all these sorts of ways where now you suddenly start having a bit.
I think you probably could do numbers in that way. But then like, like, I mean, you could go like down the binary route of numbers.
But then you're going to hit like an upper limit at some point. Now you're writing binary.
I haven't explored that angle and I got to go down that direction. But it's I mean, I could see going that way.
Yeah. This this thing here is something known as the church numerals, by the way, is kind of a name for it.
There is a challenge, though, and we're kind of we're kind of getting to it, which is well, before we get to the challenge, there's some other challenges.
One challenge is how do you implement zero?
That's a picture of the black hole, by the way, that had a bunch of Python code involved. I thought I'd include that there.
There's no no concept. Yeah.
The thing that with the zero is that first of all, there is a there's an API for for numbers.
Not to talk about APIs in here, but the API for a number is that you take an F and you take an X. If it's not that it's not a number. OK, so it's like there is a very strict protocol for what numbers are going to be.
The other the other thing. Oh, but by the way, I'm getting kind of tired of typing the lambda, by the way.
So I'm going to use lambda.
I realize that this is not going to work in your editor, but you're going to have to do a little. I'm going to require you to do a little mental substitution here. So I think the key to a good tutorial is to use a custom environment.
So we'll come to that in a second. So the zero is basically going to be lambda F lambda X.
And the question is like, how would how would you represent zero in this?
In the system, a one is it's like one usage of F and two is two usages of F and three is three usage of usage of F. What do you think the zero is?
Zero usage. Yeah, X like like you didn't use F at all. It's like you just gave me an F and X and it's like OK, didn't do anything to it.
So like the zero basically means you didn't do anything. So if I said like zero inker of like zero, it means you just stayed at zero. You didn't call the you didn't call the function.
So where this is going where this going that question in the back there.
So does this mean that zero and true are equivalent? Yes, OK.
They have the same behavior. I'm not going to make that association because I'm already quite confused as it is. And like, what's where I'm going to try to keep zero and true is different things. But but yeah, you will notice that the that the implementation of the zero is exactly the same as true.
No, no, wait, it's the zero. It's the implementation of false actually, right? Because like the behavior of false is to pick the second thing.
So here we're picking out the second thing. We're picking out the egg.
We clean up a bit while you're thinking about that.
OK, so got zero. The thing we're going to look at look at next, though, great question over here.
So it's it's impossible to implement numbers without the anchor function, right? The anchor function is a side of like that is a Python thing.
Used only for illustration. OK, yeah, so you can actually see the number. No, so that the strange thing about like if you look at that, like if you look at yeah, if you look at like three, it just comes back and says I'm a lambda function.
And then it's like it's purely abstract. Like it's like.
What is that like and like the basically the concept of three? It's a function that does something three times.
And in order to see the effect of it, I have to I have to provide a function for it to look at.
I mean, I could write different functions like like here's one that adds like a star to X. Maybe we do like strings or something.
What would happen there is if I did three of F and then gave it like an empty string or something, it's like essentially you're giving it like the starting point.
And then you're like the three represents like turning the crank three times on it.
I think it's really hard to kind of mentally like have like wrap my brain around this because there is nothing sort of concrete here, which is really sort of weird.
In each case, so you're giving it like an empty value as like the second argument. Is that is that just to give it is that because it's a natural starting point.
Yeah, you have to have to kick off with like an initial value.
Yeah.
Now the thing we're going to look at the look at next, but just kind of push forward a little bit here.
What if you did want to use do math with this thing like add and multiply and other stuff.
One of the one of the problems is that you have all the numbers hard coded least so far like I've just been typing them in and it's like, well, that's just terrible.
I don't want to I don't want to I don't want to do that.
And then the question is like, well, how would you go beyond that?
And it actually takes you it kind of into this this thought of like, well, what is the most minimal thing that you need to do math?
The picture up here of piano, there are these piano axioms for math.
There may be a little bit abstract, but the way that they're kind of phrased is they sort of they start off saying zero is a number.
And then you get into all this talk about creating successors of numbers.
Like if you have a number, can you get to the next number?
And then could you build number?
Could you build numbers?
And then you get into the idea of like, well, what is the most minimal thing that you need to do math?
The picture up here of piano, there are these piano axioms for math.
And you can do math by just being able to get to the next thing.
Basically, the act of counting like if you can count like go from the number two to the number three, can you start doing like more interesting math operations?
And the answer the answer is yes.
But the challenge here.
Is implement successor like can you write a function that would take a number and then get you to the next number?
This is typed out as suck, by the way, S-U-C-C.
So we're going to have a function successor as input is going to take a number.
And again, I'm going to have you're going to have to sort of mentally translate my lambda character into Python, by the way.
Looks like that.
So every everywhere you see the lambda character, you're going to you're going to you're going to type lambda.
And the question is, what are we going to what are we going to do here?
So just just just make sure we're clear about what's going on here.
If I say successor of two, what's going to pop out of that is basically three.
But that's what we want to have happen.
So so we're going to have this function basically takes a number.
It's going to have a number coming out.
And so the question is, how is that going to work exactly?
You're correct.
One one one more function call one more one more function.
No, you are you are absolutely correct.
It is one more.
It's like spinal tap, right?
You're at 10 and you need to go one more.
You go to 11. Right.
You know, the famous scene.
You're going to have one more function.
But before you do that, you have to you have to sort of think like we said, what like what is this successor thing returning exactly?
It's returning a number.
And the critical thing about numbers is they have a numbers have a very specific API.
Think about the API to a number not to bring API into class, but the interface to a number is that there is always an F.
And there is an X. That is the API to a number.
And it turns out that that is what you're going to do here.
Maybe parentheses might help this out a little bit.
Like basically you're going to be returning a number that takes an F and it takes an X.
OK, I'm going to return that.
We're going to use your comment, which is exactly correct.
You're going to do one more F. That's the go to the next number.
You have to go one more.
So there's going to be an F out front, which is the one more.
But then what is what is going to go in the in the parentheses here?
So the behavior of a number, right?
It's like a number.
You basically give it an F and an X and it repeats that many times.
So this is this is basically the old number here.
OK, so that's the old number.
And then we have the extra F on front.
That's taking us to the next to the next number.
So if I were to say successively, I would say successively.
So if I were to say successor of four, for instance, it's going to come back with this crazy result.
It's going to say, OK, function lambda.
You're like, what is that?
Well, if that is working correctly, it's a function.
So I'm going to use my magic underscore variable here.
I should be able to pass that like anchor in zero and I'll come back say, oh, it's five.
The successor of four is five.
So if you use that, you're getting five.
OK, now just to see the syntax of that written out.
I did anticipate this problem, by the way.
So I'm going to leave that.
What do you think about doing it as a step?
Yeah.
I really like this kind of feedback.
You have that lambda symbol and then you have the syntax because you have that lambda symbol and you have the word lambda.
But we began the talk with the idea of substitution.
So you just take that symbol and you substitute this other symbol into it and then it kind of works.
Yeah, I'm just doing it because I'm lazy.
Yeah.
Now, one thing.
Now, your comment on the notation.
I actually am.
I am doing something very deliberate here, which I'll get to.
If you read papers about the lambda calculus, they tend to use very cryptic mathematical notation with the lambda character and other stuff.
I am steering you a little bit in that direction.
So at this point, this is basically Python code, except that I have replaced the lambda word with the lambda character.
If you must know, my editor is literally doing like a string replace on it.
I have a custom environment.
It's taking my code and it's just like, oh, if you see the lambda character, just replace it with the word lambda.
So it's a notational shortcut there.
If you're done with that, by the way, I'm going to give you the challenge of implementing add-ins multiply.
Wait a second here.
Yeah.
A successor.
Do we have a decrementer?
Can we go back?
We do not.
And I'm not going to address that question right now.
But it is something to think about, which is like, how would you go to the previous number?
Like, how do you undo a function call?
That seems like a really weirdly tricky kind of crazy thing.
And I'm not going to address that right this second.
I want to comment on the underscore method so everybody's clear, including myself.
That's just a helper so you can not call successor for incrementer zero kind of thing?
Yeah. Underscore is the result of the last thing you do in the REPL in Python.
So if you've used Jupiter or the Python REPL, the underscore always holds the last result of whatever you did.
So I'm using that here.
So the result of the last thing I did here was the successor of four.
But you could do this kind of stuff.
You could say do the successor of the successor of four.
Do it twice.
And then pass in the incur function in zero and come back.
That's sick.
You know, two successors of four is sick.
That last example, by the way, is giving you a hint on how to do add.
Well, say you wanted to add two numbers.
Like you wanted to add two and three.
And you wanted to describe this again to like a kindergartener or something like that.
And you wanted to do it with finger counting or something.
You could say, well, if you had two, you want to add three, you push up like three fingers.
It's like one, two, three.
And then you look at how many you have.
Basically, you just did three successors of two.
Like two and three is three successors of two.
And you could do that.
Like basically the way that add would work is you would take y and you would say apply that.
Like take the successor function and apply it a whole bunch of times to the other number.
So when I learn math, like there's a certain way to kind of think about it.
But I mean, there's the other idea, which is that multiplication is just repeated addition, right?
And exponentiation is just repeated multiplication.
So you have these things that are kind of nesting or just like repetitions of themselves, right?
So now that you can add one to something, which is why the Italian guy for his name.
But he had to start somewhere.
So he started with zero.
He said you could add one to something.
And if you can just do that some infinite number of times, you can get anything.
Yeah.
So that's kind of what's going on here.
It's like once you have the successor function, you can start using that to get to different spots, right?
So if you have like two numbers, x and y, and you wanted to add those together, you would take like the second.
Like if you had four plus five, you could get to nine by doing five successors of four.
Like if four is your starting point and then you turn the crank on the successor function five times.
So add ends up looking like this thing that I've got here.
I'm going to put up the Python syntax for that again, just to have you try that out.
Yeah, we'll get to that later.
What you want to be able to use the lambda in your Python code now?
What, the custom environment?
Nah, nobody wants to know about that.
Better off not knowing.
Yeah.
Multiplication is something that you can also do.
In the interest of time, I might just kind of show you what that looks like.
We'll leave it as a, what it was left as an exercise to the reader to fully grock that.
Basically the way that multiply works, like imagine that you have like three times four.
What you do with multiply is you're going to take the function, like you take one of the numbers, like x.
X is one of the numbers, so that's like three.
We're going to do three repetitions of f.
Oh, yeah.
Then we're going to do that y time.
We'll try this out here.
That one is maybe, honestly this one is something that I have found very difficult to kind of wrap one's brain around, is the multiplication.
It's essentially you have a number x, and like what is the behavior of x?
It's like a repetition.
If I have a number four and I give it a function, then x of that function, that means like doing f four times.
That's what that means.
Then if you put this y out front, it's like you're repeating that four times f like three times in a sequence there.
It's a little weird, but...
The thing that breaks my brain about that one is that it has an f, and add doesn't.
I feel like I know that f is coming from the outside and that we are calling f underneath, but that's what killed me.
Not that that's a useful comment, but that's what really lost me.
I would agree on that.
Did that answer your question?
You had a question?
Okay.
Is anybody's mind fully shattered here?
A little bit.
I don't want to dwell too much on the exact implementation of that.
I think maybe the interesting thing here is that we have bootstrapped ourselves out of nothing.
This idea where it's like, oh, all you have is single argument functions and you have nothing else.
All of a sudden we do math.
We have not violated any rule here about any of the functions.
It's like pure functions.
It's like we have this behavior of math.
The thing that's really unsettling about it is that it just feels like really, again, really, really abstract and strange.
There is that.
Yeah?
Could it be rewritten with the add that was just made?
It still breaks things because it has...
The sole purpose of the incur function is for me to actually visualize what we have here because everything is basically a function.
If I were to say something like mole four times three, it just comes back and it's like lambda.
I have no way to visualize that as a number because what that is is it's like a behavior basically.
That's a function that has the behavior of doing four times three.
I can't view it unless I apply it to something.
I have to do something with that to actually see the effect of it.
The incur function is actually not needed.
It's not really part of what we're doing, but I need it to actually just show you the result of the thing.
Would it for this then make more sense to define a print function that just applies incur and zero?
We could do that. Sure.
We could do show and or something.
Again, this is Python.
We do not have a print statement in this lambda calculus world here, but this is just debugging only.
You could do that.
What would happen there is you could then show the last result just to debug it.
It's really hard to debug this stuff if you're not on top of it.
Try writing equality?
We could try, but I would not be successful.
It can be done, but we'll get to something similar to that.
This is kind of interesting because when I look at what you've written there, which is multiply four and three,
multiplication basically takes two arguments.
You've written it as it takes single arguments, but my mind just drops the middle parenthesis and substitutes a comma there.
Multiplication definitely seems to be a behavior to me.
It's a little machine that turns some crank.
Four and three represent numbers, which kind of feel like state.
You've defined them earlier as behaviors, but it has to go back to zero, which is also actually a function.
Zero itself is a function, but it's kind of the initial state starting point,
of which InKr is then your kind of grounding machine.
I'm seeing F here as a generate starting value thing where you're shoving InKr zero into that.
If you just plugged zero into that, would it still work?
Like here? Like that?
No, I mean sorry, the numeral zero just for the debugging.
Oh, that? It would blow up because it's not a function.
If you did it, well I lost my...
If I tried to do that, it blows up because it's basically trying to call that as a function.
What about InKr of negative one?
Same thing.
Same thing? Okay.
Actually, I don't want zero there.
InKr. Yeah, InKr.
All right, now I do want to do one little digression here.
You're going to indulge me for a second here.
This thing that we're doing with the numbers is a little weird.
Well, maybe a lot weird actually.
Where you have the chaining of operations like that.
I was trying to think of some way to bring this back to Python in some capacity.
One example that I was thinking about was maybe the JSON object from hell problem.
Okay, probably people do stuff with the web, right?
You get a lot of dictionaries.
It's like dictionaries upon dictionaries and all this kind of stuff.
What if you wrote a function, like you had a function like getC,
where you gave me a dictionary,
and then what you were trying to do is navigate down into that.
Like that.
GetC of data.
Essentially, what it's doing is it's navigating down into nested dictionary.
That thing that you're doing there is kind of the same as this function thing
of repeated application of some operation, basically.
You do the get on the outer dictionary, and then you take the result of that,
you do the get on that, and you're kind of progressively going down into a bunch of dictionary.
Do people see that?
Yeah, question in the middle.
I thought you said this wasn't going to be relevant for work.
Oh, you'll see in a second.
I'm going to make it irrelevant in a second here.
So you have this chain.
I've had code like this that you have to deal with.
You have the chain dictionary thing.
But one of the problems that you sometimes run into is that people give you malformed data.
Maybe they just give it an empty dictionary or something,
and then all of a sudden you start getting key errors all the way down.
It's like, oh, okay.
So I have this dictionary, but the item might be there or might not be there.
And one of the things that you might do to fix that is to do a bunch of if statements
or some crazy thing like this.
I'm going to write something out.
You're not going to like the code here.
We're going to have a horrible code review later here.
But you might write something like this where it's like, okay, I have this getC function.
It will go down into a nested dictionary.
But if you give me a dictionary that does not have the data in there,
it's not going to blow up because it's using the get method.
It's trying to basically play defense a little bit.
Does everybody see that?
Okay.
What is your thought on this code that's in there?
Yeah, D is not a good name.
One thought is just this none check.
Yeah, well, yeah, I'm assuming types.
We should have gotten rid of those.
Yeah, no, there's like assumption of types.
But one thing that's a little weird is there's a lot of code repetition kind of going on here.
It's like I do the if check and then I do the get.
So I'm going to do a little trick on this.
I'm going to write a function called perhaps.
You're going to love this.
Where you give me a D and a function like that.
And then what I'm going to do is I'm going to check the D.
Basically, if D is not none, then I'm going to return the function applied to D.
And if it is, then I'll just return none back.
So I'm going to write like a little helper function like that.
And you're saying, where is Dave going with this exactly?
Okay, so here's how this is going to work.
You would basically say like perhaps data.
And then you would give it a function.
I'm going to use lambda here just because we've been doing lambda so much.
We'll do that.
So the idea is like you give me data and a function.
And as long as the data is like a not none, like a dictionary or something, I'm going to call the function.
If you were to try the same thing on like an empty dictionary, it just comes back with nothing.
Where it's like, oh, well, the empty dictionary didn't, you know.
Well, actually, it would have called this, but you're just getting like the none back.
Okay, so I'm writing like this little perhaps function.
And maybe I could start doing some chaining with that.
You're not going to like this, but.
Oh, the data is that.
Okay.
Doing this like crazy, this crazy kind of function where it's like you give me a piece of data and you give me a function.
And it's basically it's like, well, I'll only call the function if the data looks good.
Like if I can move forward, I'll try calling the function.
And so you could start like chaining this stuff up.
Now, this is where it's going to lose relevance for work.
I mean, somebody made the comment, it's like, oh, I actually could use this at work until we started doing this.
So, you know, maybe you've got this whole like chain of stuff going on.
We're going to see if I can actually type that in.
Okay, so this is like a totally different formulation of this thing.
I've got this like perhaps function.
And then I have this like this callback or something.
And it's like it's just chaining the thing.
It's kind of like what we're doing with the numbers, right?
You know, like the F of F of F of F.
Here it's like perhaps, perhaps, perhaps.
It's actually like the song.
I don't know whether people know the song.
There's like a famous song where it's like perhaps, perhaps, perhaps.
So you're doing that.
You might look at that and just say, well, that is, that is completely nuts.
Like, why would I type that in?
I don't know how our heads here.
I'm going to fix that by introducing a class.
Classes are not part of the lambda calculus, by the way.
This is a digression.
Okay, so I'm going to introduce a class.
And then as one does, we're going to do operator overloading.
And we're going to do the check here.
We're going to do a little bit of magic on it.
What this is going to allow us to do, and let me pull the slide up a little bit here,
is you're going to be able to do perhaps data
and then start chaining it through a bunch of function.
Oh, you get an object back.
And then the value has the 42 in it.
So you end up with that.
There's going to be a quiz on this later.
This is, in some sense, this is kind of an extension of the number idea.
It's like you're turning the crank where it's like you're taking functions
and you're applying a function one after the other,
except that you've got this extra weird little check in there.
It's a little weird.
Probably job security would go up substantially pulling a stunt like that.
And so the reason that I've done this, you're like, where is he going with this?
I guess my only comment on this is that perhaps this is a monad.
If you've ever heard that term kind of floated around by the functional programming people,
it's very difficult to kind of pin down what it is.
And this is an example of one.
So if you've ever heard that, it's associated with like turning the crank on a lot of function composition
and other things.
I am carefully choosing my words here because anybody, yeah, perhaps this is an example of a monad.
I've been very careful there because like any time anybody tries to define monad,
they get like about a thousand people coming on Hacker News and pouncing on them to tell them how it's wrong.
So I'm fully expecting that.
But I'm choosing my words carefully here.
Like if it ever comes up, if somebody says anything about monads, you could just say, oh, it's like the song.
You know, the perhaps, perhaps, perhaps song.
And then they'll probably get like even more angry.
Who knows here.
We do have to do the break in a second.
So I'm going to we're going to do that.
Can you repeat what you said that the API was that something takes what?
A function and a number?
For which part? The perhaps thing?
No, no, no. I mean, just kind of earlier you said we had one basic API, right?
Oh, for numbers. Yeah, numbers.
It's always a function and a starting point.
Function and starting point.
Starting point, yeah.
All right. We are going to do a break.
When we come back, we're going to do it's going to get even more insane.
Now, when we come back, we're actually going to talk about how to do something that looks like computation with this.
Like, can you write things like recursion and loops and other other things?
We have to build a little bit of stuff up for that.
But let's do a break.
So I think we're breaking until ten forty five.
I think it's the end of the break.
Thank you.
We'll get started in about three minutes here.
We'll start in a second here.
Everybody's ready for the post break quiz, right?
Same thing.
Okay.
All right.
I'm showing 1045, so I'm going to continue here.
I've got a fair number of people back. That's good. Okay.
What we're going to start with is I actually wanted to do a little bit of discussion
about what we've been doing in the first part.
The first thing that I actually wanted to talk about was function definitions a little bit.
One thing that I kind of stepped you through in the first part of the class this morning is this idea of defining
nested functions. We had the and function, which I think
looked something like that.
One of the things that I noticed is that some of this was actually getting shortened down.
I was progressively using things like the lambda function instead.
Instead of doing that, you could say, well, return a lambda function.
Or you could write the whole thing basically as a lambda function.
Like that. Basically, just sort of making it
more compact.
One thought that you can kind of explore is just what is the minimum notation
to specify what I'm doing here?
You're writing functions in different ways. The def format is what you're probably most familiar with as Python
programmers, but then taking it down to lambdas, making it more and more compact.
I started using the lambda character.
You can start asking questions like, can you take it even further than that?
The answer is yes.
One of the things that you could do with this is you could look at parts of this where
if you have two lambdas in a row like that, you could just write it as one.
That's another syntax for it.
You could also look at some of these things like these things at the end are basically
chained function calls, like x is applied to y, is applied to x.
You could just get rid of the parentheses.
Then as a final step, you could just get rid of the colon too,
because one dot is clearly easier to type than two dots.
You could write the code like that.
The reason that I'm showing you that is that's the syntax
that you will see if you start reading papers about lambda calculus.
They tend to use this very mathematical syntax. Essentially, all of these things are basically
the same. This last thing, this is a function that takes
two arguments, sort of one at a time. It's kind of hidden.
It's applying x applied to y to apply to x. If you wanted to see the Python code for that,
that's what it is. It's literally Python code that's doing that,
but it's been written in a highly compact way.
If you start looking at lambda calculus, you're going to see
this kind of use of symbols basically.
The question I have is pretty useless, but I think it's in the spirit of the whole
exercise we're having. But it's great, by the way. I like it.
Using the syntax, can x and y be more than one character, or that's a limit?
Usually in the lambda calculus, the variables are one letter.
Okay, so you only have like 26 or something like that?
I think actually in the lambda's calculus paper,
if you need more, you just put bars above it or something, or subscripts or something.
It's a math paper, so they kind of go in the math thing. But as written, though,
you only need 26 variables. You don't need more than that.
So when I think of the word calculus, maybe this is an incorrect or incomplete
kind of understanding of it, it's generally understood as the study of the rates of change.
Is calculus in here meaning anything about rates of change, or what does the term
calculus mean when they say it's in the calculus?
It's nothing to do with calculus as you would have learned in high school or anything like that.
But your question is actually onto something else. So part of what you have in this lambda calculus
is a certain symbology, if you will, where it's like this is a way of writing a function.
You have x and y are variables, and lambda means you have a function,
and variables next to each other means that you're calling functions and so forth.
So actually where the calculus part of it comes in is there are a bunch of conversions
that take place on these lambda expressions. There's actually
some things that you can do with functions.
I'll kind of go through some of these rules. One rule
is that you can rename an argument.
Let me illustrate that. So let's say you had lambda x, y,
x, y, x. You could, if you wanted to, just change one of the variables to some other name.
This is something you can do in the IDE, right, in Python.
It's like, oh, that was a dumb name for some variable. I'm just going to change the variable to some new name.
You can do that. So that is one rule, is you can rename arguments.
There is a caveat. You can't introduce a name clash.
So if somebody was already using the variable z
for some purpose, I can't just rename x to z.
So you can rename things as long as you don't introduce a clash.
This is something known as alpha conversion.
If you kind of read papers on this.
Another rule is that you can substitute
argument.
So let's say you had some lambda expression like this.
And then you applied it to some value like
a function call.
Although it's obscured by all the lambdas and stuff.
It's basically what you're doing is you're saying, okay, take all this stuff and now pass
a, b into it. Basically what the substitution rule is saying is that you could take
whatever is in the parentheses there and substitute it in for the x.
So you could rewrite this basically saying, okay, this is lambda y
and now I'm going to put the a, b in the place of wherever the x is,
I'm going to put a, b in there.
This is kind of the essence of a function call. If you apply a function to arguments,
you can take the argument and you can stick it into the function.
Yeah.
Could we see the notation for multiply? I'm curious about the
nested parameters. Do you have to keep the parentheses or what does that look like?
So let's see, where was multiply here?
I have it up.
I think you actually do need the parentheses there.
There is a notion of precedence. Sometimes you need to group things
in a certain way and parentheses are still used to do that. So if you need to group things
in a certain way.
So the parentheses do actually have significance.
You said it was lambda y, but where does that first y come from?
So the y, this is where this thing gets really confusing.
Here there is only a single argument, which is the a, b.
And it turns out that the a, b went in as the argument x.
And because it only went into the x, the y is
remaining. There is a remaining argument y that needs to be provided.
If you had a second thing out here like z, then that would become
what you would have is the y would basically go away and you would have the z.
So the reason that was
basically a lambda y there is I only gave one of the argument.
I don't want to dwell on this too much, like the
substitution thing, but the gist of the idea here is that you can basically
substitute the arguments. It's like you literally take the argument and you just paste it
into the thing. There is also a caveat on that
that you can't introduce name clashes
also with that. Here is kind of a weird example. Let's say you had
lambda x, y, x, y, x and then you decided to pass in
x, y into that.
This is like a really mind bending thing because it's like is
that x, y the same as the x, y that's in the function?
Let me give you a python example of this. Let's say you had a function like
f of x, y like that. Maybe
2 times x plus y or something. We're in the python world.
Let's say you had an outer x and an outer y
like that. It's basically scoping issues. Is the outer x
the same as the x in that function?
No, because it's like x was basically an argument that got passed in.
The global x's and the local x's are different.
That is the same thing that's happening here. If I have a
function that takes x and y as an argument and does something with it,
any x, y that's outside, that's actually a different x, y.
You can actually run into really weird problems with that.
Actually maybe a different example of that. Let's say I were just to pass in y
there. This does not get reduced to lambda y, y, y, y.
It's like no.
The only way that you can actually fix that is you have to
rename one of the variables. That's actually what the first rule is about. If you want to do that,
you would have to rename one of the variables and then you could
do the thing.
Like that. Again, I don't want to totally dwell
on that. But that's another... This is getting back to your question. How's the calculus
coming into this? This is sort of it. You have this symbology
here where you have these lambda expressions and you can replace variables and you can
substitute things. One of the other things that you can do...
Let me just tell you what this is. This is like beta reduction is what this is called.
Oh,
yeah, yeah, yeah.
Good catch there.
The debugging is always a little difficult on that.
You have rules like that. There is another rule that is...
I'll do kind of a simple example of it.
One rule is that you can
make a function. Let's say you had this x equals 3 just sitting there in your
Python program or you really wanted to annoy people with it, like at work or something.
You could take that and just turn it into a lambda function
that just had 3 passed into it.
I don't know why you would necessarily do that.
You could just say, oh, I'm going to make a function and then I'll pass in the argument as the value of the
function. You're going to end up basically back where you started.
Think of it as gratuitous obfuscation or something. That's another thing that you can do with this
is introduce functions or introduce a variable and so forth.
If you look at some of the papers on some of this stuff,
they actually talk about these substitutions. This is a slide
from the Lambda Calculus book from 1941.
He's talking about these rules. You can replace parts of formulas
with name substitutions. It's talking about basically symbol replacement,
like substitutions and so forth. One of the reasons why
this is talking about this is where is it going exactly? You have this
weird symbolic system and these rules for replacing things.
In the early 20th century, there was a lot of discussion about the nature
of math. Specifically, could all of mathematics
be derived solely from symbolic
manipulation? If you had the proper set of axioms
expressed in symbols, could you derive all of mathematical truth
from that representation? There's a whole school of formalism in math.
Formal systems and axioms and all this stuff. David Hilbert was one of
the main figures at the center of a lot of that. Basically,
posing questions, it's like, can you decide any math problem
by just turning the crank on a symbol manipulator?
No creativity at all. If you had the right set of axioms
because you just turned the crank and proved stuff by turning the crank, would you eventually
get to mathematical truth from that? There's a whole lot of
stuff that came out of that work. One question
that got posed, it is this question, can all of math be derived from
a formal system? If you had a statement from logic, this is
kind of a statement of a problem. If you had a statement from first order logic, could you write an algorithm
that would just tell you yes or no whether that statement was true or not?
It's kind of an interesting idea. It's like, wow, that'd be kind of cool.
If you just specify a problem and then it's like Star Trek or something. Like, computer, tell me if it's
true or not. That would be awesome. It's kind of posing
that question. Is there an algorithm to do that?
The short answer is no. There's a whole bunch of stuff that came out of the
1920s and 30s. One thing that came out was the incompleteness
theorem. Kurt Gdel probably butchered the pronunciation on that.
There was a result saying that you could not prove statements about arithmetic
within a formal system. That kind of came out. The lambda calculus
early 1930s was kind of in that same school
as well, basically proving that you could not have an axiomatic system or you could
prove these statements. All the stuff that we've been doing kind of emerged
out of that. You can still buy the book.
This is the Calculia of Lambda Conversion. It's kind of interesting to look at, but this is from 1941
by Alonzo Church. It kind of talks about that.
A lot of what's actually being talked about is just how do you mathematically
describe the ability to calculate something?
How do you mathematically describe an algorithm? That's kind of like a really
weird kind of problem. We all know what an algorithm is. It's like a
step-by-step process, but how would you mathematically
formulate that? In some sense, the lambda calculus is really about that.
Some other figures at this time, by the way, you have Turing. There's Turing
machines also around 1936. One of the big results is proving that Turing
machines and lambda calculus are equivalent to each other. I'm not going to go further
into that, but just trying to put some historical context to sort of when
this took place and what they were thinking about. A lot of it was this thinking about
math. Can you prove all of math through algorithms? The things are basically
showing that you could not. That's kind of some interesting history
on it. Where we're going to pick up with it here is
talking about programming. About 20 years later,
you have the creation of Lisp programming. I think 1960
is when Lisp came out. In the start of the tutorial, it kind of mentions
like, well, everybody calls it lambda because Lisp called it lambda.
If you read the paper on Lisp, it's kind of like, why do they call it lambda?
What are they thinking about? As far as I can tell,
the only real influence possibly is the notation of the
lambda. The lambda calculus paper actually is cited in the
Lisp paper, but it's kind of cited in this way where it's like, well, we're going to use
the lambda notation to define functions because there's some convenient features
of that. The actual Lisp paper is actually talking more about AI.
They're trying to build a system for AI programming or some other thing.
I was not able to see any other mention of the lambda calculus
in the Lisp paper, but they're kind of borrowing the notation for it.
It looks like they're doing a slightly different thing with the notation because they're passing two arguments
into the...they just kind of went their own way with it.
What you can do in Lisp, like Lisp, you can write functions with multiple arguments.
They're thinking of lambda as a convenient way to encode functions and what are known as
S expressions and other things. The notation is sort of coming from lambda calculus,
but it doesn't seem like much else is actually coming from...like Lisp is not doing all this
crazy number stuff and encoding things in that way.
It's sort of an interesting connection there.
Lisp in some way is kind of an interesting jumping off point
for what we're going to do next because one of the things in Lisp that was very focused on was
Lisp processing. That's the whole name of the language. Lisp is short for
Lisp processing. One question that we sort of run into
is in this lambda calculus world, is there any way
to actually build a data structure? Let's say you wanted to do
lists. How in the world are you going to do
lists? Is there any way to make a tuple or a pair
or anything? In the Lisp world, there are some
functions for building data structures. There's basically a function cons,
which essentially builds a pairing of data.
There's a function car that gives you the thing on the left, and then there's a
function cutter, which gives you the thing on the right. The names, by the way, are taken from the IBM
704 hardware on which the Lisp was first implemented.
Those function names are kind of weird, but there's this
question. Could you build a data structure entirely out of a
function definition? The answer is
you can. I'm going to do this in Python in kind of a weird way to start.
Let's say you wrote a function like cons
av. One way that you could build a data structure is you
could define an inner function. I'm just going to call it select.
You pass in an argument, and then you just check the argument.
If it's zero, you return a, and if it's one, you return
b. Then you just return that
function back. It looks a little hacky and weird, but
it actually works. You could say p is equal to cons two, three,
and it comes back, and it's like, well, here's this function.
Then you would call the function with zero or one to get the data that you want.
You can do it.
You could write car as basically returning p of zero,
and you could write cutter of p returning
p of one. Don't do this at work. This would be a terrible thing.
Your coworkers would sort of hate seeing this sort of thing, but
it's kind of remarkable in a way where it's like actually it is kind of like a data
structure just totally from function definition.
I'm not using a tuple or anything there. It's like here's a function.
It's got this weird selector thing in the middle of it.
Everybody kind of see that?
Now where I'm going with this, you're saying, okay, where's he going with this?
Didn't we do a selector thing at the start of the morning?
Yeah, the switch thing. We just did that. We did the
switch thing. Maybe that's
how we build a data structure. Instead of doing this cons thing like that,
maybe we can do it using kind of the lambda thing.
Let me pull up the slide a little bit. We're going to have a function that takes in
two arguments, and then we're going to define a function
that's kind of like our selector here. We're going to have our argument s,
and then we're just going to use it to select the two arguments.
Now you're looking at that saying there's no way that can work.
If I say cons two, three, it comes back and it's like, ah, this is
horrible lambda function. The way that you're supposed to use that
is you would pass in like maybe true or false or something. If I said P of true,
it comes back and it picks the two out. Remember that
true is the thing that picked the first argument. True is going to pick out the A,
and false is going to pick out the three.
I don't know.
Is that crazy or not?
You can do that.
You basically have a data structure.
Keep in mind that two and three are not part of this, but I'm just using it for
illustration here. You can say cars P.
You could use your numbers here. We're not really using the arguments.
We're just storing the argument.
I'll give you a second to type that in there.
I think this is actually a really mind blowing idea where it's like
a function and can build it just from a function you can create a data structure.
Sort of out of nothingness. It's like this is not a
list. It's not a list. I'm not storing any kind of data and any sort of thing
that you would recognize, but it's just pure function.
Although we could link them together.
If you wanted to make a linked list or something,
you could do cons of two or three or something.
A question about language.
I don't know in the papers what terms they use. Maybe they use lambda or something.
Do you know when the term function got introduced or how that came about?
I have no idea. Function has been used in math forever.
I'm not sure of the history on that.
I think one of the interesting things here is when I think in a beginning
programming class, if they talk about a function, they'll often refer to it as a machine.
They'll draw it as a little box with some robot arms or something.
I think back to this time,
they were working with more machinery than what we have now.
I don't know how language comes about and constructs these metaphors
which we think about these problems with.
You're actually on to something interesting.
In the paper about lambda calculus, one of the things that he talks about is
what is a function exactly?
It's a function that you pass it in and it produces some output.
He leaves it totally as that.
There's an argument and you place it and some output comes out.
One thing that he actually talks about is, keep in mind, they're trying to prove
all of mathematics. They're thinking about way more than numbers.
In math class, you often think of, you have a function and you pass it two and then you get four out of it.
One of the things in the paper is he talks about things from the actual calculus.
Let's say you have a function and you want to compute the derivative of a function.
That's a function. There would be a higher order function
where a function comes in and it figures out what the derivative function is
and the derivative comes out.
They're thinking about functions in this really generic way where something comes in, something comes out,
and it can describe everything. If you want to do numbers, that's fine. If you want to do functions, that's fine.
It's very, very
weirdly generic.
Have you ever got this data thing up here?
I always find this deeply weird.
The first time I saw this, I was like, no way. Wait, what?
Building a data structure out of a function like that?
One of the reasons why I'm having you do this, by the way,
is because you're doing this in a way that's not really a function.
How do you get the previous number?
What in the world could this possibly have to do with pairs or data structures?
One thing that I forget, I think you might have asked it,
how do you get from the one number to the previous number?
How would you get two out of that?
You're on the right track, actually.
Maybe not the successor function, but one approach for this,
and this is a total hack, by the way, is you could
start with 0, 0 as a pair, and then you
could ratchet your way up to 3.
You could essentially say, I'm going to go up to 3.
But as I go, I'm building pairs.
The first thing in the pair is the number, and the second thing in the pair is the previous number.
Maybe I could use that
to figure out how to get the predecessor number.
I actually already kind of
did an example of that. I had this weird tuple thing. I don't know whether you remember that.
I'm not even sure it's in my environment here.
I had this weird tuple thing. Well, I'll type it in again.
I had this function, maybe I'll call it T,
where I had this weird thing where I was making a tuple
where I did like this.
Then I did some weird thing where it's like, take three applications of T
and then apply it to the tuple 0, 0.
What this thing is doing is this T function, if you make
a tuple, there's your tuple, and then you apply it to A, it basically
ratchets its way up
up through the numbers.
Maybe I could do something like that. We're in the Python world right now, but
maybe you could do something along that line.
Metaphorically, this feels like if you have a crank and it's always turning right,
you just turn that crank upside down and now you have a left turning crank. We actually don't care that these things are 0s or 1s.
We just care that the arm is turning in a certain direction.
It seems like it's easy to get hung up on the fact that there's 0, and 0 kind of means something to us as people.
The negative number somewhat means something. In a very strictly mechanical sense,
you're just performing these actions. It's a right turn or it's a left turn, and that's really all it is.
You have to figure out how to inverse this.
This isn't even really reversing the direction. It's turning the crank on something that produces something a little bit different.
What we're going to do with this is
we could take that t function and turn it into
actually, let me do it with the lambda here.
We could do this in the lambda calculus. We could write this function t where it's like,
give me a pair, and then I'm going to do exactly what's up there.
I'm going to basically say I'm going to do a cons. That's the act of making the tubal.
The first element of the cons is basically the successor of the car, the P.
I'll try to say that a couple of times.
The first item is basically, the car is the leftmost one.
The first one, yeah.
I think that will work. We could write something like that.
It's basically doing the same thing as the other function.
It's just written in using our terminology here.
P0 is basically, that's the car.
Plus 1 is the successor of that. Then P0 is the car again.
You could write a function like that.
If I were to take one of my numbers, like 4, and apply it to t,
and then apply it to a starting point,
like that,
this is exactly the same thing that I was doing with the Python thing above.
Let me save it here. You're like, well, what is that? It's basically a pair.
If I were to look at the first thing in the pair,
and then apply it to my anchor function or something, it comes back and says,
well, that's 4. It basically ratcheted its way up this sequence of pairs.
Then the second one is the previous number.
Question here.
I anticipate this is the next thing you're going to say,
but that means we're only storing one previous.
Sure, we can go back to this previous one that we stored, but we still can't undo function calls.
We can go back to zero all the time,
or you have to count from zero every time.
This is a horribly impractical way to do this.
If you wanted to get the previous number to 10,000 or something,
we've got to do 10,000 function calls to get up to 10,000, and then we go back one and throw it out.
The way the predecessor works is you basically take a number,
so here's your number n, and you're going to apply that number to this t function,
which means you're going to ratchet your way up.
You're going to work your way up, and then when you're done with the whole thing,
you just discard it and you take the cutter of it. Whatever the second number is that will give you that.
It feels wildly impractical because my brain has already
abstracted away the fact that a number is all of the calls from zero up to that number anyway.
That's why my brain was...
If I've done that right, this should work.
We had this example where we did four applied to three.
I don't know whether you remember that. We got this crazy result where it's like, oh, that's 81.
It was like doing exponentiation. If this predecessor thing is working,
I should be able to say B is the predecessor of A, and the predecessor
of A better be 80 unless I've done something wrong here, which it's possible that I have.
Oh, I think t needs to have...
You need to apply t to 0, 0.
Let's...
And apply it to t.
Apply it to t.
Let's try it out here.
80.
This is just mind-blowing.
Again, it's wildly impractical. You would never in a programming language,
if you wanted to get to the previous number, you're not going to count up to the number
back one. Why would you do that?
In some sense, you're seeing... This is the more mathematical side of this thing.
If you're just talking about pure math, it all exists in this
world of infinite abstraction. This is not an implementation so much,
but it's a way of showing that you can get to the previous number
if you need to.
Yeah.
Is this kind of similar to async programming in that you define a behavior and then at the very bottom you shove an event loop into it
and then let the magic work?
You think it needs an await in there somewhere?
I'm going to run it over to the language summit, which is taking place down the hall.
Okay.
Do people have that entered? Do I need to leave the code up there for a second?
I do think that's kind of an ingenious hack, actually.
It's like how do I get the previous number? It's like basically making a bunch of pairs
and then you just store the number in the previous number and then you toss
the first number away. I'm not sure I would have thought of that.
If I had just given a blank slate, you'd say, give me the previous number.
I'm not that sure that would have come to mind.
What is a pair? Is a pair like a state change? State one is the left-hand side and state two is the right-hand side?
I know that it's two things.
It's like a pair of two values and it's a function
where you pass it a function to select one of the two values.
Everything is a function.
I don't know.
I'll leave that up for a second there.
I forget who asked about equality, but
that is actually kind of a next step for this thing.
We're kind of building up some machinery here. We do have the ability to go down
now. Oh, you could implement subtraction, by the way.
I should do subtraction.
Subtraction turns out to be fairly easy.
If I want to take five and subtract three or subtract two from it,
how do you do that? You apply the predecessor function two times to five.
If I wanted to subtract y from x,
you would just do y applications of predecessor to x.
Let's just make sure that works there.
Yeah, it's like once you can get to the one number before,
then the way that subtraction is, it's like
you just do that. So, I'm going to do that.
If you can test a number for
zero, this allows you to start
checking things. Why would you want to test a number for
zero? If you can start doing tests,
you can start checking things.
Why would you want to test a number for zero? If you can start doing tests,
then maybe you could start thinking about control flow.
If statements. How does an if statement work?
You have an if, and then you test something, and then you pick one of two branches.
That would be an interesting feature to have
if we're going to do programming.
The next challenge here is how would you test a number
to see whether it's zero or not?
Let me give you a hint on this.
Keep in mind that a number, like if I have the number two,
it was basically that.
The number zero
was that.
Numbers are always going to take two inputs there.
Do you have a question on that?
Keep in mind numbers, they always have these two inputs. There's always an F, there's always an X.
If N is a number, then it's a function that has these two inputs. It has an F and an X.
How would I make that return true
if N is zero?
A little hint on it.
The behavior of zero
is that it always returns the X.
If you have zero, it just universally returns the X.
I'm going to do that, my is zero check.
If N is a number and it's zero, I'm just going to return true
because that's what I'm trying to test. If it's zero, it's true.
If N is zero, that is definitely going to return true.
The question is
what do you put here?
You're very close.
The thing that's going to go here
is you can make a function that just always returns false.
Keep in mind the second argument
or the first argument to a number has to be a function.
This is a function that takes an argument, but we just totally disregard the argument.
We just always return false. It turns out that that
works. If we do is zero, zero, it comes back as true.
If we do is zero, one,
it comes back as false. It always comes back as false for the other
number. Essentially what's happening with that is the zero is kind of like a special case
where the function is actually never called. This false function
just never gets executed. Instead you get true back.
If you have any other number, then this thing gets called and it's like, well, that's just always false.
Just a
realization of something that I found my brain doing
that might help somebody else is sometimes you use
F. I'm used to thinking F as a function. Yes, in this case it's going to be a function,
but it's not the name of the function, it's actually the argument.
The lambda F in the middle with the false is not
the function. It's accepting an argument.
It could be anything. It could be X, it could be G.
F has special meaning in my brain and I keep conflating it in weird ways.
The fact that everything is a function here is just
mind blowing.
I'll leave that up for a few minutes here.
Oh,
I don't know.
Like if I said is zero is zero?
I'm not sure what that is going to do.
Well, it comes back as true, but I'm not exactly sure what to make of it.
As a Python programmer, I'll just say
that's some kind of duck typing thing and I'm not sure what that is.
It works, but you don't know why and what the answer is.
Technically not true. Maybe it's a type error.
Where this is going?
Think about what we've got. We've got Boolean logic,
we've got add and subtract, we've got multiply,
we have the ability to do data, we have the cons thing.
What we have built is a weird assembly code of function.
It's pure functions, but think of it as maybe an instruction set or something.
We have all these things you can do and, or not, suck,
you've got all of this stuff
and it's kind of like machine code
in a way. It's a very strange kind of machine code
in that it's so abstract. It's just purely in this world of functions
where it exists, but if you have that,
maybe you can start doing more interesting things like writing recursive functions
and other things. Maybe a challenge here
could you implement a factorial function?
I'll do it in kind of a normal Python way first.
Could you implement that? This is a function that's like turning the crank,
it's actually doing kind of interesting stuff. Can that be implemented
using the assembly language that we had on the
previous thing? Let's actually try that out.
Here's how it's going to work.
The argument to fact is n. That's going to be the argument
to our function. We're going to take a number. What is the very first thing
that you're doing in the function? You're doing an
is zero check. We're going to do a check, is zero of n.
What is that going to return, by the way?
It's going to return true or false. What do true and false do?
They pick values out. I'm going to
break this across multiple lines, but true and false
kind of act like an if statement.
True, you have two values, A and B. You pick one of them.
That's what's going to happen here.
What is the true part of it? One.
What is the false part of it?
If it's not zero, then we're doing like a multiply.
We have a multiply operator where we're going to multiply n
by fact by the predecessor of n.
There's a fair number of parentheses there.
Make sure it's not a syntax error.
It's kind of a, admittedly, it's a little tough to
wrap one's brain around that, but it's almost a literal translation of the Python code
into this kind of low level machine code.
If it's zero, if it is, we're going to return one. If it's not, we're going to multiply n by
factorial of n minus one, or the predecessor of n.
Anybody get that to work?
Yeah.
It's kind of like the, I don't know, like one of these battle scenes
where the evil villain dies and the whole evil army dies at the same time.
We've kind of worked up to this point now that the whole thing just blows up in infinite
recursion. It's like totally disappointing.
So if you do that, do people get the maximum recursion thing?
What's going on with that?
We have definitely invented a loop, but
it has run away from us.
The, the,
the,
no.
Increasing the recursion depth will not help this.
The basic problem here is that we are using a highly inferior programming language called
Python. No, I say that facetiously.
I don't know why this is blowing up.
If I, let's say I have a function f of x and I return like three times x plus one.
If I say f of like two plus ten, how does that work exactly?
It does the argument first
and then it calls the function. Like basically Python evaluates arguments
like so if like, you know, like the arg goes first
and essentially what we have done in Python is we have written a function
that is kind of like an if statement. I mean for lack of a better description,
we've written a function like choose a, b
where we have a, like we have a test. Like we have something that looks like
this. Like if t return a, else return b.
That is kind of what's going on with like the true and false basically
or the is zero test in a sense. We're basically saying like, like imagine like
let's say you have like a is two and b is three. We've written a function where it's like
okay choose, like if a less than b, choose a otherwise b. We've written
like a conditional essentially. And the problem with that
is that that, you can't do that. Like here's an example of how you can't
do that. Like let's say I decided to choose, like choose a
not equal to zero, a one divided by a.
Like that's right.
Like let's say you've written, wrote a function like that. It's basically going to
blow up because it's actually trying to do both of the arguments at the same time.
I mean like in that function it's basically saying oh I'm doing the a and I'm
doing the one divided by a at the same time. And like it just like
explodes. Essentially it doesn't know what to do. That is not
how control flow works in most languages. Like if I were to write this out using like a
like an if statement in Python, like a if a not equal to zero else one divided by a.
Oh maybe it should be equal to zero.
Let's try that. That does not blow up.
Whereas my other one does.
The reason that this one doesn't blow up is that Python is smart enough to not go
down the else. Like it basically does the check first and then it decides
like I'm going to do one or the other. And that is what is killing
our code up here is that when you do these functions like the one
and the multiply, it's basically doing both. Like it goes down both paths.
And it turns out that the second path just explodes in infinite recursion.
Essentially it has to do with Python like
eagerly evaluating arguments. It's like it always wants to evaluate arguments.
So it's like running away with the calculation.
Yes. But not in the way that you might think.
So the solution to this is actually
yeah you can turn that off but the question is how do you do that?
Let me go to the interactive example here.
So let's say you wanted to turn off one divided by a.
This is the thing that has the zero division. So let's say you wanted to get rid of that.
How would you not do that? Well one of the ways that you would not do it
is you could shove it into like a zero argument function.
Like you could just say f is lambda. Like no arguments.
And then you put the one divided by a in there. You're like
what did that do exactly? Well what you're doing there is you're basically delaying the calculation
to some later point in time. Like if I want to do that
then I could put parentheses on it and I could let the thing fire basically.
And it turns out that you could do that with like this choose function.
Like you could say choose t a b. If t
return a per n. Keep in mind this is a really subtle
change here.
Like you're evaluating only if the thing is needed essentially. So what you would
do with that is you could say choose a equals zero
and then you would shove like basically lambdas into this thing.
Oh I need to have like my thing there.
That is
admittedly a little
weird. It's basically addressing like a problem with Python.
I mean Python wants to like eagerly do all the arguments. What we're doing with this lambda
trick is we're basically pulling it back from the brink essentially saying like okay note
the arguments basically are functions and I'm only going to
evaluate that function if I need to go down that branch. That is essentially what's happening.
So there's a question in the back there.
Everything is more sane doing it the way
Python does it. I think most programmers like when you call a function you like
to have the arguments evaluated. So almost every programming
language works in the way that Python does.
Yeah it's like if all the evaluation gets delayed
then everything just gets crazy. I mean it's like
just being a
yeah. No you would not do this.
I mean this is sort of illustrating. You're kind of getting into like this
evaluation issue with Python. Like how do things happen?
And it turns out that it blows up what we've done with the lambda calculus because
this factorial thing is not working because it's basically
evaluating like both branches kind of at the same time and it's like exploding.
Now we can fix it. Now I will just preface this
as saying that this is mainly required because of Python.
You know basically the
eager evaluation. One way that I can fix this is I can essentially
implement like a different implementation of true and false.
I apologize for doing this but
the way that you can redo it is you're going to introduce a function call.
Like that. And then I'm also going to have to redo the
zero function.
So I'm going to have to
I'm basically going to have to introduce
like this extra function call in there.
And then in this fact thing I'm going to have to do this like lambda trick.
I'm not super happy about doing this. This is really not part of the
lambda calculus that we're doing here. This is purely a hack
to get Python to not do both branches of that, of the if basically.
So I can make it work but I've got to do this like patch up.
I'll give you a few
moments to kind of type that in.
So if you do that it's going to work.
Actually this concept of when things evaluate
is actually a really big deal in functional programming. I mean if you get into some of these other languages like
Pascal and all sorts of stuff they focus a lot on this. Like when do things evaluate?
Is it evaluated lazily? Does it evaluate eagerly?
When do things happen? And we're kind of facing that.
Again having to work around some limitations of Python and that
it does not allow this kind of lazy evaluation.
I don't know.
Do you have a question, Yarco?
Are you doing
a swag bag? Like promotion?
Okay.
Yeah, it looks
at the end of this tutorial it's like Thelma and Louise or something. I'm running away and then like
all that. Did anybody get that to work?
It's pretty mind blowing. It's like wow.
Recursion here.
Do you just get around that by having a dummy argument basically?
I've had to break it here
and actually you could put a dummy argument in there
but I'm not sure that it adds clarity actually. I was actually thinking about
this in the preparation of this tutorial because it's like if you add
a dummy argument then I have to put something in here.
I mean like I could just pass like some dumb
it breaks it in spirit. No, you could make it work by just
passing a dummy argument. I kind of felt honestly in prepping
I sort of felt like this is already a hack to kind of deal with Python.
And it's not just leaving it as just a zero argument. Just acknowledge that
okay this is a Python specific hack that we have to do.
It's a little unfortunate. I mean it's like normally in the lambda calculus you would not need to do this
because it's not like the lambda calculus doesn't specify like an evaluation order.
So like mathematically it's not needed but it's like a purely Python
required thing here.
I would just argue that it's not a Python requirement. It's a programming
requirement right? Because like I said most programming languages would do this right?
Python does have a few things that it does that makes it weird compared to other languages. This is not one of them.
No, like you would have to do this in C or you'd have to do this in Scheme or Lisp.
The only place you probably would not have to, well not the only place, but you wouldn't have to do this in Haskell
for instance because you'd have to do lazy evaluation and that.
Now there is something kind of coming up. We got that to work.
We're not done with this yet. One thing that we are abusing
is the fact that the lambda calculus does not actually allow
global variables.
There are no global variables. There's no assignment. It's only functions.
And all of this stuff that I'm doing with the assignment of the names
like fact equal is zero equal and so forth, that is technically not allowed.
You're not allowed to just make a variable and store it. Because this kind of implies
storage. If I make a name, it's like, oh it must be storing it someplace.
You can't do that. That is not
a legal kind of thing to do. And it actually presents a really
interesting programming problem when you start talking about recursion.
And here's
why it becomes interesting with recursion.
If you're doing this recursive stuff, you have to
refer to yourself basically. Like that's the whole way that recursion works.
It's like you have factorial and it's like I have factorial and then a bunch of stuff and then in the middle of
factorial I have this self reference.
Like,
right, but how do I get myself? No, it's a weird problem.
I want to do this in Python for a second. But you have this function
like let's say you had a factorial function in Python. We're going to do it with lambda
here. Just like lambda n. And I'm going to do it in kind of a shorter way.
Like 1 if n equals 0, else n times fact n minus 1.
So let's say you had something like that. Let's just make sure that it works.
Lambda.
Okay, back to 24.
Okay, so here's the challenge.
How would you
rewrite that to not have a self reference to yourself?
Like to not have that fact. Like how would you get rid of that?
What?
No, we're working purely with functions.
So we can't do like for loops or anything like that.
You have to use a Y combinator? Eventually.
You're jumping the gun on where we're heading here. So we're heading to something like that.
No, it's, you can't have, like basically you cannot have
that global reference.
Like that is the thing that isn't, like we do not want that.
We're not allowed to have that. And so if you can't have that,
there's this question of like, well, what do you do there?
And one of the things that you could do there is you could pass it as an argument
at first glance.
At first glance,
that's going to look crazy.
Let me just shorten it up a little bit.
I mean, you could do that. You could like introduce like an extra argument there
and then just pass the function in as an extra argument.
I actually already kind of did a horrible trick with that. Like I think at one point I said, like if you had X is two,
you could actually say X is equal to like lambda Y, Y and then apply it to two
as this like totally just dumb thing that you could do in code.
That is kind of what we're doing here. Or it's just like, okay, if I can't have the fact
in there, I'll just pull it out as an argument.
No, this doesn't work in Python.
No, no, no. So you're going to look at that and you're going to say, wait a minute.
You're just like, no. Like all that happened there is
you moved the fact out into this outer part.
And it's like, you're like Beasley. It's like, come on, man.
You can't do that. What are you doing?
You can't do that. You cannot have the factor.
It seems like the factorial is just a name to help us describe
that particular combination of functions. There's no actual storing of global things.
We've just given it a name as a convenience for us to refer to that particular
combination. Anything that has that combination will then be a factorial.
And if you change that combination, then it's just something else and it's just some other name.
So why do we even care about storing that name?
Why do we care about globals or variables? It just doesn't even matter.
The problem here is I need to have a reference to myself.
I mean, on the implementation, yeah, but on the math level, who cares?
Yeah. Well, even kind of on the math reference,
if you're going to express recursion, there's kind of this like, okay, you're going to recurse, but how do you
reference the... There's kind of a weird cycle set up where it's like you're recursing, but
how do you get a reference to the thing that you're recursing on?
No, it's wild. Now, the solution to this will blow your mind, actually.
Okay, so keep in mind, I cannot use fact there. Fact,
that is no. Okay, so that is God there. So the solution to this problem
is to do the opposite of everything that you've been taught about proper software
and to do the opposite of don't repeat yourself.
And what is the opposite of don't repeat yourself? Repeat yourself.
If you need to pass yourself in
as an argument, you just cut and paste the code and do it twice.
So you have to keep cutting and pasting
until you get to your zero representation, right? No, because it's
F. So this thing, the first argument is F,
which is the recursive function. So I'm going to pass
myself. I'm going to take the code and I'm going to paste it in there and I'm going to pass it in there.
Now, it still doesn't work. Keep in mind,
if I try that, it's going to blow up with some exception.
And it's like, okay, what is wrong
there?
Yeah.
Now, the thing that's wrong here is I'm not following the API.
Not to get back to APIs, but the API to this thing is you pass a function first
and a number second. And I'm not doing that here.
Like when I do the recursive call and I say F of N minus 1, I'm not following the API.
I'm just passing the number. There's like, I need the F.
Like where's the F? I'm missing an argument
basically. I have a two argument function, fact, like this.
The F and the N, that's two arguments. I'm only passing one of the arguments.
So now there's this problem, like where do I get the second argument?
You just pass it in.
I think that's what you said. You just pass F. Like F is the function.
So you pass it. Like F is a two argument function.
It takes an F and an N. The first argument is F.
So you just pass it as the second argument, or as the first argument.
Works perfectly.
Looks a little bad.
A lot bad. Like having the duplicated function
thing there.
Yeah, we're going to get to that.
I guess we should do the slide update there.
No, this is crazy.
It's like, okay, so you can do a recursive function
and just,
you don't need the name there.
Maybe just to illustrate
that the name is kind of unimportant, I could actually, I could just take this code
and just drop it,
just drop it in like a print statement.
Yeah, print function. So you could just print, like, you know, lambda,
and then drop like five on it, like that.
And it would work.
It's just like a big expression. I mean, if you really wanted to make this
hardcore, you could just put it inside an F string probably, and then
it would work. I'm not going to do that, but that's
kind of amazing.
Alright, everybody get that.
Yeah, there will be a quiz later.
Yeah, question there.
That's depending on the short circuiting of the arguments, right? So if the first branch evaluates to
zero, then it just returns zero, sorry. If the first branch evaluates
to one, okay, okay. Yeah, definitely the short circuiting, we need that.
Like, that not going down both paths. And Python is kind of giving us that.
So I want to say a little bit more about that.
This whole thing, the whole repeating yourself
part of it should have made you feel like really kind of awful
in a way. I mean, normally in programming you don't want to do that, like having to repeat
like cut and paste code. I mean, actually reading that is kind of making my eyes
bleed a little bit. Trying to figure that out.
And I want to talk about an alternate way of doing this.
Before I do that, I want to talk about school for a second.
I don't see anybody like head down on the desk really here too bad. But like in school,
like in math class, did you ever have that experience of like this is so boring.
I just want to die. Like, you know, can the next 45 minutes pass?
And then in trying to pass the time, there was like a common thing
that I used to do, which was to pull out my hand calculator.
And then you just start pressing buttons on the calculator and you're like, I'm so bored.
Has anybody done this square root thing where it's like get the calculator and you punch a number
and you just start doing square root over and over and over again and the numbers get smaller
and then eventually it hits one and then it just starts hitting one and one and one and one and one over again.
I can't be the only one who's done that. So I'm sure that
everyone has done that.
So one of the things that you were doing there is actually
exploring one of the most interesting things of all about the lambda calculus
and recursive functions and other things. So one of the things that you've found in doing that
is you found something known as a fixed point.
It's kind of a mathematical term, but a fixed point, it's basically a function
where if you give it like an input, you just get the input back.
Like square root of one is one. It turns out that one is a fixed point of square root,
meaning that if you just call square root like over and over and over and over again,
you just end up back where you started.
So you end up with something, that's an example of a fixed point.
Basically you have a function, you give it an input, you get the same thing back.
And one question you can ask is like is this in any way
possibly related to recursion?
What you're doing with recursion is you're kind of turning the crank on this function, like f of f of f of f of f.
It's kind of the same thing that you were doing with the calculator, right?
It's like okay, I'm pushing the square root button over and over and over again.
Is there anything that you can get from that?
So to talk about that, I'm going to go back to this factorial function for a second.
I'm going to do it as kind of the lambda version of it.
This is what we started with. This is our kind of original function.
And one of the things that we did in the previous part
is we did this trick with the variable name.
So we did this fact where we passed it like an f.
And then we did that. This was the thing where it's like, well that makes no sense at all.
I mean like, what do you mean? Like you have the fact on both sides of the
both sides of the equation there.
I'm going to take out the middle part of that
and put it into its own variable.
I'm essentially taking out the part in the parentheses.
I'm taking that and putting it in its own variable.
Maybe I'll put parentheses around it just to emphasize that.
So if you do that, you're going to end up
with kind of this weird statement at the end. I'm going to put some comments on this
by the way because I'm not sure that the things that follow are not going to work as Python code
for a second. But what's happening is I kind of took the middle of this thing out.
And then you end up with this relation.
Fact equals R of fact.
People kind of see how that came about there.
It's basically the sneaky variable trick where I turned fact into a variable
and then kind of factored it out there.
If you look at that last statement
and you ponder it a little bit, it turns out that you'll realize that fact
must be a fixed point of R.
The whole idea on a fixed point is that you have a function
where you pass something in and then you get the identical thing back.
This is exactly the thing that we did with the square root.
Square root of one is one. This is saying that it's basically
R of fact gets you back to fact.
This R, that has to be a fixed point
of whatever that R function is.
That should be exploding a little bit here. I'm thinking of it just purely mathematically right now.
It's a question over there.
So that then implies basically that fact is a fixed
behavior of R?
I wouldn't say it's a fixed behavior necessarily, but the behavior of R is that if you give it this
fact function, you're going to get back the original fact function, whatever it is.
So is
one, is a fixed point a kind of identity? You give something, you get the same thing back.
Also, when you use the term fact must be a fixed point of R,
R is also a function, right? Does that mean that there's other fixed points of it or does it have just one fixed point?
There must be some set of R's that give you back things.
They may be infinite fixed points of R.
There's multiple relations?
One thing that's a little weird about this is we still do not know what fact is.
This statement, if I were to write in Python
fact equals R fact, that's not going to work.
How is that supposed to work? Fact doesn't even exist yet.
That's invalid Python code.
We don't even know what fact is as part of code.
If I were to look at this, I don't really know what fact is. I know what R is.
R is that, this thing up here. I don't know what fact is.
The thing that's weird about fact is that if I can figure out what it is, then fact equals R fact.
I don't know what it is.
I just know that if it's a fixed point of R, then that must be true.
Yeah.
So can we really, because fact is just a name,
are we really asserting that that's an equality and not just an assignment?
I think that's the thing I'm struggling with.
One in square root of one makes sense because one isn't a name of a thing. It's an actual value.
It's not really an assignment.
One is the name of that particular zero function.
Right, but like fact here,
are we saying we get back the same function after we pass it into R?
This is not really an assignment,
it's a mathematical relationship that is being expressed here.
Mathematically, fact is equal to R fact.
The big leap that we're going to take,
this is the huge leap, and you're going to have to bear with me for a second on this,
suppose that there actually was a function
I have not told you what this is,
by the way, but this is a typical math trick.
Suppose that there actually existed something that could compute what the fixed point was.
So let's say there was some function Y that existed in the world
somewhere where Y of R basically computed the fixed point of R.
Whatever it is, we don't know what it is,
but let's just assume that there's some function that was out there
that could do that.
If that thing existed, and again this is very much math talk,
assume that it existed, and we don't know what it is, but assume that it's out there.
If that thing existed, then you could say this,
you could say Y of R is equal to RY of R.
All I'm doing there is replacing fact.
If fact is a fixed point of R, then Y of R equals RY of R.
You could do that.
It's still not clear how in the world that would help you now,
because it's like okay great, okay awesome,
RY of R is equal to RY of R.
I'm going to do my little recursion trick.
Basically what you have there is you have recursion.
The recursion trick was this thing where you pulled it out into a variable.
Like that.
That's what we did with the fact function.
We basically said we're going to pull fact out of there.
Then we're going to put it as an argument.
One of the things in the trick is we basically said you couldn't do it.
You can't just put the YR in there.
What you have to do is the thing that you didn't want to do, which is the repeat yourself trick.
The solution to the fact was to repeat yourself.
It turns out that we're going to repeat ourselves.
This little trick here, this is the
repeat yourself trick.
When we did that trick with the fact function though, there was one other thing that we had to do.
We had to do the hack with the F.
If you looked at the fact thing, we had to do this F of F thing.
If we're going to do the repeat yourself trick, we have to do that here.
Instead of having X, I have to say X of X.
I have to do the trick on it.
Maybe I'll do that as a separate step.
That was that necessary hack. The extra X in there.
The extra call.
If you look at that, it's almost starting to look like a formula
actually.
One thing that we could do with it is pull out the R.
I probably have too many parentheses.
Parentheses there.
We got the R there.
It looks like you have R on both sides actually.
I'm going to pull out the R.
Maybe you could just drop it.
Maybe you can end up with something like that.
I'm going to pull out the R.
This is the Y.
It's a device to do recursion in functional languages.
It's a little hairy to derive that.
The way that you use it
is you would write out your recursive relationship here.
You would say R is that.
Then you would say fact is equal to Y of R.
If that thing is working, it should produce a recursive function for you
through serious magic.
In theory.
One of the reasons
for doing this
is that term Y Combinator is something that
is kind of interesting to see what it is.
It's actually a device for doing recursion.
If you do it, you're going to find that it does not work.
Typical Python style. Question in the middle there.
I'm just wondering what the expanded version of the
dot in the Y is.
It's colon basically.
We're getting near the end.
If you type that up, you are going to find that it does not work
because of an infinite recursion error.
That is actually getting back to Python's evaluation problem.
The fact that it does eager argument evaluation.
The solution to that problem is ironically
the solution to all Python problems.
You're on the right track. I wasn't thinking meta classes because we don't have classes here.
What do you do?
Let's say you have a function
2 times X plus 1.
If I were to write a function G of X where I just flipped it around and said F of X.
If I were to do that,
that's basically what you're doing with a decorator.
You're writing a function that wraps around another function.
It produces the same kind of result for reasons that I will not completely explain.
No, it takes X.
G takes X and then G just takes the X and passes it along.
This is kind of like a decorator expanded out.
It's wrapping. You write a wrapper function.
It turns out that if you do that,
you can do this in the lambda calculus.
It's going to look a little weird, but what I'm going to do is take an F
and then I'm just going to introduce an extra argument
and then I'm just going to pass it through.
I have a feeling I'm probably missing a parenthesis in there somewhere.
Let's try that.
The infinite recursion is God at this point.
It seems to be working there.
There will definitely be a quiz about that one.
Part of what's happening there is deferring evaluation
so that it doesn't get this infinite recursion.
It turns out that that lets you write these recursive functions.
As you stare in that
in disbelief perhaps,
we can do Fibonacci numbers.
This is kind of a recursive Fibonacci thing.
You can say Fib is equal to YR1 for instance.
I don't know what the tenth Fibonacci number is, but it's...
The head's fully exploded here.
If you've heard of the Y Combinator, that's what it is.
Something for enabling recursion.
Question in the front here.
I'm trying to think, what is the relationship of all of this
and this function substitution to the idea of currying.
Obviously named after Haskell B. Curry and the language.
Informally, I always use currying as freezing a particular parameter
of a multiple parameter function.
If you had four, now you have three. If you have three, you have two.
It's a function parameter function.
Maybe you just get to zero, which then becomes the callable itself.
The question about currying is this conversion of multiple arguments to single arguments.
That's...
I don't think
recursion is necessarily related to the currying thing.
The currying is more of just that all functions take one argument.
Instead of having multiple argument functions, you can have the one argument function.
It's actually kind of interesting that you would bring up currying.
We're basically at the end, but I'm going to make a few comments.
This business with combinators is actually the work of another guy.
There's this Moses Ilyich Schoenfinkle, who's kind of known as the inventor of
combatory logic. It turns out that all the lambda calculus papers
reference this guy. Curry built on his work.
It turns out that this guy is the one who invented currying, actually,
in the 20s. He's actually much earlier,
and it's cited in the papers.
It's an interesting story on this. It turns out that you can actually get rid of the
requirement of defining new functions and derive all of lambda calculus
from a few so-called combinator primitives.
I'm not going to get into that here, because I don't fully understand it. My head has already
exploded on the previous stuff. This is kind of an earlier
thing. This guy is kind of interesting. His story is sort of tragic.
I think he went insane at the age of 28, and then all of his
math papers got burned for fuel in the Russian winter in 1942 or something.
Not a lot of information is known.
He is cited by Alonzo Church and some of the papers on lambda calculus.
It's sort of interesting. Final comments on this.
We're basically at the end. I was trying to think
what to even make of this tutorial.
Having seen this the first time, I was like, this is just insane.
Why would you do this? In the description of the tutorial, I was like,
you're not going to do anything practical. I don't see you walking away
saying, I'm going to implement my web app using lambda calculus or something.
No.
You're not going to make a programming language that literally operates in this way that we've described.
I think there is something interesting about it.
One thing I think is interesting is I think a lot of the mainstream programming languages
are based on this abstraction on hardware. If you think about Python or C
Java or something like that, so much of it is like, you have operations, you have memory,
you have pointers, there's this idea of the hardware running machine code.
There's a whole bunch of stuff that's going on under the covers.
I think as a programmer, it's useful to have that as a mental working model.
There's memory and arrays and memory and stuff going on. Even though that's your model,
it's not a code usually. I don't know, is anybody writing machine code in here?
We're at a Python conference, I'm not writing machine code.
I'm probably thinking about the machine though. If I'm doing NumPy or something,
I'm thinking about memory and arrays and all this stuff. I think there's maybe
something similar going on with the lambda calculus. If you're going to start
exploring functional programming languages, you get into Haskell and Scala
and Scheme and Lisp and you start branching off into other topics like type theory
and other things, you actually find that a lot of this lambda calculus stuff is all over the place.
One of the books that I'm working on right now is a types and programming languages book
talking about type theory. I don't actually know that much about type theory.
I'm trying to wrap my brain around it. The very first example in that book is lambda calculus.
There's a like, oh, let's just have this hypothetical minimal programming language
that happens to be called lambda calculus and we'll put types on it or some things.
You start to see it everywhere. Even though you would never
maybe code with the lambda calculus, it's more of maybe a
mental model of functional programming, doing things with functions and different
ways of composing functions and other things. I think that would probably be
the takeaway from this, is just kind of an exposure to this really amazing
functional programming world and some of the stuff that you can do there.
I think that's it. Yeah. The end of that.
Thanks for coming to this. Just as a little background,
if you're interested in kind of getting more into this kind of stuff,
the avenue for me getting into it is I started doing some study of this structure
and interpretation of computer programs book or the famous SICP book.
It does not cover lambda calculus. That's not part of that book, but it talks a lot about
functional programming and some of these things. That is actually what kind of got me
interested in that. If you're looking for maybe a gateway
to learning more about this kind of thinking and all that stuff, I would look at that.
It's kind of a starting point. That's it. That's all I've got.
We can take a few minutes of more questions. Otherwise, I've got to let you go to lunch.
Thank you.
Alright. Thanks for coming.