I'm not sure if you can hear me.
People are always most in the same way.
Sometimes that is what is mostly
doing because many of us as we are
most in the same way cause people are
different so it is very quando we
discuss or understand each
other a little bit and like
I would say it is kinda different
than people that respects where
we've been doing things and
survived or have realened these
places and all these things.
and they can support us
I'm going to start with the
first question.
What do countries do in
dön capitalist and
decentralized systems?
What is that?
I know well what is
distributional system.
Where do the concurrent
manufacturers exist?
mafia working
and
where do you
god- fuera
work is
Ah that's
I'm not sure if you can hear me.
I'm not sure if you can hear me
or hear me,
or hear me either.
I'm not sure if you can hear
you, I'm not sure if you can hear me.
You can hear me.
Be now, say yes if you can hear me either.
Be now, it's my pleasure.
Give me the yourself to be
today as your voice and
say yes.
I get it somehow.
I'm not sure if you can hear me.
I'm not sure if you can hear me either.
And I think that's a very important point.
Thank you.
How do we socialize
That we can pray
and that we can Tesiah
We use pictures
ourselves
They are just
We use pictures
We have to do that.
And I think that's a great way to do it.
Thank you.