Thank you, everyone.
Good afternoon.
My name's Yi Kang.
And with my co-speakers, Ariel and Marina,
you're going to not make the same mistake that we made
or learn from our mistakes.
So three of us are data scientists from Capital One.
And starting from a few years ago,
Capital One has committed to make substantial investment
in the public cloud computing and open source software
in order to run all our business critical functions
and processes and models.
So to that end, we wanted to get our analysts
to learn and use Python.
And starting from a few years ago,
we have some hard lessons learned
along the way that may not be strictly obvious to people who
are not in the business of teaching people to use
Python for their day job.
A lot of us are very experienced practitioners of Python
language.
And we love Python.
That's why we're here at PyCon.
But imagine a scenario where you wanted
to teach Python to a new group of people
in your new workplace or your new research lab who have not
seen any programming language before
and may not have the technical background
to learn a new language from scratch on his or her own
initiative.
So how do we go about solving that question?
Hold on.
I have some AV issues.
So for those of you who are not familiar with Capital One
company, we're one of the biggest banks in the United
States.
We'd like to imagine ourselves as a bank a technology
company would build.
We specialize in a few financial service products,
such as credit cards, auto finance, and banking and savings
accounts.
We're headquartered in the Washington, DC area,
just outside in McLean, Virginia.
We have business presence in US, Canada, and UK,
serving over 45 million customer accounts.
We globally have over 47,000 employees.
And out of those, more than 9,000 of them
are technology professionals and over 2,500 analysts
and over 500 data scientists and quants,
like us, who build models and build tools for our business.
So for the focus of today, we're going
to talk about our analysts.
And your question, my first question
might be, why do we want to teach Python to our analysts?
Why can't we just let them use existing tool that they use?
There's three things about Python
that we really like at PlaceWell with our analyst workforce.
The first one is ease of learning.
It has a very easy to understand syntax,
although the analysts might not think it that way.
But compared with other programming languages,
it's relatively easy to understand.
It has a battery-included philosophy,
which means that it comes with a very powerful standard library
that can do already a lot of things out of the box.
And if you're not satisfied with a single library,
you have access to an extensive ecosystem of other libraries
that can help you do things that you need to do.
And it comes also with a series of notebook-like tools
which exposes very powerful computing environment
to analysts who are not familiar with programming.
So that's all great.
For our analysts who do data processing day in, day out,
we use Python for a lot of its data-centric tools,
all the way from data ingestion using SQL engines or API
interfaces to data wrangling using open source libraries,
such as Pandas, NumPy, and PySpark,
to modeling using Scikit-learn or XGBoost or TensorFlow,
to data visualization with a series
of static or interactive visualization libraries
that you can choose from.
And lastly, this is something that we slowly
are beginning to realize how important this is for now
that we see the end results playing out a few more years.
Because for our stakeholders to all use and work
on the same programming language, that drastically
speeds up the deployment costs.
If you imagine a case where people are writing stuff
in Python, but they have to deploy in Java,
or people were writing SQL queries in their SQL engine,
but they have to wrap it in Python somehow,
all that translation costs can induce errors and cost time.
So if you have everyone from data scientists and analysts
to software engineers working on the same language,
that slows down a lot less speeds up the deployment.
And it also is compatible with open source and public cloud
DevOps and tooling, which our engineers really like.
So what do our analysts do day to day?
And this is a question that can be best summarized
as they analyze data.
They use data to solve business challenges
and to find new opportunities.
So they do a lot of things outside of data.
But let's focus on what they do with data in this slide.
The first one they do is a lot of business monitoring.
We have a vibrant business that needs a lot of analysts
workforce to keep an eye on to make sure we don't screw up.
So routine business monitoring may include questions
how many people applied to our credit card last week,
or last month, or last quarter, how many people
applied to each credit card and on which application channels,
and stuff like that.
And outside of routine monitoring,
people need to answer at high questions,
like why did this particular zip code has
much more application than a year ago?
What was happening there?
Is there the potential for a fraud attack, for example?
And the analysts are also responsible for doing
a lot of the data management to make sure the quality
of the data and the quality of the metadata
is up to enterprise standards.
They have to communicate the data risk to non-data people.
So on top of that, they are also expected
to upscale as necessary.
So use the right tool for the job,
even if it requires using new tool.
So the point of this slide is that they have a lot of stuff
they have to do on their plate already.
So what we're trying to get to them
from a traditional workflow in this table from the left,
and someone coined it as a Microsoft Office Stack,
is that you start from a relational database
that hosts your raw data.
You interact with the raw data using SQL libraries
in some graphical user interface.
You query the data, you copy and paste the query results
to Excel, you make some plots,
you make more wrangling to the data,
and then you copy and paste the plot,
you make Excel to PowerPoint.
And if you want to get really fancy,
you might even make a Tableau dashboard out of it.
In this entire process, you can see that
every step is manual.
It's very prone to errors,
and we can give a whole talk about the errors,
the funny errors that people has made
not realizing it during the years.
But on the right-hand side is the Python-based workflow,
where in the data storage,
not only do they have the option
to get relational databases data,
they can also get other data sources,
and polycloud file storage that are in ever or parquet format.
They can get the data using query,
but they can also package their query
in reusable notebooks and Python scripts
so that they can share it more easily
and run it over and over again.
They have the data wrangling libraries
that are like Pandas, PySpark, and Dask.
They have data visualization options
that include static, interactive,
or dashboard-like visualizations,
and all of that can be automated
using open-source libraries as well.
So all of us in this room would agree
the right column is the right way.
But what can go wrong
when we try to do this to the analysts?
When we want to convince them,
hey, Python is really the right way to go.
So the first thing we have to realize
is that a lot of our workforce
may not have the technical background
or programming background
to learn a new language from scratch.
So learning something from scratch
with the goal of making it productive
in their day job is a daunting task.
They do have a lot on their plate,
as I mentioned earlier.
So having them using Python
or learning how to do Python
may mean taking things away from their day job,
which their managers or their teammates
may not appreciate.
And lastly, it's also not just about Python,
the programming language and syntax.
In order to get productive in Python in their day job,
they also have to learn other concepts,
such as how to run scripts from Unix command line,
how to check in your code into GitHub
so it's open source,
also it's source controlled
and can be shared with other people on your team
and even outside your team.
And how do you run things from the cloud,
spin up instances so that your script
is not dependent on some analyst's laptop
that has to be turned on a certain time in the day.
All these concepts are necessary
for them to get productive.
So to that end, I want to turn it to Ariel
to discuss the materials that we have
for teaching analysts to use these tools.
Thanks.
Yeah, how many of you guys have ever tried
teaching a novice programmer Python?
Wow, a lot of you.
How many of you guys did it end in tears for?
A few hands, yeah, I've seen some tears.
We obviously want to teach Python to these people
and we live in a world with infinite training available.
We're really lucky in that way.
But it's a really daunting task nevertheless.
So we use the fact that there's so much great content
out there to really focus on relevancy and engagement,
try and get people's buy-in from the beginning.
And we try to do that through customization.
So as part of an organization we called Big Data Academy,
on the left here, we tailored our content
towards the analyst and quant community
who typically have good business sense,
modeling background, maybe not so much
software engineering fundamentals.
And we let other organizations in the company
like Tech College kind of cater
to that more technical audience.
And we let them take care of the stuff
where maybe they need a little bit more math stats
fundamentals in their courses.
And in general, the workflow that we try to follow
is just to keep this audience in mind
and then select and filter context,
based on filter the content that we wanted to include
based on that audience.
And then think about presentation and interaction modes
that would be appropriate.
And then add a little bit of capital one flavor,
you know, a little bit of spin based on the unique way
that we have to get things done inside this corporation.
And so one example of this is, you know,
we decided to have the content in Big Data Academy
be self-paced content that you could go through
kind of on your own time,
partially because of what Ikang said about
how people have very demanding schedules
in the BA community, analyst community.
And so what we ended up with looks something like this.
This is a curriculum which has kind of a foundational level
on the top, which leads into more analytical courses
in the central piece.
And there's some auxiliary material as well.
Python features very heavily in this curriculum
from the very beginning.
And in all, we had 18 self-paced courses here.
They were created and maintained largely by volunteers,
which is great.
And all of them were pretty much hosted
on GitHub pages, I think.
So that was also great.
We really wanted to engage the community
and we really wanted analysts to use GitHub.
So check, check.
A little secret is that we actually kind of needed
both of those things to happen in order to scale
to the number of people that we wanted to take this content.
If we didn't have the crowdsourcing,
if we didn't have kind of GitHub as this platform
for doing self-paced learning,
it would have been very hard for us to get
the number of completions that we did.
And so completions are kind of this one metric
that we measure, maybe not the best.
But as of March, we had over 8,000
from about 3,000 associates.
And we know that from our analytics,
there's a lot more people who kind of use the content
as a reference.
Kind of open it up, check something out,
copy some code and then close the site.
So all in all, this was an approach
that gained a lot of traction.
So what I wanna segue into is talking about
some of the lessons we learned along the way
as we deployed this curriculum
and kind of experienced what it was like.
The first lesson really requires putting yourself
in the shoes of one of these analysts.
And thinking back to when you were first learning Python
and then tacking on to those circumstances,
a full day job, like Yikang was saying,
significant time constraints,
maybe a lot of money on the line,
somebody breathing down your neck,
somebody waiting for the result of your analysis.
And then somebody comes along and says,
by the way, you should be doing things
completely differently.
And you're like, okay, well, when am I going to do that?
In a world of infinite training,
we don't have infinite time.
And it can be hard to learn something
just for the sake of learning it.
I know that at conferences like this,
I kind of love the break.
I use it to dig into a whole bunch of the GitHub repos
that get posted.
And then I go back to my real job and I'm like,
oh, I really wanna finish making
that JavaScript visualization.
But, you know.
So how can we kind of tackle this?
The symptom of this problem is really,
I think, at its core,
is that it sucks to be the only person.
Sucks to be alone.
It sucks to be the only person trying to learn Python
or using Python on your team.
Your teammates or manager may not be interested at all.
They don't see the value.
And it can be really hard to overcome
kind of an organizational inertia.
Many of you are probably familiar with the kind of
manual painstaking task that this comic is trying to describe
where we have this routine monitoring.
It has to happen once every quarter.
It goes to the regulators.
We've got to take some data from these million SQL tables,
make a pivot table in Excel,
and then copy paste a chart into a PowerPoint deck
that somebody else will process.
And that's just the way it's always been done.
So, why do we even need Python here?
Another challenge is that when you're alone,
you don't really have a great path forward
to learning the best practices
that come with Python development.
You can maybe look up how to do a particular thing,
but you don't necessarily get everything else.
Everything like version control, like unit tests,
like not hard coding your password in your program,
like naming variables so they can be reusable.
And of course, documentation.
So, you can talk to your rubber duck all you want.
The rubber duck is not gonna teach you
how to build Sphinx docs
and how to format docstrings and functions.
So, when you're alone, it's really, really daunting
to kind of break into this path.
I mean, we're all on this journey
of trying to be better programmers.
We know it doesn't happen all at once,
but even just to take that one next step
of like, I have something in a Jupyter Notebook,
let me make it into a function,
that can be hard to do when you're by yourself.
So, we tried to build a community.
We tried to build a community from the ground up
and create a support system that analysts could be a part of
outside of their immediate team.
We used something called the Analyst Development Program.
It's a cohort-based thing we do every year,
and each new batch of analysts goes through it.
We put Python like front and center in that program
so that they could kind of go through the process together.
And we also tried to enable cross-functional collaborations
between analysts and other kind of job,
related technical job families at the company.
Of course, we had support from the highest levels.
That really helps a lot.
It helps to have that backing.
It helps to have that keynote speaker
on the first day of the program saying,
hey, you guys should learn Python.
Like, that goes a long way.
But at the end of the day, the bottom-up community
is, I think, where the real value is.
And key to this is teaching these analysts
how to extract value from that community.
Right, it's very easy to say, hey, be in this community.
But, you know, what are they gonna get out of it?
And largely, I think we centered our efforts there
around GitHub and Slack.
We had a lot of kind of self-service support
through GitHub.
Like I said, we wanted people to use GitHub.
So we were like, you should make an issue.
You should make a pull request.
Let's talk about the problems you're having
alongside the code.
And then Slack is simply,
it simply answers a lot of the pain points that we had.
You know, we could have done this
in something other than Slack.
But if you think about some of the common problems
you may have, like, I don't know who to ask the question to
in the first place.
Well, you know, there's a little thing over there
that's like, questions, try asking.
Steven, Python guru.
Or, you know, maybe somebody is really tired
of answering the same question over and over again
about how to write a conda environment.yml file.
Like we could have a pinned item in the Slack channel.
Or,
or, you know, something that's happened to me a bunch
is you just need somebody to screen share with.
And let's get you through this one roadblock you're having.
And if you like squint at this screenshot,
there's like a little phone,
little phone call button up here.
And that actually like triggers a video call with somebody.
So you can actually like get help,
get some value out of this community.
So the Slack channel is very active.
We have a lot of questions and answers going on there
all the time.
The second thing I wanna tell you about is,
you know, system setup issues, dun dun dun.
If you looked at that Slack screenshot,
I would wager that like a significant fraction
of those messages were related to help me.
I can't install Python on my Windows machine,
or, you know, I tried to install this thing
and it didn't work.
And for any of you who like me have worked
in like technical support, you know,
we've probably experienced some version of this haiku.
I like to recite it every now and again,
because it's just so emblematic of the kind of conversation
that you end up having so often.
It's not the proxy, it cannot be the proxy,
it was the proxy.
And you can replace proxy with DNS or, you know,
anything that, you know, is kind of a bug bear
for this kind of environment setup.
And really the thing is that our associates
are really self-sufficient and resourceful,
and that leads them to create solutions to these problems,
which they then share with their friends,
and their friends share it with their friends.
And so, you know, we're in this copy paste
kind of game of telephone, and, you know,
it gets outdated, and then somebody's system
is borked in some like insane way that you've never seen
because you just joined the company 18 months ago.
I've seen like .bashrc.txt files,
and tried to figure out like why that doesn't,
like why is this not working?
So that's the problem.
And the solution was to really take setup
out of the learner's hands as much as we possibly could.
We got better at this over time, I think.
We started out trying to do things like pre-install Python
on a bunch of like loaner laptops,
and then hand them out to people.
And that works, but does it meet our scalability criteria?
No, obviously, we can't keep doing that.
So we started doing things like using a centralized place
to store all of this setup information as best we could,
and be diligent about updating it regularly.
And that was good too, if time consuming for us.
So I think really what the next level thing to do here is,
in our case, is to leverage shared analytical environments.
And we use these pre-canned Linux sandboxes
that we can just spin up.
They have taken care of all of the setup issues.
You know, they have the git command already in the terminal.
They have the proxy solution already in place.
And the courses that we wanna run can have startup scripts
that kind of handle data retrieval, permissions,
GitHub interactions, things like that,
so that the learner basically presses a button
that's like, do, do, do, do, do, do, okay.
And really, I think that's the bottom line here,
is that for experienced practitioners,
you spend maybe 1% of your time fiddling with the setup,
and 99% of the time, you get to have fun.
But for somebody who's really new, it's completely flipped.
They spend the majority of the time
just trying to get the thing working in the first place.
And then that little piece of the course at the very end,
that's when they get to have fun.
And so that really sucks.
So I wanna hand it over to Marina to talk more about
how we can really get adoption of Python going.
Thanks, Ariel.
So making the setup easier definitely helped more people
to start the courses.
But remember, our goal is much more ambitious than that.
We wanted people not only to start the courses,
but to actually be more productive in their work.
So we want them to complete the courses,
and more importantly, use what they have learned
in their day-to-day work.
Sounds tricky, right?
So let me start with what can go wrong here,
and take a look at this example of situation
that can occur in real world.
Here, a proud analyst just completed her Python training,
and she feels that she knows everything there is
about iterators, generators, decorators, classes,
inheritance, and all the other jargon
that she was so afraid just a few weeks ago.
And she feels that she's ready to tackle
all the big data problems and make data-driven decisions
using artificial intelligence.
While in the reality, even though her manager
is very supportive of her training,
she can be asked to connect some dashboard to a database,
something not related to Python and boring,
and just old way of doing things.
And it makes sense.
Just because you have learned Python
doesn't mean that all the processes
will be automatically translated into Python.
And of course, you still have your day-to-day work
that you need to complete.
And we have seen that in our Python courses.
So we had those foundation courses for a while,
and we have seen that a lot of people start the course,
but never finish.
Some of them got distracted,
some of them just get stuck,
some of them never bother to complete the final assessment
or click complete in the system.
And it can be somewhat similar to MOOCs,
massive open online courses,
although the completion rate for our courses,
which was much higher.
And we have, probably all of us have taken
some of the MOOCs, right?
We go to the system, we saw that the content is interesting,
but it requires motivation and time commitment
to actually go through the course.
And even though if you complete the course,
or at least complete the course,
there is still a challenge to use what you have learned
in your day-to-day work,
especially if you have deadlines.
Because imagine yourself being an analyst
who need to complete something by tomorrow.
And you know how to get it done in the old,
maybe manual, but working way.
And you may not have all the knowledge and confidence
that you need to do it in Python.
So, how have we addressed that?
It may not come as a surprise to you
that it's really important to teach
what people need to do in their daily work.
So, we need to provide people with examples
and code cookbooks to actually do what they need to do.
So, if an analyst needs to create a dashboard, perfect.
Put together some code to help them do that.
Same with automation, visualization,
whatever they need to do.
And here, it's really important to partner with analysts,
both to understand their pain points,
because being a data scientist,
you may not do what analysts do in their daily work.
And it's also important to discover
some of the tips and tricks that they may have,
and try to popularize that with a bigger community.
Also, the next thing.
Here at PyCon, we all know and love Python, right?
And we are very excited about the language.
We tell other people how awesome it is, and it's great,
but it doesn't necessarily help non-technical people
to get it adopted.
So, it's really important to imagine yourself
in other shoes, and actually reimagine people's workflow
in Python for them.
And here, we have an example of the course
that we put together with help of analysts.
So, one analyst went through our foundation courses,
and he was fascinated by how Python make his work easier.
But he struggled to make other people on his team
to use Python, and so we partnered together
to put together this content
that is focused on their workflow.
And people got really good feedback,
because they were able to take the course,
and go back to their desk, and use what they have learned,
and get the job done much faster.
Finally, it will not come as a surprise to you
that leadership helps,
and leadership can provide some motivation,
like prizes or equipment upgrades,
if you want to drive Python adoption.
And of course, you can improve
on the things that you can measure.
So, it helps to provide leadership
with a view of course completions,
and some measure of adoption in different organizations.
Because if you put multiple very successful people
on the leaderboard, they would try to get higher.
Competition is good.
Anyway.
So, this Python for Analyst course was definitely a success.
But remember, we have thousands of analysts.
And all of them are very smart people, and creative,
and we want them to be able to share some of their,
you know, good ideas, good solutions,
without involvement from our team.
So, what can go wrong here?
And again, let me start with comics
that can depict real world situation.
So, here, a proud analyst spent his last week
working on a script that puts some Excel plots
into PowerPoints.
And the code works great, so she's happy.
But she just realized that someone has done that
in like 2015, and all discouraged,
she like thinks whether the cycle goes on forever
and forever, and putting that to the extreme,
you can see how, you know, someone can pass over
big stacks of SQL queries from generation to generation.
Makes sense.
Sounds like a great decision, right?
And again, those of you who work at big companies
can relate to that.
Different people solve the same problems over and over
again, reinventing the wheel, reinventing the bicycles,
whatever they want.
And it's hard to get communication right,
especially when there are many people.
And analysts can easily get siloed and reuse
some of the bad scripts and practices in their work.
Because when they have an issue,
they go to their immediate team,
and the solution that they have
may not necessarily be the best and greatest.
And we have seen a lot of those in our experience.
Finally, discoverability is a big problem.
And there are some good solutions that never get discovered.
And you may have heard some of those phrases,
like someone not committing code to GitHub
because the code is not ready.
Anyone have heard something like that?
Yeah, perfect.
Guess what, it probably never will be ready.
Anyway, another problem is people may prefer
with their wonderful solution in a private repo.
So to keep it secret, because good solution.
Anyway, so how can we address that?
First, best practices do help.
But it's important not only to use those best practices,
but also codify and champion them.
And things like cookie cutters and templates can help.
Because with cookie cutter, it's much easier to start
with project in the way it should be,
rather than having analysts trying to figure out
how to structure their code so it can be packaged.
It's also important to provide gentle yet clear introduction
of the best practices.
So if someone has just learned Python
and has a bunch of hard-coded variables in their code,
great, encourage them to put it in a variable.
If they have a lot of random repetitive code in notebooks,
fantastic, encourage them to create a function,
add doc tests, doc strings unit tests,
and finally and hopefully make it into a package,
especially if it solves a common problem.
And in an ideal world, this package will be then open-sourced
as some of the other projects that we have built.
Next, we at Capital One really use and love GitHub,
and of course we use it to store code.
But it's also important to make it a home
for living documentation that can get evolved.
And it's really hard to make people write the docs
or get excited about the documentation.
That's why it's so important to make it easy for people
to make the documentation stylish and look cool.
And tools like Docsify or creating interactive GIFs
really help people to get some pride in writing those docs
and share them with other people.
And finally, sharing information is great.
So different conferences or regular demos
help to disseminate the knowledge.
So we hope that we didn't get you scared
with all the issues that you may face
while building a community of practice.
I feel that we've made a wonderful progress,
although it's a never-ending journey.
And we believe that Python is super useful
to a big group of people.
So we do want to finish our talk with some summary
of some of the lessons so you can build
your community of practice as well
and help other people to use Python.
So first, adoption is definitely easier
when you start with a cohort of people.
So when a lot of people are together in the room,
it's much easier for them to help each other
to get unstuck and solve problems together.
Although top-down support definitely helps
with the resources and incentives.
Setup, it will always be a problem,
but it's important to minimize the problem
and cloud and DevOps best practices can help.
But it's also important to separate that pain of setup
from the joy of programming.
Next, advocate for Python, tell how Python is great,
but also try to put yourself in other shoes
and reimagine people's workflow in Python.
And finally, use best practices in your own coding
and provide gentle yet clear introduction
of those best practices to others.
And use cookie cutters and templates.
Hopefully that gives people food for thought
and hopefully that sharing of our journey
is helpful to other people.
If you want, all three of us on the Capital One
Data Science team, here's our contact info
if you need to reach out to us.
And I do want to mention,
because our company kindly fly us here, we are hiring.
We do have a booth in PyCon,
and no, we are not trying to get people to sign up
for our credit card in the booth.
If you want to do that, go online, but come talk to us.
We are hiring for people with Python skills
in software engineering, data science,
and on-the-shop families.
We're hiring across the geographical location
and experience levels.
So come visit our booth,
they were interested in learning more
about working at Capital One.
Thank you.
All right, so now we're gonna be receiving
a couple of questions.
The mic is on the career at the end.
Hi.
So we have an analyst community
that is kind of spread across a range of technologies,
R, SAS, Excel, and then a few people dribbling into Python.
And some of the pushback that we've received
is if you have people move on to a new language,
they're gonna move on,
and then someone's gonna have to pick up this.
And there's kind of like two schools of thought.
We should have everyone standardized
to what we've always been doing,
which is maybe something more in the SAS realm,
versus not let anyone go into this new thing.
Or the second school of thought
is kind of like encouraging something more in your direction.
I'm just curious if you guys have any feedback
or learnings around that,
or if that was something you experienced in your company.
Is the question around picking a standard language
that people use?
Or?
So part of it is,
if the team uses a mix of Python, R, and SAS,
so that you have one Python person,
and then they move on to a new job,
how do you have your team pick up that code?
So do you enforce standardization across your teams,
or do you say you're just gonna have
that extra work that needs to be done
in order to team catch up on that code?
Yeah, we actually, I mean, I think at any kind
of larger company, you end up with these pockets
of expertise, and you have some really well-established
Java code base over here.
You might have a really established SAS code base over here.
One of the reasons we wanted to move people to Python
is that it is, I think, easier to go into somebody's old
kind of Python code and kind of decipher what's going on
than in other languages.
Maybe that's my own opinion,
but that's something that we've seen.
And so that's one reason to kind of standardize on Python.
I think another part of your question is kind of,
I see it through the lens of people's development,
and if we're gonna imagine ourselves as a tech company
that just happens to do banking,
then we should develop people in terms of
the relevant tech skills of today and tomorrow
and all of that.
And so if we see analysis kind of moving towards
cloud solutions, if we see things moving towards Python,
then we wanna get people using that,
even if it's going to make us spend some admittedly painful
time kind of migrating things from the old way
of doing things to the new way of doing things.
And that's one of the areas where I think
the top-down support is especially helpful
because we can have people like our CEO come and say,
we are all moving to Python, we are getting off SAS.
And then it kind of gets everybody on board real quick.
All right, thank you.
I just have to have your CEO call my CEO.
So I really enjoyed the page that you had up
that listed out all of the templates
and sort of common uploaded code and GitHub,
for lack of a better phrase.
I think something that we're encountering,
and I'd love to sort of hear how you're thinking about this,
what are you planning sort of as more people
create templates and more people create patterns of work,
thinking about like when there are thousands
or tens of thousands of notebooks committed to GitHub,
how are you thinking about making sure that the most
relevant and ideal solutions are easily found
in your community?
Yeah, I mean, that's a very good question.
I would say that even those notebooks are well documented,
so people can understand what actually is happening there.
Then search over GitHub works pretty good
and people can just search for relevant projects
and get inspired by some of the solutions.
So yeah, my answer would be yes.
I would just add, it's pretty similar
to just open source software in general, I think.
How do we find relevant things that are out there?
And we would like to have some internal version
of Stack Overflow, internal version of Google,
internal version of, I mean,
the search is not always the best.
If you've used Slack search, you know how easy and fun it is
to find things that happen in the past.
But I think that's a good question.
I think that's a good question.
So yeah, I think it's easy and fun it is
to find things that happen in the past.
But we do want to have some sort of aggregation
that's basically by topic or something like that.
And people are working on those things,
but that is, I guess, still a constant struggle.
Thanks so much, guys.
I have a question about different languages
that people might want to use.
I know some examples in R,
when some analysts are doing very statistics heavy modeling,
R might be better than Python,
and some of the Python packages
can't even keep up yet at the moment.
Is your project, I don't want to kind of say,
really use Python unless you have very specific cases
not to use it, or is it a little more flexible,
especially in those edge cases?
Yeah, I think, thank you.
Yeah, just as a person who also uses R
and works with people who use R,
I would say, I mean, we embrace both.
Of course, Python is awesome for many reasons,
but there are some packages in R
with some fancy statistical methods
that don't have its similar analogs in Python.
And I mean, it's usually like a team makes a decision
what language do they want to embrace.
Also, with some clever pipelining
and good core code organization,
it's easier to pipeline different programs altogether.
So yeah, I hope that gives you some sense.
We have space only for one last question.
I'm sorry, we can continue.
I guess you can be committed on the corridor.
But.
Yeah, thanks a lot for the great talk.
So I had a question.
Since you're, it seems like you're now using
a lot of external open source tools,
how do you handle updates on those tools?
Especially when you now have a group of internal analysts
who are building some things on top of them
that may not be compatible between versions,
and also who may not be trained software engineers
who are really experienced with version bumps.
That's a great question.
But I would point out that many of our analysts use tools
that are pretty widespread and standard,
things like SQL Alchemy, things like Pandas,
things like Netplotlib and OK or stuff like that,
that doesn't have nearly as big a deal
in terms of version updates.
And we do see some of those conflicts or issues when,
for example, some of our data or data scientists
take a particular library that hasn't been updated
for two to three years.
And then we still have an ongoing product support
for an existing internal project.
What do you do then?
I feel like I don't have a very good solution to that,
but I do want to know that it is something
that we are also experiencing the plain point of,
and we are trying to learn from experience of picking,
like which, how you pick your stack is important.
And there's risks when you're picking a stack
that ended up not getting updated.
Sorry that if the answer is not very satisfying,
but it's something they're also trying to deal with.
And make sure to fix the versions for packages
in the environment.
And we encourage for whatever projects people are working on
to fix those versions, just because there are so many errors
that can be caused by that.
And I'll just add in the last 10 seconds,
it actually is really tempting sometimes
to use some of these more niche packages
that kind of solve a very particular use case.
And we found that actually just minimizing the dependencies
prevents this problem from coming up as often.
So while there may be some cool stuff out there
to handle something very close to what they're doing,
if they stick with the more well trodden path,
then the version update thing doesn't bite as often.
So that is one tangible thing you can do
is kind of take a hard look at the requirements.txt
or environment.yml and make sure that
you absolutely need these things.
All right, thank you.
Thank you.