All right.
Welcome everyone.
Just a reminder to make sure you turn off any sound devices.
Otherwise, you will get a stare from me.
We have Shannon Zhu here.
She is going to be speaking on leveraging the type system to write secure applications.
All right.
Hi.
I'm going to be talking today about how you can leverage the type system in Python to
write more secure applications.
A little bit about myself first.
I work at Facebook on the product security team.
The mission of our team is to find, fix, and prevent code level security vulnerabilities
across the Facebook family of apps.
More specifically, I work on the static analysis effort within that team.
I've spent the past two years building a static analyzer and type checker for Python called
Pyre.
In this talk, I'll be covering how you can build security tools on top of the type system
in Python and also why we might choose to approach security this way.
We'll go over two techniques in particular that are made possible by the type system,
both with the purpose of improving application security at scale.
The first of these is secure application frameworks, which work by systematically denoting certain
types as or certain objects as safe or unsafe and then leveraging a static type checker
along with some simple library modifications to catch security vulnerabilities as type
errors.
Secondly, I'll be going into taint analysis.
I'll talk in more detail about what this means later, but high level.
This is a way that you can statically trace data flow across your code base.
That's an intentionally vague description because data flow can mean a lot of different
things, which actually makes this tool pretty flexible and able to catch a lot of intricate
problems.
A brief overview of how we'll begin to discuss these two techniques.
First I'll get into some background about the problems that we're trying to solve and
why we wanted to invest in these tools in the first place.
Then I'll get into a classic shell injection example to help explain how both of these
techniques work in detail.
Then we'll get into a slightly more nuanced security vulnerability, which helps demonstrate
some of the flexibility of what taint analysis can model.
And finally, we'll talk a little bit about the characteristics of both of these techniques
and why we find them so powerful and essential for security at Facebook.
So what was our motivation?
A couple years ago we had a bit of a problem.
The Instagram code base is a very large monolithic Python code base that has gradual types.
And we already knew that we wanted to invest in type checking for a variety of reasons,
including the bug exposure, the code maintainability, and the consistency guarantees among some
other reasons.
And type checking was kind of slow, and it was getting slower with the more types that
we added.
So we really cared about having really fast, live incremental checks that would help us
push for type adoption and enable us to build security tooling at scale.
So we previously had a really great experience at Facebook adding types to PHP and then using
those types to build a graph of all the function calls across the code base, which then enables
us to build a taint analyzer that's fast enough to run on a code base of 100 million lines
of code on every change set, of which there are thousands every day.
And in doing so, find more security vulnerabilities than security review or our bug bounty program
in the past year, which is a lot of these were found before the code even lands.
So these are really huge security wins that we wanted to be able to replicate in Python.
So our solution was to build Pyre, which is a static analyzer and type checker with two
goals in mind.
So first, we wanted a fast and scalable type checker.
But most importantly, we wanted a tool that was conceived from the very beginning as a
platform for deeper static analysis for security.
And we wanted to be able to reuse a lot of the backend of our type checker to extend
and basically turn into a taint analyzer like the one we have for PHP.
So fast forward to today.
We've built this type checker and the static analyzer.
So let's get into some examples about how all of this works.
As promised, we'll start with shell injection.
And we'll discuss how both type frameworks and taint analysis work in a little more detail
to systematically catch this vulnerability.
And we'll do missing privacy checks after.
So first, a word about shell injection.
As many of you might know, this is a really large and well-known class of security vulnerabilities
that actually has known solutions.
But it's not a solved problem because those solutions are not consistently applied.
And you'll see what I mean with an example.
So here we have a function called get image, which takes a URL, constructs a get command
with it, and executes that command with OS system.
So let's introduce a problem.
So here's a function called convert, which asks the user for a URL that they're interested
in and then passes that URL into get image.
So essentially, we have user input here flowing directly into something that executes a command
with that user input.
Why might this be terrible?
So you can, as you might imagine, an attacker can just supply some whatever URL followed
by a semicolon and then whatever command that they desire to execute on your system.
So in this case, they're wiping it.
And in real life, this might actually come from, say, a Django endpoint or a piece of
a request rather than a call to raw input.
But I'm just minimizing the amount of code you have to read.
So we're using raw input.
So what we would really like to do here, the known solution here, is to sanitize the, basically
escape the argument while we're constructing the command here.
And so instead of executing this, which is two commands, the second of which is completely
determined by an attacker, you would instead be executing your intended command with the
attacker's applied input as just a string argument.
And so this will just fetch some nonsense and not delete anything from your system.
And you might say, well, duh, this is a known solution, so you should just feel bad if you
don't remember to do it.
It might be true in some cases, but you might want to remember that in this example, you
might not own or even know about the contents of one of these two functions, or you might
not be aware of where certain data that you're working with is coming from or where it might
eventually end up or what it might touch as it gets there.
So in this case, we would like a way to catch this type of vulnerability across many layers
of indirection, even if it happens to occur in something that seems unrelated to what
you're working on.
So how can we systematically ensure that all commands that we execute are safe?
We want a systematic solution that doesn't just pattern match around the syntax of sensitive
calls, and we also want a scalable solution that doesn't require the application author
to remember this all the time or put in a lot of extra work.
So going back to our example, we could write a simple library function called secure format,
and all this does is add some escaping, so that would probably be in the form of quotes
around the arguments before constructing the string as usual, which would make this
code snippet safe again.
And then the key here is that we can then leverage the type system to ensure that this
simple solution is always applied.
And we can do this by introducing a safe string type, which we define to be the same as any
other string, except it's always safe to directly execute.
And it's worth noting that all safe strings are strings and all string literals are safe
strings.
And then we can write something like this, which might look familiar to you if you've
worked with type Python before, which is essentially a type signature.
So here we're mandating that my custom library function secure format takes in a safe string
as the formatter and then any safe or unsafe strings as the arguments.
It does the escaping, and so therefore it always outputs a safe string at the end.
And then we can annotate any sensitive functions like OS system or eval as accepting safe strings.
So if you were to take a string and pass it in and you hadn't sanitized the arguments,
you would get a type error here saying, sorry, it expected a safe string, but you gave me
a string.
So awesome.
We can eliminate an entire class of vulnerability here by taking advantage of the way that types
guarantee semantic consistency across your code base and then just adding some security
implications to those types.
And a nice bonus is that you improve some code readability as well because you have
some more nuanced labeling of your objects.
And you can essentially get these warnings live.
So if you already have code editor integration with a type checker, you can see this warning
the moment you write the vulnerability before you even put up your code for review by a
security engineer or not.
And it's really nice that there's no mental overhead here for application engineers and
you're not betting the security of your application on whether or not the application engineers
have understood and have planned for these security vulnerabilities.
So now in our code base by default, instead of format, let's say we always are using secure
format.
You might wonder whether as a particularly stubborn application author that I can still
find a way to write a shell injection vulnerability into this function even with secure format.
What if we really tried?
So the key here is to take a look at this raw string and realize that the type checker
cares about the type of this raw string, but it doesn't care or know about what the contents
of that raw string are.
So you can do things such as double escape in which the manually added escapes here would
cancel out the escaping done in secure format.
Or you can write higher order shell injection in which the argument that you pass in is
supposed to be a string that will be executed as a command.
So even if you sanitize your argument, it will still get executed, doesn't matter.
And similarly, if you decide to set the command itself with your argument rather than one
of those arguments to the command, that will again be executed even if it's a string.
So it looks like we have a solution to the common use case of shell injection, but we
would still like to be able to catch very specific special cases that bypass our secure
framework.
And something like this is actually a really great candidate for a taint analysis.
So let's introduce how this works with some terminology.
So we care about three things here.
We care about sources of user controlled input, which are called sources.
And then we care about objects that contain or maybe have touched user controlled input.
And we call this taint.
And finally, we care about sensitive functions that taint should never reach.
And we call these sinks.
And these might be OS system or eval or some other functions that we don't want to take
user controlled input.
And in taint analysis, we care about tracing the flow of taint from sources to sinks.
And it's worth noting that in this case, we happen to care about user controlled input.
So that's what we're saying taint is.
But in other security vulnerability examples, we might be tracing something else as taint
instead.
So to visualize this, we're going back to our original example.
And here we want to mark input as a source of user controlled input.
And we do this by something that looks a lot like a type signature, but we call this a
taint summary.
And so here's the signature of input.
And we're just annotating it as returning a taint source.
And then we'll do something similar for sink.
We want to mark the first parameter of OS system as a sink.
And then to help visualize the flow of taint here, I've just highlighted it all in yellow.
And we see that there is a flow from a source to a sink.
But like before, keep in mind that this might happen across tens or hundreds of different
function calls.
So it might not be quite so obvious.
And in order to do this at scale, the first step that taint analysis does is to calculate
the remaining summaries based on the ones that were provided.
So here we have these two.
And let's look at get image.
And we'll start analyzing the body here.
And we see that there is one parameter.
And it does flow into a sink.
And so for all intents and purposes, we can mark get image, the first parameter of get
image as itself a sink.
That way when we see it somewhere else, we don't have to enter the body again to investigate.
So now if we look at the body of convert, there aren't any interesting parameters to
follow.
But we do see a source.
And so we're going to trace that source and see that it flows into a sink, which is get
image.
So we can flag this here for review as a potential shell injection vulnerability.
And you might have noticed actually that so far for this example, we've been using format
instead of secure format.
And this is an example of a taint in, taint out function, which is designated this way.
So we basically are saying that if the arguments are tainted, then the return type of format
will be tainted.
But as you might remember, we did have our handy secure format.
And what we can do is change the signature here to designate.
If the arguments are tainted, the return type is not actually.
So this is called a sanitizer.
And when we pass, when taint passes through this, it gets removed.
So at this point, we can model everything with our taint analyzer that we could with
our secure framework.
But we can go a little further here because we're not constrained and we're not limited
to type consistency.
So what we can do is label that remaining parameter to secure format and flag this to
our taint analyzer and say that actually whether or not the return type of secure format is
tainted depends on the contents of the string.
So like secure frameworks, taint analysis can flag data flowing into specific functions
and distinguish whether that data has been sanitized or not.
But we can see that it's especially useful for modeling high complexity bugs because
it's not tied to type consistency.
It does, however, also rely on a type code base.
And you might remember that in our previous, in our example, we were lucky enough to calculate
the summary of get image before we looked at convert.
But to do this at scale, we actually need a graph of all the function calls built with
types to inform our taint analysis.
So this allows us to scale to very large code bases and avoid false positives.
And the final thing to note is that taint analysis does require security engineers to
define those initial sources and sinks and some security input to refine some of the
rules.
And it's relatively slow, so you can't do it instantaneously maybe in a type editor
like or in a code editor like type checking could be done.
But this is fast enough to run on continuous integration on change sets.
So it is still fast enough to be feasible.
So to recap, we see that shell injection has a lot of known solutions.
And we can use type frameworks to systematically apply those.
And in this way, secure frameworks can take out huge classes of vulnerabilities like shell
injection or SQL injection or cross-site scripting without security knowledge on the part of
application engineers.
We also see that some specific edge cases do exist.
And taint analysis can systematically model and catch those.
So we can kind of fill in that type frameworks catch almost all shell injection vulnerabilities
and taint analysis can model the remaining cases.
But there are also other things that we might want to catch that aren't just edge cases
of problems that are already 99.9% solved by secure frameworks.
So let's get into one of those.
This image might look familiar to you.
It's the PyCon 2019 Facebook event, which you can view in a browser if you hit a particular
Facebook.com URL.
And let's imagine that part of the back end looks something like this.
We check if a user is logged in.
And if they are, we go fetch the event data from the database for display.
So now there might be other privacy checks that we actually want to perform here before
we just go ahead and read from the database.
So for instance, you might have a private event, which is supposed to be secret from
anyone that's not explicitly invited, in which case you do want to make sure that every time
we fetch that event, we check whether that user has been invited.
So how can we use taint analysis to ensure that the necessary set of privacy checks,
which might be very large, always happen?
So to review last time, we used taint to model user-controlled input, and we cared about
when it flowed into sensitive APIs.
This time, we care about any objects with unchecked permissions, and we care about when
those flow into database reads or writes.
It's again worth noting that this could be extended to a variety of other things, such
as modeling user information and when that flows into logging or things like that.
So in this example, very briefly, like before, we have a database read that we want to mark
as a sync.
We mark any source of a user object as a source of taint, and this might contain various types
of taint.
And then a sanitizer that is the privacy check, which removes taint when the object flows
through this function.
So like before, we can calculate function signatures and trace taint and see whether
it's been sanitized across many modules and layers of indirection.
And you might ask, okay, that sounds great.
It seems pretty familiar, but then why not use type frameworks here?
We already saw that we were able to determine whether a string was safe to execute or not
using type frameworks, so why can't we determine whether a user object is safe to fetch from
a database?
And so the key here is that for type frameworks to work, you need a valid type hierarchy,
which worked out really well with safe strings and strings, but this falls apart really quickly
if the security conditions that you care about don't form a clean hierarchy.
So if you don't believe me, we'll go into a quick example here where you have a user
object and maybe you care if they're logged in, but maybe you might also want a specifically
not logged in user.
So it's not quite a hierarchy here, so that's fine.
Let's make them parallel.
Okay, so like maybe you also care about whether they've been invited or not to this event.
Maybe you care if they're over 18 or if they're under 18, and maybe you care if they're friends
with the content creator of whatever they're trying to view.
Maybe you care if they're in some experiment group, and it just goes on and on.
And then for every sensitive function that you care about, you have to subset some but
not all of these security conditions to define your own custom type here, and we're not even
getting into the mess of global users that have global permissions set that maybe you
don't actually want to be valid as flowing into your sensitive function.
So this gets out of hand even in really simple situations.
So going back to our examples, we see here that type frameworks are not really a viable
solution to finding missing privacy checks because you have to conform to that type hierarchy,
and that's not always possible.
But taint analysis is a lot more flexible in this way, and so it can catch these.
Then it's worth noting that taint...
So we know that taint analysis can model data with a lot more flexibility than a type checker,
but there are a lot of different kinds of data flow patterns that we haven't even started
to talk about today.
So taint analysis can model direct taint to sync flows that we've seen already, and it
might also model indirect flows where user-controlled data controls the loading of other data, for
instance, and kind of separately or very differently, it can also model taint that controls a conditional,
and then we can know that everything under that conditional branch is operating under
some taint control.
And in this way, we can model things like privacy oracles or a variety of other examples.
And I would like to get into a little more detail here, but in the interest of time,
I can't, but I'd be really happy to answer questions about some of the details of the
other things that taint analysis can model.
Okay, so hopefully these examples helped illustrate both the flexibility of taint analysis and
the efficiency with which secure type frameworks can just eliminate whole classes of security
vulnerabilities at scale.
So let's go over some takeaways.
Secure frameworks, we see leverage types to explicitly differentiate safe and unsafe practices,
which is really useful when you have clear states on data that you can model as input
or output to functions, and that conforms to a valid type hierarchy.
You get warnings once a vulnerability is typed, which is really fast and also does not rely
on application engineers to understand any of the details of security vulnerabilities.
And it is, as we've seen, somewhat limited in what can be modeled, and the limitations
are described by those first two bullet points of what this typically models.
So then we have taint analysis, on the other hand, which does require some tuning to get
signal to noise, but it can model a lot of subtle vulnerabilities, and it can be extremely
useful for tracking complex data flow.
And it synergizes really well with a bug bounty program, which often reports edge cases or
very specific vulnerabilities that happen to show up in your code base.
And so given one of those, you can model this as taint, track that taint flow, and eliminate
all other kinds of that vulnerability across your code base, and also make sure that this
never gets introduced again.
And it's worth noting that taint analysis can be a little faster in this way, like it
has a shorter iteration cycle, because you can define these signatures and the rules,
and then just run it on your code base, whereas oftentimes secure frameworks require some
time to build the framework, to do the code mod and push for adoption before you get the
automatic, instant response detection that we were talking about before.
So really, neither approach is sufficient alone, and they're both really powerful because
they can analyze the semantics of code and comprehensively follow all branches of code
flow through many layers of interaction, but even so, good application security is still
an exercise in defense in depth.
And just because we have some fancy static analysis tools doesn't mean we rely on them
exclusively.
And in this talk, I've gone over the first few bullets here, which are type checking,
for frameworks and static analysis, but there's just as much depth in the efforts that we
put into dynamic analysis and other methods of catching security vulnerabilities.
So here are some quick stats on our experience with type-based static analysis in PHP and
Python so far.
And we just got started building and running taint analysis for Python a little earlier
this year, but we've already had success finding security vulnerabilities with the tool.
And our experience with PHP is a little more mature, and we were able to find well over
a thousand vulnerabilities last year and mostly before any of them were even committed.
And this is also on a massive code base with a whole lot of changes every day.
So in conclusion, we found a lot of security wins using type-based frameworks and security-focused
static analysis, and this might be useful for you, too.
If you're interested, Pyre is open sourced, and you can find the documentation and the
GitHub repository at this URL.
And if you'd like to learn more about Pyre or hear more about some of the pieces that
this talk glossed over, there are some other really great talks on how we built Pyre for
speed and also two talks from PyCon last year about how we actually built the static analyzer
on top of the type checker in Pyre and for some other reasons why you might want to type
your dynamic Python code base and how you could do that at scale.
And finally, here are the other members of the Pyre team, most of whom are in the audience
as well.
And if I have extra time, I'm happy to take questions.
Okay.
We have about room for five minutes of questions.
So if anybody has questions, feel free to use the microphones.
Hey.
Great talk.
Thank you.
Very interesting subject.
You said that the code bases you work with are basically monoliths.
Do you have any experience sort of following a Tain across the service boundary in sort
of the microservice architecture or any tips?
Yeah.
So we work with some thrift, so basically C and Python boundaries, but I'm actually
not super familiar myself with the details there, but we should talk afterwards and I
think some of my teammates might be able to answer your question.
Sounds good.
You mentioned the annotations of Taint sources and Taint sinks and using different layering
than static type checking.
Where do those annotations actually live?
Are they also in line in the code base or does security maintain them elsewhere?
Yeah, so they're elsewhere.
So the given ones are provided as configuration to the Taint analyzer and the other ones are
inferred dynamically as the Taint analyzer runs.
So these aren't actually in line in code.
They're not exposed to application engineers at all.
Hi, I was just wondering, in the code I noticed that you had the OS.system marked as a Taint
source with no further annotation.
Are they generics that take a Taint source of a string or do they obliterate the original
annotations?
So they're separate from type annotations entirely and yes, they do actually take parameters
that describe in more detail what that Taint source or sink are.
So for instance, we would say it's user controlled source and the sink we might say is remote
code execution sink.
That way when we actually follow the trace, we have all of the function calls but also
we can determine what kind of vulnerability this might be by the combination.
And they're separate from the annotations, the type annotations.
Thank you.
Hi, could you briefly give some differences between Pyre and MyPy?
Sure.
So they're both type checkers and Pyre was at least like first built as just a type checker.
I don't think, I think the biggest difference is that we extend Pyre to do a lot of the
security-based static analysis and that was the main reason why we wanted to build a different
back end for type checking.
I guess besides that, I think we try to aim for a lot of the same type errors and have
a lot of consistency between what's considered a type error or not.
So we go with the PEP and we try to catch the same set of errors.
So you would not expect it to be too difficult to go from MyPy to Pyre?
No, I don't think so.
I think the set of type errors should be the same.
And if there are any things that are covered or not covered by either of the type checkers,
I think that would be worth flagging and something that we would want to fix.
Thank you.
Hey, so you said that some of your functions in the code base were marked as taking a tainted
input and sanitizing it.
But doesn't the type of sanitizing depend on what sync is using it?
So certain functions that are marked as sanitizers will sanitize a specific kind of taint.
So it's true that maybe you have a sanitizer that's like a privacy check and user controlled
inputs flowing through that.
It doesn't matter.
It won't sanitize that kind of taint from the object.
So that's kind of similar to the previous question about whether there are parameters
on those sources and syncs and on taint.
And yes, there are.
So it would differentiate in that way.
So what I meant was even if you were sanitizing for like a shell injection attack, wouldn't
the nature of how you sanitize that depend on the exact function that was using that
string?
You mean certain syncs might not actually consider this to be sanitized?
Oh, yeah.
So if that were the case, we would probably want to model that taint as something slightly
different.
So I don't think the sanitizer itself is aware of what the syncs are or what they're looking
for.
But if the taint...
That seems to imply that the nature of taint is slightly different there for different
syncs.
So we just use different taint objects.
Unfortunately, we're going to have to wrap up the questions here.
But I believe Shannon and the rest of the PIER team are willing to answer questions outside
the hall.
Thank you so much, Shannon.
Thank you.