So our next speaker will be Lucas he will tell us about black and why we should stop worrying and embrace auto formatting
And there won't be any Q&A afterwards, but please give him a warm welcome
Hi life is better painted black
We're gonna talk about all the formatting black or as Raymond put it lack of color
My name is Woukash. I come from the internet. You can find me on github Facebook Twitter
Email if you if you want
So yeah, like I'm happy to hear about synthesizers
fallout and other RPGs
And obviously all the formatting and the future of Python
But today we're gonna go around the problem of all the formatting
So first we're gonna define like why all the format code at all like what that does what does that give you?
What do we do about doing it? Right and
What do we know about doing it wrong? We're gonna go and talk about syntax trees. How does a computer interpret programming languages? Why does?
modifying source code
You know help us and how is it done safely?
We're gonna talk about how I actually implemented black like the older formatter
And how you could implement a tool like it if you decided to do it yourself
Obviously, it's not the only way but I'm just gonna show how I did it
And then finally we're gonna go and talk about some fun problems that I didn't anticipate on day one
So let's start with the problem statement and the problem statement in the words of my dear friend Jack Dietrich is that code is the enemy
He says I I hate code and I wish we can have as little of it as possible
And I agree right on the code is complexity
It's very hard to see how all those pieces connect together in fact at my time at Facebook
When you were dealing with millions of lines of code you clearly see that there is no way a single person can actually
Understand the entire thing
So you want to remove as much?
Confusion from reading code as possible and this is where code style
Comes in so what is it? Well code style is pretty much an agreement between a group of people on a team
How certain you know parts of the code which are not important for the computer?
Should be expressed so that they're easier for humans
One of Greedo ski insights was that code is much more red than written much more often red than written
So that includes code review, right?
So the code style that you have should accelerate code review and not slow it down
So it should decrease the round trips between the author of the change and between the code reviewer
It should remove noise so that we can actually
Focus on the logic behind the code and not on things that are inconsequential and
This should be as small as possible which helps in both
But I'm talking about teams, but you are also not the same person in time right so at the team of one
Is important as well because if you're maintaining a piece of code over time like in six months or 18 months
You might be kind of surprised by
Some decisions that you made in time and having differences in formatting at the same time just creates
You know more
Tension and more friction for you to understand like what the hell was I thinking at the time?
So maintaining a consistent code style just makes the code transparent that way
Which means you can focus on the actual logic on the things that are hard
So we have pep8 right so obviously everything is solved and we can just move on with our lives
well
Pepe it was a style guide for the Python song library was written in 2001 revised a few times most recently in 2013 and 2016
But it's a style guide for Python. It's not like a framework for creating code styles it in fact itself suggests
multiple ways of
You know folding code that is too long and how you can do certain things
And it is self-like it focuses mostly on the fact that a foolish consistency is the hobgoblin of little minds
So in particular a style guide is about consistency with this you know
Document but more important with a project and even more important
You know you have to be consistent within a file or a function
So what do we do about that well we argue right because we have pep8 now
But even within pep8 that there's so many ways to do things
so to go from a
Style guide to a code style. We need to kind of settle on a subset like what are we gonna do?
We can settle on a subset by documenting what that subset is in practice most people don't really do that
What they sometimes do they put?
Some wiki page and wiki is this Polynesian word for where information goes to die so they just put it there nobody follows it
but the most often
Taken approaches just to you know have a word of mouth like oh, we don't do things around here like this
Like you know so how do you enforce it so that it helps you know other developers have your same style?
Well you can either engage humans which are expensive and fallible
During code review to maintain a code style or we can use linters and editors and CI
All right, which is I think still the most popular approach, but linters are not really solving the problem. I like human code review
Sucks for code style enforcement it literally sucks time and effort out of humans
So people get tired just you know arguing about inconsequential stuff, and they miss the forest for the trees
But linters suck even more right they slow you down
They're too dumb to actually understand that oh there's an edge case here, and they really want the thing
They're too dumb to always tell you consistency that I think that the thing is wrong
But mostly they're just disappointing because they will tell you that a thing is wrong
But very rarely and especially in the Python world they will fix a thing for you
So all the formatting is way better right because it removes code style enforcement
From the equation right you don't have to be conscious about co-signal anymore. There is no linter that slows you down during editing
there is no linter that slows you down during pull requests submission and
Reviewers don't have to comment about style transgressions and slow you down
So you don't have to slow down yourself by formatting code when you are typing it you can just write code
That is ugly and then on save. It's just gonna turn nice again
so if
Automatic formatting is so great then why doesn't everybody use it well the simplest answer is that if automatic formatting feels too destructive
Then it is not used like you are tied to like you liked how you formatted things or yourself
And you wish for a tool not to break
That you know tidily
Organized code
But one of the nicest insights that come from the go community is that uniformity trumps perfection
The good enough uniform formatting style is better than having lots of different formats that are locally better
But they're now inconsistent
So the value of style guide is just to provide that uniformity for you
And the more people think about their own formatting style the more they get attached to it and we're back to square one where people
Have to like enforce the style manually because there is no way to automate it so
Go has go format which pretty much resolves the issue there
JavaScript has prettier I used to actually work on the same floor with the author of prettier
He had a lot of input early on in blacks design
And you know kind of questions about community adoption whatnot, so I'm like eternally grateful for the guy like he's great. Hi Christopher
Hi, Christopher if you're watching it yeah, and then there's black that I wrote for Python
So how does that work and why can you even use it well?
Let's talk about trees for a second
like a why can we even write safe code transformation tools well because
we have
Grammars and those grammars tell us exactly what a given piece of code can do and what does it mean it's a context free
Meaning every time a piece of code is read by the computer is gonna understand it the same way
So the notation we're gonna use for this like very short example here is the actual notation used by Python 3 7 sources to generate the
parser
programming language grammar
Consists of two kinds of symbols right there are tokens. Those are all caps here and non terminal symbols
So these are all the others so the tokens are atoms. These are the ones that are actually read from your file and
Fed to the parser like the tokenizer just sees like oh, this is a string here is a string like he's a number
Here's a number and the non terminal symbols are produced with the rules
like the one on the slide right and
The production really looks like this like the thing on the left colon is produced from the things on the right
The first production that we have in a grammar file is called the start symbol and as you can clearly read here like oh
File input so that's the entire file and what do files consist of well statements and new lines
so that's kind of you know easy to read and if that production that we have always has just one name on one side and
Productions that are either non terminal symbols or tokens on the right side. We call those things context free grammar CFG's
That makes it you know deterministic
So just quickly following can we actually go from here to just the terminal symbols the tokens?
Just to see this one branch to the leaves in
That tree of the Python grammar like let's try to go through it and see what happens
So as I said a file is consisting of statements and new lines, so what is a statement? Well, it can be either simple or compound
So if it's simple, what does that mean? Well, there's gonna be a bunch of small statements
delimited with
Semicolons right cool. So what are small statements their expressions deletes passes flow statements imports, whatever right?
So what are expression statements were they are?
Lists of star expressions and tests and
What are those like well you have annotated assignments augmented assignments and you clearly kind of see like oh
Composes together and the most fun thing about this is that soon enough you're gonna get to more to a moment where you see
Oh, there's operators. There's or and and and not and if you read from top to bottom
You know that oh, this is actually operator precedence and it's implemented right there in the grammar
So it's not even like, you know something that Python has to think about because there's just one way to read the file
If you go even deeper to the expressions, you're gonna see that there's even more operators and again, this is their precedence
Which is pretty cool. And finally we get to
Tokens, right? So that's the grammar that we're gonna operate in like there's no reason why I'm so showing you this and
It's gonna be obvious in a second
So, yeah, like note that in our short journey we didn't even touch compound statements, right
Which include if if LFL statements and for and while loops and try accept statements and so on
So we didn't get to function calls and function definitions and classes and so on
So grammars for real programming languages tend to be really big
So how does Python actually parse those files if we were to create a parser for a grammar like this manually?
Writing all those if-else statements ourselves, I'll be super error prone
Like nobody has been doing this like since the 70s instead
We are generating a parser from the grammar, which is a bunch of generated code
But generator is written in Python what it generates is a bunch of C in case of CPython
All right
so to show you how
Python the interpreter actually sees the
Source code that we are dealing with let's just see like some
Example code right so this code it has just this main
Function which opens a file and then uses a visitor to just print lines in that file simple enough
so an ASD that we're gonna use and you see the ASD on the right like
Is the actual object oriented version of the lines that we have?
So there's a module which has an import that import has an alias. Obviously we are not using the alias
There is no ass name. So that's none, but it does have a name ASD. So import ASD is that import
There's the import from that it follows right and from the first level
We have this module simple visitor and we import names from it
We can import many but in this case we just import one and so on and so on when we get to a function definition
We see that oh, yeah, it has arguments and whatnot and then we get to the body of the function which starts with
With statement and so on and so on and so on right so finally just like this for loop
You can see like oh, there's a for loop and it has an expression that you know is now
We iterate over and whatnot
At the very end the thing that I wanted to tell you and I wanted to show is that
This is an abstract syntax tree. What that means is like it's this beautiful
operational thing that
specializes nodes for every possible construct in a language
They throw away insignificant details like whitespace optional parentheses comments
So we can just focus on the things that Python is actually going to be running right, but hang on
Formatter actually has to know about those insignificant details, right?
Like this is the ones that we care about whitespace optional parentheses and comments. So what should we do about that? Well, uh
We don't use an abstract syntax tree. We use a concrete syntax tree and in Python we ship one
part of lip two to three
There is a concrete text tree implementation that we can use and black is using it
The output of it looks quite different if you look at the same file
You're gonna see it there's file input and there's a simple statement import name
That name is Lily import and then there's another name that follows that has a bunch of whitespace and says AST
So it's simply just a bunch of containers and
Tokens that just have content and it may be some whitespace calm before the token
So there's a very little specialization here and the thing that I really wanted to like express is how even things like deaf
In the function definition is just a name that is, you know
Prepended by a bunch of empty lines and this is literally just says a deaf and then there's a space and there's main
So we no longer know for sure like what does the code mean?
Like we are not operating on a logical piece of source code anymore as an abstract syntax tree
We're operating on like the tokens as they go and just organize them in containers so that we don't lose the information about
Comments and whitespace. So this is the kind of low-level thing that I had to operate with writing black
It is way more verbose so like it takes way more time to just scroll through this so we're not gonna do this
Well, what I wanted to show you really is that like we do have a concrete syntax tree that we can use and a fun thing
That you can see in this particular slide is that there is an indent and D dent token that we are using
So if you really really squint, you know that Python doesn't have braces
But it does right like indent and D dent tokens are really just you know braces in hiding that we just used
Significant indentation for but it's the same kind of thing in the resulting syntax tree
Alright, so enough of about trees like how did you actually write the thing?
How can we manipulate that syntax tree to output something?
Right, so we're gonna talk about how I did it in particularly in black, which is one of the possibilities. It's not
The the one possible way right?
I'm just telling about the story of how I wrote the thing if you're just interested in using it
You can install it like right now and whatnot
but for me
let me try to convince you first before we get to the trees like
Why did I want to write a new all the formatter in 2018? Isn't that crazy? We already had a few right?
We had all of a paid we had the app, you know IDs like pie charm implement their own all the formatting
It's like why would you create yet a new one?
There should be only one right like you know, if you think about this enough Python
So my design goals were as follows like I didn't want to have a configurable one
I wanted to have one that just formats things the same way every time so I wanted it to be
Opinionated I wanted it to be consistent so that it is easy to explain why it did a thing instead of like having it
Just be a black box that you cannot really inspect
I wanted it to be deterministic. What I mean by this is that if you are running
An all the formatter over the same file twice in
Succession like right after like one run after the other you want the result to be always the same
And in all the pet aid any app that's not true. Like sometimes the second run might actually yield a different result
And I want it to be fast obviously, you know, like reasonably fast, but what I mean is
Back at Facebook some of the files that we're dealing with are megabytes big because they're generated by some automation
There are configuration that we're dealing with and all the formatting those files had to finish and sensible time. Otherwise, it's just useless
Right. So what are the actual?
Parts of a code style that I wanted to be opinionated and consistent
There's like four parts to it really if you think about this
Let's go through like all of them now so you can see, you know how the black code style
Which is like a subset of pep8 solves all of those four things
So horizontal white space is kind of easy because it's when to put spaces and when to avoid them
Like one example that I like to give is this you should put spaces around equal signs
unless it's a
You know a default value of an argument and don't
Unless that argument is type then do it
So like there's rules that we have to literally implement in black that just like if else if else
I can do that and some of them are surprising and people to this day sometimes would report issues on this
But pep8 really says this that if you have a non trivial
Side of a slice you should put the slice Collins
With spaces around them, so that's what the base says and this is what we do vertical white space kind of easy to write
It's like what tokens always to break on what tokens never to break on how many empty lines to use?
So the simple thing is this like I always break after columns like that, right?
So it's we're gonna always do this and then between functions
Well, if you are module level just put two new lines if you are in a class just put one new line
So that's easy
But the non easy thing and the one that people are very often opinionated against and they're like this is so weird is
the sad face
So the sad face is what is produced by having a function signature being long enough that now you have this dedented
closing parentheses and
Colon, oh, why do we do this? Well, like I thought about this
I was actually writing code manually like this before I wrote black and the reason why is that
This is the same kind of formatting as we would apply to
Dictionary lists topo literals. This is how you you know format your data structures
Anyway, so doing this is actually very useful
It has this nice property that it splits visibly the function signature from the function body
And you can get away with this without introducing additional indentation
Just moving stuff around just so that it's clear where the function signature ends and when the function body begins
So this is why we have this hot face
It is a weird for a while if you just are introduced to this style
But you'll forget about it soon enough and it provides consistency across all those language constructs
All right
So that's it
Like one thing that you can see like, you know in red here is that we have this trailing comma those training commas
Are only possible when you're using variadic arguments in Python 3 6 and newer
So blackill is gonna
Detect whether you're using Python 3 6 features in your file
And then it's gonna put the trailing comma if not
Then it's gonna play it safe and not do it because otherwise the grammar which is not accepted it will just say syntax error
So line length that's easy, right? Which one should we use 80 or 120?
Well neither
We're using nine years. Raymond Hattinger had this wonderful talk called beyond pep 8
Where he uses, you know the wealth of his experience to just say that you know in his
Practice as a teacher and as a consultant and big companies. We are just missing a few characters to be happy, right?
We usually have a module that has a class those classes have methods those methods gonna have some if statements
And finally you lost enough levels of indentation that there's not much space for your logic anymore
And just adding like just
You know a few characters beyond the 79 that pep 8 says
Solves the problem entirely and I was like, okay, I trust you Raymond, but let's test it not Facebook
I had access to like, you know tens of millions of Python code. So
Lines of Python code so I ran like black with different kinds of configuration
Like what if we do 79? What if we do 80? What if we do 88?
What if we do 120 and I was looking for how long?
The files are gonna be in terms of how many lines are reproducing and it turns out that like after 88 the difference is really
small
Like it's mostly those few missing characters that cause those ugly formatting to appear everywhere and those
Big folds to appear everywhere. So 90 ish it is and then like I said, I wanted everything to be consistent
So we have trailing commas and we're standardizing on one kind of string
Quote because like if you have this like is this an empty string or is it a double quote character?
Well, you will never know if I don't tell you
now like
We standardized on double quotes double quotes are nice because they anticipate
Apostrophes in your text. They're already what you were what you were using for doc strings
And they're the same in C and you interact with C a lot when you write Python
So to see how we actually implemented black like we have to think about like what does it actually do?
And what is it that it is formatting? Well, it's formatting like lines, right?
Those lines can be 120 lines long 20 characters long or 80 or whatnot. But what is a liner really?
right, so
When I was thinking about this originally, I kind of liked was what yap is
Doing for the same purpose, which is that each line is this theoretical line that we would put you know
our single
Statement or expression or whatever else like this single fragment that we would use if there was no
Limit or for the columns that we want to use right? So sometimes it's gonna be like three characters sometimes eight and sometimes
279 so it's this theoretical
Line that we would use if there were no column limits
So we produce this one first from this visitor that just like feeds from your initial file
We read it and then the super simplify logarithm goes like this we create a
Concrete syntax tree from this input file within the tree
We generate those theoretical lines and when a new line is generated and its length requires splitting
We do split that magic is gonna be explained a bit later and for each split
We still look like is that fitting now that column limit and if not
We just split it again
And then we track blank lines because separately we need to know like how many blank lines to put in a given place
and
We also like track comments and stuff like this
But the rule is this like a line once from Adam and emitted externally is not touched again
So we just do one pass that makes it predictably fast and linear right now in non quadratic
so
The thing that you know
I always like to mention about black is that it doesn't really look at your pre-existing formatting
Like with the obvious exception of empty lines will preserve if you had like two like somewhere or if you had one
It's not gonna remove this one between statements. I'm just gonna leave it same with comments
It really tries hard to like, you know keep comments where you where you wanted them
Which is not super easy, but the most like the most I don't know
Value added of black is really just splitting the lines. So what kind of splitting does black do?
there are actually two kinds of splits that you can use and
We're gonna just like go through them
So the first one is bracket split meaning if you have a line and there are there's some pair of brackets in it
How should you break them well either you can break after the first bracket the opening bracket that you found or
You can break after the last bracket on the line and it turns out that breaking on the last bracket
So the right hand side split it just looks better for for humans because humans write code from left to right
They go as far as the column limit will let them and only then they will realize that oh, I'm at 80 now
So I have to split so they will split and this is how most code in real life is written
Which is why people really like to read code written that way
However, there are certain cases like function signatures where the left-hand side formatting is simply way faster and just produces better results
So we use this too, but in a very limited setting almost everything is the right hand side split and then the okay
Once you already split on brackets
You have this massive body inside but still might be way too many characters on a line
So we do is we are looking for delimiters now are there any delimiters and what are those well?
operators come as spaces between consecutive string literals
standalone comments like so that comments that are just appear on their own on the line and
Like we discover them they have priorities
So like certain ones like just are more important than others and there's at least two of a kind like then we're gonna split
And check whether that now fits a line
So those split lines are still valid Python even though they look weird, you know, if you just look at this one line
Because they are within a bracket pair. So
Significant indentation in Python does not apply to them
So going back to this, you know, and I don't really expect you to read this like now like we visit the tree
Right, we still put at most one statement per line. We split, you know
We are attempting either the brackets for splits or the delimiter splits
But we visit the tree right? So how does the visitor work in black code?
Well, the visitor is essentially a generator it will generate
like, you know lines one by one and then
Like so this is the actual like abstract visitor implementation that I'm using
Then for example the debug visitor that I used to do this graphical representation that we looked at before
Like you just just fit in one slide. I don't expect you to read it now
Just I was just wanting I just wanted to show you that like it's rather easy and usable in practice
Especially that on the user side
You just iterate over the call to the visit method
So this is actual code from black where you go like, you know
For every line we're gonna do things, right? So maybe we should have some empty lines before and after
Right, we're gonna add some contents from those empty lines and then we're gonna just split so for a line and split line
Let's just go and add things to destination contents and later on we're just gonna emit them to a file
So that is the core of it and now, you know how black works
So we could just look at the code and if something is surprising you
It shouldn't anymore because that is really how it works
Like the entire thing including all the edge cases and handling of multi processing and whatever is 3500 lines
It is really, you know possible for us to understand how it does the thing it does
There are other possible algorithms
Some of which might be like what the app is doing and what not like but I won't cover them
Just going to the fun problems the most fun problem with a project like this is users
so
Users are lovely and most of them. Thank you a lot. They report actual bugs. They are patient considerate like it's amazing, right?
Some users disagree with your choices because it's an opinionated formatter and that is okay
It's fine for you to disagree with an opinion
That is fine because there's no head truth to what I'm doing
I have some reasoning for things but it's fine for you to disagree with me
but some people are offended by your choices they demand change and
They submit unsolicited poll requests and make scenes when you decide against merging them and that is sort of kind of you know
Brings you down. That is as annoying
Some demand configuration and I gave some of the reasonable I guess
Once but people always demand more even though they love your product because it is not configurable
So, you know you cannot have it both
Some don't read the documentation if it's too short then you're like you don't have it in the documentation if it's too long
Then they're like too long didn't read
So open source is really a labor of love when I first released black at Facebook
Actually, most people were happy about this. I was very happy
But not everybody was happy
So you can decide that if you are one of those like
324 you're this one person here, but it seems like the project is popular. It is actually you know, like
Almost reached 10,000 star stars on github. Please help me get there
Like obviously github, you know, like sends a cake to people that get 10,000 stars like so or so I heard
It is downloaded pretty often and who downloads it?
Well, pi test talks pyramid the Django channels hypothesis adders poetry pipe
He a applications like warehouse PIP and virtual and many others soon
Maybe Django twisted and flask from what I've heard just in the hallway track. So that's pretty cool
But not all is easy
Handling comments was very hard because comments are not part of the grammar
They're part of this white space that you just throw away
So making sure that they're still there were the human thought they put them
Is actually very hard because they're not sticky to the place a human thought
They just come after some token and before some other token. So
This required like rather tricky
You know
Heuristics optional parentheses. What do they mean? Well in
Python for example an if test doesn't have to have parentheses around it
But it might and sometimes that will format things better. So
Should I put them or should I not put them well
This is tricky as well, right? So that was a thing
Sometimes you have a legitimate reason not to format a bunch of code
So there's format off and format on that was also tricky to
Implement and finally the terminism
We are safe to use black is safe to use because it will actually format your file twice
Internally and check whether the results are the same if they're not is gonna raise an error that there's a bug
There's an internal bug that should not have happened. So the terminism actually had some issues there accidental quadratic behavior
I was you know annoying so those kinds of projects tend to be very complicated in the most unexpected places
So what is the status of black? Should you use it today? Should you wait?
Well, the plan the grand plan for the project is something like this. Oh, not this light
Yeah, so
Stable right?
And we are literally here at the sprints after the conference
I'm gonna build a stable version and we're gonna be done so you can use it. Is it safe to use?
Yes, it not only checks whether the
formatting is deterministic what it also is doing is it's
going to
It's going to check that the AST so the abstract syntax tree is the same before and after
So it didn't break any code Python still sees exactly the same thing so quickly because I'm over time already tips and tricks for adoption
Get hyper blame lets you
Ignore and bypass certain comments
So if you are adopting black create a massive comment that formats everything and then use get hyper blame to
See blame as if nothing ever happened
Then if you have pull requests that were open in the moment that you migrated to black
There is a button that you can press command line instructions that will show you how you can pull the pull requests locally
You know formatted with black and push it back and then use pre-commit so that your code stays blackened
Even if you have many contributors, I don't take any questions now because I'm already over time
But I'm gonna have a poster on Sunday morning and I have stickers with it
So if you want to share some love or hate, please do it on Sunday morning. Thank you very much
My name is oka slanga
Thank You Lukas, so no Q&A