Can everyone see that?
All right.
Hi, I'm Nina Zakarenko.
Some of you might follow me on Twitter.
I tweet at NNJA.
That's like ninja without the I.
I'm here today to show you how to light up your life with Python and LEDs.
Let's try a little bit, let's try something a little bit different today.
It's pretty fun to live tweet, so if you're learning something new, if you're excited
about what you're learning today, I encourage you to share a tweet and use the hashtag
PyCon2019.
If you'd like, you can at mention me as well.
Software is something that's been with me for a long time.
I used to have a lot of creative energy when I was younger and an interest in computers
from a very young age.
I thought the ability to trick computers into doing what I tell them was pretty awesome.
I thought I would have to give that up when I joined the workforce or nobody would take
me seriously as a developer.
My first few jobs really kind of sucked the creativity out of me.
I worked for some large corporations, I worked for enterprises and financial institutions,
and my opportunities for creative coding faded away.
I slowly built that back up with open source, but tinkering with hardware is what let my
creativity truly explode.
It's taken me years to reconnect with that part of myself and relearn the lesson that
I learned all of those years ago.
That software doesn't have to be serious.
Software could be fun.
You can use it to make code, you can use it to make art like this code right here.
This is a Python version of a processing sketch by Saskia Frick.
And hardware doesn't have to be serious either.
This is how Simone Gerz, she's an incredible maker, this is how she eats her cereal in
the mornings.
Here are some of my personal projects.
Here's one, it's an iridescent headdress.
Just know that this is Arduino code, it's basically a variant of C++.
And I only recently started playing with hardware but I also just instantly fell in love.
I've always been wary of the ephemeral nature of software, that you can't hold it in your
hand, you can't touch it.
Software is different.
You can create a physical manifestation of your code.
And I loved the idea of LEDs, of making really cool wearable projects.
I wanted to make pretty things that fit my aesthetic.
I have pink hair and pink glittery nails and I'll show you all my glittery shoes.
So I wanted to make things that looked like this.
The things that fit my aesthetic is what got me interested in hardware.
And hardware lets me be creative, it lets me imagine something and then bring that imagination
to life.
And I've been inspired by a lot of amazing shared projects and documentation from other
makers like Becky Stern.
Yeah.
Now I'm not an expert in electronics and I'm going to show you that you don't have to be
either.
But a little bit more about me.
My name is Nina Zakarenko.
I've been a software engineer for over a decade.
I've written code for some companies that you might have heard of like HBO, Meetup and
Reddit.
Now I work at Microsoft as a Senior Cloud Developer Advocate where my goal is to make
Visual Studio Code and Azure a pleasure to use for Python developers.
If you're interested in learning more about Python at Microsoft, you can check out this
link aka.ms.
But note that you don't have to jot all these links down.
I will give you a copy of the slides at the end.
A quick aside, this is my seventh PyCon.
It's a dream come true for me to be here on stage sharing what I'm passionate about with
all of you.
So thank you all for having me.
And just note that if you find these slides on Speaker Deck, you're just going to have
to download them to click the links.
There's a lot of links throughout the slide, even a slide for additional resources afterwards
that I won't be going through.
So you'll see the link here.
You'll also see the link on my Twitter.
And I have some live demos to show you today.
So please be patient with me.
And of course, I'm a newly minted hardware enthusiast.
So earlier I mentioned Arduino code, a C++ variant, and showed you some of my projects.
The problem here is that, you know, C++, it's not easy to learn.
It's very error prone.
There's a very specific syntax.
If you forget a semicolon, you know, it's game over.
And we know from experience that Python is the opposite.
It's easy to learn.
It's beginner friendly.
It's great for education.
In fact, it was announced in January that Python is going to be part of the official
curriculum for high school education in France.
So we're at a Python conference, right?
And we want to program devices with Python.
Luckily, I hope you all have your swag bags today.
If you reach in them, you should have a device that looks something like this, right?
I'm going to show you how to program it.
So if you look in your swag bag, you'll see that.
And then let's see if my hardware is coordinating today.
Sorry, it's a little glitchy.
Promise it'll stop in a sec.
Okay, can everyone see that?
Let me try one more light.
That's too bright.
Okay, here we go.
And of course, here you'll see my pink glittery nails and my matching pink USB cable.
Just the important things, right?
So here's this device.
That's the wrong window.
That's the one I want.
This is the...
We're going to write some code here.
Make sure that everyone can see that.
Oops.
Just a little refresh there.
I unplugged it and plugged it back in.
So now you should see that up there.
Okay, so this is just some pretty simple...
It's glitching out a bit.
Of course it wasn't doing this when I tested earlier.
Let me unplug that and plug that back in.
Live demos.
That's me.
All right, that looks a little bit better.
All right, we're just going to deal with it.
So this is just some simple, kind of the simplest code that you can have here.
I'm going to walk you through how this works a little bit later.
But the nice thing about this is it just shows up as a drive, and I can program it pretty quickly.
So I'm just going to make a new color.
We'll talk about this soon.
And then I'm going to update that, and let's see if that works.
All right, easy peasy.
Let's switch things back.
Okay, so there are a few other devices that run Python.
The Raspberry Pi 0W, it's a small development kit with wireless and Bluetooth connectivity.
There's the BBC micro bit, it's a computing device aimed at learning.
It was given free to every child around age 11 across the UK in 2016.
Then there's the Adafruit M0 and M4 line of devices and a lot more.
I'm going to be focusing on Adafruit today.
I'm a big fan.
Not just because they sometimes send me free hardware.
Thank you.
But because it's a woman-owned company, it's based in New York.
Adafruit products are low cost, they're easy to order, and they're very well documented.
They have a ton of projects up on their website.
This is one of my favorite hardware platforms.
It was limited edition for Halloween last year.
It's the Hollowing.
It's a spooky development kit with a little bit of a
with a color screen.
I actually have one with me if someone would like to take a closer look.
How do we get Python running on these things?
Well, MicroPython is a variant of Python 3.
It's optimized for microcontrollers and it's compact enough to fit and run within just
256 kilobytes of code space and 16 kilobytes of RAM.
That's what runs on the micro bit.
Now, CircuitPython is an education-friendly fork by Adafruit of MicroPython.
Since I'm going to be showing you demos on Adafruit hardware, we're going to be using
CircuitPython today.
And most importantly, both are open source, so contribute back.
Now, the red ones in your swag bags, they come with Python preinstalled, but if you
have one from somewhere else, depending on when and where you purchased it, it might
not have Python on it by default.
It's pretty easy to set up.
There's a link to that in my slides.
And it's my favorite option for an introduction to electronics and programming
hardware.
PEP 206 describes this idea of Python's battery-included philosophy.
It says that by having a rich and versatile standard library, which is immediately
available without having to make the user download separate packages, the idea is that
it's helped drive Python's success.
Now, the CircuitPlayground Express, the device in your swag bag, it doesn't actually come
with batteries.
But I imagine that the same philosophy applies.
It has everything that you need to get started with programming hardware on one board.
So let me give you a little bit of a tour.
Turn this off really quick.
And let me amp up the brightness.
And zoom in a little bit.
Okay, so it has a circle of RGB LEDs along the sides.
It has these two programmable buttons.
It has a switch on the front right here.
So no, that's not a power switch.
It's a button that you can use to turn on the lights.
It has a power switch.
This is a switch that you can program.
It has a little speaker right here.
It has a microphone.
There's a light sensor, temperature sensor.
There's even a little accelerometer right there in the middle.
And one of the coolest features is that it has a micro USB port.
That's how you program it.
And it's pretty standard.
It's easy right here.
And it's a little bit more powerful.
It's a little bit more powerful.
So I'm going to show you a little bit of how the hardware in the
past know how annoying some of the other programming options might
be.
Now, we talked a little bit about microcontrollers.
So the microcontroller is the little processor on that chip that
does the work.
And I'll go over it a little bit.
But it can run in this tiny package.
Best of all, the best thing about this is that there's no soldering
required, which means that it's great for kids, but it's also great
for clumsy adults.
And it can easily connect to other things with alligator clips like
LED strips.
And you can even sew onto it with conductive thread.
thread.
So an alligator clip looks a little bit like this.
Kind of see that?
It's got like a little clip, clip, clip.
And then you can pick an input pin
and just clip it on right like that.
You kind of want to make sure that it's on there pretty good.
So not this, but that.
OK.
So how do we light up these RGB LEDs that
are on the front of it, that circle?
You have to know a little bit about color theory
to figure out how to get this to work,
but I promise just a little bit.
An RGB LED is a combination of three LEDs in one package.
RGB here stands for red, green, and blue.
Take a look at the color wheel.
You can produce almost any color by combining
these three colors in intensities varying
from 0, which is 0%, to 255, which
is 100% on this scale.
0 means that the color is not present,
while 255 means it's at maximum intensity.
So for example, if blue is set to 255, green is set to 0,
and red is set to 0, what color will we see?
Blue.
That's exactly right.
And looking at the color wheel, you can see, well,
if you mix red and blue, then you see purple.
This is one RGB LED under a microscope.
Remember, the LEDs have one tiny LED inside of them
of each color, red, green, and blue.
You'll understand it better if you see it in action,
because the three tiny LEDs, they light up one by one,
but your eye sees them as one color.
That mixes the colors for you.
In this picture, they're all off.
In this one, just the red LED is lit.
That means the whole LED will look red.
You can kind of tell the color of that
by looking at the outside ring.
Now it's just green.
Now it's just blue.
And lastly, if they're all turned on,
the LED will look like an approximation
of white to your eye.
And using this technique, you can
produce all the colors in between.
Know that NeoPixels are the Adafruit brand
for these individually addressable LEDs.
You might also see them called WS2812,
or there's a few other standards there.
OK, so how do we program it?
It's a lot easier than working with Arduino-based platforms.
For those of you in the room that have tried it,
I feel like you know.
I've seen a lot of AVR dude errors in my day.
So you plug it in with a data and charge cable.
This part is very, very important.
Not all micro-USB cables support data transfer.
So it has to be a known good cable.
If you see a circuit Python drive on Mac OS,
it's in volume circuit py.
You're done.
Otherwise, here's a link to install.
And then you can create or edit a code.py or main.py file
in the root directory.
The important thing here is do not unplug or reset the board
before your computer finishes writing the file to the board,
or you can corrupt the drive.
You want to wait until the file is done being saved
before unplugging or resetting your board.
There's some editors you don't want to use,
like idle and notepad, that don't write the file out
right away.
We'll talk about some other editors in a moment.
And the cool thing here is your code runs instantly
because it's auto-reloaded.
Cool, right?
OK, so let's try this out.
Let's hope my camera coordinates with me.
Let me see right here.
Just make sure everything is in focus for you.
Lock that up.
OK.
I don't want everyone in the room
to feel like they need glasses.
There we go.
Switch this over real quick.
OK.
There we go.
Can everyone see that?
Fantastic.
OK.
Make sure we get the whole thing in there.
Brought a lot of gear to make this happen.
All right, so very quickly, let's take a look at this.
Let's see.
Let me just refresh.
If you have the directory open when you unplug it and plug it
back in, you can just quickly refresh with CD dot.
I figured that out a few days ago.
It's been saving my life.
So running tree on here on this volumes circuit py directory.
We'll see this bootout txt.
You don't have to worry about that.
The important thing here is the code.py file
that we'll be working with.
So we saw the most basic demo.
Let's take a look at something a little bit more interesting.
Going back to our most original demo,
I want to quickly walk you through this.
So the important thing that we have here
is importing the Adafruit Circuit Playground dot
Express library.
You want to import it as tpx.
The awesome maintainer of this, Katniss, in the room today.
So if you're enjoying it, just give her
a quick round of applause.
She's awesome.
Yeah.
And then I created my red color, setting 255 for red,
and then 0 for green, 0 for blue.
I'm turning down the brightness here, because by default,
it's very bright.
Those of you who've already plugged in your Circuit
Playground Express know that.
And the important thing here is that while true,
I want to loop forever.
You want to consider this like an animation.
If you just run your code once, it's
going to blink red for a second, and then turn off,
and you're going to be like, what happened?
So this part here is crucial.
And on this line, line 8, I'm calling cpx.pixels.fill.
That's a helper method on that cpx library
that fills in all of the LEDs with one color.
So looking at our more complex example,
again, I'm importing the cpx library here.
I'm making two colors, red and blue.
I'm setting the brightness, and then kind of scrolling
to the interesting part.
So I'm going to keep looping forever.
If button A, that button on the left-hand side,
let me make sure this is oriented correctly.
This one right here, if that button is pressed,
we're going to fill our circle with red.
If button B is pressed, the one right here,
we're going to fill it with blue.
Otherwise, we're going to fill it with black.
Let me quickly zoom in here so that you all
can see that these buttons are actually handily labeled.
So there's the A right there, and there is the B right there.
Should we try it and see if it works?
Yeah.
Woo!
OK, so the Circuit Playground library,
if the button A is pressed, cpx.button underscore A
will return true.
Otherwise, it returns false.
So we're going to fill this with red.
And then we're going to fill this one with blue.
And then when I let it go, it's just off black, right?
Let's add something else.
Let's do a little bit of live coding.
Let me pretend I'm Kelsey Hightower for a minute.
That's not what I want.
OK, so we got 0.
If we want to make green, it's just 255 for that green value.
And let's say that if both buttons are pressed,
we're going to make the circle green.
And then, of course, we have to change one more thing here,
make that an ulcif.
OK, so I've saved, and the code is just autoreloaded.
So now pressing button A gives us red.
Pressing button B gives us blue.
Moment of truth.
There it goes.
And if I let that one go, it kind of works like that.
So it's really pretty easy and pretty straightforward.
Let's try a few more things.
Let me see.
There we go.
My refresh wasn't working.
Now, this code is just a little bit more complicated,
but really just a little bit.
So under here, let me move this for a sec.
I'm importing my CPX library as before.
I'm importing time.
That's just Python's basic time.
I'm setting up my red, green, blue values like I did before,
setting the brightness.
This time, I'm going to define a list of my colors,
and I'm going to define a color position that's the color
that we're currently at.
Looping forever.
Now I'm going to fill in the circle with the color
at color position from my colors list.
Now, if button A or button B is pressed,
increase the color position by one.
Using the modulo operator, if that value
is increased to more than the length of my list,
using modulo will help me wrap that value around back to zero
so I don't get any indexing errors.
And I'm going to sleep for just a fifth of a second here.
To make the button a little bit less sensitive in programming
hardware, this concept is called debouncing.
Oh, no.
And that's also debouncing.
OK.
So based on this code and the list at line 10,
which let me kind of scroll up for you,
what color should I see next?
Green.
OK.
And next?
Blue.
Oops.
That's why we need debouncing.
OK.
Blue.
And then what color is next?
Red.
Just looping back around.
Doot-doo.
OK.
So let's make this do something a little bit more interesting.
Let me copy a different file here.
And let me refresh that.
So I want to add some more interesting colors to my code
because we've been looking at a lot of red, green, blue.
It's pretty basic, right?
Let me jiggle it, see if that helps.
If that doesn't work, I'm going to take the tried and true
position of turning it off and turning it back on.
So we have our color wheel here on the left.
Did not want to zoom in to that quite so big.
But here we go.
And I have some commented out code here
so that I don't have to remember the color wheel live on stage.
So I'm going to make some new colors.
I'm going to make yellow, which is a mix of red and green.
So now I'm setting 255 for red, 255 for green, and 0 for blue.
I'm going to make a cyan color.
So looking at the color wheel here,
that's mixing green and blue.
And then I'm going to make a purple color mixing
red and blue.
Save that.
So now let's add these to the end of the list.
Let's add the yellow.
Let's add the cyan.
Let's add the purple.
And let's save that.
So now we got our red, our green, and our blue.
And next, yellow.
Yeah.
Next one is cyan.
And the next one is purple.
That matches my hair.
So like I've showed you here, I think the trick really
is to work incrementally.
That will give you a deeper understanding of what's
going on under the hood.
Let's switch things around.
Just going to quickly pass through a few slides.
I had the demos recorded in case things really didn't work.
So what can you use to start writing the code?
Well, the safest bet is to use an editor that writes out
the file completely when you save it.
That does the smart thing so that you
don't have to worry about waiting to save.
You shouldn't just unplug it like I am here.
You should unmount the drive.
But I like VS Code and the Python extension for this
because it's already the editor that I use for Python.
I switched from Emacs a few months ago.
I just used a plugin to set up Emacs keyboard shortcuts.
It has great autocomplete.
It has workspaces, which are nice because the circuit Python
itself only has two megabytes of memory.
So I usually keep the files that I'm
working on a separate folder on my computer.
It has that integrated terminal that you saw me using.
And frankly, I'd be using it even
if I didn't work for Microsoft.
Who picked up their VS Code loves Python socks?
Yeah?
OK, awesome.
I'm glad to see fans in the room.
You can also program with Mew.
It's a simple Python editor for beginner programmers.
It might also be helpful for you if you're also
beginner to programming Python on hardware.
Now, it's helpful to be able to see what's
going on by using print.
The Python interpreter is running on the little device
here.
And it's not running on your machine, right?
So you need to be able to figure out a way of debugging.
So I updated my program to add labels to the colors.
And it's going to keep track of the previous and next colors
now.
So just keeping things simple, using a list of tuples,
building on my previous example.
I'm going to keep looping forever.
Now I'm also going to snag the name and the color at color
position.
I'm going to fill those pixels.
And then if button A or button B is pressed,
I'm also going to snag the next name in the list.
And then I'm going to print out changing color
from what to what.
OK, pretty straightforward.
So in order to view your printouts and your errors,
you're going to need a way to communicate with the Circuit
Playground Express.
And we do that via the Serial Console.
The Serial Console is what receives output from your Circuit
Python board sent over USB and displays it
so that you can see it.
You won't see any printouts without connecting to it.
It's also helpful for troubleshooting errors
because your board will send tracebacks to the Serial
Console as well.
The easy way to do this is with the cross-platform mu editor.
You just click on the button in the top of the bar
if you're in Circuit Python mode,
and it'll pop that open right there.
The advanced way to do it is with the terminal.
You can use a program like Screen for this.
I like using the VS Code integrated terminal for this.
And of course, VS Code is also cross-platform.
But there are plenty of other standalone apps
like Coolterm.
Know that the most important thing
to know about using Screen is how to quit it.
So to quit Screen, you press Control and A, followed by K,
and then you type Y to confirm.
Don't forget that.
It's frustrating.
OK, so let's try it out.
We don't need that anymore.
Get my next demo going here.
Let me close that up.
So just like we talked through earlier,
I have some labels for my colors.
I'm getting the name, current name, and the color.
And then when the button is pressed,
I'm getting the next name and the color.
And the trick here is changing the color from what to what.
So bringing up the integrated terminal here.
I want to LS on dev.tty.
And you should see a USB modem here.
That's the Circuit Playground Express.
If you might see a lot more stuff here
if you have stuff connected on Bluetooth or et cetera,
but it's always going to be a USB modem.
The numbers after it, they're going
to be different for you than they are for me.
And then you just want to paste that whole thing
and type in the screen.
So you won't see any output just yet,
because we have to make it do something.
Let me quickly make this a little bit bigger.
OK.
Oh, no.
I've poked the beast.
OK.
Oh, glitch time.
So now if I press the button, going back
to the kind of important code here, what will I see?
What should I see printed out here?
Changing color from red to green.
Yeah.
And then I can do it again and again.
Yeah, it's pretty cool.
You can clap.
You're allowed.
You're allowed to clap.
It's pretty fun.
OK, cool.
So there it goes.
That's how we do it.
That's how we debug our Circuit Playground Express.
One other super cool thing here, kind of a bit of an Easter egg,
if you press Control-C here, you're going to get a message.
And it's going to say, press any key to enter the REPL.
And guess what?
Just hide that there.
Yeah, there we go.
We have a REPL right here.
And here the REPL is running on this device.
So that's pretty cool.
And Scott, the maintainer of Circuit Python, is also here.
And I'm going to give you a way to find him later on in this talk
by plastering a giant picture of his face on the screen.
All right, let's switch back.
Let me go through some of these prerecorded demos.
OK, here we go.
So the Circuit Playground Express
doesn't have batteries included, like actual batteries.
But considering that, how do you go about powering your projects?
Well, USB is the easiest option.
You probably already have a micro USB cable laying around
You have a phone charging battery.
That's one way of making your Circuit Playground Express
portable.
You can power it from a computer,
a portable phone charger, or a wall.
Or you can use the battery pack.
It just has to have a particular type of JST connector.
And you need a minimum of 3.5 volts.
Know that one household AAA battery has 1 and 1 1 by volts,
so you'll need three of them.
And you can use a power adapter.
So you'll need three of them and an enclosure
to power your Circuit Playground this way.
You can also power it with lithium polymer or LiPoly
batteries.
Just a quick warning here, there are only four advanced users.
They are small, lightweight, and they're energy dense.
They have a lot of energy in a small package.
But they're for advanced users only because they're fragile.
They need a lot of special care.
You don't want to heat them, puncture them, bend them.
If they short or they're damaged, they can explode.
And for that reason, the Circuit Playground Express
does not come with charging circuitry for LiPoly batteries.
So if you want to use this option for powering
your devices, you're going to want to buy your own charger
and make sure it's suitable for your battery's capacity.
It should come with a special protection circuitry.
And note that it's not for kids without supervision.
These batteries are difficult to ship.
They're also difficult to dispose of.
So make sure you do your research
and buy them from a reputable source.
So putting it all together, there
is initial code that comes with the Circuit Playground
on your swag bag.
You can investigate it.
There's also more advanced demo code
that came with one of my Circuit Playground Expresses.
I didn't write it, but here's a link to download it.
This came from Adafruit.
And this code covers all of the necessary features
and the sensor readings that you might want to work with.
And there's even a flag you can use
to set the Circuit Playground Express into a piano
using capacitive touchpads.
Let me show you how to do that.
Let's just move that over.
I think switching the source is maybe
what makes the camera unhappy.
So I'll go ahead and not do that.
I'll try to minimize that.
Moving this to the side, I have another one that
comes with this preloaded code.
You'll see it's powered by one of these LiPoly batteries
I told you about.
Normal Circuit Playground Expresses
come in this black color.
But because yours was sponsored by Adafruit and DigiKey,
your special limited edition one is in DigiKey colors.
Yeah, so let's plug that in.
And this code says you can turn on a flag to have it do this.
If the switch is set to, I believe, the on position,
make this thing a tiny noisy piano by using these.
Oops, I pressed the reset button.
That's not what I want to do.
Make these capacitive touch input pads play tones.
So let's see.
You guys can all hear that, right?
Woo!
Yeah!
Cool.
So I didn't write this code.
It came from Adafruit.
Shh, be quiet.
Quiet now.
Let's turn that switch back.
OK.
So the code that comes on your Circuit Playground Express,
this one right here, there is a flag
that you can set to true to make your own noisy piano.
So that's the very first thing you
can do with your Circuit Playground Express.
After the talk, please.
And you can start your own chiptunes jam bands.
OK.
Wrapping things up.
If you want to get started programming hardware
with absolutely zero coding, Microsoft MakeCode
is fantastic for this.
It's a block-based editor.
You can export as JavaScript.
There might be other things coming in the future.
Shh.
Don't clap for this one.
And there are some pretty cool collaborations there,
like with Cartoon Network.
One of the projects is making a gem from Steven Universe,
which I, yes.
Uh-huh.
And the cool thing there is you don't even need a device.
Hardware is not required.
It includes this built-in emulator.
So I'm not the only one who thinks that hardware is cool.
A study done by the BBC for the micro bit
said that 90% of students that use the micro bit,
it showed them that anyone can code.
It's really important.
86% of students said the micro bit made computer science
more interesting.
This one is a little bit close to heart.
70% more girls said they would choose computing
as a school subject after using the micro bit.
Woo!
Uh, a study called Unlocking the Clubhouse
suggested that traditional computing culture is a boys' club,
and it's unfriendly to women, and we
need to find ways to unlock this clubhouse
to make it accessible.
In a study on e-textiles called Lilypad in the Wild,
Lea Buccelli and Benjamin Macco-Hill
suggest a different approach.
They call it building new clubhouses.
Instead of trying to fit people into existing engineering cultures,
it may be more constructive to try to spark and support new cultures,
to build new clubhouses, and make room for more diverse interests
and passions.
Because remember, diversity doesn't stop at gender.
We want to use Python on hardware to encourage everyone to participate.
That includes people of different ethnicities,
socioeconomic statuses, identities, the neurodiverse, those diverse in age,
and so many other factors.
Let's make Python on hardware the most diverse community that we can.
The overall hardware community, it's really awesome
about sharing incredible projects with step-by-step instructions.
There are Adafruit guides, MakeCode, and Structibles
as a great resource.
On the left is a Jack-o-Lantern project.
You only need the board, batteries, and a Ziploc bag
if you're going to opt for a real pumpkin.
And Python on hardware is still relatively new.
It's really just in its infancy.
This is Madison Maxey.
She's the founder of Lumia, an e-textiles smart fabric technology company.
And she says, you can be a creator and an artist, not just a consumer.
And I agree with her here.
Start small.
Start unlocking your own creative coding again.
Continue your momentum.
This is Angela Shien.
Let's see if I can get that video to play.
She's the maker that I look up to.
You can see she's created these incredible infinity mirror LED heels
and a lot more.
If you love her project, she's actually currently
looking for her next opportunity in the Maker Ed tech space.
So someone in this room should snap her up.
Yes.
And she follows the same passion that I do.
She makes things that fit her aesthetic.
And that's the nature of hardware.
It's being able to see instantaneous results.
It lets you customize your projects.
That helps you connect from the very start.
It helps make technology more accessible to those traditionally
underrepresented in it.
This picture of girls with their light up masks that they created
with these huge beaming smiles is one of my absolute favorites.
I mean, how happy are they?
How excited are they to have made these masks that light up?
They're super fun.
E-textiles, sewable electronics, paper crafts,
hardware focused towards education,
they all help introduce technology
in new and unexpected ways.
Introduce it to these Made by Girls participants.
Thank you to the Digital Media Academy
for snapping this photo.
So those of you with eagle eyes might
have noticed that I'm wearing one of my projects today.
Let me show you what it's made out of.
OK.
Let's see.
So the project that I'm wearing is
made with a different board called the Gemma M0.
It's made with some LED rings that look like this,
kind of soldered together.
These ones are nice because you can just snap them out.
You can kind of see that they pop out there.
So cool.
Some individually addressable LEDs.
And then one of those LiPoly batteries
that I told you about.
So just kind of assembled by starting with the LED rings
and then the little batteries sandwiched in.
And the Gemma lives on top.
And it's all soldered together.
There's a fritzing diagram there if you want to see how.
OK.
So these are based on an original design by Becky Stern.
The code is on GitHub because my earrings run Python.
I hope that you've seen now that Python opens up
a whole new world of working with hardware.
I feel like this quote by Lauren Storrell really drives it home.
He says, our inventions mirror our secret wishes.
We want to build things that reflect us.
So for those of you here in the room today,
what are your next steps?
You all have a Circuit Playground
Express in your swag bags.
Remember, I'm not an expert.
I'm just a hobbyist.
And I hope I've shown you today that you
don't need to be an expert either to get started with it
right away.
Pick your editor, your Visual Studio code, your Mew, et cetera.
Write your own code or follow a community guide.
Everyone in this room can pick up a basic project,
even if you're not a programmer.
So I implore you to learn, make things, create, teach others,
share your knowledge.
It's a fantastic cycle that we can all participate in.
And if you're in a position to maybe gift yours
to somebody who's underrepresented in tech
and show them how to get started, it's just an idea.
Yeah, you can clap.
That's all right.
You can give them a platform to unlock their interest
in lighting up their life with hardware, creativity,
and community.
So I want to say, let's start something new.
I noticed that the Python hardware
hashtag has never been used.
So let's make it our own.
Well, it was new, sort of.
Raymond Hedinger caught a preview of this talk yesterday.
And so in good humor, he's the first one
to tweet out on this hashtag.
Thanks, Raymond.
So use this hashtag.
Share your projects.
Share your gifts to the community.
Share who you're teaching.
And let's own this and make it our own.
If you're excited about getting started right away,
CircuitPython is at PyCon.
You can see some of the folks in this photo.
There's Scott.
There's Katniss, a few other lovely folks from Adafruit.
Today, they're going to have an open space in room 22 at 5 PM.
Tomorrow, there are going to be CircuitPython sprints starting
at 9 AM.
And I have an announcement I wanted to share.
I teach Python.
And as a special thank you to PyCon attendees,
I'm releasing my two-day intro and intermediate Python
screencast for free for two weeks at this link.
It's been a pleasure speaking to you today.
Hopefully, I've left you inspired.
You've learned how to program LEDs with Python.
You've learned how to light up your life with code
and creativity.
If you want to take a closer look at some of this hardware,
come find me or any of the Adafruit team
that's here at PyCon.
Slides are going to be posted at this link
if the conference Wi-Fi has cooperated.
If not, they're going to be on my Twitter.
And this image on the right-hand side,
that's the mascot for my team, developer advocate Bit.
So if you think Bit is cute, you can find me afterwards
for stickers.
And thank you all so much.
Woo!
Applause