Hello, everyone.
Welcome to the talk on Logging for Scientific Computing, Reproductibility, Debugging, Optimization.
And our speaker is Itamar Turner-Turing.
Let's give it up for Itamar.
Hi.
Thanks for coming.
My name is Itamar.
I'll be talking about logging for scientific computing.
And I offer consulting services.
And you can read about that at pythonspeed.com.
And there's also going to be on that website a prose version of this talk if you want to
just read it as text.
So I'm a software engineer, not a scientist.
But I spent a year and a half on my last job doing scientific computing together with biologists.
And I learned a little bit about the nature of scientific computing, which makes it rather
different than the kinds of software engineering that I had previously been used to.
And so there's three characteristics that I think define what scientific computing is.
And the first is it tends to be very complex calculations.
There's a lot of math.
There's a lot of logic.
It's very complicated compared to the usual kind of software that I've done as a software
engineer in the past.
Second characteristic is a structure, how you run the software.
Typically, when you're doing scientific computing, you're loading in data, sometimes very large
amounts of data.
You're doing some processing and you're spitting out a result.
And so as a side effect, you basically end up with these long-running batch processes.
And the third characteristic, which is really the most fundamental, is the goal of scientific
computing.
You're trying to make an inference about reality.
So what I was trying to do at work was take some images off a device and figure out what
the DNA sequence was on a cell culture.
If you're a meteorologist, you might be taking all these data points and trying to predict
the weather next Tuesday.
So you're trying to make a statement about reality, try to figure out something about
reality from your data.
Each of these characteristics has a corresponding set of problems that come along with it.
So if you have highly complicated logic, if you have all these calculations, you're doing
a lot of math, you're doing a lot of transformations, it's very easy to make, refer to a small typo
to destroy your results.
You have a wrong negative sign somewhere and now all your results are completely wrong.
And so you want to be able to figure out when your calculation goes wrong where the mistake
is and it can be difficult when you have large amounts of calculations to pinpoint
where exactly you made a mistake.
When it comes to structure, if you have long running batch processes, long running software
is very painful, as we'll talk about later in the talk.
And so you're going to want to make it faster.
So you're going to want to figure out how can I make this software faster.
Having something that runs for two days is no fun.
Having something that runs for two hours is no fun.
And finally, and again, most fundamentally, if you're trying to make a statement about
reality and if you're going to then share that statement with other people, if you're
going to say, these are the genes in this cell culture, if you're going to say, this
is what the weather is going to be next week, you want to be able to trust that statement.
You want to be able to say, I can trust the results that came out of this software.
And that trust has to be about like some relate, like it does actually match reality within
the limits of your modeling.
And so for the rest of this talk, I'm talking about these three problems and how logging
can help you address all three of them.
And the first problem is bugs in your code.
How do you deal with wrong calculations?
And this is made worse by the fact that when you're doing scientific computing, you might
have a very slow feedback loop.
So imagine you've run your batch process, you've processed all your data, you finally
have a result, and it only took you 12 hours, so it's a good day, and the results are completely
wrong.
So say you're processing weather data and you're loading some data about summer around
here and it's telling you it's going to snow.
And so you know it's not going to snow, like your weather model is broken, but you don't
know where or why.
And so how do you figure out where your calculation went wrong?
So one problem that often happens with this kind of thing is that it only happens with
real data.
It's difficult to get simulated data, and so it's difficult to get small edge case examples.
And so you can't just write it with a small test that runs in three minutes and get a
result showing you the mistake.
You only get, this only happens to you when you're running it with real data, which means
it takes a really long time to run.
And if it takes a really long time to run, using a debugger isn't going to help you because
you're not going to sit there for 12 hours and hit next and then wait another hour and
then hit next and then step to the code that way.
It's just too slow.
You can't.
If you're really desperate, you might do that, but you really don't want to.
So what you'd like, what would be ideal is to have a record of everything that your batch
steps, and then you can go look at that record and say, this is what happened, and then this
happened, and then we did this.
Oh, that looks wrong.
Which is to say you want logging.
You want to log what happened as your batch process ran.
You want to know which functions called which other functions.
You have branching logic.
You want to be able to see which branches you went down.
You want the inputs and the outputs to all your calculations.
And you want the intermediate results of your calculations.
Basically, you want transcripts of everything that happened.
And the way I was doing logging at my job, and I feel the examples I'm going to be giving
are using a library that I created called Elliott.
It started in 2014.
It was originally designed for a small but complex distributed system.
And I didn't actually design it for scientific computing.
But when I started doing scientific computing, I discovered it was actually a really good
fit.
And normal logging systems, like Python's built-in logging, you basically have logging
as a series of statements.
This thing happened.
Another thing happened.
And other than the fact that this one statement happened after another, you don't have any
relationship.
Like they're just isolated statements.
Also many logging systems, though not all, tend to be oriented towards pros.
So you write a English or German or whatever language's statement about what happened.
Elliott in contrast has a very different model.
At first it's structured.
So it outputs data that you can parse with a program, JSON by default.
But more importantly, it gives you a trace.
It gives you a tree of actions of what happened, which is what makes it useful for the sort
of things we'll be talking about.
And it also has some built-in support for scientific computing that I've added.
And so to see what this means, we'll look at an example.
So this is a program.
It's a very simple calculation.
We have a function that takes two inputs and adds them together and returns a result.
We have another function that takes two numbers and multiplies them and returns a result.
Then we have function multiply sum that takes three inputs.
It takes two of the inputs and adds them together.
Then it uses the multiply function to multiply them with a third number and return the result.
So for example, we're going to call multiply sum with one, two, and four.
So it's going to add one and two.
So we expect to get three.
It's going to multiply three by four.
We expect to get 12.
And so when we run this program, we expect it to output 12.
It's a very simple calculation.
And so we run it.
And we don't get 12.
We get zero.
So something is wrong in this program.
And since this is a trivial example, you can just go, if I showed you the implementation,
you would know exactly where the code was wrong.
But if you're doing scientific computation, you have a much more complex and harder to
debug piece of code.
You're not going to be able to just read it necessarily and pinpoint this point, the spot
where things went wrong.
So what you want is to have logging.
And so ideally, you've added logging before you ran the program.
If it's going to be, if you know your batch process is going to take hours and hours to
run, you don't want it to run hours and hours, see the result is wrong, and say, oh, I should
have added logging.
You want to add logging in advance.
But that is not how it happens.
In this case, we're going to add logging afterwards.
So to use Elliot, the first thing you want to do is actually tell it to emit log messages.
And so we're going to use a decorator called log underscore call.
And log underscore call will log all the inputs to a function, and it'll log the return result
of the function.
This is the simplest API that Elliot provides.
It provides a lot more sophisticated, nuanced APIs.
You don't actually have to log only on function boundaries.
You can log within a function.
I'm using log underscore call because it's the simplest and sufficient.
This is a talk about the ideas rather than the specific APIs.
And the other thing you need to do to use Elliot is to tell it, add a little bit of
boilerplate telling it where to log to a file.
So I'm saying open a file called out.log in writable mode, send all your messages to that
file.
So just a little boilerplate you add at the top of your program.
And so I've added five lines of code here, I think.
One import, if you were to do this in your application, there's three functions we annotated
with logging, and we added an import, and we added a little boilerplate to log to a
file.
So not very heavyweight.
We run the program, and we get zero again.
But this time we have logs.
So we run a program called Elliot Tree that was written by Jonathan Jacobs, one of Elliot's
users.
And Elliot Tree takes these logs and it formats them as a tree of actions.
And so this is where you can see where Elliot is fundamentally different with most logging
systems.
Most logging systems you would just have a series of messages.
They would have no structure.
With Elliot, you have a tree of actions, showing which actions cause which actions, the parameters,
the results, and you can also add intermediate values and individual messages if you want.
I have simplified the output of Elliot Tree because it's a lot more verbose and has more
information and it wouldn't fit in a slide.
But the basic structure you're seeing is what it'll output.
So if you look at it, you can see we have a top-level action, which is multiply sum.
And it has three inputs, one, two, and four.
And multiply sum called another subaction called add with one and two.
And the result is three.
You can see in the logs.
And then it called another multiply sum called second subaction, which is multiply with inputs
three and four.
Presumably three came from the previous action, although we can't be sure from the logs.
And the result of that is zero.
And then the overall result of multiply sum is zero.
So if you look at this log transcript, you can see that adding worked just fine.
We added one, two, got three.
But multiplying, we multiply three and four and got zero, which is not what we expected.
We expected to get 12.
And so we've pinpointed where the problem is to the multiply function just by reading
the logs.
And because it's a tree and not just individual statements, we can see the relationship to
some extent between all the different actions in the program.
So this is how logging can help you debug your programs and find bugs in your calculations.
The second problem we'll talk about is how do you figure out why your program is slow,
which matters a lot when it's taking hours or days.
And so the typical way to approach performance optimization is to run your program under
a profiler.
This is extremely useful and extremely helpful.
And I've gotten great results from profiling my code, optimizing it, and building the algorithms
based on that, specifically for scientific computing.
But profilers are limited.
And they're not the only...
They're not sufficient on their own to solve all the problems you might have.
And one problem is profilers are typically designed for a single process.
And if you're doing...
Running a calculation that's going to take hours or days, you are typically going to
try to use multiple cores, multi-CPUs, maybe multiple machines to speed up your calculation
parallelism.
So maybe you have 30 processes running in parallel.
Maybe you have a thousand machines running in parallel.
And profilers don't really support that notion of profiling across machines, typically.
Usually it's you're profiling one process.
And so while you can profile individual tasks, it's difficult to profile your whole execution.
And Elliott, since it was originally designed for distributed systems, has support for connecting
the logs from different processes into one big tree of actions.
So you can watch an action start in one process and then continue to another.
And it has specifically built-in support for the Dask parallel computation framework.
So if you're using Dask, it's very easy to just trace your computation across your whole
cluster that's using Dask.
The other reason the profilers are insufficient, though useful, is that a profiler is typically
focused on functions.
So it'll tell you this function is slow.
Or if it's a good profiler, it'll tell you this function will call by that function,
will call by that function.
This function, this call graph call tree, is a slow function.
But especially when you're doing the algorithmic code, your function might be slow in some
inputs but fast in others.
And the profiler can't tell you that.
It just sort of averages out all the inputs and just tells you this function is slow.
And that's useful, but you might be able to figure out the performance problem much more
quickly if you knew which particular inputs were causing this lowness.
And this, again, is where logging and Elliott's similar system is going to be very useful
because we're giving you a trace of the execution.
So you can see who called what and how long each action took.
But also it tells you what the inputs were, what the parameters were to each of the actions
that you logged.
And so you can identify slow actions based not only on which function it was or which
action, if it doesn't have to be mapped to functions, but also based on the inputs to
those functions.
So in this program, the calculation is slow.
And if you were to run a profiler, it would tell you that the double function is slow.
And so that's useful, but it doesn't necessarily tell us why double is slow under what inputs.
And if double is a simple function, that's fine.
If double is 300 line function, it would be useful to know which inputs are causing it
to be slow.
But if we have logging, we can actually answer this question.
We run the program, takes a while.
They run Elliott tree to generate a human readable tree.
And then we extract only those lines that relate to the double function because we've
already determined that the double function is a slow one using a profiler.
You could also read the whole tree, but this way it'd fit on the slide.
So we can see that double got called three times as we expected.
Each time with a different argument, it got called the 13, 0, and 4.
There's a little hourglass on each line.
Hourglass is how many seconds each action took.
And you can see the first action took zero seconds, and the last action took zero seconds.
The second action took 10 seconds.
And so we know that double, when it's called with 13 and 4, ran quite quickly.
But when it was called with 0, the double function ran really slowly.
And so we know not only did double function, logs can tell us not only which function was
slow, they can tell us that this particular function or these inputs were slow.
And the third problem I'd like to talk about is trust.
How can you trust your code?
So scientific code is an argument about reality.
You might say this cell culture has these particular genes.
The weather is going to be rainy on Tuesday.
This behavior has correlated with that behavior.
This causes that.
You're making a claim.
And you want to be able to trust that claim.
And to begin with, you want to be able to trust it yourself.
You don't want to go and share your results with someone if you don't trust that the results
are correct.
You want to be sure, as sure as you can, that you can actually trust the statement that
you're claiming.
And then once you're sure yourself, you need to then share those results with someone else.
And then you're going to have to convince them to trust your results, convince them
to trust your code, which is a little bit different than convincing yourself.
Because they might not understand what you've done as well as you do.
But they also might be more objective.
There are some ways you can gain trust in your scientific computation.
Reproducibility is a big thing.
If I run your software with the same inputs and I get a completely different result than
you did, or if I just can't run it at all, I'm going to have a hard time trusting any
of the results.
You want your results to be consistent.
You want your software runs to always be the same.
You can test your software with automated tests.
You can do unit tests with test cases for your computations.
You can do metamorphic tests for high-level properties.
The thing I learned about a couple months ago, if you search for the phrase, there's
an article by Hildelewein.
They're really neat.
You should learn about them.
And once you understand it, it's much less intimidating than the name.
It's actually quite a simple idea.
And you can validate your computation against information you have about reality.
So if you have a weather model, you can run it using past data and compare it to past
weather predictions.
If you're doing gene sequencing, you can run a similar sample from the same place through
an existing gene sequencing machine and you can compare the results.
You can compare it to your knowledge of the domain.
You know the ratio of frequency between this gene and that gene should be, say, 4 to 1.
If the results are 20 to 1, then you're missing something.
And logging can help with reproducibility, at least, because it can...
Reproducibility is often in terms...
It can be thought of in terms of the end result, but you can also think about reproducing the
intermediate results.
If the intermediate results are the same, that gives you even more trust that it's actually
the same calculation that ran before.
But all of those things, which you should be doing, reproducibility and testing and
obviously validating against your knowledge of reality, may not be sufficient to gain
someone's trust that your code is good or that your results make sense.
Because if you just hand someone an opaque black box, if you say, here's this thing,
I shove in data and I get this result, you should totally trust it.
People aren't going to really buy that.
People want to understand how you did it, how it works, why it works, what it does.
You need to explain what it is you're doing.
And so if you read a scientific paper about some computation, they'll explain the steps
they did and why they did them.
So you need a coherent explanation saying, here's why we did these things.
We did this step, and here's a graph showing the intermediate results with a relationship
that makes sense.
And then we did another thing, and here's a table with a distribution, and here's what
we think, this makes sense.
And you can talk through and explain what you did and tell a story that makes sense
and with the data and a causal explanation about why your calculation does what it does.
And the common tool for doing this is Jupyter.
And Jupyter Notebook lets you create basically a story interleaving code, graphs, diagrams,
pictures and text.
Just English or whatever.
And it's really great at writing an explanation because you can say, here's my code, here's
a result, here's a diagram, here's some text explaining what I did.
But as a software engineer, I also see some problems with writing software at Jupyter
because it encourages you to write software in ways that aren't modular, that are harder
to test.
In terms of writing explanation, it's a great tool.
In terms of writing software that you can maintain over long periods, software you can
use as a library, it's just not very good.
And it's not designed for that, and that's fine, but it's a trade-off.
But you can also think of logging as a way of explaining your software.
Because if your logs have a causal trace of what you did, if your logs show you all intermediate
results, your log in some sense is a story about what your software did.
And if you can read that story and understand it and see what it did, you're going to trust
your software better.
And Elliott is just a library you can add to any piece of software where you need logging.
And so it doesn't sort of strongly impact the way you write software the way Jupyter
does.
But as a downside, it is very much tied to the specific implementation.
It's not really, you don't have any way to add images, you don't have a way to add explanations.
And so it is much more useful for allowing you to trust your own software, whereas you
can't really put a dump of your Elliott logs as a scientific paper.
Sharing it with others might be a problem.
So it's not ideal either.
But you can imagine a future where you can combine the two.
You could, Elliott, you probably don't, right now you probably don't want, with the default
setup, you probably don't want to dump a 300-megabyte array into Elliott.
But it could be extended to support that better.
And you can add support to Jupyter to load a trace of your logs.
And then you can imagine developing your scientific software just as you write regular software
in libraries and tests and so on.
But then taking a run and taking a full trace of all the execution and then loading it into
Jupyter and then using Jupyter to analyze that data, to create visualizations, to tell
a story to explain what it did.
And so you can basically combine the, what Elliott gives you and combine what Jupyter
gives you and get the best of both worlds.
And if there's something that interests you, please come talk to me or send me an email.
I'd love to talk about this.
So in conclusion, logging can help you debug your code.
Logging can help you figure out some of the performance problems in your code.
Logging can help you understand and trust the results of a long computation.
And so next week when you head home from PyCon, if you do scientific computing, I encourage
you to maybe add some logs to your code.
And then next time you have a bug, you will have some logs that will help you debug it.
If you want to learn more about Elliott, there's documentation at Elliott.ReadTheDocs.io.
I offer consulting services, both bridging the gap between scientific computing and
software engineering and performance optimization for Python.
That's my email, Twitter.
And thank you very much for coming.
I really appreciate it.
Thank you, Itamar.
We've got a few minutes for questions.
So if you have any, walk up to the microphone.
By the way, I will be outside after the talk if you want to talk to me afterwards.
Right outside the hall.
Hi, Elliott.
Okay.
So lots of people on production systems, they use log shipping services to aggregate and
search the logs from all their services in a single place.
How well does Elliott interact with that?
Can I point Elliott to standard output and then be able to filter the things that Elliott
produces so that I can feed it into the Elliott tree file later?
How does that interact with standard Python logging, logging at the same file, those kinds
of things?
Do you have any idea?
So as far as standard Python logging, you can route standard Python logging into Elliott
and the log messages will end up in the right place in the tree.
So you don't have to switch all your logs.
If you have existing logging, you don't have to replace it all.
You can keep it and just add a few Elliott decorators and all your logs will end up in
the right place in the tree.
As far as aggregating the logs from multiple machines, I have not done this recently, but
you can pipe Elliott into logstash, which is a tool for shipping logs around, and then
put them into a log search thing like elastic search.
In certain versions of and you can sort of coax a certain log, generic log visualization
tools like Kibana to sort the log messages based on causality.
And then you get sort of the equivalent of Elliott tree, not quite as nice.
You do get the causal order of the log messages in a generic log viewing UI.
You can also each tree has a unique ID, so you can talk to the log database and extract
all the log messages for a particular unique ID and then type that into Elliott tree in
a viewer, which I know one company has done.
So it is possible, yes.
Thanks.
Okay.
It sounds like Elliott is possibly a best practice for scientific computing, or is there
another solution that may be applicable in other situations, and can you expand on those
other situations and other options?
I have not done a huge amount of searching for logging solutions for scientific computing.
I have done a little bit of research.
I haven't found much.
You can use standard logging systems.
None of them give you a tree.
Most logging systems will just give you individual statements.
There is a library called struct log that only gives you structured logging.
So at least it gives you a logging that you can parse with a machine with the software
and therefore get the parameters and service pros.
There may be other solutions.
I don't know if that is for Python.
Do you have any insight into how Elliott would work with Spark or Kubernetes?
I don't know much about Spark, so I can't really answer that.
But if you explain the execution model, I did a little research on my answer.
For Kubernetes, Kubernetes is a way of running software in a cluster.
Kubernetes will capture logs and aggregate them.
You would then have to feed it into something like Elliott tree if you wanted to visualize
it better, but I would expect it to work fine.
How well does Elliott cope with really large inputs if I have a 10 gig matrix that I am
putting into a function?
So it will work really badly.
By default.
So there are two layers.
There is a generic logging layer which has the concept of actions and then there is a
serialization format which writes it by default to JSON.
So when I added the thing where it writes the file, it just writes JSON.
You could write your own destination that did whatever you wanted.
So when I was talking about hooking up Elliott to Jupiter, one of the things I would want
to do there is to write a custom destination that wrote large arrays to some sort of storage.
I have imagined things like if you are running on AWS, you would write it to an S3 bucket
where it expires after a couple of weeks because you probably don't want to look at batch processes
from two weeks ago.
So you can write custom destinations for your logs and that is where you would be logging
in situations where you want to log large arrays.
If you want to talk about that outside, I would be happy to talk about it.
I think we are out of time.
Thank you everyone.
Let's give it up for Itamar once again.
Thank you for coming.