Very, very sorry about this delay.
I was preparing for the entire night
and a little bit oversleep today.
So, very sorry.
My talk is about machine learning model version control
and data set version control.
My name is Dmitry Petrov.
I will be talking about three open source tools.
One is machine learning MLflow from Databricks.
Another one is Git LFS.
And the third one is DVC, data version control.
I am one of the creator of a DVC project.
So, my opinion might be a little bit biased,
but I try to take a look at this problem
from different angles.
So, let's, first let's ask,
why do we need new tools?
Why machine learning is special
and why should we care about the new best practices
and new tool set?
There is an opinion that machine learning process
is not efficient, it's not efficient enough.
We still don't have any version control tools in place.
We are wasting a lot of time for the process.
Agile might not be or might be the best solution.
And there are new practices
which are not supported by the tool set.
To understand how we can fix that,
let's take a look at the difference
between software engineering and machine learning.
And one of the straightforward differences is
machine learning is matrix driven.
Matrix, this is how we navigate through our project.
This is how we compare results from today,
let's say with results from last week, last month.
We don't use code as the only source of navigation.
Now we use outputs, which is matrix,
to compare our results.
But how can we track the matrix?
If you're only one guy in the project,
you can use just a pen and pencil,
put it down and it works just fine.
But when people start working on a team,
it's just not enough.
They need to use some tools.
You will be surprised,
but the most often used tool is called Excel spreadsheet.
This is how you can put some information,
share them on the team,
and you will see what exactly happened
on each particular step.
With time step, with parameters, and final metrics.
The next problem is models.
We need to track models.
We don't wanna waste time on build model again and again.
And we need to track models as well.
So Excel spreadsheet, again, helps for many companies.
They put the models, file name into Excel file,
and this is how they share information.
Another thing is datasets.
We need to manage these large data files.
We need to move them around from your desktop
to your server with GPU instances.
Sometimes you need your laptop.
Sometimes you need to move data
to your team member machine.
So we need to have some tools in place.
And this problem become even worse
if the dataset evolves.
Because you might have new labels every single week.
You might have many changes in a single day
because you're working with data.
And everything needs to be tracked.
And again, Excel spreadsheet might be used
for organizing this information.
But you will have a lot of different copy of your datasets.
And the last problem is pipelines.
Machine learning pipelines.
Pipelines is basically the way how you manage complexity.
And this is the way how you scale your team.
So one guy can work on data preparation,
another guy on feature extraction,
the third one on training,
and one more probably on some visualization.
Many teams come up with custom pipeline solutions.
They build this from scratch.
And this is how pipeline usually looks like.
It's important to mention that
there are two different types of pipeline in data project.
One is data engineering pipelines like Airflow,
and another one is machine learning pipelines.
In machine learning, we need lightweight version
of the pipeline because our focus not real ability,
our focus is fast iteration.
We need to try ideas faster.
We need to fail faster and produce some results faster.
So the best practices we need in machine learning
are following, matrix tracking, model versioning,
dataset versioning, and machine learning pipeline versioning.
Let's go through the tool.
MLflow is the first one.
They provide for tracking,
they provide a library for Python and Spark.
You can basically put some statements in your code,
and during the training or data processing,
you'll have all the output in some directory.
Then you run UI, and this is what you will see.
Have you recognized the table?
This is actually the first table that I show you.
So they basically replace your manual work
with auto-generated table.
And this is a good engineering practice.
So we just remove manual work, replace it by automation.
So however, MLflow might be not the best tool
for datasets tracking.
So Git LFS, it's a quite popular solution.
It was designed for engineers,
especially for front-end engineers with data files.
It's not data specific.
However, it can be used for model tracking,
like 100 GB, couple GB, or 100 megabytes,
couple gigabytes files sometimes,
maybe even more, up to 10.
It might work.
For large datasets and ML pipelines,
we have created Data Version Control Tool, or DVC.
Initially it was my pet project.
Now we have 50 contributors.
Many companies use that.
The tool set solves two problems,
data versioning and pipeline versioning.
And one additional principle the tool supports.
We compatible with any cloud.
You can use any cloud as a data backend.
You can use S3, Google Cloud, or just SSH server
when you store your datasets.
You can easily find an install tool.
DVC.org is our website.
When you run the tool,
it provides command line experience, like a Git.
It doesn't require any infrastructure.
You don't need to run to any server.
And you will be using your Git as a code repository
for storing your code and metadata information.
And storage, cloud storage for data.
This is how it works.
You run DVC add and file.
It has similar semantic to Git add.
It basically adds file under DVC control.
And when you say DVC push,
data will be in your data storage.
DVC creates some meta files
to know all this information about data files.
You need to commit meta information
to your Git repository.
For example, you need to commit changes in Git ignore
and additional meta information files.
Your teammate can clone this repository
with all the meta information,
and then say DVC pull, and they will get all the data.
There is support for pipelines.
You can run your commands with DVC run prefix.
And so the tool will reconstruct
the entire dependency graph.
And then you can reproduce,
and the tool will understand
what exactly needs to be reproduced.
So as a result, we basically replaced
the last table, Excel spreadsheet,
with data sets, versions.
We replaced those table with your Git history.
And from engineering point of view,
Git history is actually the best documentation you can get.
Git logs is probably the only docs
that every engineer in any project reads.
Now you can go back and forth with your data sets,
with your pipelines, and final models,
instead of writing about this.
So there are a few little optimizations that DVC does.
And this is the final table.
What is important about this table?
You can combine different tool,
depending on your needs.
For example, you can track metrics with MLflow,
and use data versioning, or pipeline versioning,
with Git LFS or DVC.
I have seen many projects when people do that.
So why do we need,
so this tool set, we need this new tool set,
because our environment is changing.
Our entire landscape is changing.
We are basically moving from software engineering
to machine learning, to data science methodology.
We need to invent new tools.
The previous change was a change from hardware design
to software engineering,
and it took us more than 20 years.
We invented version control systems,
issue tracking systems, continuous integration,
and many other techniques and tools.
And now we need to make the same change.
But the question is, if we are making the change,
how can we make it faster?
It doesn't sound like a good idea to wait for 20 years.
I believe to make it faster,
we need to do four different things.
First, we need to think about processes, our workflow.
We need to understand when we waste most of our time,
and when we make most of our errors in the processes.
Second, we need to try new machine learning tools.
If you don't find one, you probably need to invent one.
Third thing, and probably the most important thing,
we need to share this knowledge.
We need to share this knowledge,
our successes and failures.
And the fourth one, if you develop tools,
they probably should be open sourced,
because with open source,
open source is the best way to share this knowledge,
is the best way to communicate with your successes
and failures in the process.
So yeah, you can contact me on Twitter or on any,
or email.
Actually, we have a booth today on the Startup Row.
Please check it out.
Today we are running competition for open source project.
We surprise for open source project.
Please join us.
Now I'm open for the questions.
No questions?
Yeah, all right.
Thank you.
No questions?
Yeah, all right.
Thank you.