Hi everyone, welcome. Our next speaker will be Manojit Nandi talking to us
about measures and mismeasures of algorithmic fairness.
How do I do things? There we go. That's how things happen. Okay. Sorry for the bit delay.
Hello everyone. Thank you all for coming to my talk this afternoon on measures and mismeasures
of algorithmic fairness. I'm Manojit Nandi and I'm a data scientist. So, quick about me.
According to the Google Cloud Computer Vision API, so I ran a photo of myself through the
Google Vision API and it produced some labels for me. So let's go through some of them and see how
right they are. Am I a dancer? Yes, I'm an aerial dancer and circus acrobat. I just work as a data
scientist for 40 hours a week because I got to pay rent somehow. Am I entertaining? I hope so.
You're stuck with me for the next 40 minutes. Am I fun? Oh, most of the time. And lastly,
am I a girl? Huh. So that one is not true. I am a male presenting sys man. So why did Google Vision
think I am a girl? And the thing is it's not just Google Vision. If I were to run this through
Microsoft Vision API, it produces similar results. It says, oh, this is a picture of a lady.
And so the thing is, what are these really looking for when they say this is a girl? Are they saying
how similar am I to what they've understood to be a girl? Is it because of, oh, this is a dancer and
all the dancers in my training set were girls, so therefore this is a girl as well? Or is there some
physical feature about me that makes it think that, oh, this is probably a girl? And this seems like
a fun, innocuous example, but these types of systems of automatic gender recognition are used
everywhere. For example, to basically show you better ads when you're in a taxi cab for some
reason, because after all, it's not the true purpose of data science to show you better ads.
And think about this. This sounds really dumb. It's actually quite dangerous, because if you
basically have some prototypical understanding of what this is what a man looks like, or this is what
a woman should look like, you could actually misgender people whom that is actually a huge issue
too. And so there's a researcher at University of Washington, Oz Keyes, who's done a survey of how
queerness and gender are thought about in human computer systems. And their overall findings is
that the way we think about gender in human computer systems is inherently trans exclusionary.
So now as we try to be data-driven leaders and we use these types of systems, we are sort of
using systems that are inherently trans exclusionary. We inherently make decisions
that ignore the existence and lived experience of the trans community. And I hope this example
sort of motivates why we should care about fairness and ethics when we do data science
and machine learning. So what is algorithmic fairness? So algorithmic fairness is a field
of research that's aimed at trying to mitigate the effects of unwarranted bias on discrimination
on people on machine learning. And so this is a kind of weird thing because like bias is a very
overloaded term in data science and machine learning. It's probably the second most overloaded term
after kernel, which has a bunch of different definitions in machine learning. And right now,
sort of like the focus on this type of research has been in like coming up with mathematical
definitions of fairness. We have this mathematical definition of fairness, we're going to find some
solution to it and hope that maps back well to the original problem. But over the last year or so,
we've seen some pushback against this. We've seen that, okay, in this paper, for example,
called fairness, abstraction and social technical systems, that there's sort of an over a formalism
trap that we care too much about mathematical formalisms, that even if you solve the mathematical
formalism, it doesn't really translate well to a real world solution. And the key thing to keep
about this is like, first is inherently a social and ethical concept. It cannot be perfectly captured
or represented through mathematical definitions or statistical metrics. And we'll talk about the
research. And I guess I want to take a slight, I guess, take a side about like, this is the idea
of like, okay, well, we're using algorithms and math, and math can't be racist. That's silly.
And this actually came up in January when this like alt-right journalist basically criticized
New York Congresswoman Alex Ocasio-Cortez when she said that, okay, algorithms have been shown
to discriminate against blacks and his schematics in different cases. And so the thing is that like,
when we say that an algorithm is racist or sexist, we're not saying that like, math is inherently
racist or sexist. We're not saying that like, the prime numbers are inherently racist or logistic
regression is inherently sexist. We're talking about the ways we use math, the ways we use
algorithms can reinforce societal inequalities. You know, prime numbers are not racist, but the
way we can use prime numbers to break cryptographic systems has real world implications. The way we
use logistic regression to decide who gets a credit loan or a bank loan or not has real
world implications. And that's what we need to think about when we design these algorithms.
They're not sort of just existing in the void by themselves. They're embedded in human systems.
And on the research side of this algorithmic fairness. So now this field called fairness,
accountability, transparency, FATSTAR ML. And this is like this interdisciplinary research area
about how can we get machine learning and technical systems to care about ideas like fairness and
justice and equality. And it's really exploded over the last few years. You're seeing a dedicated
conference to it, ACM FATSTAR, which was held in Atlanta. We have seen lots of open source
libraries about this. And even at this conference, we actually have another talk about model fairness
later today. And I do for anyone who's also interested in attending that I have looked at
that other talk. I do believe there's enough differentiation between our two talks that you
would get something about worthwhile by attending both talks for anyone who has a slight concern.
And it's not just researchers that are talking about this. We talk about this in popular media,
too. So Weapons of Mass Destruction by Cathy O'Neill, Automating Equality by Virginia Eubanks,
and Algorithms of Repression by Safia Noble. And so, you know, the big three. And I think
they take this interesting approach of like, okay, here's how the algorithms work on the people.
Like we as a data scientist, we as a machine learning researchers are sort of separated from
the downstream effects of how our work impacts the general humanity, a general society. And the thing
is like, as data scientists and like computer scientists, we're sort of trained in like math
and statistics. We're not trained to think about ethics. We're not trained to think about
our public policy. But we do need to understand that like our work has downstream implications.
I think deep down, like we may not be comfortable like taking the role of an ethicist or taking the
role of a public policy. But I think deep down, none of us want to cause the apocalypse. None of
us want to do harm to others. Like no one wants to be the people written about in these books.
And I think the way that they talk this problem of like talking about the dangers of these algorithms
like how these hurt people is an interesting perspective from just research, which is okay,
here's the cool things we could do. Whereas these popular media talk about like, how could this hurt
people? And talk about how could this hurt people? Well, you have to think about like, okay, maybe
you don't really care about the moral side of like, I don't want to hurt people. But I can maybe
encourage you to think about these types of problems by legal regulations of you maybe don't
care about hurting people, but you do care about keeping your job. Because if you break some of
these things, well, you're violating legal laws. And then you can lose your job because your company
will be fined millions of dollars. And so in the US, for example, we have disparate impact laws,
which prevents again, which basically regulate how you can give out loans, how you can hire for
people such that you don't harm them. And also in the EU, we now have GDPR, which is an overarching
holistic set of laws and rules of like, how we should think about the way we use algorithms to
process people's data. And we have to think about, okay, can you explain why your algorithm made a
decision? Can you explain why your neural network didn't give someone a loan? And can they opt out
of that as well? And so let's talk about the different types of algorithmic biases. And so
this is based off some work by researchers at Microsoft and research in Cornell. And this was
presented at the conference that is now NeurIPS. Someone told me it's pronounced like Europe, and
I'm not actually sure if that was a joke or not. But really, these researchers sort of identified
three big categories of way we think about like algorithmic biases of like, where we are now,
where we're heading, and where we need to be. So first, let's talk about where we are now.
So a lot of problems in algorithmic biases focus on this problem of allocation. Who gets a loan or
not? Who gets a job? And these are really just like binary classification problems of like,
do men get software engineering jobs more than women? Do whites get credit loans more than non-whites
kind of thing? This is a binary yes or no. And this is really what most of the research has been
on now, because it's sort of easy to formalize as a mathematics problem and easy to solve. And so
this was in the news, big story last year, was that Amazon had to scrape their AI recruiting tool
because they found out that it was discriminating against women. It was basically looking at things
of like, oh, hey, if you have a name like Jared, or you were on the lacrosse team back in college,
you're probably more likely to be hired as a software engineer, which really makes no sense.
And so they scraped this because they realized, oh, hey, we were harming or choosing our model
was selecting against women, but we use this. Next, let's talk about where we're sort of heading.
And so next is this idea of bias representation. And so this is focused on looking at like how
harmful stereotypes or harmful labels are propagated through machine learning systems.
And these are often related to like language problems or computer vision problems, which are
like the neural network problems of it just picks out a solution and do some black box neural
network magic. But we don't really care about why the inner mechanics of what it's doing.
And these are sort of hard to quantify the errors compared to those previous bias and allocation
problem, which is why there's less research on this now, but like we started to think about it
more. And so this is a famous example that when Google photos was deployed like 2015,
that it actually labeled a group of black kids at a graduation party as gorillas. And so for those
of you who are not familiar with like history of US, I don't know if it applies to other Western
countries, but gorillas or apes has been historically used as a derogatory slur against
African Americans in this nation. So this label, like one is wrong, but two, it also invokes
harmful stereotypes against African Americans. And the thing is, it's like, it's harder to quantify
as an error because yeah, this is the wrong label. But at the same time, Google photos is never going
to label a group of white kids as gorillas. This is specifically a label it gives to these kids here.
And it promotes this harmful stereotype. And other examples that are sort of hard to quantify
are Snapchat filters, for example. So when you apply Snapchat filter,
Flower Crown, it sort of brightens the skin of the individual. Why? Because Snapchat filters have
sort of learned, okay, brighter skin is associated with prettiness. Therefore, when I apply the
filter, brighten their skin. And so if you think about that, it's like really hard to quantify
what's wrong. It's doing the optimization process it's supposed to do. But there's just something
about that solution just sits uneasy with you. And another example is Google Translate. So when
you translate sentences from like Malay, which is a language that doesn't have gendered pronouns,
so you can have like, they are a doctor, they are a soldier, they are a professor, they are prostitute,
they are a nurse. But when you translate to English, it sort of automatically genders them.
He is a doctor, he's a soldier, he's a professor, she is a prostitute, she is a maid, she's a nurse.
And at the same time, Google Translate is doing this mathematical optimization. It's like
hard to say why this is wrong. This is a valid translation of those sentences,
but there's just something about it that just sits uneasy with you. But to give credit to
where it's due, Google has actually made a sort of hot fix where when you translate from a
non-gendered language to a gendered language, it will actually show both gendered ways. So translating
from they are a doctor translates to she is a doctor, he is a doctor now. So this is like a quick
fix for this. It's still not available on the iOS and Android version of Google Translate.
And you still see some of these biases when you do Google Autocomplete. So if you type in a search
of he is a blah, you'll probably get doctor or soldier more than if you do she is a blah
in Google Autocomplete. Finally, where do we need to be? And so this last version is called the
weaponization of machine learning. And so the key idea of this is that as data scientists,
we're taught to train models, we produce some metrics, but we don't really think about how
our work can harm people or how it could be misused. And so there's this big story back in
2017, a group of Stanford researchers tried to create a classification algorithm that tries to
predict people's sexuality or sexual preferences based on images of their faces. And so they
effectively created a GADAR of trying to predict if someone is heterosexual or homosexual. And the
thing about this is there are countries in this world where homosexuality is criminalized by the
state. If you are out as a homosexual, you will be executed by the state. And there are plenty
more where it's not criminalized, but it's really dangerous to be out as a homosexual. So if someone
takes this model, they could use it as a weapon against homosexuals in those countries. And think
about this, there's no mathematical measure, no unit test you can write that can tell you this is
a bad idea. You shouldn't do this. This is really going to require you to have cultural anthropologists
and historians in the room to tell you, like, hey, this could harm people. And that's why I'm
really glad that there is sort of this starting discussion of having data scientists and machine
learning technologists really think about ethics training. Like when you do degree programs at
like UC Berkeley or Carnegie Mellon, they're starting to include an ethics component. Well,
I don't think that will really fully solve this. I do think it's the start of developing a different
tech culture that really cares about the downstream effects of our work on people who are not like us.
Let's talk about the different types of fairness measures. So these are like the mathematical
definitions, and I'll really talk about like what they are and some of their big weaknesses of them.
And so this is based off of work by two Stanford researchers, Sam Corbett Davies and Sherrod Goll.
And they're based on this paper, Measures and Mismeasures of Fairness, which this talk is,
the title of this talk is based on. And so let's talk about different definitions of
algorithmic fairness. So there was a talk a year ago by this Princeton professor,
Irvind Narayan, where he really showed that, okay, there were 21 definitions of algorithmic
fairness at the time of the talk when he gave that talk. Now there's more than 30 definitions
of like algorithmic fairness now. And think about this, like as computer scientists and
met like statisticians, we think, okay, there's 30 definitions. There's got to be like some that
are better than others. It's got to be like this one true definition of fairness we can use. And
that's not really true. Why? Because fairness is a social and cultural concept. Like what was
considered fair 50 years ago is not going to be considered what we consider fair now. And what
we consider fair 50 years from now is different from what we consider fair today. But these 30
so definitions of algorithmic fairness can be broken down into three big groups,
additive classification, class of question parity, and finally calibration. And I'll just give a
quick warning. This is where the talk gets a bit more technical and mathematical.
So first up, there's these anti classification measures. And so what these are is that, okay,
you have these protective features, such as like race, gender, religion, place of origin,
and you have unprotected features for your model. And the way that these anti classification
measures work ideally is that, okay, when you make an algorithmic decision, it should effectively
ignore those demographic features. It should ignore race. It should ignore gender. It should
ignore religion when it makes a decision or behave in a way it does so. And so this idea of
individual fairness, you judge a person by the content of their character rather than the color
of skin kind of thing. That two people should be treated equally if they have the same unprotected
features. But the thing about this is that you can't just throw out race and gender from your
model or from your data set and say, okay, I'm done. Because we're now starting to realize that
there are proxy features that we can worry about. Features that are not directly encode race or
gender, but are highly correlated with them. And so for example, there's a story back in 2012 when
the office supply company Staples, they did a promotion that if you live within 20 miles
of a competing store, we will give you a special coupon discount so that you'll come to our store
instead. The thing is, the people who live in those neighborhoods at 20 miles from the competitors,
those are sort of like wealthier suburban neighborhoods. And the people who live in
wealthy suburban neighborhoods have certain racial demographics, for example. So when your
model discriminates or makes a decision based on location, it's inadvertently acting as if it was
making decisions based on race. And so Staples was used fine with that for disparate impact.
And as a result, these types of features are very useful for designing
fairness-aware models. So what is a fairness-aware model? So it's sort of like a traditional machine
learning supervised model, except now we have this added component. We need to think about those
protected features. So when you have these standard machine learning, you have your features X and
your labels Y. And you basically want to map the features X to the labels Y. Well, now with
fairness-aware algorithms, you have X, you have Y, and you have your protected attributes. So race,
gender, religion, place of origin, as a protected class Z. And what you want to do is you want to
learn features that learn your label. So you want to learn who to give a loan to. But you don't want
to accidentally learn race or gender. And so one really cool algorithm that does this is fairness-
aware GANs. So I think this is a really clever idea. So how this works with GANs is that you
sort of have these two sub-models. One is sort of your standard machine learning classifier. It's
trying to take the features and learn the labels. The other one is trying to take the labels and
learn a protected class. And so the way you can think about it is sort of like this dual, like I'm
trying to learn a good classifier. You're trying to break me by saying, oh, that classifier accidentally
learns race or gender. And so this is how that really works. You have to look at this loss
function. So the one in the red box is sort of saying, am I a good classifier or not? Am I
learning features that predict who gets the loan or not? The one in the blue box is saying, okay,
you learn who to give a credit loan to. Are you accidentally learning race or gender?
Is your basically- who gets the loan or not? Basically just figuring out is this person white
or non-white. And sort of this trade-off, if you really squint your eyes at this, if you've studied
machine learning and regularization, so like ridge regression or lasso regression, you squint
your eyes at this and stare at it deeply. It kind of looks like a regularization of I want to be a
good classifier, but I don't want to be overly complex. And in this case, complex is sort of
like I don't want to accidentally be discriminatory. And this is sometimes referred to as this accuracy
fairness trade-off. And I'll be really honest, I don't like that this is referred to as a trade-off.
Because if you really think about like, why are we doing all this stuff in the first place? Because
our training set is biased, because our testing set is biased, and that means our testing labels
are biased. Like our answer key is wrong. We don't want models that perfectly learn the testing set
labels, because it is also learning those biases as well. So we expect the accuracy to go down.
And I also really don't like calling this a trade-off, because it sort of ties into this like very
harmful idea that somehow promoting diversity requires you to partake in sub-optimality. And so
you see this in like tech hiring, where okay, if a software company says like, oh, hey, 50% of our
software engineers are women, that's a good thing. But then there's always like some loser on Twitter
is like, hey, I got a brilliant idea. Instead of hiring people based on their gender, why don't we
hire the most talented person for their job? And this is sort of like causing a harmful idea. Like
in order to get diversity, you have to pick less optimal candidates or less skilled candidates.
And that's not true at all. Like diversity is very good for tech. Having people with different
lived experiences and different ways of thinking in the room is important, because they can call
you out when you're being stupid. And that's very important in data science. And so what are the
dangers of using these anti-classification measures? Like, okay, this sounds like a good idea. Like we
should judge people based on their important characteristics and not accidentally learn those
protected features. Well, by removing those protected features, we're sort of ignoring the
underlying process that acts on different demographic groups. Like these metrics sort of
look on making the outcome equal. But really, fairness is making the process equal. And so one
way this is a danger is sort of prison recidivism. So who gets, when you're a prisoner and you're
defending, like do you get released on bail or not? And so how prison recidivism works is like
there's this algorithm, Compass, it gives you a score between one and 10, which is sort of like,
how risky is it to let you out? Like what's the likelihood you will commit a crime if we release
you? And the thing is that male defendants are more likely, for the same score, male defendants
are more likely to re-offend than female defendants. So if you ignore gender in this case
and sort of average the two lines, you sort of get that average line that's higher than the female
defendant rate. And so if you cut your threshold up off like a little below 60%, whereas for,
if you just looked at gender exclusively, you would say, okay, we don't release female defendants
when they have a score of eight or above. Whereas if you take the average and you now have that
threshold, we don't release anyone if it's like seven or above. And thus you're now detaining more
women who then you originally done if you had looked at gender separately as a feature in this.
So next is classification parity. So classification parity is sort of extension of like
traditional machine learning. When machine learning, you evaluate your model according
some metric like accuracy or precision or recall or AUC. Whereas now you take those metrics and
sort of do it across different demographic groups. For example, this is a famous example,
gender studies by an MIT student Joy Bululani. And what she shows is that like these commercial
face detection algorithms, Microsoft, IBM, and then Face++, they're really good at detecting
white male faces. They're really pretty good at detecting white female faces, detecting black
male faces, but the intersection of race and gender, they're really bad at detecting black
women faces. And so this is still okay across these different demographic groups, the accuracy
is significantly lower for black women. And Joy also has a very cool video on YouTube that's like
a spoken word poem about talking about, okay, how commercial computer vision systems constantly
misgender famous black women such as Michelle Obama or Oprah. And these types of metrics or
these types of classification parity metrics are what's commonly used to enforce those legal
regulations. So it's like the Equal Employment Opportunity Act or things of that nature,
are sort of using these types of classification metrics behind the scenes.
So what's the most common one? So most common one of these types of metrics is demographic
parity. So demographic parity is like, how often do we get positive outcomes by different
demographic groups or different protected groups? And this is what's really used to audit models for
disparate impacts. So like who gets a loan or not, you look at different demographic groups and say,
okay, the positive rate, like, okay, the percentage of loans given to white men versus the percentage
of loans given to non-whites, non-males should be at most 20% difference. That's what that 80% rule
means. They have to be within 80% of each other. And the thing about this is like, that sounds
nice. Okay, if we're a bank, you have to sort of balance out the number of loans you give to
different populations. The thing is about you can satisfy that immediate thing, but you could not
really think about the long-term consequences of your actions. And so this is a paper by researchers
out of UC Berkeley, Delayed Impact of Fair Machine Learning, where they show that, okay, if you do
this demographic balance for demographic parity, so you give the same percentage of loans to people
in the orange population and people in the blue population, you're giving a lot more loans to
people in the blue population who would then default on that loan. And as a result, their credit
score goes down and the overall credit score distribution for the blue population goes down
as well. So if you just think about satisfying that immediate constraint of like, we just have
to make the outcomes equal, positive outcomes equal, then you could harm them in the long run.
And so another way to also think about this is that when it comes to tech hiring, of like, okay,
we just need to hire, make sure the percentage of women we hire is equal to the number of
percentage of men we hire for technical positions. Well, if those women leave in like five, six months
because of a toxic workplace environment, do you really deserve your gold star for meeting that
hiring quota? I don't think so. Next is parity of false positive rates. So this is really like,
as the name suggests, we're looking instead of like the positive outcomes, we're looking at the
false positives. So really false positives, like the model says yes, but the actuality is no. And
this is sometimes called equal opportunity. And think about, like, if you think about what false
positive rate is, it's false positive over false positive plus true negative. So if you want to
drop that false positive rate now, ideally you're focusing on dropping the number of false positives.
But if you think about it, I could just drop the false positive rate down by increasing the number
of true negatives in the system. And so let's say you're a police chief and someone comes to you and
says, oh, hey, you're overly detaining too many black men, that the number of black men who you've
arrested and not denying bail to or denying parole to, who would otherwise not go on to reoffend,
is too high. So what can you do about this? How can you drop that false positive rate down?
Ideally, you're sort of dropping the false positive. You're sort of granting more bail to black men who
would otherwise not go on to reoffend. But you could also just increase the number of true negatives.
So what's the true negative? So a true negative is a person who is arrested, they are released,
and they don't go on to commit a crime. So who are those? Those are people who commit misdemeanors.
So how can you increase the number of true negatives in the system? You arrest more people
for misdemeanors and then let them go. Boom, that false positive rate goes down. You've achieved
equality. Isn't that great? You just have to arrest more black men for misdemeanors.
That's terrible. And if you don't think about it, you just optimize that metric and not think about
the societal factors that generate these numbers, you end up harming that vulnerable
population we want to help. And finally, last one is calibration. So calibration is a really hard
thing to explain in layman's terms. It comes to statistical calibration. And really the way you
think about this is for any event, like who wins a state in a political election, there's some true
outcome. We know someone who wins, someone who doesn't lose, and we're trying to figure out how
well are we actually predicting that outcome with our model. And so the way this is used in, let's
say, recidivism, for example, where people are given scores, come to scores from one to 10,
or child protective services where a child is given a score of one to 20, representing how much
danger the child is in. So one being the child is not really in danger in this household, or 20
being like, that child is in serious danger, get him out of the household now. And so how this works
is, okay, CPS goes in, they evaluate the household, and they give the child a score between one to 20.
And if that score is high enough, then above some threshold T, or just say 15, for example,
then you take the child out of the household because the child is in danger if they stay there.
And the thing about statistical calibration is that, really, if two people get the same score,
that should be all that matters. If you have a white child who gets a score of 15 and a black
child who gets a score of 15, they should be considered to be in the same danger level. They
should both have a 70% chance of being harmed, or 75% chance of being harmed if they stay in that
household. It shouldn't matter on racial demographics, for example. It should just
matter on, okay, we evaluate the score, and that score is the final thing. We take that score and
make decisions solely based on that score. And if it's models well calibrated, if 15 is the cutoff
for both, and we get the same percentage of children being removed from white households
versus black households. And I guess the key idea is that the scores should mean the same thing for
the same people. And so I guess, before, from my previous slides, when I talk about these metrics,
there's usually a little bullet point at the bottom that says, danger, here's why this is bad.
But I don't have this here. Why? Because I have a whole dedicated slide dedicated to what's the
problem with calibration. And so anytime you give a talk on algorithmic fairness, you have to bring
up this compass example. So here's the obligatory compass example. And I think this is an important
case study. Because, so what is the issue with compass? So this is that prison recidivism
algorithm. So in 2016, the publication ProPublica says that, oh, hey, when you use compass
in order to decide who gets bail or not, you're accidentally defending, you're detaining black
defendants at a higher rate. You're detaining black defendants who, if they were released,
they would go on to not reoffend again. And so ProPublica North Point, which is the group that
makes this compass algorithm, their argument was that, no, our risk scores are well calibrated.
If you get a score of eight or above, we detain you. So score models are well calibrated, but the
issue is that the underlying distribution of the scores are not. So if we give scores of eight or
above a lot to black men, and we really give it to white males, for example, then okay, the chance
of detaining a white male because scores of eight or above are rare for them is low, but the chance
of detaining a black male who has a score of eight or above is high because they're more likely to
have those higher scores, then well, your model is not kind of racist. And the thing about this is,
I think it also shows another aspect of using these metrics is that you can do really well
according to one of these metrics, like statistical calibration, but do horribly compared to another
metric such as positive rates. And so just trying to aimlessly optimize for these metrics will result
in solutions that really don't actually generate well to the real world. So what can we do?
And so I'm going to propose sort of a low quantitative, low tech solution, which is really,
let's write better documentation. And that might seem silly, but I think part of the issues we have
now with AI ethics is that Silicon Valley is sort of insular. Silicon Valley believes it's filled
with tech geniuses who believe they have achieved the 13th level of cognition by drinking their salt
juice and going in their cryobaths, and they don't need plebeian mortals to tell them how to do their
job. They will take care of them by themselves. They don't need government regulations. They don't
need outsiders to do their job. And that's not true at all. I think better documentation allows
for better communication of how these data sets are built, how these models work. And so even if
you're not trained as a cultural anthropologist or an ethicist, if you can better communicate the
outcomes of your work, better communicate how this is trained, how this is tested,
to those people, they can do the evaluation of, okay, will this harm people in the long run? Will
this accidentally harm these groups of people that you're not thinking about?
And so here's this really cool idea of data seats for data sets. This is done by Timnit Gebru.
T-I-M-N-I-T for the stenographer. And she basically proposes, like, well, other industries,
like automobile industry or clinical testing, they sort of have standardizations of how they
evaluate their models. And we should adopt something similar for data science data sets.
And so if you think of the two, like automobile testing, for example, like, okay, historically,
those automobile testers were tested on, like, dummy, crash test dummies with pro-typically adult
male features. And as a result, in the real world, when actual car automobile collisions happen,
women and children were extremely harmed or more likely to be severely injured in those.
And so now we have legal regulations saying, okay, we need to make sure you also test on
pro-typically adult female dummies and child dummies. And this documentation, I think,
will answer a lot of questions, like, how is the data collected? Like, is this data collected in
a way that doesn't exclude individuals? And I think this is very important because I do think
a lot of the ways we think about machine learning is sort of focused on the model,
not so much on the training set. We don't think about, like, what makes a good training set a
good training set? And you may think, okay, what makes a good training set? Like, no missing data,
no outliers. And that really answers the question of, like, can I do statistical analysis on this
or not? It doesn't answer, like, did I exclude groups of individuals that I should care about?
Did I exclude trans communities? Did I exclude non-heterosexual individuals from my data set?
But just by the way I collected the data, I do think this shifts the conversation from, like,
the model to, like, how do we actually collect good data that we've really not thought about
before? Because we just sort of assume, okay, the data set lives in the aether. I got it from
Kaggle or I got it from some other website. But we don't really think about, like, is that data
set actually suitable for my prom or is it just conveniently available? And next, something similar
from models. And so this is done out of Google research by Meg Mitchell's group, the Google AI
Fairness group. And so what they propose is sort of, like, something similar. So standardized
documentation for machine learning models. You document, okay, how was this when you produce a
model and train it before you deploy it. Let's talk about how is it meant to be used? Like,
what are the intended use cases of this? How was it evaluated? And not just, like, okay,
is it looking at accuracy, calibration, or, like, precision? But also, how is it evaluated against
different demographic groups? How is it evaluated against the intersection of those demographic
groups? Let's bring in intersectional analysis into how we do data science and machine learning.
And I think also the key thing is, like, what are those ethical concerns? So if you do design a
sexuality classifier, what are the ethical concerns with that? Like, how could this be used to harm
people or be weaponized against people in countries where homosexuality is illegal?
And the key thing about this is, like, more transparent model reporting will also better
communicate, like, how people should use our models. Because right now we sort of just, like,
okay, I want to do computer vision. Let's grab, like, YoloNet or AlexNet and just, like, apply to
all our problems, even though, like, those models are not really designed for your specific problem.
And finally, there's also this tool, D.ON, which is an ethical checklist for data science projects.
So this is D.ON. It's produced by an organization called Driven Data. They do, like, consulting with,
like, non-profits, government organizations, and they also run data science for good competitions.
So think, like, Kaggle competitions, but with the definite emphasis on helping, like,
some social good aspect of, like, helping teachers, helping education, helping
drug treatment, for example. And what this tool does, it creates a markdown file in your repo
with a checklist that checks for different things. So, like, how is the data collected?
Was it collected in a fair way? Did it actually cover all the groups of people you need to cover?
Did you exclude a group of people? And also, were people informed of how their data set was
collected? Like, informed consent is important in the social sciences. Like, you can't get
research approval unless you have informed consent for your participants. But on the other hand,
in data science, we're just able to run A-B tests on our users without telling them what we're doing
so. And you can run some pretty horrible A-B tests on people that, like, why the hell did you do this
without having to inform them? And then also think about data storage. And I think this is important
because we now sort of have this idea of, like, right to be forgotten so that if someone doesn't
want their data to be used in an algorithm, they should be able to say, I don't want my data to be
used here. Delete it from your records. And you should be able to do that easily. You should be
able to comply with that. That's part of GDPR. And then also, when you deploy the model, how do you
think about taking it down? If it does come out that, okay, there's a new story that says, oh,
your model's harming these groups of people, how do you take your model out of production?
I think it's important to think about this beforehand. And I do want to know that, like,
these things, like the model cards, the data sheets, and this checklist, they're not foolproof.
It's not a foolproof way to prevent you from harming groups of people that you don't want to
harm. But I do think it's a sort of good first step. It sort of helps us be a little less stupid
when we do data science. And finally, I want to give a special shout out to the AI Now Institute.
So this is an NYU research institute that looks at the cultural and societal impact of AI. And so
they hold this annual symposium on ethics, organizing, and accountability. And they also
recently produced this paper talking about the diversity crisis in AI. So a lot of the things,
all the issues with AI now, sort of like, we don't really have diversity. We don't have
different voices or different opinions in the room. And this makes a lot of ad hoc solutions to, like,
algorithmic fairness, like, kind of moot. Okay, if you talk about, okay, instead of just having an
algorithm, an automated algorithm, you just have a human in a loop to check decision. Well, if most
of your humans in a loop are, like, straight white men, they don't really understand the lived
experience of non-straight white men. And they won't be able to check for decisions that your
algorithm makes that they don't realize that this is an issue for other people who are different
from them. And so I think it's important because it also talks about, like, some of the more
technical, long-term technical consequences of not having diversity in AI and machine
learning and data science. And so let's really end the talk. Here are all the papers I referenced
throughout the talk if you want to check them out afterwards. And, yeah, I hope this talk was
engaging. I hope you all learned something. And if you have the time, I hope you check out the
other talk on measuring model fairness.