Hello again, everyone.
This talk is Measuring Model Fairness with Henry Hinefeld.
Please give him a warm welcome.
Well, thank you.
Hi, everyone.
My name is Henry Hinefeld.
I'm a data scientist at Civis Analytics.
And today I'm going to talk to you about measuring model
fairness.
Before we jump right into it, I'll
start with an outline of where we're headed.
I'm going to start by motivating the problem a little bit.
And the problem I'm talking about here
is specifically measuring model fairness, not
model fairness writ large.
There was a really great talk earlier today about that.
So I encourage you to go find the video for that later
if you're interested.
But today I'm specifically talking about the problem
of measuring the fairness of a model's predictions.
This is actually a pretty tricky problem.
So next I'll talk through some of the subtleties that
make this hard, and then talk through a case study using
some real world data that shows how these subtleties show up
in practice.
Finally, I'll talk about some Python tools,
some open source tools you can use
to address these problems in your own work,
and end with some concluding remarks.
So at this point, I think it's pretty commonly accepted
that machine learning models can have a big impact
on people's lives.
Things like credit scoring models
can determine whether or not you can buy a home.
Advertising models can affect what kind of job
offers you're exposed to, what kind of credit products you see.
And models can even affect how long you spend in jail.
Now as machine learning models have made their way
into these really socially impactful domains,
a consensus has emerged that it's really important
that we make sure the predictions of these models
are fair.
Unfortunately, that's kind of where the consensus ends,
because there are many different ways to define fairness,
and many different ways to measure the fairness of model
predictions.
And this last example is actually a really illustrative case
for that.
So a quick show of hands, how many of you
all have heard of the Compass Recidivism Model Controversy?
That's a pretty good response.
For those of you who are not familiar,
there is a model called Compass, which
is used to predict recidivism.
So to predict the likelihood that a person convicted
of a crime will go on to re-offend
when they're released, so go on to be convicted
of future crimes.
This model is used pretty widely across the country
in making parole decisions.
And so a little while ago, this organization
called ProPublica, which is an independent investigative
journalism outfit, found out about this
and went out and collected some data, first about the scores
that this model was generating, and second,
about the actual outcome, so about whether people actually
did go on to recidivate.
And what they found when they analyzed this data
was that the model's error rates were different for people
of different races.
So the chart I have here is comparing
the false positive rates and the false negative rates
for white and black defendants.
So the false positive rate is the fraction of people
that the model labeled as high risk,
but who actually did not go on to re-offend.
Similarly, the false negative rate
are the people that the model said
had a low risk of re-offending, but did go on to re-offend.
And if you look at these error rates for the COMPAS models,
well, the false positive rate, the people falsely labeled
as high risk, that error rate is about 24%
for white defendants and about 45% for black defendants.
And on the other hand, the false negative rate,
the people that the model falsely said
were at a low risk of re-offending,
that error rate is about 48% for white defendants
and about 28% for black defendants.
So ProPublica went out, collected this data,
did this analysis, and on the basis of this analysis,
wrote a report saying this model used in parole decisions
is biased against black defendants.
Seems pretty cut and dried so far, right?
Well, the second half of the story
is that the company which makes this model, which
makes this product, the company Northpoint,
put out a rebuttal where they showed
that the overall accuracy, so the overall error rate,
or I'm sorry, the overall accuracy of this model
is very similar for white defendants and black defendants.
So the overall accuracy is about 63% for both groups.
So this leaves us with a question.
Is this model fair?
Who's right?
Which is the appropriate way to measure
the fairness of this model, of this model's predictions?
Intuitively, you might think, well, let's just
satisfy both conditions.
Let's make sure that the error rates are balanced,
and let's make sure that the overall accuracy is also
balanced.
Unfortunately, that's not possible.
As this controversy was coming out,
some academics took a look at the problem
and proved mathematically that, except in very contrived cases,
where, for example, your model is 100% correct,
it just gives you the right answer every single time,
except in contrived cases like that,
it's mathematically impossible to satisfy
both of these definitions of fairness at the same time.
So we're left with this question of,
how do you decide what is an appropriate way to define
fairness for your machine learning modeling problem?
How do you define this, and how do you measure it?
This is a really tricky problem with a lot of subtleties.
So next, I'm going to talk through three
of these subtleties and how they impact this problem.
The first subtlety is that different groups
can have different ground truth positive rates.
So to illustrate this with an example,
say you were trying to make a model that predicted diagnoses
of breast cancer.
Well, men and women are diagnosed with breast cancer
at very different rates.
For women, it's approximately one in eight,
so something like 12% over the course of a lifetime.
And for men, it's something like one in a thousand,
so 0.1%.
So there is a very different incidence rate,
a very different true positive rate in the ground truth
between men and women for this type of problem.
Well, this makes measuring fairness tricky
because certain fairness metrics make assumptions
about the balance of ground truth between groups.
One of these metrics, which is a very popular one,
is called disparate impact.
And in words, what disparate impact is measuring
is the ratio of the probability of a positive classification
between two different groups.
So that's this equation down here,
the probability that you get a yes
or a positive classification for different groups.
And because this is a ratio,
you want it to be very close to one
according to this definition of fairness.
But if we think back to our breast cancer modeling problem,
you can see how this definition of failure
just falls on its face
because the ground truth positive rate
is very different between our two groups.
And so that conflicts with an assumption
that this fairness metric has baked in.
So subtlety number one,
there can be legitimate differences
in the ground truth positive rate
between different groups that you're looking at.
Subtlety number two
is that you don't know what ground truth is.
You only know what your data says,
and your data is a biased representation of ground truth.
There's a quote from the statistician George Box
that I like a lot, which is that all models are wrong,
some models are useful.
And I think you can kind of paraphrase that
into the data context by saying all data sets are biased,
some data sets are useful.
So you always have to remember
that your data isn't an exact representation
of the real world of ground truth.
Data can be non-representative in a couple different ways.
And one of those ways is that it can contain label bias.
So label bias is when a protected attribute
affects the way individuals are assigned labels.
People from different groups
get assigned labels differently in your data set.
As an example of this,
consider this quote from an analysis of school discipline.
In this paper, the authors found that students
from African American and Latino families
were more likely than their white peers
to receive expulsion or suspension
for similar problem behavior.
So if you were using this data set
and trying to predict student problem behavior,
but your label has been suspended,
then you're working with a data set that has label bias
because different groups
are being assigned labels differently.
This is a problem for measuring fairness
because some fairness metrics
are based on your agreement with the labels.
And if your labels are biased,
then making sure that your predictions agree
with those labels is just perpetuating the bias
that was in your data set in the first place.
A popular example of one of these metrics
is called equal opportunity.
And equal opportunity is comparing
the true positive rate between different groups.
So this is a very common example
of this in different groups.
So this is given that in the data set,
you are labeled as a one,
what is the probability that the model
classifies you as a one?
And looking at the difference in that rate
between the two different groups that you care about.
But again, here you're optimizing for agreement
with these labels.
And if the process that generated the labels themselves
is biased, then all you're doing is perpetuating the bias
that generated your data in the first place.
Another way your data can be non-representative
is that it can contain sample bias.
Sample bias is when different groups
are sampled into your data set in different ways.
So as an example of this, consider this quote
from an analysis of the NYPD stop and frisk policy.
And in this analysis, they found that people
of African and Hispanic descent were stopped
more frequently than white people
even controlling for various other factors.
So if you were trying to build a model
on top of this data set, you would be working
with something that had sample bias
because whether or not a person shows up
in your data set in the first place
is different for different groups.
The sampling process is different for different groups.
I think you see where this is going.
This is a problem for measuring fairness
because some metrics look at classification ratios
between groups.
So here I'll go back to disparate impact.
This was the first metric we talked about,
the one that's comparing the ratio
of the positive classification between groups.
Well, if you're sampling the groups differently,
then the things that you're comparing in this ratio
is not an apples to apples comparison.
If you're sampling, for example,
only high risk individuals in one group,
but then an entire population uniformly in another group,
when you do that ratio, you're not getting
an accurate assessment of how your model
is treating those different groups
because the populations aren't sampled the same way.
It's not an apples to apples comparison.
So to recap so far, subtlety number one,
there can be legitimate differences
in the ground truth positive rate between classes.
Sample number two, your data is a biased representation
of ground truth.
Subtlety number three is that the consequences
of your model matter.
I can see an argument where if your model is punitive,
so the consequences of your model is negative,
it's handing out something like more jail time,
then you might care more about false positives.
You might care more about the cases where your model
is assigning someone a punishment that they don't deserve.
On the flip side, if your model is assistive,
if your model is handing out a benefit to people who need it,
I can see an argument where you care more
about false negatives, about where your model says
a person doesn't need this benefit, but they really do,
and they aren't getting it as a consequence.
I'm not arguing that this is the only way to think about
assistive and punitive models.
I'm just saying you have to think about these questions.
This takes me to what is actually the main point
of this talk.
If you don't remember anything else from this,
this is what I want you to come away with.
You can't math your way out of having to think
about fairness.
You still need a human person to think about
the ethical implications of your model,
of the tool that you're building.
When machine learning and this kind of modeling approach
first started being applied to these different types
of domains, at the beginning, there was kind of
a common impulse to think, well, models are just math,
so they must be fair.
It's just numbers, it's just algorithms, it's math.
Of course it's fair.
At this point, I think that attitude
is pretty thoroughly debunked,
but there's a temptation to take the same kind of reasoning
and apply it just one step farther down the modeling chain.
It's not models are math, so they must be fair.
It's I'm gonna add this extra constraint to my math
and it will automatically be fair.
And that's still not automatically true.
You need a human person thinking about
what does fairness mean in my context?
What does it mean?
What are the consequences?
You need that person doing that thinking
before you can say this constraint makes my model fair.
So these are some of the ways it can be tricky.
So far this has all been kind of theoretical.
So next I'm gonna walk through a case study
that uses some real world data
from one of Civus's consulting engagements
to show how these kind of effects can show up in practice.
So the way this case study is set up
is we start with some real world data
from one of our consulting engagements.
The features we have here are mostly demographic things
and like socioeconomic status indicators.
And the outcome in the original raw data set
is the probability that a person will sign up
for the services of a state agency.
So each row in the data set is a person
and the outcome is the likelihood
they sign up for this agency.
And we're gonna investigate racial bias.
So look at fairness for white people
versus black people in this data set.
And the way we're gonna proceed
is we're going to generate hypothetical worlds
that match these different subtleties
I've been talking about.
So we'll generate a hypothetical world
where ground truth is balanced
and another hypothetical world
where ground truth isn't balanced.
To make the ground truth balanced,
we take only the white people in the original data set
and then randomly reassign race labels.
So in that hypothetical world,
ground truth is totally balanced.
We also take the original data set
where white people were much more likely
to sign up for the services of this agency
as a hypothetical world where ground truth is not balanced.
So remember this is subtlety number one,
ground truth isn't always balanced.
Subtlety number two was that your data
can be a biased representation of ground truth.
So within each of these hypothetical worlds
that we've generated,
we're gonna generate some new data sets
where we inject known types of these different biases.
So for example, we generate a data set
where we inject sampling bias
by preferentially sampling white people
and black people differently from that hypothetical world.
So we sample white people with a high score
with a high likelihood,
sample white people with a low score with a low likelihood
and then sample black people uniformly.
So by this process,
we're generating a data set that we know has sample bias.
And similarly, we can do a related kind of thing
where we take those original probabilities
and turn them into binary labels,
but we do that differently for the different groups.
So this way we introduce label bias.
So we use a threshold of 0.3 for white people
and a threshold of 0.7 for white people.
So at this point, we have two hypothetical worlds,
one where ground truth is balanced, one where it's not,
and we have a number of different data sets
where we know there's different types of bias
in the data set.
Then what we do is we train models
on those different data sets in those hypothetical worlds
and then apply the two fairness metrics
I've been talking about so far,
disparate impact, which is that ratio one,
and equal opportunity, which is that difference one.
We apply those two metrics,
two models trained on these different data sets
and see what the fairness metrics tell us.
So first, when ground truth is balanced,
this is the hypothetical world
where ground truth is totally balanced.
Things look pretty good.
So to explain this figure, I have on,
can you see my arrow?
Yeah.
On the left over here is disparate impact.
So this is the ratio one.
So that means a value close to one
indicates no measured unfairness.
Over here on the right is equal opportunity.
This is the difference one.
So a value close to zero means no measured unfairness.
And then the different bars
are different data sets that we generated.
So on the far left is one where we haven't done
either of these bias injecting processes.
Then the next one is where we injected sample bias,
where we injected label bias,
and where we injected both types of bias.
And so what you can see here
is that both of these metrics measure no unfairness
in the case where we haven't added bias to the data set.
And as we start adding these different types of bias
into the data set, the metrics report
more measured unfairness.
So, so far, so good.
The metrics are doing what we want.
The situation is a lot less rosy
in the hypothetical world where ground truth is imbalanced.
So here we're saying this is a hypothetical world
where there's a legitimate difference
between different groups.
Think back to the breast cancer example.
And now these are the same plots, the same interpretation.
So a value of one over here on the left plot
means no measured unfairness.
A value of zero over here on the right plot
Now both of these metrics
are detecting significant unfairness,
even in the case where our data
is totally representative of the real world.
We haven't injected any of these biases.
Our data is just the real world.
But these metrics are telling us
that our model is very, very unfair.
And also you'll notice the label bias,
this is when different labels are assigned
different labels differently, is very hard to detect.
And that's because in this case
where ground truth is imbalanced,
it's really hard to tease apart
where differences in labels are between
biased data generating process and just the ground truth.
So the point I want you to take away from this case study
is that it's really hard to interpret
these fairness measures in a vacuum.
If you were doing this kind of analysis,
if you were trying to measure the fairness
of your model's predictions,
you don't get all four of these bars
or all eight of these bars,
you don't get to see like,
well this is what it would look like in this case,
this is what it would look like in this case.
You just get one of these numbers
and you have to interpret that number
by thinking about the world you're trying to model
and the process that generated your data.
You have to think about is ground truth balanced
in this problem I'm trying to model?
You have to think about where did my data come from?
Is it possible that the labels are being generated
in a biased way?
Is it possible that the sampling is different
between these two groups?
You have to think about all of these questions
when you go to interpret the numbers of these
that these fairness metrics generate for you.
So that's kind of how this works in practice.
Next, I'm gonna give you a couple tools
from the Python ecosystem
that you can use to do these kind of measurements
to apply to measure the fairness of your predictions.
The first of this is called Equitas.
This is a tool out of the University of Chicago.
It's a Python library and also a web front end.
And the way it works is you provide some data.
Within that data, you select what the protected group is.
So if you're interested in looking at race or gender
or age or disability status, something like that,
then you select which fairness metric is appropriate
for your context, which metric makes sense
for the problem that you're working on.
And then the tool will go off and tell you
according to the data that you provided
and the model scores you provided
and the fairness metrics that you set are relevant,
how do those metrics evaluate on your data set?
Pros of this tool is that it's easy to use.
The con is that it comes with a non-standard license.
So it's from University of Chicago.
It has an academic license,
which isn't one of the standard MIT, GPO, whatever.
Another tool comes from IBM
and this is called the AI Fairness 360 Open Source Toolkit.
The pro here is it's very comprehensive.
It has implementations
of many, many different fairness metrics
along with lots of documentation, tutorials,
Jupyter notebooks that will walk you through the use of them.
The con is that it's probably more comprehensive
than you need.
There's a ton of stuff in here,
also implementations of some research papers.
And it also comes with lots of dependencies.
So if you're trying to bundle this
into a production environment,
it might be a heavier import than you want.
And finally, another class of tools
are things that you can use to interpret models.
I'll mention these in passing
because they're a whole nother topic
and I don't have time to go into them here.
But if you're interested in understanding
why a model is making a particular prediction,
I suggest you look into these tools LIME and SHAP.
So finally, some concluding thoughts.
There's no one size fits all solution to this problem
other than think hard about your inputs and your outputs.
Think hard about the world you're trying to model,
about the problem you're trying to model.
Think hard about the process
that's generating the data that you're using.
And then think hard about the consequences
of your model downstream.
Where are these scores going?
What kind of decisions are being made
based on the output of this tool that you're building?
These metrics can help and others,
but you have to use them carefully.
Second, use a diverse team to create these models
and do this thinking.
Throughout the course of this talk,
I've tried to emphasize how important it is
to have a human person doing this kind of thinking.
But if all the people doing that thinking
come from the same background, the same social context,
the same lived experiences,
then you're gonna have blind spots.
So when you're doing this kind of thinking,
this kind of ethical inspection of your models,
do that with a diverse team
so you have different perspectives on the question.
And finally, just know your data
and think about your consequences.
I'll leave you with this quote from Cathy O'Neill's book,
Weapons of Mass Destruction,
about how it's the job of all of us
who build these kind of models and build these kind of tools
to do this ethical introspection.
Your data is not the truth,
and even if it were the truth,
is it the kind of truth that you wanna see in the world?
That's a deeply human question,
and you really need people thinking about it.
Thank you.
We have about five minutes left.
Sure.
I'm happy to take questions if people wanna step up,
and I'll also be up in the front
if we get cut off for time.
I have a question.
So, you seem like a very civic-minded person,
and I was just wondering,
how do you deal with pushback?
So first of all, have you ever experienced pushback
in your workplace when you kind of say that,
all right, we need to think about this fairness,
and then you get kind of the reaction,
yeah, well, you know, math is fair, it's objective.
This isn't really the place for politics.
And secondly, so first of all, have you encountered that?
And secondly, how do you respond to that?
To your first point, I'm fortunate to work at a place
where I think these kind of ideas have a lot of currency,
so I don't get a lot of institutional pushback
on just raising the issue in the first place.
As to how I would address it,
I think there are a couple different tacks you can take.
One, you can try and take an education-type tack,
where if someone does come in with the perspective,
the models are just math, of course they're fair,
then you can try to kind of present
some of this kind of reasoning to say,
well, that's actually not quite accurate,
and try to educate whatever stakeholder is pushing back.
If it's a case where people understand the problem,
but don't want to make the profit sacrifice,
that's just a much harder kind of interpersonal
corporate dynamics kind of problem,
and the best I can tell you
is that you just have to advocate for it.
Thank you, that was a really fucking awesome talk, thank you.
Thank you.
On the right side.
Given the issues with ground truths,
ground truth rates being different,
depending on what sort of labels you're looking at,
is it possible to normalize them
while possibly controlling for any sort of sampling bias?
There are definitely approaches
you can take in that direction.
So there's actually a pretty substantial body
of academic literature around how you can do
this kind of rebalancing data sets,
or reweighting data sets
to try to remove some of these issues.
I think there's promising work in that direction,
but with the caveat that you really have to do this
thinking ahead of time, you can't throw your data set
into an algorithm that translates it in such a way
that now everything is independent of gender or something,
without thinking ahead of time
about the problem you're trying to model
and whether that kind of approach makes sense.
So short answer, yes, there are mathematical approaches
in that direction, but you have to use them carefully.
Thank you.
Does that answer your question?
Yeah. Okay, thanks.
How does Compass compare to just human judgment?
I mean, I presume Compass is replacing human judgment
in these matters.
I think Compass is one element that judges use
in making their decisions.
I don't know offhand of comparison I can give you
of the decisions judges make with
and without the Compass input.
That's a good question,
but I don't have a good answer for you.
So you mentioned a couple of times that you need a human
to consider this equation and consider possible biases
and how to manipulate or how to work with your data
in light of that.
I'm curious if you, like, there isn't a formula for that.
I'm curious if there are resources you know of
that provide something in the direction of a formula
or at least a starting place for issues
that people should consider when approaching these problems.
So I'm not familiar with this tool myself,
but the earlier Fairness Talk today
mentioned this Dion Checklist,
which was presented as like a checklist
for ethical questions when you're building a model.
I'm a little hesitant to recommend it
having not read it myself,
but that sounds like something in the direction
of what you're asking about.
Is that fair?
Yeah. Okay.
I think we're about at the end of time,
but I'm happy to stand up front and keep taking questions.
So thank you for your attention.
Thank you.