I've got this. Thank you. So thank you everybody for being here today. The Python Education
Summit is one of my favorite events of the year because it's the only place all year
I get to be around a whole bunch of people who are just as passionate as me about education
and Python. And that's a really special sort of nerd, I have to say. So thank you for making
it what it is by being here. So today we are going to be having a conversation together
and working together on open education resources for Python. So I wanted to really dig into
those resources work. What do we need? How can we do this differently? How can we build
on what we're doing? And because this is a Python conference, I have put all of this
into a form, the Zen of Python open education resources. So let me grab this. It works.
All right. So if it's your thing, please tweet along. Part of the theme today is bringing
together people in the technology sector and education sector. So I've put up hashtags
that are popular in tech and in education. There we go. So I want to start out by telling
you about the best Python open education resource I've ever created. I used to work for a start-up
where I was writing middle school Python curriculum. We had a visual interface that was in the
browser. Students could code in Python and very much like Scratch, they would see an
animation in the browser that they could program. So we really struggled between how do you
show guide instruction and support students versus helping them build open and problem-solving
skills. And we struggled with that balance. We had some great tutorials, but we kept hearing
from teachers, students aren't retaining the information. They aren't able to apply the
skills. So I had this great idea. They'll go through the tutorial. At the end of every
lesson, they'll complete an open-ended project that asks them to apply the skills that they
just learned. It will be creative. It will be great. So an example of that, they were
learning to program shapes. So we took the artwork of Alma Thomas as inspiration and
we asked them to look at her artwork and create something in that style using Python. I was
excited. This had everything. It was open-ended problem-solving. It was creative and artistic.
It went into expressionist art. It was bringing forward the work of a black woman artist.
I was so excited. It had everything. But I started going into classrooms and I realized
no one was using it. They were skipping all of my open-ended projects. When I asked why,
the teacher said, it's too hard. The kids don't know where to start. We just, we can't
do it. And I would always figure out a way that they could make it work. I would say,
well, have you tried all our supports? There's code comments that you can use as a guide.
There's a project planner that you should be using with your kids. I had all these supports
and I could always figure out how they must be able to make it work. Well, three years
later I was coaching a teacher in a classroom who happened to be using this curriculum and
they were skipping the open-ended projects. With some distance I was able to see that
I had missed an opportunity to make my resource work. Because it didn't work in the classroom,
it didn't matter that I could make it work. It mattered that the teachers could make it
work. Because they couldn't make it work, no students were using these amazing projects.
I still think they're great, but I missed the opportunity to have them actually be used.
So that brings me to one of my biggest mantras that teachers I work with will constantly
hear me say. If it doesn't work in the classroom, it doesn't work. End of story. So we have
all these great ideas and great interventions for computer science teachers, but if they
can't make it work, it sits there and it doesn't get used. So how can we make our open
education resources work instead of sitting on a metaphorical shelf? Well, before we get
into that, you might be asking, why am I talking about classrooms? Maybe when you think of
these resources you're like, well, they're used after school. They're used at home for
free learning for kids who are really interested. They're used in nonprofits. Those are all
great uses and that's very valid. I want to challenge everyone here, no matter what area
that you work in, to think about, in addition to that, starting to contribute to classroom
resources. And here's the reason. There is a movement called CS for All. This is a movement
to include all public school students in computer science education. Think of this, you might
ask why. Think of this like science. We teach every kid basic science and then when they
get to high school they have to take a certain number of credits and then if they want to,
they want to go into a STEM career, they can take more advanced courses or more specialized
courses. But we want every student to have a basic understanding of what is the scientific
method? How do I evaluate things in the real world using science? That's important to them
functioning as an adult and this is the same philosophy. That we want them to be computationally
literate. So the gold standard for this is a required class, a standard for a class,
during the regular school day. That's not happening everywhere and that's okay, but
that's where a lot of places are moving towards. So it's also widening our circle of who takes
computer science courses and who programs. This includes lots of groups who have been
underrepresented in the past in programming and that also, just to point out, includes
students with disabilities. So as we're programming, I mean as we're writing materials, we want
to think about students who are from different cultural backgrounds than us. Students who
learn in a variety of ways. There are many things to consider and then additionally I
want you to know that this isn't a singular movement. It's being adopted in different
areas, in different ways and it's slowly all growing, but different states and cities may
define this differently. So now that you have a background for that, I hope that I've inspired
you to think about the classroom as we move forward. I also want to give us a background
of open education resources versus open source software because I think that many people
in this room may have worked in open source software before, but not necessarily open
education resources, possibly vice versa. So they're similar in that both resources
are meant to be shared widely, used, remixed, repackaged and I think that's a good thing
for everyone. For both contributors are very passionate about what they do and also in
both of them there can be a problem with borrowing liberally without attribution from others,
though not always. So there are commonalities. Some of the differences are open source software
really focuses on and again this is very general, this may not be true of every project, but
to be very general on collaboration. Programs are living projects, so they're taking contributions
from others, their projects are changing. So that's one thing that's happening there.
In open ed resources often you're creating a lesson, you're creating a project, you create
it, post it, it's done. And a lot of times that's a single person working on it. It might
be a teacher who's sharing what they did, but it's not an ongoing collaboration in the
same way open source software has been. And so what I would like to do is think about
taking the principles from each of these and how can we bring them together and work
together as technologists and educators to take the best of both worlds. So to dig into
that we're going to use a case study from a program I started last year called Raspberry
Pie in a Box. This was through the K12 education initiative at Cornell Tech. They were able
to, they had a mandate for us to innovate and see, make computer science education work
in schools, and so this was part of that. So the problem we wanted to address is that
everywhere but specifically in New York City, middle school students, especially middle
school students in Title I public schools, did not have access, the same access to physical,
computing, like Raspberry Pie, Arduino, all sorts of digital making that students in private
schools and better funded schools had the opportunity to do. And so we were like, why?
Why does that happen? Well, the teachers aren't trained. It's a big time commitment for this
type of training. The cost is prohibitive because it's not just somebody can donate
Chromebooks, it's all the little pieces, all the parts. It's very complicated to manage
in the classroom, but we see that middle schoolers really need something tangible in their computer
science classes, and it also addresses some of the topics that are missing in curriculum,
such as networks and computing systems. Another thing that we notice is middle schoolers were
learning to program in the browser, and this was building up some misconceptions for them.
So they would log in just like they log into an online game, and they would make something
happen, just like they could do in some other type of game or activity, and so they weren't
really understanding how does software work with hardware? What is coding really doing?
What's it good for in the real world? I can make a cat move, but what does that mean?
So we wanted to make this tangible and help students see computing systems in action.
Our solution was a one-to-one Raspberry Pi program. What that means is we envisioned
incoming sixth graders receiving their own Raspberry Pi. These Raspberry Pis would live
at the school, but by the end of their middle school years, when they graduated eighth
grade, they would take home with them a working computer full of a portfolio of their computer
science work. In addition to that, so it also addressed students who didn't have access
to computers and portfolios for getting into high school, etc. Our goal was to keep the
cost as low as possible, low enough that a teacher could go onto DonorsChoose and raise
enough money. We wanted everything ready to go. Here's how you set up. Here's what you
buy. Here's the curriculum that you can choose from. We wanted to start to move kids out
of scratch by eighth grade, start to move them into Python, and we wanted subject area
integration so they had time during the school day to do the work. So this is our big idea.
Well, what did we learn from this idea? This is the first thing we learned. This is a slide
from the official Raspberry Pi Foundation teacher training called Pi Academy. So this
is really part of Raspberry Pi's ethos is that first attempt in learning or failure
is common and desirable. It's part of the learning process. And as experienced educators,
we thought that shouldn't be part of our process. But if you're dealing with a Raspberry
Pi, if you're dealing with people, students, and classrooms, this will be part of the experience
and that's a good thing, just like it is if you're a student using the Raspberry Pi.
So what bumps did we encounter? The first was in curriculum. I want to thank Chantal
Mason. You can tweet her. She is the one who developed all of our open source curriculum.
So she learned some things. Teachers weren't able to take what they saw on the internet.
There's all these projects for Raspberry Pi. There's endless education resources. Teachers
weren't able to take that and then make it into something that they knew what to do with
in the classroom. They were unable to do that because they needed a format that fit into
their schema for what education is. So we formatted our lessons to look similar to what
they might see if they planned a unit or a lesson plan. It's a little bit different because
it needs to be flexible for everybody, but we wanted to cue some of the things that they
would recognize so that they knew what to do with the information. Next, we did not
reinvent the wheel. We relied heavily on Raspberry Pi's open education resources and we used
that as the foundation and then we built on top of that. Finally, Chantal really dug
into the standards. A lot of us want to approach it as, oh, here's what I wish I would have
learned. Here's something really interesting. But Chantal started with what do the teachers
need to teach and can I understand where the kids are actually at? She was able to really
dig in and because of that, she created subject integrated lesson plans. For example, in science
class, they study urban farms and they make an urban farm and monitor it with a Raspberry
Pi. In English language arts, they are studying propaganda and so they read a book and they
create a series of podcasts that are presented in a Raspberry Pi radio project. This is part
of their assessment for their ELA class. That was pretty easy to overcome. Once we recognize
the problems, we could address them and we are able to come up with good curriculum solutions.
On the other hand, peripherals and networking. I would say that there are perhaps no great
choices in this area. We still have not solved this problem. This one is ongoing. The first
thing that I learned is to be really clear about your program goals and base the choices
for this on those goals. For us, we did not want to use laptops and SSHN because we wanted
kids to have the tangible hardware software experience. We want them using the Pi and
seeing the Pi. We ended up using Pytops which obscured our goal of using and seeing the
Pi. On the other hand, it solved some of the schools problems. Where are we going to put
30 more monitors in our school? There are several options. We have not found something
that works for both the school and the students yet. We are working on it. We also learned
that it is not just us. Every time we hit a bump in the road, we thought that we just
cannot use the Raspberry Pi that well. We must not know exactly what we are doing. What
we actually found out was that with certain products, there were user design issues that
were causing these problems on a wider scale. It was important for those companies that
we went to them and told them what was happening in the classroom because to go back, if it
does not work in the classroom, it does not work. This does not apply to most open education
resource projects, but I just want to touch on it because there are some programs that
are open. Scheduling and budget are big obstacles in schools. If you are creating some kind
of open education resource just because what you created is free does not mean it is free
to implement in the school. Thinking about what are the costs, a lot of times there are
cost tradeoffs. Schools can work harder to have something for free or pay less money,
but they may need more in-house expertise than they have. Again, you might have a solution
that works for you, but it is not going to work within the school day for the teachers
who are there. Just something to think about. We also found it was great for teachers, more
than one teacher to do this, to have a cohort that is in it together at the school. Lastly,
we found teacher training is important. Nobody was going to use our curriculum unless we
could figure out some type of training. Because we want this to be a program that is accessible
and ready to go, we are looking at what is the least amount of training? What is the
most accessible way for them to get the training? We cannot send every middle school teacher
in New York City to Pi Academy. How can we give them enough training to implement this
program so that their students can have the physical computing experiences? We are looking
at lots of different options. Can we get it down to a one day thing that is offered throughout
the boroughs? Can we do it online? Can we use some of Raspberry Pi's online resources?
This is an area we are also still exploring. We have also realized teachers need to do
the projects. They need to play and they need to master the materials. Many computer science
educators are new. They are new to computer science even at the high school level. They
are learning along with their students. In our trainings, we really focus on them building
confidence and building their skills. Moving forward, we did learn that students can do
this despite all the bumps and obstacles. Teachers without the official training can
do this. We have subject area middle school teachers who have never touched code before
having their kids use Raspberry Pi with Python to build these projects. They can do it and
they enjoy it. That told us that it is worth dealing with all those failures that come
up. It is worth dealing with the bumps because the kids get an experience that they would
not get with an online tutorial, which for them was the alternative. Iteration is really
key. You just have to keep trying and keep addressing problems as they come up.
I want to break this apart and abstract it out a little bit and think about some principles
that we can apply to every open source education project. The first concept is that content
matters but not at the expense of logistics. What does that mean? I am not saying forget
about the content. It does not matter. I am saying if you have the greatest content in
the world, if schools cannot figure out how to implement it, students will not get to
use it. Next, you should never assume that your user looks like you or thinks like you.
Refuse the temptation to design for your younger self. Access counts. It is so easy as an educator
for me to think about myself when I was in seventh grade. How did I learn? What would
have been fun for me? That does not work. Every educator learns pretty quickly. It is
very tempting. User-centered design, thinking about your audience and what will work for
them. Most of them are learning programming in a non-traditional environment, the traditional
way of learning Python, which is what I did. I went online by myself. I worked through
learn Python the hard way and I was off and running. That is not going to work for our
students in classrooms of 30 people each with no background. Access counts. That means two
things. That means access to the curriculum for students with disabilities, but it also
means to think about what access they have to technology. Do not assume every student
has a computer. How else can they program? It is not ideal, but there are apps for programming
Python on your phone, on a tablet, in the browser. There are all sorts of options, so
think about alternatives and do not assume that kids have access to these tools. Just
accept that you are a UX designer. I am sorry. If you have a blank white page full of information
of text filling the page, that is not going to work. A teacher is not going to know what
to do with that or how to pick it apart. If you want your projects to be used, you want
to think about design. Testing in an education environment is better than having a kid related
to you test it. If your fourth grader can do it, it does not matter. Can a fourth grade
class do it? Why do not you go try? Go see. We can talk about different ways how you can
build relationships with schools to do this testing. If there are too many Python in jokes,
it is probably a bad idea because they exclude new users. If you think it is too obvious
to explain, but explain it anyway, it is probably a good idea because it was not obvious. Your
contributors need guidance, especially in these areas. I love Python in jokes, but my
students do not. They really do not get Monty Python. I wish they did. They really do not
care once I explain it to them. When students and teachers read that, they feel like outsiders
because that is another thing other than the content they need to decode and figure out.
We want to be welcoming with the materials. Also, if you think it is obvious, if you think
you went all the way back to the very beginning, stop and go three steps before that because
they do not know. A lot of teachers, even high school computer science teachers, have
never used Git. You have a project up on Git that is amazing and they do not know how to
use it. These are just some things to think about to make sure that your projects work
and letting your contributors know, giving them some guidance so that you are not alone
in making it work. Again, if it does not work for the intended user, it does not work. You
will fail and it will still be worth it. This work is so important. We have a huge need
right now in computer science education for projects, for collaboration between educators
and people in technology. There is a lot of curriculum out there, but it is not all great.
Your contribution can make a huge difference. Even if you make some of these mistakes, it
is still worth it. Finally, resources that exist are better than resources that do not.
So please, if you have an idea, do it. Even if it is not perfect, resources that can be
found are better than resources that cannot. If you have an idea and you do it, how will
you get it out to teachers? How will they find you? Resources that can be found and
used by your target user are even better. Let us do more of that. I present to you the
Zen of Python Open Education resources. Sorry. Write it down quickly.
I could go back to it during the Q&A. What are four takeaways that you can use today
during your sprints? First, think about how you can create templates or guidelines for
your contributors. How can you educate them in this area so that you can bring in the
widest amount of contributors and they can contribute in a meaningful way? How can you
give them guidance? One idea I have for my project is to use GitHub pages to create a
template and let contributors know that they should use the template to submit their projects
for our open source project. Next, bring on educator advisors. Or if you
are primarily a group of educators, bring on advisors who are Python developers who
are in the industry. If you are primarily in technology, bring on educators. Let us
work together. Next, let us start turning these educational materials into living documents.
They are anyway. Teachers virtually cannot take something off the internet and then just
turn it around and use it at face value in class. They are already having to make changes.
Let us make that part of our culture. Let us start taking pull requests. Let us start
making things live and taking contributions. Next, whenever you can, test in a classroom.
If you can plan for that during your sprint, that is great. That is it. Thank you for listening
today. Please contact me and keep the conversation going. I did write a book this year. If you
are interested, it is there. If you are not, no big deal. I would love to take questions.
I am just going to flip back here since everyone wanted that one. Yeah.
Sure. Actually, it is much easier to use Scratch because Scratch is available in so many different
languages. There is a drop down of like 40 languages. You can pick and it switches the
blocks to that language. Python does not have that. We do not even have documentation in
a lot of languages, let alone documentation for a middle school student. A lot of times
we are differentiating with Scratch. Another thing is we use an approach called trans-languaging
and also pairing that with something called literate programming. An example of literate
programming is where a student might describe what they want to do and start to, they might
ask a question like, how can I tell a story about X with Python? Then they might start
writing it. They might start writing how they are doing it. Then they gradually start writing
it in what they think is pseudo code or in pseudo code in using commands that they think
might be in Python. It is okay if the command does not actually exist. Then we take that
and we look at those commands even if they do not exist. We talk about that and we talk
about what could that be in Python. There are some great people, Chris Hoadley and Sarah
Vogel at CUNY and Columbia who are doing research on teaching computer science to students,
to English language learners. They are doing this research and have shared it with us.
That is my source on that. I would also love to learn from you since you have been doing
it with kids in the field. I will. Yes?
I have a kid who has done a lot of research on computer science. I have failed a lot of
times to do Python. How do you approach them? What are the good things that you have found?
That is a great question. It is hard. There are lots of solutions online. There is not
a lot of research to show us what actually works. There are a lot of attempts at solutions.
One of those is the company that I used to work for, Codestars, that lets you drag a
block over. It turns the block into Python once you drop it in and then it asks the students
to modify the Python. That uses an approach that is called use remix create that is research-based
in computer science education. We do not know that that actually works for transitioning
students. Trinket has the Python blocks and then Python. We do not know if it works. It
is worth a try. I think finding something that is motivating and interesting for the
students and especially because he is not in a classroom. He is working with you. Something
that is personally motivating a project he wants to do to start figuring out Python.
I thought it was just middle school students in elementary that the hardware made a difference
for micro bits and Raspberry Pi. When I go to SIGC, the special interest group on education
of the ACM every year, I hear graduate professors talking about how crazy their students went
for Raspberry Pi because there was something magical about holding it and touching it and
improve their pass rates. It is not just young kids. It is everybody.
I have found that school librarians are often on the forefront of this type of work and
not just computer science but especially digital making. I mean just librarians have a history
of leading the maker movement in this country. I do not see why they should be leading it
in schools. Also, oftentimes in middle school, it is not just the students who are leading
the maker movement in this country. I do not see why they should be leading it in schools.
Also, oftentimes administrators feel that is a good place for their digital resources
to fit in. The librarians are already managing a bunch of digital subscriptions and things
like that. We have school librarians also managing all the robots and being the expert
on the different robots and having students come in. Then the library becomes the place
where they can come to figure things out and to get extra help outside of their computer
science class. I do not know if that answers your question. Great.
Cor racks, these are all the resources they can learn and interest in or just go to.
Absolutely, you hit the nail on the head. That is a tension that will always exist and
it is so true what you said. So first I just want to point out that by starting to incorporate
computer science education during the school day at every grade level we are already making
we are already part of one of the most massive systemic changes in public school education
in the last century. So that's a big deal and that's a huge amount of change for our
public school system because as you were saying change is not easy and the culture is not set up
for innovation and learning through failure and building and making and experimenting. So that
said there's a couple different approaches that I take one as a coach I try to create that space I
let administrators know this is not a tested area so this won't be part of the evaluation of
the teacher. The other thing is that we find that as we train computer science teachers to have this
mindset it is starting to become contagious in the rest of the school. So I'll see a ninth grade
classroom that is it's a computer science classroom and the other teachers in the school all know
that that's where the kids go to learn how to use resources how to problem-solve independently
and it's they've sort of discovered that that teacher is helping them with all of their work
because of the open problem-solving that's happening that wouldn't normally happen in the
other rooms. In a kindergarten class I was in last year the teacher said to me this is the only place
the students get to practice cutting they didn't know how to use scissors they don't get to practice
and I said if that's what that's a great use of computer science time let's keep doing that. So I
think individual teachers are making change you know as they're creating this environment within
their classrooms and to some degree because it's still not tested you know we have some protection
for that we'll see what happens in the future.
Paraprogramming does there's research there's a lot of research to back that up. Paraprogramming
does improve performance and improve participation from girls specifically. Flipped classrooms the
jury's out that can create an access issue it works often in maybe a middle-class school environment
it doesn't work all the time for everybody so it just depends on the learners but I would say the
jury's kind of out on that. Thinking about children where they are developmentally is very
important. I kind of rearrange the way that I teach Python to them I start I think about math
and math we do concrete representational abstract and I use the same principles for Python how could
we start with objects both objects as a programming construct and literal manipulatives objects and how
do we move and build from there. So with Python we often actually start with something a little more
advanced an object sometimes a spray if we're using Pygame or something similar and then go from there
rather than just starting with numbers strings etc. I personally don't at Cornell Tech I work with some
graduate students who are trying to and it's been really difficult it's difficult to teach to teachers
and it's more difficult to teach to students it's a great problem for us to work on and solve together.
Yeah so in many places there is a university that's facilitating computer science work
in K-12 so that's a good place to start trying to find who are the people in my area that are maybe
researching CS education there's often somebody in a CS Ed department or an education department
who's doing that and they're often looking for practitioners people who want to be part of that
and do related work so that's one way I don't think there's an easy answer to this because again it's a big
unsolved problem I've had I actually met somebody at PyGotham years ago he said I'm really excited
I want I want to do this and I said okay just you know get to know a teacher and go do it a year later
he was like I've been working in a classroom for a year with a teacher just as a volunteer on his own
I think that's really rare there are programs like volunteer programs like TEALS which is a national
program where software engineers can volunteer in the classroom and work directly with teachers and
I think that's a good place to start and then you build the relationship with the teacher maybe they
want to continue work together and contribute something maybe you could do a small project just
by if you have a child approaching their teacher hey can we try this in your classroom so there's
different options I don't think there's a ready solution yet but if you have initiative and you
want to start building those bridges it's a great idea one more thing it could be going to educator
technology educator meetups in your area and asking who's interested yeah
yes
she just said public school public libraries have a good in with many public school systems
thank you yes
okay yes
mm-hmm so specifically for students who are blind or low vision there is a learning language called
quorum that is made specifically for those students also I would direct you for students who
death who are deaf deaf kids code is an organization that focuses on that access
computing out of the University of Washington focuses on accessibility and CS education but
primarily students who are blind or low vision or have a physical disability my area of study
is students with invisible disabilities so that might include a learning disability autism spectrum
disorder ADHD emotion and behavior disorders which do affect learning so everything in that
realm and we've found so if you're familiar with Seymour Pappert in the history of computer science
education it's based on the idea of constructivism and what he also calls constructionism which is
building to learn but we've found for those students they need help accessing constructionist
activities so we have a philosophy of supported construction constructivism so what that means
is we scaffold the process for students we focus on all of their executive functioning skills we
help them set goals we help them plan we help them how do you break down a project how do you
plan a project how do you figure out steps all of those things we scaffold to start to teach them
how to do this so that they can have access to these more open-ended projects we want to start
with direct instruction but we don't want to leave them at direct instruction because
then they wouldn't be able to access the richer learning experiences though they need that
direct instruction to start.
Excellent if you couldn't hear he was saying there are ways to configure the screen reader to read indentation in Python for
programmers who are low vision or blind thank you.
Cool.
Yep.
So this was part of the problem we were trying to address with the Raspberry Pi in a Box program
because we were running into these problems with just doing things in the browser and we wanted to move them out of that we couldn't afford to buy laptops for the school so we said okay let's try with Raspberry Pis so that's one way there are different options I mean I think just using the best tools in the browser that you can
is probably the most realistic unless you can you know influence school budgets etc.
A lot of times though if you are in a position to advise administrators on their tech purchases we have been advising them to purchase laptops instead of Chromebooks they don't understand why so they really need education on why that's important
and an explanation of how it will benefit their students.
Yeah.
So how do you I mean so what is your suggestion to Google or an industry or tech partner who is working with the school what can I take back?
Do you mean in the context of giving Chromebooks?
I mean I would say so for when I think about Google I think about Google CS First which we use with students.
So thinking about applying some of these things to CS First and the open education resources that Google puts out there.
So for example I know they've done a lot of testing in schools and it solves some problems for example it's not like the tutorials where the students just do the thing they're told and then they're not able to really retain it they have to take in some information and then apply it to their project.
But then they also get lost they don't know where they are what to do next they need education for like how to use the interface.
So I would say just talking with teachers and being having the engineers themselves go into the classroom is a great start not just you know somebody on the customer service side but the engineers who are making decisions about the product.
And oh and then just also to talk to somebody to bring in an expert to talk about accessibility as well.
Yeah.
Yeah well part of the reason is if we look at the K12 CS framework we have a lot of curriculum related to the strand about programs and programming and algorithms.
We don't have a lot of curriculum related to the strands about computing systems and networks in the internet.
And the people who are sort of running the CS framework they are actually looking for curriculum when they talk about alignment they don't mean oh you're aligned to this one area.
They mean you hit on everything in our framework.
So that's a huge need that needs to be filled and I think that's part of it.
Hi.
Yes.
I have not. That's a great idea. That's actually part of.
So today during the sprint the mini sprints.
Part of my sprint is about doing some of these things building some of these templates and one of the projects is starting the framework for a database that will eventually become a guide for non educators to be able to look up standards and understand them.
I think that's a ways off.
I definitely haven't seen it for.
I haven't seen it for non educators and where the places that do have this kind of thing definitely don't have computer science standards as part of their database.
So.
Exactly and so somebody in technology I feel like a big problem is it's not just finding the local CS standards that apply to you because it's different for every state and it can be different for different classes and grade levels where you go to even look to find these sets of standards.
Right. Are they getting a CSC?
Is it an AP course?
Is it you know in a state that has adopted CS standards?
In addition to that like you're saying they don't have time during the school days so many of them will want to do it as part of another subject area and then you need to find and interpret those standards for that subject area.
So it would be amazing to see a project that helps people in technology to not just find the applicable standards for their projects but that sort of interprets it for them that helps them to understand how that fits into their project.
So if anyone wants to brainstorm about that please join our mini sprints.
Yeah.
Oh awesome question.
He asked about what role do I see for para educators.
Are you so it's there are different terms in different states.
Will you just clarify what you mean.
Do you mean like a para who's a teaching assistant or a para educator who's like running an informal learning program out of school.
Okay.
I see.
So it's not in New York a para educator is somebody who assists specifically with students with disabilities in the classroom.
That's not what you mean right.
Yeah.
Okay.
Awesome.
But in the classroom.
Yeah.
So this is something well specifically to para educators who might help students with disabilities.
I've done research with my Israel related to this.
She has a guide up which I'll have to share.
I don't know where it is exactly.
She has a guide up online in her lab about how to help para educators to teach CS and how to train them and how teachers can work with them to be more effective.
And I think a lot of the same principles would apply.
So it's about training them even if the teacher has to be sort of modeling and training them on the fly teaching them emphasizing least to most intervention.
So meaning not having them jump in and do for the student not just para educators but teachers also have a tendency to oh they need something fixed.
I'm just going to jump in here and start taping.
We tell students not to touch each other's keyboards or mice or materials and we tell teachers not to touch students keyboards or materials.
And the same would be for para educators.
So I think really emphasizing how they don't need to be fully trained to be able to walk a student through problem solving and to not try to solve the problem for them which is a natural instinct.
Oh thank you.
Thank you for finding it.
I appreciate it.
Awesome.
All right.
Thank you so much.