This is Hanim, and I1ed as a transparency praise pitch.
Fraktion SPF, оказsın segend k~!!
Thank you.
to Python 2 to Python 3.
So please give it up for Jordan Adler and Joe Gordon.
And
How's everyone doing today?
Good afternoon.
All right.
That's what I like to hear.
Joe and I had a lovely flight coming here
with a bit of delay.
So if we are groggy and stumble a bit, bear with us.
My name is Jordan Adler.
I'm a software engineer on the API platform team at Pinterest.
And I am Joe.
I'm an SRE on the same team.
And we're from Pinterest, as I said.
Our mission at Pinterest is to bring everyone the inspiration
to create a life they love.
Who here has heard of Pinterest?
OK, most people.
For those who don't know, this is essentially
what we aim to do.
And for me, a life that I love looks something like that.
There are cats available too.
So please, no.
No flame wars.
We're going to talk a bit about our Python 3 migration
project, the approach that we took, and some of the pitfalls
that we discovered along the way.
So when Pinterest started, it was one giant Django app.
I think this is our testament to Django, how well it worked.
Since then, we've sort of migrated to a much bigger and more
complex system.
And now we still use Python as a really essential part
of our system today.
And it serves every single request
for every single over 250 monthly active users.
And Python's speed and flexibility
is really essential to enabling quick experimentation
iteration for Pinterest.
So our problem statement here is essentially
that we needed to migrate this large code base from Python 2
to Python 3.
I don't want to go into the motivation for that.
I think we're all pretty clear at that at this point.
And hopefully, that's not something
we have to continue to discuss.
But as we look forward to moving to,
as we start to think about this problem,
it's kind of difficult at our scale.
We have a very large code base, 2.6 million lines of codes,
excluding dependencies.
For context, the Linux kernel, with all its modules,
has around 24 million lines of code.
CPython only has around 1 million lines of code.
So we had a very large code base that's about twice as large
as CPython itself.
Complicating this further was also the age of the code base.
We had over 10 years of many authors focusing
on their problems and making incremental changes
towards that.
Pinterest is a growing company, and we still
have many, many folks editing our code base every day.
And in fact, we have more now than we've ever had before.
Additionally, this is a multi-stakeholder effort.
We have a shared code base with dozens of teams,
different goals and objectives.
And we have abstractions for which
we've grown beyond the need in our code base,
and they haven't necessarily been actively managed.
So the coupling situation our code base
is suboptimal for this kind of problem.
And when we thought about how to solve it,
we considered Pinterest engineering principles.
These are our guiding principles, the facets
and characteristics that we use to consider our approach
to solving problems at Pinterest.
And based on these principles, we
decided to take an incremental approach,
wherein essentially we incrementally
de-risk the migration until we could
run code under both 2 and 3.
So the rollout plan was long and complicated.
This is a multi-year project, actually.
The first step is to make sure Python 3 is available
in all our development systems and production systems.
The next step is to start to upgrade all our dependencies,
all our requirements.
We audit everything and upgrade our internal and external
dependencies.
Then we decided to featurize our code base,
and we'll talk about that in a minute.
And we want to do a test-driven iterative process here.
And so we actually want to make sure,
as we do this migration, code works under Python 2
and Python 3.
And to do that, we're using unit tests.
Once all the unit tests work under Python 2 and 3,
we switch everything over to Python 3 in production slowly,
very, very slowly.
And only at that point can we actually
start dropping Python 2 support.
And then once we drop Python 2 support,
then we can actually take advantage
of all the really great new Python 3 only features.
To upgrade requirements, we sort of
want to start at the bottom of the dependency graph.
This is because, as I said before,
we're actually trying to do it based on test-driven.
And we can't actually test a piece of code
that has hundreds of dependencies that don't support
Python 3 yet.
And to do this, we've been using a tool, can I use Python 3?
Anybody here heard of it?
OK, a few people.
So hopefully this is a big takeaway.
This works.
This uses the version classifiers under the Cheesep,
so essentially, any time you go to pypi.org,
you actually see it says Python 2, Python 3,
or something like that, or the license.
We actually use that metadata to tell something's Python 2
or 3 compatible.
It's a bit of a side that we actually had to fork it
and add a few features to it.
It didn't work for our use cases, too.
Specifically, internal dependencies and dependencies
where we haven't upgraded it.
But the newer versions of the package
actually support Python 3.
I think the upstream maintainer thought
we shouldn't do that in general.
And I agree with them.
But we were a bit of a funny point
that we couldn't change that.
Related to that, we have a lot of unmaintained dependencies.
Many of these packages were over eight years old
and had to be upgraded slowly.
Eight years of changes from some big thing like Flask
over a period of a few weeks.
And to make sure people don't add new dependencies that
are not Python 3 compatible, I've been using,
can I use Python 3 as a CI test for our requirements file
to make sure nobody adds new things that don't support it?
And lastly, one of the ways we got around some of these edge
cases is if they've been using a version class,
environment markers to say, only install this code under Python 2
or only install it on Python 3.
Only install under Python 2, maybe it's not 3 compatible yet
and we don't want to deal with that yet.
Or we're going to delay that work to a different point.
Or it's a code that's been backported from Python 3
to Python 2.
And there's a few of those as well.
When it came to migrating our own code base,
there were two approaches that we considered.
Two tools out there in the ecosystem.
The first one is Modernize, which
is a set of fixers, code transformation tools built
around the sixth module.
As well as Futurize, which is built along the future package.
And they both take different approaches
to solving the same problem, which
is writing code that can run under Python 2 and Python 3
equally well.
For our use cases, we decided that Futurize
was a better fit for us.
By the way, for those who aren't familiar,
Python Future is a great library.
It's out there.
It includes a lot of fixers.
We'll go into some of that detail later.
There is a code sprint.
If you're staying for the code sprints,
we'll be taking some time to iterate on it and back,
sorry, upstream a lot of the things
that we discovered at Pinterest.
And hopefully iterate on it to the point
that we can give it a 1.0 final release.
So if you're here next week, please definitely
drop by the development sprints and join us
to get Futurize at 1.0.
So Futurize has a set of fixers.
They are organized into two stages.
There's many fixers in each stage.
The first ones tend to be low risk
and require less effort to manual adjustment
after applying the fixer.
The second stage includes more nuance
and complicated changes.
There's also a number of things that Python Future
doesn't cover.
For example, the bytes and strings
teasing out whether something should be a byte or strings
is not something you can programmatically do.
And I mentioned before that this uses fixers.
And I'm giving actually a talk tomorrow on the details
that if you're interested in more on how that works,
come to my talk tomorrow on syntax trees in Python
automated code transformations.
So as we futurize our code base, the process
that we use essentially to apply each fix individually
with linters and continuous integration tools
to prevent regression.
So if we had a package that's migrated over to Python 3,
we required that it continue to run as expected under Python 3
with our unit tests.
By applying each fix individually,
we simplify the cognitive overhead of the change
by logically grouping by each fix.
This makes code review faster.
It also enables us to deploy incrementally,
which reduces the entropy per push, which is nice,
because essentially some of the risk here
is discovering issues as we deploy.
There are also the fixers aren't style aware.
And we don't have any automated enforcement of style
for things like black.
After running the fixer, some manual effort
was required to ensure that some of the fixers
passed under Flake 8.
And unfortunately, part of the process
is also discovering what your unit test code
coverage looks like.
Ours was relatively good, thankfully.
And if that's not the case for you,
I would strongly recommend that as the first step
before proceeding with any major refactoring, certainly
one of the scale.
One of the challenge we face is where do we
start with this whole thing?
So we could start with some external dependencies.
We actually wanted to start working on the code itself.
We can actually featurize large parts of the code.
But we actually want to now see what code actually passes
into Python 3 itself.
And so to that, we had to introspect
through the internal dependency graph.
So our graph is actually really complex and confusing.
With two million lines of codes and not ideal abstractions,
you get this spaghetti ball of chaos and confusion.
And so we couldn't actually just say, hey, start with this module.
This module has no dependencies besides third party
dependencies.
So we actually had to introspect that.
To do that, we did something that is generally
weird to do, I think, which is monkey patching import.
It worked pretty well, surprisingly.
And so the way we did this is we actually
built a list of modules that runs our Python 3.
So we take the tests.
We know they work under Python 3.
We see where they import.
We get the dependency graph from that.
Then we apply the same tool, the same monkey patching
of import, onto all the tests run under Python 2.
And then we see which tests have what dependencies.
And we take that and we find the Python 2 only
tests that have the fewest dependencies that are not
ported to Python 3.
And then we started with those.
This was a really great way for us
to solve this bootstrapping problem and allow
us to iteratively build up and start at the bottom
and work our way up.
The next step is we actually want to run our tests under Python
2 and Python 3.
Most people's test runners, hopefully, are very clean and simple.
Ours was not that.
Ours was actually pretty terrible in every way.
Our test runner actually imports most of the code in the repo.
So what that means is that we actually,
to get the test runner to work under Python 3,
you have to do most of the work to get the whole repo
to be Python 3 compatible and to work under Python 3.
And so to solve that problem, we actually
pulled out a smaller test runner that
didn't import the whole world effectively
and a smaller test-based case that solved that.
Yeah, I think one of the things to note here
is that the fail paths can change
depending on the fixer.
As I said before, some things are observable only at runtime
when you actually run the thing in production.
But there are different classes of errors
that have different classes of potential errors that
have different classes of fail paths.
So syntax errors generally are detectable by Flake 8.
Flake 8 also, some of the scoping changes
are detectable by Flake 8.
And there's a handful of other things
that can be easily picked up.
Some things are detectable at import time.
So for example, any bad dependencies or code
that's evaluated on import, statements
at the top level of the module.
When you import that code into your production code,
or sorry, into your test code as you run the unit test,
it will fail upon import at the import stage, which
is great because you don't actually
need to have unit tests for the exercise path.
You just need to actually make sure it compiles.
And then there's another class of errors,
which are only detectable at runtime,
either via unit tests that exercise those code paths
and enable you to discover the failures.
Or unfortunately, if there's not good unit test code coverage,
you're going to have to detect some of these in production
changes.
And so with that in mind, complicating that further,
so that's one set of characteristics
that makes some of these fixes more complicated than others.
Another is that we just have a large and complex code base.
If you spot test a code transformation
on a portion of our code base, given its large and complex
size, it could potentially have effects
on another part of the code base that, quite frankly, you didn't
know existed.
It's not possible to have 2.6 millions of lines of code
in your head, especially when they change this rapidly.
And so some amount of stochastic thinking
is required to really understand how to do a code migration
at this scale.
Test coverage is part of the challenge here, too.
If a particular change to a particular portion of the code
base does not have test covering for that path
or that particular branch, or even, quite frankly,
if the test that's being done is of low quality,
if it doesn't check that the actual responses are
as expected, and even if you have good coverage,
it doesn't mean your coverage is high quality coverage.
And so that can be a challenge as well.
Additionally, some of the fixers simply cannot.
There's limitations in the fixers themselves.
For example, all div safe and fix dict.
These use approaches that were a little more conservative.
The fixers are more conservative,
which is perfectly reasonable and exactly what
you want to do, but not necessarily
what we want to commit to our code base.
And so those required some manual adjustments
after having run the fixer.
And there are some things for which there is no fixer.
For example, the string and bytes difference
is something that you kind of have to go variable by variable
and decide what the correct approach is there.
So the good.
A lot of things actually worked really well.
I think the rest of the talk is going
to be about terrible things, bad and ugly.
But I want to stress that a lot of things actually
worked really well.
In fact, most of the hard work has been done for us.
It's a bit of a side note.
Python 3 is actually 10 years old.
I think it's 11 years old now.
So we're not actually talking about migrating to a new thing.
We're talking about migrating to an old thing.
As a bit of reference, our code base
is roughly the same age as Python 3,
which is, I think, a side note.
So often the only changes required for a lot of these
changes was actually making sure we passed Flake 8.
Everything else is done for us.
So I think the really good things here are our Futurize
worked really, really well as a lib 2 to 3.
So a few examples.
Here's one print with import.
Hopefully everybody here knows about this Python 3 change.
Anybody be surprised by this one?
OK, nobody raised their hand.
That's good.
Right in Python 3, we have print.
You have to pass in parentheses to it.
And so if you have on one side here,
we have the Python 2 style.
We have the result of the fixer.
And it sort of handles all the cases perfectly.
You have bare print.
You have print with high.
You have Python 2 style and Python 3 style print.
That all works.
You have rerouting to standard error.
Everything works great.
Another one worked really well is accept.
Python 2 has this really tricky notation
that actually has caused multiple problems in the past
for us.
If you want to do accept exception, comma, e,
e is the variable for the exception
that you caught all exceptions here.
But the other thing you may want to do in this case,
if you want to catch several exceptions,
the notation you're supposed to use
is accept parentheses, exception 1, exception 2,
close parentheses, comma, e.
But a lot of people just do accept exception 1, comma,
exception 2, in which case you catch an exception
and you store it in the value for exception 2.
Then you cause all kinds of weird problems
because you essentially are monkey patching something
at runtime and it gets really confusing.
So Python 3 decided to say, no, we don't want to do that.
And it turns out the fixer works great for that.
It also works in this less clear notation here,
except exception bracket a.
And you can see here on the other side in the results here,
it actually takes the arguments passed into the exception.
So this case, it would actually be b.
a would be b in this case.
But this is sort of one of the limitations of fixers here.
It doesn't know what variable to use.
It's a nice simple variable xxx to do change me.
And so presumably you should be changing that
and not sprinkling it all over your code base.
Another one here is meta class.
Under Python 2 and Python 3,
the meta class notation changed significantly.
Python 2, you do double underscore meta class equals meta.
But in Python 3, you do class foo meta class equals meta.
The problem with that is you can't have a code base
that supports both of them.
And so this is a good example of where Python future
has a shim to use.
You do from future utils import with meta class.
And in this case, the fixer does it all for you right away.
Another one is absolute imports.
So under Python 2, this is concept of doing
implicit relative import.
So you can see here we have import foo.
Foo is a module in this directory I'm in.
And I'm accessing this variable, this constant x.
The confusing thing about this is that it could be
if foo happened to be named os, let's say,
then you could actually be unclear what you should import.
Are you importing the os in the directory
or importing the standard library os?
And this has caused multiple problems for us over the years
as we refactor code.
And the implicit import caused all kinds of problems.
So Python 3 has absolute imports.
So you have to do explicit relative imports.
And once again, the fixer does it in most cases,
but there are ambiguous cases in your code base.
And in that case, sometimes future will break
and you'll have to fix a few of them by hand.
But it fixed 90% of the issues right away.
Others were surprising.
You know, a large code base means we have lots of edge cases.
Here are some of the issues that we hit along the way.
So this is a nice, simple example here.
We have 1 divided by 2.
Under Python 2, we get 0, right?
This is an integer.
Anybody know what it should be in Python 3?
Just shout out the answer.
That's right.
OK, so this is a nice, simple one.
In this case, Python 3 makes sort of behavior
sort of more expected.
I know many of you say, but it's not.
These are two integers, and that's not how division works.
But this is how I think humans think of division,
and so it's a nice change to reflect how people really
think about it.
Here's another interesting one.
We have rounding, round 9 comma 1.
Under Python 2, we get a float, 9.0.
Anybody guess we get a Python 3?
We get 9, not a float.
So we get an integer now.
Once again, I think this makes more sense.
It sort of reflects what we put in.
We get out.
Here's an interesting one we have.
This is the one I thought was really fascinating myself.
We get round 2.5.
Under Python 2, we get 2.
We round to a number.
What do we get in Python 3?
Anybody know why?
That's right.
Bankers rounding, very impressive.
So the idea here, previously, you
would round down to 0 every time.
And the problem with that is if you're a banker, let's say,
and you have a bunch of numbers, the error from rounding
adds up over time.
But if you round to the closest odd,
it'll hopefully balance out over time,
because you're assuming your numbers are randomly
distributed with regard to where they are in the float.
And so once again, this actually makes the numbers
sort of work better in a better way.
Although technically, these are both completely valid answers.
Rounding 2.5 has two correct answers, not one.
And so this is sort of a weird case here.
Here's another one.
You have x equals none.
Maybe it's a fallback from a function
that it returns a value, but in some cases, it returns none.
And we're trying to compare x to some constant,
in this case, 1.
Under Python 2, we get false.
None is not greater than false.
Python 3, any guesses?
Yep, we get a type error here.
It turns out you can't compare none and int.
That doesn't make any sense.
I don't know why we could have done it before.
This is a case where we found in our code base
that lots of people sort of assumed this behavior worked,
and we have lots of edge cases that hit this.
Here's another one we have.
Month equals 0, 1.
Right?
It's January.
We're going to try to print the month.
Python 2, we get 1.
Makes sense.
Python 3, anybody?
Nobody?
OK.
We actually get invalid token.
It turns out this notation is not correct.
The reason is because under Python 2, 0, 1 is not base 10.
That is base 8.
It is octal.
The 0 is for octal here.
And so you can't actually do, for example, 0, 9.
And in Python 3, they say, hey, that's not a great idea.
This is super confusing.
It turns out it is super confusing in our code base.
And so the actual correct notation is 0, 0, 1.
And that'll work in both cases.
But in most cases, you could actually just drop the 0
and then make it just be 1 and then don't use octal,
because using octal in most code bases is a bit unusual.
All these changes are sort of making the numbers align more
consistently with people, sort of expect them to do.
The rounding, the comparisons, everything else.
And these are all part of a big PEP 3141.
And there was a numeric tower.
And it sort of simplified the whole process
and made it much more aligned with reality.
This is one of the things that big surprises for us
in this migration was how many edge cases there were here
that we actually hit.
So we also had a number of issues
you can imagine around bytes and string.
So here we have some example code.
We get a user ID integer from some part of our code base.
We cast it to a string under Python 2
by passing it to bytes.
Any guesses what happens in Python 2?
It's a string.
What about Python 3?
Here.
Yeah.
Essentially, we get a memory error.
Because in Python 3, when you pass a value to bytes,
it assumes that that's the number of bytes
that you wish to allocate.
So you can imagine our very large user IDs
resulted in us allocating more bytes
than we had available in memory.
Not fun.
We have this case here where we iterate over a byte string.
Any ideas what this might produce under Python 2?
So it'll produce 1, 2, 3.
What about Python 3?
The ASCII code points.
So essentially, in Python 2, the byte string
is treated as a byte sequence.
And so under Python 2, it's treated as a character sequence.
And so each thing is interpreted essentially
as a character that was passed into the byte literal.
And under Python 3, no encoding is applied to it.
And so the byte string literal is
interpreted as the ASCII code points that
correspond to those characters.
Here's another example.
So we have string.letters and string.ascii letters.
We use those in our code base.
Under Python 2, they return the same thing.
And in reality, string.letters is locale-specific.
Under Python 3, it's gone.
And so part of the reason that it's
going is because it is locale-specific,
and it was dropped as part of going Unicode Native.
The locale-specificity made it kind of difficult to debug.
And so this is generally, I think, a good change,
as most of these are.
Here's another example.
We have a bit of Unicode code in our code base.
We pass in our encoding UTF-8 signal into the compiler.
We create a new exception with some value
that we get passed in from elsewhere in the code
with some emoji characters in it, perhaps user-inputted text
in Python 2.
This is not allowed.
Essentially, the exception expects
an ASCII-encoded character in Python 3.
This works just fine.
And so the root cause of much of this
is essentially reorganizing the containers, the sequence
the sequences for Unicode's strings and bytes.
So in Python 2, string and Unicode
are sequence types along with list and tuple,
and there's a couple others.
The decision of which one you use as a programmer
was decided whether you wanted an 8-bit interpretation
or a Unicode interpretation.
So typically, the 8-bit was ASCII by default.
In Python 3, this distinction was removed.
A new type, bytes, was introduced
for representing raw binary sequences
with no application of any code map.
And then the string type was intended
to present an encoded overview of the bytes,
or an encoded representation of a sequence of bytes.
So let's talk about scoping here.
This is what I think a lot of you have probably seen.
Under Python 2, we have a list comprehension.
Anybody guess what should be in Python 2?
Nine.
Anybody actually use this kind of code in their code base?
I'm curious.
A few people?
OK.
We use it a lot too, surprisingly.
Under Python 3, I think this is a weird thing.
There's no scope here.
You leak variables.
Python 3 fixes that.
It says i is not defined.
That makes a lot of sense here.
Although it is a nice behavior you could use before,
so you have to refactor some code.
This is actually a good example where
this is really easy to spot with actually flake8 will spot this.
But it's not always easy to refactor the code
programmatically, so you have to get in and actually
manually modify the code.
Here's a bit more complicated one.
We have another interesting scope
on our list comprehensions.
Anybody guess what this should be under Python 2?
It's a little confusing code.
We have a variable i, I mean a and b.
It turns out b should actually be 2.
We're just going over b is using a.
Python 3, any guesses?
No.
It gives you an error, a name error.
It turns out a is not actually defined here.
So it turns out this is a quote from a bug I found.
I'm not sure who the author was, but if you're in the room,
thank you very much for writing this.
This is because list comprehensions are now
implemented with their own function object,
like generator expressions always have.
Effectively, what this is saying is this code should
have never worked.
Under Python 3, they fixed that, and it doesn't work.
Under Python 2, it does work.
As a bit of a side note, if you do this outside
of a class as a top level, it does work.
So this is sort of a weird edge case I think we saw once,
and we're just blown away by it.
And then it turns out it never should have been there.
Here's another one for scope.
Anybody guess what this does on Python 3?
Print out the locals inside of a class.
Any guesses?
We get one local here.
In this case, it is self.
Under Python 3, we actually get two,
which is now we have class.
It turns out you hit this if you do anything
in your code with locals, and you're iterating over locals
and expecting certain values to be there in locals,
certain ones not to.
And this is actually a fairly easy one to fix in most cases,
but it required manual changes every time.
Here's another one about dictionaries.
Dictionaries are big things that change
under Python 2 and Python 3.
Here we have a function foo.
We're passing in b equals 1 and a equals 2,
and we're printing out the keyword arguments.
Under Python 2, we get a equals 2 and b equals 1.
They're actually switched around here.
Under Python 3, any guesses?
It's actually a trick question, as you'd imagine by now.
It actually depends on when you run it
and what version of Python you're running.
So if you run it on Python 3 to 3.5,
the ordering depends on when you run it.
If you run it twice in the same code base,
it'll always be the same.
But if you run it twice in the same instance of Python,
it'd be the same.
But in different instances of Python, it'll be different.
And then under Python 3.6 and above,
it actually changes to the ordering.
It's always b1, a2.
And this is because there's two major changes to dictionaries
under Python 3.
The first one is hash randomization was added.
It's intended to protect against denial of service attacks
with big O of n squared complexity.
And this was true for Python's 3, I think, through 3.5.
And this is true beyond.
There's randomization in there.
And so that's why we get random ordering when
you run it different times.
We are using Python 3.5 in a few instances.
So we actually decided to hard code a random seed
for our test environments.
I think we picked some number.
So it's the same every time.
And this actually made it much easier for us to test
and sort of isolate these problems
and deal with them later.
And part of the problem we're not dealing with now
is because there's another part, which is under Python 3.6
and above, there is a new dictionary that is more compact.
It's, I think, 20% to 30% more compact.
It was done.
The main motivation for it is to use less memory.
But one of the interesting side effects
is now order preserving.
But as you see here in the release notes,
the order preserving aspect of this new implementation
is considered an implementation detail
that should not be relied upon.
It turns out that under Python 2,
we had a deterministic order.
In Python 3.6, we have deterministic order.
And a lot of people made assumptions
about the ordering of dictionaries under Python 2.
And so not relying on this has been really hard for us,
especially when you have hundreds of developers working
on code independently.
Sort of a common case of this is maybe you're printing out
a dictionary and an exception, and you're
sort of assuming the ordering of the representation of it
is always the same.
Another case of Python 3, here we have a dictionary.
We're printing out the keys.
Python 2, we get 1, 2, 3, as expected.
Anybody guess this is Python 3?
We get an error.
We get a type error here.
Actually, it's Dick, keys, and list.
It turns out there's a huge change of Python 2 to Python 3
in dictionaries.
Now we return dictionary views for keys, values, and items.
And iter items, iter, et cetera, are all gone.
And one of the things is this is more of a set-like component
instead of a list-like thing.
And in this case, you cannot add them together.
You cannot pass it into sort because you
can't sort this thing that's only an iterable and not
actually a list.
In this case, this is actually a fairly easy one to fix.
And there's some good fixers for it under a futurize.
So also some changes around exceptions.
So here we have a bit of code that raises an exception
and then takes the sys.exe info to get information
about the caller.
Any ideas what this might produce under Python 2?
I think we've scared you guys.
As you might expect, it returns two exceptions.
What about Python 3?
So it returns one exception and then none.
Any idea why that might be?
Yeah, that's right.
So essentially, the thing that changed
was the definition of the phrase handling an exception.
Under Python 2, handling an exception
is defined as executing or having
executed an accept clause.
Whereas in Python 3, it's defined
as executing an accept clause.
So the distinction here is that you can no longer expect
sys.exe info to be available outside
of the context of the accept clause.
And much of our code base is dependent on this behavior
and it's difficult to discover.
Here's another exception issue from exceptions in Port Keyer.
Any idea what this might do in Python 2?
Nothing.
It does literally nothing.
Not just because it's not doing anything,
but also because the from exceptions import foo
processes in no op.
In Python 2, the exceptions were pulled
into the built-in namespace and so this line
was basically ignored.
What about Python 3?
In Python 3, the deprecated exceptions module was removed.
And so essentially, this is a vestigial holdover
from Python 1 where the exceptions were in 1
and were in the exceptions package in Python 2.
It was deprecated and so it's available in the built-in
namespace.
In Python 3, it was removed.
And so this no op became an error in a way
that we would not have predicted.
Some things were painful.
So this is a really interesting one for us.
This is actually something that's near and dear to a few
of my colleagues right now.
Hashability.
We have this class here, MyString,
and MyString defines EQ for equality.
In this case, it's not doing anything special.
Let me try to print out the hash of MyString PyCon.
Anybody guess what that'll be?
A big number, right?
Positive or negative number?
It's a really big number.
Python 3.
Any guesses?
Type error.
That's correct.
Yeah.
So it's unhashable type.
Specifically, in Python, you should always
have if two objects are equal, then their hashes
should be equal.
And that should always be true.
And if you define your own equality operator,
you're probably breaking that explicit contract that
should always be done.
Under Python 2, it lets you shoot yourself in the foot
and have a happy day.
Python 3, they actually said, no, this
isn't a good default behavior.
And they actually fixed it.
So if you define EQ, you have to define hash as well.
And this turns out to be a fairly easy thing to fix.
But it's also very subtle and very confusing.
And the edge cases under Python 2
actually are the scarier part, that this could cause
all kinds of weird problems.
So one interesting case here is we
had a string that was coming in from a user-generated content
that contained ASCII and Unicode.
Or not ASCII and Unicode, but it contained essentially Unicode
characters, including emojis.
So we were iterating over each character in that sequence
and printing out some information about that character.
Here, we've converted to ord and hex
so we can look at the code points.
What do you might expect this look like under Python 2?
Well, your first character is going
to be your code point for the ASCII letter A.
The second character, 20, is the code point for space in ASCII.
And the next two characters are the code points
that represent bytes that combined,
refer to the lovely emoji that we have here.
Any idea what this might look like under Python 3?
How many prints do you expect to see?
Three.
So in Python 3, we logically group the Unicode characters
and we treat them logically as characters, which is correct.
This is no longer exposed to the Python developer.
Essentially, this is an implementation detail
under the surface because we're encoding in the Unicode
character sets.
However, when we were debugging this,
we had some inconsistencies because in some
of our environments, we were seeing the Python 3 behavior
under Python 2 as well.
Any idea where that might be?
Not quite.
So in Python, below a certain version,
you could compile what's called a wide or narrow build.
And essentially, that would change the internal
representation for characters to be UCS2 or 4.
The gist of it is that it would either use two bytes
per Unicode character or four bytes.
If you have two bytes, then what happens is,
or so-called narrow build, then multi-byte characters
that refer to a code point that cannot be encapsulated
in that number of bytes, you get essentially
two separate characters that combined refer to
the actual glyph that you care about.
In Python 2, you can also do a wide build,
which is what we had in some of our environments.
And so the challenge here is that the compile time flags
that we were using to override the behavior here
was not consistent in all of our environments,
which was something we did not think to have to expect.
So here's another really fun one.
We have from C string import string I-O.
And we have two things.
We have some image data as bytes and some text as Unicode.
Anybody guess what happens to Python 2?
It just sort of works, right?
Nothing actually happens.
We actually get no result.
We're not printing anything out.
Under Python 3, any guesses what we get?
We get an error here, actually.
We get module not found error.
Turns out C string I-O is deprecated and removed
in favor of I-O, bytes I-O, and string I-O.
And those are in Python 2, actually, as well.
So let's try this code again.
From I-O import string I-O, we have string I-O,
the bytes, and the Unicode.
Under Python 2, we actually get a type error.
It turns out for string I-O, it requires Unicode,
and bytes I-O requires bytes.
And actually, thankfully, in Python 3,
we get the same behavior.
But here, the catches we've been using
from C string I-O import string I-O to handle both cases.
Now we actually have to go through and manually sort out
each case.
And there's some particularly ugly complications around this.
Under Python 2, opening a file by default opens it in binary.
Under Python 3, it opens as Unicode.
The CSV module changed some behaviors in a similar way,
as well.
So you combine all these three things together,
you get this really sort of hairy knot
of these weird binary Unicode problems to handle.
One of the fun things about a migration of this size
and a code base of this size is that your Python code does not
run in isolation.
It integrates with other components and other systems
that are not necessarily built with the same technology stack.
In this case, we have some Node.js services,
or some JavaScript environments that communicate
with our Python stack.
And so we're going to drift quickly over
into the JavaScript world and look at how
we can do that.
So we're going to go ahead and do a quick run
quickly over into the JavaScript world.
And we're going to run these two statements in the Node.js
REPL.
What do you expect might return from this
based on your understanding of computer science in general?
Yeah, so essentially, in JavaScript,
numbers are always 64-bit floating points.
Because both of these numbers are outside the threshold
of precision for doubles, you get
capped at the functional equivalent of max int,
or max double.
This is defined in IEEE 754, which
you're curious to learn more about.
David Wolver will talk about it tomorrow
in a lovely talk entitled IEEE 704.00.
Oh, zero.
Zero.
So the fun thing about how IEEE 74 numbers are implemented
is they're not necessarily accurate.
They're accurate enough.
They're sort of like scientific notation.
So to work around this in our current base, what we did
was we converted longs to strings
when passing to JavaScript.
Unfortunately, our isInstance test for longs
doesn't work under Python 3, because in Python 3,
as well as to some extent, int and longs
are effectively the same type.
And so our test to see if it's long did not pass.
And so it was not coerced into a string.
It was passed to the JavaScript system
directly as a numeric literal, which
it was not able to interpret.
That means it no longer works as Python 3.
We had to go back to the drawing board
to figure out how to solve that problem.
Another challenge we dealt with is mocks.
A lot of the fixtures we use actually
do a lot of things great for us.
But I don't think any of them actually handle changing mocks.
So here we actually have a mock.
We're mocking built-in open and Python 2 with open,
not a file here.
There's a hint this is not actually a file.
So if you weren't mocking it, it will throw an exception.
But in this case, nothing actually
should happen because we're mocking open.
And open will just do nothing, and it'll be fine.
It'd be a magic mock, and we get nothing under Python 2.
Any guess you get under Python 3?
So let's actually see.
It turns out module not found.
It turns out double underscore built-ins
is renamed to built-ins.
And that means actually the mock is no longer valid.
So we're actually not mocking the thing,
but we're trying to mock a thing that doesn't exist.
And so we actually get mock throwing the exception.
It turns out we have lots of code now where it says,
if Python 2 mock this, if Python 3 mock that.
This is something we showed how to manually find in each case.
It turns out these are fairly easy to find.
This is true for essentially all the standard library
changes that are made under Python,
including things like built-in.
So these are some of the most interesting edge cases
we discovered along the way.
We're still in this process, and if you're
curious to learn more about some of the things we expect,
or we will discover as we continue,
we expect to update the Pinterest engineering
blog with information about the Python 3 migration project
as we come closer to a close on that.
Hopefully we'll have some information
about the impact of that, which we expect to be significant.
Thanks for coming to the talk.
Since we're kind of short on time here
and we're the only thing between you and lunch,
we'll take questions at the Pinterest booth on the expo
on the fourth floor at 4 o'clock.
Cool.
Thank you so much.