Full room, thank you very much.
It's nice to see you all.
Welcome to PyCon.
Thanks for inviting me.
I've been waiting for a long time to do this.
Live long and prosper.
Peace and long life.
43 years have I waited for that.
There it was.
I was a young man.
I saw a show that inspired me.
This fellow is Spock.
They have a terrible problem.
They have a smart computer.
Kirk was assessing the danger of the problem.
What was the nature of it?
And Spock said something that inspired me for the rest of my life.
What was the M5 computer?
The multi-tronic computer made by Dr. Deistrom.
It is the human mind amplified by the instantaneous relays possible in a computer.
And it sent chills down my spine.
It wasn't a great episode.
But that sentence was important.
And to me it wasn't about the Dr. Deistrom computer.
The more interesting part is the human mind being amplified by the instantaneous relays
of the computer.
Can we use our machines to make ourselves smarter?
We've waited a long time to have that happen.
Algorithms have been around for a long time.
Depth first search, breadth first search, Monte Carlo tree search, graph traversal algorithms.
Over 30 years ago I was reading books on neural networks.
None of these things are new.
What has changed?
They have been put together in interesting ways.
The algorithms have become smarter.
Our computation power has become massive.
And these machines have gotten smart.
And so we have a new way that we can program that we didn't have available to us before.
And so the theme of the talk is instead of writing programs, we write descriptions of
the problem and then let solvers go solve them.
And I think we live in a wonderful time.
It's a great time to be alive.
And I'd like to show you some of these tools.
Actually the best way to show them is not with real world applications, is to show games
or puzzles or toy problems.
To the extent that these tools can solve those problems, they can also solve our real world
problems.
So I'd like you to use your imagination a little bit.
If I show you the solution to a puzzle, we have to mentally translate that to something
interesting, which is optimizing our programs, finding bugs in multithreaded code, et cetera.
So without further ado, I will take you through.
Let's do a quick intro.
Where are we headed?
Problems to find or wills solved?
I found something on the net that said things better than I could say them, so I'll just
put it up on the screen.
Actually it's easier to make rules than to find a way to follow them.
So sometimes if you just have a description of a problem, it automatically gives a solution
if we put it into a solution finder.
So the tour I'm going to give you is I have a lot of stuff to cover.
I'm going to show you depth first and breadth first search.
That doesn't sound interesting, but it is in fact powerful.
The next step up in capabilities is called SAT solvers.
In a way it's kind of boring.
It's following truth tables, but once the truth tables become really large, they become
very, very powerful.
So I'd like to show you what they're capable of and how to access them from the Python
world.
Reinforcement learning is a very simple concept.
We do it to ourselves all of the time.
We've taught machines how to do it.
I'll show the simple algorithm for that.
Then I'll take you into a space probably a lot of you have never been into.
How many of you have heard of TLA plus?
This is fantastic.
It is actually becoming more popular as we speak.
A year ago possibly no one in this room would have heard of it.
How many of you have used Z3?
My work is done here.
All right.
You guys are ahead of the game.
Then the next step up in complexity is can we combine all of those tools together and
Monte Carlo tree search, convolutional neural networks, and reinforcement learnings to defeat
human beings.
So we'll talk about AlphaZero, which is an amazing, amazing accomplishment.
So what to keep in mind as we explore is one, how little code is needed to express these
ideas.
Number two is how generic the tooling is.
What is great about all of these problems is that the best solutions to these problems
weren't custom designed for the problem.
The custom designed solutions in the end got outclassed by the generic solutions.
So keep that in mind as we go along.
The generic tool is more powerful than the specific tool.
Then also keep in mind, I'll show you fun toy problems, but these problems will be at
the periphery of human capability, the outer limits of our ability to think, which is great
because if we can take a computer that far by amping up the computational power, we can
take it beyond our own abilities, achieving the goal that Spock had laid out for us.
That said, that episode was a cautionary tale.
We'll talk about that a little bit at the end to see where this all ends up.
Do we all die or do we all reap the benefits of AI as we go along?
We'll explore that at the end.
All right.
First thing, depth first search, breadth first search.
Do those diagrams speak for themselves?
Depth first, which way does it go first?
Down or sideways?
Down, which is why it's called?
I see.
Okay.
Breadth first.
Which way does it go?
Okay.
So different types of problems warrant one solution or the other.
Often if you're trying to find the shortest path to a solution, you do breadth first search.
However, you'll find the Monte Carlo tree search, the tools that were used in Alpha
Zero for example, do a depth first search.
They play out an entire game of chess several times and then go back and decide based on
how the game turned out what move to make.
What tool do you need in Python in order to implement a depth first search or breadth
first search?
Does anybody know?
It's going to be kind of a search.
I don't want to give any hints here at all.
Okay.
So collections deck is a tool that works really great for this.
You decide whether new tasks should be prepended to the queue for depth first or appended to
the queue for breadth first search.
It's actually very easy code.
By the way, everything I'm going to show you I'm giving you code for.
When these slides go up, you can run all of the examples including the chess program.
Sound good?
All right.
Once upon a time, many years ago, I wrote a generic puzzle solver.
It solves a broad class of puzzles.
Here's the core idea.
The puzzle solver doesn't know anything about the puzzle.
All it knows is how to solve puzzles.
So the puzzle solver, the way it's used is we subclass the solver and we add in some
extra information.
What is the initial position of the puzzle?
What is a rule to generate all the possible moves from the next position?
What moves can I make?
And are we at the goal?
Keep in mind the solver knows nothing about the nature of the game.
It just says where do you start?
What can you do?
Where are you trying to get to?
I'll take you there.
That's fantastic.
You can throw in some extras.
A nice repper will make the output of the puzzle recognizable to us.
Some problems have complementary explosion and that can be managed sometimes through
exploiting symmetry.
So there is a way to exploit some positions that are considered equivalent.
For example, in Tic-Tac-Toe, if you start a game in the upper left corner, it's isomorphic
to a game where you start in the lower right-hand corner.
So we can teach the computer to recognize that those positions are the same.
And that speeds up the solution.
Neither of these two things are required to get a solution.
They either just make it faster or they make it look prettier.
So here's a classic simple problem.
Given these two empty jugs with three and five liter capacities and a full liter jug
with eight liters, find a sequence of pours so that you get four liters and the two largest
jugs.
The purpose of this example is to show how to use the solver.
We import the puzzle, subclass the puzzle, and describe the problem.
And so we give it an initial position, zero liters, zero liters, and eight liters.
We put in some constraints.
What's the capacity of each jug?
And what's the goal?
Four liters, four liters, and zero.
The interesting part is the iterator here.
It's not the clearest code I've ever written, but it gets the job done and it's short, sweet,
and easy to test.
So given a position, if you run the iterator, it generates for you what is the next possible
position, what pours are possible.
So from this initial position, you can pour the eight ounce jug into the five, leaving
three, or you can pour the eight ounce into the three, leaving five.
And so this generator generates those two possible positions.
The interesting thing I think about this puzzle problem is this solver didn't know anything
about this puzzle.
When we tell it to run solve, it outputs the example.
So here's how to run it.
We make an instance of jug fill.
We ask what is the initial position, is it the goal, and to loop over what are the possible
moves.
But if you run the solve method, it starts, picks one of those moves, and it finds the
shortest path solution to that problem.
Now this is an easy problem.
This is the kind of problem you give to a fifth grader and let them toy out and learn
a little bit of math.
But if you start to throw 10, 20, 30 jugs in there, it becomes an enormously complex
problem, isomorphic to the knapsack problem, a very hard problem, a problem that quickly
exceeds the limits of human capability, and actually at some point exceeds the limits
of our computational power as well.
In other words, while this was a cute problem, when you scale it up to a harder problem,
it becomes really interesting, such as optimizing a program.
Everybody get the basic idea of how the generic puzzle solver works.
Describe the puzzle, it gives you the answer, which is the theme.
Describe the problem, and the solver solves it for you.
So there's another interesting puzzle going back into my history here that also dates
to about the time I saw that Star Trek episode.
There was a puzzle that looked like this with different colored pieces at my grandfather's
house.
I called him Paw, so I have labeled this code the Paw Puzzle.
What was interesting to me about this puzzle is not so much what the puzzle was itself.
The puzzle was to slide the blocks around and take this big block.
By the way, can you see my arrow?
Yes.
Take the big block and cause it to be in the lower left position, which sounds pretty easy.
The fascinating thing to me about this puzzle is my grandfather was a fairly smart man,
knew lots of other smart people who liked to come over to his house and they'd find
the puzzle and all attempt to work it.
I have never met another human being ever in my entire life who was able to solve this
puzzle.
The only person I've met in my entire life who was ever able to solve the puzzle was
me.
Would you like to know how I did it?
I wrote a computer program.
One of my first computer programs was written in BASIC that solved this puzzle in much the
same way that I am solving it now.
Only when I saw the solution did I realize why it was hard.
The combinations spread out quite a bit, but they loop back to each other and it makes
this very tight graph with one little exit door.
If you don't know that you're at the exit door, you pass it up.
If you go through that exit door, it opens up to another graph that has lots of positions
that can cause you to go back to the original state, but it has an exit door.
If you don't find it, you stay inside that little loop.
Then there's another exit door on the other side.
There's an enormous number of moves in the solution.
Well, at least for a puzzle that looks as simple as surprising, the solution is about
80 moves.
Essentially, all I needed to do was to come up with a representation for the position.
In this case, I've got a nice wrapper that will print this out in a block form so we
could recognize the piece numbers of the puzzle.
Then for the goal, I used a regular expression and said, if the one block ends up in this
position, we've solved the puzzle.
In other words, it needs to know where do I start, have I achieved my goal?
The more interesting part is the iterator.
Again, not the most beautiful code I've ever written, but this is about 15-year-old code
for me.
There's a couple updates that are inside, but mostly it was originally written.
This tiny bit of code that describes the problem solves it.
Let's see if I actually got this up here.
You are running Python 3.8, are you not?
It's out.
Alpha, but you can run it now.
This output was, it gave me from the initial position every possible move until you got
to the end.
It's not a particularly pretty output.
That said, without the wrapper, each one of these would have been on one line.
That was about 88 moves.
It makes very short work of a problem that as far as I know, no smart human I've ever
met has been able to solve this problem.
You guys get the theme of where we're going, describe the problem, solver solves it.
first search are amazingly powerful.
Did the world get more interesting after tools like that came out?
Yes, SAT solvers.
Is it okay if I get technical at a technical conference?
Can I get all technical on you?
If I show you a little math that reminds you of your worst days in college, are you going
to get up and leave?
Here we go, a SAT solver.
SAT is spelled in all caps, it's for satisfiability problems.
The idea is it solves problems that are specified using propositional logic formulas.
Most people start running at this point.
The idea of a propositional logic formula is you take a problem statement.
If our tire's flat when I remove it, then I will have to remove it and take it to the
gas station.
Our first step is to translate that into logic statements.
So take each phrase and assign a letter to it, P, Q, and R for each of the predicates
in the solution.
Write it in symbolic form.
This is not hard to do.
Most of you have forgotten how to do it.
But if you'd like to use these tools, you need to recover that knowledge.
Use these slides as something that takes you through step by step and will let you reacquire
the necessary knowledge.
So here's the truth table for that.
In these statements, is this one true?
So in the truth table, our states are essentially these first three columns.
Our output state is the last column.
What SAT does is ask the question, on the right column, are any of the outputs a T?
Are they true?
And not all SAT solvers, but most of them, can give you an example of a row where a T
is true.
That doesn't sound particularly interesting because we could just loop over these and
find a T and print it out.
Does that sound powerful?
It does not sound powerful.
And this problem is not very interesting.
Where it becomes interesting is these tables, the size of this is with three variables,
we got two to the third power, eight rows.
So if you have 10 variables, you're at two to the tenth, looking at about a million rows.
If you have 20 variables, you start to go up again by square root of that again, and
30 you're up into billions.
So what if you had a thousand variables?
Would the problem become complex?
There are more states than there are atoms in the universe.
Does that sound computationally tractable?
It is an intractable problem.
It is provable that it's intractable.
But most real world problems have symmetries and patterns inside.
And so we live in a great time.
During the course of my lifetime, every year somebody has attacked this problem and said,
are there little patterns inside that we can exploit in real world problems?
And every year, SAT solvers have gotten smarter.
Not a little smarter, a lot smarter.
It is not uncommon now for people to run SAT problems with over a million variables and
have it find a solution.
This is astonishing.
It reminds me of Asimov saying, any sufficiently advanced technology is indistinguishable from
magic.
It is magic that we can find answers to these problems.
So why do we care?
There's many otherwise really difficult problems that we can solve.
Our amazing fact now is that this problem is now tractable for thousands or even millions
of variables.
So what do you need in order to do this in Python?
There's a tool called Picosat and an interface to it in Python called Picosat.
It's not the only solver.
There's a number of them out there.
And in order to use these tools, you have to sound like a mathematician.
You have to say things like, conjunctive normal form with straight face.
Try it all now.
Without cracking a smile, say conjunctive normal form.
Okay.
Which just means a product of sums and and of r's.
So here's an and, here's some r's.
And so that was that original problem statement, the previous expression, rewritten in conjunctive
normal form.
In the SAT solvers, it's common to write the negative case, negative p, as a minus one
and the positive case as a positive one.
And in the second variable, this would be a positive two and this would be a negative
one.
So in Picosat, we describe this problem with this list.
Minus one two and minus one three.
Doesn't look very humanistic.
And the output is this, which is the five true states.
Fair enough?
Okay.
So all that did was you described the problem and it went through the output.
That doesn't seem impressive.
So our core challenge in working with this tool is to take things like this that are
not humanistic and make them more humanistic.
It doesn't ship with such a tool.
So I wrote one and I'm giving it to you.
It's not a lot of code, but essentially takes phrases that we can understand and translates
them into this.
In particular, if my translate function says let's rewrite that input as not p and q and
not p and r.
And it translates it into these numbers for you.
Does that sound like an improvement?
Interestingly, it's kind of difficult sometimes to get things into conjunctive normal form.
We actually start normally with something like this.
Disjunctive normal form.
And turning one into another is an absolute pain.
Wouldn't it be nice to have a computer do that for you?
So I wrote a function called from DNF.
That converts this one into this one.
And then the translate turns it back into this number.
In other words, it takes something you can understand and turns it into something the
machine can understand.
And so to make this all pico-sat readable, here's a problem input we can understand and
an output we can understand.
That said, it's better to not use variable names like p, q, and r.
How about flat tire, need to remove, and go to gas station?
And here's all of the true conditions.
Is that a little bit better?
So I'm giving you these tools.
I hope you use them.
You can run all of this code.
So I wrote some higher level convenience functions.
Some of says at least one of these is true.
One of says exactly one of these is true.
And a quantifier says the quantity of trues in this case is less than or equal to one.
And it turns out that's a really nice input form because lots of problems fall into that
format.
So I think at every point people get curious about machine learning and solvers.
At some point you write a Sudoku solver.
It's not a difficult thing.
Actually, I'd like to poll here.
How many of you have written a Sudoku solver?
Okay.
Lots of you.
And I wrote one a long time ago.
This is not about that.
I reject my earlier Sudoku solver.
No matter how much effort I put into it, I cannot make it as good as this one.
We have a generic solver that's been polished every year, year after year.
There's conferences where people devote themselves to making small improvements to the underlying
solver.
And if I want to have a good solution to, let's say, a very complex Sudoku, 100 by 100,
which is something that most of your solvers would fail on, all I need to do is describe
the problem, hand it to a really bad-ass solver, and let it make short work of the problem.
So the interesting part is not us writing a Sudoku solver.
Our interesting problem is we describe it and the solver solves it for us.
So this particular puzzle, we can enter it in row major order like this.
That's just my representation.
And our expectation is that the computer will solve it, and this is the answer that it actually
gives.
I think I have five such puzzles in here.
Write down 3, 8.
Sudoku.
Bam.
It takes five puzzles, and here's the input puzzle, and then here's the solution for
it.
I don't know all of the source code for that, but I didn't do any logic on this.
I did none of the things that the rest of us did when we made Sudoku solvers.
Instead, I merely described the problem.
What does the grid look like?
How do we fill it out?
Establish facts about a given point.
Most of this is just converting this input and showing how to output.
This is the repr for it.
So the logic part of it is basically this amount of code.
For each point, we said every point is assigned one value.
You can put one number in a box.
Also, one number only goes in one box.
This is a bijection, a one-to-one relationship.
That describes the puzzle generically.
We have an unconstrained puzzle.
The constraint that we have is for a specific puzzle, we have some clues.
What is it that we already know about this puzzle?
Which numbers go where?
So we established the basic fact.
It takes basically five lines of code to completely describe what a Sudoku is.
It takes another two lines to describe a specific Sudoku and then tell it to solve it is, solve
it.
How do you like that?
Was that a little easier than the Sudoku solver that you wrote?
Keep in mind, unlike the one you wrote and the one unlike the one I wrote, this one scales
to enormously hard problems.
So what's up next is the Einstein puzzle.
Who made it?
Who made this puzzle?
Aha.
None of you fell for it.
Reportedly Albert Einstein made this puzzle, but it is not true.
And reportedly he said less than 2% of the population can solve this puzzle.
This is lore, neither fact is true.
That said, it is a rather famous puzzle.
And let's look at the description of it.
There's five houses in unique colors.
Each person has a unique nationality.
Focus in on the word unique.
That means we're going to use the one of function that we mentioned before.
And there's going to be a bijection here like we did before.
Each one of these values is uniquely assigned to a house.
And so this describes the unconstrained problem.
Now we get the constraints.
The Brit lives in the red house.
The Swede keeps dogs as pets.
The greenhouse owner drinks coffee, et cetera.
And the goal is who keeps the fish.
So there's a really nice write up if you're interested in the problem on how to solve
this problem manually.
Something I'm profoundly uninterested in at this point.
What I'm interested in is getting this answer to pop out automatically.
And this is more than just the answer to this question.
It says exactly where every value is assigned to every house.
So the interesting thing, I think, is how we describe the puzzle.
We say what are the house numbers?
What are the various groups?
You'll recognize that these lines correspond exactly to these lines in the problem description.
All we're doing is translating a problem description into code.
And the constraints, things like the Brit lives in a red house.
That comes next.
And we said same house, Brit in red.
In consecutive house, the White House is after the Green House.
And a specific fact, the milk is found at house three.
Now solve it.
There's really nothing more to it than that.
Is that my first 10 or second 10?
Okay.
Engage warp drive.
All right.
So I had to write a couple helper functions in order to do this.
That just took my one of and from DNF that I mentioned before and gave them nice humanistic
names.
You should always do this.
It isn't hard but it makes your life a lot easier than trying to talk to the tool directly.
It means your problem descriptions are completely humanistic and you can explain the output.
So the utilities you need for that, this is the code that I wrote for you so that you
could write generic solvers.
And if you use this, PicoSat becomes something you can use in the first few minutes.
Otherwise you'll spend two days coding your problem into it and it would have been cheaper
to solve it by hand.
Fair enough?
All right.
We are done with SAT solvers.
But before I leave, I should just say these are really bad ass.
I showed you toy problems.
These scale up to enormous problems.
Imagine this problem with a million variables.
And so where do these problems come up?
So it's used in a conda.
What's the installer?
Conda.
So in conda, conda has to make decisions about what packages conflict with one another and
what their dependencies are.
This is a complex problem when you have lots of packages.
What tool do you think they use to solve it?
It starts with a sat and ends with a ta, has three letters.
They use PicoSat.
They use exactly this technique for a fairly complex real world problem.
Okay, pattern recognition and reinforcement learning.
I can do this one fast.
Problem statement.
I need to get my son to eat broccoli.
He's seven.
It turns out he actually does eat broccoli so this is no longer a problem.
I'm amazed by that.
I didn't eat broccoli until I was my children.
Strategies discussed between Rachel and I.
One, acclimatization.
We can serve it once a week until he gets used to it.
A better alternative.
You know, broccoli is better than spinach.
Or I can entice him.
You know what?
We'll watch your favorite movie after you eat the broccoli.
And if your parents have tried all of these strategies, trickery.
Oh, eat the broccoli.
It's candy.
Testimonial.
Oh, your best friend, Luna.
She likes broccoli.
You like Luna.
Therefore, by the transitive law of likes, you like broccoli.
Weighted up.
Young man, we're not leaving this table until you've eaten your broccoli.
Just try a little bite.
No, not that little.
I didn't know you could eat a bite that soft.
And appeal to reason.
You know, it's a great source of vitamins K and C.
These are all strategies which raises the question, which strategy should we use?
How about we randomly try a strategy and if it works, we choose that strategy more often.
And if it stops working, we choose it less often.
Easy enough?
Aha.
You're taking a picture of my screen.
That means I did a great job making my slides.
But did you know?
I will give you these slides.
All of them.
And not in picture form.
Like you can get, these slides will be in HTML so that you can run the code directly.
That's it.
I'll stand in front of it so you can take a picture later.
There.
You can go pose.
All right.
So I've given you a rock, paper, scissors game here instead of eating broccoli.
We pick a strategy randomly, see if it works.
And the interesting thing about this is I first saw this program in Creative Computing
Magazine over 30 years ago.
And I was amazed by it.
Because rock, paper, scissors is an unwinnable game.
It should just net out to zero.
But what if you can anticipate what your opponent is going to do?
You can do better than average.
Which means you have to pattern match and figure out what has your opponent been doing.
So this game is more interesting when we do repeat play.
So I had some Python skills that I've listed in order to understand the code.
We don't have time to go over them now.
But this will teach you some Python that you might not have known.
How to transpose keys and values.
How to group pairs.
How to use the new random choices function, et cetera.
But essentially we define the game rock, paper, scissors.
Paper beats rock is a one.
And we come up with the ideal response.
What is the winning response?
And our options, what do we have to choose from?
Our strategies are we can choose randomly.
We can choose one thing proportionally.
Let's say rock two thirds of the time.
We can do digraphs.
Whenever a person plays scissors, scissors, you know they're going to do rock next.
So these are a series of strategies.
It doesn't really matter what they are.
You just need a set of them.
The interesting thing is I make a list of them and the algorithm is roughly choose our
move.
How do we choose a move?
We take our strategies and choose one strategy randomly according to the weights.
And the initial weighting is everything is equal weighted.
All strategies are equally good.
Then we find out what the opponent's move does.
So I chose telling my son that it was candy.
And the opponent decides not to eat his broccoli.
So what we need to do is update our move history and strategy weights and say I'm not going
to try the candy trick as much anymore, but I never fully take it off of the list.
This is the entire algorithm for reinforcement learning.
Does it sound impressive?
No.
Anything that you can write in a few lines of code doesn't sound impressive, which is
not to say that it isn't badass.
This thing can learn and beat you at rock, paper, scissors over and over again.
I defy you to do better than average on this.
You will find it's not a fun game to play.
It gets really boring because the computer is really quick.
But you can do a hundred rounds in about five minutes and at the end of that you will find
that as random as you try and be, this I have never seen a person defeat this thing ever.
It will learn your random patterns and figure you out.
Oh wait, Google and Facebook already do that to you.
A lot of what we do now is trying to figure out what other people are going to do.
So this is called a multi-armed branded approach.
It scales to other games like this and it scales to more interesting games.
Everybody got how that one works?
So the next level after this is SMT solvers.
So if you want to sound super technical, you need to know some lingo.
If you know what SMT stands for, you're going to be very popular at Silicon Valley parties.
You know it stands for Satisfiability Modulo Theories.
You're like, wow, can I buy you a drink?
All right, see how that goes.
All right, so I say this is the next step up because we've gone up from a tree searcher
and SAT solvers.
Our state is now more complex than just a truth table and we're searching a graph instead
of a tree and we're introducing temporal logic.
How many of you know about temporal logic?
It should be exactly the people who knew TLA+.
I don't know why I had fewer hands go.
TLA plus is all about temporal logic.
I'm not evaluating my goal status.
Did I get to a goal now?
It's the succession of states.
Do we get a series in a row?
Did I get a chicken and then later did I get an egg?
Did the two come one after another?
So we have goals that say something is always true, something is eventually true, something
is always eventually true and that says it's a reasoning about a succession of states.
So a good example of this is the dining philosophers problem.
How many of you are familiar with dining philosophers?
This is great because my picture for it is not showing up on the screen, but it involves
five philosophers and five chopsticks.
You actually need ten chopsticks, they only have five.
In order to eat food, you need to have two chopsticks.
So the interesting thing is how to model it.
It's very interesting, easy to do the unconstrained model.
Every chopstick is either unused in the hand of the philosopher to the left or in the hand
of the philosopher to the right.
So you can get an entire state by describing it with just five letters.
All five chopsticks are unused, this one is held by the left philosopher, this one is
held by the right.
The number of possible states is three to the fifth power.
Does that sound like a big state space?
It does not sound big, but we're not interested in the states.
We're interested in all possible paths through the state tree.
Now if you know this state, you have an implied state for the philosophers, the philosopher
thinking, eating, or trying to eat.
And so here's our transitions.
If a chopstick is unused, it can be picked up by the left philosopher or by the right
philosopher.
If it's currently in use, it can become unused.
So there are only four transitions out of each state.
So this is like the Sudoku model before we have the clues.
Now the clues are our strategies.
The interesting thing about the dining philosopher problem is most people's first attempt to
solve it always sounds correct but is actually wrong.
It's very educational, and the reason we use it in education is it teaches people how hard
it is to make correct multi-threaded code.
So here is an obvious strategy, which is when you're hungry, pick up the left chopstick.
When the right one becomes available, pick it up.
After you eat, put them back down.
I call this strategy D because it results in deadlock.
This fails.
Strategy S is a really terrible strategy, and it says the first philosopher picks up
the left chopstick and never lets it go.
This causes the person to his left to starve.
Strategy S stands for starve.
That person never eats, which is not a desirable outcome.
Here is the happy strategy.
You can make a request for a chopstick.
This is not the best strategy, but it is one that works, which is when I want to eat, I
put in a request to eat, and we keep a queue of who gets to eat next.
And if you are not next in line, you wait.
And then when your request becomes available, you acquire the left, acquire the right, and
when you're done eating, release both.
This strategy works.
The interesting thing is it is not obvious which of these strategies works and which
one fails.
What we would like is a tool where we input our strategy and it tells us whether it succeeds
all the time, and if it fails, gives us a failing test case.
Does that sound useful?
Have you ever written multithreaded code?
Complex multithreaded code.
How many of you have written complex multithreaded code that's correct?
How many of you wrote complex multithreaded code that was correct and then somebody bypassed
a lock and made it incorrect after the fact?
So how many of you have ever written a complex multithreaded piece of code that you believe
to be correct and has a test suite that can prove that it is always correct?
Oh, then you have a use for this sort of thing.
Because the kind of tool that can verify this for you can also generate all the test cases
that shows all allowable state transitions and you can have your program inform you if
it's ever going to not match the model.
So the interesting thing about these solvers is they have transition graphs.
They say they use temporal operators.
A temporal operator says things like predicate P is eventually true.
Our problem is a person with a left chopstick eventually gets a right one.
Another one is that something is always eventually true.
That is kind of different from the other one.
It says after you eat that someday you might get to eat again.
And more than once.
So here's an example.
The solvers we saw before would look at one of these states and say is this a goal state?
We no longer care about this.
We never actually stop.
This thing doesn't terminate.
The dining philosophers are always eating and thinking.
What's more interesting is this person eats then eventually they get to eat again.
So the temporal logic gets to express if you have this state at this point you get this
other state at another.
You get the time part of the invariant temporal.
This thing was true at one point.
It will become a true again.
All of these things have happened before.
All of these things will happen again.
No Battlestar Galactica fans.
All right.
If you want to feel really mathy you should express it in TLA plus.
It's incredibly mathy.
This is a TLA plus description of the problem.
I've given you a link to a nice write up on it to get started with it.
And a link to how to get started with Microsoft Z3 that also makes short work of this problem.
And what's great is the Z3 pie package lets you get there from Python.
We learned something new.
You're never going to write a complex multi-threaded piece of code ever again where you haven't
model checked it and generated test cases to make sure that it always stays correct.
Oh, so you learned something new and useful.
This is good.
All right.
Next one up is a little bit harder problem.
Learn to play the most complex games known to humans but the input is only the rules
to the game.
So how about I teach my son to play chess by showing him just the moves for the game
and teach him nothing else.
Is that a cruel way to teach a person chess?
But I can use reinforcement learning.
I can just beat him game after game after game.
But my son is smart.
He will observe what I'm doing and learn from his defeats and eventually beat his father.
I know this is true because this is how I learned to play chess.
My father showed me the moves in second grade and beat me game after game after game after
game and I never gave up.
And then in eighth grade, he encountered something he'd never encountered before, defeat.
And it was repeatable.
I got good at it.
I got better than my dad.
Did it take a long time between second grade and eighth grade?
How would we like to compress six years into six hours?
That's Alpha Go.
Or Alpha Zero.
Alpha Zero was kind of cool.
What we proved is how generic it was by we gave it the rules for chess.
Then we gave it the rules for Shogi, which is a computationally more complex game than
chess.
And we've got the lance piece that can move like a knight but an extra one forward.
But also pieces that can switch sides after they're killed and can land anywhere on the
board.
And then Go, which all three of these games, the input to them was simply the rules of
the game.
And in each case, after six to eight hours of training, Alpha Zero learned to beat the
best humans in the world but also the best computer programs in the world.
The best computer programs in the world for chess were custom designed for chess.
This one wasn't custom.
All it knew was the rules.
And it means that there's a broad class of problems that we can solve now simply by describing
the problem.
Keep in mind there was enormous computation power.
Six hours is impressive until you know how much computation power they threw at it.
They threw a lot at it.
So this is a thing of beauty.
This is a typical result.
This is after a few hours, Alpha Zero destroying the best program in the world, which was Stockfish.
It is nice to play this one out.
If you're interested in chess, just move the pieces and you will see a thing of beauty,
possibly the best game of chess ever played.
It's a wonderful thing, which raises a question.
What do we think about this?
Here's two assessments.
In the AlphaGo paper, which I've given you a link to, there's one behind a paywall at
Science Magazine, but they've also got a preprint that's available for free.
They said, our results demonstrate that a general purpose reinforcement learning program
can learn tabula rasa.
That means no inputs at all.
No domain specific knowledge or human knowledge can succeed in multiple domains, many games,
achieving super performance in multiple challenging games in a few hours.
This is pretty badass.
Gary Kasparov had what seems like a self-serving comment on the whole thing.
I love its style of chess.
It plays just like me.
And that seems self-serving, except Gary Kasparov was pretty badass.
And this thing learned to play like a human.
It could set traps for people.
All right.
So I've got a stop sign, but my stop sign says I've got five minutes to stop, which
is great.
I'm actually on time.
This is amazing.
So code you can run.
Is AlphaZero open source?
No.
But Lila chess is.
And the install is using Python 3's Mesa, Mason.
I would say this whole thing is Python 3, but Python is not fast enough.
C is not fast enough.
Can we do better?
What it does is generate a code that runs on your GP.
And this is great.
And so you can go to this link, download it, and start playing chess against the best chess
program in the world using exactly these techniques.
So this is Monte Carlo tree search.
It essentially says let's select a pattern.
Let's run it out to the end of the game, determining a win-loss.
Run multiple simulations, and then back propagate the results, waiting them along the way, saying
this move ended up being a good move.
This ended up being a bad move.
This is almost exactly our reinforcement learning algorithm that I mentioned on the previous
page, but with a tree.
And if you want the full algorithm, this is basically it.
And let's talk about the future.
Where does all of this go?
This is a risky page, because what did Master Yodas tell us?
Difficult to predict the future is always in motion.
That said, we have to ask ourself, does this end badly?
How many of you think it's going to end badly?
There is reason to think that is true.
That however, there is a very deep thinker who has thought deeply about this problem,
a person who has done battle with these machines, a person who has defeated machines initially,
then defeated by one machine, and then routinely defeated by him.
One of the smartest people in the entire world has thought carefully about this problem,
and I love his book.
Garry Kasparov doesn't think this is going to end badly.
I highly recommend his book called Deep Thinking.
It reads like a work of fiction.
It's a real page turner.
It will tell you a lot about AI.
And keep in mind he was one of the brightest of human beings who early on did battle with
a computer and eventually lost to the machine.
And he's got some very deep thoughts on how we're going to interact with these machines
in the future.
Which of our jobs it's going to replace?
How it will help us?
How it will harm us?
How it will adapt?
I think it is a fascinating, wonderful, and great time to be alive.
Thank you so much for coming to this talk.
Please get these slides.
Please run all of this code.
This stuff is ready to use today, and it's not that hard.
Live long and prosper.
Thank you.