.
Sciences, and Eric is a research scientist at Novatis in Cambridge.
So let's start.
Again, if there are still any issues with the setup, please use binder.
Can we get a thumbs up?
Everyone's ready?
Yeah.
Before we start, a bit of housekeeping.
There would be a break at 10.15, a snacks break, and lunch is at 12.20, and we have
power outlets all around, so use them.
There would be a server link for the tutorial, which we'll post later through the tutorial
email.
So before we start, let's just get our gears running.
This is...
We have created a list of dictionaries, right?
So can anyone tell me what would be this function if you want to find persons with the surname
in this data structure?
You don't have to write the code, you just have to tell the idea behind that.
Yeah.
Anyone?
Yes.
That's a perfect answer, yeah.
So in this tutorial, we're going to work a lot with lists and dictionaries.
So by the end of the tutorial, you would be pretty comfortable with working with that.
So just to present how the tutorial is, the logistics of it.
So you see every notebook would have two versions.
One is instructor and one is student.
In the student version, you have exercises.
So if you want to...
I would suggest you actually work on the student notebook version, so you can go and actually
solve the exercises, which is much more fun than just looking what's there.
And if you're stuck, feel free to move to an instructor notebook and see the solution.
That's totally okay.
It's not an exam.
And if I am too slow for you, that is okay, too.
And there is a lot of material in this repository.
You can use this material for a seven or eight hour tutorial.
So feel free to go ahead.
So that's okay, too.
So let's start with the introduction.
So this is a list comprehension.
Can someone tell me what are the plausible data structures for S and my favorite things in this?
S is a string.
Okay.
Yes.
What else?
What are my favorite things?
Yes.
So yeah.
So you could see in here, this one is basically, it's a string.
It's an iterable of dictionaries.
Yeah.
It could be anything with the Dunder Git.
Dunder Git.
Yes.
Yeah.
That's all right.
And in standard data structures, that would be a dictionary.
So before we talk about networks, can someone tell me an example of a real world network
they can think of?
What is the network for you?
Home Wi-Fi.
Home Wi-Fi, yeah.
And what are the nodes and edges in that network, according to you?
Phones and tablets are the nodes in this.
Any other examples of what is a network?
Social networks.
So you have Facebook, Twitter, LinkedIn.
Can someone tell me what's the...
Suppose there is a Facebook social graph and there's a Twitter social graph.
Can you think of a structural difference between a Facebook social graph and a Twitter social
graph?
What's the difference between Facebook?
Suppose I'm friends with you on Facebook.
And suppose I follow you on Twitter.
There is something different between the structure.
Can anyone think of that?
Twitter doesn't have a response to that.
Yes.
So in this case, for Facebook, if I'm friends with someone, they're friends with me back.
So there's no direction in our relationship.
But on Twitter, if I follow some person X, that does not necessarily mean that the person
X follows me back.
So there is a notion of direction in this.
So these are two basic concepts.
Twitter is called a directed graph because you have direction, and Facebook is called
an undirected graph because there's no direction.
And one thing to keep in mind is the information, the heart of a network or a graph is its edges.
Because just by looking at the nodes, they don't give you any special information.
But the way they are connected, that's the whole point of creating a network.
So edges are the most important part of a network.
So we have discussed the examples.
So our hope is by the end of this tutorial, you would be comfortable with using the NetworkX
API, how to manipulate data, how to create networks, how to model them, and how to analyze
them.
You should be able to visualize networks using some basic techniques.
And you would be comfortable with writing some algorithms on using graphs and computing
some network statistics.
And on a more conceptual thing, it's about how to think about network problems and how
to map those interactions and create a network out of it.
In network science research, there's a funny saying that every problem in the world can
be modeled as a network.
I don't necessarily agree with that, but if you think hard enough, you can model everything
as a network.
So that's there.
So reiterating on this, there are student notebooks and instructor notebooks.
If you want to solve the exercises which I recommend, which would be more fun, always
open the student notebooks.
And if you're stuck and if you're too tired right now, if you're jet-lagged, feel free
to follow the instructor notebook too.
That's okay too.
I won't be offended.
And feel free to skip ahead and just go full steam ahead till the end of the tutorial.
So this work has been inspired by a lot of previous different work.
And much of this work is written by Eric in this repository.
And now today he's TAing me.
So the apprentice has become the master now, apparently.
So let's start.
Run at that.
Just to interject a few points, midway through, if there are any issues, just raise your hand.
If you have a question, raise your hand.
I'll come by with a mic.
And I'd really like to encourage people to ask questions for everybody.
And the reason I have a mic is because we want to keep your questions recorded on video
for the benefit of other people who might be watching the tutorial later.
Okay?
Also, this is a tutorial.
This is not a talk.
So please feel free to interject and ask questions.
If you don't want to interject me, that's okay too.
You can raise your hand and ask Eric.
He can solve your problem.
But make sure that this is not a one-way interaction.
And also, that's not a one-way interaction.
Feel free to talk with each other and create a network.
You are the nodes and create new relationships.
See what I did there?
So let's start.
So the basic building block of a network, in this case, are nodes and edges.
Node represents some entity, some person, a train station, a computer.
And edges are the relationship between those things, between those people.
And to understand the API of NetworkX, we will use some data.
This is a very controversial data set.
And we'll get to that later.
So don't kill me for that.
But this is a very controversial data set.
Disclaimer.
But before we do that, let's talk about data representation, how it's represented in NetworkX.
So if you're familiar with Python, if you're familiar enough with Python, you'll see that
this is a dictionary of a dictionary of a dictionary of a dictionary.
It goes all the way down.
So if you have done computer science or mathematics before and you know how graphs are represented,
so you will understand what I'm saying.
But it's a dictionary of a dictionary of a dictionary.
So you need to be comfortable with playing around with dictionary.
And in this notebook, we do that.
So let's load this controversial data set.
So this data set is a friendship data set.
So some researchers went to a seventh grade class and asked a person, who's your best friend?
They said, ta-da.
But what if that person doesn't say that, oh, I say person X is my best friend.
But the person X is like, no, he's not.
He's not.
Person Y is my best friend.
So this is a controversial data set.
So let's see what we can look into this.
So there are some custom loaders in here to load the data set into the graph.
You don't need to worry about that right now.
But if you are interested how they're working, there is a custom folder in the repository
you can look at the code there.
So let's start with some basic statistics.
Like, how many people are there in the graph?
So to access nodes, you use something like g.nodes.
And the only reason we're using NetworkX in this tutorial is because the API is very,
very intuitive.
Like, OK, you need to find the number of nodes in a graph, right?
So we have g, which is a graph object.
We do g.nodes.
You get the number of nodes.
You get something called a node view.
You don't need to worry about that right now.
You just get a list of nodes.
You don't get a list.
You get a view of node.
And you can typecast this to a list to get a list of this.
And if you want to calculate the total number of nodes, you just use the inbuilt length.
So there are 29 nodes in this network.
So far, so good.
So I talked about casting this view as a list because it's a bug or feature, as you may
like, of the NetworkX API as it moves towards 2.0.
Initially, it used to be g.nodes returned a list.
But now it returns a view.
But you can't slice a view.
You can't do this thing.
It will give you an error.
So if you want to select five nodes, then you have to first cast it as a list and then
do the slicing.
010, you have the first 10 nodes.
So this is one thing to keep in mind if you are working with an older version of NetworkX.
So things may break.
So this is one thing to keep in mind.
So the first exercise.
Can you write a single line of code that returns a list?
Can you write a single line of code that returns a number of nodes in the graph?
Well, that was already done.
Once you are done, give me a thumbs up.
Yep.
Oh, thank you.
When you cast nodes to a list and then slice it, are you guaranteed to always get the same
nodes back?
Like, is it ordered or can it be different?
So according to Python, if you are using Python 3.8 or 3.7, order is guaranteed because the
dictionary underneath is ordered by default.
But if you are using an earlier Python 3, then no.
You can't say it's guaranteed.
But again, it depends on the order of insertion.
So if we have the same order, like if you have the same notebook, we'll get the same results.
If you have the same Python and NetworkX.
Everyone done with this exercise?
Finding the number of nodes?
So one way would be just to calculate the length of g.nodes.
And another way is to calculate the length of the graph.
Which is like, these are some concepts from graph theory, which is like a length of a
graph is known as the number of nodes.
So if you do that too, you'll get 29 again.
So now let's figure out the more fun part.
Who is connected to who?
Who thinks you are my best friend?
Who thinks like someone else is my best friend?
So again, just like nodes, very intuitive.
You want to find edges.
So you do g.edges.
You'll get, again, something called an outage view.
Again, don't worry about what outage view is right now.
But you see that you get a series of two tuples in which you have like a starting node and
an ending node.
And suppose you want to just get a sample of nodes.
So we see that one is connected to two, one is connected to three, and so on.
And here one, two, and three, four are people in our seventh grade.
So yeah.
Does the directionality here or the order matter?
Like is one, two, like one said two is my best friend, any other way around, or something
like that, or does it not matter?
In this data set, it matters because it's created as a directed graph, but we'll get
to that later.
In this, it matters.
So exercise number two, can you write a single line of code that returns the number of
relationships, which means the number of edges in this network?
We know how to get g.edges.
So you have to calculate the number of those relationships.
Once you're done, thumbs up.
So just like g.nodes, if you want to calculate the number of edges, we just pass it through
and we'll get the total number of edges in this network.
And everyone got 376.
Yep, yep, yep.
Perfect.
So now we are understanding what's the basic concept here, a network or graph.
So the fight between network and graph is if you're doing mathematics, you'll say graph
because it comes from graph theory.
And if you're doing data science, you'll use the word network because that's network
science.
So it's the same thing.
It's not a different thing.
And conceptually, it's a set of nodes which are joined by a set of edges.
And for the representation, a node list can be represented as a two-tuple where the first
element is the node itself and the second element contains metadata about the node.
Can anyone think of metadata in this network?
We know every node is a student.
What could be a metadata about every student?
Yep, we have name.
Yep, we can have the name.
What else?
Physical address.
Yeah, physical address.
So we can have a lot of metadata about the node itself.
And just like that, even with an edge, we can have metadata about that too.
So an edge is a three-tuple.
You have a start or an end, like where the edge starts, where the edge ends, and data
about that edge, metadata about that edge.
Can anyone think of the metadata about the edge?
What could be an example metadata in this dataset?
Yep, how strong the friendship is.
So we do have something like that in this dataset.
We'll look at that.
You had a question?
Question.
Is the number of edges associated to a node always going to be included in the metadata
of a node?
Likewise, is the direction of an edge counted as metadata for that edge?
That is data related to the node, but that's not exactly metadata because you can just
count the number of neighbors.
You can just count the number of neighbors and then you have that information.
But that is kind of metadata about the node too.
I think that's a good point in that there's computable properties of a node and then there's
just intrinsic properties of a node.
And the intrinsic ones are the ones we can't compute on the fly from the graph.
So number of neighbors, yes, it's metadata, but it's the kind that you can just compute
directly.
Whereas in this case, what's the name of the student?
That's intrinsic to the node.
So the graph we loaded in, it had a lot of metadata too.
So to look at that, you need to pass in this argument data equals true.
So if you don't do this, we'll get something like this, just a list of nodes.
But if we do pass in data equals true, we'll get the biological sex of the student in the
class.
So you have gender for every node.
And if you look at the data structure, it's again, it's a two-tuple.
You have the node and then you have a dictionary which has information about that node.
You can have multiple attributes, right?
So that's why it's a dictionary.
So you can have gender, you can have their name, where do they live, and many other things.
So let's do an exercise again.
Can you count the number of males and females in this network using the things that we know
right now and your Pythonic knowledge?
Just to give you a bigger overview, this is our data set.
So we have 1 to 29.
Some are male, some are female.
The exercise is to count the number of males and females in our data.
You have three minutes for this and once you're done, give me a thumbs up.
And again, if I'm slow for you, feel free to go ahead and there are a lot of exercises to do.
Okay.
Just wanted to check.
No one is stuck with the setup, right?
Yeah, you are.
Can you?
Okay.
People done with the exercise?
Thumbs up.
So does everyone get 17 females and 12 males?
Yep.
This is what you should get.
And this is my answer of doing it.
I use a counter object.
This is not the only way of doing it.
There are a lot of other ways of doing it.
But until you are getting the final answer, that's more than perfect.
So just like nodes, edges too can have this attribute dictionary.
And in this data set, every student was asked a series of questions.
And they were asked to pick up who is your best friend in this case or something like that.
Who is your best friend in this case, in that case?
So you have this thing called count.
The number of times one chose two is one.
The number of times one chose six is three.
And it's always between one and three for some reason.
I'm not sure why, but that's the data.
So can you figure out the maximum time any student has rated any other student as their favorite?
The answer should be three.
So again, to reiterate the exercise, you basically need to find the maximum of this dictionary
all through the data set.
If I check the full output of this thing, I have count dictionary in every edge.
And I have to find the maximum of count in this list.
Again, you have three minutes for that.
And once you are done, please give me a thumbs up.
For those of you who might be a little bit confused, if it's the first time you've seen
assertions in a function, that's a test.
Tests are good.
We can talk about them for all day long.
But basically, you won't see any output.
If your function is correct, you won't see any output.
Only if your function is wrong, then the assertion will fail and there will be a big error.
Okay.
Thumbs up if you're done with the exercise and you got three.
Perfect.
Again, in our answer, we use a lot of list comprehensions because, come on, it looks
very nice and neat.
It's the Pythonic way of doing these things.
But even if you're doing it without using these fancy list comprehensions, that's okay
too.
But we hope by the end of the tutorial, you are convinced that list comprehensions are
a good thing.
Okay.
So let's say if you're trying to replicate this in a production environment, network
environment, like say data center or Internet Edge.
So using this module or dictionary, we can call it how many devices we have in the node
which are active and pulling back to us.
I'm trying to correlate this to the real world scenario for network analysis.
Let's say for network analysis.
If you want to do some analysis for the data center, for XYZ, like an issue or whatever
it may be.
So how do we correlate this module or function to the real time?
If you have like 100,000 nodes, you can work with this thing.
But as soon as you go to a couple of million nodes, in that case, what matters a lot is
how you model the network.
Like what kind of metadata you are putting on the edges and the nodes.
So once you have a network problem.
So let's do another exercise.
When people did this survey, they basically missed out two people.
So let's add those people in this network.
How to do that is basically you can go through the documentation of network X out here.
The function is gaddNode, which basically adds a node.
And gaddEdge adds an edge.
So in this exercise, you have to add a new relationship between a male which is named
30 and a female which is named 31 and the other individual 7.
These three people are besties.
So whenever you ask a question, who's your best friend, they'll be like, oh, 31.
And 31 will be like, oh, no, 30.
And if you ask the same question to 7, it's like a bestie triangle.
And you have to model that.
So basically, in this, you have to add nodes and add edges.
And if you want to understand, if you have any doubt with the syntax, you can check out
this thing here.
You can check out the documentation of network X, which introduces everything perfectly.
And once you are done with this thing, thumbs up.
Yep.
So if we didn't already have g instantiated, could we do this?
Could we do g.addNodes from scratch to create a network?
No, no, no.
You need to instantiate the graph object.
Then you can add whatever you want.
But for example, you don't need to add nodes to add edges.
Like suppose if you just did addEdge 30, 31 count 3, it would add 30 and 31 as nodes.
But it won't add the metadata, gender.
But you need to create a graph object first to manipulate that.
So I noticed that when you're adding edges, it's unidirectional.
Is there a bidirectional way to add edges?
Yes, there is.
So just to show you that, if we do something, if we take the type of g, you see it's a directed
graph.
So it's like a diagram is directed graph.
And in this case, if you want to add edges which goes both directions, you need to add
an edge which goes from 1 to 2 and 2 to 1.
But if you want to add edges which are without direction, there is something else called
just a graph.
And we look at those later.
But in this, because...
A nice API addition to NetworkX might be, if you want to PR, would be to automatically
add bidirectional edges.
So add bidirectional edge or something.
I have to wait on something called hybrid network.
Because you have directional less edges and you have directional edges too.
But no one could actually come to consensus how to implement this.
So that is the problem right now.
But if you want to go ahead, I think there's a PR open with hybrid.
So basically you're asking questions to the...
Last three questions, the student will reply three times that this is my best friend.
One, two, three.
So the count thing basically comes from the way that the data were generated.
So I noticed you talked about it as like a keyword argument to the add edge method,
right?
And so that...
What NetworkX does is it actually collects all of the keyword arguments that are passed
into add edge and it adds them as dictionary keys for the metadata.
So count is not by no means like a fixed keyword argument.
You can add anything you want.
So if you look at the signature of the function, it's like the starting edge, the end of edge
and just...
You can pass in any keyword you want.
It's a weight on the edges.
Just a reminder, if you want to ask a question, please raise your hand and I'll bring the
mic over.
Thumbs up if you are done with this thing.
Add node, add edge.
Once you're done with that, verify that whatever you have done is right.
How do you do that?
What?
Because I didn't run this.
Yep.
People with the thumbs up, did you get all tests passed?
So this is the answer flashing on the screen.
So it's again, add node and add edges.
And you can create a loop to do this too.
You can create a permutation of three and shift routine them if you are feeling fancy
today.
But I just did this.
And let's just take a detour and actually look at the graph structure.
So suppose I pass in...
Because it's a dictionary, right?
If you access dictionary, how do you do that?
Let's use square brackets.
So if we do G1, you see you get this thing called Atlas view.
Again, ignore view for the time being.
You see that it's kind of a view of dictionaries, right?
So once you pass in G1, too, you have one, right?
Which gives us the metadata of the edge 1, 2.
Suppose I pass in 2, 1.
In this case, there is a bidirectional edge.
But when you're talking about directed networks, suppose this thing exists, G1 to exist, that
does not necessarily mean that G2, 1 will also exist.
So in this case, it exists.
But that's just by incident.
Again, an API note.
If you are using 2.0 and later, both of these ways of accessing the weight or the attribute
will work.
But this is the...
Oh, yeah, sorry.
But this is the more Pythonic way now.
So if you're creating a new application which depends on NetworkX, so use this.
Because I'm pretty sure this wouldn't be deprecated in the future anytime soon.
But if you are writing new code, use something like this, which is the new way of writing
NetworkX code.
We won't do this exercise, but this is for break time.
If you are done with your coffee fast, you can do this.
The controversial part of this data set.
Let's try to find out unrequited friendships.
I always say, oh, you are my best friend.
But that person is like, no, sorry.
So basically, you need to find these friendships.
And you can do this later in the break.
There are solutions to this if you want to check out.
And talking about tests, again, as Eric mentioned, tests are something which are used a lot in
software engineering.
You have test development and stuff, but there isn't enough momentum behind testing in data
science.
So it's always nice to have, like always test your data, not just your code.
Just test your data.
Like if someone gives you data, just actually check it.
It has what it says.
It can happen.
You never know.
Sorry?
We'll have the break later.
Once we'll have the break.
It's at 10.15, so it's like 25 minutes from now.
So, yeah, so this is iteration over list comprehensions.
Like this is the way of, this is the Pythonic way of doing that.
You can see this in your notebooks.
So let's take a detour and talk about drawing graphs.
So if we just try to plot our graph that we had, what do you see?
Do you see this beautiful picture?
What do you think of this beautiful picture?
Yeah, chaos, spaghetti, or hairballs.
So, I mean, again, like you don't get, or you get some information about these.
These are probably the 30, 31, and 71, that triplet of besties.
But you don't get a lot of information from this standard pictorial representation of
a network.
And so the rule of thumb is that if you have 20, 25 sparsely connected nodes, like if you
don't have a lot of connections, then you can have a picture like this, which actually
gives you information about the network.
But if you have like 100 or even millions of nodes, you won't get a lot of information
out of the visualization.
So this just happened like last week.
Someone tweeted that, oh, I need to visualize 20 million nodes and 80 million edges.
I'm like, I mean, yeah, like, okay.
So a lot of people are like, oh, cool, nice.
But if you just count the number of pixels in your screen, they're less than the number
of nodes.
So you can't really visualize it just by plotting it like this.
You need to do something more.
You need to do something with the data first and then visualize it.
So if you want to do that, if you have 20 or a billion nodes, a very standard way is
actually to compress the nodes into clusters of nodes and then try to represent the results
of the relationship between clusters.
I think we will discuss that later in the tutorial.
This doesn't give you information.
So you would argue because you don't know anything about the nodes.
Let's even add the name of the nodes.
Still, it doesn't give you anything except the bestie relationship.
This will always be there.
It doesn't matter your plot.
There are other ways of plotting a network.
So one of them is the matrix plot.
And this is my favorite plot because this comes from the representation of a network.
A network can be represented by an adjacency matrix.
People who have done computer science or maths, they'll know what I'm talking about.
But if you don't know what an adjacency matrix is, it's like you create a matrix and you
have a number.
So this is our matrix.
So if one is connected to two, these are number 1 to 29, 1 to 31 in our case, 1 to 31, 1,
2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, till 31.
And if one and two are connected, you'll have a number here.
So there is something in the matrix.
And if they are not connected, you have zeros.
So this is our matrix plot, which comes up from this.
So can someone say anything about this matrix plot?
Do you see anything interesting in this plot?
No diagonal, yeah?
What does that mean?
So diagonal is what?
Yeah, so that's a good thing, right?
So no student said, oh, I'm my best friend.
So that's good, I guess.
Our society still has hope.
And any other thing that we can see from this matrix?
Yes, it's not symmetrical.
Because this is a directed graph, you're not guaranteed symmetry in a directed graph.
But if it were an indirect graph, you would see that this matrix is always symmetrical.
Another thing that I like to do with this plot is, you can kind of create QR codes with
this graphs, because this looks like something like a QR code, right?
So you can create random graphs, and using those random graphs, you can create random QRs.
So if you want to waste two hours of your life, try doing that.
It's fun.
So let's talk about something called an arc plot.
I don't use these plots a lot, but Eric swears by them.
They look very nice.
They do look very nice.
The idea is that instead of worrying about just plotting nodes and just trying to draw edges,
worry more about the position of nodes, how nodes are positioned.
And once you have that figured out, the edges will flow from that.
So in this you can see that you have, first you have grouped nodes,
like you have females and males grouped separately,
and then they are also in a descending order of how connected the graph is.
If you have a lot of different connections for a node, you are at the top of this chain.
So it gives you more information, especially than this hairball, right?
You have more information, and you can actually go show these to people,
and say, this is our graph and this is what's happening here.
Circus plot is arc plot, but joined.
And again, this looks perfect, right?
If you want to sell something, this is what you show.
So all of these visualizations are not in NetworkX.
NetworkX is not a visualization library.
They have an Nx.draw, which does the work, but they are not a visualization library.
There are other options.
One of them is NxVis, which is written by Eric here.
It's a nice library if you want plots like this.
And then there are, I think in the Python ecosystem, you can use Bokeh.
You can use, I think even Dask has something now to visualize.
Oh yeah, they use Pygraph vis.
So there's Pygraph vis, there's Bokeh.
And if you are okay with moving out of the Python world,
there's something called Geffi, which is used a lot by people, at least in academia,
to make graphs.
But again, like, oh yeah, this is one of my favorite plots.
It's called a Hive plot.
It's really nice because it gives you relationships between the nodes in a group
and the relation between the group.
So for example, these are male students.
These are also male students.
This is just a copy of those students.
And this is how they are connected inside the group,
how males are connected to males.
And this is how males are connected to females.
And you'll see you have a bunch of popular fellas with the females.
And you don't see that in females.
It seems like it's evenly distributed all across females.
So that's an interesting observation too.
So let's now move to notebook three.
It's 9.56.
It breaks at 10.15.
If the snacks are not out, we'll just introduce this notebook and then we'll go for snacks.
In this we'll use a dataset from socio-patterns.
Add a chip to your lanyard or something.
And you're just going, talking to people.
If you're talking to people for 30 seconds, there's an edge connected between them.
So this is how you created this network of people.
How people talk to each other.
How they interact in a room.
How they interact in a conference or something.
So that's how they created this dataset.
So the idea is how infections can spread through people.
These are just hypotheticals.
Suppose you need 30 seconds for a virus from person A to spread to person B.
So stay away and how to model that.
So let's load in the dataset.
And let's check what's there in the dataset.
So we have around 400 nodes in the dataset and 2700 edges.
Let's talk about analyzing the network.
Till now we just had a look at the description of the network.
How many nodes, how many edges, how do they look like.
But this is where the fun begins now.
How do we evaluate important nodes?
For example in Twitter, right?
Who do you think is important?
Is John Musk important?
Is he important?
I don't know, maybe he is.
Suppose we are just looking at the Twitter network itself.
Followers.
One way of looking at it is just calculate the number of followers.
So this person has 20 million followers.
This person must be an important person.
It makes sense.
So this is how any sane person would say.
If you go to a person who doesn't know what network science is,
and they are like, who is the most important person on Twitter?
Just count the followers.
That makes sense.
There is nothing wrong with that.
So instead of followers we count number of neighbors.
So basically neighbors is like the number of nodes a node is connected to.
That's the neighbors.
So let's just...
Let's just say that we have a number of neighbors.
So let's just say that we have a number of neighbors.
What is the number of neighbors?
Here I go the timepiece.
So what we can do is we can go to the manager my name is Shavir.
Thank you!
We've been trying to get more people involved with our videoided Zen methods,
all through Japan.
We have been trying to get more people involved with our videoided Zen methods,
with the
community of Japan.
And I think we need to start slowly but surely
of neighbors in our case.
So let's create a ranked list of who is the most important node
in this network.
So we have this network G, which we know here.
And we calculate the neighbors for,
so basically the idea is to calculate the neighbors
for every node and find the maximum of that.
You do that, or the better way to get a ranked list,
who is the most important one?
And once you are done, please give me a thumbs up.
Thank you.
If someone's done, can someone tell me the answer?
Who is the most important node in this network?
51.
So we know what the network is.
It's how people interact in a conference.
So what can we say about the node 51?
What kind of person is node 51?
Maybe, yeah, an extrovert.
And in a case of a flu outbreak, what do you do with 51?
You stay away from 51.
Thumbs up if you're done.
As you can see on the screen, I have the answers flashing up,
because again, there is no one way of doing it.
So you can create a data frame and then try to figure this out.
Or you can use the sorted function to solve this.
And you can just create a list and then sort it.
You can use whatever you fancy.
And again, there is no one right answer.
So we used our basic approach of counting followers, right?
Because that would make sense.
Just count the total number of neighbors.
Whichever has the highest one should be an important node
or an important person in this network.
So now let's talk something about degree centrality.
Degree centrality is nothing but a fancier name for a number of neighbors.
So what it gives you is it gives you a normalized version of number of neighbors.
So degree centrality is the number of nodes you are connected to divided
by the number of nodes you can connect to.
So suppose you have 100 nodes in a network.
How many nodes can I connect to?
Anyone?
Sorry?
I have 100 nodes in the network.
How many nodes can I connect to?
99, yes.
Assuming we don't allow for self loops, right?
We don't have any narcissists in our thing that they'll just talk to themselves.
They're like, oh, yeah.
So we have that number n minus 1.
That's the denominator.
And we know the numerator is the number of nodes you're connected to,
which is whatever the number of nodes you're connected to.
So again, degree centrality is just a fancy way of saying count the total number
of neighbors.
And it will give you a normalized version.
And if you sum everything, you'll get one.
If you sum all the degree centralities, you'll get one.
Yeah, you should, yeah.
And so to do that, again, networkX gives us a nice little function called
nx.degreeCentrality.
You pass in a graph.
It will give you a nice looking dictionary, which is keyed by the node,
and a nice little float, which is the degree centrality.
So if we just look at any five, we get this thing.
I don't think we'll do this exercise after the break.
But does anyone know what is ecdf?
Anyone?
You can tell me.
Testing.
My favorite chart, the empirical cumulative distribution function,
I think, just shows you like.
I think those are the best ones.
I love that chart.
I think I love that too.
So instead of using this program, we can do something called an ecdf.
It's a very, not a very obscure concept, but not a lot of people do it.
And apparently, a lot of people should use it.
So we will do that later.
But in this exercise, you have to calculate the start right now.
And then you can just go straight and come back.
You have to create an ecdf of the distribution of the degree centrality.
And then compare the plots of these two and make sure that it's an actual straight line.
Because as I said, degree centrality is exactly what number of neighbors is.
So you should end up with something like this, a plot for degree centrality
versus number of neighbors.
Yes.
Yeah.
Could you just real quick explain the whole it has to sum up to zero thing?
Because it doesn't seem intuitive to me.
Like if you and I are both best friends with 90% of people in the room,
I don't understand how the degree centrality would sum to one, conceptually.
OK, suppose n minus 1.
n minus 1 is our base, right?
If I'm friends with you, if everyone is friends with n minus 1.
I think it wouldn't also.
It wouldn't sum up to one.
It shouldn't sum up to one.
And wait.
I need to think about this.
So yeah, we can talk about this in the break.
And I think we can take the break now.
Yep, yep.
So I think we can take the break now.
So I think we meet at 10.20, 10.25.
So let's be back by 10.25.
And if you come back early, just start working on the exercise.
There are snacks out there, so have fun.
Back.
I hope you had a good snack and coffee break.
So you can start working on this exercise.
And if you're not very familiar with matplotlib, it's OK.
Just open the instructor notebook, and you can get what's happening here.
You need to be familiar with matplotlib for this exercise.
And once you're done, give me a thumbs up.
And this is what you should end up with, a plot looking like this
for degree centrality, a very similar plot for number of neighbors,
and this straight line plot.
Somebody mentioned that you use these instead of histograms.
I vaguely remember this in college.
If it's straighter, the line, the more normally distributed it is, or no?
OK.
How do you read this?
I imagine you'll probably get it.
OK, I'm going to do my spiel on ECDFs, OK?
All right.
ECDFs are really cool, because they tell you more information than a histogram.
You can read off much, much more information than a histogram.
The only thing is that people are not used to it.
That's it, OK?
So let me give a bit of a demo, OK?
We got this ECDF up here.
On the x-axis, you have values that your data points take on.
And on the y-axis, we're showing the cumulative number of points
that are smaller than any particular value inside the data set, OK?
So a number of things are immediately, like, you can read it off.
You can read off the median.
If you draw a line from the 50th percentile over onto the curve, or the dots,
and then you project back down, you can see what the median is straight away.
And because you can read off percentiles so easily,
you can read off interquartile ranges.
You can read off the 25th to 75th percentile very easily.
You can even read off, like, the minimum and maximum.
So actually, Mriddle, can you change this to plt.hist?
So, and I think it's just degree centralities,
just plt.hist degree centralities.
Misspelled degree.
Whoopsie.
It probably needs to be run first.
Oh, yeah. Whoops.
Try reading off the median from there.
Try reading off the interquartile range from there.
You can't.
One of the big problems about histograms is you have binning bias.
If you change bins to like that, oh, oh, suddenly, yeah, we got, like, three outliers,
potentially three outliers.
But did we know that if we used the default settings?
No. Do people change default settings?
No. Sometimes. No. Rarely.
Yeah, yeah, you get something like this.
Now, what's going on there, right?
Use an eCDF, right?
And bring it back to your institutions, like, eCDFs give you the same information as a histogram,
just richer, just richer.
And in fact, bimodality is what some people are used to looking at, two humps in the data set.
If you've got strong bimodality, you'll see that inside the eCDF,
in that you'll see a middle plateau and then a second plateau.
If you have trimodality, you'll see three plateaus.
If you can't see plateaus, you don't have bimodality no matter what your histogram says.
Okay? Cool? All right.
And coming back to the normal thing, if you have a normal distribution, you'll get a perfect S.
A perfect S, which, and a perfect, like, bimodally you have, like, perfect S with a...
If you do a lot of the degree centralities, is it the same deal where you should expect an S for normality or no?
So if you simply log transform the X values, that still might not necessarily get you to,
that might not necessarily get you to normality. We can try.
For normality, like, if you have a normally distributed degree,
the log-log plot will also be a normally distributed degree.
And if you have an exponential decay, then you'll get a straight line.
What are the purposes of doing the log of this?
So at least, like, the log-log plot is, so basically, I think what the reason was is,
so there was this theory of preference, of how networks grow,
how the degree is distributed all around the network, and that followed a decaying power law,
which is this decaying exponential function.
And if you take the log-log plot of that, you get a straight line.
So I think the idea comes up from, like, it's a test.
If you get a straight line in a log-log plot, it's a scale-free network.
So I think we'll discuss that, like, for a bit later.
So this is what you should get in the plot. And let's just discuss this plot for a bit.
Like, as Eric mentioned, like, the 50th percentile, so 50th percentile goes to, like, 0.03.
So we can say that the degree of centrality of 50 percent of the nodes is less than 0.03.
Like, then if we go up, like, the degree of centrality of 0.95, like, 95 percent of the nodes is less than 0.08.
So we are getting something here. Like, you know, 95 percent of the nodes are very sparsely connected.
They're not connected to a lot of other people because they have a very low degree centrality.
And you have these three, not outliers, exactly, but you have these three people in this network
which are connected to a lot of other people.
So what does this tell us about the real world? Like, does this mirror your expectations?
Like, for example, in Twitter, right, like, you don't have, not everyone has 20 or 30 million followers.
Majority of the people would have 100 or 200 followers. But you will have these three, these three people are like, you know,
I don't know. I think Shakira has the most followers. Who has the most followers? I don't know.
I think, I know a female pop artist has the most number of followers on Twitter. So these are those artists.
No, no, no. Kardashian is a US thing, thankfully.
Yeah. So if you look at the degree centrality ECDF and the number of neighbors ECDF, it looks similar.
But it's not just similar. It's the exact same plot because degree centrality is just a normalized version of number of neighbors.
And if you would plot the XY plot, you'll get a straight line, the relationship between degree centrality and number of neighbors.
This is as expected. So this is an exercise, but we won't do this.
Let's just look at the circus plot of this. And now we'll see why having a plot like this makes sense.
So the first thought of this picture, this looks like a nice pretty picture, right? Yeah. Everything works.
And if you look at, like these are the nodes because this is a circle, circle plots.
And this represents the incoming time because this is an event, right?
And we have information about when every node or every person enters into this conference.
So like it goes in an anti-clockwise direction. This is increasing time. This bar is increasing time.
So what can we infer from this? Anyone? This is a plot between interactions.
These are the nodes with an increasing time order. Can we infer anything?
Look at this space in the middle. What can we infer from this?
It looks like people like lunchtime because you get a lot of activity. I mean, I assume this is one day.
So what I see is that at the beginning, there's not as many. At the very end, there's not as many because that's like the left hand side.
Not as many. It's not as dark, which I assume is representative of the number of interactions. You see a lot more on the far right.
But so like let me make that clear again. So this is node three, which enters at a certain time.
This is suppose node 20, which enters at a certain time. If there is a link between them, it means they had an interaction.
Like you're like that makes sense. You know, people, if it's if it's darker, people are interacting more. That's perfect.
But there is another interesting thing that we can take out of this plot.
So that people are mostly interacting with people who came in at a very similar time.
Yes, as you can see, like if you come at 8 a.m., you're just interacting with the people who came in.
I think this interaction goes up to maybe like 10 or 12.
So you are interacting with the interacting with the people who came in at this at a similar time as you.
So if that wasn't the case, you would see a lot of you see a lot of connections in this middle.
So this is one of the reasons like, you know, choosing a correct visualization is important.
Like if you if you just plotted this on our annexed or draw like, you know, yeah, good luck with that.
Good luck with that. Try inferring that from a hairball. Good luck with that.
So this is again one of the reasons why visualization is important and choosing the right visualization is important.
So let's move on to another concept in network science of graph theory is parts.
And in my opinion, this is one of the one of the most useful and one of the most important part of networks is graph.
Graph, graph traversal, like suppose I suppose talking about this social pattern network, suppose I tell a person X something.
How much time will it take to like how does things spread in this network?
Right. If I know the path from this person to every other person in the network, I can I can try to model these things.
This is one of the reasons graph graph traversal is important.
I mean, even Google Maps that I assume a lot of people use here is is basic problem graph traversal.
And you can actually create your own Google Maps or Jupyter Notebook.
If you want to know that, meet me after the after the tutorial.
I was kind of working on that. So let's let's talk about shortest path.
Like they're like going from point A to point B, there are multiple paths possible.
Right. But one thing that we are very interested in is finding the shortest path because that's sometimes a good thing.
And sometimes you're not. But sometimes that is what we're interested in.
And if you remember from your college days or assuming if you have done computer science or math,
there is something called Brett BFS, Brett for search and depth for search.
These are standard algorithms to find the shortest path in a in a network.
So the basic idea is that suppose I want to find the shortest path between me and let's suppose we are in the Facebook social network, right?
Where every node is a user like I'm a user of Facebook.
So I'm a node in the Facebook social network and every friendship is an edge.
So suppose I want to find the shortest path from me to Mark Zuckerberg.
Right. So basically I'll start jumping. So I look into my neighborhood.
I look to my friends. I go to every neighborhood and then ask, are you friends with Mark Zuckerberg?
Are you friends with Mark Zuckerberg? Are you friends? I do this for all of my friends.
If I don't get an answer, yes, then I'll jump in my friends of friends, assuming I have access to all that data.
Then I'll ask everyone. So basically you keep on expanding your neighborhood search with degree one, degree two.
But in this case, I mean how far I'm going from my initial set.
And this is how you find your like this is how I find the shortest path between me and Zuckerberg on Facebook.
So talking about this, does anyone know about six degrees of separation?
Can someone tell me that?
It's the concept that if you have any two people, they should be connected by at least like through a path of sex.
So I think it was some like some sociologists came up with this in like 80s or 90s that it's called a small world theory that we live in a very small world that I can jump from one person to any other person in this world in less than six steps on average and on average being the keyword term here.
So I think so Facebook is the largest known social network of the world, right?
Well, there is one sort of friendship and knowing each other.
So I think they ran this couple of years back when they had one point three one point six billion people and they found out the average shortest path.
The degrees of separation is three point eight on Facebook.
So and that's a very interesting fact, right?
That within four jumps within three point eight jumps, I can reach anyone on Facebook.
Like like if I'm friends with you, you are friends with someone else in this like Dustin, like four jumps.
I can reach to anyone in the in Facebook and Facebook has one point six billion people at that time.
And when they did this, they actually release a tool where you could see your personal listing, not just average your personal shortest path length.
That if I am here, like how many jumps will I take?
And I think for me it was three point nine and for Zuckerberg it was three point one.
So I mean, I'm pretty it's not three point one for him.
It's one. But that's a different story.
But but they have removed that tool now.
So oops, oops, you can't you can't use that anymore.
So coming back to shortest path.
So this is a basic idea behind BFS to and BFS.
It's called breadth first search.
So in this you suppose you are a node, you start looking at the neighbors of the node.
Does my destination exist in the neighborhood?
If no, then I look at the neighborhood of every node in my neighborhood.
You just keep on doing that.
If you implement this, you can implement this in a recursive way.
And like it's an exercise in the notebook, but we won't do it because it can take a lot of time.
So let's just go through that.
And the funny thing is the thing that we asked you to implement in the notebook is already present in NetworkX.
So you don't actually need to do that.
So suppose you want to find that does is there a path between node 400 and node one?
It gives you true.
This does not necessarily mean that 400 is connected to one.
This means that there is a way of going from 400 to one.
Somehow by jumping around the network, you can reach one from 400.
And suppose you want to find that path.
How do I reach from 400?
How do I reach to one from 400?
You just do just run this little algorithm.
Not an algorithm.
You just call this function shortest path.
And if you're familiar with graph theory and like graph algorithms, you would know that there are not tens,
but there are a lot of different algorithms to choose how to find the shortest path.
There is BFS, DFS, Dijkstra, A star, a lot of algorithms.
And if you call shortest path, NetworkX will take care of finding the most efficient algorithm for your graph.
And for your use case.
And there's nothing fancy going on behind these.
There are a bunch of heuristics that just always work.
So you don't need to worry about that.
If you don't really care about the implementation, just use shortest path.
And you'll get the shortest path from node one to 400 in this case.
Yes.
How would you figure out what algorithm it's using to get the shortest path?
I think, for example, the heuristic is that if it's a simple graph, which you have no weights, no nothing,
like just nodes and this thing, you use BFS or DFS.
And if you have weights, you start using Dijkstra.
If you have negative weights, you have A star.
So it's just like it will use the simplest algorithm for your graph.
If you don't, as soon as you start complicating your graph, it will use a more complicated algorithm.
What is DFS?
DFS is so breadth first search is like looking into your neighborhood.
In DFS, you go into one way.
I look at one of my friends and then I look at his or her friends.
And I just keep on going in one direction until I reach an end.
And if that end is not my destination, then I retract back.
So that's the idea of DFS.
You go depth first and then breadth you just swim around your neighborhood.
I mean, if you want to, you can implement this exercise after the tutorial to get a better understanding of BFS.
So but let's do this exercise instead.
So in this you have to write a function that extracts the shortest path.
So we know that this function and it's not shortest path gives us the graph rate.
It gives us the part.
It gives us the part that going from one to four hundred and need to take this route.
I jump from one to fifty fifty to one eighty eight to two thirty to three thirty five.
And I reach my destination four hundred.
Now you need to create a new graph which has just this part.
And how to do that?
Use this command cheater subgraph.
If you if you pass in a number of if you pass in a set of nodes cheater subgraph will extract those nodes and its relationship and give you a new graph.
And once you're done, just give me a thumbs up.
And if you're done, try to plot it to like you should get something like this.
Try to plot that graph.
Thumbs up if you're done.
Okay.
Yep.
Thanks.
Is there a reason that running this multiple times gives you different looking graphs each time you run it?
No, it's supposed to do that.
So whenever you call annexed on draw, it will give you a randomly drawn picture.
If you want to fix it, you need to like there are other arguments in the function that you can give in.
So which gives you a fixed answer every time.
But the but the picture is drawn randomly.
So you should get you should get different pictures.
So if you look at this, like if you look at the solution, which is flashing on the screen, we have this check here.
Is it possible to have like is it possible that there is no path in the graph?
If yes, then when?
When is it possible to not have any any part in the graph?
When does that happen?
If your graph is disconnected and you can do different sections.
So it's it's very much possible that your graph is not connected.
We will talk about this later, too.
And so that's why we have this check.
So if there is a path, then create a new graph.
Otherwise, let's say there's an exception.
And if you look at this is our plot, it looks like a straight line.
Is it possible to have a different plot for the subgraph?
Is it possible to have is it possible to have something like you have this line graph and then there is a connection between 90 to 230?
Is it possible?
Not when you're grabbing the shortest path.
Yes, if you're grabbing the shortest path, then as soon as if you have a connection between 90 and 230, it will it will end up taking for 90 to 30 rather than going all the way.
So this is the only possible answer for this subgraph.
And this is if you want to give a name of this, it's called a line graph, which is basically a line.
It's called a line graph.
So again, there are more exercises that you can do at home.
So in this, we basically this is we create a star graph in which we basically look at the neighbors of the graph.
And there are more exercises for home.
So let's go back to hubs and the notion of what is important, what is not important.
We just mentioned one thing like degrees and 30 on neighbors.
Just look at the number of neighbors.
And if if the highest number of neighbors is the most important node, that is what we concluded.
But it's very much possible that that is not the right way of measuring importance.
So can someone think of a way where just by looking at the number of neighbors, it's not the it's not the best way of measuring importance.
What could be any other way of measuring importance in a network?
Yeah.
Like if you have distinct groups and you had people that connect those groups, so they serve as bridging the gap between two otherwise pretty segmented communities, I'd imagine that be an important person.
Exactly.
Exactly. So it's like if there are bottlenecks in the graph, like suppose there are three different groups in a network and you have only one node in the network, which actually like connects to all these groups, even though that node is connected to only three different nodes.
But it connects the whole graph together.
In that case, it's an important node.
You can count it as an important node.
And the funny thing is that there is no whenever someone asks me, how do you measure importance, there is no right answer for that.
It depends what you are trying to measure.
For example, if you're trying to measure the, like, you know, which is the bottleneck in the node, it has a different answer.
If you want to just measure how to spread things in a network, then degree centrality is one of the basic ways of measuring that importance.
So we look into something called betweenness centrality.
And the intuitive definition of betweenness centrality is that I start finding shortest path between all the pairs of nodes in a network.
So I find shortest path for every node, for every pair of node in a network.
And then I try to find the node through which most of these paths go through.
Does this make sense?
I try to find a node through which most of the shortest path in a network go through and which is basically the bottleneck.
Like, every shortest path in the network has to go through that node.
Not every, but most of the shortest path have to go through that node.
And basically, you try to find these nodes.
And as soon as you have these nodes, these are the most important nodes.
To give you a better picture, we'll look at that later.
But before that, let's see how degree centrality and betweenness centrality interplay.
Like, can we say anything about a network?
Suppose a node has high degree centrality.
Can we infer anything about the betweenness centrality using the degree centrality?
Any guesses?
Should we be able to infer degree centrality from betweenness centrality?
Yes, no.
Let's see.
So in this exercise, you basically plot.
In this plot, we plot the degree centrality versus betweenness centrality plot.
And as you see, you can't really say anything about how they are related.
Like, for example, this node has very high degree centrality, but has very low betweenness centrality.
That's the whole point.
The way we are calculating these centrality measures, they are very, very different.
They're very different.
So we can't infer degree centrality from betweenness centrality or the other way around.
So I mean, I think you can, if you try to make a network, you can probably make a network which gives you a straight line.
It is like, degree centrality is always related to betweenness centrality, but you have to over-engineer that network to give you that result.
But in the real world examples, you won't find that.
You won't really find that.
So coming back to how you find bottlenecks, can you come up with an example where a node has very low degree centrality, but very high betweenness centrality?
What would that example look like?
Anyone?
How would that example look like?
I would imagine that it would be like a node that connects two clusters of nodes.
Exactly. Something like this, right?
Yeah.
So in this case, if you measure degree centrality and say, oh, you want to find the most important node, you find the degree centrality and that's our final order.
But according to degree centrality, these two nodes will be the most important nodes because they have the most number of connections.
But according to betweenness centrality, this node will be the most important node, even though it has only two neighbors.
But every path, if you want to go from this cluster to this cluster, you have to pass through this, right?
So if you remove this fella right here, you break apart the network.
But doesn't every one of those paths also have to go through the one on the edge of the top left and the one on the edge of the bottom right?
Like wouldn't those three middle ones all have the same betweenness centrality?
No.
Because, for example, if you start a network from here, it will have that network too, right?
If you want to go from here to here, then you have...
Oh, OK.
In the calculation, it will end up adding those paths too.
Oh, I gotcha. Cool. Thanks.
So, funnily enough, in the eighth notebook, that notebook is about US airports data set and how airports are connected.
So if you run the standard algorithms, which is the most important airport in this data set, if you run betweenness centrality, you get a very interesting result as the most important airport.
Can anyone take a guess which is the most important airport in the US airport directory?
New York?
Yeah, these are the usual guesses that you would make.
But now, according to betweenness centrality, if you look at just the structure of the network, again, I'm emphasizing on structure.
I'm not emphasizing on number of people, number of flights, anything.
If you just look at the structure of the network, Anchorage, Alaska, is the most important node in the network.
And if you want to find an answer for that, I don't think we will be able to cover that in this...
We don't have two parts this time, so you can talk to me later or you can just look at the eighth notebook.
You'll have your answers, what's happening there, why Anchorage is the most important airport.
So moving on to the...
Before we move on, any questions, any doubts, any comments?
Okay, let's...
Is there a question back there?
Sorry, I just wanted to make sure I understand. So this algorithm is based on shortest path?
Yes.
So if the graph was weighted, it's not the number of nodes, it's the shortest path?
You bring in an interesting question. So again, now this depends.
When you're measuring shortest path, how do you define that weight?
Sometimes, for example, in the case of airports, when you recreate this network,
should the number of flights be equal to...
Suppose you have number of flights as a weight. Should we use the weights just like that?
Because suppose there are 100 flights from New York to Chicago, and there are 100 flights from Chicago to San Francisco.
You have 100 flights because these are important routes, right?
And you have only 20 flights from maybe New York to Anchorage or something.
So if we use standard shortest path algorithms, it will penalize routes like New York, Chicago, and Chicago, San Francisco,
because you're giving it high weights. So a way to counter that is to use...
You need to make sure that you're modeling your network correctly, otherwise you'll end up with very wrong results.
So when you're adding weights, things get tricky, so we need to keep a lot of other things in mind.
So thanks for pointing that out.
So let's move to notebook number four, I think.
So till now, we were talking about nodes individually.
Now in this notebook, we'll look at something else.
We'll look at the structure of a network.
We're not really talking about just one node.
We're trying to find local structures.
Is there any interesting thing happening if you look at a cluster of nodes or something like that?
We'll talk about that.
So in this, we work with a data set of the physician trust network.
So I think these are four or five different cities, four different towns in Illinois.
And this is a trust network between physicians, and it was taken in 1966.
So it's like if you go to a physician and they're like, oh, if you want some advice, or if you want to refer someone, who do you refer to?
So that's how this network is created.
And you have this result of four different cities.
And let's create a plot of that.
Can we, like, we have the data.
We made a plot.
What can we say about this plot?
We know that it's from four different cities.
Do we see anything happening here?
Oh, hold on, hold on.
Where's the comment from?
How do you tell which cities are present in the visual?
That's part of the game.
You don't need to know that.
You just need to infer what's happening.
Like, if you look at the structure of this, is there anything special in the structure of this plot?
So it looks like you can almost see the four distinct cities with a very large city being on the very bottom with the well interconnectedness.
And then you can see minor gaps between the other ones.
Yeah, I guess that's the correct inference on this.
Because you can see four different clusters of cities.
I guess because it was 1966, communication wasn't that easy.
I think a family doctor is a more intimate thing.
So you won't just randomly say, oh, no, go talk to that doctor in that town.
So you see that these physician networks are localized to cities.
So that is what we can infer just from putting it out there.
And again, if we plotted the hairball, you wouldn't see anything here.
But with the Circos plot, we can see a clear representation of that.
So let's talk about structures in a graph.
Before structures, let's talk about something called cliques.
I mean, so in a clique, everyone is connected to each other.
It's like an exclusive group or sort of thing.
What is the simplest clique you can think of in a network where everyone is connected to each other?
Everyone is connected to each other.
You just have to pick a set of nodes and everyone is connected to each other.
Which is the simplest clique?
Sorry?
Family?
Yeah, family.
Family is the right answer.
But I'm talking in the sense of networks.
Like you have nodes and edges, which is the most simple clique.
Just like two people that are connected to just each other?
Yes, like an edge.
Just an edge is a clique because there are two people and both are connected to each other.
What is the most simple complex clique?
Anyone?
Three people?
And how would that work out?
A triangle.
Yes.
I was looking for the word triangle.
So you would see that there are triangle formings.
And basically you can build every clique with triangles.
Like if you're looking at four people and all of them are connected to each other,
it's basically a set of one, two, three different triangles.
Four.
It's a set of four different triangles.
So you can build up like the nth clique with triangles.
So that's why we focus on triangles.
Because finding triangles is still a hard problem.
But I think finding maximal cliques is a NP hard problem.
So we won't talk about that.
In this piece of code, what we have implemented is that if given a graph and given a node,
it returns that is that node in a triangle.
What does that mean?
So basically I give you a node and I look at the neighbors of this node.
And once I look at the neighbors of the node and I look, do they have a connection?
If two of my neighbors have an edge between them, they're in a triangle relationship.
Right?
Make sense?
Network gives us a function to calculate the number of triangles.
So this means that node three is in three triangular relationships.
Node one is also in three.
Node two is also.
Apparently all the nodes are in a three triangular relationship.
So exercise time again.
So in this exercise, you have to write a function that takes in a node, that takes in the graph,
and it returns the list of all the other nodes it's in a triangular relationship with.
Just to give you a better intuition again, you start with a node.
You just look at all of its neighbors and you try to find if there are any two neighbors
which have an edge.
As soon as you have that, you have a triangle.
Thumbs up if you're done.
Okay.
So if you look at the answer flashing on the screen, it's again, we check for every neighbor.
We run through a combination and we get a combination of two pairs of all the neighbors
and we check if that pair has an edge between them and if yes, then we add it to our triangular set,
these triangular nodes.
Just to show it pictorially how it works, in this case, three is in a triangular relationship,
42, 67, 41, 9, and 11.
Just to make sure that our answer is right, we also plot all the neighbors.
If you see that these are all the neighbors of node 3 and only these are the triangular relationships
and we get those relationships.
That means our code was right.
Let's talk about a nice important application of these triangles.
It's friend recommendation.
I'm pretty sure it's much more involved than just solving open triangles.
This was the first implementation of recommendations in LinkedIn.
I think that we know.
I'm not sure about Facebook, how they do it, but this is a way of understanding how recommendations work.
Suppose you have an open triangle.
What do I mean by open triangle?
Suppose I have two neighbors and they're not connected to each other.
Maybe they should be.
That's the recommendation we're talking about.
Suppose I have three friends and they're not friends with each other, but they're friends with me.
There is a slight chance that they know each other.
That's the recommendation that maybe these three people also know each other.
That's a very basic recommendation algorithm that you can come up with of how to recommend people in a network.
In this exercise, you have to write a function that identifies the other two nodes which are in an open triangle relationship.
In this exercise, you just have to consider the one in which you are the central node.
Suppose I'm friends with X and X is friends with Y.
You don't have to return that.
I can be friends with Y.
In which you are the central node and there are two friends.
You have to find these open triangles.
The implementation is very similar to the one in which we are finding triangles.
In the triangle zone, we were finding which two nodes are connected.
In this, we have to find which two nodes are not connected because they should be possibly connected.
That's our recommendation algorithm.
Once you're done, thumbs up.
Okay.
Thumbs up if you're done.
So if you look at the code flashing on the screen, instead of looking for nodes which have an edge between them,
we look for nodes which don't have an edge between them and then we add it to our recommendation pile.
So if you look at this thing, so like going back to the data itself,
it means that node three interacted with one and nine, right?
And node three interacted with all these other nodes.
So if node three interacted with node one and nine, so maybe there would be, you can go to node one and say, go talk to node nine.
Maybe you'll have something in common.
Not a sophisticated way, but it may work.
You never know.
So let's quickly talk about cliques.
So again, finding cliques is a very hard problem.
So in this, like when you use this function, we'll find cliques.
It will give you all the cliques in a graph.
It will give you two cliques which are basically like, you know, every edge.
And it will give you, like if you have four nodes in a clique,
which that means that every node is connected to every other node in the graph.
So just to give you a better picture of that, if you look at, this is a clique.
This is a four clique.
This is a six clique where every node is connected to each other.
And it's called a complete graph in graph theory.
So we won't do this exercise.
But in this exercise, we basically write a function to find the maximal clique.
You pass in a size, and I want cliques of only that size.
Now let's talk about connected.
I think there's one really neat point about cliques.
If you have a five clique, it is exactly decomposable into all of its constituent four cliques,
which are exactly decomposable into their constituent triangles,
which are exactly decomposable into their constituent edges.
So all triangles can be described as a set of edges.
All four cliques can be decomposed into three cliques.
And so all k cliques can be decomposed into their k minus 1 cliques down to k equals 3,
where the k minus 1 clique is 2.
And building upon on top of that, this is one of the ways of aggregating information in a network.
Suppose you have a very big network and you want to visualize that.
Instead of printing out every node, you try to find these.
Suppose there are cliques. There are a lot of cliques in the network.
You take that clique, create a meta node of that clique, and then you plot out the network.
So it's one of the ways of aggregating data to find cliques.
And talking about different aggregations, going back to the case where it's not possible to find a path.
You cannot go from node A to node B.
And that's where connected components come into the picture.
So components are these different clusters in a graph in which you cannot go from one cluster to another because they're not connected.
And let's try to find connected components in our graph G.
Oops. This is the physician network.
I was still thinking about the conference network.
So this is our physician network.
And we see that there are four different components.
And this is what we expected.
There are four different cities in the network, in the data set.
And every city is a network in itself.
They don't communicate between cities.
So if you try to plot this out, as you saw in the Circos plot, you have four different parts of the network.
So again, in this, we do the same Circos plot, but we add the notion of what the city is.
And once we have that city, we basically see that the bottom half was our one city.
And we have different colors to signify that.
So this is a prettier Circos plot of the same data.
And yes, and this is the interaction between Democrats and Republicans through the years.
So 1949, 1951.
So let's go to 2011.
So what can we say about the betweenness and variety of these people?
Remember?
Yes.
So who is the most important member of parliament?
That's a British thing.
Member of House of, Senate, Senate, Senator, US Senator.
Who is the most important US Senator according to this network and what we know about network science?
Anyone?
Who is the most US Senator?
Yep.
But again, it depends how you define importance.
In this case, suppose we define importance who can get things done.
Maybe someone who has connections in both sides of the house.
So you would need someone who is somewhere in the middle.
And that person will have a very high betweenness and variety.
So this is one of the real ones.
How to get politics working.
Eric, he has a question.
If you look at some of the charts further up, like 1973, there are a couple Republicans that are so far left that they're, what does that mean?
Does that mean they're more connected with all them than they are with the rest of the world?
Like how do we interpret some red that's penetrating super far to the left or some blue that's penetrating really far to the right in the network?
I'm not sure.
Do you know the answer for that?
Yeah.
So part of this is how we've chosen to visualize the network.
Or not we, but more like New York Times.
Okay.
So this is one of those classic hairballs.
And if I'm intuiting it correctly, this hairball is drawn by a force directed layout so that if you have a very high level of influence,
and if I'm intuiting it correctly, this hairball is drawn by a force directed layout so that if you have an edge between two nodes, there is an attractive force.
And if you're not connected, there's a repulsive force.
And the effect that the effect that force directed layout has is things like this and things like that can be visualized very clearly.
So and also the other part is just so that this is clear, the XY positioning of nodes in a force directed layout carries no meaning.
There is no meaning here.
So it is by convention that red is put to the right and blue is to the left in US politics that might be flipped in another country.
And that is just an artifact of how you just drag the nodes over, the red nodes over, and the rest of it will follow.
And you drag some blue ones over to the left and the rest will follow.
And then okay, now we roughly have them in some orientation that an ordinary person would be familiar with.
So that I want to make very clear.
The XY positioning in this chart inherently only carries meaning because someone decided that red and republicanism and right are put together and left and Democrats and left are put together.
Okay.
Blue.
So now you'll notice that yes, you've got some of those red nodes that are right in the middle and of the divide between the two and the same goes for the blue nodes.
Now, if we were to look at it graph theoretically, thankfully, in a force directed layout, they will match up with our intuition.
So we will have some of these more bipartisan all kind of senators or House of some representatives if this was the House of Reps instead.
Or if we're in the British Parliament, then members of Parliament, right?
People who bridge different political parties as covered as colored by the color that's attached to their nodes.
The force directed layout can help us discover it.
I still, though, would have a preference for making sure that we quantify explicitly how many same group connections I have versus other group connections I have as a node.
And that is the clearest way of visualize of like computing how many by that's the clearest way of computing the by a bipartisan or multi-partisan metric.
And yeah, it's good to visualize it this way.
But I think there might be better ways to do it right like you can do things that you can put all of the you can do this.
The arc plot as an option where you have the or rather.
Sorry, it's not the high plot.
The high plot. Yes, you have the high plots.
And let's say you have three political parties like Canada should write like three.
I'm Canadian. So you have three major political parties.
You put them each on the axis. You clone the axis for inter intra group.
And then you plot the inter group between the two.
Right. And so then that's a much more rational way, I think, of visualizing this.
And then you can compute the metric, the by or multi-partisanal metric and order nodes according to how many times they vote together with a member of another party.
Right. You can order it that way. And that's another great like.
Yeah. So it's a better way, I think, of visualizing than a hairball.
So we have we have 50 more minutes.
And so we have been talking a lot about like, you know, what our networks, what our cliques, what our paths.
So basically we're talking a lot about the theory. Right.
So let's see a real world example of that.
Let's talk about, you know, why this is useful.
And I'm going to give you a very nice reason for that.
The reason network sensors are useful is because we can understand Game of Thrones better.
And so how many of you like Game of Thrones?
OK. OK. Disappointing number. That's OK.
How many of you don't care about Game of Thrones?
That's OK, too. But you have to sit through this.
So. So Game of Thrones is the seventh notebook.
Again, if you want to do the exercise, you open the student one.
If you want to do the you don't want to access, you open the instructor one.
So even if you even if you're not a fan of Game of Thrones, has anyone ever seen this picture before?
So in this picture, again, and so people who are not familiar with Game of Thrones, what Game of Thrones is,
it's a TV show which is based on a set of books and it goes through a fictional fantasy world
where people are fighting each other for, like, you know, for the ultimate, like, you know, who becomes the king or the queen or I don't know.
Yeah, yeah, it's cool. Yeah, maybe.
So so so in this network, this is the interaction network between characters like every all these names of characters on the TV show and in the book.
And so the bigger the font of a net of a node, like, for example, John, Daenerys, Tyrion, it means the more important that node is.
And in this case, they have calculated importance, not by degree, not by between us, but something called PageRank.
Does anyone know what is PageRank? Has anyone heard about PageRank before? Yes.
So PageRank is known as the billion dollar algorithm.
It's behind Google's like it was behind the first Google search search index and it's named after Larry Page and Web Page.
See everything worked out there.
And so so so bigger the font, higher the PageRank.
And the colors you see in this are communities in the network.
We haven't talked about what are communities.
But just to give you a basic intuition is it's someone it's it's kind of like weak components, weak connected components.
It's like you don't have a clear cut difference between different components.
There could be some edges between component one to component two.
But this is a basic intuition behind communities.
It's like you can, you know, force them apart somehow.
And if you are familiar with Game of Thrones, you'll see that you have these communities like you have this purple looking community of people who are close to John.
John Snow, as others would know him.
And you have Daenerys and you have her community.
So you have these you have this nice pictorial representation of how things work in Game of Thrones.
And this is based on the books.
So apparently there are enough differences to make a difference in this final representation.
And I think this is from Book One.
Yeah. So in this in this notebook, we'll go through Book One, Book Two, Book Three, Book Four and Book Five, because we have only five books till now.
And we see that how the notion of importance has changed.
Like, you know, can we predict that?
Not predict, but can we say who's the most important character in Game of Thrones?
Like who should win this battle of battle?
And if you are behind Game of Thrones and you actually like Game of Thrones, I'll make sure that there are no spoilers.
But again, no guarantees.
But I tried hard enough to make sure that there are no spoilers.
So let's start.
So we read in.
Let's have a look at the data.
So in this, this is a Pandas data frame.
And we so you have a source, you have a target, you have this type thing and you have a weight and a book.
The type is the type is a pretty much useless column in this because all the networks are enacted in this in this in this network.
And even source and target does not make sense in an undirected network because it's not a source going towards the target because the connection goes both ways because it's an undirected network.
And the weight comes into the picture.
Weight is the number of interactions in that book.
So and the way they define interactions is is if if two characters are in a are in a neighborhood of 15 words, this is created from the book, not from the TV show.
If two characters are in a neighborhood of 15 words, like their name is mentioned, then there's an edge between them.
This is not the best way of making it this.
I'm not even saying this, but this is OK enough a way of making it to get some actual results.
And we'll see that, you know, this actually works of creating a character network.
So let's create five different graphs, one for each book.
So we have.
Yep.
Question.
Wanted to seize on this real quick because we're looking at the base data.
A lot of us are going to have super unclean data that's not already packaged in network formats.
Is there a best practice that you recommend when you're trying to just create a network from scratch?
And is it like if it's directed, then this is what the data structure should look like.
And if it's undirected, then this is what it should look like.
I mean, it depends on your it depends how you how you're modeling your system.
If you know that there is direction in the system, then you just created the object directed graph.
You use directed graph instead of using graph.
If you know that there is no there's no notion of directions in your system, then you create a normal graph.
And the and the topic of data cleaning, right?
And every data science problem, 90 percent of the work is data cleaning.
So I think I think there are some tutorials on data cleaning, too.
So that's another field altogether.
But once you have your data clean and you have a clear picture of a system you want to design, you know, how how nodes are defined and how interactions are working.
Once you have that picture and you have cleaned enough data, what are nodes and what are the edges, then I guess it goes just straightforward.
So like in this case, because like because someone if someone just gives you a book and says make a network out of it, there are there are certain a lot of like a lot of decisions that you had to make to end up with a with a network.
Right. So what those decisions is like, you know, those are pretty subjective.
I think I'll add like Paul, you had asked a little bit about best practices.
Notice how middle has a network actually stored in the form of a panda's data frame.
And that's a really, really useful starting point.
Network X has built in functions that let you import a panda's data frame as a graph.
You will need to data frames to store every graph.
You will need a node data frame and an edge data frame.
It's like having a node list and an edge list.
The node data frame stores the list of nodes, plus all of their keyword arguments attributes and the edge stories stores the edge list.
So you have two columns, one for the node at first node ID one for the second node ID, and then you have all the edge properties there.
Notebook five shows that and middle in this notebook also shows like an example of a real example of how we take a panda's data frame and convert it into a network X graph object.
So like like like in the fourth cell, we create new graphs and to populate this graph, we basically I trade through the to the pandas data frame.
I mean, I'm doing in this way, but there is a direct way of reading it too.
But like it's it's it's an extort.
If you go and extort from like you have a lot of ways you can read data into this.
And so basically, yeah, so you can have a you can have a adjacency matrix and cells that you can read.
You have you can have a panda's edge list.
And this is this is what is called an edge list in which you have a like you have a source, you have a target, you have a and you have attributes about that data.
You can you can you can run this code like this too.
But like to make it more explicit, I'm I'm I'm using a for loop.
And this is a bad way of doing it.
So you don't do it.
Use from pandas from pandas edge list.
But just to make it explicit, like so I have I add a source, which is my first node.
I add a second node, which is my target.
And then I add two attributes, the weight and the book.
And by doing that, I create these five different networks.
And let's just look at this network.
So in book one, there is an edge between Jamie Lannister and Laura Sterill.
And there is a weight of three.
So there are three interactions between Jamie and Laura in book one.
So this is this is our descriptive study.
Not said this is the description of our of our network.
And that's like that.
If you have edges in all the networks.
So now comes the most important part of this tutorial, finding the most important character.
Like how do we do that?
Any any ideas?
We already know what is like we already have discussed, you know, what is important.
We know what is degree, what is between us.
Any ideas?
How do we find the most important character?
First, we have to come to a consensus on what we mean by important.
Isn't that the million dollar question?
Yes.
We first need to define what importance is.
But then we reach a consensus and we won't.
So instead of doing that, like suppose you're giving you are given a you're given a network data.
And someone asks you what's the most important node in this network.
So this is how like at least for me, this is how I progress.
Like I first started, you know, the standard ones, degree between us or page rank.
And there are a ton of other centrality measures.
There's load, there is closeness, there's flow centrality.
So there are a lot of other things that we can do to make sure that we have the same
So there are a lot of other measures.
And but once you know enough about the data, then you can like, you know, then you can argue that this is more important.
In this case, we care more about this rather than more about that.
So, for example, suppose suppose in the suppose in the airport network, right.
I do care about something like the data.
I do care about something like the number of number of flight number of connections.
The airport has a number of places I can fly from from this airport.
But I also care about making the network connected.
For example, I should be able to fly from any city in the US to any other not directly.
But there should be a way.
Like the US airport network should not be disconnected.
But fun fact, if you look in the eighth notebook, there is there are some issues with that.
The US airport network is apparently not connected.
There are airports that you cannot fly to or fly from if you are if you're in New York.
But it's not a major it's not a major issue.
I don't want to give any spoilers.
But I do care about the data.
But it's not a major it's not a major issue.
I don't want to give any spoilers.
But if you're interested, you can check notebook eight.
And yep.
So again, that's how you define importance.
And in some cases, you want bottlenecks.
And in some cases, you like suppose you want to suppose you have a supply chain problem, which you have modeled as a network.
Like you go from warehouse A to warehouse B to warehouse C, and you try to find bottlenecks.
In this case, you care about between the centrality.
You don't care about how many like how good the warehouse can distribute.
But where is the bottleneck?
And that you care about that.
So let's let's just start with our standard measures.
Let's calculate degree centrality.
And if we see in book one, according to degree centrality, Eddard Stark is the most important character.
And people who are familiar with Game of Thrones, this kind of makes sense, right?
Yes. Can we can I get a yes?
If you if you if you know what I'm talking about.
I'm sorry if you're lost.
What's happening?
What what these names are?
But trust me, I thought Stark was an important character in book one.
Oh, I'm sorry.
Sorry.
But and as you see in book five, you cannot see that stuck anywhere.
Does that mean anything?
I don't know.
That's it.
So and in book five, we see that, you know, Jon Snow, then Daenerys Targaryen, Stannis.
These are important characters according to degree centrality.
And these like just by looking at these rankings, it kind of makes sense.
You know, these are known characters that we like, you know, that we predict.
You know, these these are characters that would be important.
So till now, so far, so good.
Like, you know, the way we model our network, maybe it wasn't the best way, but it was good enough way.
So like, here comes the sad histogram.
But it's an important way of looking at this is like because I want to show you the decay thing in a real world network.
It's like there's a theory of scale free networks.
And what scale free means is that in a real in all real world networks, the number of the number of connections,
the degree will always have an exponential decay.
That means like, you know, you'll have some nodes which will have a lot of connections,
but majority of the nodes will have less connections.
Just like Twitter.
If you try to plot the degrees centrality of Twitter, a histogram, you'll get something like this.
You'll find an exponential decay.
That's the theory behind that.
And here is that log log plot, the fancy log log plot that a lot of academic people love.
I don't know why, but because if if this was a if this was a proper network, like not a proper network,
if this was an exact network which was following exponential decay, you would have gotten a straight line.
But we get something like a straight line.
So we say, oh, yeah, maybe this network follows the scale free property.
So in this exercise, we create a new centrality measure because we say that we are not happy with.
Oh, yes. Yeah, go ahead.
I was just wondering.
So is there a is there a metric to describe the amount of people that so let's just use Twitter for an example.
The amount of people you follow to the ratio of followers.
Is there a metric to describe that?
Yes. So like in in network terms, you say that, you know, this is in degree divided by out degree.
So like, for example, when we when we are calculating degree till now, we're assuming there is no direction to the number of neighbors.
Right. As soon as you have a directed network, you have something called an in degree.
Like, you know, how many nodes are pointing towards me?
And then there's out degree. How many nodes am I pointing towards to?
And this like again, like follower follower folly following ratio is an important ratio in Twitter analysis.
So coming back to the exercise.
So so I say that, you know, I'm not happy with these measures that, you know, I don't like the results.
I need a I need a measure that captures more information.
So we create this new measure called weighted degree.
And instead of just counting the number of neighbors I have, I'm counting the number of I'm counting the summation of the weight on the edges.
So suppose instead of like if I had an N neighbors in the first case, my degree is N.
But suppose I have N neighbors, but every neighbor has some weight on its on its edge.
Then my new is my new weighted degree is the sum of all those weights on the edges.
Make sense?
If I'm following you, so what you're saying with the weighted degree, it's how many other important nodes are directly related to me?
Not exactly. No, I'm just saying that I'm just I'm not I'm not even saying this is a good measure, but I'm not even saying it's a good measure.
I'm just saying that I'm just creating a new measure in which I'm counting the number of I'm just counting the weight that is pointing towards me.
Like I'm just counting how close are my connections?
Like suppose suppose as a node, I'm connected to 10 different nodes, but everyone every connection has a weight of one.
And suppose I'm not now I'm connected to four people, but every connection has a weight 10.
So I have very strong connections like I'm not I'm not a I'm like I'm not a loosey that you know I'm just I'm not just an extrovert.
I'm an extrovert and an introvert.
Like I'm connected to a lot of people and I have those my connections are strong.
That's the concept of weighted degree.
Let me know once you're done.
And just as a hint in the in the exercise this end here, this end here would be a three tuple.
If you remember from our first notebook, it would have the first would be our the start node, the end node, and the third would be a dictionary, which has attributes.
Thumbs up if you're done.
You should get a similar plot like this.
As you look at look at look on the screen, we have this new histogram of weighted degree and distribution of that.
And again, it doesn't give us a lot of information, but we see a very similar plot that that find there is some exponential decay in this network.
And but let's see if it made any changes to our rankings.
So we still have a dot tag is the most important node.
So not a lot of change.
But if we concentrate on this character called Jon Snow.
So in an according to weighted degree, Jon Snow is the third most important.
And according to just degree centrality, he is at fifth.
So this measure bumped up Jon Snow to three.
So maybe it is a good measure.
That was a joke.
So you shouldn't choose your measures according to your results.
So so let's do let's do this for between a centrality.
And remember between a centrality is the one which always gives you interesting results.
Doesn't matter which data set it will always give you a nice particular result.
So let's see if that happens here too.
So if we do between a centrality for the first book, it starts again.
Maybe this Adar Stark fellow fellow is an important character in first book.
Maybe like we have two very different measures.
One is degree centrality and one is between us.
And if you remember that plot, they are not correlated at all because the way they're calculated are very different.
And both of them say that this fellow named here, Adar Stark, is an important person in book one.
So maybe just maybe we say that fine.
That Stark is important in book one.
Let's see in book one.
And in this case, in this case, we use the term of weights.
So if you look at this, you can calculate between a centrality because it's the shortest path between a weighted version and an unweighted version.
And this when we take weight in this, we are not taking any weight.
We're just doing the structure.
We have Adar Stark.
And when we look at the weight, which is a number of interactions, we see that it's still like he goes to the second position, but he's still important.
So not that different.
And we'll quickly talk about page rank.
So you don't need to worry about the implementation per se.
But the intuition behind page rank is if an important node points towards me, then I'm important.
It's not about the number of neighbors, number of shortest paths going through me.
But it just depends if an important node points towards me, I'm an important.
And in turn, if I point towards someone else because I am important, that node is important.
So it's a very neat equation.
If you want to go into the mathematical details of that, it's a very neat short and sweet equation.
And it works perfectly.
So if we calculate a page rank to again, I got stuck.
So maybe, maybe.
And that's the most important character in Book One.
But.
Earlier on, you said in both in the notebook, it says as well that we were doing an undirected network though.
So how does that work with?
Yes. So the thing with page rank is page rank was when it was initially defined, it was defined only for directed networks.
But it works both.
It won't give you the best results for undirected network.
And like I would still trust page rank, but it won't give you the best results for undirected networks.
But it still works because it's basically it's a it's a edge between an undirected edge is two edges.
It's one in this direction, one in that direction.
It still works. But when it was defined, it was defined for directed networks.
So you said that the page rank thing had it looked at the number of links and the quality of links.
So when you're doing an unweighted form of page rank, is that really similar to degree centrality?
And in Paging, it also looks at the path of the link, like how that link is coming towards me.
It's not like it's not just looking at the absolute surrounding, but also, you know, how it converges.
Let me check if I don't have the picture here, but we can talk about this.
So and in this, we see that if there is any correlation between these instead of plotting them out,
let's see if there is a correlation between these matrix that we just calculated.
So we see that there is a very high correlation for some reason between page rank and weighted degree.
So if you see you have a point nine nine. This is the Pearson correlation.
There's a very high correlation between page rank and weighted degree.
I don't have an answer for that. Why there is a correlation.
And it does not say anything about, you know, these measures.
It's just it's just coincidental that you have this very high correlation.
Now, let's talk about how these how these measures change.
Because as the story evolves, like, you know, things happen, you know, so like how the character develops.
Like, you know, this is how you can study.
You can pretty much put this to any other.
You can put this to Harry Potter or Lord of the Rings.
And I'm pretty sure people have done that.
So you can study how character develops, you know, how like does an important character stays always important or do they die off or something like that happens?
So let's just plot it for like, you know, three different characters.
So these are we have a dark stock, Tyrion and Jon Snow, people who don't know.
These are, you know, well known important characters in the show.
So in this plot, we see that.
I got stuck. This is the first book.
That stock is very important.
And then something happens and he slowly like his graph slowly dies off.
And like that stock is no more important for some reason.
I don't know what happens, but something happens.
And and you see that there is a in the third book after the third book, something happens to Jon Snow.
And apparently in the fourth book, Jon Snow is not that important.
But and here he is.
Here is, you know, important again in the fifth book, you know, character evolves.
Something happens.
Story changes.
So you can you can try to.
This is how you can use data science and network science to better understand your TV shows.
So let's just work with these set of characters.
And in this exercise, we basically look at the evolution of weighted degree centrality and how like, you know, how it evolves for these characters.
And so basically this this set of characters is is the intersection is the union of top five from every book.
So you have like enough important characters from all the books and we see how these characters evolve.
And you have this nice, pretty looking graph, not so pretty, but nice.
And we see that according to according to weighted degree centrality, we have.
We have Jamie Lannister as the most important in book five and then there is the second most important.
And this is this was a dark stock and whoops, not so important anymore.
So so again, like, you know, you can see that, you know, the story is evolving book by book.
And the notion of important, not the importance of character is changing as you progress through the as you progress through the storyline.
And let's see if we get a different.
Does someone dip below zero there?
I'm not sure. I mean, I think this goes to zero.
Brain of that goes to zero.
Maybe there is no mention of her in book four.
I'm not sure. Let's do the same thing.
But for between us and charity and see, because between us and charity will always give you nice, peculiar results.
We have this fellow right here, which basically goes, which you can see this is this is this is amazing.
This is a major outlier. And this is not Jon Snow.
This is not Denaris. This is not any stock.
This is any guesses for people who like to watch.
This is Stanis Baratian and people who don't watch or don't like like.
So what the answer for so what is this is not this is not you would something expect like, OK, so he's an important enough character.
But you won't say, oh, like, you know, this is the most important character in the network.
So this is why the result is surprising. And and so this is the between us and charity.
So what can we say about Stanis Baratian?
Any guesses? Stanis Baratian is important according to between us and charity.
What's happening there? Can anyone try to predict what's the storyline here?
Why is Stanis Baratian important?
I'm not telling you to actually tell the story, but like he has a high between us and charity.
What does that translate to? Yes.
So so it basically means that this like, you know, Stanis Baratian is some maybe something like this.
So if you if you have read the books or was the TV shows at the end of Book 4 and at the end of season six, I guess,
you have these you have certain events that happen and those certain events,
those certain events end up bridging multiple communities in these networks.
And and all those events have one person in common, and that is Stanis Baratian.
And because of that, those events, certain events, we have Stanis Baratian as node five here.
Does that make sense? Is that a good enough explanation for Game of Thrones fans?
Just like that, if you see for a bit degree centrality in Book 5, see, even even with degree centrality, Stanis Baratian is important.
It's not like he's not an important character.
But when you check it for between us and charity, the if you just look at the ratio of how high the score goes,
it's much, much more in between us and charity as compared to degree centrality.
This is why I always whenever I get a new data set, I'm like between us and charity.
Let's see what happens with that.
But surprisingly, I did this for the Indian Airport Network to there are no surprises there.
So I was disappointed.
I wasn't able to find a surprising little airport in India,
which is important for the integrity of the structure.
It's not. So let's let's look at the data set.
And this is one of the most hotly debated area because I think in the I think network sciences as a field is like 20 years old.
And still no one has come up with a definition of what is a community like apparently there are 39 different not 39,
but there are 39 different areas of the network.
But no one has come up with a there is no consensus.
You know, what is the definition of community?
But in this we use the most famous one, which is called Lua Community Detection and which is the same one which is used in the picture that we saw to find those communities.
And and that picture was drawn using Geffi.
So that's if you if you like visualization, it's if you're OK with moving out of the Python world, Geffi is an option.
And I do this. I try to do the same thing, but with Python.
So you have this.
And I do this, I try to do the same thing, but with Python.
So you have this not so pretty looking community.
I mean, if I do a circus plot of this, I'll get a much better visualization.
But if you want just want to have a look of, you know, how things are going ahead, you can plot it like this.
And we create and these are our communities like it's it's keyed in by zero and it's keyed in by an integer and you have list of characters in all those communities.
And so I'm not going to explain what is Lua Community Detection, but the intuition behind that is like the intuition that I really like is you basically try to find clusters of nodes which have high density.
And how do you define density?
It's like there's an actual definition is number of nodes, number of edges in a network divided by the total possible number of edges in the network, which is suppose you have m edges and which is divided by nc2.
Like because like if you have n nodes, you can and if you pick two nodes at random, that's the total number of possible combinations of edges.
So it's m divided by nc2.
That is the density of a network.
And you basically try to find clusters of nodes where the where this density is very high.
So in which basically the intuition is that you try to find clusters in which nodes are interconnected to each other a lot as compared to other nodes in the network.
So to to see that pictorially.
So if I if I plot a community here, so this is the plot of that community.
You see that there are a lot of interconnections.
You see this is very, very dense.
The structure right here is very dense.
So that's a community.
And again, if I if I plot it for any other community, again, you see a very dense structure like characters in characters in this community are all of them are connected to each other.
And just to have a look at the actual numbers, if I calculate the total density of the network, it's around zero point zero four.
And if I calculate density of these communities that I found, it's like it's point zero point two.
So you have like, you know, these communities are, you know, five times as dense as the network itself.
So this is how you find communities.
So we won't do this exercise.
So talking about a bit of network science theory, I like to end on this.
We talked a lot about Python or talk a lot about working with real networks.
So again, you see this beautiful, magnificent plot, right?
And let's let's go back to nineteen sixties when, you know, graph theory was all the rage.
All the cool kids in mathematics were doing graph theory.
And there was this guy known as Paul Aldous.
And does anyone know what Aldous number?
So, yeah, one guy knows.
So apparently, so Paul Aldous was a mathematician.
And if you have written a paper with Paul Aldous, you get the number one.
If you have written a paper who has written a paper with Paul Aldous, you get the number two and so on.
If you have written a paper with someone who has written a paper who had someone written a paper with Paul Aldous, you get the number three.
And in the same in the same idea, there is something called as a Kevin Bacon number.
Has anyone heard about that?
So it's the same idea.
If you have worked in a movie with Kevin Bacon, you get the number one.
If you have worked with someone who has worked in the movie, you get number two and so on.
So and then there's a Paul, then there's an Aldous Bacon number, which is a summation of both of them.
So if you have a very low Aldous Bacon number, that means you are you are a mathematician plus a movie star.
So that's an interesting combination to have.
So coming back to Aldous graphs.
So suppose I don't give you data like right now we have a lot of data.
Suppose there's an algorithm that you came up with and you want to test this on some data and you you come up with some you have to come up with synthetic data.
Then the first question is how do I generate this?
The first answer that pops up randomly.
Randomly, yes, you can generate randomly data.
But even even even how you know, which you so you you you you generate normally distributed data.
But how does that translate to networks?
Right. So that was the first question.
So I think Paul Aldous came up with any this model.
It's called Aldous-Renny model in which you give you suppose I give you a probability of zero point five.
So you you basically go to every two nodes that you pick two nodes and with a probability of zero point five you add an edge.
So this is how you end up with a random graph.
This this was in the 1960s and in late 90s another model was proposed, which was called Barabasi-Albert graph.
And in this model, the idea is that most of them like this is what our real world network looks like.
Most of the nodes are connected to a small number of nodes.
But there would be one node who's connected to a lot of nodes.
So like if you look at the histogram plot, I'm sorry, but histogram plot.
This is the difference.
If you look at like because see because histograms are not nice, you don't see a nice plot.
But if we increase the number of nodes, we'll get a much smoother plot.
So yeah, this is the plot of Aldous-Renny graph and the degree distribution of that graph.
It's a normal distribution.
It's not it's not a normal distribution.
It's not a normal distribution, but it peaks at zero point one as you see, because I put in the probability as zero point one of having an edge.
So it peaks at zero point one.
So you have this nice looking random graph.
And then you have something like this.
This is the Barabasi-Albert graph.
And if you remember, this was our degree distribution for our Game of Thrones networks, right?
So which is much closer to a real world as compared to something like this, because these two are very, very different networks, right?
Like structurally very different.
How this is how the degrees are distributed here and the degrees are distributed here.
If you plot the ECDF of this, you'll get a smooth S curve.
And if you plot ECDF of this, you'll get a cliff, which is which is what most real world networks will give you.
So and this is our log log plot.
If you were interested in this, this is the log log plot of Aldous-Renny graph.
And this is the log log plot, which is our straight line of Barabasi-Albert graph.
So this was this was my detour to a bit of network science theory.
And if you want to talk more about this, I'm here for the next eight days.
So and there is still a lot of material left in the repository.
There is book five, six, eight, three bonus notebooks.
So if you are more interested, there is a lot of more material.
Feel free to go through it.
Feel free to talk to Eric on me during PyCon.
So thank you.
We got a few minutes.
Mirza's got some announcements.
And then if there are questions that people want to ask right now and leave for posterity on YouTube, we're happy to entertain them as well.
So lunch is at twelve twenty.
So that's in two minutes in Grand Ballroom A and B.
So any questions from people that are burning questions?
Right. So Paul, you've asked a lot.
I'm going to go to the back first.
Sorry, I misunderstood.
All right. So Paul, you get the first one.
What are the most interesting areas where you could apply this in prediction and data science?
So the open triangles is obviously one.
But what are the other ones that we might want to take back to our respective institutions?
I guess that's a very particular question.
It depends where you work.
I could probably. So we can talk later about that.
It's quite highly context specific.
What are some interesting networks you've seen that maybe didn't seem like it makes sense as a network at first until you start looking at some of these plots?
I'm not the best person to ask this question because I've been doing networks for the last four years.
And whenever I look at some data, I'm like, oh, that's a network.
But last week I was working on, I started working on some spatial networks.
It's like how you, I mean, it's a very, it's a very, like, if you try hard enough, you can make spatial points as networks.
So like last week I was working on that.
But for me, I have a bad habit of like, you know, that could be more or less a network.
I think that speaks to like once you get used to this, you know, you're not going to be able to do it.
It becomes very natural to take a row like to take your data table, which we for in which each row is basically a node and start asking the question, how are the nodes, how are the rows related to one another?
And then once we find a good definition for a relation, suddenly we have a graph.
And now we can ask questions about how we can do that.
And now we can ask questions about the relationships between the nodes.
That's a quote that I have in notebook two.
The heart of a graph is not in its nodes, it's in its edges.
The edges are what make a graph interesting.
The relationships between the nodes are what make a graph interesting.
Now, there have been questions before about scalability.
Before we go to the last question at the back.
Is that unscalability?
No.
Okay. But before we go to that question on the back, I just want to put this out there for everybody.
NVIDIA is working on Cougraph.
And I've been on GitHub talking with the NVIDIA developers to make sure that Cougraph's API accelerates graph algorithms and matches NetworkX.
So hopefully within the near future on some undefined timeframe, we'll be able to have NetworkX APIs on the GPU.
They recently had a very big project, this thing, right?
With a lot of researchers and...
Yes.
Final question at the back.
So obviously the math is fantastic.
But do you find that you actually use the plots to kind of investigate?
I mean, they're great to look at the visual graphs, but are they useful for investigating kind of, I don't know, your ideas about how the network is working or how it behaves?
Do you find that it's more than just...
You start seeing patterns that can repeat that you're like, oh, I see where there's a problem in this graph or network.
For example, if I look at a plot like this, I know that the graph has a scale-free property.
And once I know that, I know that the scale-free property defines that there are less nodes with a lot of neighbors.
So I can start thinking towards that direction.
And for example, with an ACDF plot, I know exactly what's the percentile distribution, right?
And I'll just know a lot more about the data.
And then I can start thinking from that way forward.
So it does come with experience.
The more you do it, the more familiar you are.
That said, visualization is one of the biggest tools that we need in any type of data analysis, right?
So that's why we have them.
And these graph-specific ones hopefully are useful, right?
So for example, we had that...the exhibition one.
Like we would not have...if we didn't choose the right visualization, we would not have been able to immediately intuit that inference that, oh, yeah, people are just local in time connecting with one another, right?
So visual inferences and your visual toolkit, very important.
Cool.
Well, thanks for coming.
Thanks, Mriddle. Let's give a hand for Mriddle.
The apprentice is really the master now.