and cannot see me.
That's me on the left.
Best wedding photo ever if you ask me.
I'm a senior software engineer at Clover Health.
Yes, we're hiring, let's talk later.
We also do engineering remotely, so.
I've been interested in issues of representation
and diversity for like 15 plus years now,
and I love that my technical skills allow me
to affect how we go about doing things at Clover Health
to improve diversity and inclusion.
So you chose to be in this room,
you're gonna get one of them.
You can follow me on Twitter at ZuckerPunch,
or if you are interested in the web app
I'm gonna show you later, DM me and I will send it to you.
I'm like too embarrassed about the code
to put it publicly on GitHub anywhere,
so it's not there, but if you wanna talk about
any of these things, let me know.
So the fact that tech is struggling to hire
or retain employees from diverse backgrounds
has been written about and discussed extensively.
The economic, social, and moral benefits of diversity
are also super well documented.
So why is it hard for well-intentioned organizations
to shift their demographics?
There are a number of reasons of course,
there's no silver bullet, but one that does not appear
to have been thoroughly discussed enough if you ask me
is the challenge of gathering and responding to data
about diversity within a company's hiring pool
and with their existing employees.
One hack day, I was involved in a few too many projects
and could only devote a token amount of time
to the one I was really interested in,
which was seeing if we could determine
whether we had sufficient diversity for any given role
to start interviewing candidates,
or if we needed to spend more time sourcing candidates
from diverse backgrounds for the pipeline.
So I accomplished an MVP in approximately an hour
once I had an API key and permissions,
which turns out that was the hardest part,
but it doesn't actually, if you take anything away
from this talk, let it be this.
It doesn't require a huge effort to make a big difference.
I'm a perfectionist, so I always used to think
if something's worth doing, it's worth doing well,
but also if something is worth doing,
it's worth doing poorly first
so that at least you have something, right?
So here's what you're in for.
In this talk, I'll walk through my MVP
indicating for each role,
whether it was sufficient diversity,
and then I'll talk about what our V2 was,
and I'll also address some gotchas and limitations
so that you don't have to make the same mistakes that I did,
and then we'll go forth on the what now, the glorious future.
Y'all in?
All right, let's do it.
Okay, so disclaimer, I put together this web app
for a Hack Day project.
This is my MVP.
The front end literally has no styles in it.
It was as bare bones as can be, but it works,
and that's what's important, right?
It's a simple Django web app.
It has one view.
It makes real-time API calls to greenhouse to fetch data.
Who works at a company that uses greenhouse?
Yeah, it's a pretty commonly used tool.
It has an API.
It's pretty handy.
There are other tools that you could use,
and I think those also have APIs.
This is just the one that we happen to have.
So this is pretty hacky code, and in production,
this would never fly with that nested for loop,
and performance of this code is terrible.
I'll show you more about that later.
But as a proof of concept, it's really effective
to give people a chance to see exactly how homogeneous
or diverse our candidate pool was at the top of the funnel
for any given role.
So this is my one Django view for the project.
It gets a list of jobs.
It gets, for each job, all the applications to that job.
And then for each application, it goes back to greenhouse
and fetches the EEOC data associated with that application.
It does a little number smushing,
which you'll see on a later slide,
and it renders a list of jobs with data
about how diverse the candidate pool is for each job.
So by the way, in case you were wondering,
EEOC is Equal Employment Opportunity Commission,
because I need to look it up every time.
The API calls are not super fancy.
They're just some hard-coded URLs.
I hit the Greenhouse's API and load the data
for the three endpoints.
You can see it's very abstracted, right?
And so this is where I add an application status
to a dictionary for each job.
It says, like, women tally,
and then disability status, there's a tally,
for race, for each of the races that there are,
there's a tally.
I anonymize and tally the number of applicants
who self-attest as belonging to a protected group
and display only aggregates for each role on one page.
Here's what it looks like.
Isn't it beautiful?
For any role, it says whether there is sufficient diversity,
and we'll talk about sufficient diversity later,
to move forward with interviewing candidates for the role.
So stylish.
Okay, so that was my MVP,
and that was, like, approximately an hour of time,
but I have visions for the future.
So what was our V2?
So normally, when you're hitting your website to get data,
you don't want people to have to wait 10 minutes
to see results, right?
That's not just me.
And when you first get all the jobs
and then the applications for each of those jobs,
and then the EEOC data for each of those jobs,
that's a lot of API calls.
This is what my terminal output looks like
when I make this request,
and it just goes on and on for pages.
Obviously, that's not ideal.
It'd be much better to collect the data regularly,
store it in a database where we can make fewer queries
faster by using table relationships, right?
So our first order of business is to sync new data
from Greenhouse to our database,
then there's no synchronous API calls to a third party,
and our page can load in a snap.
The next hurdle is how do we know what data is new,
how do we upsert changes
without getting everything fresh each load?
That's a problem for future Nicole.
For now, it's enough to drop and create every time,
and I cringe every time I say that,
but, like, it does the job.
Another thing we decided to do for V2
was to only show diversity stats
for candidates who have already exited the pipeline.
Otherwise, there's potential for a hiring manager
looking at this stuff to see a candidate
we're still evaluating and go,
oh, we already have enough veterans for this year,
let's not hire this one because that's illegal.
So the other thing we wanted to accomplish
was showing diversity at every step of the pipeline,
not just the top of the funnel,
from the recruiter's screen
all the way through offer acceptance,
and being able to slice data
to see the story for a particular group
or from a particular source
or from a particular recruiter.
So that's all well and great,
but there were some things that made this a little hard.
Be careful with people-sensitive data.
Where can you host it so that not everyone can access it?
We anonymize our data when pulling in information
about candidates using the API,
so we didn't store any information
that's personally identifiable for anyone,
just their EEOC stuff and their candidate ID,
which isn't identifiable
unless you have the Greenhouse API key.
Which brings up another thing.
Put your API keys in a private place,
and I'm not talking about a place
that's accessible to all of engineering.
Otherwise, even if you have your database stored
in a place where not everyone can access all of the data,
if they can access the API key,
they can get the data for themselves.
And they can slice and get information
from people who are currently in the pipeline
and make those illegal decisions.
I recommend you be sensitive
about who can see this information.
Maybe everyone should get the 10,000-foot view
at an all-hands.
That's the cookies.
But being able to view per-roll slicing on different tags,
you might wanna have limited access
to have people see things at a more granular level.
We decided to show results only for groups
of a minimum pool size or greater,
even though that meant that we get data
on a slower cadence than real time,
in order to give the pool size
a chance to get large enough for real anonymity.
Beware combinations.
Veterans who have a disability,
who are of a certain gender and a certain race,
is identifiable without anonymity.
If you wanna see musicians, that's one group.
If you wanna see the Muppets that are blue,
that's another group.
But if you're like, give me the blue Muppets
who are musicians, it's only that one,
and we all know who that is.
So don't show slices of multiple things at the same time,
unless that slice fits or exceeds a minimum pool size.
Plus Muppets.
Let me stress again how important our decisions were
about anonymizing data,
in addition to not allowing slicing
until a resulting group was above a particular pool size,
or not including, that part about not including candidates
who are currently active in the pipeline in your results,
is vital, because you don't wanna make hiring decisions
based on that information
that you're not supposed to make hiring decisions.
Like that example of,
we have enough veterans for this year,
we don't need to hire this one.
You don't wanna run into those legal ramifications.
I'm just an engineer, I don't have sufficient confidence
that my web app is bug free,
and there's absolutely no way
to get identifiable slices of data.
So only when those puppies have exited the pipeline
do we count them, unless you are super duper confident
that no one is gonna be able to like,
figure something out with your site.
Another problem we ran into
was that not everyone fills out this information,
it's sparse.
It's not available for referrals,
or for candidates that are sourced internally.
And even on the website,
not everyone chooses to fill it out.
Understanding why data is sparse
is clutch in figuring out what you can do to mitigate it.
And understanding what makes data sparse
has a lot to do with humans, turns out,
and solutions are usually specific to the particular group.
What works for employees is not the same
as what works to get more data from candidates.
Folks are often, especially if they don't know
your organization very well, like candidates,
they're often suspicious about what you're gonna do
with their information.
Will it be used against them in some way?
Whereas with your employees, you, I hope,
have a little bit more trust built up.
And sometimes there's no opportunity to collect data
from non-system inputs, like source candidates.
So try to, if you can, put processes in place
on the recruiting side to make sure
that you gather that information.
That's one way to handle that.
Another hangup was that sometimes the data
we need to collect by law doesn't match up entirely
with what we want to collect
or what people might be willing to divulge,
and we're limited by what it's legal to ask.
We need to decide what labels and groups to include.
Like for gender questions, what will our options be?
I know that there are non-binary humans
for whom the labels like male and female,
or like man and woman, don't really apply.
So how do you take into account that
when the government requires that you ask like,
male, female?
Also, making a survey is an art unto itself,
and it's possible to ask questions
and elicit a response that you did not intend.
Just so you all know, federal contractors are required
to request this information
for the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission.
There's certain questions that you have to ask,
and if they don't match up with what you'd like to ask,
that leads to having like multiple surveys,
which causes survey fatigue.
There's also suspicion.
So find out what you need to do
and decide what the best balance is for you.
Great balance in terms of like survey fatigue
or like getting the questions answered that you really want.
So now we get to the part that I find really interesting.
What actually constitutes sufficient diversity?
Well, it turns out with zero diverse candidates in a pool,
you're obviously not gonna hire anyone
from an underrepresented group.
But according to a handful of studies
that the Harvard Business Review did,
even with one candidate from a minority group in the pool,
that person has like zero chance of actually getting hired
because of our preference for the status quo.
And there's this great quote in that article.
Deviating from the norm can be risky for decision makers
because people tend to ostracize people
who are different from the group.
So for women and minorities,
having your differences made salient
can lead to an inference of incompetence.
So if you're the only woman in a pool of finalists,
it highlights how she is different from the norm
and makes her inherently riskier candidate
and likely one that you won't go with.
But if you have even two people
from an underrepresented group,
they actually stand a chance of getting hired.
The odds of hiring a minority were 193 times greater
if there were at least two minority candidates
in the finalist pool,
controlling for the number of other minority
and white finalists controlling for pool size.
So like that is not inflated.
How impressive is that?
But two candidates, come on, that's a pretty low bar.
What we saw was if there was like
a relatively small pool of finalists,
like six finalists, eight finalists,
if you've got an applicant pool
for a role like software engineer,
you're gonna have far more candidates
to choose from.
So even if you have two people
from a minority group represented,
if there's a thousand people in the in group,
even if you put aside unconscious bias,
which totally exists and will whittle down
your diversity of your candidate pool
every step of the pipeline,
and if you put aside our status quo fix
of having two candidates,
you're still statistically unlikely to hire someone
different from the status quo
because you have two of them against a thousand other
probably equally qualified candidates.
So what can we do then?
I've got a crazy idea.
Why not go for parity with the eligible
labor force in the US?
Then at least if the top of your funnel is balanced,
you stand a greater chance of having those people
make it through your hiring process.
Not that it's smooth sailing from there,
we still need to institute systems
to limit the effective unconscious bias
in the rest of the hiring pipeline,
but at least it's a start.
This is part of a table of race and gender
in the potential labor force.
The base number is a thousand.
So for 2017, the total number of black women
in the workforce was 10.5 million
out of 17.5 million black women
who could have been in the labor force.
Not all of these people are qualified for every job
or even are interested,
but if we support programs that give training
and opportunities to underrepresented groups,
while we also try to get as close as possible
to having our pipeline represent the population pool,
someday those might converge and we'll get there.
But like, you know, aim for the stars.
We're doing this now at Clover Health.
So that glorious future that I talked about,
what does it look like?
I found out after I did my MVP
and when I was like halfway through V2
that there's actually a company
that does a lot of this for you,
and we ultimately decided to use them for the future
so that engineering hours don't need to support this web app,
this like hacky web app that I made indefinitely.
We didn't discover until we were like deep in V2.
So like, could we have done research to discover
that this company existed first and save ourselves some work?
Absolutely.
Would anyone have thought to Google it
before I made my MVP?
Probably not.
We found out about this company
through our diversity and inclusion manager
who joined right after I made my MVP.
So if you have diversity and inclusion folks at your company,
talk to them early.
This company is called Atypica,
and they'll, if you connect them with your recruit track,
or recruiting tracking software,
and give them like an API key or something like that,
they will look at your candidate pool
and do the slicing by role or by department,
by stage in the pipeline,
and they also do analysis to figure out
how to solve the sparsity problem of the data
so that they have like an 80 or 90 something percent
accuracy rate in determining gender and race,
and they don't do it just by like photo recognition
or like facial recognition,
so I think that's pretty cool.
If you don't have the budget to outsource
the way that we ultimately did,
the web app we talked about is perfectly usable though.
It probably requires a little further iteration
to handle the sparsity of data problem
that we were talking about,
but even if your time is limited,
the MVP is still better than nothing at all.
If you go this route,
make sure to include any DNI people at your company.
You'll need weigh in from HR and recruiting
as well as possibly legal,
but if you're willing to do the work,
most of the time folks are happy to give you their opinion
and send you on their way,
but don't try to do this without the knowledge
of what's legal without like consulting anyone.
Doing the problem solving without these people
would have been a huge mistake for me,
because I'm just an engineer
and you can't just tell me to implement a data ingest
because I'll do that,
but I should be part of the design of the thing,
but I don't have all the answers about like
what we should do, what we can do legally.
And also you can't just like
not include engineering in this task,
because obviously we all know that we have useful opinions,
and boy do we have opinions.
So the next challenge is how do you integrate data
for current employees with information
that's available for your hiring pipeline?
They're like two separate sources of information
and geez, but like reconciling them is like pulling teeth.
I just found out earlier this week though,
that Etipica now has like an API
that you can use for looking at information,
I think about like promotion and retention and stuff
for your existing employees.
So hey, maybe this problem is basically solved for me
and I just need to go check out their API documentation,
which I'm honestly likely gonna do on the plane home.
So now when you identify departments or roles
where there isn't representation across different groups,
the next step is going back
and sourcing from those missing groups.
If there's a big drop off at one step of the recruiting funnel,
investigate why people are leaving there.
So this is fake data, but this is like actually a report
that I pull from Etipica like quarterly.
So for one role, you see the counts
and the pass through rates for men versus women
for each stage of the pipeline.
At the beginning, you start with 100 men, 50 women.
It's not representative of the population,
but it's not awful either.
But in the application and resume stage,
50% of men make it through,
but only 20% of women make it through.
So it looks like you need to take a look
at what's happening in your resume review stage, huh?
At the phone screen stage,
you have many more men than women, 15 and 10 respectively,
but they make it through at the same rate.
So that stack, that frame seems to be okay.
Then for the onsite,
you have 80% of men making it through,
but only 33% of women.
So you probably need to take a deeper look
at what may be happening during that stage.
And because I work at a great place,
everyone accepts their offer,
but wow, we lost the chance to hire women
at the resume and onsite stages.
This is hard, but it's really worth it.
Since this problem is one of people and systems,
it's inherently challenging,
especially if you're a person
who's at the apex of privilege in our society.
But do what you can.
It's worth it to even go 50% of the way
rather than not do anything.
From one perfectionist to another,
admit that you won't have it perfect.
Try to build process around data collection
wherever you can,
and please don't guess about people
unless it's required by law
or outsourced to a company like a Typica
that does it professionally.
They're less likely to mess up than a biased human,
even a well-intentioned one.
And if you are at the apex of privilege,
ahem, cis whitehead men,
you should involve people from underrepresented groups
to be involved in the process.
Listen to them,
because they know how things are gonna come across,
but please don't make them do the lion's share of the work.
My recommendation is to solicit their opinion early and often,
do some work,
show them what you did and ask for feedback,
but don't make them carry this whole boulder by themselves.
So these are just some examples
of what I have done at Clover Health.
There's a ton of other things you can do
to instrument your hiring pipeline
or measure changes in inclusion at your company.
Share out what worked and what didn't work for you
so that we as a community can learn from each other
and develop best practices.
There's no reason for the best practices
about diversity and inclusion to remain a secret.
I want this special sauce all over tech.
So this is me, and that's my dog Chloe.
You can follow her on Instagram, corgi in the front,
because her front legs are a little shorter
than her back ones.
And I work at Clover Health.
We are totally hiring.
Come work with me.
And like I said, we hire remote engineers.
The end.
woven
LE tomorrow
One minute for questions.
If you guys want to step up to microphones
and ask your questions please.
Nicole, why is your hair so good?
I don't know.
I was born that way.
I'm a natural purple.
So I have two questions.
First is have you considered tying diversity goals to things like compensation and bonuses
for the people in the recruiting team?
And also what are your thoughts on the benefits of standardized interviews in removing bias
from the interview phases?
My brain is a sieve.
Let's do one at a time.
The first one is tying compensation and bonuses to like how you do on these diversity stuff.
My company, we have a one-role, one-compensation policy, basically so that women and minorities
don't get underpaid in the first place.
So we don't have that.
It's a good idea, I think, if you don't have this policy to reinforce that people should
actually put their efforts toward this by putting your money where your mouth is.
I think that our top-level executives are going to be held accountable to these numbers
over time now that we can measure them.
And also for our internal employees, like retention and stuff like that.
If we see those numbers diving, I think the plan is to hold leadership accountable for
that.
So does that answer your question?
Kind of, but it's very easy to say people will be held accountable.
For sure.
It's hard for me to believe that people in leadership will be held accountable for things
like this because they generally aren't.
When people say held accountable, they never say how they will be held accountable.
This actually came up in all hands that we had a month ago or so where it's like, okay,
so we're making these part of our OKRs for the company, but what happens if we miss them?
I'm just going to be the one saying to our CEO or whatever, you didn't reach diversity
in the numbers.
You're out.
And honestly, we've only been doing this for a year or so, so the proof will be in the
pudding.
But I, as a relatively privileged human in this system, feel like it's my responsibility
to say, hey, we said we were going to hold people accountable.
What have we actually done?
And we'll see if it actually works.
I agree with you that 90% of the time people are like, yeah, we really care about this
stuff and people will be held accountable and then nothing changes.
But I personally intend to remind people of these promises and if they don't follow through
on them, then that is something I will absolutely agitate about because I feel like I'm fortunately
in a position where I don't have to worry about staying employed.
So I can afford to fight for it.
Does that help?
What was your second question?
Using standardized interviews to help remove unconscious bias.
Yeah.
I actually gave a talk at Pi Gotham, I think, with James who was sitting up here a few minutes
ago and we talked about some of the benefits of anonymizing resumes, taking out information
that would let people figure out your gender or your race, like from name or from college
you attended or where age is concerned, like the years that you were doing something.
And I know that there are other tools out there that make the process even better for
the phone screen or the on-site or whatever where it basically removes the identifiable
information like voice recognition, but there's some things that we can't do like speech patterns
and stuff where I think that is still like the next frontier where we're not going to
be able to isolate bias from the hiring pipeline entirely until we get to some of those things.
But I do totally think that we should make it so that it is not abundantly clear when
you're interviewing someone what their background is.
We should at least try it and see how that goes because I fully believe that there are
qualified minorities and women and people with disabilities out there, I think we just
don't perceive them that way because of unconscious bias.
Thank you.
So you mentioned at the outside that one of the challenges you had was getting an API
key.
What were some of the things you experienced sort of working with HR at the outset just
convincing them that this project was worth doing and getting rolling with it?
Fortunately my HR folks are like totally on board with this.
I had to ask, I wasn't asking them to do anything except give me the key so that helps, like
it didn't require work on their part, although now they're like happy to take advantage of
the information that I can give them as it informs their process.
At the beginning I had to say, hey, I want an API key and here's the reasons.
They were like, okay, that's asking for a lot of access to greenhouse.
How are you going to protect it?
I had to say, well, I'm only going to get these pieces of information.
I'm going to anonymize it in this way.
Then they were like, okay, great.
There was a bunch of back and forth about, oh, it turns out I actually need this permission
also.
Can you add that to the key?
I have to give you a new key, whatever.
That is the part that took a while.
It wasn't actually convincing them to let me do this thing.
It was a hack day project, so it was my time.
Anyone else?
All right.
Well, oh, wait, one last one from the back.
This is not my personal opinion.
Just a disclaimer.
Are you playing devil's advocate?
Yes.
How would you respond to those folks that do say, for example, if minorities and women
are having a pay gap or a disparity where they become more necessary with jobs or various
other things, why don't we all just save the 2% or 20% or 18% compensation cost and hire
all the women since they're a bargain?
I don't believe that.
I just want to hear your answer to it.
Wait, are you saying that these people say we should hire more women because they're
cheaper?
Correct.
If there's a pay gap, then why isn't capitalism solving it?
Because capitalism inherently flawed system that we should burn to the ground.
Fair.
I put the pro-claimer first.
Not my personal opinion.
But also, honestly, I would probably send them to one of my like cis head white friends,
dude friends who are like ready to be allies.
Like, all right, I got this 101 question for you.
Like, I want to answer the 201 questions and let them answer the 101 questions.
Okay.
Anyway, thanks.