Hey everyone. Thanks very much for coming to this tutorial this afternoon. So I'm Kevin.
I'll be the instructor for this course. Just a little bit about me. I work at a company
called Cambridge Park. We're doing courses in data science and all sorts of workshops
a bit like this one. Just a little bit. So I've sent an email yesterday. I've seen at
least some of you receive it. I already got a pull request on my repository. So you'll
you've got that email, you'll see a link to GitHub where I've hosted all the content for
today. So if you check the Read Me, I've got some instructions on how to install everything.
So you've got two options. First one is you set it up on your machine. So it's just a
matter of installing the requirements. So you've got a requirements.txt with all the
libraries and the versions you need. And then start a Jupyter Notebook. So it's all
based in Notebook. If you haven't done that, you can either do it now, but it might be
a bit slow on the network. Otherwise, you've got a second option, which is to use Google
Collab. So I don't know if you've all used it before. But basically, you just click on
one of those links, and it should bring you to Google Collab. Yep. And so you've got the
Notebooks loaded there, and you can just work in the browser directly. There is an extra
step at the beginning where you're just setting up and installing all the libraries. So that
might take a minute or so, and then you can get started. So that's it for the install
instructions. Then just a quick word about the structure of the repo. So we'll have three
main Notebooks that we're going to work through today. Each Notebook is divided, has two versions,
version skeleton, which has some holes in it, and that's where you're going to have
to work on. And then the version solution, if you just want to go straight to the solution
and see how to do the different exercises. Yeah. And then this morning, someone opened
a pull request to add an environment YAML. So thank you very much for that. So if you're
using Anaconda, you can also directly install, create a new environment with it. Yes, that's
pretty much it. And I haven't added the slides yet, but I will just after this talk, I'll
push them there so you can also access them. Right. So this tutorial is about model interpretability.
So that's how we will divide the time. So first an introduction, explaining a bit why
do we even care about it? Why do we want to do that? And then we'll see three main libraries.
So the first one, Eli5, and a technique called permutation importance. That is the most
basic place to get started for model interpretability. And then two other libraries that are a bit
more advanced. The first one, LIME, stands for local interpretable model agnostic explanations.
And then SHAP, which is probably the most advanced one here. Just another thing, we'll
have a break at 3 p.m. So it's in about an hour and a half, so right in the middle of
the session. Cool. So first, why do we care about model interpretability? Why do we want
to do that? Well, let's take this scenario. So you've worked quite hard on a project.
You've cleaned and preprocessed some really messy data. You've engineered some really
fancy features. You're really happy with that. You've done a lot of work to select the best
model and tune it properly. And then you've got a final model that has really good performance
on some test set. So you're pretty proud of that. You're pretty happy. But then there's
a catch. Your boss comes to you and is asking, well, just one more thing. Can you explain
how your model works? Can you explain how is your model taking decisions? What does
your model care about in the data? And that, unless you take the steps to actually try
to understand your model, you usually not know the answer. At least it's not straightforward.
So that's what we're going to do today. So just a quick word. So you all know that algorithms
are everywhere and more and more industries are starting using machine learning in their
work. So you'll have things like insurance or banks or even the police trying to build
models to predict all sorts of things. And that actually has an impact on people, the
predictions that those models will do. So if you work for an insurance, maybe it will
define whether or not, how much you're going to be charged for a specific model. And then
if you work for a specific plan or if you work for a bank, your model might decide who
is going to get a loan or not. So it's really important to know how your model works and
how it takes its decisions. If you work for a bank, you don't want your model to have
any sort of bias in who it's going to give a loan to or not. And another example that
I quite like is social media. So it might look like a less important one than the three
others here, but I think it can have an equally bad impact on people. So let's say you're
working on a model that should predict who is most likely to click on an ad on whatever
social media you're working for. And let's say you're working for an advertiser that,
I don't know, is doing online gambling. So then your model, if you don't take care, will
probably try to target someone who is addicted to gambling. And we'll try to find in the
data set some features that are good proxy to know who is addicted to gambling, because
that's those are the people that would be the most likely to click on an ad. So that
can have a really bad impact on people, even though that seems to be a fairly simple thing.
So all of that to say that black box models are not really an option, and you will need
to interpret them if you work in all those fields where you might have quite a bad impact
on, I mean, powerful impact on people. So I like to see interpretability having three
main goals. So the first one is building trust in your model. So here, another example, you're
trying to predict employees' performance for a large organization. And the data you've
got available is performance reviews from the past 10 years, for example. But then what
if the company just tends to promote men more than women? Then your model, the only thing
your model is going to do is try to mimic this process that your company already has
and will learn from this bias. So even if you're quite happy with your model at the
end, your model has a really high accuracy, the only thing it will be doing is looking
at the gender as a priority to predict the performance of people, which if you don't
actually look inside the model how it works, you will not necessarily notice, and you'll
end up putting that in production and potentially be really damaging. So there's a really good
quote from Cathy O'Neill about that, which is models are opinions embedded in mathematics,
so your model is only as good as your data, and it's really important to understand what
your model is picking in the data to make its predictions. The second kind of aspect
that I like to see is it helps decision makers. So let's say, for example, you work for a
hospital, and you're going to have to predict the likelihood of a patient to develop, I
don't know, some disease X, and you've got access to symptoms and information about all
your patients, and you want to know whether or not they're going to have this disease.
So here your model itself will, you'll never put your model in production to directly give
a treatment to people or anything like that. You want this model to be used by doctors
to help them with their diagnosis. So the doctor will have to not take the prediction
itself, but understand how the prediction was made, then try to understand if that makes
any sense or not, and just come up with their diagnosis based on that. So here the model
is only to empower the decision maker. And finally, another example I quite like is using
model interpretability to debug your model. So here an example that is used in the paper
from Lime, which is one of the libraries we'll see today, is the following. So you've got
images of wolves and huskies, and you're trying to build a model that will predict, classify
those two classes. But then the problem, so they did, people actually built really good
model, has a really good accuracy, and they were really happy with that. It predicts,
I don't know, 99 point something accuracy, what is a wolf, what is a husky. But then
when they actually used the library Lime, that we'll see later on this model to try
to understand what was the model looking at in the data to make its predictions, they
noticed that the model was just looking in the background, because the pictures of huskies
or wolves, I forgot which one, tend to have more snow in the background. And that's what
they noticed here, when they have the models provided with this picture here, it was only
looking at the background and saying, if there is snow, it's probably a husky, if there is
no snow, it's probably a wolf. So the problem here is that you're really happy, you have
your fancy model, you think it's a really good classifier, but it's just basically a
snow detector. It can only, it's only looking at the background, is there snow or not. So
that's something that here, model interpreting your model would have helped actually seeing
that, and not putting into production before debugging it.
So then what do we do? Well, first some models will be easy to interpret by design, so something
like a linear regression, for example, you'll have a weight on each feature, and it's really
easy for you to interpret exactly, to see exactly what's the impact of each single feature.
So here, if you've got something like that, increasing X1 by one single unit will increase
the output by three units. So that's super easy for you to actually explain that model
to anyone. Same thing for decision tree, right? You've got the exact decision path that you
have to predict something. So here, that's I think some model from the Titanic, and we
see that, well basically, if you're a male, you're probably in trouble, because it goes
pretty bad from there, and you're the most likely to die. So you can explain exactly
how your model made prediction, and that's pretty good.
Some other models will be harder to interpret. So here, you've got the example of an ensemble
model as an ensemble of trees, something like a random forest, and here, it's a bit harder
to understand the role of each single feature, because you don't have a single tree anymore,
you don't have a single decision path, you've got multiple trees that are grouped together
in some way. So the good thing is that random forest, since they're based on trees, they
can still provide you with a feature importance, but the feature importance is usually just
given number to each feature, like kind of weighting how important it seems to be for
your model, but you don't know how a single prediction was made, you don't know exactly
how that feature impacts the outcome, is it positive, is it negative, you just know that
it seems to be more important than others. So still not extremely bad, but you won't
be able to explain your model properly. And then some other models are just really complicated.
So something like a deep neural network, it's really hard to actually explain how changing
the input layer will affect your output layer, and it's really hard to explain to someone
whenever your deep neural network has made any prediction, how do you explain what it
cared about, what it picked in the data. So those models will be seen more as black boxes.
So great, a bit of a joy killer here. Does that mean that you've got to stick to only
simple models if you care about interpretability? Well, sticking to simple models at least has
the advantage that the interpretability will be granted. So you're sure that you'll be
able to explain your model properly, but then there's a trade-off between the interpretability
and the performance that you get from your data. And then the second option is to use
some of those techniques that we'll see today, which are model agnostics, so they'll work
any sort of model of arbitrary complexity, and they'll allow you to have both the performance
and the interpretability. So that's the motivation for what we'll do today. Just a quick word
on two different types of interpretation before we get started. So I like to divide it as
you've got the local interpretations, so those will be basically explaining how a single
prediction was made. For example, in the case of our doctor, for a single person, we predicted
that they will have a disease Y or X. How do you explain to the doctor how that specific
prediction was made, what attributes of the patient was important towards making this
decision. And then the global interpretation is more explaining how overall your model
will work, what on average your model seems to care about, what it doesn't seem to care
about. So that's the example that we saw with the husky maybe. Like you would like to know
that on average your model tends to look mostly at the background and not actually on the
animal itself. Or for the case of the hospital, it's also important to explain that those
symptoms seem to be important for your model, whereas those other symptoms are never looked
at. So those would be the two different kinds of interpretation we can do and we'll see
how all the libraries we'll see today provide one or the other or sometimes both. Right,
so let's get started with the first library for today, Eli5. So Eli5 stands for Explain
Like M5. So I think there's a subreddit for that where they explain all sorts of things.
So Eli5 will have two things. It implements something called permutation importance that
is an algorithm we'll see a bit later. So Eli5, it's a Python implementation that is
an algorithm that works with all models that have the scikit-learn API. So any sort of
model that will have a dot fit dot predict, so that means every model from scikit-learn,
that means xgboost, lightgbm, catboost, any library that implements a scikit-learn API.
If you've got white box models, so like models like linear regression, decision tree that
are actually easy to open and look at what's going on inside, you'll be able to create
a nice visualization that gives you both a local interpretation and a global interpretation.
So it can be really useful to communicate the result of your simple models. Now if you've
got more complex models like, I don't know, like some boosting algorithms, some neural
networks, it implements another technique called permutation importance, but here it's
only limited to global interpretation, so you won't be able to explain a specific prediction.
So that's the plan for this first exercise. So just to show you a bit what it will look
like, so if you're applying Eli-5 on a white box model, so here I think I've applied it
on a linear logistic regression on the breast cancer data set, so here it gives you something
like that. So if you want to explain your model globally, you're just calling the function
show weights from Eli-5, passing your model, and you will be able to look inside, try to
find the weights, and give you some output like that, which I think it's quite nice to
explain to some decision maker how your model works. So here, that's the breast cancer data
set. If I want to go to a doctor and explain what my model seems to care about in the data,
I just go with this table and I show that, well, the most important, the three most important
features seem to be those three here, asking does it seem to make sense with your intuition
and your experience, and those features here seem to have a negative impact. So I think
here we're predicting whether something is cancerous or not. So in the first, those features
will increase the probability of it being cancerous. Those features here will decrease
that probability. So I can start to explain what my model seems to care about when it
comes to making decisions based on this data. Then as I said earlier, Eli-5 on a white box
model can also explain how a single prediction was made. So here, if I want to explain a
given prediction on a given observation, so for a specific patient, I just call the show
prediction function, passing my model and the observation, and it gives me a table that
is really similar where it tells me exactly the contribution of each feature. So here
I know that the fact that the worst area contributed that amount to the final decision and the
final probability is that the cells aren't cancerous with a probability of .79. So I
can really explain how that specific prediction was made by my model and justify what's going
on. Now if your model isn't white box, so if you can't actually open it and look at
what's going on inside, Eli-5 also implements a method called permutation importance. So
this one will be more diagnostic. You can use it on any type of model. It doesn't need
to open it. It will provide unfortunately only a global interpretation. So do you have
to use the same method? Not even. So those ones here work only for white box models,
so when it can actually find the weights directly in the model. So here those weights are exactly
the weights of your logistic regression. Here the weights are, the contribution is the weight
times the actual value of your, yeah. So Eli-5 wouldn't tell that to you. If you actually
created a term yourself for the interaction, then it will just show that the multiplication
is the same. So that's for white box models. Then as I said, you can use it on black box
models as well, but you'll only get a global interpretation. And here even, it's not even
that good either because it only gives you an amplitude. So really something similar
to the feature importance that you're probably used to on random forest or decision trees
where you have a number associated to each feature and tells you how relatively to each
other they're important, but you don't know in which direction they affect the outcome
or whatever. So it's quite limited, but it's a nice place to start. So the way that works,
briefly, you'll get your data set and your model that you want to explain and you'll
focus on each feature one by one. What you'll do is first for a given feature you'll shuffle
all the values in the provided data sets to kind of make this feature not powerful anymore.
Like whatever your model used to pick and to care about in this feature, since it has
been shuffled, it's not supposed to make any sense anymore. And then you'll generate predictions
using this new data set, using your model on this new data set, and you'll compute the
decrease in accuracy. So you're expecting the accuracy to go down once you've shuffled
that feature, and this decrease in accuracy corresponds to the impact of the importance
of that feature for your model. Yes?
Can you describe the shuffling more? If we had a bunch of comments that are totally different,
do you think shuffling would be worse, but is it between different?
So for each feature, you pick a feature, you've got all the values and you shuffle completely
all the values for that specific column. You don't mix the columns together. So shuffling
is kind of equivalent to deactivating that feature or deactivating its predictive power.
And then you just have to compare the impact on accuracy of each of the features and that
gives you the importance of the feature. So it's a pretty simple method.
And that's how it would work with Eli5. So you'd import the permutation importance model
that has scikit-learn APIs. It's quite nice. You just import it, instantiate it with your
model, then you call .fit on your data set, whichever data set you're trying to explain,
and then you just call show weights, same way we did before, in order to display this.
So in fact, it will not shuffle it only once, it will shuffle it a couple of times, return
the average importance of that feature and the standard deviation as well. So you get
a little bit more information, but you still don't know in which way this affects your
model. If we go back here, we see that each feature, I know if it affects the outcome
positively or negatively, because that's a white box model with permutation importance,
I only have this, I only have this, which is just the amplitude of the impact.
Right so any questions about that? Yes?
So you don't retrain the model, you just generate predictions. Yeah, okay. Cool, so
we've got the first practical then, which you can either open this notebook if you've
got it locally, if not, you can just go there on Google collab, click on skeleton, and
you'll have that. I think yours might look a bit different because you're not the owner
of the notebook, so I think there'll be something open in playground or something like that,
you can click on, that will just open it on your own Google drive, and then you can start
working on it. So the way we'll do that is that you can all start going through this
notebook, I'm here helping out, I'll walk and answer all the questions, and then in,
let's say, okay the time is not right here, let's say in 20 minutes I'll go through the
notebook and we'll go through it together and I'll take all the questions and everything
and explain what's going on. Cool. 20 minutes, 25, let's see, depends how long,
how long. So let's go through it together at 10 past.
Okay.
So you've got that format as data frame.
All right.
Do you want a little bit more time or should we go through it together?
What do you prefer?
Okay.
So let's say that I go through it.
Cool.
So first thing we do is importing a bunch of things.
So just a quick explanation of what we've got.
So we've got pandas, of course.
We've got some tools that we'll use from Psychiclone.
So just to process the data.
So the one hot encoder and the column transformer.
And then the grid search CV and the train test plates just in order to tune our model properly.
And then we're importing a couple of metrics.
So the balance accuracy score, which is just the accuracy score,
but taking into account of the imbalance in the data and the classification report.
So we can see a little bit more about the performance of our models.
And then the most important is we're importing four different models.
So that's the models we'll actually try to interpret for all the different,
with all the different libraries we'll see today.
So logistic regression should be fairly easy to interpret that.
Then decision tree, not too hard either.
And then things are starting to get complicated.
So random forest, it's a bit harder.
And boosting, so here let's light GBM.
So it's really similar to XGBoost.
It's the Microsoft version of XGBoost.
And that's probably the most complicated one to interpret.
So let's import all of that and then loading some data.
So the data that we provided here is from a bank in Portugal,
and that corresponds to some marketing campaign that they run.
And they wanted to have their prospects or clients to subscribe to some plan,
I think to some like deposit something, a special plan that they put together.
And so the data has got some information about the different clients,
some demographics, some information about whether they've been defaulted before or not.
And then the targets, what you're trying to predict is whether or not the person subscribes to the plan.
So here our goal will be first we want to model that.
So we want to build a model that can predict given characteristics about the people
and the campaign if that person actually ended up subscribing.
And then the second thing we want to do once we've got that model,
we're pretty happy with the model, is go backwards and explain that model in Tap Reddit
so we can maybe give some recommendations to our marketing team
and tell them well, looks like you did something differently at this point.
Looks like targeting those people is probably more efficient.
That kind of recommendation.
So let's do that.
First we're going to load the data.
So that's what I was talking about.
We've got a lot of different features.
They explained a bit in more details below.
But basically we've got the age of the person, their job, marital status, education,
whether or not they've been in default.
And then you've got information about the campaign itself.
So we know how those people were contacted.
Some were contacted by telephone, some by email.
So we want to know if also that affects the outcome.
They've been contacted at different month of the year,
so we can also see how that changes something, and at different days of the week.
We know also how many times they've been contacted before,
so that's the campaign feature,
and how many days between two times we've contacted them.
So here, if we contacted them only once, P days is going to be the maximum,
because there were no delay between two times they were contacted,
since it was only one time.
But sometimes we've got some people that contacted multiple times in the same week,
which might end up not being efficient, or maybe it's really efficient.
That's what we want to know.
Cool. So with that in mind, just a quick thing that we need to check is the imbalance in your data.
So here we see that most people actually didn't subscribe to our plan, which is a bit disappointing.
But that's something to keep in mind,
because we need to ensure that we don't only look at accuracy straight,
because it wouldn't be representative here.
We also need to stratify when we are creating our train test set.
So first thing is we're proposing a little bit, getting the X, the feature matrix,
with all our features and the target vector Y.
We're mapping a 0 to a 0, yes to a 1, and we're ready to get started.
So here just quickly check the types.
So we've got a few numerical values, so the age, the number of days,
number of times they've been called to campaign,
and we've got some categorical features, so their job, their education, etc.
So you can read more information about all those features right here.
I'm not going to describe everything.
So we're ready to go.
In order to preprocess the data, we'll first define two different lists,
because we want to treat differently the numerical values and the categorical values.
So here I've just provided a list of numerical features, a list of categorical features,
run that, and then I can create a column transformer object.
Who has used a column transformer before?
Only one person? Really? Okay.
So it's fairly new. It was released in Scikit-learn version 20,
so that's probably the latest.
But it's really powerful because it allows you to map a different transformation
on different groups of features.
So here I can easily say, well, for my numerical features,
so that's the list here, numerical features, I'm just deciding to pass through,
means I'm just going to keep them as they are and not changing anything.
But for my categorical features, I decide to use the one hot encoder.
So in just one single object, I can decide what transformations I map on different features.
So it's really powerful.
I just run that, and I've got this object, the preprocessor,
that I can apply on my data and directly get everything out of it.
So once we've got that, we can split the data into training set and test sets,
so I'm just going to pass X and Y. I'm going to do test size equal, let's do 30%,
and I need to make sure I stratify that because it's imbalanced,
so I'll do stratify over Y.
And then out of that, I get X train, X test, Y train, Y test.
Cool, so I'm ready to go.
Now I can actually fit this object to the preprocessor that I've created before.
I train it on the train set and I call .transform in order to actually apply the transformation,
and that returns something like that, so that's a NumPy array.
Not necessarily the easiest to read, but I've got everything there.
The next code provided here is just me trying to wrap the whole thing into a data frame
so it's a bit nicer to visualize and interpret,
so I'm just basically getting the list of all the categories that it has created when it created the dummies,
and I'm here having a list comprehension where I'm basically saying that each column should be called
the name of the feature it maps to, for example, if it's the education,
first it's going to be education double underscore and whatever value it has,
so education university or education high school or something.
And then I'm just grouping all my features together,
so my numerical features that I haven't changed and my new one hot encoded features.
So if I check all features, that's basically a list of names for my features, right, job, student, blah, blah, blah.
So with that, now what I can do is wrapping my data again into a data frame,
and it's much nicer to look at.
So I've got all my data here, quite happy with that, and I can start training models.
So the first model here will be logistic regression, so I make sure that I have class weight equal balanced.
I'm setting a random state just because I'm hoping we'll all get the same results.
Hopefully that will work, everything will be good. Yes?
Can you explain a little bit how the Stratify algorithm works?
Yes, up here? Yes, Stratify is just, since my model is imbalanced,
whenever I'm calling the train test split, which is in charge of separating,
of creating a test set in the train set by sampling at random from my data,
I want to make sure that the distribution of values in my Y target vector will be the same in the test data and in the train data.
So like that ratio that I've got up here, that ratio of nos and yeses,
I want to make sure that I've got the same ratio on the train set and on test set so the two are representative of each other.
So Stratify is just doing that by saying Stratify equal Y is just going to ensure that whenever it's doing the splits,
I've got the same ratio in the train set and the test set.
So back here, I'm instantiating a logistic regression.
I'll do the same thing for decision tree, random forest, and logistic, and light GBM.
So if I just do DT model equal decision tree classifier class weights, same thing.
I want that to be balanced. That's pretty much it.
RF model is going to be random forest. Same story here.
I want it to be balanced.
And finally, GBM model is going to be light GBM classifier and it needs to also be balanced.
So now I've got my four models, so logistic regression, decision tree, random forest, and gradient boosting,
and I'm ready to start using Eli5.
So first thing, I'll tune my model to make sure it actually has good parameters.
I can check the parameters.
Best parameters are here with C equal 1.
And the score I got on the training set was 70% accuracy.
And I'll just set my model to be the best estimator, get the parameters just to make sure everything worked well.
And now I can do...
If I go back here, yes.
So now I can just call it predict on X test and generate some predictions, right? Yes.
Yep.
What did that mean?
So that's a grid search, right?
I'm telling it, the logistic regression will have this parameter C, so I want to test multiple versions of C,
and you return to me the one that gives the best score.
So here it tried all those values and returned.
So banded the one that has the best score is 1.
Cool. So I've got my predictions here.
I'm quite happy with that. I can compute the accuracy.
So I'll do the balance accuracy just to make sure it takes into account the imbalance and properly weights it.
And I do white test first, white bread.
That's the accuracy I've got on the test set, right? 69%.
I can also check the classification report, white test, white bread.
And I need to print that.
So I've got information here. So it's not that good, but whatever.
Here the idea is not really to have the best model in the world, right?
We want to spend more time interpreting it.
So that's great. I've got my first model. That's a linear model.
That is white box so I can actually see the weights easily, understand it easily.
So Eli5 will do that for me.
So if I just do Eli5 show weights and I pass my linear model, that's what it provides.
Yeah, that's what it provides. So, yeah, not the nicest, right?
I've got the weights. That's great. But the features here are just numbers.
So it's not super easy to read.
So Eli5 has an argument feature. Oh my God, I can't spell. Names.
And here I can just say X test columns.
What did I do wrong?
I think it doesn't make sense.
Oh, okay. So I would have to do two lists, right?
Yeah, thank you.
Right, so yeah, it has to be the feature names has to be a list.
We could have used all features, the list that we created earlier as well.
But anyway, so this is much nicer to interpret.
So here we see that the most important feature in my data set seems to be the fact that the month is March.
So maybe we've done something different in March.
I don't know. It's worth asking the marketing team what happened in March.
Same with a few other months, actually.
The fact that the person was contacted by phone seems to be also important.
Maybe students are more responsive.
So all those things in green here will increase the probability of the person to subscribe to our plan, according to our model.
And the things in red will decrease that probability.
So here, maybe in November and August, we did things a bit differently that maybe we had less chances of people subscribing at those months.
But it's worth investing a bit more.
And that's information that we can use.
I mean, not that we can use directly, but we can start discussing with the domain experts.
So here you're not actually expected to provide a full explanation of everything.
It has to be discussed with the domain experts.
What's going on? Does that make sense? Is it a bug?
Maybe it's not normal that your model peaks the month of March.
So maybe there's something wrong with your model or maybe there is actually something meaningful that happened in March.
So that's something that needs to be discussed.
Right. So with that in mind, now we can look.
Look, so as we said earlier, if your model is wide boxed, the i5 also allows you to explain a specific observation.
So here we'll select an observation.
So I've selected the fourth, the fifth row in the data set, which for some reason is not the same one I had earlier.
Great. So the random doesn't seem to work so well.
Anyway, that's fine. Was it number three?
Okay. I can't find. Do you guys have the one with someone who is 27 years old?
Yeah. Okay. So it's just me then. That's going to be fun.
Oh, yeah. Thank you. That's probably it.
Yes, I don't have the random seed. So we put random stay equal 42, right?
You're getting what?
You're getting this. Okay. Maybe you're just lucky then.
Let me go back.
Yes, that's the one I wanted. Great.
So I have selected this row here. So that's person 27 years old.
So 27 years old, we've contacted that person four times already with on average three times, three days between two contacts.
This person is something. We don't know their job.
I mean, we know it, but I would have to actually do.
I'm not going to check the row now, but we would have to go back to the original data set to actually see without the one hot and coded features because here it makes it a bit harder to to find which one is actually equal to one.
Anyway, and that person ended up subscribing to that's why I wanted absolutely this one because that that specific person subscribe to plan.
So we'll see. We'll try to explain why do we why did that person subscribe to a plan actually something we can verify is that our model.
Our model predicts properly this.
Well, actually, we'll see it when we plot it. So let's just do that.
So in order to explain a specific specific prediction, we're going to use show prediction passing the model passing the specific observation that we want to explain.
So here that's my X test. I look I and then the name of the name of the feature.
So if I run that, yes, so here gives me all the information I need.
So first thing tells me, well, the true the true value that was supposed to predict is y equal one.
I predicted that with a probability of 96 percent.
So my model is quite confident that this person would have subscribed to the to the to the plan.
And here is the individual contribution of all the other features.
All the features. It looks like the most important thing my model cares about to make this precision is that this prediction is that is the fact that the marketing team contacted the person on their phone.
And then the second most important thing is that the person did not have default before here.
Also, some interesting information looks like the fact that we contacted that person four times actually decrease that probability of the person subscribing.
So here I have information also about about how maybe I should have even though the person still end up ended up subscribing.
It looks like the fact that I contacted them too many times might have decreased my chances.
So that's that's quite interesting information here. You can also share with the marketing team and reflect with them.
See if if if they would agree or if there is something that they would have done differently and you can explain why your model says that.
So the next step is to do that with the decision tree.
So we'll use the grid search the same way.
So here I don't want to type the whole thing. So I'm just going to move to the solution.
So we're going a bit faster on this part.
Decision tree just copy paste that here.
I'm just training the grid search on the decision tree instead.
And I'll check the best parameters. And what we care about the most is to actually interpret it.
So could be the one below as well.
So now I've trained my decision tree. I can.
Get the best model in here.
Compute its performance. So let's see how well our decision tree is doing.
So that's already a bit better than now.
The contribution is is yeah it's really model specific. So here for the logistic regression the contribution will be the like the weight multiplied by the by the actual value.
So here well the value is one. So there is the weight basically.
So here this is model specific. So you want you wouldn't you wouldn't compare two models with with those values.
Well other methods that we'll see later actually allow you to since they're more the logistic that they give you things in the same unit every time.
But here no I wouldn't I wouldn't compare two models.
So back to our decision tree.
Again we want to call Eli five show weights to explain it.
I passing I'm passing the decision tree model and I need to pass feature names equal all features.
And here we are. So that's what my model seems to care about. And that's where things are starting to be a bit disappointing.
So if I compare that to the result I had before for my logistic regression what's less good because this is only a feature importance only giving me amplitude of how important relative relative to each other.
Those features seem to be but it doesn't actually tell me in which direction. So here you see that I don't have anything in in red.
It just tells me what seems to be the most important for my decision tree decision trees the number of days between two contacts.
But that's that's all I know. I don't know if I increase the number of days. Is it better. Is it worse.
I don't get this information.
The best thing that I can do is the decision tree here is probably just floating it assuming that my trees and too complex which here it's starting to get a bit complex.
But that's probably the best I can get in terms of in terms of interpretability. So that's a bit disappointing.
And in fact it's it won't stop here like when decision tree is probably the last model that I can keep visualizing.
But then when we have if you remember we have the random forest coming next we have the XGBoost the light GBM model coming next.
So those ones will not be able to to interpret them at all.
So that's why we're introducing another method that is more the like no stick which is the permutation importance and that we discussed before.
So to use the permutation importance you import it first from Eli 5 and then you just instantiate it.
So if I do perm equal permutation importance you take the features that it takes.
So here first the first thing it needs is the actual model that I want to interpret.
So here my decision tree model my decision tree model and something else that I want to specify by default scoring will be accuracy.
Here I want to make sure it computes the balance accuracy right because my data is imbalanced.
So I'll just do balance accuracy and that's that's going to be my my permutation importance object.
Then I call I fit it on the test set.
Oh by the way something I haven't mentioned yet is here all my explanations.
I will do it with using that test set or that validation set or like whatever is not the train sets.
The reason why I'm doing that is because I want to know how my model works when it's generalized on some new data.
So I don't want to know how it's mapped the training set and it learned something from the training set.
What I want to know is that if I put this model in the wild how would how would it behave with some data it hasn't seen before.
So that's why here all my interpretation I'm doing it with the test set.
So I'm calling permutation importance I'm fitting it and now I've got the object train.
So I've done that and I'm ready to pass it.
So if I just do show weight and I pass it and again I'll need to do feature names equal all features.
And here that's the information it provides to me.
So as we said before what it's doing in the background is that it's just shuffling each feature one by one and seeing how that impacts the final the final outcome.
And then it's able to tell me how in terms of amplitude how how all those features like had an impact on the on the predictions on the quality of the predictions.
So again it doesn't actually tell me the direction in which the feature contributes it doesn't tell me if it's helps.
So like here the fact that the person was contacted on the phone it doesn't tell me if it's better to contact them on the phone or not.
But it at least tells me that this contacted them on the phone is important.
The month of June seem to be important as well the number of days we've seen before the age and then all those features here seem to be relatively not important.
And again since this since this method here is completely model agnostic you can use it on any any model.
So if you've got a new network if you've got the random forest or the XGBoost like we have later you can you can just call it on that.
Here I think I'm going to skip that part just to make sure we've got enough time to do everything.
But if you were to go through the following steps we just training let's check in the solution.
So we just training the random forest the same way we're getting the output of it and we're training the light GBM model.
Same thing in the same way and we're just comparing the feature importance for those different models.
So here the takeaway is really use Eli5 if you've got a white box model and you want to just try to visualize a bit a bit more nicely either local or global explanations and share that with with some people.
That's great.
If your model happens not to be white box you'll have to use something like permutation importance that gives you only some feature importance with only amplitude for each feature.
But then you can compare different models and see what they seem to care about at global level.
Any question about this Eli5 permutation importance this not work.
No great.
Yeah.
It's so it just wants to know how each individual feature contributes just on its own.
Like so it has no notion of how how it would interact with other features or anything just because they can map.
Yeah.
So that that is like probably the simplest method.
We'll see another library called chef that actually has is more interesting for what you're saying it can look at all the kind of the marginal contribution of a feature based on all the other features it's linked to.
So it's going to be better.
But for now that's that's what we've got.
And yeah that's not great but it does the job and then gives you some first so maybe that's where you'd start and like start debugging a bit your model and see what what you can get out of it.
Great.
So with that in mind.
So that's that's good but what the main limitation that we've seen is that if you if you've got something if you've got a model that is a bit more complex you'll only be able to see the global explanation of your model and not local so the new the other library will
see will see lime allows you to is both local and model agnostic so it will allow you to explain a single prediction in your from your model.
So that's the local aspect but for any any model so here we actually don't care at all if it's random forest and your network or anything it treats the model really as a black box and can tell you how important each feature is so here that's a diagram that I stole actually from the from the paper
from the paper why should I trust you which is the paper that was released with the library lime and written by the authors of lime and so that explains a little bit what's going on so here the idea is that we've got a model so that's ugly thing here with arbitrary complexity and at the same time we've got a row a single
observation with some information here that's the case like for for hospital again with a passion that a patient that has multiple symptoms so the person sneezes we've got the age of the person we know that the person doesn't have any fatigue and our model predicts that this person has a flu.
Great so that's the modeling part of it then where lime comes to play is that it trains something that will call next planner and we'll see later what what that is exactly and the explainer is able to give you something like that so that's a bit similar to what we've seen with the visualization in in Eli five so it tells you that the fact that that specific person sneezes or has a headache will contribute and contributes towards predicting the future.
So that's predicting that the person has a flu whereas the fact that the person doesn't have any fatigue contributes negatively to that that prediction so then when I go is that to whoever is taking decisions so here a doctor will say well that's what the model seems to care about and that's why the model predicted that the person has a flu.
So what do you want to do do you want to investigate a bit more do you want to give a treatment to that person do you want to maybe tell us that we should be able to model again because it's not good all those those outcomes are possible so how does that work so.
So this is the most simplified version of how high works and again that's something that is using the in the paper so it's not exactly how it works but I think it gives the intuition so let's start let's start with that so here the idea is that we have a model that is really complex really not linear or simple and it predicts two different classes.
That's in blue that red orange.
You see that we've got two different features about X one and X two and your prediction is here let's say that you've got the flu.
That's a really complex model and we also have a single observation that we want to explain so here this observation is the red cross that you can see here right so provided with that lime will be in charge of explaining how X one and X two interact and and and can be used to to expect the
use to to explain this this prediction so here by the way the model has predicted that this single observation is in the red zone so I think I said it's no flu or is it flu forgot what I said.
So, with that, with that, the first thing that lime does is sampling a new fake data set around the observation so it will, it will take this observation and create a lot of points all around it so that's all the points that you see here.
And for all those points since we've got the model we can also generate a prediction. So we've got with sampling all those points here. We call the predict from our model and we know that those are in the zone in the blue zone.
We can sample all those points here we know that they are in the red zone.
And then once we have all those points, we weight them, according to their distance to the to the prediction that we are interested in.
So here we only care about this prediction here so surely those points that we've created around there and that really event to explain what's going on here, whereas those points here and here really relevant so those will have a larger weight.
Those ones will have a smaller weight. And then the next thing that lime does is just fitting a linear regression on those, on those points by taking into account the weights and that linear regression here will be your approximation of your model in that local in that local area.
So we we basically assuming that the model could be approximated by something linear in that area. We actually fitting the linear model and we using that to explain the specific the specific prediction.
So here if if I'm using this line then to explain what's going on around here, I can explain that around here. X one seems to have really like it is a certain impact and X two has a certain impact as well.
So I'm using the weights of this to explain what's going on that.
Yeah.
So it's not necessarily over fitting. It's more a notion of so first thing how it actually samples those points so it knows the distribution of of all the points from the training data over X one.
So it just samples from that and knows like it's trying to build a new fake data set that is representative of your training data over X one over X two creates all the points and then it generates prediction out of it.
But I don't think over fitting would be the world the word here because what that's that's exactly what we're trying to we want to understand how model works. So we generating predictions from our model and then we fit a simpler model that explains it.
Yeah, you could you could see it like that. So we we're trying to say that in that local area model could be seen as almost linear.
And then we fit a linear model data is supposed to approximate it right. So if everyone gets the intuition that it's already already pretty good turns out it's not exactly what's going on.
So I've got next slide to explain a bit into more details what's going on. The reason why it's not what's going on is because we're not working with binary binary outcome.
So either blue or red here we're working with probably probabilities. So instead of your model is 100% sure that the prediction is red or the prediction is blue.
Instead of that your model will always predict probabilities of being in one or the other. But then probabilities are a bit harder to show in two dimensions.
So I've instead I've done another plot with one single dimension. So here let's say we've got one single feature and super simple simple model which is the age of a person.
And let's say that based on the age only so imagine there would be much more features than that. But here to simplify only the age your model is able to predict the probability of of the person having a specific disease.
So on the y axis here that's your that's your probability of having a disease. So between zero and one and there the age goes from zero from zero to 80.
So let's say we've got a first prediction that we want to explain. So we're like this person is 20 years old and my model predicts that they have 20% point two probability of having that specific disease.
So I'm asking what can you explain why do you think this person has the specific probability of having the disease. So then as I mentioned earlier lime will generate new points weighted by the distance from the observation.
Around that axis here and it will use the model itself to generate predictions right so it's it's sampling different values of the age and then for each value of the age is able to use your model that you're trying to explain to predict the probability.
So here age equal I don't know 25 or something like that I can use your model to predict that gives you this specific probability here I've sampled age 60 what it looks like the model has a higher probability for this specific age.
So I end up with data sets it's similar to what we've seen earlier where I've got points associated to a probability.
Yes it's generating new points.
So yeah.
Yes so that's what I was saying earlier so it learns from the training data the distribution of points over age so it has actually a long distribution of how how your points look like on the on the axis age.
Then it samples from that new points and it's able to generate prediction using your model so it's kind of see maybe you can see it as it's simulating your model in that area to see like how your model seems to work in that area to create a data set that can then use to fit a linear regression.
And once it's get that it's able to just fit a line at this at this locality and and that line will have specific weights and those weights will be used for the for the explanation.
So here you can see that if I'm using lime on this specific points and the specific data set it will learn that the weights associated to age at around age 20 seems to be quite quite low.
So it will tell me here that the age doesn't seem to be such an important feature for this specific for this specific observation.
Whereas if I had something like that so maybe around age 70 when I sample all my points the probability seems to go all this way so when I fit a linear model in that area here to wait on for the feature age in that in that local space is much higher.
So it will tell me for this observation age doesn't seem to matter so much it's almost flat for this observation age seems to matter a lot and that's exactly the kind of explanation I want.
I want to know why for this person it seems that age is the main reason why we think they have this disease for this person we don't think age is that relevant.
Right. Does that make sense.
Yeah.
Cool. So that is pretty much how lime works.
So that's a little bit more to it which is better described in the algorithm here.
So the first step is that for a specific observation.
We actually not asking to explain the observation.
Yeah.
Yes. So it's got the older the distribution of all the older features together.
It's. Yeah.
So, the, the only thing that was missing in this in this explanation is that we don't actually, because you've got to imagine that your model potentially will have 100 features.
And if I'm if I give you an explanation with 100 features that will be much harder to interpret.
So the way lime works actually when whenever you're calling it you're providing it a model you're providing it an observation but also how many features you want to use in your in your explanation.
So like how what are the top how many top features you want to do when I return.
And then from there the way the way it does it so it creates a new data set as we've as we've discussed then create it calculates the distances between the points to be able to measure the seminar similarity so what points we're going to care about what points we're not going to care about.
Then it's generally it predicts the probability of the points. And here, the number four is the thing we didn't mention earlier.
It's using some feature selection technique in order to select only and feature.
So if you're asking explain the model using only three features, it will select the top three features fast and run the linear model on those on those three features only right so it's got an extra step of feature selection to reduce your the dimensionality of your data first and then it fits the linear model and then it gives you the explanation.
Yes.
Yeah, so it's actually doing something like last so before like other feature selection technique to to reduce the dimensionality and then it trains.
It turns normal linear model on it.
So it doesn't do linear regression in the it doesn't do regularization the last step.
And yeah, so.
So what you've got at the end is is weights on the different features on the top and features that you're interested in.
So how it looks like in in practice when you're using it.
So you, it will give you something like that where the plot at the left corresponds to the actual probability that you you predicted so here for this specific sample and again I'm using the breast cancer data set so here predicted.
Class zero with probability of 80.8 sorry and here on the right.
You see the importance of each feature and that's the part we interested in here is the the explanation of how each feature contributed to that outcome.
So here we see that everything in blue will predict will contribute to the probability increasing for the class zero.
Whatever I've got in orange here contributes to this the to push it on the class one so you have to see it as like features push your your prediction one side or another for the binary classification here.
And then something else to note is that for categorical features it's being a little bit funny for categorical features sorry for numerical features it's being a bit funny.
It's just that since your outcome will be a linear model to to see the actual contribution of a numerical feature you'd have to take the value the actual value of that of that features multiplied by the weights which means that it becomes really hard to compare.
To compare contributions of different of different features together because you wouldn't have the weight only but the value multiplied by the weight that means that if you've got a value that is negative multiplied by weight that is negative it will end up contributing to your model positively which makes it harder to interpret that on the plot.
So what lime decided to do that to make sure that all the weights are easily comparable as they will discretize your your numerical values into different bins.
So here for example I've got the worst texture which is supposed to be a numerical value it will say well if was texture is in the box higher than 25 and smaller than something else then it's got this specific weight and it's user dummy value to it so that means that the weight is actually just multiplied by one for each feature which makes it like directly comparable.
So here you'll say the interpretation of this graph is that the fact that it's a shame we don't see the end here but the fact that the mean radius is between 13 and some other value has this exact impact on your on your final outcome the fact that the worst area is between this value and this value has this exact impact here.
Right does that make sense so that's the kind of graph you will be able to see with lime and again that explains only a local local prediction.
Lime can also be used on images so here we've seen tabular data only but if you've got say some some fancy neural network that can classify images you can apply a lime to it so what it will do is they will first divide your images into what it calls super pixels which are just larger areas that contain multiple pixels.
Then it will it will gray out some of the areas and same thing like create multiple new images with some of the so each area will be a feature and so like changing some of the blocks and see how how that affects everything and then it gives you some output like this so for example this is a frog.
This is a frog it tells you probability of point 54 of being a frog and that's what is associated to this prediction so that seems to be looking at the head seems to be the most important feature to predict that this is a frog.
It also has a really small probability of being just a bull and that's those are the parts in the image that it looks at to actually predict that so here you see that the eye actually looks like it could be a bull so it predicted it based on that and an air balloon as well so it looks like the heart here might be seen as a as an air balloon.
So we'll do that later and if you remember at the beginning when I was showing the pictures of the husky and the wolf that's basically the technique that was used to show that you just have a snow detector here.
So some drawbacks of lime so first thing it depends on the random sampling at the beginning of the new points so it can be it can be unstable like you might want to run lime multiple times before you actually believe the the explanation that gives you because you could just be happen to have sampled some points that are not representative and then the explanation isn't great.
Yes.
How would you report that how do you mean.
Yeah, so if you run it several times then if it keeps if it keeps giving you the same explanation because every time it gives you tells you what features seem to be important what feature is not important.
So if it always tells you the same thing you start having more confidence. If it changes every time well maybe you don't trust it so much.
Yeah, and then it also happens a lot that your linear model will be inaccurate because the the assumption here is that your model can be approximated locally by your linear model which is not always the case so the good thing is that you can actually check the R squared and see what's how good your model your local approximation is but it will often be quite inaccurate.
It's also quite slow sometimes in particular with images because it needs to generate a bunch of data, then call your model to predict on all those points and then fit fit the model.
Just before we, we dive in the notebook.
A few available explainers so lime works really well with tabular data with.
So like just all the, that's what we're going to do like everything that fits in the spreadsheet.
It has also an explainer for time series.
It has an explainer for images and for text for text it's quite nice actually that.
If you check the repository lime it's got an example where it's, it has read some images and it can predict.
Forgot what it predict predict some characteristic of the person who sent the email, based on some words that it picks in the data and able to highlight this the fact that the person use that word means that they're probably X or Y.
And then in terms of the API so it looks quite similar to what we've done with the permutation importance.
So first you'll need to instantiate your explainers whatever explaining you choose to use with your data.
So that's when it actually learning the distributions of the different features.
Then you pick an observation that you want to explain and you call explain instance on your explainer.
Here you provide the observation instead of providing the whole model you only need to provide the predict function.
So that's because lime is completely model agnostic so you don't even need to stick to some psychic learn model here whatever function you create that can generate prediction lime can use it to to approximate it.
And then you also pick the number of features you want it to use.
And finally, you'll have multiple functions so you've got one.
The main one that we're going to use today is showing notebook that just shows a bit that shows the graph that we've seen earlier so this one.
And then if you want to show the pictures the same as we've seen for the frog.
You'll call the function get image and mask, which returns exactly that.
And we'll see that in the notebook as well.
So, it is time for the break.
And then after the break we can go through the notebook.
Apparently the snacks are going quickly so you might want to run.
Do you know how long the break is 20 minutes.
Okay cool.
Okay.
Yeah.
All right.
So let's take another 20 minutes to look at this notebook and then again we'll go through it together.
So that's for Lime this time.
So just maybe we can just get started together.
So it's basically doing all the same steps we did at the beginning to train the model just quicker so we can you can just run that nothing new.
We're doing the train test splits.
We're creating the preprocessor then we're training all the we preprocessing the data.
Then we are training all the models so we're creating the logistic regression decision tree random forest light GBM.
And here we are.
So at this you can just execute all the cells quickly up to this point.
And that's where things are starting to be fun where we actually using Lime.
So then we'll ask you to create a new explainer and start playing a bit with it.
So let give you maybe 20 minutes.
Take a look on your site.
Yeah.
Yeah. For those of you they're using collab to run it.
There's just one thing.
So I forgot to I forgot to add help us that the help us that by file that you see here to collab which is used only for the Lime notebook.
Look it's like I just created a function that does some ugly stuff with the column names just to to properly like handle the data sets.
So the easiest way if you're using if you're not using collab you're fine.
You've got everything in the repo.
If you're using collab you might want to copy paste that function here in the help us that pie and just add it to the top of your file.
What is doing.
Sure. So it's in.
So it's in.
I mean it's going to be explained later in the notebook but basically Lime is is expecting your get critical features to be with integer labels.
So there is a lot of like just boring stuff that you've got to do to change them to integers and then change them back to strings, which I don't think it's the most important part of this tutorial so I provided the helper function for that.
But yeah so if you're using collab you're going to have to copy paste that in your notebook just to make sure you can access it later down.
Okay.
Great.
So once I've got that now things should be easier so I'm just going to call explain instance
on my explainer and I need to pass the row.
So here the row will be my observation.
And then whatever function I want to explain.
So here let's say I want to explain my...
Let's do the most complicated one.
So the light GBM.
And I want to specify as well how many features
I want my solution to have.
So let's do five, I think.
And I need to create to save that in an object.
And now I've got an explanation object
that I can visualize.
So I think it's the next step.
Yeah, that's here.
Then whenever I call showing notebook
on my specific explanation,
it gives me the graph that we've seen earlier.
So here I've got the prediction that my model did.
And most importantly, I've got the explanation right here.
So here it says that
the fact that the month is equal June
seems to be the thing that contributed the most
to my model, to my prediction, sorry.
The fact that the person was contacted by a phone
seems to be important as well.
And again, so we're seeing some consistency here.
That's quite nice, I guess.
Like Eli 5, if you remember,
was telling me that the fact that we contacted
that person too many times so that the campaign
is the number of times I've contacted a person.
So here it's telling me that the fact
that we've contacted them more than three times
actually played against me and decreased the probability
of the person subscribing.
Yep.
So it's a balanced, unbalanced dataset.
Could the campaign situation of contacting them
more somehow if you're aware of that?
Like if I do sign up, if I sign up early on,
maybe they will continue to contact me.
Would this outbreak be able to see that
or are we confident there?
So I think the data set,
the way the data set was constructed is that
campaign is how many times you've contacted the person
before they actually subscribed to the plan
and then we've got the outcome either they subscribed
or they didn't subscribe and then that's it,
end of the story.
We don't keep collecting data after that.
Right, so that's good.
So that gives you a local explanation of that.
Then you might want to try it again
multiple times with different seeds
and see if that has an impact
or if it gives you the same prediction over and over again
to know if you trust it.
Also to get more confidence in that
kind of approximation you can look,
you've got access to the actual weights of your model.
So here I can get the intercept,
I can get the exact weights that are associated to each.
So if you check,
if you check here, for example it says feature seven
has a weight of .153 something something
which I don't know why it was rounded to .16 but it was.
So that's this one here, oh no that's this one.
Wait where is the 16 then?
Oh it's here, it's the first one, sorry.
I'm just blind.
Right, so you can actually access the different weights
that have been associated to each of your features
and the ones that are displayed in this table.
You can also access the intercept
which here is an extremely useful
but you can also access the R squared
of your linear regression.
So here it's quite low but it will always end up being low
because it's a bad approximation in the first place.
But at least it gives you some idea of how good it is
compared to other approximations that you might do.
Pretty cool as well, you can take your explanation
and save it to an HTML file if you've got to share that
with your colleagues that don't necessarily
want to open a notebook.
So here I'll call that explanation HTML.
And then if you just go there, where did I save it?
Can't see it, yeah.
Is it gonna open, damn it, anyway.
Okay, I'm giving up.
Anyway, so you can save it as HTML,
it saves exactly what you see there.
It's just I'm struggling to open it.
I don't know what I've done badly.
It opens it with Visual Studio.
Anyway, so the point here is that you can save it
as an HTML, it saves exactly that graph here.
So you can just put that on the website
or share it with one of your colleagues
that will be able to open it
without having all the context around
and see exactly this thing,
see how all features impacted that specific prediction.
So here that's exactly what we've done,
so we're not gonna do it again, but you can explain.
Actually, that would be interesting
to explain different models.
So let's just copy paste what we've got above.
So here, this same explanation showing up,
I'm just gonna copy paste that as well.
Right, so I can check, so here that's the explanation
for my logistic for the model.
So I can just copy paste that as well.
For my gradient boosting function,
I can explain my logistic regression here.
So seem to be the same features actually that are important,
which is a good sign.
So it seems that my model are picking up
similar things in the data.
So the fact that the campaign was quite high,
the number of times I've contacted the person,
and the fact that the month was June
seems to be important as well.
If I check my decision tree,
oh, here campaign doesn't seem to be important
for my decision tree,
but the fact that the month is June is really important.
And if I check finally the random forest,
got the same thing.
So here, you've got that single framework
that allows you to get local explanation of your models,
but also compare them,
because they will all be in the same unit,
and you'll be able to see how different features
might be important for your different models.
And maybe I trust more one of my models than the other.
Based on that, but at least I'm able to explain them.
Yeah, any question about that part?
So I'm using Lime on tabular data.
Think that's, yeah.
How does the data get normalized
when you're looking to see this list
for the way you're normally normalized
for a logistic progression?
I'm just wondering, especially because of the kind of
you've weighted in code, categorical.
Yeah.
So I don't think it does any of that,
because here,
I don't think it does any of that.
Any of that, because here,
that would be, you would do that
when you're training your model, potentially,
but then you want whatever units to be the same as
your original data.
So if you're changing your features themselves,
it isn't gonna be in the same units
as what you've got originally,
so your explanation isn't compatible, basically.
It becomes inconsistent.
I mean, like, build the approximation here.
Yeah.
So, because whatever output it returns,
like the weights need to be compatible
with the data that your model is expecting.
So if your model is, if you've actually scaled your data
already for your model that you wanna explain,
then your weights that you return
will be compatible to this model.
Okay, that makes sense.
Yeah.
More questions about line for tabular data?
So here, I think it's supposed to be quite
straightforward and easy to use,
except for categorical data where you've got to
to do quite a bit of work before.
And then another cool thing with Lime
is that you can use them on non-tabular data,
for example, on images.
So that's what we're gonna do here.
So we're just loading some random neural network,
just instantiating it with preloaded weights.
So it's been trained on image nets,
so it already should be able to predict
that this is a token.
So I'm loading this image,
and I'm just gonna check actually that,
okay, first I preprocess it.
I'm gonna check that it predicts properly.
Right, so those are the predictions
of the model I just loaded, right?
So it's quite confident that this is a token,
99.999999, and then it thinks for some reason
that it might be a school bus or animal and fish.
Do you have a question?
When I execute predict in Co-Ed,
it says what it expects it to be,
2.9 by 2.9 by 3, and it found that it was in fact
in the dimensions of the pixel size in that time.
Yeah.
And it looks like it was that net.
Right there, if you get the 29.99.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
I forgot where.
You did some setup, yeah.
We did that line, and then we typed it for made up.
Okay, that's great.
Interesting, okay.
Great, and let's just do that, and hope for the best.
Right, so where was I?
Yeah, so I've loaded a model, I've loaded an image,
and I've just generated prediction on that image,
and it looks like that model is pretty good.
Now what I want to do is use Lime to actually know
what it's trying to look at in the data
to make those predictions.
So here, I'm gonna load the explainer for images,
so Lime image explainer, instantiating it.
Then, as usual, once I've instantiating the explainer,
I can explain a specific instance
and generate an explanation object.
So here, same thing, I'm passing the image,
I'm passing the model, I'm saying how many features
I want to return.
That's running now.
It's a bit slow, so that's what I was saying earlier.
Now it needs to actually work with many images,
process a lot of images, and then fit a model on it,
so it can be fairly slow, hope not too slow,
so that I can show the outputs.
I don't know if it's gonna run on colab.
Have someone managed to run that on colab?
Did it kill it before?
No?
Took quite a while.
Five minutes, okay, great.
I don't know, I've tried it before,
it was faster than that.
Anyway, so maybe I can explain the rest in the meantime.
So once we're creating our explanation,
here you'll have a function from Lime,
that is get image and mask,
that you can pass, that you can use directly,
and then here what you need to specify is,
the first thing is the class that you want to explain,
so my model has predicted multiple classes,
so that's what we see here.
So it's predicted 96, 96 corresponds to the token.
That's the first one here.
Then it's predicted 779,
so that corresponds to the school bus.
So here whenever I'm calling the get image and mask,
I'm saying, well, try to explain
why it predicted this specific class
and explain this specific thing.
So that's what I have later.
So if I just run that, still not ready.
Oh my God.
Do you have any questions in the meantime?
I really want to show the output
because it's supposed to be quite nice,
so I don't really want to skip that, but yeah.
Is the non-sample argument for the explain and something,
is that 1,000, which is like the ballpark number
that normally works, or is it like,
what's the threshold for reducing that for speed
versus something high enough that you don't lose control?
So yeah, 1,000 seems to be the good trade-off.
It just happens to be fast enough,
which isn't great either,
but yeah, if you go much higher than that,
it would just take forever.
Lower than that, it starts to be less trustable, I guess.
So yeah, but maybe I should have taken something lower here.
So, in the meantime, we can take a look at the picture.
It's quite nice.
Oh, it's done, cool, perfect.
So let's see, so let's try to generate,
so here what I'm doing is I'm saying,
explain why do you think it's a toucan?
Give me only those features
that contribute positively to the outcome,
so what specific things in the image
do you think looks like a toucan?
Then I'm saying, give me five features and hide the rest.
So here, if I run that, that's pretty good.
So it tells me that those things
are what things looks like a toucan in the image.
Those are the five first, so it calls it super pixels,
so it's some group of pixels that it put together.
Right, so let's see now what happens
if I select only one feature, so I'm asking,
oh my God, that's disappointing.
So I'm asking, show me only the top feature,
the one that you think is the most important
to say it's a toucan here.
I would really have hoped
they would show the beak of the bird,
but it shows that, so I guess it tells you
that it's not really that reliable,
like, did you all get that result,
or did someone get the beak?
Because if I run it multiple times,
sometimes I have the beak and I'm quite happy.
Yeah, true, true.
Yeah, you need to see the bright side.
Great, so that's the explanation of why it thinks it's,
let's try two actually, give me two, yeah, okay.
So the beak is the second one, it's not so bad.
But then I can also ask to explain
the other predictions it made, right?
Like, the first, the most likely class was a toucan.
It also thinks for some reason it might be a school bus,
so, and that's probably more interesting here.
So I wanna know why would you think that's a school bus?
And so I can run that, and there it tells me,
and it's actually pretty good.
So here, another thing I've added
is that I do positive only false,
so that means it will plot in red
what it thinks, like, put the prediction
in the other direction, so less likely to be a school bus,
in green, what is most likely to be a school bus.
And here, what it shows is that
this one actually makes sense.
So if you look at it, so it, everything that
is basically a toucan tells me, well,
this decreases the likelihood of being a school bus,
but this little bit here is what I think
might look like a school bus,
and if you were zooming on the image a little bit,
that's this part here that is a bit angled,
a bit square, so that, you could argue, maybe,
something that I'm interpreting my interpretation, right?
Please, so this little bit here,
at least that's a way to see it.
No, you don't buy that.
Yeah, anyway, that's.
Yeah, that's a school bus.
Anyway, so I guess that,
so LIME is pretty useful to kind of debugging a bit
and try to approximate your model,
but yeah, as we've seen, just with those toy examples,
it's not extremely reliable either, yeah?
I think before you said that what it was doing
was like graying out different parts
and then looking for features.
Yeah.
So really stupid question.
Would this be awful with classifying gray walls?
I think there isn't actually changing a color of it
like smooth gradient like that.
I don't know, actually.
I don't know if that's like, is it hiding the pixels
or is it actually smoothing?
Well, so it can't completely hide the pixel.
It has to somehow deactivate them in a way
by replacing them by some other numbers.
So I think it's not actually gray but black.
So it's just setting everything to black.
Yeah, if you've got different, yeah.
That's a really good question.
Is that what you do?
You classify black walls?
Okay, that's great.
You classify them as black.
Yeah, no, that's a really good point.
But I guess, yeah.
I kind of want to try it actually
just to see if it decreases everything.
But I guess even if you've got your black wall,
like you're interested in the parts of lights
that you're not interested in the whole black part of it.
So probably it would do something.
I'm not sure.
Yeah, more questions?
Yeah.
You mentioned briefly that when you pre-run lines
sometimes they give you different images.
Yeah.
More focus on the beam, more focus on the lighting.
So if you run this once and you take action on it,
how certain can it be that you actually can turn it off?
If the image doesn't change, more clarity about it.
Yeah.
What do you mean by you take actions on it?
So.
So if I wanted to change my color
based on what I saw here,
how would I do it?
So first you'll need to try to build confidence
that what Lime is telling you is true.
So I see it more as kind of a way to point
potential errors that you've made,
but not necessarily like telling you,
hey, this is wrong, fix it right now.
So it's more like if you see that
if I'm running Lime multiple times on this image
and it keeps telling me that it's another part
of the image, like if it would tell me every time,
well, here I'm trying to classify a toucan
and it consistently shows the background
as the most important feature on my thing.
Well, maybe there's something wrong with my data set.
Maybe I've got only the toucan is pictured
in a jungle or something, and then it picks the background
as the most important feature.
And then you go back to your data set
and you see if you've got some bias in there.
So that's more like giving you an indication
of what seems to be important for your model.
And then you don't necessarily take action directly,
but you try to explore and validate or not this thing.
So if it tells you the most important here is the background,
go back to your data set, see if there is some bias
like with images, mostly with this background or something,
and you can confirm or not.
Does that answer your question?
Yeah, yeah.
It feels like you can offer this a little bit.
It's too familiar.
Yeah, but that's the funny thing with interpretability
is that you, so you've got your first step
is you're building a model
that you don't necessarily trust that much.
And then your interpretability is basically a model
that explains the model,
which itself can be not that reliable.
So yeah, that's like you always have to kind of iterate
and build confidence step by step.
Yeah, more questions about Lime?
Nope, great.
So we can see, oh my God, and we've got half an hour.
That's perfect for SHAP.
So the last library I wanna talk about today is called SHAP.
So that's something that came up after Lime
and try to generalize to build a framework
that kind of generalize all those approaches.
So here the idea is a bit of what I just said a second ago.
So we've got your data set,
you're building a complex model
and you're generating predictions from it.
And then whenever you wanna actually explain this model,
you'll build an explainer.
So in the case of Lime,
the explainer was that linear model locally,
and that explainer can be used to generate explanations.
So that's the generic framework, the idea.
And then what SHAP is saying is that basically
all those libraries like Lime
and what SHAP is doing, what we'll see later,
consists in having an explainer that can generate
an explanation as a linear combination of all your features.
So like every sort of explanation that you'd get
out of SHAP or out of Lime is basically a weight
associated to each feature.
And when you combine all those weights together,
that kind of explain the final prediction.
So that's kind of the really generic framework.
Now more in depth, what SHAP is trying to do here
is that for a given,
so it works mainly as a local interpretability model.
So for a given observation,
what we want to do is compute the SHAP values.
And the SHAP values that define need to follow
the following equation, I guess,
which is whenever, so you'd have a SHAP value
associated to each single feature in your data set.
So if you've got age, you'll have a SHAP value for age,
and that will correspond to the weights associated to age.
If you've got education,
you have a SHAP value for the education.
That will be the weight that will be shown later, right?
So those are the weights of your linear combination in here.
And the idea is that SHAP values is basically trying
to find the correct weight for each of your single features
so that when you're summing all those weight together,
they explain the difference between the prediction
for that specific observation
and the expected value of the model.
So just to explain a little bit the terminology here,
what we call the expected value of the model
is the average prediction made by your model.
So like if you've got a data set
where you've got 50-50 of two different classes,
well, the expected value of your model will be 0.5.
So it's expecting that on by default,
if it doesn't do any prediction,
it will predict 0.5 for each value, right?
So that's kind of the distribution of your training data.
That's what your model would predict by default.
And then what we were saying with SHAP
is that every set of features
for a specific observation contributes
to pushing this expected value
towards whatever your model ends up predicting
for this observation.
So here, let's say my expected value is at 0.5
because my data set has 50-50 of each class.
And for this specific observation,
I predict 0.75 probability of being in the class.
Then I've got a shift from the expected value of 0.25, right?
And that's what I'm gonna try to explain
with the SHAP value.
So I'm saying, well, I've got,
for this specific observation,
I've got a shift from the expected value,
the average value of my model of 0.25.
How do you explain that feature per feature?
And then you'll have age maybe contributes
to 0.1 in that shift.
Education contributes to 0.5, et cetera.
So it will be able to say how each single feature
contributes to this shift.
So that's the main idea, that's what they want to do.
And then the second question is how they actually do it.
And yet here, just to reiterate that the interpretation
will be really that the SHAP value,
so the value for each feature for a specific observation,
a specific prediction will tell you how each feature
contributes to push the prediction the way it is.
So how it does that?
So from a really model-agnostic point of view,
and we'll see that later,
SHAP actually does more complex things under the hood,
but if we take the completely model-agnostic aspects,
SHAP is leveraging something called Shapley values
from game theory, which is just a way to know
the contribution of the marginal contribution
of something in a set of features in this case.
So the domain example that you've got is,
say you've got three people that contribute
some money or some skills to a team,
and what you want to know is how on average
each person brings to the equation,
but this person can have skills that overlap
with other people, so maybe myself alone,
I've got a certain contribution, so I get a certain score,
I'm that good at that level, maybe me combined
with another person, say we're talking about students
and we're doing group projects, so maybe me alone
working on a project got a certain grade,
me working with another student, I've got a grade
that is slightly better, me working with two other students,
I've got a grade that is even better,
how do you know the contribution of each student to that?
That's what Shapley values are in game theory,
to basically try to see the marginal contribution
of a single student, so the way to apply that on features
is that you first get a subset of,
like all the possible subset of features
that do not contain a specific feature,
so let's say we want to see how important is age
for your model, so you first get all the subset
of features that do not have age in it,
and you try to see how well your model
can generate prediction without knowing
the age of the person, so that's the first thing,
and then you see how adding the age to each of the subsets
improves the accuracy of your model,
and then what you've got to do is just aggregate,
average those contributions over all the sets,
so here the idea is a bit different
than what we've seen with permutation importance,
so permutation importance, we're just taking
all the features every time and randomizing
one single column and see how that affects the output,
so we only see the impact of one single column,
here we're actually observing how adding this column
to every other possible group of columns of features
impacts the model, so that takes into account
what you were saying, if you've got some overlap
between two features, it will take it into account,
maybe if say you've got, with a concrete example,
let's say you've got education, age, and job,
so maybe adding age to only job has a high impact,
but maybe adding age to job and education
has really limited impact to your model,
so here we'll be able to see it,
because maybe age and education are,
okay, let's do job and education,
maybe job and education are correlated,
so adding education to a set of features
that already contains job will have a really limited impact,
really limited improvement on your model,
whereas adding education to something that has only age
will improve your model, so here we take
every possible subset and we see how adding
this specific feature improves it, am I making sense, yeah?
So you have a lot of features that would be-
Yeah, so that is super expensive computationally,
because you've gotta try every possible subset of features,
so if you've got a lot of features, that's a lot of subsets,
and then every time add the single feature
you wanna test for, and that's for every feature,
so for every feature that you wanna get the importance of,
you have to do that, right, so does it make sense,
or should I do it again?
It's fine, not fine, fine?
Yeah, so just to summarize, I think the example
is actually the easiest to understand,
so I've got age, education, job, I've got three features
I wanna see which one is more important,
if I were to use the permutation importance,
I would just randomize each one one by one,
and I would know how each one is important on its own,
which is good, but it doesn't take into account
if two features are correlated,
so here by using this technique,
I've got those three features, I see how if I take only age,
so I wanna see how important the education is for my model,
so if I only have age, I add education to that,
I see how that improves the model,
if I have only age and job together,
I add education to that, and I see how that improves my model,
turns out that when I add education to age only,
it has a huge impact, if I add education to age and job,
it has a really small impact,
because most of the information contained in education
is already contained in job, right, so it handles that, yes?
So if you're not reprinting your model,
the models will expect three variables coming in, let's say,
so you have to choose some kind of an arbitrary variable
to put in there, you need to choose what you need.
So that's the next slide, so yeah,
so if you get that as the first step,
then there is this great question, which is,
well, here I'm talking about deactivating features,
like trying to generate predictions
with some features missing,
and with your model already trained,
you won't be able to provide some data
with features missing, so instead,
you need to be able to fill whatever feature
you want to deactivate by your default value,
so the way SHAP does that, which is just a choice
they've made is that they're saying
there's the same idea of expected value for your features,
and we say that if you're given the distribution
of all the values you've got for a given feature,
if you set that to the average value of all the values
that this specific feature can take,
you're basically saying that you take central value,
and you can't, it's like, will be a default,
and then your feature can either move higher or lower,
so you're setting, to deactivate a value,
you set it to its expected value,
to its average on some training data that you've learned,
and that will be the default behavior,
you'll see that as your feature is neutral,
it's not higher or lower than usual,
it's just the average, and then when you increase,
you can either increase or decrease this value,
and that's when you're starting to measure the impact.
Missing feature in this case
would be the wrong way to see it,
what we're saying instead is that we get average,
so like a neutral contribution of that feature.
And then, so those two things,
whenever you wanna use SHAP,
you'll need to provide some training data
from which it can learn all this information,
so it will need to learn the expected value,
so it will need to learn what's on average
the prediction of your model,
so it's 50-50 if your classes are perfectly balanced,
but it can be something different,
and it also needs to learn the expected value
of each feature, so the average,
the neutral version of each feature.
And then once it can do that,
it can start simulating the exact,
the thing we just said,
where it's building all the subsets of features,
some of them being set to their neutral value,
some of them keeping the value we expect,
and then we see the contribution
of adding the specific feature we want.
But as you mentioned earlier,
this is something that is gonna be
really computationally expensive
because that's tons of things to simulate
and predictions to generate every time,
and let's say you've got something like a K nearest neighbor
which is really slow to generate predictions,
and you need to generate predictions
in every subset of the data,
so that's gonna be really, really, really slow.
So what SHAP does is that it's got
some optimized version of that for different models,
so for example, for trees, we've got here,
it will have something called a tree explainer
that works only for trees where it's able to learn
the expected value instead of just take,
learning it from some,
approximating it from some training data,
it will know exactly the expected value of your model
given by the structure of the tree,
and we also know the contribution of each individual feature.
It's got an algorithm to actually learn it
from every single node in the tree
directly without having to simulate it,
so it's just a shortcut instead of having to simulate
and generate all those,
like manipulate all those,
all the data and generating prediction,
it will learn it directly by looking at the different rules,
binary rules you've got in your tree,
taking the different values from there
and compute directly as a closed form solution
the contribution of each feature.
So conclusion of that is,
if, so SHAP is model agnostic,
so you can use it on any sort of model,
but it will be really slow on,
on around the model,
so it has optimization for different classes of models.
If you've got trees,
you can use something called a tree explainer,
which will be really fast
and will take a lot of shortcuts.
So that works with scikit-learn, xgboost, lightgb,
and catboost anything that has trees
in scikit-learn way inside.
So that's really good,
because that's all the models we've got to test today.
For deep learning, they just released a class as well
that is able to also same thing as a shortcut,
just directly compute the contribution of each feature
without having to simulate it.
But then if instead your model is completely a black box
and you can't, it's not able to find shortcuts
to contribute those, to compute those contributions,
it will have to simulate it,
and then that will be really slow.
But if you need to do that,
you just import the kernel explainer.
So what does SHAP provide?
So that's the output that you can get
for each prediction that you wanna explain.
So you'll have, it will display the base value.
So the base value is the expected value,
so what your model would predict
if it wouldn't have any information,
so like just the default value.
So here, .59 for the specific example,
and then the output value is what it actually predicted
for this specific observation.
So here, from here to here, is the actual shift
that I have for the specific observation.
And then SHAP displays nicely
how each of the feature contributes to this shift.
So it says that this specific feature
for the worst concave points contributed
quite a large amount to push the prediction
in this direction, so increasing the probability.
So this in red here increased the probability quite a bit.
The worst radius here decreased the probability,
so pushed it on the other side,
and then you've got all the features like this.
So it's pretty nice visualization
that shows how the features are kind of working together
to push the prediction on one side or another,
which again comes down to this.
Like when you're summing the contribution
of each single feature through the SHAP values,
you have the shift from the expected value.
Right, so in blue you have the negative SHAP values,
everything that pushes your prediction
to decrease the probability,
and in red increases the probability.
Any question about it?
So that's SHAP for local interpretation.
Yep.
How does it do the average selection of the categorical data
to expect the most probable class?
Yep.
Oh, the most probable?
Okay.
So that's, because that's gonna be your like neutral level.
Yeah, so that's for local interpretations,
but then the cool thing with SHAP is that you've got,
since you've got contribution of each feature
for each specific observations,
if you plot all the observations together,
you can understand how your model
works at a global level as well.
So here what SHAP does is that it computes
this graph for each single observation,
if you need a new data set,
it plots everything together,
and that shows you the importance of all features.
So here what you're seeing is,
and this one is a bit hard to understand at first,
so if you see on the X axis is the SHAP values.
So on the left, it's negative,
on the right, it's positive.
So you can see that the X axis is positive,
and it's positive.
So all the points that will be on the left
will contribute to push the prediction negatively.
So here we're predicting whether something is cancerous
or not, whether a cell is cancerous or not.
So everything that is on the left
will make the likelihood of something
being cancerous smaller.
Everything on the right will make the likelihood higher.
So that's the first thing.
Then it shows every single feature as a rule like this,
so it's similar to the feature importance that we're used to.
And then this axis here shows the value.
So if it's in blue, it's a small value.
If it's in red, it's a high value.
So how do we interpret that then?
So here what we can see is that for this specific feature,
LSTAT, high values of LSTAT,
so all the things in red,
seems to decrease the likelihood
of a cell being cancerous.
So it's like in one single graph,
you can already start seeing not only how important
each feature is, but also in what direction it pushes it.
So here looks like for some of the points,
so some of the points that have a high LSTAT
seem to have a super high impact
on decreasing the probability.
So here that has a really, really small,
I mean highly negative sharp value.
So those points here, I might wanna look at them,
but it looks like the fact that LSTAT was high
had a really huge impact on the probability being lower.
Here same thing, I've got some points
with really low value and seems to have a really high
positive impact on the prediction.
Yes, you had a question?
Computationally, are these pretty inexpensive
and maybe because you already need to run it
to get one of those?
So there's multiple levels here.
The first one is we need to be able to compute
the sharp values for a single observation,
which for trees happens to be fast,
for non-trees, or yeah, for something that is not a tree
and you'll have to do that process,
that would be really slow.
So that's the first thing.
And then you've got to compute a bunch of points,
a bunch of observations to be able to generate
a graph like that.
So maybe dozens of them, which adds another level
of complexity.
So yeah, that can be quite slow.
If you're not using tree, that is gonna be really hard
to generate this graph.
It will take like hours, like really.
If you're using trees and you're limiting it
to maybe a dozen points or something,
that should be doable in a couple of minutes maybe.
Compared to the time it would take to categorize one
into linear, or do you get some savings?
So here you're literally computing one by one,
all the sharp values on every observation you give.
So yeah.
Yeah.
I'm sorry, I didn't hear you.
In this individual line, what is the weight
of the points that you're computing?
The weight here, it's just trying to show you
how many points are there.
The three of them?
Yeah.
So here you, so those seem to be potentially outliers
and most of your points seem to be here.
So this graph shows you a lot of information.
Here I see, actually that's a really good point,
I see for the DIS feature, so I'm not sure what the DIS is,
but what I see here is that there is a big chunk
of points here that have quite limited impact,
so it's pretty much zero sharp value.
So all those points here, for all those points,
this feature seems to have almost zero impact
on my predictions, but then for some outliers
that I see here, this feature, DIS,
seems to have really high impact
and those points have a low value.
So those points have a low value of DIS
and they seem to have, the DIS feature
seem to have a really high impact on my prediction
and here, positive impact, that means the cell is cancerous,
so probably I wanna look at those points
and see what's going on there.
So that provides you this information.
Same story for the RM here.
It looks like a few values that have a high,
a few observations that have a high value of RM
seem to have a really high impact
on the final prediction here, this RM feature,
whereas most of the points seem to have a low sharp value,
like a close to zero sharp value.
And then all those features here, so age
and all the other features seem to have
really small impact on my predictions
because they're all around zero sharp value.
All right, so that's how you'd interpret that.
Yes?
What happens if you use the average
to define what's neutral?
What happens if someone's using the average?
Yeah, that's a problem.
It's just, so that's the assumption here
that, because it needs a way to define missing value
and the way it decided to define missing value
is just giving it a new, whatever it calls neutral
and the neutral would be the average.
So yeah, that's a good point.
Yes?
That's when we can change that.
Like, could we just hard code,
change this as the reference point?
I don't think that the implementation
allows you to do that, but if the problem
is really skewed data, you could process your data
before trying to explain it.
Yeah.
Any questions?
So, I guess that, I don't know how obvious that was,
but we start with like, sharp is a way to explain a local,
to give a local interpretation,
to explain a specific observation,
but if you plot all the points together,
that gives you actually a really powerful
global explanation of your model,
which is much better than the feature importance
that you usually get on trees and those things.
Just, oh my God.
Just a quick word on the API.
So yeah, you'll build your explainer,
you'll compute sharply values,
and then you can either use something called force plot
to explain a specific explanation, observation,
or summary plot is the second one I see here.
It's time for the notebook.
So, how is that gonna work?
We've got two minutes left,
which is not a lot of time to work on a notebook.
So, maybe I'll just go through it
to show you what's going on there,
and you can take a closer look later.
How does that sound?
Yeah.
So, we'll load everything first.
Here, I'm training all my models,
so same thing we've done before.
And I'm importing sharp, and now I'm ready to go.
So, all the models, like I only want to explain
the light GBM model here.
It happens to be my best model, so I'll stick to that.
So, light GBM is doing boosting with trees.
Quite lucky here,
because that means I can use the tree explainer,
which is fast.
And you can try, actually, if you want,
you can train a K-nearest neighbor model,
and try sharp with K-nearest neighbor,
and you'll see it's really slow.
Right, so now I'm selecting the same observation,
so we're really starting to know a lot of things
about this specific person.
And here, my light GBM model predicted
.89 probability of subscribing to my plan for this person.
Cool, so now let's compute the sharp values.
Ooh, you see it was really quick.
Because here it doesn't have to simulate anything,
it just gets it directly.
And if I check the dimension of this matrix
that is written by sharp value,
is a vector with 57 values, right?
57 is the number of features.
So here, if you don't believe me,
that's what it gives you.
So, an array with a value
for each of the features that you've got.
Here, just a quick sanity check that we do.
So, the units of the sharp values that will be returned
will be in the same unit
as the default output of your model.
What that means is that if your model predicts
probability by default,
the unit of your sharp values will be probability.
If you're here, turns out that the light GBM
by default returns predictions as log odds.
So, all the sharp values that I've computed will be log odds.
So, I just need to keep that in mind
if I use the array directly,
what unit that is in.
So here, just doing some sanity check where I'm generating.
So, I wanna basically, I'm saying,
I don't really trust that sharp,
what the expected value of sharp is.
So, if you click on your explainer,
explainer.expectedvalue, that's what it is.
So, here, I just wanna prove that the expected value
corresponds to this.
So, to what's, to the average log odds
of the predictions of my model.
And here, if I do that, it's the same thing.
So, here, the only thing I've demonstrated
is that the expected value is what I said it was.
Which is great.
So, once we've got that here, just wanna prove again.
So, that's difference between the expected value
of your model and,
and so, here, lgbmodel.predictProbar
is the probability that my model predicted.
I convert that to log odds to be able to have
the same unit as the expected value.
And I find a difference of 262.
And if I check the sum of my sharp values,
it's 262 as well, right?
So, the sharp values have the property
that we mentioned before where the sum of them
correspond to the difference between the expected value
and whatever you predicted.
Great.
So, that doesn't actually tell us much.
It just verifies that it seemed to be working.
So, now, the first thing you can do
is generate an explanation for your single observation.
So, we'll call force plots on,
I need to provide the expected value of my model.
So, I have it explain the expected value.
I need to provide the sharp values that I've computed
for the specific observation.
I need to provide the observation itself.
And here, actually, sharp is being quite nice with you
and giving you a parameter where you can choose
what you need to display it in.
So, by default, it will display in whatever unit it is.
Here, I'm saying, can you show it as probability
because it's probably easier to visualize.
So, here, that's what I've got.
So, that's quite interesting.
So, the base value is .38, so as a probability,
and the output value, so what my model actually ended up
predicting for this specific observation is .9.
And then, it's saying the fact that the number of days
is equal to three seems to be the most important thing
that mattered for this observation.
And it had this big of an impact.
And the fact, again, that the campaign,
so that we called the person four times,
had a negative impact, and that's how much
of a negative impact it had in the final outcome.
So, that's quite an interesting plot.
And here is all my interpretation of it.
And I haven't got time to read that,
but the idea is, it kind of leads to some questions,
like, well, that's great.
Seems to be, like, the number of days
between two calls seem to be important.
The number of times we call the person seem to be important.
What happened in June, is it important as well?
So, that kind of leads to questions,
like, first, you want to ask maybe to the marketing team,
but also, you want to explore if those things
that are important for this specific prediction
are actually important for the model as a whole or not.
So, that's why we want to see
some global explanation of that.
So, here, turns out that if you want to do that,
you first have to select some observations.
So, I could do it on the whole data set,
but as I say, it's probably gonna be slow.
So, instead, I've only sampled
a dozen observations at random from my data set.
I call that observations.
Then I compute Shapley values on that.
And here, if I check Shap values shape,
I've got a dozen rows and each row has 57 values, right?
So, I've got a Shap value for each feature
for each observation.
Then, I can call force plot.
So, force plot works if you pass Shapley values
for a single observation,
but it also will generate something
if you call it on multiple observations at once.
And that's what it looks like.
So, that might be hard to read,
but basically, imagine it as each line like this
over the y-axis, so like this,
corresponds to the red and blue line
that we used to see horizontally.
So, what that is, is that here is a single observation
and it has grouped the observation that look alike.
So, here, I've got a bunch of observations
but 100 observations from index zero to 100,
100 observation where the number of days
seem to have a really high positive impact on my prediction.
So, here, all those values seem to have p days
with a high positive Shap value.
So, pushing my prediction
to increasing the likelihood of subscribing.
So, all those points here seem to have that.
Then those points here seem to be around 50-50 prediction.
So, I don't really care much about those.
Here, I've got points where, again,
they have a high probability of subscribing to the plan.
So, that's the probability that you see here.
High probability of subscribing to the plan
and I can't see, but it would tell me
what features seem to be most important for those points.
So, it's kind of trying to group them like this
and then you can do all sort of things
like sorting them by number of days, for example.
And here, that's interesting because I see that,
let's do instead, let's do age actually.
Age is really interesting.
So, age, so if I say, okay, sort all my Shap values
for all my points by age.
So, here, you see on the x-axis is the age.
It goes from about something like zero to 90.
It grouped them.
So, I see that here for age around 20,
age around 20, I've got a really high chance
of subscribing to the plan and I've got all those features.
So, here, the age itself is actually really important
to push the likelihood of subscribing to the plan up.
So, there's a group of people between maybe 15 and,
that's not the unit, okay, that's not the same,
between 15 and around 25 that seem to have
a high likelihood of subscribing to my plan
and the fact that they are that age
seem to be the most important feature here.
So, that's one group.
Then I've got all those people here
between the age of 25 and around 60,
for which, first thing, they have about like .4 chance
of actually subscribing to my plan.
So, those people are actually not interested
in my plan at all and they have multiple features
that seem to be pushing it up and down,
but not having a huge impact.
So, here, it looks like for all those people,
the different features that I've got in my data set
don't seem to affect the outcome very much.
So, those guys probably, I wanna tell the marketing team,
well, for those people, you can't really do much.
They seem not to be interested in it.
And then I've got another huge group of people
between the age of 60 and 90 that seem to be really impacted
by different features.
So, here, it's hard to see.
I wanna know which one is that.
So, that's the month is June.
So, for some reason, one of the important feature
you see in red here seems to be the fact
that the month is June and the age as well.
So, all those things are pushing the predictions up.
So, you're seeing like already two groups of customers,
three groups of customers.
Young people were likely to buy my plan.
People in between that don't seem to care much
and older people that seem to potentially care a lot.
Then you can also select, for example, number of days.
And here, I can choose only the effect
of the number of days.
And that's, again, really interesting.
So, here, that's number of days from zero to a thousand.
And I see how the number of days between two contacts
seem to impact the likelihood of subscribing.
So, here, I see that if I don't wait too long
between two contacts, I increase quite a bit
the likelihood of subscribing to the plan.
So, here, from .4 up to .8, pretty much just because
of the fact that the number of days is so small.
But here, if the number of days is really high,
around here, I see that that is having
pretty much zero impact on the prediction.
So, here, if I'm waiting more than, I don't know,
about 600 days, then the number of days end up,
it doesn't matter much anymore.
Yeah?
So, could you say then that your customers
really are between this age and that age,
and you should contact them no more than three times,
but no more than 600 days?
Right.
Yeah, I mean, if you would want to jump to conclusion
directly, that's probably what you would do.
But it's more likely that what you want is to take notes
of those and discuss, actually, like, does that make sense?
Does it correspond to your intuition,
or like what you've seen on the field?
And also, one other interesting feature
that I wanted to show is campaign.
So, how many times, how many times,
how many times we've contacted the people?
So, here, I can see that,
like, if I contact up to maybe, like, about nine times
a single person, doesn't seem to matter too much.
It doesn't seem to have too much of an impact
on the final prediction.
But here, looks like, for a lot of people,
if I contact them more than, say, 12 times,
the number of times I contact them seem to be
super important and have a super high,
super high negative impact on the likelihood
of subscribing.
So, here, I can go to the marketing team and say,
well, it looks like if you contact them more than 10 times,
it's really being counterproductive
and really decreasing the likelihood
of the people subscribing in the end,
which, again, is some interesting finding.
So, also, I think, and there is more that you can explore
here by just changing how you wanna sort your SHAP values
and how you wanna filter if you wanna show the whole thing
or just the impact of a single feature.
So, if you haven't followed the whole interpretation,
I've tried to write it down here,
so you might want to look at that later.
Just to finish with that, summary plots,
so the one we've seen in the slides,
but for this specific thing here,
so tells you that the contact,
the fact that you contact people by phone here
seem to be quite an important feature.
I'll decrease that a bit.
Seems to be quite an important feature,
and it's perfectly ordered.
So, it looks like if contact cellular will be zero or one,
so it looks like if it's one, it has a positive impact.
So, I can tell the marketing team,
well, it looks like all the points
for which you've contacted people by phone
seem to have, the fact that you contacted them by phone
seem to have a positive impact on the outcome,
whereas all the people that you did not contact by phone,
it seems to have a negative impact,
and sometimes quite a high negative impact.
So, at this point here, it's further than this one.
Here, the number of days, that's something
we've already noticed on the previous graph.
So, number of days, if it's,
yeah, if it's just normal value,
it doesn't seem to have much of an impact.
So, if number of days is between,
like, I don't know, higher than some values,
I forgot what did we say, but if it's too high,
it doesn't seem to have an impact at all.
But now, if your number of days is really low,
so that will be the color blue,
it seems to have a huge positive impact on the outcome.
So, here again, just by looking at that,
I can say number of days, if it's low,
it has a high positive impact.
Then you can see all sorts of things.
So, you can see campaign is the opposite story.
Like, if I contact people too many times,
so here, I contacted that person too many times,
it looks like it has such a huge negative impact
on the final outcome.
So, here, those points are probably outliers,
but I contacted them so many times
that that ends up being the main reason
why they didn't actually subscribe to the plan.
So, you can see a lot of things like that in this graph.
Here, those things don't seem to matter too much.
Those points here are around zero, sharp value.
Yes, someone had a question, yeah?
I don't think it would cause a big relationship.
I think if you nag someone at a time,
and they haven't responded yet,
and you nag them more, it won't help you.
So, saying that calling them four times
is a negative predictor is because if I call them four times
and they haven't signed up yet,
calling them four times won't cause that.
Yeah, so.
Calling them more is gonna make it less likely to subscribe.
It's just that if you have called them four times
and they haven't subscribed yet.
Yeah, so that's.
Calling them more times is probably not gonna help you at all.
But so, that's exactly the kind of things
that you need to end up discussing
with whoever is the domain expert.
Instead of just going through conclusion yourself,
you're like, well, okay, so that's what seems to happen,
and that's what I can see in the data,
the impact of different things.
And then you discuss, well, is that something
we can actually take action on,
or is that something that, as you said,
that is just how it is,
and that we're just seeing a normal impact.
Changing that will not make any difference.
It's not like you're gonna call them
and they're like, hey, forget it.
Yeah.
And they're not gonna subscribe.
Yeah, exactly.
They stop once they say yes, right?
So there's a big difference between what you see
in the data and what recommendations you make,
and whether those recommendations will be any useful or not.
And then just to finish with that,
something that I didn't mention,
an extra thing that you can see,
what you can do with SHAP is dependence plots.
So here, just really quickly,
if I wanna see the impact of age condition
with whether the person was contacted by telephone,
for example, here you've got the age on the x-axis.
So from 20 to 90 and the impact,
so the SHAP value here.
So I see that around age 20,
I have actually a high impact.
The age has a high impact.
Age, like between 60 and 90,
it has a high impact as well.
Age between 25 and 60,
it doesn't seem to have a high impact.
And there you can see how contacted
those different groups by telephone
had a different outcome.
And here it doesn't seem to show anything interesting.
Yeah, not much to see here.
But ideally, where such a plot would be useful
is that if you see that around age 60 and 90,
maybe the impact of calling someone on the phone
would be more important than another age or something.
So that could be an interesting,
here it turns out there is nothing interesting to see
with this specific plot,
but you've got the option to do that
and see how different features,
when they're linked together,
they might end up having a different impact
on your final outcome.
Right, so that's the end of this tutorial, a bit late.
Just to finish, so model interpretability,
it's important to give trust
that your model is doing the right thing.
It can allow you to debug your model
and really spot some biases in your data potentially,
and you might want to fix your model after that.
It allows you to explain to others as well
how a prediction was made.
If they're the decision maker, it's really important.
And also you have regulations that make it mandatory
to actually explain your model.
Now practically, what you end up seeing is that, well,
if your model is tree-based or something,
SHAP will be perfectly fine
and will probably allow you to do a more in-depth analysis
and see, get much more information locally
and globally as well.
So if your model is tree-based, you're in luck,
and you can use SHAP, and it's gonna be quick enough
so that you don't have to wait ages to get a result.
Now if your model is, if you want a method
that is completely model-agnostic,
you can still use SHAP, but it will take forever to compute.
So it's either how much, I guess, you value the output of it,
and if you wanna take hours to compute the SHAP values
on this specific model to be able to interpret it later,
then you might stick on SHAP.
If you prefer to go for a quick approximation,
you might want to use LIME instead.
I guess that would be a rule of thumb.
Yeah?
Yeah.
It would make sense to do
like this sort of standard feature importance first,
and then, oh yeah.
Off like random features.
Yeah, so even like something like permutation importance
would generalize to all models fairly quick to compute
and gives you something that you can compare.
So yeah, probably you'd start with permutation importance
to see maybe as a feature selection as well,
or just to first debugging intuitively
what seems to be important or not,
and then if you want to really go into more depth,
SHAP or LIME depending what's,
how much time you wanna spend on it, I guess.
Yeah?
Great.
So that's all for me.
Yeah.
Yep.
Thank you.
Bye bye.