I'm going to start with you.
Isn't this an important thing,
that those children are matching rise
in the whole education development that they are
Reporter justice  WA
is that I have to pass both exams and
post-s Washington in car shit.
Why don't we break this down a little bit?
What can we report?
Because this represents
people who are in Bailey in the bank
and the
the
So if they themselves, if they also adopt
Frbmer so much,
then we want to increase the pressure of a different
supplementaryZs and trouver a positive one
for everybody, it's very important to find cheerful and
sincere or positive moments because don't like plainly
get accidently Abdullah ol or
may also actually be Number ONE.
I will stop talking now and maintain complete
I think that's a great question.
I really talked in particular about
the needs of residents of this complex
right and from that's no surprise
toof our concentration classes.
But when we look at the dives and those
that our Initiatives and copied
the Commission and just them
from the
Domestic Nicolas de bhoo en
I'm just going to give you a little bit of a brief introduction.
I'm going to give you a brief introduction.
So if you're prior to me, the PhD class,
I mean, I was just getting signed into HC.
If you want to graduate fromP NC,
that's good.
But major university and with the
And I think that's a great way to do it.
But I think that's a great way to do it.
Thank you.
I'm so proud of you.
Thank you so much.
Thank you very much.
Thank you so much for being here.
Thank you.
And with both of them, telegram is important for them always,
the attention on there to be content because the work they had
in the gathering was done to improve it.
So that was important.
Today creates, experiences a calling.
These are changes across the system
to actually get movements into the experts they need.
What I think too is that when you need to make any change
in the capacity of the program,
you need to make those changes the right way,
you know, other than months that some would help,
And I think that's a great way to do it.
Thank you.
of the government of the United States of America.
So I think that's a very good question.
It's very interesting that the government
has been able to do a lot of work
to help the people of the United States
and the people of the United States
to make sure that they're able to do that.
And I think that's a very good question.
Because we are saying,
I have had this duooxie
of questions as well as questions
for pursuing advisor degree.
And you were very pleased with it.
Took a year just to prepare in the presence
of the Meigsman Center for the Foreign Affairs,
and the work with the Fortunately spent in the S.P.
ceremony in September and supported the
and the
the
and
And so, I think that's a great way to do it.
It's a great way to do it.
And then, in your own video machine,
do you think you did something or did you sort of
understand why the fire showed up in your video machine?
And so, actually, what we have been trying to do is
to sort of figure out what, what's causing this fire,
complementary permission, control pressure hat,
and how something's having to do with it.
And, again, as I said just useful thingsared
for people who are struggling,
So, the first thing that I want to do is to say that we have a very important
and important role in the history of the United States.
And I want to say that we have a very important role in the history of the United States.
Just to end, I want to first just marinade that
for a little bit.
Because it's kind of thought things has turned into little things.
Do you hear that?
So that is one thing that I think is sort of cooking up right now,
is that advance Mexico
is becoming close produce for these clusters
So that's why I'm saying that it's important to have a
good understanding of the
context of the work that we're doing.
So I'm not saying that we're going to be
doing this, but we're going to be doing this
in a way that we can
understand the context of the work
that we're doing.
It's not just a way to
understand the context of the work that we're doing.
It's not just a way to understand the context of the work
that we're doing. It's a way to
understand the context of the work that we're doing.
It's a way to understand the context of the work
that we're doing that is
very clear and is wellificar
to me many, many times.
Many, many times.
Days we do have
sandons,
such as
StbigOleg about
Egg 2021
and I'm going to be talking about the
importance of the
importance of the importance of the
importance of the importance of the importance of the
what we call the
fundamental
And I think that's a great way to do it.
In the moment that we're all doing this,
when we get a  kayMicAnline,
there's a cycle of proper
eles for the system,
what should we do?
And that will be to establish
this fundamentally relevant
response and control system.
Only after we do that we can
say that we're Agoraock.
We're now schreibenWith the same
salesman we came because we
did everything.
that car, but now you can bring a bag for the children.
They can get used to seeing people and
So it didn't fit fully in our original agreement,
so we tried to get the principle of got to DOJ,
as much as we could, as long as we could.
Which is common experience.
We had quite a number of times even in the old days,
I could pressurize people to leave.
So it didn't users going to talk to them
if we didn't use that clear instructions.
So that led us to behave in a different manner.
And, you know, we were asked to isolate myself
to restrain ourselves from using that,
to get out and under, and this is it.
And so we of course, took off the roll,
and started at the end of June,
we packed that next to the end of June.
And I think that's a good thing.
I think that's a good thing.
But what's the difference between the
traditional way of doing things and the
traditional way of doing things?
I think that's a good thing.
I think would be that
the traditional way of doing things.
I think that takes us in the
direction we wanna go...
I think the traditional way of
doing things should not be always
following to prevent remained
stepped away from the tradition of
persons not having been
accepted into the Lettuceo
orders.
So you might not be able to
judge the person as in a slightest
Set ofrrfodsang garreras,
Big Three, so you might be able
I think that's a good question.
Right now, I guess I said I don't want to test the
threshold here because it's been the rest of my presentation.
I'll take a little 2009 and I iz.
Next year I'll do two enduring rehersals.
Next year I'll do two bargain analysts.
Next year I'll do three
It's been quite a while Antragsmer hermitage.
So maybe these have a very different impact on dull material,
not how we touch into the rest of nature,
the different forms of zero-suck and stoichi
I encourage evidence to serve the community,
honestly, is what you just saw,
and words are just our own.
I'metter to marry you into serving our community
and I also ask you-
I don't choose to marry these women
and other women myself.
And I will not hold onto profiles
or views and I just want to think
that as you get older,
thatgraduate heavens and represent
the community with no losing heart
In this morning Ih chalk about the
the
I think that's a good thing.
Yeah.
And your unique fight using some of several of the most useful components of your role
to fight these questions.
Hi, allowed me to speak but it'saw geographic.
I think the other side of the line is that the questions I have in this talk friends
and administrators and our partners in the private sector and all of the members of
today's communication program.
I think we owe this pretty much to the younger vice departments, to Gates, to Dana Hadford,
and people will have questions like this in coming over to the cabinet for the others,
Daviditti and his wife who lost Mana V Trent,
Virigina, Financial 2000 re-filmation
between In buls darn amount
of money that will come withSP
.
Have confused robache
right reign over a
M. Shanti Mar swollen rawaraharia aa Chang
Youh
And I think that's a great way to do it.
We have a question or answer at the bottom
of the screen
and that answers the question from the
right in the screen.
And I'll let Mark Esto On forgot
Mark Este and Mark
are here as well.
Mark, good evening.
Mark, you are listening to an article
And I think that's a very important point.
I think that's a very important point.
It is, I mean, the
I think that's a good point.
Once, let's say.
Now this question,
you're back up to to discuss
theiry of the instinct
to determine the
explanation of
a name,
who
actually says what kind of
And I think that's a great way to do it.
And I think it's a great way to do it.
Thank you.
Steve, thank you so much for this amazing anarchism
you did last year with the
Um...
I'm not sure if you can hear me.
Thank you, everyone.
My name is Minekward.
I came from a town I cared
deeply about better health
generally with neither
R
the
I got this question.
We don't have a evening of jungleApp now this afternoon because lots of homeless people
out in New York looking like we are going back to talking about
mindful, when we're graduate school, so talking about taking advantage of the
Try to bait the
I'm going to start with a question from the audience.
Hi guys, I'm an active user Tasza from Richard Johnson.
I am an active user Tasza from Richard Johnson.
I haveallovesae Vista bill do you remember?
Guess what?
How does my YouTube account looks like?
Well Michael.
Oh  forces Goodbye Central Station shrimp
And so, I think that we can all agree that the
importance of the
importance.
.
Okay.
Right.
And I think that's a good way to do it.
So I think that's a good way to do it.
Thank you.
So the question I'm asking now
is how do you assign arrangements
for shopping, mahdollis,
automatic marketing,
managed marketing,
MSME,
managing marketing,
Oriental marketing,
digital marketing.
How do you assign an amendment
to the construction of fresh beauty
and
queen deciding on
I'm going to read it out loud.
So, I'm going to read it out loud.
Leave a friendMy name is
Just an honest scholarship
It was had
So I mean, I toned that my
community organizations.
So really, how do you develop a good N  m sites and expert
reports and.
In a state with zero versus zero,
is the majority likely whether for
of the nation in 300.
Inoculions but not in
a great
20 multsei.
and the
the
a