Thank you everyone. Welcome to the first afternoon session here on Saturday. First
up we're gonna have Dustin Ingram talking about pep572, the walrus
operator. Please welcome Dustin Ingram.
Hi everybody. Yeah so I'm Dustin. I'm a developer advocate at Google. I focus on
Python. I also work on the Python package index and some other things but
I want you to just sort of think of me as for this the purposes of this talk as
just a regular Python user just like all of y'all and what we're gonna talk about
today is a pep, pep572. But before I tell you about this pep and what it does we
need to talk a little bit about Python governance. So Python governance is the
answer to the question how do we govern the language of Python? How do we make
changes to the language? How do we implement new features and that kind of
thing? How do we make decisions about Python? So when Python was first created
its creator installed himself as the BDFL, the benevolent dictator for life.
Dictator meaning that he can do whatever he wants to the language. Benevolent
meaning that he's generally going to be looking out for us. So this is creator of
Python, Gito Van Rassum and yeah he's our BDFL and the thing to note is you
know maybe at the beginning of Python Gito was making all these decisions
himself. Gito didn't until recently didn't really make all these decisions
himself anymore. Instead what we do is we have a process and that's called the
Python enhancement proposal process, the pep. So a pep is kind of like an
amendment to the Constitution for a country. The Constitution determines how
a country is going to be governed. So each pep determines what we're going to
do with the language and how we're going to change the language and each one sort
of builds on a previous pep. So we started with pep one and we went along.
So can anyone name a pep? Yeah, pep eight. I thought you were gonna say that. So pep eight is a
style guide for Python code. It's a pep that describes sort of a general way to
write Python code. Its author is Gito Van Rassum. So this is a pretty early pep and
it was authored by Gito himself. Another well-known pep is pep 20. This is the
Zen of Python. This is what you get if you type import this in your Python
REPL. Its author was Tim Peters. Tim was one of the also the core Python
contributors. My favorite pep is pep 566, metadata for Python software packages 2.1.
The reason I like this pep so much is because I am the author of this pep. So
when I wrote this pep, this is kind of what the process was like. First I wrote
a draft of the pep in sort of this format that all the sort of peps fall
into. Then the pep was accepted by somebody and then it was implemented. So
sort of a three-step process. And the important thing to note here is that
Gito himself did not approve my pep directly. I'm actually quite sure he has
never read it and he has no idea who I am. Instead, and that's okay, instead we
have what we call BDFL delegates. So these are people that Gito has entrusted
to make decisions about the language either because they know more about a
certain area of the language or about Python than him. He thinks they're
better stewards of that area or he just doesn't know or doesn't care about that.
So for example, packaging stuff, he thinks other people can make that
decision better and so he's entrusted someone else to approve peps in that
area. So the flow of power is kind of like this. Gito gives power to the BDFL
delegates and those delegates can then approve or reject peps and thus change
the language. And sometimes Gito is also still, you know, accepting peps himself.
So you might have heard about pep 572. This is a relatively recent pep that was
created. Its title was assignment expressions and the reason you might have
heard about it is because it caused just a little bit of drama and we'll talk
about that in a second. This pep is centered around just two characters. This
is a new operator in Python. It has a name. I'm not going to tell you what it
is. Instead, I'm going to call this the walrus operator because it kind of looks
like a walrus lying on its side, right? And an important thing to note is I gave
this talk once before and someone was really concerned that this walrus was
dead. He's not dead. He is just resting. Okay. So instead of just reading you the
pep, I'm going to give you some short examples to show you how the walrus
operator can be used and what you can do with it. So one thing that you might want
to use it for is balancing lines of code and complexity. LOC versus big O
complexity. So here's an example where we have a list and in this list we have
three items. F of X, F of X to the power of two, F of X to the power of three, right?
And we're assigning it to the value foo. Let's say that the function F of X is
really expensive to compute here. Let's say it takes like a full minute to run
that function. So when we create this list, we're calling F of X three times
and if it's really expensive, it's going to take three times as long to run. So
what can we do to make this a little bit more efficient? We're going to get the
same answer from it regardless of how many times we call it. So let's just call
it once and put it in a variable and then we can reuse that variable in the
list. So this is great but some people might say I kind of like that first one
better because it was on one line. This one's on two lines and I'm like creating
a variable. With the walrus operator, you don't need to do either of those
things. Instead, you can use the walrus operator to assign to the variable Y
inside the list and then reuse Y later on in that list. You can just reuse that
variable right there in line in the list. So that's avoiding expensive
computations. Another thing you can do is avoid inefficient comprehensions. So
here's a little example and I'll just walk through this real quick. So first we
initialize a list that's empty, results. Then we iterate over something called a
variable data and for everything in data, we call a function and we get a result
from it. And if that result is truthy, we append the result to our results and if
it's not, we don't do anything with it. So this is just a pretty straightforward
little loop and generally when I look at something like this where we have that
initialization of an empty list sitting outside of a for loop like that, that's
kind of a code smell, right? Generally if you see that in Python, you know that I
could probably turn that into a list comprehension. If you did, you would be
right. You could turn that into a list comprehension pretty easily and it would
look a lot nicer and be a few shorter lines of code. However, it would also be
more inefficient. So the problem here is that we're calling f of x again and if f
of x is again really expensive to compute, we're doing it twice here instead
of before when we were only doing it once. With the walrus operator, we can do
the same thing. So in the sub-expression of this comprehension, in the filter
clause, so that if statement, we can assign y to the value of f of x and then we can
reuse it in the comprehension later. Another thing we can do, we can avoid
unnecessary variables in scope. So here's an example. This is kind of familiar if
you do anything with regular expressions. Maybe we search over some pattern or
search over some set of data for a pattern and we get this like match object
back and then we need to test if the match object is truth or not and
determine if we have a match or not. So this might look a little weird to you
because we're creating this match object but we're only using it inside that if
statement. That's not going to be used later and we just need to know if it
exists or not and then we can do things with it if it does. With the walrus
expression, walrus operator, we can just in that if conditional assign match
right there and then it doesn't exist outside the scope of that if statement.
It's just like a little bit of a tighter piece of syntax and it's just right there
in two lines and match isn't hanging around later. Another example, processing
streams in chunks. This is a pretty common pattern. So if we have like a
really big file and we want to read it in little pieces at a time, one common
way to do this is we'll take a chunk and then we'll iterate. We'll process that
chunk and we'll take a new chunk and we'll reassign to a chunk variable over
and over and over again until the file is empty. So while chunk. So this is
works, this is fine but one thing that's kind of like not pretty here is that
that chunk equals file.read and some magic number is being repeated twice
here. So like if I decide I want to change the size of the chunk, I have to
change it on two lines not just one and like maybe I could put that in a
variable and that could live outside but we can make it even simpler with the
walrus operator. So here again we just use chunk just like that if statement
before, put it inside the while expression and then we just process it
until it's falsy and then the while loop exits. Okay some short examples. You might
say why? Why do we need to do this? All those examples before work totally fine
and you know let's not change anything. Okay so one thing to note is that
generally fewer lines are better. Programmers kind of hate change and so if
you can minimize your diffs by just at least like one line it's usually worth
it right? It's less noise in your pull requests and things like that. So here in
this example if I can take these two lines I can turn them into just one line
like my co-workers are gonna totally love me and it's a 50% reduction in code
so it's just less lines to review. Also fewer lines could be more efficient too.
So some of the people that were sort of evaluating this pep they went and found
some examples. They found an example like this where we're doing the regular
expression thing and we're checking to see if the match is in a group and
instead of writing this the programmer wrote this. They decided I'm just gonna
throw this all on one line and you know then it's just a simpler read one line
fine. But what they're doing here is they're calling read out match twice and
again that's more inefficient right? You're calling the exact same thing over
again. This line is gonna be twice as slow as it was before. With a Wallace
operator they could have written this. It's exactly the same length it's still
one line but you're only calling match once. So ultimately this is kind of a
trade-off between developer and computer efficiency. Okay you might be looking at
all this and you might say yeah this kind of actually looks like something I
know this kind of looks like the equals operator and even kind of looks like the
equals operator too right? It's got the equal sign in it. One thing it's
important to note that this is actually nothing like the equals operator and
everywhere that you can use the equals operator you cannot use the Wallace
operator. So one example is multiple targets. With the equals operator you can
say X equals Y equals Z equals zero X Y and Z all become zero. You can't do that
with a Wallace operator. Another example is assigning two things other than a
variable name. So we can do A of I the index and set that to a variable. You
can't do that with the Wallace operator. Another one is assignments to things
other than a name. So we can set self dot rest to an empty list. You can't do that
with the Wallace operator. And again here's another one comma priority. So X
one comma two that creates a tuple one two. With the Wallace operator that
doesn't. It sets X equal to one. The priority is with the comma it's closer
to the operator. Another one is augmented assignment operator so the plus equals.
So we can do you know total plus equals tax with the regular operator. We can't
do that with the Wallace operator. And actually like I don't even know what we
would call that at that point. It's kind of like a walrus with a popat on top.
Okay so that's PEP 572. Let's talk about the reception of how this PEP was
received when it was first drafted. So like I said before most people kind of
hate change. Programmers especially hate it when things change. So one of the
first like most obvious receptions to this was backwards incompatibility. So
this is changing where is this gonna work? Like if we add this to Python it's
not gonna work on older versions of Python. It's not backwards compatible at
all. Another concern was teachability. Like what do we call this? So I've
avoided actually using the real name for this operator. I've been calling the
Wallace operator. We can't call it the Wallace operator. That's jargon.
We need a real name for it that tells us what it does. So we can't call it the
assignment operator. We could call it the becomes operator. We could call it the
named expression operator. And so that last one is actually the name for it. The
named expression operator. But it's still it's hard like if I tell you oh we're
adding a named expression operator to Python you might not understand what
that means. Another is just attractiveness. A lot of people looked at
this and they said wow that is that's just ugly. I hate it. It's really weird
and different. And so there was a lot of discussion about this. There was long
mailing list threads debating the merits of this pep. Like really long mailing list
threads. There were polls where core contributors were polled to see if they
liked it or not and the results were actually you know a lot of a lot of
people disliked it. Some people liked it. Some people had no opinions. Some of the
core contributors weighed in with opinions of their own. So Tim Peters said
that the current proposal would have a modest but clear improvement in quite a
few bits of code. Barry Warslaw said that since it changes the syntax of the
language people are tending to focus on that without understanding the kind of
deeper issues here. Uka Shalanga said dictators should dictate. He thought that
Guido should just do whatever he wanted and ignore what everyone is talking
about. And in fact Guido himself said that he had to stop reading the threads so he
wouldn't go insane. So after a long period of discussion Guido accepted this
pep. He marked it as except it went from draft to accepted. He merged the pull
request and then he sent this email to the Python committers mailing list
stepping down as BDFL. He said that now peps 572 is done I don't ever want to
have to fight so hard for a pep and find that people despise my decisions. And so
he's going to remove himself entirely from the decision process. So in my
talks I like to post Twitter reactions that people have. So here's some of the
things that people said afterwards. This person is pretty funny. A long time
before this happened he said dear Python all I want for my birthday is the chunk
example that I showed before. And then after this happened he said I just
realized that thanks to pep 572 I'm getting my birthday present but at what
cost? Our BDFL has stepped down. Henix said pep 572 rocks. What a
farewell gift. This person said TFW Reddit says pep 572 lost the zen of Python
but the author of the zen of Python is a co-author of the pep. This person said
Guido is stepping down as BDFL Python and he quoted the first line of
that message and he said I'm shocked by the vitriol we throw at the people who
run our most important free and open source software projects. And as an
example of that there was also this tweet. Pep 572 is a trash feature and I'm
sad that it was the straw that broke Guido's back. So I want to be really
explicit and clear here. If we're talking about straws that are breaking people's
backs the straw that broke Guido's back was not trash peps that were heaped upon
him by pep authors. The straw that broke Guido's back was when people were
calling your work trash by like anonymous and strange people on the
internet. I think when we're on the internet we kind of tend to forget who
we're talking to. Like dictators are people too right? And it's true Guido is
a person his thoughts and feelings just like all of us and just because he's
like super famous creator of our language doesn't mean that we have to
get to treat him that way and actually it's not just true for Guido this is
true for like all people that maintain and work on open source software in our
community. Maintainers are people too. Really just like think about like this
people are people too right? Okay I'm gonna preempt some questions about this
so one question what does this mean for Python? Okay it actually had a pretty big
effect on Python. I had someone asked a question is this gonna be the pep to end
all peps and that was kind of true actually so like I said before the power
to approve and change language drives power from Guido so when Guido stepped
down with no Guido we had no BDFL delegates that got their power from him
and thus we could not approve any peps and we couldn't make any change to the
language so we're like a little bit stuck. That said it's gonna be okay so
really immediately after this happened some smart people got to work on this
new governance problem and they created another pep the Python language
governance proposal overview and this sort of outlined exactly what we were
gonna do to create a new governance model for Python. They also created pep
8001 which outlined the voting process for how we're going to decide who gets
to vote and decide what we're gonna do and had made an explicit list of who
could vote on that and also they did a survey of all the other open source
projects and ecosystems that have similar governance models and see if we
could emulate them or learn from them in some way. There were a whole bunch of
proposals there was a voting period where we selected one of them the one
that was selected was announced in December of last year and that was pep
8016 the steering council model and this was proposed by Nathaniel Smith
and Donald Stuffed. Then we voted on who would be on that steering council and
I'm not gonna tell you what happened because tomorrow morning the keynote is
actually the steering council everyone that was elected to steering council is
gonna be up on the stage doing a panel discussion moderated by Eva and
actually even right after that if you really want to geek out about the
governance problem Shana Gordon-McKean is gonna give a talk right afterwards in
the first track about the new era of governance so I'll leave that to her
it's gonna be a great talk. Let's get back to the the walrus operator so
some more Q&A. Will this become part of Python? The answer to this is actually it
already has so most of you probably aren't using Python 3.8 but you could be
using right now it's in alpha. Emily Morehouse is a core developer she's
already implemented this in 3.8 so it exists you can go and play with it today
if you install Python 3.8. You might say I don't like it that's totally fine you
don't have to like it if you don't like it then don't write it it's that simple
no one is gonna force you to use the walrus operator if someone on your team
is telling you that you should be using it then just convince them that you don't
have to use it or that they shouldn't use it you know that's a discussion you
need to have with your team. Another question you might have is Guido coming
back so this kind of depends on what you mean right so like is Guido coming
back to Python well yeah he's he's here like he's here he's gonna be there for
us he's not actually on a vacation on a beach somewhere. Is Guido, the answer
that's yes, is Guido gonna come back as BDFL? The answer to that is definitely no
we have solved the governance process we found a new model we've elected new
people to that committee and so there will no longer be a BDFL for Python. Another
question you might have will this ever happen again and that again kind of
depends on what you mean so maybe your question is will another pep ever be
this controversial? I'm gonna say probably not this pep was an outlier it
was a very small syntax change that was easily understandable by people that
looked at they could look at it and make a decision really quickly kind of a gut
reaction to it I think this was just the unique it was a unique pep that was
particularly controversial however maybe your question is will people
continue to be negative on the internet? And my answer is like I don't know I
hope not I'd really like it if we all could learn from this and sort of just
treat each other a little bit better and be more open and receptive to new ideas
but so many people use Python now and for most of those people the language
already kind of feels perfect and they don't want to change so maybe this is the
new status quo maybe we're gonna get really upset about every time the
language changes but I think we can work past that so come to find me after the
talk and if you promise that you're gonna be nice on the internet I will
happily give you one of these walrus operator stickers that that Emily
created I'll be happy to give one to you thanks everybody
do we have time for questions okay I'll take some questions
please be please be sure to phrase your question as a question I mean I didn't
know anything about this but it sounds like it's actually a good thing because
you know keto is not going to be around forever and having a council like this
means Python will live on beyond Gitos lifetime yeah I think we were probably
all hoping that you know would live forever but yeah I like I said he's a
person too so yeah yeah we had to solve this problem eventually anyway
unfortunately it was a bit dramatic would have nice to have you know like
actually just choose to retire than reactionary to some event but yeah it's
a good thing that we solve this problem because we're gonna we're gonna do at
some point anyway right thank you for the talk and the thing about there about
having it being my birthday present but not what I expected cost that sort of
sums up my feeling as well my question is other languages have something like
this and Python is a continually developing language do you see more
changes like this where Python is pulling things in from other languages or
do you see Python as being more static and a leader in terms of what a language
should be and therefore not changing to adopt these that's a great question so
I'll preface that with I'm not a core developer so I'm not actually making any
it's a value judgment sure actually it's funny when I was originally talking to
this to someone about this pep they were like oh we should just make Python a
standard like literally just freeze the language make it an ANSI standard and
it just will never change and like that that's great but like Python needs to be
able to evolve to keep up with other programming languages but also just to
you know add new features and syntax when we find new uses for the language
so like I said Python is being used everywhere for lots of things so yeah
it's it's totally likely that we might you know again need to add pulling things
to other languages make modifications and improvements the language it's it's
still evolving thank you any other question you've still got a few minutes
if anybody else has a question
okay thanks everybody I'll be in the hallway afterwards