Ladies and gentlemen, we would like to start at this time, welcome to the first talk of
the session.
And please welcome Ruben Lerner, and he's going to be presenting Practical Decorators.
Hey, everyone.
Good morning.
Welcome to PyCon.
Pretty exciting stuff.
So my name's Ruben, and I have a fantastic job.
I help people get better at Python.
I do that a few different ways.
I have a newsletter that about 10,000 people get every week.
I do corporate Python training.
I go on site all around the world.
I have a service called weekly Python exercise.
I do online video courses.
Earlier this week, my book was published by Manning.
Note this is the first Manning book to have the author's picture on the cover.
And this morning, the episode of talk Python with me was also released.
So I can annoy you in all media all day.
So we're going to talk about decorators.
Let's decorate a function.
Let's say I have this decorator here.
So what do I have?
I have at my deco.
I should add, by the way, this is an advanced talk.
So if things seem a little weird, hard, difficult, that's okay.
After a little while, I promise within 20 years, it will make a lot of sense.
So basically, if I want to decorate a function, I say at my deco, and then I'm going to say
def add of a and b, return a plus b.
Pretty reasonable.
And this is the standard syntax we use for decorators in Python.
When you see this on the left, you really need to be thinking something different.
You need to be thinking, first, I'm defining my function.
Now, what does def do in Python?
It actually does two different things.
It creates a function object, and it also assigns that object to the variable add, to
the identifier add.
So you always need to be thinking that's doing those two different things.
Well, right after I define my function, that at my deco on the left does something really
kind of wild.
It does a reassignment.
It says, actually, what we're going to do is we're going to call my deco with an argument
of add, and we're going to assign the result back to the variable add.
It's a little switcheroo there.
This means that we could, if we really want to, write it like on the right.
But that would be really annoying, because then I have to write the word add three different
times.
And no one wants to do that.
That's just super annoying.
If you mess it up even once, bad news.
So while the left-hand side has perhaps more magic in it, and it's less explicit as to
what's going on, it saves us time, it saves us energy, and it saves us from having to
perhaps make those mistakes.
The thing is, when we do this, we have three callables in this code.
This seemingly simple code has three different callables.
Now, what's a callable?
Callables fancy Python speak for something we can execute.
If you've ever tried to say, like, five parentheses in Python, what happens?
There's no compiler to tell you, hey, you can't execute five.
You can't execute integers.
Instead, what happens is, at runtime, Python tries to execute, says, wait a second, integers
are not callable.
You can't do that.
Well, how does it know?
Well, certain things in Python are callable, and that's typically going to be functions
and classes.
So we actually have three callables, either functions or classes here.
For most of this talk, I'm going to be talking about functions.
Toward the end, we'll talk about classes as well.
So where are these callables going to be?
Well, first of all, we have the decorated function.
That is our first callable, add.
The second callable is the decorator itself.
And the third callable, and here is where this syntax gets a little weird.
The third callable, which is really the most important one, is actually invisible here.
It's the one that's returned from when I call myDeco on add.
And that callable is the one assigned back to add.
And so when I call add, I'm not really calling my original add.
I'm calling whatever was returned by myDeco add, which then is going to sort of hopefully
call the original add.
So this is how we have to think about our decorators when we use them.
Well, what about when we want to find them then?
We're going to have to deal with these three callables.
And so a very typical way to write our decorator is as a function inside of another function.
So I have here myDeco.
That's my decorator.
It's on the top level there.
That's the function.
And it's going to get a function.
It's going to get our function here as an argument.
The inside function here, which is often called wrapper, that's where a lot of the magic is
happening.
And it's going to actually be returned as we can see here.
And notice that it has a funny sort of function signature.
It's getting splat args and double splat kw args.
Why am I doing that?
Because I want to be able to decorate any function at all.
And this way I can get any combination of arguments coming in.
And then what am I going to do?
I'm going to call the function, just pass those along.
So whatever I get as input, I'm going to pass along to output.
Now this decorator is pretty boring.
All it does is it takes any function whatsoever.
It calls that function, sticks the result of the function into a string, and then adds
three exclamation points afterwards.
OK, not the most exciting function in the world.
So what's going on here?
Let's once again talk about our three callables.
We have our first callable, which is our decorated function.
It becomes our argument.
The second callable is our decorator that we are calling on it.
And the third callable, that sort of mystery one at the end, that's wrapper.
That's the internal function.
Whatever is called a mydeco add, this function then returns and is assigned back to our original
function name.
And that's how the decorator sort of works.
Here's another perspective on it.
We can think about it in terms of time.
We can say that at the beginning, when we decorate the function, this outside function
is running.
But the inside function runs once each time we run the function.
So the outside one runs once only at set up time.
And the inside one runs as many times as we need.
That's pretty great.
By the way, I should add, how is it that the internal function is having access to funk?
Funk, after all, is a local variable in the external function.
This is thanks to the magic of Python scoping.
L-E-G-B.
Local enclosing global built-ins.
Basically what happens is that inside of wrapper, it looks for the name funk.
It says, is there a local variable funk?
There is not.
So let's look in the enclosing function.
Hey, what do you know?
There's a local variable funk there.
Let's use that.
So we have access to that external function inside of the internal function.
Well decorators are pretty cool then.
That's pretty great.
And for a long time I thought they were cool, but I also thought they were sort of a solution
looking for a problem.
Like okay, I can now twist my mind in all sorts of different ways, but really and truly
where would I want to use them?
Well it turns out they are actually useful.
Shocking, right?
They are actually useful.
So I want to give you about five different examples of decorators and how we can use
them, how we can think about them.
And I want you not only then to understand how decorators work and how we can write them,
but sort of the perspective that decorators give us on how things work in Python.
And you'll start to see more and more opportunities to use them as you deepen your understanding.
And so a classic example to start with decorators is timing.
So how long does it take a function to run?
Well I can do that in general.
I can use time.time, get back the number of seconds since the 1st of January 1970.
I can do that before I run the function.
I can then run the function.
Then I can run it again, run time.time.
I can subtract the two numbers there and find out how long the function took to run.
And indeed then I can do that in my decorator.
So here's my decorator.
I've got my outside function which I'm calling log time.
It's going to take func as an argument.
And my inside function, what's it going to do?
Well the important thing here is going to be start time equals time.time.
Right?
So I'm going to time it.
I'm then going to run the function.
Notice I'm not doing anything to the function at all.
It's running as per usual.
I'm going to pass it all its arguments.
It's going to return a result.
Excuse me.
I'm going to just put the result inside of the variable cleverly called result.
And then afterwards I'm going to find out how much time has elapsed.
Then I'm going to write it to a file.
I'm going to say with open timing.txt and granted time log.txt.
Granted here I'm hard coding the name.
We don't need to do that.
I'm using a to append it to append to the file as opposed to reset it each time.
And I'm going to write what is the current time, what function name am I running, and
how long did this function take to run.
Fantastic.
And if I do this, right, here's how I could apply it.
So I could apply my decorator very easily.
I could just say at log time to slow add and at log time to slow mo.
And by the way, one of the beautiful things about decorators is I can add and remove their
functionality to functions by not touching the function itself just by putting the decorator
before it.
So if I want to start timing a bunch of functions, I can just put at log time before their definitions.
And when I'm done timing them, I can just remove that.
I don't need to touch the functions themselves.
They stay exactly the same.
Well what happens when I run my function slow add and slow mo a couple of times?
This is the sort of result I'm going to get in the file.
I'm going to find out at what time each of the functions ran.
I'm going to find out which function ran.
I'm going to find out how long it ran for.
So I can add this sort of logging of my functions with pretty great ease.
OK, well what was going on here is of course I have my original decorated function.
Still, I have my three callables.
Something just fall.
No worries, no worries.
Yes.
Ominous.
All right.
And then I've got log time.
There's my decorator.
And then I've got the return value from log time func is assigned back to func's name.
Fantastic.
OK, so that's a pretty simple decorator, but it demonstrates some of the ideas.
So let's get a little more complicated.
Let's say I have a function that's very expensive to run in terms of the resources it uses,
in terms of the timing it takes, in terms of all sorts of different stuff.
So maybe I want to make sure this function can only run once per minute.
If it runs more than once per minute, then I want to get an exception back.
So how am I going to do that?
Well, here's a skeleton of my decorator.
I'm going to call it once per minute.
Very clever name.
Right?
And I'm going to have func be its argument.
And so we see here once again I have my decorated function.
I have the decorator, and we're going to return it.
Ah, yeah, but what goes in the middle?
OK, that's left as an exercise to the reader.
OK, not at all.
So basically, what are we going to do here?
Well, think about it.
Each time a function runs, it doesn't remember what happened in the previous runs.
That's sort of the whole point of a function.
And it's not like in some languages where we have, pardon the obscenity, static variables,
where we would be able to carry these variables over from one run to another.
So I can't really do that.
Now I could use a global variable to keep track of this stuff, but then I'd feel super
icky and have to shower each time I ran my code.
So I've really got to find some other better way to do this.
And what I'm going to do is I'm going to use nonlocal.
I'm going to put the time, the last invoke time, in the outer function, the one that
runs just once.
And it's going to set up this variable once.
Then I'm going to say nonlocal.
Now what does nonlocal do?
It says to Python, listen, normally when you assign to a variable inside of a function,
you are either creating or updating a local variable.
Not this time.
So we're saying nonlocal, we say, I want you to update, change the variable in the external,
in the enclosing scope.
So now what's happening is that each time I run wrapper, my internal function, it's
going to say nonlocal last invoked, and then it's going to say, I'm going to update that
external variable.
I'm going to update that enclosing variable.
And this way we're able to carry this information across different runs of our function.
Pretty great.
Okay?
Now I need that.
So we're going to run nonlocal because this stuff is executing only once.
We know that last invoked is only going to run once in our function, in our decorated
function, whereas this stuff is going to be running again and again and again each time
we run our function.
And does this actually work?
I sure hope so because I put it in my slides.
So we're going to say add two plus two, and sure enough that's four, that's really mathematically
not inclined.
I'm giving you the answer here.
But then if I say add of three and three, well, I ran that too often, called too often
error, only four seconds have passed.
Pretty great.
Yeah, but who wants just once per minute?
Let's generalize this to once per n.
Now what I want to do is restrict people to run my function once per n seconds.
So in order to understand what's going on here, we're going to have to go back to what
happens with a decorator.
So when I see this at once per minute on def add a and b return a plus b, remember, we
should be thinking this.
Def add of a and b return a plus b, our function is defined as per usual, but of course the
rewrite means that on that last line what we're going to be doing is taking the decorator
name once per minute, applying it to add and whatever we get back, we're going to
put into add.
So what happens when I add an argument to my decorator?
Right now I'm saying at once per n of five, and then I do def add of a and b.
So what do we need to be thinking?
We need to be thinking, okay, I've got my function definition as before, and then I
have this on the bottom line.
So what am I doing?
I'm going to call once per n with an argument of five.
The result from that is then going to be applied to add.
The result from that is then going to be assigned back to add.
In other words, we have four callables running around here.
So what do we have?
We have our original decorated function.
We have our decorator once per n.
We have the result from calling once per n on five, because that's a callable, we can
then invoke that on add, and then the result from once per n on five on add is assigned
back to add.
Well, that's great, but how are we going to actually implement this?
That's right.
We're going to have a function in a function in a function.
So what's this going to look like?
I'm going to have once per n on the outside there.
That's going to be my top level function.
That's what's going to get my argument.
I'm then going to have a middle function, and that's going to get the actual function.
You can think of these outer two functions as sort of splitting up the responsibilities
of our original outer function before.
And wrapper looks pretty much the same as before.
In fact, we can see what we had before.
We have last invoked equals zero, nonlocal last invoked, because once again, we want
to update that variable in closing scope.
So I'm doing basically the same thing as before.
I've just switched things around a little bit so that the outer function becomes two
different functions.
And why do I want to do that?
Because I need to have the decorated function here, not at the outer level, but in the middle
level, and then I want to have the decorator itself there that takes the argument, and
then I'm going to have the return values from each of my other functions.
And the combination of the four different decorators here gives me exactly what I want.
And we can think about this once again in terms of time, that this outer function, outermost
function, runs once when we get the argument.
The second function executes once when we decorate the function.
And once again, our wrapper, our middle function, runs as many times as we want to invoke our
function.
And once we do this, well, does this work?
Now I'm going to run it, right?
Slow out of two and two and slow out of three and three, and I put a limit there of I think
it was five seconds.
So now I'm going to have four once again.
And now once again, I'm going to get an error because too little time has passed.
But now that timing is variable.
So I can say this function can only run every minute, but that function can run every two
minutes, and this function can run every 30 seconds, whatever I want.
OK.
Another example.
Memo-ization, not memo-ization.
That would be easy to spell and say.
Instead it's memo-ization, which is one of these things you learn about a computer science
class and then forget unless you're a nasty instructor like me.
But memo-ization actually is not a new technique at all.
I just looked it up to find out.
It's more than 50 years old.
And the idea is basically if I have a function whose arguments always lead to the same value,
always lead to the same result.
So think of basic mathematical functions, you know, adding and multiplying and dividing,
all that.
If I add two and two, the next time I add two and two, it would be better before once
again.
It's not going to change on me unless we've got some really big problems.
So basically wouldn't it be nice if every time I would take a look at my arguments,
And if I've seen these arguments before for this function, just return the cached value
from the previous time.
Why run the function?
Now, it's pretty stupid to do this for addition and multiplication, I admit.
But if you have something a little harder, a little longer, right, even take like, you
know, SHA-1 or RSA or something like that, you know, then you might want to actually
do this sort of caching.
So how are we going to do this?
Well, I'm going to define memoize.
That's going to be my decorator.
It's going to take a function.
And right up there at the top, I'm going to define a cache.
How are we going to cache something in Python?
I'm going to use a dictionary because we love dictionaries and we'll use them wherever we
possibly can.
So basically what's going to happen here?
I'm going to set up my cache to be a dictionary.
I'm then going to take a look at splat args.
Well, args is defined to be a tuple.
And so I can say, hey, take a look at these arguments.
Have we seen these arguments before?
If not, let's run the function with all the arguments, take the results, stick it into
our dictionary.
And then I know after running this if statement, no matter what, I have the result from this
function.
Fancy, huh?
So now I can take the decorated function.
I've got the decorator.
I'm returning it back.
Everything is great.
And indeed, if I want to think about it in terms of my timing thing, this is running
once and this is running multiple times.
You might be saying, wait a second, didn't he say we have to use nonlocal if we're accessing
variables in the outer scope?
And indeed, I did say that sort of kind of almost.
Basically if I'm assigning to the variable in the external scope and in the closing scope,
then I have to worry about it.
But if I'm just saying cache square brackets, then I'm accessing the variable.
I don't need to worry about it.
So long as I'm not saying cache equals, I'm all set.
I don't need to use nonlocal.
So actually this works pretty well.
Let's take a look just in case.
So we'll do memoize of add.
And notice here that my add and multiply, multiple functions are going to say when they're
running, right?
They're going to sort of declare to the world because that's what we want to do when we
add numbers, find out the computer is adding numbers because it's a pretty rare operation.
So now I'm going to say add of three and seven and multiple of three and seven.
I'm going to do each of those twice.
So the first time we're going to see then that when I add, look, memoize notices that
I haven't gotten this back before, so I'd better run the function.
Then I run the function and then I get the result back.
And then moal once again, right, it's going to be the same sort of thing, caching the
new value, running moal.
And now the second time I run add, it's going to say, wait, I already have that result.
I'm not going to run the function at all.
So just sidesteps the function altogether.
And the same thing is true for moal.
And notice then even though I have exactly the same arguments here, because it's separate
functions, they have different decorators.
Different decorators means that their caches are completely separate from one another.
I don't need to worry about them stepping on one another.
That's pretty great.
But some of you are probably saying, wait a second.
What if ours contains a non-hashable value?
And what about kwrgs?
You just ignored it and that's hurting its feelings.
And kwrgs does not take kindly to that.
So what should I do about that?
Well, I could cry.
Or I could remember that we've got pickle.
And pickle gets me out of this pickle, as it were.
Pickle basically says, I'm going to take a Python data structure and turn it into a
string or into a byte string.
And byte strings are, of course, hashable.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to pickle args.
I'm going to pickle kwrgs.
I'm going to stick them into a tuple, because I can stick them into a tuple.
And then I'm going to use those as my cache key.
So now I'm going to take args and kwrgs, cache, put each of them in pickle, use that.
And I'm going to say, hey, have we seen this before?
And then every unique combination of args and kwrgs is being cached.
And then I can check for that.
And then we'll always return the caching of t.
Last example, attributes.
So attributes are, of course, what we have on all sorts of objects in Python, but especially
when we're dealing with classes and objects.
So methods are attributes in the class.
And every time we create an instance, we have Dunder init.
On Dunder init, I'm going to set all sorts of data there.
What if I want to have a whole bunch of different classes that have the same attribute, especially
the same method?
Well, you might say, oh, well, obviously, then I should use inheritance.
Yeah, but inheritance is only really appropriate when the objects are similar, when the classes
are similar to one another.
But if I have very distinct classes, but I still want them to have similar behavior,
then it's not so easy.
So I could do it with attributes.
I could do it with inheritance.
And I could even use multiple inheritance now.
The only problem with multiple inheritance is, as you know, there are two opinions about
multiple inheritance.
Some people think that it's terrible.
And some people think it's the worst thing ever created on earth.
So no matter where you stand on this debate, I think we can sort of sidestep it and say,
fine, let's just assume we're not going to use inheritance at all.
How can I use a decorator to basically add this sort of thing?
So here I have my better wrapper.
And I must say, one of the things that I most love about data classes in Python 3.7 is that
the wrapper is improved.
So it's actually usable.
The current wrapper is, well, not so great.
So here I'm going to define fancy wrapper.
And it's going to return a string that says, I'm a whatever, type self, with vars of varself.
Fantastic.
So how am I going to decorate my class then to get this?
Well, I'm going to do this.
I'm going to define better wrapper of C.
And so C is going to be a class.
Notice, now I'm decorating a class.
But it's a callable, so who cares?
It's fine.
So here I've got my class.
Here's my decorator.
And what am I going to have inside?
Well, I'm going to assign C.dunder wrapper equals fancy wrapper.
I'm changing the method inside the class.
Great.
And of course, I'm going to return wrapper because I have to return a callable.
But you might be thinking, wait a second, this wrapper is doing nothing.
That's OK.
There are lots of people who do nothing, and we don't complain about them too much.
So basically, I've got wrapper here.
And wrapper takes r's and k, w, r's.
But all we do is then pass it along to the class and return it to the new object.
Really what I can do is just this.
I can define better wrapper.
It'll take the class.
I'll just add the new method to it.
Then I'll just return the class.
Nothing wrong with that.
Indeed, that works just fine.
Here's my decorated class.
Here's my decorator.
Here's my callable.
I don't need a function there.
And does this work?
Yeah, this works great.
Because now if I print f, what am I going to get?
I'm a fool with vars x10 and y10 2030.
Fantastic.
Well, that was great for setting a class attribute like a method here.
Can we do that for instances of course?
Can we do that for object instances also?
Of course we can.
It's Python.
We can do anything.
The world is putty in our fingers.
So basically, what can I do?
I'm going to give every object, every new instance its own birthday.
Everyone deserves a birthday, including objects.
So when I use the object birthday decorator, I'm going to add a new attribute here to each
and every instance.
And it's just going to be the timestamp at which we created the object.
So what's going to happen?
Well, object birthday, that's going to be my decorator.
Notice here I'm not doing anything to the class.
I'm not modifying the class.
When do we have an opportunity to touch the instance?
Well, remember that a decorator runs in two different stages.
It runs when we create, when we decorate the object.
And the inside stuff wrapper runs every time we execute the callable.
Well, every time I execute the class, that means every time I create a new instance of
the class, right?
So wrapper is going to run each time I have a new instance.
And when we have a new instance, now I'm actually going to use that syntax that I had before.
I'm going to call the class with args and kwrs.
I'm going to get a new object back.
Then I'm going to stick a new attribute onto that object.
What's it going to be?
It's going to be created at time.time.
And then I'm going to return the object.
And here I have my decorated class.
Here I have my decorator.
Here I have what I'm returning.
All is great.
And indeed, if I run it now, if I have object birthday with class full, printf, well, now
I've got my original wrapper.
And print the birthday created at, fantastic.
I've got the number of seconds since the 1st of January 1970.
Let's do both.
I'm going to define here a decorator that modifies the class to take a new method and
modifies the object to get a new attribute.
And here I'm modifying the class.
And here I'm modifying the object.
And I can do both inside of the same decorator because we think of these two different stages
at which things run.
So decorators are pretty cool and pretty exciting.
First of all, decorators let's dry up our callables.
Dry is this idea, don't repeat yourself.
You don't want the same code to be happening more than once in your software.
And I don't know about you, but on several occasions, okay, many occasions, too many
occasions in my software career, I'd be like, you know, I'm just going to copy this code.
What are the chances that I'll have to modify it in both places down the road?
I can tell you right now, 100%.
There's a 100% chance you will end up modifying the code in both places.
Don't do it.
And so if I can take code out of multiple functions, multiple classes that's the same
and put into a decorator, I will be saving myself time down the road.
Also, understanding how callables work is really central to this and it allows us to
see how this all works together.
Understanding how many callables are involved in our decorators, it lets us pick apart the
decorator and say, oh, I'm going to take advantage of this part versus this part versus this
part and really play with it in different ways.
Decorators make it dramatically easier to do all sorts of different things.
Basically, it lowers the bar to messing around with our functions and our objects in all
sorts of different ways.
You could argue maybe that's a problem, right?
But in Python, we like to give people opportunity to do things.
And things that previously required all sorts of black magic like meta classes, now we can
just do with decorators that are much more understandable.
And all this depends on the fact that in Python, functions and classes are just plain old objects.
They're objects that everyone can use.
They can pass them around.
They can be returned.
And so that lends itself to this amazing, amazing sort of behavior that we can take
advantage of in all sorts of different ways.
If you want, thanks to the magic of the internet, I think this should now be working.
You can go to practicaldecorators.com and get the code and the slides from this talk.
I think we have a few minutes for questions as well.
I have a booth here for weekly Python exercise.
You can email me.
You can get me on Twitter.
I'd be happy to talk to you after this about this or anything else.
Thanks very much.
At this point, if you have any questions, please line up at the microphones and ask
the questions.
I can't hear you.
I'm sorry.
You're still good.
Oh, we have five minutes.
So we have five minutes for questions.
So if people have questions, problems, personal problems they want to share, I'm open to it
all.
Yeah, please.
So you were talking before about the enclosing scopes.
How is the enclosing scopes different from the concept of closures in JavaScript and
other programming languages?
So it's basically the same idea.
Basically the idea then that the enclosing function stack frame sticks around even when
the enclosing function does not stick around is exactly what allows us to do this.
Basically what I'm teaching this sort of stuff with inner functions, I'll be like, by the
way, this is known as a closure.
And you'll have like a third of the people go, oh, and the other people say, huh?
So it sort of depends on who learned this and who did not.
So it's 100% the same?
It should be.
As far as I know, it's 100% the same.
Yeah, absolutely.
Thank you.
Yeah, please.
Hi.
Thank you for the wonderful talk.
I wanted to ask if you have any tips or gotchas when it comes to writing tests for decorators.
Oh, I'm sure I do, and I can't think of any offhand.
Let's go ahead.
Thank you.
Sorry.
Yeah.
When have you found it beneficial or detrimental to use functools.wraps?
Oh, so as you might be able to tell, I'm a dinosaur.
And so that's actually very, like basically every software I'm like, oh, I should probably
use functools.wraps because it does a lot of this stuff sort of for you that you don't
need to play with it.
I must admit that I'm not as familiar with it as I should be, but the idea is basically
to lower the bar even more and make it easier to do some of this stuff so you don't need
to be thinking in all these different scopes.
Yeah, please.
Hi.
So from the Zen of Python, flat is better than nested.
And from like the three nested functions, that sort of goes against it.
Do you have any thoughts about using functools partial to sort of get rid of those nests,
or have you experimented with that?
So I'll tell you, I really like the idea of functools partial.
It's super cool and fun, and yet I find that for many people, it's just like extra confusing.
Like it adds another layer of, wait, what do you mean partial function?
Like some of it works and some of it doesn't.
I'll tell you, sometimes when I introduce decorators, I use not multiple functions, but
I use classes because then you can have init.
Init is sort of like the outer function, and call, under call is the inner function.
And then you have this very clear separation.
It's not nested, but you're like, oh, this happens once, this happens many times.
The problem is you can't use class decorators to decorate certain things like methods.
So I'm, shall we say, partial on functools partial.
Thank you.
All right.
Yeah.
You had some pretty harsh things to say about static variables, but it's unclear to me how
sort of the variables embedded at the one time execution step are going to avoid any
of the pitfalls of static variables.
And I think a similar thing could be applied to multiple annotation versus multiple inheritance.
All right.
So first of all, I actually have nothing against static variables.
Some of my best friends are static variables.
No.
It's just that in Python we tend to think it's a dynamic language, so the word static tends
to be something that I shy away from.
I actually think that it would be nice and useful to have something like that available
to us, but it doesn't exist.
The best we can do is the enclosing function sort of thing.
Yeah.
So, wait, is this working?
When you're writing class decorators, how do you decide between modifying attributes
after they're created, modifying instances after they're created versus wrapping functions
on the class like init?
In particular, it stood out to me that you get less efficient attribute access if you're
adding attributes after init has completed.
I couldn't tell you about the efficiency of it.
Good thinking idea.
I really had never thought about the idea of decorating init so that you don't have
to add the attributes there.
Again, I don't have a good answer for you, but that's excellent food for thought.
No more questions?
Ha!
I must not be in Israel.
All right.
Well, if people have more questions or comments, I'm happy to talk to you afterwards, and thanks
very much.
Thank you very much.