All right. Hope you had a fantastic lunch and you're ready to learn. Our speaker today
is Matthew Seal. He works at Netflix and he's going to teach us about how to control Jupyter
notebooks with Python.
Thanks.
All right. So first thing, just a little bit, if you want to follow along with these slides
later or go look at anything in more depth because I'm going to be going through a lot
of slides, there's a tiny URL here and then the very last page will have it too. So you
will be able to see what was up here.
So we're going to be talking today about programmatic notebooks with Papermill. Papermill is a library
and it's in Jupyter space and I'll talk about what that means in a minute. So first off,
who am I? My name is Matthew Seal. It's the intro very kindly stated. And then I work
at the big data platform team at Netflix. In particular, I work on scheduling and orchestration
and we have a big overlap of that with notebooks because we actually do a bunch of scheduled
notebooks and we kind of make that easy for our users to do.
So that kind of leads me into, well, you said you're a big data platform team member. What
does that mean? Not everyone knows what that means, including some people on data platform
teams. We were like, what am I doing to help people? So the way I like to kind of state
this is we're helping build these data platform services that help people kind of get out
of the way of people doing their job. So we have lots of data inputs from events, from
users, from system metrics, and the user needs to be able to collect those up, say something
about them, either put them in another system so someone can live query them faster, build
a report, do some machine learning on it, feed it back into another ETL system. All
these things, they need tools to do this because it's a complicated problem, but the conceptual
problem that the user's trying to solve is relatively simple. I want data from A to B.
Why is it so hard not to work? So we try to make it easy so they don't have to come ask
us why nothing works. And so some of these tools, these things I'm talking about, this
is all open source stuff that we use to help make that possible. So in the short version
of this, the data platform tries to open doors for folks, just not that door because it's
scary. Everything that I'm presenting here is open source projects, so you can go see
the contributions there. I'm a maintainer in both the Jupiter space and the Interact
space, and I do the releases for paper mills, so if you have paper mill specific things,
definitely I can help you or point you to the right discourses. And all these things
have been contributed by Netflix, so we have a notebooks team which contributes a lot of
code in this space, and then I also contribute a few other members that aren't on those teams
specifically contribute. All right, so first thing is, how many of you know what a notebook
is? That's awesome. That means I can go faster. How many of you know what a Jupyter notebook
is than a Zeppelin notebook? Yeah, like 5% of you. Cool. That's part of why I'm here.
A little bit talking about the Jupiter specific things and what the ecosystem allows to enable
this kind of functionality that I'm about to describe. So a Jupyter notebook, in its
most basic form, something like this, you see notebooks, but the Jupyter ecosystem as
opposed to some of the other notebook ecosystems that have similar functionality is really
about the specs that enable the protocol between a client and the actual run time that's running
your code. So there's a lot of APIs that have been established on which these systems talk
to each other. What this means is that in a notebook like this when you're working on
one with a rendered repel of some sort like Python or Scala, because in Jupyter everything
is going over this communication protocol that has a fixed standard about how to execute
code and markdown and other things, it means you can make kernels in many different languages.
The kernel is the piece that actually runs the code in the back end. It also means you
make clients of many types. So I'm showing you here this is a UI from an interact which
is a kind of place that builds a bunch of components for using in notebooks and they
have a collection of those components that makes a UI. Similarly, there's Jupyter lab
and Jupyter classic are both UIs on Jupyter and a lot of platforms have their own proprietary
UIs that talk on the same protocols and they can provide a look and feel matching their
platform. So a little bit on what a notebook is. I'll go quickly here because you all kind
of know, but it's basically rendering the interactions with a repel. A repel being a
realtime interactive process where you're sending it strings and it gives you back executed
code results. And notebooks in this space are really handy because it gives you a place
where there's code, logs, documentation, execution results all in the same interface. And not
just the same interface, in the Jupyter ecosystem, it's also in the same file. So the file format
that gets saved when you're running a notebook or saving a notebook is saving into an IPMYB
file which is basically a glorified JSON file with a schema. So I'm going to skip through
the breakdown a little bit because I think most of you said you're familiar with notebooks,
but here's some kind of high level concepts here. You have a saving indicator, a code
cell that generates some displayed outputs. In this case, we generate a graph from some
code and it's all saved in the same document. If I share this document with someone, that
document embeds this information inside of it. And the places where notebooks actually
have good wins is they're shareable, they're pretty easy to read, you get this documentation
of code pairing and outputs are associated with that code as well. And it's also a familiar
interface for many users. It's gotten enough popularity that you can give someone a notebook
and they kind of know what to do and how it works, even if they don't know that particular
flavor of notebook. And notebooks are growing even more in a multi-language sense. So while
everything I'm showing here is going to be Python, there's also other languages that
can run notebook code in the background, including multi-language kernels, which are kind of a
fun thing if you're ever looking into it. So how does a Jupyter notebook actually execute
code? We're going to talk about this a little bit first so that we can explain how the tools
we use work. So a very high level. It's more complex than this, but this gives you a kind
of visual idea of what's going on. As a user, when you're typically using a Jupyter UI of
some sort, you're talking to your UI in a browser. That is talking back to a server,
which is hosting the UI and some basic APIs for it. And then that server is responsible
for ferrying messages to and from this thing called a kernel. Now, a kernel is a terrible
name for what this wrapper is, because if you're in machine learning, there's a different
thing that's a kernel. If you're in OS, there's another thing called a kernel. There's a lot
of kernels. In this case, when we're talking about kernel, we're always going to refer
to a Jupyter kernel, which is basically a command that wraps the REPL that accepts the
communication protocol that Jupyter has defined. All right. So we're going to talk a little
about traditionally where notebooks come from, because it's important about where it's
going and what it's being used for now. So back when I first started using Jupyter notebooks,
which is before I knew I'd be involved in Jupyter, a long time ago, it was around in
data science. It was really popular. And the reason why was because you could explore and
analyze not really knowing what your end result needed to be, but knowing you need to try
a bunch of things and that they were expensive computations that you needed to do. So the
really good things about notebooks are you get quick iteration cycles. I can run just
one snippet of code on the same live context over and over again until I get it right or
until I find the right data or until the model I chose did the right thing. You can leave
all your expensive queries higher up in the context, and they're sitting there, the results
are sitting there in memory, and I don't have to recompute them. I don't have to refetch
my 10 gigabytes of data to run my whole code again. And it also records what you did, so
it's really handy when like, oh, geez, what was the outcome of that other code cell or
the other execution the last time I ran this? You don't have to go search or lose a log
file. It's always inside the notebook that you ran. And they're pretty easy to modify.
You don't even, non-technical users can even modify an existing notebook because you can
even make interfaces within notebooks that hide some of the code or even make very simple
code like SQL that any user could do minimal learning, get into without being a full-blown
software engineer. But there are some things that are not so good about using Jupyter notebooks.
In particular, in the past, a lack of history. I may have changed a cell and I click save.
Oops, I don't remember what that cell was. And you close your browser, you're not getting
that back probably. They're pretty difficult to test in the sense that I have a bunch of
code and cells. It's kind of a glorified script in many ways. And if you don't structure it
well or have a placeholder to run unit tests, that can be difficult. It's a mutable document,
so you're changing in place what's happening. So if you make a run and you save your outcomes
and you rerun it, those outcomes can get lost because you overwrite the outcomes with the
next run. So maybe if you do an experiment and you found a really good result and then
you tried a different experiment and forgot what you did to get that good result, you
could lose that information, which is kind of frustrating. And then live collaboration
only really exists in a few niche corners of Jupyter. In reality, if two people try
and touch the same notebook at the same time, bad things happen in the future. We hope that
will not be true. So one thing we did when approaching this notebook space was we actually
wanted to help start filling some of the gaps. In particular, we really liked the results
linked to code, the visualizations being coupled with the execution context, and the ease of
sharing. Like we had a lot of users who loved these aspects of notebooks even outside of
data science. But some things that really needed to be improved. Versioning was pretty
rough. You know, you didn't know what you ran last time you ran this notebook or three
times ago. The mutable state kind of leads into that. The fact that, you know, when you
want to use a production setting, you have to really be able to audit what happened,
how did I execute it, what did I do, who authored this. And then templating. Most of the time,
templating before paper mill came along was I share this notebook with another person
and I give them instructions as a document at the top that says change this cell this
way and rerun everything and it will run the way you want. Paper mill helps solve that.
So we're going to talk about paper mill. Paper mill is a library which is gaining a lot of
popularity. It's actually kind of just a lightweight wrapper on things that were already there.
But it has a stronger opinion about how to do things. It's in a project called interact
which is a collection of notebook repositories that are notebook projects which all add little
enhancements to notebooks or make different components or things like that. So what's
paper mill and how does it do anything different? So one thing that paper mill does is actually
isolates the inputs from the outputs. It's a Python library that has a command line interface
which lets you give an input notebook path. It will compute that notebook and then after
it's done computing or hits an error, it will store that notebook to a totally different
place. It won't touch the input notebook unless you point the output notebook back to the
input. So what this means is you can get some isolation between when you execute the notebook
what the template source was and what the outcome was. In this case we see run one,
two, three, four. So we were just iterating through maybe a loop and we just saved each
output to a different place and then we can see what each execution actually did. All
right. So how does this look in Python a bit maybe? So in Python it's a pretty simple interface.
You import paper mill. You say execute notebook, input path, output path. If you do this very
simple thing, it will work and then you can actually see your outputs in the folder. In
this case I've put all the outputs in the outputs directory and just given it the date
int as a prefix so I can sort by the date I ran this. You can also add parameters. This
is the templating aspect we were talking about with notebooks. In particular here maybe we
have a notebook which runs some sort of analysis on let's say how many people are viewing a
particular site on particular types of devices. So here we've said well this notebook can
take region and devices so we're going to give it some inputs. What this will do when
you actually execute this is inside the notebook you're going to see a we'll have a section
there. This cell execution two is something we defined. We said hey here's the region
and here's the device PC and then we calculate date sense. This is the default parameters
that that cell has been tagged as this is my default. And then when paper executes it'll
inject a new code cell right below it with this it'll look exactly like this. It'll say
parameters region California and then devices phone, tablet. So we took our input JSON like
object in the input and made it into code inside the actual notebook. So when it executes
it looks like someone typed in an extra code cell and injected in all the parameterizations
after your defaults. And you can do the same type of input from a CLI. In fact we used
this most often in kind of like any system that can call out to the command line can
execute paper mail through the base almost the identical interface. In this case we gave
it region as a parameter with dash P and then we gave dash Y for YAML and just pass some
JSON to give it all of this stuff. So you see a little bit what this looks like if you
actually execute it in a CLI. Here you see we have a file up here. If you can't see the
red text I made it as bright as I could before this but the lighting is a little rough. If
you can't see things please do go look at the slides afterwards and you can see a little
better on your screen. So here we're executing paper mail and you'll see like this is the
default behavior it'll print out the input path, the output path, it'll do a status bar
as it goes. You can configure these things and control what it's going to output. And
we can do the same thing where we're going to give it these inputs and you'll see essentially
the identical input. Here we're giving it some conference, PyCon, and it'll print out
a fifth cell here. So you see I have five out of five instead of four out of four. So
how would this look in Python? Similar thing, we're actually using a notebook to run a notebook.
So this is kind of a fun thing you can do. And here I'm showing you the input notebook.
This is the input notebook we were running before. It has some really basic things. It
prints out an image and it has some parameters called paper and mill and it adds them together
to print out a string. The most basic Hello World notebook thing I could come up with
that demonstrated everything. And here we have another notebook which is going to run
the paper mill execute notebook. You'll notice when you're running paper mill from a notebook,
you get this nicer progress bar that's HTML. And here we're going to add a parameter in
here. So we're going to change that mill parameter that defaulted to mill two. Now we run this,
same type of execution. And if you go look at the outcome, you'll see this is the notebook
output two that we made and it has that parameter mill replaced with mill two which overwrote
the cell execution three. And now when it printed, it printed paper mill two instead
of paper mill. So that's kind of the basic interface. There's a whole bunch of other
components in there that we'll dig into. But how does this change the picture that we had
before where we had Jupyter being executed by users in a notebook server in a kernel?
Well, it acts just like any other client in a sense. The paper mill execution is just
like a UI client. It's following the same protocols your browser server is taking to
talk to Jupyter. And in this case, paper mill here is reading in an input notebook, storing
it in memory, and then it's sending each cell one by one through the kernel manager it launches
to the kernel that actually executes the code. And it collects the results just like your
browser would and then saves them into the notebook just like your browser would. So
at the end of the day, you can make all sorts of different types of clients that aren't
that simple. And then you can also use the notebooks that can interface with kernels
in a way that's creative. And paper mill just takes advantage of that. You know, a little
bit deeper into what's inside paper mill that makes it work. It's just a slightly more complicated
picture than the first one we showed with the input output. You have notebook sources,
which can be of many different schemes. And then it takes that source notebook. It has
a register for how do I load this in the memory. It'll load that JSON document in the memory.
And then the parameters will come in and it'll convert those into a dict in memory. And then
it knows how to translate that dict for a variety of languages. And then it'll splat
that back in as code in the execution. And then it launches this runtime manager, which
actually goes and launches the runtime process, which is the kernel. So each time you're on
paper mill, unlike in a notebook, you actually it launches a whole kernel and shuts it down
at the end. So it won't have a shared context between executions. And it'll isolate memory
and everything. And it'll clean up at the end because it's actually closing that process.
In a notebook, when you're running a notebook, it sits in the background and holds memory
for a while until you either kill it or it decides you aren't using it anymore. In this
case, you don't have that problem. But on the flip side is you can't reattach that kernel.
There are ways to change that or extend it. And then the output, you get these notebook
sinks where you can save out to the same type of sources that you drew from. So now paper
mill actually lets you do things like maybe have a notebook that does something like analyzes
a confusion matrix over some machine learning process and says, hey, which one did the best?
You can actually parallelize that execution and ship it out to a whole bunch of notebook
executions with the same base template with slight variations on the input. This makes
notebooks actually look a lot like a black box function. And then maybe you have a DAG
that continues past this point. All right. So we can talk about what paper mill did and
what in essence it tries to achieve. It's a really simple library. It actually only
has like 2,000 lines of code and 4,000 lines of tests. So you can actually just read all
the source code. It's pretty simple. But what this actually changed for us at Netflix and
for other groups in the world is that now the story about using notebooks can expand
to more use cases. In particular, we had seen analytics engineers and data engineers and
even platform engineers start to use notebooks for various tasks. And then the story was,
oh, you wrote a notebook and did the same. Cool. That's great. Rewrite it over here in
this other library in this other way. And that was a pretty high friction point that
we kept seeing with our users. They had a tool they liked and then we told them to abandon
that tool when they actually wanted to share it or use it in the platform itself. And so
paper mill was kind of an effort to sort of bridge that gap some and start reusing the
technology and integrating the technology they like to use rather than complaining that
it doesn't do what we like. And in this case, now these larger, wider group of users can
actually use notebooks where they would have traditionally just written some Python script
and threw it away someplace. Now they have a notebook which gives a more structured way
of executing and a way they can share the code with engineers or their colleagues better.
And it also is able to integrate into platforms. So a lot of platforms now support paper mill
as a notebook execution. So you can do things like schedule your notebook without rewriting
anywhere else. The other nice thing with paper mill is it's a very plug and play. So it actually
supports all these schemes out of the box. So if you have a Google Cloud store, any of
the Microsoft Azure stores, S3, even HTTPS, which isn't shown here, you can connect to
those and actually pull and read and write from those locations and it just works. And
as I said with a plug and play, the really important thing with paper mill is it's designed so that
it can be extensible to use cases we haven't thought of. So every single component of the library
is actually a registered component by some key name that it goes and looks up what to do just
in time in executing. So what this means is let's say we want to implement SFTP. You think, oh,
well, I've got to fork this library and add a bunch of code and then figure out how to source
code it back. Maybe it's something more proprietary like an internal system you would never share back
what you need to figure out how to make it work. This is all the code you would have to write if
you implemented read and write to add SFTP to paper mill. And you wouldn't even have to install
a new CLI. So what this code basically reads as, you just need to make this handler for the input,
the source or sinks. If you implement read, you can read. If you implement write, you can write.
And then inside of your own package, you can use set up tools and use the entry points to add a new
entry point and then it automatically gets registered into the IO register of paper mill.
And then if you run the command at the very bottom where you say, okay, now I want to execute SFTP,
you can point it at some SFTP server and read and write from it. So how we implemented all those
other schemes, actually teams from those cloud providers oftentimes just made a PR and said,
hey, could we add this? And it was really easy. So other aspects of the library work a very similar way.
All right. So we're going to dig into where some more value with using notebooks and places you
wouldn't traditionally use notebooks. Failed notebooks in the ecosystem, like in a mature
ecosystem, are actually really, really valuable. This is probably the number one thing that has
added value to introducing notebooks into our platform. And you may be thinking, like, okay,
I'm not sure why that would help. But let's say you had that same fan out parallelization that we're
executing and job number three here failed. So we scheduled this notebook template, we ran it a bunch of places.
And number three failed. Okay. What's the traditional story for how you debug and fix this?
Well, hopefully you have some tools that point you to some places and you look at some logs and you
look at what code actually ran. And maybe you have to go like jump through some links and find what
actually happened. Here, when we actually run a notebook, even if the notebook is just setting up
templating for another, some other script to run, the output is actually a full encapsulation of
exactly how it executed and how it failed and associates all the logs with the individual code cells
that actually ran. So if we look at, you know, something like the script on the right, we have some
execution that we're doing where we, the code doesn't really matter. I'm going to jump by this.
But let's say you're trying to create some table in SQL and you have some code that helps you run
that in Spark and it blows up. Well, the thing is, as you're prepping that code, you can print out
useful messages and things like that. You traditionally do this in good software engineering.
And then you would go read the logs. But maybe as an end user, that end user doesn't know how to get
to the logs or doesn't know how to associate lines in that log or the five log files to the code that
actually ran. It can be a pretty complicated process for anyone who isn't used to these systems.
So now if you had that notebook run and then you had this exception happen, which is a connection error,
you couldn't connect to a host genie.typo and you exceeded max retries. In this case, you actually get
an execution failure. And you can actually take that notebook, clone it into your notebook dev
cluster, execute it with any variation you want, find the issue, fix it, and then you can send that
back. And you've actually got a full, like, enclosed circle of, I had a notebook outcome that was
immutably saved, and I can clone that and run it exactly the way it ran elsewhere. And I also can
see exactly how it failed and which parts of the code failed. And that's hugely, hugely valuable.
It saves a ton of time in debugging. And I mean, it gets to the point where even we've had people
who haven't touched code in years who ended up on call and then something went wrong and they just
said, hey, there was this link, I saw there was a notebook, I clicked it, and it was already clear
what was wrong. And I figured out, oh, our table name changed. I saw the table name error right in
the notebook, so I just went and changed it and everything fixed. It's really handy for a lot of
users. So what this execution, like, separation of inputs and outputs and templatizing has done is
it's really added isolation for making immutable inputs and immutable outputs if you set up your
system the way you like or the way you should. And it also allows for the parameterization of
notebook runs and the configurable sourcing and sync is really valuable, too. So, like, for example,
when we run our scheduled notebooks, we default the output path to always be to a output path that
has a unique ID based on the run and the date and all those other things in a GUID. So we have, like,
a collection of all the history of a particular notebook's execution in one place that we kind of
look through and can read and see what happened. It also gives a lot better control of notebooks
via library calls. Because Papermill is a Python library here that you can just import and manipulate
in other ways, you can do more fancy things, like even replace how it executes to do other things,
like maybe you want to save it to another location before it actually runs all the execution, or
perhaps you really want to do something after it finishes running, or you want to inject more than
just the input cell for the parameters. For example, there's one extension that takes it and says,
oh, I don't really like keeping the default parameter cell. I always want to replace it and
just put a new cell there so they, like, 20 lines of Python code were able to change the behavior of
Papermill without, you know, forking and rewriting. And this is kind of leads into how notebooks are
helping us integrate. So one thing I do want to make really clear, notebooks don't make good
libraries. They're really good as an integration tool. And they have a lot of applications. They're
strictly better in most cases than just making a Python script and throwing it in your favorite
file store and then praying that that works in the future. You get more visibility and things like
that. So it is a strict upgrade in many cases, but I'm not going to, like, play down that if you
make a really complicated notebook, it is going to be problematic for you because the unit testing
space is not super great in this context. But notebooks are really good at, you know, building
a result, taking much actions on various pieces of technology, and then kind of summarizing what
happened and collecting errors and things like that. So it makes a really good integration tool
for real production systems. So some development guidelines to keep if you're using notebooks in a
critical path as opposed to maybe just enabling the user to not have to rewrite their things. So we
use these kind of guidelines in writing notebooks for actual production execution for critical
things. And this would be you want to keep a low branching factor. It's difficult to test a notebook
if it has many branches because you don't have the unit testing abstraction like baked first class
into notebooks. Short and simple is better. This is kind of true of all code. Keep one primary
outcome. If you think of the notebook almost like a black box function, you should kind of have one
result that you're trying to achieve. Kind of follow functional programming paradigms, leaves you in a
better place. And then really try to leave library functions and libraries. I'm guilty of not doing
this as much as I should, so do as I say and not as I do all the time. But it's a good indicator if
you're seeing a problem with a notebook, for example, we have a template that runs and occasionally
it has issues because we've got some functions in there that are fairly complicated. It's like, oh,
well, if this is important and we're running the issues and it wasn't tested very well, we should
probably pull that out into its own library. So in that process when you see these critical notebooks,
you can slowly move things into like a utilities library or a library that's associated with the
notebook that you're running. And then you can do the proper unit testing there and then make your
notebook more and more of just an integration of libraries and API calls. So one place where we do
also get a benefit where we didn't have good testing before is integration testing. So end-to-end
testing of a notebook is actually really easy. You just call paper mill on it with some dummy inputs.
So here's an example where we're going to run paper mill and we're going to use this spark template
notebook that we were looking at before. And then maybe we'll save all our test run outputs to some
test run ID path. And then we're going to put in some fake things. So in this case, we're going to
see how many people on the particular day from the moon watched our show. That number should be zero,
but in the case of tests, you can do these kind of dummy tests and make tables that have data that
don't make sense just to prove that the execution works. So here are our parameters we actually get
injected into the notebook are going to be region Luna, run date 2018-04-02 because I think I wrote
that sometime around then. And then debug equals true. You can do things like say drive run if you
want to avoid certain API calls or things like that. And then we actually run your SQL, maybe your
SQL statement that's inside your notebook is something like this where you're inserting into a
table where some run date is equal to the run date and you're in the region that you actually want to
run. And here we're putting in our debug information. We can do things like target our test DBs,
target test data that we don't care about. So we don't really care about like did we get all the data
and it moved over in this execution. We're caring that hey, it can spark execute successfully. If we
did care also about is the outcome accurate because maybe it does some calculation in the notebook
that's the notebook's responsibility, you can follow this by another job right after that would
validate the results or put a test notebook that would validate alongside the actual execution.
So another thing I want to kind of talk about and dig into is some of the other ecosystem goodies.
So as I said, Jupiter, since it defines a protocol and a spec, it actually has a wide collection of
other libraries that help you do different tasks. And putting these things together is oftentimes
the work of your notebook team at your particular company where they'll try and get these pieces
that fit the business needs that you have to support various actions. So these are a few.
There's a ton, ton more. I just threw a few that I've worked on or use a lot. MBConvert is a
conversion tool we use that Papermill actually uses during the execution. Commuter is a read-only
interface for notebooks. Can't say how much, how useful that is. We put all of our output defaults
into a bucket prefix that is read-only in the sense that we can launch and render these things
for our users and they can't edit the outcome. So they can just read what's happening there.
I'll show you what that looks like in a minute. And then we have MBFormat, Bookstore, Scrapbook is
another fun project. And that's around saving outcomes. So these are things on more the compute
side and rendering, but there's also lots of other things on the front-end side about different
component libraries and integration of different tools. So I'll talk really quickly just about one
of these goodies called Scrapbook, which originally was functionality. It was in the early versions of
Papermill and we pulled into its own library. And what Scrapbook does is it lets you basically
save the results, the data results, into the notebook object. So you can actually make the
notebook also store what was the result in a programmatic way. And here I'll show you what
this does. So it's only a few lines of code, much like Papermill. It's not a super complicated
interface. But here we're going to import Scrapbook inside of our notebook and we're going to say
Scrapbook.Glu and we're going to say model result. So you have a model execution and the model result
is some accuracy value. I'm using a lot of machine learning metaphors only because the
data science space has been really strong in notebooks. So it translates to some real-world use
cases you might have users asking to do. In this case, we save the model results into the notebook
and then later, outside of that notebook, we can go read the results of that notebook with this one
line of code. So we can go read the notebook which ran, some ML experiment run 71, and we can ask it
for its scraps, which are all the things we glued into it, like our metaphor game here.
And the scraps that we get here are the model results. We can ask for that by key name. So you
could glue a whole bunch of things, model results, graphs. Matter of fact, in the bottom one here,
you could actually put performance graph, or why did we pick that model? What was the information
around it? You can save a whole PNG on the notebook and then re-reference it this way and
re-render it elsewhere. And that's just a kind of nice little utility if you're interested in kind
of getting functional data results out of notebooks, I would encourage taking a look at that.
We'd love more contributors for various use cases we haven't supported yet. And then commuter is the
read-only interface I was talking about. This is the commuter interface. This is actually our
integration template for running Presto jobs. That's the whole thing. Fits on one page. It's
nice and simple. And this has a read-only interface when the user executes this notebook. This is the
template they would see if they go click on the link for how's my job input look. If you look at
the output, it would be this, but with all the actual log out pumps right alongside it.
In this case, too, you don't need a really expensive server or runtime launching. It
just needs a server with basic JavaScript rendering. So a quick thing about notebooks at Netflix and
how we use them, because I'm talking about the open source side more. One thing we did when
we started this project about a year and a half ago to really deep dive into notebooks is there
was this kind of strategic bet that notebooks is becoming a common interface for many of our
users. We had lots and lots of analysts, lots and lots of data scientists, and more data engineers.
They were starting to use notebooks and then having friction when they came to using them.
So we invested in a lot of areas of notebook infrastructure and tried to get really involved
in the community and hire people from that community in order to foster the open source
approach to how to solve these things. And since then, we now run over 10,000 jobs a day
on notebooks. They run like 150,000 queries or more at this point. And all of those are running
on notebooks. And the way we've achieved that is by actually making it like a simple templating
of how they run a normal job. It maps into our notebook templates instead of into like a
traditional scheduler template you might see. So when they say I want to run a Spark job,
here's my query, we say great, we'll take that. And when it actually runs and they want to see
what happened or debug why it failed, there's a notebook link that shows them, hey, this is
what we did. And as we've gradually brought users into cases where notebooks are useful for them,
they can also just schedule their own input path notebook and works the same way.
So that's what I wanted to kind of share with you all and definitely encourage you to go look at
the open source projects we referenced. And the slides I believe are going to be, yeah,
the slide link will be here, so I'll leave this up if you want to copy that. And here's a few
interfaces to come talk to some of the open source groups on these topics. Thank you.
Thank you, Matthew. We have some time for questions. So if you have a question,
please step up to one of these audience microphones. Please make sure to keep your
questions directed at the speaker. If you have longer questions or comments, you can find them
in the hall afterwards. Hi, go ahead.
Hey. So if you have engineers and stuff and they want to spin up a cluster and attach a notebook
to it, how does that work? Do you run notebooks locally usually or is there some way to spin up
a notebook in a spark cluster that you have automated? Yeah, so the question was around
how do you connect when someone asks for a notebook, what do we do? In our case,
we have container launching service which launches a Jupyter notebook server for the user
and they can connect to that. Whenever they want to launch, we connect them. If not, we make them
an instance and it comes up with the notebook infrastructure. And then it mounts the file
systems that are shared between the systems. So if the user is saving things, they'll see it in
their dev home directory as well. So we just kind of give them an experience there. And then the
other thing we do is for those URLs and paths for hitting their custom notebook server, if they
provide those to the scheduler or another tool, we can translate via paper mill, a wrapper on
paper mill to translate those schemes and paths into the source of the file. So the user can give
us the URL and we'll run it in other places. Sounds awesome. Is that open source? Yeah,
you can do things with Jupyter hub is a good first starting point to go look and it has
really, really good tutorials they've made now for how to get Jupyter hub launched in one or
two pages on all sorts of cloud platforms. So there was a group at Berkeley that did a whole
bunch of work around that. I would encourage looking at that. Hey, great talk. Quick question.
For testing notebooks, I see the use case a lot of times for programmatic testing of Python outputs
because that's more quantitative in nature. My question is if you want to test say graph outputs
where it's an image and you want to, that's something that you as a human qualitatively assert,
how would you go about asserting that from an automation standpoint or even taking it further
like a JavaScript widget as an output for inside a notebook? How would you go about testing those
things? Yeah, so what I would actually say in that case, if it's isolated all the way inside the
notebook, I would look at maybe combining paper mill and scrapbook and you save the data results,
the data frame or whatever input you built the graph with and the visualization and then you
could run your test to say, hey, fetch the result out of the notebook. If it matches my assertions,
great. If not, render maybe the graph as well so you can see what it actually did or the link to
the notebook. We do a lot of integration tests where we actually run and then we'll link it to
the run, the exact run that ran with the commuter link and then the user could just go look at the
notebook. So it's always going to be qualitative in its nature but just making that easier so that
way it's just a few clicks to qualitatively assert it. I think there's always a human involved when
your test fails but to assert, I would look at saving data with scrapbook if you don't already
have a place to save your outcomes. Okay, great. Thank you so much. Hello, I'm just kind of wondering
great talk by the way. I'm wondering sort of what best practices you guys use for doing things like
dependency management when you're running notebooks. Yeah, so dependency management is
another sticky point in notebooks. I think it'll be better in the future. There's been a lot of
push to make it more natural in notebooks to define dependencies. Today what we do to get
around this pain is we actually have like a single image that we maintain as a team that has the
majority of the dependencies for our users and we do this not to satisfy dependency needs but we
actually do it so that our users get a consistent experience. So if they're running in their dev
server or they're running in the scheduler or they're running someplace else, their notebook
will have the same set of base dependencies and then we give them tools for defining extra packages
they want to use if they want to install them just in time or as they run. Thanks. Yeah. Hey,
you go first. A file format that takes the essentially plain python file that just has the cell
breaks as comments in the python file. Does Papermill consume that as well as a regular notebook? It
does not today. It'd be pretty easy to add it and I think a lot of the tools that do that cell separation
are adding in notebook export as well. So like hydrogen and VS code are both either have beta
versions of that or will have it fully soon. So it could integrate pretty easily but yeah,
make an open source contribution and we'll add it. Cool, thanks. Hey, great talk. One of the issues
that our team has had with notebooks is version control like committing things to git and do you
guys do anything to kind of do that especially during the development process? Yeah, so one place
I would look is the version control story and git isn't so great because you're diffing json,
not because the diffs are bad. There's a few things you can yeah. I think that the integration
story there like everyone wants to solve this problem and there's lots of people trying to
work on it right now. I do say there's a few things to look at today. Jupiter slash nbdime
is a really good library for doing notebook diffs. It's not integrated in all the stacks and that's
partially because things like bit bucket and git labs still need to add some extensions to their
API to make it work within the UI. But if you're on git hub there's also some open source and
closed source options that do extensions so that you can see rendered like two pain diffs of
notebooks where it's like highlighting the code in a notebook format. It's pretty nice.
What's that? Do you have any idea if that's what Databricks is using when they have version
control connected to it? I am not sure what Databricks is using. I haven't looked recently
but likely they're using one of those two or three options that are out there.
Hi. Good talk. I was wondering you mentioned about testing these notebooks. Does PaperMill
have any sort of programmatic API for getting the test result errors or which cells are erroring out
or any sort of that kind of information? Yeah. When PaperMill executes it injects a whole bunch
of metadata into the JSON document it's saving. So when it errors it will actually save that
document one last time. It actually saves as each cell executes and if the cell fails it also saves
and it will inject a whole bunch of error info and run time info into the notebook object in
the metadata and that's the first place you can look and then if it's more specific I would look
into like saving the data results of something like scrapbook. Thank you. Hey. So I think you
make a I think this makes a pretty good case for how to run notebooks for analytical data science
type use cases. I'm wondering if you guys are using this approach for maybe more like production
data engineering like ETL jobs or jobs which are going to have like customer impact or if you know
your teams are still using maybe traditional you know type jobs for those. So yeah I would say so
actually when I said that scheduler project almost all of our ETL is now running on notebooks even
if the users don't know it. So we've made a pretty big commitment to it like we run millions of
notebooks now as if you consider each run a different one. So that's definitely like taken
off and done really well for us. I would say like users developing their own notebooks there was
some history there that story's a little bit better but I would say it's not a dominant pattern to do
all your ETL work in a notebook purely but we do try to like translate that into a notebook execution
so that it's easy to see what happened. So like a lot of really important critical systems are running
on notebooks now. I would say some of the more custom notebooks there's a few that do also do
like their whole dev notebook style.
Hi so I come from a scientific background and scientists really want to collaborate on notebooks
and have shared workspaces. Can you comment a little bit more on that? On collaboration? Yes.
Do you mean like multiple collaboration on the same notebook while they're working? Yes. Yeah so
that's actually probably something that will be coming. There's been a lot of discussion within
the community and there's a direction to go. There is one tool out there which already has
real-time collaboration called CoCalc. It's really oriented towards academic use so it's more like
classroom type learning setting. So it has a few things that wouldn't work as well in a production
like engineering space but the model they have is really good and we're probably going to push for
pushing that model into Jupiter Core. Hi I'd like to follow up on the version control question with
ETL. I'm blown away by your description that most of the ETL has been moved over to notebooks.
What in practice are you doing in terms of storing and managing the source notebooks? Yeah so it's
a mix. So all our templates that we use to say hey you can use this template like Spark, Presto,
and Transport, things like that, they're all checked in the git and then we have a big
integration suite which runs pay-per-mill against all of those every time anything changes from any
source and then we kind of promote those towards standard asset promotion pattern you see with any
code asset and then those become the default template they can use and then we can pin back
the old version so it looks a lot like any kind of other dependency management
sort of asset pipeline for non-managed notebooks like in the sense of just the user's notebook.
We do encourage putting it in git and then just referencing but we also don't block people because
we have a lot of analysts that don't quite know git yet or people that aren't familiar with it or
don't have a team that's using it and in those cases we've been trying to work on a project
called Bookstore which is the new thing which helps give you linear versioning automatically
by every time you save it kicks off a unique version into S3 and just saves it there so you
can always go back and look at old versions and then when we schedule notebooks one thing we do
is we copy that notebook in the S3 for that version and we copy all the assets you reference
so if you say hey I need this file and this file and this file from git we copy all of those and
bundle them into an asset bundle for the scheduled job that won't change even if the git changes and
we associate back to that git commit. So if I understand you're when promoted you're mirroring
at templates and assets from git hub to S3? Yeah we mirror to the git commit that that code came from.
Okay cool thank you. I'm just wondering if you had any special tricks around authentication
particularly passing kind of auth tokens or other kind of credentials when you're calling one
notebook from another or does everything kind of run in a single authentication context when
you're accessing different kind of data? Yeah so what we encourage and try to build tools to help
with is we try to make it so that they can add secrets to their execution context without having
it be in the notebook so they might refer to a tool that's going to go try and load the credentials
that need to be made and we try to keep people from putting anything plain text or even encrypted
into the inputs as parameters because those are pretty prevalently visible. In general for us
usually there's already tools for doing that in our platform so we just integrate with those
tools that are already there and make sure that the API calls you're making just kind of fall into
those. There is some work on a few cloud teams that are doing to make interfaces that do this for you
in a way in the notebook. There's not too many open source versions of that yet. Thanks. Yeah.
All right so could we please get another round of applause for Matthew.