Welcome, everyone.
Just as a reminder, please make sure to put all of your devices in silence, otherwise
you will have a glare from me.
We are welcoming Rachel Tatman.
She will be presenting Put Down Your Deep Learning, When Not to Use Neural Networks,
and What to Do Instead.
Hello.
Sorry, I just wanted to make sure my phones were on silent, especially since they're right
next to that microphone.
Good afternoon, everybody.
Thank you for coming.
I am Rachel Tatman.
I'm a data scientist advocate.
I'm trying to say that my...
Have a job title that says what I do, so I'm trying this one out.
Let me know if it's helpful for you guys.
At Kaggle.
I'm very happy to talk about Kaggle, but that's not what I'm here to talk about today.
Today I'm here to talk about deep learning and, more importantly, alternatives to deep
learning.
Just to get a sense of the room before I start out, who's heard of deep learning?
Yay.
Pretty much everybody.
Presumably that's why you're here.
Who's done some deep learning?
Anything from TensorFlow to poets to it's part of your job?
Okay.
I'd say about half the people.
Some folks were like, kind of.
I probably actually don't need to tell you guys this, but I think it's worth going over.
Deep learning is a fantastic set of technologies, and we've seen some amazing wins lately.
I've just picked a couple of examples of things that I think are particularly impressive.
Open AI 5 is the model that just beat, they say, Dota 2 gods.
There are several video game players at the video game that they play professionally at
a live sporting, e-sporting event for the first time.
It's very exciting, and that happened, I think, last week.
Previously, AlphaGo Zero was a Google model that beat the best Go players, it's a board
game in the world, at the board game that they play professionally.
Another really exciting instance of computers being better than humans at a very, very narrow
task.
There's a robot that came out relatively recently, or the paper came out recently, and it looks
in a bin of things, and it picks out things and it tosses them into other bins, so it
basically sorts by throwing, which seems really dumb, and like a toddler could do it, but
it's actually very hard computationally.
That's an impressive finding.
This particular newspaper is a little bit hypey, a little bit fiari.
I think the actual paper title is, like, towards human parody, and it sort of got juiced up
a little bit in the PR rounds, but speech recognition has gotten much, much better.
It's maybe not quite at the point where we can replace human transcribers, thank you,
and especially if you want high-quality transcriptions, I probably wouldn't use it for everything,
but we're getting to the point where it's fairly usable for most things.
Thank you.
So, it seems like, especially if you're sort of outside the field and just learning about
it through headlines, machine learning can do anything these days, right, and especially
deep learning, which means that we can use deep learning to do everything, right?
Not so much.
So I think that being in the deep learning field right now is a little bit like being
a paleontologist.
So you tell people you're a paleontologist, I'm assuming I'm not a paleontologist, and
people are like, oh, cool, I'm thinking about dinosaurs, they're so powerful, they're so
big, they're so exciting.
Maybe small children are impressed.
Small children generally aren't impressed when I tell them I do machine learning, but
maybe someday they will be.
And then you have the sort of the glamorous experience of what people think deep learning
is like, and then you have the less glamorous reality.
So building deep learning models, even if you're not doing research, is slow, it's tedious,
it's painstaking, it takes a lot of time, it's really expensive.
We'll talk about how expensive in a little bit.
And it's frustrating because there's this sense of uncertainty.
When you set out working on a project and you're building a specific model, you don't
know that it's going to work.
And you don't know that the specific parameters that you're using and the specific hyperparameters
that you're using are going to work for your problem.
You don't know what architecture is going to work best.
The state of the art right now is guess and test.
And I am in no way exaggerating.
There's a lot of deep learning models that we don't have a deep theoretical understanding
of, we just have a lot of empirical results that show that they're good for a certain
set of problems, which is really frustrating.
And I have a really good example of this.
So this is a passage from the BERT paper.
BERT is a large neural network based, what am I saying, language model, that's the words
I'm looking for, which is unsupervised.
So it's basically trained on a bunch of text data, it notices patterns more or less.
And then the idea is that you have your big language model and on top of it you have a
little bit of fine tuning for your specific task where you do have labeled data.
So it's a lot of unsupervised learning, a little bit of supervised learning.
It seems to be pretty transferable between tasks.
So that's exciting.
Unfortunately, and this is a really good paper, it just won best paper at NACL, which is one
of the premier NLP, natural language processing conferences.
This is state of the art research.
And something in the paper that they said that really stuck with me is that as they
were doing this fine tuning, building this sort of little layer on top, sometimes it
just didn't work.
And when that happened, they just restarted it randomly.
And sometimes it did work.
So you just have to run a bunch of models and figure out which one works well and use
that one.
That doesn't feel super satisfying as a working methodology, at least to me.
I'd like to know what works ahead of time.
I also mentioned expense, and I know these are a little bit hard to read.
I'll give you guys a link to the slides at the end.
People don't generally tell you how much it costs to train their model, but folks are
also very willing to go on Twitter and do sort of back of the envelope math.
So here's one estimate for big GAN, which is an image generation model.
I think it came out in January.
You might have seen headlines like, this dog doesn't exist.
A computer imagined it, or something like that.
And the estimate for back of the envelope math is around $60,000 just of compute.
That does not count what you might need to pay to license the images to train it.
GPT-2 is another big neural language model like BERT.
This one was bigger and trained for longer.
And again, back of the envelope math, maybe around $43,000 worth of compute.
And these are by no means the biggest models.
So I mentioned OpenAI 5, which is the algorithm, or sorry, the model that won Dota 2.
That trained continuously for 10 months.
I cannot tell you how much it cost.
I feel very comfortable saying many millions of dollars.
Right?
And I don't know about you guys and your relationships with your managers, but if I go to my manager
and ask for $50,000 worth of compute for something that might work, I would be encouraged to
explore other approaches to that problem.
So when would I actually use deep learning?
And I'm going to keep this talk very high level and just sort of talk about my experiences.
I'm not going to go into the math.
There are many resources out there, and feel free to hit me up afterwards if you want recommendations.
I would use deep learning for a problem if, one, a human can do it in less than a second.
The longer it takes you to do something, especially something cognitive, the more complex it probably
is, the more data I'm going to need, and the bigger the model I'm going to need to train
in order to approximate it.
So one second is just sort of my personal litmus test right now.
I have to have a high tolerance for weird errors.
Neural networks have neural in the name.
They are not cognitive models.
They are not telling you what a human would do in this situation.
So a really good example of this is humans use silhouettes when identifying objects.
That's just sort of a cognitive bias that we have.
Most computer vision models do not use silhouettes.
They use collection of pixels.
So they're much easier to fool with textures than they are with silhouettes.
So humans have a very gestalt view if you have taken much psychology, and neural networks
don't.
I would also only use a neural network if I didn't need to explain myself.
So if I were, say, working in finance and needed to show with a certain degree of confidence
that I did not use race or any correlative race to decide whether or not to give you
a mortgage, I can't do that with a neural network.
And we've been doing as a field, not me personally, a lot of work on interpretability and explainability,
and it is getting much better, but we're not to the same point that we are already with
regression models.
I would also only use neural networks if I had a large quantity of labeled data.
I say more than 5,000 labeled items per class.
That is very much a low ball.
You can get away with less if you already have a trained model and you can do transfer
learning, but still, you need a lot of data, and all of the research so far has shown the
more data, the bigger the model, the more compute, the better the results.
And finally, I'd only do it if I had a lot of time and money.
So training models takes time, especially if I'm doing model comparison.
If I'm doing any sort of hyperparameter search, that takes much more time because I have to
train multiple models and see which one is better.
And money.
So for data annotation, if I need additional labeled data, if I need someone to go through
and maybe do some sort of human-in-the-loop tuning, that costs money.
And compute, of course, also costs money, and we talked about sort of the orders of
magnitude that we're talking about there for a really large model.
So deep learning.
You need a lot of time.
You need a lot of money.
You need a lot of data.
Some of you may be in that position.
Fantastic.
Go forth and deep learn.
If you are not, you have lots of options.
I am not going to cover the entire fields of statistics and machine learning today,
but I am going to talk about three different types of models.
So in particular, regression, tree-based models.
Tree-based models didn't fit well in my matrix.
And then distance-based models.
Let's start with regression.
So if you have done much machine learning, I'm hoping you are already familiar with
regression.
Quick show of hands.
Who here has never learned about regression?
Either in a blog post or everyone has.
Fantastic.
I'm really, really, really happy to hear that.
I talked to a lot of aspiring data scientists and people who want to get into the field
who started with deep learning and aren't familiar with other methods like regression.
That's part of the reason that I put this talk together.
I love regression.
I'm a big regression fangirl.
In regression, you do need to do a little bit of hands-on pointing of the model in the
direction that you want it to go.
So you need to pick the family of the function you'll use to model your data.
In this case, we have the simplest case of linear regression where the thing on the x-axis,
whatever it is, has a linear relationship with the thing on the y-axis, whatever that
is.
This is just a picture of a regression that's in the public domain.
And there's really a lot of kinds of regression models out there.
And unlike with most types of neural networks, we have a really principled understanding
of what types of problems these are going to be good for.
So if you're using regression, you can basically sit down and work through a flow chart to
fix the specific type of regression that's going to work best for your problem, which
is really nice.
Some really big advantages of regression, fast to fit, much faster to the fit than neural
networks, especially if you're working with a well-optimized library.
The Python regression libraries tend to vary wildly, so you might want to do a little bit
of shopping around.
It works well with small data.
I've done regression on a dozen data points and learned something useful and interesting.
And it's also really easy to interpret, and I'll walk through an example of interpreting
it a bit, but it looks like most of you are already familiar with regression, so that
might be a little bit redundant.
There are some downsides.
You need to do a little bit more data preparation than for some other methods.
If there are two variables that are strongly correlated, you might want to spend some time
either creating a feature based on those models or correcting because you're going to have
a higher standard error on account of multicollinearity, classic machine learning interview question.
And they also require validation.
So regression models are based on strong assumptions about the distribution of the data points
or the distribution of the errors, and if you are using a regression model, you need
to check that those assumptions are true.
Otherwise you'll get numbers out.
They just won't mean anything.
My personal favorite type of regression model is mixed effects regression.
If I had to pick a single machine learning model to use for the rest of my life, honestly
it would probably be mixed effects regression.
And this is a little example of Simpson's paradox.
So who's familiar with Simpson's paradox?
Oh, not everybody.
Excellent.
So the idea with Simpson's paradox is if you look at all the points together as a group,
you see one trend, but if you divide the groups into subgroups that are meaningful for your
specific problem, you see the opposite trend.
So here, for example, let's say that the x-axis is amount of time spent playing an educational
video game and the y-axis is test scores.
And we want to see if playing this video game improves people's test scores.
If we look at all the students, so let's see each point as a student, we will see a negative
trend.
So the more time you spend playing the video game, the worse your test scores are.
I'm asking you to imagine axes and axes levels here.
If we break things down by classroom, where each color of student, each color of dot is
a different classroom, we see the opposite trend.
And so it might be that different classes pattern together differently for other reasons.
So maybe some teachers were given an easier version of the test or maybe the classes were
sort of divided by ability in the particular subject area that we're looking at.
So when we model each class individually, we see that spending more time playing the
video game actually improves our test scores.
And with mixed effects regression, we can really easily pull out these effects.
And that would be the random effect here would be which group you're assigned to or which
classroom you are in.
I'm not going to show you a whole bunch of code here.
The main thing I want you to get from my code samples is that all of these models are very
easy to implement.
They don't take a lot of code.
Even a very minimal TensorFlow or Keras deep learning model is going to be more code than
this.
So I'm using the stats model library module, sorry.
And I've used the mix LM method.
And here I am modeling the chance of being admitted to graduate school based on your
GRE, which is a standardized test for people who are interested in going to graduate school
and TOEFL score, which is a test of English as a foreign language.
And then I am grouping things.
So I'm using as a random variable here, university rating.
So I think that maybe really prestigious universities are going to pattern together and maybe like
smaller regional universities are likely to pattern together.
And then I fit my model.
And that's all there is to it.
I mentioned that regression models were particularly easy to interpret.
And here is the model output that we can use to answer specific questions.
So if a student came to me and was like, hey, I have a limited amount of time to study,
should I focus on my GRE or should I focus on my TOEFL exam?
So by looking at the coefficients here, I can see that every one point increase in GRE
score increases your chance to admit to graduate school by half a percent.
And every one point increase in TOEFL score increases your chances of admitting to graduate
school by seven tenths of a percent.
So assuming that one unit of studying is going to raise your score in either test by the
same amount, I suggest focusing on the TOEFL score.
So that's a clear, actionable recommendation I can make based on the model output that
I have.
And if this was a business setting and people were like, hey, should we focus on, you know,
I can't come up with a good example right now, I could tell them based on the features
that I had.
All right.
So regression modeling takes some time.
You need to do a little bit more hands-on stuff.
You need to do your validation.
You probably need to do some additional data cleaning.
It does not take that much money, doesn't need a lot of compute, and can work with pretty
small data sets.
Trees.
So hopefully everyone has seen something like a decision tree at some point.
Has anyone not run across tree structures at some point?
Okay, I see a sample hands.
So the idea with a tree structure and specifically a decision tree is at each node you look at
one feature for each of your items, and depending on the value of that feature, you decide which
path to go down.
And when you go down that path, the next node has another feature, and you base on the value
of that feature.
So basically, you are recursively cutting your decision region into smaller and smaller
chunks.
That's the idea.
Nobody uses trees.
Everybody uses forests.
So random forests are ensemble models.
So they combine a lot of different decision trees together into a single model.
They are extremely popular on Kaggle.
If you're in the machine learning community, you might actually associate random forests
with Kaggle.
And about from 2010 to 2016, about two-thirds of all Kaggle competition winners used random
forests.
Less than half used some form of deep learning.
And random forests continue to do very well today.
They also tend to have better performance than logistic regression, especially for classification.
There's a paper there you can read if you're interested.
And they work really well.
Some benefits and drawbacks.
You don't need to do a lot of data cleaning or model validation.
You can pretty much shove anything into a random forest.
You don't need to convert your categorical variables.
It'll just sort of consume them and give you a model.
And there are a lot of really easy to use packages with a really fantastic developer
experience that are also very well optimized.
So XGBoost, which I like, LightGBM, CatBoost.
There's going to be a new one in the next Scikit-learn release candidate.
You can check that out if you're interested in yet another very good option, I'm sure.
Some drawbacks.
They are very easy to overfit.
You can imagine if you're building a tree, the natural end case would be you had one
data point per leaf.
And then you have perfectly described the distribution of your training data, which
is the definition of overfitting.
So to get around that, people will usually trim and remove the bottom couple layers from
their tree.
They're also really sensitive to differences between datasets.
And this is a little bit blown out, but this is actually the decision region of a single
decision tree.
And it sort of looks like a plaid.
And you can imagine that if there's a point in one of those plaid stripes of the opposite
color, then a tree trained on that dataset would actually have that stripe be a different
color, if that makes sense.
It's a little bit hard to see.
They are also less interpretable than regression.
You can get information out.
You can get feature importance out, ranked feature importance pretty easily.
But it's harder to say, hey, if I change this, what would change?
And tweak the knobs in quite the same way.
And they can also require a lot more compute and training time.
So I mentioned a lot of well-optimized packages.
But ensembles require building a lot of models.
And for every additional model, there's additional training time involved as a cost.
And again, a little code example.
I happen to like XGBoost.
One thing that's really nice about XGBoost is that the default parameter, hyperparameter
settings are very reasonable for the vast majority of problems.
So you can pretty much just use XGBoost out of the box.
And most of the time, it will work well enough.
If you're hoping to win a Kaggle competition, you are going to need to do some tuning.
But it's a really good starting point.
So tree-based methods take some time, especially if you have a big ensemble, a big data set,
and you want to do maybe some cross-validation, some jackknifing, some bootstrapping to help
avoid that overfitting to data sets.
Again, not a lot of money.
They don't take that much compute.
And they do need some data and a little bit more than for regression, again, because you're
going to want to do more rigorous cross-validation.
And finally, distance-based methods.
So this is a very vague term that I've used to group together a large class of methods,
where the general idea is the closer some things are in a projection of feature space,
whatever feature space you're using, the more likely they are to be in the same group or
to be related to each other.
So I have a little example of k nearest neighbors up there.
You decide the value of a point based on the whatever number nearest neighbors, so majority
vote.
Gaussian mixture models, which is more of a clustering thing, which suggests that any
distribution of points is going to be a mixture of different Gaussians.
And support vector machines, which I like to think of as a cat that doesn't want to
be petted, so the line is trying to be as far away from all the data points as possible.
Or support vector regression, which is sort of the opposite, where the cat wants to be
as close to as many points as possible, where the points are hands, I guess, in this metaphor.
So benefits and drawbacks.
Support vector machines in particular work very well with small data sets.
You need a minimum of four points.
They also tend to be very fast to train, in my experience, at least in order of magnitude
faster than a regression model on the same data.
Overall accuracy.
There are other methods that tend to do better, but for especially quick and dirty modeling,
they're perfectly fine.
They're good at classification.
If you want to do estimation specifically with support vector machines, it's a little
bit slower, so you might want to use regression for that.
Usually these days people tend to use them in ensembles, but it's a nice fast first pass
for a problem.
If you're sitting in a meeting and someone's like, hey, is this predictable?
You can just open R or PyCon or whatever you're using quickly.
Run a few lines of code and tell them very quickly.
And again, here is just the code that you need to train this.
In the code sample I'll give you, I've done all the preprocessing beforehand, and the
same preprocessing was done for all three models.
And here I'm using support vector regression, because I'm doing regression in all of my
examples, just so they're parallel.
All right, so distance-based measures.
Very little time, very little money, very little data.
They're extremely lightweight.
So what message should you use?
And for some reason my shruggy emoji isn't showing up, even though other emojis have.
Mysterious.
So it depends on what you have a lot of.
If you have a lot of time, data, and money, go ahead and use deep learning.
If you don't have any of those things, maybe distance-based learning.
But I have been a little bit disingenuous.
There is a hidden fourth column that I haven't been mentioning, and that's performance.
So what is the ideal maximum?
How well can this model do in the best case?
And the fact of the matter is, based on empirical evidence, right now it looks like deep learning
will perform the best on a given data set, given sufficient time, money, and compute.
Next, at least, again, empirically, trees and specifically random forests.
After that, regression, and then finally, distance-based measures like SVM.
But again, there are things to consider other than whether or not you're going to get state
of the art results at NeurIPS, unless you are like a Google research lab, in which case
you probably wouldn't be here anyway.
And if I were going to give each of these model types a little high school superlative,
I would vote deep learning the most powerful, the most flexible.
Regression, the most interpretable.
If you need to know why, if you need to answer what-if questions, I'd go with regression.
Trees, the user-friendliest, especially if you're just sitting down to do classification.
And then distance-based measures, the most lightweight, because they're fast and you
don't need a lot of data.
And just a final caveat, data science does not equal deep learning.
I know that outside of the field, that's what we've been communicating out, because it's
the most exciting.
But you can do data science without deep learning.
It's really okay, guys.
It's extremely powerful and it's not for everything.
So I would like to encourage you all, in all aspects of your life, to avoid being a person
with a hammer.
So there's a saying, to a person with a hammer, everything looks like a nail.
There are many tools out there, and they're going to be better for different jobs.
So explore your options and don't be wedded to your specific favorite tool.
And also saying that to myself, there's places where you can't use mixed effects regression,
and it's fine.
And just a final note, deep learning isn't a core skill in professional data science,
and it's going to depend on your particular job ad that you're looking at.
But Dan Becker, who is in charge of Learn at Kaggle, posted the other day, and I thought
this was really interesting.
He was looking at, I think it was the hacker rank who's hiring thread, and he set out a
400 job posts.
Only five of them called for PyTorch, TensorFlow, or Keras, which are all deep learning frameworks,
or deep learning.
So people aren't necessarily only looking to hire deep learning people.
All right.
And I'm going to open it up for questions.
Thank you.
All right.
We have time for about five minutes of questions, so use the mics on both sides.
I also post a link to my slides.
Hi.
So I am a social scientist working in education, and so I guess I'm going to go opposite.
Are there opportunities for deep learning in education?
I think we have a tendency to want to understand why we're finding out why kids aren't being
successful, so just being told at the end of a deep learning model, that doesn't help
us as much.
Can you think of some applications of deep learning within maybe the social science sphere?
Yeah.
I can think of some bad ones.
So my big worry, particularly in social science and things with learning and things where
you might, like, say, be allocating education funding is you're going to end up modeling
a latent variable that you don't necessarily want to model, like how high property taxes
are and how well that correlates with, you know, whether kids get a good lunch and then
how well they do in school for that.
Yeah.
I think probably the most immediately useful applications of deep learning in social sciences
would be for things like annotating large image data sets.
So if you're looking at what's written on the board in the classroom, I guess, and you
want to get that information into a way that's machine readable, I think that could be a
good application.
Okay.
Yeah.
Thank you.
I think you could probably come up with better ones than I could.
So given enough time and data, are there any reasons why you wouldn't want to try all of
these, for example?
Or are there certain situations or contexts where you would really say never do this as
opposed to just doing a train test set and seeing what works best?
There's no reason not to do all of them if you have the resources.
And in fact, it's very common to do all of them and then squish them into a single ensemble.
So yeah, no reason not to.
Great talk.
I really enjoyed it.
I guess one question that comes to mind is it seems like there's a paradigm where there's
those who have the resources and those who don't.
So I guess, could you comment on that?
And what should plebs like me do when I don't have the resources?
Well, I'm glad you asked that.
So there are a couple of places where you can get access to, say, large public data
sets and a compute environment that's GPU enabled, and that's Kaggle.
And there are also other places as well.
So Colab is a hosted notebook that offers GPU access.
Data there are some areas where it's just going to be really hard to find data without
paying for it, particularly financial data or image data sets where the images aren't
all under a friendly copyright or a friendly license.
Yeah, no, that is something that I stay up at night worrying about as well.
Because I mean, I can't spend $45 million training a game playing robot.
That's not on my capability list.
I have no good answers other than we're trying to help.
Hi, Cass Storrs.
Simon and Schuster.
I'm curious, do you have any good resources on interpreting and validating models, particularly
regression models?
I think it's really important.
You can easily run a regression model, but you might be using the wrong model in that
case, right?
Yeah, absolutely.
I have actually written a series of notebooks that are hosted on Kaggle that go through
– it's in R. If you're going to be doing a lot of regression, consider maybe looking
at R. It goes through model validation and selection for regression in particular that
I'm happy about.
So I'll tweet out a link to those.
And I am R.C.
Tatman on Twitter.
That'd be great.
Thank you.
Of course.
I have one problem where we use a deep neural net to solve this problem.
But it turned out that actually all we really needed was regression.
And where would you start?
Should you start with a regression or would you start with your list and start at the
bottom and work up?
Yeah.
I generally only use distance-based methods if I'm in a real time crunch.
My usual step through if I'm doing a regression problem would probably be regression, random
forests, deep learning if I have to.
If I was doing specifically classification and I wasn't as concerned with interpretability,
I might do random forests, regression, and then deep learning.
But every problem's different, right?
Sure.
But it occurred to me in our problem we started in the wrong place.
Yeah.
Don't start with deep learning.
Also in your personal learning journey, please put deep learning like after regression.
It'll make me happy.
I got one question.
One of the issues that I see a lot is the issue dealing with extrapolation versus interpolation.
One of the issues with neural networks is that outside of the domain, you get completely
undefined output.
Are there any models or any approaches that you would suggest to take when you want at
least you have a reasonable expectation of what the value should be but not necessarily
a data point there for the model to train on?
If you have strong a priori reason to believe that given X, you'd get Y out, you can use
simulation for data augmentation.
That is kind of a dangerous path.
If I were doing that, I'd want to have a really strong reason to believe that there is data
that exists here that I just don't have access to and I believe that these are its qualities.
We're going to have to wrap up questions here, but I'm sure you're willing to answer
some questions out in the hall if you have any other further questions.
Let's say thank you again.
Thank you.