Good morning, everybody.
My name is Enric.
I'm a production engineer up in Facebook Seattle.
Those of you who aren't aware, Facebook is a platinum sponsor of the PyCon, yeah, the
PSF.
And we're always very grateful to be here at PyCon.
This is actually my second PyCon.
My first PyCon was in 2010, so I'm hoping to do at least another one in the next decade.
For those of you who aren't aware, Facebook actually does use Python quite a bit, not
just the PHP shop.
From the more obvious, like, data analysts and things like that, to the less obvious,
like, our entire configuration management system.
We also use it quite a bit in a little product that we have heard of called Instagram.
Now, personally, I wasn't a big Instagram user until I got a puppy.
And all of a sudden, everybody wanted to know his IG handle, and I had to get one.
So IG uses quite a few open source technologies, such as Celery and Django, to help deliver
those cute puppy photos to your inbox every day.
Now, we're also proud to be a sponsor of several open source projects, like PyTorch, which
is a drop-in replacement for NumPy, and actually lets you use a lot of those juicy GPUs to
get more performance out of your software.
We also provide Pyre, which is a performance type checking system, which really speeds
up your testing.
And finally, this is actually my favorite I just found out about this one.
It's called Monkey Type.
Actually allows you to profile your code, and it will actually provide stubs or directly
annotate your code to automatically add type hints, which honestly blew my mind.
Now, I'm extremely proud to be at Facebook.
We are very grateful to be here.
We're very thankful for all of your contributions to the Python community, and, of course,
to the rest of the world.
Without any further ado, I want to give a brief thanks to the Python organizers, to
PSF, and thank you for all of you guys for making this the best PyCon to come.
I'm looking forward to seeing everybody next year at Pittsburgh.
Thank you.
Oh, excuse me.
Sorry.
As out running this morning, so a round of applause for everyone who took part in the
5K.
I was a little worried people would get lost in the fog, but we made it.
A quick reminder, this is our contact information and more information that you can find for
our code of conduct.
And if you need to report, you can use that contact information or find someone wearing
one of these shirts.
And once again, there it is.
Reminder mother's rooms are in room 17 and 18.
Those are continuing to open today.
You can find instructions for access at the front of that door.
Quiet room is room 24 if you need to get away.
A reminder that the expo hall has been completely reconfigured into the posters and job fair.
That's going to begin immediately after this session and run until 1 p.m.
Lunch will also be served in there around lunchtime.
I don't remember exactly when.
Talks.
Talks continue today.
There are three talk sessions this afternoon after the poster and job fair.
The open spaces are still open until 11 p.m. tonight.
You can still go to PyCon.us to find out what's on the board right now and head over to the
board to add if there's any slots that remain.
The final plenary session, which will have the PSF community update and awards, final
keynote and closing remarks will be at...
I don't have my speaker notes.
Anybody know what time the final thing starts?
3 10.
And that will be in this room.
Sprints.
Oh.
Whoa.
It's all working.
So sprints continue after today, Monday, Tuesday, and Wednesday.
If you're interested in sprinting and you'll be in town, make sure to allocate some time
to stick around after the closing session.
So that will be around 4.30 on.
The little sprint rows will occur.
This is when everyone who's...
What's that?
Oh.
I was like, Kushal, am I lying?
So Kushal will be leading sprint rows, which is where if you are planning to sprint on
a project, you can come on up here and announce to everyone who's interested what you're working
on and how to get in contact.
There we go.
So a quick reminder, the PSF is running a fundraiser concurrently with PyCon.
You can find more information on that fundraiser and how to contribute at PyCon.us.
Speaking of the...
Here we go.
So right now I'm really excited to welcome to the stage the inaugural Python steering
council.
So this is the group that is responsible for governance of the Python language and C Python
interpreter.
The panel is going to be moderated by Eva, the executive director of the PSF, and we're
going to do introductions of the panel members shortly.
So go ahead and welcome them to the stage.
Good morning, PyCon.
Thanks so much for joining us.
So welcome to our panel with Python steering council.
My name is Eva.
I'm the executive director of the Python Software Foundation, which is the nonprofit behind
Python.
I'll be the moderator for this session.
Python's governance recently shifted from the BDFL model to a steering council.
If you're interested in reading about this change and how it was achieved, you can check
out these links above.
We are here to learn more about the steering council members, what the steering council
does, and learn about their mandates.
At the end of the panel, we'll open the floor to audience questions, so please start thinking
about what you'd like to ask now.
So on stage with me, we have the five steering council members.
We have Barry Warsaw, Brett Cannon, Carol Willing, Guido Van Rossum, and Nick Coughlin.
Before we get into what the steering council does, let's get to know you all a bit.
You can tell us things like why you became a core developer, or in Guido's case, why
you even created Python, what types of Python development interests you, projects you've
used Python for, and so on.
Barry, let's start with you.
Okay.
Well, thanks.
So I work at LinkedIn, and I'm on the Python Foundation team.
Many of my teammates are here, which is awesome.
We do a lot of Python.
We basically support Python at LinkedIn.
You know, I think I've told my story many times.
This is Guido Van Rossum's Python World Tour.
It happened in 1994 in Gaithersburg, Maryland, and that's when I met Guido, fell in love
with Python and Guido, of course.
And I think, you know, just like not going away is part of the trick, right, sticking
around long enough.
There were 20 people at the first Python workshop, which is pretty amazing to look out at this
crowd.
I think all of us knew Python was really special when we first were introduced to it, and we
certainly knew Guido was very special.
But to see where both the language and the community has gone in 25 years, none of us
could have expected it, and I think it's kind of miraculous, actually, because it's not
only changed the tech landscape, but it's changed all of our lives.
I know certainly for myself, I wouldn't have the life I have without Python, so I'm amazingly
grateful for that.
That's a great story.
Many of us are in the same boat.
Yeah.
Brett, how about you?
Yeah, so I'm a dev manager for the Python extension for VS Code at Microsoft, where
I get to do that most of the time, but any spare time I get, work lets me actually just
spend on Python itself.
In terms of how I got started, it's a slightly long story, but the gist of it is I got the
recipe in the Python cookbook.
It was not perfect.
It drove me nuts for about a year.
I figured out how to make it perfect.
At least in my mind.
And then Alex Martelli, the editor, I asked how do I get this into Python because I think
other people might find it useful.
I said, oh, email this mailing list called Python dev.
So I did in June of 2002, I believe it was Skip Monero, actually, who responded and told
me how to do it and go through the workflow.
I did it.
It got accepted.
I was doing a gap year between my undergrad and my graduate program start, so I figured,
oh, this is fun.
I'll keep doing this.
And lo and behold, I kept doing it enough that eventually I asked I'd do a PR for something
and then I just said I need someone to merge it and Guido said, well, we'll get someone
to give you a commit where you merge it yourself.
I think I was just bothering everyone a little too much.
And just been involved ever since.
Basically I'm somewhat known for a phrase where I said it came from the language but
I said it for the community and part of that is the people up on this stage and the people
I've gotten to work with and know over the years from the dev team.
I basically learned how to program, honestly, from these people and have just become great
friends and that's why I keep coming back year after year.
Yeah, the community is a great aspect.
Carol, how about you?
I'm Carol Willing.
Thank you all for being here.
Back in 2016 I did a keynote in the Philippines and I talked about how Python was the people's
programming language and when I started back in 2012 using Python, as a person, I thought
this is really fun to program in.
And then I also got involved with Jupyter Notebooks and thought this is great stuff.
We can spread learning about Python, learning about different disciplines, whether it's
science, data science, embedded computing, web stuff, and I saw the power of it then.
And I wanted to be a part of it and so I started more on the community side with the Python
Software Foundation and working with Open Hatch, which was a non-profit that helped
people make their first contribution to open source and through that I started learning
the core Python workflow and what I really wanted was to, from a technical standpoint,
learn how to be a core developer but even more so to develop processes and an environment
where the core team reflects how we use Python in the real world and who we serve because
I think Python is used to really touch so many people's lives and it will be for the
next 20 or so years.
So it's up to all of us to make it better year by year.
Absolutely.
So thank you.
Guido?
Oh, that was so wonderful to hear.
I don't even know what the question is because the sound here is terrible on stage.
Tell us something fun about yourself.
About myself, well, I was a programmer.
I was on an environment where there wasn't a language that I liked so I made one out
of pieces that I had learned previously.
And because I can't write code and not have other people use it, I made it open source
and the rest was really the community.
APPLAUSE
So fast forward to last year when I was at the top of responsibilities, controversial
pups left and right, and I had a case of burnout where I thought I've done this almost 30 years
being the BDFL of this language, it's time for someone else or some other structure.
And so I announced that one day.
Literally the night before I had approved a very controversial PEP.
You may be familiar with the Walrus operator.
The next morning I woke up and I thought I don't want to be BDFL any more.
I spent 20 minutes drafting a nice email to the core developers asking them to go take
care of themselves.
It was really like what are you going to do?
Set up some government.
Do it however you think is the right way to do.
And it was such a relief.
But I don't know.
You know how this goes.
When your kid goes off to college, some of you may have experience with that.
I will soon have that experience.
You're no longer directly involved in their lives, maybe, but you never stop worrying.
And that's how I feel about Python at the moment.
And that's why I...
APPLAUSE
Why I nominated myself for the steering committee and here I am.
LAUGHTER
Nick, tell us something about yourself.
So for me, I actually came to Python as a hardware and CC++ guy because I needed to
test some signal processing code.
And Python had the unit test module.
It had the wave module and it had this thing called Swig to let me wrap our C++ drivers.
And so I did that for hardware control for comm systems.
And now I do it for electric vehicle fast charges with Tritium.
And it's just this language that lets me reach out and touch the real world without having
to worry about all the messy details.
And then I got involved in Core Dev.
This was this community of people on the internet that talked about this language and how we
make computers, how we bridge from that to the way people actually think and just make
that more accessible and make it, yeah, talk to the computer the way you think and have
it do what you meant is kind of amazing and a lot of fun.
We're all very grateful to have your experiences and backgrounds part of our community.
Guido, now that you've experienced being both BDFL of Python as well as the Steering Council
member, tell us how do you think governance has changed and will continue to change?
I'm sorry.
I did not hear the full question.
Now that you've experienced being BDFL and also part of the Steering Council committee,
how do you think that the governance has changed and will continue to change of Python?
Okay, yeah.
So while I was BDFL, sort of the way it felt to me and I think the way it felt to most
other people as well was whenever there was some controversial decision, it would eventually
bubble up to me, which meant that I was always scanning Python dev and Python ideas for things
that might become controversial and trying to nip it in the bud if I could and every
PEP basically eventually became my responsibility after the people with the greater domain knowledge
and expertise had sorted it out to the point where they had a yes, no question or an A,
B choice.
And that's pretty stressful.
And so I'm very glad that sort of that responsibility is now divided, distributed over five experts
who have more of the trust of the community because they've actually been voted in rather
than just become the leader or leaders by happenstance.
So the voting has sort of voting for the Steering Council, I think, creates a real different
relationship between the Steering Council and the core dev community than whatever existed
between the core devs and myself as BDFL.
Going forward, I think that we're also structuring the decision-making process somewhat differently.
The Steering Council is not actually the group of people who decide about most PEPs anymore.
What's written in our constitution, PEP 13, and what we sort of use as guidelines is that
for most decisions we actually pick an expert from among the core devs and sometimes external
contributors that we know well, and we settle them with the question and the decision.
And so far, we've only got a few months' experience with that process.
So far, I think that is going great.
And so going forward, the Steering Council is going to delegate whatever it can with
the understanding that the delegate who decides eventually gets to report to the Steering
Council.
If a delegate suddenly turns around 180 degrees and does wild things that the Steering Council
think that's too much or maybe that's too little, we can recall them, but I expect that
to be a very rare occurrence because we pick our people based on many years of experience
with their behavior and their expertise and so a real connection and trust.
I think that's what I have to say about the governance.
Yeah, maybe in three years we'll get on stage again and do this over, see how it's changed
since now.
Python and data science continues to grow in popularity.
Carol, you're also a Project Jupiter Steering Council member.
As the one with the strongest tie to scientific Python community, can you tell us why it's
important for the scientific community to have representation on the Steering Council?
Sure.
I think it's important in general for the Steering Council to be willing to listen to
new ideas from all areas of the community.
The needs that we have in web and embedded education, science, data science, are going
to be slightly different depending on certain things.
These things will be very similar, but there will be specifics that impact maybe the science
world or the education world more than others.
I think by having a variety of experiences and backgrounds on the Steering Council, whether
it's specifically science or just what you've done technically, is important because I think
the diversity is what gives us better decisions, better understanding of what's happening out
in the community and really trying to address where we need to make improvements and where
we want to go forward and actually blaze new trails.
I think the science community and the data science community brings us a lot of technical
expertise and in many cases also research opportunities as well, so maybe potentially
some funding down the road.
So I think it's a good thing.
Absolutely.
Brett, you've managed a lot of core Dev infrastructure work, so I'll ask you about PEP 581.
PEP 581 authored by Marietta, outlines the steps needed to migrate Python's issue tracker
from Roundup to GitHub.
Looking at the schedule, even PEP 581 was discussed at the language summit on Thursday.
Can you tell us all a little bit about what was discussed and what the next steps are?
Sure.
So PEP 581, as before, what, a week ago, two weeks ago, outlined the rationale of the idea
of moving our issue tracker from bugstoppython.org over to GitHub under our repo there.
As of a week ago, I believe Barry took an initial stab at splitting up between keeping
581 as the rationale and PEP 588 as the actual steps that would be taken to actually do the
migration.
Basically, the status of all that is when we first formed the council, we went through
all the open PEPs, PEP 581 by Marietta in the front row was there, so we discussed it.
We all agreed that we are amenable to it.
No official decision has been made, though, and we realized that PEP needed to be split
up.
At the language summit, Marietta presented on it.
We took some feedback from the room about what people thought and such, what we thought
might need to happen.
We started to have initial discussions with Eva on the PSF about potentially trying to
have a PM sort of role to help handle the migration because we realized that if we go
forward with this, the migration of those issues is going to be critical and we don't
want any problems because Lord knows I've had my own handful of those over the years
moving our infrastructure around.
So basically at this point, it sits at we all think it's a good idea, no official decision
has been made, and we are talking to you about how to make sure we can get that staffed and
handled appropriately if and when we decide to go forward with it.
Absolutely.
We'll keep that process going.
Nick, you're also a member of the PSF's grants work group.
I'm sorry, packaging work group.
Last year the work group rolled out the warehouse code base thanks to the Mozilla grant that
the PSF received which made several improvements.
In March of this year, the work group launched work for the next set of improvements which
will be around security and accessibility.
What do you now as a steering council member think should be the next steps or features
or improvements that the packaging work group should take?
One of the points I would like to make is the two roles I suspect are surprisingly separate
for a lot of people.
There's the Python packaging authority which uses the packaging working group to essentially
coordinate with the PSF and then Python core development and the steering council in a
similar role again working with the PSF around resource management and that kind of thing.
So I think on the steering council side we have some work to do clarifying those relationships
and making them clear to the wider community, not just the folks involved.
But on the actual Python packaging index side, the authentication stuff that's currently
in progress with the open tech fund, after that there's a lot that could be done around
improving the publisher experience.
We've put a lot in recent years in terms of improving the consumer experience.
But on the publisher side, releases are getting a lot more complicated.
So people are wanting to upload source distributions plus multiple wheels for different platforms
and different Python versions.
And at the moment, the packaging index is kind of this instant published thing.
Like you push it up, it's done.
It's like you committed, that's it.
No changes.
It's out there.
And we'd really like to be able to offer a staging area where people can put up all the
artifacts for release, make sure everything's in order, make sure everything's there.
And then once they're happy with the release, push a button and have it go publish.
So yeah, so there's some ideas around how to do that.
But yeah, I think that's one of the next big areas of improvement coming down the pipeline.
Yeah, continuing improvements is going to be something we need to concentrate on.
And I know that the packaging summit is happening the first day of sprints as well, so I'm sure
other ideas will come out of that.
Barry, as one of the authors of PEP 1 and the entire PEP process as it is, can you tell
us a bit how the PEP process has changed with the new governance model?
Sure.
So you know, PEPs, the idea of PEPs kind of came out of Guido and my time at CNRI because
CNRI ran the IETF, so we were sort of familiar with RFCs and Internet standards.
I thought that would be a good format, although I wanted something much more lightweight that
would just be enough process for us to get our work done without being too much process.
I don't know how successful that has been.
And the purpose of the PEP was so that Guido didn't have to go through thousands of emails
and try to figure out what the actual proposal was so that he could just read one document
and get an idea of both the pros and the cons for a particular proposal and then make a
decision and then we would record that entire process, the decision-making process within
the PEPs.
You know, as Guido alluded to, all those decisions kind of funneled through him and I think that
that became untenable for many reasons, partly I think because there's aspects of this amazing
ecosystem that other people are maybe better equipped to decide or Guido just isn't really
involved in that.
So then we came up with the idea of the delegates, the BDFL delegates, who Guido could say that's
an expert, we're going to let that person make the decision on this particular feature.
We talked about this a little bit earlier in the steering council.
BDFL delegate was sort of a last resort.
It was for the things that Guido wanted not to be involved in and I think with the new
governance model, it's really sort of the first resort.
We don't want to make those decisions.
If there are people in the community who are better equipped to do that, that's what we
want to do.
We want to allow other people to become engaged with shaping where Python is going to go in
the next 25 years.
I think that's really important because none of us are getting younger, certainly.
I'll speak for myself.
The Python community is so much bigger now, right?
So this gives the next generation of Python leaders an opportunity to step up, become
involved, make important decisions that will shape the language and eventually move into
those leadership roles.
I think that's the way we keep the community healthy and keep the language healthy and
vibrant for the next 25 years.
I'm really excited about it.
I'm really glad that we've sort of moved to much more delegation.
There are a few PEPs where we're kind of keeping for ourselves because we might think that
they're sort of more appropriate for the elected steering council to decide, but we work with
the delegates and we work with the PEP authors to come up with the right solution there.
Sounds like a great change.
So now asking the entire group, do you all consider implementations of Python part of
the scope of the steering council preview or do you just focus on the language itself?
I'll take that one.
We totally see implementations of Python as something that we care about and that we should
care about and where we are discussing our thoughts about how should we move the language
and the implementation or implementations forward.
Just to ask the audience, how many people still use Python 2 in the room?
Whoa.
Not as many hands as I thought.
I know.
That's actually the nice one.
So Python 2 will not be maintained past 2019.
The sunset is around the corner, only about eight months away.
So what's the game plan for Python 2's retirement?
A party.
Yeah.
I know that we spoke about the possibility of hiring a PM and that person is going to
probably be tasked with communication and directing people to the right place, but can
you give us a little bit more information on things like that?
Yeah.
I mean, obviously the plans are moving forward.
They're not going to change.
Thank goodness.
And as you've alluded to, we are starting to talk about potentially having a PM come
forward to help us sunset and just figure out all the little minute details because
obviously, for instance, search for something in the standard library.
Right now search engines often go to docs.python.org slash 2, which is not the version you're all
going to care about starting in 2020.
There's other things on the website in the documentation where it says 2 and 3 because
starting in 2020, there's just Python because we won't really have to care about the major
number as much anymore.
So just little details like that I think still need to get worked out, but otherwise this
trend is very much moving forward and it's going to hit that date whether basically period.
One resource I'd point people towards is a talk Chris Neugebauer gave at PyCon Australia
a couple of years ago called Python 3 for people who haven't been paying attention.
And it's just really good talk going through some of the options.
We do expect there will be commercial vendors offering support beyond 2020 for the people
who have business critical systems that haven't been migrated yet and they're just going,
look, we just really, really need a bit more time.
There will be options there.
But yeah, the 2020 deadline is we're not doing this for free anymore.
So I got a couple comments.
I tend to be the pragmatist and if I look back two to three years, we were in a very
different space regarding Python 2 and Python 3 support.
We've come a long way in terms of the major packages that support Python 3.
Brett had a wonderful graphic ticker and I think we've got all the top, what was it,
300 and something.
I think from the science standpoint, we've been using 3 for a long time.
And I recognise that there's a lot of legacy code out there that's using Python 2.
And if I look back a couple years, like Instagram did a great keynote about how they were moving
things from 2 to 3.
I think one of the things that we want like a PM to help us in this transition is to really
take those best practices that we're learning from large companies who have found the business
case to transition to make it easier.
And we recognise there's going to be bumps along the way.
But I think as a community and over time, we'll get there.
And I think we'll get there more by pulling together than to try and polarise apart.
Finding the bright spots in a situation like this are always a good example to go by.
So we're kind of running out of time.
So I'm going to pick one more question for the group and then after that we're going
to start taking questions from the audience.
What does the steering council have planned for growing and sustaining diversity within
core development?
I'm sorry, I didn't hear the...
Growing diversity.
Well, I think we just need to first celebrate the progress that we have made.
2017, it wasn't that long ago.
Marietta was the first core dev as a woman.
And we have a long way to go still with diversity.
But I think what we're trying to focus in on is leveraging the interests that people
have to be inclusive, to create processes and tooling that allows more people to be
able to contribute and to have the learning curve towards contribution to become less.
And also to really strengthen the third party library ecosystem as well.
Because a lot of folks get their start in third party packages, which is fantastic.
For those of you who are at the sprints, I hope you have a great time.
If you've never been to a sprint, you're a little tentative, please come.
And thank you to the folks that attended and organized the mentored sprints yesterday.
That's an excellent step in the right direction.
Yeah, absolutely.
So...
So I mentioned this when Paul Everett and I had our little interview.
I look out here and I see this crowd.
Every one of you can become a core dev.
Every single person.
You don't have to be a C programmer.
All you have to do is care about Python and want to learn how to become a core dev.
And I know many of us on stage and there are many people in the community who are mentoring
people.
And so think about diversity in all the axes of diversity.
Like what your experience is.
You don't have to be a professional programmer, right?
You can be young, old, doesn't matter.
So widen your horizons.
Think about yourself as a core dev.
And then if that's something that you really want to aspire to, engage with mentors and
learn the process of contributing to Python.
Because we need everybody.
There's so much work to do and so many interesting things to do that I think everybody can really
contribute to Python.
There's no reason why you can't.
That's such great advice.
Thanks for adding that, Barry.
So next up I'm going to post this link where everyone can go and add their questions for
the steering council.
So it's PyCon.us slash panel.
And Ernest, somewhere in the back, is going to pop some questions up as soon as they come
in.
It's like I need the Jeopardy music playing right now.
Do do do do do do do.
Mine did Ian Pickens live.
Kudos to the AV folks.
We're done here.
All right, Anonymous.
What is your favorite PEP?
That's easy.
PEP 401.
3100.
Carol.
Probably 581.
All right.
Guido.
484.
384.
343.
All right.
The next question is, what are the first steps to take to become a core dev with Python?
Look at the dev guide.
Yeah.
Devguide.python.org is a good place to start to get an idea of our process, how things
work.
Just kind of see the lay of the land and just see if it's something that interests you.
Yeah.
Can you give us that URL again?
Devguide.python.org.
Thanks.
The next one is, what do you see as the biggest gap in the language right now?
I actually don't know that there are big gaps in the language, but I think that the CPython
interpreter needs...
I guess the way I sort of talk about it with people is that the language is pretty awesome,
right?
That's what we love about it.
And Python is kind of unique in the sense that it's great for one-off scripts, and it
grows as you start to get more ambitious and as your team grows, and then you can run Instagram
on Python, right?
Like, that's a big code base.
And Python, and especially with the typing, type annotations, it can grow to large teams,
small teams, and so on.
You know, the interpreter, in a sense, is 28 years old.
And, you know, the state of the art of virtual machines has come a long way in that time.
And I think that what I'm particularly interested in is how can we make Python faster?
You know, how can we take it into more environments where it's not in right now?
Those are the things that I think we need to spend some focus on.
The language is pretty good.
There's not a lot missing that I, you know, not a lot of things that I'm missing from
it.
So that's my take.
I'm similar to Barry.
The language itself, I don't think it's missing a lot.
The thing I'm most jealous of from another ecosystem is JavaScript source maps.
Because the way our trace specs currently work, there's a vast difference between what
you get with a pure Python module versus as soon as you do any kind of transformational
compilation on that module, you basically break your own trace backs.
And there's a lot of stuff around source maps in the JavaScript world where they can do
lots of transformations in their pipelines, but their debuggers and their trace back generators
can still figure out what was that originally before it got transformed and tell you, like,
in the original source code where you need to go look to find the source of a fault.
And in theory, we could adapt that to Python.
There's nothing intrinsically JavaScript specific about it.
But yeah, it just requires folks to sit down and do the design work.
All right.
I think we have time for one more question before we wrap this up.
Anonymous posted, we hear a lot about burnout of core developers.
What does the council have, does the council have any plans to improve this?
Is there anything that the community can do also?
I think you're going to start hitting me.
So yeah, so in terms of specific plans, I think in general, it's to just make being
a core dev easier in terms of time and effort required.
Hence some excitement up here, obviously, for pet 581 and such, and just various ways
we can just make it easier for core devs to get their work done.
In terms of what the community can do, honestly, just be nice to core devs.
We are on social media.
You can watch my keynote from last year about this.
But basically, we are all on social media.
So when people go online and start griping about a decision we made, we do see that.
We do read it.
We do feel it because we do care a lot.
And so constructive feedback is always welcome.
But just flat out negative feedback really doesn't help anyone.
And it just adds to the negativity and just the burnout rate.
So honestly, just be nice online.
And that would help immensely.
And Carol, you have something to add.
Yeah, I had a few more things.
Going back to where I said Python's the people's programming language, we are all people.
We have feelings.
We make mistakes.
We do good things.
We try and celebrate people's efforts.
Sometimes we get it wrong.
Tell us kindly.
And I think one of the things that really pleasantly surprised me and I'm very proud
of is from Guido stepping down as BDFL to where we are now with the steering council,
The core team and the greater community did a fantastic job of pulling together, working
to the common goal of we value the language.
We want it to persist.
So we're going to be decent through this process of trying to come up with different options
for the language to ultimately selecting a steering council.
And I think a lot of what Brett says is what you write, remember, there's a person on the
other side.
What you say, there's a person on the other side.
If you get it wrong, apologize.
I'm sorry goes a long way in at least making environments kinder, safer to work in, and
ultimately a lot more fun and productive.
So thank you to the core team.
Thank you to everybody that contributes to Python and uses Python.
And thank you all.
Yeah.
Nick, you want to add something?
And I'll just add one last one for this one, which is we are actively working with the
Python software foundation to look for ways the foundation can better support.
So one concrete way to help is a better resource to Python software foundation can do more
things to help core development.
So the PSF fundraiser is currently running and that is a concrete way to help as well.
Pycon.us slash PSF.
That's where you can find that fundraiser.
That's a great note to end this on.
Thank you all so much for joining us this morning.
Enjoy the rest of Pycon.
Thanks, Eva.
All right.
Why don't you stand up?
Another round of applause for Eva and the steering council.
All right.
So last reminders.
Job fair and poster session will go until 1 p.m.
We'll have another three sessions of talks and then come on back here at 3 10 p.m. for
our closing plenary.
Thanks.
Have a wonderful day.