Good morning, everyone. I'm going to start off with two questions. Please raise your
hand if you are in K-12 education. Good. Excellent. Excellent. Raise your hand if you consider
yourself to be an activist in the Python community. Okay. Perfect. So what I'm going to talk about,
I would argue, is of interest to both those communities and why they need to work together,
which is Python certification. I'm going to give you a specifically K-12 slant on that,
and Chomar will be following up with a broader look at certification. So real quickly, and
I'm going to, Elizabeth has given, I mean, I've permission to fail, so I'm going to deviate
a little bit from my slides, especially since I've been so inspired by the talks this morning,
and I think we need to have a conversation about that. So I've been a high school teacher
since 1991. I started teaching computer science in 1993. I've been active in the free software
movement and in the open educational resource movement for a long time, and I've loved it.
I'm a bit of a rebel, and I work for Arlington Public Schools, and they've kind of let me
do that, and so it's been fun to teach for all these years. I still love teaching. I
have 16 students here, and I've told them to mix it up, so please say hi to them, talk
to them. They're a little bit shy. They're kind of grouping together. I told them they've
got to get out and mix it up with you all, so please do that, and thank you for that.
So why do I care about Python certification? Well, I am a CTE teacher, Career and Technical
Education, that's what they call me, and beginning, I'm going to read this, beginning with first-time
ninth graders in 2013-2014 school year, requirements for the standard diploma shall include a requirement
to earn a career and technical education credential that has been approved by the
board. So it is now mandated for Virginia teachers, CTE teachers, to give certifications.
I have resisted this for years. I just tried not to do it because these things can be pretty
awful, and I'm kind of, now there are two Python certifications, and so I'm going to
talk about those. So there are some benefits I've seen to the certifications. They provide
a common measurable, I guess, measurement of skill, and they provide a common reference
point for curriculum development. So those are two potential positives. The cons, which
I personally felt for the longest time way outweigh the pros, are that they limit creativity
because they enforce standardization and mediocrity. I mean, seriously, you have a state mandate
and you've got to pass this test, and let me tell you, I heard so many innovative things
this morning about raspberry pies and interesting curriculum. It is dead in the water if teachers
are being told that what they have to do is get their kids to pass this Microsoft MTA
98-381 certification because their job depends on that, and as long as their job depends
on that, they're going to have to do that, and they're not going to hear all these other
cool things that they might be able to do. And also, the certifications have a real strong
kind of corporate bias, and for me, that's not the kind of thing I want to be communicating.
So within the Virginia Department of Education presently, there are only two Python certifications.
The first one has been around for a while. It's the one I mentioned. It's part of the
Microsoft Technology Associate Exam, and it's called Introduction to Programming with Python.
The other ones have just emerged on the screen, I mean, on the scene this year. I actually
have now taken both of these two certifications, so I can tell you a little bit about them
if you're a K-12 teacher interested in my thoughts on it. It seems to be that Pearson
is developing a whole stack of Python certifications, and Cisco has been partnering with them, so
the Virginia DOE approves Cisco's test and Microsoft's test.
So I went looking on the web before I gave this talk and said, well, what is best out
there if you were going to do certifications? Not surprisingly, Dr. Chuck shows up on the
top, right? But none of these are the certifications. Well, there is this Introduction to Python
Absolute Beginner by Microsoft, and on edX I haven't seen that. I don't know if that
relates to their certification exam. My hunch is it doesn't, but I'll have to check that
out further.
So I'm going to go a little bit quickly through these slides to talk about what we might want
to do next, because I've only got a couple of minutes. So I did some research, because
this is all new. So now you have this thing called the Open Education, OpenEdge Python
Institute. They're developing this exam, and then Cisco is using it. These are the three
certifications that they're going to be offering now. The PCAP was the first. I took the PCAP
back in October, and the others didn't exist when I was preparing the slides for this.
Oh, there's two more now. So I'm going to reflect on those. So the PCAP is fairly expensive.
So in fact, it's so expensive, our school system's not going to offer it, because we
have some deal with Microsoft where we can offer the other one, because we've already
paid for some package, and that's the one my students are going to have to take.
It does align fairly well with the solo learn course. I found this to be the least offensive
of the two exams. They're more like AP puzzle type tests. They're short. They're testing
the syntax of the Python programming language. I found it to be fairly challenging. I've
been a high school teacher for many, many years, but I learned some Python tricks in
preparing for it. So it was of the two the least offensive. This is not the one I'm going
to be giving. I have to give the MTA 98-381, because we can offer that unlimited times
for free already. That exam was horrible. I can't tell you enough about how it is a
lot of reading. It's not at all ELL friendly. I mean, I had students who should have known
Python fail that test, because you're driven through this time thing where you have to
answer a bunch of questions after reading droll text. And in fact, I describe it as
having an unintentional corporate drone bias in the theme of the thing. You know, you read
this, oh, you're the manager of such and such region, and you've got to, you know,
what high school kid's going to care about that? And then you answer some little question
about that. So that's really pretty awful. And that's what we're giving right now. So
in the interest of hacking that situation, because I went looking for, oops, let me back
up. So in the interest of looking for resources to help students prepare, there's tons of
them, but you have to pay for most of them. Everybody's commodifying their prep for this,
you know, exam that's required. And I've got a group of students who will be pitching
a mini sprint this afternoon. We've started to create our own power through Python certification.
So at least we can, yeah, we can make a problem out of together solving this thing that we
all have to do. It's not, my students are actually in a dual enrolled program that is
going to give them an associate degree in computer science when they finish school.
And now actually what I'm interested in after hearing Dr. Chuck is teaching his program,
right? I mean, what you laid out is pretty much what I'm already working on and a series
of courses all open source, we need a certification. So we need to find a way as the Python community
to have a certification that we have some input into, because we don't have any input
into this. And if we ignore this problem, and we have for a long time, we didn't want
anything to do with it, that was fine. But for me, I can't avoid it. I'm a public school
teacher, Virginia has mandatory K-12 computer science standards now. We have to teach computer
science all across the state from all across the grades, and this certification is part
of that. So having an approved certification that the Python community had some input into
would be such a wonderful thing, I think, for our community. And thank you very much.
I appreciated Jeff's comments. I'm going to elaborate on those a little bit, especially
toward the end. My name is Chalmer. I'll tell you a little bit about who I am and kind of
the role that I have in terms of certs and the types of certs that I've pursued, and
the things that I've seen in acquiring and looking at some of those certifications. I
work for a company called Booz Allen Hamilton. I do cyber security related things. I also
do a lot of data analysis and data science types of things. I do a lot of teaching. I've
taught in the collegiate field and in the commercial field. I teach in my client space.
I teach to people at Booz Allen Hamilton. I teach at meetups, et cetera, et cetera.
And I help run the education summit every year. I think this is my fifth year helping
to facilitate the education summit. I am a certification holder. I don't necessarily
say that proudly. I do have some. I am an exam author for certification exams. These
are some of the certs that I have. Again, none of these are particularly things that
I necessarily hold up proudly, et cetera. They're just there. Many of them I acquired
because either I got a chance to take it, my employer might have paid for it, or because
I felt like it might be a way to influence my resume. So the decisions might sway my
direction when I wanted to get a new job or take on a new opportunity.
Jeff mentioned a couple of certs that are out there. There is another cert out there
that is related to Python. It's the GPYC. The GPYC is a cert that is a certification
that is associated with GIAC, the Global Information Assurance Certification. They're
an organization that is focused on information assurance or cybersecurity. GIAC has a wide
variety of certifications that they offer. This one is the only one they have that's
related to Python. GIAC's sister organization, SANs, which stands for SysAdmin Audit Network
and Security, those folks offer a class that helps you prepare and get ready to be able
to pass the GPYC certification. Later on you'll be able to get the slides and the
URLs to get to some more details about these at the bottom of this slide in the small font.
The skills that are covered in the GPYC are a lot of the typical types of things that
you might see in any sort of Python class. How do you make executables? What are data
structures? All those kind of things. There is a focus or a nuance though to this class.
This class was intended for penetration testers, people who are doing vulnerability assessments,
people who have an interest in cybersecurity and information assurance. There is a bit
of a leaning toward that. Nonetheless, while learning those really cool cybersecurity skills,
getting your hacker on, if you will, you're also learning a lot of cool Python.
In terms of some of the details for this particular cert, the exam is proctored by Pearson VUE.
It is 75 questions, about a two hour exam. The cost of the test is close to $800. If
you wanted to take the SANS class, it's $6600 to take a six day class. A little bit of confession
time here. We're all amongst friends, so I'll tell you the truth. I worked for SANS. I worked
for JIAAC back in around 2010. I reviewed course content that was delivered in some
of the SANS classes. There were several of them. I authored exam questions. Back in 2010,
I had a very good view into how JIAAC went about creating questions that they used to
kind of assess people's skills. I do not currently work for them. I've not worked for them for
about eight years. I just want to get that out there and let you know that the next few
slides, these are my opinions. These are all buyer beware. I'll talk a little bit about
the pros of kind of the JIAAC certifications, et cetera. We'll talk a little bit about the
cons. Then we'll close off with, much like Jeff was talking about, how does the Python
community create a certification for the Python community that meets the needs that we have?
In terms of some of the pros for the JIAAC certification, they generally have a fairly
strong reputation. When I speak to people who are looking, say, to hire folks in the
cybersecurity field and they see a certification from JIAAC that tends to lend a certain amount
of weight, I don't want to characterize how much, but a certain amount, so that registers
on a resume to a hiring manager, those kind of things. The weight that they carry is often
a little higher than some of the certifications you might see from other organizations, so
they have a strong reputation in the community. Based on my experiences both in reviewing
the author content and in writing exam questions, I feel like they had a very high level of
quality in those exams. They put a lot of professional effort into the things like regular
and consistent review processes, multiple levels of review. I got many of my questions
kicked back like, hey, can we clean these things up in various ways? They use a lot
of psychometric types of evaluations to get a quantitative answer. Does this question
essentially address the types of things that you want to have addressed? They run them
through a whole series of test exams so that people who've already passed the certifications,
they'll take these new questions and make sure that those questions are answerable by
people who have the skills that we've already claimed that they had. The training content
is generally fairly spot on. In terms of the focus for this particular cert, because there's
that cyber security focus, that helps to bring somebody's resume a little closer to two different
skill sets, both of which are in high demand, the ability to automate and program, as well
as the ability to address things from a cyber security perspective. That extra focus on
cyber security could be a pro. It could be neutral. In terms of cons, the biggest con,
probably the cost. Jeff was mentioning some of the costs of the certs he talked about,
and there's a significant difference just for the cert, much less for the classes. I
have no recommendation here about, gee, you or your students should go out and get this
particular cert. I'm not going to say that it is a worthwhile thing. That's a decision
I'll let other people make. What I am interested in, and what we'll talk about here for the
last couple of minutes is, what makes a cert worthwhile, and if the open source community
pursues trying to build a cert that we want to stand behind, what should be included in
that? Certainly the class qualities that will help people prepare for a cert. I mean,
that's fundamental, and I think that's something that we can all get behind. Classes need to
be well designed. The learning experience should be high quality as well. The exams
themselves, if you are looking to create a certification exam, the exam must be relevant,
and it must have the backing of things like psychometrics. Can we check to see if the
question is a valid question, is it a reasonable question? Is it simply rote memorization,
or is it application? Is it assessment? Those kinds of considerations. Does the cert have
perceived quality? Again, if I'm looking at a resume and I see a cert by organization
X, or I see a cert by organization Y, and I feel that organization Y has consistently
delivered staff to me who have skills that are represented by that cert on the resume,
so a cert we produce must have perceived quality, and people must be able to see that cert and
go, ah, yeah, I know what's behind that cert, and I know what to expect when I bring that
person onto my team. There has to be some level of perceived return on investment. A
lot of the SAN certifications, those are actually funded by companies. Large companies will
go out and they'll pay money to send their employees to get a SAN certification, so those
employees could then be offered up to clients, et cetera, like we have people with these
certs, those kind of things. So if a company is going to invest in getting a cert that
this open source community comes up with, they have to have a sense they're going to
get a return on their investment. An open source is often very low cost, right, so that's
probably an easy bar to make, but it's definitely something we need to consider. And that's
the end of Jeff and I's essentially kind of foray into this conversation. I hope that
over the next couple of hours when we get into sprints and stuff, if folks have thoughts
or ideas, I'm sure Jeff and I would both love to hear those things. We'd love for you to
share with us what you feel ought to be included in certs, and hopefully as we as a community
over the next six months, 12 months, years, we can start to look at what does a cert mean
and what should be an assert, and what can we do to ensure that certifications that are
useful and meaningful to us and to our students can promulgate. And with that, my time is
about up, so I'll be around afterwards for questions.