Hello, everyone. Hi. My name is Brent Clements. I'm with Capital One. I'm a developer over
there. And this is about my fourth year I've been here. I've seen a lot of new faces here
at PyCon. It only shows how great the community is, how much it has grown over the past couple
of years, and quite frankly how far the language has come. But me being from Capital One, you
may or may not understand why Capital One is, why we're a sponsor, why we're here. And
quite frankly, we love the language. It powers a lot of our innovation at Capital One in
our open source projects such as Cloud Custodian and our customer facing projects such as Eno.
We support the community and we want to see the advancement of the language go forward.
And quite frankly, these are a lot of the same reasons I came to Capital One, because
we really truly do love the community and want to support it and see it move forward.
We do appreciate the community helping us out in our own project and the ecosystem.
We're proud to be principal sponsors of the community, of PyCon, and look forward to seeing
you at future PyCons going forward. Do you want to welcome Eva, who's going to be giving
updates on the Python Software Foundation and presenting the Community Service Awards.
Thank you and have a great day.
Since I've been on stage already, I'll just do a quick intro. My name is Eva. I'm the
executive director of the Python Software Foundation. If you're interested in Python
community updates, please follow myself and the PSF Twitter. So let's talk about giving.
We gather at PyCon in similar events because of opportunities. These in-person events give
us opportunities to learn, network, collaborate, catch up with friends, make new friends, teach,
mentor, and so much more. Through these opportunities, we foster the growth of Python and make our
community stronger. Through these opportunities, in a way, we give back to Python. By registering
to attend, you're giving back to the community. Sponsoring the conference, instructing a tutorial,
presenting a keynote gives back to the community. All these forms of giving help our community
grow. The Python Software Foundation is the nonprofit behind Python and its community.
The PSF has grown into an organization that gives to its community through its programs.
This year, we published our first ever annual impact report. Here we see a snippet from the
report showing our program service expenses from 2018. Approximately 75% of our expenses
go towards putting on PyCon. Our next largest expenses are the funds that go to our grants
program, which totals 16%. As the PSF continues to grow, we also want our grants program to
grow. Our grant funds go towards events and supporting regional communities all around
the world. We want to continue supporting events and communities because they provide
those impactful opportunities that I spoke about earlier to folks not just here but everywhere.
In addition to providing our community that support, we want to increase the PSF's expense
budget for funding things like Python and education projects and dev sprints. We want
to have enough funds to help Python make it to the next level. Russell's keynote on Friday
really hit home for me because I felt like it addressed all the ways that the PSF can
support Python to keep it sustainable. At the PSF, we listen to what the community needs
and we want to deliver on so much of it. And of course, we can't deliver on everything,
and that's not the point here, but to even support core development, we need more funds
to be able to do that. Giving is what allows us to do that. A few days ago, the PSF launched
its first fundraiser of the year. Most people in this room have had their lives impacted
by Python one way or another. I'd like you all right now to think of those opportunities
the Python community has given you. With that in mind, I want you all to consider giving
back to Python so it can continue to positively impact the world. This year, we have two ways
to give to the PSF. One way is donating cash through the donate button on you can find
it through PyCon.us. The second is through a collaboration that we're lucky to have with
JetBrains. If you purchase a PyCharm license through this link that I put up, all proceeds
of those purchases will go to the PSF. Our fundraiser ends May 22nd. Please consider
giving. Part of the PSF's growth has included making decisions that strengthen our sustainability
so we can continue to support our community and our staff for years to come. We understand
the importance of diversifying our revenue streams so we're not solely dependent on
PyCon to sustain the PSF. Additionally, we decided that we need to have a financial reserve
for at least one and a half years of operating costs. In addition to financial responsibility,
we have addressed sustainability of our staff so we no longer have a bus factor of one.
We recently hired additional people to work on PyCon and our accounting team. When I started
back in 2011, it was just two of us. Now there are eight of us. I wanted to take this opportunity
to bring everyone on stage because everyone here should see the folks behind all the work
that the PSF does. Seeing names in emails and chats is nice, but putting faces to those
names is even better. PSF team, come on up.
Thank you.
So, this friendly face that you've been seeing, you know, years at this conference, especially
the last two years, has not only been the conference chair of PyCon for 2018 and 2019,
but Ernest is also the infrastructure director of the PSF. Ernest helps support our community
with infrastructure needs and problems. Additionally, Ernest manages all of the PSF-owned infrastructure
such as Python.org, helps maintain PyPI.org and us.pycon.org and many more.
Phyllis Dobbs joined us two years ago and is now leading our accounting team. Phyllis
is helping us ensure we have important policies and procedures in place as our nonprofit continues
to grow financially. Jackie Augustine joined us in September of last year and Jackie is
now the manager of PyCon and lead organizer. I am sure many of you have already interacted
with Jackie about registration and going forward you will see her involved in much more.
Betsy, Betsy Walaszewski has been with the PSF since 2015.
Betsy does an outstanding job providing sponsorship and fundraising support. Betsy did an incredible
job with PyCon sponsorship this year and she helped all of the sponsors that you all interacted
with in the expo hall with their logistics and needs.
Joe and Laura both joined us earlier this year. Joe, Laura, please step forward. Joe
and Laura both joined us to help with the accounting team. We are super grateful to
have their help with the financial aspects of PyCon and the PSF such as financial aid
and even at the PyLadies auction this year. Welcome to the team Joe and Laura. So, Kirby
Kaiser, please step forward. Now I am going to start crying. Kirby Kaiser has been with
PSF for 12 years.
Kurt is responsible for establishing the PSF's accounting system and helped pave the way
to where the PSF is today. Kurt is retiring this year and we all owe him a big thanks
for everything that he has done for the PSF over the years. Thank you Kurt.
Thank you all for joining me on stage. Thank you.
Now let us give some recognition to community members. Community service awards are given
out quarterly usually to two Python uses at a time. These awards are a way for the
PSF to offer recognition for tremendous time and effort contributed by those that help
strengthen and improve Python's ecosystem. Let us welcome Mario Corsero to the stage.
Mario was awarded a community service award in 2018 for his leadership and organization
of PyCon ES, PyLandinium and the PyCon Charlestrack here at PyCon. His work has been instrumental
in promoting the use of Python and fostering Python communities in Spain, Latin America
and the UK. Thank you Mario.
Next we have Chuck Woody Nookchukwu. Chuck's unfortunately could not make it to PyCon this
year but Chuck's received this community service award in 2019 for his contribution to spreading
the growth of Python to the Nigerian community and his dedication and research to the PSF
community. Next I would like to welcome Alex Gainer to the stage. Alex received his CSA
in 2018 for his contributions to the Python and Django communities and the Python Software
Foundation. Alex previously served as a PSF director in 2015 through 2016. He serves as
an infrastructure staff member and contributes to legacy PyPI and the next generation warehouse
and has helped legacy warehouse insecurity and cutting down bandwidth costs by compressing
404 images. Thank you Alex.
Now let's welcome Marietta Vigia to the stage. The 2018 third quarter award was given to
Marietta for her contributions to CPython, her efforts to improve the workflow of Python
Core team and her work in increasing diversity in our community. In addition to that her
work as co-chair of PyCascades and co-organizer of the mentor spritz here at PyCon helps spread
the growth and diversity of Python. Thank you Marietta.
Now let's welcome Mayella Sanchez-Miranda to the stage.
The 2018 fourth quarter award was given to Mayella for her work as the PyCon charlis 2019
chair and founding member of PyCon charlis as well as being the organizer of Python Day
Mexico and Django Girls Puebla. Thank you Mayella.
Up next we welcome John Roa. The second 2018 Q4 award went to John Roa for his work as
founder and conference chair of PyCon Columbia. Additionally John Roa has been instrumental
with Python Outreach in Columbia especially via Django Girls workshops. Thank you John.
The second 2018 Q4 award went to John Roa for his work as founder and conference chair of
PyCon Columbia. Thank you John.
The 2019 Q1 award went to Stefan Bechnell for his work as main developer and maintainer
of two important Python projects, Scython and LXML. Unfortunately Stefan could not join
us this year but let us give him a round of applause.
Now let us welcome Eric Ma to the stage.
The 2019 Q1 community service award was given to Eric because he has continually gone above
and beyond his responsibilities as PyCon's financial aid co-chair and chair this year.
Additionally Eric has been a dedicated PyCon program member for several years. For those
of you that receive speaker grants or financial aid be sure to thank Eric for his dedication
when you see him around. Thank you Eric.
That wraps up our awards this year. There are so many awesome contributors in our community
and this is a great way to recognize their work. If you would like to nominate someone
for a future community service award please send your nomination to us. It is PSF at Python.org.
Thank you everyone.
Thank you Eva and thanks to all of you for your work. Can we get one more round of applause
for the award winners? Thank you. Eva spoke a lot about the PSF staff but didn't say much
about herself. The dedication and work that Eva puts in consistently to make sure that
the Python Software Foundation and PyCon happen is immeasurable. If we get one round of applause
then Eva will be the first to say a few words. Thank you.
Applause just for Eva.