All right. This seems slightly silly now since he's been talking to you. But this is Steve
Dower from Microsoft to tell you that Python on Windows is okay, actually.
Thank you. I am really excited to finally get to give this talk at PyCon. I've given
it a couple of other times at some other conferences, and I'm actually using some data right at
the start that's based on PyCon. So it's great to finally be here and get to share it with
all of you who contributed to the first few graphs. Obviously, as we know, Python on Windows
is not that big a thing, right? We look around at the operating systems, the computers that
people at largely PyCon conferences in general use, and we see something like this. There's
a really, really big section of people with glowing fruit on their laptops. There's a
smaller group of people that didn't pay anything for their operating system at all, and then
there's the people like me who are running Windows. And when you get into the talks,
and if you look over and if you can see the laptops, then you see it's a little bit more
narrow at least for the area that I'm sitting in. And, you know, I'll do a quick scan around
this room now, and it kind of looks like this is where we're at. But is this reality? We
actually have sources of real data. Obviously, these are made up charts, right? So let's grab
some real data. PyPI has a way to access all of the data for who's downloading packages,
and it's filtered. Some of it's censored. You can't actually get specific information. But
looking across a handful of popular packages, the breakdown looks kind of like this. The majority
is for Linux, unsurprisingly. That's where most of our code ends up running. But then you see a
roughly even split between Windows and Mac OS, and depending on the package, it'll swing one way
or the other. But for the most part, Linux dominates. If you look at packages installed
using Conda, you start seeing a bigger chunk targeting Windows. Two years ago, there was a
survey for the PSF where the question was not asked what operating system you're using, but
apparently we decided afterwards that it would be great if we could figure that out. So we actually
went through and looked at the people who submitted answers to the survey to see which kind of operating
system they were submitting from, and this is roughly how it broke down. The big gap there,
we assume, is like mobile phones, but it's not relevant to right now. When the survey was run
last year, and you can look this data up, the question was asked. It was actually included,
what operating systems do you run Python on? But it was multiple choice. That doesn't make
a very good pie chart. But I can tell you what happened in that survey is the Windows and the
Mac OS levels stayed about the same, and Linux grew to 60%. So that's 60% overlapping. Essentially,
the ratios don't change, and the same percentage are using Windows, Mac OS, and there's a big
overlap with using Linux as well. That's my read into the data at least. It was not asked
specifically enough to make that assertion 100% solid, but that's certainly how it looks. The
50% of Python developers on Windows from that survey did not change. And if we go to Visual
Studio Code and look at some of the data, courtesy of Microsoft, we see that just over 50% of Visual
Studio Code users are running on Windows, despite the fact that it runs just fine on Mac and Linux.
And courtesy of JetBrains, if we look at pie chart usage data, we're up to about 70% actually
running pie chart on Windows. The percentages are getting smaller and smaller for the other
operating systems. Periodically, I am allowed access to the Python.org download stats. These
are not normally public, but I'll do some analysis, especially for this talk. And so in March 2019,
there were 29 million downloads of files from Python.org. The ratio is a little skewed. I'll
be honest. There's not many reasons to go to Python.org to get Python for Linux. You're better off
getting that from your distributor. Mac OS, similarly, homebrew is a far more common way that
people get Python for Mac OS. Windows is the primary place. Python.org is the main place you
would get it for Windows. So it's skewed that way. But I do just want to point out that this is 24
million downloads in one month. That's 200 million downloads a year, more than that. That's a huge
number. No matter what the breakdown is, there's a lot of people downloading and installing Python
on Windows. So what that gives us is a community that probably looks something like this.
But what we see around us is this part. When you go to a conference, this is the part that you get
to see. And there's a huge, huge number of Python users out there who look different from what we
see at a conference. There is, in fact, a serious gap here where these people are, for whatever
reason, not participating in our community. They're not participating in our community.
They're not coming to our conferences. They're not contributing packages. They're not writing blogs.
They're not making a whole lot of noise and fuss on Twitter. But they're still using Python.
So why aren't they part of our community? Why aren't they here? Why aren't they engaging with us?
I want to be very clear. I'm not saying this is the conference's fault.
I'm not saying this is something for conferences to change or they have a responsibility to fix.
I'm simply saying conferences, I think, are where we would see this not being an issue were it not
an issue. We'd be looking around and seeing a representation of operating systems that kind of
matches the reality at conferences. And let me also be totally clear. This is not your fault.
The reason I bring this topic up with all of you here in the room is not because it's your fault,
but because part of this gap you can help fix.
Python itself runs really well on many, many different operating systems. Those of you familiar
with our engineering setup know there's a lot of effort going into running tests on many different
OSs, keeping things in place. And Python is a great place to be. It's a great place to be.
It's a great place for you to be. It's a great place to be. It's a great place for you to be.
So, I want to say a few words about the environment. Python is running well. Making sure that it
behaves the same as much as possible across OSs. But Python itself isn't all of Python. The
ecosystem is so critical that users come to rely nearly 100% on libraries. And the libraries are
that I'm going to ask. I'm going to point out ten ways to be wrong. And when you're wrong about
these things, it leads to libraries that don't work well across different operating systems.
For each of these five questions, I'm going to give you one simple way to make it right,
which, spoiler, it's actually just writing more clean, more pure Python code. It's not adding
operating system-specific code. It's actually ways that take out the assumptions that your code is
only ever going to run in what you believe it's going to run in today. And anyone who's had to
maintain code for more than a few years will know that it ends up in all kinds of places you didn't
expect it. At the end, just to be completely upfront, is one simple checklist. If you're
planning to take notes or photograph every single slide, feel free, but there is one slide at the
end that you'll get warning. That's the one you want to take a picture of. And that's the one that
I hope you'll take away and apply to your own projects. So question number one. How do I run
Python? And this also includes how do I run my Python script? How do I run my Python code,
particularly for those of us who are implementing tools?
The first assumption is everything is on path. That's false. And I'll break down a little bit
why that's false. If you're used to a POSIX-based system, you're used to kind of a hierarchy like
this, where there's a user path, there's a site path or a distribution path and a system path.
Different commands are going to show up at each level, and if the user installs something, then
they get a command that's automatically going to be looked up from the user path, and that will
override the lower level ones. It's actually a really good system. Works really nicely.
Windows has a similar kind of path, but it doesn't look like that. The path is designed for system
files, so those are on there. If you install an app and put that on path, then you'll show up
somewhere in that hierarchy the order the files are going to be found. Someone else comes along
and installs their app, and they put theirs on there as well. Someone else got a bonus for being
the most important app in the world, and they get to come first. Which now means that they're
actually more important than system files, and all sorts of things break. But more importantly,
what this means is that if you rely on path or if you tell your users to rely on path,
you are rolling the dice. You're going to get something. You're going to get a message,
and a lot of the time, that something is going to be a crash.
Next assumption is that Python 3 will launch Python. False-ish. Since the last time I gave
this talk, I've actually done some work to fix this. So I'll get to that after this slide, but
in general, for a long time on Windows, Python was not called Python 3. It was not Python 3.7.
It was just Python. Python.exe. And so whenever you see commands online that say just type Python
3, and it will launch Python, that flat out doesn't work on Windows. And what this means
is that for people on platforms where it doesn't work, they try and follow your commands, and they
fail right at the start, and it's very, very rare that there's any instruction to help them work
around it. To make it easier to deal with finding the latest version on Windows, another launcher
called py, which is secretly .exe. This one is guaranteed to be on path, and it has logic in it
to locate and launch the correct version of Python for the particular script. But again,
it's a different name. So your instruction that says use Python 3 or use Py on Windows
now has a switch in it, which is not so great. Unless your users have installed Python from the
Microsoft App Store. So on Windows 10, there is an App Store where you can, rather than installing
packages through a regular installer, they are packaged up by the developers, in this case by the
Python core development team, published to the store, reviewed by Microsoft, and put in their
store so that you can easily access it. This package went up with Python 3.7.2 late last year
and is freely available. It also includes a few added features. This one does include Python 3.
It's Python 3.exe, but that part is optional. So if you give the instruction type Python 3,
sometimes it will work if the user got Python from here. Our hope is that over time, more and more
Windows users will get Python through the store. More and more of those standard commands that
we've been telling people to use on Mac and Linux for years will start to work. Pip also works. Pip
3 also works. Idle also works. Idle 3 works. Idle 3.7 works. However, the regular commands that have
existed forever on POSIX are now available on Windows through this package. So some of this is
getting better. There are still some caveats right now, some aspects of this that we're working
through, but this package is available. So users today are installing Python through the Microsoft
App Store and have access to those more commonly used commands from other platforms.
So the one simple idea. Support dash M. Dash M, if you're not familiar with it, is a feature of Python
that was added quite a while ago at this point. And what it lets you do is it lets you launch a
module by name. Quite often if you install a tool, I'll use black as an example, not because black
ever did this wrong, but because I like black and you should like it as well. If you pip install
black, then you would run that by typing black on the command line. Because things are not always
on path, because Python is not always started with Python or Python 3, you cannot always rely on
black being on path either. But a very common work around for this is launching it as a module,
but that's not automatic for the most part. There's a little bit of work to be done. I'll
let you research that yourself. It's quite simple, but more than I'm going to include right now.
But using dash M to launch that module provides many more ways for users to actually start your
code, to actually use that tool that you've created. You can use it with the Py launcher.
You can use it with a full path to the Python executable. It works better everywhere. There
are certainly cases on Linux systems, on Mac systems, when this is useful as an option.
So add it in and document it. Include in your readme that this works, because then when people
encounter your project and need that alternate way of launching it, they'll know straight away
that it's there and that it will work and help them out.
How do I handle paths?
Okay. Incorrect assumption one. Everyone uses forward slashes. That's false.
Windows uses back slashes most of the time. As it turns out, you can give Windows functions
forward slashes and it will correct them for you, which is very helpful. Unfortunately,
if it ever gives you a path back, it's not going to work. It's going to be a very difficult
it's going to give it to you with back slashes, which means when you wrote this path.split
that's not going to do what you hope it will. That's going to give you one big path element.
Second assumption is that you know how to handle paths. A lot of people think they know how to
handle paths. Okay. Quick pop quiz. What's this? Which path is this? It's root directory.
On Windows, what path is this? Also root directory. This is also a root directory.
This is not a root directory. That's a root directory.
Is your script able to handle that? Have you invested enough in manually managing paths
to be able to handle this? I suspect the answer is no.
So here's a better idea. As of Python 3.4, if I recall correctly, we added pathlib. Pathlib
is an object-oriented module in the standard library for managing paths. It's cross-platform.
It's going to work on any platform that Python works on. It's part of our test suite.
So if Python is running on that system, pathlib is doing the right thing on that system.
So rather than using string manipulation, you can use object-oriented Python.
So rather than using string manipulation, you can use object-oriented methods. You can use some
very neat-looking operator overloading. It will do forward slash and backslash conversions.
It will do case conversions for comparisons. And it has enough functionality, therefore,
very likely whatever it is you need to do to generate the correct paths for your platform.
So we're going to go ahead and start the test.
We very often like to store settings in places, or caches, or logs.
And quite often, these go in the TILD directory, because that's the home directory everywhere,
right? That's false. On Windows, TILD is just a character that you can put into any path,
so if you really want to create a file called that and write settings into it, then
the next program that also does the same thing is going to fight with you for it.
It's not the home directory. But even assuming it was the home directory, is it the best directory?
And the answer to that is definitely false on Windows and almost certainly false on most other
operating systems as well. If you use that and you get as far as the user profile directory,
that is the user's space. That is their space that they own, that they control. And depending
on the platform, that's going to come with different assumptions about what's in there.
To give you some idea of what Windows assumes is in there,
there's at a minimum documents, pictures, videos, probably a few other folders that are for the user.
These are actually user-visible. They can see them, they can edit them, they own the files inside it.
That's their content. At the same time, there's a section for application data.
Users can see this if they want, but for the most part, it's hidden. And it comes with local and
roaming categories and a handful of others. Depending on your system configuration, how
involved your IT department is, they may have very different semantics about where they get backed up
to, when they get copied between machines. There's a lot of semantic information in the directory
where your settings are stored, and getting it right is not as simple as using the user's profile
directory. One simple idea, import apt-dos. It's a very small single file module which you can
easily copy into your project if you don't want to add a dependency. It's very friendly licensed,
and it just gives you some easy functions to find the right place. So whatever platform you're on,
you can use the user data to find the directory to store user data in. Use a config if you're
storing configuration. Machine data, machine configuration, logs, caches. It has some opinions.
They're not necessarily universal opinions. Some platforms define these things, other platforms
don't. But it's going to get you 90 something percent of the way in a way that's going to work
with user expectations for the most part. Okay, which text encoding should I use?
First incorrect assumption, UTF-8 is always the correct encoding, and that's false.
History lesson. Who knows what happened in 1985, and who knows what happened in 1991?
1985, a product called Windows 1.0 was released. As you know, when you lock down the first version,
everything's basically locked down. You can't change it easily. 1991, I think called,
apparently the power cord back here is not providing as much power as I hoped.
Unicode 1.0 was released, 1991. A little bit late to update all of Windows to use a different
system. So what that meant is that Windows comes with essentially two sets of APIs. It has what's
called the A APIs, which take a char star. Those are all encoded in the current code page,
which is a machine-wide setting. Then there's the W APIs, which take UTF-16.
Why UTF-16 and not UTF-8? Okay, second history lesson. What happened in 1993 and what happened
in 1996? Windows NT was actually the first version of Windows that had full Unicode support in the
form of UTF-8, UTF-16. 1996 was when Unicode 2.0 was released that first defined not by
name UTF-8, but it had all of the same semantics. It was later renamed to be UTF-8.
And so again, Windows had already shipped without UTF-8 as a core part of the operating system.
It's too late to go back and add it in. The second assumption is that bytes are not text.
That sounds backwards because we often say that text is not bytes.
But also bytes are not text. There's a common assumption because this works almost all the time on
POSIX systems that if you take a blob of bytes, pass it to the operating system, and get it back,
it will be completely unchanged. But that's a black box. Doesn't hold true everywhere.
And on Windows, doesn't hold true at all because that black box is actually UTF-16.
So that's the second assumption. What happened in the early 2000s?
So the idea is that if you take a black box, pass it to the operating system, it will not hold true
at all because that black box is actually UTF-16. Which means you can take any arbitrary blob of
bytes and the operating system will convert it through an encoding that may be lossy and send
back probably question marks, which means that your round trip no longer works if you're relying on bytes.
So we have a great Strurr type, which as of Python 3 does whatever Unicode you need with
linear time indexing, no matter how big your characters get, so emoji are totally fine.
And Python will do the conversions for whatever operating system you happen to be on. You don't
have to worry about it. Even on a POSIX system where you may get arbitrary bytes that are not
valid Unicode, Strurr is able to do the right conversion if you let Python do its thing.
That said, when you're accessing the contents of a file, that's yours.
Python is not going to tell you what the contents of a file has to look like,
but and so you should refuse the temptation to guess and always specify an encoding.
Question five, how do I make my code work?
False assumption, nobody can install anything on Windows.
That's false. For a long time we've had very good installers on Windows that have been reliable,
that have not required administrative privileges, that have been used by everyone from
individuals at large companies through to IT departments at large companies through to
young students in Africa on 15 year old laptops with great experience in the field of
Windows. Installing Python on Windows is not a problem and with the Microsoft Store package,
it's even easier for people who are on up-to-date systems.
I always struggle with this one.
I can't test on Windows, you can test on Windows. You don't want to.
We saw earlier half the Python user base is trying to test your code on Windows,
so if you think that you can't, sorry that's a personal problem. You can totally test on
Windows, but you have to want to. You have to recognize that you are deliberately crippling
your user base and restricting it down to the people that are most like you by not even making
an attempt to reach out and understand them and empathize with them and run your code as they're
going to be running it. Okay, you get a bonus idea on this one. Two simple ideas. Get continuous
integration or collaborate. There are so many free CI providers out there right now. Azure
Pipelines is one that I'm more than happy to talk to you about. AppBear can also do Windows.
You don't have to actually own Windows. You don't have to own a second machine to be able to do this
testing. So if you have a project that you know people are using and you don't have CI covering
all of the operating systems that your users are using, then there's very few excuses for not being
able to set that up. Like I say, I'm more than happy to help out. Come and chat to me afterwards.
Also, there's a whole lot of Python users that are trying to run your code on Windows,
but they try and they fail and they assume that they're not welcome. All it takes is one message
on your GitHub page saying, hey, I don't have Windows. I need some help. If you can help me,
here's how to get in touch. Get some collaborators. But it does take a deliberate reaching out.
So where to from here? This is the point where you get your camera ready.
Next time you go to make a release of your project, run through this checklist. Ask yourself,
does dash M work? If people need to launch my script, how many choices have I given them?
Do I manipulate paths by hand? Do I put configuration in weird or unusual or unreliable places?
Do I keep text in non-string types? And do I have continuous integration? Do I have collaborators?
Do I know that this is going to work before I release it to the world?
Because this bothers me. That's a lot of Python users out there who feel separated from the rest
of the community. Part of that welcome is using the libraries that we write for them, that we
distribute. And when those libraries fail is when they feel left out. Closing this gap is a huge
task. It's going to take a long time. But one simple thing that you can do is the code that
you're releasing, make it work. Make these people in your one small way through your one little
thing that you're sharing with them, make them feel welcome, and make them feel as if you value
them and want them to be using your code. With that, my name is Steve Dower, Python engineer
at Microsoft. Thank you very much.