But, so meanwhile, I'm going to do some extra credit conversation here, okay?
So how many of you have significant experience in another language that is object-oriented?
Okay, so I'm going to tell you a little story. This is, so I don't know how many of you know,
but I wrote a book called Fluent Python, and the book has been a success. People love it.
It's been selling well. It has been translated to eight languages. But Fluent Python is not a book
for people that are learning Python. It's actually, Fluent Python grew out of a course
that I used to teach in Brazil where I live that was called Python for people who know Python.
So the idea is you are already using Python. Python is very easy to get started, and so that
course was about making the most of Python and trying to code an idiomatic Python, because as
somebody said, I forgot, somebody famous in the history of computer science once said that it's
possible to write for trend in any programming language, right? And I have seen, because Java is
one of the most popular languages. In the domain that Python is used, Java is also very popular.
So I've seen a lot of Python code that had a very strong Java accent, just like my English with a
very strong Portuguese accent. So I've seen that in Python code. And anyway, because I started
writing the book in 2013 and finished in 2015, and then I went to work for ThoughtWorks where I'm
doing other stuff besides coding in Python. I'm also coding in other languages and doing non-coding
tasks. This all means that it's been about eight or nine years since I've taught an introductory
class about object-oriented programming in Python. When Python has chapters about object-oriented
programming, but they assume that you already know the basics of object-oriented programming in
Python. And this was really interesting for me to, you know, after all these years, start thinking
about what should I teach, what should I show to people that are getting started with Python in
terms of object-oriented programming. And I went through old slides and exercises from courses that
I used to give like ten years ago or something. And a lot of this stuff was wrong, you know,
because over these years I've learned more about object-oriented programming, for example. And
there's been trends also. I'm going to talk about that more, but there's a huge trend away from
inheritance. You know, object-oriented programming was always, you know, when you took an introductory
course about object-oriented programming, a lot of time was always spent with inheritance, right?
And you had all those crazy examples of, you know, animals, you know, so you have the animal class
and then the mammal class, the mammal subclass, and then the dog subclass of mammal and the cat
and the bat, whatever, right? This is just wrong, people. This is not the way to program classes
anymore. So for one thing, in reality, we don't use the inheritance hierarchy to do classification
like an animal taxonomy. We don't use it for that. And so I'm going to talk about that. And another
thing that, and also for instance, there's the famous Design Patterns book, the one that's
nicknamed the book of the Gang of Four because it has four authors, right? So in that book,
the introduction of that book is excellent. I think it's actually worth the price of the book,
and the rest is not so important in my opinion. But the introduction is awesome. And in the
introduction, the authors say that you should favor composition over inheritance. I'm going to
talk about that and show examples. But this is a famous like proverb that has been written in,
I don't know, it was written in 93 or 94, that book, and it's gaining more and more traction.
And now we see programming languages emerging, for instance, in the data science space, there
is a language called Julia, which is actually why Jupiter starts with G-U, because the Jupiter
project supports Julia, Python, and R natively. So Julia is a programming language that has
inheritance, but only of abstract classes. I'm going to talk about that too. Concrete classes,
you cannot inherit. Go is another language that is growing very fast. It has a concept of types,
they don't call it classes, but they have types with methods, which is very similar to a class,
and they have the concept of interfaces, but there is no inheritance at all in Go. So these
are some of the things that I had to, basically I had to rethink a lot of it. I created lots of
examples just for this tutorial, and this is unlike any other course that I've given about
this subject, because of the things that happened during this past few years in that area.
What else can I say?
Also, before this talk, or before this tutorial, whenever I talked about bitonic objects, I gave a
lot of emphasis in the special methods. I'm going to talk a little bit about them here, but not as
much as I talk. My whole book is about 700 pages of special methods. That's the core of the book,
because the special methods are the way Python presents itself to the programmer as a toolkit
for building frameworks, which is really interesting, but it's not something that you should be
concerned when you're just getting started with object-oriented programming in Python.
I am going to show one example at the very end that has lots of special methods, but most of them
are going to use only a few of the most essential special methods. So just one more minute, and then
it's 9.10, and we're going to get started. So for those who arrived after I showed this, that URL is the URL of the
repo where the content of the talk is, and I decided not to do slides this time. There's only this opening,
sort of like a title card, and everything else is Jupyter notebooks and also examples in code as
Python modules. Everything is in this repo. All right. So you can clone the repo or you can just browse it
through the GitHub UI. All right. Let's get started. So from now on, it's going to be recording. So good
morning, people. Thank you very much for choosing this tutorial. I'm super happy to be here presenting
a tutorial at PyCon. This is a conference that I love. I would like for you to not be shy and ask
questions whenever you want. Just raise your hand. If I don't notice you, then you can start yelling.
And there's a mic that we need to use when people ask questions so that the question is recorded as
well. Okay? But please don't be shy. All right? So my name is Luciano Ramario, and I work for Thoughtworks,
and we are going to talk about Pythonic objects, which is the essentials of object-oriented
programming in Python. We're going to talk a lot about idioms and specifics of Python. Okay?
So here's the thing. One thing that always bothered me when teaching object-oriented programming with
Python, by the way, I love Python, okay? And I think it's a very deeply object-oriented language.
In some respects, it's more object-oriented than Java, for example. Because, for instance, in Python,
we don't have primitive objects. We don't have primitive values like the numbers in Java.
Everything is an object in Python in the sense that everything was an object in small talk. Okay?
But there is one particular topic, which is kind of an essential topic of object-oriented programming,
that has always been a problem for me to talk about when I talk about Python. And that's because
of this. I'm going to show you this screen here. It's from the book, Small Talk 80, the language.
And that book has... So the language, small talk, grew together with an entire system,
which was an operating system and a graphical user interface and what we call today an IDE.
So this is one of the windows where you programmed it. So you see here are the
class categories. And then the selected category is New Project. And then you see
Financial History, which is the name of the class that's just been created here,
that was just created. Actually, the previous screenshot in the book showed the person clicking
accept to this definition. So the person typed, the user typed this definition. And then when
she chose accept, it appeared here as one of the classes. And then it says here, no messages,
which means that no methods have been defined for it. But if you look at the class definition,
it says Object Subclass Financial History. So Object Subclass means this is a subclass of object.
In Python 3, we don't need to say that anymore. If you declare a class, it's already a subclass
of objects. If you don't specify a specific superclass, it's going to be a subclass of object.
So this is what this definition says, the name of the new class and where it belongs in the hierarchy.
And then you see here instance variable names. And then there is a string
of names separated by spaces, which are, so Financial History. I'm actually going to show
a Python version of this class later on. But here we have cash on hand, incomes, and expenditures
are the instance variable names. So right at the start in Smalltalk,
you tell the system the names of the attributes of the class.
Let's take a look at another important reference, the official Java tutorial. The Java tutorial has
these pictures. They talk about what is an object, and they say an object is fields in here,
and it's surrounded by methods. The idea being that other objects can only communicate with
this object through the methods and not have access to the fields directly. In Smalltalk,
it was like that too. In fact, in Smalltalk, all the instance variables were private. There was no
way to do a public instance variable in Smalltalk. So it was very much like this. And this is an
example of what they call encapsulation. So the object encapsulates some values here, which are
the fields. Okay. And here's a definition that talks about that. Hiding internal state and
requiring all interaction to be performed through an object's methods is known as data encapsulation,
a fundamental principle of object-oriented programming. Right? So here's an example.
I like the example in the picture, although the code is not so good, but the picture, the idea is,
this represents a bicycle. So you have methods that are like verbs of actions that you can
do with the bike. So like change gears, break, change cadence. And then you have the values
inside the fields. So this would be the speed because it says 18 miles per hour. This would
be the cadence because it says 90 rotations per 90 RPM. And this is the gear, the currently engaged
gear, fifth gear. Okay. Now, a crucial idea here is that there is no way to change the speed
directly. There is no method called change speed, because the speed of the bicycle
is one of the fields in there. It depends on other things. Right? So for instance, if you apply the
brake, this will decrease the speed. Right? How much? Well, it depends on how much you press the
brake and also whether it's going uphill or downhill or whether somebody is pedaling still or not.
Right? So that's the idea. The idea is that this internal state of the object is changed
through method calls that are not necessarily just straight setters and getters like we often see
in introductory tutorials. Like I said, it doesn't make sense in a realistic simulation
to be able to change the speed directly. Right? This would be like you're in a car and you pull
the, how do you call the... The speedometer. Yeah. The little thing, how do you call the
pointer in the speedometer, and that would make your car go faster. Doesn't make any sense. Right?
So no. The speed is a consequence of other things that are happening. All right? And if you look at
the Java code, it's very clear here that the class bicycle has three fields, cadence, speed,
and gear. And then there is other methods. There are methods. Right? So what I'm talking about here
is that both Java and small talk, which are very important object-oriented languages, have specific
and explicit ways of defining what are the fields of a class. Right? And so I think the way in which
Python is less like all the other object-oriented programming languages that I know is the fact that
Python historically did not have a way of doing that. And now it's growing a way of doing that.
I'm going to talk about that through the typing module and the data classes. But historically,
there was no way of telling Python, okay, this class has these fields. Right? Also, Python has,
well, all object-oriented languages have slightly varying terminologies. Right? But if you know about
Java, it's useful to know that the Python term, what we call attributes in Python, is a generic
term that encompasses the concepts of fields and methods in Java. Okay? All of that we consider
in Python methods, attributes of the object as well. Right? And then when we talk, when you want
to talk about what Java people call a field, we need to use this qualifier and call it a data
attribute. Okay? And then method is a method. All right? So it's important to understand these
different terms that I use. So like I was saying, Python prior to Python 3.6 had no way to declare
instance variables without assigning. Actually, the assignment is what creates, the initial
assignment is what creates a variable. Okay? But it's more than that because Python historically
had no way to declare variables at all. No kinds of variables. You had any way of declaring.
The only kinds of variables that you declare in Python are function arguments. Right? Okay.
So the first assignment is a declaration and the attributes defined in a class body are class
attributes. I'm going to talk about that. But then I don't know how many of you have studied
or used Django? All right. Lots of people. So I was using Python, I started using Python in 1998
and about, I don't know, 2005, 2006, around that time, I started studying Django and I looked at
this and I said, what's going on here? You know? Because what you see here, I just said that
attributes defined in a class body are class attributes. So these attributes here, which are
in the body of the class and not inside the function or method, they are class attributes.
But clearly, they are defining something that has to do with the instances. Right? So a musician
has a first name, a last name and an instrument. Each musician would have a different name.
Right? So this is an instance attribute. However, it's defined in the class. How does that work?
Well, this is a very advanced topic called descriptors. Right? So these objects that
are instantiated here are descriptors. And I want to say, I want to talk about that just because
I don't want to go deeper into this subject, but I want to make sure that you believe and
understand that everything that is defined in a class body are class attributes.
However, a descriptor is a class attribute that is designed to manage attributes in the instances.
Does that make sense? You know, think about a getter or a setter. So a getter or a setter
is just a method that just retrieves the value of a data attribute. Right? That's all it does.
So a getter is a method. And methods, because they are defined in the class, they are basically
class attributes. But methods usually handle attributes of the instances. Does that make sense?
The descriptor is another category of things that are not methods that have the same characteristic
of something that is attached to the class, but that is designed to handle the instances.
Okay. But I was surprised when I saw this in Python or in Django, because I was already
using the language for several years, like seven years when I saw this, and I had never seen the
descriptor before. And because the fact is, in the Python standard library, there are no
data-oriented descriptors like this. All the ones that exist out there are provided by
frameworks like Django, SQL alchemy, and things like that.
So it's kind of a foreign idea. Of course, the infrastructure is there in the language
for people to use it, and the framework authors have used it, but it's an advanced concept,
this idea of the descriptor. So let's get back to basics, really basics. And now I'm going to start
running code here. So the first thing I always do when I teach with a Jupyter notebook,
so I don't know if everybody knows about Jupyter notebooks, the idea here is I am actually running
this from the terminal here. This is the log of the server. Right? I run it by typing Jupyter
space notebook, but I didn't, I don't think it's important for you to be running this right now.
And the thing is, each of these cells, when it doesn't have a number, like this one and this one,
it means that they were not executed yet. And this one was just executed. To execute it,
I hit shift, shift, shift return. Okay? So I'm going to execute this cell, and now I just defined
the class coordinate. Okay? What I had done before was just printing the Python version
to make sure everybody understand that we are using Python 3.7 because some of the features
I'm going to show depend on 3.7. All right. So I've defined the class. What does this class have?
It just has a doc string. In the second line of a class, if you want to declare an empty class,
you have to put something in there because of the syntax of Python requires. So you can put the
pass keyword or I prefer to put a doc string. It serves the purpose of filling that space,
and it's better than the password keyword because it says something. Okay? So I can create
a coordinate, and I can assign a latitude and a longitude to it, and then this last line
will make Jupiter show the value. Okay? So this is what we saw. So we have an object.
Okay. And this is how it's displayed. I'm going to add another line here or another cell just to
show you that I can actually look at the latitude of Cleveland. See? So I'm accessing
the attributes. So this is the first thing that is very surprising.
Not only there is no way to declare, there's no way to declare class or instance attributes
or data attributes, but you don't need to because you can create a class and just assign
merrily attributes to the instances. Okay? By default, this is how Python classes behave.
It's not a good idea to be, you know, hanging new attributes while the class is being passed
around the system. I also saw a very ugly bug that was because of that, but you can do it.
All right. So in order to teach and also to test and document, I like to implement
a method called Dunderwrapper. All right? So this is one thing that I consider an essential
characteristic of a Python class. So what's the idea? Since the times of small talk,
the people who have created object-oriented programming languages have realised that it's
important for objects to have a way to present themselves as a string. Right? So if I have a,
if I say print this object, the object, the print function will call something on the object
so that the object is responsible for displaying itself. Okay? This is a very object-oriented way
of thinking. Objects should be responsible for actions that have to do with their internal state.
Right? So for instance, if I have to display myself, I have to show some attributes, my name
or whatever, this should be my task as an object. But also, so in other languages like Java, you
have a two-string method. Pretty much every object-oriented language has some method that
is designed that you should implement so that your objects can represent themselves as strings.
But Python has two methods. And we pronounce this
dunder wrapper. So dunder is the double underscore on both sides. Dunder wrapper
is one of the methods that you use. And the idea is that dunder wrapper is to
show a technical representation of the object. Let's call it that. Okay? So a way of showing
the object that is useful for debugging or for logging or for teaching. And that's in contracts
with a way of displaying a string, a user-friendly string of the object. Okay? Which we are going to
do soon. But anyway, I don't need this import hash right now here. This is leftover from another
iteration. And now see the difference? So because now I have a dunder wrapper, my object doesn't
display like that anymore. This is the dunder wrapper that my class inherited from objects.
The object class shows objects like this. The name of the class and the position in memory.
Just to, as a way of uniquely identifying that instance so that you know whether two instances
are the same or different. Okay? Now, if you implement dunder wrapper, then you can
make your objects appear some other way. And this is actually a good way of doing that, which is
to display the object as the source code that you would use to reconstruct
a copy of the object. Does that make sense? See? This is like calling the class and passing
two arguments to build the object. Right? So some good best practices about the dunder wrapper.
So dunder wrapper is good for exploratory programming, documentation, docs tests and debugging.
The best practice, if viable, it's not always viable, but you should implement dunder wrapper
returning a string with syntax required to create a new instance like the one inspected.
Like I just said, right? This string here, if I copy and paste it in a terminal, in a Python shell,
it's going to create another coordinate like that one. A more technical way of saying is that
the wrapper function, which is a built-in function of Python, calls the dunder wrapper of objects.
Right? So when you call wrapper of X, you get a string. If you have all the string,
you should get an object that will be equal to the original X. Does that make sense? Now,
I want to explain something that is kind of weird. Why do we – so we have a method called dunder
wrapper, but then let me show you this thing here. So what happens if I do this?
Sorry, I have to call it. I get that string, right? And what happens if I do this?
The same string. So which is better?
Of course, this is more readable, although it does cause some concern to people coming from
other languages because this doesn't look object-oriented. Most object-oriented languages
these days have this kind of syntax where it's always object dot method to make the call, right?
But in this case, it's like this. And you will see this over and over in Python. You have the
len function. You have a bunch of built-in functions that are named like special methods
and that you use like this. You should never do this, right? The special methods are not
designed for you to be calling them. Python calls them for you when necessary. So what's the sense
of that? Why is this like this? Because the thing is, for built-in objects which are part of the
Python interpreter and that are implemented in C or for things that are not part of the
interpreter but are also implemented in C, like for instance, the NumPy objects, the nd array,
everything else in data science, most of those objects that you use when you're doing data
science in Python, they are implemented in C. Some of them are implemented in other languages,
but most of them are implemented in C. For an object implemented in C, Python has a shortcut.
So when you call wrapper of an object, Python sees, okay, is this implemented in C? So there's a
quicker way of making that happen that doesn't involve all the machinery of calling a method,
you know, which has to do with expensive machinery because it has to do with
all the dynamic way of looking up methods in the inheritance hierarchy and so on.
And so the thing is, that's why you have this syntax, because this syntax is faster for built-in
objects and objects implemented in C, but when it has a fallback, which is when you apply the
wrapper function to an object that you created or somebody created in Python, then the system will
fall back to call to do this, right? So does that make sense? I wanted to explain because sometimes
people accuse Python of not being object oriented because of this syntax. But it's just like,
it's a pragmatic solution to be able to be very fast with the built-ins. Okay?
All right. I've already said that. So there's another, I said that there's another representation
for end users and that's done with the Dunderster. And here is a nice Dunderster. I'm going to run it.
So I just define the class again and then I'm going to explain the code soon. But
see, isn't this nice? So now when I print a coordinate, it looks like the way users like to see coordinates.
Right? So,
all right. Oops.
Okay.
Something's not great here.
All right. Thank you.
Okay. So another thing that is a bit surprising when people get started with Python is that
a method definition like this,
when it's an instance method, the method that deals with the instance and most methods that
you're going to create deal with the instance, they have to receive the self-arguments,
which is not part of the call. Right? So,
but the idea is that this actually has to do with the descriptor mechanism as well. But anyway,
this makes, so when Python sees this, it passes this instance as the self-arguments.
And so we have this other thing. Now I have a little shortcut here that I don't know if I am
ashamed or proud of it, but I'm going to show you because it's kind of interesting.
How does this work? So in order to select whether I'm going to write N or W or N or S
or W or E and the coordinates, I use this crazy expression here.
This actually doesn't look like Python, but it is Python. So let me tell you what's going on here.
This expression here returns a Boolean. Right? All the comparison operators in Python return
Booleans. And a Boolean in Python is actually a subclass of int. The true value is one and the
zero value or the false value is zero. Okay? So because the Booleans are a type of int,
a subtype of int, you can use them in arithmetic, which sometimes is interesting. You know,
you can have an equation where there's a certain term that should be zero if a certain condition
applies. So you can use it like that. And in this situation, I'm using it as an index to this string.
So if this is false, then I'm going to display, so the result of this is going to be zero.
So then I'm reading the zero index of this string, which is the letter N. Right? Otherwise,
if it's true, then it's going to select the S. Okay?
And over here is the, all the cool kids are using F strings. It's really cool.
I'm not going to explain it a lot. I'm just going to say that it's pretty powerful because
it allows you to put actually expressions. See, I have a method. I have a function call here.
I'm calling the abs of the latitude. And then I have the, so this part here is an expression.
And after the column is the formatting, all of this inside these braces here.
Right? And this is just the variable, this variable here. Okay? Anyway, so,
so it seems to be working this class of ours, except that we kind of punted on the whole topic
of attributes, which is what I was talking about. Right? Because when I created the class to
demonstrate every time I did like this, I created an instance and then I assigned the attributes.
If I don't do that, I get an exception that says object has no attribute lot. Okay? The reason why
I wrote all of this exception handling here is because otherwise we would see this here.
And also, if I tell Jupyter Notebook to run everything to see if everything is okay,
it stops here and it doesn't run the remaining cells. So that's why I do this.
This way here, where I catch the exception and I print the message. Okay? Anyway, so what can I do
to fix this? So the quick and dirty fix for this is to create two attributes here.
So if I run this again, so I just added the attributes there in the body of the class.
Right? So they are class attributes. But now when I run this, it works.
And this is a peculiar thing about Python. The fact that
what is happening implicitly here for this print to execute, this Dunderster is being called.
And the Dunderster accesses self.lat and self.long. Right? So it's looking at attributes in the
instance. However, the instance doesn't have the attributes. So then Python looks at the class
and gets those values. So this way here is a way of having sort of default values for
attributes. But I don't think this is very clean and I actually don't recommend it anymore.
I'm going to be talking a lot more about that. Okay?
Here's another example of using class attributes as default. So for instance, I have a class called
pizza. It doesn't have any methods. Just class attributes. Class data attributes to be more
precise. So I can create a pizza instance and I can ask for the slices and I get that. And I can
ask for the flavor. And it's cheese. And here's the thing. The Dunderdict is a special attribute
that most Python objects have. Some don't have it. But most Python objects have the Dunderdict.
And the Dunderdict is basically a dictionary that tells you what are the attributes of that
particular instance. Okay? And as you can see, even though I was asking about the slices and
the flavor of the P instance, it doesn't have any attributes because it's getting everything from the
class. Now, if I assign and look at the Dict, then I see the value appear as an instance attribute.
So there's an asymmetry here. Which is when you read an attribute that doesn't exist in the
instance, it goes looking at the class. But if you assign, it doesn't look at the class. It just
assigns to the instance. Which means that the, you know, if I create another pizza here
and ask for the flavor,
it's going to be cheese. Because that's the default that's in the class. Right? The fact that I
assigned to the instance didn't change the class at all. So I can check and see the Dict of the
pizza of the class. The Dict of the class, the Dunderdict of the class is wrapped into this thing
called the mapping proxy. It's just sort of like a read-along. It's just a little bit of a
read-only dictionary. But as you can see, it has the attributes that are declared explicitly in
the class, like diameters, lices, flavor, flavor two. And then it has other things,
including this is where the doc string would be, if there was doc string. But I didn't create doc
string in this case. All right? So now to wrap up this session here, I'm going to show a better
pizza. So this is what I consider gourmet professional pizza. Okay? And what I did here is
I separated, I created those two attributes. I considered them class attributes. Okay? Because
every pizza that I make are going to be 40 centimeters in diameter and eight slices.
Okay? They are sort of like a configuration option of the class. And the class is a factory
of objects, right? So I can configure the class so that it starts making instances with those
characteristics. So these are class attributes. And the instance attributes, the proper way of
doing them today is to assign them all inside the Dunderdict. Some people call it the constructor
because it does what the constructor does in Java. But it's actually not a constructor
because it gets the object as the first argument. So the object has already been constructed.
What the Dunderdict does is it initializes. That's why it's called Dunderdict. Right? So it gets the
instance and then you initialize whatever you need to initialize here. And this is the most
official way traditionally of declaring instance attributes in Python. It's assigning them in the
Dunderdict. And it's a best practice. You should always assign everything that is going to be in
all instances in the Dunderdict. And not do it piecemeal in different methods and so on
or later. No. If you want to create an attribute later, the best practice is to create it in the
Dunderdict and assign none to it. Okay? Or some empty value. Like an empty list or whatever.
And then later when you have data to put in, the important thing is that the attribute is already
declared so that people reading your class will know what to expect. So this class,
so here we're dealing with the deficiency in Python. Get it? The deficiency is there is no
explicit way of telling Python what are the instance attributes. So the best we can do is
adopt conventions. And this is the best convention we have. Assign them all and then they're in it.
All right? So the good practices shown here are that I use class attributes for attributes that
are shared among all instances. And the attributes that are expected to vary among instances are
instance attributes. And the instance attributes were all assigned in the Dunderdict. And the
default value for instance attributes are argument defaults in the Dunderdict. So I can
create a pizza without specifying the flavors because it has the Dunderdict has default arguments.
So this is the best practice. And actually besides readability, which is a very important thing to
have in a system, because systems, source code is read much more often than it is written.
So it's important for source code to be readable. But there is now for people who are more motivated
by performance, performance, performance, there is a technical reason to do that.
There was a PEP and it's kind of it's not so new, actually. It came out around Python 3.4.
So PEP 4.1.12, document and optimization, which is designed for this situation here.
Let's suppose I have an Amazon pizza. So I have a million pizzas in the queue.
And that means that I will have a million dictionaries with the attributes of each pizza
has its own dictionary with the attributes, right? The Dunderdict. What this PEP does is
they created this optimization where Python notices when you
create an instance that the keys of this instance dicts are the same keys of another instance's
dict and they share and Python shares the keys, which is basically a hash, the name and the
hash and the value of the key, which may be a long string or an arbitrary object. So
this key sharing can lead to significant economy of memory. But it only happens if you follow
strictly this practice of initializing all your instances with all the instances attributes at
once. Any time you, after the fact, decide to add another attribute, then this forces Python to
remove that dictionary and copy it to another place where it's going to be a singleton and not
be sharing keys with others. So I would like to propose that you do a little bit of coding
and the idea is there is actually in the Google, oh sorry, I forgot something. I need to hand out
something. Let me get it here. Yeah, okay. So oops, wrong, okay, wrong link. There's no,
yeah, I simplified the link but I forgot to edit there. I'm gonna edit there.
So this is the link and I'm gonna fix the notebook, sorry. Later I decided to simplify,
or actually what did I do here? Wait, I think it's, I know what I did. I changed the label but I didn't
change the actual link. All right, so now it works and I'm gonna commit and push so that you have this
fixed version.
All right, so I suggest that you do it in pairs and what I want to propose, so the exercise is
described in this document here. All right, so there's three steps but let's call it the
third step a bonus, okay. Do it only if you have time and what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna hand out
post-its and if you want to do the exercise I'm gonna ask you to do this.
If you have an issue, if you need help, you're gonna stick a red post-it to your screen here
and when you're done with the step two, okay, because three is a bonus. If you're done with
step two, you stick the green one. So when there's a bunch of people with the green one,
we need to move on, all right. That's the idea. So please pass them around.
So take one of each color
and what I'm gonna
do is I'm gonna, so the basic instructions I'm gonna show what's happening here is that we have
sorry, oh yeah.
Yeah.
Oh okay, the fix is, the fix needs a fix. Okay, sorry.
Oh it says one here.
Yeah, but what you.
Yeah, I'm gonna show you how to get there. So if you go to the repo,
it's so PIOB, the link and then
then lamps and then one and then this is it, right.
So for instance, if I use this command here,
here. So this is another feature of Python that is not very well known,
which is the dock test. I'm gonna show you how it works. So if I go there to the labs, one, okay,
this is what I have and I type this command and what happened is this,
this. Okay, so what is going on here?
I'm running the dock test module which comes with Python.
So this is what the dash M dock test does on the readme.rst file, which is a text file.
And the dash F at the end is just so that it stops at the first failure, because otherwise it's gonna
show a lot of other things that are wrong, that are what the exercise is about. The exercise is
about fixing those things. But anyway, if you do dash F, you're gonna do step by step, okay.
So it stops at the first. And what does it say? Failed example, goof of guinea,
goof of guinea, coordinate object has no attribute lot. Okay. So the problem is that
it's asking you to create an image accepting a latitude and a longitude, right?
The class that you have there doesn't have that.
Okay. So I'm gonna cheat and just say, and this is not what the exercise is intended to do,
but just to show you the dock test running. If I create the let attribute like I had done over there
here, and I run it again, oops. Now it's gonna complain about the lack of the long and so on,
right? So actually the dock tests, if you run it like this with dash F, they're gonna guide you
through what you need to do. But if you start by doing the first step, which is to create the
image like I had shown before, you can pass. So this is the example that is actually running.
So what dock test does is it looks at text that has prompts that look like the Python prompt,
executes the code and checks whether the output is the same as appears here. This is what dock
test does. The idea of dock test is to make sure that the examples in documentation are accurate.
But I also like to use them as a scaffolding for exercises like we're using now.
So the first step is actually like the code that I just showed you with the image. The second step
is new. The idea is that you're gonna create a class attribute. The example shows that you can
access the class attribute through the class coordinate or through an instance.
And step three is where you implement and encode
the geohash method here.
And here's what's gonna happen. I was supposed to read these announcements to you.
Because we have a break. So we're gonna have a break at 10.15, okay? And it says snacks go quickly,
so please let your group out at the right time. Right? So actually, if you wanna
step outside soon, you know, go ahead and then we can come back. I don't know what's the length of
the break, the duration of the break. Let me try and find out.
Well, let's do a 15-minute break, okay? So the idea is we'll come back. You can step outside
whenever you like and we'll come back at 10.30, okay? Or you can come back earlier and finish
the exercise or whatever. Lunch will be at 12.20. And then it says here, we have placed as much power
as we could afford. Please share the outlets. And there's a survey link to the tutorial. I don't
know if you have that. Have you gotten a piece of paper that has this link? Otherwise, I'm gonna
put it in the presentation here. It's a Survey Monkey link with a bunch of letters.
I'm going to put it in the last presentation, the last.
Yes, all right. So I put the link in the last page that we're gonna see.
So I'm gonna step outside and come back in 15 minutes, okay? And then we resume. Let's go eat
before it's all over.
Let's get going. So maybe you noticed that there was a spoiler because the solution was right at
the page that we were looking at, right? So and the GeoHash is a very interesting thing
because it computes an alphabetical, an alphanumerical hash that has some very interesting properties.
Oh, that's in the readme, actually. The property is that,
you see, I have here the coordinates of the airport of Cleveland, the one in the west,
and this is the coordinate of the city as it appears, I think, on Wikipedia. And you see
that the first three letters are the same. So this is what is cool about GeoHashes, is that
it's super fast to compare. It's very easy to determine whether two things are close,
depending on the number of letters that match. And if you have more letters matching, that means
it's really close. If you have like 10 letters matching, that's probably in the next room,
right? Of course, there are exceptions because it involves cutting the world in squares,
and if you are on a boundary, then you have to check other things. But at most, you do
eight different checks and you can determine whether something is very close or not.
Anyway, GeoHash is cool. All right, so what I'm going to do is, so the next topic is actually
something that is, these are the first examples that we just saw are new for this tutorial.
The examples here are from my book, and I'm kind of,
I want to, there's more interesting stuff to see rather than these examples. What I'm going to
talk about, so I'm going to just speed through this page and then we're going to go to the next one.
But this page is something that you can study later if my super quick explanation here
leaves you with questions or you can ask me later too. But these are all, you know, the haunted bus
and the haunted bus version two and the Twilight bus, they are bad for you, okay?
The good bus is the bus, all right? So this is basically three counter examples that talk about
problems that can happen when you have like a default argument, a default class attribute
that is mutable and you're using it as the default for the instances. So what happens with the
haunted bus is basically you created this bus one instance and you put two people in it and then
when you create the two, when you create the bus two version, the bus two instance,
you have the ghost of the same people. So they are in both buses. This is really scary.
And the other example is you don't have a class attribute anymore but you have a mutable default
in the constructor and that basically has the same issue because think about it.
Like I said before, methods are class attributes, right? And the full values in method declarations
are attributes of the methods. So this empty list is an attribute of Dunderinit
and Dunderinit is a method of the class. So indirectly this is an attribute of the class
as well. So you have the exact same issue. This last example is more subtle. Oh, sorry.
Actually this is fixed. This is not what I wanted it to be.
Sorry. I was trying it out later, sooner and it's wrong. So this is correct and we're going to
save it soon. This is what it was intended to be. The idea is for this example, this looks pretty
good, okay? Because you don't have a default in the class and you follow this idiom of
for any mutable arguments you put none as the default and then you check and you explicitly create
an empty list in this case, okay? So this looks okay. But there is a subtle problem with it.
So we have a hockey team here with six women, all right? And then I am loading the bus,
the Twilight bus with the six players, passengers. So what happened is passengers, not none in this
case, it's the hockey team. So I have this assignment here. And now the bus, which is bus 5,
is going to drop Sue and Pat. And you can see that they are no longer in the bus. Yes, but they are
no longer in the hockey team either. So they fell into a void, right? And, you know, a lot of Python
programmers will look at this code and say that it's okay, but there is this subtle problem. And
the solution to the problem is this assignment here is dangerous because you're using this as a
list. You can see that it's a list because I'm calling append and remove methods. And also in
the default case I'm creating an empty list. But if I just assign the arguments, my instance is
actually sharing the list that was passed. And as I drop people along the way, I'm actually removing
them from the list that I got. And this is probably not what the end user wants. So there's two ways
to fix this. One way is using this notation, which creates a copy of the list. But if you get a
tuple argument, the addender in it will work, but will create a copy of the tuple. But then the class
will break later because you're going to try and do append and remove in the tuple and it doesn't
work. So the best way is to do this. So what I'm doing here is actually I'm using the passengers
list as the argument to the constructor of a new list. So this does create a copy. But it's more
flexible than the other notation because if I get a tuple as an argument, I'm building a list from it.
If I get any iterable as argument, I'm building a list of it. So it's flexible and safe at the same
time. And this is the best solution. So now if we run the test, you see that the hockey team is
still complete. So this is the best practice to take whatever arguments that you get that are
mutable and make a copy. Of course, there are exceptions, right? Maybe it's 10 million
items in this list and you don't want to copy 10 million items, but then you have to document,
pay attention, I'm going to change whatever you pass me. But by default, I think this is a very
good practice. And it's also, yeah, so this is the solution of the bus. Yeah, all right.
Okay. And it's also an example. If I do, like I said, as I convert the argument to a list,
I'm offering flexibility to the user. They can pass any iterable object and I will build a list
from it. And this is an example of Postel's law, which is one of the
best practices in the internet, right? Be conservative in what you send and be liberal
in what you accept. In fact, if people did that on Facebook and on Twitter, that would be awesome
too, right? Anyway, so let's now, so I started talking about how
Python doesn't have an easy way of declaring
class attributes. And this is particularly painful with classes like this one that I,
I'm back to the page one here. So this class is basically, you know, a pair of coordinates,
right? There's not a whole lot of functionality. The most interesting functionality here is the
geohash method that we added later. But it's basically just like a struct or a record in a
database. It has two numbers and that's it, right? So the fact that Python didn't have an easy way
to declare the instance attributes made it difficult to avoid this kind of boilerplate
of having to write this in it with a lot of repetition of the names of the arguments
assigned to the, and then the wrapper, which is like a standard thing that looks like this.
And so there's a lot of boilerplates involved here. So over the years, and this is our next subject,
the Python community has evolved ways of dealing with these kinds of classes,
which are called data classes. And here I'm using a space, okay? Because I'm using the term in,
like a general term. What is a data class? A data class is mostly just like a struct. It's a class
that looks like a database record. It doesn't have a lot of algorithms. It doesn't have a lot of
weird methods. It just stores fields and displays fields and lets you access the fields, okay?
So other languages have grown this kind of features too. Ruby has always had a very simple
way of doing this. And the first solution to this problem that appeared was NameItTouple. NameItTouple
is pretty old. I don't know when it started, but probably more than 10 years old. But anyway,
so NameItTouple is actually a function that you call
passing two arguments. The first is the name of a class that, so NameItTouple is a factory of classes,
okay? And by the way, this is one way in which Python is more object oriented than Java.
Because in Java, the classes are not
full first class classes or objects. What I mean is, in Java, you cannot write Java code,
just pure Java code to create a class at runtime. If you need to create a class at runtime, you need
to write byte codes. You need to generate byte codes at runtime. But in Python, these
classes are objects. And as such, they can be created at runtime. And this is a function that
creates, when I invoke this, it creates a class with this name and with these attributes, okay?
Okay. And now I use it like this. And you see it has a very nice wrapper by default
that spells out the name of the argument. And it's any class created by NameItTouple
is actually a subtype of tuple. So that means I can use this notation here to unpack the values.
See? This object is an instance of my class. And it also behaves like a tuple. I can do
this multiple assignments. And I can read the different parts. All right? And it includes
a Dundee queue method. The Dundee queue method is the one that implements the equality operator.
Right? And the Dundee queue that is generated by the NameItTouple factory actually knows how
to compare my instances with any tuple. See? So NameItTouple is pretty cool. I use it a lot.
But there are some limitations. Limitations are not always bad, right? Sometimes it's good to have
limitations because you're being explicit. I don't need anything fancier than a NameItTouple here.
I'm going to use a NameItTouple. NameItTouples are also, they use less memory than classes.
Because they don't have a Dundee dict. They have another mechanism called Dundee slots,
which is less flexible but saves memory. The problem is the instances are immutable. This may
be a problem or not. It's a limitation. Maybe it's a feature, depending on your situation.
And there's no simple way to implement custom methods. So, for instance, if I wanted to put
our custom Dundee stir or the Geo hash method that we created before, there's no simple way to implement
it before. There's no simple way to do that because I just can't edit. I don't see the body
of the class anywhere in my source code. Right? So you could do it through monkey patching, but that's
not the case. Anyway, so then something interesting happened. So Python is now doing this whole
movement towards a system of typing that allows you to declare the types of variables
and function arguments and function return types and so on. And in Python 3.5,
they invented this thing called NameItTouple, typing NameItTouple, which is very similar to
the NameItTouple, the traditional NameItTouple, except that when you specify the NameItTouple
with the typing NameItTouple class, in that case it's a class, you can specify the types.
And there's actually two syntaxes, but this is the more interesting syntax that appeared
in Python 3.6. So in Python 3.5, the typing NameItTouple had a syntax that is similar to the
old NameItTouple, and in Python 3.6, they added syntax for variable declarations,
and that allowed this kind of notation. Okay? So basically this does everything that our, well,
except it doesn't have the, this has a nice wrapper, it has equality, it has a lot of features,
and I can also add methods. But there is a trick, because remember when I said that for
all of the history of Python until Python 3.6, anything that was declared at the class level
was a class attribute, but not anymore. Whenever you have a type annotation near a variable name
at the class level, this is interpreted by Python as an instance attribute.
So now that thing that was missing for many years in Python, we have it.
But unfortunately, my opinion as a teacher is a bit confusing, this scenario, because some things
that you always thought was true, like anything declared at the class body is a class attribute,
is no longer true. In fact, notice the situation here. This is a class attribute. You know why?
Because there is no type declaration. So that's really subtle, right?
I don't like that too much. I like the features, but I don't like to explain it,
which probably means there's something wrong with it. Right?
Yeah. Okay. So the other day, so I'm starting to dive deeply into the typing, the whole typing
infrastructure, because that was something that appeared after I wrote my book, and I'm working
on the second edition. And this whole subject is very complicated, and it's probably going to
take three chapters in the new edition to explain, and that's not going to be super detailed, just
give an overview. But one thing that is true about it, that I tweeted the other day is,
the good thing about typing in Python is that it's optional. Actually, the best thing about
typing in Python is that it's optional. And this is not just a joke. It means that you can add it
when you feel like it, but when you don't feel like it, just use a node, name it up, or don't declare
the types anywhere. You know? This is so you can ease into it by using it step by step. It's sort
of like TypeScript, and also the Dart language from Google. Those are examples of languages that
have this characteristic of optional typing. Okay? Anyway. Oops. What is happening here? Oh,
okay. I need to run this because I need to... I ran this, and now I'm going to run this, and it works.
And then the nice... Oh, here's an interesting thing. Now I'm going to try and do an assignment.
And look at what happens. I got an error because it's a tuple, remember? And tuples are immutable.
So once I created this coordinate, I can't assign to its attributes anymore.
And I cannot assign, interestingly enough, to... I can read the reference system, which is the
class variable there, the class attribute, but I cannot assign to it either. See?
See?
All right. So this is another option that we have now to create these kinds of data classes.
And now let's talk about the properly named data class. So data class is a brand new thing,
and it comes as a decorator, right? Yet another example of how inheritance is going out of fashion.
Because they chose to implement this as a decorator and not, like in this case here,
through inheritance. See?
And...
Anyway, so what is a class decorator? A class decorator is actually a function
that when the Python interpreter reads this class the first time, when it defines this class,
it's the... What happens when you execute a class statement? Everything in the body of the
class is defined, and this whole bundle of things becomes a class object, right?
This object which is a class. And this whole object is passed to the data class
decorator, which can then do stuff with it. And what the data class decorator mostly does is
it creates methods for you. So that the boilerplate is gone, right? Like the Dunder wrapper and others.
Now there's a different kind of syntax here. I could have
written this like this, like in the example of the name of the name of tuple. So this is a class
attribute. But if you want to specify the type of a class attribute, and in this case,
the class attribute is a class attribute, then you can specify the type of a class attribute.
It's more important because it's mutable. It can be updated, right? So in the other case,
it's not supported. I don't know why, but it's not super important because in a name of tuple,
this cannot be changed. So by reading the source code, you know what the type of this is, right?
Because it's a string here, and it will never change. But in this case, because by default,
data classes are mutable, what if I want to specify the type?
Then you have to use this notation here. And so you need to import from class var,
and then you see class var, and then within the square brackets, you see what the type is.
So this is the way of... So again, it becomes tricky to write the syntax because
this is a class attribute. This is an instance attribute.
But this is a class attribute.
Right? It's becoming a bit complicated.
Now, does this mean that with those type declarations, even in the case of the
name of tuple as well, does this mean that Python will do type checking for you?
It does not. And this is kind of weird. But the whole point of these annotations is to support
IDEs like PyCharm and others, and to support tools that you can use in the command line like MyPy.
Okay? So I can actually show an example here that I have, which is...
In order to show this example, I cannot use the Jupyter Notebook because I want to use MyPy to
show you. So in examples here, I have coordinates. See, I'm going to do...
So these are the coordinates of Sao Paulo, the city where I live, more or less.
Okay? And I'm going to run this.
See? And it shows the coordinates. Now, what if I write here...
Blah. Well, what happened was a type error because of some operation that I did. Right?
So there was no type check. You had a runtime check. But if I run MyPy...
So MyPy knows to read that. So in addition to the kinds of tools that we use to check the correctness
of the code and other linters, if you use MyPy in your toolchain, it will catch these errors
without running your program. That's the idea of the annotations. Okay. So the data class decorator,
I used it in the simplest way, but it's actually a function that you can pass a lot of arguments to
it. And I have this little table here that summarizes what the arguments are. So the first...
Most of them have to do with whether or not the decorator will generate methods for your class.
Okay? So by default, it generates a Dunder init, a Dunder wrapper, and a Dunder EQ.
If you want to be able to sort, for instance, collections of this type that you're creating,
you need to also pass this order, which by default is false. But if you set it to true,
then it will generate other methods that allow you to compare whether a certain thing is greater
than another or smaller or equal than another, things like that. The hash I won't be able to
comment. It's complicated, and I put it here. It has complex semantics and several caveats.
But the idea is that it has to do with implementing Dunder hash is one of the things
that you need to do to enable... To allow your objects to be hashable. And when they are hashable,
they can be put in sets and they can be used as keys in dictionaries. But this is a complicated
topic that we don't have time to cover here. And you can also say that it's frozen. By default,
it says false, but you can say frozen equals true, right? The asterisk in the beginning of the
declaration here means that if you're going to use any of these arguments, you need to prefix it
with the name of the keyword. Okay? So it doesn't matter the order. You have to spell out all the
names of the options. So if you want something that behaves like a tuple in the sense that it's
not mutable, you say frozen equals true. All right? Okay. Just to show another example of
a data class that's more complicated, this is a data class that represents a dublin core resource.
Dublin core is a standard in information sciences for describing media in general. Books, films,
recordings, pictures, whatever, paintings. And this here, I just created, I just instantiated the
card, the class, and I'm going to put the data about my book. So I'm creating a resource with all of these
values. All right? And then I'm going to, and if I ask to show it, it shows a nice wrapper that
is broken into several lines, but this would work as source code, right? Because when Python
sees an opening parenthesis, until that parenthesis closes, all the line breaks are ignored. They become
like spaces. The same thing happens with braces and square brackets. Right? So this actually is
valid syntax. But I'm going to show you, because this has two fields that are lists. The creator
field is called creators, is a list of strings. See? But I want to have a default value because I
want to be able to create a resource like this and then later fill it up. So I have the default list,
but I don't want to have a haunted resource that has ghost values floating around.
So how do you do that? Is by using this field function that comes from the data classes
module. So the field function, the most common use of it is this one, which is to
give a function that's going to be called by the data class to create the default value of every
new instance that's created when the default value is required. Right? So that the list is not shared
among the instances. Okay? And in the wrapper here, which I created because I wanted to be able to
display a nice, you know, wrapper with one argument per line here. So I hand rolled
this wrapper and you can see that I'm using the fields function, which is also from the data classes
module. And what that does is it lists the fields of the class for you. Right? So here I iterate over
the fields. So in the end, remember when I said at first that in Python terms, we call what the
Java people call fields, we call data attributes. Okay. That's true. But in the specific domain of
data classes, the things that are named with types are fields. So a field is a specific type
or a specific kind of data attribute, which has a type annotation. Okay.
Um, and the field function also takes a lot of arguments. If you look at the, so
Jupyter notebook has this shortcut like IPython does. You put a question mark and it shows the
help of the thing. So see it has a bunch of attributes or arguments that I don't have time to
explain, but, um, the main part, the most important one by far is the default factor.
The in it, which by default is true means that it's going, this, this field will be
an argument for the cost for the initializer for the other in it. And it's going to be assigned in
the dunder unit. Maybe you have a few that you don't want to be an argument for the
dunder unit. Then you set this in it to false and so on. Uh, the compare for instance,
by default is true, but if it's false means that that specific field will not be used
as a criteria for comparison of two instances. So this is a super quick overview of different
ways of doing data classes in Python. So we have the traditional name and tuple, and now we have the
more modern typing name and tuple, which allows you to create methods and, uh,
what requires you to do type annotations and data classes, which are, uh,
more flexible. Okay. So, all right. Now let's talk about classes.
Um, so one of the issues with the examples that we've seen so far is that
they're very data driven and also they're like standalone classes. And I wanted to show examples
of, of classes interacting. In this example here, I'm using, uh, UML to describe what we're going to
have. Uh, let me show what it does first. So actually I'm going to skip a little bit and then
we're going to come back. So the idea of this example is I have this budget, budget class.
Okay. Uh, whoops. I have this budget class, which I, it's for people, you know, you know, when you,
I used to go out camping a lot. Uh, and when we went, went camping, a bunch of people,
some people had to buy stuff before we went on the trip and people bought stuff with different, uh,
spent different amounts of money. So the idea of this is you stop, you start a budget by giving
the names of the people that are going to be on the trip. And then, uh, initially the total is zero.
There's a method called people that list the people that are on the trip. And then there's
a method called contributes that you call with the name of somebody that is on the trip and, and the
amount that they've spent. And then when you ask for the total, it gives you the total amount that
everybody has spent is a hundred here. And the most interesting part is the reports,
because the reports, if you run the reports method, it's going to tell you what was the
total, what is the individual share. And then it says, Charlie paid zero. His balance is
25 minus 25 and paid 10. Her balance is minus 15. Debbie paid 40. Her balance is 15. So she needs
to get 15 and Bob paid 50. He needs to get 25. Okay. So that's, that settles all the, uh, expenses.
All right. So this is what this class does, but it has to, the solution that I created has two
classes. A budget has several campers, right? And in UML, you have, uh,
these boxes here that represent a class, the name of the class.
These are attributes. The underlying ones are class attributes and the, without an airline,
instance attributes. And this bill and the box below is the methods. Again, there are methods
here. Budget apparently does not have instance attribute, but it actually has because this
notation here means that budget has an attribute called underscore campus, which has a bunch of
these instances. Okay. So we don't duplicate this name in there. Anyway, so this is the description
and now we are going to take a look at the, so, and what, what is, what does a camper do? So a camper,
you create a camper with a name and then you all, you, you invoke the pay method. So that adds to
the amount that that person has paid. And then there's a function called display,
which is a little bit complicated because I want to be able to create this tabulation at the end,
see where the columns are aligned here. So the, this, the, the logic to do the columns alignment
is in the display method here. So if I just display one person, it's like that. But if I use
display in the, in a, in a loop like this, I have the columns aligned and I'm going to show you how
that's done. Okay. So this example is in the repository right here. Camping. So it's pile B
examples, camping, and I have, I created three solutions, but I won't have time to show the one
class solution. The one class solution is just what it says. It has just one class budget.
The two class solution is the one that I'm talking about. It has the, the,
the camp, camper and the, and the budget classes.
Okay. So the camper has two class attributes. One is just a template that shows, that is used by the
display methods. Okay. So this template has a trick, which is this. You see that here
within these calibrations is the name of a, okay, here. Calibrations, name of a field,
colon, formatting. Okay. In this case, we have name of a field, colon, formatting,
but the formatting has another field inside. This allows me to parameterize the
this allows me to parameterize the
right justification. See this greater than sign here will do right alignment of the names.
And this is going to give the, this could be a constant number, but since it's a variable,
it's going to give me a variable with of the column. Okay. And the way I do this is I pass
as the name, then the self dot max name, then which although I am reading from the instance here
is actually a class attribute. So that's not a very good example of course. Sorry about that.
I should have written camper here, but it does work. You know, it's just not clear.
Okay. Here, this is better. Camper dot template. If you're going to talk, if you're going to
refer to a class attribute, use the class name. Makes it more readable. This also should say,
should say camper dot max name. So what happens here is every time that I create a new camper,
I update the max name, max name land when I see a name that is bigger than the, the
all the others that I've seen so far. So this class has a memory of the width of the
longest name. Okay. It's not a super smart solution. If I had a bunch of these, I would
have this thing growing forever. So it works for a command line script that wakes up and dies,
but for a, a system on the web or a server side long running process, this would not be a good
solution. It's just an example that I wanted to use to talk about because most of the
class attributes that we've seen so far were static and this one is updated. I wanted to show that.
And like I said before, if you need to update a class attribute, you need to put the name of
the class. That's for sure. Because if you don't, if you put self here, then this would be a bug,
right? Because it would create the attribute in the instance. So there's this asymmetry again.
I can be, I, I, this can work by reading from self max max name land, but if I was writing
to self max name land, then it wouldn't work. It would be a bug. All right. Well, so anyway,
and the budget class has a bunch of, of matters. But what I want to, I want to talk about some
details. I don't want to describe the whole text of the class, but what I want to talk about is
the fact that this class here has an attribute that I called underscore campers. All right.
And so this is a convention. Python doesn't have a way of declaring something private explicitly,
but many Python programmers, this is a situation, this is something where if you ask around at PyCon,
you're going to hear people with one, a lot of people would have one opinion.
There are a lot of people who have another opinion. The two opinions are, oh, private method,
private, private fields. I just use this one underscore, which is a convention. It's just a
convention. Anybody can write to this easily. Okay. The other alternative would be to write
two underscores. And I have an example here in the, in the number four classes
of this notebook that talks about that. So, so I have a class here called black box.
Let's say that the black box is something that I used to, it's a physical black box that I have that
I store things in it. And anyway, so it has a top and a bottom, but notice that the top is with,
the top attribute is written with one underscore and the bottom is written with two underscores.
Right. And I put, so when I create this black box, I put gold in the top and diamonds in the bottom.
Okay. So if I do that, I can read the top easily. Right. But if I ask whether there is a bottom
attribute, it says false. If I, if I ask about the top, it says true. Actually.
So this function asks, does this object have that attribute? And it says true, but it says
that it doesn't have a bottom, even though it's written right here. But the thing is with two
underscores, you're telling Python, please hide this a little bit. And the way Python hides it is
by prepending the name of the class with one underscore in front of the name of the
attribute that is preceded by two underscores. So this is what, this is the best we can do in
terms of private attributes, okay, in Python. However, a lot of people that are super smart
and that I respect a lot hate this. They think this is just too private.
My main reason for not using this on a daily basis
is that I think it's ugly. And I think it's, this one is good enough. You know. But anyway,
this is, so it's easy to bypass, right? So if I write this code here, I am reading the diamonds
from the bottom, but I'm doing it on purpose, right? It's not an accident. I am going a little
bit out of my way to read that, right? So the main idea of that is like a safety switch like this,
or a safety cover in a switch, you know? This won't prevent a terrorist from
hitting the switch, right? But it does prevent somebody from doing it by accident. That's the
idea of the private. And by the way, it's the same thing in Java, you know? Because through
reflection, the reflection API in Java also lets you go and access the private fields,
except it's more code. But it's the same situation in Java in terms of, it's not really
a security feature, it's a safety feature, okay? So like I said, Pythonists are divided about that.
And another thing that is related is some people advocate that you just use public attributes
everywhere, no underscores at all. And if one day you need to protect it, then you turn it into a
property. It's another option. And another thing that is, I think, a good point is that
excessive use of getters and statuses is actually weak encapsulation, right? Because if you have a
lot of getters and statuses, that means you're exposing the state without any controls, right?
So that's about, so the camping budget allowed us to see some techniques about using a
class attribute that we updated. We also saw the interaction between two classes
where the API, the end user API of this, it only presents the budget because the camper is created.
It's used internally here. So the end user doesn't need to know that there is a camper class,
only the budget class. In fact, I could write this with an underscore in front.
Just to tell people that the camper is part of my implementation, but it's just a convention.
However, in this case, it's not just a convention because there's a difference,
because this is an attribute of the module, right? The class is an attribute of the module, right?
The top level. If I import star from a module, Python does not import things that start with
one underscore by default. So it becomes a little bit more private, but not really.
That's just the detail. Anyway, I don't do that often. Okay.
Now let's go to the fifth thing. Okay. Now finally let's talk about inheritance.
And because of all the discussions about inheritance, I decided to go
pick an example from the book of the people who invented the name, the term object oriented,
right? So this specification says financial history, class protocol,
the word protocol is used in small talk, but also in Python and some other languages as a
synonym of an interface. Okay. So this is the description of the interface of the class.
It says the methods and it explains what each method does. This is from that book.
This example is a running example in that book. So this text is actually in the, in the,
the, like the first page of the book.
And this is our UML diagram. And in this diagram, you see financial history is the one that is
here, although here it's with Python syntax, not small talk syntax, the names. And this arrow here
with the open triangle is inheritance, right? So contrast this with this.
This is composition, right? So it says that a budget has one or more campers in it.
And this is inheritance. This inherits from that. Okay. And
so let's take a look at the, the example that is in the repository.
So financial history is, oh, let's, let's take a look at the readme because the readme has some
doc tests. So this is like a high level description of the API, but this is the
demonstration is more interesting. So financial history is a class where you, it would like,
would be like a super simple implementation of a bank account. So you start the financial history
with a certain amount. And then when you display it, it shows the balance, the wrapper shows the
balance. And I spend it and I see that it's the value is going from the balance. Oh, this is
actually okay. We can't see that it's a decimal, but we're going to see soon.
Anyway, I'm formatting the number, the balance.
And now I can receive. So I say, receive the amount from that source.
So I want, I want a thousand and one, a thousand dollars and one cents at Molly's game. And
I found $10 on the street. So this is my balance and I spend the money. And now, and I, so I have
methods that allow me to filter. So I can ask, what's the amount spent for a meal? And it says
this. So this value is a decimal. See, this is what I was formatting over there when I did
the balance. So this is a decimal and I'm going to talk about why it is a decimal.
And I can check the amount spent for travel is zero. I didn't travel. All right.
So let's take a look at the implementation.
Okay. So the interesting thing about this class is besides being a classic example from the history
of object oriented programming is that in Python, I decided to use decimals to deal with money,
which is a best practice because I don't know if you've seen this, but I'm going to show
one problem with.
So I have X equals one, X equals 1.1. Okay.
Okay. Good enough. Now let's print X.
All right. Now let's print
X with lots of decimal cases. Oops. Sorry.
Oops. So even a simple number like 1.1 as a float has an infinite number of decimal cases.
Oops. So even a simple number like 1.1 as a float has an imprecision. Right? So the problem is
every machine, this is not a Python bug. If we call this a bug, it's a bug that exists in every
machine that implements the IEEE 7.2 standard for floating point arithmetic. This standard
converts decimal numbers into a binary representation where one tenth is a repeating
bit, not a repeating decimal, but a repeating bit or a repeating bit pattern. And, you know,
just like when you divide one by three, you get a repeating decimal. When you divide
one by 10 and represent that as a floating point number, you get a repeating bit.
So there is no way to show these things with precision or not to show, but to represent them
in precision with the way the machine architectures are implemented today. So the solution is to use
float, I mean decimal, the decimal class, which is what I used here. Okay. So that's why, for instance,
where is the, so decimal is like this, for instance, if I do,
it's kind of tricky, but let me show you. So
if I do,
so fraction is another Python class, so I can do
tenth equal to such,
infinite fractions
Lind guides
was fraction 110. So the issue here, let me show you, is if I try to build a decimal
from this X, I will have the same problem. Take a look. See? Because X is a float, so
it is hiding this error. But if I do like this, I create a fraction, for example, then
I don't have the problem. Oops. I thought I could do that. That's weird. Well, okay.
So here's the thing. I can do this. Sorry about the detour into the fraction. But if
I convert the float into a string, then Python does a trick in order to not scare people
when you do print, which is although internally 1.1 is really this weird number here, when
you the the the the under stir of floats has an algorithm that goes like this. Okay, so
this is the float that we have in the machine. This is its value. But are there other floats
with less digits that result in the same periodic repetition? If yes, then it's going to pick
the shortest string that does that. Does that make sense? So this is something that
was introduced, I think, in Python 3.3. And now if you don't care about revealing this
imprecision, you can always create decimals by converting the float into a string, and
then you have a decimal that looks like what you wanted. Okay? So anyway, this is the trick
that I'm using. Now, when I created this example, I want to tell you that my first idea was,
okay, I wish the decimal class did that for me. When I passed a float that it converted
to string and then did the decimal from the string to lose the error of the float. But
then I actually talked about that on Twitter with some people even with who answered my
questions about that, and they said, no, no, no, the decimal must be utterly precise. So
if you're constructing a decimal from a float which is imprecise, the decimal will be as
imprecise, will be precisely as imprecise as the float that you gave it. All right?
This is how they want it. And I said, okay, I'm going to create a class called newDecimal
that inherits from decimal and that looks at the argument to the constructor and converts
it to a string before, okay? So that was my first idea. And this is another example of
why often inheritance gives you more trouble than it's worth. My first idea was, okay,
I'm going to create a more perfect decimal, the new decimal, okay, as a subclass. The
problem is then I had an init that was like this function here, okay? The init would take
the argument, the value, and see if it's a float, then it would use the wrapper to convert
into a string and then would build, you know? So if I gave it an integer or a string, it
wouldn't do anything with it, but if it was a float, it would convert with this. This
was the logic that was inside my Dunder init. However, it didn't work. My subclass of decimal
with a Dunder init with this logic didn't work. You know why? Because the decimal is
immutable. So when I get the self that was constructed by the Python machinery, the value
is already set. I cannot override that value. So that meant that I had to go under or deeper
and implement another method that we seldom use on a daily basis, which is the Dunder
new method. Dunder new in Python is the actual constructor, the method that builds an object
and returns it. Dunder init doesn't return anything. It just initializes attributes,
right? But then when I created Dunder new, it behaved in a weird way because I needed
to use the decimal to construct the class, the instance. So I had my own class, but when
I instantiated it, the instances were all decimals and not new decimals, which was kind
of weird. So I said, you know what? I don't need inheritance. What I need is a function.
This is an advice. Think hard if a function isn't better than the class that you're thinking
about. Maybe it's all you need, a function. So this is what the new function, the new
decimal function does. So everywhere in this code here, I'm using new decimal to start
the balance. The incomes and expenses are default dicts. Default dicts is a special
subclass of dicts in Python that you pass, when you build a default dict, you give it
a function or a class that is going to be used to create instances when no such instance
exists. What does that mean, for instance? The expenses is a dictionary. But if there
is no travel expenses and I ask for travel expenses, this will immediately create a decimal
and return that to me. This is what the default dict does. So it's a dict that when what you're
looking for doesn't exist, it will create at once that thing and return it to you. So
this is the default dict. This is a default dict that is going to be by default returning
zero decimals. The initial balance is also a decimal because of my new decimal function.
So everything here is in decimals. So this is just an example of doing proper Python
coding using money, which is using decimal instead of floats to avoid those accumulation
errors that happen when people insist on spending fractures of 10, like 0.1. Anyway, yeah, so
the rest of the class is not very interesting. Another thing that I did here is I decided
to have the balance as a property. So this decorator here means that I can read the balance
as if it was a data attribute. And you can see that in the example. That's in the history.
See here, I'm not invoking the balance as a method. There's no parenthesis here. I'm
just reading it. And the way to do that is by declaring something a property. There's
more to properties than this, but I am afraid I don't have time to talk about that. Oh,
sorry, this is another example. So this becomes a read-only property. It's basically a method.
It's a getter. But because it's decorated with a property, I invoke it. I access it
as if it was a data attribute and not a method. I don't use the parenthesis. Okay? Another
thing that is interesting to talk about is that although it is a little bit of work using
decimal, it's less work than it would be in some other languages that don't have operator
overloading. Python has operator overloading, so that means that this works. I don't have
to call a method on the decimal. I just use an operator. In Go, for instance, there's
no operator overloading. In Java, there's no operator overloading. So you wouldn't be
able to use this short notation to add and subtract. You would have to have a method
like dot subtract dot add and so on. Anyway, so I wanted to show an example that is a classic
example, but I also implemented it using decimals, which makes it a little bit more interesting.
And this is also an example of subclassing, because in the book they give an example which
is the deductible history. So the idea is that the data is not a method, but a method
that makes it possible to make a donation. So in this case, in this class, you can do
expenses that are partially or totally deductible. So in this example here, I'm saying that I'm
spending 600 for a course, but the course is I can deduct $150 of that course, of that
course. I can also make a donation, and in this case there's another method called spend
deductible that is to deduct the full amount. And then I can see what are the total deductions,
400, because I spent this course cost 600, but I deducted 150, and this course cost $150,
or this donation was 250, no, yeah, donation 250, so far my deductions are 400. So this
is how it works. It has some different methods that allow you to expand with deductions,
and this is the code. The code is interesting because it shows an example of inheritance,
which requires the use of the super function. So the thing is, when you create a subclass,
you need sometimes to invoke a method of the superclass to do stuff. For instance, my dunder
in it. So a deductible history is basically a financial history with the deductions, and
this extra attribute, it is the deductions, which is just a decimal number, and this spend
method that now has an extra optional argument, and the spend deductible, which is a new method,
and the deductions, which is a new property. So in order to leverage the machinery of
financial history, I have to be explicit about this. For instance, in the initializer, I
invoke the initializer of the superclass. And by the way, this is different from the
way it works in Java. In Java, the constructor automatically invokes the constructor of
the superclass. In Python, you have to be explicit about that. And there's two ways
of being explicit about that. I could write here financial history dot in it, but then
I'm calling the method on the class, and I would have to pass self as an explicit argument,
which is ugly. And also, Python supports multi-point hash, which is a method that is used to pass
inheritance. It doesn't mean it's a good idea, but it does support it. And it can be
used, you know, it's used very judiciously, can be useful. It's not like the example that
I used to have, for instance. I was so ashamed when I found that. So I had a, like remember,
I said I had animals, and there was mammals and dogs, and there's several kinds of dogs,
like Labrador. And then there was the San Bernard. You know the San Bernard? That legend
says in Switzerland they use San Bernard dogs patrolling the roads, and they have like a
little vat of cognac. So my San Bernard, I swear to God, inherited from dog and vat.
That's just stupid, okay? What it should be is a subclass of dog, the San Bernard, that
has a composition that includes this component, which is a vat. Okay? This is what it should
be. Not an example of multiple inheritance. But anyway, I wanted to show it. I don't want
to show it anymore. Multiple inheritance most of the time is bad. But anyway, you never
know, right? Maybe you don't like multiple inheritance, somebody else in your team, somebody
in the future, something happens in the hierarchy that you don't control. Maybe it's a third-party
library that you're subclassing from, and you don't control that code. In order for
your methods to cooperate correctly with a hierarchy that has multiple inheritance,
you have to use super, okay? This is what super does. So the super function is a magical
function that returns a proxy that by default does what it needs to do in order for your
dunder init to resolve up in the hierarchy. So what I'm doing here is my initializer is
delegating the initialization up the chain of inheritance. And by using super, this is
going to work predictably, as predictably as possible, in a multiple inheritance situation,
okay? On the other hand, if I hard-coded the name of the class here, then maybe I could
have problems if it turned out that the hierarchy became a multiple inheritance hierarchy later.
So the syntax improved in Python 3 is still ugly, in my opinion. Calling this function
like this, it returns this proxy object that then you invoke methods on it. But in Python
2, it was worse because you had to pass two parameters here. And now Python is smart enough
to introspect the frame where this is happening in the code and getting that information that
defaults for you, okay? So the dunder init delegates to the hierarchy and then initializes
the deductions, which is this new class, this new instance attribute of my deductible history
class. The spend also uses the same mechanism. The spend calls super spend, so it uses the
mechanics of the spend and the super class, and then if there was a value deducting, it
adds to the deductions, okay? So this is an example of a method that is not the initializer,
but just any other regular method, delegating some of its functionality to the super class.
And the last example here is an example of one method of the instance delegating to another
method of the same instance. See? The spend deductible is implemented by calling spend
repeating the amount here, right? Because the idea of the spend deductible is that it
records the expense with full deduction. So it just repeats the amount and uses that one.
So what I want you to notice here is the use of super and self in this delegation. Delegation
is a fancy word that object-oriented programmers use to say when one object tells the other
object to do something, right? And in this example here, this is called a self-delegation.
The object is telling itself to do something, right? And this is a super delegation. Anyway,
so it's an example of inheritance. However, although it's like I said, it's a classic
example from a very important book in the history of object-oriented programming, nowadays
it's not considered an excellent example. Many authors don't recommend anymore to do
inheritance of concrete classes. Okay? So what we have here is financial history is
a concrete class that can create instances of it, and the deductible history is another
concrete class. This creates complications that because both classes have inner states
so they can step on each other's toes. You may forget to invoke super. It's actually,
it would be a good exercise to rewrite this just to feel the difference using composition,
you know? So deductible history is a class that has a financial history inside it. And
then it wouldn't need to use super anywhere. It wouldn't need to do self-delegation. You
would write a little bit more code, but it would be clearer, and it would be more flexible.
The problem with, one of the problems with inheritance of concrete classes is that it's
a very tight coupling between the subclass and the superclass. And that's something that
you want to avoid to make systems easier to evolve, this kind of tight coupling. Okay?
But I needed to show you this because I needed to show examples of super. When you notice,
when you are inheriting from an abstract class, you don't have these problems because
there's no implementation for you to leverage. You need to implement everything mostly. This
happens really when you're, the need of super appears when you're doing inheritance from
concrete, from one concrete class to another. So, you know, super is a class that has a
super. Okay. So, this was, okay, this is the inheritance, the classic example. We've seen
that. Okay. Another, so this is a series of examples that talk about different ways of
doing inheritance. Right? So, each of them will lead you to a part in the examples over
there. So, the bingo, bingo is a very simple class that emulates a bingo cage. So, the
idea is you fill it with balls, this cage, and then you call pop and it gives out a random
ball. Right? So, that's the mechanics of the bingo cage. You put a sequence of balls,
or a collection of items in it, and it's, each time you call pop, it will give you one
of those items picked at random. There's also a dunderland so that you can ask how many
items are in the cage, which also allows you, because the bool, the bool built-in function
of Python uses as a fallback dunderland to determine whether something is true or false.
So you can do this code. While cage, print next item, else no more items available. So
this will be, this will be a loop that will repeat until the cage is exhausted. Okay?
Anyway, the implementation of this is super simple, but, where is it? Yeah, this is it.
I use that trick that I told you about before, which is making a list, because I'm going
to, otherwise, every time I do pop, I'm going to be throwing away something that belongs
to my user. So this is a very simple implementation. Now the fun part of this is with the other
examples here. The other examples here, which are in the tombola directory. So tombola is
an Italian or Portuguese word, which is a synonym of bingo. And this directory here,
tombola, has several implementations of different bingo machines, and it has a single test suite
that works for all of them to prove that they're all, that they all behave the same, even though
the implementations are very different. And this tombola.py is the ABC. So this is how
you declare an interface in Python. If you want to formalize an interface in Python,
what you do is you, you import ABC and the ABC package, there is an ABC, uppercase ABC
class, which when you inherit from it, it means that your class is an abstract class.
And in an abstract class, you can use these decorators, ABC abstract method, to say that
you expect the subclasses to implement that. Okay? So this is the, this is the, this is
the, that you expect the subclasses to implement that. Okay? So I'm saying here that a tombola
machine has to have a load, a pick, and a loaded, and an inspect module, methods. The
interesting thing here is that load and pick are abstract methods, so they only have a
doc string, there's no body, but the loaded and the inspect are concrete methods. So this
is something that Python allows you to do. An abstract class can have concrete methods
as long as they depend only on the abstract methods, because then the subclasses will
complement the abstract methods and the concrete methods from the abstract class will be able
to leverage them. So, for instance, the loaded, which should tell you whether there is at
least one item or not, will call inspect and convert the result into a Boolean. The inspect,
this is very strange, okay, but I was just, my idea was to illustrate a concrete method
in an abstract class. So the inspect returns a sorted tuple with the items currently inside,
but I can only, I cannot look at the implementation, right? I don't know what the implementation
is. This is an abstract class. What I know for sure is that the implementation will have
a pick method, right? And the pick method will raise lookup error when the instance
is empty. This is written in the documentation. It's the contract. It's in English, not in
Python, okay? Anyway, so my inspect relies on that. So what it does is it creates a list
called items and then goes into this loop where it's calling pick and append into the
list until it gets a lookup error, then it breaks, and now it has emptied the machine.
And now it loads it again with the items and returns the tuple of the items, okay? So the
way that inspect works, since it's limited to rely on the abstract method, is by invoking
pick until it exhausts everything and then puts it in, it loads back the things in the
machine, right? So that's how it works. So this is an abstract class. And here there
are other examples that I use it, where I use it, okay? So the lotto, for instance,
is a lottery blower inherits from Tombola, I initialize load and pick, and I have a better
implementation of load and inspect, okay? Because I know the implementation, so I can
override these methods with a better implementation. But you can also have something like the drum
implementation which just implements load and pick, and it doesn't have the inspect
and so on, but it will inherit from the Tombola. Anyway, all of these examples, if you look
at them later, you will see that they have very different implementations, but they work
the same. But one interesting example, I think the most interesting example is this one here,
TomboList. So TomboList is interesting because it, let me hide that line for a moment, it
inherits from list, okay? Not a very good idea. All the others use lists inside with
composition, okay? But I wanted to show that it's also possible to create a device like
that that inherits from lists, so it uses self-pop because it inherits the pop method
from lists and so on. But the interesting thing is, okay, so if I inherit it from lists,
how do I tell people that this is actually a TomboList? And the way to do it is because
TomboList is an abstract class, I can call, I can use it, abstract classes in Python have
a function called .register, which when you use as a decorator, it registers this list
as a subclass of that class even though it doesn't inherit from it. This is what is called
a virtual subclass, okay? So a virtual subclass is a class that doesn't really inherit from
the other one, but you declare that it works like that one, that it fulfills that interface,
okay? Does that make sense, people? Yeah? So this is an option that you have, and you
can even do that with third-party codes because there's this other syntax here. You know,
if I imported something from somebody else's module and I want to say, okay, this thing
that somebody else implemented actually implemented this interface that I need to make, and I
need to make this fact explicit so I can call my abc.register, the other person's class,
and it's, what I'm doing here is I'm telling Python, trust me, this thing works like that
thing. It works as if it was a subclass of that thing, okay? But now when I do that,
there's no inheritance involved, so I really need to implement everything, even the concrete
methods that the other classes are inheriting. Okay, so this set of examples have to do with
inheriting from an abc. So this is what I was showing, variations on a bingo machine,
different examples that implement the same interface via different means, okay?
All right, so what are the takeaways of this section? The takeaways are, you know, you
know, I was kind of saying that inheritance has a bad reputation, but in fact, one of
the things, I found a quote by Alan Kay when I was writing my book, but I forgot to put
it here, but one of the things that Alan Kay says is that they think, that he thinks
inheritance was a mistake because it does too many things at once, right? So I'm saying
that inheritance has a bad reputation, but in fact, one of the things, I found a quote
by Alan Kay says is that he thinks inheritance was a mistake because it does too many things
at once, right? And there's a book that I'm going to show you in the next section called
Introduction to Object-Oriented Programming by Tim Budd. I have a picture of it in the
next section. So in that book, the author actually lists ten reasons why you would inherit,
or why people inherit stuff. One of the reasons is classification, you know, like I was saying
before, like hierarchies that look like taxonomies. This is considered wrong in most situations
these days. So the author lists ten reasons for why people inherit stuff, or why people
subclass. But the two main reasons that many authors talk about are interface inheritance
and implementation inheritance. So the idea is, are you inheriting because you want to
say that this fulfills that interface, or are you inheriting because you want to leverage
the implementation of the other thing and do your own stuff. Java has this very clear,
this distinction very clear, right? When you say extends or implements, right? So extends
means implementation inheritance, and implements means interface inheritance, right? However,
C++ and Python don't have this distinction very clear, and a lot of times when you inherit,
you're inheriting. And here's the thing, when you're doing implementation inheritance,
even though you're maybe just interested in the implementation, you're also inheriting
the interface, right? And maybe that's not what you want, but that's what you want. So
that is what you're going to get. So a classic example that people talk about is where squares,
a square class should inherit from rectangle or vice versa. And if I, one way to think
about it is that the square is simpler than the rectangle. So if I'm thinking about implementation,
I don't want my millions of squares to have the overhead of rectangles when they are simpler.
They have only ones with its attributes, right? But on the other hand, you can say that okay,
but all squares are rectangles. But if I do that, that also means that maybe there are
methods in rectangle that I'm inheriting and that I shouldn't. For instance, maybe
I have a stretch method that doubles the width without increasing the height of the rectangle,
and that would not make sense in the square. But if I inherit, I will inherit that too.
So what do I do with it? Oh, okay, so you can implement it and raise an exception. You
cannot stretch it, right? So it's a complicated situation, but you have to be, it's a very
simple problem. This is an important thing. This is a hint. I don't, if this is new to
you guys or to some of you, I put it here because I think it's something that you need
to pay attention and go after and understand. But it's important to understand the difference
between interface inheritance and implementation inheritance because the bad things that I
said about inheritance are mostly about implementation inheritance. Interface inheritance is not
a big problem. So Python actually has, for instance, a huge... So this here doesn't look
like a hierarchy, but it is because you can see that it says here, this inherits from
that and so on. So this is a diagram of abstract classes that the Python library brings. So
for instance, you can see that a sequence inherits from revertible and collection,
collection inherits from size and container. This is actually examples also of multiple
inheritance. But multiple inheritance is usually not a problem when you're doing interface
inheritance. And in fact, Java allows it, right? You can implement lots of interfaces,
but you can only extend one implementation. And then you have a mutable sequence which
inherits from sequence, sequence C. So this is a tree of collections in Python that is
useful to study to understand what is available and how the collections in Python are organized.
So the point is that... And like I said, for instance, when I mentioned Julia before, the
Julia language allows interface inheritance arbitrarily deep, but it doesn't allow implementation
inheritance. You cannot subclass concrete classes in Julia. Yeah, I already said that. I've
already inherited from concrete classes. Oh, here's the thing. Butynes, I put one example
here where I implemented TomboList as a subclass of list. Okay? This example works because
the things that I do with the list are not complicated. But there is a problem that the
built-in objects in Python which are written in C, they don't always call... When you subclass
one of those, they don't always call your methods as they should. In terms of the C++
world is what they call their... The implementations in C of these objects have non-virtual methods
which are hard-coded to do something. So one example of this is, for instance, let's say
I have... I want to create a list that only allows numbers in the list. Okay? So what
I'm going to do is I'm going to override the method append to make sure that whatever
is being appended is a number. And I also want to override the dunder set item which
is the one that when I assign to a position using square brackets, it's also going to
do that. But then there's a method called extend, right? Which you call to... You can
append a bunch of items at once. And if you think you can rely on the C implementation
to call your own append repeatedly in the extend implementation, it's not going to do
that. Right? So this is a tricky thing. And that's why in the collections page that I
just was showing to you, there is a user list, a user string, and a user dict class. These
are the ones that you should subclass if you want to have your own custom list, your own
custom dict or your own custom string. Okay? And it's interesting if you take a look at
the code of these classes, they are done with composition. So the user dict actually
has a real dict inside of it. But it implements all the methods to do delegation and so it
makes sure that everything goes through those methods that are written in Python. And that
advice from the Gang of Four that I already mentioned, favor object composition over class
inheritance. And we got a sign that we have five minutes and that's good because now we
can go to the big ideas. All right. So big ideas. So I had a lot of fun going back to
the origins of these ideas to give... To think about an introduction to this subject and
so one of the things that I found was an email from Alan Kay who was the leader of
the project that created Smalltalk. This guy, Stefan Ram, asked him, what does object-oriented
programming mean to you? And he says, OOP to me means only messaging, local retention,
and protection, and hiding of state process, and extreme late binding of all things. It
can be done in Smalltalk and Lisp. There are possibly other systems in which this is possible,
but I'm not aware of them. So it's interesting because inheritance is not here. Messaging
is basically method calls. And there's another... Local retention and protection of health and
hiding of state processes, encapsulation. Right? Extreme late binding is doing that
thing that I just told you that the Python built-ins don't do correctly, which is to
respect the inheritance hierarchy when method delegates to the other and go to the proper
level in the inheritance hierarchy to resolve that. This is what is called late binding.
The problem with the implementation of Lists and Gicton string in Python is that it's
early binding, so some of the methods in there are hard-coded to delegate to others in C.
Another thing that I found is a message by... Oh, recently there was an interview, very
interesting interview with... I don't know if you remember, but I was in a meeting with
Joe Armstrong, the inventor of Erlang, died last week. And Erlang is a language that is
totally based... It's not an object-oriented language, but it's totally based on the idea
of multiple processes talking and exchanging messages. So although it's a functional programming
language, it goes closer to the core idea of what Alan Kay now defines as object-oriented
than Python and Java and so on. There was an interview that was great. Joe Armstrong
interviewed Alan Kay. I really recommend that you look it up on YouTube. And the last thing
that I wanted to share with you that was a result of this research that I was doing,
I already have a bunch, I have like, I don't know, two yards of object-oriented programming
books in my office that I bought over the last 30 years. But this one is a new one for
me. It's not new, it's from 2003, but it's super interesting. I don't know why I never
stumbled on it. So it's called An Introduction to Object-Oriented Programming by this professor
Timothy Budd, who teaches at, I think, Oregon State. And what is great about this book is
it's the only book that covers general topics in object-oriented programming with a very
good depth and that does it with several languages. It's not focused on a single language. The
book actually has examples in all of these languages. So it's really interesting to really
understand object-oriented programming, the paradigm in general, as opposed to particulars
of this or that implementation. And one of the great things, I want to finish with this,
one of the great things about this book is that I found a super elegant solution to the
eight queens problem, which is a classic problem that Dykstra created to demonstrate
backtracking. He didn't create it. The problem existed since the 19th century. The idea of
how do you place eight queens on a chessboard so that none of them attacks each other. And
that's super hard to do, actually. If you want to try it, I recommend starting with
four. There's no solution for two or three. With four, there's basically one solution.
And you can find it in a few minutes. With eight, I don't know. If you're serving time,
that may be a good pastime because it's... Anyway, but what is beautiful about this solution
is because when I thought about it, okay, so object-oriented eight queens, how would
I think about that? And the way I would do is, okay, so I'm going to have objects that
represent the queens, and then there's an object called the player that is going to
move the queens. And then I implement Dykstra's algorithm in the head, so to speak, of this
player, right? Well, this is an anti-pattern of object-oriented programming called, you
know what it's called? The God class. It's when all the logic of a system resides in
a class that just moves the others as pawns. So the nice solution of this, the nice idea
of this example, and I wanted to show you this because this is an example that for me
really summarizes what object-oriented is all about, is that you have this queen class,
okay? There's a problem with the... So the queens, the idea is that the queens communicate,
so each queen will collaborate with a neighbor, and this will work recursively. So this is
a solution. So when the last queen found a solution, that means that everybody else
found solutions as well. The first piece of the solution, the first queen in one of the
implementations here has a lot of ifs, because, oh no, if I am on the edge of the... I don't
have, you know, if my neighbor is none or whatever, this kind of thing. But this solution
here has a special piece called the guard, and if you look at the API of the queen, it
has can attack, advance, find solution, locate. The guard has three of those methods implemented,
and for advance it always returns false, meaning I can't advance. Can attack false, meaning
I can't attack, and locate, meaning this would be to return a list of the positions of everybody
else, but I'm the... like the sentinel, so they start with an empty list. And the queens,
so for instance, when a queen... the queens are in a position, each in a row, and they
move until they find a place where they cannot be attacked. If they can't find a place where
they cannot be attacked, then they will ask the neighbor to move again. So this is basically
how it works. And the main program is this. So it creates a guard, this is the figure,
and then for each row of the board it creates a queen passing the number of columns so it
knows how to move, the number of the queen, and the figure, which initially is the guard,
but in the next iteration is going to be another queen. And then so it creates a queen and
asks the queen to find a solution. If any of them at this stage say not found, that
means there's no solution. The first one is easy, right? The first one anywhere that it
rests, it's okay. The second one, the first position will be attacked by the first one,
second position also, third position, no, it's fine, okay. So it rests there. And the
third one and so on. So the great thing about this is an example is that it goes back to
the idea of another of the visions of Alan Kay was that an object-oriented system is
an autonomous system, is a system of autonomous objects, sort of like cells in the body. Each
one, each cell goes about doing its own thing, but they also collaborate. And the solution
of the problem is, it's difficult to understand the algorithm, but it's elegant because it's
very object-oriented in this sense that the queens collaborate to find the solution and
there's no god class. Anyway, so this was a great finding when I was doing research
for this workshop to discover this book. I learned a lot reading it. And this is basically
it. And if you can please fill the survey, we will be very happy. And I'll be around
the next days. I also have cards here if you want to contact me. I do have, there was
another lab that we didn't have time to do. If you want to do the lab as homework, you
can write to me. There's my email here. And I will help you do your homework if you want.
And that's it. Thank you very much, folks.