Okay. Thanks for coming to this tutorial. Python by immersion at PyCon 2019. The survey
link is here. Please fill it out afterwards. And the Jupyter Notebook link is there. It's
a set of Jupyter Notebooks. I'll be running them individually because the one that has
all the Jupyter Notebooks combined is really big and slow. I'm going to give you lots of
information in three hours. You're not going to understand all of it. You're not going
to remember all of it. You might start to feel bad because I'm going so fast and think
that I should slow down. But my goal is, my thinking is, I would like learning a language
by immersion. I'm just going to show you lots of things. And my theory is, and I hope this
is true for you, is that in a few weeks or a couple months when you're doing something
and you go, oh, yeah, I wonder if there's a function that, there's got to be a function
that does and then you'll be thinking of some problem you're trying to solve. And the reason
you'll know that is because you saw it and kind of got a sense for the language today
in over a thousand lines of Python code that I'm going to show you. Okay? So this is a
broad overview. Don't write down the details. They're in the notebook. You can look at them.
The pattern is I will show you. I'll lecture and demonstrate some of the code and talk
about some things and then I'll let you do some exercises. Most of you won't finish the
exercises. I will stop and move on when maybe half of you have finished in general. And
you can go back and look at them. But I'm not just going to skip past. I'll actually
go through the exercises and show you what to look for. When you're doing the exercises,
you'll find that the ones later on, they sort of ramp up sometimes in complexity and difficulty
because I want everyone to sort of, even those who are really fast with that, to still be
engaged and not just sit there twiddling their thumbs. When you do the exercises, and I'll
remind you of this later, don't just hit shift enter to see what it does. The point is, you
know, I want to help you learn to think about how Python is working. Because if you understand
that layer, then where you're working in Python, whenever you're working in any layer of abstraction,
understanding what's going on sort of the layer below is really helpful. You know, if
you're riding a bike and you've done your own maintenance on it, it's just going to
work better. Same for other, you know, cars, et cetera. I'm running Python 3.6. If you're
running 2.7, you'll see a few weird things. I think that's all. Oh, and the last thing
is I will, the first 10 to 15 minutes, some of you will, might want to leave because it's
going so slow and it's so boring and you already know it. It's going to get faster, okay? And
I do that first part really slow intentionally because I want to, especially those of you
coming from a different language, I want to change your way of thinking about how Python
works from what it probably is even if you don't know it, or at least it may be. All
right, so let's get started with the actual stuff, the actual content here. So, objects,
let's just first see what version I'm running, Anaconda 368. Okay, so here's the first really
slow boring part. What happens when you type one, hit the one on your keyboard and then
hit shift enter in Jupyter Notebook or JupyterLab or you hit enter at the REPL, the read, eval,
print loop, which guess what it does? It reads what you typed, it eval, it evaluates it,
it prints it out for you, the value of the expression, and it does that over and over
again. That's why it's called the read, eval, print loop. It's the REPL. So, when you hit
type one and hit enter, what happens is Python, and I'm going to show you this picture over
here. Python goes over here in memory, and I'll sort of use this side of the room. This
is like memory where Python has all its objects. It goes off here and it allocates a chunk
of memory and it, well first of all, it parses that and says, oh, okay, I know what that
is. That's an integer literal, meaning it represents an integer and it's literally,
it's typed as an integer. It goes off and either finds or creates an object that represents
the integer one. I put a hundred here, but the point is it represents an integer, right?
And that integer is not just 64 bits in length or depending on whatever hardware you're running.
It's actually bigger because it's got some pointers to some other things. It's got a
pointer here down to the type int, and it's got something over here which is a, which
has a one, which is the ref count, how many names are bound to that object. And I don't
know exactly what's in there. I haven't looked, but the point is it's got a few more things,
and these are the two that we'll care about. Then it's done. It created the object. Everything
in Python is an object. It created the object, and because it's the read eval print loop,
it prints the value of that object. And so what you get back on the output is a one,
right? So that one right there where it says cell three, that's the, in Jupyter Notebook
by the way, in case you're not used to it, the in is cell three and out, so the input,
what you typed in, what you get back out. What you get back out is a visual representation
of the object or the expression, the value of the expression, which is always an object,
okay? So when we see 3.14, that's a float literal, I want you to think of all those
things that just happened, okay? Any questions about that? Okay. So you create objects in
Python. You can do them with literals like ints and floats and strings and lists and
tuples. Those are some of the basic types, not all of them. Everything in Python at run
time is an object, and it has a single value, it has a single type, it has some number of
attributes, one or more base classes, a single ID, and it has some names. So let's look at
those and I'll start to speed up a little bit. So I'll go a little faster, but I'm
going to slow down occasionally again. Oh, look, I'm going to slow down here. So type
one, what happens here is Python sees the name type and it looks in something that's
a lot like a dictionary with key value pairs. And the keys are the names, like somewhere
in here it looks for the word type, the t-y-p-e, the string, and if it finds it, then it dereferences
it, there's the value, it goes and looks for the object which the name type is bound
to and then it takes that object, it goes and sees the one and says, oh, I've got to
go create or maybe reuse an integer literal, an integer one. So it goes off and creates,
maybe it creates another one even though it threw, because it might have thrown the
earlier one away, and then it takes, then it calls the type object which is callable,
it's like a function, and it passes a reference, like the arrow part, off to that type function
and type does something and then it returns a new object or an object. And that object
that gets returned is then displayed, that's the print part, okay? So what happens there
is we get the letters i-n-t, okay? Well that's because i-n-t happens to be a name that Python
knows about and so it shows it to you as the name. So it doesn't, can't show you the bits
in here, it shows you the name that it knows, okay? Alright. So we can check the type and
what type does in this case, you pass an object, it returns what type the object is, right?
So some people say Python is not a strongly typed language, it's not typed at all, it
actually is strongly typed, very strongly typed and it's dynamically typed which means
we don't declare upfront what the type is associated with a name, instead we create
objects and those objects know their own type and then we just bind a name to the object.
So the name has no type information stored in it, the name only refers to the object,
the object has the type information, okay? Name binding which I've shown here as sort
of the way it's implemented, a good way to think about that is post-its, right? So you
can call me teacher, there's a post-it that says teacher, right? My kids call me dad,
there's a post-it that says dad, right? My wife calls me husband or spouse or partner
or steward or whatever, I mean the point is I've got lots of labels on me and some of
you are probably dads and your kids call you dad, they don't call me dad so the same name
can be reused as long as the context tells you how it distinguishes it, makes it unambiguous.
Okay, so let's look at the type of the string spam, it's str, list, tuple. Objects have
attributes, here's some examples, right? So attributes, in this case true is a built-in
name that references an object and that object has a dunder doc attribute, double underscore
doc double underscore is pronounced dunder doc, so if you haven't heard that, that's
what I'm saying, that's what it refers to. So I can access the attribute of an object
just by putting a dot and another name. So just like I have global names like true and
print and type and then we'll see how to create our own later, an object has its own
set of names, right? So imagine a table like this in an object, so dunder doc is one of
the names inside the object, right? So that's a long string with some new lines in it looks
like, I can actually print that thing and you get the documentation. So when you look
in the documentation in your editor and say show me the documentation for this object,
it's going to go and ask the object and display it to you. So the documentation for a python
object is built into the runtime.
Alright, there's another attribute, spam dot upper, here we got a less than functions
str dot upper greater than, those angle brackets are the way python, it's the convention that
python uses to display an object where you can't type it back in, right? So this string,
you could put that back into the repl and you would create a new string object. The
type tuple, the type of that tuple is tuple, you could type tuple and it refers to the
object in the repl so it works. The function, sorry, the function str dot upper, you can't
type that function in, it can't easily represent that function because it's implemented in
C in a way that you could type it back in and make it work. So it puts the angle brackets
around it, so that's what those mean.
So this one is callable, alright, so what's going on here? Alright, so python sees the
string literal, goes off and creates a string object, it uses the dot, the dot tells it
I want to get the upper attribute of it so it goes ask the object for that attribute,
then it takes the object, it gets back, looks up callable to find an object, passes a reference
to that object, the upper function, off to the callable function and it returns a new
object, right? All this stuff is happening every time you do a simple expression, okay?
And callable is yes or no? Can I call this thing? The answer is yes, so let's try to
call it and what happened there is the function returned a new object, the upper function
which is actually called a method because it's a call on an object and it returns a
new string, right? It didn't actually change the string SPAM to capital SPAM, that old
one still exists or could, it creates a new string, okay?
By the way, SPAM and eggs are sort of the standard junk variable names or variable names
and I'll use them in here because of Monty Python. Objects have base classes, this is
the boring part, we're about halfway through it, how many people think I'm going too slow?
How many people think I'm going too fast? Okay, and I'll revisit some of this, you
don't have to memorize all this stuff, I'll remind you, maybe more than you want. Objects
have base classes, so let's import the inspect module, we'll talk about what that does later
and we'll take the SPAM string and pass it off to type to get the type, pass it off to
the get MRO function in the inspect module, right? So I'm reading it backwards because
that's sort of how it gets evaluated. Get MRO means get the method resolution order.
In other words, show me if I call a method on an object of this type, what super classes
is it going to go look in to see if I can find it? Well that tells us what the class
hierarchy is for this object and the answer is type of SPAM is STR, STR is a subclass
of object. Object is the name that refers to the object in Python that every other object
in the Python runtime when you're running it is a subclass of eventually, okay? So it's
the parent, the top of the tree of all the objects. Here's a more interesting one. Boole,
so true is a type of type bool which is a subclass of int which is a subclass of object.
How many of you don't know what I'm saying when I say subclass? Everyone knows about
object oriented at least a little bit, excellent, at least a little bit. Okay, every object
has an ID. In CPython, I'm running CPython because it's written in C, it's called CPython.
There are other versions of Python like iron Python written in C sharp that works well
in the CLR or DLR space on .NET and Windows. There's Jython written in Java that is a little
bit stale, still I haven't gotten to three, I don't know if they ever will. That's written
in Java and works with, like it compiles to the JVM. There's PyPy which is a Python written,
a lot of it in Python. That's a very interesting project that a lot of people use and then
there's a few others, stackless, et cetera. Lots of implementations, oh, MicroPython, I'm
sure I've only named half of them but those are the big ones I can remember. Anyway, CPython
written in C, when you ask Python to show the unique ID of an object, it shows us the
memory address which is an easy way to make it unique. So it's not guaranteed to be the
memory address in every version of Python and I don't think any, I've never used this
because I've never, the only reason you would need to know the memory address is if you're
writing an extension probably that's written in C for example and you need to pass pointers
around. But usually Python handles all that so we don't need to worry about it. We just
know it's a unique ID. The only other thing that's kind of interesting is look at those
numbers. You notice how the ID of three is relatively small compared to the ID of the
other two? That gives us a hint about where it might be stored in memory and we'll touch
on that briefly later. Okay. So usually we create or access existing objects by calling
something else. So here are some examples. Here's the ABS is a function which returns
the absolute value. It is callable. If we call it with minus three, it gives us three.
Int is callable. If I call it pass it a float, it truncates it. Okay. Okay. Don't look at
this code. You don't need to know what it does. But I need to load it because it's the
only way I could figure out, sorry, to show you this easily. Okay. So what are the current
names in my namespace? Nothing. So name, value, ID. The only reason I'm showing you the ID
is because I want you to see that sometimes if two names refer to objects that have the
same ID, well they're actually the same object. So that's why I'm showing you the ID as well.
All right. I'm going to slow down here again a little bit. So the way you've learned that
computer programming languages work, many of you, not all of you, is that you name something
like an I. You say, okay, I want to use a variable I and I want it to represent an integer.
And so the compiler says, okay, every time they use I it's an integer. And I will remember
that. It then creates a box big enough to hold an integer. Then when we say, okay, I
want to use a or a, let's probably use a instead of I. Anyway, if we take that I, then there's
an assignment statement. So I can see you'd say int I equals one. Then what the compiler
does is it puts, it makes it such that when the code is running there is a box that has
the one in it. And if you later say I equals two, it takes the one out of the box, it overwrites
the memory and puts two in instead. And when you say I plus one, it issues a machine instruction
which is an integer add which is different than a float add because the computer needs
to know there's just bits in this box, what should I do with it? Because adding floats
and adding ints are very different parts of the CPU and treat those bits very differently.
So it has to remember what's in the box so it knows how to do things like add. Python
doesn't do that. Python, the object remembers what type it is and it knows how to add itself
to a float or vice versa. It doesn't do it very quickly because it's not compiled, but
it does it quick enough. So in Python what happens is A equals 300, well guess what gets
evaluated first? The 300. And you know what I'm going to say. Python goes off and creates
an object in memory that represents the integer 300. It has a link to the type int. And then
it sees the A equal and that is not, I am not going to use the term assigning a value
to a variable. At a high level of abstraction mathematically a variable is a good word and
you can use it all the time, just not today. Today you're going to use the words I am using
because I want you to start thinking that way. Because then by making you think that
way a whole bunch of other things become much clearer. And then you can go back to using
variable later tomorrow, but you'll have that different understanding slightly of how things
are working and that saves you a lot of pain when you're using Python. So what Python does
is it sees the A equal and when it sees name equal that's a name assignment. That's a name
binding operation. It changes the namespace. So it's not changing the 300, it's not changing
anything in memory because the 300 already got created. So what it does is it adds the
A to the current namespace and it remembers that A has a pointer or a reference to that
object in memory. Assignment operator in Python is a namespace change. It's putting a post
it on the object and then later I can use that to go look it up. So let's do that. This
is monumentous. We're actually going to change the namespace. That's what happened.
So let's see, let's show what my current names are. Let me back up. The reason I'm using
this complicated code, usually I would use dir, it gives you dozens and dozens of variable
because the Jupyter Notebook has lots and lots of names. So that's why I'm using this
underscore vars IDs. So let's see what's in our namespace. I've got a new name A and
it's got the value 300 and it's got that ID. So now when I type in the name, it's
not a string literal, it's not an int, it's not a float, it's not a list, it's not a
tuple, it's not any of those other things, but it is a valid identifier because it starts
with a letter and has nothing but letters and numbers and underscores after it with
no spaces. So it goes and looks up this, goes and finds this object and then throws away
the A in a sense. So now Python has this object which represents the integer 300 and it prints
the value of it. So by the time it goes to print the 300, it doesn't know that it was
called A and in fact it can't ask. Python can't know what the names of that object are
by asking the object. The object does not store its own name. So nowhere in here is
a reference back to the word A or the identifier A. So that's another thing that's helpful
to understand. Let's see if it works. It did. So, it's a reference back to the identifier
A. Let's do it again. Still there, same one. Oh, no it's not the same one. Look at that.
It moved. Well, no it didn't move. So what happened is once I did the A equals 300, so
I assigned it here, it saw the A equals 300, it went off and created a new object, 300.
That's not guaranteed to happen. It's up to Python what it does. Ints are immutable, they
can't be changed. So whether it creates a new one every time or reuses one that exists
doesn't change what you're doing with your programming. So we'll sort of think about
that to help us understand the layer below, but it doesn't really matter. So, let's keep
going here. So now we can access A and it's going to show us 300 looks like the other
300 did. And again, at the level we're programming in, they are the same, they are equal. So
what if I try to access this? Those of you new to programming and even some of you not
are used to ignoring errors, I know this from helping people who are learning programming
at my workplace and you just ignore the error and try to figure it out some other way. Read
the error message. Trust me, after you read the tenth one, they'll start to make sense
and it will benefit you a lot. So the error is a name error. So the capital N, capital
E, camel case name error, that's the name of the exception that Python raised. It gives
you a trace back which is very boring when you're working in the REPL because usually
it would tell you this function in this file called this function and that file called
this function. Well, here it's just there's no file, it's just the console and there's
just one line. And then it actually shows you, tells you what happened. Well, the name
B is not defined and it shows you where in the line it failed as well which again you
can't even see that there if it's even there, I think it is. Okay. So what's going to happen
when I hit shift enter here? Anybody want to try? You'll get it wrong because I'm
awful in terms of I want to use exactly the right language. Say again, louder so others
can hear. Close, very close. He said a new object 400 will be attached to the name A.
I would say an object representing 400 will get created. It might be new, it might exist
already. We don't know. That's a Python implementation detail that isn't our problem or business.
And the name A is attached to the object 400, not the other way around is the better way
to think about it. So the post-it is put onto the object. The letter A, take that post-it
note and stick it on here. And then when Python has an index of the post-it note, so when
you say give me A, it can find it quickly. But the object doesn't know its own name.
Great. And it did it. And there we go, 400. Now we can access it. What about this? What
is B equal A going to do? Well, it's going to look up the A first and get back an object
reference. And then it's going to do a name assignment, B equal, which is a namespace
operation. It's going to add a B. And what the B is going to refer to is that object
because that's what it got back from the A lookup. Right? So there we go. And now B
is 400, A is 400. I'm going to use is. You should almost never use is. If you're writing
linked lists and you really need to know have I come around like a circular list and I need
to know have I got back to the beginning, then you would need is maybe because you might
not, they might be duplicates in the list. And so you can't tell if equality if you've
gotten back to the same one. You should use is. You'll often see is in a function when
there's a default parameter, which is none, and you'll see if parameter one is none, then
that's okay. Otherwise, don't use is. What you should be using is equal. Okay? Equals,
because all you care about is like there were two 300s earlier, right? Do I care that if
I say is that 300 the same as that 300 when you mean to say are they the same value, you're
going to write code that's incorrect. Right? But I'm going to use it here because what
it does mean is is is an operator that you give it two object references and it just
checks their IDs to see if they're the same. And if they are, it's the same object. Right?
So in this case, is this going to be true or false? Cool. I got both answers. So A lookup
gets a reference to that object. B lookup gets a reference. Well, here's the ambiguous
way to I could think of it this way. Well, A refers to an object that represents 400
and B refers to an object that represents 400, but I don't know if they're the same
object. However, because I said B equals A, I actually do know because I got the object
reference back and then added a new value. So here I know that B and A are the same object,
i.e. they are two names for the same object. Okay? Oh, good. And we can see that if we
look at the IDs. Right? They are the same address. How about C equals 400? Can anyone
tell me that if A is C, it's going to be true or false? No, that's not my question. Can
anyone tell me? No, no one can tell me what the answer is. I can't tell you what the answer
is because I don't know what Python is going to do. Right? It turned out in this case it
allocated a new one, but it might not have. Right? So again, Python has freedom to implement
how it wants. You have freedom to work within the contract that Python has given you. The
contract is insurmutable. So it doesn't matter if it makes multiple ones because it doesn't
use ID. Well, that's enough. Okay, so let's look and see. Right? Okay. And you can see
this again. It's just the ID is how I'm getting those. That's what's printing out there.
All right. Now, A is an int. Right? And I'm going to put string in a box that was designed
for an int. No, that's not right. A is a name. So if I say A equals ABC, not a problem.
It goes off and creates a string object down here that represents the string ABC. And here,
instead of adding a name to the namespace, it overwrites this value in that key value
pair. It's kind of like a dictionary. Right? And so I'm going to say please take the Post-It
off of the other object and put it on this new string object that got created. Okay?
So that's not a problem. So the notion that it's a variable and it can only have one type,
well, that's meaningless in Python because it's just a name referring to an object. The
object knows its type. Right? Okay. And again, most of this you know, but now you know why
you know it. Right. And B is still 400. We look at this thing. We see. Okay. All right.
Del A is a namespace operation. It is not a request to Python to delete an object. Python
does delete objects when it can. And when it can is when the reference count goes down
to zero, then it can clean it up using garbage collection. But Del A in this context, Del
space and a name says please remove A from the namespace. So cross this off. Right? And
can anyone tell me if the object that A was referring to got deleted? No, none of you
can tell me that. That's the right answer. Right? Now we might be able to. I'm wrong.
Did I say A and B are the same? No, hang on. A, no, B and C. Right. So before when A and
B were the same, this diagram which is further up, if I had done a Del A then, you could
have told me no, this didn't get deleted because there's still a name that's bound to it.
Then I put the A equals ABC. Thank you. Okay. All right. So what's Del A? Oh, wait. I did
that. Where am I? Del B. Let's get rid of that name and let's get rid of the C name.
So it probably cleaned up those things but can't be guaranteed. All right. So here's
how you're supposed to do it. Right? Let's say use equality. Use double equal to check
equality. So let's, let me just demonstrate something here. I equals 10, J equals 10,
I equals J. We know that's true. Is I the same object as J? We don't know. Turns out
it is in this case. And I can sort of do both of those at the same time. If you put a comma
between two expressions in the REPL or in Python, it creates a tuple without the parentheses
and then it returns. And in creating that retuple, sorry, it's a tuple with the value
of each expression and then it prints it so you see it prints it as a tuple. And you can
see that those are at the same address. What if I do I equals J equals 500? So this is
not C where J equals 500 is an assignment expression. It's not that. Meaning assignment
statements in Python do not have a value. So if you say A equals 3, that expression
doesn't have a value that you can then do something else with. But you do, are allowed
the convenience of saying I equals J equals 500 if you want to give two names to the same
object up front. So we'll do that. Give two names to the same object up front. And you
can see that they have the same value of course and they are the same object because I just
gave two names to the same object. All right. So we're saying similar to this, the A, B
point to the same one. We've got those there. Same there. What if I do an I equals 500,
J equals 500? There they're different. All right. So in case you're curious why that
is, you can watch videos of my epiphanies course which is more advanced where basically
Python preallocates certain integers close to zero for efficiency. That's why some are
sometimes it recreates them because there's lots of zeros and ones and fives floating
around in the runtime. Let's save a little memory. Okay. All right. So if I type this,
is it going to work or not? You can't really tell, right? I know that abs worked and callable
worked and true worked. So there are some names that I haven't shown you that are built
in names that aren't visible when you look with vars or with dir as a call, dir open,
close, print. I keep saying that. What I mean is this. If you do that, it shows you the
current names, the names in the current namespace and this is lots of them. That's why I don't
use that. So if you do a dir, you won't see abs but abs is available. So there's the
names you create. There's the built ins that are sort of hiding in the background. Then
there's the ones that don't, they're in the standard library is another one. So math
is a standard library module in Python. So if I access it, I get exactly the same error
as I did back up when I tried to access the name b before I had added it to the namespace.
So math is not defined. I can define it as in tell Python to go get the library and import
it and put the math name in the current namespace by doing an import which we'll talk about
a little bit later. So again, it's got that little angle brackets around it. I can look
at the attributes of the math module and there are some dir attributes that are sort of implementationy
things and then a whole bunch of functions and some constants. One of which is math.nan,
not a number. And its type is a float. So just as another example of don't trust is,
math.nan is math.nan. That's going to be true because it has to be true because this
is, I'm asking Python, do these two names refer to the same object? Well, they're the
same name. They have to refer to the same object, right? They're the same complete
name, right? Like math.nan and spam.nan might not be the same. Math.nan and math.nan are.
So it's going to be true as the second value but the first value is math.nan equal to itself
and the answer is no. And I'm not going to tell you why that's for another tutorial.
It has to do with, there are good reasons why that thing exists. It's not a number.
It represents not a number. And it's useful in scientific programming, other kinds of
stuff. Okay. So that's the end of the lecture, the first part. Now what I'm going to do
is let you do the exercises. Remember when you look at this, don't just hit shift enter.
Think about what it's going to do. Try to predict what it's going to do. Write it down
if you want to, whatever. And then hit shift enter and see what it actually does. And ideally,
it will always do exactly what you think. I'm pretty sure I've put enough weird things
in here that you're not going to be able to do that. You'll be surprised sometimes.
There are approximately 50 to 100 errors in this intentionally. So you will see error
messages. It's because I want you to see the error message. I'd like you to maybe think
that, so sometimes you'll figure out ahead of time, well this might not work. Sometimes
you won't. And then I want you to think about why did this raise the error message. And
then we'll talk about it as a group. I will go through it. So you don't need to, don't
worry about understanding all of it. Okay. Question?
Sort of. It's a function that I wrote and I put in the notebook. And I put it in the
notebook with a write file, which means if you execute this cell, it will write it and
then I loaded it back in because I want to actually evaluate it. And then I clicked back
in that cell and hit shift enter to evaluate it after I loaded it. So it's kind of my hack
so that you can get it too without me shipping all those files. Although I did in the zip.
You have it there as well, the VARS ID. So load VARS ID, that percent load is, which
once it does it, it comments it out, is the magic that puts it in that name space, in
the current name space. And I didn't just do an import because it actually has to do
some weird stuff with the names to try to, yeah. If anyone has a better way to do it,
I'd love to hear it. Okay. So your turn to do exercises. And yeah, so there's not too
many. So I'll give you about, this one I'll give you lots of time. I'll give you a good
five minutes. And I'll wander around and ask you questions and then we'll go through it
together.
Okay.
So, no surprises here. Now that my mic is on, I'll just repeat that. These are all fairly
straightforward. You've seen the pieces of this. We just put them together there. M is
N? It is because I said M equals N equals N. M equals N equals whatever. So I told Python
I want two names for the same object. So this one, I said earlier if you have name equal
and something, it's a namespace operation. This is not name equals something. This is
name square bracket something square bracket equal. So this instead is a request to the
object that M is bound to. And the request is to change its element at index one. And
Python starts counting at zero to be something else. And so you can see it changed it. And
of course because N and M are bound to the same one, it changed. They both changed. There's
only one and it changed. Okay. Okay. Well, let's go a little faster and just explore
numbers for time. So numbers. So numbers are the numbers that are bound to the same object.
There's another error. Syntax error. It shows you exactly where with the little hat there.
So it's showing you it's just after or at. It got done reading the minus and didn't know
what to do with that. Obviously something like one minus two would work, but one minus
by itself isn't going to work. One equals two. Syntax error. Can't assign to a literal.
Good. That would be strange. True and false values coming from equal and not equal. Less
than, less than or equal to. Multiplication works. Addition works. Division works. Or
you can use floor division, which always returns an integer. And that's what Python 2's slash
did. That was one of the big changes between Python 2 and Python 3. Clock or modular division.
Right? Like if it's 9 o'clock, what's in 14 hours from now? It'll be 11 o'clock, right?
Because 14, it's two hours after 9 in a sense. That's why we call it clock division. So all
of these are available to you. It's remainder is what it is. Sorry. This is the remainder.
Nine divides three cleanly with nothing left over. Here's the int we saw earlier. We know
it's callable. Let's try calling it a few times. So we call it pass it a two. It just
gives us back a two. Maybe the same one, maybe a different one. If we give it a float, does
it round it or truncate it? It truncates it. If I give it a string, it will convert it
from a string. It'll take the string and derive an integer from it. If I give it a float that
looks like a string, it says, no, that sounds like a bug to me. Tell me exactly what you
want if you really want to do that. Here we get another. We got value error now. So value
error is any time there's something wrong with a value. This is one you might commonly
use. If you're writing code and someone gives you a value that's not good, raise a value
error and give it a different argument. Right? So you're reading the error message, right?
Because I told you you got to read the error message. Anything interesting about this error
message? Yeah, what's that about base 10? Invalid literal for int with base 10. Why
is it telling us about base 10? Well, it's because there are other bases. So that's a
clue actually. And it cannot read your mind. So int four is obviously going to fail with
it. Float. So float we can use on 2.9 and it knows what to do and allows it. This is
going to do what? Raise an exception. So it throws or raises an exception and that's the
zero division error. So there's a new one. Can we add types that are different? Yeah,
it'll coerce. So it creates a new one. So I just used the word coerce and I didn't want
to do that because coerce usually in statically compiled languages coerce usually means I
told you compiler that that I represents an integer but I want you to actually start treating
the contents of that box as a float instead or something like that. That's what coerce
usually means. That's what coerce often means in statically compiled languages. So here
what it's doing is just saying well yeah, basically what this really is going on here
is the integer object if you pass it, if you call its add method, it's actually its
thunder add method and you pass it an object which is a float, the integer object knows
how to add those two together. And it says oh I can do that and I'll return a float.
Okay and I don't need to do that because I already, oh yeah I do because it's a new notebook.
The reason I put this in every notebook is because you have to reload it. Those of you
who are not using Jupyter Notebook just use DUR instead is my suggestion. Right. Okay.
A plus one. That should just give me a new two. It does. But why didn't it change it?
Well because I didn't change it. Right. I just, like by the time Python had the two
it didn't even know that I named it A or used the name A earlier. If I do B equals
A plus one though, well that's going to do it on a regular assignment so it's adding
a new name to the namespace based on the value two. We got the two and we got the one. Okay.
A plus equal one. That's valid Python. And what it looks like it does is the same thing
as A equals A plus one and that's sometimes true but not always. So plus equal is actually,
and again if you don't remember this this is fine, plus equal is actually an operator
in Python that calls not the Dunder add method, it calls the Dunder i add method. And Dunder
i add is supposed to try to change itself but if it can't like an int which is immutable
then it just falls back on turning it into A equals A plus one. So that's kind of some
interesting stuff. I think we see some of that later if I remember correctly. A plus
plus, sorry not allowed. Some of you won't like that. All right. Okay. Abs, abs, yeah.
What's this one going to do? What? It's going to fail. How is it going to fail? What exception
is it going to raise? A name error. Right. So it's going to say I don't know about that
name. Name error. Name sign is not defined. So I import math because again I imported
it earlier but that was the earlier notebook. I've switched notebooks so I've lost all
that history. So I import math and I can see the math modules in there and so now what's
sign going to, pi over two going to do? Okay. So that's the first one. So what's the second
one? It's going to fail because look at the names in my namespace. I got A and I got B
and I got math but I don't have sign and I don't have pi. Right. So that's different
than some languages. Some languages you import the module all the names come in. Python,
just the module name comes in unless you do something different. Okay. So let's see. Oh
I was right. So but math is there, right. Math is there and there's the module and I
can look at what's in the math module. There are the attributes of it which includes sign
and pi and et cetera. So I can do this math dot sign math dot pi and this is actually
the recommended way to do it. Right. And the reason for that is when like for a short
module name math dot sign math well again usually the recommended way to do it. So you
could just import the names you want from modules. It's recommended good style is to
just import the name of the module and then it's clear to the reader of the code who's
never seen the code before. Oh you mean the sign in the math module as opposed to the
sign in the num pi module. Right. Like because the names do show up other places. There are
exceptions where it's a really long module name you can shorten it but usually spell
them out. It takes a little more time to type but you're going to read your code a lot more
than you're going to write it and other people are going to read your code after it's written.
All right. Get off that soap box. There we go. But you can do a from math import sign
to pi and obviously if you just write in code I need this script I'll throw it away after
this afternoon. Do whatever you want. Do a so you can do that. You can even do from math
import star and it'll just bring them all in. So good when you're exploring but not
when you're writing code that's going to be around for a while. Okay. So then sign pi
over 2 works. What do you think this is going to do? Can you can you do that? Can you do
tell me what this is going to do? Referring to the same object. Yup. So do these two names
refer to the same object? Can you reliably answer that question? You actually can unless
python unless something weird has gone on with the imports. Normally when python imports
a module it only imports it once. And so when I do even though I imported math and then
I did from math import sign it didn't go reload a new module object and then go grab
something from inside it. It reused all that. So there are some weird edge cases with like
the way pi test works for example where if you've done things wrong you might get to
but that's a bigger problem. So yeah this is reliably going to be true. What we've
done so far it's the same. So those are just two names for the same object. Okay. You can
use help as a built in function by the way that lets you just look at stuff right in
the and in the jupiter in ipython which is what jupiter is running you can also do it
this way or this way and depending on like jupiter brings up this little window down
below which you can then hit escape to close. You can do other things too by the way like
you can hit tab and it will bring up completions for you. There are a few things that jupiter
notebook does. Okay. So that was a little faster. We'll go faster yet. You like drinking
from a fire hose soon. So go play for a little bit see what these do.
Okay.
Okay. So I'm going to go through these the ones you didn't finish. You can see what I'm
doing. You can do them yourself later. And again don't memorize all this stuff. This
is just let it wash over you and you'll absorb it and you'll remember parts of it later and
you'll get a sense for how python works and that will give you more value than memorizing
less of the things. Okay. So integers all these are fairly straightforward. Order of
precedence. Well you can look it up or you can add parentheses to make it more clear
for your reader who might also not remember them exactly. You can do this one's kind
of nice. You can actually check the less than and have three values or more. It just instead
of putting in the ands. Exponentiation. What if we go over our 64 bit architecture? Python
doesn't care. It slows down but it works. Rounds. Makes sense. Let's create a third.
And if we round it. No surprises there. Now this looks like an error doesn't it? Round
with a minus one. There are a lot of cases in python where there are sort of edge cases
that it's like oh yeah we can't use that. Oh but there's something neat we could do
that with that that would be really useful. Like let's move the decimal plates the other
direction. Okay. So look for those and you'll see there's lots of little things. I keep
running into them occasionally. And then our advanced exercises. That's exciting. Type
int callable int help callable. What else? Int. If you call int with no arguments it
gives you back a zero and of course it's equal to zero. Type of int is type. Type of one
is int. Type of int is type. Interesting. So what I'm calling as a function is actually
a class or a type or again the lines between a class and an object if it's callable that's
what matters and I can call it. It acts like a function. Okay. And of course type of zero
is int. Okay. Int four three. What else? We did this before. You saw it. You saw it. You
saw it already. Int z same thing but if I pass a second argument. Right. So this is
an optional argument. Python has optional arguments that you can put in sometimes. You
don't have to. And here's an example of and so they add lots of richness and power to
the functions you're calling is that you know int converts from ints. Oh but it also converts
from ints using different base cases for example. Okay. Let's move on to strings. That's a string
of four characters. That's a string of one character. There is no character type in Python.
There are only strings and they have zero, one or more characters. Okay. Like that is
four like that is one. The types of these are the same because they're both type str.
You can use single quotes or double quotes which is convenient because if you want to
put a quote in the middle it ain't going to work. Right. I've got a quote and then a quote.
So that's a string and then Python sees the rest and says I don't know what to do with
that. So I could escape it with a backslash to say don't escape. The backslash says don't
treat the following character the way you usually would. So in this case it means don't
treat it like the end of the string. Just put it in the string. Right. So that works
and you notice it comes back and puts quotes with a single quote in the middle. Double
quotes on the outside. That's sort of a clue that if you want to put a single quote in
a string use double quotes. If you want to put a double quote in a string use single
quotes. That's convenient. Here's another example. What if I want to have a string that
goes over multiple lines? Well it can't work unless you put triple quotes. So Python lets
you put triple quotes and then it does work. You notice that the new line got inserted
here as the escaped end which means put a new line character in here. Not a backslash
and an end. So put in a single character. Right. There are cases that won't quite work.
Like here I've got four quotes in a row. Yeah. It doesn't know what to do. So I use triple
single quotes instead. You don't need to have the triple quotes. You can actually put the
backslash end directly like that. In is an operator in Python that says is something
in something else? In this case it means for strings is this string in the other string?
Is it a substring of that string? The answer there is yes. And if you put a not in front
of any expression it will reverse it. You can also use not in. Two words, one operator.
Which just makes it read easier. So that's kind of convenient. Square bracket zero. We
saw it earlier when we assigned M sub one equal quote B. Here we're going to access
this. So we're going to say give me the first element of that iterable or that sequence.
Not iterable. Sorry. That sequence. So sequence types, tuple, dict, string, list and other
ones that people have written. So this says get me out that element. And it gives you
back in this case you ask a string for its first character you get back a string of one
character. I think this is the last time I'm going to use this thing. The vars ID. Put
it in there. All right. So S equals T equals hello. Right. And these. We can look at both
its values. Yes. Why what? Why do I have to do what? Oh, so the load loads it into the
cell and then I have to go back in the cell and hit shift and shift to evaluate the cell.
And it's a hack to make it not normal but it works because I want to do stuff with it.
The reason I have to do it that way is because of this stuff here with the global. That's
what the percent load. Percent load loads the contents of a file into a cell. It does
not execute it. Okay. So there's the S and the T which are two names for the same object
kind of like that. Right. So if we do this, S is now a name that is bound to or refers
to a string jello because plus does concatenation. And what about T? Yeah. So S equal. This is
a namespace operation. So I changed S. I didn't change T. Right. So T is still going to be
hello. How about if I do it this way? Okay. So I'm going to do this. I'm going to do this.
Strings are immutable. It's not going to let me do this. It does not support item assignment.
Right. I can access the j that I put in this string but I can't change it. And you can
see that S is still of course jello. Okay. How about this? M equals N equals 1, 2, 3.
Right. So there we could change what was in there. Lists are mutable. Strings are not.
So this didn't give me an error. All right. How about B1 equals B quote. So there are
a number of things you can put right in front of the quote, a string literal. A string literal
is the beginning quote, end quote and the characters inside. A B in front changes it
slightly. There's B for bytes. There's an R for raw. There's U for Unicode which isn't
needed in Python 3 because they're all Unicode. And I think OF which we'll see later. So B
is the way we ask Python to give me a binary representation of something. And when I do
that, what's B made of? The answer is, it's a binary representation of something. And
it's made of numbers. Right? And I can, it's a sequence of numbers and I can iterate over
it. Oh, bytes is another one I forgot to mention. I can iterate over it. So if I pass it to
list, list will take whatever you give it and try to iterate over it and it will then
create a list of those values. So when I look at it that way, you can see that hello. So
it's convenience that lets, I'm harping on this because character encoding is really
difficult to get right and it's really hard to think about partly because it's so ingrained
in our way of, like it's abstracted away so well by our tools that it's hard to see what's
really going on. Debugging, at least twice a year I'm helping some team decode some,
sorry, debug, diagnose a character encoding problem and they're always confused. And
so then I start explaining it to them and I start getting confused because it's just
a really confusing thing. So my hint to you here which I'll credit to Doug McNeil who
showed me this pointed out the fact is that the fact that Python lets you type a string
to create a bytes is a little bit misleading. Worse than that maybe is the fact that it
shows it to you as what looks a lot like a string. It's not a string. It's just a bunch
of numbers that for convenience sake it will show you what they represent in ASCII. Okay.
If you remember that it'll help a little bit in terms of not getting confused about Unicode.
Sorry, character encoding generally. All right. So it's 2 equal to 2.0. I could probably do
a poll and figure out who the real mathematicians are in the room. All right. Sure it is. 2.0
is a floating point representation of the number 2. Exactly. Exactly 2. You can write
your own language and do it differently but this is what Python decided. I actually don't
know. I think that's probably generally true in languages isn't it? I don't know. Anyway,
B1 and S1, are they the same? Absolutely not. Why? Because if they made this the same like
in Python 2 it makes you write bugs more easily. So Python 2 had lots of good support for character
encoding and Unicode. Python 3 just tightened up some areas to make you think about it and
force you not to just do it without intentionally thinking what you're doing. If I decode it,
so bytes I can decode it and then it will turn it into a string. So string in Python
is a high level, an abstraction representing characters. It may be stored as numbers. I'm
sure it's stored as numbers. Everything is in a computer but it's representing characters.
When you get a file from someone else, they should tell you what the encoding is. You
can read it, decoding it into characters and then when you're ready to do something with
it like send it to someone else or send it over the wireshed then you can encode it in
a particular encoding and you should always say which one. As recently as last year I
think I told people in an audience like this that the default encoding for Python is UTF-8.
I was wrong. It's actually, see it's easy to get wrong. It's actually dependent on the
platform. So if you write code on one platform and your encoding files as in writing a code
a string to disk and you don't specify the encoding and you move it to another operating
system and run the same code, it may produce a different result. You have to think about
these things. All right, I'll get off my soapbox. You got a question?
Yeah.
Ah, yes. I used, this is comparison, equal equal and some other people may have missed
that too. Thank you. So I used equal equal. That's why it's true. If I'd done is, absolutely
false. Okay. So what does decode do? Well, it does stuff and it's interesting and you
can look at it later. I have an advanced exercise at the end of this and one of the later notebooks
which we almost certainly won't get to which lets you play around with encoding. I encourage
you to do that to understand it better. Okay. Your turn to do some stuff with strings for
a few minutes. Who thinks I'm going too fast? Too slow? Okay.
Okay.
Okay. I'm going to move us along. I'll go through these and then break in about five
minutes. So this is exploring the raw string, the R you put in front of it. So if you put
an R in front of a string that has an escape character in it, it changes what happens,
right? So it says don't, the raw string says a slash is just a slash. Don't use it to escape
characters. Useful in regular expressions, some other cases. And you can see these, you
can sort of figure out that, oh yeah, those are different. The backslash N is that one
or two characters. It depends on whether you've used, how you've done it. Right, expression
of value. I'm going to skip that because we're close to the break. You can do math with strings
which means multiple concatenations. You can't concatenate ints and strings. Oh, new error,
type error, unsupported operand types for plus int and str. Okay. Not much interesting there.
Later on we'll see the same type error and the same error message and it will give you
some clues about something you can do. I can add strings together though. Interestingly,
I can even add them together without an add. So in source code in Python, if there are
two string literals next to each other, it will combine them and that's convenient for
certain cases. Especially if you're trying to have a single string go across lots of
lines for example. Okay, we'll do a little bit more with encoding here. Here's a backslash
U says give me code point 24 from Unicode and turn that into the abstraction of code
point 24. And this one says don't give me code point 24, give me the Unicode character
that is named dollar sign and they're all the same. Okay, so just, again the advanced
exercises that you'll do on your own at the end are interesting. Okay, so strings have
functions and methods, lots of them. Again, this will just be a blur. Don't remember
them, just remember that oh yeah, you can do stuff like that with strings and that will
be helpful. Length is a function that takes any iterable and figures out how long it is
or asks it how long it is depending on whether or not it's supplied the Dunderland function.
It depends on how it implements that. But regardless it'll, I think I might be wrong
here. No, I think I'm right that it will take any iterable and consume it but I'm
not sure now. Okay, min is a function that same thing, max. All right, so what it did
like takes spam, iterates over it into the separate characters as strings and then returns
the one that's the smallest. Sorted, right, always returns a list of whatever you iterate
over. Does it start with S? Yep, does it start with SP? Does it end with M? Give me
an uppercase version of that, give me a lowercase version of that. Strip spaces from the front
and the back, strip spaces only from the right side, spaces, whitespace, sorry not spaces,
tab, probably vertical tab, maybe form feed but basically tab space are the ones you'll,
oh and new line, of course. Or only from the left side, right. This is misleading. Doesn't
that look a lot like it's the right way to remove the extension from a file name? Well,
it's not. See, the strip functions take a string and interpret that string as a set
of characters that it should remove. So it will remove any of those characters until
it gets from the right side in this case, until it gets to a character that's not in
that set and then it stops. And this is easy bug to write and there's good proof of it,
right? It's going to just keep going until it gets to the dot. As long as it's in, no
sorry, until it consumes the last dot because it says any dots, C's, S's or V's just chew
them all up and when you run out of those then stop and so it stops just before the
E. Oh sorry, stops. Yeah, there's OS path, has a bunch of functions and there's a newer
path lib module. If you're doing file names, so if what you want to do is work with file
names and remove extensions, use path lib or the older OS path. Path lib is nice, nicer
in many ways. A split is a method called on a string which returns a list of strings split
on white space by default, not just one but could be multiple white spaces or if you give
it a specific string it will split on that specific string. So if you give it a space
character, it won't split on tabs or new lines. New lines it might not, I can't remember.
So here it will actually split on that exact one and it throws away the other piece, right?
So it throws away the space dash space and just gives it a list of three strings. Type
of spam, here all the function, let me just, lots of functions there, let me print them
on one page there. So all the Dunder functions you could ignore for now and then here all
the other ones, case, capitalized, case, center, count, encode, lots and lots of stuff. Anything
you might think you would want to do with the string it's probably already in there
and if not stack overload. All right, yeah that doesn't matter. I'm going to, okay,
you can look for the offset, find in spam, P A and you find it at character offset one.
If you look for something that's not in there it raises a value error. Find is just like
index except instead of raising a value error it returns minus one. Choose the one you want.
Break time, I'm almost done. Find, right, so we can find those things. You can replace
all the E's with 3's or just one of them, optional, optional argument there, say just
for first one. All right, so I will stop there. You can do exercises now and then go for break
or vice versa. We will start, come back from break in, well, break is 20 minutes so I'll
give you 25 or 22, whatever, so you have time to do the exercises before or after, whichever
you prefer.
Break over, 10-15 to 10-35, what's that? It's 20 minutes, 10-15, so 10-35, so we're done.
All right, I'll turn my microphone on soon.
Okay, welcome back from the break. I will go through these exercises. All right, so
we saw this order before, reverse equals true and optional argument. If we do reversed it
gives us back a reversed object which is kind of interesting. Basically it's lazy evaluation
so it will iterate over that later when you actually try to iterate over it if needed
and you can force that. Easy way you can iterate over an iterator is just pass it off to list.
List tries to iterate over whatever you can do it and then it will return a list of whatever
it iterated over of those elements. Upper is upper, there's a whole bunch of these,
title is title. Remember these are returning new strings, which reminds me, one of the
questions someone asked is how did this work? How did it change the string? It didn't change
the string, it gave us back a new string which was a copy of the old string changed. Python
is allowed to change strings, like it basically copied the string and created a new string
and it did that in code written in C so it's pretty fast. Going back down here though,
so here's title and here's an example where we take, where we do what's called method
chaining. So in method chaining what happens is, so the method is called on the object
and it returns a new string, that string object that then you can imagine replacing this,
the swap case method is called on that new string and it returns yet another new string.
So you get that title case reversed kind of. Here's the in you saw earlier. So the six,
the optional argument to find says start looking at a particular offset. All right, so what
is s.index zero, s.index space? Anyone figure that out? Looks for what? S.index zero, s.index
zero. That's right, it looks for the, I would say it looks for the first o after the first
space. And there you can see how that worked. So how about an expression to check for more
spaces than non-spaces in a string? Well this is going to be part of it right? How many
spaces are there in the string? Is that more than, what's that? So that's the, that's
the, so I heard some people took the length of the string and divided it by two. That's
an option. What's that? Yeah, okay, so what you said, so you have to, yeah, so that's
one way to do something like that. I may have the point is that's the gist of it, you can
figure out the details. Another is something like that. Again, I'm not saying that's the
right answer, but that's the way to figure out how many are non-spaces in a string. Well
you could take the length, what would be the length of it, wouldn't it be? You can take
the length of it if you got rid of the spaces. Right, and again I may need an extra half
for something like that. I'm not worrying about the details, I'll let you worry about
that. Okay, any questions before we go on? Alright, string formatting. Well you remember
what three does. If you put a three on a line by itself in a Python script or program and
you run it, you will not see the value three printed to standard output. You would need
to use the print function, okay. The reason we're seeing it here is because it's the
read eval print loop, it's the P in REPL. Right, so print is an easy way to get stuff
out to standard output. You can print multiple objects, it puts spaces between them, not
between the objects but between their string representations that it prints, right. And
if you print, it might be hard to see there, but if we print, there you can see if you
put new lines it prints multiple lines in there like that. You can use this, those of
you who are sad that plus plus didn't work, well at least you got this. This was the print
formatting, the string formatting operator in Python until, I can't remember when they
added dot format 26 or 27. And most people I think find, I certainly anyway find the
dot format method on string more powerful than the percent operator, sorry this percent
operator which obviously, well which we saw earlier as modulo, it's also, it's here, it's
used to say interpolate, basically take that three and stick it in where the percent D
is. Question?
No, or so if there are two string, the question is why is it different with string literals?
If Python sees two string literals, and these are the quote marks, with only white space
between them or even a new line that's still a valid expression like in parentheses, it
will just create one string literal, it will create one string object from the two of them.
So that's part of the syntax of reading the Python code. Print takes whatever objects
you give to it and asks them for their string representations and then prints them out with
a space between each of those.
So dot format, basically it looks for curly braces in the string and the technical term
is interpolates or inserts the value of three as a string into that location, you get three
good reasons. You can pass it arguments that aren't used and that's okay and occasionally
that's handy. So here's, and you can have a string that doesn't have any arguments and
doesn't have any curly braces, it just says okay, I'll give you the string back. So there's
another example of an argument that's not used. Here's an example of an argument that's
missing and we get an index error, a tuple index at a range. Kind of an odd error but
it's because of how it's implemented. So it couldn't find, it said okay, I'm supposed
to substitute something but I can't find anything. So here, hello class, hello class,
so here you can do multiple ones and it counts, so the H goes in the first place, et cetera.
You can use numbers if you want which is handy if you, here's a bad case of using it, that's
just confusing but this one is actually useful, right, because I wanted to repeat one of them,
I didn't want to put it in over here a second time. So it does, zero gets to high and the
zero here also goes to high whereas the one goes to class. Lots of stuff here, you can
see the format. So if you see a colon D, so curly brace and then maybe a zero or a name
we'll see later and then you have colon and then some format specifiers and there's a
whole mini language, format specification language but it lets you do tons of stuff.
Like you can, D is, you know, show me this number, a line, this decimal, a line, left,
right, centered, put a plus in front of it otherwise it's only for negative. I'm not
going to explain all these things. So here are the left, right and center. So you can
look at these later or go look at the format mini language spec. This one's centered I
think and uses a different character. How many decimals after the decimal point? Truncate
a string, like say, show me the string S, S means string but limited to eight characters.
More interestingly you can put in names, right, so you can say greet who and have placeholders
that are easier to read like that. Let me just remind myself, I converted this from
a different format recently. The edit, I'll remind me later to clean that up a little
bit. Which reminds me, part of why this is as good as it is, which hopefully is good
for you, is because other people have given me feedback in the past saying, oh, maybe
you could do that differently. So at the end in the survey if you have comments saying
this part was more confusing than that part, anything you can do to give me feedback I
can improve this for future uses. And you can thank all the people that gave me feedback
in the past for what you're seeing because I've learned lots of stuff teaching this
class, especially when people point out mistakes. That's the great thing about learning is
it really makes you think hard about what you're teaching. Anyway, so you can also
do this. So here I'm going to have a method, sorry, an M. I'm going to have M bound to
this list of those two strings and then in here I'm going to say zero and zero. So I'm
accessing the zeroth, in both cases the zeroth argument which is M, that list and I'm going
to use square bracket zero and square bracket one. And so I get the high and the class put
in there. You can also use dot. So here is one way, this doesn't use dot, it just says
P is trues under doc attribute or I could just pass P equals true and then use P dot
under doc here. Right, so you can do some of the syntax inside the string. Python 3.6 added
F strings which are really nice, make code much easier to read. And what they do is when
the F string literal is, when it's compiled it saves the string and then when it's executed,
when it actually runs the F string, when it's actually used in this code, I might be not
quite saying that precisely enough. Then it looks in the local namespace, it looks in
the names, current namespace to find the names. So greet, it will go look outside of this
statement into are there any names that I can use to do that substitution. So that's
it. F strings don't just do name substitutions though, they do lots of expressions. Right,
so we could do that or we could do that. So here I'm showing you the difference. This
is a regular string, not an F string and it just prints that out. This is a regular string
with curly braces and it just puts in the curly braces. This is an F string and it has
curly braces and because it's an F string it looks at the curly braces and does something
which is it evaluates this and basically it does the code work of going to find abs and
calling it and getting back the 3 and it puts the 3 in. Okay, so you see the difference
here, not an F string, not an F string, is an F string. Okay. Hang on, make a note. I
didn't like that delivery as well as that changed that and I'm not totally happy with
how it went. Here's another example, right. So here the dot upper is inside, so here's
the F string that starts with the quote and ends with the quote. Inside the curly braces
I have a string dot upper, so this expression gets evaluated. Again, that's kind of confusing.
I'm not sure I would write code like that because it's got the quotes and the F string
and everything else, like a quote inside there. Here's an example of one with a new line and
F string expression part cannot include a backslash. So there are some limitations. You can't put
arbitrary code inside an F string, but you can do some pretty crazy things. So don't.
Doing crazy things is not good. It's easy to be too clever with Python. Make the code
easy to read for future readers. Your turn to do some exercises.
Okay.
Okay. I'm going to go ahead and go through this quickly. There's not a lot of new stuff
here. Well, lots of little details, but the core, there's no big new ideas, I don't think.
So I can change by default print adds a new line. I can change the line size. I can change
what it prints. I can change that to print something else, like a space and a less than
and a dash dash and a new line. Suppose I don't want to print a new line at all. You
would think that saying n equals none would do that, but it doesn't. And the reason is
n equals none is how it was written when the function was written, the print function,
if you don't pass an optional argument, Python passes none. So this is a gotcha you need to
watch out for. So in a case like that where you actually want something that's kind of
like none, well, what I want is an empty string. What string should I put at the end? This
is the way you get that. Right? Is end it with an empty string as opposed to ending
it with the default is sort of the way you can read the difference between these two.
Okay? So that's a little bit tricky. Nothing surprising here. Nothing too surprising here.
Right? It's just doing various values. Colon B is how you do stuff in binary if you want
to do some binary math or colon X for hex or O for octal. Percent will do both the math
for you to make it 3, 3 point instead of .33 and add the percent. And you can say, here's
how much of it I want. Right? And it puts the percent character on as well. This one's
kind of cool. So sometimes you don't know maybe this digits here, like here I know I
want 5.2. I want 5 wide and 2 decimal points. But maybe you don't know until it's some
configuration file or they entered it, someone entered it in your application as part of
the run. Or it changes depending on the type. So you can put the curly braces here and it
interpolates that as well. Right? And there are the .format method can be implemented
on other types. There aren't very many that have. Date time is one of them. Here's some
other examples where we're doing a dot and again a more complicated expression. Okay.
I didn't get ahead on this. Okay. So moving on to tuples and
lists. Any questions? All right. Lists. Nothing new here. The list is 1, 2, 3. So what's
m sub 3 going to give us? Index error. List out of range. Okay. Length of m? 3. Okay.
So what if I want the last element? Well, I need to do some math. Or thank goodness
there's the minus 1 option in Python that says give me the last one. So minus means
start counting from the end. Minus 1 is the last character. Minus 2, minus 3. So I'm getting
the 3, the 2, the 1. If I try minus 4, I'll get an index error. Tuple, very similar. You
can pass the tuple to a list. I'll give you that list. Let's see what else is here. This
should all look familiar. Right? Just sort of refreshing those little gray cells. I can
take a list and pass it to a tuple and it'll create such a thing. So a tuple is immutable.
It doesn't mean it's homogenous, right? Or homogeneous. You can still have mixed data
types in a tuple. And that's very common. So let's look at that tuple. Oops. All right.
There it is. And tuples are immutable. Therefore, this will fail. Tuple object does not support
item assignment. We saw that similar. Same message with string, I think it was. So if
I want to create one like that, I could though. And I can see it. So if M is a list 1, B, and
3, and I do M plus 4, adding lists together does that. Creates a new list from the two
lists that got added together. And if I look at M, what does M bound to? Is it going to
be 1, B, 3, 4 or 1, B, 3? Yeah, I didn't change it. All right. How about a tuple? Let's say
tuple. And if I add 4 to that, what's this going to do? Read the error message. It can
only concatenate tuple, not int, to tuple. That's giving me a hint. Always read the
error messages. Getting that habit. Right? So let's try doing that. Because earlier
I did M plus square bracket 4. Here I just did T plus 4. Here I'm going to do T plus
round bracket 4 because tuples always show up as round brackets. And I still get the
not int. So it can only concatenate tuple, not int to tuple. So in other words, this
got evaluated as an int. Parentheses are used for tuples. They're also used for math. So
in Python and mathy things like grouping things together. So Python saw the parentheses around
the 4 and threw them away. Right? What does this do? That worked. And it's going to be
a tuple. Right? So I can create an empty tuple like that, but this doesn't work for an empty
tuple. And obviously adding more parentheses won't help. Well, I actually don't know that.
Adding up to 3 more parentheses won't help. I haven't tried more. I can do this. No. Int
object is not iterable. So I have to pass tuple an object which is iterable. Okay. Let's
try passing an object that is iterable. That works. So here's the answer. If you need a
tuple of one item, you need a comma or something. So that's sort of this weird edge between
two different uses of parentheses in a language. So now that we have that, okay, that's good.
Now I can do that. And I get back 1, B, 3, 4. And T will now have 1, B, 3. Right? Because
we can't change the tuple. Can I do math like I did with strings as in multiply? Can I use
the star to do something? Yes. Right. And that's actually quite handy. For example,
what's easier to read? That. Oops, sorry. Okay. So that's a good one. So I can do that.
Or this. Right? So that's the rare case when I've actually used star with strings is I
need a certain number of spaces. There are other ways to do it too. But anyway, call
tuple like all the data types. You call it with no arguments and it returns sort of the
empty version of it. And the type of that is tuple. Okay. Let's do some stuff with lists.
There's the BCDF. It's got a length. It's got a min. It's got a max. I can call sorted.
I can call reversed. It's the same as before with string. I can pass it off the list to
actually instantiate the, or to actually do the iteration and pull them out and then turn
them into a list. M is BCDF. Insert 0, a says please insert an a into this list at element
0. Okay. Lists are mutable. You can change them so you can do that. So what's m.insert-1
going to do? Remember what minus 1 does? It refers to the last element. So if I want to
insert before the last element is what this means as opposed to insert at the end of the
list. All right. So there's that. Look at all those E's. Okay. Three E's there. So if
I do remove E, it removed 1 or 3? Well, if it removed 3, it removed 1. So it's going
to say remove 3, then when I do this, it will give me an error. So I think it just
removed 1. So every time. So remove doesn't ask. It's looking for, remove doesn't say
remove from the, it's not an integer offset into the list. It's saying just remove the
element that matches that, that's equal to that. Okay. Pop. Again, just to remind you,
this is just, here's an overview of all the things you can do with lists. Very, very handy.
It takes, removes the last element and returns it as opposed to these others. Remove returns
nothing. Insert returns nothing. None specifically. All right. Okay. Tuples, you can do assignments.
Name binding, namespace operation with tuples. Right? So that's a way to assign I1 and J2.
I can't believe I said assign. To bind the name I to the object 1 and et cetera. Right?
Of course, you don't need the parentheses. You can just do it that way. So here, for
example, there's a tuple and there's a tuple. Right? So you don't need the round brackets
for tuples. In most cases. Sometimes you do. Depends on if it's confusing syntax basically.
T1 is equal to T2. That's interesting. Right? So T1 I created a tuple. T2 I created a tuple.
Are they equal? What does that mean? Well, the answer is two tuples are equal if they,
if their elements are all equal. So it marches through the two, both of those tuples and
does a compare on each one. And if it gets to the end of them and it's been true all
along, then it says, yep, these are the same. They are equal. Sorry. These are equal. These
two tuples are equal because their elements are equal. Okay? Is T1 the same object? No.
I can do count. I can do index. These familiar from string? Yep.
I think it would be possible to change Python's implementation to do that without breaking
any existing code. So Python could optimize that, I think. No, no. It is. This is to use
my earlier language. And I forgot to repeat the question. Could it be that this could
have, that is, could have returned true? Yes. I'm pretty sure my understanding of the Python
language that they could have, they could implement, maybe in Python 3.8, they will
implement an optimization where tuples that are the same should save memory. I doubt they're
going to because it would take a long time to figure that out. It would slow down Python.
But I think that no existing code would break if you did that. In practice, this implementation
doesn't. It stores them separately. Is the one that's in this tuple and the one that's
in that tuple the same? Yeah, they are in this current version. Okay. Count index. Okay.
This is pretty cool. See that star there? I've got one, two, three, four things on the right.
And I've got not just ing, but I have n3, n4, and star rest. What happens here is Python
does the assignment. This is called tuple unpacking, I think, or iterable unpacking.
I can't remember the name. Sorry. And now if I look at those, you can see that I've
got a tuple. And the reason it's a tuple is because I just entered it as a tuple, right?
So I put n3, n4, rest. So that's why it's showing it as a tuple. The point is it's
just three names. I'm just showing three names. What's interesting is the five, six got put
into a list, right? So this is a tuple. So the n3 is three, the n4 is four, and the rest
is the list five, six. And that would be clear if I did it as three lines. Okay. See what
happened there? And how about here? What do you think will happen here? Okay. So this
could be an empty list or could be an error. It's an empty list, right? Which kind of makes
sense. Star, our intuition might be star means zero or more. Okay. So this is very handy
when you need it. And you can put the stars in the middle. The star, sorry, in the middle
of the list. Obviously if you don't use star and you, yeah, it's going to fail. Okay. Your
turn to do exercises. I'll give you about, wow, this is a long one. But there's so much
other good stuff. I'll give you like three minutes probably for this one. Okay. So this
is a very long list. Okay. I'm going to start going through these already. Did anybody finish?
Okay. Yeah. Good one. Darn. I didn't start. I know it's kind of frustrating that I'm
pushing so hard, but there's a lot of stuff. This is just, I'll take time later and go
through it. So what I did a lot in the first half was let's understand the time. I'm going
to go through the time and how stuff's working behind the scenes. And now I'm sort of doing
a lot more. Let's just explore and see all the stuff that's out there with some areas
where I'm going back and saying, okay, but here's something you've got to watch out for.
And we'll see a couple of those in this section. So there's a list. M plus equal. Okay. Int
object is not iterable. That tells me that if it was, I bet I could do something. So
let's try to give it an iterable. All right. So plus equal. Again, this acts a lot like
M equals M plus four or five. It's like a rebinding. Although it actually doesn't do
it through a rebinding. It does it because the plus equal I mentioned before, the Dunder
I add method actually changed the list. So this is the, basically this becomes, this
plus equal becomes a request to the list. Please take this iterable and add these elements,
the four and the five, to the end of yourself is what's going on there. Okay. And it says
iterable. It doesn't say list. So that should work. And that should work. And they do. Right?
Append is how you would add a single element to a list. And that's the list. And then you
add a single element. And it only takes a single argument. So if I want to add three
elements to a list, that will do it. But maybe not quite the way you thought. Right? Append
takes exactly one argument and it appends that argument to the list. It did exactly
what we told it. Right? So it appended that single argument to the list. Del M square
bracket minus one. Is this a namespace operation? Not in this case. This is a request to the
list to the object that M is referring to, which in this case is a list. It's a request
to that list. Please delete your last argument. Sorry, your last element. So change yourself
in that way. Right? And now I've got the M maybe. And if I want to pass call, I can call
M extend and it will iterate over whatever I pass it and add those elements to the list.
Lists take time to get to know them. Strings, yeah, if you're using lots of string stuff
do. Lists you can use all over the place in Python. Dicts you can use all over the place
in Python. So get to know them. I encourage you two months from now, put a note on your
calendar, go read the section on dict in the standard library module and spend an hour
and you'll go, you can do that too. There's all this stuff you'll find. Okay. See that
list, one through seven and A through J. Is 10 in M? No. Then we saw the not in versus
not 10 in. Either of those works. Are five and six in M? Well, that's not actually what
I asked. I asked is the list five, six in M? Right? What if I pin the list five, six
and look at M? Now is five, six in M? Yeah. What about this? Okay. There's a couple ways
I could have gone. I find this interesting because it's checking the type and the contents
to see if that thing is in there. So in is kind of doing equality. Anyway, there's M.
Okay. So let's keep going here. So now I've got M which is one, two, three, four, blah,
blah, blah, blah, blah and I've got N which is one, two and four. So what will this do
you think? You'd think it might give us an error, right? Because the list is the wrong
length. But I'm not asking if they're equal. If I were asking if they're equal, it's going
to say no. But I'm not asking if they're equal. I'm saying is M less than N? What Python does
is oh, yeah, I'll check. I'll do what I can. I will check. Is one less than one? Sorry.
Is one less than one? No. Okay. Well, I'll keep going because I haven't answered the
question is M less than N? Check the two. Is three less than four? Yes. Oh, therefore
M is less than N. Okay. So you can do comparison of list. That's how less than works on list
and similar things. Okay. Sort of like string. Doesn't have to be the same length. Okay.
List we saw. That's kind of fun. You can do a swap without a temp in between. We saw
all these. I'll let you do the rest of those on your own. Splits I showed you. I didn't
show you join though. Join I don't think is a method on string that basically takes all
the elements of whatever you pass it and puts them together with a space in this case or
with a comma space or with a whatever you want or with nothing. If you just want to
concatenate a string, this is the fastest way to do it. Fast as in performance. Okay.
You can build them up but it's creating a new string every time whereas this one doesn't.
It goes down to the C level where Python implemented this and goes oh, I can take that list in
memory and just stick it in very fast into a single string. Okay. Sort is a method on
list and some other objects. It returns none but it asks the list to sort itself and it
does. Reverse is also a method. Returns none. Asks the list to sort itself. Okay. If I take
that list and I call sort on it with reverse equal true. Okay. So this probably looks similar
to sorted and reversed with an ED on the end but they're not. These are methods on list.
Sort and reverse. Sorted and reversed are functions that you pass an iterable to and
they return something either a list or something that can be turned into a list, an iterable.
In this case we're calling methods on the list. So if I do this, what's that going to
do? This string will get passed off the list. Sort will be called on the list and sort does
what? Sorts the list. Asks the list to sort itself and what does sort return? None. And
none. Does none have a reverse? That's right. So let's see if the error says that. None
type has no attribute reverse. And these are intentionally, the behavior is done this way
to make sure you don't mix them up. Whereas sorted, the function is not a method. So there's
a sorted function. It's not a method on list. But it is a function that you can pass any
iterable to and it sorts it. It gives you back a list which is sorted, the sorted elements
of whatever you pass to it. Okay. And that works. So here's months. Months zero. Try
it again. Here's months. Months sub zero is March. Three is June. Minus one, minus two.
This is called a slice. This specifically is a slice. Python actually sees that and
creates a slice object. You can create them yourselves with the slice function which is
handy occasionally. And what it does is it says please return me a list containing the
elements starting at zero and stopping before you get to one. So this is going to return
me a list of how many elements? One. And it's going to return me a list or just a string?
Returns me a list. Or stop before you get to two. Element two. So March, April but not
the third one. I should start that with January. So what will this one do? Remember the list
is March, April, May, June, July. So it's going to give me March, April, May, June and
stop before July because months minus one is July. And what's this one going to do?
Who thinks error? Come on. Who thinks it will give me a whole list? It could go either way.
This is what it does. Again, what I'm showing you these things for is not to say, isn't
Python weird? Python shows this way of working. And once you get to know Python, there's
a lot of consistency in lots of places. So once you've seen this and a few of the other
things, then I can show you other codes. Say what do you think this is going to do? You
say, oh, well, given what I've seen before, it's going to do that. So it's consistent
in the way it treats things. There's lots of empty cases and optional arguments, et
cetera. So what's this one going to do? I didn't say stop before minus one. So it's
going to go all the way to the end just like this one did. Oh, by the way, again, if you
read this as start at element zero and stop before you get to 100, then it feels okay
because it did. It stopped before 100. It stopped at the end of the list. Okay, so this
one is just going to return a copy of the list. Not the same list, a copy of it. That's
one of the three ways you can copy a list are that, that and that. So if you need a
copy of a list, any one of those works. Oh, look, copy works on tuple too. Where does
it work? It actually works on byte array, dict, frozen set, list and set. Those are
the built-ins that have a copy method. Okay. March, April, May, June, July, Mon, July,
Months, two. Is Months two equal to Months? Yes. Are they the same? No. All right. Remember,
let's delete Months zero and of course Months sub zero. We're going to drop March from
Months and Months two, it changed the list Months, right? But Months two is a different
list. So this should all be pretty clear. Okay. So this is the list. So this is the
list. I can do this. All right. I can change elements in the list using, just like I used
Dell and equal before. I can append August. If I want to change August based on what it
is currently, I have to do this, right? I have to pull it out, create a new string which
is capitalized, put it back in. Okay. Yep. No. I'm almost, no it's not. I'm 99% sure.
No, I'm sure. Prove me wrong. Okay. I did that already. So Dell Months two, this is
how you delete an object at an offset in a list as opposed to remove. Remember remove
says go search for that and pull it out, drop it from the list. This one says go find element
at index two and delete it and it just sticks back together. Lists are very efficient in
Python or a wide range of use cases. So they're good for short ones, long ones. They sort
of, when they get to a certain point and you have to grow them, they sort of grow a lot
as opposed to growing a little bit at a time. So they work well in lots of situations.
There's a nested list, a list of two lists and you can access the elements that way.
You don't see that very often, especially because it's places where you would want
to do lots of nesting of big lists. You're probably using NumPy or Pandas or something.
Alright. Here are exercises. I think I'm going to, I think I'm going to go back to the
give you one minute for it. Yeah, because only the first one is really that interesting.
Okay.
So, these exercises are, teach you one new thing here. M sub one equals 10, 20. We've
seen that before. We said change the element, you know, list, please change your element
at index one. Replace it with the following object. So this is going to create a list
within a list. Okay. So, if you're using NumPy, you're going to be using NumPy, and
you're going to say, well, what is this? I'm going to say, well, this is a list. So,
this is going to create a list within a list. Alright. So, let's put it back to zero, one,
two. So, you can do slices and assignment. This says change the elements of the list
starting at one and ending before you get to two, which is the element, which is the
one, and replace them with these elements instead. So, that's the way you can splice
a list. Okay. That's quite handy. This here, you can explore later. It's just, there's
things you can do with the range. Range is a built-in function that returns an iterable,
and you can use it to iterate, well, an iterable over numbers. Start at 10, stop before you
get to 20. Same thing, but count by threes. Count by tens from zero. Stop before you get
to 100. Alright. You can step backwards instead. This is the stop, the start, and the step.
Notice that with, oh, I didn't actually show that. I should show you. If you only give
it one argument, it assumes you mean the stop, and start is, zero is the default for the
start. If you give it two, then it says, oh, you mean start at 10 and stop at 20. That's
kind of unusual, but intuitive. Here, well, what's going on here? Here, I'm saying, give
me a list from zero to 99, and then do a slice, which is starting at offset 100, counting
by stop before you get to as far as you can go, and instead of, and here we're doing a
step as part of the slice instead. So, this is going to give us, this one's hard to predict
if we get it right. I don't think I will get it right. I'm going to start at 99 and
give us 89 all the way down to 9, maybe? Yes. And this one's similar, right? Start at minus
one, which means start at the end. Stop before you get to the element at offset one, which
is the number one. Zero is going to be zero, and count by minus one, and count by tens.
So slicing and indexing work on strings and tuples, too. So all this stuff, all this fancy
stuff in here, you can use on strings and tuples, but you can't change them, of course.
So, range eight gives me this range object. I can create a list by doing a for loop. You
haven't seen a for loop before, of course. Most of you have seen a for loop, but this
is the way you do a for loop in Python. You do for, name a variable that's going to get
bound to each of the elements in range eight as the for loop iterates over that object,
right? Think of range eight as a list, and that's the easy way to think of it. It's
actually a little bit more complicated. It's an object that every time for loop asks for
the next one, it gives it the next one, but it only computes it on as requested. And then
for each one, append i to the list m, and maybe I shouldn't show what m is here. And
we get that list. This syntax is called a list comprehension, and the nice thing about
it is, well, one, it's a little bit shorter code, but much more important, and this is
the way I suggest you think about it, it's a declaration of what you want, not how to
get it. And that's part of why it was adopted as a feature in Python. So it's similar, though.
We define, sorry, in a sense, we're saying for i in range eight, for e in range eight,
let's change that to i. And then what it does is it evaluates the first expression before
the word for, and whatever that evaluates to becomes the element that gets added to
the list as it builds the list. So it does that several times. And so this is just going
to give us the same thing we saw above. But I can have other expressions, right? I can
have two times e. So now I'm going to get two times zero, two times one, two times two,
all the way up to two times seven, right? Or I can do two plus, which would give me
two to nine instead of zero to seven. You can also have an if statement in there that
says, but only put this expression in the list if this value here has, if that evaluates
to true, right? And then it's just going to skip the odd ones. It's going to only include
the even ones, right? Put that in the list if it evenly divides by two. And you can have
other stuff here, right? Here's an f string, a big, long, complicated f string, relatively
speaking. It's bigger than the rest of the list comprehension. So it's going to put a
string in and evaluate that each time for all of those eight. And I get that. And I
can combine the, you know, complicated string and an if statement. Right. So I think this
is easier to read than that and cleaner and nicer. I think this is easier to read than
this is maybe not as clear as a for loop. So use list comprehension sparingly. Right?
It makes sense in some cases, but not all cases. So you notice here I didn't use the
E in the expression that gets evaluated to put stuff into the list. So it's just going
to give me eight spams. Right? So again, unusual use case. I think this is weird. I
would look at this code and say, is that what you meant? Yeah. Do it some way that's clear
that that's what you meant. Anyway. Okay. Oh, and you can do these nested, by the way.
You can have spam for E in range eight or you can have spam, E2 for E in range eight
or E2 in, I have, I've never seen a nested list comprehension that made sense to me easily.
So I would usually avoid that too. Anyway. All right. Let's, let's create months. Give
a name months, bind it to a list of three tuples, which are in alphabetical order, April,
February, March. They're not in month order and they're not in order based on the number
of days. There we go. So if I sort these things, as in create a new list which is sorted from
the old list, I get the same thing. If I reverse it, yeah, that's fine. It all works. And you
notice the way it's doing that sorting is it's comparing the tuples. Right? And you
know how it compares tuples. It compares the first element, then the set, then the third.
Right? All right. Let me show you some cool stuff in Python. Months sub two gives me,
oh, zero, one, two. It gives me March three thirty-one, which is why it's right there.
All right. So let me define a function called get index one, which instead of, which accesses
the element at, whatever you pass it, it accesses element at index one. So if I call get index
one of months, well, here's zero and here's one. So it should give me back that tuple,
right? So I've defined the function. Here's how you define a function in Python, by the
way, in case you've never seen it. Right? You choose the name of the function. You choose
to name the arguments, whatever you want. You use those names in here. You return something
when you're done. Okay. So let's do a get index one of months and hope we get the February
tuple back out. And if I do get index one of months sub two, this is just to make you
think. Right? So if I take months sub two, which would be March three thirty-one, and
call get index one on it, I should get back the three. Right? Okay. So Python, it's very
common in Python to have functions that return functions. So at the top of your screen, you
see my screen is the straightforward way to define the function get index one. At the
bottom here is I import the operator module. I call its item getter callable, which is
a function, and I pass it the number one. It returns me a function that does the same
thing. Okay? And for some of you, if you're like me, having worked in other languages,
this is a function that returns a function. That's really weird. But once you get used
to it, it's really, really powerful. And so if your brain hurts a little bit for some
of this stuff, that's normal. Keep trying and pretty soon you'll become fluent in it.
And you're like, oh yeah, this is way easier. It really makes sense. So I've just created
a function, and I bound that function in the namespace to this. Right? So it's kind of
funny because I take a function object and do an assignment of the name. I bind the name
get index one in the current namespace to that new function object. Well, that's exactly
how the DEF works. DEF basically evaluates some code, creates a function object, and
then adds the name to the namespace. Anyway, a little digression there. So now if I call
get index one, month two, I'm going to get the same thing, of course, as I did earlier.
Three, and there's the two. And what is index one of these tuples? It's the number of the
month. Now here's the trick. Is I can, oh no, wait, wait. Yeah, so that's just the third
one. So all I've done here is instead of having get index one, I just substitute the item
operator, item getter one. So here's this call. This is a hard one to read, eh? Let
me walk it through you slowly. Look at operator. It's a module. Access the object, which is
item getter. Look at the one. Create an integer object. Pass it off to this function. Whatever
it returns, call it because it's a function object. I can call it. Passing it, well, that
thing. All right? So that's what's going on there. And again, hard to read if you haven't
seen it before, but easy once you get used to it. So it works. It returns two, meaning
months sub one, which is February, is month number two. Okay. So here's the way you might
see it is, again, these are the same, but this is a common idiom. You'll often see,
I want to sort this based on a certain key. Right? And so what this does, this is called
a callback. So I pass sorted. You saw the sorted months reverse equals true. Well, here
I'm saying don't sort month in reverse order. I'm saying pass it by using as the key. When
you want a key, sort method, sorry, sort function, when you want a key to figure out how to compare
two things, to figure out the key for the sort, what order they should go in, call this
function. So every time that sorted, so sorted gets a list, it might be huge, and it goes,
which one goes first? We'll have to compare all these. It's doing all these comparisons.
Which one's less than, which one's greater than, which one's less than, these two are
equal, et cetera. Every time it does that, it looks at the objects. If key was passed
in, it calls that, it takes the object, passes it off to whatever operator, item getter,
one return, which is a function, and that pulls out of the object the piece that I should
actually, the sort function should be comparing. Okay? So that's how you can sort on something
other than just the straightforward order of a tuple. So if you're brave, don't snicker
at your neighbor. How many of you found that confusing? Oh, come on. I don't believe
you. I would have. Yeah, no, it's hard to get used to, but this is functions as first
class objects in Python were the most, very powerful thing. Okay. I'll give you one minute
for this one. For the exercises, go ahead.
Okay.
Okay. I'm going to keep us moving along. We're in the home stretch, less than an hour. I think
we've only got 40 minutes. Is that right? Thanks. Thanks for checking my math. Okay.
So this was straightforward. Straightforward, I think. Oh, yeah, nested. Yuck. It's getting
hard to read. Don't do it. Enumerate is something that, so in Python, in many languages, you
need to create an index value and enumerate and count starting at zero in order to do
things to a list. Python, you don't need to do that. So enumerate, you'll often will find
being used when you actually care as you walk through a list what element am I at. But you
can see what enumerate does is it takes an interval and it returns for each of the elements
of that interval, it returns a pair, which is the offset into the interval and the element,
the offset and the element. So here we get zero A one B two C. So basically, instead
of returning A, which it would have without the enumerate, it now returns the tuple zero
comma A. You can do various things with that. Zip is sort of like a zipper, but instead
of like this, it's, instead of like this, it pairs things together. Whatever you pass
it, two or more elements, it takes them all and puts them into tuples. So what this is
going to do is create a list of Jan one, Feb two, Mar three. All right. I threw in the
split just to, you know, keep things interesting. What's this going to do? I've got three months
and four months numbers. I know you can do it. Who thinks it's going to work? Raise
your hand. Who thinks it's going to give an error? It works. Weird, eh? But again, there
are, once you get used to this style of zip's going to stop when it gets to the end of one
of them, it's really handy. There are lots of places where you don't need to, lots of
places where what would have been two lines of code or an if statement is just, well,
just do this thing and for the default empty thing, it'll do the right whatever. That
wasn't very articulate. Sometimes you actually do care and you want something else, so you
can call ittertools.izip longest, I think, in supply default. Well, that's to do the
opposite. Anyway, so that's a little surprising, but that's the way it works. All right. And
these are just different ways to do fancy. All right. And then I told you to do that
and I'm not going to show you how you know how to do that. So, on to the next section.
Dictionaries are amazing. What I mean by that is they're really fast in Python and they
have order and lookup time and over the years, if you program in Python that long, you will
find yourself using dictionaries for more and more solutions to problems. And you'll,
and at first you're like, oh yeah, does that work? You'll see solutions to problems where
dictionaries, they're really powerful. Anyway, to explain dictionaries, we sort of hinted
at them over here. It's key value pairs. So let me start by explaining dictionaries by
reminding you at a higher level of abstraction, sort of mathematical. A list is a mapping,
a one-to-one mapping from a domain to a range. Anyone remember this from high school math?
And the domain is zero, one, two, three, et cetera. It starts at zero, counts up. So it's
ints to something. So that's what I mean by here, from ints to anything. You can have
anything in a list. Right? So here's an example. And I'm going to take January Firmware. I'm
going to add none to the front of it. Or if you have a newer version of Python, you can
just do that, which is kind of cool. Another example of this unpacking. And now, conveniently,
index zero is none. Index one is January, which we call the first month of the year.
February is the second month, and March is the third month. So that's why I did that.
Right? So now I can say, what's the first month? January. Second month. Third month.
A dictionary, you don't need to go to that hassle. You can just put in one maps to January,
two maps to February, three maps to March. I didn't have to put in some weird none. So
now I have something like that. Right? Now I can just say, tell me what month number
it is. Right? Or I can do that and get the reverse. Right? So what I'm doing here is
N, N, M. You notice I have for N, M, and then I have for M, colon, N. So this is a list
this is a dictionary comprehension where similar to a list comprehension uses a curly brace
instead of a square bracket. And instead of a single expression, it has two expressions
with a colon between them because that's the syntax of dictionaries as you see down
here. The key value pairs are separated by a colon. So same idea, slightly different
syntax. Play with it later and you'll get used to it. So here what I have is I've turned
that list into, well sorry, that list of, the list way up there in cell one into mapping
from month to month number. Okay? So now I can say, well what month number is January?
February? March? And it just works. Right? April, key error. That one's new, right?
Key errors when you try to access a key in a dictionary that isn't there. So I can add
it similar to the same syntax as list except instead of giving it an int, I'm giving it
almost whatever I want. I'm giving it a key and it puts the key value pair in. So it inserts
April four as a key value pair and then the lookup on April, that's the part that's just
really fast. No matter, a list of a million and it would look it up super fast because
it uses hashes. Go read about it. And then once I've done that, I can look at it. So
in Python three, if you're using an older version of Python, like three, I can't remember,
I think it's three, six is when sort, is when dictionary order of insertion was preserved.
So in this case, you notice when it prints out, it prints it in the order that they were
put in. I added month, April last and it shows up last. Before three, six, you, no guarantee
what the order was because that wasn't the purpose of dictionaries, was not primarily
about ordering. Anyway, so you can use in and it looks for the key. If you want to look
for the value, it's a lot slower. Month to int, if I do a del, it's going to delete
the one at that offset is what is the, is the terminology I use for a list. In this
case, delete the one at that key or that key and its value. The key value pair gets deleted.
It's gone. It's not in there anymore. Okay. Let's do a few things fun with dictionaries.
Here's an empty dictionary. For C in Mississippi, letters sub C equals one. So it's going to
add keys M, I, S and P to the dictionary multiple times except the M, it'll only add it once.
It'll keep overwriting some of them and each one will have the value one, right? So there's
the dictionary and those are the letters in Mississippi. So there's an example, trivial
of okay, I need, I've got this huge list. What are the unique keys of it or something?
What are the unique values in this list? Dictionary is a quick way to do it. You can also do this.
Dict dot, so dict dot, what I'm doing here is I'm, dict is the type from keys is a function
that's in that. So I'm not calling a method on a dictionary. I'm calling the function
that's in the dict that's sort of hanging off the dict type. And I'm saying create
me a new dictionary from the following keys. It's just going to create a dictionary with
those keys M, I, S and P and they all have the value none by default. You can add a different
default in here if you want as a second argument. Okay.
And here's another way to do the same thing where I'm using a dict comprehension. All
right. Okay, let's import collections. Remember that int returns zero if you call it with
nothing. So now I'm going to call, I'm going to create a default dict. Default dict is
a type that lets, that basically it's a dictionary that to start with is empty. But if I access
an element that's not in there, it doesn't fail. Instead it goes off and calls whatever
function I pass to it, puts in whatever that function returns and gives it back to me remembering.
Oh, all right. And now it knows that M is zero. Right? So now I can do this. I can actually
pull the value out, add one to it, put it back in. Even for letters like S that aren't
in there yet, it'll assume that there was a zero in there. Oh, so now I actually have
a count of the letters. Right? How many S's are in Mississippi? There are four. And I
can look at the, there's a, dictionaries have dot keys, dot items, dot keys, dot values
and dot items. The keys give just the keys, the items, values just give the values and
the items give the pairs. Okay. There's also collections, a counter thing that's a lot
easier, so you can just do that. Interestingly, dictionary views are these things that keys,
values and items return. You can iterate over them and do membership tests on them. So I
can iterate over them. What's the most, how many, find the highest number of, it's hard
to describe, Mississippi has letters. What's the most common letter? This doesn't answer
that. It's how many of them are there? The answer is there's four. There's more than
one letter that have four. Okay. And is Z in counts keys? No. Okay. There's also a set
type in Python, which is basically implemented and think about it a lot. Like it's the keys,
a set is like a dictionary with only the keys where the values are ignored. They're not
even stored in the dictionary. Right? So the set of Mississippi gives me that. You notice
there's no ordering on that, by the way. It doesn't order at M and then M. Like the set
order doesn't matter. Assiniboine is the river that I live close to and it also has lots
of I's and S's and N's, which is nice. So I can do things like what are the letters in
Assiniboine? I can do subtraction. I can do intersection. I can do or. Right? I can do
equality, of course. So lots of stuff you can do with sets, which are nice. And you
can do those straight on the views that dictionary gives you back. You can actually do set operations
on those directly, which is very nice. That doesn't do what I expected it to because
I didn't give it what I thought. Sorry. Because what I wanted here is probably the set of
sets. Doesn't matter. Trust me, it works. We'll keep going. No. Trust me, this doesn't
work because I did the wrong thing. But what I'm pointing out is you can do set operations
on the keys. The problem is the count keys. Oh, because count is, I don't know why it
didn't work. I'll figure it out later. Okay. So I said at the top here, you can put almost
anything in the dictionary as the key. You can't put everything. Hash is the way they
work. Hash basically returns a unique value for a string. Well, very unlikely. So it's
the way that dictionaries are fast. Try not to get distracted into those digressions.
And you can take a tuple and hash it. You can take a list and it says you can't, you
can take a list and hash it. And it will tell you it's unhashable. And the reason it's
unhashable is because you can change it and that would mess up the dictionary lookup if
you changed it after you put it in the dictionary. So that's why this is a valid dictionary and
this is a valid dictionary and this one doesn't work. Right? So if you really need to create
a dictionary with lists you know you're not going to change, you can create a subtype
of list and do stuff. But basically, the things you put into a dictionary, their hash can't
change once it's in the dictionary or it will mess up the way dictionaries work. Okay.
This one I'm going to just do a couple of these. I'm going to do, and I'll let you do
the rest later. Right? So pop and pop item. So pop item is the way that dictionaries work.
So a dictionary, once you put stuff in there you can access keys and values and items.
Pop says go get this one, take it out of the dictionary and return its key, sorry its value.
Take this key out and return its value. Pop item just says well go get me one and return.
Pop it out and give me some. Similar to list pop. Okay? And this one I'm going to skip
and the set stuff I'll let you play with. And I will just move on to this dictionary
example. I like this example. I hope it's helpful because the fact that functions are
first order objects, they're first class objects in Python, that and some other things
about Python blur the line more than usual between code and data. When you write Python
programs often you'll have stuff in code that looks in data, in a data structure that
looks like, that is code. And this shows you an example. And when you first see it it kind
of looks odd but you'll quickly, over time you'll learn, you'll say oh that thing I
wrote in that other language three years ago that was like 500 lines of if else statements.
I could have done it in a dictionary. And here's an example. So I'm just going to,
there's a little digression here to, let's create a calculator. Seven plus three. It's
a calculator that handles three characters. You can only give it three characters, a string
of three characters. So I'm going to start by reminding you that, oh, operator that had
item getter has a bunch of other things. It also has all the operators like the plus but
as names to objects that you can use as a function. So I can call operators add function
pass it two arguments and it's exactly the same as if I said seven plus three. Why don't
I just say seven plus three? Because I don't have to write an if statement. That's why.
You'll see why. Right? So that works. I'm looking for puzzled looks. I don't see too
many. So here I'm going to do the unpacking of my strictly three character calculator
input and get seven and a plus and a three. I'm going to turn the left hand side and
the right hand side of the plus operation into ints. So I get seven plus three with
the seven and the three as ints now instead of strings. Because then, oh, and now I'm
going to turn them around. Let's put the operator first so it looks like the order that operator
add needs. Now I've got the plus corresponds to the operator add and it passes the two
arguments in. Right? So that works. So now I do this. Right? So this is a dictionary
where the keys are a single character string, a string of length one and they happen to
be the operators plus and minus and the value is a function. So now, and again some of you
will go, this is obvious, others will go, this is really hard to think about. Ops sub
op is look in the dictionary for the key plus, for example, and whatever you get out, call
it, see the parentheses come right after this. Actually I put a space in there. But the point
is this is if you have an object and you put parentheses and some things and close parentheses,
that calls the object. So it's going to call the function. So when I call the function
add, I'm going to get ten. So here's my calculator. I define it taking an expression of three
characters. I do the same lines of code I just showed you and it returns the call of
the function it got out of the dictionary based on the single character string. Calls
it with the arguments it got out of that single string. I'm going to have to define it first.
So now I can do calc seven plus three, calc minus five, right? So it does math plus and
minus but it doesn't do slash. So the way you may have implemented something like this
in a class long ago or on your own long ago would have been an if statement. If it's a
slash do divide and all this stuff. Here if I want to change that I just add something
and it works. Again it's hard to imagine here but when you're doing something where you've
got lots of options often the data structure of code that holds code in the form of functions
is a lot easier to work with and all easier to maintain and reason about etc. Okay. Okay.
Anybody know what this is going to do? What? Syntax error. Yes. Indent error. I'm wrong.
It's an indentation error similar to a syntax error. So Python indentation matters. You
probably know that already but there's proof. Here's an example of a for loop. So you have
while and then an expression that evaluates to true or false or is evaluated as true or
false and we'll see later that some things that you might not think you could put there
you can like an empty list is false and a non-empty list is true. Anyway we'll see that
in a moment. So basically the colon starts a block. You put four spaces. You can do other
numbers and you can use tabs. Don't always use four spaces. It's what everyone does almost.
And then it executes these two lines of code and then it goes back up and says well is
i still less than five? If true it will keep going around the loop and as soon as it's
false it skips it to the end. Okay. So let's see if this works. Yes. The genie is out of
the bottle. Python is doing what we want. Here's an example of an if statement. If,
elif, elif, else. Just does some printing. Here's a for loop iterating over a string
which you've seen pieces of before but here's typically how it would look. Here's a nested
for loop. Right? And again it knows when does it, you can't see here but it ends the block
when it gets to the end of the file like in this case or when it gets to an unindented
line. So that's how it tells. So it's very clear. But unusual if you're used to curly
braces. Let's create a little dictionary. So you can see what it looks like. So it's
going to see what it looks like. Here's a simple for loop over a dictionary. So here
key and value for D in the items. So this is how you would iterate over. So you notice
here K comma V. This is a tuple. This is doing name tuple assignment. So items is going to
return pairs. Half the pair gets into K and the other in V. So K is bound to one. V is
bound to the other. Right? And I should do a nest string for that. Right? Here's a, loops
can have a break which says if you get to this, so here it's going to count, this for
loop is going to keep going, keep going, going until a thousand unless it hits a break which
it's going to because we have a nest statement in there. So a break is the way you stop early,
stop a for loop early. A continue is how you stop part way through the block of a for loop
and go to the next iteration around the loop. Okay? I can't remember why I have that one
in there. Well, you can have a pass. It just passes the empty. It does nothing. So apologize
for not remembering why. And these, 20 minutes left. So I'm going to stop here. So I'm going
to keep going. So is this going to print true or false? I told you two minutes ago. Well,
it's never going to print false because I didn't say to print false. Sorry. Is this
going to print true or not is what I should have said. All right? And the answer is it's
not going to print true because in Python, an empty list, an empty dict, an empty set,
the number 0, the number 0.0 in floats. Anything, I can't remember what else. Anything that
defines a dunder bool method and there's something else with non-zero. That might have been a
name change. Anyway, the point is there are things that are kind of falsy it's called.
And so, and that's confusing if you're not used to it. So this one especially, right?
Here I've got a list that only has something that is falsy because none is falsy. If you
say if none, it won't do it. Although as I mentioned earlier in a function, you would
often say if none, if argument is none because you care what they passed. You don't, I'll
explain that later. So this really looks like it ought to print true. But does it? Only.
Oh, it does because list is not empty. Non-empty. So it doesn't matter what's in the list.
As long as it's not empty, it's going to say, yeah, that's true and then therefore
I will execute that. So you can see that bool of that and that is why it did that.
And here are some other examples, right? Bool of an empty string is false. So an empty string
is falsy, truthy and falsy. I've only ever heard those talking about Python. How about
bool of false? It's true because it's a non-empty string and we don't need to convert. Like
int, it did a conversion. It's not going to convert the string false to false because
there's no point. So dictionaries, here's a, if you iterate over a dictionary without
the items, it actually just iterates over the keys. Okay? And you can do that. And I'll
skip those. I will skip all of those and let you do those. Okay. So let's talk a little
bit more formally about iterables and then just explore them a little bit. So what happens
in a for loop is whatever the expression is, is evaluated, right? So I might have some
complicated expression as opposed to just a single name that refers to a single object.
It gets evaluated and that's an iterable. We call that an iterable because it is able
to be iterated over. It then calls the iter built-in function on that object and that
produces an iterator and the next function is called repeatedly on it through the dunder
next method. And then eventually it raises a stop iteration which is an exception but
it's a special one that's actually not an error. It's just something convenient as a,
like when you're, like think of a function, a function that calls a function that calls
a function. In this function I might have a return and a return and a return but somewhere
in there if I have an exception, it might not be caught in that function, might not
be caught in that function, might go all the way back to the third one that called, right?
So exceptions are another way of returning a value but they go through a different route.
They don't just return to the caller as a function does. They return to whoever catches
the exception further up. And stop iteration is used internally by Python to implement
for loops because it's convenient. Okay. What does iter do? Well, it looks for a dunder
iter and calls it if it exists. If it doesn't then it calls dunder get item. So lists are
iterable because they have get item which is what the square brackets do. Anyway, that's
a high and dry, high level and kind of dry presentation but let's just play with it.
Remember this? I said you have to pass to a list. Well, we don't have to. We can remember,
like I saw what the object is. Let's just grab the object here. Actually maybe it would
be easier if I here did. Let's just look at it there, right? And its type is, doesn't
tell me much more. It has some arguments including a dunder next. So I can call it.
And what do I get? Well, it's a list 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 reversed. Well, no. It's something
that can iterate over a list in reverse order. So behind the scenes it's actually storing
the list and then marching through it backwards because it's better to do it lazy. Do the
evaluation later and there are times when that saves memory or CPU. Okay, so I can call
it again. So again this is the built in that you can call without the dunder iter. So the
first is a method on IT. That's what next calls. So I can call it again, call it again,
call it again. This is how the for loop works. It kind of knows to know that. And by the
way if an iterator is exhausted is the term, then when you call next on it again it should
still raise the stop iteration. So if you ever write your own iterators from scratch
it's easy to do. Make sure you handle that edge case correctly. Of course here's the
normal way we would write it. Right, we just do a for loop. We don't need to use the next.
It's the for loop that did the next for us. And when it got the stop iteration we never
saw the stop iteration. It just exit the loop. Okay. A list object doesn't have an iterator.
But if I pass it to the iter function and get back an iterable, sorry an iterator, take
the iterable, pass it to the iter function to get an iterator, it's got one. Right, and
it does similar kinds of things. And this is the way it works. So get item zero, remember
list here is one zero through five. Get item zero is what actually gets called when Python
or equivalent to when Python sees the square bracket. Right, so get item zero is the same
as M square bracket zero. Think of it that way. I can get the next one, I can get the
next one, I can get the next one. Sorry. Just a note to myself to remember I might change
that slightly. Okay. So here's a list comprehension. So here's a list comprehension. So here's
it is of type list as you can see. This looks almost the same except it uses round brackets
instead of square brackets, also known as parentheses. All right. Generator object,
gen expression. This is called a generator expression, similar to a list comprehension,
similar to a function which is a generator which we probably won't have time to see.
And its type is generator. Does it have one of these? Yes, it does. It has a bunch of
other stuff too but it's got in there, it's got GI code, frame, running yield from close,
send and throw, those are interesting things you might find out about if you go read about
generators. So I can call next on it and it raises a stop. Right, so this is an iterable.
So this thing is iterable and here we're just exploring how the iterator protocol uses
it by calling next and then it raises a stop duration. Okay. And I'll let you play with
this on your own. How much time we got? Twelve minutes, right? Anybody tired? Oh, I'm getting
tired a little bit. Well, if you're not, let's just keep going for three hours. Okay. So
I'm going to show you one more section probably which is this one. I don't think I'll get
to the next one which talks about classes a little bit and then there's another one after
that which has some exercises you can do on your own. So this is all great to have, you
know, one liners but this is not the way we actually code. So I thought, let me tell
you a little bit. So if you're going to write a script or module in Python, if it's a script
you're going to run, put that as the very first line. Even on Windows it works if you're
using the Pi tool. If not, on Windows you can use suffix.py. There's also a pyw that
works for reasons of whether or not it shows the console. When it evaluates the script,
when you import a module or run a Python script, it compiles it into bytecode on the
fly and stores it in a folder that looks like that. So if you see those line around, that's
what's going on. Only compiles it the first time it's used until you modify the py again.
Always name your scripts with lowercase and valid Python identifiers because then you
can use imports on them later as they change and grow over time. So what I'm going to do
here that you can do too is I'm going to write that file which happened to already be there
which is why it warned me using this special syntax. If you unpack the zip you should have
this file in there anyway so if you're not running Jupyter Notebook you'll be fine.
Import play zero, what's that going to do? Which one? Which error? No module close. Oh,
yes, totally right. Module not found error. So that's what import. When you try to import
so what it did is import took this not string but identifier. So it's not a string literal,
it's an identifier which is a valid identifier but it turns into a file name and it goes
looking for a file called play zero dot py and there isn't one here so it failed to get
it. It actually can look in dot py file dot pyc dot pyd and zip files that have things
in it. All sorts of things is where it can actually look but typically it's looking in
play zero dot py. Can't find it. So this one play so here this is interesting. When
it loads this code it runs it so x equals three y equals two and then it should do a
print. I only noticed last night that this is not going to print. It doesn't work with
Jupyter Lab which I was using last night. Jupyter does this correctly. Jupyter Lab
I think is either a bug or they just didn't do it. I don't know. So you notice that it
printed module loading when we imported play one. All right. That's why I have these comments
here is because it was doing different in Jupyter Lab which is the newer version. So
if I import it again it didn't print that. Right? So the first time it loaded it it loaded
the module. This print statement was executed as was the assignment the y equal and the
x equal. But when I load it when I do an import and it's already been loaded it just says
oh I've got that already and it doesn't reevaluate the code. It doesn't recompile all that and
get the function definitions or whatever else in that module. It just uses the one it already
has. If we look at what's in that module what attributes that module has. Well it has the
x and has the y. Right? Which are at the global module level up here. It has some other stuff
like the file which is where it came from, package, spec, etc. So we can access those
attributes and if they don't exist it will say not a name error but an attribute error.
Module play has no attribute. I can add them. Anybody get nervous seeing that? I can just
take someone else's module and put stuff in it. That's kind of weird but you can do that
in Python. You probably don't want to. So we trust you to do good things with Python.
Not write crazy code. Then I can access it. Now if I look at play one there's the z.
I can change the name and just give it a... So all this does is it does the import which
means it goes and finds that it's already imported it and just inserts a new name. So
what this does is it says when you go find where that module is called use this as the
name in the current module that is added in the namespace as opposed to using the name
I gave you which lets you go find the file. I can look at that object and see that it's
got the same attributes. I can delete that. Of course these are just two different names
and so neither of them have the z attribute now. If you really need to reload which occasionally
is handy when you're doing development for example you can import import lib and it tells
you what you can do. So you can do a reload of it and you notice it says module loading.
If you want to force a reload that's the way to do it. It won't automatically go look.
Every time you do an import it's not going to go look to see if it changed on the disk
because that would just slow Python down with not much value. It's pretty rare that you
need to do a reload. It's almost never would you do this in production code or regular
code you're running. It's almost always you would only use this when you're doing some
work.
So let's do this and import snt. So here you can just import some of the names from a module.
So I did from play to import snt, do your play to. Remember what this is going to do?
I only imported snt. I didn't import play to. It's a name error. It looks for play to.
Couldn't find it. But it does find snt. So I'm just helping you think here about what
the again focusing on namespaces. If you understand how names work everything is easier in Python.
Alright let's look at a bigger one. So this is a bad idea to actually have a module. When
you write a module it should never do anything other than define functions, define classes,
define constants and maybe import other modules. So putting a play right in here is a bad idea.
This on the other hand is allowed. So what this does and this is the right way to do
it and it looks weird I know but it's using that dunder name attribute of modules. Basically
what this does is if we are running the play module, python play3.py it will do all these
definitions and then this is the only code that gets executed. And if we're calling
it by typing python play3.py then the name will be made and it will execute test play
or whatever we want it to execute. That's the way you write a script or program that
top level runs. If we import this module and if we import this module it won't execute
test play it will only define functions and the global player. Okay so let's see if that's
right. Oh I've used the import star I told you not to use. Alright but you notice it
didn't, oh sorry this really needs to have a, I really want to prove it. I should have
a print in there but trust me it didn't actually run test play. It defined it but it didn't
run it and you can see that those are there. Player is one and there are the two functions
and their function names they've got these longer names to tell you where they came from.
Three minutes. Function, there's a longer exercise in section 11 that I'm not going
to do that does, talks about functions and lets you explore them more. Just some nomenclature,
the signature is even and if you want to use the precise terminology n is the parameter
and two is the argument. Not a big deal but when you're reading stuff that might make
things clear. Here's an example, an example, example, I'm going to skip this. Okay so
I'm going to skip this and talk about generators, last thing. So generators I mentioned them
in passing, we saw a generator expressions, here's how you write a generator function.
So this is a function but instead of having a return in it, it has yield and what that
does is, here's the function, it's a function right. So if I call it will I get one, two,
three? No, I get a generator object. If I pass that iterable off to list it will get
the one, two and three and stick them in a list for me. Okay let's do it the way we
saw a few minutes ago, there's the iterator, it's type is a generator and we can call
next on it right. So this function is something that a for loop can iterate over. So this
is a function, okay so here's how you would typically call it. Right so whether you call
list one, two, three and it returns a list or whether you call it and it only returns
an item every time as it goes around the loop, that's fine. So if you put a print statement
right in here in between these things you would actually see the prints interleaved
in here because it actually puts the function on hold and then it starts it again to get
the next one. It starts it again until it hits a yield, starts again until it hits a
yield. So the for loop and the iterator are working interleaved. Okay so here's a faster
way to do, a simpler way to do the same thing right. I could just instead of yield one,
yield two, yield three I could just do that and same kind of stuff. Alright let's try
factorials. Here's a way to do a factorial function. So let me call that, call that,
call that, call that. So what if I pass this factorial generator, which I should have named
that in there. What if I pass the factorial generator off to list? What's that? I will
run out of memory. I won't get a recursion error because I'm not doing a recursion solution.
I'll run out of memory because it will just never quit. Right? So I'm not going to run
that actually. But I, so what I will do is I'm going to, I'm going to create another
function which just stops when the length of what it returns is passed a certain length.
There we go, oh nice. Okay last thing. Here's a function that returns a list of even numbers
less than ten. Here is a generator that on demand returns a list of, not a list, a sequence
an iterable of even numbers less than ten. Which one's easier to read? Which one's simpler?
The first one I would say no. At least once you get used to it. You don't have to do
this thing. You don't have to do this thing. You replace, or you don't have to do this
thing. You just yield and it's simpler. Right? So generators are nice because they're lazy.
Some things you don't know when you don't want to compute all the factorials. But you
might want to compute some. You don't know how many. So you just only compute on demand.
Reading a file, you might be trying to read a file that's bigger than the amount of memory
you have. Well don't read it all at once. Read it line by line. There's lots of places
where that's true. Network traffic, same thing. And generators are important for async
stuff. But they're also just easier to think about and read and write. Well once you get
used to them they're easier to write. And you notice that the use of these two things
is the same, right? For renom and even ones, renom and evens two. Sorry. They do the same
thing. And there's an exercise and some stuff with calls and I'm out of time. And thank
you for coming.