All right. And speaking of presentations, I would like to introduce you to the first
presentation of this block at PyCon 2019, Shu Hong Wong, speaking about releasing the
world's largest Python site every seven minutes. Please make him feel welcome.
Hi. Hi. Good morning. My name is Shu Hong. And my talk is about continuous deployment
and how we do it at Instagram. So something about me first. Who am I? I'm a father of
three lovely kids. I went to Instagram since 2014 to about four and a half years now. I'm
a production engineer and manager. So the state of server release right now. In Instagram,
we release server code 70 to 100 times daily. This is about every seven minutes at PyG.
So at Instagram, we operate a very large fleet of web servers, serving Instagram.com. And
every weekday, we deploy new code. So during PyG deployment hours, it can be as fast as
every seven minutes. In this talk, I will walk through the series of evolution that
brought Instagram here, sharing the insights we learned and the problems we had. Everyone
can identify with at least a stage of this continuous evolution. And I hope that this
can either be an inspiration or a blueprint for your continuous deployment system. Just
like every one of you, we started with a deploy script. A deploy script that copies a package,
unpack it on the host, change the system link and reload the server. We made this script
accessible to all engineers and encourage anyone to deploy the site and take down the
site themselves. So to make it accessible so that any engineer can deploy at any time,
we added a simple locking mechanism so that we don't have more than one person deploying
the site at a time. We have very good test coverage from day one. So we hook up the script
to run our test suite before deploying. However, tests can have its blind sides. So we then
build a simple process that deploy the code to a few machines and monitor the written
HTTP status code. So you can see in this simplified table, we compare the 200 HTTP status code
returned for the Dynas overview. And since the change is small, it's safe to deploy.
As we have more engineers and become harder to track what commits were being deployed,
we built a system to track deployments. This gave us better visibility and we are able
to correlate what changed when we saw errors in production. Then we also want to notify
the authors so they can be around to support their changes. The call me author is usually
the best person to figure out if an error we see in production is related to that change.
Eventually, we also needed to upgrade our parallelism engine as one machine couldn't
handle deployment just quite fast enough. So we have a tier of machines that allow us
to do parallel SSH execution. So what I'm trying to say over here is that we have a
deployment script and it matured over time. There are a lot of features. We kept on building
it. It's been deploying Instagram for many, many years. It also laid the foundation on
how we do deployment in Instagram. This is a simple yet very significant phase of our
deployment journey. Much of our deployment process was conceived and codified during
this time when it was easy and fast to prototype and improvement. Implement running our tests
can be done in a day, canary can be done in a week. Automation doesn't need to be complex.
Improvement to the script also came organically. When anyone can deploy code, actually encourage
the commit authors to own the process. So when Instagram engineering team was small,
many people actually contributed code to the deployment script. A lot of ideas that went
to the deployment script came from the people that used the script. So human is also the
weak link. So we wanted to empower engineers to deploy their own code. However, you can
push code or deploy code. It doesn't mean you will deploy code. I can land code on Friday
night and promise to deploy on Monday morning. But Saturday came, we need to deploy a hot
fix and my broken code that I landed in trunk just went out together with the hot fix and
caused a lot of confusion where the additional breakage came from. So there are also escape
doors and options in the script. When put in the hands of humans, sometimes inconsistent,
I can say I know I broke this test, but it's just a test. We can still deploy and I'll
fix it in a little commit. So the deployment script empowered humans, state control and
ownership. We also found that humans were not the most trustworthy lot. So for example,
do you want to run tests before pushing? Yes, of course. Test failed. Do you want to continue
pushing? No. So at the same time, we noticed that all the options in the deployment script
can have safe defaults. Most of the time, people should just use automatic safe defaults.
Lessons learned is do not present them with options to override. So override only became
explicit and only when we needed to take calculated risk to fix an urgent problem. So what happens
when you have safe defaults? So if you manage to take a log, manage to run tests successfully,
canary successfully, deploy successfully, it can just go to the next one. So when all
the stars are aligned, we don't need any human input. So it came after a while, we think
about it. We have a commit. As the safe defaults in the deployment script continue to mature,
we realized that we can probably hook it up to the post-commit hook so that it runs the
deployment script with the auto defaults. And this is the start of our continuous deployment
journey. Starting with the script, polishing it, putting in the automation brush to the
point where we can do continuous deployment. And maybe you have all the ingredients that
you need and it's already primed to do your own continuous deployment. So what do we get
at this stage? The computer is doing deployment for us. We deploy every single commit consistently
and as soon as it lands, it reduces time taken to narrow down the error to a change we know
as soon as the build breaks. Continuous deployment also became a service. So we noticed a shift
in paradigm. The whole intent of setting up the post-commit hook is to remove the human
and we were successful. The paradigm shifted from I'm going to deploy this myself to I'm
going to land this and let automation take over. There are a few side effects to this.
So fewer people actually know how it works, how to deploy the site and how to roll back.
As we scale and we have more and more engineers committing code, we have more instances of
the build breaking because people accidentally commit broken code. So this is not scalable.
The deployment team became the bottleneck. So we came up with an idea. Why not just don't
break trunk? So trunk was often broken because engineers unwittingly land broken code. Can
we stop them from doing so when build is broken? It's almost always extra effort to resolve
because the people who notice the breakage are not the people who are not the best people
to understand the breakage. When a post-commit doesn't pass, it doesn't deploy. It runs
block and slow down. So we built a land blocking flow. As soon as an engineer tries to land
a diff, it's based on the master. Run test, run canary and many of these instances can
happen in parallel. Dozens of changes can be in flight at the same time. And we only
allow a change to land on the master when it passes test and canary. So the commits are
stacked on the master branch. We only use the master branch. We know the last deployed
marker. As soon as commits are landed, we run test and canary on them again. The reason
why we run test and canary again on them is because commits can raise when they land.
Two independently passing commits can conflict and fail post-commit. So test and canary
run at their own speed. Sometimes a diff that landed later might finish testing earlier.
When we have a commit that passed test, we immediately deploy to that commit. And this
goes on and on. So what does this land blocking flow give us? So we ensure that the commit
is production-worthy before allowing the land. So we push back the ownership back to the
commit author to own the change. This is very effective because they are the best people
to understand what went wrong when test failed. And this also localizes the impact of breaking
the bill to the engineer himself. Also putting back the responsibility back to the hands
of the engineer. So everyone moves faster when they are not blocked. And this reduces
the load on release engineering. And it actually reduces release engineering as the bottleneck.
So lesser incidence of trauma broken means that commits are now deployed more reliably.
Commits will be pushed to production within one hour of the commit landing. Because of
the land blocking flow, we have a higher guarantee that the commits that landed will be deployable.
So now we could establish an SLA of deploying commit within one hour of it landing. The
real upside is that now we can put forth the expectation for the engineer to be online
to support the other changes when they are deployed. There's no risk that when we deploy
the change, we realize the engineer has already left the company. So another important control
flow is the landlock. Sometimes we need to pause the pipeline. So production is in trouble.
We need to roll back or do manual investigation. We usually take a deploy log so that, well,
we don't deploy anything right now. We also have a landlock where we can take to stop
anyone from committing code. It happens sometimes. We have to take all the logs, manually understand
and resolve the situation before resuming the pipeline again. This allows us not to
pull out commits waiting to deploy. We typically do not accumulate more than tens of commits
waiting to deploy. So what really happens when an error slips past test and canary?
We take all the logs and do manual firefight. So Instagram, so what's worth pointing out
is that Instagram has a culture around building tests. We always ask in post-mortem, why wasn't
that error caught by test or canary? This culture actually is a backbone and reinforces
continuous deployment. Of course, test and canary are not bulletproof. Sometimes you
need volume to overload a back end. Some of the slow firing errors only become obvious
at scale. Test coverage is good, but humans do make mistakes. So to catch errors that
are only obvious at scale, we're set up to improve the deployment system that can do
deployment in phases. So canary used to be our last time in defence. We go through div,
testing, canary, and deploy to everything. We added the C1 tier. So the C1 tier is the
first tier we deploy to is about 2% of all hosts. So the div now goes from div, testing,
canary. We let it sit in C1 for five minutes, and if we don't see an increase in errors
in C1s, then we deploy to everything. So for a single commit, the time taken to reach all
production increases by the time you need to sit in C1. So test, canary, type check,
typically takes about ten minutes. C1, seven, C2, seven. So at this point in time, you're
thinking, hey, how is this deploying every seven minutes? So if you're the first commit
of the day, the first deployment takes about 24 minutes from the time the commit landed
until it's pushed to the end of production. Remember that test, canary, and type checks,
so as soon as if you have six, ten divs that land, they'll all run in parallel at the same
time. Then we have a list of ready commits to deploy. So C1, with a keyword hazard commits,
the throughput of the system actually depends on how fast we can move commits through C1
and C2 because they are pipelined. As soon as something passes, it will move to C1, C1
passes, it will move to the next commit. So C1 and C2 moves every seven minutes. So at
this point in time, our deployment script gets way too complex. There's massive coordination
needed to do deployment in phases. Script was just doing too many things. It was a nightmare.
So we finally threw our many thousand lines of deployment script. But note that we came
a really long way. We used our deployment script for a really long time. So we still
have the post-commit hook. What it does is it pushes commit info into a database. We
build a controller that is a decision maker to move deployments along. So the controller
queries the DB for a list of commits, understands what is last deployed, what is ready to be
deployed and makes a decision to promote a version to a tier of machines. Then we have
two runners. So the runners are responsible for the tier that they belong to. So the runner
pulls the version for the tier from the database and broadcasts the instruction to roll to
all the machines. And within those machines, we have a deployment agent that implements
the roll and the log interface. So rock simply means that I'm going to the machine itself
knows how to pull a package, load a new code, reload itself, and yep, you're done with it.
Log just means that we do not move the version until the end of TTR. So we can log a machine
and say that please do not continuously deploy on. So in this system, solve a few problems
for us. We were able to codify a state system that we can deploy in phases. And it actually
decomposed a complex system that was a script into simpler components as a controller, a
runner, and various agents that we can reason, debug, and improve iteratively. So we have
a pipeline deployment system that's deploying once every seven minutes. C1 became our second
line of defense for the site. And the system is modular. But it is still a fact that a
single commit takes longer to deploy to production. The line became longer by the time taken to
sit at C1 and C2. And how fast C1 and C2 can progress depends on how fast we can reload
the code. Next, so we try to deploy as fast as we can. But really, we want to answer why
do we want it fast? So you see the commit on the right very often. We definitely care
about iteration speed. But it's actually more than that. Being able to deploy fast means
that we get better support from the commit authors when the code is being rolled out.
So this means we can react faster to breakages. And our engineers, they don't slow down for
us. The longer it takes to deploy means that more commits are batched at once. This makes
deploying even more dangerous. So this just, like, deploying faster just means better productivity
and safety for us. So when there's only one commit in Cure, we just obviously deploy a
single commit. So when there are two commits in Cure, so we know that the time taken to
deploy the first commit is 24 minutes. Pipeline deploy means that the next one takes several
more minutes after the first. Still deploy commits one by one because we have time to
deploy both in an hour. But what if we have 20 commits in a Cure? So theoretically, we
can deploy about eight times an hour. So we need to deploy three at once to go through
20 of them in one hour. So it's just a balance between batching as little as we can and still
deploying within one hour of commit landing. So we can only deploy at the speed of a lot
of capacity loss. Ideally, we want to widen that rate band over there so that we deploy
the many machines at once and be done with deployment as soon as possible. But that also
means that we need to have machines sitting idly around waiting for us to deploy, and
that's a waste of capacity. So how do we go about making sure that we are reloading as
fast as we can by using as little capacity to reload as we can? So we use UHG. We build
a hop swap mechanism to reload code without draining the server. So the idea is that we
fork and re-exec a new master. We shut down the idle worker that we find as idling between
requests. We spawn a new worker on the new master, eventually moving all workers to the
new master, and then shut down master with the old code. And the server reload is done.
So throughout this time, the server is continuously taking traffic. Yeah, the server is continuously
taking traffic during this time. So what this gives us is that it exploits all the minute
idle time that we have when a server is sitting waiting between requests to reload the code
as fast as possible. So during low load time, low traffic, the servers reload faster. During
high load, servers reload slower. But the message here is that we can't limit the volume
of commits that engineers chose at us. In fact, we kind of exist to enable the development
of the server. So how fast we can deploy really affects how many deployments we can do in
one hour and how many commits we need a batch for deployment. Deploying faster, smaller
batches of commit equals to easier to find out if something broke. As we grew, we increasingly
met problems such as needing to run slightly different versions of server runtime, scaling
parallelism for our runners. Our fleet used to be 100% homogeneous. But it wasn't always
so. Sometimes there was once we did a pi 2 to pi 3 migration. We needed to run different
Python runtime for different parts of the fleet. C1, C2 is now a permanent feature.
They move at different times. Maybe we do a runtime upgrade and we need to leave it
for a few days. Another team needs to test a new version of a library in a virtual. And
the point is that we need different configuration at parts of the fleet. And in Trollkey 3,
we use various hacking methods to make that happen. Sometimes we're taking a file into
the machine, teaching our pieces of tools to understand that. So we came up with the
thought, what if each individual server knows exactly what code is supposed to run and does
its own deployment? So when we need to run different configuration in production, the
runners quickly become unwieldy. Like, we need a different runner for each of the different
configuration we run. And the scale to more machine, we need to shut them. So we remove
the runners. And we have each server's agent read its own tier mapping to understand what
version it needs to be at. So this is... So on a single server, the server reads the tier
assigned package. It fetches the package itself. It promotes itself. It reloads. And this repeats
again. So with this, we do not need to worry. Or we work the system when we need to add
more machines to the fleet. So over the years, we solved one problem after another and ended
up with this system here that's deploying seven to 100 times a day and every seven minutes
a peak. So the landing strip enforces the land blocking flow. It's our first line of
is a parallel workflow. An engineer should only block him or herself. Without signal
from the landing strip, we will never be able to operate our continuous deployment system.
The controller does what a very disciplined human would do with 100% consistency. This
is the part that moves aside every seven minutes. Then each machine in the fleet is then responsible
for itself and deploys as fast as possible through hot reloading code. This is the grand
overview of the system. However, in this presentation, I want to point out that it is not the system
or that we deploy 70 to 100 times a day or we do that every seven minutes that's interesting.
I feel that the cool parts are the problem that we had and the north stars that guided
us to build this deployment system. In Instagram, we always say do the simple things first.
So, it is true that we never had a grand plan of what continuous deployment and Instagram
will be like. We did what is enough for us to scale. When a step was mundane and repetitive,
we let the computer take over. When lands were breaking trunk, we made it compulsory
to pass all tests and canary before landing. When we discovered that one single big push
was breaking production, we broke it up in phases and we still run the controller on
a cron job. So, next thing, like pushing as fast as we can, this is a rather simple yet
important concept that regular pushes make production change these things. Remember the
XKCD comic? That's what we tell people that we care about their experience and deploying
faster. But really deploying faster allows us to deploy in smaller batches and it turns
out to be safer for production too. So, this also means that when we push more frequently,
the more we do this, the easier it gets. We are definitely bolder when we know that each
deployment changes small. And this is the last slide and the most important one. There
is no continuous deployment without signal if the change that we are about to make is
going to break production. And the truth is that my team would never be able to build
such a system without a culture around code quality and testing that is held to a very
high standard by the engineers in Instagram. It is the hard work by the larger Instagram
infrastructure team to push type checking to 100% in our behemoth code base, the push
for comprehensive test coverage, relentlessly asking why wasn't this caught in test, the
server-side frameworks that made building new features safe that made all of this possible.
And some of the amazing people from Instagram that are carrying this culture are sitting
amongst you right now. So, go grab them at Instagram booth at the exhibition. Talk to
them and learn more about engineering at Instagram. So, in short, the last slide is just saying
about you can't do continuous deployment without signal. That's the end of my presentation.
Yeah, I can do that. Thank you very much, Xiong. We have a couple of minutes for questions.
If there are any people who would like to ask them, there are microphones in the aisles.
Please step up if you have a question. Thank you. That was very interesting. One thing
that I'm wondering is you seem to kind of rely on the fact that every possible program
that could be introduced by a commit actually shows up within these, well, seven minutes
or 24 minutes. Is that really true? I would expect there is often problems that only show
up like maybe after six hours or so, and if you've deployed another 10 times since then,
can you really easily attribute this back? Okay, so six hours is too long. So, usually,
at Instagram's rate of scale and traffic, you know it the minute it hits production.
To come back to that question, I would say that the pre-landing flow is just about running
tests and making sure that the things that the engineer put in is not complete garbage.
The canary is the one that saves the site a lot of times. Typically, we catch one or
two bad commits a day. The C1 is the extended coverage that we say that, well, if production
looks right, then there is a small amount of things that actually slips through. This
is the part that keeps the team awake at night, right? To keep reiterating on that, taking
a look at, oh, how did this actually get to production? And those small bits of things.
So sometimes it's about increasing canary coverage, like increasing the number of machines
that we run canary on so that we get better signals. Sometimes it's about whether if we
actually surface that signal at all through logging or metrics into our logging system.
So I feel that I went about answering your question. So in short, usually if something
is obvious in production, it's really obvious in the first minute. And if we miss it in
the pipeline, we iterate on it and find ways to improve it.
Hi. Did you ever think of doing a more traditional alpha beta production staging?
No. I thought about that, but is it like the best, I keep saying that you can't do continuous
deployment without signal. The best signal comes from actually the real code hitting
production. That is, I mean, this is not to say that it has in production, but like the
slower when it hits every user, the slower that we get that signal back to iterate. I
wouldn't completely reject that thought, but it's just that we care a lot about development
speed as well. And this model works very well for us right now.
How many different services is this deploy pipeline interacting with? Are you pushing
multiple services at the same time, or is this infrastructure running for each individual
service? This is a monolith. So Instagram.com runs
on a monolith right now. And this system over here pushed the main Instagram.com site. And
there are also other microservices that we have, but they have their own push cycles.
I'm interested to know how much your engineers rely on the deploy time tests and the canary
versus tests they run themselves before they make the commit in the first place to know
the quality, like the signal, if their code is good or not.
So I have no data point on this, actually. I have this hunch that people usually put
a change through the system and test if the system catches that error for them.
Hi, I've got two questions, actually. First one, do Instagram engineers also use feature
flagging, and how does that fit into the deployment system?
Sorry, can you repeat your question again? Do you use feature flagging, and how does
that fit into your deployments? Feature flags, yes.
We do use that. So it is not affected into this at all. So we want to expand our canary
system to also cover that surface.
And one more question. How do you deploy your deployment system?
How do we deploy our deployment system? That's a really good question. So we deploy our deployment
system continuously as well. It breaks, but we also like to know as soon as it breaks.
And usually when a deployment system breaks, it is always under control, and we can always
roll it back really fast. So it's more about maybe a 10, 20 minutes outage of the deployment
system, and we can bring it back online, turn ourselves in the bag, and move on.
Last question here. Hello? Okay. I'm curious if you could talk a little bit more about
how the UWSGI removal master process fix up works, or is that like a trade secret?
Yes. So one of my ex-collegues gave a talk at PyCon Australia. So for more details, watch
that talk. But feel free to look at me at the Instagram booth. We can explain to you.
Thank you. Thanks.
Thank you again, Shu Hong.
Thank you.