Okay, great. Good afternoon, everyone. This is great. Looks like a full room Instagram
celebrity status. Okay. A little bit by myself. My name is Dui, and I am not cool enough to
have a Twitter handle, but that's my LinkedIn custom URL, Pugs rule. So if you want to connect
with me, go ahead and do that. And if you're looking for a bit.ly link, it's bit.ly PyCon
Pogge. So pronounce my name. It's like that with all the E's afterwards. Dui. And so currently
I live in Boulder, Colorado, and I work as a software engineer at Google. We... These
awful products. And I work on an organization known as Core Systems. So it's like this horizontal
infrastructure layer. I particularly care about gender equality and mentorship in tech.
These are just areas that are very near and dear to my heart. Before that, though, I used to lead
the data team at an ed tech startup in Boston, Elevation Education, and then I left to travel
the world. I lived out of a suitcase for a year and a half, and I bummed off friends, and then I
wandered from hostel to hostel, but programming was still a passion of mine. So it's something I
continue to do. And I even continue to program in a rainforest, like here. So I lived in that musty
van for three weeks. Surprise, it had access to Wi-Fi. How's that for accommodation? And one of
the projects I worked on while traveling was this idea I had about Pokemon. So that's what we're
going to be discussing today. Let's get into it. So I really do love Pokemon. I am not referring to
Pokemon Go. So I am referring to the classic handheld games. And there's a site online where
you can go and you can play other people online. But one thing that I didn't love about it is that
the community is not that welcoming to newer players. So more experienced players, they actually
go through great lengths to hide their strategies. It does make sense. There's precedence for this.
So if you know Amon's moveset and their EV spread, it becomes very formulaic about how you deal with
it. So if you told me you had physically offensive setup sweeper Mega Charizard X, there's a very
finite set of checks and counters for that Pokemon. But still, this was not okay with me. I thought
that we should be better supporting to our newer players and we should be able to democratize that
information. And then one day, I noticed that all of the battles do not require authentication to
look at them. And so here I am in the middle of a rainforest and I signed myself up for that free
tier AWS account, which is ridiculous. And then I started scraping all their battles.
So that's what we're going to do today. We're going to talk about this passion project of mine
and use it to draw specific examples so that we can better understand working with distributed
systems, working with microservice architectures in the cloud. I will mention that when it comes to,
I refer to this as Distributed Systems 102. So at the bottom there, you can see that link
for LVH's Distributed Systems 101 for PyCon 2015. Disclaimer, it is an exceedingly technical talk.
However, I do want to continue that discussion. And today I want to talk about how can we maybe
ground some of the concepts for working with distributed systems and make them more practical.
I want you to leave today and think, oh, you know, I'm working on this new design. Hold on,
I've seen this pattern before. I've seen this problem before. How can I reproduce this?
When it comes to, so this is how I break down with distributed systems. Oftentimes teams will
pursue distributed systems because they care about scalability. Maybe they want to scale compute,
they want to scale storage, they want to even scale human resources. These all make sense.
A common way you do that is with concurrency. However, there are non-trivial consequences.
So two that I'm going to call it right away. One, holistically the system just becomes more
difficult to reason about. And two, you have to come to grips with the fact that your system
will now fail. So how can we compensate for these two things? So today that's the framework that
we're going to be working with. We're going to be talking about distributed systems. I'm going to
show you how we can achieve the concurrency while also providing techniques for compensating for
this, how do we assert the correctness of our system? In other words, how do we test our
distributed system? And at the same time, how do we build in resilience against failures?
Okay. So oftentimes when we're talking about these technical presentations, it's helpful to
start with an architecture overview. On the right side here, this is what a Pokemon battle looks
like. So as you might imagine, there are two players, they have their respective teams,
and they're battling each other. This is, yeah, Shift Gear Megina and Specs Ashgrin Ninja.
It's actually all open source. So that's also how this made it a lot easier. It's a reverse
engineer. So if you go take a look at their GitHub page, it turns out that the web UI,
it's communicating with the server using this text protocol that resembles a domain-specific
language. If you spend enough time looking at that text protocol and you're able to replay all the
logs, you can exactly replicate the state of the battle. Okay. So then I started thinking, well,
what if I just create a little bot and the bot just sat on the page and then when the battle was
done, it just scrapes all the battle logs from the DOM. It's like, oh, that seems pretty reasonable
to me. But that only gets us one battle. How do we get all the battles? On the left side,
if you go to the main chat room, there's this list of battles. It's something like the most recent
10 or 20 battles or so. The reason they have this feature is maybe you're visiting the site and you
want to spectate on a battle, you can go check out those. It only shows the most recent 10 or 20 or
so, but that's not really a problem when it comes to programming. I figured if we have a process
that's on a tight enough loop, then we could definitely collect all of those URLs without any
gaps in them. And then that way we would have all the battles on the entire site. So now we have a
way to download the logs for a single battle and replicate the exact state and we have a way to
get every single battle on the website. And a link if you want to play is at the bottom.
So I implemented this using Python and they were on Docker containers in EC2. But a bit
higher level, so this is the flow of the system. So starting from the upper left, we have this
component that watches the list of rooms, gets all the battles, and then as it scrapes those URLs,
it pushes it onto an SQS queue. Then there's this some farm of download bots that will slowly pop
work off this queue and then sits on the battle, waits for the battle to finish, and then scrapes
the battle logs. The battle logs are persisted in S3. I also had a lambda function that would be
triggered on S3 puts and every time there's a new blob there, it's going to index it in ElastiCache.
Yes, when you're unemployed, you have so much time. So much time. Okay. So for today, we're
going to really focus in on that left column. So the component that watches for all the battles
on the site, it putting all the work onto the queue, and then a farm of bots downloading those
battles. Okay. So take a look here. This is the code snippet that we're going to be working with.
I hope it's not inspiring code to anybody. Pretty straightforward. We have a roomless
watcher. It scrapes for all the battles and gets a list of URLs. We iterate through the URLs and
then we serially download them. This was great for an MVP, but then I quickly already ran into problems.
Already, like, in my head, I wasn't able to keep track of everything that was going on.
Sometimes I'm working on the bot that's just downloading the battle and then I forget, like,
maybe do I need to do some special authentication thing for SQS here or do I need some special
retry logic when I'm working with the roomless watcher? I always had to keep the whole breadth
of the application in my mind at the same time. People here who are working with microservice
archers, I think you're already picking up on the language here, right? When the application grows
too big to fit into your head, this is often a good sign that we should decompose our application.
There's more that we can push this because the download bot, it just wasn't achieving the
throughput that I wanted. So these were all these indicators I thought, like, okay, maybe this is
time. Maybe I should start to make this into a distributed system to get the scale that I want.
On the left side there, this is how I view it. So I saw, okay, the roomless watcher, the download bot,
they achieved some type of business logic. Whereas the URLs in the middle, this is just state. This
is just data. So we have components that when we talk about them, they get highlighted as some type
of component. We have a roomless watcher. We have a queue that holds state. We have a download bot.
And in addition, there's a separation between business logic and state. This was not quite
persuasive enough for me, though. And so I started to take a look at how my different components
differ in terms of rate of work, specifically magnitude. That's a mouthful. Let's unpack it.
Okay. So the roomless watcher. So I'm using Selenium as the web automation framework.
So once you've initialized the page, let's say that takes on the magnitude of three seconds or
something like that, it's fine. We have the page open. But you see that refresh button in the upper
left in the red rectangle. It turns out that the list of the most recent 10 or 20 battles,
you can refresh it with just a simple async call. So now that means that the magnitude, once you've
initialized the page, is actually on the magnitude of only 300 milliseconds. So that's pretty fast.
That's like acceptably fast. But the download bot, it's very different. It's much more erratic.
Let's say that, I don't know, you and I were battling. And then it might be that once as
soon as we get into the battle, I have to DC. I have to disconnect because whatever, my girlfriend
says we have to go eat dinner or something. So the battle could just take two seconds.
But maybe in some other situations, the battle could take 45 minutes because both players
brought stall. And by stall, what that means is you bring fat mons, mons like Chansey or Venusaur
or Clefable, these Pokemon that have really high HP stats and just take forever to wear down. So
yeah, a battle could take 45 minutes. But now that we've seen that there's a difference in
responsibility, there's a difference in the type of components, business logic or state, and there's
also a very significant difference in how the rates of work are operating. We're talking
magnitudes of difference. So this was the evidence that I needed. So I understood the
characteristics of my system. So you start by analyzing the characteristics of your system.
And now this is when we can decompose the application. You've probably seen the diagram
a million times. You take this monolith, which is like a blob of colors, and then you break it into
subcomponents. And that's basically what I did here. I partitioned the application along these
responsibilities. And another phrase you might hear is to draw seams through the application.
So we've analyzed the characteristics of the system. We've seen where would be appropriate
to partition along responsibilities. And now what can we do? Well, now we can layer on top of this
a model of concurrency. Okay? On the left side, what you can do is we can have producers on the
left side. And maybe there's a main thread and it spins off one to end child threads for the
rimless watcher. On the right side there are some consumers. And the same thing, maybe one to end
child threads for these download bots. Between them they communicate on some thread safe queue.
We have this in the standard library. It's queue.queue. So this is the model of computation
that I'm using here. Producers on the left side, consumers on the right side communicating over a
thread safe message queue. At the bottom there, I draw a link, okay, to Raymond Heddinger's
fantastic talk from PyCon Russia 2016. If you haven't seen it, I strongly recommend that you do
specifically if you're getting started working with concurrency or you just need a refresher.
I would strongly argue this is the must have first go to talk. Absolutely. So he starts by positing
that and I paraphrase it at the top there. Unless you're implementing an operating system,
you should strongly favor using higher level primitives such as thread safe message queues.
And in this case it would be queue.queue for Python. He also includes something called
Raymond rules. These are rules of thumbs. These are best practices for working with concurrency.
And some of them, if you don't, it's not like, A, maybe you should follow this if you feel like it.
It's really if you don't follow these rules, your algorithm is simply not correct. So I strongly
recommend thinking about concurrency by Raymond Heddinger. This gave us throughput, right? So on
the right side there, if I wanted to, I could more or less achieve linear scalability. If I double
or quadruple the number of download dots, I will double or quadruple the throughput of that right
side. Again, for those of you who have experience working microservice architectures, you notice a
problem. And that's the state in the middle. So if we're working in the cloud, you need to assume a
node is going to drop. It's not like maybe it's going to drop, but it will definitely drop
eventually. Maybe through maintenance or maybe just through, I don't know, a freak storm and
somebody trips over the power wire. If I had something like 100,000 URLs in that queue, what
happens to those? Do they just all disappear and I just lose all those URLs? So that's not good
enough. However, because we've partitioned the application, because we've decomposed into smaller
subcomponents, we can swap it out really quickly. So instead of just having queue.queue,
you can swap it out for an SQS queue. And this was a really easy solution. All of a sudden, by
swapping out that component, I achieved this rich feature set of cloud services, right? The message
durability, the scalability, the instrumentation, you just get that out of the box. But that's only
possible because beforehand, we've analyzed the characteristics of our system, we've decomposed
it properly, and we're focusing on not like these implementation details, but how do we get that
out of the box. So in Go, concurrency is a first-class citizen. So what that means is that
concurrency was a conscious decision to include into the language specification. It's not
implemented as a library. Think async IO, which is implemented as a library. It's not
a library. It's a language specification. It's not a library. It's a language specification.
So it's not a library. It's a language specification. It's not a library. It's a
language specification. It's not implemented as a library. Think async IO, which is implemented
as a library. But concurrency is part of the runtime. That gives us three constructs. Go
routines, channels, and selects. I'm just going to talk about go routines and channels today.
And so this is how the analogy plays out. So if I want to do the same solution in Go,
on the left side, maybe I'll launch one-to-end go routines to watch that list of new battles.
On the right side, maybe I'll watch, I'll launch one-to-end go routines to download the battles.
And in the middle, they still need to communicate. How do I get the work from the producers to the
consumers? So in Go, we have a contract called channels. And channels, what you do is from one
side, you can send in work or messages. And from the other side, you can receive that work.
I want to point out that across all three of these examples, whether it be Python or AWS or Go,
three technologies that were written by three different teams and written across multiple
decades, they all arrive at the same solution. So the reason for that is because we're not focusing
on small implementation details, but we're focusing on how we are composing our components.
How are we orchestrating the work? And that's what I urge you to focus on as well.
Same solution, three different technologies. So that's great. And now I have the scalability
in my system and I'm able to download like, you know, hundreds of thousands of Pokemon battles,
and it's a really good time. But I have no idea if it actually works. So it introduces several
problems. Loss of determinism. Let's say I had five URLs in the queue. Well, on one run of the
test, maybe I get through all five and the work is processed sequentially. That's great. On the
next run of the test, I might only get halfway through and maybe the order is scrambled. In
exchange for the concurrency, you give up the predictability of the system. We also have longer
startup time. Starting up an in-memory queue, that is trivial. Starting up an SQS resource,
that could take on the magnitude of minutes. That's something to think about. And in addition,
everything, my processes are now in different memory spaces. Maybe they're on different nodes.
And all of a sudden, we've introduced flakiness. I could have a network partition. I have to deal
with loss of availability for dependent services. When we have these types of problems, we still
can handle them. But they all revolve around this problem of how do I deal with these external
dependencies? Let's get aligned on terminology really quickly. I want to talk about mocks and
fakes. With mocks, mocks are these objects that we can just extend on demand. You interact with
them and then afterwards you can introspect them to understand the history of the interactions.
We can understand who called you, how many times were you called, with what arguments were you
called. Fakes are a bit different. With fakes, they should be able to serve as drop-in replacements
for the real resource. This means that they fulfill two criteria. One, they have to implement
the same interface and two, they have to guarantee the same invariances as the real resource.
For example, if for whatever reason I was trying to implement a fake queue, there has to be a way
for me to put and pull work from that queue. In addition, if the original queue were FIFO,
I can't suddenly have a fake queue that does not maintain sort order. That would break one of the
invariances. How did these come into play? I'm going to talk about testing external dependencies.
Currently I work at Google. The complexity and scale of Google is mind boggling. It's surprising
that testing external dependencies is a challenge we deal with on a day-to-day basis. It is that
technical. It is that overwhelming. I'm going to break this down into three different segments.
I'm going to talk about how I tested external dependencies in my Pokemon project,
how Google subscribes for testing external dependencies, and how we think we as a Python
community should do it. All three actually are different answers. So for me, I went with fakes.
Keep in mind, I had no steady income and no job, and I was living in a rain forest and hitchhiking
to get everywhere. If I went past that AWS free tier, that would not be okay. I have no money.
So that's why when I did my testing, I really wanted to prefer something that was a bit more
realistic. Fakes give you that. Fakes are a little bit more realistic, but they cost developer time.
That's okay. I have tons of time. I have nothing to do on a day-to-day basis. So that's why I
preferred fakes. I needed the realism, and I was willing to trade the developer time. What do we
do at Google? At Google, we have this document that's actually linked to the bottom. Don't
bother clicking on it. It doesn't go anywhere. You don't have access to it. But at Google,
we prefer using the real resources. The reason for that is at Google, saving developer time
is paramount. Just full stop saving developer time. That's what we need to be doing. And what
are we willing to trade in exchange? Let's say that you have some test that runs and you need
to start up a spanner instance. That's fine. Just start up a real spanner instance. If you need a
thousand of them, that's fine. Just start up a thousand spanner instances. And I put the word
they're computationally expensive. What I mean by that is if you want to use the real resources,
I can't sit here and wait for a thousand spanners. It's a startup. We just can't do that
serially. So what do we have to do? We have to bring them all up at the same time. If you have
a server farm as large as Google, that is possible. Now, that does take way longer, but ultimately,
because Google is trying to save developer time, we're willing to make those tradeoffs. We're
willing to use the real resources. How about us as a community? So over at the Instagram team,
Mike Krieger, the CEO and co-founder, he mentions how, and this was a talk at Airbnb, maybe from,
I don't know, 2015 or something, but one of the engineering philosophies over at Instagram is
do the simple thing first. There's no question that will definitely fail one day, right? But
that's fine. When you get to that point, just do the next simplest thing. In practice, what that
means is I really believe that we as a Python community, when we're working with distributed
systems and we have all these external dependencies, I believe that our default
should be to start with mocks. Now, mocks are fast, they're lightweight, they're easy to reason
about, and most importantly, if you have a newer developer, let's say you have an undergrad right
out of college, it's okay. They could spend a day reading through the source docs or maybe a couple
days, but they will be able to get started rather quickly. That has real tangible benefits. There
are drawbacks. It's the furthest from production, right? And in addition, you get some issues with
interface drift. Anything you throw to mock is going to work. So there are some problems with
that. But I would still argue that the benefits of mocking in this scenario are well worth it.
So, again, to summarize, I decided to go with fakes because I needed the realism. Google prefers
to use the real resources because they have oodles of money. And then we as a Python community,
I strongly believe that we should just focus on mocks. It's the simplest solution. Good enough is
good enough. So what do we have here? So now we have this Pokemon application. We have all these
bots everywhere and they're downloading tons of battles. And we also know it's correct. So I know
that I'm not just burning through EC2 instances. However, it fails all the time now. The system is
just getting big enough that it fails purely through coincidence. So we need some way to figure
out that how can we build in resilience against this failure? There is a .NET C sharp framework
called Polly. Don't let me lose you. I'm not going to talk about C sharp. The reason that I found it
is just that the way that if you go to their GitHub page, I link it at the bottom, the way that they
help you digest the problem is fantastic. If you're thinking about, like, oh, I've got the system and
it just keeps failing. And there are so many policies out there. I'm sure you've heard of
Hystrix over at Netflix. They have the circuit breaker pattern. And you're thinking, like, I don't
even know when I use a circuit breaker or when I use fallbacks or when I use retries. The way that
Polly describes the problem space is really helpful to think about. So here's an example of
what they'll do. They'll have this, like, little witty saying on the right side, like, don't wait
forever. Or maybe it's just a blip. So now I'm going to show you how I use timeout retries and
fallbacks in my Pokemon project to make sure it's resilient. So starting off, this is the easiest
part, right? On the download bot, when you get to a battle, it doesn't mean that the battle is
immediately completed. I mentioned earlier that it could be going on for 45 minutes. So using the
Selenium Web Automation framework, this is what it looks like. You can see on line two, it says
element to be clickable. So that's the condition that I'm waiting for. I'm waiting for that download
button on the bottom right to be done because that tells me that the battle logs in the DOM are ready
to be scraped. That's the element. That's the checkpoint that I'm waiting for. So this one's
pretty simple, right? I just have this at the smallest unit. I have my download bot. And I say,
hey, go to that page, check it out for three seconds or so, and if you don't see anything,
let's just wait a while. It's probably not ready yet. So timeout. That's pretty simple.
At the same time, it's not good enough. So all these different external dependencies and most
importantly, the Chrome WebDriver. So the Chrome WebDriver is implemented using something called
the Gang of Four command pattern. It's a very cool-looking pattern, but what it makes is
debuggability is basically impossible. It becomes a total black box system. It's very
possible that while my download bot is trying to operate with this page, it just gets into a bad
state, and I just have no idea what's wrong. In addition, so Pokemon Showdown, it's a chat
application. So let's think about the characteristics of that system. It means that a lot of the
connections are very long-lasting, right? We're going to try to persist connections from minutes,
if not hours. Unfortunately, there are only two developers or something like that for the website,
so reliability is not the greatest. I could have a bot sitting on a battle, and they just get dc'd.
They just get booted by the server for no reason other than the server can't maintain all these
connections at the same time. So if you take a look at lines 10, 11, and 12, so on line 10,
connection loss, that's what that means. So the server for whatever reason just booted me,
but that's okay. That's an acceptable error condition. If that occurs, just try again on
another attempt. We're not going to kill the runtime because of that. A WebDriver error,
so this is something because maybe when working with a Chrome WebDriver, I get into a bad state.
This is expected, though. So it's fine. We're going to continue to try again. And the last one is the
most obvious one. If the bot goes to the page and the bot finds out the battle is not yet completed,
again, that's fine. We're going to continue. This code here, it's inspired by our holder's
Guava retrying. Guava, for people who don't know, it's Google's common libraries for Java,
and then our holder, he wrote an extension to it. And then inspired on his design for retrying,
it's how I wrote this code here. So what we had at the smallest level, we have a download bot that
has this retry logic, and now when it goes to the page, it might not work, but that's fine. We'll
try again. And this is what really brings in the resilience at a higher level. Now we account for
the WebDriver, we account for the server, we account for the Selenium Web Automation framework
not working well. But lastly, there's also a fallback. You can see there on line 9, so let's
say that I exhaust all my retries. Let's say I expect that the battle will take 45 minutes,
and for whatever reason it's just gone on for an hour and a half. Okay, we're not going to wait much
longer. At a certain point, we're going to kill the retries, we're going to assume that it just fails,
and I need to return something. So in this case, I just return an empty list, a zero-valued object
on line 9. But even cooler than that is on line 13. So I learned this from PyCon 2017. There's a
talk on error handling paradigms, and there's just like this little nugget that she mentions about a
project from Microsoft called Midori. And over in Midori, they use this technique called abandonment.
I've never had a term for it, but so when we're working in the cloud, we assume that resources
will fail. We assume there will be network partition, we assume there will be loss of
availability, and we assume that nodes will just get into a bad state. So what do we do in those
cases? Well, it's fine. They should be very trivial occurrences. We just kill the node and
we instantiate a new one. The same thing here. So sometimes my download bot would just get into a
bad state, and I had no idea how to handle this. I couldn't debug it because the Chrome driver is
too confusing or maybe like the number of network calls with the server and maybe there's like some
bad state there. And so what I did is I would force garbage collect that download bot and then
reconstruct the entire object graph. I'm not going to go into the implementation details here,
but it's a technique that I think is just so, so cool. And that was definitely what set this
project over in terms of just making it rock solid, that abandonment strategy on line 13.
So we've seen how at first I started with this tiny project and was all running in a single process,
and then I needed to scale. I couldn't keep it all in my head and I wasn't getting the throughput
that I wanted, so I sought to achieve concurrency and I did that using the message passing.
But even though I had the concurrency, I had no idea if things were working correctly.
So we really had to step up our game on how we test, right? And we use those strategies like
in my particular case I use fakes. So now that we have the concurrency, we know that the application
works pretty well. And then with these resilient strategies, we also have some kind of backup
strategies for when things will fail, which they inevitably will.
So unfortunately, I don't have time for questions. However, I hope that it's like
reasonably apparent that I'm an okay approachable person. So if you see me in the hallway,
I'm more than happy to talk about Hawaii or gender equality, or if you're interested about
what it's like working at Google or interviewing for Google, it's the worst. Interviewing for Google
is so hard. Feel free to just come grab me and talk to me. And also if that's uncomfortable,
you're happy to just talk to me on LinkedIn as well. And I did want to leave with this mention
though. So Jack Dietrich from 2012, he said this on the top line there. So we don't ship code,
we ship features. And I want to build on that. So I would also say that we don't solve problems
for computers. We're solving problems for people. I think it can be very easy to forget about that
sometimes and just want to work on the newest, sexiest technology. But I would urge the Python
community, as great as we are, to really focus in on the user. And I think that's how we can
deliver great value. So thanks for your time, gang. I'll see you around.