Good morning, everyone.
Please be seated.
Our first talk is just about to start.
So our first speaker today is Luciano Hamaleo,
and he is going to be talking about sets.
The talk is titled Set Practice, Learning from Python Set Types.
So please give a warm PyCon welcome to Luciano.
So thank you very much, everyone.
Thank you very much, Maras and the PyCon organizers.
I love this conference.
I've made many friends over the years here.
So I am Luciano Hamaleo.
I am a principal consultant at Thoughtworks,
a company that has offices around the world.
It's an American company that has offices in many countries.
And I'm a co-founder of the PyCon.
I'm a co-founder of the PyCon.
I'm a co-founder of the PyCon, a company that has offices
in many countries.
And I live in Brazil.
And I work in their Sao Paulo office.
So I am better known in the Python community these days
because I wrote fluent Python.
And that's the Chinese edition that I learned
only a couple months ago.
Has already sold 30,000 copies in mainland China.
And there's another Chinese edition in Taiwan
where it's available.
So I'm really happy that the book is a success
and people like it.
And I want to tell you that I'm working on the second edition.
I signed the contract with O'Reilly to do that.
And my goal is to get it finished as soon as possible
after Python 3.8 is released.
The Python 3.8 release is scheduled for October.
And so my idea is to get done by October, November,
something like that.
And then O'Reilly needs probably three months
to finish the post-production.
So the book will be available early next year
in the first quarter.
OK?
So let's get started.
So this talk is broadly divided in four parts.
The first part is motivation.
That is, why should you care about sets at all?
I'm going to talk about how sets work in Python,
meaning how you use them from a user perspective.
Then we're going to discuss a little bit of some
of the ideas of the set API, which can inspire you
when you do your own APIs.
And I'm going to talk a little bit about the Dunder methods,
the magic methods that make the sets work.
And I'm going to do that by showing the source code
for a completely different implementation of sets
that I've developed, that although the implementation is
radically different from the one that Python has,
it fulfills the same contract.
So it fulfills the same API and can
be used in place of other sets.
All right, so about motivation.
We often need to work on stories that are like this,
for instance.
Display product if all words in the query
appear in the product description.
OK?
So another language that I've been studying and using
recently has been Go.
And Go doesn't have sets as built-ins.
So I had to write code like this.
You know, if you look at the, it's not a lot of lines,
but the cyclomatic complexity of this code
is pretty high because there's two nested loops,
and then there's an if in there.
There's two ifs.
And notice that, so there is a found flag that
breaks from the inner loop.
And then there's the not found flag
that breaks from the outer loop.
So it's kind of tricky to write this.
It can be better if you split it into different functions.
But the thing is, step back and look at that.
You know?
What if, and then the guy says, later I'm
too busy coding nested loops.
The thing is, you can look at this as a set operation.
So you have a set of words that describe the product
and a set of query of words that are in the query.
So in this case, the query is coffee grinder,
and the description says manual stainless steel coffee grinder.
And so this is basically asking whether the query is
a subset of the description.
Right?
And if you think about that in a more declarative way,
that's better.
And sets allow you to do that.
Another example.
Mark all products previously favorited
except those already in the shopping cart.
So now we have the F set, which is the favorite favorite
products, and the C is the cart.
And what you have here is a difference, right?
Which we would write in Python as F minus C. OK.
So the thing is, sets are really powerful.
In fact, I found this quote.
Nobody has yet discovered the branch of mathematics
that has successfully resisted formalization into set theory.
Right?
And so logic conjunction is intersection.
So the end operator is intersection.
Right?
The or operator is union.
Symmetric difference is what we call an exclusive or.
In computer science.
The difference is basically the elements of one set
minus the elements of the other.
Right?
So in my opinion, people in the Python community
don't use sets as much as they should.
Put it another way.
I've done code reviews where I saw code that
could be drastically simplified and also made faster, which
is a big win.
Right?
When you get to have something that becomes more readable
and faster at the same time.
That's excellent.
And sets often give you this kind of opportunity.
But people missed this opportunity,
perhaps because of experience in other languages.
I did a little research.
And I found out that in some other major standard libraries,
there are sets.
When there are sets, like I said, in the Go language,
there are no sets in the standard library.
But when there are sets, most of the set implementations
available in other languages are very poor.
Meaning they don't implement a rich API with all the common set
operations.
So people coming from JavaScript may think of sets.
OK, a set is a way of having unique elements.
That's one part of it.
But the other part is having those operations,
intersection, union, symmetric difference, and so on.
So among those languages, only Python and Ruby
have what I consider a rich set API.
So let's talk a little bit about sets in Python.
Ignore the code above.
It's just a generator to generate Fibonacci numbers.
But the important thing is I have this F set below
that I built with a set comprehension.
So it's the set of the Fibonacci numbers up to 10
and excluding 10.
Another example, the primes.
So I have this function that generates primes.
And I have the primes up to 10.
So we have the F and the P set here, right?
So some operations.
A basic operation is to determine whether an element is
in the set.
And we do that with the in operator in Python,
which is implemented underneath using the DunderContains
method.
And this is super fast in the Python standard library
because it's implemented using a hash table underneath.
I'm so old that actually when I started with Python,
there was no set in Python.
But we used dicts because of the hash table
to emulate sets or to build on dicts to do sets.
And then you have all of the fundamental set operations
also implemented as operators, as infix operators in Python.
So the ampersand is intersection,
which makes sense if you think about the default meaning
of that operator in Python is the bitwise end.
And the pipe is the bitwise or.
So naturally is the union.
And the carrot is the symmetric difference
because it's the bitwise shore.
And then the minus is the difference.
So we have these operators as infix operators.
And we also have the subset and superset comparisons
that are implemented that are coded
in math with those symbols.
In Python, we use the less than, greater than, less than,
equal those comparison operators.
They are overridden in sets to do
that kind of supersetting subset testing.
And you can have complex expressions.
I'm not going to go into detail here.
But it's like, so this is a demonstration of De Morgan's law.
In line 20 there, it says that the difference between a set
and the intersection of the second and a third set
is like the difference between the first set,
the original set, and the second, and the original,
and the third with or operator inside.
Anyway, so this is De Morgan's law,
another example of De Morgan's law.
Just think about these expressions written
without the infix operators, calling methods.
That would be really sad, right?
Difficult to read.
And that's what you have in some other languages
that will not be named, that don't
have operator overloading.
Anyway, but Python, and this is where
we learn some good ideas about the API of sets
that we can leverage in our own APIs.
Because the Python standard library also
offers lots of methods for sets.
And this is a table from my book.
But as you can see, for instance, in the first,
so this table is basically split in two parts.
The top part is about intersection,
and the bottom part is about union.
So you have these three different,
you have these operators, infix operators,
to do intersection at the top.
But also you have the methods that
implement those operations underneath,
and that you should never call your own code.
You should not call those methods usually.
But what you would call if you wanted to use the method form
would be s.intersection.
But a good idea here, an example of good design in this API,
is that this is not just redundant, another way of calling.
But they leverage the fact that the function call notation
allows you to have more than two operands.
So infix notation is just for two operands.
But here you can have as many operands as you like.
You have the receiver, which is s.
And then within the parentheses, you
can put as many other things as you want.
And then you have the intersection of all of those things.
And I'm saying things here because they
don't need to be set.
They can be any iterables.
And that, again, is another thing
that they did in the method that is
different from the operators.
The operators strictly operate with sets.
If you use the n% form, for instance,
you need to do one set, n% another set.
But if you want more flexibility,
then you can use the method.
And it allows you to use any iterable.
And it also allows you to use multiple iterables.
So this is a great idea of how this API is implemented.
Think about that.
Often, if you code your API so that you get iterables,
you make it more flexible for the users
to pass whatever is convenient for them
to pass into your API instead of assuming that you're
getting a list, for example.
But an interesting thing that I talked about in my tutorial
the day before yesterday is that maybe you do need a list
inside your operations.
Or in this case, maybe they do need
the set the way that this method is implemented inside.
It's OK, because the set constructor and the list
constructor both know how to handle
iterables, generic iterables.
So one thing that you can do, which is very easy,
is you accept an argument of any iterable type.
And then immediately, you convert it
to whatever you need inside your method.
In this case, a set, or in some other case, a list.
So that gives you flexibility and also gives you safety.
Because at the point that if somebody passes you something
that is not iterable, it will be easy to debug,
because the program will break right there
at the start of the method.
Does that make sense?
So I think this is a good practice.
Of course, it has a cost attached to it,
because when you're using an operation like that,
you're doing a copy most of the time.
Python is smart enough that it doesn't copy, for instance,
frozen sets or tuples, because they are immutable.
So when you use notation in Python to copy those things,
Python cheats underneath and passes you
a reference to the same thing, because it's immutable.
So it doesn't matter whether it's a copy or the same.
Anyway, and so it's like this.
The other operations, the difference
and symmetric difference are also
implemented within fixed operators
and also with methods.
Oh, one thing that I wanted to comment here
is also that there are, here I am describing the full set API,
but there is the frozen set, which is a smaller API,
because it's immutable.
So for instance, both kinds of sets
have the intersection methods and the infix, sorry,
the inplace end, which is written like ampersand equals
to change in place the receiver.
But the set, which is mutable, also has an update version.
So that's one difference.
And I like the naming that is very explicit in this case.
In the case of the union, it's just
called update, the version that changes,
because that goes with the update method in dicts as well.
So it makes sense.
But the other operators are insertion update, difference
update, and symmetric difference update.
OK.
And then you also have the different sets
or the different tests that return billions.
And you have a bunch of other methods
that are mostly about, that don't have anything
to do with set theory in math, but have
to do with practical computing, like adding elements,
removing all elements of a set, making a couple of it,
removing an element, a specific element, iterate over,
get the len pop, which removes some elements
and then raises an exception if the set is empty, and so on.
Now, there is ABCs in Python that define
what a set should look like.
And those ABCs are like that.
So you have the set ABC, the set abstract base class,
that has many other methods that are basically the most of them
have to do with the infix operators.
And set inherits from container, iterable, and sized.
And it's interesting that the set type there,
although it's abstract, all of those methods are concrete.
OK?
It assumes, they assume that you have implemented
the abstract methods that are inherited from container,
iterable, and sized.
And if you have implemented those,
then you get everything else for free.
And in the case of mutable sets, you
need to implement add and discard, which are abstract.
You see the italics there mean that it's abstract.
And then if you implement that, you
get the other methods for free.
Those concrete methods in the abstract classes
is what the Python documentation called mixing methods.
All right, so now let's talk a little bit
about operator overloading.
So the idea of operator overloading
is that you have those other methods that
are called when the Python interpreter sees
one of those infix operators.
Pretty much all of the standard operators in Python
are you can override with this notation,
with the Dunder methods, except for, I think, four of them.
The is cannot be overridden.
The and, or, and not.
The and, or, and not that are written as words cannot be
overridden.
Because of the way the short-circuit evaluation works
with and, and, or, it would not be
possible to implement them as methods.
And the is is not overridden, because what it does
is just compare references.
So there's nothing to change there.
Anyway, but the implementation of the comparison operator
is the simplest part.
That's why in my book I cover that first.
Because there is a symmetry in all of these operators, right?
If you ask whether a equals b or b equals a,
it's the same thing.
And if you ask whether a is greater than b,
it's the same thing as asking whether b is smaller than a.
So you have the forward method and the reverse methods.
There's a symmetry that comes by the definition
of these operators.
But with the other operators, the situation
is more complicated, because maybe you have just
invented some new type, and you wanted
to interoperate with the built-in type.
So let's say I just invented a new set type,
and I want my set type to interoperate with the built-in
set types.
Now, the built-in set types don't know about my set type.
So they wouldn't be able to do, for instance,
the ampersand operation, like built-in set ampersand my set.
This would be a method call on the built-in set,
and it would look at the type of my set
and say, I don't know how to handle that.
You know, the built-in source code of Python
doesn't know about that.
So the way this is solved is the method that
doesn't know how to deal with the other operands
returns a special value called not implemented.
This is not an exception.
It's a special value.
And when you return that special value,
you're signaling to the interpreter,
you need to try something else.
And what the interpreter tries is to reverse the operands
and call the method with the R prefix.
So the end, if the other end doesn't
know how to do with the argument,
then the Python interpreter, then it
will return not implemented, and the Python interpreter
will call the R end method on the other operand,
passing the initial, the first argument as argument.
So with this reversal, the interpreter
is now giving an opportunity for my set class
to handle the built-in set class.
And there's a whole, I drew this flow chart
that talks about how this mechanism works.
And I think it's really elegant.
I think it's really beautiful the way this works.
So one thing that I did was to create an example
implementation of a different sort of sets.
And my set that I created is actually
inspired by a great example in the Go programming language
book by Donovan and Carnegie.
That's one of the best programming language books
that I ever read.
Carnegie is the K in the KNR, classic C book.
And that's also awesome.
And this book is really great.
And in one of the examples there,
they actually implement a set type for unsigned integers
where the values are stored in an array of bits.
So they have an array of uints.
And each bit there tells you whether there is or not
an element there.
So the idea is, for instance, in my implementation,
this constructor here, I'm constructing an uint
set with those numbers.
This is represented by these long ints in Python.
Go doesn't have long ints.
So when they did that in Go, they
needed to use an array of uints.
And that's actually what I did when I first ported this code
to Python.
But then I realized I was suffering
a case of the von Neumann bottleneck syndrome, which
is when you think like a stupid CPU that only reads
one word at a time.
And we are using a high level language, very powerful
high level language.
And we have ints that are arbitrary precision.
So those are implemented underneath the covers
in C, which is a von Neumann limited bottleneck language,
as an array of uints or something like that.
But I don't need to care about that.
So I can represent that set by this number.
This is a long in Python.
We used to call them longs in Python 2.7.
Now we just call them ints.
This is so elegant.
And that's actually represent that.
How does that make sense?
Because it's this bit pattern.
Now I'm going to switch to another slide here
that has only one element, which is the last element.
So this other set, which has only the element 290,
is represented by that huge hint integer, which
has the same number of bits.
But all of them are 0.
And just one of them is 1.
That represents the value 290, because it's
in the position 290.
Does that make sense?
So that's how the implementation that I did works.
And so, for instance, a tricky thing
is how do you represent an empty set?
You represent it by 0.
0 is the empty set.
The number 0 is the empty set.
How do you represent a set with 0?
It's 1, because you need to have one set
bit to describe a number that's there.
And this one set bit is in position 0,
meaning 0 is in the set.
And a set with one number 1 is represented by the number 2,
which is like that bit pattern.
And that's how this thing works.
Now, the source code for this is on github.com
slash stand-updev slash uintset.
And I don't have time to show that now.
But what I've agreed with my friends that work for JetBrains
is 15 minutes after this is over,
I'm going to be at their booth.
And I'm going to be going over the code
for this implementation.
But you can look at it here.
It has tests.
And it's a complete implementation
of the set interface using these crazy mechanics of having
bits representing integers.
And so that was what I wanted to tell you about.
The key takeaways here are that set operations
allow simpler and faster solutions for many tasks.
The Python set classes are good lessons
in idiomatic API design for two reasons.
I think it's not easy to always justify operator overloading.
Sometimes it's overused.
And in fact, there's a key reason
why James Gosling didn't put it in Java.
I read a quotation of him saying that they didn't put it in Java
because operator overloading was way overused in C++.
And they didn't want to have this problem.
But I think everybody has learned not to overuse operator
overloading.
But it's a feature that we have in Python.
And it can be used judiciously.
And I think sets is a great example of using that
in a way that makes sense.
Also, I like the fact that they have the other methods that
take intervals.
So those are the key takeaways.
And like I said, at 11.45, I will
be at the JetBrains booth giving an overview of the code.
The code is on GitHub, like I said,
in my account called stand-updev there.
And also, at 4 PM in the O'Reilly booth,
there's going to be a book signing.
And that's going to be a book signing.
In the O'Reilly booth, there's going to be a book signing.
And the way O'Reilly does is they brought a bunch of copies
of my book, I think about 40 copies or something like that.
And they're going to hand them out.
I don't know what's the procedure for that.
But I think it involves handing out little tickets to people
that are in a line.
And then if you get one of the tickets,
you can stand in a line.
And you will get a copy.
And I will sign it for you if you want.
So those are the things that I'm also going to be doing today.
And thank you very much.
I'm honored to be talking to you.
And I will be hanging around in the hallways as well.
Thank you.