Hi, everyone.
Welcome.
Our next speaker will be talking to us about statistical profiling and other forms of the
CIS model.
Please welcome Emeen Martina.
Thank you very much, and thanks for coming to my talk.
So today I'm going to tell you about why you might want to do statistical profiling.
I'll tell you about some of the various Python tools that are available, and I'll give you
some details about the auxprofile statistical profiling package, which I've written.
These slides and the source for all of this is on GitHub at the address below, so you
don't have to take notes or anything.
Okay, so we're going to learn how to use profilers, and hopefully you'll also learn how to write
your own.
One of the things I really love about Python is it gives you access to the internals of
the system in such a way that you can do things like debuggers, profilers, code coverage that
would be very difficult, at least for me in a language like C.
So let's start with what is profiling.
According to the python.org website, a profile is a set of statistics that describes how
often and for how long various parts of the program are executed.
So profiling is basically useful to find out which parts of your program are slow.
That way you can spend your efforts in optimizing things and writing really nice, tight code
in the parts of the program that really matter.
So for deterministic profiling, there's a number of profilers you can use.
Cprofile is one of the built-in profilers.
It's very easy to use.
You do import Cprofile, and then you do cprofile.run, and you give it a string for the function
you want it to run.
It will then run your code, and it will give you back what's called a profile, which tells
you how many function calls there were, how often each function was called, the total
time, the per call, cumulative, and it will rank them in order of the function that took
the most time.
Then you can look at that deterministic profile and see which parts of your program were
slow or took longer than you thought, and work on optimizing those.
So again, that's deterministic profiling.
So how does deterministic profiling work?
Well the Sys module provides you a couple of really neat hooks.
One of these is set profile.
So if you call sys.setProfile, you can give it your profiling function, and then the interpreter
will execute your profiling function on each function call.
And if you want even lower granularity, you can call setTrace, which is like setProfile,
where you give it a tracing function, and then the interpreter will call your tracing
function on every single line of your program.
And you can use that to figure out what code coverage is, or what parts are slow, or whatever
else you want to do.
Okay, so once we call these things, we get a hook to inspect the stack frame.
So you might say, well what is a stack frame?
So the way the Python interpreter works is you have some function foo, let's say, which
calls a function bar, which calls a function baz, which calls a function boo, and so on.
And the interpreter needs to keep track of the state of each function, the local variables,
and what's going on.
So it creates an object called the stack frame, which we show here.
The stack frame has a number of interesting things.
One of them is fback, which points to the caller's stack frame, so you know where your
function got called from.
There's also fglobals, which tells you which globals you can see.
There's a lot of other useful things in there.
The one we're going to focus on here is fcode.
Fcode is a code object, which is shown in that elliptical feature there.
And the code object has a lot of information about exactly what code is running in that
frame.
It's got the co-file name, which tells you the file name where it was created, co-firstline
number, which is the number of the first line of the source, a bunch of other interesting
things, and co-name.
And co-name is the one that's most interesting for us, because it gives us the name of the
function that is executing that stack frame.
So for a profiler, you look in the stack frame, you look at the code object, and you look
at the name, and now you know what function is executing, and you can keep track of that.
Okay, so let me give you a diagram of how the profiler works, or how deterministic profiling
works.
So you have your program, it's in its main thread.
Let's say there's some loop that's going to execute function one, then function two, then
function three.
So what happens is the interpreter enters function one, and then immediately calls that
profiling function you've given to sys.setProfile.
And then your function will record the name of the function that's executing by looking
at the stack frame, what time execution starts, and then it'll pass control back to the main
interpreter, which will execute your function one.
Then when function one is done, the system will call your profiling function again, you
record the function name, the end time, and then you pass control back to the interpreter.
And then the interpreter moves on to function two, and similar things happen, and moves
on to function three, and again your profiling function gets called to record the name, the
start time, or whatever other things you want to record.
So the key idea here is that for each function call, your profiling function gets called.
Or if you're using setTrace for each line, your trace function gets called.
So that's great, it gives you really detailed information about what's going on.
But the downside is it's slow.
These hooks have to run for each line or each call.
So deterministic profiling is great, but one of the drawbacks is it's slow.
Okay, so what's another drawback?
Another drawback is C number one.
It's slow, and it's really slow.
And so this is important because it makes it difficult to use profiling in production,
deterministic profiling in production.
So deterministic profiling is very useful when you're in the development stage.
You want to run some tests, you want to run some use cases, you want to see where the
bottlenecks are, you optimize it, you write great code, fantastic.
And then you deploy that in your production web server or your consumer application, what
have you, and the users do all kinds of crazy things which you didn't expect, and they complain
that your awesome program is slow.
And they often do that because regular users may not be programmers, so they're going to
use it differently than you.
And so that's a problem with deterministic profiling.
It's harder to get the production experience.
Another, you could say drawback or just kind of a difference in focus is that deterministic
profiling usually is not thread aware.
So this little blurb is from the documentation for set trace.
It says it must be registered using set trace for each thread being debugged.
And there's similar documentation for set profile.
So that is out of the box, deterministic profiling doesn't handle threads really well.
It's not so much a drawback, it's just kind of the way threading works, which is imagine
you're in some function foo and your profiling function gets called and says, okay, we're
in function foo starting at 2 p.m.
And then there's a thread switch and the interpreter starts running function bar, and function
bar takes a long time, and then the interpreter switches back and now it's 2.05 and function
foo finishes, and your deterministic profiler says, well, function two just took five minutes
to run, even though function foo maybe is really fast.
And so that makes profiling threaded code a little bit complicated.
You can do a deterministic profiling, but it is a little bit complicated.
Okay, so what we're going to talk about for the rest of this talk is a statistical profiler.
Now, the way a statistical profiler works is you have your main thread, you still have
your function one, function two, function three, just like before, but the statistical
profiler is going to record a sample of which function is running.
And it's only going to run occasionally to keep the overhead low so that it doesn't slow
down your production code and you can actually run it in production.
So here's a diagram of what it looks like.
So again, you have your main thread running, and then you have a sampler thread, which
is either another thread in your Python program or maybe a completely separate program.
What the sampler thread does most of the time is time.sleep, so it does nothing.
Every once in a while it wakes up from the time.sleep and it peaks in to see what the
main thread is doing, which function is it running, and then it records the name of that
function and then it goes back to sleep again.
So it's basically kind of waking up periodically and seeing what you're doing and going back
to sleep.
Okay, so how do we implement the sampler?
There's a couple different ways and there's packages for each approach.
So one thing you could do is use the POSIX timer.
So the POSIX timer is a low-level timer.
You can set it to wake up and interrupt your process.
And when you get that interrupt, you can check the call stack, see what the call stack is
doing, what function is executing, and keep track of things like that.
A couple of programs that use this are statprof and plop.
So those are great programs.
They're not available on Windows because this is a POSIX call.
Another way you can implement a statistical profiler was something called ptrace.
Now ptrace is a really neat system call in POSIX.
It lets you look at what some other thread is doing and control it or inspect it or whatever
you want.
And ptrace can actually be called completely outside of your own program.
So if you're familiar with something like GDB, GDB works along these lines, which is
you have your program that's running perfectly fine, it doesn't know anything's different,
and then some other program like GDB or a profiler will use ptrace to reach into your
running program and pause it or see what's going on in the stack or otherwise inspect
it.
So that's how Pyflame works, which is a very popular and nice statistical profiler.
Again, it's not available on Windows because this is a POSIX call.
Okay, so you might say, so I've mentioned two approaches, both of which are POSIX, and
so you might say, do we really care about non-POSIX?
I mean, a lot of us use Linux, a lot of servers run Linux.
Why do we care?
So one answer is it's nice to have a portable implementation.
That is, all other things being equal, it's nice to have something that's pure Python,
that's easier to move around to different systems in case, for example, you want to
use Windows.
Another reason is using only Python features makes it a little bit easier to understand
for those of us who are Python experts but maybe a little rusty in OS internals like
set-timer or ptrace.
And in particular, if the whole goal of using a statistical profiler is so you have a low
overhead profiler that you can run in production, it's nice to have an implementation which
is easy to understand, it's pure Python so you can look at what's going on, and then
we can get confidence that this statistical profiler you're using in production is not
going to mess up your code, or if heaven forbid it does mess up your code, you can at least
figure out why and go yell at the maintainer.
The third reason is there actually is software, believe it or not, that does run on Windows.
One good example is games, there's lots of other consumer software.
To take games as an example, if you want to find out why a game is going slow, Python
implemented game or game server for example, and you put a deterministic profiler on it,
it's going to slow down the game, it's going to slow down the frame rate, it's not only
going to make the game unplayable but it's going to make the user behavior a lot different.
So it's going to be essentially impossible to figure out what parts of something like
a game are slow if you use a deterministic profiler and slow it down.
And so for that you'd like to have something that works on Windows.
Okay, so now let's get into how we're going to do this.
So there's this really neat function in the sys module called underscore current frames.
And the way you know it's really neat is because it starts in an underscore in the sys module.
So something special is going on here.
So sys.currentFrame basically lists each thread's current frame.
And so then you can peek into the frame and figure out what's going on.
So this is how pprofile works and also oxprofile which is the profiler I wrote.
And because these are pure Python, they work on Windows, which is nice.
So let's look at how this works.
So again, you have the main thread.
It's in say function one.
You call sys.currentFrames, which tells you the active frame is in function one.
You get that stack frame.
You look in the stack frame for the code object.
You look at the co-name and you get the function name and then you keep track of it somehow.
And then if your program goes on another time, you wake up and you sample and you call sys.currentFrames
and it tells you program is in function two.
And so you record the name and you move on.
Later on you wake up maybe in function three, repeat the same process.
Okay, so I've told you some kind of high level thoughts about why you want to do statistical
profiling, how you want to do it.
I'm going to give you a concrete example here with oxprofile and then I'm going to go into
kind of how it works and the logistics of the sys module.
So if you wanted to use oxprofile, you would do pip install oxprofile.
You would import something from the module.
You would call a launch function to launch the profiler and that's it.
And then you just go on, run your code as normal, start your web server, run your game,
call your URL functions and so on.
And then at some point later when you want to see the profile, you call profiler.show
and it'll show you the profile and you'll see what's going on in your program.
And then if you want to cancel it, you call profiler.cancel.
So relatively easy to use.
Great, so how does it work?
So this is an oversimplified illustration of the sampler loop.
So we have while one, so we're going to loop forever.
This is going to be in a separate thread, so it's not going to block your main program.
We're going to do time.sleep for some interval and then we're going to call sys.currentframes,
which gives you back a dictionary and we're going to iterate over the IDs, which are the
keys, that's the thread IDs, and the stack frames in there.
Then for each stack frame, we'll look at frame.fcode.coname to get the name of the function that's executing.
And then in some dictionary, we'll just increment a count.
So that's it.
So we have a statistical profiler in four lines of code, which again, Python is a really
neat language and these sys module functions are pretty impressive.
You can do something that at first might seem complicated in four lines of code.
A couple things to mention here.
So the way you control the overhead is through this interval.
So you can call profiler.cent interval and it'll change the sampling interval.
So for example, if you use something like a five second sampling interval, it'll give
you a negligible overhead.
You won't even notice it.
And so what we have here is a trade off between various goals, which is accuracy, collection,
time, and overhead.
So in a deterministic profiler, the profiler is always running and looking at each function
call and keeping track of what you're doing.
And that's why it slows you down because it's doing something pretty much all the time.
Whereas if you set interval to something really long, like let's say 100 seconds, almost all
the time, the statistical profiler isn't doing anything.
As you bring that down from say 100 seconds to five seconds, you'll get more accurate
sampling of your program.
As you bring it down to one second, you'll get even more accurate sampling.
As you bring it down to say 100 milliseconds, you'll get super accurate sampling.
And so what happens with the longer sampling times is you just have to run the program
for longer so that your sampler wakes up and sees all the different parts of your program
and gives you an accurate estimate.
So you can tune that knob between accuracy and overhead.
And in theory, if you took the sampling interval all the way down to zero, it would go to become
like a line profile, which is constantly checking what your program is doing.
Another comment to mention is in some applications you may want to add some random jitter in
case you're worried about the statistical profiler waking up and somehow getting synchronized
in your program and never seeing certain aspects of your program.
In general, the Python threading tools tend to have enough randomness that you probably
don't need this.
But I mention it just in case you have some specialized application.
OK, so what does the output look like?
So we call profiler.show and we get this list.
It shows the function name in the module and the number of hits and the percentage of the
overall hits.
So you notice that this statistical profile is a little bit different from deterministic
profiles that you see.
That is, we don't have the time each function takes.
Instead we have a number of hits, how often we saw that.
There's how often when we woke up was the program running a given function.
And through that you can get an estimate not of how long each function takes, but of how
much time of your program it's taking up.
So for example, in this case send is taking is where we wake up most often and see which
function is running.
It's taking 2.8% of the program hits.
So if you want to optimize something, in this case you might want to optimize send or you
might look at other functions and see like, oh, such and such connect, let's say, is 1.5%
of program hits.
Maybe you expected that to be much lower.
And so you can look at this statistical profile to figure out where to focus on.
OK.
So now let's talk about the basic theory of sys.currentframes.
So we start a thread that's doing mostly time.sleep.
Periodically we wake up and we call sys.currentframes to get the stack frames that are executing
and record the info from the current stack frame.
And that's it.
Really simple four line program we showed you earlier.
So in theory you can write a simple statistical profiler with just these.
Now in theory there's no difference between theory and practice and that's just going
to work fine.
But in practice there's a little bit of a difference.
OK.
So let's go back to just the two line core of what we were showing you.
So we're going to call sys.currentframes, iterate over it and record.
Now I've started to make a few changes here which is instead of having self.myDB just
be a dictionary, maybe some other more complicated structure and you want to call a record method
just for generality and nice software engineering.
And instead of just directly grabbing the code name from the frame, maybe you want to
call some function called measureTool.
Maybe you want to record some other things from the frame.
That's not a big deal.
But the question you want to ask is OK, what could go wrong even with something as simple
as these two lines?
So you might want to think about it for 30 seconds.
OK.
So one thing that can happen is a thread contact switch.
That is your sampler thread gets control.
It calls sys.currentframes to look at what's going on.
It starts iterating over the current frames that are active.
And then all of a sudden the interpreter decides, OK, I want to switch to a different thread
context.
So it goes to a different thread, maybe your main thread or some other sub-thread, and
comes back five seconds later and you continue iterating over the frames that you've gotten
returned but now those frames maybe have gone away because the interpreter has moved on
in the other threads.
And so you try and read a stale frame and depending on your Python version you get a
crash.
OK.
So one thing we can do is we can use this other function called sys.getswitchinterval
and sys.setswitchinterval.
So sys.setswitchinterval will tell the interpreter, look, please don't switch away from my thread
for 10,000 seconds or whatever amount of time you give it.
So here what we do is we get the current switch interval, we set it to 10,000 saying please
don't switch away, then we do our really quick iteration over the frames, and then we say
set switch interval back to whatever it was before.
So this will help reduce the problem of looking at a stale frame.
There's other ways you can do it but this is a nice way to illustrate switch interval.
OK, great.
So now we're safer, more robust to contact switches.
Now what could go wrong?
Well anytime you're doing some kind of resource allocation you always want to keep track of
exceptions because if you had an exception here it would prevent switch interval from
being reset and then your threading might start to work strangely.
So this isn't really so much specific to statistical profiling but in general when
you're doing multi-threaded code you want to be parent-oriented.
So here what you want is a try finally so that no matter what happens even if there's
an exception you set the switch interval back to whatever it was originally.
OK, good.
So we're trying to protect from a contact switch, we're using try and finally, OK,
what else could go wrong?
We are just getting started in all the things that can go wrong in multi-threaded programming.
So I should say I don't want to discourage you from doing multi-threaded programming
or statistical profiling.
These things are reasonably robust but you just need to be careful of all the things
that could go wrong when there's multiple threads.
OK, so let's look at recording a sample.
So we have this simple function record which gets a measurement and it's going to look
in a dictionary to see have we seen the name of that function before and then we're going
to increment and if not we start with a count of zero and then we increment the count by
one.
OK, great.
So we're looking at a dictionary, we're incrementing the count by one, it's a two line function,
surely nothing can go wrong here, right?
So what can go wrong?
Well one thing that can go wrong is imagine that you're calling this record or the interpreter
is calling this record method when it's sampling a frame at the same time that the sampling
thread is sampling a frame somebody calls profiler.show to see the profile right now
or some other way they decide to access the self.mydb dictionary.
Then you've got one thread modifying the dictionary while another thread is reading the dictionary
iterating over it.
Python gets really upset if you have two threads, one of which is modifying a dictionary and
another one which is iterating the word.
So depending on your Python version you'll get a crash.
So what you want to do is you want to use a thread lock.
In this case I'm using threading.lock with a context manager and then you make sure all
the code that accesses mydb uses the same thread lock so that nobody accesses the dictionary
at the same time.
So we've got switch the context interval, we've got use try and finally, we've got use thread
locks, seems like we're being pretty paranoid here for multi-threading.
So what else could go wrong?
No guesses?
I don't know what else could go wrong.
There's always unknown unknowns.
So one other thing I would suggest anytime you're doing multi-threaded programming is
use fault handling.
So fault handler is this nifty little module that if you call fault handler.enable when
you start your program, if you have some really bizarre crash it'll still print out some basic
debugging information.
Now you're all probably used to having something go wrong and you see that nice stack trace
of the exception and then you're like, oh okay, it was function foo that caused it,
let me go debug that.
Now if you do multi-threaded code sometimes what you'll have happen is you'll corrupt
the memory.
Like if you read a stale stack frame or try and modify a dictionary while you iterate
or do some other funky stuff.
And if you corrupt memory you might corrupt the entire stack and so when you get an exception
instead of printing out that nice stack trace you'll get a core dump or some other really
ugly crash which won't tell you what's going on.
And then you'll start pulling your hair out saying like, well where did it crash?
Why did it crash?
Whereas if you use fault handler.enable when you get any type of crash it won't allocate
any new memory, it'll immediately print some really basic stuff so that even if your memory
is corrupted you'll still get something.
Okay, so let me mention some additional issues.
So in the sampler thread that we're using and in general for threading you want to set
this to be a daemon thread.
If you don't set it to be a daemon thread then when your main program exits your sampler
thread would still be alive and it would prevent your program from exiting.
Whereas if you set it to self.daemon equals true for your sampler thread then when your
main thread exits your daemon thread will also exit.
Another thing to keep in mind is that, so I mentioned before that in theory if you have
the sampling interval going all the way down to zero then your statistical profiler is
going to turn into a deterministic profiler.
So that's true in theory but time.sleep currently has some minimum granularity of like 1 to
10 milliseconds.
It's not really a big deal unless you're doing super high frequency trading or something
where you can execute code really fast but just worth keeping in mind.
So I want to mention Flask here.
So if you're using Flask and you want to use aux profile you can use this in a very simple
way to plug it in.
You import a blueprint, you do app.registerBlueprint for aux profile and you configure some admin
users and with just those three lines you can start using this profiler in Flask.
It will provide you four endpoints.
One is unpause which will turn on the profiler.
So the statistical profiler even though it's low overhead it doesn't turn on by default
you have to turn it on.
You can use pause to pause the profiler so it's not affecting production.
You can call status to show the current profile and the status of the results and you can
use setInterval to change the sampling frequency.
So again one of the main motivations for using statistical profilers is you have some website
or you have a lot of websites or application servers or something that's deployed in production
and you want to see what's slow or what's the bottleneck or what's the program doing
in real operation with real users.
So to do that it's nice to be able to have a statistical profiler inside there either
as an endpoint or in some other manner.
Okay let's look at some additional uses.
So what else can you do with sys.currentframes?
So again I want to say again like how awesome this function is.
So if there's any core maintainers in the room right now please don't take away this
function because it's just really neat.
So I'm going to give you some other thoughts of ideas you could do to have fun.
So what else can you do with sys.currentframes?
So first of all you can do some major damage that's really hard to track down.
So be careful because it lets you look into every thread that's running and mess with
it.
So be careful.
Okay more seriously one thing you could do is you could take a data snapshot.
That is you could use sys.currentframes to look at the active frames and then you could
periodically snapshot not just co-name but something like frame.flocals.
That is you could take a snapshot of what are all the local variables that are active
in some given function.
And particularly if you're dealing with a lot of third party libraries and you just
want to know what's going on that's kind of a nifty way without having to rewrite those
third party libraries to write a simple tool that can peek at what's happening in your
program.
You could even modify flocals.
You could go into flocals and you could add one to every integer you find or multiply
it by two or do some other crazy stuff.
Now why would you do this besides wanting to cause major damage which I'm obviously
not advocating.
If you're running your tests you might have invariants or assertion checks or other kind
of things in your tests.
Now those tests are great for your test cases but if you can go and randomly modify flocals
it's testing your code in a different way which could be kind of interesting.
Another thing you could do is you could do something like a statistical debugger where
you periodically snapshot some debug information like a full stack trace on all the locals
and either dump those to a log or save those so in case there's a crash maybe you have
a random snapshot of like 10 or 20 functions that were called recently.
You could use statistical code coverage just like coverage.py but turn it on periodically
and record which lines are being executed and then turn off so you don't incur much
overhead but you can track which code which lines of code are being actually covered in
your real use cases.
So let me summarize.
So profiling is designed to find bottlenecks and improve your code.
You can use deterministic profiles for that but they can be slow so you can use a statistical
profiler to sample your code periodically.
It'll let you use your statistical profiler in production to see what real users are doing
without providing too much overhead.
You can use ox profile which is open source non-GitHub or you can write your own and really
not that many lines provided you're careful of a few things.
The key functions here are set profile, set trace and sys.currentframes which lets you
peek into what the interpreter is doing or have the interpreter call your function periodically.
And it's simple in theory but anytime you're using threads be careful.
Use tri-finally, use locks, maybe use a switch interval and use fault handler.
So that concludes the main talk and ready for Q&A.
We've got a few minutes for questions now.
If you have a question just use one of the microphones here.
Hello, can you hear me?
There we go.
My question is with regard to statistical profiling in the example you gave where the
number of hits kind of tells you what to go look at for potential improvement, how would
you differentiate the fact that that number of hits may be due to just the fact that that
particular program, let's say a web crawler, would obviously have a huge percentage of
hits on request.get or whatever versus that number of hits suggesting that those particular
function calls are slow or need improvement.
Does that make sense?
Yeah, so let me rephrase what I think you're asking.
So I think what you're saying is what if you have something like request.get which is not
really slow in CPU terms but it's slow in the sense of time.
You just have to wait for things to go back and forth in the network.
So it's not CPU bound but it's still slow and the statistical profiler would be telling
you like it's slow.
Most of the time in your program you're waiting in this particular function.
So one thing you could do is if you know that's the case you can just ignore that line and
go down and look at the other things.
There's not a ton of stuff you can do because the fact that the Python interpreter is sitting
there waiting in there is going to be hard to figure out in a profiler because it really
is a slow function.
Does that answer your question or does that get at what you're saying?
Sort of. Yeah, it was more how do you like request.get was just an obvious example.
But really what I'm getting at is based on what you're seeing from a statistical profiler,
what clues do you have that can help you differentiate that a function call actually needs improvement
versus that it's just used a lot in the program?
So that's a good question.
So it's not so much a statistical versus deterministic profiling question.
It's just a question of how do you know if something is slow or it's just called a lot.
So a profiler can't help you so much with that.
That's more something you have to figure out.
And so the way to think about a profile is not necessarily what's the...
So you can look at what's the top hit or what's the slowest function.
And the more you can speed that up, the better your program will be.
Or you can look for what functions seem to be taking a lot more time than I expect.
And you can use that to drive what you look at.
Okay.
Thank you.
Maybe on this side?
Yeah.
Have you any experience with running a statistical profiler inside a Docker pod?
Inside a what?
Docker?
Docker.
Kubernetes?
So, it should work just fine in...
So statistical profiler should work just fine in Docker or Kubernetes because it's running
inside the Python interpreter.
And it's just telling you when the interpreter is running, what function is it in most often?
Does that answer your question?
Did you mean something different that I misunderstood?
I was wondering if the fact that you're really faking that you're on one processor but you're
really sharing a processor, does that change your statistics?
It won't change your statistics.
If for some reason your particular Docker process gets shoved to the side while other
things run, then that could be an issue, of course.
That's not really a problem you can solve with profilers.
Back to this side?
Just on the same note, first of all, great talk.
This is really educational.
Also in terms of messing with things such as context switching, how far down is that
propagated down?
Is that just propagated down to the Python interpreter?
If it's running on a virtual machine or there's hypervisors and stuff involved, it's not safeguarded
against that, right?
Good question.
The context switch, the set switch interval is only going to protect you from a context
switch happening in the Python interpreter.
It won't protect you from the operating system deciding which process gets to run.
That's true.
But the thing that we're worried about in that example is that if the Python interpreter
switches away and then switches back to you, you've now got stale stack frames potentially.
You're looking at stale memory and so that'll cause potentially a crash.
There's other ways you can try and check if those stack frames are live or stale, but
that's one simple example.
Back to this side.
Hi.
Thank you for the talk.
Two questions.
First, have you had a chance to measure the performance implications, say, with a 100-millisecond
sampling?
And second question, have you considered recording, let's say, if a function A calls function
B and you ended up seeing that a function B was called, that also implies that function
A was called, so the counter for the function A should also be incremented and that might
address one of the first questions there was.
Excellent question.
I'm glad you asked that.
So let me answer this.
So let me take that in order.
So if you set the sampling interval down 100 milliseconds, the sampler is going to run
more often.
It's hard to say anything concrete because if you're running on a 15-year-old laptop,
running it every 100 milliseconds is going to mean a lot more than if you're running
it on a top-end Xeon server or something.
The actual time for the sampler to run is relatively small, but that's what matters.
How long does it take the sampler to run relative to the sampling interval?
And that's how much overhead you're going to have.
Okay, so the second question was, what if function A calls function B calls function
C?
So let me go back to a diagram we had earlier right here.
So we have foo called bar, call baz, call boo.
So because we have F back, what you can do is you can say, okay, I'm in frame number
four, which is boo, but that was called by baz, which is called by bar, which is called
by foo.
So one thing you can do in your statistical profiler is say, don't just count the function
I'm in, also add a hit to each of the callers.
So I didn't show that just to keep things simple, but in Oxprofile, you can't not just
the function you're in, but all the callers.
So you'll capture that if there's some top-level function calling everybody.
Thank you.
Do we have time for more or are we done?
One more.
Okay, that's all the questions I think.
Sorry, I'll be outside in the hall if there's more questions.
Thanks, Emyn.
Thank you.