Welcome, everyone. The title of the talk is strategies for testing async code. And the
speaker is Neil Shezin. Welcome, Neil.
Hey, everyone. Like the title of the topic of the slide says, I'm here to talk to you
about strategies for testing async code. I thought I'd start by telling you a little
bit about who I am. First of all, this is my first talk at PyCon. In fact, this is my
first time talking in a room with more than a couple dozen people in it. So I've been
programming in Python since the early 2000s. I think I started on 2.2 or 2.3. It was a
long time ago. And I've been doing async programming for the past four or five years in other
languages. And in 2017, I started using async in Python with 3.5. I believe that testing
software is very important. I'm trying to make sure that all the software I write is
well tested. And you can find me on Twitter at Neilithotep. And then I thought I'd talk
a little about work because they're paying for me to be here. And also, it's why I started
using async in Python. I work for an email security company called Agari. And I'm a senior
software engineer and tech lead there. It says on the screen, I don't think I should
read it, but Agari has a pretty audacious mission to prevent basically bad email. And
the team that I work on for our advanced threat protection product is responsible for a high
performance email ingest service where we process email that comes in and extract information
on it that we can then send to our data processing pipeline in order to determine if the email
is bad. We do a lot of Python at Agari. Some of it's still Python, too. But we're trying
to fix that. So now a brief outline of my talk. First, I'm going to talk about why I
decided to do this talk. And then I'm going to do a brief intro about async and async
I.O. just to kind of level the playing field for everyone here. And then I'm going to talk
about the challenges of testing that I ran into. Some solutions and kind of go through
some various challenges and the solutions that I found. And then I'll wrap up, which
is pretty obvious. So first of all, why? Well, I guess I got to answer a couple other questions
first before I can talk about why I did this talk. First of all, why do we test? Testing
is important. Unit, functional, integration tests, they all help us keep our software
high and make sure that as we change it in the future, the quality remains. Another thing
that is important in software is performance. And async I.O. is a really powerful tool in
the Python library to provide performance in certain circumstances. There are some other
async frameworks available like curio and trio. And some of these strategies in this
talk apply to them. But it's primarily focused towards async I.O. However, when you put these
two things together, I kind of got confused. I spent a lot of time running up against these
challenges and I hope that I can reduce some friction for everyone else. So now a very
brief intro to async in Python. So first of all, when I say async, I pretty much mean
asynchronous programming. And this definition here is applicable to more than just Python.
Pretty much any language that has asynchronous, this is what they mean. Concurrency through
cooperation. Different threads of execution yield control of the processor or processors
while they're waiting on their external I.O. and they explicitly yield control. So they
cooperatively work together to perform multiple tasks sort of simultaneously. Async I.O. is
the standard library implementation of asynchronous computing in Python. It's basically the Python
framework for asynchronous computing. It became available in the standard lib in 3.4 and then
in 3.5 they improved the syntax into a way that I think is pretty much the way it's going
to stay. And then we've got incremental changes in 3.6 and 3.7. I'll talk a little bit more
about 3.7 shortly. There's two primary concepts of async I.O. The first is coroutines and
the second is event loops. So coroutines perform asynchronous work. The 3.6 standard library
doc has an interesting definition for coroutine. It basically says a coroutine is either one,
the function that defines a coroutine, or two, the object obtained by calling such a
function that represents a computation and or I.O. operation that will complete eventually.
So it's kind of self-referential. But the basics of that is this is the interface that
allows you to have cooperative concurrency by performing work while waiting on I.O. The
second main concept is an event loop. An event loop is something that schedules asynchronous
work and what I mean by that is it runs a coroutine and then when a coroutine performs
I.O. it basically delegates that I.O. and while it's waiting for the return it runs
another coroutine and then when the I.O. returns it can resume the original coroutine with
the result of the I.O. call. And here we have the key syntax that you need to know for most
of async I.O. and Python. There's two keywords and in fact these keywords were defined pretty
much in 3.5 and became reserved in 3.7 which I think has broken some code out there. I
think particularly for await. So async defines a coroutine and await calls a coroutine and
there's an example here. On line one I'm creating a coroutine by calling async def my coroutine
and then on line two I'm awaiting the output of another coroutine that I call and as I
mentioned before when you call another coroutine with the open params closed params what you
get back is a coroutine object which represents an eventual completion of some sort of task
and that's what you're actually awaiting on. So it's nice to have some example to work
with as you do these tests and the way I've seen it mostly is for complex microservices
or network servers and I thought it might be nice to have something a little bit simpler
to keep in our minds for these things. So that brings us to cats. It's nice to have
a cat pic and a tech talk. It makes people happy. It also brings to mind the phrase hurting
cats which is getting cats to do the same thing like posing for a photo but really that's
not what it means. It means something more like this. A bunch of random actions happening
at various times and just a bunch of confusion. So to that end I have created a little cat
object. A cat has two main members to it. It has a name and a mood on line six and seven
and it also has a method defined pet which when you pet the cat you make its mood pleased.
And then I also defined a coroutine for moving a cat. And basically when you try to move
a cat if it's pleased it will eventually move. Then it might become displeased but if it's
not pleased it's not going to move for you. So there we have our little async example.
So then it brings us to our first challenge. How do we test a coroutine? This is something
I spent a little bit of time bashing my head over a few years ago. So first thing that
I try to do, well, actually take one step back. I'm going to find a little method to
test called herd which basically wraps petting a cat to make it happy and then moving it
in a function or a coroutine rather. So line five defines our method under test and then
we have a test case. This is using the unit test framework. So we have this test. Test
forward and then all we do is check to make sure that we get true when we try to herd
Garfield forward. I want to say that Garfield is not necessarily my favorite cat name but
it popped in my head when I wrote this. So that's just what there's there. And then the
output of this when we run it is well, at first it looks okay. We ran one test and it
returned okay. But really it's not okay. There's a runtime warning. Coroutine herd was never
awaited. The okay is because when we evaluated the return of that function call, we got a
coroutine object which is truthy. So asserting a truthy thing is true. So the runtime warning
there is something important to look for. Okay. This means we need to call await instead.
So here's another little iteration where we call await on herd. Run the test and we get
a syntax error. You can't call await outside of an async function. So you need a coroutine
to call a coroutine which is a little bit of a catch-22. But there's a way around this.
And that's using the event loop. So we add an import of async IOTR test and then we can
get in a loop as you can see on line 15 and run our coroutine in the loop, close the loop
and check our result. And this works. This is the most simple solution to the problem
that's available if you're using any sort of framework, any version of Python that supports
async IOTR. Even 3.4 should work this way. But there are some other things you can do
to test these functions. I don't know. How many people out here are using PyTest? So
there's a plug-in called PyTest async IOTR that makes things a little easier. So you
just pip install PyTest async IOTR, import PyTest to pull in all the dependencies and
then you can mark your test function with a decorator, PyTest mark async IOTR, and then
instead of defining a test method, you define a test coroutine. So you can see instead of
running test forward as a method, it's actually a coroutine and we're just calling it wait
as we would want to do on line 14. And we run this through PyTest and we get a nice
green bar at the bottom. I do like the output of PyTest. It's really straightforward. You
see green? You know everything passed. See red? Probably not. So that's pretty much a
nice way of using PyTest. There's one other thing that I found while I was researching
this talk, which is a new method in async IOTR in Python 3.7. This is async IOTR run, which
basically runs a coroutine. I guess essentially it's a purification of creating a loop, running
the coroutine and closing the loop. It's marked provisional, by the way, in the library, but
I doubt it's going to change. And you do it really simply. Like we see on line 15, you
just call async IOTR on the coroutine and you get a result and you can check if it's
true. This is really straightforward. Actually, now I remember something I forgot to mention.
I'm going to go back for a second. To this example, it's kind of verbose there. You probably
would want to do something like set up a tear down for your test case to create the loop
and get rid of it. Sorry about that. But here you don't have to worry about that because
that's just one line of code. Actually, that was here. All right. That brings us to our
next challenge. Mocking and patching. I know everyone doesn't use mocking and I think there
was a talk that kind of tried to convince us not to use them all the time, but regardless,
people do use mocks and they're an important way to separate the concerns of our unit tests
from other methods. The problem is that unit tests mock dot mock just won't mock a coroutine.
And let me show you an example of what I mean. So we're using the patch method to overwrite
cat dot move. You can see on line 14 we're using patch, which means that in the context
of the function, whenever you call the test function, whenever we call cat dot move, we
will call our new mock instead move mock. We're using our normal async IO get event
loop run until complete methodology here, but this is valid for any of the other things.
So when you do this and try and check to see that you called the mock object the way you
expected, you get a type error because you can't await a magic mock. Because instead
of getting a coroutine and for when we call movers turned the mock object returns another
mock object. Okay. So there's got to be a way to do this. And the best thing that I
found is this little basically wrapper and Google and Stack Overflow were very helpful
here. So we have a little new class called async mock, which is a super class, subclass
rather of magic mock. And it has one method, one coroutine actually, call of dunder call.
And what this does is it overwrites the policy for what happens when you call open friends,
close friends. And in this case, all we do is call the dunder call on the super class.
So we get the async call into the magic mock and we translate it into a normal method call
in the mock object. So we create our mock object by using the keyword argument new co-object
callable, which means instead of getting a normal mock or magic mock for the mock object
in patch, we actually use async mock. And because of the pass through that we created
in the object, we can simply call the normal mock methods and see that it was actually
called with forward. So that's nice and it's straightforward. And that brings us to our
next challenge. Context managers. This is actually a similar problem that I ran into.
Sometimes you'll have a method that expects to take an object that implements a context
manager and an async framework or you use async with to use a context manager. And if
you don't actually care about the context manager but you care about the function that's
testing it, you might want to use a mock. There's a pretty straightforward pattern
to addressing this, which is you create another type of super class to magic mock. And in
fact, you could probably do all this in one class if you wanted where you overwrite the
Dunder A enter and Dunder A exit methods and have them simply pass through to the Dunder
enter and Dunder exit on the underlying mock object. That's also pretty straightforward.
So then that brings us to the more complex use cases. So everything that we talked about
before really addresses the common issues and how you get started and everything when
you're just getting started async I O and trying it out. But some other things happen.
There's shortcomings that I found. In particular, sometimes you have coroutines that aren't
running in the main thread that might behave differently. I ran into this in particular
when I was taking code that was synchronous and migrating it to asynchronous code. And
we expected some certain signal behavior that didn't happen the right way because the signals
only operated properly in the main thread. So it's nice to be able to make sure you're
running signals and running your coroutines in the threads you expect. Other thing is
sometimes it's hard to test methods that are synchronous functions that eventually call
into event loops. Event loops might not always be there or working properly. And other thing
that I ran into problems is functional tests. Like what happens if you have a while loop
that's sitting there accepting network connections, creating async tests and just spinning forever?
That's never going to complete. And the final thing that I found problems with, this one
is event loop variance. And I guess the simplest thing to explain is the concept of event loop
is a generic class that you can plug in other things to. And there's one called UV loop
which is a very high performant implementation. You can look it up and it looks like it's
a performance as go or other things that tout their concurrency performance or node. Anyway,
so I created this thing called the loop runner that can manage a loop for you. This is a
little bit of an eye chart. By the way, all this code is posted in repo. I'll give you
a link to it later. But I'm going to go over the most important parts of this. So the main
interface of the loop runner is a method called run co-routine. And this is an interface that
runs a co-routine pass through it to inside the loop of the loop runner which is a subclass
of threading.thread. There's a method run co-routine thread safe which essentially makes sure that
you run the co-routine in the thread that event loop is running in. So we can do that
and get the result. And then here's the way you might use it. So you might use set up
and tear down methods to create a loop runner and start the thread. And then you can simply
say hey, run my co-routine in that loop. This is pretty simple. This actually looks like
running to loop complete. And it is essentially that. And if you can do that, you might not
want to use this. But there's some other cases that are more complex like when you're calling
a cost threads. So this is another example. This is on the surface. It might look a little
contrived. But this is actually really simple, similar to something that I wrote before kind
of as interface between synchronous code and asynchronous code and other asynchronous code.
So I called this herd router to keep in the herd, herding kittens pattern from before.
But the main thing to see here is that we have this method add command which runs its
own method thread safely with the key passed to it. And it does that in a thread safe manner
in this co-routine on line 12 which you can see actually uses a lock to make sure that
it is indeed thread safe. So this is how you might want to test this in a test case. So
we set it up by creating an event loop, creating a herd router on the event loop, creating
a runner on the event loop and starting the runner. And then in our test, we can say,
all right, let's call the method test and check to see that our results there. And this
works. That actually brings us to the end of the talk. A couple minutes ahead of where
I expect it to be. So I hope that this either gets you to try out async I O programming
if you are afraid of it for any reason or helps you get back into it if you ran into
testing problems. I hope that you keep testing and you can find my sample code and the whole
presentation at bit.ly slash nshazen dash PyCon 2019.
Thank you, Neil. We've got a couple of minutes for questions. So if you have any, come up
to the microphone and ask your questions.
Hi. Thanks for the talk. You spent sort of most of the content talking about unit testing
and testing sort of individual functions. In my experience, often when I'm using asynchronous
code, it's in part because I'm interested in running several things concurrently that
need to interact with one another. I was wondering if you have any suggestions or any ideas about
how to make it easier to orchestrate or like test more effectively the interactions of
things?
That is actually I think one of the things why I made the loop runner. That allowed me
to set some things running, particularly if they have loops that wait for processing in
the background, particularly if those are tested elsewhere, you can assume that they
work right and have your code under test run in the main thread and pass stuff there. I
originally had some example for that, but it was way too confusing. I couldn't keep
it. But basically, yeah, if you can do loop management for other event loops, you can
run other things concurrently.
Thank you.
Sure.
That's fine.
In the absence of any more questions, we have come to the end of the talk. So thank you
now.