So, this is my first lightning talk.
I'm just waiting for my slides to show up.
So my name is Jonathan Biddle.
I lead a team called Developer Acceleration at Wayfair.
And today I'm going to talk to you about one of the ways that we spread best practices
around Python and Python excellence across the company.
So for those of you who aren't familiar with Wayfair, I'll give you just a really brief
idea of what we do.
We are an e-commerce website that focuses on furniture and home decor.
And we're kind of big, a little bit.
We've got 14 million products, 16.4 million customers, which means we're like 2.4 million
products away from literally having something for everyone.
And we've also got 2,300 people across our various tech teams.
So what about Python at Wayfair?
Well, two years ago, I was given the opportunity to do what I think is probably my favorite
job ever.
And it was basically to figure out how do we make it intuitive and easy for any software
team to use Python to solve their problems and reach their business objectives in the
form of a Python platform team at Wayfair.
One of the things that we thought about early on is like, okay, if we're going to get a
bunch of people adopting Python, how do we make sure they adopt Python the right way?
How do we make sure they're using idiomatic Python and leading into some of the Pythonic
things that may come naturally to you if you've been doing it for a few years but out of the
gate are a little mystical.
You don't really understand what Pythonic means.
If we're going to have a bunch of people doing this for the first time, it's kind of important
that we have a good story here.
So we could do a lot of training and point people to good books to read and things like
that, but we were concerned that that wouldn't really take in the way we really wanted.
So what we came up with is this model called auxiliary engineering.
And what it is, it's kind of like embedded engineering.
We work with the team on something, but we have two goals.
One, we want that team to be successful.
We want them to reach whatever MVP or goal that they have to achieve some business outcome,
but we also want to transform the team in some way.
We want to bring in those best practices that come second nature to us.
You can recognize any project that we contribute to because we have a little badge and readme
files for any of these projects where we've been involved.
So let's talk about what an auxiliary project looks like.
There's some preparation before we even get started.
One thing that's really important, we don't want to force this on anyone.
We don't want to feel like there's some group of experts that are going to come across the
company and then say, oh, no, this is how you should do it.
We want teams to come to us.
We want them to feel like whatever we're doing is so valuable that they'll kind of reach
across the company and say, hey, could you come and partner with us on this?
We also make sure that we have really clear goals.
We want the software team, our auxiliary engineer, and the product owner to feel like they are
aligned on a common outcome.
That includes business objectives, but it also might include things like code coverage
or some bringing in best practice, maybe black or automatic linting pipelines, things like
that.
We also do three-month durations.
Now, yes, that conveniently fits into like a quarter of time, maybe makes planning easy,
but there's another reason that we do three months.
There's some research that shows that it takes about a bit over two months to form a new
habit, and that's kind of what we feel like we're doing.
We're going to that team, we're working with them, and we're helping them build good habits.
If we were to do this for a few weeks, maybe we'd see some of it, but I have some concerns
that once we leave, they're just going to reach for whatever feels most obvious to them,
and those habits really aren't going to take.
We spend a lot of time just reinforcing and trying to make that what's second nature to
us, second nature to the team.
During a project, it's very important, very important that we are part of that team, not
some outsider who's kind of like advising it.
We are in the team, we are working towards the same goals.
We sit with the team, we do meetings with the team.
We want to feel like we are a member of that team throughout the project.
Also, we pair on the hard work.
We don't take it on ourselves.
We absolutely do not want to go and solve the hardest problem in a project ourselves
because that robs the team of the ability to learn.
That robs them of the chance to understand really why a particular solution was selected.
So it's important that whenever a hard part of the project shows up, we pair with them.
We make sure that we're passing that knowledge on to whoever else is involved.
We also focus a lot on feedback.
Feedback is very important to us.
So we do weekly retros with the team, specifically on the AuxEngine engagement.
What's going well, what's not going well.
We talk about the project.
We also talk about our role in the project.
Is it working?
Is it healthy?
We want to get really good feedback.
We actually encourage teams to give us critical feedback.
If something's not going right, we want to know that and we want to address it.
Which leads well into the learning aspect of this.
It really goes both ways.
It's not like we're bringing a whole bunch of knowledge as experts onto the team and
taking nothing back ourselves.
We get a lot of really good information from this.
And I say a lot.
It is impossible for us to know what it's like to learn Python for the first time today.
Or what it's like to use our platform for the first time.
But when we're sitting with people and we're watching them get confused because some documentation
wasn't clear, it's extremely obvious.
And we also funnel that into 20% time.
So anyone who's doing auxiliary engineering gets one day a week to just take all of that
information they got in the course of the week, maybe it was something that was unintuitive,
and address it.
And then we're really self-directed, just take action.
There's no real process to go through.
Just work on improving the platform.
We follow up six months later with the team.
Want to make sure that whatever knowledge that we brought in actually stayed and we're
seeing that take hold.
And often case that is that's what happens.
And actually even gets a little better than that.
We've done this about 10 projects.
A number of them, what we've observed is not only does that team start to become strong,
but the teams adjacent to them start to become strong too.
They start to spread those best practices that we tried to spread.
And the idea of what Python is starts to replicate across the company.
And it's really quite amazing.
There's also a really high demand for this.
It's not like we have to go and find teams to come and like, hey, would you want to work
with us on this?
No, we actually have to turn away people, unfortunately, every time we go through a
planning cycle.
Because there's just not enough engineers on the platform team to meet that demand.
So that's a really good indicator that what we're doing is extremely valuable.
It's also led to a ton of platform improvements.
Being with the team, seeing what was working well and not working well, make sure that
we are not...
Okay, this is a clap.
I wasn't sure if you were telling me to cut off because of time.
Okay, so we've made a ton of platform improvements just because there's a lot of good feedback
in that process.
So my name is Jonathan Biddle.
I work at Wayfair.
You can find me here.
And if you want to talk to me, we have a recruitment booth at the job fair.
Thank you, Jon.
Shhh.
Okay.
Will the next person come and sit up over here?
Number three, you know who you are.
Loading Gmail.
So our man really wants to touch this tractor.
This is the, you know this thing called the imp of the perverse?
He wants to touch it.
He knows he shouldn't, but he kind of leans over the velvet ropes and he just touches
the kind of like, what do you call it, the little arch over the front wheel.
And a little shiver goes through him.
And he looks around.
He's the first person in this whole convention, right?
There's no one around.
There's no security guards.
And he's already transgressed.
So he just goes, okay, well, unhooks the velvet rope, gets himself around and gets just a
little bit closer to this tractor, right?
And he runs his hand across it and walks around the tractor.
It's incredible, right?
This thing is massive.
It's brand new.
The tires are spotless.
He feels them.
And he really gets to know this tractor on the way around.
And as he's walking around, he notices the front door of the cab is open.
So he goes, look, well, there's no one here.
Come on.
And he sort of takes a step and then he just climbs into this tractor, sits in it, and
he goes, this feels amazing.
He sat in a few tractors before, but nothing like this.
It's very comfortable.
Cabin is full of all the equipment.
He's read about it.
He's seen a million pictures of what the entire area of this tractor is going to look like.
But being in there is amazing.
And then he sees that the keys are in the ignition.
So he had a little fight with his conscience, but in the end he can't resist.
And he leans forwards and he touches the key and he goes, come on, I just want to hear
the engine, all right?
I'll just switch it off straight away, but I just want to hear what it sounds like.
I just want to hear what it sounds like.
So he leans forwards and he turns the engine on.
The engine roars alive, like gently, like modern, powerful engines do.
It's not like a blurgh, but it goes, but the power is really evident in this thing.
And then he just loses control, right?
He puts his hand on the steering wheel.
He puts his hand on the gear stick, puts the clutch down, he puts it in gear and he takes
this tractor and he drives it off its podium out into the convention hall through the velvet
ropes, crashing through dozens of exhibits amongst several flimsy panels.
He's just going on a mad tractor rampage, laughing maniacally at himself.
They call in the police, they call in the National Guard, they have to eventually stop
this tractor, they block it with an APC, they wrestle him out of the cab, they drag him
off to jail.
It's quite a scene.
But not as much of a scene as the one that you're about to cause.
In order to welcome our next speaker, please give Breanne a huge, huge welcome.
Thank you.
Hi everyone.
My name is Breanne Kaplan and I'm the founder of Code Our Dreams.
We're a 501c3 nonprofit in Chicago.
We serve under-resourced high school students and teach them computer science so they can
build applications that drive positive change in our communities.
So I think we can all agree on two things this morning.
Number one, this is my dog Piper and we can all agree that she is super cute.
But the second thing, probably more importantly, is that computational thinking is important.
Teachers agree.
According to a study by EdSurge, 88% of K-12 teachers said that computer science is crucial
to preparing students for the workforce.
And as Pythonese says, we know that STEM education is more than just preparing students to become
scientists, engineers, or mathematicians.
It's just as important as a liberal arts education.
But the reality is, with the same study, only 20% of students are actually being reached.
So there's a disconnect between the belief that computer science is important and the
actual application of these skills in schools.
So the problems, they can be put into four buckets.
The first two, lack of teachers, lack of standardized curriculum.
Over half of public school districts in the nation report struggling to recruit and retain
certified and effective STEM teachers.
And this figure raises to 90% in districts serving large proportions of African American
and Hispanic students.
Number three and number four, lack of gear and lack of funding.
In Illinois, where I live and where I teach, it has the most unfair school funding system
in the nation, according to a study released by the Education Trust.
And in this study, individual schools were underfunded by $2.4 billion.
So I know you're all asking, what can we do?
We really need your help.
As a community, let's invest in the schools that have the least.
And this is why I started Code Our Dreams.
As I said, Code Our Dreams is a 501c3 nonprofit in Chicago.
Every student cohort that we teach starts with the question, what communities are you
a part of?
What makes them great and beautiful?
But also, what problems do you see?
Our students ideate on applications they can build that address some of those problems.
And then that's the applications that they build throughout the year-long program.
They learn everything from ideation to user experience and design, Python programming,
and the delivery of the product to showcase to their communities.
And coming this fall, we'll have three different tracks, data science, web development, and
physical computing, all for social good.
So there are a few things that we're doing that we think are important and that are different.
So the first is that we think it's important to reach students where they are.
Nearly all of low-performing Chicago high schools are on the south side and sit on or
border the poorest census tracks.
However, the majority of STEM programming occurs in the city center, which is inaccessible
to the majority of students who need it the most.
It's really important that we meet the students where they are.
The second is focusing on schools that need it the most.
There's a huge gap between resource versus under-resource schools.
So in Chicago, where I live, I can give two examples.
There is a school up north called Stevenson.
That school has an Olympic-sized pool, an espresso bar, two different gyms, and theater
performances versus a school in Waukegan, which typically has 28 students to just one
computer and their band plays in the hallway because they don't have enough space.
The third thing that we think is important is exposing students to all opportunities
in tech.
Our students have the opportunity to take on the roles from product manager to product
designer, programmer, sales and marketing.
Something in there will resonate with all students, so let's get together and expose
students to everything within tech.
And lastly, I think it's important to empower students to actually create the change that
they seek to see.
Our students build applications that make positive impact on their local communities.
And if you or your company is interested in sponsoring or donating to 501c3s, please give
me a shout or drop me a business card.
You can visit our website at codardreams.org and we'd love to talk to you.
Thank you.
Thank you so much.
Our next talk is Daniel.
Please give him a big hand.
Hi.
Hello.
This isn't nearly as serious, so I apologize in advance.
So I'm from here, but really from here.
This is my daughter in addition to liking Unicoin.
She also likes Minecraft and I like Minecraft, which is, you know, I thought that might be
worthy of study, but apparently that doesn't actually work as a thing.
But as a result of the research, I ran into this and I like the idea of transforming your
world with the power of Python.
That seems like a good idea.
And the way this sort of works in practice, it's for the Java version of the thing and
there's a you take the Java version of the program, you embed it in a server, it exposes
a Java-based plugin framework.
It's built for the Raspberry Pi version of the game.
There's a beautiful Python client that some folks from Python UK has printed on and got
to work really well and it works really well to inject content into the game.
So my problem is that this is mostly one way.
You know, you can put stuff in, but what I really want to do is I want to be able to
respond to game events.
You know, players move, you know, blocks change, you know, there's a chicken appear, you want
to do chicken things with it, you know, and anything else that you sort of have this really
sort of rich API that is actually exposed by the game.
So I figured, well, let's see if we can sort of do this with some modern Python and it
turns out there's a thing we can do.
We can write a WebSocket adapter, use that as sort of a transport.
There's this beautiful library called Trio WebSocket, so those folks have been doing
a really good job in getting an asynchronous client that sort of works on that.
We can write something between, I mean, it's big, it's a washer, I don't know, and then
you can sort of write on that.
So the scope of the implementation is we have to write this Java WebSocket plugin.
I mean, there's others, but it's like for web things for web people and I'm not one
of those.
So we need our own and what we're really doing is serializing and deserializing a bunch of
these Java API things.
And for the sake of actually making it easy to use on the same level as my API, we need
a Python module to hide all those details.
So let's say we have something that looks kind of like this.
We register a bunch of callbacks, we can set blocks, and in this case the idea is to respond
to a player moving and sort of put a block behind them.
In other words, Tron.
So you have something that sort of looks like this.
You've got the game, it talks to the server, the Python client.
What's the current state?
This is the software development life cycle.
This is the proof of concept stage.
So it works.
This actually works.
The Python client can sort of do that and send messages.
The Java thing can send messages to connected clients and so on.
If this is where your nerd is, that's where mine is, you know, let's chat.
Thank you very much for your patience.
All right.
That is definitely the first time I've seen the poof of concept emoji.
Poof of concept.
My project is the poof of concept stage.
The next speaker is Chaim.
Please give him a huge hand.
Good morning, everyone.
I know everyone is having a great beginning to the third day of the conference.
So I'm going to talk quickly about PySlackers because everybody needs more work spaces in
their lives.
Slack has an amazing work space switching interface.
You just switch your interfaces and so you should all make use of it by joining PySlackers.
I'm going to tell you what that is in just a minute.
That's our logo.
It's a Slack for Python.
It's been around for about three years.
I actually joined in December and if anybody here has spoken to me at the conference or
in any other time, I participate.
Let's put it that way.
So I joined in December.
In February they were looking for new admins and I was nominated and made an admin.
So there's about 10 of us.
And that was really cool.
And I joined PySlackers because, you know, I do Python at work every day.
But I don't get the community like this every day.
And I wanted to find one.
And I found it on PySlackers.
And it's amazing.
So some information about PySlackers.
We have 21,352 members as of 1230 last night.
I checked a few minutes ago.
We have three more.
79 channels.
We make them new channels with thoughtfulness.
So we're open to creating new channels but we like having a channel used and not just
channels that aren't used.
So if there's a new channel that we need, great.
But if not, use one that's there.
90% of the messages are public.
We tend not to use threading.
Like I said, Slack has a great workspace switcher, the threading interface.
Not as much.
But 90% of the messages are public, which is great.
But because there's 20,000 of us, we don't pay for Slack because, well, that would be
kind of insane.
So messages only live for about a week.
So if you're going to join, check things out.
It's amazing.
I'll give you a brief moment to just look at that.
That's a sampling of our channels.
If you want to find me any other time today and talk about some of them, I'm happy to.
I'm active on more than a few of them.
And that's great.
And I love it.
So I'll leave that up for just a minute.
You can peruse.
And that was 10 seconds, which is plenty.
So join us.
I would love everyone here to join.
I know not a lot of people have heard about it, even though we have 20,000 users.
So if you haven't heard, come check it out.
We get about 150 new users a week.
Because of this presentation that I'm giving, I would love to increase that by an order
of magnitude this week, just so I could say, ha ha, I did that, and that's awesome.
In particular, if anybody is between UTC plus seven and plus 14, which is also known as
minus 10, which I learned last night, and that's amazing that there are two time zones
that are both plus and minus time zones, we don't have as much coverage there.
And we do definitely have users from there that are asking for help in their time zone.
And things are quiet.
So if you know Python, if you want to help people, and you're in those time zones, please
join because that would be awesome.
Thank you.
Again, I'm Chaim Kirby.
I'm not going to give you an email address because if you want to talk to me, you've
got to join.
Thank you, Chaim.
Felipe, are you ready to go?
Then you first, your audience must give him a big welcome, and then he must go.
Hello.
Good morning, everybody.
So Anthony and I, we're here to talk about Conna Forge, a community pattern that works
for you.
And our actual talk is going to be about reinventing the wheel.
Funny thing, our first title was Beyond the Wheel, and then we realized that a better
title would be Work in Progress.
So just a little bit about Conna Forge before we go.
We tried to address all the packaging needs.
It's going to be a one-stop shop for all the platforms, Windows, Mac, Linux, ARM, Arch,
Power 89, and NoArch.
So if you have to support multiple platforms with a single tool and you need a lot of packages,
Conna Forge is the tool for you.
Conna Forge is big, and it's growing more and more every day.
Like we have more than 100,000 artifacts, totaling up to more than 450 gigabytes, spread
over 6,000 feedstocks with more than 1,000 maintainers taking care of all these packages.
We have so far more than 4,000 pull requests, and I believe we broke the record on GitHub
for the repository with the most submodules.
So we're here to talk about wheels, and then I would like to introduce you CondaPress.
CondaPress is a new tool that converts Conda packages to wheels.
You can find it on the reorganization CondaPress.
It's a pretty new project.
CondaPress tries to address some of the problems mixing PIP and Conda, because that usually
ends up with all this ABI incompatibility, so our goal is to try to fix that.
Some people may want a package with different builds or newer ABI than the many Linux, like
for example, if you want a TensorFlow with a different, like say a latest GCLIP.
And Conda has a lot of packages that are not on wheels, so maybe we can try to port
those over there as well.
Now because I'm not crazy enough to speak a foreign language and do a demo, I'm going
to hand it over to Anthony, and he's going to show you.
Hey, everybody.
Let's get out of presentation mode here.
So we're going to go ahead and build up a little Conda index here with CondaPress.
So here what we're doing is we're going to build a wheel for Python 3.8 using a CondaForge's
3.8 package.
So we're going to go ahead and run this.
Oops, sorry, time dot dash P. And you can see this is actually just taking the actual
CondaForge artifact, so the tarball, and then turning that into a wheel without doing a
lot of extra things, right?
It's not rebuilding that package.
What it's doing is hopefully, assuming I'm connected to the internet.
No, I'm not connected to the internet.
So the, oh no.
Live demos, boo.
That's why I didn't want to do it.
Yeah.
Okay, so let's turn off the Wi-Fi.
Let's turn it back on.
This was literally working a couple seconds ago.
And I am going to try hotspotting right now.
But it looks like we might be back on PyCon.
So let's try it again.
And yes, no.
Yes, there we go.
So right now it's converting these things.
What it's doing is it's taking all the metadata out of those tarballs and repackaging them
into metadata that wheels understands, moving all the files around such that in a way that
is meaningful.
Oh, come on, people.
What's going on?
Why is it taking so long?
So is the internet really that bad here?
Yes.
Okay, let's select network here.
And do I need to disconnect?
Oh, yeah, let's connect to my personal one.
And hopefully this works.
Come on.
Big money.
Failing space because space needs to be filled.
Wow, that took a long time.
So hopefully we're on the right network.
Okay, it's going again.
Hopefully this actually works.
And it gets to the next package.
There we go.
Okay.
It looks like it's actually moving now.
So right now what it's doing is it's also walking the dependency tree.
So it's going and actually getting the runtime libraries and taking the artifacts for those
runtime libraries, building those.
Right now that's what it's doing with libgcc.
You'll see it do open SSL and SQL light and all of the things that term info and TK and
all of the things that Python depends on.
And it only took 30 seconds once it's actually working.
You see all of the wheels for these crazy packages.
We've got a virtual M down here.
So you can see it's clean.
It's a clean virtual M. So if you do Python dash dash version.
Sorry, I don't normally use bash, right?
This is this.
But now because we have these wheels, we can point pip to the local index directory where
things live, tell it not to go use PyPI and then install this Python 3.8 wheel.
It'll install all those packages as normal, resolve them, and now if we go ahead and we
run Python dash version, bam, we have just pip installed Python 3.8 here.
This works for all packages.
If you want make, if you want CMake, if you want GDAL or other crazy packages, yeah, this
is where we're come talk to us.
And there we go.
We're done.
Bye, bye, bye.
Thank you very much.
So up next is some regional Python conference announcements.
Would you like to announce them, Dustin?
In case you didn't know, in case you didn't know, in case you didn't know, there's lots
of regional PyCons that happen as well.
One is happening close to you.
It's smaller than this PyCon but it should be a lot of fun as well.
So we're going to introduce a bunch of regional ones and announce their dates.
Starting with PyCon.
So our usual rule for conference announcements is one slide, one minute.
It's going to be one slide, one sentence.
Just make it a really good sentence.
Everyone don't clap between the announcements because otherwise it will take forever.
Everyone please assume your claps are there and then go as quickly as you can.
Clap all the speakers now in advance.
Clap all the previous speakers.
Clap everyone that's involved in PyCon in any kind of way.
Regional conferences, go.
Okay.
PyCon CZ will be in Ostrava.
We have a PyData track.
So if you want to do data mining in an actual former coal mine, come to PyCon CZ.
Hello.
So you have to choose one and only one conference.
Don't trust anyone else.
It has to be PyLondinium.
We have the Spice Girl coming before that weekend.
It's in June.
We have the Backstreet Boy afterwards.
We have amazing speakers.
Check the schedule.
And all the profit from the conference are going directly to the C Python core developer
sprints.
Oh, yeah, there's also a Donald Duck week, but I think it's not the right audience.
Also if you have to choose only one conference, go to EuroPython this year.
It's July 8 to the 14th.
It's in Basel.
If you have gone to EuroPython before, you know it's an amazing conference.
You cannot miss it.
If you like Python in Ohio, PyOhio is in this summer.
The weather will be nicer.
Most likely no promises.
It's in Columbus, Ohio.
The CFP is open through May 12.
Registration is free.
And we're looking for sponsors to help keep it free.
I am the very model of a Django AUCFP.
I cover complex, yes, but also elementally.
I'll take your talks on testing and contributing to open source on data and converting ASCII
into Morse.
About stack automation and on scientific things of note, the packages you love to use and
engineering anecdote.
Your team work hacks disaster plans and writing docs for all that code on what to do and all
your applications overload.
In short, on topics both complex and also elementally, I am the very model of a PyCon
AUCFP.
We are having our first ever PyCon Africa.
So this is the first one.
It's very important.
It is going to be a group of people from across the continent.
Africa is a continent.
For those of you who are not aware, the weather is going to be amazing.
It's in Accra, Ghana.
It's so much better than the weather here.
So the CFP is open right now until June 1.
So please come and give a talk.
Thanks.
Well, PyBay is happening on the third weekend of August.
We have two days of workshops and about 60 talks this year.
And we are taking CFP until the 12th.
We are likely going to sell out this year at 800 people.
So please do come get a ticket.
And we are running a special with discounts this week for PyCon members.
Thank you.
All right.
So we are here for PyCon Latam.
It's going to happen in Puerto Vallarta, Mexico, August 29 to 31.
Call for proposals end of this month.
And we're going to have two tracks, English and Spanish.
And also, repping for Euro Sci-Fi 2019 in Bilbao, in the Basque Country in the north
of Spain, September 2 to 6.
And call for proposals end May 12.
Thank you.
So is this our slide?
Next slide.
Do I have to hit it?
Sorry, I didn't know.
So, okay.
Both the Gold Rush and the Silver Rush proved that Colorado had way more hidden beauty than
one could see in their eye.
Our sunsets inspired America the Beautiful.
Our peaks make the picturesque skyline of the American West.
And this September, we invite you to Denver, the mile-high city, the queen city of the
plains and the inaugural location of PyColorado.
CFP's open 11 more days and tickets are still selling.
Thanks.
PyCon JP, PyCon Japan, Tokyo.
This year, middle of September, CFP opened.
Japanese and English is available.
Please contact us.
Thank you.
Okay, 20 seconds.
I think keynotes make a conference memorable, so I want to give a big warm welcome to KLR
Sloan, Andrew Godwin, Maria Mitrovich, Nicoleta Ginassi to make the next PyCon Balkan memorable.
It's from the 3rd to 5th of October in Belgrade, Serbia, just across the pond.
Thank you very much.
You should all come to PyGotham in New York City this October 4th and 5th.
Our call for proposals is open now through May 12th anywhere on earth.
There are going to be 600 people, 60 talks, and a great time.
If you'd like to help us choose our schedule, we have public voting opening shortly after
our call for proposals end.
Find out full details at 2019.pygotham.org.
You know what I'm going to say, right?
You have to use one and only one conference, okay?
If you're into good food, good weather, and going to the beach, what are you doing here?
Come to PyCon Spain.
It's in October.
Check out the schedule.
It's going to be published in a month.
We're still getting proposals, so send your proposals, and maybe you can be a speaker
there as well.
Thank you.
All right.
This is not mine, but we have SyPyLadam in Bogota on October 8th to 10th.
We also have PyCon DE in Pydata Berlin coming up October 9th to 11th.
Finally, okay, North Bay Python in Petaluma, California, which is just an hour's head of
San Francisco.
This is our third year running a two-day single track event in beautiful wine country.
CFPB will open July 1st.
We run November 1st, 2nd, and 3rd.
Thank you.
Hey, everybody.
I'm Elaine.
I'd like to invite you all to PyCon Canada.
It's taking place in November 16th to 19th because you should all come to Toronto in
middle of November.
I hear great things about it.
Our CFP is currently open.
Check it out at PyCon.ca.
I stole this talk from John, so like he said, you should propose a talk on any topic that
would be of interest to the Python community.
So check out our website.
We have stickers.
Come see me.
We're also looking for volunteers or Alex.
We're also looking for volunteers who are interested in helping out, and we're also
looking for sponsors.
So thank you.
And I just want to also announce that PyCon Columbia is taking place in February of next
year.
The dates are there, February 7th, 8th, and 9th.
Any questions, please go to the website, and they have a Twitter at the bottom.
Thanks.
Hi, I'm Armer Kramer, organized PyTexas.
We just had our PyTexas 2019 conference on April 13th.
It was great.
It was our biggest win yet.
We would love to see you in 2020.
We've got our act together.
We're looking at our dates, May 16th and 17th, and Austin, if you want to help us, you want
to find out more about us, go to PyTexas.org or follow us on Twitter.
PyCascades next year is in Portland during the rainy time.
Please come.
It is lovely.
Hey, I'm here.
I wanted to talk to you a little bit about PyCon Argentina.
We have a really nice PyCon there.
It's rather big.
Last year it was in Buenos Aires.
We had almost 1,000 attendees.
Next year it's going to be in Buenos Aires too.
With your help, it's probably going to be bigger even.
We have a really nice community, a really nice country.
It's free, so no excuse.
If you wanted to know Argentina, this is a great excuse to go.
Hey, everybody.
My name is Andy.
Would you like to see a PyCarolinas?
I would.
There isn't one right now.
This is a call for action.
Please help make me happen.
We have an open space at 10 a.m. in room 22 to start kicking things off.
You can contact me at automationpanda.com.
Please I really want this conference.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
I'm not on.
Thanks to each and every single one of all the speakers for the regional conferences,
including the ones that announced not their own conferences but other people's conferences.
Thank you to Dustin, my co-host.
Give him a big hand.
He's going to be up on stage next year.
Look how much more attractive he is than I am.
It's going to be so much better for you all.
The end of the tractor joke can be found online or you can ask me afterwards.
But, actually, that's not how it works, is it?
That's not what we do, right?
What we'll do is we'll do the end of the tractor joke at PyCon 2020, which is in Pittsburgh.
I'm sure it's going to be great.
And that's a reason you can all look forward to it.
So just remember where we are in that one.
So yes, thanks to all of our lightning talk speakers.
And thanks to each and every one of you for filling up this room.
Here is the last day of PyCon.
You've all been beautiful.
I'm so glad you're all here.
I'm so glad they're all here.
Please give a massive, massive, massive round of applause to all the lightning talk speakers
all day.
All the ones that we missed that weren't here.
All the ones that are going to come back next year.
All of you guys are going to propose a talk.
If you've never done a talk before, please do a lightning talk and enjoy the rest of
the conference.
And now, a word from our sponsors.