Okay. So we'll be starting now, so please everyone take your seats. So in the next 30
minutes or so, Joe will tell us about syntax trees and Python, so make a big cheer for
him.
Hi. Thanks, everybody, for attending. So today we're going to talk about syntax trees and
Python and specifically around automated code transformations. First a little introduction
about myself. I am an SRE at Pinterest on the API team. I've been there for, I think,
four years this summer. And Pinterest's mission is to bring everyone the inspiration to create
a life they love. Who here has actually heard of Pinterest? Okay. That's good. Who here
has not heard of us? Okay. For you over there, the inspiration I get from Pinterest is dogs.
There's many other things on Pinterest, but it's useful for lots of things, and so I think
pugs are adorable, and so I have lots of pugs. A little bit about Python at Pinterest. We
use Python to serve over 250 million monthly active users, and every single request to
Pinterest, whether it's on mobile or desktop in Europe or the U.S. or anywhere, goes through
Python, and it's been that way since day one. We actually started as a big Django app, and
ever since then we've been using Python. We have over 2.6 million lines of Python code
along with 600,000 lines of comments, so our code base is not small, and so a lot of
the challenges we have that are very simple and small code base are exceedingly difficult
when you have 2.6 million lines of code. For a bit of a data point, CPython itself is about
a million lines of code, roughly, and so we are quite a bit bigger, and so we have quite
a few problems as well. So the problem that we were actually dealing with is this is a
talk I actually gave yesterday with my coworker Jordan Adler, which is reporting our giant
code base, 2.6 million lines of it from Python 2 to Python 3, and it turns out refactoring
at this scale is really, really painful if you don't have any sort of automated ways
to do it, and so there's a few things you want to do. We want to have a safe and a quick
way to apply transformations to a large code base. Safe so it doesn't introduce any new
issues. If you make a transformation, you make a change. You don't want to hunt all
these new bugs that you caused. Quick in this case isn't actually about the runtime it takes
to apply. This is much more about the developer time it takes to apply. If you need to apply
this, a 2.6 million lines of code, something that takes five times as long could be a really,
really long time given you have to do it so many times, and in general, this is sort of
a bigger problem that a lot of people have. Maybe many of you in the audience have a similar
problem here, which is refactoring anything at scale is really complicated and requires
something that is safe and quick. So let's talk a bit about some theory behind what we're
trying to do here. Automated code transformations have a few ways of working, but the most common
way to do it is you have source and you convert into some sort of syntax tree. You do a transformation
on the tree. Sometimes you're called code mods, code transformations, a whole bunch
of different terms out there. I have looked for a standard definition for what these are
called. I cannot figure one out, so I called it automated code transformations. You modify
the syntax tree and then you convert the syntax tree back into source code. And the way these
often work is you apply a series of fixers to transform the source code. So you have
one fixer to do one thing, another one to do another thing, and so you have maybe a
dozen or several dozen of these that you apply sequentially. And this is a fairly safe way
to automate very tedious tasks, and many of them are, for example, part of the Python
2 to 3 migration that many of you have or will be experiencing. So there's many applications
of automated code transformations out there. One application is in style guides. For example,
black is one tool that does that. YAP, I think, is yet another Python formatter, is another
one. We primarily use it at Pinterest to port Python code, but we've used it for many other
cases as well. It's also useful for the general refactoring. If you're changing an internal
interface from moving a module from somewhere in one directory to another directory, that's
really this is a nice way to do it. If you're changing the definition of a function, this
is also a nice tool to use as well. Automated code transformations are really popular in
the general development ecosystem. Anybody here use any of these tools before? Okay,
good. So GoFormat is a nice one. This is actually, I think, one of the more interesting ones
out there. This converts the code to an abstract syntax tree and then it walks the tree and
prints the code out in a standard format. And one of the things this allowed Go to do
is actually to have this tool called GoFix, which allows them to update code automatically
to support new syntaxes and things like that. And one of the main motivations at GoFormat
was actually to support this behavior so you could have code that could be automatically
rewritten instead of having to deal with handling format or anything like that. And this means
that any Go code always has the same format if you use GoFormat. Another interesting tool,
BabelJS, this is used to the same pattern here. It converts the code into abstract syntax
tree and in this case it's often used to convert code into backwards compatible versions to
support older versions of JavaScript and things like it. And C in the C family has clang format
out of LLVM that does very similar things as well. So how do these all work? How do
syntax trees work? And how do code transformations work in general? The most common case I've
actually still think is regex, who here has done something like this. Okay. That's a lot
more people than I was hoping. I've done this too. This is actually not a real example that
we use, but I've used many similar examples. So often regular expressions are really simple.
They work really well for really simple cases. And this is sort of like the first thing many
people try. So here's a nice simple example we have for you throughout the presentation,
which is let's say you want to remove the author tags from code. So here's a simple
way to do it. You could do something like said to say remove the author tag. And in
this case, so we actually this code will work. It will remove the line and everything should
hopefully work. But this doesn't actually work for all cases. This isn't very safe.
This is very quick and it works in the very simple cases. I'm sure many of you like me
have tried to do a regular expression for a really long complicated thing. It turns
out it causes lots of problems. And so regular expressions are often not really a great long-term
solution for transformations. I personally find them really good for one-off transformations
where you're making some change very quickly. Maybe it's in one file, makes it a bit safer.
But you often have to manually review all the changes for safeness. Some examples this
wouldn't have caught this regex here is if your author tag had a bunch of spaces in it,
it wouldn't have caught that. If you had a comment after the line, it may actually remove
that or may ignore the line and leave it in depending on the regular expression. And if
your author tag was inside a doc string, it actually would catch it, which may not be
technically valid because it isn't an author tag and you actually maybe should leave it
in. Although in this case you may want to remove it, but either way it actually makes
the regular expression fairly complicated to deal with.
So this is where abstract syntax trees work really well. And so this is a model we're
trying to use the rest of the presentation here. So here's a basic piece of code we have.
We have a function and we're returning a plus b. We're summing two values here. So in the
top we have the function definition and this function is called sum. We have two arguments,
a and b, and then we return a binary operator bin op. And this is as opposed to simply a
tertiary operator with three values. And the operator is add and we're adding a and b and
returning it. So abstract syntax trees, who here has actually learned about these ever?
Okay, quite a few of you. Good. So this is sort of a textbook example of a syntax tree
here from computer science classes and it represents the structure of the source code.
And it's abstract since it does not represent every detail of the real syntax and instead
contains the structural content related details. And so a bit of a better example that is actually
here. So this is a bit of a more complex example. So in this case we have a importing OS and we
have a similar function before. In this case we have an extra variable total and we have a comment.
So now we have module imports OS. Then we have the function in this case is called sum. It has
two arguments, a and b, and here we can see the default values added in. We are assigning two name,
a plus b, and we have total is what we're returning. Sorry, we're assigning two total a plus b.
And note here that the comment is not actually stored in the syntax tree. This is because it's
abstract and that information is not really relevant for the abstract syntax tree. And so you
see here compared to the previous example, abstract syntax trees get very complex very quickly. I don't
know about you but this is not more readable than the source code. But if you're a computer you would
think otherwise. And this is actually much easier for computers to sort of scan over and do things
on it. This is why compilers and many other things use abstract syntax trees to do analysis
instead of using the source code. So let's go to our example. Before we're trying to actually find
this author tag over here and potentially remove it. So abstract syntax trees are not actually very
good for code transformations because they don't have the original information. But they are useful
of finding problems and reporting them back. So for example, Flake8 actually supports doing a
linter using an AST, an abstract syntax tree. And so let's see what that actually looks like. So this
is actually an example of a linter that we actually do use at Pinterest, something very similar to what
we use. In this case we're trying to find the author node. So we have four node in tree body. If it's
not in the sign operator, for example, we ignore the function def a whole block so you know that's
not related. And then we want to scan all the sign operators here. And if it has, you look at all the
targets of the sign and if it's assigning to author, then we return the node and we actually have found
this node here that we're trying to do something with. And so while this is a bit more complicated
than the regex, it's actually a bit safer I think and it's actually much easier to read. And I think
it also makes the more complex cases easier to comprehend as well. So we talked a bit about for
linting, but let's talk about it for actual code transformation. Syntax trees are often much safer
than regular expressions. It's often much easier to handle the edge cases. And a big part of this is
because you can leverage the syntax trees such as here to actually do a lot of the heavy lifting.
You know exactly what kind of object it is. You actually have a lot more information about the code
you're looking at than actually just trying to look at it by string. It's often much easier to do
things are multi-line transformations. Say you're trying to refactor the name of an import, but you
maybe have a local variable in some files where you're not actually importing the module you're
trying to rename. And so you have to say is this file, is this module imported? If so, rename it at
the import and rename all cases of it. If you do a regular expression, that'll get really complex
really quickly. But if you're using a syntax tree, it makes it much easier to do. And even though
it's much easier to do a lot of things in abstract syntax trees and concrete syntax trees, it often
gets really complex quickly and the hard cases are always complex. But I think this makes the
hard cases possible but complex and the easy cases easier. So this is a direct quote from the concrete
syntax tree in Python. So this is a very concrete parse tree. We need to keep every token and every
comment and even the comments in whitespace between tokens. So there's two kinds of syntax trees here.
We talked about abstract syntax trees and now we're talking about concrete syntax trees. Abstract
has none of the extra information. It doesn't include any whitespace, any comments, anything like
that. But in this case, because Python doesn't have a standard format, we actually need to keep all
that information to solve the problem of recreating the original source code. And so we have the second
option besides abstract, which is concrete, and this is what we're going to actually be using for
everything else, these concrete syntax trees. This is something that's often not taught and this is,
I think, part because it's a weird edge case wherein we're actually trying to convert code back to the
original formatting as much as possible while modifying very small pieces of information. So
there's actually three different parsers in Python to do syntax trees. The two I talk about here,
there's another one which is parser. And this uses Python's internal code to actually do it
internally. And this is optimized to generate byte code and is often too low level for code
refactoring. So we're sort of going to ignore it here. But the other two, AST, which was introduced
in Python 2.6, is for abstract syntax trees. As I mentioned before, it's often used in things like
flake 8. And lib 2.3, which is also introduced in Python 2.6, is a concrete syntax tree. And this
was primarily introduced to actually do the Python 2.3 transformation. And it does things like, it's
bundled with built-in fixers to do things like changing the accept format from accept x,t to
accept x as t. And as we talked a bit about before, this preserves all the relevant information about
whitespace and all kinds of formatting information that AST does not include. So we see here we have
an example x equals 1 plus 1, so that should be 2 for x. But the important bit here actually is it's
hard to read, but there's actually two spaces in front of that 1. And so in the AST, we actually do
not preserve that information. But in lib 2.3, we actually preserve that information. You see the
node on leaf as the equal operator. We actually could get the suffix, and there we see that it
actually has two spaces instead of one. As an interesting side note, I think, related to this
conference today, there's actually a lot of interesting work being done by people in the
community right now around new syntax tree libraries for Python. The Facebook booth actually has
an interesting presentation that they're doing about a new parser they're building that sort of
merges lib 2.3 and AST in ways that makes it a bit easier to do. And there's a bunch of work, I think,
in Python 3.8 about a new parser module. And so this is actually a very interesting sort of relevant
bit of development in this space right now, which I think is very welcoming. So I talked a bit about
the tooling. We're going to talk about... We talked a bit about the concepts and the theory. Let's talk
about some of the tooling here around lib 2.3. So one option is to use lib 2.3 directly instead of
using any tools built on top of it. There's some gotchas with this. Lib 2.3 was bundled, as I
mentioned before, with the tool 2.3, and that's called, according to the docs in Python, that's
for automated Python 2.3 code translation. And as you mentioned, it's a concrete syntax tree. It has
a fairly complex interface that actually makes it really sort of funny to do ad hoc one-off
transformations and to actually write new fixers and run them if you're not shipping your code in
any or installing your code in any standard way. It's very powerful and very safe because you use
a concrete syntax tree. If you have any concerns about edge cases, it's very easy to handle. And
it has a very useful framework around fixers, and so it actually makes it fairly easy to write these.
And it has some nice tooling around it. For example, you could optionally show the change you're about
to make, or you could actually apply the change and things like that. So if you write a fixer,
you get a lot of things for free. So let's dive into a bit how Lib 2.3 works. So it could be very
confusing at first, and it often is sort of not what you expect, and the syntax tree produces is
a bit complex, but it's very, very powerful. There's two types of nodes. There are nodes and
leaves. Leaf nodes actually contain all the code in this case, and leaf nodes have a type telling
you what it contains. There's things like indent, such as indentation increased, string, for all
strings, including doc strings, a number for any kind of number, integer, float, hexadecimal,
octal, et cetera, right parentheses, left parentheses for parentheses, name for keywords or
variables, et cetera. And note here that a lot of these things are actually overloaded for different
meanings. So we have name for keywords and variables, or number for string or integers and
floats and hexadecimal. And this is, I think, in part because Lib 2.3 was designed for the code
transformations and not for actually understanding if something is an octal or hexadecimal. That
wasn't really the goal of Lib 2.3. And so this is a place where if you're trying to do that kind of
analysis, it gets a bit complex and you need a bit more work to sort of understand that. So here is
a, I think, the smallest Lib 2.3 transpiration I could find at the standard library. So here's a
fairly simple one. This is actually changing the format of longs and octal in this case. Both of
those have changed under Python 2 to Python 3. 1L is now 1 because there's no concept of longs. 0755,
that was actually in base 8. That makes it confusing. So you have a different octal format,
which would be 00755. So here's a fairly basic example. Let's walk through it. We have this
base fixer case, this class which you have to override two methods, match and transform. Match
or return either false if you don't care about the thing you're looking at, the node you're looking
at, or return something that is not false if you want to actually pass it on to transform. And
transform takes the node you're trying to transform and the result of match. So in this
case, what match is doing is it's looking if we're starting with a 0 or ending with a L of some sort
and then we pass the information into transform, although we don't use it in this case, and then
we check the node and if it ends with the L, we just truncate the L here because that's all we
have to do in that case. But if it starts with a 0 and it passes val is digit, in this case,
that means that there is no 0 O character in the string here and there are no other values
besides 0 in the string, then we actually want to prefix the thing with remove the first value
and prefix this thing with 0 O instead. There's another bit here which is accept type. And accept
type is optimization here because otherwise match will take every single type of thing. It'll take
too long to scan. So in this case, we know we only care about numbers. So here we say we only match
numbers and then we run it through match and then if it passes match, we actually do the transformation.
So here's a bit of a more complex case but still a fairly basic one here. So this is a second
transformation from the standard library. In this case, this is changing asserts. So a lot of asserts
have been deprecated so this is renaming them. So in this case, we actually don't have match,
we have pattern. Pattern is another way we could do it. So when we set pattern in the base fix itself,
we'll actually compile the pattern into a matcher and use it for matching and it also takes care of
accept type as well. So you automatically get both of those for you and there is actually a tool out
there called find pattern that allows you to find these patterns. I don't know about you but I don't
think I've ever written one of those patterns by hand. I don't know anybody, maybe there's people
here who can but I know I can't. And so the tool out there that actually goes through code and
essentially it's a very basic tool and it prints out the pattern for each line and allows you to
sort of introspect it and dig in a bit more and do different things. So this pattern is entering
essentially what it's saying is we're looking for a dot and then we have the variable meth,
M-E-T-H in this here for method and we're looking for a certain method. Anything that is the dot
after that then matches and we do this joining of the map here and we get all the values and names
over here. And then in transform, we actually take the result, we look up, we get the name there and
we actually look up in the names dictionary what the new name should be and we put it inside. And
the important thing to note here is we have prefix equals name prefix. This is a way of actually
taking the prefix and the concrete syntax tree to preserve all the extra formatting and keep it in
the new syntax tree so we don't actually lose that data. So the interesting thing here is we
actually have the pattern actually is a bunch of patterns joined by or and we actually this is a
fairly common way in lib 2 to 3 to apply similar transformations to slightly different things. You
have a dictionary with key values and you can look up all these different things and map them
together. This one is probably not very readable and that's somewhat intentional. Lib 2 to 3 gets
very complex very quickly. This is a fixer for generator.throw. The format has changed once
again from Python 2 to Python 3 and this is actually one of the smaller examples in the
standard library. So they actually get very complicated very quickly and so they could still
be very complex to write. So going back to our case before, we try to remove the author tag
here. So here we have the input author equals Bob and this is the fixer we would have here. So in
this case we're using a pattern. So we have a simple statement and an expression statement. We
look for author equals anything and in this case note that we have the return character at the end
of what this actually does in the output here you can see the bottom that actually returns removes
the new line. Otherwise the new line would be included and the trade-off here is if you remove
if you look for the new line here anything after the author tag a comment or anything like that
will actually be removed as well. This case is actually still fairly naive. We actually if you
have extra spaces in author equals it actually will not catch that. We could definitely handle
that in Lib 2 to 3 but the transformation will get much more complex here and I want to keep it
simple for example. Also this is what I mentioned before about the runner. You have to do weird
things with the path to sort of inject the path and that's because Lib 2 to 3 has all these
assumptions on how the fixers are named. For example this is fix author. So if you actually
use Lib 2 to 3 and you say author and it automatically look up fix author in the module in this case named
fix author. So there's a bunch of Lib 2 to 3 based tools out there so you don't actually have to write
sort of stock Lib 2 to 3 code. The first two are fairly similar. This one's Python feature. This is
a compatibility layer between to concurrently support Python 2 and Python 3 and it uses Python
3 idioms and it's based on Lib 2 to 3 and it has quite a few additional fixers besides the ones
Lib 2 to 3 provides. A Python modernize is a very similar one. It does a very similar thing. In this
case it uses 6 and the idea is you actually convert Python 2 code to a subset of Python 2 and 3 that
are overlap and so it actually is a slightly different mechanism but it uses the same basic
concepts. It uses in this case 6 and Lib 2 to 3 underneath and in comparison it tries to convert
Python 2 code into almost standard Python 3 code. So here's an example. We have a fairly simple
example here. We have iter values. In this case it's important to know that iter values does not
exist under Python 3. So under modernize we actually have 6 iter values and we have 6 string
types for this instance over here but under futureize we actually do a few different things. We
have pass built in space string and we do x.values which is much more aligned with the Python 3
syntax. Another tool out there is BOLR. This came from Facebook. Has anybody here heard of BOLR?
Okay, a few of you. This is actually my tool of choice currently for writing any kind of code
transformation. It requires Python 3.6 but it can be run against Python 2 code. It is Lib 2 to 3
based although it uses a slight upstream copy of Lib 2 to 3 called physics, I believe. It's a much
easier interface. It's very simple to run things. You just do BOLR run and you do the transformation.
It's a much cleaner API. You do query, select, modify, execute. Query you select which files
you're looking for. Select which methods and things like that you're actually looking to modify,
which piece of code. Modify tells you how to modify it and execute is what to do. Do you want
to show the diff? Do you want to save it? Do you want it to be interactive output so you can say
yes or no to apply each thing? This actually makes the really easy cases really easy but it also,
it still reveals all the powerful features of Lib 2 to 3 and oftentimes you have to dig into those
and use some of the more complex features of Lib 2 to 3. Here's a fairly simple example of what
Lib 2 to 3, of BOLR supports. BOLR supports the select statement here. You can actually still use
the Python Lib 2 to 3 pattern mechanism or you can actually do all these different selects. You
can say select root, select module, class, subclass, etc. This is I think a much easier interface to use
in that Lib 2 to 3 native. Here's that same example we talked about before but in this case we're
using BOLR. In this case if you look at the bottom line, line 11, we have BOLR query the input file.
In this case it's a single file but also takes a list of files if you choose instead. We're selecting
a variable here, in this case author, and we're going to modify it. It turns out there is no built
in modifier for remove so we have a very simple one that looks for the parent node here and then
it just says if they're a parent then remove the parent and that fixes everything. We see in the
output here we actually remove on line four, remove the author tag although we do add that extra line
over there. This is the same comparisons I showed you, the same two transformations I showed before.
The top one here is the BOLR one and the bottom one is actually the Lib 2 to 3 native one.
As if you note here the native one actually is smaller. I do think that the BOLR one is
actually easier to comprehend and easy to read. I don't know about you but I find the pattern
sort of things much harder to read than actually a few lines of code here and I think it's a much
easier interface and it's been very good for us to sort of see the actual, be able to break it down
nicely and actually be able to use the BOLR interface instead of Lib 2 to 3 directly.
So in addition to these transformations another really common tool that's gotten popular the
past number of years is Black. Black is an uncomprising Python code formatter and once again
it requires Python 3.6 but it runs against Python 2 code as well. It uses Lib 2 to 3, in this case
it's also a slight fork of Lib 2 to 3. This is something currently at Pinterest we do not use
but we are looking to use it hopefully in the very near future and interestingly enough this
validates the concrete syntax tree transformations it makes against the abstract syntax tree. The
idea is if you're making any sort of style changes to the code it should still mean the same thing
which means your abstract syntax trees before and after should still map up. So this is a good
example where you actually could use a syntax tree to actually transform your code in a very elegant
way instead of having Flake8 report to you a bunch of hours and you have to spend 20 minutes fixing
it all by hand doing very silly things like adding new lines and adding spaces. So in conclusion
while popular in other ecosystems code transformations I think are underutilized in
the Python community. I think that's really starting to change. I think all of you should
be looking into them for any problems you think they could solve. They often make really hard
problems quick and safe. They've saved us countless hours of tedious labor for things like the Python
2 to Python 3 migration refactoring code in general hopefully soon to be enforcing style guides
and although they're really great the complex edge cases are unfortunately still very complex.
And thank you very much for listening and I think I have two or three minutes if anybody has any questions.
Thank you.
So anyone has a question?
Hi I was wondering if there was such a tool that is able to work on Jupyter notebooks would you know?
That's a good question. I don't know the answer to that. I imagine there it
shouldn't be too hard to do but I do not know of anything. That's a great question though.
Okay.
Anyone else?
Do you know of any experiments that have done been done with optimization on the AST?
Yeah that's a great question. Under Python I do not know but this is how compilers work in general
and so there is a rich academic you know corpus information on how to do this. Roughly the way
compilers work is they convert the code into computer readable code and they do optimizations.
I imagine there are optimizations you could do in this in this way but you probably could also
do it in a different layer probably inside of Python itself but I think that'd be probably
an interesting space to explore more.
There was a really interesting talk earlier about feature flags. Have you looked into maybe using
this to automatically remove feature flags from code?
Yeah that's that is a great question. We have not done that yet although that's a very good
idea. I think that's probably something worth exploring. We definitely have had problems
in the past where you use a feature flag to launch something and you leave it there for three years
and maybe cause problems in three years. I think that's something that's probably
that's a really great suggestion. Thank you.
Would you recommend using these type of tools if you were trying to undertake the ambitious task
of making your code base that your team uses more readable just from a general readability standpoint?
Yeah I would. I think for a few reasons it makes makes the general transformations easier.
I think readable is a very subjective thing and I am a big believer in like a standard style guide
and I think that's not because nobody has to agree on what it is they all could disagree on
like what's right but the important part is it looks the same and so I think having a standard
style guide and something like black to sort of standardize that and make all the work done for
you is really nice. Things like lib 2 to 3 make refactoring in general really nice if you have to
you want to let's say you're moving a module from you know module a to module b this kind
of transformation makes it really easy to do in a general way very quickly. Cool thank you.
I would have a question so you said it can easily get really complicated so what is the line where
you like still done it? Sorry what is what? What is the line where you would say it gets
the way too complicated to work it like would you do like I don't know comprehension generation
for for loops it's too complicated or? I think it's the I think the more complicated cases are
often the ones that require analysis of an entire module or an entire function to understand something
so often it's the multi-line sort of analysis that you have to do if you're looking at like
the definition of one thing or maybe one line it's usually not so bad well if you're trying
to solve something here's actually a pretty good example. Let me go back. This one's actually
surprisingly complex over here so it turns out actually knowing what is a test case using assert
or assert true versus something else that's not inheriting from test is actually not very easy in
this case so if you look at this transformation we actually do not make any assumptions or any
introspection about where this is coming from we're making the general assumption here that
if you're calling assert equals it's actually coming from the standard library somehow which
is clearly not always true but it's true enough in most cases that there are edge cases you will hit
and it's really hard to not hit these edge cases but they're usually small enough that you could
catch them by hand. Have you ever considered any use cases where you use this for code generation
instead of transformation? We have not I have seen cases where code does use something like two to
three to actually do on the fly migrations of code to make it two compatible or three compatible.
In general I don't think we have uses for on the fly code transformation or code generation.
That was all thank you very much. Thank you.