Good morning, folks. How's everyone doing? Cool. Awesome. We've got a great talk. This
is the Zen of Python teams. Please welcome Adrienne Lowe.
Hey, everyone. Can you hear me okay? I'm so excited to be here. I always like to start
with a thank you because it's such a pleasure and a privilege to get this stage and I don't
take it for granted. Thank you for having me. I'm so excited to talk to you about the
Zen of Python for teams. First, we need to talk about what the Zen of Python is. Let's
do that. The Zen of Python is a collection of 19 guiding principles that have influenced
the development of the language and you can see them here. The lines are short and open
to interpretation on purpose. Typically, they're taken as direction on how we should write
our code but they have plenty of guidance for us about how we should treat each other
while we're writing that code. My argument is that not only has the Zen of Python influenced
the design of the language but that it's influenced the way we interact on our development teams.
There's something uniquely Pythonic about Python teams where we emphasize values of
collaboration and transparency and trust. Reinterpreted for teams, the Zen of Python
has plenty to tell us about communication and conflict, building inclusive and transparent
processes and promoting psychological safety. And today, I want to teach you about some
of the attitudes, processes and practices that can help you grow and be part of happier
teams who deliver better software faster. Because delivering software to users in production
is what we are here to do. I believe in shipping and I remind my teams that that's what we're
here to do. I love this quote from Intercom's VP of Engineering from his article, shipping
is your company's heartbeat and I recommend you read it. He reminds us that software only
becomes valuable when we ship it to customers and that good products are really a side effect
of combining great people with an idea in an agile and dynamic and collaborative environment
that helps them ship. Unfortunately, lots of managers forget that the healthy culture
is critical to helping people ship. The Zen of Python has lots to say about healthy culture.
So let's talk about how to build psychologically safe teams that ship informed by the Zen
of Python. Many of my stories will come from teams I currently manage, so let me tell you
a little bit about us. I work as director of engineering at Juice Analytics leading our
operations and platform teams. We use Python and Django to build what is basically Squarespace
for data stories. If you or your company has some interesting data that you want to share,
our product Juice Box helps you tell an interactive story that your users can explore by asking
and answering questions in a really delightful way. Python has been a big part of my life
for most of the last decade. I've been an individual contributor on Python teams and
open source projects, an organizer of Django girls, an organizer of Python meetups including
Pi ATL and a director at Django project. So my stories come from pretty varied work, from
my work as an IC, as a volunteer on open source projects, but most recently as director of
engineering. No matter where I've been or what I've worked on or who I've worked with,
I've always valued working on a healthy team. So now as an engineering manager and director,
I ask myself every day, how can I create a better experience for the people on my team?
How can I help them feel safe and challenged so that we can ship valuable code to users
together? How can I help them feel more connected or empowered or successful? What actions can
I take to encourage that? So this talk is about the action that we can take inspired
by the Zen of Python to improve our teams. As you hear me share my team's stories, I
hope you'll compare it against your own experience. Think of the way the Zen has shaped you and
your teams. Ask yourself, which of the sayings stick with you? Do any of them confuse you?
Do you find any of them challenging? And why? When you leave PyCon and go back to your teams,
what will you bring with you? So here's our roadmap for today. First, I'm going to introduce
you to the Zen of Python. Maybe you haven't seen it in a while, maybe you've never seen
it, so let's start by taking a look. Second, we'll walk through just six of the Zen's famous
lines and interpret them for teams. I'll often start by giving an interpretation as
it relates to code, but mostly I'll focus on reading it anew and applying it to teams
and team dynamics. Third and finally, I'll wrap up with a call to action to take your
reflections back to your team. It's fun, it's interactive, it's my own little Easter egg
that I'm excited to share with you. So let's take a look at the Zen of Python. Here's where
it all began, actually. The Zen of Python got started like many great ideas in a conversation
on a mailing list. As you probably can't actually read from your seat, the author Tim Peters
playfully offered up the 19 lines as an outline that Guido could start from. The Zen of Python
is technically 20 lines with the final line left blank for Guido to fill in. I really
like how Tim used the word outline and the phrase start from. From the beginning he emphasized
how this is not complete, how it's a work in progress. By its very nature and from the
very beginning, it's an invitation to interpretation. So we should feel really good about coming
up with our own interpretations today. It's totally in the spirit. And the spirit is joyful
and playful and fun. Let's take a look at the lines. I won't read these aloud, but please
take a moment to read over them. So the Zen of Python came to us from this humble beginning
on a mailing list to being incorporated as part of the Python enhancement proposals as
PEP 20 to being printed on the back of our PyCon shirt two years ago. It's seemingly
everywhere and it's also right here with you baked into your interpreter as an Easter egg.
That's right. As long as you're running Python, you can run import this at nope, nope, wrong
you. And read the Zen of Python. Give it a try. That's not the type of manager I am.
I am not a snapping pointer just for the record, but that would have totally spoiled what we
were trying to do. The word is here's your cue. So now that we've seen the Zen, let's
step through six of the lines and interpret them for teams. Let's start at the beginning
with beautiful is better than ugly. So okay, the Zen of Python totally comes out swinging
with this one. It's a hard one. And it's hard because words like beautiful and ugly are
tricky because we implicitly understand how subjective and contextual they are, right?
They require context to make meaning. And even when we have that context, we can totally
still argue about it. One person's clean code is another person's cave painting. And some
people think clean code isn't even a thing and we should stop saying that phrase. When
I was little, the word ugly didn't just mean aesthetically displeasing. It was actually
used to describe behavior as in ugly behavior, as in actin ugly. Actin ugly meant misbehaving,
but a special kind of misbehaving usually directed towards adults, usually connotating
disrespect. You need a little context with parents and kids, possibly in the southern
U.S., to wrap your head around the idea of actin ugly. But if you'll grant me the idea
that we can act ugly, then we can ask what kind of behavior is ugly on our development
teams? What have you personally seen done on your dev teams that has put your group
two steps back? I have a few ideas of some things I've seen. How about hoarding information?
That's when someone knows something helpful that they could share, but they choose not
to. It defeats the purpose of collaboration and growing together when we hoard valuable
information that could be used to help others. Or how about bitter cutting code reviews?
Has anyone in this room ever been subject to a bitter or cutting code review that seemed
designed just to cut you down and make you feel bad? That's horrible, and I'm sorry that
was your experience, because that should not be the goal of a code review. It should be
to critique the code, not the person. Or how about if somebody wants to get started on
your project, but there's no information about how to get started? There's no read me, there's
no docs, there's no one to ask for help, there's nobody who wants to help. So let's break this
down just a little bit more. To help interpret this line for teams, I want to introduce you
to Ron Westrom's typology of organizational cultures. Westrom wrote a paper in 1988 where
he identified three types of leadership styles that give rise to different types of team
culture and communication. He'd been researching human factors in system safety, particularly
in the context of accidents and technological domains that were highly complex and risky,
such as aviation and healthcare. So big deal. His types are pathological, bureaucratic,
and generative. Your team's type will be reflected in its leadership, the way it approaches problems
and conflict, and the way communication flows or does not flow in your organization. On
pathological teams, information is viewed as a personal resource to be used in political
power struggles. These power-oriented organizations are characterized by large amounts of fear
and threat. People often hoard information or withhold it for political reasons or distort
it to make themselves look better. These environments discourage taking responsibility because people
are scared. Sounds pretty ugly to me. On bureaucratic teams, in contrast, alignment with one's team
takes precedence over alignment with the larger mission. In other words, individuals feel
more loyalty toward their immediate team or group than they do toward their company and
its goals. They protect departments. There's an idea that they want to maintain their turf.
They insist on their own rules. They want things to be done by the book, but by their
book. It sounds imperious. It sounds authoritarian. And when you're working on teams, it is not
a good look. Some might call it ugly. On generative teams, in contrast, and this is what you want,
the leader emphasizes the company's mission and they rally people around that mission.
They ask, how can we accomplish our goal? And they think of we expansively. Generative
teams have high cooperation. People feel like they can take risks because the risks will
be shared and they won't be scapegoated. Failure leads to inquiry, not blaming or scapegoating
or root cause analysis, and information flows more freely as a result. I think we found
something beautiful. Westrom noted that leaders set the tone for their team, but we're all
still responsible for our own actions. So ask yourself, what kind of team do you want
to be on? We could debate beautiful code all day. Thankfully, kind behavior is a lot more
clear. Being explicitly welcoming and sharing information freely, providing support and
making it safe to ask questions, challenging code, not people, are just a few of the hallmarks
of a healthy team. For more on Westrom's model as well as other technical and leadership
capabilities that will help your team ship, I highly recommend Nicole Forsgren's book
Accelerate. It's been a huge help to me, but let's get back to the Zen of Python and our
second line today. Explicit is better than implicit makes me think of how important documentation
is. Healthy teams document their processes and expectations and offer how-to's. They
provide playbooks and resources and onboarding guides and tutorials. They make it clear how
to contribute and what steps to take and what to do when you're confused. They do this because
documenting your processes makes it easier for others to join you. Now, without good
docs, people who already know each other can mostly muddle through. This is because
they are cheating and they're leaning on existing relationships that they already have to get
unblocked and get their questions answered. But what if you're a new person? You don't
have that shared context. You don't know the back channel. So we need to document our processes
in order to make it more accessible to people who don't look like us or who aren't already
part of our group. Along with public docs, it's also important to keep conversation in
the open. Keeping your chat about your code in a public place is another way to lower
the barrier to entry. If you use Slack or a similar tool, this means keeping your conversation
about your work in the main channels and not buried in DMs or other obscure places. Keeping
the conversation open makes it, as we see here in this example, possible for anyone
to check it out and jump in or help if somebody has questions. And while Slack is not documentation,
keeping your chats in the open does create something of a public record that is somewhat
searchable depending on how you feel about Slack's search feature. All shade. So documenting
your processes also improves relationships between teams. And this is part of my team.
Healthy teams lead off conflict by setting ground rules and SLAs or service level agreements
that define how they'll work with other teams. On our team, one of our values is consistency
of process. We have several types of SLAs with our customers, both internal and external,
where we try to be crystal clear about how work will get done and on what timeline and
who will work it. Before we wrote these SLAs, our inter-team relationships were pretty strained.
But once we took the time to document our processes and expectations, we found we had
way less conflict and more mutual understanding of what it was going to take to get the work
done. This meant fewer fire drills, fewer last-minute requests, fewer people paged on
the weekend for work that should have been planned. We also publish our processes. Here's
a snippet of our calendar, my calendar actually, that shows how we show when our sprints are
going to happen and when we're going to be doing our sprint planning and demos. And we
invite other people, not on our team, into our processes as observers, as listeners,
and we share our documents and artifacts afterwards. We also document our people. Recently I put
a call on Twitter to ask about your favorite lines and I really like this response from
Lee. And Lee refers to code in this example, but I think we can do this with people too.
On my team, I led us in an activity where we created individual profiles to share on
our team. The profiles answer some of the following questions, and I ask that my people
refer to these periodically, especially before working closely with others, because the doc
explicitly reminds us how our colleagues know that they'll feel successful and what
might cause them to stumble. It was a really fun activity. I just gave a whole talk on
the process at Lead Dev this past Tuesday, and the video will be posted soon, so definitely
check that out. A lot of people really, really loved it, and I hope you get a lot out of
it as well. Because you're going to learn how to get answers like these, and these are
real responses from my developers. I hope that you can already see as you're reading
how valuable these answers are, and there's so much more that came out of that process.
So let's move on to the next line of the Zen of Python. Simple is better than complex.
We build complicated features and solve complex requirements with sets of smaller, more straightforward
features, right? That's how it works. And we build meaningful relationships the same
way. We work through tough issues by building a foundation of small interactions that build
emotional bank account or trust with each other. So make sure that you're taking the
time to have coffee with your colleagues or catch up on the weekend or ask about each
other. Show that you care personally. You don't have to be a manager to do that. On
our team, we're mostly remote, so we do something called remote happy hour, which is just where
we meet and hang out, just kind of chat about our lives. And for some people, it might feel
tempting to skip a meeting like this because you don't see the immediate value in the way
that you might say spending some time debugging some code. But you're building that trust
and familiarity with your colleagues when you do this. You're building that shared language
and the good feelings that you can lean on when times get tough. Because things will
get tough. Here's the thing about real work. It's messy. And it's messiness and pressure
and ambiguity is frustrating and hard and painful and disappointing. And it can take
a real toll on relationships unless they're strong. And we can make them strong by investing
in them. So let's build that emotional bank account so that so we're ready when the real
world comes to make withdrawals, when deadlines and stress and team conflict threaten to take
its toll. Our relationships with each other are the most complex and complicated features
of our lives. Like software, let's build them with small but meaningful actions that
show that we care and we're here and we're invested. When I asked my team which line
of the Zen of Python they like best, one of my ops engineers said this one. Makes sense,
right? It's a good ops engineer. If something goes wrong, people want to know. David loves
this line because as he says, if something is wrong with my code, I want to know. Interestingly,
that very same week in another conversation with a different developer, the developer
said if I do something to hurt someone, I want to know. With code, we can write more
code to raise and log errors. But with humans, we have to rely on other humans to tell us
when we broke them. And feedback is the tool that we have to help others understand the
impact that they have on us. We owe it to ourselves and to each other to give timely
actionable feedback that describes what happened and the impact that it had on us. On a healthy
team, if someone screws up, they shouldn't feel like they need to hide it or from it.
We understand that people make mistakes and feelings get hurt, but we value each other
enough to take responsibility for our actions and try to improve. We don't let issues pass
silently because we know that letting things pass silently damages trust on our teams.
The pain of giving or receiving negative personal feedback is only painful in the moment, but
it's bleeding. Allowing it to pass silently is something that can accrue and damage teams
permanently. The other day, I tweeted about how to respond when you wake up to a wall
of text from one of your developers who is like, oh, my goodness, I broke this thing.
I fixed this thing, but I feel terrible about it. Basically, they were feeling shame for
making a mistake, and we've all been there. But mistakes are normal. And I said that you
should respond to things like that by hearing them and affirming them and appreciating them
and reminding them that mistakes help us grow. I was careful about the way I responded because
I love working on a team where we can be open with each other about our mistakes. It's a
signal that your team is on the right track if they can talk about their mistakes. If
they're hiding, if they're yelling at you, don't touch my garbage, that can indicate
that like this possum, they're scared. But if they come right up to your door and they
say, look at my trash, look at this beautiful trash that I have amassed, that can indicate
that they trust you, right? That they're not scared. So be kind to people who show you
their trash. It was probably hard for them. And let's show enough of our trash that we
get so used to showing our trash that it becomes something that we enjoy doing. It gets easier
for us the more we do it. So let's move on to the next line. In the face of ambiguity,
anybody refuse the temptation to guess. When it comes to code, refuse the temptation to
guess at someone's motives. Don't get blame and stew about it. You're only going to cause
yourself more frustration. When you see code or behavior that frustrates you, don't assume
the worst and certainly don't assume that that person is actively attacking you. Humans
are complex and their actions are influenced by all kinds of ideas and experience and tradeoffs
that you may never understand or have access to. So grab some time with them if you can
and care enough to ask. Ask where they're coming from. Ask what they were trying to
accomplish and why they took that particular strategy. And if you can't reach out to that
person for whatever reason, try to get some context from someone who might be able to
help you. Put the questions on the PR, open a GitHub issue, address it, confront it, be
assertive, challenge directly while caring personally, refuse the temptation to guess. I really
love this reflection from my lead, Megna, on why this is one of her favorite lines. And I think
it works for people, too. It can be really tempting, sadly, to explain away people like we
might say, well, she's in sales. She probably doesn't care how the code works. And while it
can be tempting to explain away people like this, I found that if you set really clear expectations
and give clear guidance and have good docs that show that you care and make it safe to fail,
people will typically exceed any expectations you ever could have had for them. And one final note
for the managers in the room. Do I have any managers in the room? Awesome. I really tried to
keep manager-specific advice to a minimum in this talk, but this one's for you and I think it's
important, so I'm going to call it out. Your weekly one-on-one time is your time to beat the
guessing game. Please don't guess about how your direct reports are doing or what they're struggling
with. Use the time you already have scheduled to ask good questions about what's really motivating
them, what's frustrating them, and how they'd like to grow. Please don't guess. If you'd like advice
on how to have better one-on-ones, I have another lead talk that I gave last year that's already
available online. Okay. It's time for the last line of the Zen that we're going to focus on today,
and what better time for the line is now is better than ever. One of my developers, Steven, shared
this wisdom with me. He said, it's really easy for me to overthink my work. Sometimes in the process
of trying to figure out what would be the most efficient thing to do with my code, I can end up
being vastly inefficient. Now is better than ever reminds us of the value of taking some action,
however small, to move closer to our goal. It's oriented toward doing, because doing, even if we
end up being wrong, gives us information. When I was a developer, I had a single sticky note on my
monitor. It's something that my EM said to me in a time when I was being really hard on myself.
Doing and being wrong is a lot better than not doing it all. He gave me this wisdom in a time
when I was being really hard on myself, and he saw that that was holding me back. He wanted me to
feel safe to try things, even if it meant screwing up and breaking stuff. It helped me through some
really hard times as a developer, and now I pass it on to my engineers as a manager. There comes a
time in my relationship with each of my direct reports, no matter how senior they are, when I
have to share this sticky note wisdom with them. I share it when I feel like they need it. Sometimes
they're being too hard on themselves like I was. Sometimes they're just having a hard time getting
started. But it doesn't matter how many years they've been working as a developer or how much
they know about Python. They all benefit from this at some point. That's because everyone benefits
from being reminded that they can start where they are. On a psychologically safe team, people
feel safe to make mistakes because they understand it's part of growth. So there you have it. Six
sayings from the Zen of Python interpreted for teams. I hope it's been useful for you. I hope
you've been thinking about the teams you're a part of and how you'd like to improve them and how the
Zen inspires you personally because if you have been thinking about these things, then you're ready
for the third and final section of my talk, the Easter egg. Volunteers, this is your cue. Yes,
the Easter egg. The Zen of Python is an Easter egg. So it just made sense that my talk would have an
Easter egg as well, right? PyCon volunteers are now coming around the room with something special
for you. Thank you, PyCon volunteers. It's an egg. But what are we going to do with these eggs? Well,
we know that the Zen of Python is itself an Easter egg and we also know that the final line
is as yet unwritten. And we remember that the Zen of Python started as an invitation to interpretation.
And finally, we remember that Tim Peters left the last line of the Zen of Python blank for Guido to
fill in. Well, here you go, Guido. We're going to help you out. Hashtag here you go, Guido.
Inside the egg, you're going to find some directions. Write a phrase that you would
like to bring back to your team. Write something that you want to be reminded of, something that
you would stick on your monitor or something that you would tell someone new on your team or someone
new to development. Write the 20th line of the Zen of Python and then share it. Post it on Twitter
with the hashtag and the hashtag ZOP20. Tag me too. I'm Adrienne Friend. I'll probably retweet you.
Take a picture and drop it in your team's Slack channel. Take your wisdom back to your teams.
I'm really excited to read what you've been dreaming about and what's challenging you
and how you want to grow. I'm thrilled for the teams that you're part of.
Thank you again. Long live the Zen. Long live Python.