We are going to hear from Philip James.
He is giving the elephant and the serpent using Mastodon with Python.
Please welcome Philip.
Hi.
My name is Philip James.
Welcome to the elephant and the serpent.
This time slot is a slot of incredible talks.
And I know you had to choose between myself, Lin Root talking about async, Simon Willison
talking about SQLite APIs, Jacob Kaplan talking about Django and Webpack and a talk about
Django channels.
If any of those talks sound more interesting, feel free to go to one of them.
I promise it will be fine.
If you decide to stick around, thanks.
I really appreciate it.
So this talk is going to be about Mastodon, an open source federated social network and
Python, the community wrapped around a programming language that brings us all here today.
Before we get started, who am I?
Like I said, my name is Philip James and I lead the platform team at Patreon who graciously
support me being here.
I've also given a number of talks at various PyCons across the globe, including a talk
tomorrow with my frequent speaking buddy, Ashish Laroja.
This slide here is from the talk we gave last year at PyCon titled All in the Timing.
I speak about programming and technical topics all over the world because I still believe
that programming is the closest I'll ever come to doing real magic.
I've been programming professionally for over a decade and I still find it somewhat magical
to be able to create something useful out of bits and bytes and computers that we've
tricked into thinking by shoving lightning into them.
Now some people in technology have trouble with the word magic.
When I say magic, I mean something magical in its effect, not necessarily in its cause.
The power that technology brings to the world is magical.
The communities that technology help foster are magical.
Even though we can explain every step that happens, every bit and byte and circuit, it
is magical to the people who use it and still magical to me.
And while I wouldn't call myself an expert on the subject of magic, I know more about
stage magic than most.
That is my username across the vast majority of the internet and I bet there are people
in this room who have seen that name flit across their screen and didn't know who was
on the other end until right now.
Hello, I'm FilDini.
But before FilDini was my internet handle, it was my stage name.
I spent my early teenage years making pocket money by performing as the great FilDini at
birthday parties all over California.
The feeling I got then when I was able to pull off a trick is very similar to the feeling
I get now when making a piece of technology do what I want it to do.
Of course, that string is also instantly recognizable as a Twitter username.
Twitter is magic.
The communities that Twitter fosters, communities that many of us in this room take part of
in a daily basis, are magical.
Through Twitter, we make connections that help us find work, chat with our peers, share
our favorite activities, or sometimes even find love.
Twitter is also magic from an engineering perspective.
It operates on a scale that many of us in this room have trouble fathoming and it mostly
just works.
The magic that exists in programming exists double in systems engineering and large amounts
of it are performed at Twitter on a regular basis.
Twitter is also dark magic, magic that destroys rather than creating.
It's a place where the most misguided amongst us feel free to express every negative opinion,
where we are constantly inundated with reminders of violence or targeted with violence ourselves,
where it seems like the political bombs are always going off, and where it feels like
we have to wade through toxic waste to get to the parts that we like.
All of this happens in a set of systems that are currently using our data, our connections,
and thoughts and ideas to aggregate ourselves and sell us off to advertisers.
And this is because there is a misalignment of incentives with large social networks that
I think cannot be easily resolved.
The people running those social networks want to make money for their work, which is completely
fair.
Most of the people using those social networks don't want to or can't pay for them, but do
want a place to form communities with all their friends already live.
There is still a mental model amongst Internet users that the Internet is free, and it's
hard to blame them.
We in the industry of making the Internet haven't done enough to educate users otherwise.
The piece of black magic that tries to bridge these incentives is advertising.
I don't necessarily believe all advertising is inherently evil, but I do think the advertising
at scale necessary to fund something like Twitter forces companies to make compromises
that are hard to align with the average user's incentives, and which promote either a blind
eye towards or willful encouragement of the dark magic I was talking about earlier.
Towards the end of 2016, I was deeply despairing about all social networks, Twitter especially,
and I thought we were never going to get anything better.
I didn't think there was a way to build a global community online without funding it
through ads.
In early 2017, I discovered Macedon.
Macedon is magic.
Macedon is an open-source social networking platform based on a set of technologies that
are being adopted as open standards for building social networks.
Macedon solves some of the problems of modern social networks by not having any single server.
Instead, anyone can create a server, and that server can federate with any other server
on the network.
Imagine anyone could start their own Twitter server, and you could join that server, but
follow and be followed by anyone on any other server.
Because there's no central service trying to make money from this, there's no tracking
of user data, no ads engine trying to collect data, and each user and server admin has control
over what they see and who they interact with.
Macedon looks like this.
This is the main Macedon web interface.
If you think it looks like an older era tweet deck, you're not wrong.
I know this text is small, and there's a lot going on here.
I'm going to try to explain what's going on column by column.
Also, anywhere I've blurred things out, it's because I felt I didn't have permission to
make them public to the world, even if they might have been public status updates.
This is the main compose bar.
Here you can access your account settings, search hashtags and users, and compose toots.
The standard way to describe a status update in Macedon is toot, mainly because that's
what the button in the software says.
We'll be using toot and status update pretty interchangeably in this talk.
Default Macedon lets users send 500 character updates.
Users can, of course, include emoji in their toots, including per server custom emoji that
still get rendered correctly across all the servers.
There's a robust community of creating and sharing custom emoji across servers.
Toots can have polls, and you can set a visibility and content warning for each of your toots.
A brief word on that.
Content warnings deserve special mention.
If you think your content, what you're trying to share with the world, needs a Twitter warning
so that people can opt into seeing it, or as a spoiler for some pop media, like, say,
end game of gamer or game of thrones, you can hide it behind some text and use it to
chew to see it rather than being confronted with it.
Content warnings and toot visibility make an attempt to solve the problems outlined
in this XKCD.
You can set your toots to be public, unlisted, or followers only.
Public is what it says on the tin.
It's public, but it won't show up in the federated or local timelines.
More on that in a minute.
Followers only is exactly that.
It is only available to your followers.
Speaking of followers, this is the home column.
This is all the toots from all the people you follow, no matter what server they're
on.
You can do all the things you might expect from a social network, like replying, boosting,
and liking.
The local timeline shown here is all the public non-reply toots from people on the same server
as you.
What's being talked about on the local timeline is one of the best ways to judge the community
you've joined on the local server.
Here we can also see an example of marking images with a content warning.
The user has to choose to see this image and therefore gets to choose what they want to
be confronted with in their social media.
The federated timeline is one of the most interesting things about Macedon, and we're
going to talk more about it in a minute.
This timeline is all the public toots your server knows about.
If it gets federated to your server and it's public visibility, it'll end up here, and
it's an incredible way to discover new people to follow and see what the Fediverse as a
whole is talking about.
I've said the word federation a lot, but I haven't really explained it.
To give us all a grasp of what's going on, I'm going to talk about one of the open protocols
that powers Macedon.
Macedon is powered by a technology called Activity Pub, which is currently a recommendation
to the W3C.
Activity Pub is a decentralized social networking protocol, and it powers the vast majority
of the universe of federated social networking sites, collectively known as the Fediverse.
Activity Pub specifies two main pieces, a server-to-server federation protocol and a
client-to-server protocol.
To understand Macedon under the hood, you need to understand Activity Pub, and I'm going
to explain Activity Pub with two of the most famous users in computing history, Alice and
Bob.
This is Alice.
Alice is a user, what Activity Pub calls an actor.
Alice, according to Activity Pub, has an inbox and an outbox.
The inbox receives messages from the rest of the world, and the outbox is where Alice
puts the messages she wants to send to the rest of the world.
Alice's inbox and outbox live in a server, in this case, Macedon.social.
Alice's full username in the Fediverse is at Alice at Macedon.social.
Her client makes API requests against the server to take actions, like getting new messages
from the inbox and posting messages she wants to send to her outbox.
This is the client-to-server protocol.
If Alice wants to send a message to Bob at Macedon.social, she posts a message to her
outbox, which Macedon.social posts to Bob's inbox, which Bob then gets with his client
and reads.
If it feels like email, it is, deliberately so.
If Bob is on a completely different server, this works mostly the same way.
Macedon.social knows how to look up Bob on a different server, and Macedon.social will
post the message to Bob at other servers' inbox.
This is the server-to-server protocol of part of Activity Pub, and in many ways, it really
is that simple.
I'm simplifying somewhat, but not that much.
This server-to-server protocol is the beating heart of Federation.
Every user has a home server, and all the servers know how to talk to each other by
posting to the right inboxes for the right users.
Those of you who have worked with networks probably already understand this, but one
of the benefits of Federation like this is resiliency to any one node in the network
going down.
This has, in fact, happened in the past to the largest English-speaking server, Macedon.social.
Macedon.social has gone hard down for hours, and the rest of the network of servers kind
of didn't notice.
They kept sharing messages and kept the network alive.
When Macedon.social came back up, the other servers attempted to replay messages back
to the right users' inboxes, and the Fediverse rolled merrily along.
Now, yes, messages can get dropped, but the software is smart enough to try really hard
not to let that happen.
This idea also applies to server-to-server moderation.
If one server in the Fediverse decides to become a hotbed for trolls or Nazis, the admins
of the other servers can choose to blacklist that node and prevent that garbage from entering
their users' feeds.
I want to say another word here about the magic of communities.
Magical communities require community norms.
In the modern parlance, this means that communities we belong to have codes of conduct, rules
for how we should behave, and procedures that get followed if we break those rules.
It's interesting to note, from my perspective, that it's only with the rise of sites like
Twitter and Facebook that this has been seen as hotly contested or strange.
When I joined the Internet back in the days of IRC and web forums, the admins and operators
of those spaces had the power to enforce community norms through silencing and banning.
Often this was at the whims of the admin, and I would argue that explicit codes of conduct
make this better by making it clear what is expected of the admins as well as the community
members.
One of the cool things about Macedon is that admins on servers can mute or block entire
remote servers and people on remote servers from interacting with the users of their server.
An admin can enforce what happens on their server even if the users involved are on a
remote server.
This helps make magical communities.
Admins can work with the users they're supporting to make sure the place they're building together
is what everyone is looking for in an Internet home.
Okay, so we have message sending.
We have a federated network of servers, but we're not quite a social network yet.
To power a true social network, we need one more thing, the ability to follow others and
be followed.
Activity Pub has a solution for this, a follower and following collection.
Let's explain with an example.
Bob wants to follow Alice.
He via his server posts a follow action to Alice's inbox.
Alice's server receives the message and adds Bob to Alice's follower collection.
Now that's supposed to say Bob, not Ben.
I have no idea why it says Ben.
Now when Alice posts a message to her followers, Bob is on that list and Alice's server will
post the message to Bob's inbox.
Congrats!
You now know most of what you need to know to understand how Macedon and the whole Fediverse
operate and how all the servers connect to each other.
If you're interested in learning more, definitely check out the Activity Pub Rock site and read
the W3C spec.
It's pretty straightforward.
It's deliberately a simple protocol with a lot of power, and beyond powering Twitter-like
sites like Macedon, the open source community is building alternatives to YouTube, Instagram,
Facebook, and many more off the Activity Pub protocol.
And the cool thing is, because they all speak that protocol, it's like you can follow someone
on YouTube from your Twitter account, or follow someone on Instagram from your YouTube
account because they all speak the same protocol.
Because there is no central server, every Macedon server has a complete set of Macedon
API endpoints.
The Macedon API lets you basically do everything the Macedon web interface lets you do via
the API.
These two bots here use the Macedon API and special characters in the Unicode set to make
aquariums and space scenes.
Bot accounts aren't frowned upon in the network, and there are options in the account settings
on Macedon to mark an account as a bot account.
There are even some servers that are specifically bot-friendly.
Botsin.space hosts some pretty neat art bots that are using the Macedon API on that server
to make the whole Fediverse more interesting.
So let's prove this by building a bot.
What's our bot going to do?
It's going to toot random lines from the Zen of Python.
It's going to live on that botsin.space server since that server is so friendly to bots.
The first thing we're going to need is an OAuth access token for an account on botsin.space.
The Macedon API uses OAuth authorization to make API requests against protected endpoints
like making status updates.
And as a developer, you can choose the right scopes you need for the applications or bots
you're developing.
Fully explaining OAuth is sadly outside the scope of this talk, but I'm happy to chat
about how OAuth works if you come find me afterwards.
The Patreon API which I work on is also protected by OAuth and I help maintain our OAuth integration,
so I'd love to chat with people about how that works.
But we still need an access token, so let's get one from botsin.space.
Let's make sure the video is working.
Yeah.
We're going to start by going into our settings for our botsin.space account, clicking development,
and clicking new application.
Our application needs a name and a website and some scopes to give us the right access.
Since we're going to be the only ones using this app, the default scopes are fine.
Once the app is created, we need the access token that's auto-generated for us.
It's that long hex string that we're copying here.
Note that there isn't really an approval process.
Because every server hosts its own copy of the APIs, anyone can interact with the network
and get kind of full access to the API.
You just make apps on servers and start using them.
With our access token, we can now make requests against the API at botsin.space.
Whenever I'm building a bot, I like to test things in the Python shell first so I can
play around and get a feel for what I'm doing.
As we build our bot, we're going to do the same thing using the Python request library.
Let me fire up a Python 3 shell real quick.
I'm going to import requests in the Python shell.
And then I'm going to make a post request against the botsin.space API with my oauth
access token and a data blob saying what I want the status text to be.
The response came back okay, so I should have successfully posted to botsin.space.
And it turns out I did.
I love using the request library when I'm playing with APIs because I get a feel for
what goes into an API and what kind of responses come out.
But when I'm ready to start building an app, I normally look for a client library for
the API I want to use.
It turns out there is a Python client library for Macedon called Macedon.py.
Macedon.py is a community maintained Python library for Macedon that supports a large
set of features in the Macedon API.
Let's do what we just did in requests in Macedon.py.
So the first thing I'm going to do is pip install Macedon.py, open a Python 3 shell,
the correct class from Macedon.py, and then create an instance that I can use to interact
with the API.
Once I have my instance created, I should be able to use this to toot to botsin.space
using the Zenbot account.
Cool.
In what I get back, I get a URL that should be the toot I just created.
I'm going to use the Python web browser module in the standard library to open the URL directly
that I just basically created by tooting at botsin.space.
Cool.
And there's the toot.
So after that, we have a toot posted to botsin.space.
Hooray!
But you might be wondering why we would use a client library when requests work just as
well.
There's a few great reasons to use a client library that I can think of.
You should use Macedon.py or any good client library because that library will almost certainly
have tests for the functionality it provides.
Tests that you don't have to write for your requests-based code.
Libraries like Macedon.py even provide coverage metrics for their tests so you can make better
choices about how much you trust the library.
The second reason to use a client library is it provides abstractions.
A good client library will translate the response from the API into Python objects that are
easier to use in the rest of your Python code, i.e. translating a JSON response into a Python
object.
As a result of those abstractions, when the API changes and the library updates with the
changes, often you as the developer don't need to worry about it because the abstraction
the library provides hasn't changed.
So why shouldn't we use a client library?
Either because we have special functionality that isn't provided by the library that we
want in our app, or we're really worried about lag between the API updating and the library
updating.
I would say in both those cases, consider committing a patch or diff to the library
before rolling your own.
If the patch is accepted, you get all the benefits of using a library in your special
cases covered.
Okay, we have an access token.
We know how to post toots.
Now we need to wire the Xen of Python into our bot.
We need to get the Xen of Python as strings, randomly choose one of those strings, and
put that string into a toot for our bot.
So again, we're going to start a Python shell, import the Xen of Python by doing import this,
a variable called Xen to the split string of the printed out Xen of Python.
It prints with a bunch of new line characters that we want to split on so that we get the
right strings.
It looks like we've got some decent strings.
We're going to import the random library after importing Macedon in web browser and try to
choose some of those strings at random to make sure that we're actually getting what
we want out of the output.
Okay, that looks pretty good.
Okay.
So it looks like we're correctly choosing strings that can go into our Xen of Python
bot.
We're going to create an instance of the Macedon API like we did previously to post the toot
and then compose a toot using one of the random strings that we chose.
One of the nice things about the Macedon client library is that you can specify an
API base URL and potentially use multiple base URLs if you are maintaining multiple
clients for like a larger scale application instead of having to hard code that every
time you want to use it with requests.
So our toot is going to say the Xen of Python says and then some new lines and then use
the magic of F strings to do random.choice on the Xen string.
We'll toot that and then open the result in the web browser so that we can see it again.
Cool.
It got a little cut off, but there we go.
We have created a little Xen bot that's tooting strings from the Xen of Python.
This is the full script that I would be running if I wanted to have this running in the background.
We don't the import random got cut off at the top and I'm using OS.getend because I
want the access token not necessarily live in the script in case I check it into GitHub.
I want it to be an environment variable that I can set somewhere else.
But it's deliberately a pretty simple script because writing bots should be kind of a fun
and simple activity.
Another thing that I could do with the Macedon API through Macedon.py is look for replies
to my bot and then respond to those replies or modulate my responses based on the replies.
Okay.
So now that we have our bot, where do we host it?
Lots of places are options.
If you only want it to run when your laptop is open, you can have it running in the background
of your laptop with cron.
That works for Mac and Linux.
For Windows, you can use some Windows scheduling daemon things, but that's a little bit more
complicated.
If you have a server just laying around that you own, again, you can use that server in
cron.
My actual favorite way to host bots is to use Heroku plus the Heroku scheduler to run
just a worker dino with the bot script on some sort of regular interval.
With Heroku, you don't need to be running a web application.
It can run background tasks just fine.
Okay.
All of that covered, how do you choose a server to be on?
Hopefully by this point, I've convinced you to at least give Macedon a try.
How do you know where you should be?
The first thing you should do is go to join Macedon.org.
There's some considerations.
Because you can follow more or less anyone on more or less any server, the choice of
which server to set up your account on becomes one of which community you want to most closely
associate with.
Generally speaking, you should find servers where you feel like you could find a home
that have a good code of conduct and where the admins feel like they're on top of things.
For example, I run a server called the wandering shop that accepts all kinds of people but
is focused on people who enjoy or create science fiction and fantasy.
If you want to learn more about that server, find me afterwards.
Also, you can always try different servers out, have multiple identities, and ask your
followers to follow you at a different server.
Macedon even provides some tools for making this easier.
Okay.
That's basically it.
So after this talk, what I want you to do is find a server, join the community, build
a bot, and help make some magic.
That top line there is my email address, phildini.net.
I'm also at phildini at wandering.shop.
And if you want to find me on Twitter, I'm at phildini.
In this room tomorrow at 1 10, I'm going to be doing a talk with my co-presenter on account
security best practices for Python web applications.
And I think we do have a little bit of time for questions.
Thanks.
Do I see someone with a question?
Yeah, great.
Step up to the mic.
I will say your question needs to be in the form of a question.
If you have something that's not a question, come find me afterwards.
Okay.
So there are a lot of social media networks.
How do you recommend that we get people involved necessarily in Mastodon, prying their Twitter
out of their cold, dead hands?
So Mastodon has some tools for helping with this, including a Twitter user follower where
you can log in with your Twitter account and see which of your friends already have Mastodon
accounts.
That's one way to encourage people to start porting things over.
There also are Twitter cross posters going in both directions, so you can still maintain
a presence on both sides.
In terms of how do we start moving people over, I'll be honest.
One of the reasons I gave this talk is to show off Mastodon, to show how interesting
and easy it is to make bots and interact with it as programmers, but also to encourage people
to start using it.
There was a time when no one in this room used Twitter because either Twitter didn't
exist or Twitter was still so new that it didn't feel like something that people wanted
to use.
So I think it's one of those things where the more we build the network there, the easier
it's going to be to convince people to move to that network.
For me, it has the best combination of old school IRC chat rooms and forums where it
felt like a very tight community that people had control over, but you still have access
to the whole universe if you want that.
We'll switch, so we'll go to you.
In the Mastodon server that you helped moderate, have you encountered some of the darker people
who are doing some not so nice things on the internet and how have you managed that and
what kind of overhead is associated with that?
That's a great question.
I admin a server called the Wandering Shop that has about 1,500 users.
By the way, the Mastodon community as a whole, I think, is getting close to 2 million total
users, so it's not Twitter scale, but it's also not tiny.
A lot of those servers are English speaking, but also there's a huge chunk that's French
speaking.
There's a massive chunk that speaks Japanese.
I think we have users in most countries at this point.
In terms of my admin overhead, it's less than an hour a week, realistically speaking.
Have I seen those dark corners of the internet?
Yes, 100%.
There is a community of administrators that shares tips on, hey, this server seems bad.
One of the nice things is because everyone on the server that I run has opted into the
code of conduct, as an admin, I feel pretty okay just like whole on blocking or banning
servers that are deliberately not following our code of conduct.
There are some that are deliberately, we are a server that is full of free speech for Nazis,
and I'm like, well, that's an easy instant block.
We never want to see any of you have a great life.
That's the kind of cool that you can do that.
The Wandering Shop has blocked probably a dozen servers, like hard block.
Nope, sorry, you're not going to be good members of the community.
You can still be part of the rest of the Fetaverse, but you're not welcome here.
It's cool that you can do that.
You can also do that as a per user basis where you can, like, as a user say, I, as the user
account, don't want to see anything from this server.
Go away.
Additionally, when you make a report on a Toot, it goes both to your server admin and
the admin of whatever server the account that made the Toot is hosted on.
There's a community of moderation as well, which is pretty cool to see.
In fact, recently, we just blocked, the admin community just blocked a server that was refusing
to accept reports on their users.
And we're like, if you're not going to follow safe reporting practices, you don't get to play in our sandbox.
Hi.
Hello.
My this kind of compound question.
First is, what is the kind of the age demographic for Macedon user?
Is that something that you're aware of?
And the second is, do you remember FidoNet?
Do I remember FidoNet?
Vaguely not very well.
Age demographics.
One thing I forgot to mention, especially since people are starting to filter out, which
is totally okay.
I'm still impressed you all chose this talk.
There is going to be a Macedon open space at 3 p.m. in room.
Check the board.
In room, check the board.
If you're interested in learning more about Macedon, a couple of people who are using
the software are going to be there.
So definitely go check that out.
Average age demographics.
It runs the gamut.
I would say that the average age of a Macedon user is probably, let's just call it millennial.
But I've seen literally the gamut.
There is, yeah.
Yeah.
Hi.
I remember FidoNet.
But my question is, would you speak a half a second or so about standing up a Macedon
server?
Yeah, absolutely.
So there's three main ways to do it right now.
One is there are a lot of hosting providers that are providing Macedon packages.
I think DigitalOcean now has a built-in droplet for it, which is click button, receive Macedon.
There's also a site called Masto.host, which is like this is what we do as Macedon as a
service almost.
You can stand up your own Macedon server and pay them 20 bucks a month.
It's like, here you go.
I have a Macedon server.
There's two if you really want to get into it.
And actually, those services didn't exist when I was spinning up the wandering shop.
So the way that I do it is I have a DigitalOcean server that's running the Macedon Docker compose
configuration because there is a Docker compose configuration and Docker images that are maintained
by the project.
And then there's a I am committed to systems administration way to run the application
with the full NGINX config and maintaining your own Postgres and that kind of thing.
So I am a very lazy systems administrator.
And so Docker compose.
Thanks.
Yep.
Hi.
Thank you for the talk.
And I think everybody's a lazy system admin.
It's part of the job.
My question was you talked about this being sort of similar to IRC where you can get to
everything.
Do you see it as a replacement for IRC, especially given that Mozilla is saying, OK, we can't
support this anymore.
I think we can't use it as our internal communications.
Do you see this as being a real time communication platform?
Do you see this being a sort of offline social network?
How do you see this filling that space?
That's a great question.
I would call it closer to a social network but not a real time communication platform.
And Activity Pub, if you're willing to poll a whole bunch, it can work in real time.
But Activity Pub isn't necessarily designed for real time communication.
It's designed for status updates and all of the possible things you can fit in a status
update, like a follow request or a media request or posting a video.
The thing that I haven't seen anybody build yet that I'm really looking forward to is
some sort of event solution off of Activity Pub.
What?
So I don't think it's designed for real time.
In terms of what's out there for real time in the open source space right now, there's
going to be a ton of competing solutions.
Probably the closest that we have to a real true end to end open source, viable alternative
to modern proprietary chat systems is Matrix, quite honestly.
They've been in the news a lot recently for some unfortunate reasons, but I still think
that they probably are the best shot at a full end to end open source chat solution
that can speak to all the protocols and still has a nice user interface and all that kind
of stuff.
Thank you very much.
Thank you for the talk.
Also Zulip.
Yeah, thank you.
Last question.
Hi, thanks again for the talk.
Kind of a quick question for you.
Why do you still use Twitter while continuing to use Mastodon?
For exactly related to the first question that was asked, I still use Twitter because
most of my friends, especially my friends in tech, are still primarily posting to Twitter.
As soon as I can get a critical mass of my friends to use Mastodon, and trust me, I encourage
them on a regular basis to do so, I will happily turn off my Twitter account.
The thing that I have done, which makes Twitter amazingly better, and there's even a little
glitch app that you can Google for that will kind of auto do this for all your followers,
turn off retweets.
It turns out that the content that the people you follow are posting directly is often incredible
content and all of the stuff that gets retweeted is like rage bait.
So honestly, turning off Twitter has made Twitter a much better user experience in terms
of like my happiness with the platform.
But it still has some of the like dark magic that I talked about at the beginning in terms
of being ads funded and what it allows and doesn't allow on the platform.
But the reality is like here, if I were to search for the PyCon 2019 hashtag on Mastodon,
it wouldn't be anywhere near the volume of searching for the PyCon 2019 hashtag on Twitter,
right?
And so while I would love for everybody to move, I also don't think it's reasonable to
ask people to cut themselves off from the conversation.
We should still have the conversation in the place where the conversation is, but we should
be encouraging people to kind of like evaluate their social media choices and maybe move
to a platform that has better community ideals.
All right.
Thanks, everybody.
I think I'm going to call it there.
Have a great rest of your PyCon and maybe see you tomorrow.