Thank you all for coming this morning. This is to introduce the first speaker, Eddie Schuman,
who will be speaking about thinking inside the box. Please welcome him.
Hello, everyone. So thank you for coming to my talk today about how our team used Python
to adapt to an existing data ingestion pipeline. I've been a software developer with Pacific
Northwest National Laboratory in southeastern Washington for about four years now. I've
used Python for the majority of that time and I've really fallen in love with the language.
So first an introduction to the talk. So the talk today is going to be about how we used
Python to ingest, that is process and standardize the raw radar data that we dealt with. It's not
going to be about the data itself, rather our particular use case and how we leveraged Python
to adapt to existing systems and constraints. So the project that I spend the majority of my
time on is for the atmospheric radiation measurement user facility, or ARM for short. So ARM is a key
contributor to national and international research efforts related to earth system changes. ARM was
started by the United States Department of Energy in 1989 and has grown to be managed by nine
national laboratories. So ARM has some extensive data collection efforts. It has six atmospheric
observatories collecting data from around the world and has had more than 30 past research
campaigns. The data is standardized and made available to researchers at no cost and ARM currently
has radar sites in Alaska, Oklahoma, the Azores in the Atlantic Ocean and Cordoba, Argentina.
So as for the radar instruments themselves, there are multiple radar types, multiple versions,
different frequency bands and they're provided by different vendors, which taken altogether means
that there's a wide variety of different data formats that we need to accommodate. So our job
for the radar industry is to process this data, standardize it and classify it by frequency band,
instrument type and scan strategy. So with a long-running data program means that we need
to adapt to some existing ARM systems and constraints. So the first system we need to work with is ADI,
the ARM data integrator, which processes most of ARM's data products. We need to set up process
definitions which define which ARM sites actually have radar data that we need to ingest. And we
need to create data object designs or DODs to define specifications for the output data,
such as the dimensions, variable names, variable metadata or product level metadata. And these data
object designs require review and approval by ARM's metadata group in order to make sure that they
meet ARM's standards and are actually useful for users. So the ADI system's functionality,
it features automatic data averaging or interpolation, enforces data standards and the
DOD specifications. It provides error checking and enforcement of variable dimensionality and
operationally the data integrator tracks which instrument data time intervals have already been
processed, preventing the operations team from accidentally re-ingesting the same data or ingesting
really old data. So some of the difficulties we faced while creating the radar ingest was that
we need unique readers for each of the instruments. We need to properly integrate the data integrator
into our workflow. We need to set up data design specifications and process definitions. We need
to consistently meet ARM's standards. And through it all, we wanted an understandable workflow and
code structure for future maintenance and development efforts. So with the setup of the
data design specifications, normally for our processes, we would set them up through a GUI
web application, which is fine for other data products, which may only have a couple of data
designed specifications. But the radar ingest would need more than 800 DODs. And a small change in
one of the ingests, such as changing a variable name or the units for a variable, would result in
needing to change over 180 of these in the worst case. So this is a quick snapshot of the radar
ingest workflow. So we start with the raw radar data on the left and work through the different
ingest components until it's ready to archive. We also include utilities and data definitions
that are referenced throughout the ingesting process. So first, I'm going to talk about how
we handled the data definitions and setting them up. So our solution for creating the data object
designs was what we call the Python radar toolbox. This toolbox is utilized across all the different
radar ingests. It contains scripts, helper functions and configuration files. But mainly,
it contains multiple JSON definition files in five main categories. Moments, variables, auxiliary
variables, global attributes, and auxiliary attributes. The moments we define as the most
data-intensive variables and are usually the most interesting to users. The auxiliary variables and
attributes are used by the radar technicians and engineers to diagnose issues with the radars or
the radar data. So a quick side note. So for each stage of talking about the implementation,
I'll reference some specific modules that were helpful for that stage in the process.
And they'll be covered in the top right banner. So first, we created a JSON definition file for
each one of those main categories that I mentioned before. So inside these are all the different
variables and attributes of that category that any of the radar ingests might possibly use.
And they create the DOD-required metadata, sorry, they define the DOD-required metadata
for that particular variable or attribute, such as the descriptive names, the data types,
the associated dimensions, or the units. We also have JSON definition files for each frequency
instrument combination. So these define the product-level metadata, such as the instrument
name, the valid scan strategies for that instrument, ADI process name, but they also contain a
categorized list of all the different variables and attributes from these previously mentioned
categories that are utilized by that particular data product, which helps us generating the DODs
later. So for the actual generating of the DODs, the ARM development system has a utility script
which is able to load Perl hash representations of the DOD definitions into the database.
So we can generate these data design files from these JSON definitions. Taken together,
we can take all the variables that were in the categories at the product-level definition
and then check their entries in the category-level definitions to fully flush out the data
specification. We then load them into the database one at a time. So for small updates,
like the variable name changing or update to data types, as I mentioned before, we can generate
hundreds of these DODs and load them into the database in less than a minute. This circumvents
navigating through hundreds of DODs through the web application and saving them one at a time,
which we found to be untenable. And then finally, we can go back to the web application to review
the DODs we generated to see if it triggered any of the web applications inbuilt checks before we
send it off for review. So throughout the generating process, we naturally use the JSON library
because it makes it effortless to read from the JSON files and load them into Python native dictionaries.
So we tried to design the toolbox with iterative growth in mind. So the Python Rader toolbox
also collects a variety of utilities shared across the ingest. As we noticed common functionality
between the different ingests, we tried to generalize it as much as possible to stick it
into the utility functions in Python Rader toolbox. So the toolbox grows more refined
and useful over time. As the JSON definitions are updated, fixes propagate across all future
ingest development and future releases. A couple of the helper scripts we created,
which updates instrument definition files according to the past metadata review feedback.
So new feedback from reviewers is applied into the script and then the script is run on all future
and updated ingest. The review process becomes streamlined over time as all the past feedback
has already been applied to the future ingest. So another script we created was set primary.py,
which interfaces with a database API to classify certain variables as primary measurements.
Arm data discovery and archival tools can direct users based off the most important measurements
to help them find the data they're most interested in. So for this stage in the toolbox,
once again, we used JSON to read in the definition files. We used arg parse for handling all of our
scripts command line arguments. We used request library to make calls to the APIs and we used
get pass for handling user credentials. So now I'm going to talk about the actual
ingest components themselves. So the first lowest level component is the reader component.
As I mentioned before, across the radars, there are different radars, vendors and software versions.
And even radars from the same vendor can have significantly varying data formats.
So the reader structure is designed to match the input data as much as possible using vendor data
structure and variable names. It effectively acts as a sort of documentation for the input data.
A developer should be able to look at the structures in the reader component and quickly
understand the structure of the underlying input data. So for the reader component,
one of our vendors outputs HDF5 raw files, so we read that in with H5Pi. But we mostly
use NumPy's from file function to read custom binary formats as most of the vendors prefer to
provide their own binary format. So the second middle component in the workflow is called the
standardizer. So for the standardizer, the over all structure matches between the different ingests.
It has the same functions and attributes available, especially the moments, variables,
auxiliary variables, global attributes and auxiliary attributes. The same five categories
that kept showing up in the definitions earlier. The inner workings of each function or attribute
can vary significantly. So the standardizer is designed to serve as a translation layer
between vendor structure to ARM standards on things such as names, units or other various metadata.
Sometimes it's as simple as categorizing and renaming a variable. Other times it might just
be unit conversion. The vendor might supply nanoseconds and we might want seconds. And
sometimes it says involved as calculating a new derived variable from multiple vendor supplied
variables and attributes. So for the standardizer, the end result should be that all variables and
attributes are categorized the same across all the ingests. The data is accessed nearly
identically for each ingest writer and all the variables and attributes from the instrument
definition JSON should be saved and matched the definition names in the standardizer.
So throughout the standardizer, we used NumPy for easy array handling and array based calculations.
And as ARM's data is usually in net CDF format, we used net CDF for type converters to prepare
the variables for writing. So the final highest level component in the radar ingest themselves
is the writer layer. So each writer for each of the ingests is nearly a clone of the others.
So we eventually want to create a generic writer that we can stick in the radar toolbox and use
across all the different ingests. So the writer sets up the data integrators input and output
interfaces. It runs the reader and standardizer components to read in and translate the raw data.
It uses the instrument's JSON definition files to verify that the expected entries do in fact exist.
It calls the ADI Python bindings to transfer the data into the ADI system. And then it tells the
data integrator to store the data set, at which point the data integration system performs ARM's
standard compliance checks, data quality checks. It verifies that the given data interval has not
been processed before. It saves the file into the ARM's file system and readies the files for
archival. And it logs any events that may have happened during ingest processing and sets the
operational status of the ingest. So for the writer component, we used custom ADI bindings
to interface with the data integrator. And once again, we used NumPy and NetCDF4
to prepare some of the product level variables and attributes for writing out.
So after we were done ingesting the data, we would inspect the data to make sure that everything was
processed and handled as we expected. So we would use NetCDF4, X-ray and NumPy to read in and
manipulate the data from the files. And we would use Matplotlib for easy and pretty visualizations.
And the whole thing was a bit easier to do consistently inside of a few Jupyter notebooks.
So a couple of reasons why we specifically chose Python. One of the things we wanted to do is be
consistent. The old set of radar ingest were written in a mixture of C, IDL and Python by a
variety of different developers with different coding styles and wildly varying structures.
So we wanted to consolidate it into one language to encourage code reuse and utility functionality.
The biggest draw for us for Python was the incredible flexibility that Python offers.
So it allowed us to use Python at all the stages in our development workflow. It allowed us to do
quick and dirty data inspection, one-off scripts, helper functions, configuration libraries, the bulk
of our data processing with NumPy, and Python continues to have emerging technologies and
libraries and a large pool of developers to help. Another draw of Python was readability.
You know Python was designed with readability in mind and described as almost pseudocode.
This means we can share code snippets with researchers and developers who may not have
even touched Python and still get constructive feedback on algorithms, workflow, or calculations
without them knowing the language. We can also share it with those familiar with Python
and the readability facilitates a quick understanding and a short onboarding for new
developers. And finally, familiarity. Our team members already had moderate to extensive Python
experience and many of our colleagues at the lab have been picking up Python because it's such an
incredibly popular language finally. It felt like a natural choice. So in conclusion, Python is
incredibly flexible. It has an immense utility for a wide variety of developers. It can be a
small part or the heavy workhorse for a large project. Our team found that its flexibility
helped us to adapt to a wide variety of required systems and constraints.
So we do want to eventually make the toolbox publicly available and we're working on it.
If you want to talk about the arm data pipeline or lessons learned, the radar ingest data,
share your experience or if you've got some cool library suggestions,
feel free to contact me at any time. So thank you for coming today.