Welcome for the second talk in this session.
Our speaker is Fridolin Procorny,
and he's going to talk about, thus,
how to recommend the best possible libraries
for your application.
Please give him a hand of applause.
Thank you.
So thank you very much.
Welcome to this presentation about TOD,
and we will talk about how to recommend
the best possible packages for your applications.
Before we start, let me introduce myself.
My name is Fridolin.
I'm a software engineer at Red Hat.
My focus is mostly on disability systems, machine learning,
and of course, I love Python.
I find Python like programming language that is a pseudocode,
and you write it, and it just runs.
It's awesome.
I started my career as a reverse engineer in a research group.
Then I slightly shifted.
I did some kernel development.
Then I did distributed systems.
I developed Selenon.
That is some kind of enhancement for Celery.
And right now, I work on a project that is called TOD,
and that's the project I would like to introduce to you.
So project TOD is, as of now, developed
by six engineers in total.
But initially, we started two engineers,
and the project is inside a bigger team that
is called AICOE, which stands for Artificial Intelligence
Center of Excellence.
This team is part of office of the CTO, so the Red Hat CTO,
and our focus is on emerging technologies
and coming up with solutions for these emerging technologies.
You can find project TOD on the GitHub
under TODstation organization, and we have also a website.
It is todstation.ninja.
So that would be something about the project.
And now, let's talk about what actually TOD is
and why we developed TOD.
If you take a look at PyPI, the Python Package Index,
you can find something like 170,000 projects.
Each of these projects have releases,
and last time I checked, it was 1.3 million releases.
You can say it's quite a huge code base.
So let's use some libraries that are available out there,
and let's develop an application.
What we will do, we will develop an application
using TensorFlow, so a machine learning library that
is quite popular, especially given the number of stars
that it has on the GitHub.
And we will use Flask for serving our machine learning
model.
If you take a look, what we do, we basically
pick TensorFlow and Flask.
We glue them together.
We write our own code to provide our desired functionality.
How do we do that?
We simply issue pip install tensorflow,
then pip install flask, and we run our application.
Unfortunately, there is some error,
like tensorflow requires some other version of NumPy.
I found this error on GitHub, but in project TOD,
we found very similar issues when running tensorflow,
especially with NumPy.
There were issues with API incompatibilities.
So you see the point.
You install some library, and it does not work as expected.
If we take a look what pip did on the background,
we issued pip install tensorflow.
Pip searched by API and found out
there are 59 releases of tensorflow.
And as we did not provide any version range specification,
it automatically picked the latest one.
The same was for Flask.
It searched by API, and it found 28 releases,
and it picked the latest one based on the current status.
If we give some math to it, we see
that there are at least 1,600 combinations
how you can install different version of tensorflow
with different version of Flask.
Unfortunately, when you do pip install Flask,
it's not just Flask that it's being installed.
There are dependencies of Flask.
These dependencies are air direct or indirect,
so dependencies of dependencies of Flask.
I will refer to them as transitive dependencies.
So Flask depends on click.
It's dangerous.
Jinja to markup-safe, very quick.
Air directly or indirectly.
So when you install Flask, it's also these libraries
that are installed.
I did rough estimate, and there are at least 54 million
combinations how you can install Flask with dependencies,
meaning any Flask version with any dependency given
the version range specification for these libraries.
This number is estimation, and the actual number
varies based on dependency graph traversal.
If you take a look at tensorflow,
then things might get even worse.
TensorFlow is a bigger project.
It depends on much more libraries,
and these libraries have more versions.
So when I did estimation, how many combinations
are there for different tensorflow releases
with different versions of its dependencies,
I found that there is approximately 1.3
multiplied by 10 to the power of 20 combinations
how you can install a tensorflow release with its dependencies.
I will refer to this as a tensorflow stack,
and for Flask case, I will refer to it as for Flask stack.
Now, if you take a look at how many combinations are there
to install tensorflow and Flask, then it's quite a huge number.
It's like 7.6 multiplied by 10 to the power of 27.
That's a really huge number, and we haven't finished it.
Our application runs in some operating system.
This operating system provides some kind of environment
for running our applications.
So it provides Python interpreter that can, again,
be in different versions, and there
can be different versions of operating system, meaning,
for example, Fedora 30, Fedora 29, CentOS, and so on.
This operating system provides also native dependencies.
So it provides, for example, glibc.
And if you are familiar with Python wheel package format,
you know that there is many Linux standard that
tries to standardize or try to provide requirements
for operating system in order to run your Python applications.
It, of course, cannot handle all these dependencies.
So if you run tensorflow and you use GPU,
then there is a CUDA library that is not in many Linux
standard, but you still require it.
And these have also different versions.
So there are different versions of CUDA.
Now, the operating system runs on some hardware.
So you have different types of CPU, different types of GPU,
and you remember that huge number.
So we are basically multiplying with more and more combinations.
If you take a look at it in abstract,
what I've just described, we are developing a Python application
that has some direct dependencies.
These direct dependencies have also some dependencies,
meaning transitive dependencies.
This lives in Python ecosystem.
This is then run with Python interpreter
that can be also in different versions.
And these dependencies can use native dependencies
or native packages that are provided by operating system.
Operating system also has some kernel modules.
So if you use CUDA, there needs to be aligned CUDA version.
And this runs on hardware.
So you have a lot of combinations.
And you can imagine that if you make one single mistake
in any item in this stack, your application
will simply not work.
If you make mistake in a Python application,
you simply fix it.
You wrote, you own the code, you have the knowledge,
you fix it.
But if there is an issue with direct dependencies,
transitive dependencies, Python interpreter,
native dependencies, or kernel modules,
it's much harder to fix it.
And that's basically the main idea behind ToT.
In ToT, we are creating a knowledge base,
how applications run, if they run correctly,
and what is their overall performance.
So we are interested in building applications,
meaning if the given Python package installs correctly
into your runtime environment, if it runs correctly,
so you don't see issues that can be seen in the previous slide
with TensorFlow and NumPy.
And we also are interested in whether applications
behave correctly and if they give reasonable results,
so they perform well.
So the idea is to create advanced Python resolver that
uses knowledge base to resolve software stack not
to latest versions, but to the best possible versions
of libraries that you use.
OK, so now let's take a look at how we are building
ToT's knowledge base.
We have right now at Red Hat two instances of ToT.
One is test, one is stage environment,
and we are provisioning also production environment.
And in these environments, we are aggregating knowledge,
like if the given package or if given software stack runs.
If there are some build failures,
we aggregate this knowledge.
If there are some installation failures,
And we use for this purpose, for example,
Jupyter Hub that is deployed internally at Red Hat,
and data scientists use it.
So we aggregate each time there is a build of container image,
we aggregate information into ToT's knowledge base.
We analyze also ToT's container images.
So ToT is analyzed by itself.
These are, I would say, real world use cases.
We also have other sources of data for our knowledge base.
But we have a service that is called Amoon.
And what this service does, it automatically
verifies that the given software runs correctly,
that it builds and behaves correctly.
There is a tool called Dependence Monkey that
can switch different versions of libraries
and can run specific software on some specific hardware.
And then we aggregate data into our knowledge base.
So we burn some CPU for you in order
to come up with the best possible software stack.
We also do performance-related analysis.
For example, TensorFlow is quite a huge project,
as you saw with the number of dependencies
and number of combinations that can be installed.
And the core part of TensorFlow is built in C, C++.
So what we do, we analyze the performance of TensorFlow
by switching different versions of TensorFlow.
But we also have our own builds of TensorFlow.
And these builds are automatically
verified in our CI system, that is Amoon.
And we gather performance-related characteristics
of these machine learning libraries.
So we have optimized TensorFlow builds.
You can find them on our index.
There are also instructions how you can set up your environment
in order to use that index.
And we simply found out that by recompiling TensorFlow
on some specific CPU architecture,
so enabling CPU-specific compiler options of the core parts
of TensorFlow that are written in C, C++,
you can gain performance.
This work was also in cooperation with Google.
And there is a TensorFlow on-demand project.
So if you are familiar with TensorFlow,
you see our community section of TensorFlow,
you will see what's going on in this area.
OK, so we aggregated knowledge.
We have our knowledge base.
And now let's come up with recommendations.
So how do we do that?
Let's imagine that we have a software.
So we run our application.
And this application has only two dependencies
called simple-lip and another-lip.
These dependencies do not have any other dependencies.
So what we are looking for in recommendations,
we are looking for really good score, whatever that means.
It can be performance.
It can be security vulnerabilities.
So it can be a single score, or it can be also
compound of multiple scores.
And if we dive into mathematics a little,
then we can plot this function.
So we have different versions of simple-lip.
We have different versions of another-lip.
And what we are looking for, we are looking for really high
spike in this case, so very high score.
And we would like to recommend simple-lip and another-lip
in some versions.
So we are looking for combinations
of different versions, which have very good overall score.
Now let's consider that these libraries
have other dependencies.
If we would plot that, we would just
introduce a new dimension that's not that easy to plot.
But now let's consider that simple-lip in version V1
depends on dependency 1 in version V1 or V2.
So dependency 1 is installed in version V1 or V2.
Then let's consider another-lip has dependency 2.
And if we install another-lip in version V2,
we need to install dependency 2 in version V1 or V2.
That's the dependency.
OK, so let's take a look how PIP, PIPenv, Poetry,
or other tools would install your software stack.
They will automatically try to resolve
to the latest possible versions.
So there will be install simple-lip in version V2,
another-lip in version V2, and dependency 2 in version V2.
Now take a look at how TOD approaches this problem.
So we have this dependency graph.
And before the actual resolution,
we take a look into our knowledge base.
And we find out that dependency 2 in version 2
has some issues.
For example, it does not install into your runtime environment
because of different Python version.
So what we do, we simply remove the dependency
from our dependency graph.
Now we take a look into our knowledge base again.
And we see that simple-lip in version V1
performs very well with dependency 1 in version V1.
So what we will do, we shift these versions
to take precedence when there is done actual resolution.
Now let's take a look at how TOD would resolve this example.
So simple-lip is resolved in version V1 with dependency 1
in version V1 because these are well-performing libraries.
And now another-lip is in version V2.
But instead of installing dependency 2 in version V2,
we install V1 because that does not cause any issues.
This is accomplished in TOD using
Stack Generation Pipeline.
That's the term that we use.
The input is runtime environment.
So there is information.
Where do you run it?
On what hardware?
What is CPU?
And stuff like that.
Then there are provided requirements.
So if you're familiar with requirements,
the .txt file, that's basically the requirements
that are provided.
And then there is also input that is, as of now, not used.
But we perform static analysis of your source code,
of your application.
So that's also the input of this Stack Generation Pipeline.
Then this Stack Generation Pipeline
adjusts the dependency graph, adjusts
how the resolution algorithm will produce stacks.
And then there is a stream of stacks
that are subsequently scored and gated based on final score.
The output of the Stack Generation Pipeline
is a log file stating fully pinned down
software stack, so specific versions that
should be installed, together with justification
why you should install these dependencies
instead of using latest ones.
To support this use case, we had to extend information
that is provided by PyPI, the Python Package Index.
If you take a look at setuppy or metadata that
are provided together with Python packages,
you can see that there are, for example, license, information,
classifiers.
And then we had to know some purpose of package.
You can use keywords for stating the purpose.
But a lot of packages do not simply put anything
into keyword section.
Or there are sometimes really weird strings.
So we wanted to build a model that would automatically
create or answer simple questions,
like is the given package affecting performance somehow?
So we can score these packages separately
in different steps of Stack Generation Pipeline.
So what we did, we created a model
that is vector space model.
And we analyzed each and every package
that is available on PyPI.
And we aggregated information such as reading files,
descriptions, so any free text that
is describing the project.
We extracted relevant information,
such as is that project related to Django,
is that machine learning application, and stuff
like that.
So we extracted this information and constructed a vector
that describes this Python package.
This allows to create or form this vector space model.
And what you can do, you can perform feature-based queries.
So for example, you can ask, what
is package that is machine learning and provides some UI?
So this is feature-based query.
You can also browse similar packages.
So what you can do, you can, based on these features
and looking into this vector space,
simply by computing a collidian distance,
you can find similar packages.
There is visualization.
If you go to a .station GitHub organization, you can see,
this is t-SNE, so dimensionality space reduction.
And this is the vector space that I spoke about.
You can see clusters that are formed.
These are typically very similar packages.
So you can see, for example, MicroPython,
MicroPython cluster, and stuff like that.
This vector space model is served by API.
And we would like to provide it for community.
Project.todd can be found on the website, .station.ninja.
You can find us also on Twitter.
You can follow us for updates.
As stated, we have two environments right now.
The third one is provisioned.
And what we plan to do, we plan to offer .todd to community
so anyone can use it and anyone can benefit out of it.
We sit on GitHub.
That's our organization that is called .station.
Everything is open source.
You can even provision your own .instance,
and you can run it locally.
If you're a developer, this is the website.
Right now, we have API that is accessible only
at that internally.
So we did internal release.
We would like to make it more stable
and provide it to community.
If you want to integrate, we have a CLI that is called TAMOS.
It's a simple CLI tool that you install.
You go to your repository directory,
and you issue TAMOS config that performs automatic hardware
discovery that is available on your laptop or on your machine.
And it creates configuration file for .todd.
And then you issue TAMOS config.
And then you issue TAMOS advice, and it will automatically
advise you on what software you should use.
Right now, we follow PIPenv.
So if you use PIPenv, meaning PIP file and PIP file log,
the service will provide you PIP file log
based on your PIP file.
Another point of integration is our bot, the de-skebehat.
And what de-skebehat does, it automatically
manages your GitHub repositories.
So it opens pull requests.
It opens issues if there's anything
wrong with your software in your application.
So you can also use that bot.
There is planned integration with GitHub API,
so it will be a plug-in to GitHub.
But that's like more future.
Now we support, or we first will provide TAMOS CLI client.
This way, I would like to thank you.
Hopefully you liked thought.
If you have any questions, feel free to reach out to me.
I will be in conference.
Everything is open source.
Follow us on Twitter for more updates if you are interested.
And thank you very much.
Thank you.