Happy May the 4th, everyone.
We're going to go ahead and get started.
Just as a reminder, please make sure you turn off all sounds from your electronic devices.
We have Pablo Galindo, who is a CPython core developer and also works at Bloomberg.
He'll be giving time to take out the rubbish garbage collector.
Awesome.
Thank you very much for coming.
In this talk, I'm going to work you through basically the current implementation of the
CPython garbage collector.
At the beginning, we're going to make a gentle introduction of memory management and reference
counting.
The idea is that we are centering our efforts on how the current algorithm for garbage collection
works and why it's needed.
A very brief introduction.
This is my Twitter handle.
I'm a Python core developer.
I work now as a software engineer at Bloomberg.
Before that, I was in academia doing blood hole physics research.
If you're interested in that, please come after the talk and talk with me.
One of the authors of PEP 570, the implementer, we merged this last week.
I spend my free time squashing bags and raising conditions on CPython.
Awesome.
Let's get with the introduction of what garbage collection is and why it's needed.
So in mind that you have a variable, right?
For example, here is this list.
Then you delete the variable.
As you know, this is basically removing the name.
But we're interested in what happened at that point.
So this scenario also presents itself when you have a function, for example, in this
case, this factorized function.
And then you have an internal variable local to the function.
In this case, it's this list of primes.
And when the function finishes, the list of primes is not needed anymore.
So we say that the variable goes out of scope.
And we're interested to know what happens or how CPython behaves to clean up that list
that is not needed anymore.
So what happens to it, right?
So some definitions.
So first, we are going to define garbage as the memory that is occupied by objects that
are no longer needed in the program.
And therefore garbage collection is just a form of automatic memory management.
We can go to the actual Python repository and we see how it defines the process of free
memory when it's not used anymore.
So why do we need this thing?
Because otherwise, we will run out of memory, right?
If we don't clean the memory that we are using, we will soon run out of memory.
And the idea is that it has to be automatic.
And this is very important because first, we don't need to do it ourselves.
So we have to do it manually.
And that's the problem.
And we have to do it manually.
So we have to do it manually.
And that's the problem.
And the problem is that it involves less thinking and therefore fewer bugs because all of you
that have compiled languages, especially low level ones like C, you will know that memory
management is one of the most challenging parts of the language and the source of many
of the bugs and memory leaks.
There is a problem though because having it automatic can be a bit slower if it's not
done properly.
So for example, Rust.
Rust is a good example.
Rust doesn't have garbage collector.
It has a very clever new approach, which is the borough checker.
So this is a way, apart from giving other nice features, it's a way of avoiding sort
of manual memory management or even garbage collector.
So C and C++ usually were designed for having manual memory management.
But there is some implementation of garbage collected version of the language available.
OK.
So let's walk also through some pieces that we're going to need to understand the algorithm
and the different phases that it went through.
So the first thing that we need to talk is finalizers.
So basically, imagine that we have a class, in this case this class dog, right?
And then we create one of these dogs and then we delete the dog.
And then we assume that this frees up memory, right?
So it's actually a bit more complicated because if we go to the Python docs, we will see that
It's actually not guaranteed that the Dell method is called, especially when the interpreter
exits.
Usually it's actually called, but we cannot rely on that method to be called.
Why not?
Well, because the first thing is that the purpose of the Dell method, which is called
the finalizer, is only to free up memory when it's no longer necessary.
So we should not rely on this method to do some kind of cleanup of resources.
We have other approaches in Python, particularly with the statement and context managers, that
will help us with these things.
So for example, if you are going to close a file or finish a database connection, you
should use a context manager and not Dell.
Then we are going to introduce reference counting.
So reference counting is one of the, basically the major way that CPython manages memory
and lifetime.
So reference counting is a strategy.
So the idea is that every object has internally has a number, which basically refers to all
the other objects that are referring to it.
For example, you have a list and an object is inside a list.
And the number will be one because the list owns the object.
For example, in this case here, we have x, which is a list of three elements.
And then we create a second variable.
So we know, we say that x has two references.
One is the name x and the other is the name y.
You can actually try it for live objects.
So for example, in the sys module, we have this function called getRefCount.
And you can call it to any object and it will return the number of references that are pointing
to the object.
So basically internal integer that lives inside the object.
There is a catch though, because the function will always return one more.
And this is because the function needs to see the object to return the reference count.
So you need to be aware that you always need to think one less.
So for example, let's make an example.
So we import the module sys.
We have this list that we talked before.
And then we check how many references it has.
It says two.
We know that actually it's only one.
Then we create another name for the list, which is y.
And then we check again and we see that actually it increased one.
We know that actually it's two.
And then when we delete the name, we say that we're back to two again.
So that's OK.
You have to be aware as well that a container also claims ownership of this.
So it's not only names to the variables.
If the variable is inside a container, the reference count will also be increased once.
For example, in this case, we have two variables.
So if we check the reference count of x, we know it's one.
But when we put this variable in a set, we see that actually, because the variable is
in a set, the reference count increases by one.
And the idea is that when the reference count goes to zero, we know that no other object
is actually using the one that we are talking about.
So we can actually destroy the object.
So now we're going to be deploying, which is cycles.
So let's imagine this situation.
I'm only using two nodes because three is like a tree and people just sat down attention
when there is a tree in the slides.
So in this case, we have A and B and these objects point to each other.
And then there is this arrow on the left, which is basically a reference from the outside.
So some other object outside is referring to A. So A has two references, one from B and
one from the outside, and B has one from A. So there is a problem, right?
Because if we delete the reference from the outside, then A points to B, but B points
to A. So even if these two objects are not reachable anymore, the reference count will
never fall to zero.
And therefore, we cannot clean them up.
So we need something else.
And this something else is the garbage collector.
So the situation, to give a little more clarity, will be something like this, right?
We have a lot of objects in our program, which are here, the blue cycles, and the blue circles.
And then we have these two, A and B, sitting around, and they are not reachable.
This means that there is not an arrow from these other objects pointing to them.
So we need something else, a mechanism to identify these cycles and delete them.
So this is a garbage collector.
So to walk through the algorithm, we are going to imagine basically a situation in which
have several cycles.
So first, we need to know how these cycles are created.
So for example, this is a simple example.
You can create a class node.
You can create three of them.
And then setting attributes, you can basically make every node point to the other two.
The situation is actually more complex.
This is an actual diagram of the relationship between all these classes.
You don't need to actually understand this thing, but bear in mind that there is actually
much more hidden objects that have reference inside.
In particular, you can look how there is a lot of things that point to the node type
in there.
And that is actually one of the major sources of cycles that you can form.
So the situation, even if you think that cycles are a bit weird, it's actually very, very
common that happens.
So it's important to have it handled in the runtime.
So OK, so let's go through the algorithm.
So bear in mind, the idea is to identify cycles and remove them.
So first thing, how are we going to identify the cycles?
So OK, as an example, let's consider the following situation, which is this one.
So let's consider these three cycles, which are separated.
We have x, y, and z, which is like a triangle of cycles.
Then we have a and b and l.
The form is not important.
And it's just to have three of them that will yield different behavior along the algorithm.
So basically, the triangle is created as we saw before with our class node and internal
reference.
And notice that we have an extra cycle that will help us see some behavior later, which
is set that points to itself.
Then we have a and b, again, with our class node.
And both a and b points to itself.
And an interesting one, which is a list that contains itself.
This is a cycle of only one element, which is cute.
Cool.
So bear in mind also that the situation is a bit more complex, because every object has
a dictionary inside.
And is the dictionary the one that actually points to other things?
So we have to consider not only the ones that we saw before, but every dictionary associated
with the class.
So this is the situation, right?
We have all these arrows pointing to each other.
So in the first row, we have the objects.
In the second row, we have the dictionaries and the list that has no dictionary inside.
And then the algorithm uses two linked lists.
The first one is the linked list of all the objects that are being considered.
And the second one is a list of all the objects that are going to maybe be destroyed.
And I say maybe, and you will see why.
So the first step is identifying which are the cycles.
So for that, we basically are going to copy the reference count into a separate field,
because we are going to modify.
And we don't want to mess in case the objects are not going to be destroyed.
So in this case, the algorithm starts basically copying this thing and decrementing the reference
count of all the objects that are pointing for every one of them.
And then when an object has a zero reference count, we mark it as maybe and ritual.
So for example, these are the numbers that are for the reference count.
So we start with the first object.
And we decrease the reference count of the only object that is pointing by x, which is
the dictionary.
So the dictionary becomes maybe and ritual.
That is what is marked in a gray color, because it has reference counts of zero.
So we go with y.
Y points to the dictionary.
We decrease its reference count.
Same thing with set.
The dictionary of x actually points to y and set.
So y and set are decreased by one.
The same thing for y.
And when we read the dictionary of set, then y and set are no longer referenced by anything.
So both become maybe and ritual again.
The same thing happens with a, b, and its dictionary.
And then the list that points to itself only has one reference, we decrease it.
So if you see in this situation, what happens is that after this algorithm, only the objects
that are ritual from the outside, which is that arrow that you see up there, has a reference
count bigger than one.
So basically, these are the objects that are ritual from the outside.
And all of the rest are basically isolated cycles.
OK.
So now we are not finished, because as you may imagine, if x is ritual from the outside,
we cannot delete any of the things that are actually referred by x, right?
Because we will destroy the internal state.
So the next part of the algorithm is trying to figure it out which objects are actually
ritual for it.
So the way it works is that we start with the first object.
If the object has a reference count bigger than one, we mark it as certainly ritual,
which is going to be this green color.
Notice that we also mark x, because x is the only object that is ritual, sorry, the
dictionary of x, because the dictionary of x is the only object which is ritual from
x.
OK, so we know that these two are ritual.
Then we go to y, and y has a reference count of zero.
So we don't know if it's going to be ritual or not, so we will move it temporarily to
the second list, which is the object that we maybe are going to destroy.
The same thing happens with set.
Then we visit the x dictionary.
And the x dictionary is very interesting because it's pointing to y and set.
And notice that y and set are already in the second list, which is, oh, maybe I'm going
to destroy them.
But because they are being pointed by an object which is green, we know that those, we cannot
destroy those.
So we need to move them back to the first list.
And we move them green because we know that certainly those are ritual.
Then we go to the dictionary of y, and it has zero reference counts, so we move it to
the second list.
The same thing happens with the dictionary of set.
A as well.
B as well.
So we have the dictionary of A and the dictionary of B. So we are basically moving all of these
objects to the second list because they have zero reference counts.
And notice an interesting thing, which is that every time we have one of these red arrows,
all the objects to the left are green.
This is an invariant of the algorithm.
And it's very important when you're implementing it because if this is not true, you have a
lag.
And then with l has zero reference count, we move it as well to the second list.
And then we need to visit y.
Notice that y is visited twice.
The first time we visited, it has zero reference counts, so we move it to the second list.
But the second time we visited, it was moved to the first list because someone else pointed
to it.
And we need to repeat the algorithm, like which are the objects pointed by y?
So actually, it's the dictionary of y.
So we move it back from the second list to the first.
And then the same thing with set.
The object pointed by set is the dictionary of set.
Also x and the rest, but we know that they are ritual, so we don't need to do it.
And then we visit the dictionary of y, but everything that is ritual from here, we know
is alive and the same thing for the dictionary of set.
So when we finish this step, basically we know that all the objects that are ritual
from the outside, so they are marked as green, and the objects that are marked as gray, we
know that they are isolated.
So this is objects that form cycles and they are not ritual from the outside.
And I'm repeating this because it's very important in some of the assumptions, well,
assumptions.
One of the things that we're going to do afterwards.
And it's very important to bear in mind that nobody outside these objects that we have
here can refer or see any of these objects.
So right now that we know the objects that we need to destroy, we simply destroy them,
right?
Which is actually not, because nothing in Python is actually that easy.
So there is this thing called weak reference.
So what are weak reference?
So weak reference are basically a way to refer to objects that don't count towards the total
sum of reference counting.
This is especially useful for not forming cycles in the first place.
But it has other usage, especially for example if you are wrapping C++ or other languages
that have problems with thermistic destruction.
And weak reference are especially tricky because weak reference have sometimes callbacks.
So basically the idea is that if you have many weak reference to a certain object and
the object dies, all the callbacks are executed.
Basically it's a way of saying, oh, the object that I'm referring to have died, so I need
to do something else, right?
Maybe closing files or maybe removing other cycles.
So these are very tricky because every time you call a function when you're finalizing
objects in C Python, you have to be extremely, extremely careful.
So in our case, we know that these are the objects that survive the last pass.
So these are the two blue objects that we know from before and the list that contains
itself.
So we have two kind of weak references that we saw before.
So here the one that has the little f of x are the ones that have callbacks and the
other two, so it's the green ones, right?
And the other two are weak references that do not have callbacks.
OK, so for the one that do not have callback, we can just remove them.
So the weak reference are stored actually in a linked list which is hidden from Python
that lives inside the object.
So we just reach into the linked list and we unlink them and destroy them.
So for the ones that have callbacks, we have to be very careful because it can be two possible
situations.
The first one is that the weak reference objects are actually outside the cycles.
Remember that these weak references cannot refer to the objects inside the cycles, so
that's OK because they cannot mess with them.
But we have to be extremely careful with the second case.
The second case is one of the objects that we're going to destroy as part of the cycle
happens to be a weak reference to one of the others.
And this is especially complicated because the callback of the second one can actually
mess with our object.
So for the first one I say, we can just remove them because there is absolutely no risk.
They cannot reach the object in our cycle.
They cannot create new references or resurrect them or change the field.
So we just remove them.
For these ones, there is a…
So the danger I saw is resurrection, which is like the callback can actually increase
the reference count again and it can bring it back to life.
So more later on this.
But there is a trick, which is that the garbage collector doesn't guarantee order of the
extraction.
And under that assumption, we can pretend that the weak reference just happens to be
before the object and we just don't call it because we say, oh, the weak reference
was actually destroyed before the object was destroyed.
So there's no reason to call it.
It's a trick, but we can do it because we have this guarantee that I talked before.
Okay, so we have called all the weak reference.
So we can forget about those.
Now let's call finalizers, which is the second problem.
So finalizers are especially tricky as well.
Why?
Because, let's imagine this situation.
So we have A and then we have B and they point to each other.
So the finalizer remembers that they are the Dell method that you can implement in Python.
Inside is a function pointer called tpFinalize.
In Python 2.7 or well, at some point it was a legacy one called tpDell that was linked
to the Dell function.
But as we will see later, that's legacy and has been replaced with a better system.
So the problem is the following.
So we have these two objects and we need to destroy them.
And then we need to call the finalizers.
But we have a problem because which finalizer we need to call first, right?
Imagine for example that the finalizer of A needs something in the finalizer of B. Imagine
for example that A is a database and B is a connection or something.
When you are going to destroy the database, you want to make sure that the connection
is closed or something like that, right?
Which is not the best way of doing it as we saw before, but imagine that is a possibility.
So what happens if the finalization of A calls the finalization of B for whatever reason?
So we don't know the order.
And there is another problem which is for example this one which is resurrection.
Imagine for example we have a global variable called x, we initialize it to none.
And then we have this class that we implement the Dundell method.
We print something to know that it was called.
And then basically when the Dell method is called, we put the object in the global variable.
So basically this is resurrecting.
The class, the object is going to be destroyed, but it just happens that the Dell method points
the object in the global variable, increasing the reference count and putting it back to life.
So in this case, when you create one of these objects and destroy the only name that points to it,
basically the print function is called and we see that the x variable instead of none
now is our object.
So this is especially tricky because this can mess up with so many things.
It's actually so tricky that Python 2 decided, you know, if there is one of these and it
becomes in a cycle, I'm literally not going to do anything.
And indeed we can actually check that this is true.
So this is Python 2 or more known as legacy Python.
So we have this class now, we implement this Dell method, we print something to know that
it was called.
It's the better debugging strategy.
And then we create one of these two nodes, we create a cycle pointing A to B and B to A.
And then we destroy both names and force a collection.
In this case, we are forcing a collection there, basically calling gc.collect, which
is a function which is available in the gc module.
So basically this runs the algorithm that we saw before.
So after that, we saw that these two objects are actually not destroyed.
They are in this special list called gcgarbage.
So there.
And basically this means that they are never destroyed.
They're going to be there for the remaining of your program.
And this is more or less a leak.
So in Python 3, we have perf442 by Antoine P. True.
And this fixes this and adds safe and deterministic object finalization.
So this takes into account all the things that are very, very complicated like resurrection.
It takes into account also something very important that every destructor here is finalized.
But every finalizer is only called once.
So basically if the object is resurrected and then destroyed again, the Dell method
is not called again.
And also it takes into account safety and correctness.
So if we repeat the same experiment again, so we create the null, we create two of them,
we create a cycle, we force a collection.
We know now with our incredible debugging strategy that we see that both prints have been called.
Therefore the Dell has been made.
And you can actually check that A and B are no more.
So how this works.
So inside the object there is this function pointer called tpFinalize.
The tpFinalize is basically pointing to your Dell function.
So these are the objects that we have before from the algorithm.
And the idea is the following.
So for every object, let's start for the one which is the first there.
So we call the finalizer if it's present.
If it's not present, we don't care.
If it's present, we call it.
Here we're going to represent that with this green circle.
So that means that it's called.
Then inside the object, we mark that we have called the finalizer.
So we are going to represent that with this tick.
This is very important because this means that every object needs to know if the finalizer
has been called.
And this is something that we need to store inside the object.
And this is true for every object which is tracked by the garbage collector.
Which means that absolutely all the objects need to have an extra fill inside somehow.
Therefore increasing the memory consumption of all your Python program.
Imagine that all your Python objects will have an extra little fill.
But when you add them all together, it can be an important increase.
So when you do this kind of thing and when you modify the Python object, you have to
be extra careful not to add arbitrary stuff.
Because if you do this thing, basically you're going to increase the memory consumption of
all the programs that use Python.
So then you have to also be very careful.
Because another thing that can happen is that when you call the finalizer of the first object,
it can actually go and destroy some of them.
So for example, the finalizer of the first object can go and destroy the last one.
And this can happen.
In this part of the algorithm, you have to be extremely tricky.
Because when you have the collection of the objects that you are iterating over, they
can start appearing and disappearing.
And then your algorithm needs to be resilient of this effect.
This is one of the parts of the garbage collector code which is full of comments explaining
how crazy this is and how careful this needs to be.
But it works, sort of.
It works, it works.
OK, so then we know that this can happen.
And then the second time, we call the other object finalizer and we mark it as finalized.
And this little mark is the one that we need to inspect the next time we try to call the
finalizer.
Because if the mark is there, we know that the method was called before.
So we don't need to destroy it.
So you may think, OK, this is OK.
But what happens if the first object is actually resurrected as we saw before?
So if the object is resurrected, it means that we need to abort all the collection.
It means that that object cannot be actually destroyed because it has been resurrected.
But not only that, all the other objects that have been referred by that one need to be
also resurrected as well.
Because you cannot leave the object in an inconsistent state.
So basically, you abort the collection and put all the objects back.
But that's basically all the possibilities that can happen.
You just need to be very careful with where you put things and that your data structures
are very consistent.
If you check the code, there is actually a lot of assertions around this.
The algorithm checks all the time that all the collection that it's using is consistent.
The reference counts are bigger than zero at this stage.
That the different objects that happen to be there are never deleted.
So the last step in the algorithm is clearing the reference cycles.
So basically, the idea is that we are left with this object.
This object we already know that we have called all the finalizers.
There are no weak references to these objects.
And it's isolated from the outside.
So the reference count that these two objects have are only maintained by the internal reference
of both objects.
So you think about this, it means that if somehow we destroy these arrows, the object's
reference count will fall to zero and they will be naturally destroyed.
So that's the work of an extra function, C function, inside the object which is called
TP clear.
So in Python, you don't need to implement this thing or worry about that.
It's implemented for you automatically in the object object.
But in C, if you are implementing some extension module or some custom class or even in Siphon,
you may want to implement TP clear.
Usually, we recommend that you always implement TP clear.
So the idea is that even if you are doubting if you need to do it or not, you need to.
And the idea is that this function, the only job of this function is remove these internal
arrows.
So for example, imagine a simple case, the list that contains itself.
So for the list that contains itself, this function just deletes all the elements in
the list.
So it calls list.clear.
For a dictionary, it basically empties the dictionary.
For a set, it empties the set and so on.
For an object, it basically can set all the attributes to none.
And the idea is that after calling this function, there will be no internal reference.
So we will be in this situation.
And the reference count has fall to zero, so we know that we can literally destroy the
object.
And at this stage, the thing that is going to be called right now is the actual destructor.
The actual destructor is a function pointed inside the object called tpDialog that you
don't see in Python.
But when you're implementing extension modules, you can implement it in case you want to clean
up also some other things like C objects or extra things that your extension model needs
to care about.
And at that point, we have done our work and this object up there, are we just finished?
So this is the end of the algorithm and the end of the round.
But there is more.
So the interesting part now is to talk about some optimizations on top of that.
Because if you think about this, basically this algorithm runs over all the objects that
are tracked by the collector, which is like the majority of them.
So there is some optimization that we have on top.
One of these is the generations.
So the idea is that the generational garbage collector is an optimization on top of this
that is based on the idea that objects that remain reachable after a run of the garbage
collector, so the green ones in the algorithm that we saw before, will also remain reachable
in future runs.
So the idea is that the older the objects are, the more likely to be used by the program.
And this idea is basically also in contact with the idea that in Python, there is a lot
of scenarios when you create a lot of objects very fast, very little and very short lived.
So the idea is that objects will be created very, very fast and will be destroyed very,
very fast as well.
So if an object has survived a lot of runs of the garbage collector, we probably need
to run over it less and less because it's very likely to survive.
So the idea is that we have three collections, which we call generations.
CPython has three by default, but you can compile CPython with more if you want.
The first generation, which is indexed by zero, is the younger generation.
Then you have the other ones, and the third one is the older.
And the idea is that objects that survive a pass in the generation are promoted to the
next one.
Basically, they are moved.
And objects in older generation, as I said, basically have survived more and more collection
passes.
So if an object in the older generation, the object is very likely to be around for a long
time or at least has survived a lot of passes of the GC.
So let's see, let's inspect this thing in a graphical way.
So the generation in the bottom is the younger generation.
Then we have another and the older one.
So think that there is some errors on the top, which I don't know if these are there,
these errors here.
So these two errors can be, they can be objects that are eternal.
So some objects live in the actual data segment of your program, and these objects are never
deallocated.
So it may be some errors also from the outside, from objects that will never be deallocated
until Python finishes.
And those errors can be also taken into account.
So let's do the thing.
So we start with the younger generation.
We collect, so we run the algorithm that we talk about.
And after finishing, we know that the objects in gray are the objects that we need to destroy.
The objects that remain blue in the bottom box are the objects that we need to promote.
So we do that.
So we destroy the objects in cycles, and then we'll promote the rest to the second generation.
So some time passes, and there is a new collection in the second generation.
So we run the algorithm again, cleaning, you know, weak reference, calling finalizer, et
cetera, et cetera.
And then after that, we know that all these other objects need to be destroyed because
they are not used anymore.
Notice that this means in these generation diagrams that there are no errors from the
upper generations to the lower generations, right?
So we see that the only object that is blue in the middle is the only object that has
an error from the upper generation.
So after this run, we just promote this little guy there, and then we have the objects in
the latest generation.
The latest generation is also a bit tricky.
It also suffers garbage collection runs.
In this case, I'm not going to show it here.
But also, when the latest generation is run, there is an extra, a lot of extra steps that
are done.
So, for example, the free list, the internal free list are clear.
So free list is basically optimization because when you create certain objects, for example,
floats or tuples or objects that are very likely to appear, when you destroy them, instead
of destroying them, you mark as unused.
And if you want to create a new one instead of creating a new one, you use the corpse
of the other one to put new things in.
So this basically makes that it's much faster to allocate them.
So when you run in the latest generation, all of the free lists are clear.
Some of the free lists are clear.
So that you may think, OK, so when do you run the algorithm in a generation?
So you basically run the algorithm in a generation, what we call a pass of the garbage collector,
when the generation reaches a certain threshold.
This means that the generation has a certain number of objects inside.
And you can actually inspect these numbers.
So for example, you can import the GC module, which is for garbage collector, and then you
call this function called getThreshold, and it will return a tuple.
In this case, there are three elements in the tuple.
It's 700, 10, and 10.
Those are the defaults.
And these are the number of objects that need to be in the generation to start rigging in
a collection.
In this case, if you have compiled Python with more generation, the tuple will be bigger.
You can actually call a function called getSetThreshold and pass n numbers, where n are the numbers
of generation if you want to change this value.
This is an interesting trick, as Victor Estiner here will know very well.
Because if you have bugs that happen in the garbage collector, you want to trigger more
and more collection very fast.
So putting long numbers in this threshold triggers more collection, and it will trigger
your bug more likely so you can reproduce it.
This is especially useful if the bugs are raised conditions.
So in this case, we set up to 1,000, 50, and 20.
And then when we call again getThreshold, we see that the values are changed.
So you can use it if you have an extra knowledge of how often these generations are filled
and you have a better strategy, or you want to delay or make more often garbage collector
runs.
So you can force also a collection by hand if you want.
So there is this function called gcCollect.
And it receives a parameter, which is the generation.
So you can make a run on a particular generation if you want.
If you don't provide any parameter, it will run on the latest generation, and it will
promote everything up.
You can actually also expect all the objects that are tracked by the garbage collector.
This is sort of give me all the objects that are alive in the Python program.
Of course, this is not all the objects, Victor, because all the objects that are not tracked
by the GC will not appear here.
But this is still a bunch of them.
So the function that you can call is called getGcObjects.
So it was like this.
And then you get this list here, which is very big, so I have not completed.
And since Python 3.8, you can actually now specify a generation.
So you can say, oh, actually give me all the objects that are in a particular generation.
And this is especially interesting if you want to improve the GC or do some experiments
of how your program is using the GC or how many objects are in your generations.
OK, so let's talk about the GIL briefly.
So the GIL, as you may know, is a mutex.
It's actually just a combination of mutex, a condition variable, and a Boolean.
Basically, the idea is that one of the important things that it does is that it protects access
to Python objects.
So basically, when you have multiple threads, it protects them to modify the reference count.
Because when you grab a Python object or you refer to it, basically, you need to increase
and decrease the reference count of the objects.
And this is just an integer.
So you have multiple threads accessing the same value.
This is a race condition.
Because this is a Python runtime, doing this wrongly can create real problems.
So as you know, the GIL basically makes your threads not happy.
But you can use multiprocessing instead.
So the idea is that one of the main reasons to have the GIL is that it protects the reference
count.
That's one of the main purposes.
Because we need basically atomicity when we increase them and decrease them.
If you go to the actual Python documentation, you can see actually that this explains it.
So it explains, for example, the case of a multi-threaded program when two threads simultaneously
increase the reference count of the same object.
And therefore, you can have objects that will be leaked.
This is never destroyed.
Or objects that will be destroyed before they should.
Other features of the language and extension model have grown to depend on the guarantees
of the GIL.
But memory management becomes basically the main reason that we have this thing.
And this is the reason that removing the GIL is so hard, one of them.
Because basically, if you want to remove the GIL, you need to get rid of reference
counting.
That's it.
So we basically need a new garbage collector or some modified garbage collector that will
basically do the job that the reference count is doing.
And this is really, really hard for many reasons.
So the garbage collector is also atomic.
It means that there is, first, only one.
So it's global.
There is no one per thread.
One consequence is that it will stop all your threads from running.
We know that because of the GIL, there is not two threads running Python in parallel.
But it means that if you inspect the times that the threads take, one of them will take
a bit longer because it's running the collection.
Another interesting thing is copy and write.
So what is copy and write?
So copy and write is an optimization in some platforms.
So basically, it's used for fork processes and the like.
And the idea is that if you have a process and you fork it, this means that you have
a copy of it itself.
There is an optimization that says, well, if you're not going to modify the memory,
because both processes will have the same memory, so if you're not going to modify it,
we can share it.
So only when you actually modify some value of the memory, it will trigger a page fold
inside the operative system, and then it will make a copy.
This means that if you have four or five or six copies of your program, you don't need
four or five or six times the same memory.
But there is a problem.
And the problem is that reference counting.
Because just looking at a Python object increases this number just by looking at it.
And because it increases the number, it's writing to memory.
And writing to memory copies an entire page.
And this is a lot of memory.
What is worse, running the garbage collector increases and looks at the reference count
of all the objects that are tracked by the GC.
And this means that all the pages in the memory layout where this object lives will be copied,
which basically will make that if you have 10 processes, you'll need 10 times the same
memory.
And this is a problem.
As you may know, this is a problem that is stuck on our face.
There's a lot of interesting talks about this.
They tried to disable the garbage collector.
You may think, oh, is the memory going to grow indefinitely?
So actually, not really.
There is still problems.
So they actually made some new adjustments in the future.
But the idea is that reference count is still the primary mechanism for this.
So you will still have a lot of variables getting destroyed because of it.
After that, they actually continued back to see Python and implemented GC freeze.
So GC freeze is a function that basically freezes all the objects tracked by the GC.
And you can use it in combination with fork.
This is basically what is in the documentation.
So you can read it there.
And you can use it in combination to fork to basically make it a bit easier in this
situation and don't suffer that much for this copy and write violation semantics.
Once you want to restart the GC over all these objects, you can call GC unfreeze.
So let's go to some interesting practical applications of this to basically wrap up.
So one interesting thing is the bug in reference cycles.
So you may be interested in saying, OK, I have my program, right?
I basically want to know which objects become part of cycles.
Because one of the things of cycles is that it's very difficult to know when they happen.
Because it's not only your immediate objects.
They will have internal structures inside.
And they will form cycles of themselves.
And they are really, really tricky to find.
So one thing you can do is, for example, let's do this situation.
So we have our class node there as before.
So we create two of them.
We point one to each other.
And then in the GC module, there is this variable here called setDebug.
And then you can plus a flag called debugSable.
So when you plus that flag, what it's going to do with the GC is that instead of destroying
your objects, it's going to put it into this special variable in the GC module called GCGarbage.
So in this case, if you follow the code, sorry for the background, if you delete the names
and force a collection, you can inspect the GC garbage list there.
And we see that our two node objects are there.
So the idea is that you set this variable.
You run your program a bit.
And then you inspect the contents on this GC garbage.
And then basically, you have an idea of which objects are becoming part of cycles.
So you may want to now use maybe weak references or, I don't know, look at your program to
improve it or something like that.
So this is an interesting thing.
Another interesting thing is, for example, calculating memory costs.
So this is like simple stuff.
And the idea is that the GC, every object for the GC algorithm to work needs to know
how to reach all the objects that contain.
So for example, a list needs to know how to reach all the objects that are in the list.
A dictionary needs to know how to reach the key and the values.
A class, all the attributes, et cetera, et cetera.
Basically, an object needs to know how to recourse itself.
And you can use this thing.
So for example, if you have this list here in the top, so it's a list that has multiple
lists inside, you may be tempted to calculate the total size of the list.
And then you can say, OK, I will get size of in X, and it reports 96 bytes.
And then the problem is that that's not the recursive size of the list.
It's only the size of the list plus the size of the pointers.
Because if you get this other list here, that one, which has the same number of elements,
but they are less because they are not list by themselves, the size is the same.
But you can use this function in the GC module called get reference.
So this value, this function here, will automatically know how to reach all the objects
that are inside.
And then you can call this function recursively.
And then calling get size of in every element of the list, actually there are dictionaries
as well.
So you can actually know the total size.
In this case, I'm not calling recursively.
I'm just calling it in the first level.
But you can use it as a genetic way of reaching all the objects in a generic one.
So the last thing that I want to talk about is an interesting thing that happens, which
is exception blocks.
So let's imagine the following scenario.
So we have a for loop there.
So we have for x in range something, then whatever.
And the thing is that the variable x that we have in the for x in range, you can actually
inspect it after the loop is done.
So in this case, range 10, actually the last element is 9.
So you can actually print x over there.
And you can print the last value of x is 9.
This also happens with context managers.
So for example, you can say we open something as file.
And then you print the variable file.
And the value of file is still there.
So basically, these variables outlive the context manager.
So this is a known thing.
But if you do exception management here, so you have this try block.
So you do try.
You divide by 0 to create an exception.
And then you do exception as e.
And then you print e.
So print e works.
But you try to inspect the value of e after the except block is done.
The value of e is no more.
So basically, the variable e is not accessible
after the except block is done.
And there is an interesting reason for it.
The interesting reason is that the variable e contains the exception.
But the exception contains the frame object inside.
And that contains the variables in the frame, which contains exception,
which contains, so it's a cycle.
This means that if we don't do this thing, all the exceptions that happen,
and this has to be also take a thought, like when you recourse up and up
and up, the exception chain will form cycles.
Imagine, for example, that you have a gigantic NumPy array
on a function.
And then you raise an exception.
If the NumPy array is 1 gigabyte, if we don't do this thing,
it will leak 1 gigabyte until the garbage collector is run.
So it's not a leak technically, because the garbage collector
will end cleaning it.
But the problem is that it will delay the extraction
until there is a pass.
And if it just happens that your program never creates more objects,
there will be no runs.
So you basically have to maintain that gigabyte of NumPy object
alive forever.
It's not important.
It's just an interesting thing that happened.
And it might change in the future.
But this gives you an idea how tricky garbage collection is,
how tricky reference cycles happen.
And they can appear in the most unexpected places.
So the idea that you need to take out is that we have to take care of this.
We have put a lot of effort into making it correct.
And it's really, really tricky.
There is a lot of pieces involved.
We also collaborate with other open source projects,
like Siphon, to try to find bugs related to this and solve them as well.
But you have to sometimes, or only sometimes,
be aware that there is something called the garbage collector,
and what it's for, and when it runs.
And it's related to the gill.
And that is very key in case you want to remove it in the future.
So this is the end of the talk.
I hope you have enjoyed it.
And we have now to have some questions.
OK, we have room for about three minutes of questions,
so about three questions.
Could you provide any example use cases for when you might want to change
the number of generations in the generational collector?
So real ones, with real, I mean real applications.
I don't have any that can come to my mind.
But one of them is the one that I mentioned before.
You have a race condition that only happens in the GC.
And this is very likely for C extensions,
because sometimes there is memory that is corrupted,
and it just happens that the GC, when it's inspecting the object,
it crashes.
So you want to reproduce it, because it's a race condition,
lowering the number.
Instead of forcing new collections, it's a good way
of making it appear more often.
For real applications, it's more like a try to see what happens
and look at the memory consumption.
Or at least I don't have any that is obvious.
Maybe Instagram actually knows something else,
because they have played with it a bit more.
Thanks.
Thank you.
Hi, thanks for the talk.
Hello.
Thanks for the talk.
In some of your code examples, you were using Dell
with two variables at the same time.
I didn't know that was possible.
And I'm a little surprised that Dell isn't actually
trying to de-reference or decrease the reference
count of the tuple that goes into it.
Can you explain how that works?
So it's actually part of the grammar.
So it's not really creating a tuple in the middle.
It just goes to every variable in that particular list.
It's the same thing as, well, it's not exactly the same.
But it's the same when you do unpacking and unpacking.
So it's not really tuples sometimes getting created.
It's just a part of the grammar.
You can actually see, so in the documentation,
there is a nice explanation of how actually Dell
works with multiple arguments.
You don't need a parenthesis, for example.
And you can also check the grammar file
in the CPython source code.
So it's in grammar slash grammar, TXT, I think.
And you can check, actually, how is the exact way of or where
you can put it there.
Yeah, thanks.
Cool, thank you.
Hi.
Hi, you first-time listener, longtime caller.
So I was curious, when you have a reference cycle
and then you're calling TP finalize,
and then something in that cycle resurrects the whole cycle,
what prevents TP finalize from being called more than once
on one of the things that was deleted first?
So the algorithm first calls TP finalize on everything.
And then it checks if the cycle is still isolated.
And then if it's not, it resurrects everything,
well, everything that is reachable.
So basically, first it runs all the finalizers
independently if it's a resurrection or not.
And only after that, it actually
checks if the cycle is still isolated.
And then it runs checks to know which kind of things
need to be resurrected and which not.
So the finalizers can be called more than once?
No, no, no, no.
So it calls all the finalizers.
It marks them as called.
And then it runs the check for the isolation.
Yeah, but if the whole cycle gets resurrected and then
deleted again later.
But because the mark is there, you
know when you try to call the finalizer
that you don't need to because it's marked as already
finalized.
Thank you.
Cool.
Thank you, everyone.
And thank you, Pablo.