Hello, everybody. Welcome to our next talk. Our speaker today is Eric Snow. He is a C
Python core contributor, core developer, and he is going to be talking to us today about
to-gil or not to-gil, the future of multi-core C Python. Thanks, Eric.
All right. Thank you, everybody. Today we'll be talking about C Python's gil and how we
can move past it. I'm going to try not to talk too fast or this might be a short talk.
So follow that URL to get to the slide deck, all the updates to the slides or other resources
on Twitter. You may or may not recognize some of the things that I've done as a Python core
developer. So why is the gil a topic in which I have any interest? In late 2014, I had an
experience that motivated me to work on fixing Python's multi-core story. So it's been a
while. Along those lines, we'll work on an understanding of the situation and how it
can be changed. But let me be clear before we start, I'm not going to be perfect in this
description and I don't have time to go into every detail. And there are a lot of details.
If we have time at the end, I'll take questions. I'm guessing that we will. Okay. So brace
yourselves. There's a fire host coming. We're going to zip through a lot of these upcoming
slides. But by the end, we should have a pretty good understanding. These are effectively
the layers of CPython. So there's just one runtime in the process. And then there are
one or more interpreters in the runtime. There are one or more Python threads per interpreter.
And there's one call stack per Python thread. And then there's one eval loop per frame in
the call stack. So let's see how this applies in practice. The next bunch of slides are
a less than exact representation, but it's going to be good enough for us. When a process
starts, there are certain resources it has which are global to the process. Likewise,
certain exclusive resources. The runtime is effectively everything Python related in the
process. And an interpreter is all runtime state that Python threads share in common.
We usually use this term a bit more generally, but for this talk, we're going to use a lot
more specific meaning. The Python thread is associated with the OS thread and it keeps
the thread specific runtime state. So when loaded, scripts, modules, functions, classes,
and a number of other things compile to code objects. So when your Python program runs,
it gets loaded. And so we end up with that code object, a key part of which is the sequence
of bytecode instructions to be executed by the Python interpreter. For simplicity, let's
say that our imaginary Python program compiles to only a handful of instructions when loaded.
Real Python program would have a lot more instructions. So the frame here holds the
execution state of a running code object. And the eval loop in the frame or for the
frame executes one instruction each time through. So as we step through the program, we're going
to do that now. Watch how we visit each instruction in a deterministic order. So that's kind of
the nature of a single thread. And here's a rough sketch of what happens in the eval
loop. At a high level, it's pretty simple. But there's certainly a lot of detail in there.
And including here, you get kind of a sneak peek at the driver for this talk, the gil.
At this point in our code, let's say that there's a function call. Again, there would
be a lot more instructions involved in the real sequence of bytecode. So for the call,
we push another frame onto the call stack in the thread. And then we walk through the
code of the called function. So here we're at the last instruction, and then we're back
to the original code object. And we pop that frame off the stack. And then we end our original
code object here. And now we're done. And everything gets cleaned up at this point,
and the process ends. So as I hinted earlier, we could have deterministically flattened
all that execution just into a single linear list, kind of like we see there. But what
happens if there is more than one thread? So again, we have a simplified fake program
similar to the first, and we pretend that the program matches the two lists of instructions
shown here. Once the second thread is running, we'll see it both in the process and in the
Python runtime state. Each Python thread will be associated with its own OS thread. And
then in our code, the new thread will split off at that A20 labeled instruction, and we'll
wait for the thread again at A40. So let's walk through this execution now. And as we
do, try to imagine how we might possibly flatten this code as it executes. At this point, the
new thread is created. And then now the eval loop in each Python thread is running different
code. And on a multi-core processor, they'll probably be running in parallel, not just
concurrently. So we can see we have both eval loops. I put arrows there, but that's kind
of what we're running through the eval loops. So we get to walk through both instruction
sequences at the same time. And here the second one, the second thread is about to finish.
So here the second thread is finished and cleaned up, but the original thread keeps
going. And then the new thread had already finished, so when we get to this point, we're
joined. There's nothing to do, so now we're done. So if we look back at how the execution
unfolded and we had the two things going on at the same time, you know, you can't really
flatten the code like we did before, deterministically. Why? Because threading is non-deterministic
concurrency. And so there are a bunch of different permutable permutations of the instructions.
And here I'm just showing four of the permutations. And there's a closely related problem that
is pretty important to what we're talking about today, which is race conditions. Because
of that non-determinism, code in one thread may modify code in another thread unexpectedly,
or modify the data relied on by that code. And this is known as a race condition. Notice
how it's possible for thread A to make the assumptions of thread B invalid here. If you
get into that if block, you would expect that spam.a would still be 42, or not be 42, but
that gets broken. So mostly we solve this by using something called a lock or a mutex
around the critical sections of the code. The locks allow you to synchronize between
two threads, thus giving you deterministic order for the locked code. Only one thread
can hold the lock at a time, which is from the time it is acquired until it is released.
If another thread tries to acquire the lock while it is held, then that thread blocks
until the lock gets released. So we're not going to have both threads running at the
same time through those sections. So if we assume that thread A acquires the lock first,
we end up with the execution order that I have there on the right. So you notice how
the logic of thread A, it doesn't interfere with that of thread B anymore. And if thread
B had gotten the lock first, then that section would have run first, but the same protection
would have taken place. Okay. So that's a lot of detail. Take a breather. You've learned
it. Okay. That's enough. So the gill is the lock that protects CPython's runtime resources
from races. And if the gill wasn't there, then CPython wouldn't be thread safe for the
gill. You'd have some pretty serious problems. So here's a look at a lot of the state that
the gill is protecting from races. The eval loop we see here is the main driver for how
the gill guards those resources. Only one eval loop runs at a time. So when we're multithreading,
this is the state we're in. We have one arrow instead of two like we did before. The Python
threads take turns executing a few bytecode instructions in their eval loops, which is
kind of in this position in our simplified look at the eval loop. The gill is also released
in blocking situations in a few other places. Now that we know what the gill is, let's talk
about why we care. There are probably some maybe more than this, but really this is the
best I could come up with for the costs of the gill. But when I thought about the benefits,
these are a number of the ones that I could think of. And it really, if you think about
it, there's a lot to be gained by the gill that people don't consider when they talk
about the gill. But aside from the technical considerations, there's also an unfair perception
that the gill hurts everybody. I don't want to downplay the pain that it causes on people
who really need to do some CPU intensive Python code, but otherwise, I mean, is the gill really
a problem? So why isn't it as big a problem as so many people suggest? One of the big
reasons is that the gill gets released in a lot of key situations. So unless you're
doing some serious computation in pure Python code, the gill really isn't going to hurt
you all that much. But as long as there's a gill, folks will complain. It's just the
way it is. So people have a few ways of dealing with the gill. So in C extension modules,
you can take advantage of various features that allow you to release the gill around
C code that doesn't really touch Python's, the different resources in the Python state.
Over time, there have been a number of attempts to remove the gill. And each ran into its
own problem, a lot related to performance of single threaded code. I will point out
that the work that Larry Hastings has done with the galectomy, while it's kind of on
hiatus right now, there are certainly opportunities if some of the blockers can get taken care
of, then it's entirely feasible that that might actually remove the gill. So I think
that's a good idea. I know that he would say that he's already removed the gill, and
that's correct. But it's about getting the performance up to stuff. And what's interesting,
one of the best things about PyCon is that people get talking in person. And so there's
some neat developments going on that I really hope bear fruit in that regard. So we may
be seeing more from the galectomy. Or not. We'll see how things play out. But it's neat
stuff. I recommend reading up on galectomy and watching Larry's past talks about it.
So C Python isn't the only Python implementation. And sometimes we forget about that. Some of
the others don't have a gill. They already support multi-core Python code. And yes, they
aren't up to maybe the Python version that you want. But, you know, you can always help
out. And sometimes it's worth really diving in and see what you can do to help these tools.
And then you can take advantage of them. So worth looking at. If you're really interested,
there are opportunities there. Okay. We made it. So I think that's a good
So let's talk about what we're doing about the gill. Changes to the CPI are one major
way to deal with the gill. The CPI is a great thing. But it's got a handful of problems,
some of which we've worked at resolving and some we're still working on. And they have
a cost to us. To a large extent, the CPI is one of the main blockers to removing the gill.
The hard part is that we can't just change the CPI in any way we want. Backward compatibility
has always been very important for the core development of Python. And notably, the same
problem also impacts efforts to improve CPI's performance. So why do we have these problems?
Well, it's not like anybody messed up. It's just it's hard to look 20 years in the future.
But let's look at possible solutions. So just to be clear, nothing's going to change on
its own. And Python's all volunteers. So there's a limit to how much gets done based on how
much people have time just to use for free to do this stuff. But that's the nature of
open source. And we own that. Two things that help are things that we're already working
to improve right now. And specifically, one of the things we're doing is trying to layer
the CPI so things don't leak out of the different layers quite as easily. It's part of that
the leaking is part of the problem. Here are some of the ways we might resolve CPI problems,
particularly for the sake of the gill. And there are plenty of other solutions, possible
solutions. These are just a few of them. So quite a few people are involved in the effort
to fix problems with the CPI. Here are some of the projects with which I'm most familiar
or I'm involved even. So these are and you can follow these links. You can look at my
slides later and take a look at some of these things. Really interesting projects going
on. A lot of discussion on here, on the CPI SIG and also on the Python dev mailing list.
So what else is there? So if any of you have ever talked to me about this stuff, then you
should have expected this. What are subinterpreters, you might ask? Well, so remember we said that
we're using the interpreter in kind of the more specific way. And a subinterpreter is
any extra interpreter beyond the main one in the process. We started with one interpreter
like in our diagrams and then we add more. Each of those extra ones is a subinterpreter.
So if we look at that earlier diagram, here we have three interpreters, the main one and
two subinterpreters. They're all doing different stuff. You have multiple threads per interpreter.
They're all more or less the same. And they each have their own state. All interpreters
are mostly effectively isolated from one another. We're working on fixing some of the corner
cases. But for the most part they're isolated. And that's really the objective. It's also
worth noting that not all C extension modules will be able to run in subinterpreters quite
yet for a number of reasons. But we're working on that too. Finally, subinterpreters aren't
a new feature. They've been around for a long time. And the new thing that's going on is
we're working to possibly expose them in the standard library. So my PEP, which is PEP
554, is focused on exposing the existing subinterpreter C API in a useful but minimal way. The proposal
is still under consideration for Python 3.9. And there's no guarantee it will be accepted,
but I'm hopeful. And first off, with this PEP, what we're doing is we're adding a new
module to the standard library that exposes that essential functionality from the CPI.
Here's a simple example of executing code in a subinterpreter. First we create a new
interpreter, which is what that call does, but nothing gets executed yet. And then we
execute some code. So for now, we only execute text strings. We'll at some point look at
the possibility of executing other stuff too, like code objects, functions, whatever. But
we're starting with minimal and moving out from there. Also note that when the code runs
in a subinterpreter, it runs in the subinterpreter's Dunder main module. Subinterpreters will be
most useful when combined with threads. So here's another example. This one, same thing,
just running in a thread. So here's another example where we're using the same subinterpreter
multiple times. And what's neat is state is preserved between runs in the Dunder main
module. So we'll look at that. It can be super useful. In the first run, we set up some state.
And then in the second run, we use it. So what's nice is if you've got a whole bunch
of workers set up in subinterpreters, you can initialize those in the interpreter ahead
of time and then handle requests coming in with your subinterpreter already prepopulated
and set up ready to go. Okay. So the CIPI only covers creating subinterpreters and running
code in them and that sort of thing. So at first, the PEP exposed this functionality
and nothing else. And I found pretty quickly that that wasn't quite enough. So isolated
interpreters aren't really useful. They are useful but not nearly as useful as when you
can pass data between them safely. So the PEP adds a minimal mechanism that I've called
channels based on law prior out there. And currently, only simple mutable built-in types
and singletons are supported in channels. Also, for now, we pass serialized raw data
between the interpreters rather than the actual objects. And finally, channels are currently
unbuffered. And there are a few other details. But basically, again, we're starting minimally
and we're going to kind of expand out from there. So we do have plans for addressing
these limitations in future iterations. Here's an example that generates some data in a thread
under a subinterpreter and processes that data in the main interpreter. So first, we
create the interpreter in the channel and we get back the two ends of the channels,
distinctly typed objects. And then we start a thread that will execute some simple code
in our subinterpreter. And here, notice how when we call run, we specify the channel end
to inject into the subinterpreter's Dundermain module. And then we use that channel end in
the executed code. And there, in that case, we're sending data out. And then finally,
we pop the data off the channel in the main interpreter so we can process it there. An
important feature of channels is that sending and receiving are both blocking operations.
And this is the main way that interpreters can be synchronized. Async await, for me,
doesn't really fit in my brain. It just doesn't work for me. I suspect I'm not the only one.
So, I'm happy to say that subinterpreters facilitate an alternate concurrency model
that I find fits my brain quite well. And this model is pretty well described. A lot
of research, a guy named Tony Hoare, CSP it's called, communicating sequential processes.
So, a key here is that unlike traditional threading with its unbounded data sharing,
with subinterpreters you get opt-in sharing. And next, even though it isn't perfect, we're
getting better. I love this analogy here. It really matters in a lot of situations.
So, let's get to the part where this intersects with the gill. Subinterpreters are a way that
we can get rid of the gill. But how? We're going to stop sharing the gill. So, currently
subinterpreters still share the gill between them. And that's how you get all the downsides
of the gill. If you remember this chart, with all the state that we have to deal with, currently
the gill is part of Python's global run time state. If we move it to per interpreter state,
then we can get multi-core parallelism. So, I'm a bit hand wavy here, I'll admit. But
making this happen shouldn't be a terribly invasive change. In fact, that's an important
requirement for what I've been working on. I don't want to make big changes. So, all
this sounds too good to be true. No one's done it yet. But why? Because, well, possibly
they didn't know about subinterpreters or subinterpreters weren't important enough
to those people. But regardless, I'm doing the work right now. I came along. I'm trying
to make this happen. Regarding the blockers, there are some blockers that are straightforward
and pretty discrete. We're working on those. We've got to figure out what to do. If we
don't have a gill anymore to protect global state, then we have to minimize global run
time state and guard the remainder with more granular locks. But that's not really going
to impact the execution of Python code. Now, my projects advanced kind of slowly. I just
haven't had a lot of time. But I've relatively recently joined Microsoft, and they've been
kind enough to give me time to work on this each week. And so I'm hopeful that we'll make
a lot more progress coming up. So I've, there's another blocker that's really a serious pain
point. We've got to deal with this. There are all sorts of things, especially in C extension
modules. We can handle the C Python part, but C extension modules is kind of a problem.
We're working on a solution, though, or a variety of solutions. It's going to be important,
though. So the bottom line is I'm working on this. It's an active thing, and I'm really
hopeful that it's going to happen. I'm always looking for people to help. So if you want
to help, let me know. So what's nice is that a lot of my underlying needs for this project
coincide with those of other core developers and also other projects out there, even in
a lot of enterprise use cases. So I'm getting a lot of help indirectly that way. My project
entails these three efforts. And the most important one of those is moving the gill
down to the interpreter level. Here's all the state we're going to probably be moving.
And then really all this stuff is a good idea regardless of how my project ends up. Like
90% of the work that I'm doing is worth doing regardless. So, you know, I've got that. I
will never feel like I've wasted my time on this regardless of how it turns out. I'm still
hopeful though. So this is my plan. Pretty straightforward, right? That's it.
So I think we have like zero seconds for questions. So if you have any questions, just I'll stay
in the hall for a few minutes afterward or you can find me during the conference or get
in touch with me. Thank you.
We've actually got about three minutes for questions. So if you have questions, you can
go up to the audience microphones there. Please keep your questions short and directed at
the speaker. If you have longer questions, you can grab them in the hallway.
So what is the difference from and benefit of subinterpreters versus multiprocessing?
You didn't really talk about that.
Subinterpreters are a variety of aspects to it that put more load on the system, various
system level resources that in a single process you're sharing those between your threads,
but in a multiprocess situation you have to allocate that set of resources per process.
At a large scale that can be a real problem. And at a small scale, not so much, but it
really makes it a lot easier to deal with. You don't have to deal with interprocess communication
and a variety of other aspects of multiprocessing. You get a lot of the benefits of threading
with a lot of that isolation from multiprocessing.
The other Python interpreters you mentioned, PyPy, IronPython, all those, the ones that
don't have a gill, can you explain some basics about why they don't?
So Jython and IronPython are both built on other runtimes. Those runtimes don't have
a gill. That's most of it.
They may have some gill-like equivalent inside them that protects their state.
Maybe, but the JVM and for IronPython, like the CLR, don't really.
Great. Thanks.
So the g in gill stands for global. With this proposal, it won't really be global anymore?
It won't be process global. It will be interpreter global, though. Yeah, we thought maybe calling
it lil or something, but...
Okay. Thank you.
Thanks for the PEP and all the work you're doing on gill-less Python. Will there be any
support in CPython for atomic variables or persistent data structures and something like
Java util concurrent in CPython in the library in the future?
I don't think there are really any serious plans for... Well, I don't know. I'm not aware
of anything like that.
Okay.
Everybody has all sorts of ideas, so we're always talking about stuff.
Cool. Thank you.
So please give another round of applause to Eric.
Thank you.