So can I, okay.
Okay, hello everyone.
Today is the, in the morning,
in this room there's like two trust or two test workshop.
So hopefully you are all waiting for this
and sorry for the delays, we had some small problems.
I wanna start from, hold on.
Oh, it's not the end of the problems.
Okay, so I wanna start from a small introduction.
So I'm Dorota Jarecka.
I work for MacGyver Institute at MIT
and I have PhD in physics and yeah.
And I'm Anna Jaruga and I work at Caltech
and I also do have, and to have a PhD in physics.
So we have, we actually met at a university in Poland
and so as you can see, we don't have really like
proper background in computation,
but we do have like a lot of experience working with codes
and working with codes that are written by people
who also didn't have experience
and definitely the code didn't have any tests.
And we kind of like, after a few years of PhD,
I couldn't be more sure that like having tests is nice.
Like, you know, like when you have like 30,000 lines of code
and no single test that you can run
whenever you are changing any single line,
that is actually, I have some small nightmares about this.
So because we are like 60 people,
I think like it would be like slightly too long
to introduce each of you, but maybe we can find like
your friend for like next three hours
and you can just introduce to each other
and just tell what you are doing, et cetera.
Because also we wanna work in Paris during the day,
so three people, whatever, so maybe you can just
start introducing to each other.
I mean, you have code by yourself,
but we encourage discussion and collaboration, so.
So we will give you like a couple minutes for this.
likes.
.