Welcome to this afternoon's session of PyCon 2019.
Our next presenter is Bernard Gabour.
He will be speaking to us about type inting.
Please make him feel welcome.
Thank you and thank you everyone for joining for this session.
I'm Bernard Gabour and I will try to convince you in the next half hour that type inting
in Python is a good thing and hopefully you should use it.
Okay.
So first, who am I?
I'm quite a wide participant of the open source ecosystem.
I maintain both the virtual and the talks tool.
Plus, I work at the Bloomberg as a software engineer, mostly on data ingestion and quality
control.
But most importantly for this talk, I did attend the typing summit which happened just
a few days ago, which means that hopefully I should be perfectly positioned to actually
not just what is in typing, what is next for typing.
Okay.
So I hear you all.
Yeah.
Typing in Python, I get this question, yeah, really?
And I'm like, okay, why should I add typing to the Python?
Shouldn't I just write Java in that case?
And my answer is that no.
Actually adding typing in Python is good.
And just a disclaimer, I do like very much seers and penguins and because this is quite
a dense subject, I added a few of them into the slides so it gets a bit more congestible.
Okay.
So typing was added in Python back in 2017, I think, with Python 3.5.
The foundation lay down in the PATH 4.8.
It was actually initially designed, the accepted solution was initially designed by Juca in
MyPy and then Guido inspected that and liked what he saw and basically together with Ivan
and Lucas kind of adopted improved on the MyPy and that's what we have now in the language.
With Python 3.5, you can actually just do from typing import any and that typing module
actually contains a lot of type definitions what you can use to type into your code.
Okay.
So the obvious disclaimer, if you're still on Python, we have bad news for you.
You don't have much left, meaning like seven months.
This era has come to an end.
But you don't have to disappear.
You can actually still use typing even on Python 2.7 and Dropbox, for example, uses
heavily like this, the type information, and it has been backported via PyPI package so
you can just import it and happily use it.
Okay.
So the first question is, like always, why do it?
This is the part where I try to sell you this.
Why do you think, why do I think that adding type information is going to improve your
code base even if it might hurt a bit?
So the first and the biggest argument, I think, is that once you add type information, the
code base becomes a lot easier to understand and reason about it, meaning that it's going
to also become a lot easier to maintain and it's also going to become a lot easier to
actually debug your code base because you're always going to be in control.
You're always going to know what function, what type of input types it actually accepts.
So for example, if I have this random function called send request, without type information,
it would be quite hard for me to tell what each of these accepted arguments are.
For example, I know that in this case that the request can really be anything, but for
example, the headers always must be a dictionary of string to string.
For example, I cannot have numbers inside the values there.
Okay?
And this makes it just much more declarative, much clearer if you like even want to debug
or just read the code, what kind of cases you need to care, what kind of options you
actually have to treat within your code.
So it makes also refactoring easier.
If you can actually, if you have type information, you can easily find out what are the usages
of your type.
You can easily find out call here for your code.
You can actually make the life of your idea a lot better.
You're going to actually know where and how your objects are used, even without actually
running and inspecting the code.
Okay?
One of the biggest benefits, at least, I find is that my editor suddenly becomes not the
best effort code suggestion, but instead becomes a very accurate code suggestion.
Whenever something is there, so what kind of functions can I call on this function?
It's going to exactly tell me with the exact argument types what are the right and what
are the bad way of evoking it.
And one of the big benefits is that now you can actually run rain checkers on your code.
Your ID, both Python and Visual Studio code, actually does this lovely.
It's going to display your suggestion that, hey, whatever you have here are really bad.
Maybe you should not do it.
But more importantly, you have multiple type checkers available.
For example, MyPy is one of these type checkers.
It is kind of like the reference implementation of the type checkers.
But you have other tools.
For example, Pyre is developed by Facebook or PyType developed by Google or PyRyc developed
by Microsoft are all valid type checkers that you can use to actually improve it or check
that type annotation while your code is correct.
The interesting thing about this, one is that the PyWrite, for example, is actually written
in TypeScript.
So actually there is now JavaScript code that helps Python, which is kind of odd.
So another thing is that your documentation will be much improved.
You no longer will have to specify in your documentation with a long list of human readable
way of what are the correct types.
You can actually now take the type annotations and put it directly in your documentation.
And the user will have a well-defined way of reading exactly what are the correct type
information.
But this is OK.
Another use case which you can have is basically data validations.
For example, you can use the PyDentic library, which is going to take all this type information
and can actually enforce at runtime the values.
So it means that you no longer have to have at the start of your function like five lines
where you just validated the arguments.
You can basically just ask, in this case, PyDentic, hey, use the type information and
make sure everything I pass there is also accurate at runtime, not just at the static
analyzer at the analyzing time.
OK.
Another interesting use case, for example, Facebook users, this is to actually detect
security vulnerabilities.
Because for example, if you manage to type in all your user inputs as unsafe strings,
you can actually use the static checker to validate that unsafe strings never get passed
into the unsafe functions.
For example, calling out the subprocess or generally just like maybe database injection,
that kind of thing.
You can then check with the type enter that everything that is in your code base is first
validated and escaped before actually passing on to any security flaws into the downstream.
OK.
So for example, in this case, we can know that this first one is an error.
You should never pass into a subprocess check called an unsafe string.
But if you pass the second one, that's perfectly fine.
That's probably something that the actual programmer wrote in and it's like an approved
type of invocation.
OK.
So yeah.
So what it is not.
So I tell you what everything that was the dream was for typing thing to be.
I'm going to also tell you what it wasn't designed to be, just to give you like a hint
of if you want to use it for this, you might find rough edges around it.
So it wasn't used to actually do runtime type inferences.
Like the Python interpreter will never actually try to at runtime check that whatever your
type is there.
Essentially, any type information you had, the interpreter basically treats it as comment.
So it's ignored.
It also wasn't added to improve performance of the actual framework.
But wait, this was actually two days ago, but apparently no longer.
Because there's these people at the MyPy who found that the MyPy itself is kind of slow.
And they were like, how can we improve it?
And because MyPy itself is written in Python, they had this great idea that what if we can
actually somehow remove all the unneeded checks?
So they created a MyPy which actually compiles your Python code into C code.
And this way you can get performance benefit out of that.
For example, MyPy itself managed to get a four-time speed improvement, mostly by avoiding
hash table lookups.
For example, whenever you do an even like a function call, or you just call a property
invocation, during that, Python will always do hash table lookup because all those are
stored in hash tables like what is the function I'm calling, what is the property I need to
call.
And if you compile it with MyPy, see all these kind of hash table lookups get eliminated.
Okay?
So, yeah, for now it's MyPy.
Use it, but it is planned to even improve the performance on the black in the future
so we can have our favorite format even faster.
Okay.
So, yeah.
Bottom line, it was designed to improve the developer experience, not performance.
Oh, wait.
No, yeah.
And performance nowadays.
The performance part is definitely still kind of like a research project, work in progress.
It works mostly and doesn't support the entire language, but definitely maybe a few years
down the line it's going to be widely usable.
Okay?
If you want to try this out, definitely reach out to the MyPy team and they might help you
get if you can see if at the moment it's good or not.
Okay.
So, hopefully I managed to convince you now that why you should use typing and why it's
good.
So, let's have a quick look what kind of typing hinting or type information is added to the
Python language.
So, MyPy treats it basically gradual typing, meaning that you don't have to type into your
entire code base.
If you type into only a section of your code base, it's only going to type check that section
of your code base, meaning that you can actually gradually adopt type hinting.
You don't have to do like a big boom for your entire project.
You can type in function parameters, function return and variables, and yeah, only whatever
you type into are checked.
For example, in this case, the type hinter will be able to tell you that, hey, wait,
this call if you invoke the MyPy, hey, this call is actually not correct because the first
argument is a number but should be a string or hey, you call these names but these names
doesn't actually exist on the type and it even can suggest to you that we have this
name and underscore name.
Maybe this is what you actually wanted to call it.
This was just a typo.
So how to edit?
So once you decide, okay, I want this.
I want speed.
I want improved maintainability, improve everything.
How do I edit?
You have multiple options.
And the most simplest and cleanest way is by using the type annotations.
The type annotations for the interest in Python 3.0 at the function level.
At the variable level, it will interest in Python 3.6.
And it means basically that if you have a function like this, you can annotate the function
or you can annotate the actual string or the actual variable as you see there, basically
using this double code or double colon or the arrow annotation.
Okay?
So, yeah.
So type annotations, quite clean.
Meshes really looks really nicely in Python.
The packaging is solved because all your type information is already there in the code.
The bad side is that it does require Python 3.6 and granted this may become less or less
of issue as we go ahead but for now, we still have a lot of Python 2.0 which we need to
migrate or we have dependencies that are still not there for us to migrate right away.
So the downside is that it does require importing all your type dependencies.
This may be invoked type penalty.
It also gives extra information that the interpreter needs to evaluate.
But it's not all despair because with Python 3.7, you can actually add this magic from
few import annotations.
And once you do this, the interpreter actually treats all the type information as a comment
and actually doesn't get evaluated.
Nothing gets constructed.
So this should alleviate some of the performance penalties that you might otherwise get.
So yeah.
Another way you can edit and this is how you can edit even in Python 2 and also support
it for both Python 2 and 3 is by using type comments.
This is what Dropbox uses for the entire code base and works under any Python version because
his comments really was supported with the language 1.0 or 0.1 so it shouldn't be any
that kind of issue.
The type information is still kept locally.
The packaging is solved because you're going to ship your comments hopefully.
I'm not sure if anyone removed their comments after they shipped the code.
The bad side is it's kind of like ugly because all the type information is right beside where
it should be but not exactly where it should be.
It has a lot of unused import.
Especially your linter might start complaining that hey, you have this list.
It only is in the comments.
It's really not used.
More importantly, it starts confusing linter and then you need to add further disables.
So just to give you a better impression of this, imagine I have this simple swap function.
It basically swaps two elements as a context manager.
So if I want to actually type in this, I first need to add the actual type information for
each and every variable and the return value.
And you see this can get quite big, especially if your type information is more complex.
Then you also need to add further imports to actually ensure that the type checker knows
where to pull all this type information.
And maybe you use a few aliases to actually fit into a line and be like more readable
code base.
And then you end up basically making the six lines into this lovely 14 lines, which is
only good if you get paid by the number of lines you write because double your salary
easily.
So this is kind of like a downside of this, but there's no real workaround.
It works mostly fine, though.
Another option that you can go to is instead of writing comments, you can write stuff files.
This stuff files is basically what you already know from C++, the headers.
In this stuff files, the good thing is that you no longer have to even touch your current
code base.
You can basically just add further files to it and it's going to get all these wonderful
benefits which I listed earlier.
It works under any Python because here no interpreter actually looks at this stuff files.
It also doesn't carry out the source content change.
Can use any latest Python features because again no interpreter actually interprets these
files, only the type checker.
And the type checker is smart enough to understand the latest fancy syntax and doesn't conflict
with linters because again the linters don't really check this.
So and it is also very well tested because the entire standard library is actually type
aware made by using this option.
So the downside is that now you have a duplicate code.
Basically instead of one file, now you have to maintain two files.
So and it's kind of like you also have to package extra content for which there is a
PEP you can do it and it's standard supported by the old type checkers.
So you can actually use hint to the element that hey yeah you can add this information
or like to pull information from alongside the stuff files.
The biggest downside which I see is basically at the moment it is kind of troublesome to
maintain because once you add it basically all type checkers or linters treat your stuff
file as a single source of truth meaning that if you add something in your source file and
you don't have type annotations for the linter those additional functions don't exist.
So from this point on this is kind of like not gradual typing.
It's like either everything or nothing or you're running into issues.
So yeah we have an actual plan to address this but I'll talk about that a bit later.
So yeah another bonus way where you could like historically if you read really old code
you could also if the type information were added in the doc strings this is kind of documented
but the it's not fully functional it doesn't allow you to actually type into all the complex
code so I would really not recommend this kind of option going ahead.
Okay so the other question is so what kind of types can you add.
Basically at this point the type is kind of like have two options.
One of the options are the nominal types.
Nominal types are basically all the types which actually have a name you can actually
name them like a classes the top of the dictionary.
These actually have a proper type that you can kind of envision.
Vector like even distinct types or you have also the composer operations like you can
specify this or that or that this is optional that kind of arguments.
You can even similarly have like callbacks which are basically this is the type information for a
function or type variables which are more allow you to even define kind of like generic type
information for your class when depending on the construction of the class you can have different
types into your class.
Okay and you have also the any then is the magic keyword because any basically means
this is treated just as it was before type checking means disabled type checking more or less
on the any and that means anything is allowed on whatever that type or on that object.
The other options that you can have is basically the pythonic way of if it looks like a doc and
it works like a doc it is a doc the protocols are kind of like this here instead of specifying an
actual type I can say if whatever you pass in has that get item and that get item returns an int
I'm happy and I'm good and that's what I want so this is a more generic way of defining the
requirements for the arguments of your functions.
Okay so I'm going to quickly go over a few gotchas these are the kind of gotchas that once you do
start adding this type information you might run into these kind of problems.
So if you have a code base that you need to maintain both on python 2 and 3 and this is what
you had on python 2 once you move to python 3 and for example add the for future input
unicode literals now your wrapper will look a lot more complicated because depending on the
interpreter your type information needs to be different because it needs to be like
unicode on python 3 and it needs to be like by stream on python 2 so it kind of like makes
your wrapper a lot more complicated or the other option is that if you want to have like
depending on the input type the output type can change the first impression of you do it is you
can specify that yeah the input can be both this and the output can be both of these types
and this kind of things but now the type checker going to think that that type might return also
the additional type for example in this case even to the first function is called with an int
it might think that the return value of that magic can also be string and there is a solution
for this you basically can use multiple return times by using overloads the overloads are
basically how you define that depending on this input what would be the output the only downside
of this is that now you need to define this interface one per every file or one per every
combination and it is kind of like now your type enter the kind of things that you're disabling
the same or declaring the same function multiple time which is a bit not the best other option
that you have you basically can have this issue of the how the type lookup happens for example if
you define this class and the value of the class can interpret it in multiple functions it's just
kind of natural that you're going to have multiple properties or functions which return the name of
that element so if you run that code against mypy mypy going to complain that hey this is in the
type and use like what test a dot float wait no i just say this float not that magical type
and the reason why this is is that basically the way the type checker works whenever it discovers
the type it tries to locate that value going out from that namespace so to say and in that
namespace the closest float that it can find is actually the function itself so it kind of thinks
the type of your return value of that function is the function type itself and you can work around
this by making explicit here you explicitly declare that the built-ins that float is what
you want and not any type of float and this will solve the problem and just now you need to import
buildings to actually be able to refer to it both under python two and three and to do that you can
use this guard this if typing dot type checking this this is guaranteed to be only be true under
python under the static linter the interpreter will always set this to false so whatever you
put behind this will never be executed another interesting example is that when you do start
doing inter inheritance you run into this issue of contravariant arguments for example if you
have this function and you inherit from it it might be easy for you to think that hey i have
this base class the business can take both type but in the master class i basically gonna root
an egg subtype to actually handle one of the use cases for example you say that be only
going to have int and i want b to only get three that case once you're still running to that this
cannot happen the argument types for inheritance or when you extend classes can only treat more
you cannot like treat less than the parent actually defines it treats
yeah and you basically like this would be a valid one you can say that the base class
also handles bull but you cannot say that i'm gonna handle less than my parent cause
and the reason for this is basically the parent anyone can take a look at your class as the parent
and that's a valid thing and the parent whatever the parent defines must be always satisfied by
the children of your inherit of your inheritance chain okay so this is another interesting problem
so imagine you have this lovely class and you basically say yeah i want to define this class
method this class method may basically instantiate the class and it's going to return the a and once
you inherit the inheritance also takes an additional argument because i need to use it for something
so once you're going to try to actually run this if anyone has like a few seconds just to think
about it this will actually fail at runtime because actually it turns out that you never passed in the
float value for the b so it's going to be like wait you did not pass the position or required
argument and the type checker will also actually warn for this and i'm going to admit this wonderful
error and you can fix it easily by basically just making that argument optional and now this actually
will work and the type checker will also be happy but you're thinking okay so i have this for the
class method what if i do the same for like constructors like the init method basically
what's gonna happen if you run and one would you run the same code it's gonna feel just as the same
but what happens if you like run it with the type checker oh yeah that's the last sign is actually
what the type checker says meaning the type checker says yeah everything's good and even to this
fails and the type checker doesn't complain the reason for it that is apparently it's too common
to prohibit incompatible init and new and this is kind of like an edge kill which you might run to
like why wasn't the type checker actually handles this but it seems in the real code basis by usage
there were way too many false positive and this kind of disabled even it does work for class methods
which are kind of like additional constructors okay so once you see all these sketches you might
have kind of like this feeling and especially just seeing how much your code extends and i'm here to
tell you that no you don't need that bridge yet because whenever you hit the wall and you feel
like this is too much you always have a bit of help you can use the reveal type to actually
print out what the type what the type checker actually thinks your type there is at the moment
this is kind of like inspect whatever happens within the type enter or the type checker or
you can use the cast when you can say basically say i know this is going to be this type just trust me
it's basically an unsafe cast if there's something like it meaning that it's going to basically force
the type checker to treat it as it is or if it's too complicated even with casting to solve you can
always just ignore it i don't recommend this usually should put something at the end of it as
a temporary workaround like maybe this is a bug in the framework or maybe this is actually
something that is too complicated now for you to fix and you want to come back later on just
ignore it for now and put the to do after it okay so one more thing which i kind of like get hinted
earlier but i got back yes you can actually merge your doc string and the typing meaning that
you can actually use the pep 257 defines how type information should be in the documentation string
you basically just need to include this to information into your documentation string
and if you have type hinting this is possible by using this things documentation and you
are also using things as a documentation generator meaning that if you install this package and you
configure it as an extension in the swings you can make code that looks like this notice that
there's no type information in the doc string but once the generation runs it's actually going to
inject all the type information for you into the actual doc strings now the only kind of downside
of this at the moment is that it's actually going to unroll your type information so it might get
very long and complicated we definitely should improve it to be able to like use the actual type
or the type aliases for example in this case instead of the should use that reducer and module
instead of actually injecting the full expanded value so yeah so this is kind of like where we
stand at the moment in the final few minutes i would like to present you where we are heading
next so what are the further improvements we're going to add to the typing and how we plan to
actually make this experience even better for all of you so the first thing which is the accepted
pep and it's also already implemented in my pi is the literal types this means that basically you
can whenever based on the literal type of the argument such as the open function the return
value of the functions change now you can actually do it for example in this case if you open a file
by just using the read literal you can actually hint it that the return value going to be always
a text like a unicode in python tree at least or if you open a file with the binary literal it's
always going to return bytes this should make your code whenever based on like a you know more
literal the type of the output change much more nicer to use another improvement that's coming up
is the acceptance of the type dictionaries this is again an accepted pep and also is something that
implemented in my pi this allows you to basically type in type your dictionaries too not just your
list itself another thing that's happening is the final qualifier this is again accepted
and implemented in my pi this is basically the type the python typings gray joy style but instead
of what is that may never die now we're what is set may never ever be set again so once you set
something you'll see that if you try to set it again the type checker will just complain that
hey you already set this variable earlier maybe not try to override it because that's not going
to be a good thing another thing that we plan to add is basically what i hinted earlier we plan to
improve the maintenance of the stuff files by actually checking and omitting errors if your
stuff files and your source file differ in any way and we also plan to like the way the current
vision is the way we do it we merge the two files so you can use like local type annotations to
actually annotate your local variables because those are actually not part of the interface
okay another thing which is happening is numpy and panda support we have these three requirements
to make that true and for each of this the typing team has a plan the exact type there is
very type variables or the key types are going to be added into the typing and with this hopefully
we can start annotating all the numpy and pandas code base too so another thing this all the
everything else after does comes is more like we would like to and there is a plan for it but it
might change so one thing is everyone kind of gets annoyed that why do i need this capitalist and why
do i need capital dictionaries wouldn't be nice if i could basically just not have to import it
and basically just do this it's a bit cleaner so there is definitely a tentative to make this a
truth another thing is we can also maybe have the union and the option is probably the ones we're
going to use the most of the time and you can make even this shorter by basically using this syntax
for as proposed for example so the question mark is the optional and the or operator as a union of
elements and we'll also now that we have four plus type checkers we want to make easier to run the
multiple type checkers on the same code base and have like unified error code so there is a plan to
actually define for each type of error what is the type code error code that should be raised
this would mean that you could usually transition from one type checker the other type checker
and would also have like a common database of all the possible errors and how we should fix them
okay so basically just unifying the error codes between the various type checkers so yeah my
conclusion is that basically you should always use types whenever you would write unit test
the type is basically just like a type of unit test you and remember that you can achieve much
more with this you can even improve the performance of your application if you really want to but do
prepare for some discomforts and challenges on the road do allocate a bit of time to actually
migrate your code base or just do it very gradually okay so thank you very much in case my talk was a
bit too fast or did not catch everything on that link there down you actually have a more detailed
description of all this thank you