Hello, everybody. Up next is understanding Python debugging internals with Liran Hamovitch.
Thank you.
Hi, everyone. So my name is Liran, and I'll be talking today about Python debugging internals,
how does it work behind the scenes, and what can we do about it. This is my first time
at PyCon, and my first time giving this talk, so I'd appreciate any feedback you have on
it. So sorry about that. So start by introducing myself. My name is Liran Hamovitch, and I'm
a co-founder at CT8 Rookout. Before founding Rookout, I spent about a decade doing cybersecurity.
Now in the cybersecurity space, much of what we do is reverse engineer software, trying
to figure out how it works, how can we stretch it to the limit and beyond, and how can we
change its behavior of what it was originally meant to do. So Rookout is a platform for
live data collection and delivery. It allows you to debug applications anywhere. And my
background in cybersecurity, much of our employees, helps us a great deal here. Rookout
allows you to attach to a process running anywhere in the world, not only on your machine,
it can run in the cloud, it can run in Kubernetes, it can run in serverless, and we allow you
to set non-breaking breakpoints in those applications and get variable state, get stack traces,
get anything you want from the application without writing more code, restarting the
application or redeploying it. Now, as I was writing the Rookout SDK for Python, I learned
quite a lot about how Python debuggers work behind the scene and how does it actually
function. So now I want to share with you some of what I've learned. So what's your
favorite debugger? Actually, GDB does have support for Python debugging. So I'm going
to show you a few. Yeah, that's two different debuggers. You have GDB support for Python
and you have the PDB, which PDB is a debugger built into the Python standard library. I've
heard outside, I didn't know it, that Python includes now two new debuggers, the breakpoint,
which was released in one of the latest versions, and it's also people have been talking a lot
about IPDB, which I haven't heard about. You have the Python debugger, which might
be the most popular one out there, both PyCharm, which have a booth outside, and Eclipse use
Python debugger behind the scenes. Rookout supports debugging Python as well as Node
and JVM. Python idle, ATOM, each of their own built-in debuggers. And I'm sure there
are others out there. What almost all of those debuggers have in common is that they are
based on the csetrace function. This function, I'm not expecting you to read this documentation.
Those are the official docs for csetrace in the Python manual. I think that's 2.7, but
I'm not sure where I took the screenshot from. Anyway, this just might be the most complicated
function in the Python standard library. And while the documentation for it has improved
quite a lot since I got to know it two and some years ago, I'm going to walk you through
it step by step. So what does csetrace do? What does csetrace do? What is it all about?
Well, with csetrace, you register a callback for the Python interpreter, and whenever the
interpreter decides something important is about to happen, it's going to call your callback
and notify you just before it does. What are those events? Function call, line execution,
function return, and exception raised. Before any of those events, you're going to get a
callback. Let's take a look at a quick example. Here we have a very simple tracer callback.
It's called simple tracer, and it accepts three arguments. Frame, which provides you
with a window into the interpreter's state. Frame is what the interpreter, what's the
state of the interpreter just before the next event is about to happen. Let's say if the
event is line execution, then frame is going to be what's going on just before the line
was executed. Where in the code we are, what's the line number, what are the local variables,
what's up the stack, and so on. Event is a string describing the events that we are just
receiving. It's going to be either call, line, return, or exception. And R is an additional
argument that provides us a bit more information about the event. What does our simple tracer
does? It starts by collecting information on the frame. It collects the function name
and line number. And then it prints the event, function name, and line number to the standard
output. Finally, our tracer returns itself, which we'll discuss a bit more later. Let's
take a look what happens when we run this example callback against a sample Python code.
This is our example. Method A returns B multiplied by 2. Function B returns response from B.
And C setrace, simple tracer, we call setrace and set our tracer as the callback, and we
invoke A. What's the standard output for that? C setrace has no output. Neither does A. But
once we invoke A, our callback is executed for the first time. We get a call event, which
means a frame is about to be created, a function is about to be invoked. The function name
is A, and the line number is 1. The next event is line. Line number 2 is about to be executed
as part of function A. Now we get the third event. Function B is about to be called. Line
number is 4. And line 5 is about to be executed as part of function B. Next, we are going
to get a return event. We return from B with line number 5, and we return from A with line
number 2. So that's a very simple flow of what happens with the tracer. We get every
time a function is invoked, a line is executed, and the function is about to return, we get
notified, as well as exceptions, which I've left out from these examples. Now, I've mentioned
that simple tracer return itself. If you were to look at the debugger implementation of
all those debuggers we mentioned earlier, you would see that they often return the function
at the end of its function. Not always, but sometimes. Why is that? Well, there are actually
multiple callbacks working here behind the scenes. When you call syssetrace, you register
a global trace callback. This global trace belongs to the thread you are in, and is going
to be invoked any time a new function is about to be executed. So whenever a new function
is about to be executed, whenever a new frame is about to be created, the interpreter will
call our callback. Now, the return value for that callback is going to determine the local
trace for that function. And the local trace will be the one receiving the local events.
So line return and exception are only being received by the local trace. If the global
trace will return none, then there is going to be no local trace for that function, and
the local events won't be triggered at all. A few more things that are important to know.
That the global trace is the one determining the local trace. Whenever you're in a function,
regardless if there is a local trace, or there isn't a local trace, or what's the local trace,
the global trace is the one that's going to be invoked in order to determine what's the
local trace for it. And the last thing to keep in mind is that Python offers no way
to determine the local trace once a frame is started. So if there is a long-running
function that has been invoked before you have called setTrace, there is no clean way
to set the tracer for it. Now, let's go back to our example and see when are those traces
are created. When you call c setTrace, the global tracer is created and set a simple
trace. When a is started, we return simple tracer so it is set as the tracer for function
a. And when we call b, that tracer will be set. The reason Python gives us this power
is because the local tracing has a significant performance impact. So Python allows us to
decide which functions we want to monitor and which ones we want to skip so that we
can minimize the performance overhead for the debugging. Now, I'm sure you're... As
I've mentioned, the setTrace sets the trace function for the current thread. How do you
handle multithreading? Well, lucky for us, the threading module provides a setTrace function
of its own. The threading setTrace functions allow us to pass a callback that will be registered
as the global trace function for that thread, for any new thread created by the threading
module. Essentially, after you run equal threading setTrace, whenever threading creates a new
thread, it will call c setTrace on your behalf with the value you have provided. Now, a couple
of things to keep in mind here is that if you want to debug a multithreading application,
you want to call threading setTrace as early as possible. Once the thread is started, there
is no easy way to set the global trace function for it. The second thing to keep in mind is
that this is part of the threading module. If somebody is using the underlying thread
module or a different approach to multithreading, then that's not going to help you and you
need to figure out a different way to do it. On a happier note, if the application you
are debugging is using an event loop-based concurrency model, such as gvent or eventlet,
then for all Python curves, there is only one thread. So as soon as you've called c
setTrace, you are set, and all the greenlets will show your global trace function. Now,
this might be a bit intimidating, everything we've been talking about so far, and it might
make you wonder how hard it is to build your own debugger. Well, there is a quick shortcut
I'm going to teach you that allows you to build your own debugger in just three simple
steps. Well, we've mentioned earlier Python PDB, the Python debugger. Well, PDB is built
on the top of a lower level package inside the Python standard module, which is called
BDB, the base debugger. The easiest way to build a Python debugger is to inherit from
BDB and customize it to your own needs. So what does our debugger look like? A class
debugger which inherits from BDB and does really simple things in its constructor. We
call the underlying BDB constructor to initialize the class we inherited from. We create a dictionary
for breakpoints, we want to keep track of, and we call setTrace. What setTrace does is
it actually has BDB registers its own trace function as the c setTrace function. So BDB
calls c setTrace on your behalf, registers its built-in trace function. Next, we add
our set breakpoint method. We accept the file name and line number we want to set the breakpoint
on, and we get a method. This is the method we want to execute as a callback whenever
the breakpoint is triggered. We call setSetBreak, which is a function we inherited from BDB
that have BDB sets the breakpoint in its own internal data structure, and we update our
breakpoint dictionary with a list of methods to be called. So if there is no method, we
go to the key error exception clause and add a list with a single element. If there is
already a list, we just add our method to it. And last but not least, we override user
line. User line is a BDB method that says nothing but pass. But whenever BDB wants to
inform us that the user line is about to be executed, it calls user line. So all we have
to do is override it, and we get notified of any breakpoints and other significant events.
The only argument for user line is frame, which we've mentioned earlier. It provides
the state of the interpreter just before our breakpoint is hit. What does our user line
do? It starts by checking if break here. BDB will occasionally notify you on events besides
breakpoints you have set. So if you want to make sure a breakpoint is actually on this
line, you call break here. It turns to a false. And in this case, if there is no breakpoint,
we just return. We then get the file name and line number from the inspect module of
the frame. I'm going to talk about inspect a bit later in this talk. And then we get
from the breakpoints the callbacks that have been registered for this file name and line
number, and we execute each of them with the frame object. That's it. In those three
simple steps, we've built a breakpoint-oriented debugger for Python. Now, you may be wondering
how fast is it going to go? What's going to be the performance impact on my application
using this debugger? Well, as I mentioned, Rookout is a general-purpose data collector
that aims to run in production. So we are obviously aiming for a very, very low overhead.
So what we went and after building that simple debugger, we went and tested it. Here is the
simple performance benchmarks we've done. We've written two very simple methods, one
that does nothing and non-hesitant 10 assignment statements, and we are going to execute each
of those functions 16 million times. And then we are going to see how much time does it
take in four different scenarios. The first, how long does it take without a debugger?
How fast is Python in executing those functions so that we can have some baseline? Second,
we are going to run it with a debugger but no breakpoints. Third, we are going to run
it with a debugger, setting the breakpoint in a different file. And fourth, we are going
to run it with a debugger, setting the breakpoint in the same file. It's important to keep in
mind that in all cases, the breakpoint is never going to get hit. We are never measuring
the overhead of the breakpoint itself, but the global overhead of how slow are we making
the software. So here are the initial results. If somebody can't read for far, that's very
bad. Without a debugger, each function takes an average way under a millisecond. But once
we turn up debugging, then performance is about 100x slower. Not very good for us. So
how can we optimize this? There are three major avenues you need to consider when optimizing
the debugger. First, as I've mentioned, local tracing is much more expensive than global
tracing. You get notified on a lot more events. So as much as we can avoid local tracing,
as smart as we can be about deciding where we want to local trace, and as we're not
to local trace, the better we are at pruning out those functions we don't care about, the
faster it's going to go. The second part is optimizing the call events. Whenever the global
interpreter, the global trace function is called to determine whether or not we should
trace a function, we need to make the decision as fast as possible. The faster we make it,
the less overhead we have. And third but not least, once we've gone into local tracing,
once we're looking at a specific function, we want to determine very fast if this line
is a break point or not. If it is, we need to stop. If it's not, we need to resume execution
as fast as possible. So we went through the BDB source code for
the hot branches, walked it to the side, removed a lot of unnecessary features, simplified
the code, and optimized for hot branches. What were the results? That's much better.
Especially on the left side, where we managed to avoid local tracing, you can see the performance
impact is still significant but nowhere near where it was. But on the right side, while
we still have local tracing, then the performance overhead is quite huge. How many of you are
familiar with Cyton? Oh, that's a lot. So Cyton is a pretty cool project. It allows
you to take your Python code out of the box and as is transpile it into C, compile that
C code, and place the generated shared object or DLL as an exact filler of the code.
That's the filler for the Python code you have dropped. So that Cyton essentially allows
you to create a much faster replacement of Python code with virtually no code changes.
If you want, you can even do additional optimization based on Cyton features that will push the
performance even faster. So we went around and did that. And as you
can see, Cyton gave us a pretty big performance boost, about two and a half times faster,
which is nice, significant. But seeing this graph, I was getting desperate. I mean, we
are looking for a performance grade debugging solution, something that will have somewhere
between no overhead to maybe, I don't know, 5%. And that's not 5%. So I took a minute
to stop and think about what I was doing. So it's quite clear that Python BDB is very
naive. It was never optimized for speed, and we can improve it by a lot. But the more we
improve it, the harder it gets to keep improving it, the harder it gets to make it even faster.
And we are pretty far from where we want to be right now. So what happens if you set an
empty tracer? How fast is local tracing going to be if we do nothing? We get called, we
return, no processing at all. It won't do much. It obviously won't provide us the functionality
we need, but it's going to give us some benchmark about how fast can we make it. So this is
what I ended up with. Even with an empty tracer, performance takes a big hit, especially once
you turn on local tracing. Now, there are still, seeing this, I decided to take a step
back and take another look at the C Python source code to understand what's going on
behind the scenes. I'm not going to belabor you with everything I've learned. I'm just
going to show you some of the top insights. So turning on tracing sets up C Python for
extra work. Some of that extra work happens in Python. Since for every instruction that's
about to be executed, we'll be running additional Python code. And this is where most of our
optimizations have been focused on. This is what we can change. Unfortunately, some of
the performance penalty comes from the C code of the Python interpreter itself. For
instance, here's a screenshot of maybe call line trace. I'm not expecting you to read
it. But what maybe call line trace does once you turn on tracing is that after every instruction
is executed before the next instruction, the interpreter has to go and figure out is this
a new line event? Is this something I want to notify you about? This is just one of the
cases where C Python has to do a lot of extra work for the debugging mechanism regardless
of what you do on your end. Now, as optimizing this code is definitely possible, but it would
require a pull request to the Python source code. And even worse, it would require new
releases. And we obviously want to support customers without having them change the Python
interpreter. We kind of gave up on the tracing mechanism. It's very awesome. Mostly Python
debuggers out there use it, but it just wasn't good enough for us, not for what we had in
mind. So to explain what we did, I'm going to take a step back. How many of you are familiar
with the Python bytecode? That's tougher. Yeah. So here is the Wikipedia definition
for bytecode. It's a form and instruction set designed for efficient execution by a
software interpreter. Essentially, Python compiles our sources into its bytecode and
executes that rather than our own original source code. Let me give you an example. Here
is a very simple method. Def multiply AB, result equals A times B, return results. Do
any of you have any idea what's the bytecode for that going to look like? That's close.
Yeah, that's exactly what he said. To be fair, that's exactly what he said, and even I can't
read that. But bytecode is just a buffer. In Python 2, buffers are strings, so we get
a nice string. It has a set of instruction set. It's much shorter than our string with
the def multiply stuff, but instead of going through syntax, cyclexing, and syntax trees,
and so on, the Python interpreter stores that. I'm sure all of you know the PYC files, so
that's the content of the PYC files. It's just the bytecode generated from your code.
Once we disassemble this string, we get something that's quite more readable, which is quite
far, quite close to what the gentleman said. Load into the stack A, load into the stack
B, binary multiply the both of them, store it in a variable called result, load result
back onto the stack, and return it. Now, if we take a look back at what the interpreter
is actually doing, it looks a bit like this. There are two main stages. The first is compile.
During the compile stage, the interpreter goes through our source code, figure out what
it all means, and builds the bytecode, which is a string like what we've seen, stores it
in PYC files or just in memory, and then comes the second step, the execution step. During
the execution step, the so-called interpreter loop is literally looping through our bytecode
and doing it one step at a time. Now, there was actually a lecture about an hour ago about
the gil, which is the dreaded gil everybody's been speaking of. That's the interpreter
loop. The gil is about the interpreter being able to execute one set of bytecode at a time.
It can run multiple threads of the interpreter loop. And everything we've seen so far about
the C setrace and the tracing mechanism, it all takes place during the interpreter loop.
So whenever the interpreter does something that we might care about as a debugger, call
a new function, execute a new line, return for a function, and so on, the interpreter
has to notify us. And that's what the performance overhead we've seen happens. Every time the
interpreter does something, it has to notify us. And that's expensive. So Rookout is taking
a different approach. Rookout goes back to the bytecode that we've seen. It finds the
line of code that belongs. We find the instruction, the specific instruction that maps the line
of code using the debug information, and we insert our breakpoint. We literally set, we
just insert a call instruction into the bytecode. So the interpreter doesn't really care about
Rookout. The interpreter just goes through the code happily, not aware of tracing or
any debugging mechanism. But when it sees that call instruction, which is the same as
any other call instruction it might have, it calls it. And that's when Rookout gets
notified, and this is where we defer from all the other debuggers out there. We don't
work with the interpreter step by step, tracing everything it does. We try to avoid the interpreter
being aware of us at all, just being there when it needs to be. While bytecode manipulation
is a big topic and might deserve its own lecture, I do want to give you some resources about
where you can read more about it. So the Python standard library is two important package
that can definitely help you with byte manipulation. The first is inspect. Inspect is a package
that allows you to see into the interpreter, take a look and see what the interpreter
is doing. Among its other useful functionality, inspect allows you to extract the bytecode
for any function or class you have in memory, and it was used when I showed you. For me
showing you the bytecode I used inspect. The second package is this. This is short for
this assembly, and it allows you to take those ugly strings we've seen and make them into
something a bit more human readable. Now, unfortunately, Python does not offer any way
to write bytecode in memory. So you can read it, but you can't write it, you can't edit
it, you can't change it. In order to do that, you need a native extension that bypasses
the Python standard interfaces and interacts with the C APIs. If you're interested in that,
Google has an open source project called Cloud Debug Python that does a bit of it, and you
can take a look at that. Now, so far we've discussed how do you know when to break? How
do you decide which line you care about, when do you stop the application and take a look?
But what happens after you break? How do you take a look at a running application and understand
what its state, what it's doing? So if you remember, the frame, as I mentioned throughout
the talk, is our window into the interpreter. It allows us to see exactly what is going
on. Additionally, the inspect built-in module is quite well documented, it's easy to use,
it allows you to see the line numbers, file names, stack traces, and so on. And unlike
what I've shown you earlier in this talk, everything here is very, very fast. Performance
is awesome due to the simple fact that everything we're doing here through the inspect module
is quite similar to what the interpreter is doing behind the scene. So when the interpreter
is working with your code, is running your code, it's using the same data structures
and the same functions we are discussing here. So here is a simple example. Function test
frame info, frame equals inspect current frame. Now, inspect current frame is one of the coolest
functions out there. It allows you to literally get the frame of the code you're currently
executing. This is some production users, which we might cover a bit later, but it's
also the most useful function you can have if you're testing or experimenting with the
byte code and the Python interpreter. As you get on the fly, you can just get the frame
and then you can see what it's doing and even run most of our unit tests are built using
that function. So this is the output for it. You get the file name, frame inspect.py, which
I'll show you the repo for a bit later. Line number 16, function name, code context, index
show where we are in the stack trace. Since we are currently executing, the index is zero,
but we can also traverse the stack trace and go up. And the second example, let's take
a look at how do we access local variables. My str is a string, my dict a dictionary,
my list is a list, and here we print f locals, part of the current frame. Does anybody have
any idea what's that going to do? So turns out that behind the scenes, the local variables
are stored in a dictionary, just a regular Python dictionary, and that's f locals. So
once we print it, we get a dictionary. Variable names are keys. Variable values are the values
of the dictionary. So my dict dictionary, my str string, and my list list. Quite easy,
unlike what I've shown you earlier. So what can you do with what I've been showing you
so far? First of all, you can show off your Python skills. That's definitely useful if
you're here at Python. You can get source information. Have you ever wondered how does
the logging module know the file name and line number you are writing the log from?
So the logging module uses inspect.conf frame and walks up the stack to find who called
it. And from that frame gets the file name, function name, line number, and that's how
you get that information in your logs. You can also walk up the stack. If you're looking
at profiling or you just want to get that extra variable somebody forgot to give you,
the interface, you can always go up and get it. Or you can build your own debugger. So
I've placed most of the source code that this lecture is based on at our public repo. So
feel free to go ahead and browse it. And that's kind of about it. Feel free to check us out
at rukka.com and ask me more. And yeah. So now would be a good time for questions if
you have any of what I've shown you.
Great presentation. Thank you. I wonder about the byte code manipulation. Can you manipulate
the byte code which has been loaded into memory?
Yes.
Okay. And if you do that, like, what do you need to, like, there are any security which
you have to pass to do that? Or, I mean, how does this work?
So Python doesn't have any built-in security module. Everything running in the application
is at the same level of isolation and security and trust. So all you have to do is use this
native CIPI that are not exposed to Python and you can use them to edit.
So you said you can do remote debugging. So I don't have to do anything on the remote
machine to be able to modify that byte code?
No. So that's, to do byte code manipulation, you need to be in the same process. What Ruko
does is that you install an SDK. You install an SDK that connects back to our service and
then only you can access that machine remotely and debug it.
When would you use inspect, when would you use flocals instead of just the locals function?
I knew that once. I can't remember right now. But they're essentially the same. The locals
function returns you that dictionary.
Okay. That's all I needed.
Hey. It was a great presentation. I was wondering if you had any performance numbers with the
byte code way of doing?
Yeah. I have some. I can show you.
I was just wondering how much faster it is compared to what we were looking at earlier.
The global overhead is nothing because the interpreter doesn't see anything or doesn't
care anything. Even the breakpoint itself takes under a millisecond to execute. So I have
some performance metrics if you want to see on my laptop.
All right. Thank you.
When you manipulate the byte code there, are you doing a insert in place and then a jump
table somewhere for the extra bytes or are you just actually extending the whole thing
so it's longer?
You have to expand. You have to expand. But you have to keep in mind that unlike more
traditional languages such as C, Python doesn't build just one big buffer of code. It builds
a lot of small buffers. So you just have to expand the specific buffer you're editing.
And over there you have to expand it because there are pointers for jump instructions and
loops and debug information and so on.
Okay. So the cost penalty for actually doing all the mem copy and that, you don't worry
about it. It's low.
It's copying a few bytes of memory.
Yeah. Okay.
It's nanoseconds.
Hey. If you are in a debugging session, then your code calls subprocess call. And I cannot
really go into the process that I call in to continue to debug. I just wonder if you
have any tip.
Again, so most of this talk has been about Python debugging in general. For Rookout,
you install the SDK into your application. And once you install the application, then
you can debug that process because it creates a network connection.
Okay.
I can show you later.
Hi. Thank you very much for your talk. Just out of curiosity, have you ever tried to use
all your knowledge to kind of set a bunch of checkpoints in a malicious code that you
know is malicious? Is it even safe to do it? Probably not. I don't know.
You actually had that talk with a few security professionals about setting breakpoints in
a malicious code they want to debug. I haven't seen much rise from it yet, but it doesn't
make any difference from a technological standpoint. Just like you debug a piece of code you don't
know. It doesn't matter if it's malicious or not. It's not very different from running
a malicious piece of code with WinBug or GDB or whatever it is. You can do it.
So that's safe, right? I can use it to, let's say I have a piece of malware and I can use
your approach to analyze bytecode of this malware?
Yeah. If you have malware written in Java, Node or Python, you can definitely use Rookout
to debug it.
Thanks.
Which would definitely help regards if they have anti-debugging tools and so on. There
are probably not going to detect it.
I had a lot of trouble using, performance issues using the inspect library. When I was
trying to build something similar it was slowing things down a lot compared to using the sys
library to get the frame. Yeah, I ended up giving up on it. Is there a reason to do it?
Is there a reason to do it? Do you have to use the inspect library as opposed to other
ways of getting a current frame?
It's all the same as long as you get the current frame that's good. Inspec does offer a bit
of overhead and we generally try to use it a bit less when we are actually running production
code but I'm not sure.
Thank you everyone.