Good morning.
I couldn't be more excited to welcome you to the 2019 PyCon.
PyCon 2019 here in Cleveland, Ohio.
On behalf of the PyCon 2019 staff, I want to start by saying thank you.
Thank you to all the volunteers that make this conference possible, to the Python Software Foundation for taking on the fiscal responsibility of this conference.
We would not be here without the board and staff of the PSF.
I want to thank all of the presenters who came to share their work.
And I want to thank the sponsors who made this, who support this conference as well.
And of course, this conference would have no purpose without you.
So I want to thank you, and we're just going to give all those people a round of applause.
The very first thing I want to talk about is that PyCon is committed to providing a safe environment and a positive experience for everyone.
And that's regardless of any difference that we may have.
In order to ensure this, all staff, attendees, speakers, sponsors, and volunteers at any PyCon event are required to adhere to our code of conduct.
Please familiarize yourself with the code of conduct at that URL, as well as the procedures for handling incidents that are linked therein.
You can find these documents there or by going to us.pycon.org under About Code of Conduct.
If at any point during the conference you're concerned that someone may have violated the PyCon code of conduct, you're encouraged to report it.
If you're unsure whether the incident is a violation or whether the space where it happened is covered by this code of conduct,
we encourage you to still report it.
The organizers are okay with receiving reports where no action is taken for the sake of creating a safer space.
At any point, you can make a report by email to pyconusreport at python.org, by SMS or telephone to 1201-862-8572,
or during the conference you can find an incident responder who will be wearing a brightly colored t-shirt like this.
Once again, this is the contact information on screen. I'd encourage you to take a photograph or write it down or save it in your mobile phone in some manner.
Got it? Cool.
So quick orientation. Once more, welcome to PyCon. That's where you are.
If this is your very first PyCon, I want to apologize.
As PyCon has grown, trying to detail each and every event and every part of the conference that makes these...
Who's calling me?
And trying to detail each and every part of the conference has become pretty much untenable.
However, if this is your very first PyCon, I hope that you heard about or attended our newcomer orientation yesterday at 4.45.
If you didn't make it, that's okay.
At this URL at some point today, the video from that orientation is going to go up, and you can go and you can watch Adrian share each and every detail of the conference, including things that have already passed.
Now more generally, you are in this conference center. It's fairly large, and so we're just going to walk through it piece by piece.
First, I want to talk about some accessibility things that we've got going on.
We will be providing live captioning for all talks this year, similar to what you see to my left and to my right.
Additionally, space has been reserved in the center of each speaking room for wheelchair access.
The conference is ADA compliant. However, if you have any concerns or need additional accommodation, just please let a staff member know.
We will do everything we can to support you.
You are here. This is exhibit hall A, which will host our plenary sessions over the next three days.
During those plenary sessions, we'll have some keynotes soon. Russell, Keith, McGee, we have Shaw, Jessica, and then on Sunday, we have the Python Steering Council panel and Nina.
Additionally, in this very room, in these seats, you'll find the lightning talks today at 5.40, Saturday morning, Sunday morning, and also Saturday tomorrow at the end of the day.
Consider making some time to attend lightning talks. You sort of never know what you'll see.
And if you're interested in giving a lightning talk, which is a very short five-minute talk, you can find the signups near registration.
To your left is the expo hall. This is located in exhibit halls B and C.
So you probably already found it because that's where we're providing meals this year.
All meals through Sunday will be in the expo hall.
And you can find the menus and ingredients for these meals at the URL on screen.
If you've indicated that you require a kosher consideration or allergies when you registered, please look for the signs in the hall to locate your meals.
The expo hall is also the place where all of the sponsor booths are.
I encourage you to stop by our sponsor booths and find out more about what they're using Python for, why they've decided to support PyCon and the Python community by being here.
Our sponsors make PyCon possible, and we depend on them to keep PyCon's registration costs under control.
Their presence here represents an incredible investment in our community and this conference, and also make the operations with the Python Software Foundation possible.
They're here to meet with you, encourage you to check out their projects and products, and possibly even hire you.
A reminder that the sponsor booths will only be out there today and tomorrow.
On Sunday, that entire space will be reconfigured.
In addition to sponsors, I want to take a moment to very poorly show all the names of the corporate companies who sent people to PyCon on a corporate registration.
These registrations help offset the cost of individual and hobbyist registrations.
I'm sorry, student and hobbyist registrations, and go to support the Python Software Foundation work as well.
In the expo hall still, it's a big room, we do a lot with it, is Startup Row.
There are some tables, and today and tomorrow, there will be people who competed and won a spot on Startup Row.
These are new companies, and we're going to be doing a lot of work on that.
So check those out.
Note that these change, so the people that are there today will not be there tomorrow, and then they'll be replaced with other companies.
So you want to stop by Startup Row twice if you get a chance.
On Sunday, that entire room gets reconfigured into our posters and jobs fair.
So that'll be Sunday after, oh, I'm sorry, Sunday after.
All right, so on screen are our breakout rooms.
Note that there are some distance from where we are generally over to these other rooms.
Those are the atrium ball rooms, and they're right there.
So if you made it here, you just need to go up that escalator or up that escalator or come through this concourse to find them.
They're right there.
They are a little bit of a distance from the other talk rooms, so if you're planning to see a talk in there, make some consideration for time.
We have five talk tracks with 95 sessions once again this year, and you have 19 opportunities to see one of these talks.
But don't worry, most of the talks will be recorded and available online after the conference.
If you do see a conflict between two talks you'd like to see, go with your gut.
If you do attend a talk where time remains and the speaker allows for questions and decides to ask and asks for those questions,
in the legendary words of PyCon chair emeritus Brandon Rhodes, remember to phrase your question in the form of a question.
We have a veritable fleet of rooms available for open spaces.
All day today, Saturday and Sunday, these rooms are allocated for anyone to self-organize a one-hour meetup style event.
They'll be open from 8 a.m. to 11 p.m.
They're a great opportunity to connect and have a deeper discussion on something or find people who have a shared interest or a common goal.
I want to encourage you to consider shaping the conference by having your own open space.
You can stop by the board next to registration to post your own open space or peruse what's already there.
And new this year, you can go to the URL on screen and at that location you'll find a photograph of the current day's board
that you can sort of pinch and zoom around in to see what has been posted so you don't have to constantly be crowding around the boards.
So these rooms are something that is sort of near and dear to my heart.
These rooms, which are 25C and 26A, B, C, are home to the PyCon Hatchery program.
PyCon as a conference has grown and evolved over the years through the direction of volunteers, the board, and staff.
Last year we launched the Hatchery program, and it's intended to offer anyone the opportunity to see their idea come to fruition at PyCon.
Whether the intent is at a permanent fixture of the conference or something that's just ephemeral and topical or important for any given year,
the Hatchery program offers space and resources at PyCon for that idea.
We're excited to have the inaugural Hatchery program returning this year and three new concepts joining us for 2019.
All day today and today only, you can attend Las PyCon Charles.
It's a full day of talks given in Spanish. That will be in room 25C.
The Charles schedule is matched to the primary talk schedule, so you're welcomed and encouraged to jump in for just a single talk or stay all day.
New this year is the art of Python. It's a miniature arts festival, and it's going to focus on narrative, performance, and visual art.
You can find that event this evening in room 26ABC tonight from 8 to 10 PM. So if you're up for a show, you can see that there.
The PyCon Hatchery Maintainer Summit is also new this year, and it's seeking to build a community of practice for project maintainers and key contributors
with the goal of helping the Python community sustain and grow healthy projects and communities.
This will be a mixture of lightning talks and discussions, and it'll be going on from 10-50, held tomorrow from 10-50 until 2 PM in room 25C.
Also new this year are the mentored sprints. They'll run from 2-30 to 6-30 PM tomorrow in room 25C.
And this is a newcomer's introduction to contributing to an open source project, and it's done under the mentorship of somebody who has more experience and has worked on the project in the past.
These focus on providing less experienced developers a supportive environment in which they can learn, collaborate, and expand their network, and celebrate their victories at the end of it.
So these are the PyCon Hatchery programs for this year, and if you have an idea, the Hatchery program is very likely to continue, so keep an eye out for the CFP, which will be launching sometime between now and next PyCon.
I really ran out of arrows. I bought too many arrows, so I had to use them all on this slide.
So PyCon has consumed nearly entirety of this convention center for the next few days, and during that time, all of the public spaces will be scattered with Python Eastons.
It's not an official event, but this is a happening that I never really get the chance to miss out on at PyCon.
There are no rules that say you have to attend any given event. There are no rules that say you have to fill all of your time with a structured event.
So consider spending some time joining a table or a group and meet someone new, open a laptop and explore a problem together, spend some time catching up with someone you've never met in person before, or an old friend.
One suggestion to improve the experience in the hallway track and throughout PyCon generally, though, comes from PSF board member Eric Hulshur, and this is the Pac-Man rule.
When standing in a group of people, always leave room for one person to join your group.
This suggestion can help create a physically welcoming space for someone to join your group and makes it easy for attendees to identify groups that they can join, so it helps meet new people.
Throughout the space, we have three gender neutral bathrooms. One is near rooms 17 and 18. One is near rooms 25 A, B, and C, and one is inside the expo hall, so when you're entering from registration, it's on your left.
There are also two mothers rooms in the conference center. These will be rooms 17 and 18, and instructions for access to the room are posted outside.
So if you need help or if you need getting it needed in there, check there and get the instructions.
If you find that you need to take a break, focus on some work or just breathe. We have a quiet room in room 24.
This is this room has a specific purpose, so please be respectful of the word quiet while you're in the space.
And stepping outside. It's always beautiful in Cleveland. There's never rain or clouds.
We can see our place in the Civic Center of downtown Cleveland.
Around the venue, there is the Pie Ladies auction, which is Saturday, May 4th at 630 p.m.
That's in the Hope Ballroom in the Connecting Hilton downtown Cleveland, so you don't even have to go outside if you don't want to, but take a walk.
Last year, $30,000 was raised to benefit the Pie Ladies. For a $5 cover charge, it's a hard bargain to beat.
It's probably one of the most fun evenings we got going on here, even if you don't come to bid and win for an excellent cause.
Just around the corner from here, so if you go down Lakeside, make a left on 9th, and then down to the pier, you'll find the Rock and Roll Hall of Fame and the Great Lakes Science Center.
These are home to the PyCon dinners, one this evening at 630 p.m. and one after the close of the conference at 630 p.m. on Sunday.
These evening events are both ticketed events, so when you checked in at registration, you should have had little tickets.
You'll need to bring those tickets to these events, and since food's already been pre-allocated for them, if you did get a ticket and you don't plan to attend, convey your ticket to someone else however you see fit.
This helps reduce food waste and keeps the events fun and lively.
That's a lot, and that's even skipping what we've already done.
So if you'd prefer to have this information with you, there is a printed program.
It looks like this, and there is us.pycon.org, which can be a little bit fiddly to navigate, and we have a guidebooking in this year.
This is a specific app that has all of the schedule information and room numbers and such in it, and you can get a guidebooking in there.
And yeah, I think you're oriented.
So time for some housekeeping.
First off, the Python Software Foundation, which does take the fiscal responsibility of this conference, is currently running a fundraiser.
We couldn't do this without them, so if you're able, consider going to this URL on screen, and it will take you to a page that includes all the information about that fundraiser, and you can get a free copy of that.
If you registered for the PyCon Fun Run and Walk, that kicks off Sunday at 7.
Bussing begins at 6, but probably show up around 6.30, so you're not just left waiting.
But if you're punctual, 6 o'clock it is.
Tomorrow morning, there's a different run.
It's not ours, but we'll be doing it tomorrow.
You can run along, I guess.
But note that if you're coming to the Convention Center, particularly by car, this will cause some congestion.
As you see, we are sort of right in the middle of the route, and so from about 7 a.m. to 11 a.m. tomorrow morning, plan a little bit of extra time to get here.
The swag bags are a bit of a pain in the ass, but we'll be doing that tomorrow.
So, thanks to DigiKey and Adafruit, all attendees will receive a Circuit Playground Express, which runs Python.
So, two notes on this.
One, if you're going to be traveling through something that involves security checkpoint, go ahead and take this out of your bag and tell the screener about it.
It'll save you and them a lot of hassle and questioning and considering.
Just a tip.
And the second one is, consider bringing this with you on Sunday to our closing keynote.
By the end of it, you might feel inspired to run out immediately.
By the end of it, you might feel inspired to run out immediately and start programming on it, or you might even code along with some of the examples.
So, also that needs picking up are your t-shirts. They look like this.
But I want to take a moment to warn you that due to the cut and weight, which is the same as last year, our choice in color doesn't quite have as much pigment.
So, in full transparency, these shirts are quite sheer.
So, make sure that you try your shirt on and are comfortable wearing it before you wear it in public.
If you have concerns about your t-shirt after picking it up, let us know.
And lastly, I think, almost, there are some schedule changes.
US.Python.org, the mobile guidebook app I mentioned earlier, and the signage have all been updated.
Your printed program has not.
So, please take a moment to double check the boards in front of the expo hall for substitutions.
But the long short of it is that there has been a substitution in Grand Ballroom B on Saturday.
And the next slide, the elephant and the serpent using Mastodon with Python by Philip James replaces code review skills for Pythonistas by Nina.
And shipping your first Python package and automating future publishing by Chris Wilcock substitutes coded readers using Python to uncover surprising patterns in books you love at 315 and Grand Ballroom B.
That's right.
We have a professional photographer on site this year.
If you're comfortable being photographed in a candid fashion, you can go pick up a badge holder that looks like this.
And at registration, swap your badge into it, put your lanyard on it, and the photographer will avoid photographing you.
But more importantly, in post, we'll make sure not to use any photographs of anybody wearing a badge that has this red banner at the bottom.
So, one last thing, which is about social media, a thing near and dear to my heart.
I'm going to take a selfie with you.
That's perfect.
All right.
And if you want to tweet at the conference, so this is to get the attention of the staff or the organizers, tweet at PyCon.
If you want to post about the conference so we can look back and remember everything that occurred here, tweet with the hashtag PyCon 2019.