Hello, everyone.
All right.
I think we're going to get started.
If anyone has not attempted to clone the repository yet,
I recommend doing so now.
We're going to start with kind of an introduction.
So if you haven't done that yet, you
will be able to kind of sit there and listen to me talk
and attempt to clone.
I did mention earlier, but for those who may not
have been here yet, when you do go to the ReadMe,
the instructions that it has for cloning the repository
assumes that you have an SSH key installed.
If you don't have an SSH key installed
or you don't know what that means,
you can also go to the top here, click the Clone or Download
link, make sure that this says Clone with HTTPS,
and then try to run a get clone on this
instead of the other URL that's in the ReadMe.
That should help solve some problems.
All right.
So how many people here, this is their first PyCon.
Yeah, OK.
Cool.
That's quite a few of you.
How many people did a workshop yesterday as well?
OK.
So you have like half a brain left
after everything you crammed into it yesterday?
Cool.
So first off, I want to thank everyone
who responded to the pre-workshop survey.
I got almost 60% of people to respond,
which is really, really great.
That really helps me kind of cater my materials
and the tutorial to all of you who are in the room.
So thank you for that.
I will note that there were quite a few more people who
had very little experience with Python than I anticipated.
And so I just want to encourage everyone to not,
if you are somebody who's a beginner,
try not to get caught up in the details.
And if you happen to have problems with your environment
or anything like that, I do sort of
recommend pairing up with somebody
who might be sitting near you who has it running
and who can kind of walk you through it.
I think that you'll get a lot more out of it
if you try to just pair with somebody else instead
of fighting, getting a virtual environment running
or something like that.
Does everybody have these resources?
If not, get them now or get them from your neighbor.
OK.
All right, so a little bit about me.
My name is Emily Morehouse.
I am the director of engineering at a company called CuddleSoft.
We are a digital product development company
based in Denver, Colorado.
So I get to kind of touch on a lot of different pieces of tech.
I help write mobile applications, web applications,
backends, CI pipelines, embedded systems,
really the whole nine yards.
So this talk is a little bit broader than most tutorials
probably will be.
It's probably more rare to see such a deep dive on back end
testing as well as some front end JavaScript stuff.
So I hope that you are all excited about that
and that you are along for the ride.
I'm also a Python core developer.
If you are in the JavaScript world,
I help maintain a package called Axios.
It's basically like the requests of JavaScript.
I'm a huge visual testing proponent.
I'm a huge auto format fan, so you'll see that in my editor.
And in general, I'm just a really big language nerd.
OK, so this is our schedule that we have set up for today.
Like I said, these first 20 minutes
are really going to be me kind of talking to you
and giving you an overview of the different things
that we're going to cover in this talk,
as well as the reasons why it's important.
Just kind of like lay that foundation
so that we can really dive into some code.
We will have a quick 20 minute break after that
just to make sure that as many people are up to speed
as possible and have their environment set up.
Hopefully all those really slow clones
will be finished by then.
And then we'll have about an hour
to dive into regression testing in Django.
And I'll talk a little bit more about exactly what
to expect for that hour.
Then we're going to have a quick break.
There will be snacks and coffee and all that stuff
out starting at 3 o'clock.
Also during that time, if you need additional help
setting up, whether for questions on the Django section
or for the next section for JavaScript,
that's an additional time that we can use to help everybody.
And then for the last hour-ish, we'll
dive into visual regression testing.
So we're going to start this off with a quick overview
of testing.
I'm going to talk a little bit about why
consistent testing is important and what consistent testing
really means.
We're going to talk a little bit about software correctness,
because in order to test your software,
you have to have a good understanding of what
you're testing for and what correct software means.
Going to go through a few different approaches
for software testing.
And then we're going to dive into the anatomy of the test
and really all the different pieces
that you're going to be touching,
whether you're testing a back end or a front end.
So I think that when you approach testing your software,
it's really interesting because the time that you spend writing
tests for your software is not time that you're actually
delivering features or value directly to your users.
So it's a really interesting mindset
that you have to get yourself into of understanding
why testing is important and why, especially
for the longevity of a project, why it's really important
to write solid tests.
And specifically why regression tests
are important to make sure that all of your future users
are not encountering old bugs.
And that you're not getting into a cycle where
you break one thing and you fix the other thing
and that breaks something else.
And you just get into the cycle of your software not working.
So there are a bunch of different types of testing.
I'm not going to go through all of these.
We don't need to focus on all of them.
But if you start thinking about how to test your software,
you're going to come up with a bunch of different ways
to approach it.
And so one of my favorite ways of testing software
is using regression testing.
So again, really focusing on known bugs that are coming up.
And then visual regression testing,
which we'll get into why visual regression testing is
really cool in a minute.
And so one of the really interesting things
is the human brain is really terrible at distinguishing
between stimuli.
So if you take a look at these two images,
they're both screenshots of the PyCon website.
And even if you were to look at these full screen,
it would be really, really difficult for the human brain
to actually detect the differences between these two
screenshots.
But there is a difference.
And so it's a lot better to let a computer kind of handle
automatically detecting these changes
than to rely on a developer or a QA engineer or somebody
actually going through and looking at this themselves.
And so one of the huge gotchas with tests
is that tests only actually catch bugs
when you run your tests and you write tests.
And so knowing how to approach testing
and how to kind of pinpoint these different areas where
bugs can arise is super important
and can actually be a bit trickier than a lot of people
kind of expect.
So with that in mind, we know that we
need to have tests that are really fast so that we
can run them locally.
Maybe that's as we're developing,
doing test-driven development, before we commit,
before we push, before we release to production.
All these things, you need to run your tests before that.
We want to make sure that we can run them
across different browsers and platforms
and that we're not going to take the entire day for a test
to run.
Because if you have a test suite that takes 20 hours
to run in the cloud, you're not going
to be able to push out quick releases to your users.
And then you'll basically be in a holding pattern
for however long your tests have to run before you can,
hopefully before you push production.
So we know that our tests also need to be reliable.
We need to know that when they're given the same input
that they have the same output.
And one of the things that you don't want to get stuck in
is just constantly debugging your tests
or having tests that break.
So it's really important to put a lot of thought
into your architecture around that.
And thirdly, you want to make sure that your tests are really
modular and direct.
So in the same way that you want to think about having
functions that maybe do one single thing really,
really well in a few lines of code
and then kind of modularize it out from there,
you want to approach your tests in the same way.
If you have too many things that a single test is
trying to check, the whole test could fail
and you would not know exactly what line is failing
or what's happening there.
OK, so a lot of this I like to borrow from something
called formal verification.
I see a lot of parallels between formal verification
and software testing because the ultimate goals of both
are to make sure that your software is correct
and that your system is fault tolerant and stable.
And so one of the pillars of formal verification
is that no software is inherently correct.
And so there are two different ways
that we know software is correct.
And I pulled this quote from a Medium article
by somebody named Andrew Helver.
So these are not my words, but I really
kind of identified with it.
So one of the ways that we know that software is correct
is that the supreme deity of the universe
descends from the heavens and decrees
with all of the weight of objective truth
that a certain piece of software is correct.
But in reality, what happens a lot more frequently
is that we'll have a list of things
that we want the software to do and a certain amount of logic
to prove that the software does these things.
And as our software grows, this list
gets longer and longer and longer,
and it gets a lot harder to keep track of exactly what
our software is supposed to do and what having correct
software actually even means.
So now in the first scenario, as silly as it is,
we're talking about objective truths.
We're talking about things that are not going to be debated.
This sort of all-knowing, powerful knowledge
that everything that has been and everything that
will be known is right is not something
that we actually get in software.
And so functionality of our software can be subjective.
It can be very ill-defined, and it can certainly be relative.
So different approaches for testing.
So when you start to approach testing,
it's really common to come at it from one of two ways.
The first way is that we can say,
how do I know that the software is correct,
or how can I break this?
So this gets kind of fun.
So the first way, when you have something that's really,
really well-defined, you can take that logic
and kind of put it forth into a test.
So we know if we needed to test, say, multiplication,
we know that we have a very finite set of input,
whether that's a positive number, zero, a negative number,
and how that can interact with the same input,
multiplied together.
So we can say, I know that when I have 2 times 2,
that it's going to be 4.
When I have 2 times 3, it's going to be 6.
And we kind of have these very discrete set of rules
that we can apply.
But in this case, all of our edge cases
were sort of defined for us, which
is one of the really fun things about testing.
And one of the reasons why it's really important
is that you have to really start diving into what
those edge cases are.
And especially when you start testing front ends,
it's like, what happens if a user mashes on the Submit
button?
Those are not things that you necessarily think about,
but it's things that automated testing can help you with.
So a lot of what I've been saying right now
is kind of talking about software testing
in theory versus reality.
So in theory, you can have 100% test coverage,
and all of your tests are going to catch every single bug that
possibly exists in your code.
But the reality is that that's not going to be the case.
And even if you have 100% test coverage on paper,
doesn't actually mean that you're necessarily
catching all of the issues that could happen.
And so as an engineer, going back to this idea
that the time that you spend writing tests
is not delivering direct value to your customers,
or your clients, or whoever it is,
I know that the more time that I can spend writing really
useful, pointed tests is going to be a lot better than just
arbitrarily writing tests for the sake of writing tests.
So I'm going to talk about some of the things that you can do
just arbitrarily writing tests for the sake of writing tests.
So one of the ways that I've tried to optimize for this
is a theory that's popular in a lot of software design.
And that's that I really try to approach everything
from the user's perspective.
Because the user doesn't care if an API endpoint is broken.
They just care if they can't log into your app kind of thing.
So once we start framing what is important
for the end user, we can also frame how we approach testing.
And so regression tests, and especially
the visual regression tests, really kind
of frame that for the user.
And it gives us the ability to say, OK, here's my application.
If I don't directly test my authentication endpoints,
et cetera, if I just test my login page
and I know that my login page is failing
and the user sees an error that says error could not,
I wouldn't put this as a direct user facing message.
But if there is some sort of error that says cannot connect
to the server, like login failed,
and you know that the user's credentials are correct,
you can then pinpoint that, oh, there's
something else going on that is affecting my user
and give you a better idea from a really high level of what's
broken in your application without having
to write a million different integration
tests across your stack.
So I'm going to dive a little bit into the anatomy of the test.
I think I'm doing OK on time.
We're just a minute off.
So the anatomy of a test, you need
to have a test environment.
You need to have a testing structure.
You need to have some sort of assertion library
to be able to say, if these certain set of requirements
are met, then the test passes.
Otherwise, the test fails.
Some other really helpful things to have are mocks, spies,
and stubs.
So if you want to take different parts of your application
and abstract them away, so say you do want to test an API call,
but it's also relying on a third party API,
you might want to mock out that third party API
so that you're not necessarily relying
on an external services success, that you're only
relying on your code success.
And then especially once you get into the front end testing
world, you need some sort of browser
or browser-like environment.
So the process of testing consists of basically
three major steps.
So the first is that you want to generate, display, and watch
your test results.
So as you're running your test, it's
going to tell you exactly which test it's running through.
You can see the success and failure as you go.
Maybe if you realize that your first 10 tests are failing,
you just kill the process and try
to figure out what's going on instead of just letting
the whole process run.
As those tests are running, each test
that you're running through will compare and check
different assertions.
And we'll get into exactly what that means in a minute.
And then at the end, you want to generate code coverage reports
and really be able to see which areas of your application
you are testing and the success and failures
in those different areas.
OK.
So we're getting close to our first break.
We're going to make sure that everyone is as set up
as possible.
I do want to go through a little bit of how the workshop is
going to work.
So there is example code in the repository.
And so let me actually pull this up.
OK.
So there's a section in the README
about how you can use this repository.
And so basically, the way this is set up
is that there are two separate branches.
There's one for our Django walkthrough,
and there's one for our visual test walkthrough.
If you check out to the branch, you'll
be at the end of the tutorial.
So if you want to skip ahead and miss all the fun parts of learning
and exploring along the way, that's
what will happen if you check out the branch directly.
But if we take a look at this branch, basically,
all of the commits are kind of separated out by step.
So any of these commits where you see a number in them,
that corresponds back to the class notes, which
I'll show you in a second.
And so each branch also has a tag.
And so the tag is the very first commit of that walkthrough.
So there's a visual in it and a Django in it.
So if you want to walk through on your own,
that's where you'll want to check out.
And then in here, you can click directly to the steps.
Or there's also steps here in the content and notes.
So for example, for regression testing in Django,
if I click into this, this takes me
to the readme, which has a list of all the steps.
And then as you go through here, you can kind of follow along.
These are the steps that will correspond to the code
that we're going through.
And then everything links together
at the bottom between steps.
And so I know that I have a pretty wide variety of skill
levels in the room.
And so there are a few ways that you can approach this.
I am going to go through and explain everything.
I'm going to walk through all these steps.
I'm going to code it on my machine.
I'm going to demo it.
I'm going to explain it, all that stuff.
After I do that, it's then up to you in terms of how
you want to use your time.
You could check out from the Django init tag
and code everything yourself as well.
You could pick a certain commit and go off
in your own direction if you're like,
I really want to dive into more of how
this specific thing would work.
Or your other option is that you can actually just check out
commit by commit and run it on your machine locally
and not necessarily code everything yourself,
but just check out the commits and see
it running on your machine.
And then really just dive into the differences
in the code that was written by looking at the commits.
And to do that, I would say for anybody
who's not as familiar with GitHub,
there are some instructions about checking out
different commits in the ReadMe.
But you can also go in here and click on the commit ID.
And then it will show you a diff of the previous code that
was there.
In this case, there wasn't any other code here.
And then the new code that was added for these steps.
So hopefully that gives everybody a lot of options
that you can choose your own adventure on.
And at this point, we have a few TAs
that can help get people set up.
Yeah, just let us know if you need any help.
Just to be super clear, the only section
that we're worried about right now
is getting started and installing dependencies
for a Django application.
So if you haven't done that, check out subzero.
Follow these instructions.
Make sure you can get your virtual environment set up.
And then hopefully, once you get that set up,
you can run these three commands to get everything kicked off.
All right.
So I think it's probably about time
to call it on attempting to get environment set up,
because I want to make sure that we're
using the rest of our time for at least me to go through
and work through all this with everyone.
I'm going to go through everything now,
so I think this is going to be a lot of watching me do things.
But at the end of this, if you haven't gotten your environment
set up, it really is your call if you want
to try to keep working on that.
But otherwise, I suggest that you find a friendly face
that you might be sitting next to who perhaps has this running
that you can work through it all with them
once we get to that point.
Any questions before we dive in?
OK.
All right.
So I have just run through all of the same initialization
on my machine.
So I've run the migrate, the create superuser,
and I'm now running the server.
Well, I'm not running the server.
That's a lie.
I'm not running the server.
If you go to that URL, you should then
see this example regression testing boilerplate.
If you see this, everything is working correctly.
We're not actually going to do a whole lot of interacting
directly with the front end of this application.
We're going to go through how we're approaching testing
different pieces of our Django application.
Let's see.
So right off the bat, if we run Python manage by test,
you'll see that there are currently not
any tests in this repository.
It's not finding anything.
So the first thing that we're going to do
is start diving into adding a test case.
Hopefully, this is large enough for everyone.
I think if I make it too much larger,
it kind of doesn't fit on my screen.
So if you need to follow along with the repository
on your local machine, you can do that too.
All right.
So first, we're going to create a new file.
So let's see.
So I have my editor open to the source directory.
So you can see that here.
So the tree that you're seeing of all of our code
is actually within that source directory already.
All right.
So inside of our regression testing boilerplate,
we are going to add a file called test.py.
Let's see.
So the first thing that we're going to go through and test
is something fairly straightforward.
We're going to test that the page is actually just rendering.
So when we go to this view, that we
are able to retrieve the file from the index of our website
and that we are getting a 200 and that this page renders.
So to do so, we are going to grab not that.
Don't have two minutes right now.
VS Code.
Sorry.
So we're going to say, let's grab.
There's a sort of base test case that we can grab.
And as everyone knows, typing in front of 50 people
is when you make the most typos.
So that's fun.
So we're going to grab our base test case.
We're also going to go ahead and grab
something called reverse that's basically
going to let us retrieve the view based
on the name of the view.
So what we're seeing here in our Django application,
this page is called home.
So we can basically pass home to reverse and get the URL for it.
So let's make our first test.
Again, we're just testing that the page is opening.
So I'm going to naively call this the page open test case.
We are going to extend from the base class test case, which
is going to give us a lot of mix-ins.
It's going to give us a lot of those assertions
that we talked about earlier.
That's all going to be baked into this test case.
So within this, we can now start defining basically
different methods on this test case
that will represent different isolated functions that
are going to be called against our class.
So these are the places that I mentioned earlier
we want to make sure that these stay pretty small.
Because when one of these tests fails,
it will say, hey, function one failed.
And sure, it will point you to an exact line.
But if you're testing too much in one of those tests,
it's going to get really confusing to try to actually
pinpoint any of your errors.
All right, so we first want to make sure
that I would say that our home page exists.
We're going to make sure that this page can be rendered.
So we'll make our function for that.
Again, we're going to retrieve our URL from reverse.
Like I mentioned, this page is called home.
I know that there are some people here who aren't
necessarily fluent with Django.
I unfortunately don't have a whole lot of time
to dive into that and where exactly all this is set up.
If that's something you want to learn more about,
come find me afterwards or during one of the breaks.
And I can show you all that.
All right, so the next thing we're going to do
is actually test to make sure that we
can make a call to this URL.
And so baked into this test case,
we have something called the clients.
So we can run a get on our clients
using the URL that we just retrieved.
So we've gotten the URL based on the name of this page
that we have set up.
And then we call a get to that URL
to make sure that we have all this information.
And so at this point, I'm just going to run this test.
And my auto formatter is going to change everything
I just typed.
So I'm going to run this test and see what actually we're
getting back from R. I'm actually
that's probably just going to print out an object.
So I'm going to also run dir on R
so that we can see all of the different methods
that we can get from it.
Cool, okay, so now we've just run this test.
We have a response object that we have retrieved back
from calling this URL.
We can already see that our status code is 200,
which is good, 200 okay.
That means that the page is rendering,
everything is going normally.
And then if we look at the dir of this object,
we can see that we have a bunch of things
that we can call on it.
And so this is where it gets really interesting
that you can kind of dive into more specifics
of this request.
But for right now, basically what we want to make sure
is that when this page renders, we get a 200 okay.
So now if we come back here,
I'm going to take out my print statements.
And at this point we can run an assert.
So again, baked into our test case class,
we now have something called,
I'm going to use assert equal.
And I want to make sure that the status code
that we have retrieved is equal to 200.
Hopefully I typed all that right.
Hey, all right.
So it ran one test and everything is successful.
So one of the things that you'll also notice
that you kind of get out of the box when you run this test
is that it's already kind of baked into Django,
that it's going to create a test database.
And then it's going to destroy that test database for you.
So that's just kind of one of the niceties
that you get batteries included with Django.
All right, so let's see what else we have on this page.
Not a whole lot going on in this application quite yet.
So we have our homepage and then we have our about page,
which apparently we don't have.
So let's actually, let's practice a little bit
of test-driven development here.
So let's say that we know that we want to add an about page.
So we're going to write our test.
And actually I'm going to do myself a favor.
I'm going to copy this code
because we're going to do basically the same thing
for our about page as we did for our homepage.
So now basically all I've done is I've added a new method
to our page open test case.
And I now have a method to test that the homepage exists
and that the about page exists.
So now if I run this, interesting.
So it's not actually telling us anything at this point, right?
So we're running this, it's saying that it ran two tests,
but we know that this test case should be failing,
which is sort of interesting.
Let's see.
I'm actually curious.
So this whole thing is a lie
because that's the joy of live demos
and coding in front of people.
So the reason why that about page didn't work before
is because my server wasn't running.
So that's fun.
So if I go back to this page,
we can actually see that the about page does exist
and that's why all my tests were still passing.
So now that's not what I want.
So now if I go back, I'm gonna kill my server
and if we go back to our code,
we now know that our about page does exist already.
We're gonna do the same thing for a new page
that doesn't actually exist.
So I'm gonna do this for our contact page
and then hopefully we can actually see a test
that properly fails.
Hey, okay.
So we can now see that we have a failing test,
which is what I was going for.
So we get this nice trace back.
It tells us exactly which method failed.
So again, that's helping us pinpoint what's going wrong
and then we can see that we are getting an error
that says no contact found,
contact is not a valid view or pattern name.
So I do kind of want to pull over to the readme real quick
because I wanted to kind of point out a few different things
that we have kind of right out of the bat
or like right out of the gate for our test case.
So there are a few different built-in test cases
depending on exactly what you're trying to test.
So there's a simple test case, a transaction test case.
If you're specifically dealing with database transactions,
live server test case,
there's a bunch of different ones
that you kind of have built in.
So I definitely recommend kind of exploring
and figuring out what efficiencies you can gain
from using the built-in tests.
But I also wanted to point out some of the main asserts
that we have that basically come from unit tests
that are built in.
So asserting equal, not equal, true, false,
it's really important to kind of rely
on these built-in assertions to make sure
that you're properly tying into your test runner
and making sure that you're not relying
on the actual Python assert statement
because there are some weird things that happen
if you use the Python assert statement
and not one of these built-in functions.
So these are just a few examples
of what you can kind of rely on that's built in.
Cool.
All right, so now we have a nice failing test.
So our goal here is going to be that we can actually
fix this test case and get this test to work.
So now we know that we have these two pages,
we need to add a contact page.
So the first thing that we're gonna wind up doing
is adding a URL path.
To our URL patterns, that's usually where I start
when I go to add a new page.
So we can put this anywhere in this array,
but we're going to add a path for contact.
Just kind of as a practice, I like having the slash
at the end of all of my URLs just to keep things consistent.
And then we're gonna do something similar to this,
so I'll just copy it and paste it.
So we are going to want to create a contact page,
and this is where we set that name
that we use for the reverse function.
Cool, I think this looks good.
I don't think I've misspelled anything
or typed it wrong yet.
All right, so next thing that we're going to want to do
is actually create this contact page.
So if we go to our views,
I'm just gonna put it in this high level views.
You can see here that we already have our home page
and our about page.
For a lot of Django applications,
you're gonna wind up splitting these out,
but for this example, we kind of have everything
in one place just to make it a little bit easier to deal with.
So we are going to create our contact page class.
So we're gonna do the same thing
that these other ones are doing.
We're gonna create a template view,
and then give it the template name.
We're gonna make this a contact page.
So basically what we've done so far
is we have created the URL for it.
We've pointed it to a view.
Now we've created our view,
and we need to actually provide the HTML content
for this page.
So if we go back and look,
and my very small sidebar,
we can take a look at this templates directory
and we can see that we already have
a few other HTML pages in here.
So we're going to add our contact.html page.
And this one I actually am going to
just kind of copy paste in.
The actual code that goes here
does not necessarily matter at this point.
We just know that this is going to be
a page that is going to render something
that we have just given it.
So if we go back here,
I think that everything is set up correctly.
So even before having to run my server,
I was able to run my test and see
that I'm now getting back a 200 from this page.
Just to make sure that we know what is going on
and know that I can still type the word run server.
We can now go back here.
I haven't actually added a link to get to the contact page,
but I can go here and go to my contact page,
which is not rendering.
So this is a pretty common approach
for testing your views.
Certain things that view testing is really important for
is making sure that people have
proper permissions to view pages.
So if you have an admin portal or certain pages
that are only controlled by somebody
who is a super admin or admin of a site,
it's important to make sure that those pages
remain protected.
So doing things like testing as an unauthenticated user
that I get either a 404 or a 401 response from those pages,
that's a really common way to use these view tests.
Does anybody have any questions?
Cool.
All right, so I'm gonna close out all of my files
that I was using there.
Collapse that back up.
So the next section that we are going to focus on testing
is testing models.
So if you're following along, this is step two.
Yeah.
All right, so now we can set up an example model test.
So let's go ahead and dive into some of the existing models.
So if we check out here,
I can't make that any smaller.
So if we look at this, this is our profile models page.
We have a base profile that we're setting up.
Again, we kind of have these like built-in classes
that we're pulling in from Django itself
that are letting us kind of scaffold out a lot of this code.
So we have a basic user model.
We have a slug that's going to allow us
to get the user's profile, like page URL.
The user's gonna have a picture, a bio,
and we're gonna make sure that the user's email
is verified before they are able to sign in.
And so we're gonna default that to false.
I think that is pretty much the important things in here.
So let's write some tests for our user model.
Let's see.
So we already have our page open test case.
Let's actually keep this a little bit more modular.
So because we're writing tests specifically
for our profile module
and not for the application in general,
we can actually go ahead and use our test file
that is inside of our profile module.
So I know it's a little bit hard to see
because the screen is a little bit small,
but this test file is inside of the profiles directory.
All right.
So some of the things that I like to test for this
is just making sure that you can create objects
for different models.
And again, we have a few things from Django
that we're going to kind of build off of.
So if we go back here and look at,
actually it isn't mentioned there, that's a lie.
So somewhere along the lines,
this is registered as our user model.
So that is actually something that we can kind of tie into.
So I'm gonna grab our get user model.
There we go.
That's the joys of linting folks.
I'm also going to import our model itself.
This is way harder than I expected it to be.
Okay.
And then basically we can say,
we're gonna set our user model to this.
So this is one of the helpful things
about these little pop-ups that keep getting in our way.
So get user model is going to return the user model
that is actively set up for this project.
Cool.
Okay, that is all looking pretty good.
So now we're gonna set up some test cases for user model.
So I'm just gonna call this user test case.
As your application grows,
you'll figure out different kind of naming conventions
that you want to use.
A lot of times things will start out
maybe a little bit more generic
and you'll kind of increase the specificity
of the names of all of your classes and methods and whatnot.
So what we're gonna do here is we're gonna start tying
into some of the life cycle methods of a test case.
So one of the things that you can do
is you can have a setup command.
So if you want to kind of like create different resources
to use while running your tests,
you can do that in this setup command.
And that will automatically take precedence
over all of your other tests that are going to run.
So basically it will go through and say,
do I have a setup function?
Do I need to create any objects?
Yes, this has a setup function.
I'm gonna create whatever it's asking me to
and then that resource will kind of be available
in the rest of your test methods that you're running.
Okay, so let's say I want to,
I'm gonna use get or create
just in case this user has already been created.
Okay, so now in my setup command,
I am getting or creating this user object
and then I wanna just test to make sure
that we have different attributes
that are defined on this user model.
So I'm gonna say, we're gonna test our base profile
because that is what we are,
that is the model that we have set up as our user model.
It is possible to have like a bunch of different user models.
So you might have one that's different for admins
or different like user hierarchies of your app.
So I like to be really specific about
which user I'm testing.
Okay, so now I'm gonna test
that our base profile can be created.
So in here, since we already have this set up,
all I have to do is actually retrieve that object.
So I'm gonna say user.objects.get.
It's gonna be the same email.
So I retrieve that user.
And then again, let's just see,
make sure that we have all the things that we wanna have.
So I'm gonna print out our object
and then I'm gonna print out a dir of that object.
So now if we go through and run our tests,
cool, I have four tests that are running.
You'll notice that this test is not yet failing
because we don't have any asserts in it.
We're just able to kind of like run it
and print stuff out and kind of see what we've got.
So I'm gonna kind of pick out just a couple of things
that I think might be important on our user model.
One of the things that's always super important
for a user model to have is an ID.
So we wanna make sure that that exists.
We also wanna make sure maybe that when we create an object
that the values that we're providing to create that object
are getting set properly on it.
So because this is a pretty simple example right now,
the only thing that we're setting on the user object
is its email.
And so that might be one thing that we wanna make sure
that the email gets set properly
as we're like asking it to set the email.
All right, so we've seen what that user object looks like.
So let's just say,
we wanna assert that the user has an ID.
We want to assert that the email address
that we have provided and the email address
of the created object are the same.
So I'm gonna say that is equal to u.email.
And really you can kind of go through
and if you look back at the user model,
I would definitely try to make sure
that all of these things exist.
One of the things that I might do is assert
that when I create the user object
that the email verified setting is set to false
because that's really important.
Maybe it's part of our business logic
that a user has to click a link in an email
to make sure that they're using a valid email address first.
So this is something that's probably important
to make sure gets that correctly.
So now hopefully,
oh, this is why you're at test.
So we want is not none.
We definitely want them to have a user ID.
So let's see.
So user doesn't have an attribute email verified.
So let me look back at what this object actually looks like.
Yeah.
Huh.
Well, I'm not gonna dwell on this necessarily
because I don't wanna debug why this isn't working
at this moment.
But just know that that's definitely just something else
that you can kind of keep an eye out for
in making sure that you're testing
all these different pieces.
Yeah, because I think I only have about,
according to schedule,
I only have about 15 minutes left for this section.
So I'm gonna keep trucking.
All right.
So going back to a little bit more kind of like in depth
on testing our views,
sometimes it's going to be important to test
more than just the status code that we received.
Sometimes we're gonna want to make sure
that different elements are appearing on the page,
that there is a link to get to the signup page,
that kind of stuff.
And so we have a little bit more information
from those views that is sometimes helpful
to kind of dive into.
Let's see.
So if we go back here and look at what else we can get
from our response objects.
So let's look at,
let's just look at the dir of R again
and see what else we have here.
Hopefully I put everything back
and everything's passing.
Okay.
So as we kind of dive into this,
one of the things that can be super important to look at
is content, which is split between two lines.
So just out of curiosity,
let's see, not caps lock.
Let's see exactly what this looks like.
Ooh yeah.
So this is cool.
We actually get all of the HTML
that is going to render on the page.
And something that gets important
when you're looking at making sure
that your view code is working
is you can make sure that,
say you have different variables
that are getting rendered in your template,
you can make sure that those variables
are getting interpolated and either calculated
or retrieved correctly.
So for example, I'm not gonna dive into this right now,
but one of the things I would say to test is,
say you have a user profile page
that displays their name and their email address on it.
I would make sure that I'm retrieving the user model
correctly and that those values
are getting displayed properly by asserting
that the first name gets displayed in the page
and is actually present where I expect it to be
within all of this HTML.
So again, you can kind of dive really, really deeply
into exactly what parts of this you wanna test,
but some of the really simple ways to approach it
is just to make sure that a string exists in that content.
So let's just say,
let's see, this is gonna differ a little bit from the notes,
but just kind of going along with following
those best practices in terms of making sure
that our tests are really kind of like modular and atomic.
I'm gonna add a new method to say test home page title.
I think it's the title on this page.
Cool.
All right, so I can kind of do the same thing.
And again, I would suggest always taking a look at your code
and figuring out what you can move into a helper module.
If you have noticed a bit,
this is gonna get really redundant really, really quickly.
So perhaps you have a method that gets your response for you
and you just pass it the name kind of thing.
But yeah, again, see what kinds of patterns kind of emerge
as you're writing your own tests
to kind of find out how you can optimize this for yourself.
So now we can basically just say,
an interesting one is assert in.
And so you can use assert in HTML,
which gives you some other kind of like helper methods
for actually like targeting different pieces of HTML
based on different selectors and whatnot,
which we won't dive into right now.
But we can basically say,
I want to make sure that the word home appears
on my homepage.
So the user knows that they are on the homepage.
Hopefully this works.
Cool.
And so again, not gonna do it now,
but I would encourage you to kind of like figure out exactly
what exists on these pages that you wanna dive into.
Let's see.
How many more steps do I have?
I wanna make sure that we try to stick to time
as much as possible.
So we've got a little bit more on views and forms left.
Okay.
So I'm actually, I am going to skip over 3B,
but I'm gonna point it out here really quickly.
So 3B, we were basically going to like walk through
adding a variable that gets computed
and then rendered into our template.
So if we were to go into say our contact page,
we can add a way to kind of set this variable
within our context that will be rendered on our page.
This was just a simple example.
So I just set it to two plus two very arbitrarily.
So I could show that this was being interpolated.
So this gets calculated.
It gets set into this two plus two variable.
And then inside of our template,
we can then go through and actually render this
as a template variable.
So that's what these kind of curly braces mean
is that this is actually interpolated as a variable.
And then we can go back through and edit our test.
I think in this example,
I replaced contact with two plus two, but yeah.
Basically this section was going to be just testing
that variable gets interpolated
and then exists inside of our content.
But yeah, we're gonna skip ahead.
Okay, so next up is testing forms.
So this is one that gets, I think,
a little bit more complex
because this is where we get to deal with user input
and users like to break things
and do things that we don't expect them to.
So this is definitely one of the other areas
that I like focusing on different inputs
that I wouldn't necessarily expect to be rendered.
And we'll talk a little bit more
about how you can approach automating that as well.
All right, let's see.
So trying to see, do we have a user form?
We do have a user form, cool.
I don't know why my linter is sad right now.
Hopefully all of these things are gonna be okay.
All right, so if we already have our user form
that was already set up for us,
we're gonna do something similar
where we wanna make sure that our data
gets properly filled into our form.
So say for example, going back to that user profile page idea,
if we have a user object and they can say,
go in there and change their information,
edit their email, password,
well maybe not password in this, but bio,
anything that they would necessarily wanna change.
The thing that we're gonna test for is making sure
that our existing user model gets filled into our form
properly.
So we have this form here already.
I'm gonna keep this file open.
I'm going to go back to our profile tests.
Again, as your application grows,
you might separate these out into like a models test
and a views test and a forms test.
That's a pretty common pattern that you'll see.
But for right now, I'm actually just gonna go ahead
and extend off of this user test case
because our application is still pretty small.
So I'm gonna test that our form is valid.
So I'll call this test valid user form.
Kind of similar to what we did before,
we are going to want to retrieve our user object.
But at this point, I'm actually going to go ahead
and create a new object that has maybe a little bit
more information set on it.
So I'm actually going to, I'm gonna copy and paste this
for time.
Okay, so I'm gonna create a user object for Leia.
I'm going to set up a data object.
So I'm gonna say my name is set to my user's name.
And then I'm going to create my form,
which I think I will have to add an import for that.
I'll have to double check.
So I'm gonna say user form and I'm gonna pass it
my data object.
Let's make sure.
This is probably going to fail.
So I'm gonna say from forms, import.
User form.
Yeah.
Okay, that should work.
I don't know why it was sad about it.
And again, I'm just gonna make sure that all of this
is working before I get too far off.
Create takes one positional argument, but two are given.
Huh, oh, that's because I didn't.
There we go.
Okay, so now we can see here that we actually have
our form that is rendering.
If we take a look at this form,
it's a fairly straightforward form.
All it has set up right now is a name field.
So you can see, you can start to see some of the things
that Django gives you out of the box as well.
So we have this label for ID name.
We have an input field with name, value is set to layer,
max length required ID, all those things are kind of
already set on there for us.
So the thing that we're gonna test for right now
is just making sure that this form is valid.
So if we look at this form, the things that are required
on it are just the name.
And so since we've pulled out our user object,
initialized our form with this data,
we just basically wanna say that the form is valid
and that it has a name set.
So there are a couple of ways that you could go about this.
You could test directly that the name is set,
but what I'm really worried about is that the form is valid
and that the user will be able to submit a change.
So, I'm gonna add,
basically just using this helper method,
calling from the form directly to say that it's valid
and that that is true.
And I'll clean up after myself.
Cool, so this test is passing.
All right, let's see.
Where I'm at.
So other things that we wanna make sure that we test
are the things that users can break.
And so if we're setting requirements for a user,
we wanna make sure that those requirements
are actually being enforced.
And again, I'm just trying to be cognizant of time
because I know we still have a lot of stuff
for the actual visual testing part.
But this is one of those places where it's really important
to kind of like dive in and identify your edge cases.
So say that you have a user bio
and the user bio has a length requirement of 200 characters.
I would kind of test those boundaries around the edge cases.
So like testing with 199 characters,
with 200 characters, with 201 characters,
and making sure that I'm kind of like getting the errors
that I want on either end of it.
And then I also like to go for like extremes.
So like if somebody put in like 10,000 characters,
just to make sure that like there's not some sort
of weird bug where it's like, oh, well, we made sure
that it was less than 300 characters.
We rejected 201 to 300 characters,
but somehow somebody can put in like 10,000 characters.
So those are kind of like the fun pieces that you'll see
that you can dive into.
Also, I'm gonna skip coding out that part because of time.
So, oh, I think I have a broken link in my,
yeah, I have a broken link in the notes, by the way.
Testing forms, I think, refers back to itself
and doesn't let you continue.
All right, so one of the things that I did wanna kind
of leave you with for the Django testing section,
specifically, is a bunch of different testing tools.
So I highly recommend checking all these out,
especially if you're using Django specifically.
Django web test is really, really helpful.
Factory Boy is really helpful.
You can have fixtures that basically allow you
to like generate a bunch of different objects
for your tests.
So instead of having to go through
and like create a bunch of objects
and like having a bunch of stuff like hard coded
into your tests and like a bunch of data objects
hard coded into your tests, this is really helpful
with like spinning up a bunch of different objects.
I'm a huge fan of PyTest.
So everything so far has been using the built-in unit test
which Django ships with and works like out of the box.
I think I had a couple of people on the survey say
that they were really interested in PyTest specifically,
as well as PyTest is like standalone.
I'm a huge fan, definitely talk to me about that later
if you're interested and check it out
if you're trying to write tests for Django.
And then one of my favorite libraries is called Hypothesis.
And basically it allows you to like write parameterized tests
and generate a bunch of different information
to really kind of like ease the difficulty
of creating test data.
So in this example of like testing the user bio,
sure I could probably come up with a bio
or find like a lorem ipsum that I could copy and paste
and use as like my 200 character bio
or my 10,000 character bio.
But you can actually tell Hypothesis
to generate these things for you.
So Hypothesis will be able to generate like names
and addresses and data that looks realistic
but is not necessarily something that you have to hard code.
And one of the other really, really cool things
about this too is that by using a library
that's kind of randomly generating data for your tests
that you're running,
you can also sometimes find super weird edge cases.
So I have a story about that
but I'm not gonna go into it now.
If anybody's really interested in a really weird bug
that broke a car radio in Mazda 6s,
come talk to me.
But yeah, so it's just, it's kind of a cool way
to be able to test a bunch of different input,
test different address links and name links
and different character encodings
and stuff that you wouldn't necessarily think to test.
And it kind of handles it all for you.
And so I think I tried to touch on kind of pointing out
a lot of these best practices as we were going through it.
But again, modularizing your tests is super important.
Being able to kind of pinpoint which areas
that you're testing is also really important.
Running your tests is probably one
of the most important parts.
Because if you write tests and you don't run them,
one of the things I see a lot is that people write tests,
nobody runs them, somebody tries to run them
at some point a month down the road and they're all broken
and then nobody wants to fix the broken tests
and then you don't write tests anymore.
So running your tests is important.
If you can have a continuous integration server set up,
we'll dive into a little bit more
of what that looks like at the end.
But continuous integration is kind of the best way to do it
because you can run it on a server,
somebody else's machine, you're not worried
about configuration, everything is running
in the same environment and it can kind of run
without everybody thinking about it.
And you can enforce that for pull requests or merge requests
and actually make sure that your tests are passing
before merging code together or before pushing code
out to production.
I also highly recommend checking out using local Git hooks.
So there are ways to basically tell Git
to run certain commands before allowing a user
to either commit to a certain branch
or push to a remote repository.
Just make sure that all your tests are passing locally
before you go and push it off to somebody else.
And so one of the things you'll see oftentimes is like,
sure, you should make sure that your tests are passing
on your machine, but then once you push
to a continuous integration server,
it's gonna run on like a bunch of different machines,
especially with front end tests,
making sure that you're testing cross browser
and all that stuff.
That's something that's really nice to automate
and kind of like let CI handle.
And then of course, like set meaningful benchmarks.
Having 100% code coverage does not mean
that your software is bug free.
And so really just being able to like focus
on the really important parts of your code
is definitely important.
And then find a standard and stick to it.
Be willing to iterate, find the things
that are gonna work best for your team and for yourself
because making testing a more positive experience
is gonna encourage you and your teammates to write tests.
So if everybody hates writing tests
or thinks that certain things are like,
have too much boilerplate or are really difficult,
nobody's gonna wanna actually write the test.
All right, at this point,
we are just a couple of minutes over, which is good.
So we're gonna have a break.
We'll resume around 3.30.
So feel free, go grab coffee, snacks, water.
If you have anything remaining for phase two
for the visual regression testing that you wanna set up,
you can use this time to do so.
If you wanna dive into some of the Django stuff on your own,
again, this is kind of your time to use until 3.30.
All right, I think we are ready to get started.
Okay, so this is gonna be like a huge gear shift change.
This is something completely different
than we were doing 30 minutes ago,
which is part of the fun.
Okay, so what I have going here is I have my,
this bottom terminal I was running yarn start.
This is basically starting up my web application.
I can go to this URL and it will open in the wrong window.
And this is just a really silly example React application.
One of the really important takeaways from this
is that this approach for testing
is meant to be like really, really, really agnostic.
You do not have to be using React.
You do not have to be using
any sort of JavaScript framework.
You can apply the same mentality for testing
and same testing practices to a Django front end
or whatever, it could be a static site.
It really doesn't matter what you're testing.
It's very, very, very agnostic.
But in this example, we just have a React application
because that was a little bit easier
for me to throw together.
And let's see, what else do we have here?
So I've run all of my dependency installation.
Everything is set up.
I can now run a couple of things.
So I can run generate golden, which will now work.
An important thing to note is that you do have to have
your server running in order to run this.
Basically, we'll dive into exactly what's going on here,
but there are calls in the generate golden screenshots
and the testing that will actually call your web server.
So typically, you'll be testing against something
that's already deployed or that's kind of already running.
But when I'm testing locally right now,
I do have to have both of these processes running.
So I was just kind of running a sanity check here,
making sure that my generate golden was running.
And then if I run yarn test, that should also work.
Okay, cool.
Let's kind of hold my breath there for a second.
Okay, so let's see.
I'm actually gonna switch back.
I have a little bit more left in the slides
that I want to kind of go over first as well.
So there are a bunch of different ways
to approach visual regression testing.
If you have done anything in the JavaScript world,
especially with testing,
you probably will have heard of something
called snapshot testing.
Now snapshot testing is really interesting.
So if you remember when we were going through
our Django application,
how we basically were able to render a page
and get back the actual rendered HTML
that the browser had,
like with all of our template variables interpolated.
You can do something similar in the JavaScript world
where you can tell it to give you a snapshot.
And the snapshot is going to be a code representation
of what that page looks like.
But again, as you saw when we printed out
that big long HTML content,
there's not really a whole,
it's not as easy for a human to go through
and look at that and say like,
yeah, my snapshot is fine.
Everything looks good.
There's a lot more that you have to put into it manually
when you're doing those things.
So being able to identify different areas of the page
that you want to have rendered,
you're really missing out a lot of
like the visual side of things.
So you can take a snapshot and re-render it,
which we'll also talk about later.
But actually being able to go in and have a screenshot
that humans can look at
and make sure that everything looks good
is really important.
Okay, so the way that we're gonna dive into this is
when you approach testing,
a lot of times you'll have a set of data or information
that you know is correct or that should be correct.
And so whether that is screenshots or snapshots
or pieces of data, whatever it is,
we kind of have this idea of
what I like to call golden images.
So our golden images can be anything from mock-ups
that maybe a designer has provided to us
and we're trying to match as closely as possible.
Or it can be previous screenshots of the application
when everything was kind of in like an approved,
like solid testable state.
So we'll have golden images
and then our kind of current screenshots of the application
that we'll be using.
We're also gonna use an image diffing library.
There is a really neat cool called resemble.js
that basically allows you to take two images
and generate a bunch of different information on them,
including like a percent match between the two images.
And then it will actually also give you back
a rendered image of the two overlaid
with highlighted areas of where they're different.
And so this is gonna be one of the really key components
that we use and it's really specific for screenshot testing
that allows us to kind of do this.
So running visual regression tests
really relies on having a browser
or a browser-like environment.
And so previously visual regression testing
was tied to using an actual browser
using something like Selenium or Phantom.js.
There are now really interesting things
called headless browsers
that you don't actually need like an interface
to interact with it.
It's basically like interacting with a web browser
over strictly an API and not an interface,
which is kind of an interesting thing
to kind of wrap your head around.
I didn't do that on purpose.
Okay.
But yeah, so it makes it really, really easy
to programmatically interact with it.
It is also not 2018, which is kind of funny.
Since 2018, visual regression testing got a lot easier.
There is a library called Puppeteer.
It is maintained by Google,
but it makes interacting with headless Chrome
really, really, really easy.
So if you start looking into different techniques
for visual regression testing,
I really highly recommend just like sticking with Puppeteer
and headless Chrome and really just saving yourself
like the pain and suffering of dealing with stuff
like Selenium and Phantom.js.
There's also a lot of like built-in abilities
to interact with the browser
as well as to interact with your code.
So a lot of the same tools that you have
as a developer using like the in-browser developer tools
to debug your code,
you also have access to those things in Puppeteer.
Okay.
So now we're gonna switch over to kind of like the details
of how we're actually approaching this.
So like I mentioned, we're gonna use Puppeteer.
We're gonna use resemble.js,
which is our visual image comparison.
And then we're gonna use a test runner
and assertion library.
This is really up to you with whatever you want to use.
In this, we're using just an enzyme,
but it's really whatever you're most comfortable with
or whatever you wanna dive in and learn.
Those are very like up to you.
So those are like our key dependencies.
In the package JSON in your example project,
there's a bunch of other stuff
for like the boilerplate itself.
But these are really like the key players
for the agnostic part of our testing.
And so what I've done here is I've basically taken
the important parts of the code
and put them into the slides just because I think that
based on the survey that I got,
a lot of people were a lot less familiar with JavaScript.
I wanted to be able to kind of highlight these things
individually before like throwing everybody into code
and moving too quickly through that.
So the first thing we have to do is create our directories.
So we basically are going to have a golden directory
where we store all of our golden screenshots,
a screenshot directory where we store
like all the live versions of whatever test run
that we're going through.
And then a separate directory where we will output
those visual diffs of the two images overlaid
with the like highlighted differences.
Okay, so once we start our tests,
the same way that we kind of had this idea
of a setup function in our Django tests,
we have a similar kind of concept in our JavaScript tests.
So we can say either before all or before each test,
we want to kind of set up whatever environments
or dependencies that we want to use.
So for this, we're going to basically launch
a new web browser using puppeteer.launch,
and then we will create a new page
just using browser.newpage.
And so again, if you've worked with other
like browser emulators and libraries,
this is often a lot more difficult.
The API for puppeteer is really, really, really clean.
So this is all you've got to do to set up a browser page.
Okay, so we have basically a helper function
that's gonna let us navigate through our application
and also take a screenshot of that page as we've navigated.
So this is a function that takes in our page object
that we created from our setup function,
and then whatever route that we want to navigate to.
So this is a straightforward example.
This is directly navigating to a page.
We're not interacting with the page quite yet.
We're just going to be able to kind of like navigate
directly through the URL for different pages.
So we take that route.
You don't have to specify a route for your index view.
So we give it kind of a default file name,
and then we're gonna save our screenshot
based on the route name so that we can easily identify it
as a person looking at these images later.
So right now, this is hard-coded for our application
that's running on localhost.
It takes in the route.
You can call page.screenshots,
tell it the path where you want to save it,
and then we have a compare screenshot function
that we can then call
to retrieve our additional information on it.
One thing to note is that there are a lot of options
on how your screenshot is taken.
So you can kind of control if you only want to take
a screenshot of the page that's actually shown
within the browser viewport.
You can take a screenshot of the whole page.
A bunch of different stuff there
that's worth kind of like looking into the docs
and exactly how you want to set this up.
Okay.
So we have a helper function
that's going to process our screenshot.
And so this is just some JavaScript
that is retrieving the images off of our file system.
So this is just a way to basically run
a couple of parallel tasks and wait for them to come back.
So saying here are two images, read them,
and we can continue after they have both returned.
And then we destructure them off of that object.
So we read the two files out.
We now have our image1 and image2.
So compare is a built-in function to resemble js.
This is the programmatic API
for something that I'll also show you in a second.
But basically it takes in our two images,
some optional data, and that's just like a configuration file.
And then basically waits for this information to come back,
gives us back our image output,
and then also gives us back
something called our mismatch percentage.
So our goal is for a mismatch percentage to be,
this is actually wrong.
It's right in the code, I promise.
We actually want our mismatch percentage to be zero
because we want there to not be any difference
between our two screenshots.
And in the case that there is a difference
between our two screenshots,
that's where a human kind of has to come in and say like,
yes, I approve this change or no, I don't.
Okay.
So this is two separate screenshots
of the React application
that you could have running on your machine locally.
They have very slightly differing things.
You can kind of see that the images
are slightly different sizes.
In the image on the right,
the dinosaur images are slightly larger than the other one.
And so when we run this through the visual diff,
this is actually what we get.
So this would give us back a mismatch percentage
of greater than zero.
And it actually goes through and kind of highlights
and shows us exactly what pieces of the page have changed.
So you can see where your differences are.
And so kind of wrapping up this whole flow,
you run through your tests,
you take screenshots of all of your pages,
you can then compare the current screenshots
that you've taken against your golden images.
And then if you're getting any sort of mismatch percentage,
you can alert the user and say,
hey, this test failed, these screenshots don't match.
You should go check out this specific file
to see if those are changes
that you want to approve or disapprove.
And then at that point you can say,
yes, this is fine.
Generate my new golden screenshots
and keep everything up to date.
Or no, this change was not intentional.
There's something actually wrong.
We need to go back and fix this
before we can regenerate our screenshots.
And so some really good examples of this are,
say for example, you have a specific button
on your login page and the decision is like,
we're gonna make the login button purple.
But you accidentally change all the buttons to purple.
So this is something that would be able to catch that
and then you could say, okay,
we want to only change the button on the login screen,
regenerate that golden screenshot,
but the other ones are broken, we need to fix those.
Okay.
So now we're gonna switch over to a little bit of code.
Okay, so I do want to just kind of go through
and point out the different things
that are in this boilerplate at this point.
So I have opened up the code directory
and the visual regression testing directory.
I am on the visual init commit.
And let's see what we've got.
So we have our source directory.
All of our tests live in this, ironically,
Dunder tests directory,
which should feel familiar to some of us.
And then we have our directory where we store our diffs.
There are probably already some,
there are some directories in here from future steps
that we're gonna go through.
But basically we have our index page,
which is rendering sort of oddly in here.
We have our golden screenshots.
And then we have, oh wait, sorry.
This is our diffs, that's why it looks funny.
And then we have our two original golden screenshots.
And so currently, I haven't made any changes
to this application.
So my index and my, sorry, my golden index
and my screenshot index are identical right now.
All right, give me one second to pull up.
Okay.
So basically everything that we went through in the slides
has already been implemented in this code.
So all of our helpers are living in this helpers file.
We have these diff options, which are super interesting.
So I'm actually gonna show you,
resemble.js has a web interface
where you can go in and kind of test different things.
And so this was an example of,
I made some very small changes just live on the PyCon site
where I think I made the images on this slightly smaller
and I made the border slightly larger.
So you can see these really interesting specific changes
that happened in this area and how things were shifted.
But what I really like about using the web interface
is that it lets you play with the different settings
for resemble.js.
So I'm setting a bunch of our diff options
and so you can control the error types,
how transparent it is, the different colors.
One of the things that resemble.js does really well
is it handles anti-aliasing,
which basically means that it can ignore differences
in how fonts render depending on the machine.
That was one of the big problems with screenshot testing
is that you could compare screenshots
from different operating systems
and the fonts would render differently
and it would cause these false positives
for saying that there was a difference
when there wasn't really actually a difference.
It was just anti-aliasing of fonts.
So yeah, this is really, really cool,
especially if you wanna see different things
that you can kind of change and rerun it,
shows you the difference, that kind of stuff.
Okay.
So what else do we have in here?
So we've got Puppeteer.
We're using compare images from resemble.js.
We have our take screenshot, which takes in the route.
I think this is a little bit different from the slides,
so I'm glad I'm going through this.
But take screenshot gives you the directory
where you wanna put it.
This allows us to dynamically generate
either golden screenshots or live test run screenshots
and put them in different places.
Again, this is hard-coded, so maybe not
what you would actually want to do
in a production version of this.
Then we can go through, take all of our screenshots,
generate golden screenshots,
and process them.
So hopefully all this makes sense.
Let's take a look at our test file.
Okay, so in here, again, we're using just an enzyme,
so we're grabbing all of that stuff,
grabbing configuration.
So we do have a place for restoring the paths
for our directories, just so that we can
kind of reuse those throughout.
Very little test boilerplate, which is nice.
A lot of this stuff does kind of just work out of the box.
And then again, running this kind of before all setup,
making sure that our golden directories exist
and that our test directories and diff directories exist.
And then this is really where the meat of it is,
where we're running a test on our index page.
So we are going through setting our viewport.
Default viewport right now is 800 by 600.
And then we want to make sure that our index page
is rendering properly.
So this take and compare screenshot
is a really excellent helper for being able to go through,
take the screenshot, generate the difference,
make sure that everything is asserting properly,
and then you just return the true or false value
out of that helper.
All right.
Let's see, so I think one of the first things
that I wanted to go through and do was show
one of those strengths of using visual screenshot testing
is that you can test a bunch of different browser sizes,
as well as kind of emulate different devices.
So let's set up in our config,
where we also are storing diff options
and directory information.
I'm also going to set up a few screen sizes.
So let's say we want to test for both desktop and mobile.
And we want to maybe have a list of different viewport sizes
that we want to test.
So I'm cheating, and I have a list
of a couple of the common ones.
So 1024 by 768, and 1366 by 768.
And then we'll also test a couple of mobile ones.
I think these are all iPhone sizes.
So this is going to be a little bit more,
I can't think of the word I want to use.
It's not super realistic, because there are a lot
of other things that go into how a page is going to render,
whether that is the user agent of a phone
is going to cause pages to render differently.
Devices will have maybe certain pixel ratios
that cause pages to render a little bit differently.
And so these are all really interesting things
that you can actually use Puppeteer
to also emulate those different changes.
Let's see.
I'm actually going to copy the rest of the mobile ones.
Okay, so now we've set up our screenshot sizes.
We need to do a couple of things here, right?
So in our helpers, we're going to need to be able
to take in different screen sizes.
I'm actually really curious why I was doing this.
I think I was having issues with importing this,
so I'm going to move this over so that I'm not
debugging imports uselessly right now.
So you can pretend that that import would have worked.
I'm going to just put those here
so that we don't waste time on that.
Okay, so now we have our screenshot sizes.
So what else are we going to need to do?
We are going to want to update our take screenshot
so that we can also take into account our screen size.
And so we're going to do a couple of things.
We want to place these into a separate directory
so that we have everything in kind of one place,
depending on the screen size.
So let's say we need to get screen size
and our screenshot size.
Okay, so if we have screenshot and screenshot size,
let's say we want to, instead of just placing this
into a file name, we want to actually nest this
into our directory.
So this is like a string template.
So anything that's inside of the dollar curly brace
is going to get interpolated as a variable.
So I can also say here, let's take in our screen size
and group all of that together.
And then I'm actually also going to add in our screenshot
size and so let me be a little bit more specific
because I think these are a little confusing.
My intention for these variables is for screenshot size
to be the actual dimensions of the page that we're taking
and then screen size is just like mobile versus desktop.
So at the end of this, we're going to have a mobile
directory with all of our mobile screenshots separated
by the screenshot size, like the actual dimensions of it
and then same for desktop.
Okay, so this is where types comes in handy.
So screen size, I intend to be a string.
Screenshot size will be an array.
So let's see, I'm actually going to copy this as well
just for the sake of time.
So this is going to get nested, screenshot size nested
into the array, so this is grabbing the first value
by the second value and I'm missing the ending curly brace
and these are spelled differently.
Okay, cool, so now I have this directory that I'm going
to kind of like save everything into really neatly.
The next thing that I'm going to do is, so even once I have
my page object, you can go through and change your viewport
at any time, so also in this function, I'm going to say
page.setViewport and I'm going to set, again I'm going to
copy and paste this, I'm going to set my width and my height
to the values that I'm passing in.
Let's see, and apparently my linter is just going to freak
out about weird things.
Okay, so I think this take screenshot function should be
good to go at this point.
The next thing that we'll want to do is, we can make our
lives really easy, so basically for each route that we want
to take screenshots for, we can automatically take them
for every single viewport size that we wanted to define.
So let's see, let's actually look at our test file.
So when we run take and compare screenshot,
we're going to want to run this for every page.
So in take and compare screenshots, we're going to tell
us to take the screenshot and then process it.
Let's see, I actually think we might want to do this
at a different spot.
If we do it in take screenshot, we can make sure that
we're setting the viewport.
Hmm.
Let's see.
I think I'm confusing myself.
One second, so take and compare screenshot, take and compare
screenshot is going to call take screenshot.
Oh, and then we're going to also need to generate
our golden screenshots, that's where I was getting lost.
Okay, so let's take care of that first actually,
and make sure that all that gets generated properly.
So generate golden screenshot will call
take screenshot directly.
And let's see, if we now have our screen sizes object
in here, let's see, I'm going to go ahead and do this here.
So we can basically iterate over all of our screen sizes.
And we can say for each screen size, these are fancy
JavaScript arrow functions, so this is, I'm going to take
this in as an argument, and then I can basically say,
I'm going to copy this as well.
So at this point, we just want to make sure that all
these directories exist that we have just created.
So just creating these like base screen size for mobile
desktop, okay, so now we have that done.
We can now generate all of our desired screen sizes.
So again, this is generating all of our golden screenshots,
we just made sure that all of the directories existed.
Now instead of just taking screenshots for this exact
viewport, we're going to want to do the same thing
and kind of iterate over all of the screenshots.
So I'm also, for the sake of time, going to copy this
as well, or maybe I'm not, because it doesn't like me.
One second.
Okay.
So now instead of doing this directly, this is going to be
another iteration, so for every single screen size,
we want to go over every single screenshot type
and make sure that we are now generating for each of those.
So we create our screenshot size based on the screenshot
type, if you remember what that object looked like.
This is a nested, an array of arrays basically,
is what we're kind of indexing into here.
And then basically what we're doing is creating a list
of all of the screenshot actions that we need to take,
and then we can kind of run all of these in parallel
and make sure that they all complete and then return.
So we can actually replace this here and say like,
once all of our screenshots actions return,
then we can close our browser and clean everything up.
So I think at this point we've done everything
for generating our golden screenshots.
Let's just see, yeah.
So I did something funny with sub-uport.
Let's see.
So take screenshot, call setvport,
and this call setvport.
So I actually think this is not happy about
calling setvport here.
Calling setvport here.
I'm gonna try for the sake of time,
I'm gonna try just creating a new page here.
I think it's not happy about that.
Let's see if this works.
So I'm also going to take in our browser here,
creating a new page.
And then when we call take screenshot,
yeah, we now have a browser, okay.
Now this should work, hopefully.
Well, that's unexpected.
Something has to go wrong, right?
Interesting, I'm curious to see if it generated any of them.
I know this is really small, fix it in a second.
Interesting, so something actually did go right.
I don't think I can make,
I don't really know how to make this too much bigger,
but I can temporarily zoom in for you.
So something's definitely going right.
We have our desktop and our mobile directories.
We now have a bunch of screenshots that are taken,
and we have the different viewport sizes
and the filenames for desktop and mobile.
So something is going well.
Okay, so at this point,
I do know I'm starting to get tighter and tighter on time.
So I am going to cheat a little bit
and check out to these different commits
so that I wanna make sure that you all can see
all of this kind of working
and not just watch me kind of like struggle
through live coding in front of you.
Okay, so, and I'll actually show you what I'm doing too.
So this is kind of what I mentioned earlier
for like one of the possibilities
of how you can use this content.
So I'm going to go through,
I want to look at the commits that I have.
And so I think I was trying to get screenshots
for various desktop sizes working.
I do wanna show you for different devices specifically.
So if I go through and show you this diff,
we're basically now going to like take into account
different device types as well as the actual sizes.
And so this is some really cool stuff that you can do
is Puppeteer will actually have built in
like emulators for different devices.
So instead of having to go through
and like figure out the exact like pixel ratios
and like dimensions of devices
and trying to do that all yourself,
you can just tell it like,
I wanna emulate an iPhone 6 and iPhone 10,
a Galaxy S3, five, I don't, an iPhone person,
whatever the like the device types are,
you can just like give it a string
and it will actually kind of just render it based on that.
So I am going to cheat and show you this.
So you can see the screenshots.
So I'm gonna go through
and generate my golden screenshots real quick
and then I'm gonna go through and just run the test
and make sure that all of that is working.
Maybe.
Okay, cool.
So we can see here,
this is gonna go through and print out
all of our information.
And I'll show you exactly how this is doing it too.
So this is a little bit of like kind of generating
these different devices that you're seeing here.
So not all of these are hard coded.
We're actually iterating over this
and creating test cases for them automatically.
And then if we go through and look at our files
that we now have, you can see that we have desktop.
These didn't get regenerated,
these are just leftover from before.
And then we have our mobile devices.
So you can see this page looks really wonky on an iPhone 6,
but at least we can kind of like see this here now
and have a really good idea
of what needs to be fixed for different devices.
Okay, so let me see if I can pull up
exactly where this is doing this stuff.
So now if we go back and look at our tests,
let's see, so in our tests,
we, that's all the setup.
Cool, so here's where we're actually like generating tests
for different screen sizes.
So really similar to how we started off before,
we're just gonna iterate over the like setup config file
for all the screen sizes that we want to test.
And then we can generate these tests using describe.
And then I still really like using the string template
where you can interpolate in directly
in the function parameter and create all of this.
Yeah, and then it's taking the screenshot type,
screenshot size and is able to figure all of that out.
And then do we do have specifically,
we didn't add a configuration for,
we didn't add a configuration directly for the device types.
This was just an example with an iPhone,
but you can also go through and add like a device's
parameter and do the same thing here.
Okay, let me see if there was something else
that I wanted to specifically walk through on here.
Yeah, so a lot of this is gonna be kind of walking through
and just doing some sort of best practices.
So moving that base URL into a configuration variable,
creating all of our different
like routes and whatnot based on that.
Yeah, I think that's most of it that I had
in this repository currently.
Some other options for how you can actually
create all this stuff.
So I'm curious to see, let's just go ahead and check out
the end product.
So now we can go through and generate,
hopefully all of this works.
Yeah, somehow I'm not surprised.
So this probably, JavaScript does get kind of tricky
and kind of likes to complain about promises
and different things.
So there's probably just something that I didn't have caught
that was not getting returned properly.
Okay, so this is just not gonna like me much at all.
But this actually, so this leads me into the next section
that I really wanted to dive in and kind of talk through.
So at this point, you can kind of see that there are ways
to set up this foundation for visual testing
where you can go through and set up different devices,
different pages that you can view.
A lot of this, once you get through,
you can actually start to see what's going on
and then you can see the images that you can view.
A lot of this, once you get the base foundation set
is really easy to automate and just kind of like,
as you add new pages, you already have this foundation
for all of your different screen sizes and whatnot.
So again, this is probably a lot of boilerplate
and a lot of things understand,
but it's kind of like a set it and forget it kind of thing
and then you can build on top of it.
So next thing that I wanted to kind of talk through,
is actually navigating to pages.
So what we were doing in this example
was going directly to URLs, which is really, really great.
If that's your goal for screenshot testing,
is making sure that your site looks good
and is scaling across devices,
you're probably gonna be set with just kind of using
the URLs and navigating to it directly.
But there's a lot of power in what you can do
with actually navigating through your page as a user would.
And so you can use the standard CSS selectors,
if you haven't seen those before.
You can target HTML tags directly,
you can target classes directly, you can target IDs.
There's a whole list, I actually,
I really like the list that HTMLDog has.
That's a great resource, check it out if you need it.
But basically, you can use these selectors
to tell Puppeteer to interact with the page
in different ways.
And so you can do things like clicking on a button,
focusing on an input field, filling out an input field,
submitting a form, pressing enter.
There's actually a really, really, really huge list
of all the things that you can do with Puppeteer.
So I know this is probably kind of small,
but I wanna show you, where's the list of all of them?
Yeah, so this is the list of all the API interactions
that you have.
So some other cool things that you can do
is tap into these dev tools that I was talking about.
You actually have access to all of those.
There's a lot of ways to tap into your render cycles
for animations, that's all there.
And then there's just a bunch of different ways
to navigate throughout your application.
So especially when you're dealing with SPAs,
making sure that your back button actually works,
the way that your in-app back button works
is super important.
I think going through and using this,
I think that they have support for testing accessibility,
which is also really important,
and usually something that your developers
are probably not thinking about as frequently
while they're building it.
So making sure that you have tests
for things like accessibility can be really important
to make sure that that remains a priority
and doesn't break in your application.
So yeah, this is a really, really, really great resource.
There's so much stuff that you can do with this.
They just make it so easy that you can't not.
Okay, so I'm gonna talk a little bit
about some best practices.
One of the things that you'll often see
are really, really long selectors.
And so it's really interesting to kind of compare.
If you've worked with CSS,
you've probably learned a bit about some CSS best practices.
So the selectors are the same,
but the best practices are not.
In both worlds, long selectors are typically not great.
As you can see, this didn't even fit.
And so the more nested your selectors are,
the more prone to breakage they are.
And so if you, for example, figured out
that you didn't need this div
that was enclosing your container,
and you just took it out,
you would probably have a bunch of tests that would break
because your selector was relying
on this kind of useless div.
The other interesting thing is that
a sort of best practice for CSS
is to try to not use IDs as selectors as much as possible.
Because that typically makes it so that
you're only targeting a single element on a page,
which if that's the intention is great,
but if you're trying to style all of your buttons
or something like that,
that's typically not a good practice.
But IDs are really, really ideal with testing.
And a lot of frameworks actually have it built in,
so you can specify a test ID specifically that you can target.
So you can get really clever with how your team wants
to kind of set up your own best practices.
You can add your own data attributes to tags.
So like the same way that an input field
has like a type or a name,
you can set up your own kind of naming convention
for an attribute that you use for all of your tests.
And then even if you wanted to,
you could kind of strip all of those out
before you push them into production
so that all of your IDs are kept private
and internal for your company.
So IDs are really ideal.
It especially always follow best practices
where there's a single element on a page
that has a single ID.
Having multiple elements with IDs is not necessarily ideal.
I wanted to do a select your live code,
I don't think that it's going to work,
but I will pose it to you all as a potential exercise.
My intention was that I wanted to go through
and basically write a test for logging into the PyCon website.
And so it would be a really interesting,
if you want to use some of the time today
to go through that, I think that would be cool.
I was basically going to go through and test,
going to the homepage, clicking the login page,
and then submitting false information
or invalid credentials that would cause an error on the page.
And so taking this kind of foundation that's laid
and figuring out how you can navigate through,
I think would be a good exercise to build on this.
So, okay, so I wanted to talk a little bit more
about these best practices and what you should expect.
So some really great places to start are from user stories.
Again, this is really, really user-centric,
so focusing on what your user is going to see
and looking at your user stories
is going to be the best blueprint for you to get started.
But it's possible that you don't have user stories
or that your user stories are out of date, et cetera.
But again, they could be a good place to start.
The most important parts, I think,
are the critical business logic
and also the parts that are kind of set it and forget it.
So one thing that you don't want breaking is your login page.
That would be kind of a crucial piece that would break.
Also probably something that you set up
in the beginning of a project and don't really touch a lot.
So those kind of set it and forget it ones
are ones that you want to make sure have solid tests
that you don't forget about.
And also a good way to do it is just a site map.
You can go through and make sure
that all your pages are rendering right.
Again, those pages probably get forgotten sometimes.
If you have an about page or a static page
that nobody is really working on,
a lot of times you can have inadvertent style changes
or whatnot that make those pages render incorrectly.
Oh, I don't know why that's a problem.
Yes, I don't know why this is rendering really badly.
My notes got really torn into this.
So I wanted to talk about some next steps.
So I mentioned snapshots earlier.
There's a service called Percy
that does a really interesting kind of combination
of snapshot testing and screenshot testing
where they actually have custom rendering agents
that will take your snapshots and then rerender them
into like an in browser view
and let you approve and deny your changes in their website,
which is really, really helpful,
especially if you don't want to go through
and set up all of this kind of like from scratch.
I'm also totally down to talk about how to roll your own.
I didn't want to get too vendored in my talk specifically,
but I'm a huge fan of AWS.
They have a lot of code pipeline tools that I've used.
If you're interested in talking about how you can roll
all of this into like a fully featured CI service,
I'm here to talk about that.
And I think that was everything that's rendering there.
So at this point, I am hoping that all of you
can kind of dive in.
If you want to have discussions amongst yourselves,
if you want to come talk to me,
we have about 20 minutes left of our official time.
Yeah, I think that's it.
Does anybody have any questions
that they want to pose kind of to everyone?
Oh, okay.
Uh-oh.
Yes, that is one thing that I wanted to talk about.
It is totally possible to do all of this with Python.
So like Aaron mentioned, there is a library for this
that you can do all of this in Python.
You can still do all of like the rendering and whatnot.
I'm not sure if there is a good wrapper around resemble.js
but I know that there are really advanced
image processing libraries for Python
that you could kind of roll your own on this.
I forget the technical term but there's like a,
it's like a, some sort of like,
the image merging has like a specific name for it.
I can't think of it.
But all this stuff you can do in Python
if you really wanted to.
It's just gonna take a little bit more
of like piecing some parts together.
But yeah.
Awesome.
All right.
I leave you to yourselves.
I'm here if you need me.