All right, everyone, if you could take your seats.
I'm here to introduce Paul Gansel, who
will be speaking with you today about working with time zones
and everything you wish you didn't need to know.
Woo!
All right, they saved the best for last.
But I think all those other sessions are closed,
so you will have to stay in this one.
OK, so as Chris said, I'm Paul Gansel.
I maintain date util.
And today I'm going to talk to you about working with time
zones.
So we'll start easy.
We'll talk about UTC.
UTC is the reference time zone.
It is monotonic-ish.
Why they decided to put leap seconds in the reference time
zone and in civil time in general, I do not know.
I sort of wish they had asked me.
I would have said no.
I think it's also important for you
to understand the difference between time zones and offsets.
So UTC plus 1 is an offset.
That's the offset that applies now in London.
Europe London is a time zone.
Time zone is a set of rules for what
time zone offset and other time zone information
applies as a function of the time.
BST, which is the abbreviation that applies right now
in London, is a highly context-dependent abbreviation.
So in the context of London, it means British summertime.
And that's UTC plus 1.
But if you're in Bangladesh, that
means Bangladesh standard time, which is UTC plus 6.
And if you're in Papua New Guinea,
it's Bugainville standard time, which is UTC plus 11.
Now this is the part of the talk that I'm sure
is the main reason you came.
I'm going to talk about all the weird stuff
people get up to with their time zones.
You may have a friend, it's OK.
I know you're asking for a friend, who
thinks that there's only like 24 time zone offsets,
and they're all just exactly one hour increments away from UTC.
But if you go to Australia, there
are places that are half an hour away.
Or in Southeast Asia, you'll see some places
that are multiple of 15 minutes away.
And historically, it wasn't even true
that time zones had to be an integer number of minutes
away.
In Liberia, before 1979, they were 44 minutes and 30 seconds
ahead of UTC.
There's also the situation where you may think,
well, the only time that offsets will change
is if daylight saving time has changed, and vice versa.
Daylight saving time will not change
without the offset changing.
But in 1992, Portugal decided that they
didn't want to be on Western European time anymore.
Instead, they wanted to be on Central European time.
So they were going to shift their base offset by one hour.
And they decided to do this at a time that
would be convenient for humans, but it turns out
to be kind of annoying for computers, which
is when daylight saving time was going to end,
instead of going from Western Standard Time to Western
European summertime to Western European time,
they just switched over to Central European time.
So the only thing that changed about the offset
is that they went from daylight saving time to Standard.
So you can have a daylight saving time status
change without any change in the total offset.
As an aside, in 1996, they decided
that having the sunset after midnight was not a good idea.
And they did the reverse.
So after going from Central European time,
instead of going to, I guess, Central European summertime,
they just went directly to Western European summertime
with no change in the offset.
So now we know that a couple of things that can happen.
But you think, OK, well, the only times
that things will change is if the base offset changes
or daylight saving time.
And daylight saving time is obviously only once a year,
not the case in Morocco.
So in Morocco since 2012, there have
been two daylight saving time transitions every year.
So what happens here is in the spring,
they go on to daylight saving time.
And then in this case, in 2012, they had, at the end of July,
they decided to just turn off daylight saving time.
And they'll just go back on to Standard Time.
And then one month later, they turn it back on.
And people who've seen me talk about this before
may know the spoiler that Morocco
is a majority Muslim country.
And this month is the month of Ramadan.
And during Ramadan, Muslims are not
supposed to eat until the sun goes down.
So they would much prefer to be on Standard Time
during that time.
So they just said, well, let's just go back to Standard Time
just for that one month.
And they've continued to do that with surprisingly little notice
every year.
All right, so you say, OK, well, I
know that there can be more than one daylight saving time offset
change per year.
But these only happen at like 2 in the morning.
So I'm never going to see an ambiguous time or something
like that during the day.
But in 1994, Christmas Island, which
I guess is part of Kiribati, they
decided that they wanted to be on the other side
of the international dateline.
This is some island in the South Pacific.
And presumably, they decided that one trading partner was
more important than another one.
I don't really know the details.
But the upshot of it was that they
decided they're not going to have a December 31 in 1994.
They'll just go December 30, 1159, and then one minute later,
happy new year.
And you say, oh, well, that's just something
that happens in the far past.
This was the 90s.
We were inventing programming languages and watching Seinfeld.
That's not going to happen today, right?
But just eight years ago, the same thing happened in Samoa.
And historically, you've also seen things
happen going the other way.
So Kwajalein Atoll switched from one side to the other.
And there were just two September 30s in 1969
in Kwajalein Atoll.
So you say, OK, fine.
Daily saving time changes can happen whenever.
And there can be millions of them.
And it's just chaos.
But there's one thing that I can rely on.
And that's if I know someone's location,
I know what time zone they're in.
But I think you know where this is going.
In China, they decided that it would be a great idea
to have one time zone for the entire country.
And this is a country that normally would span
three or four time zones.
But I guess administratively, it's easier.
So they went with UTC Plus 8, which
I think is great in Beijing, somewhere over here.
In Xinjiang, which is far to the east
and west, the west of China, the sunrise
is about 4.30 in the morning.
So that's not great.
So they decided we're going to be UTC Plus 6.
But Beijing, the government, does not like this.
So all the trains and the post offices and all those things,
they still run on UTC Plus 8.
And then the people just use UTC Plus 6.
And according to Wikipedia, the main difference
of when you would choose which time zone
is actually whether you are part of the Han majority
or the Uyghur minority.
So what this means is that this is actually a racial time zone.
So I guess it is true that if you
know someone's location and their ethnicity, then I suppose
you can know their time zone.
OK, so I've scared you.
I said time zones are crazy.
There's no possible rules.
Why would we want to work with these at all?
Why not just convert everything to UTC right away
and never work with time zones?
But time zones are actually very convenient.
So if you're working with something like business
markets or something and they have a business closed
time of 5 o'clock during the weekdays,
it's very easy for me to express this in an R rule
and say, every day at 5 o'clock, that's the market close.
And it happens in New York.
So I'm going to attach this New York City time zone.
And if you look, if I print each of these,
I always get 5 o'clock.
And I have the right UTC offset applied for each one of these.
And I can get UTC from this.
So I can compare between time zones
by just converting over to UTC.
And if you look at it, it's not obvious
how you would do this if you were just working in UTC.
Because then I would have to know when this 10 o'clock
to 11 o'clock transition happens.
And in fact, knowing that when those transitions happen
is basically a time zone.
So now hopefully this is the most convincing argument
that you've ever seen that time zones are worth using.
And we can just jump right in to how
Python represents time zones.
Python uses TZ info, which is an abstract base class.
A concrete implementation of a time zone
would be a subclass of TZ info.
And it's supposed to implement these three methods, TZ name,
UTC offset, and DST.
As an aside, I would not recommend using this DST
function.
Anytime I've ever seen someone try and use it,
they were kind of making some assumptions
about daily saving time that don't always apply.
So I would just kind of stick to the TZ name and UTC offset.
But one thing that you should note
is that each of these is implemented
as a function of the date time.
So what these do is they get attached to a date time,
and then you call corresponding methods on the date time.
And it will give you this information
as a function of the date time.
And I'm going to make this concrete
by showing you this example implementation of a time zone
representing Eastern time.
And I don't recommend that you implement this,
and you'll see why in a second.
But what I've done is I have this is daylight method,
and I've implemented the other three as a function of that.
It just says, if daily saving time applies at this time,
return this, or if it doesn't, return this other thing.
And so if I construct one of these Eastern time objects,
and I attach it to something on the daily saving time side,
I get UTC minus 4.
And if I attach the same object to something
on the standard time side, I get UTC minus 5.
But what happens if I attach it to something
that's in the middle?
So if I go with the Eastern daylight time side first,
I go to the last possible time before it switches,
or close to the last possible time.
If I say 1.30 Eastern daylight time,
it looks like that works fine.
One hour after that, because we're
about to set the clocks back, should be 1.30 Eastern standard
time.
But in my implementation, if I do this,
I get 2.30 Eastern standard time.
Why is this happening?
It's because I didn't properly handle ambiguous times.
Ambiguous times are times like the one
I just showed where when you set your clock back,
you're going to see the same time appear more than once.
But as I mentioned earlier, the offsets
are a function of the naive portion of the daytime,
whereas these daytimes, 1.30 Eastern daylight time
and 1.30 Eastern standard time, they're
differentiated only by the output of that function, which
is the offset.
So how do we handle this?
Well, the answer prior to Python 3.6 is we don't.
Throw your hands up.
It's not possible.
And you were just supposed to always return
Eastern standard time.
But in Python 3.6, pep495 fixed this
by introducing the fold attribute of daytime.
And what this does is it adds a fold attribute,
and that makes which side of that transition
you're on a property of the daytime.
So now you can write functions that
take the local portion of the daytime
and whether or not it's on one side or the other,
and you return different tz-info information based on that.
And how it works is that fold defaults to 0,
and if it's 0, it represents the first instance,
and if it's 1, it represents the second instance.
So now we can implement functions that handle the fold.
There are other changes that went in along with this that
have to do with comparisons of time zone-aware daytimes.
And so I'm going to just go into how
the semantics of comparison work in daytime,
because it's actually a little bit complicated.
So there's two different regimes that apply.
One is when the two daytimes you're comparing
are in the same time zone.
If they're in the same time zone,
then the assumption is you only care about the local time.
So in an ambiguous daytime, you'll
see in most cases this makes no difference
whether you're comparing the absolute time or the local time.
But in ambiguous times, the question
is whether you care about the time that's
whether the thing you want to be equal
is the time that's shown on the wall,
or whether it's like the time that it would
be if you converted to UTC.
And they chose the time on the wall.
So here you can see that if something is different only
because of its fold, then those two things
will compare equal.
In the case of different zones, then they
will just be converted to UTC and compared.
So that's maybe more what you would expect,
except when either daytime is ambiguous, in which case
it just is like, whatever, it's false.
I don't know.
And I don't actually know why this is.
It has something to do with hash invariance.
And I'm sure that it has a very good reason
because the people involved thought about this a lot.
So I'm going to show you an interesting case that
came up on the DateUtil issue tracker for TZ.
So here what I have is I've created a daytime that
represents 1 AM on March 25, 2007 in London.
I convert it to a timestamp.
And then I convert it back and get
an object that represents two of the timestamp and then back
using the London time zone, the original object.
And then I create a brand new object
that also represents London.
It's the exact same data as there.
And if I check whether x and y are equal to each other,
I get false.
So that's not a great start.
But now x and z, those do equal each other.
So that's good, but surprising that it's different.
But at least that just means, like, why is this weirdo?
But oh, wait, y and z.
So now we have this weird non-transitive relationship.
And to explain why this is, I have
to explain imaginary times.
So an imaginary time is a wall time that
doesn't exist in a given zone.
So this happens when you push your clocks forward by one hour.
So it'll be 1.30, and then one hour after that is actually
3.30.
So Python is fine with you constructing a daytime that
is like 2.30 in New York, or apparently 1 AM on March 25,
2007 in London.
So this 1 AM date that someone passed actually doesn't exist.
So if I represent the one hour before and after this in UTC,
I get midnight and 2 AM in London.
So this happened during a transition.
But that still really doesn't explain why it's non-transitive.
I guess you could be like undefined behavior or whatever.
It's not where it wants.
But there's actually a reason why it's non-transitive.
And the reason is that imaginary datetimes can't make round
trips because once you map to something that's in UTC,
you have an absolute daytime.
And that will always map to some time that existed.
So we start with our imaginary daytime.
We convert it to UTC.
And then when we convert it back, we get a different daytime.
And so if you look, y and z were both products of a round trip
because they went to timestamp and back.
But we attached actually different time zones to them.
Even though they represent the exact same data,
the way the same zone, different zone semantics get applied
is whether the time zones are exactly the same object.
So because we have different object equalities,
the first one, x and y, are using same zone semantics.
And x and z are using different zone semantics.
So in x and y, they just check whether 1 AM,
they just check whether this 1 AM and midnight are the same.
And they say false.
And with y and z or x and z, they
convert them both to UTC.
Both of them will get to midnight UTC.
And those are the same.
So you'll get true.
All right.
So now we know all the edge cases.
There's no more left.
And we'll go into the practical aspects
of working with time zones.
So if you're working with time zones with date util,
and I know the maintainer is a great guy.
I recommend using these time zones.
You can just attach them regularly to the daytime.
And it's a little surprising that I have to say that.
But you just use the constructor.
You pass it to tzinfo.
And it will give you this.
It'll have the correct time zone information.
If you have a naive time or say we
wanted to take that first daytime
and then reinterpret it to be in a different zone.
So it's at 2 o'clock in San Francisco.
But everyone in the meeting moved to New York
all at the same time.
And we still want it to be at 2 o'clock.
So we're just going to switch the time zone on there
to US Eastern.
It'll retain the, if you use replace,
it'll retain the 2 o'clock portion
and just change the offset.
If you want the same exact time, so for example,
if that first daytime represents a meeting that's
taking place in San Francisco and someone from New York
is calling in, we want to know what time it is in New York.
We use as time zone.
And that will do the conversion for the same absolute time.
So that gives us 5 o'clock.
With PyTZ, you can still use as time zone.
But if you use the constructor or replace,
it fails in this horrible way where
it says LMT, which is local mean time.
The offset is minus 4 hours and 56 minutes.
So why that happens is because PyTZ's time zone model is
actually different than Python's time zone model.
In PyTZ, they expect all TZInfo to be static offsets.
They don't change as a function of the daytime.
And which one gets applied is determined
by the time zone itself.
So instead of attaching things directly,
you would use localize.
You would call the localize method of the time zone.
And it would attach some object to your daytime.
And that will work.
And then if you do anything to it,
you have to normalize it afterwards.
So if you add like six months, it'll
still say that it's in daylight time,
even though it should have transitioned by then.
So you have to call normalize, and then it'll fix that.
This was important back before the fold attribute existed.
And now it is considerably less so.
And what we're left with is something
that is not a great interface.
And I know a lot of people who see this slide,
and they're like, I have to go fix code that's
broken in production today.
And there's more detail on my blog post
called PyTZ, the fastest foot gun in the West,
that explains more about the history and how things work.
OK, so when you're working with ambiguous times,
you may have a couple edge cases to handle.
So if you use as time zone, datutl and PyTZ
will both do the same thing, because it's
taking an absolute time and converting
to another absolute time.
But you'll note that PyTZ does not
set the fold because they don't use the fold or need the fold.
If you want fold support in, say, Python 2.7,
you can use datutl's backwards compatibility method tz.infold.
So in Python 3.6, this just works.
It just attaches a fold.
In Python 2.7, what it'll do is it'll
create a subclass that has fold whenever
you need to use the fold, and then everything will just work.
So datutl's time zones all use and fold internally.
And so datutl will just kind of work even for Python 2.7.
If you need to detect ambiguous times, like for example,
you want to ask the user whether they should be on the daylight
saving time or the standard time side of the transition,
you can use datutl's datetime ambiguous,
and that returns true if something's ambiguous
in a given zone.
And you can use this to selectively attach
the fold if you want.
But you don't actually need to selectively attach the fold.
If you just say fold equals 1 for everything,
it will be ignored for anything that's not ambiguous.
To work with, there's a corresponding method
for handling imaginary times.
It's called datetime exists.
And that will return false if a datetime is imaginary.
And it's not terribly uncommon for you to say,
well, if I land on this datetime, just tell me what time
it is.
Tell me what time it exists that corresponds to whatever time
it would have been if the same amount of time
had elapsed after the transition had happened.
So you can use datutl's resolve imaginary for this.
And if the gap is one hour, it'll
shift your datetime by one hour.
And if the gap is 24 hours or 17 minutes
or some other weird thing, it'll figure that out
and do it correctly.
So in datutl, you can use it has a couple
of different implementations.
It has UTC and static time zones.
Both of these are actually in Python 3.
So after Python 3.2, you really don't
need datutl's tz.utc object or their tz offset.
Those are just available in datetime.
And if you want access to the INA database,
datutl provides a method gettz, which
will try and find the information on the system.
And if it fails to find that, it'll
use its own internal database that it ships.
And this has historical information.
So if it works in a modern context,
it'll just show you Eastern Daylight Time or Standard Time.
If you go back to the 40s, it'll
have stuff like Eastern War Time, which
was Permanent Daylight Saving Time during World War II.
If you go back far enough, you get back to that crazy LMT
minus 4.93 seconds if you miss PyTz.
And just in general, the best way
to get a time zone from datutl is to use tz.gettz.
So if you pass it nothing, it gives you local time.
If you pass it something that is a representation
of your local time zone, like LMT is one of the time zones
abbreviations, it'll give you a local time.
And if you pass it an INA zone, it'll give you this tz file
object.
So I'm just going to wrap up with some time zone tips,
because everyone always wants the silver bullet.
How do I work with time zones?
You have 35 seconds.
And unfortunately, that does not exist.
It really all depends on your context.
I would say one very important difference is civil times
versus timestamps.
A civil time is like a wall time.
It's the time on the wall.
And a timestamp is an absolute time, the time in UTC.
And just know which one you care about
and which one you're going to use.
So if you're using a civil time, that
would be for something like in the future, like a meeting
or some kind of thing.
And the reason why you would want
to store this as the actual civil portion of the time
plus the time zone is that that mapping changes.
So instead of just saying, the meeting is next week at 12.
Let's store it in UTC and just change it back
when the user is going to see it.
You really want to say it's at 12.
Because if you convert it to UTC and then, say,
the president says, daily saving time
is canceled as of tomorrow, which
happens a surprising amount, then you've
just lost that information.
You can't recover it.
So it's best to keep your abstractions close
to what you actually care about.
And then finally, the way that these things are serialized.
Never rely on those three-letter abbreviations.
They're ambiguous.
The keys, like America, New York, or whatever,
those are just lookups in the time zone database.
If you want to show them to a user,
pass them through CLDR, which will localize them,
and say, in the native language,
and they will be something that a user can look at.
All right, so thank you very much for coming to my talk.
And thanks to PyCon for putting on a great conference.
?
All right, we have enough time to take probably two to three
questions.
But I'm guessing Paul will be happy to speak after,
if you're not one of those two to three people.
I can talk to her as long as you need.
So we have this practice of pinning our dependencies
so things don't blow up when we least expect it,
when we're going to be building our thing,
or building our system.
And it sounds like we need to be reinstalling
dateUtil every 30 seconds so that this stuff stays up to date.
Because how does it stay up to date
when something can happen like today,
and we need to be able to adjust to it?
I don't know.
How does that work?
So by default, dateUtil will not use its own.
It ships its own info information.
But that's mainly used on either Windows or on certain cloud
providers, anywhere where the TZ data is not
installed into the system.
By default, dateUtil has a number of paths
that it'll look for the time zone information on.
And it will pull it from the system if it's available.
And I am hoping to, at some point,
pull that data out of dateUtil and have it
be a separate package so you don't
have to upgrade both the data and the code
if you're on Windows or something where it doesn't
know where to find that information.
But yeah, for now, you kind of have to keep it up to date
or make sure that you have TZ data installed on the system.
I actually wanted to defend those leap seconds.
I come from space sciences, and all those leap seconds
mean big deals to me.
Thank you for a prompt for me to talk about leap seconds,
because I have some thoughts.
I have a few bad experiments.
No, I think that my understanding
was that most astronomers use Julian time and TAI
or something, which is monotonic, right?
But this is FPGA experiments for ionospheric disturbances.
And so our data has to be right on.
So those leap seconds are calculated into the position.
Yeah, to me, my main problem with leap seconds
is actually just that it's in civil time,
because if you're in space science
or if you're in navigation or any number of situations
where you need this information, I
think people should be calculating it,
and there should be a reference time that
has leap seconds in it.
But the average person does not need this information.
And it's easy to calculate it as an offset from TAI.
TAI is another reference time that is monotonic,
and it's like 17 or 35 seconds behind UTC.
Who knows?
You can maybe tell that I'm not great with details,
left or right, west, addition and subtraction.
If you want to talk more about Daytime with Paul,
I'm sure he'll be around.
Otherwise, if you want to head down to Hall A,
there are community awards happening,
being presented by AWA, followed by a keynote
and closing remarks.
Thanks, everyone.
Thank you.