opportunities. So let's please welcome Lorena Mesa. She'll be giving the talk Esquincla
Barbosa, Creating a Tele-Novela, Script and Three Deep Learning Frameworks.
Excellent. Okay, can you all hear me all right? Very cool. I naturally am a loud person and
use a lot of hand motion. So this will be great because I think it goes with the topic
pretty well. So yes, if you were staring at the name of this talk and you're like, I don't
think there's English in some of this, you are correct. You're in the right place. So
Esquincla Barbosa, Creating a Tele-Novela, Script and Three Python, Deep Learning Frameworks.
Side note, I will be actually on some of the slides, there is a URL that you can actually
follow along with the slides. And I do actually have all my content linked to the GitHub repository
that has this code. And there's a surprise of another GitHub repository at the tail end.
So who am I? Hola, soy Lorena Mesa. Puedo hablar en inglés o español. But I will obviously
be talking in English for this talk. It is not PyConcharlas. So the topic, I personally
am just really interested in deep learning. I hear the term deep learning and I'm like,
what's so deep about this learning? So I'm really just kind of curious about this topic.
And I also really loved El Novellas. So when I was thinking about a topic, it felt like
a very big win-win for me. So why not? Why not? But actually, more practically, I actually
work as a data engineer at GitHub and I sit between two teams in the data org. My team's
name is Software Intelligence Systems, which is a little bit of a mouthful. SIS for short.
And the teams that I work with are our semantic code team and our machine learning team, our
machine learning engineers are increasingly talking about different deep learning techniques
and using GPUs and a lot of these kind of techniques I hadn't used before. So why not?
Why not marry my interests and try a little toy session and see what I can learn about
deep learning and share with you all in a PyCon talk. I do some other work in the Python
space as well. I'm in Chicago. I help run PyLady Chicago and I'm also on the Python
of directors. Yay! If you do have any questions about those things, again, you can find me
later. So I'm a bit curious how many of you may have seen some of these headlines floating
around. Oops. Sorry about that. Let me go to the next slide. Okay. Excellent. Did anyone
see this headline floating around about this AI generated script starring David Hasselhoff?
No? Okay. You should watch it. It's this really interesting and absurdist eight-minute short.
And the creator of this, Ross Goodwin, who is a creative technologist in Google's artists
and machine learning program, actually used a R and N, a recurring neural network, to
actually generate all the lines that were in the short for David Hasselhoff's script.
The short is quite interesting. It's very ephemeral. It's not quite clear what's happening.
When I first saw this headline, it got me thinking about the intersection of art and
technology and this was something I never really had thought about before. What happens
if we can automate the idea, the creativity process? What does that actually look like?
Another place that I kind of started seeing this floating around, as one does, lots of
conversations on Twitter. Specifically, this is a screenshot from a chat that was March
2018 wherein someone alleged that they took all of the scripts from all the scripts of
the various Saw movies, and no, I do not know how many there are, and apparently developed
a neural network and allegedly trained it for a thousand hours, whatever that means,
to generate this script. And this script is supposed to be a horror script. And in the
script, that first line, it says, a sexy woman, Becky, sex woman, is covered by a bed. She's
in a whale but doesn't know she's in a whale. And it's a very confusing piece of text. The
part on the right-hand side that kind of continues to go into this a little bit starts talking
about how this is a really interesting application of neural networks to try to create an idea
with text generation of movie scripts. However, they do start asking questions about why are
the words in the vocabulary used in the script including such a language as Trump and whale?
The person then goes on to critique to say, actually, nowhere in the Saw movies are these
two words appearing. And if you know anything about neural networks, and by the end of this
talk, you will a little bit, that can be a little problematic because as the neural network
is learning, it learns from the corpus of text that you provide it. So if you're allegedly
providing it the Saw scripts and it's coming up with words it had not ever seen before,
can we say this is actually an AI-generated script? I don't know. Either way, I think
this thread is very interesting and it started poking a lot of questions and made me want
to actually try my own example. The whale did that. It became a meme. You can go find
out more about this script. But there's a lot of people that are starting to think about
what is the intersectionality of creativity and technology? So you might be asking why
telenovelas? Also, what in the world is a telenovela? Well, you came to the right place.
I'm here to inform you about one of the most epic meltdowns in a telenovela that has ever
happened. So do I have any telenovela fans in here? Yes. Okay. That's exciting for me.
So maybe some of you remember this one. Mariela del Barrio, which is a beloved Mexican telenovela
from the 1990s, I believe specifically 1995 to 1996 with like 195 episodes. But this scene
and the images might be a little hard to see, but this scene includes some of the characters
of where we get the beloved phrase, escuincalababosa, which is in the title of this talk. So we
have at the top two, we've got a love struck couple. We have Alicia to the left and we
have Nandito to the right. And the main character who's shown on the right hand side and also
in that third panel at the bottom, that is Soraya. So she is our main character of this
telenovela. And Soraya, she's got some complex history going on. So she's the stepmother
of Alicia and then Nandito is her ex-husband's son. Right. And the thing here is Soraya is
still desperately, desperately in love with Nandito's father. Like to the point of maybe
there was like a restraining order. So she's desperately, she's desperately in love with
Nandito's father and she's stuck in a marriage though where she's got this daughter, Alicia.
So she happens to walk into the room where Alicia and Nandito are starting to express
their love for one another. Nandito very tenderly says, may I, Alicia, please have a kiss. And
as they're leaning into this moment, in comes Soraya. And Soraya is like, what is going
on? I don't understand. Because for her, this shatters, I guess, her master plan to get
back with Nandito's father. Essentially, she then screams and calls Alicia escuincalababosa,
which means use boiled rotten bread in nice speak. And what then ensues is the most epic
fight, I guess we could call it. There's a lot of kind of air slaps. You can very, very
specifically tell that there's not any contact happening. There's people diving over beds
to protect one another. Some random gentleman in a suit walks in and is trying to break
up the fight. His character is in no shape or form explained as to why he's there. And
then the nanny, the nanny here, she walks in. And what that says in Spanish here is,
this woman is, this woman is, she's got problems. She's possessed by the devil. So this scene
and all this kind of trope of like love and complex family relationships, and the idea
that we all have this trauma that's near and dear to our heart, that leads us into what
a telenovela is. So Jorge Gonzalez, in talking about telenovelas, he's a sociologist, kind
of commenting on the impact and social phenomena of telenovelas, basically says they are melodramas.
And these are serial melodramas. You get increments of 25, 30 minutes, maybe five times a week.
But what happens here, because it is a stable relationship that you're making with the audience,
people become very passionate and very connected with these narratives. To the extent that
when we talk about telenovelas, there's about two billion people worldwide who consume telenovelas
that are from Latin America. That's about like a third of the world population. So that's
a pretty sizable number. And if you want to know more about why telenovelas are a big deal,
here's some stats of some of the viewing and patterns of viewing of Latin American telenovelas.
So Latin American telenovelas have been viewed in over 100 countries. They have generated
over $800 million in marketing on various telenovelas in a five-year period. I believe
that stat is 2010 to 2015. And just generally speaking, this is a global phenomenon.
So in breaking down the arc of a telenovela, because if we want to try to emulate and create
a telenovela with a neural network, we need to understand what it is we're trying to create.
So back to kind of thinking about that kind of relationship and things that pop up. One
of the things that's interesting about telenovelas is this idea that there's not really any
cliffhangers or kind of open-ended stories. Dr. Rios, who talks about telenovelas and
kind of understanding their social impact, specifically says that at the end of the telenovela,
things have to be cleared up. So in our Maria de la Barrio, for example, if we have the
character Maria and we want to know what's happening, she would hypothesize and say,
our audience doesn't want to worry about Maria. We don't want to know if she didn't find her
true love, her true mother, her true father. We want all those answers. So unlike English soap
operas, which I think some have been going for more than 15, 20 years, what happens with
telenovelas is you have a fixed melodramatic plot line. And yes, it's going to be lost loves. It's
going to be mothers and daughters fighting. It's going to be long-lost relatives. It's going to
be love found. And maybe as quickly as you found that love, something happens where that person is
shipped away and we don't know what happened to them. Maybe it's the guy in the suit. He's from
El Teatro Novela. I don't know. But our telenovelas have a finite beginning and end, and they're
generally tied up with a very big happy element at the end. So for example, like the world's
largest wedding. If you watch Casa de las Flores, there's kind of some of that maybe that's being
built up too. But yes, there's always this idea we've got a fixed arc, a lot of intricate kind of
heart-wrenching moments, but it's going to wrap up with something happy that we can all feel good
about and move on with our lives and not wonder what happens to these characters. So if we're
thinking about examples of telenovelas, let's take a look at some of the ones that are available to
us in Spanish. So this is Kate del Castillo, who I swear, I think she's like my role model in life.
She's fantastic. If any of you like watched that documentary about talking with Chapo, who's a
narcotraficante, she was doing that with Sean Penn because that's what she does in her free time.
But she's very famous. She's been in many telenovelas and one of the ones that is most
known is La Reina del Sur. So that's an example of one that is really, really popular in Mexico.
And then many of us may know Yo Soy Betty La Fea, because actually some of these telenovelas have
crossovers in English. So the ones that I looked at, because again, we're predominantly an English
speaking population, I looked at popular telenovelas in Spanish, looked for their English crossovers,
and then worked with that text. So Queen of the South, which is actually on USA, talks to us a
little bit about that narrative with Kate del Castillo. In this one, in Queen of the South,
essentially what we have is the character who becomes the most prominent drug lord trafficker
in South Spain after she has to flee Mexico because her beloved is actually captured by
the cartel that's pushing drugs in that area. So of course, as one does, you relocate to another
country and then you start your vast drug empire. So that one's going to have love lost, it's going
to be a thriller, it's going to be a drama, and it's going to be high emotional kind of action
impact. And then with Ugly Betty, what we have is more or less a rom-com. This actually started in
Colombia and it's had, I think, three or four crossovers to different Spanish-speaking markets
starting in 1999 in Colombia. But essentially what we have is a character, Beatriz, who works
in the fashion industry and is considered ugly because stereotypical things like she has braces
and she has glasses and things that I have all worn in my life. But anyways, it's all about the
story about her struggles working in the fashion industry and trying to find love. And then Jane
the Virgin actually, I know I said I looked for popular crossovers from Spanish to English,
but for this one, because I think there's enough comfort and knowledge for people of what this one
is, Jane the Virgin is actually a satirical melodrama, but it's fantastic because essentially
we follow Jane, who is a virgin, who after visiting a doctor's office somehow becomes
artificially inseminated and becomes pregnant. So she's a pregnant virgin and then various things
that unfold afterwards and how she finds love or how she doesn't find love leads us into this
complex story that is Jane the Virgin. So in thinking about telenovelas, we understand a
little bit of the arc. We understand that's a melodrama. We understand that it has finite end.
We understand it's going to wrap up with something happy and we understand some of the trips that
may be employed. So now how can we start applying this to deep learning? When we think about machine
learning, and I'm not sure if many of us in here do machine learning, some of the things that you
may think of are some of the language that's provided to us by the founders of this discipline.
So Arthur Samuel, who actually coined the term machine learning, actually provides us with this
language saying that machine learning is a field of study where computers have the ability to learn
without being explicitly programmed. So there's this idea that there's something that's not
requiring us to actually have some intent or some purpose. So that is where we kind of can start
with machine learning. Now, as we see here at PyCon, there's many various talks that may talk
about data science or machine learning, and this is a very, very, very, very vast space. So if we
were looking at, for example, technology and tools, we may see things like Python. We may be talking
about things like Spark or Julia or other scientific programming languages. If we're talking about the
kind of problems we can solve with machine learning, we'll see the problem categories on the bottom
left-hand side. We might be doing classification, clustering, optimization kind of problems.
However, what we want to focus on is this idea of a subfield. So when we talk about deep learning,
deep learning is a subfield. It's a type of machine learning and is alongside other categories such as
maybe ones you may have heard of, supervised, unsupervised, semi-supervised. So to broaden on
that definition of machine learning and kind of challenging us to think about how we can actually
have a deep learning model that can actually generate a manuscript, we probably need to
reconceptualize what machine learning means. So this is a great definition given to us by Tom
Mitchell, and Tom Mitchell, the former chair of the computer science department at Carnegie Mellon,
who wrote, I think, the quintessential book on machine learning published in 1997. It stands
up really well. I highly recommend reading it. Basically says, when we think about machine learning,
it's not so much that it's a program that isn't explicitly programmed, but instead it's that we
want to – there's something that we want to accomplish. So if we're thinking about a computer
program that's said to learn, let's think about it in this framework. We have some objectives,
so we have a task that we want to accomplish, and in order to accomplish that task, we need to be
able to provide it with some ability to understand what that task is. So we have a task, and then we
provide it some ability to understand what that task is, which is the experience. And then as
that program continues to attempt to do that task, we can develop a performance measurement
to understand how it's improving over time. So this language gets us a little bit closer
to thinking about what machine learning is when applied to deep learning, but it doesn't get us
out of the way. So the trend with machine learning over time – and it's kind of wild to think that
in the 1950s and some of these algorithms that we're talking about today, you know, naive Bayes,
for example, this is not new math. This is not new algorithms. These are things that have been
that have been out there for 20-plus years. But what we're seeing in the trend of the world of
machine learning and what does it mean for a machine to learn, we start with this realm of
artificial intelligence. We move into machine learning, which is, again, that idea of a program
not having to be explicitly programmed to do that task. And then we move into this world of deep
learning, and we start hearing about these things called neural networks, which sounds very sci-fi
and very unclear what that is. To frame it a little bit more simply, if we were to think about
what it means that this evolution from AI to deep learning, we can say that an example of an
artificial intelligence program is a door sensor because it's able to adapt to its environment
around it. With a machine learning, we can say an example of a machine learning program is our spam
filters. We all know it. We see it in our various email inboxes. The idea that we know spam when we
see it, can we teach an algorithm how to do that? Yes, we can. And we've done that with machine
learning. Now, if we're moving into the realm of deep learning, what we start getting into is this
idea of using these neural networks that drives its own learning. That is the engine by which
learning is empowered. And if you see on this right-hand side here, this project is called
the deep dream, which came from Google research, wherein they are providing an image of an object
to an algorithm with the desired intent and output to say, tell us what you see in this image. So
what we start seeing on the other side is if we provide, let's say, an image of an apple, it's
like, okay, I understand that this is an apple, but what other images do I see in it and what can I
infer from this image that I'm seeing? So kind of flipping it a little bit on its head and getting
into the realm of do Androids dream of electric sheep? That's where we start saying, okay, we're
going to give you some idea, some definition, but using this neural network, we want you to drive
your own learning. So if we were thinking about an example of applying deep learning to, let's say,
a classification problem, if I had something like a flashlight and I wanted it to respond
and learn from audio cues to turn on, we could say, let's say I want to have a flashlight that
if I say the word dark, it turns on. Well, with a deep learning implementation, it wouldn't just
have that fixed understanding of saying, okay, dark maps to turn on because this is the task
of bringing light to the world, but instead it might understand other cues, other verbal cues
that I might be able to supply to this model. So I might say something like I can't see or
the light switch won't work. With a deep learning kind of implementation, the neural network would
be able to learn and infer these other kinds of words that may fill in to suggest that there's an
absence of light, to suggest that the area around you is dark. So this learning, again, that happens,
the brain, which is that neural network, happens with an activation method.
So moving now back to telenovelas, there's a type of problem called text generation that we're going
to be looking at. So text generation is sequence processing, and sequence processing has a lot of
applications in the world of deep learning. We can use it for video processing, price modeling,
and yes, text generation. Essentially what we want to do is there's two approaches that we can have.
Using language, so actually using a body of text, we can say we want you to look at the individual
words that are in this text to actually generate some text on the other side, or we can actually
develop the deep learning model to actually look at the individual characters that are provided in
the corpus that we're working with. Either way, given the text that we provide to the
sequence processing model that we use, what it's going to start trying to do is approximate the
relationship of what words mean, what the relationship between one word is to another,
and then as it tries to understand the relationship between words, try to think about how it is that
it can build its own patterns and generate its own vocabulary that models the relationships it
sees in this corpus of words that we provided. So I've been using the words neural networks
in deep learning a little bit interchangeably, and while I want you to understand that there are
these artificial neural networks, what essentially deep learning is, it actually makes use of several
neural networks. And when we talk about neural networks, the power that drives a neural network
is the neuron. So the neuron here, it's got three parts. We have the inputs, we have the weights,
and then we have the activation function. So essentially what's happening is our words are
going to be the inputs, and we're going to represent those as either words or as either characters.
We then apply an arbitrary weight to it, and then as it runs through each layer in our neural
network, it's going to start trying to approximate that relationship to understand relationships
either from word to word or character to character, and then it's going to go through
this activation function where as it's learning these relationships, it starts adjusting those
weights to try to find the optimal weight to use to actually start generating a thing,
or in our case, generating text. So the activation function, you can think of something like a
sigmoid function. So essentially what we have is some kind of function that is a nonlinear function
that is going to allow us to actually start doing some math. So if we have a weight applied to a
word, let's say it starts at 0.5, but we need to start shifting it either higher or lower based on
the relationship between these words that the network is learning, we've got this activation
function to help us do that. So when we're training a neuron, essentially what we need to do
is these three steps. The neuron takes an initial guess at classifying the sample, and then updates
the guess by adjusting the weights, and then it goes ahead and repeats and tries again.
So this process is very iterative. And with neural networks, there's many kinds of neural
networks that we can use. Feedforward, radial basis function, or an RNN. And RNNs are good
for sequential processing problems like text generation. And what's really cool about this
is that it actually allows us to propagate data back and forth. So as our neurons are all connected,
so a deep neural network would be an example of what we have on the right-hand side. Basically,
it's a directed graph. We have input going from one node, but also we can move backwards. So using
an RNN, insights learned upstream or downstream can move back and forth across these neurons.
So if we wanted to make an RNN in Python, how do we do it? Well, there's more than one way,
as we like to do. So there's three really popular frameworks, Keras, TensorFlow, and PyTorch.
And yes, I'm going to borrow the language from the 2017 keynote, but yes, Python is surprisingly
super awesome, or maybe unsurprisingly super awesome at scientific programming. So these three
frameworks, when you're thinking about which ones to use, I like to think about questions to help me
think about what tool is best for the task at hand. How much technical expertise is needed
to start using it? What are your requirements? For example, do you have a certain SLO you have to
meet? What's the size of data you're working on, working with? And also, how easy is it to start
using the framework? So if we're looking at making an RNN in Python using Keras,
we've got these three steps that we're always going to be emulating. Basically, we have to take that
text and we have to transform it either into characters or words. So we tokenize it. Then
once we've tokenized it, we generate these hot encodings, which basically gives us, let's say,
on the next slide, this actually gives us a nice example. Let's say our corpus is the word bad.
And because we've got the letter B, what we want to do is we've got nine characters in our corpus.
We have other words that introduce these other characters. What we want to do is basically be
able to understand and predict the likelihood for each corpus, for each character in our corpus,
to actually say what's the likelihood that this character will appear. So as we generate this hot
character encoding, we're going to use that as input to our neural network, and we're then going
to pass it through our RNN and basically say, hey, start learning the weights and start coming up
with the optimal weight to represent the likelihood of what character you should be generating based
on these, again, trying to approximate that relationship in the underlying text, and let's
see what we get on the other side. And to train this, we're going to run it through some number
of epochs. So with Keras, what we can notice here, for those of you who may have used scikit-learn,
we've got a really, really nice high-level API we can use. Notice how I said sequential
processing is a text generation is a sequential processing problem? Surprise, we're going to use
a sequential model. So LSTM, long short-term memory, is a type of RNN propagating that data
back and forth. This is pretty straightforward because it allows us to pull in the sequential
model. We specifically say we want to use an RNN of this type. We then basically add in our data,
and then we say, okay, let's go ahead and compile that model, and notice this fit. We're going to
have 20 epochs that we're going to train over, and what we want to do is we want to find that
optimal weight that we can generate. So Keras has a very nice and user-friendly interface that we
can start using. And if you were kind of looking at what it may look like for that process of
running through epochs, well, you can just basically think of a for loop. It's very iterative.
If we have 20 loops or we have 1,000, we can start doing things like that. And then when we start
wanting to actually use it, we've got that model.predict functionality. So Keras is pretty cool.
Now let's look at TensorFlow. Mind you, I did some lifting of this data, so there's some logic
that's kind of not captured, but it is actually in my GitHub repository. But again, when we have
when we're using TensorFlow, again, we import TensorFlow, and we've actually got an RNN that
we can pull in. Unlike in the last case where we've got the sequential model and we've got
the LSTM that's kind of baked in, we're going to actually have to start making and creating our
own object to represent the RNN. We're going to be working with tensors, which is, again,
a representation of the vector data. And what we need to do then is start writing a definition of
the RNN that we want. So notice that we've got the basic LSTM here that we can pull in.
But essentially when we're using TensorFlow, we're going to have to have a little bit more
knowledge about the underlying we're not given that high-level API interface where it just says,
hey, here's the thing out of the box. You actually have to go and take the components and actually
start building it yourself. And likewise, then when you're actually optimizing the weights,
what you have to do is you actually have to run a session, a TensorFlow session, and notice again,
we have this epoch loop. We're going to go ahead and do N iterations. And then when we find the
optimal weight, what happens in both cases is you can export those optimal weights once you've found
them after running so many epoch sessions. Those weights then, let's say they're in a flat file,
you can then import those for later use. So TensorFlow, we don't have that high-level
interface. We've actually got to kind of meld some of those components together ourselves.
But we understand what we're doing. We've got to build the model. We've got to fit the model.
We've got to train the model. And with PyTorch, PyTorch actually gets a lot more interesting.
And you have a lot more flexibility to go in there and build things as you want. So notice here as
we're building our RNN, with PyTorch, notice how we're having to actually build the interface for
actually how forward propagation works. So remember how data can move forward and backward? Now you
are able to actually go in and write that logic how that happens and how you're interacting with
these other neurons. So the interface actually is much more low-level. And again, when we're
training, we have that great epoch loop that we've come to know and love. And also when we
get our output, we can then export that output to then import to our model for later use as well.
So with those three neural networks examples, what actually can we start generating with
an RNN using Python? This is some of the most coherent text I actually started developing,
which is to say that it is a work in progress. So one of the things I noticed is as I started
asking to make longer pieces of text, it just started getting really, really wild. Remember,
the whale did that. So some of the more coherent units of text I found was actually getting
character strings of about 200. So why is that? This kind of feels like it's in line that it could
be in a telenovela. Don't threaten me. Do you not understand me? Well, well, well, well, right.
Maybe we're making that famous fight scene all over. But in thinking about the tooling that we
need to build, think about those three questions. How much technical expertise is needed to start
with a framework? I've told you that I'm new to deep learning or relatively new, so I probably
want something that's a little bit more beginner-friendly, something that allows me
to build a small toy project quickly, and something that has, for me, this is super important,
a very, very good robust user group that gives lots of documentation and lots of examples of
how to use it. For my second question, what are my requirements? Well, actually, because I focused
on just looking at those three English telenovelas, I actually did not have that much data. I had less
than 100 megabytes. And it was actually just looking at the raw text spoken word data itself
that wasn't including things like sometimes there's cues in scripts that say something like, oh,
15-second pause with a dramatic stare to the side. So those weren't actually, those kind of nitty
gritty pieces of information I actually didn't have in my text that I was working with. So
thinking about that I had a small data set and something that I wanted to have some ability to
debug a little bit more friendly, let's continue on to my third requirement, which is basically
how easy is it to start using a framework? And essentially, what I wanted was to get something
that allowed me just to be able to bootstrap and get going because I just wanted to know what it
means to actually start working with text, start processing text, and actually start doing text
generation. And all that to say that the one that won for me, notice my priorities? Caris? Yes! I
opted to work with Caris. So what's really cool about TensorFlow is you can actually,
Caris you can plug in and you can use with TensorFlow and you can do the, you can use
TensorFlow and Caris quite nicely together. But on the side of how to make a telenovela script a bit
more intelligible and more interesting, think of it this way. Maybe I can write along an RNN model
for each character that I want in my plot. So maybe like the David Hasselhoff, maybe I have
five characters in the fight scene and I want a model for each of them. Maybe I look for similar
sources of inspiration. Maybe I'm like, okay, I want telenovelas that have strong women leads.
And maybe that's what I can use as the input for my strong women lead LSTM model. Also, what we
can start doing is weaving these models together or maybe even having models based on categories.
So long lost love, rom com, things like that. So all that to say, and I know this is a little bit
of a cop out, but yeah, text generation is hard. It's pretty hard. So creating a learned plot,
you know, sorry, I don't know if I'm going to come up with a consultancy tomorrow to take away all
of Hollywood's jobs, but I'm going to try. So how can we do better? There's no surprise here. One,
always validating your data. As I kind of said, there's a lot of time spent processing and looking
at that data. So notice there's some strange characters on the right-hand side. Notice on the
left-hand side you get this character, the Latino lover who's the narrator, which is a very strange
thing to read out of context. But notice how on the right-hand side we may include character names,
but I had some text that actually didn't name the characters. That got a little bit more complex.
So data validation is always a thing. And on that note, I'm just going to say to you all,
if you want to add to my corpus of ever-growing telenovela data, you should add. I'm collecting
it here, and it's a really fun process and really interesting. But yeah, text generation is difficult.
We've probably all seen this one. The surprise here is deep learning is only as smart as you make
it. So if you have more data to provide it, the better it is to use. So we've seen a lot of deep
learning models get hacked out in the wild, for example, obscuring your face because if it's
learning that a human face is oval and your hair is pulled back, but then you have this wild haircut,
if the deep learning model is actually learning that the relationship to a human face is a certain
shape and we're representing that data as such, again, we have to think about all these things and
how the model is actually only learning the relationship that we provide it. So if you want
to keep learning, I have examples of various resources here. Again, I will share these slides
on Twitter. And that is the end of my talk. But as a total, total serious ask, if you do own
Mariela del Barrio, I was looking everywhere for it. I ordered it on VHS. We'll see if it arrives.
Also, that gets into the place that I now need to have something that works with VHS. But that
would be great. But if you do have any questions about this or want to kind of look at the
repository and dig in and maybe help me make a more robust telenovela, come talk with me. I would
love to see what we can create. Thank you.