Why am I giving this talk, right? I don't represent Bridge Crew. I just think, having
come from data, ML, Python being great, that I started working more in infra, DevOps, thinking
about security. And I thought that was probably going to be missing from this conference,
so easy enough to stop, you know, down the block and give a quick talk. Cool. Hey, what's
infrastructure as code? Hopefully some of you guys are deploying in cloud and thinking
about deploying stuff. Infrastructure as code is, let me define, you know, via Terraform
as the standard, but also CloudFormation, Deployment Manager, et cetera. This is from
the title of the talk. What is static code analysis? Hopefully some of you guys are doing
that, right? Like, let's look at, let's have something that takes a look at my code and
verifies that it's reasonably secure. Generally that's from, like, package management, dependencies
or whatnot. But there's, with infrastructure as code, there's ways to define policies via
something like policies code. GitHub repository here. This is open source and usable. There's
a website, checkoff.io. You can pip3 install it. Great. It's Python. Brew if you like your
Mac. Found it pretty weird. It's checkoff by Bridge Crew. Bridge Crew is brought to you
by Prisma Cloud. Prisma Cloud is brought to you by Palo Alto Networks. So, you know, trace
that chain, whatever. Okay. Why is checkoff cool? I think there's even a talk following this on
another form of that, right? I don't intend to say, like, please use checkoff, right? But, like,
think about using something like this if you're going to deploy infrastructure. Infrastructure
code is a great idea. DevSecOps is a great buzzword. Policies code, I've already said it.
Ultimately, if you're running CI-CD pipelines for deployment, define your infrastructure as code
and put some policies in place from a security perspective to ensure that's the case. Checkoff's
great in that it works not only with the major cloud providers but also Kubernetes and more.
Okay. So, how does it work, right? So, realistically, we pip installed or brew installed
our bit here. We have, you know, then have access to a checkoff command, right? Here's two examples.
Realistically, this is about Terraform, right? Where I, and also I skipped, I was going to work
through a demo, but this is easier to share this laptop, so these are slides. Skip whatever things
if you don't want. It's pretty flexible. I guess this is what I'm going for here. You can skip
them via the commands or in the Terraform code that you've written. Feel free to annotate things
and you can, you know, forego this bit. Kind of the powerful thing and what I wanted to get across.
Hopefully, everybody, you know, you guys are developers. Hopefully, you're using Git, but like
use pre-commit hooks for a whole lot of stuff. That works here. I generally don't trust that
people actually use their pre-commit hooks, so also, you know, consider after a pre-commit hook
something on, you know, like a pre-receive or whatever else before things actually make their
way into the shared Git. Here's some references for, you know, those that aren't Git fans are
on board yet. I think that's actually about that, and then, you know, here's a few other,
you know, advertisements, right? Check out Hacktoberfest is going on, a way to contribute
to a bunch of open source projects that need some stuff, and I'm a huge fan of Beam,
a Python-based, but also a multi-language way to write data pipelines, and Flight is,
you just heard about orchestration like Dagster, pretty equivalent, although you can also
use languages other than Python, which, you know, Python's why we're here. Yeah, here, just to
show there's like Python code under the hood once you call, check off, and I think the thing I was
even going to point out here is the actual test, right, from the, or the,
encouraging everybody to please write tests for their code, and even from this project itself,
the testing code is two of these slides versus the actual code that does the thing is one of
these slides, so like, you know, it's okay if tests are longer than your code. That's all I got.