Right, so I want to talk about how you would draw base year curves using Python.
So just to start off with the basics, what is base year curve?
If you have used Photoshop before, you most likely have seen base year curves before.
It is the way you draw the pen tools, and it's a very natural way to draw the curves
on the computer using only a few control points.
So it was a really good match for Photoshop in particular.
But then I want to talk about how to draw this in Python programmatically.
In my case, I just had to use this to draw a few pen patterns, but that's a long story.
And so there are many dedicated packages to do base year curves, but today I want to talk
about how you would do it using SciPy.
So SciPy is a scientific computing tool in Python.
It has been around for a while.
It is very widely used, and you definitely should use it if you have a chance.
And yeah, so the problem is how do we use it to calculate base year curves?
And it does have a utility to calculate that, and it's called SciPy.interpolating.bpoly.
So if there's any takeaway, it's basically that bpoly is what you would use to draw base
year curves.
And if you are like me, my first reaction was, what the heck is that name?
So it's interpolate, interpolate kind of makes sense, but why is it called bpoly?
So it took me a while to actually make sense of that, and which is why I want to talk about
it today, about how I made sense of it.
So first of all, what does interpolate mean?
So in general, interpolate is the way that we connect the dots.
It is how we fill in the blank between the data points we have.
A naive way to do that would be a linear interpolation by just connecting the dots with straight
lines.
It's janky, it's not very pretty, and so base year is actually a way to interpolate the
control points.
By using techniques that interpolate them, we kind of glide across the points smoothly,
and then we start with the first point, we end with the last point, and the other control
points kind of control where the curves will end up in.
And instead of using linear coefficients for the points, we instead use a basis called
Bernstein polynomials, which is where the name bpoly comes from.
So yeah, bpoly means Bernstein polynomials.
And it is kind of a complicated thing, but for Bernstein polynomials in one sentence,
it is basically a way to do weighted averaging of the points, where the points are emphasized
sequentially from the beginning to the end, but the weights always sum up to one.
So you can see how the curves, different curves, correspond to how important the point
is at each place in the curve, and you can see that the peaks shift between the points.
You start with full emphasis on the first point, and then you shift to the second point,
third point, fourth point, and then the last point.
So yeah, that's the basic of what bccurve is, and then the usage of it is actually not
that complicated.
So I have a small demo here.
So you would just import bpoly from interpolate, and numpy and matpoly are useful in general.
So I have my example here, but let's see if I can code this.
So first, you would start by defining your control points.
Control points is because I have four control points, so it would be a cubic base here.
And then you can define the curve using just bpoly, and then you just pass in the control
points.
And then you just have to do some weird stuff with it.
And then you pass in the interval where you want to say the points, the curve spans in.
So in this case, I say that as the points go from the beginning to the end, it is going
from zero to one.
And that's really it.
That's your basic curve right there.
But then when you want to draw it out, you need to generate a bunch of numbers in between
zero and one.
So I do that using linspace.
So this will generate out the 20 numbers in between zero and one, all the decimals.
And then the points can be created by just calling the bpoly object as a function and
pass in the number.
And you would just get a list of two-dimensional points, just like that.
So it's a really nice syntax, if you ask me.
And then when we have that, we can just plot it out, just like that.
Cool.
And if we also plot out the control points, you will see that it would make sense.
It would look just like a pen tool in Photoshop, just like that.
Cool.
Oh.
Okay.
All right.
That's all I have.
We have 30 seconds left, so cool.