The title of my talk is htmx plus flask modern python web apps hold the javascript and it
should say on the client side this is not something that says you can't write javascript
if you want to write javascript you can htmx is a really cool technology that lets you
use a lot of the server for the exact same behaviors you would get on client side javascript
so there's a lot of people in node using this so it's not an anti javascript it's a you
can choose whatever language you're working with already I imagine many of you would like
python around here and you can choose that and you can keep working it okay so that's
what htmx is my keyboard doesn't work so maybe I'll just type up here or there we go so htmx
it's a library that allows you to do ajax like things server exchange but also css transitions
animations web sockets and so on it's a really cool library it's incredibly easy to use as
you'll see I don't work on htmx I'm not associated with it I'm just a big fan about how it enables
us as python web developers to write way cleaner code and what I'm going to show you later
you're going to be able to look at and say that's the whole thing that's the entire implementation
of it it's really really neat so one of the ideas around htmx is the howl stack this is
something that Carson Gross came up with the guy who created htmx and howl you've heard
of the mean stack and the lamp stack and all these various stacks well with htmx we have
hypertext on whatever language you want you want to write python write python you want
to write go you write go whatever you want so you can write it however you want and I
really appeals to me I had mentioned this talk that I was coming here on Twitter and
someone said I'm really excited about htmx and flask it sounds great but outside it's
kind of being cleaner I mean there's really not anything different because this is what
I'm doing you see like I'm I'm writing code over here on the server and I'm getting html
from the server and I'm putting it on the page and I looked at it I said this this is
not the same thing this looks the same look at the bottom this is the htmx equivalent the entire
code at the bottom is the same as the top hx trigger equals key up hx get equals suggestions
hx target equals place for suggestions that's it that's the whole implementation same as above
really really neat Ryan went on earlier about how it's cool to have declarative code instead
of imperative code where you have to say all the steps htmx is very declarative you just say these
things like I want when this happens when this event happens I want this CSS transition and this
bit of code or this bit of html from the server to show up so just to get a real quick sense of
what's going on here I'm going to show you an example and I'm not a hundred percent sure on
the network here so I may want to switch over so let's see let's go to my phone because this would
be better on not the slow slow network that we've been suffering through all right so let's go over
to htmx and over here they've got some examples and there's all sorts of cool stuff you can do
you can do click to edit you can do like bulk edit you can do infinite scroll you can do progress
bars but let's just look at this real quick click to edit because this is a very different way of
thinking about web development we've thought about writing code on the server and returning
HTML we've thought about Vue.js or React and a bunch of stuff that just shows up on the page
and gets built up out of API's this isn't really either of those so let's let's see here so what
we're gonna do is we're gonna write let me just show you what it does first so down here do a
little zoom for you so we've got this non editable section of our page and we want to edit it so we
want to be able to do something slick like inline click to edit it and change this to you know Sam
or whatever and then hit save then it goes back to non editable there's no JavaScript in this page
that's it's really neat so what is happening how does that work on the examples they have this
little debug toolbar thing at the bottom notice this it says initially that part of the page
started out with this where it had a target what to do when the event happens to replace itself
with whatever it gets from the server and when you click the button where does it get the HTML
it gets it from there that's probably written in Python or you know whatever right for us it would
be written in Python and so when that runs when we click the button what did the server send back
it sent back the HTML that is the form and it put it right there so when I click this
htmx replaces that part of the DOM with that HTML that is a form you can even see when you
submit it back the details that it posts back so this is the exchange is a kind of a mind-bend
you've got to do here to get used to it so it's a little bit different but it is quite neat all
right wait for the screens to catch up all right so I encourage you to check those out we're gonna
write some code because writing code makes it real and what we're gonna do is we're gonna take
an existing web page that I built that has no interactivity on the client side whatever
whatsoever and we're gonna add this idea of active search that is as you type the search results come
out on the page rather than you type something you hit enter you see what happens right so we're
gonna type something up here and get some results there and we even go so far as to add browser
history and the ability to link back deeply into the state of the spa the front of the application
if you will all right so hopefully that sets the stage let's go write some code here don't need
this yet so first let me show you I'm not sure is running at the moment it is not so let me show
you here's this app that I've created for you all it's called the video collector and it it's like
Yahoo from the olden days where you just kind of bookmark and categorize things you like so are
you excited about Python well you come down here and here's some of the Python videos and we can
go watch them like let's see we'll watch this one that Hannah did at one of the this was
Python right so eventually shows up on on YouTube here in a place right so that's really cool and
there's all these different categories like there's stuff on EVs there's stuff on JavaScript
but we go up here we can also search for stuff like if I want to search for in one Apple there's
all the stuff that has to do with them one if I want to search for I don't know car there's all
the results that have to do with car but if I I don't know accidentally refresh the page I get
there's a warning some weird thing is about to happen to your website because I don't know you
were just searching for something now you you can't go there anymore and you can't bookmark it right
you definitely can't send that URL to somebody and have that mean anything right and they've
got to press the button so what I would like is as they type I would like that to happen so
let's go write that we've got 20 minutes to do it might sound like a lot of work not so much all
right so I'm just gonna kind of jump around a little bit this existing page this existing site
is here you know like I said we have 20 whole minutes to do the whole thing so we we don't
have too much but this page here that has the search results it has the search collector the
input and then it has some stuff below let me just give you the quick HTML here so up here is the
input down here is the search results section all right and then it says look if there's some search
text we're gonna loop over the videos and we're gonna show them there's more HTML about how they
get shown it just shows like the YouTube thumbnail and the title and stuff like that so what I want
to do is I want to change this so that we can use HTMX and so what you saw you saw a little bit
of it in those examples before what we will need to do is we need to add a few HX attributes I
do wish there was some kind of autocomplete for this anyone who wants to write a plug-in I would
love you so we're gonna go over here and we're gonna say what are we gonna do to get the search
results we're gonna do a get for videos slash search like that and one spells videos correctly
you're gonna have a way better chance of getting it to work thank you and then where do you want
to put the results when you get it you're gonna say HX target equals you do a CSS selector there's
a thing at the bottom down here that has an ID of search results so you just hash search results
not there you just hash search results it's gonna go into that section that's super easy and the
last thing is what what is gonna cause this it could be a button click it could be the page is
loaded so you got to have a trigger and the trigger is going to be a key up now this is
gonna look like it might might do what you want it's probably not gonna do what we want all right
let's rerun this flash should restart but let's just be safe so if I go over here again and we
go to the search and I say let's search for M1 look at this no what is happening at the bottom
there well I told it to give me what is that video slash search that's the whole page that's weird
right I don't want that that's odd so what we can do there's a couple ways we can solve this but we
can go over to the the complicated implementation area on the server where we're doing our Python
and we can ask a cool question we can say if this view model which sort of holds the data of the
exchange if this is an if this is an HTMX request if it is we're gonna do something different and
what we want to do is we just want to have a little bit of the HTML just the fragment of HTML
so we're gonna not create a notebook we are going to create an HTML page that's like a partial so
I'm gonna call this search results yeah sure it can go and get up that's fine thank you get up
and what we want is just the code that we had here which is I'm gonna collapse it so that I
can actually copy it successfully so I want that bit right there okay I'm just put it over here
and did I miss a piece something has gone wrong oh I called it Python didn't I you all didn't
even stop me HTML there we go so we're gonna return this that's the same code I just literally
ripped it out of there I'm gonna say if it's that I'm gonna do a little bit of work I'm gonna say
HTML equals flash dot render template and if you look over at this section it needs some videos
it's all the data that it needs is videos so I gotta come over here and say the template name
which is videos videos slash partial gotta love the autocomplete search results and then we got
to pass some data so videos equals video VM dot videos and then we got to return this as a
response so return flash dot make response HTML all right let's try this again this was not
looking pretty I know I'm still in that we're out we're free finally so if I type in one look at
that what else should we search for HTML yeah HTML X there we go we could search for Indycard
and search for Python search for bytes all right now did you see all that flicker that was not
nice that's not nice at all and our server hated it I mean even though we're running an engine X
maybe be good but no wasn't good so what we can do is we can go back over here to this one in our
HTML X section and we can go for that trigger I want a few more things I want to say delay delay
I think it's delayed I'm gonna find out 250 milliseconds the other thing that you didn't
notice is if I move the arrow keys that don't make any meaningful change to the page or the
input it'll still do that so I can say I want to make sure the value of the text actually changes
so rerun refresh let's try this again right look at that now if I type in one you can it'll wait
oh no it doesn't I got to refresh it maybe not you know I'm guessing it's delay not delayed what
do you all think there we go all right so now we can come out yeah look at that Indy and boom
in that smooth in one and then the answers come in so let's go back and review let's review where
where is the server side or the client side JavaScript well that's that's what we wrote to
make that happen there's a lot of code running there's a lot of searches and database stuff
happening but it's happening on the server over here I mean there's not a lot of code right but
that's where it's happening so that's pretty cool now one more thing I would like to show you do
we have time oh yeah we got so much time okay so let's go over here and add one more thing because
check this out so suppose I want to search for Apple now was it m1 now is it dub dub dub DC type
it out the way you say it now let's go back maybe I want the one before wait it's gone where to go
right like there's no there's no browser history which is weird so we can actually go a little
farther and say hx-push-url equals true we refresh and wait I don't know why that is in there all
right so you go over here and let's say search for m1 can you all see that did that zoom right on look
at that search is in one now let's go to Apple let's go to Indy and now now let's go back look
at that I still haven't written more JavaScript right five ten okay this is a super cool technology
it lets us write the code that we want on the server we don't have to deal with weird API
authorizations because you're on the server you just talk to the database you interact with your
APIs whatever you need to do on the server you just do it and then you get the answer right here
it's really fantastic so there is a problem though now that we have this what is the temptation to
paste it or share it or link to it if you have a URL and you have a web app you should probably be
able to use the URL in the web app that seems reasonable right in spas in rich JavaScript apps
is often called deep linking so we would like to be able to do that here as well now it turns out
it's actually already working but something is odd so remember when I cut this code out here I
said we're gonna go and put all this stuff over here well the reason nothing's happening is if
I actually put this back in that's duplicating a bunch of nasty HTML but let's just go with that
for a minute and I hit enter look at that now we got deep linking again pretty straightforward
pretty easy but we have this really challenging problem of linking this stuff together so then
you want to talk about ginger partials this thing that I released that allows you to create this
code in one place and then use it in multiple places like that it is similar but not the same
as there's a whole discussion at the bottom that it's not include and it is not macro it is similar
but not the same okay so over here at the startup of this app I've put one line of code
this ginger partials register extensions and by doing that I can then go over here and say you
know what that was a bad idea to put all that there what I'm gonna do is I'm just gonna say
render partial and let me just copy this so I don't make a mistake this like that and then
we got to pass the this is like a function in HTML videos equal videos and now if I rerun it to
make sure it's totally new go over here run the same code you get exactly the same output here it
is but it allows us to build up these really cool little partials and then reuse them throughout
our page so let me show you five minutes close yeah okay oh so much time okay so let me show
you another feature over here then I'll just walk you through it so another thing that's cool is
we have infinite scroll so you can come down here and we have infinite scroll for all the popular
videos right that's also not very much so how would you go about implementing implementing infinite
scroll let's do that in HTML which is feed right there this this is the HTML page for infinite
scroll here's the title and here's a fragment of videos I got come from this video list and
then over in the video list we've got a couple of videos and if there are more videos after this
set after this page I'm going to do an HX get more videos the trigger is revealed replace this
little animator spin thing and that's it so this idea of render partial plus HTML allows you to
build super clean web pages and flask and avoid using a second language which happens
to be JavaScript as your only choice but it allows you to just stay in Python work on the
server but get something that feels like behaves for the user like some kind of front-end application
some kind of spa all right so let me just wrap that up real quick a few things wait for it to
all right so to trigger that remember all we had to do is set four attributes HX get HX triggers
key up HX target is the place it goes and then we added the history in deep linking with push URL
how do we know what to do on the server side there's actually this HX HTMX header is HX
header that is passed along I buried in a class so I don't have to think about it again but down
inside that class we just say HX requests in the headers that means it came from that's a
partial request you should treat it as partially otherwise it's just give me the page super easy
and then if you want to deep link all you got to do is handle both requests at the same URL so this
one is the partial response and this one is the deep link and it's good to go all right so I
interviewed the creator of this framework Carson Gross on talk python when was that episode 321
I guess this summer so if you want to hear more from the guy who created it you can listen that
episode he's a really clever guy he's got a lot of interesting philosophy about how software should
be built and put together and stuff so definitely check that out if you're interested if you want
the source code from this presentation if you want that demo app you can go to talk python.fm slash
htmx there it has the that's the landing page for this course I have on htmx you can check that out
but as far as the source code goes right down at the top right at the top of that page you can click
and go over to github and see that so if you want more info talk python.fm slash htmx check that out