My name is Ryan Morced. I'm the creator of IDOM and I'm going to be talking about how
IDOM is like React but in Python. IDOM is a new framework for building full stack interactive
web applications in pure Python. And I think it can be best compared to other solutions
like Plotly Dash, Streamlit, PyWebIO. Basically, if you're trying to build web application
but you don't want to learn JavaScript, just like it was mentioned a little bit earlier.
So before I talk about IDOM, I want to talk a little bit of history and give some insight
into why I created IDOM in the first place. Like, why does it need to exist? I'm going
to start with that by talking about the IPython notebook. So the IPython notebook is a browser-based
computing environment for Python that came to popularity around 2010 to 2012. At a time
where Python was relegated to being a backend technology that really just rendered HTML
templates. Well, in years prior, that might have been okay. There was a growing need for
a browser-based interactivity. And at that time, Python really didn't have a good answer
for that. Through the notebook though, with its rich graphical output, Python developed
an answer in the notebook. And the notebook has really remained popular today in the form
of JupyterLab and the rest of the Jovian ecosystem that has succeeded it. And part of the reason
that Jupyter and what was previously the IPython notebook has remained popular is this technology
called IPyWidgets, which is a related project that came about around 2012. And it leveraged
the IPython notebook's APIs to give Python some bi-directional communication with the
browser. And thus, it brought interactivity to Python beyond what you could just get from
a standard REPL or even just the graphical outputs that you were originally getting in
the notebook. So from this example here, we can see there's a basic slider. And as you
move it back and forth, it's triggering some Python code that in turn prints out, I guess,
the square of the number that's on the slider. So I also want to emphasize the fact that
IPyWidgets was especially important not in just growing the popularity of the IPython
notebook, but also in growing the popularity of Python among scientists because it allowed
for the creation of interactive computing tools by non-engineers. And scientists no
longer had to learn JavaScript in order to make user interfaces for themselves or others
that would make their work more understandable and accessible. Since the IPython notebook,
we've grown spoiled for choice in this kind of domain. You have Bokeh, Panel, Potlydash,
Streamlet. And even IPyWidgets has kind of become a UI framework in and of itself through
tools like Voila that strip away the whole notebook interface and just show you the outputs
of your code. But before we get too excited about this progress, I want to take a step
back and talk about what some of these frameworks could do better because many suffer from a
similar set of problems. And the way I want to do that is by looking at what has happened
in the world of JavaScript UI frameworks as of late. And this is where the React part
of the title comes in. And just for some context for myself, how many of you guys have at least
heard of React? Okay. That's a lot. Even at a Python conference, that's pretty impressive,
right? So, I think it goes to show like how important React is that a bunch of just Python
developers know what this JavaScript technology is. And if you haven't heard of React, don't
worry about that. Part of the point of this talk is that I don't want you to actually
have to learn JavaScript and React. And basically, what I want to focus on with React is what
it got right about building UIs and how that's informed IDOM as a technology. So, basically,
in this world of JavaScript UI frameworks, around 2015 to 2017, there was this paradigm
shift where these new declarative JavaScript frameworks like React and Vue started gaining
popularity over old imperative ones like AngularJS. And just looking at this graph here, this
trend is rather decisive and React isn't going anywhere anytime soon. So, to understand
why this is, I want to discuss those two terms I just mentioned, imperative versus declarative.
And at a high level, what these two terms mean is they refer to programming paradigms.
And depending on what context you're working in, what paradigm you're using could just
be a stylistic choice when you might not even be fully aware that you're making or it could
be something that's kind of restricted for you by the framework you're using or the language
that you're using. So, what's the difference between these two? Well, what it means to
operate within an imperative paradigm, if you're developing a web application, is that
you as the developer are responsible for defining the states that your app evolves through,
but you're also responsible for dealing with all of the details of the transitions between
those states. How do you get from A to B? So, you kind of have, you're forced to have
a lot of fine-grained control over all of what's happening in your application. And
the declarative paradigm though, on the other hand, you're only responsible for defining
the states that your application evolves through, but you're not necessarily responsible for
dealing with all of the details, the transitions. That is handled for you by the framework or
the language that you're using. So, why are these declarative JavaScript frameworks gaining
market share over the imperative ones? Well, you may have noticed from the description
I just gave that in the declarative paradigm, there's just kind of one less thing for developers
to worry about. Now, this comes at the cost of some control, but usually we aren't concerned
with that because in the process of implementing all of these transitions, we can introduce
bugs and it's just a lot of work. So, given all this context about what's happened in
the JavaScript world, we should look back at this kind of ecosystem of Python UI frameworks
that's developed and ask whether or not they've kind of learned this similar lesson that building
UIs using declarative patterns makes, is easier and easier to do correctly. And unfortunately,
no, not really. Almost all of these in one form or another suffer from the problems of
imperative design patterns. Plotly here, it might be one exception, but it's limited in
some other ways that I'll touch on later. And so, this is where IDOM comes in. Unlike
its peers, IDOM takes heavy inspiration from the React UI framework and thus has many of
its same declarative virtues. Beyond that though, IDOM as a UI framework for Python
is unusually powerful because it puts nearly all the same capabilities of React into the
hands of Python developers, which mind you, React is a JavaScript framework. And having
near parity with the features of a JavaScript framework is kind of unheard of. I personally
haven't heard of anything that does this. So, what can you make with IDOM? Well, let's
just go here and look at some of these. So, in IDOM, you can make some kind of basic interactive
dashboards. And the interesting thing about this is I implemented this in pure Python.
I didn't even have to write a JavaScript binding to this victory charting library to get this
to work. And this is a little bit slow because of all the things going on right now, but
yeah, you can see this is working live. Here's another example of me integrating with a JavaScript
library without having to write any JavaScript binding. This is the pigeon mapping library.
And I can also use some basic HTML components, just like this little audio bit here. And
you can see I get some event information back from this as well, like what is the current
time in the audio. And the other cool thing is I have all the same awesome bits of Python.
Like, I have this Matplotlib plot here. Like, sometimes you really can't. Matplotlib is
extremely fully featured and sometimes you can't beat it. And this last example here,
I think is, while it's not a particularly practical example, I think it does demonstrate
like the complexity that you can get with IDOM. I'd challenge anybody to try and implement
Snake using Streamlet or something like that. I think it'd be a great challenge. So, this
is all pretty cool. Oops. So, what does it actually look like to create something with
IDOM? So, I'm going to try and do this live here. It's a little bit low. So, maybe I can
type like this. So, sorry about this. So, I'm going to import IDOM. Oops. This has happened
every time I've tried to do this. Okay. Cool. So, I'm going to import IDOM. That's the first
thing I'm going to do. And the very next thing I'm going to do is I'm going to define what's
called a component. And a component is basically just an independent and kind of isolated portion
of your UI that you can reuse over and over again. It allows you to just think in the
context of that component without having to worry about the rest of your user interface.
And you create these components using functions. Now, just to get started here, I'm just going
to create a little button that just says, hello. And then I'm going to run it. Now,
in this demo, this is happening live. But if you were to actually do this for real,
you'd have some little message in your terminal saying that there's a server that was started.
You navigate to the URL. And then, then you'd see this little button show up. So, the next
kind of expansion that I want to do on this is I want to make this button track the number
of times that we click it. And this is for people who are familiar with React, this is
going to look incredibly similar to anything that you would normally do in React. But for
people who aren't, it might look a little bit weird. And I don't really have time to
go into all the details on this, but I would encourage you to investigate, not just say
this looks weird, but investigate it a little bit because like I tried to demonstrate earlier,
these kind of declarative patterns have really won out in the JavaScript world. So, we shouldn't
just dismiss them here. So, the way that we're going to do this is we're going to use what's
called a hook. Oops, this is again. And basically, what's happening here, oh, goodness, that's
not happened before. Okay. Hopefully, I don't run into that same bug.
Okay. Well, I don't think we're going to get to look at this. So basically, yes,
this is crashing the whole thing. Shoot. Classic. Okay. So, we're going to skip over this. But
basically, what idon does is it uses a pattern called hooks that is adapted from React. And
the way it works is that you get back this kind of count and you get this set count callback
back. And when you call the set count callback, that function that I was defining before will
actually get rerun. And instead of modifying an existing button, you actually return a new button
that includes the new count. So, it's kind of a different pattern. And if we were to look at this
code in idon, it would look almost identical to this React code here. It's not super important
that you understand this JavaScript code, but there would be kind of this similar pattern of
having a function. You'd have this hook and you'd return this button that has an event handler
attached to it. Okay. Hopefully, we're back on track now. So, how does this work and why
haven't some of these other UI frameworks done the same thing? Well, the main reason they
haven't is it comes down to their general architecture. Items peers, I think PlotlyDash is a
particularly informative example here. Go down the route of synchronizing models between the
server and the client. And so, basically, what that means is the model is representing some
underlying state of the application and the server changes the model and it sends it over to the
client and the client turns that model into the actual view that you end up seeing. The problem
with designing things in this way is responsibilities of displaying something to the user are divided
between the server and the client. The server is responsible for updating the model, the model
state, and the client is responsible for turning that model into the view. And since Python
developers are stuck on the server, you basically lose out on having control over how that model
turns into the view that you actually see. IDOM, on the other hand, goes this route of synchronizing
a representation of the view and that representation is called VDOM. I'm not going to get into the
details of what this VDOM is because that could be an entirely separate talk in and of itself.
But as a result of this, it gives Python developers control over how the model, the underlying model
of their application is being converted into the view. And the specific implementation here shows
how these kind of composable components that I mentioned earlier get put together. They create
this representation of the view and what the layout does is it looks at the last time that
the view is rendered and it looks at this time, checks for the differences and it only sends the
client. So, given this, that's how IDOM gets so much control over what's happening. So,
the last thing that I want to touch on here that is enabled by this kind of pattern as
well is ecosystem independence. And actually, I'm realizing this is maybe another good way
to show you that example I was trying to before. So, what this means is that a lot of these other
frameworks kind of lock you into their way of doing things. And if you were to write a JavaScript
component or even on the Python side, if you were to try and take that to somewhere else,
like, I don't know, if you wrote something in Streamlit and then you wanted to take it to a
Jupyter Notebook or vice versa, that's simply not possible. But with IDOM, you can take the
exact same code that you might use in a standalone application and just run it, say, in a Jupyter
Notebook. And you can see all these same examples from before just kind of show up. The other
especially cool thing about doing things in this way is that integration with JavaScript is
incredibly simple. I was talking about how I didn't have to write any JavaScript bindings
to get some of these examples to work, like this plot here. And that's because I'm just loading
them right from a CDN. And here's an example of that. Here's a material UI button, if anybody's
familiar with that kind of UI style thing. I'm just loading it directly from a CDN and very little
Python code to make that happen. And yeah. So, see, that's kind of the end of the content. So,
given that my demo didn't really work before, hopefully, I should have an opportunity here to
go through and show you what I wanted to do before. So, I've been trying to do this demo
little component. And I was trying to get this count, set count. Okay. And we now have this
hello text to start out. Okay. This is working. Okay. So, basically what's going on here is... So,
I was trying to explain before is this concept of hooks. And basically what's going on with this
use state thing is it returns some count, which defaults to zero. And I also get this callback,
which allows me to update the count later. And when I call this, it's not going to modify an
existing button, like I was mentioning before. It's actually going to rerun this demo function.
But when I get to this line, instead of the count being zero, it will be the new count that I just
set. So, let's take a look at what that actually looks like in practice. So, first thing I'm going
to do is I'm going to update this button, the text of this button to be clicked count times. And the
next bit I'm going to do, I suppose display that. So, next thing I'm going to do here is I'm going
to actually bind a callback to this button that responds when I click it and will increment the
count. And I do that through this kind of special name on click. And I'm going to assign a lambda to
it, which gets an event as an argument. And then the action of this callback is that I'm going to
increment the count. Count plus one. And there we go. Oops. Don't need that. There we go. So, now
when I click this, it'll increment the count. Okay. So, I was a little out of order, but yeah,
that's the end of my talk about IDOM and how it's like React, but in Python.