Happy Thanksgiving weekend. I know it's kind of weird having Thanksgiving on in
October but I am from Canada. I'm actually came and flew down from Toronto
originally just because I really wanted to show you about a lot of diagrams of
arrows and boxes and talking about architecture because it's something
that we don't talk about too much. Yes we should and basically as systems grow
bigger they get complicated. So at the very start of the project you know we're
super happy high-fiving yes we've just made our first sale we raised our first
round of funding or maybe these are the people before you joined where they're
super super happy and then all of a sudden god damn it I need help I can't
manage this code base everything is going wrong I can't make heads or tails
of it we need help and basically these are some slides from Jason Gorman and as
a project continues on productivity just plummets in a lot of projects and guess
what the cost skyrockets in payroll and this is very unsustainable this kills
companies this is something that you need to keep the check of and it's all
about developer velocity we want to maintain developer velocity over time so
what happens well too much knowledge is required to make simple changes our
simple system is no longer simple you have many people working on many parts
of the code base basically stepping on each other's toes I'm sure everybody in
this room has been in this situation at least once in their lifetime so what can
we do well it's all about building high cohesive systems that are loosely
coupled so the goal of software architecture is really to minimize the
human resources required to build and maintain a required system so what we
really want is we want to build a bunch of Lego blocks so then we can build
amazing structures like the CN tower so first let's talk about like what our app
might be today so many people use whether it's Django flask rails you name
it a lot of MVC frameworks I know some of them are gonna be called MVC some of
their multi-view presenter I'm just gonna call them MVC just to make life
easier for myself and if you think about you got a client the top layer you have
like that controller view layer and then you have the model layer usually some
kind of active record pattern which is your arm and then you talk to the
database and as things grow you should be like all right where the hell do I
put all my logic so you really have like two choices that people talk about you
got fat controllers or fat models and unfortunately neither of them really
really work so someone comes along says you know what you need a service layer
so let's put all of our codes somewhere in the middle and if you think about it
you have the controller service layer model layer you basically recreated an
enterprise pattern that's been around for 30 40 years called layered
architecture and specifically you're most likely following open layered
architecture where each layer you can actually access there's no protection
between them and that kills your project I don't know how many times I've seen
code where it goes through some kind of business layer but then the controller
just decides to talk to the model directly and save to the database and
get and basically bypass all the security rules what we probably would
rather do is the closed layered architecture it's that same MVC but
this time we basically only depend on the layer below us and you cannot go and
jump layers so we again want a very very small presentation tier we don't want a
fat presentation tier no one likes to get fat we want all of our logic to be
right in that middle and then we want the data layer to be pretty simple
because we're not really programming databases in enterprise web apps what
we're doing is we're programming behavior and we actually don't want to
be tied to our databases but we still have a problem and that is that
everything still depends on the data layer we really haven't really changed
much we just move the code around and now we still have to figure out okay how
can we get rid of the dependence on the data layer which is really an
infrastructure concern so let's do some thinking and is there a concept that you
learn very very early on in some software theory that could actually help
us with this problem and as we write code we we learn to write modular code
because it's easier to read easier to maintain and we really will have like
smaller units of work and but we still have the dependency problem instead of
having one huge thousand line function now we have a bunch of classes all over
the place they all still depend on each other so we can have either implicit
software dependencies or we could have explicit software dependencies and
implicit software dependencies that in the code you just directly create the
model or the relationship that you want an explicit one is that you actually
pass it in and I'm going to name that motor less dependency injection where
the two most common ways of doing an explicit dependency is either through
the constructor when you construct the object or through a setter sometimes you
have to use the center because the framework that you're using just won't
allow you to have access to that constructor and this allows us to at
runtime specify what our dependency is so I could have a booking manager system
so my example here is basically a clone of an Airbnb booking system rental
property system where the booking manager has a method called process
payment and that's directly hooked up to a stripe implementation but that's
still not really what we want because we're still dependent on stripe we're
still dependent on our database models and this is where polymorphism comes in
so polymorphism is the whole if it walks like a duck if it talks like a duck if
it quacks like a duck it's probably a duck so we can use polymorphism and what
we can do is we can actually invert the dependency so we actually can move the
dependency management in this diagram to the left by introducing an abstraction
and what we want to do is we want to program to these very very stable
abstractions and what a stable abstraction really means is that
something that does not change frequently so what we want to do is we
want to isolate the code that we're going to be working on over and over and over
again maybe we're changing an algorithm to be more performant but that does not
change the behavior of our system and that's really what we want to focus on
so here in the diagram you can see that we actually created an interface that
has one method called process payment and then we have multiple we have like a
stripe implementation we could have a PayPal implementation or even a fake a
testing fake implementation that we can run our tests faster where we can
actually run end-to-end unit tests that are collaborative where we don't actually
have to depend on a web call so here's some examples of actual Python code
because it is a Python conference I thought some Python code would be nice
yeah so I believe in type checking I also believe that typing really does
solve a lot of problems I do know that you can do implicit typing which is
basically again the whole reason why Python is duct typed in the first place
but I find that you can't trust that especially as your application grows
very well because then you end up the only way you can trust is by doing a
lot of testing and sometimes it's just easier to do this part of your CI
process so on the left hand side I have structural typing so here we're doing
typing through using a mixin or through inheritance and then on the right hand
side there's a way of doing kind of nominal typing especially in MyPy and
that's more of you still get the type checking and still get duck typing where
you don't have to do that inheritance chain I personally think inheritance is
the devil I'd prefer composition but you do have a little bit of a runtime cost
and these are just two ways that you can actually create this interface this
abstract interface and the implementation that goes with it to
break that dependency so let's go back now so we know at the code level we can
invert our dependencies and we can program to standard stable interfaces
could we do that with the layers and yes we can we take our original on the left
layered architecture and we can actually invert the dependency of the data layer
up towards the business and domain layer and I don't know about you but this has
a name this has many names actually so we have hexagonal architecture some
people call it the onion architecture clean architecture or ports and
adapters architecture and the whole idea is is that instead of pointing down
towards your data layer data flow still goes that way we actually point inwards
and we have a very simple rule while we're developing is that the domain
layer or your business layer is nothing but plain old Python objects plain old
popos and we all the dependencies have to go inwards in the inner code cannot
depend on anything on the outside and this is basically as you grow your
application you have to again change a lot of infrastructure code your
infrastructure code actually changes usually more often than your domain
code and this way you don't have to rewrite your application every time you
change what database schema you're using here's just another diagram as I
mentioned clean architecture this one's more of a circle and you can see that
on the left-hand side I it's a slice of a cone where the very middle is your
abstract general rarely change that's where your business rules are again
plain old code nothing special and then the very outside is the part that really
changes all the time and this is how you can isolate those changes and again not
have to rip all your hair out while you're building a system so let's talk
about a little bit of those layers internally so we have the entity layer
and this is really where your main models live and in this is where like
domain driven design can really really help I'm trying to keep a really DDD
light for this talk because I could be bore you forever for DDD and in terms
of DDD you basically have inside of this layer you have also entity models I know
it's confusing because it's the entity layer but you have entity models value
objects domain services factories and aggregate routes I'm gonna go through
them like a lightning talk so first we have value objects wouldn't it be nice
if we just use very simple data types to actually do attributes on our object so
we know how we use strings we know how we use integers so when we change an
integer on an object we don't like mutate it we just throw the old one out
and put a new one in couldn't we do that with data objects that are more
complex that provide meaning so I have here value objects so value objects have
no identity they do not exist on their own and the best way to use them is by
creating immutable objects data classes that have frozen keywords awesome
because you have a runtime check to make sure that you can't modify this in
Python so this is just a simple way of describing a class and you're getting I
got sorry not a class an address but the address is now treated as one variable
that you change in a get-go then we have entity objects and an entity object has
two special properties one it has a lifespan so it changes over time and two
it has uniqueness within your system so in this example I have a rental property
and a rental property can change its availabilities it can be booked it can
be unbooked and we use value objects to also help describe entities and entities
can actually have an object graph to other entities but when you're designing
your entities what you really want to avoid is anemic domain models every
single person including myself especially when I'm prototyping I am not
going to do a domain model at the very beginning I'm just going to do very much
a transactional script where I'm gonna have a data object and then I have a
bunch of code that changes that data object which if the app is very very
simple that is the right approach but over time that model you spread all your
logic everywhere around I'm gonna show an example in a second and you just you
bleed you cry and you just sweat and your life is a living hell and it just
sometimes worth creating a rich model from the very beginning so here's an
anemic model I tried to keep it really simple hopefully it's not too simple so
we have a renter object and the renter object is just like a data class but it
mutates and you can see that all the logic is in some other method like
you're fetching the renter and you're changing the address from a web request
and what ends up happening is that every single client of your code
re-implements logic and now you have and in places where you have to figure out
how the code works and it's even worse where sometimes people push this logic
to the client which could be a JavaScript app now your JavaScript app
has to figure out what parts of a renter are you changing are you changing their
contact information are you changing their billing information because the
model itself does not know and unfortunately anemic models come a lot
when you're using arms because we don't actually put methods on them to actually
help them manage themselves so we're kind of breaking that classic OOP theory
of you have methods you have command methods that change internal state so
this is a rich domain model the only difference here is we actually have a
method called update address and this is where the object can change itself and
all the logic lives in one spot even better you can use invariants and variants
are just a way of protecting yourself where if a programmer tries to use your
object you will throw an exception your code should never get here in production
this is more of a something to catch an error from the very beginning or you can
use descriptors and domain services are just code with no state that helps your
domain model now the biggest thing I want to take away is the aggregate route
that is your unit of work and that's what you fetch from the database and
that's what you're going to actually save in the database so that's what you
hydrate in this example we have two entities we have a property owner or
rental property and these are also aggregate routes because this is where
our operations are going to be and these are going to be the resources in our
restful API if we go that route but what about the database how do we keep that
simple well the repository patterns again a way of abstracting data where
we can use Elasticsearch Postgres Mongo and the aggregate route is perfect for
NoSQL because usually it can be a document so here's just a way of
defining it you just have simple CRUD methods and you implement them depending
on what your back end is and this is just an example of how you can call from
a Django app an API view to create that web tier facade to actually call into
your code another best practice is using data transfer objects between layers
because you don't want to leak abstractions do you do this all the time
not really it's really if you need to if you want to protect your layers and this
is just a detailed example of data classes are great for that and you can
see here that I have the same arc the same components in all three
architectures the first one is layered then I have component based hexagonal
based and hybrid and I just moved around the components but this the same
components exist everywhere and this is just a way of organizing your code and a
great way of thinking about doing unit tests is you want to test behavior and
you want to test the behavior of a component and you want to keep all the
inside messy so you can change it without having to rewrite all your tests
all the time one thing I hate is test maintenance and people do too much
testing or no testing at all so in this case you would only test the things are
not grayed out and it makes your life a lot easier and that's just talking about
that and you want to use collaborative unit tests want to reduce mocking as
much as possible if you're going to use mocking inject it don't just monkey
patch it or duck punching as it used to be called and do I always follow this
rules well it depends if I'm building a very simple microservice crud app I
probably won't follow these rules if I know I might have to change the database
because I need to do optimizations maybe I will do the request layer and the
domain layer as one unit and the database will switch with a repository
pattern or I might even invert that the other way where I might never switch the
data layer and I'm only changing what calls into my application and the whole
point is by really simplifying where the code changes and we keep it in one spot
and that's all I have so thank you