Just as a quick overview, for several years now, Python has had syntax for type annotations
where you can annotate variables and in functions and more recently on classes and local variables
and there are a variety of type checkers that are used with this. This can help you catch
a lot of bugs at sort of before running the code. Here, we complain that we're calling
a method eggs on a string which doesn't exist and perhaps more useful in a lot of cases,
we can catch errors like passing none when you expected to actually have something which
is an advantage we have over type systems like Java's, for example. There are a lot
of different type checkers. MyPy, which has some people at Dropbox working at it and general
community, PyType out of Google, PyWrite out of Facebook, PyWrite out of Microsoft and
PyAnalyze out of Quora. I'd recommend MyPy but then again, I would. I think it in general
has more community upkeep and is less focused on sort of just one company though also it
has plenty of its own problems. But the main thrust of this talk is just talking about
what the developments in typing have been sort of in the last year or two in Python
3.9 and 3.10 and in recent MyPy's. So, one of the big ones is what we call modular typeshed
and if you're not familiar, typeshed is a collection of type annotations for lots of
different Python libraries. Historically, it had the standard library and a few important
third-party libraries and would be bundled with MyPy itself. This had a bunch of downsides
like that it was tied to the MyPy release cycle. But we've moved to a model called modular
typeshed where each third-party library that has stubs in typeshed for what their types
are can be installed separately through PyPI. This is inspired by the TypeScripts world
definitely typed. It maintains a lot of the advantages of having a big monolithic repository
of types which is that you don't need each project to sort of manage it themselves because
they might not care about typing and you can sort of have one throat to choke about it.
But it allows sort of each library to be versioned independently. It means that type checkers
can be released separately from the stub changes and everything's sort of lower risk. So that's
been a big improvement. One thing, another thing is PEP 585 which adds type hinting to
standard collections. Previously you needed to import everything from a typing module
and write your lists and dicts with these uppercase lists and dicts but now you can
just write regular lowercase dict and str and have the types there which is great. Another
nice thing is for union types you can now just write them with an or. So you can write
foo or baz instead of having to type out union foo baz with something you imported from typing.
You could also write instead of optional str you could write str or none. I hate that.
I think that's just so ugly but that's fine. Not everyone needs to agree with me. There's
I think that or is fine. I think or none is just it hurts my soul even though it's true.
PEP 612 is a PEP out of the pyre crew at Facebook that allows you to do much better typing for
decorators. Historically MyPy has been able to type decorators that don't change the type
of the function but sometimes you have something that adds a argument or two or changes the
return type and there's now a system for specifying that kind of type which is really nice except
MyPy doesn't implement it. So hopefully we'll do that soon. And then there's another nice
feature that came out of the PyWrite crew at Microsoft which is MyPy and other type
checkers have always let you sort of refine what the notion of a type is in a function
by checking like if x is instance of something and then you know that it's that type or if
x is none then you know it's none in that branch and not none in the other. But if you
had a more complicated thing like wanting to check if all objects in a list were a string
for example there's no way to do that. And type guards add a sort of user specifiable
way to say like if this function gets called and it returns true then we know that its
argument was this type. And this is in some sense really unsound because there's no way
for the type checker to check that like it's true that we're right about it. But assuming
you write the function right it can be very convenient. All right. So that was a lightning
overview of what's happened in most of what's happened in the typing world in the last year
or two. If you have any other questions about it I'll be around. Thank you very much.