Okay, can you hear me well? Okay, amazing.
Hi everybody, thanks for coming.
Today I'm going to talk about testing.
And testing is great, but if you do it wrong, sometimes it's not so great.
Quick intro, my name is Shai. I've been in the industry for a while now.
Mostly hands-on engineering, but also other roles like products and management.
Principal developer at Codium AI, so my day job is working on tools to generate tests.
So that's a pretty nice thing for someone who loves testing.
Lots of interesting stuff going on in that field if you want to talk about, come catch me later.
My purpose for the talk today is to help you get a better ROI on the way to doing testing.
And I'm going to talk about concrete things I've seen that have a tendency to hurt that,
either to make us work more on testing or make that work less effective.
And naturally not everything is going to be a good match for everything.
We saw some stuff also going through an adjustment, so we take the basic concepts and see what applies to you.
We're going to talk about different practices, different ways that we can work,
and how they affect our lives by changing some important properties of our tests.
And the main properties that we're going to see, first, strength, how we good our tests are at catching bugs.
Maintainability, how easy it is for us to deal with the test as things change.
And dealing with change is very important because as developers,
dealing with change is one of the main things that we do.
Changes to requirements, changes to scale, even stuff like changes to the team as new developers join.
And performance, long does it take for the test to run?
And this might seem like a secondary consideration because computers are fast,
but as we'll see, it doesn't matter.
So, 10 ways to shoot yourself in the foot with tests.
Foot gun one: there are no tests.
It is better to have some tests than to not have any tests.
Even if they're not well written, even if they seem like just a drop in the sea,
they still catch bugs and it's still improvement.
So if you don't have any tests, my suggestion, start with something small, simple,
and just slowly keep improving.
Foot gun two: If it doesn't fail, it doesn't pass.
Sometimes our tests lie to us.
We have a test that's supposed to protect us from something, but that something still happens.
And obviously in these cases, the test just didn't check what we thought it does.
Maybe we copypasted and forgot to change something.
And my suggestion now to avoid this is to always make your test fail.
Whenever you write a test and for every assertion,
make a tiny change either to the code or to the test and see that it fails in the way that you expect it to fail.
And only then after you've saw that it fails, consider it a passing test.
Foot gun 3:
Testing too many things.
So, just like product code, if you try to put too many things in the same place, we get a mess.
And my rule of thumb here is that we want to check a single fact about the behavior of the code.
Right? And it helps you use these words mentally.
Single fact about the behavior.
For example, let's say we have a book store and we want to test the edit book functionality.
Now, this is a single fact about the behavior of the code.
The user can edit their own book.
And this is not a single fact.
Test edit book.
It's general.
How do they compare?
Well, with a single fact test, it's clear what it checks.
And it's clear that it only checks that.
But with a more general test, we don't know.
Anything can be there.
And in order to understand, we're going to need to read and understand all the code of the test.
And when the single fact test fails, it's very clear which functionality has stopped working.
And also because it doesn't check a lot of things, it's probably going to be easy to debug it.
But with a general test, if it fails anything related to edit book, might have failed.
We're going to need to find out.
And also, again, because it does a lot of stuff, it might be more difficult to debug.
So I really recommend going with a simple, smaller one.
Foot gun 4:
Unclear language.
The words that we use make a big difference in how we think about a test.
And also, of course, in how easy it is to understand them.
And the guidelines I use for myself is, first, like we said,
try to test a single fact about the behavior of the code.
Well, this is not the language itself, but it's a really sets the tone.
We want to use decisive language, and we want our language to be specific and explicit.
And a few examples, starting with the one that we saw, test edit book.
Again, this is general and pretty hard to understand, so it's not the way that we want to go.
Adding things like "works" or "is correct", usually that's just bloat and doesn't really help us.
Test users should be able to edit their own book.
So this is bloated and very long, but it's also better.
It's much more specific.
And the only problem here is this incisive language.
It's pretty confusing.
I mean, why "should"?
Are we not sure about this?
Is there any way that sometimes it's not going to be true? So that's not really optimal.
And again, that just sounds like a single fact.
A user can edit their own book.
It's decisive, specific, and explicit, and I suggest to always try to go with this kind of language if you can.
Foot gun 5: the devil's in the details.
Tests that show or hide too much detail are much more difficult to understand.
For example, let's say we're testing a browser and we have the data in a different file.
So in the beginning of the test, we're going to read that file, then we're going to use that data.
And no matter what the test checks, the problem is it's impossible to know if it's correct
without going somewhere else and looking.
It breaks the flow.
And it's definitely a problem if it's in a different file, but even if it's a constant at the top of
this file, it still breaks the flow.
And sometimes we can't avoid this, right?
But a lot of the times we can.
Maybe try something like this.
Exactly the same test, but the data is local.
And if you can find a data sample that's small enough, that fits locally, it really does help.
But the flip coin side of this is when we have too much detail, so much stuff going on.
It's going to be pretty hard to spot the important stuff.
So my suggestion here, just try organizing a little bit.
Some empty lines in comments go a long way.
Not a lot of work, but it still helps a lot.
Foot gun six:
The test are not isolated.
If your test are not isolated, it means that if you run them in a different order or you only run
some of them, you might get different behavior.
What I have to say about tests are not isolated is... don't.
Just don't do it.
If you have 30 tests and test number 24 fails because of some stuff that happens during test 8
and 15, I mean, you're not going to have a good time debugging.
And this gets really, really, really bad.
I cannot stress how much I think it is not a good idea.
Foot gun seven:
Improper test scope.
This is the root cause of many, many testing problems.
And my approach is to test some cohesive whole.
Some makes-sense story.
It's really similar to the notion of testing implementation instead of behavior, and it's just a more
general way of phrasing something similar.
Let's say that our bookstore is a web service and it uses a database.
We're going to think about two alternative test suites that we might have chosen where to use behavior tests
and implementation tests.
And we're going to try to imagine how our lives are going to be different if we went with one of them
or the other.
We look at tests that are almost identical in both test suites.
The test checks something very simple.
If we edited the description of a book, then the value has really been updated.
Both tests have exactly the same flow.
We create a book, we edit the book, we update the book, we get the updated description, and then we make the
assertion.
And the behavior test is going to do everything against the external HTTP API in the same way as things
will be done in the actual system.
The implementation test is going to do some of the stuff at the lower level.
It's going to create the book by directly creating a record in the database, and it's also going to get
the updated description of the record in the database.
Now, the behavior test only looks at the "what."
It looks at the code only as it appears from outside.
The implementation test also understands some things about "how."
It knows how the code is going to change the database.
And checking implementation like this, it's usually equivalent to checking behavior, but not always.
So how does this affect us?
Let's consider a scenario.
Let's say we have this test for a while now.
This takes weeks, maybe even years, we've invested a lot in them and we rely on them.
And today we're making a change to optimize the database.
We're moving the description out of the data, out of the book table, and into its own separate table.
Now, the original description field: we're not deleting it yet.
We're going to do that after we finish migrating the data.
So we finished with everything else, and now it's time to update the edit book endpoint.
Now, what if we forgot to update the edit book endpoint?
Maybe we forgot.
We can now update the wrong thing, so behavior-wise, it doesn't do anything.
If we do go to production, we have a real problem, right?
It's a major bug that's made it into production.
Now, if we went to the behavior test, well, the behavior test only looks at the external behavior
of the code.
The behavior test does not care about implementation details.
So if the behavior is correct, like here, the behavior test is going to fail,
just like we need it to.
The regression bug was prevented, and everything's okay.
But if you want to do implementation tests, implementation tests looks at the outdated,
wrong field in the database.
So when the test runs, that field is going to be updated just like before,
so the test is not going to fail.
And this means that the regression bug is not going to get caught,
and it will make it to production, which will make it not okay.
The other side of this, what if we made the change correctly?
We updated the edit book endpoint and everything is fine.
If we went with the behavior test, well, they'll pass, because the behavior was correct.
We didn't need to do anything.
But if we went with the implementation test,
they looked at the wrong field in the database, so it's going to fail.
The test is going to fail.
But the reason for failing is not because of the endpoint, right?
The reason for failing is that the test is now become technically invalid.
And we have extra work because of that.
We're going to need to, first we're going to need to figure out whether the failure is technical,
or real, and then we're going to need to update the test, either way.
And another important thing that happens is that because we're changing it,
this is no longer the test that we've been doing for two years.
So the level of confidence in the test has become smaller.
We're going to need to learn to trust it again.
Now, in large code bases, it can become a real pain.
You're always going to update the test even though the code is correct.
And sometimes, even if the test has nothing to do with the feature that you're working on, right?
And a lot of times, it spends hours and hours, and you really hate your test suite.
So, summing up.
Cohesive behavior tests:
Closer to reality.
The better at protecting us from bugs.
We don't have redundant work because of them, and we trust them more.
Another thing worth noting here is that what we saw here in this example is a small,
incremental change, but sometimes we need to do big changes, scary changes.
For example, in a lot of companies, there comes a day that the db doesn't do well with the scale.
We start having stability issues in production.
And we probably need to do some big change.
Maybe we take a lot of data and move it to a different database type, right?
And at that point, the tests are most important.
And if we went with behavior tests, everything is going to be fine.
Because they only look at the Delegate.
So, the moment we reproduce the original behavior with a new database, they're going to pass.
And we're done. We can move on.
If we went with the implementation tests, well, they all become technically invalid and they all fail.
So, we have there some work that we need to port them to a new database, but much worse than that,
because we've changed them, we're not going to trust them enough to say,
okay, the db has been moved, we've moved to the db correctly.
So, this might make a difference between a project that might take just a few weeks to
move a new database and is a company-level event.
It drags on for months while the product has stability issues.
So, test behavior, the cohesive whole.
Foot gun 8: Test doubles everywhere.
Sometimes in the test, we need to switch part of the system dependency,
with some alternative implementation.
These are called test doubles, stuff like mocks and fakes and stubs.
The main reason we do this, there are others, but the main one is performance.
If the real thing is too slow to run a lot of tests with it, then we switch it to the fast test doubles.
And test doubles are very useful, but they are re-implementations.
The test double knows the implementation details of the thing that it's replacing.
Different test double types do it differently, but that's what they do.
And the problem is that this is correctness, of course.
The test double is not necessarily exactly the same as the real thing,
and that makes the test less correct, less accurate.
And also, as time goes by, we might be changing the real thing slowly,
but the test double remains the same, so it gives further and further from reality.
And this kind of thing can really hurt your foot.
It's a flavor of the implementation versus behavior problem.
And there are some differences, but essentially it's the same thing.
Same category of issues.
Test doubles are not as good at catching bugs,
and sometimes they break even though everything's fine,
and cause all that extra work, as we've talked about.
So, test doubles: use with caution.
But how do we avoid the pitfalls?
How do we avoid getting into these problems?
And I suggest a few different ideas.
First, code design. So important.
If you can, try to design the code so that you can test a good chunk of functionality
and fast unit tests that don't need test doubles.
Now, it's not always possible, but a lot of the times it is.
Another thing is to choose what test double type you're working with.
And I would suggest to normally, usually use fakes.
Think of something that behaves like your dependency,
but again, fast.
For example, we can fake a db table with an in-memory list of tuples,
where each tuple represents a row.
And in the test, this is going to behave exactly the same.
And about the correctness problem of the fakes,
we can make them more reliable by testing them,
by writing tests not for the code, but for the fake itself.
An example of such tests can be to run the same actions against the fake
and against the real thing, and make sure we always get the same results back.
And they're never going to be 100% the same,
but it's a tradeoff.
We choose how much we want to invest in the thing, the reliability.
Sometimes a reliable fake already exists.
You can just take it and use it.
For example, you're using SQLite.
Python actually has built-in in-memory SQLite implementation.
You can just take it.
So it's worth Googling, maybe you'll get lucky.
Another nice thing that we can do with fakes is that we can run the same tests,
exactly the same tests, once against the fake and once against the real thing.
And let's say for example we have 10 tests, but it's too slow to run the real database.
So we run them with the fake, and then we choose the two most important ones,
and these ones we run also against the real thing.
And this way we get some real-world certainty.
And the essence of the idea here is that we use the test doubles,
but we selectively verify correctness until we get an acceptable tradeoff.
Another way to use this idea of use-and-verify is by caching recordings.
We can record side effects, for example, HTTP reports,
or we can also record the db actions or anything like that,
and we can then use them in the tests.
For example, in Codium we have an HTTP service,
and it uses another HTTP service, an AI model that analyzes and generates code.
So in our test, we record the HTTP interactions between the two services.
Locally, when we run the tests, we usually run them against the recordings,
so they are very very fast.
But we also need to verify them, so sometimes in the cloud,
we also run tests against the real thing to make sure that the tests still pass,
again giving us real-world certainty.
Foot gun 9: Slow tests.
Yeah, slow tests are not fun.
We're going to talk about two ways in which they are not fun.
The first one that I like to think of is the bottleneck and the time bomb.
The bottleneck here is when the test was so slow that we get a long queue of tasks
waiting to be merged into the main group.
What kind of numbers are we talking about here?
Let's say we have 10 work hours a day, and the tests take five minutes.
That means that we can merge five tests per minute, 12 tests per minute, sorry,
that's to main, on each hour, which is 120 tests to main each day.
For most teams, this virtually never happens. So five minute test suites: not a bottleneck.
The other extreme, you will never get that, but just so that it's easy to imagine,
what if the test takes two hours?
In that case, we can only merge five tasks per minute a day.
And with these kinds of numbers, whenever we get a bunch of tasks that we need to wrap up quickly,
the merge is going to take days, there will be days of waiting.
And if some tests start failing, we can get to that on any random day.
It doesn't work.
The team will probably just stop waiting for the test to finish,
before they merge to main, and spend a lot of time with the tests being broken.
We can survive this way for a while, but it's a lot of extra work, and it's really not what we want.
Really, even with most numbers, even a 30 minute test suite,
same thing is going to happen, really not as often, but same thing is still going to be a real problem.
And a few years ago, I was actually a part of a team where that happened.
When the test took 20 minutes, I understood that we had a time bomb and at some time,
at some point in the future, things were going to get really bad.
But I didn't have this clear explanation of just how the slowness would be a problem,
this bottleneck.
And another problem that we had there is that the tests were flaky,
so they always needed fixing real world, fixing them,
and so it seemed to most people like flakiness was the issue,
and the slowness was not the urgent thing to do.
After a while, that was the situation where every few weeks,
we would get these days-long merge queues and everything would stop, it was a real crisis mode.
And it only became okay after we did an expensive project, and made all the tests running parallel.
They would still fail, but sometimes, but it wasn't a crisis because the queue would go to zero fast enough,
so it wasn't a crisis.
And the question is, how do we avoid getting into this situation?
We all want to do premature optimization, so what we need to do in day one
is make sure that when we need to optimize, it is not going to be a very expensive project.
And specifically, we want to make sure that we run the tests in parallel,
because it's probably going to be the go-to solution.
And that actually is easier than it seems,
we just need to remember the foot gun about isolated tests.
Tests that don't affect each other must be run in parallel.
So I would suggest making this a must-have.
Now, the other way we talk about that slow tests can hurt us is by making the feedback loop slower.
And the feedback loop here is how long it takes us to find out about bugs and understand what happened.
And I'm talking about any type of bug here, even a small typo.
The feedback loop is super important, makes a lot of difference.
Anything that impacts is a great thing, even a red squiggly line in the IDE is very important.
But first today we're talking about tests.
And I usually aim for a setup where I'm running, most of the time I'm running tests in watch mode,
so they rerun every time a file changes.
And I'm running some subset of the tests so they finish within at most three seconds.
And being on the fast side like this, it has a lot of advantages, just one for example:
If the test turns red three seconds after I change some code,
I immediately know what happened.
It was just three seconds ago.
And compare that to slow tests with running CI, the commit with the failing test,
it might have a lot of code, it might have a lot of bugs in it,
plus, my brain has done a context switch.
I went to check up on Slack.
So when I get back to the test to check what went wrong, it's going to be a lot more work to understand.
Now, some tests have to be slow, maybe some tests can only run in CI even,
but the good news is that you can still have a pretty fast feedback loop.
And what helps me is that instead of asking how long does it take for the test to run,
I'm asking how long does it take to catch a bug.
And I'm visualizing this using the bug funnel.
All possible theoretical bugs come in, and at every stage some of them get figured out by the test that we catch them,
at that stage.
And the key observation here is that to have a good feedback loop, to be quick most of the time,
we don't need to catch all of the bugs.
We just need to catch most bugs.
The feedback loop needs to be usually fast.
For example, let's say we start out with a bug funnel, which is like this.
We only have an integration test, slow integration test, and we only run them in the CI.
And let's say we're working on some task and we would have done 10 bugs, right?
So in this case, we would need to wait for the CI and debug the results, 10 times.
Now, if we start writing the fast unit tests, pretty soon after a while we're going to get a bug funnel that looks more like this.
We do need to wait sometimes for the CI, but not so much, maybe for just two of the bugs
and most other bugs would be caught by tests a lot earlier.
So most of our life is spent when the feedback loop is much, much faster.
And consider also when we run some of these tests in watch mode.
You have a two second feedback loop even if it's not for all the tests.
Another thing we can do to improve the feedback loop is use tests double, that's what they're there for, making things faster.
And by the way, specifically, one thing that specifically has a nice tradeoff here is using cached recordings locally.
It's very nice, you really should try it, it makes a lot of difference.
For a jump, over to the last foot gun, I didn't mention specific tooling, so here they are, a bunch of software worth checking.
You don't need to take a picture of the slides and I put a link in at the end of the slides.
Foot gun 10: wrong priorities.
So we saw a lot of great work that can change our experiences by influencing the properties of our tests.
Right? The bug funnel was all about performance.
And testing implementation instead of behavior is strength and maintainability.
The question is how do we prioritize, when we work, how do we choose what we put emphasis on?
And to be clear, I mean, the objective of tests is their strength. We have tests so that they catch bugs, not for any other reasons.
But the unintuitive thing is that's not the thing we should prioritize while we are working.
First make them maintainable, then make sure they're fast enough, and then make them strong.
And here's the thing, if the tests are slow, they are not going to be good at catching bugs.
Slow tests are weak, or they are eventually weak.
So, for example, the team really has decided that we're not willing for the tests to run for more than, say, 30 minutes.
If the tests are slow, at some point they reach 30 minutes, and then it becomes more expensive to add more tests, a lot more expensive to add more tests.
So, at some point, a lot of new code is going to have fewer tests, so it's not going to be well tested, and essentially the entire test suite is not going to be strong enough.
The same thing happens with maintainability.
A little more subtle, but essentially the same, if the tests are difficult to maintain, it costs more to have them.
So, at a certain point, it's going to be too expensive, and we're going to have fewer tests for new code, and again, the tests are weak.
Same thing happens sometimes with maintenance and performance.
We saw an example with test isolation and parallelization.
In other words, maintainability is sometimes a necessary condition for performance, and both are always a necessary condition for strength.
So, make maintainability the priority.
Test isolation, testing a single fact, code design, all of these.
Whenever you need to make some choice, I suggest you almost always go with the choice that is more maintainable, even at the cost of other things.
Because in the long run, that's the way we get the tests that help us move fast, and make us confident in our code.
Thank you very much.