Hello everyone. Today I am going to present a talk on three musketeers: Sherlock Holmes,
Mathematics and Python. So in today's talk I will briefly discuss about forensic investigation
process, then Daubert Standard and Python, then few real-world problems, then finally
digital forensic applications in Python. Now when we say mathematics, maths is everywhere
or it's around us. You take sports, maths is there, you take music, maths is there,
you take any real-life scenario, maths is there, maths is also a part of nature. So
similarly we have got some applications with respect to forensics. So why maths and forensics?
So before discussing that let us see the definition of forensic science. It is the
use of scientific methods or expertise to investigate crimes or examine evidence that
might be presented in the court of law. So basic goal of forensic science is to find
out the evidence and present it in the court of law. It's a highly scientific process.
So mathematics can be used to determine how crimes are committed, when they are committed
and who committed them. So basically forensic scientists they analyze crime scene for possible
clues pointing towards suspects and evidence. So few of the mathematics concepts which are
widely used are mentioned here but of course these are not the only ones. There is no limitation
actually. So some of the concepts which are mentioned here are measurements, trigonometry,
proportions, handling data, probability distributions. Apart from that you can also go for many statistical
concepts, even calculus, differential equations. It depends on what kind of problem you are
solving. You may also need to make use of machine learning concepts also. It depends
on what kind of problem you are solving. But in this talk we are going to address very
basic problems. So some of the forensic applications which use mathematics are like lie detection,
then determine the time-sense strength, then to determine whether it is an accident or
suicide or a murder, then calculate the percentage of concentrations in blood, then compute blood
strain thickness, then perform blood spatter analysis, then requisite analysis and aspects
of ballistics and other applications. So when we say forensic investigation process, as
I have said it is a highly scientific process and as well as it is a legal process. So if
we don't follow the standards, if we don't follow the procedures laid out by the regulators
or the government or the law enforcement agencies, then whatever evidence we produce
out of this process, it may not be acceptable in the court of law. So there are basically
six steps in forensic investigation process. So first one is identification. So in identification
we basically visit the crime scene or basically investigation officer visits the crime scene
and try to identify the different rules. In second step investigation officer collects
the different objects. These objects may include, say most of the times I give examples of cyber
forensics. So they need to collect the system, pan drives, even the cables and they also
need to ensure that the system status is maintained. Say for example if the system is on then they
should not turn it off. If the system is off then they should not turn it on. So that is
because if you turn on or turn off the system then there is a possibility or most of the
times it happens that the evidence may be tampered or evidence may be lost, especially
the evidence which is present in the volatile memory. So whenever they are collecting the
system, so they do live forensics. Say for example they simply just pull the plug and
take the laptop or computer to the lab to perform other analysis. The next is the validation
of the objects collected. There are actually several forms. So they need to record what
all things they have collected and when they are collected. Then fourth step is examination.
So in examination basically the analysis is performed. So here actually the various concepts
are used because we have collected the evidence. So on this evidence we need to perform analysis.
We need to find out the clues. We need to relate the evidences. We need to find the
correlation between different pieces of evidence. Then next is the preservation. In preservation
what happens is whatever objects or whatever things you have collected, those needs to
be stored in a secured place. So secured place means even the temperature of the room should
not affect or should not tamper even for magnetic devices. If they are not stored properly then
the evidence may be tampered. So there are some bags like called as caraday bags or electrostatic
bags. So in those bags you need to prevent your physical devices and it has to be stored
in a proper room temperature inside a locker so that any unauthorized person should not
be able to access it. Then final step is the presentation. So if you have followed the
steps prescribed by the regulators for law enforcement agencies then you can present
the evidence in front of the court. Now why Python? That's because there is something
called as Daubert's standard. So in United States, I am not aware of laws of United States,
but it's an example which is mentioned and many times it is taken as a standard. So the
Daubert's standard is a rule of evidence regarding the admissibility of expert witness testimony.
So a party may raise a Daubert motion, a special motion in LeMain raised before the trial to
exclude the presentation of unqualified evidence to the jury. So last line is very very important.
You exclude the presentation of unqualified evidence to the jury. So if you don't follow
the procedure then it may result into that. Then the court has suggested some illustrative
factors. So these illustrative factors you can call it as a scientific methodology. So
what are these five illustrative factors are? Has the technique been tested in the actual
field conditions and not just in laboratory? The second one is has the technique been subject
to peer review and publication? Then what is known or potential rate of errors? Then
do standards exist for control of techniques of operation? Then has the technique been
generally accepted with the relevant scientific community? Now why Python is because there
is one to one mapping between Python's features and the illustrative factors. So in 2003,
Brian Carrier published a paper that examined the rules of evidence standards including
the Daubert and compared and contested open source and closed source forensic tools. So
on examination he found out that so using the guidelines of Daubert tests, so he has
shown that open source tools may more clearly and comprehensively meet the guidelines of
the requirements that would close source tools. So if you see the questions again here, so
the first one says that can the programmer algorithm be explained? So this expression
should be explained in words not only in code because legal experts may not understand the
terminology of programming basically. Then has enough information been provided such
that thorough tests can be developed to test the program? Then have error rates been calculated
and validated independently? Then has the program been studied and peer reviewed? Then
has the program been generally accepted by the community? So if we see the Daubert standard
and Python's features here, so there is one to one mapping. So that's why we are going
for Python. So we can also go for some other programming language which is more open source,
but provided it satisfies these illustrative factors and conditions. Now let us discuss
few real world problems. So first one is pressure of shoe print on a software. Then let's discuss
next problem after the suicide, murder or accident. Then, okay, so the first one is
pressure of a shoe print on a soft ground. So when I was in school I was in scouts though.
In scouts and diets generally they are trained to observe the footprints. So basically footprints
of animals are observed. So similarly here the measurements are taken of the length of
the shoe prints and the depth and the how far apart the prints are. So these are the
parameters. Now you can draw a conclusion here. The taller the person, the longer the
feet and the stride. The bigger the person, the deeper the shoe print. Then to complete
the pressure in this context you can use the formula P equal to M into G, M multiplied
by G divided by A. So where G is equal to 10 ms raised to minus 2, then where M is the
body mass and A is the contact area with the surface. So you need to manually measure these
things with a tape or a scale and put those values into the formula in order to determine
the pressure of a shoe print. So depending on the output you can decide whether the person
was taller, whether the person was a bigger person. So based on that it can point to some
suspects. Then second one is suicide, accident or murder. So let's assume that there is a
building and from that building some dead body has fallen and we really don't know whether
it is accidental fall or whether it is the murder or somebody has murdered someone and
thrown the body. The criteria here you can see here that there is a graph. So this graph
is distance versus height. If it is accidental fall there is no initial launch angle or initial
jump angle. So it will be closer to the building. But if it is a suicide then the person will
put some effort, right? So there will be more jump angle. So because of that body will
fall apart from the building. So there will be more distance between the body and the
building. Then similarly murder. So somebody might have killed someone and tried to throw
the body. So in that case it will be less than 21 to 38 degrees. It may not be 0 degrees
but it will not be between 28 to 38 degrees also. So it may be close to 0 degrees. So
you can consider this as 5 degrees or 10 degrees. So there is excellent book which is mentioned
here as a source. So I strongly recommend that you can try to get that book. And there
are lots of examples which are mentioned there. So that is Essential Mathematics and Statistics
for Forensic Science. Now once you get the values you need to put the values into this
formula in order to determine why. So depending on the value of why you can determine whether
it is accidental fall or a suicide or a murder. So these are all direct equations. So you
need not have to write longer programs. Just a single line statement in Python or just
two to three line statements in Python will do the job. Then Pythagoras theorem. It is
a very famous theorem. So you already know about Pythagoras theorem. So it states that
the square of the hypotenuse is equal to the sum of the squares of the other two sides.
So let us discuss the problem here. So the problem is titled as Artifact Smuggling. So
here the authorities have a video evidence. So footage from assistive camera of a possible
suspect in the museum break-in. So the suspect was seen carrying a briefcase and the dimensions
of the briefcase are mentioned. So it is 20 inches long and 16 inches high and 3 inches
wide. And one of the artifacts stolen was 24 inches long and 2 inches wide. Now investigators
now have to determine whether the artifact was possibly smuggled out of the museum inside
the suspect's briefcase. So here Pythagorean theorem can be applied on the dimensions of
the briefcase. So it is 20 square plus 16 square. So we get 656. Square root of 656
is 25.6 inch approximately. Now if you consider the artifact's dimensions, so we may not be
able to fit the artifact either in horizontal direction or vertical direction, but definitely
we can fit it in diagonal direction. So because of that we can conclude that artifact was
stolen. In the next case is the resolution of human eye. Now we know that the human eye
has got certain limitations. So we cannot see infinite, right, infinite distances. Everyone
has got their own limitations of the eyes. So here we need to consider an example of
a witness statement concerning the identification of an individual valid given that the suspect
was the same distance away at that time. So here the fundamental result underlying this
is that the unaided, that is he is not using any additional devices, an ideal human has
an angular resolution limit of around one minute of arc which is equivalent to 0.0003
radians. Now if there are some aids like specs, then again it may change depending on the
situational capacity of the person 5. Now such resolution limit means that any two distinct
features in an object that subtend an angle greater than this will be resolvable by an
eye. Otherwise features will merge and you can see that the pictures are blurred. So
if a particular feature is separated by the dimension d like at the distance l from an
observer, then by the definition of the radian we require the following condition to hold
for the object to be resolvable. So that is d by l should be greater than 0.0003 radians.
Now let us consider an example. So now here a witness with perfect eyesight who viewed
a suspect from a distance of 200 meters in daylight claims that he was wearing a striped
jumper with the stripes being around 4 centimeter wide. So now we need to determine is this
statement scientifically reasonable? That means we also want to determine whether the
person is telling truth or he is lying. So after calculating, so we get a value of 0.0002
radians. So it is not satisfying the previous condition. So we can conclude that the person
is lying or his evidence or his witness cannot be considered. Now this is the interesting
problem that is bank account or fund trail analysis. So in India basically most of the
investigative agencies they have the requirement of this application. So they usually conduct
a lot of hackathons on it in order to find out the solution. So the most common and continuing
offense in recent times is that the money laundering. So to make it easier for the police to trace
the illegal origin of money and undo the complicit is created in a series of bank transfers.
So police department was looking for a solution that facilitates efficient analysis of bank
accounts to identify the links among them. So basically how money laundering scenario
works is it is mentioned in this diagram. So there is a sender and there is a receiver.
Now the entire process is divided into three layers. First one is placement, second one
is layering and third one is integration. Now the sender gets the money and sender is
going to deposit the money into multiple accounts. Again these multiple accounts belong to the
several people. Now those people in turn will again divide the amount and again deposit
into multiple accounts. So it's a long chain. And the difficult part here is that they are
not depositing the money into single organizations. They are depositing the money into multiple
organizations. So that's a challenge. Because when police get the bank statements they need
to get the statements from the many banks. And the challenge here is that each bank produces
the statement in a different format. The biggest challenge itself is before analyzing is to
bring all the statements into unified format. Then do the analysis. Then finally what happens
is the amount will reach the receiver. Now you can see here that there are some red lines
and there are some green lines. So when you see green lines that's a genuine transaction.
Because the money is not dividing into multiple, multiple senders is not depositing into multiple
accounts. Basically it's not following these three layers strategy. That is placement, layering
and integration. Whereas the fraudulent transaction chain it follows these three steps. That is
placement, layering and integration. So the goal of the investigation officer is to identify this
chain so that they can hold responsible all the people who have been involved in this fraudulent
or money laundering transaction. Now the solution. So the solution is that each bank produces
gives a different statement and it will be in a different format. Now there is a formula or there is a law
called as Benford's law. So this is an interesting law. Not a new law but it's a century old law.
But this can be used to identify the frauds in the bank accounts. So after that you can import the data
of suspicious accounts. Then convert it into unified format. You can also check it with PEP, RCA
and Sanctions data. Then generate a graph showing the links between accounts and the transaction.
Then apply machine learning algorithms above the graph. Then predict the possible money laundering
and generate this chain of accounts with the fraudulent transaction. Now the important thing here is that
generating a report. And before generating a report it has to record each and every step for generating
the evidence. That is very very important with respect to any forensic application. Of course we can do
the same thing with using Microsoft Excel or spreadsheets also. You can just apply some direct formulas
and we can get the analysis. But we will not be able to record the steps. So if your opposition lawyer
if your lawyer or if other lawyer asks how you have arrived at the result then you will not be in a position to
defend. So that's the problem. So that's why here we need to record each and every step. Now for recording
each and every step we can use Python's logging packages. So that will help us a lot. Now what's
Benford's law? So it's called as phenomenological law. Also called as first digit law. So it's going to
extract the first digit of the numbers. So numbers means the amount which is deposited or basically the amount of
transaction. Then it's going to extract the numbers from 1 to 9. And if we see the probability, the probability of
each number of occurrence is 11.1%. But there's a probability table. So the digit 1 tends to occur with the probability
of approximately 30% which is much greater than the expected 11.1%. Now this is the law. Basically P of D is equal to
log of 1 plus 1 by D to the base 10. So where D is the values of leading digit from 1 to 9. So what is the approximate
percentage? So you can see here number 1 is approximately 30%, 2 is 17%, 3 is 12% and so on. Now if you write a Python
program there's actually a small package called as Benford's law. So you can directly install it and it's a small package
but you can also write a very small code and get the result very quickly. Because you do not have to even draw the graph
with Matplotlib. So first step is again import the Benford's law package. Then use Pandas and read the statement. So usually
banks gives you statement in the form of PDF. You need to convert that from PDF to CSV. Again there are packages in Python
which will help you to convert the PDF file to CSV. So import the content from CSV file to data frame here. Then create the
objects. So pass the parameter basically here. So use Benford's law method. Then set the alpha is equal to 0.05 and methodize
G square. Then you have to fit the data. So what that will do is it will draw the distribution. So here we are drawing the distribution
of the first digit, second digit and the third digit. So now you can see the graph here now. So if you have seen the similar graph
in the first slide of Benford's law here. So it resembles almost same. But the problem is that the probability here is 35.1%. So that is more.
And for second case it was less than 17%. So that means what is that there is anomaly and it is detected. So similarly you can go ahead
and do the experiment with respect to second digit test. So here also you can see that there is lot of variation here. So similarly with respect to
third digit. So Benford's law was a very simple method to identify the suspicious transactions in a bank statement.
The next is hash functions. So we know that hash functions are related to cryptography. So basically whenever we collect the evidence, we actually take the snapshot of the entire system.
When I say snapshot of the entire system, it consists of all the configuration files, the content stored in the RAM, everything. Not only the data stored on the hard disk.
Now when we perform analysis, we are not going to perform analysis on the original data. That's because there is a possibility that that data may get tampered.
So what we do is we take the snapshot of the system, make a copy of it, then perform the analysis on the copy of the data. Now before performing the analysis, we compute the hash of the original image and the copy of the image.
So both should match. If it doesn't match after analysis, then that means that there is some interference which is happening through the program. So your program must ensure that whenever it is performing the analysis, it is not interfering with the evidence.
So basically hash functions ensure that integrity of the evidence is maintained. So it's a very small code here. So we are using hashlib library and start of the six method and using a simple string to compute the message digest using start of the six algorithm.
Even if there is a small change, the hash code will change. So small change in the input will change the hash code. So that means that integrity is compromised.
The next is forensic indexing and searching. Now this is also very, very important. What happens is whenever we take the snapshot or whenever we take control of the hard disk of the criminal, there is actually huge data. So there's actually a data in terms of gigabytes or even in terms of terabytes.
So here you really don't know what to search there. It becomes very difficult. So in that case, you can use simple file search and index functions in Python and try to find out the truth.
Now there is a library called as push. So it's basically used for forensic indexing and searching. It's basically a library which helps you to build your own custom search engine.
So you can decide which data to index and you can pass it and you can query the same data. So this is how it works. So first import the data, then define the schema.
So in schema we are defining what is the part, what is the context and what's the title. Then add to the index, then use query parser package and search for the clues.
So next is forensic evidence extraction from the screenshot. So I don't have much time. So basically Paya screenshot takes the snapshot of the hard disk, not the hard disk, the screen.
So you can take full screenshot or a partial screenshot. So in forensic, performance does not really matter. So let me go to the last slide. So forensic investigation is a highly scientific process.
So since Python is a scientific computing language and conforms to the our standard, it is one of the most suitable languages for developing forensic tools. In forensics, accuracy of the clues and evidence matters rather than the performance of the application.
So that's the end of the question. Thank you everyone for patient listening. So if you have got any questions, I can take them.
There's no question. We thank you so much, Ms. Raymond. Without this speaker here, we don't have the opportunity.
Hello, hello. I guess I do have a question.
Do you have any question? Oh, good.
Hello. Yes, I just have a quick question. I might be the only person here who is not a programmer by trade. I'm actually an attorney.
I work for the government as an attorney and I am also on the prosecutorial side of being an attorney for the government, being trained in digital evidence as well.
Really what I want to ask you, and all this was brilliant. I want to follow up with you more. I would love to continue to have a dialogue with you about this and using this moving forward.
But I want to know from you, how are we going to be able to translate this to a jury? Because I'll be honest with you, this is all brilliant.
As an attorney first turned programmer, I understand what you're doing, but how is John Smith, Gene Q. Public, et cetera, that we're selecting off of the jury,
how are these people going to be able to understand what you're saying and then apply that to, say, for instance, a financial fraud case or a larger scale case of that nature?
Because, I mean, everything that you said, placement, layering, integration, that is actually what we on the other side of this use in our elements of trying to prosecute financial crimes.
So this is all actually very cogered. But what I really want to try and understand is, if I were to call you as an expert witness,
how are we going to be able to take this and then make it more digestible for the non-programmatic community?
Yeah, actually that's a challenge and a very good question. So we really need to have people who understand technology and the law.
So only then a single person who understands both the sides can actually convince common people as well as the judge or the best select.
And then I suppose I just another follow-up, obviously, because I'm extremely interested in this.
Obviously we're going to use logs to sort of show our steps, how we did this, what we used, how we got this result.
However, how are we going to be able to take the explanation of that, but then explain, are we going to have to explain how logging works as well before we explain what the logs explain?
Yeah, so the second part, we again, as I have said, we need a techno-legal expert who can actually explain the process.
And as you know, logs are not in, many times, they are not in human readable form.
So whenever we are building custom applications like this, we have to make sure that logs are in human readable form.
So whenever something is recording, we need to add appropriate comments automatically so that it becomes readable and it becomes understandable by the non-technical guys.
Thank you, I appreciate it.
Thank you.
So that's also a great question.
And what essentially occurs before the trial will happen is that we can do what's called maybe an in-camera review,
or we will have some type of evidentiary hearing that will just be the attorneys and the judge,
and then that is the process in which we would explain this to the judge.
Or we could do what's called motion practice, and then I would draft a legal document in which I would explain this entire process,
how it works in the written form, and then I would submit that, and then the judge would review that,
and then the judge would then decide, I'm going to allow this evidence into the record, and then it would be up to us,
once it has been accepted via that in-camera review or through motion practice, to then explain it to the jury,
and then the jury would have that evidence, and then they would be able to decide then how they would apply it to the legal burden that they would have as the jury.
So, yeah.