Hi everybody. We're going to start our session. I'm very happy to introduce our speaker,
Samweli Mwakisambwe from Tanzania. I would like to welcome our speaker.
Thank you.
Hi, I'm Samweli Mwakisambwe. I'm going to present to you how you can use Python and PyFuji as your call maps.
About myself, I'm from Tanzania. I work for Katowice as a software developer. I'm also a QGIS core and QGIS Python plugins developer.
The following are topics that we are going to go through. We're going to look at what is QGIS, how you can make maps with QGIS,
what's the relation between QGIS and Python, and what's the PyQGIS API.
Then we're going to look at how we can make Python applications and plugins using QGIS.
Then we're going to look at QGIS and power control functionality. After that, we're going to create some awesome animated maps using Python.
So what is QGIS? QGIS is a desktop application for creation and editing of geospatial data.
So you can use it to create some additional data. You can use it to do some analysis on the data, but you can use it to align the geospatial data.
It has a number of features, and it enables you to create any number of styles that you want in your map.
This is one example of a map made from QGIS. This is the place in Bogota, Colombia.
The map tries to show how the building in that place will look like in night, but by using a thing called the strain lamp.
This is just one example of how QGIS is powerful and allows you to customize your map to your need.
This image shows QGIS in action when one of the QGIS users is making a map.
This map is for network analysis. They are called answer-conse maps. They are usually created in order to show the accessibility of different service areas to different social facilities.
This is another map made from QGIS. QGIS also has compost support. What you see right now is a map that shows the movement of isobates in the source core.
This is another example. You can see on the right side, you can see the timelapse.
These are just a few examples of the maps that QGIS can enable users to make. There are various and many examples, and one would be able to cover all of them in this session.
QGIS enables you to make analysis and publish the special data. You create your maps and manage your maps. It is free to download and use.
It is open source, created by a number of developers from the world world.
Now we know what QGIS is. Let's take a look at the relation between QGIS and Python. QGIS application at core is developed using C++, but it also supports Python through Python bindings.
You could have a developer for a Python plugin that adds the functionalities in QGIS.
The users for Python in QGIS is that you can use Python to write standalone Python applications, as we will look at at a later moment.
You can also use it to create plugins.
This is the plugin manager inside QGIS. It shows all the plugins inside QGIS.
As you can see already, we have a number of QGIS plugins developed for the user side of QGIS.
I think there are around a thousand plugins. You can use it to access and download and use the QGIS that we need to create for this plugin manager.
How do we like Python applications and plugins for QGIS?
First of all, there are different ways to install QGIS. You could install it as an application on the computer, but you could also download it and use it as a package.
The way to go through that is by using an account.
When you are writing Python applications, you could write applications when you have installed your QGIS applications on your computer.
Or you could write your application by using the QGIS package.
You see there is a bit of difference when you are writing your Python application when your QGIS is installed as standard compared to when QGIS is installed as a standard application.
This is a simple example of a Python application.
Just to show a simple one layer, you can see on the left side there is the code that we used to create the light window.
On the top there you can see there are some libraries. QGIS is built on top of PyQT.
You can see that we are setting the prefix.
This is where the difference is between whether the user installed the application as a standalone or using Conda.
If you installed it as a standalone, then the location and the prefix packs will be different than if you installed it as an application itself.
How do we make plugins for QGIS?
The most recommended way is using the plugin builder.
If you want to start making plugins for QGIS, let's say there is a functionalizer that does not seem like QGIS, but you want to add that functionality, you have to use this plugin builder.
We do not recommend for beginners to use that.
It is also a QGIS plugin, so you just go open QGIS and search for plugin builder.
Once you install it, you can learn it.
It gives you this option where you enter your details.
After you create all those details, you have a template that looks like this.
After this, you can start your QGIS plugin development.
This is an example of a QGIS plugin.
This is written in Python.
It is available in the QGIS repository.
According to QGIS, it does not support natively using your stack API data.
The aim of this plugin is to add that functionality to QGIS.
Let's say if you have a stack API and you want to navigate and download the guest patch for data, then you have to install this plugin.
What is Tempo Controller?
Tempo Controller is QGIS feature that enables QGIS to be able to handle temporal data.
Before the Tempo Controller, QGIS didn't have support for temporal data.
You required to install the plugin.
One of the plugins that was very popular was called Time Manager plugin by Andy Tompey.
It was very popular and it had almost 10,000 downloads.
Now there is Tempo Controller and it handles all of the temporal data that's inside QGIS.
One of the things that I would like you to know is that because you have to dive into the technical details when you are making an invented map with QGIS,
you have to understand how the Tempo Controller is built.
One thing that I would like you to understand is that inside the Tempo Controller there is a QGIS temporal navigation object.
Each time you want to make an invented map using a Python application, you should always look out for the API for this object.
Let's go through just one example of how you can build a Python application and showcase how to make an invented map using Python QGIS.
I'm just going to use weather data from the Canada Metrology Project.
I'm going to use that to create just a simple app that will navigate through the weather data.
I'm going to specifically show you the air temperature of the world.
This is the script that does the job.
You can see that when importing the main libraries from Qt, we are setting the dates that we want to navigate on that data.
After that, we have this function called line, which is setting the QGIS application.
The other part here is to check the perfect pass.
Because I'm using Ubuntu and I've installed QGIS locations of our one that we use at Anetka,
so that's why I'm setting it here.
Then I'm going to initialize the QGIS application.
After that, I'm creating the window and I'm pulling down the last layer, which is the layer that contains the weather data.
After that, I'm adding that layer into map canvas.
As you can see here, I'm setting the extent of map canvas.
If you just learn this, I'm going to show you the spreadsheet.
This is the world air temperature as of today.
This shows us for today.
We have a number of battles below here.
You can just click and see that the weather has changed.
It has showed the data for that day.
Also, if I just click for the...
The interval between those dates is just three hours.
For the next three hours, it's looking at this.
The next three hours, it looks at that.
Then the following hours, it looks at that.
I also added a slider just below here.
You can just pull down the slider.
Then you can see how the air temperature changes.
It just does come down.
We could also just come in and just add another date.
Let's say we want to add another one.
We only have five dates.
I'm just going to add the sixth date.
I'll just call it that way.
The time it fixes copies.
These are called fixes.
I'll just put it back.
I'll just go for it.
Fix.
So we used our fix.
I'm going to call it fix.
So one and twenty.
Then I'll just add it in the list.
I also want to add that time.
Let's just make it the maximum is three hours,
four hours, the maximum is five.
Then we're going to add the widget to the layout.
Let's say six.
I'm going to push the date.
I'm just going to stop the application.
Then I'm going to run it again.
What's the point?
Okay, so the video is over there.
Let's remove that.
Run it again.
Hello, the name is here.
Save it.
Yeah.
So there we have it.
So you can see that instead of only five entries,
we've added another entry here, which is...
Yay!
So if we click that, we should be getting data for that time.
So you can see the changes.
So if you're in the mid-night, it's like that,
but three hours later, it should be back.
And the slider, so forth, should be working.
It should be.
Don't have any issues navigating through this.
So this is an example of how you can just write
a Python application that uses QGIS capabilities,
because without QGIS, you won't be able to point that way.
I'll show the different data and different dates.
And this Python application is available
in the presentation request,
which I'll share with you later
after I finish the presentation.
Another thing that I would like to just...
So we have seen this example that I would like to show you,
because this is just a simple example,
and it's not that complex.
But inside QGIS, the Tempor Control itself is very powerful,
and it has more options compared to what we've just seen here,
because here we have just this text,
and then we have this slider.
But if you use QGIS Tempor Control feature,
which you should also be able to use it here
in the Python application,
it should be having something like what I'm about to show you right now.
So this is the same layer open inside QGIS,
but right now we are not using Python.
We are using QGIS itself.
So you could also navigate inside QGIS.
You could also go through the different layers
that you want to view, go through it.
The only difference is that because of this Tempor Control,
which we are seeing right here,
it has more features.
You could just go back or go to the end.
You could play it.
You could add more steps.
Let's say you want to go up to 20,
let's say 24.
And then just go through the layers data.
Yep.
So each time you go, it changes the image.
So then you won't have to change it again after you come back.
And then, yeah, as we were saying,
this Tempor Control has more features
compared to a simple app that we used.
And one of the features that are very cool
is that the Tempor Control has the loop,
which is this one,
where you can just loop your animation
and choose the sequence that you want
to navigate the animation.
Let's say you want to...
So something is in the digit-fixed file,
filling in the CD.
Let me just go back and...
Yeah, it can be fixed so well.
So it's very cool when you are able to fix
the languages that it's adding to our settings.
So just push it a bit.
Yeah, that should do it.
Yes, right now if we go back
and just play the animation,
you can see the small detail
and it gives you a feeling of how the air temperature on Earth is.
And you can also, if you don't want to make it fun,
you can also just increase...
Very cool, right?
Yeah.
So, yeah, so...
And other layers, too.
This is just air temperature,
there's wind waves and a number of different layers
that you could use for the Tempor Control.
But this capability is also possible
inside the Python application.
So what you need is to just sit down
and dive in how the QGIS temporal application
works and then put it inside your Python application.
Because I've already shown you this is a deep what you could do,
but if you want to do more with it,
then you need to sit down and go to your Python application.
Yeah, so I just came back to the slides.
I would like to show you more of this animated mask,
but we don't have much time.
It's just for...
There's a...
For those who want some inspiration on how to work
with QGIS navigation, QGIS Tempor Control,
there's this plugin called QGIS Animation Workbench,
developed by Tim Sarton and Nile Doosan,
and it's a contribution from other developers.
So this plugin exposes and shows how you could use
the PyQGIS, CKR, with the temporal controller
to make some cool maps.
And this is all Python.
There's no C++.
It's only Python that you need to like.
So one example of the cool animation from this plugin
is that code.
So what you're seeing is developers across the world,
the QGIS developers across the world in their home locations.
So if I just replay that, you could see a couple
of developers from America, South America.
There's two in Africa.
The upper one is me.
Yeah, and yeah, so we invite people to come
and contribute to QGIS.
So because when you contribute to QGIS,
you want to contribute in order to QGIS.
And then you're also supporting the Python developers
who are wanting to talk with the QGIS functionality
in Python, the content at functionality.
So yeah, so support for QGIS.
That's the QGIS user repository.
And if you want to open an issue,
you can just go to that issue page.
Yeah, so these are the resources.
The QGIS API is found there.
The presentation materials, if you want to see those
Python applications that I just showed here,
you can just go to that GitHub link.
And then you could also visit qgis.org.
That's the website.
Yeah, that's it.
Questions?
Yeah, I think that's it.
I think that's it.
Thank you.
If you have a question, you could come close to the mic.
Yeah, next there.
Thank you for that.
One question is, do they have any plug-ins
with like the Google Maps API, then,
if you ever want to say,
like, to match this data or maybe like that,
or maybe, say more,
if I'm assuming this is from a separate database,
how would you know it's going to change
if you're going to have to do a lot more than that?
Yeah, so you can do that
if you have your data that is changing.
That means that's how you implement it on your plugin.
So QGIS doesn't stick to you at all.
So we have a number of plugins that we use
that are for all that have
the user being stopped and want only to export
their service to when best possible,
because QGIS doesn't interact with your
Python implementation at all.
So it's just you and how you implement maybe
your authentication or the phishing of data.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
I was wondering, can you embed any of these
maps or animations into web pages?
Yeah, so due to the time, I couldn't show you,
because the tempo controller also has an option
to export these animations.
So you could use that.
Yeah, and you could also
copy into that and save your Python application.
This thing, relative Python application,
you could also add it, you know,
another way of taking your source of exporting,
of course, and implement it also.
Thanks.
Right.
Thank you.
Are you aware of any plugins or anything that
we could use for satellite images,
analysis combined with QGIS and Python
or any other videos that you use?
Yeah, I know a couple.
Do you mean the one that's going to register for?
Do you have an idea for?
Because there are a number.
I understand that Planet has the plugin,
and it's inside QGIS.
That's only useful for the user who have Planet account.
So there's something like that.
Maybe.
Yeah.
No more questions?
Well, there's no more questions.
Thank you so much.
Okay.
Thanks.
Thank you.
Thank you so much.
Thanks.
Thank you.