Welcome everyone. Thanks for coming. This is going to be the repo we're going to be
working out of. You don't have to go there right now. I'll put this back up in a minute.
But I just, in case for some of you who wanted to get started, you can go over there. But
we'll get to that. You are here at PyCon 2023 to attend building a Python backed frontend
with HTMX and Tail1 CSS. If you're not here to attend this tutorial, you may have wandered
into the wrong room. But hopefully we're all ready to go. Let me just get this. Quick introduction.
My name's Mario. I am not a software engineer by trade. I'm a business analyst. I do try
to sprinkle in some Python into my day to day from time to time. But most of my Pythoning
is done in the off hours between my wife and four year old who are there in the back.
That tends to happen at night. So I have this blog Python by night. That's what I try to
do in the evenings. Now, we have a lot to get through today. So I just want to get right
into it. I'm going to show you how to build something really cool. We're going to use
which we'll keep coming back to. Now, Fast API is the web framework I've used in the
past. I've used Django for a couple projects. You don't have to have Fast API experience
to kind of get through this. We'll just be using some features. But hopefully if you
have any sort of experience with any other web framework, you'll be right at home. We're
going to use Jinja for templating. It's very similar to Django templates if you've used
those in the past. And of course if you come from Flask, you're pretty familiar with those.
Tail1 CSS is the utility first CSS framework that we're going to be talking about. Very
awesome. It gets you going really quickly. I'm super excited about that. And of course,
HTMX, which brings all these awesome modern browser features directly into your HTML.
So that's super exciting. That's going to be our tech stack. I haven't talked about
a little piece. We are going to be using a library called TinyDB. It's a very small...
It's meant to emulate a basic database layer if you've used any other ORM, whether it's
from Django's side or something like SQL Alchemy. That's usually what you'd put in place of
that. TinyDB is just a... It uses a JSON file. It's the local database, kind of like TinyDB.
So without... What you didn't see there is you didn't see any JavaScript. We're not going
to be using any JavaScript. Now the intention here is to reduce as much complexity in the
building of your web application. So we're going to get rid of that and we're only going
to be using hypertext. Now I know that sounds kind of like a retro science fiction term.
That's probably because it is. I think it was coined back in the 60s. Now the idea of
that is that text is displayed with these hyperlinks and ordinarily that's linking to
data that's in a database. And that's kind of where the concept of the World Wide Web
came from, from the idea of hypertext. And that's what HTMX embraces. And then we use
Tailwind CSS to style that up for us and we don't put in that client side JavaScript layer.
Now Tailwind CSS, again, you use these utility classes to style up your HTML. Now if you
don't know too much about it, there are somewhat valid criticisms that it makes your... It
looks a lot like inline styles if you've used HTML and you're kind of putting inline styles
and then they get really, really long. It does make your HTML look a little busier and
at first it starts seeming a little repetitive. But what you'll find is when you're styling
strictly from your HTML and you're not going to a separate file, to a CSS file, it will
dramatically increase your productivity. And it remains fairly lean because you're compiling
at build time. You're only compiling a CSS file to use that's based on the classes that
you're using. You're not bringing in this huge framework and then picking and choosing
and leaving it in your design. And because these utility classes are already preset,
it allows for a very consistent design pattern and also it helps to think of responsive design
from the very beginning. It's very easy to bring in some responsive features. Now, HTMLX,
I'm super excited about HTMLX. It allows you to make requests from any HTML element. So
usually you use a form or an input element and you hit submit. That sends a post request
to the server or you're using hyperlinks, send a get request to the server. So you can
do that. But with HTMLX, you can send a get request, a post request, delete any of those
HTTP verbs from any element. You can send it from a div element, from a paragraph element,
and you can define what triggers to use, whether it's a mouse over or a click or a key press,
all sorts of cool stuff with no JavaScript. You're just putting it right in the HTML and
then from the server side, you're just receiving that request and sending back the response
that replaces only that DOM element. So you're not doing a full page refresh, you're just
refreshing that one element or a separate target element that you define within the
HTMLX call. So all without leaving the comfort of HTML. You could be doing all of this, the
tailwind stuff, the HTMLX stuff, all within your HTML. You can see how quickly you can
get through prototyping and designing your website. So we're going to build a pretty
simple website, I'd call it. Now, I generally don't like the word simple because simple
for some might not be so simple for others. And the usage here with me is kind of ironic.
The sense is that we're trying to reduce complexity and that is definitely something that we're
doing when we're getting rid of JavaScript in our build process. So in other words,
if you're already familiar with HTML markup, then HTMLX fits right into that paradigm
without much more mental overhead, trying to learn a new framework or another front
end library. So the complexity of the behavior then is sent to the backend, which is something
that hopefully we're all comfortable with in the Python sphere. You're doing all that
logic on the server side. So the loops you see here playing is kind of how I started
this project as a simple site where it starts with just a very basic ugly HTML page that
just starts being built up little by little. Now, where we pick up is at the tail end of
this so that we can really just get into the features of tailwind and HTMLX. So that's
where we're going to start today. But a little bit of housekeeping before we jump right in.
If you have questions, you'll notice that I put some Post-It notes in between any of
the tables where you'll be sitting. Those Post-It notes are there to help you if you
have any questions. What I want you to do is take one of those Post-It notes and just
put it on the corner of your laptop like this so I can see that you have a question. The
reason for that is sometimes when you have a question, you might be thinking something,
but you don't want to lower your hand to type. So that way you can keep typing, troubleshooting
through whatever question you might have. You might even find out why you're typing
at which point you can just take your tab off. But that'll help me see maybe a lot of
people have questions. We can stop back. I can step back. So I'll either answer your
questions from up here or I'll walk by if it seems like it's something you just kind
of need assistance with. I'll be happy to walk by. So with all that said, are there
any questions so far? All right. Let's dive right in. We want to set up your environment.
That's usually the most important part when we're getting ready with a tutorial. This
is again the repo we'll be using. I have it both as a bit.ly link or fully typed out there.
If you want to go ahead and navigate to that. There are a couple ways to set up your environment.
If you've done tutorials in the past, sometimes it involves just cloning the repo, pulling
it locally, setting up your environment. That's the traditional route. If you're comfortable
doing it that way, you can go ahead and do it that way. I recommend to use Codespaces.
Codespaces is a newish feature with GitHub. You do have to have a GitHub account. So if
you do not have a GitHub account, you'd probably want to just go a separate route. But with
GitHub, there is a feature called Codespaces. Now what Codespaces does is it containerizes
the entire repo. I think it uses Docker, but it doesn't matter because it's all on the
cloud. That's pretty much it. You get it started, it containerizes the repo, puts it on the
cloud, and then it gives you, I think it's 60 hours per month thereabouts to kind of
play around with it. You don't have to install dependencies. You don't have to activate environments.
It's all within the browser. It's VS Code-like. If you're used to using VS Code, you can
just go right in there in the browser, and you can also open it up in your local desktop
version of VS Code, and it'll be tunneled right into that containerized environment.
It's really pretty great because then you don't have to worry about cloning and setting
up your environment and installing from requirements.txt, etc., etc., etc. All those instructions,
though, for either one of those are in the repo on the README, so you can check that
out. Of course, if some of you are more hardcore, you can build from scratch. Some of you have
your own bootstrapped ways of getting started, and that's totally cool. If you're comfortable
doing it that way, just get the requirements.txt file, load up your project, and go at it
your own way, that's perfectly acceptable. Feel free to do that as well. I am going to
be kind of moving quickly. I will wait until we all feel kind of comfortable getting that
set up. If you're using Codespaces, what you're going to want to look for is the button over
here. There's one that says code, and there's one that says use this template. You can use
either one to get the Codespace started. I like using the template. If you use the code
one, it actually gets you the git history and a couple other things, but using this
template just pulls up a very fresh version of the latest version of the repo. You click
use this template, open in a Codespace, and then it takes you to a screen that looks something
like this. It takes it about a minute to two minutes to build that container. That only
happens the first time. If you exit out and you come back to GitHub and go to Codespaces,
you can just fire it back up. It doesn't have to rebuild the container, so that's only that
first time. Again, it takes about two minutes or so.
If you're getting all set up and getting that set up, I'm just going to talk really quickly
about Fast API. Again, that's the web framework I use. It's a modern fast web framework. It's
in the name there. Mostly for me, the fast is not just merely performance based. It's
also for the developer. It really helps with your development speed when you have type
hinting, which is used for validation and for editor support, for autocomplete. It really
speeds up your development when using Fast API. That's why I like to use it. It has session,
cookie support, all other sorts of features you'd expect from a modern framework. That's
why I use it. Again, if you're coming from any other web framework, whether Django or
JavaScript, hopefully the things we're doing here are not too out of the ordinary. If you
have questions, I'll be happy to come by and answer them.
Then I talked a little bit about TinyDB. Again, it's just a document-based database that uses
JSON. It's meant to emulate any ORM or ODM that you're comfortable with. I like to use
Beanie with MongoDB. That's the ODM I prefer to use. It's just there just to get us moving
I've also built this helper class called CRUD to further abstract the database operations
you'd ordinarily be doing in a web-based application. For example, a user makes a request that goes
to your server. You're usually making some sort of database call and then you're doing
some sort of logic and then you're presenting a response back to the user. That's a pretty
common workflow operation. That's what TinyDB is there for. That's as much of the intro
as I can get through. Now I just want to have you go ahead and open up the application and
make sure it runs. If you're not used to Fast API, there's the equivalent of Run Server
or I forget the Flask command. It's going to look something like this.
Uvicorn is the server application. App.main represents the path to the module that has
your application, the instance of your application. It's called App in this case. If you had called
your app something else, you could do it that way. Then the reload flag there is it's a
watcher. Once you start your application, any save to any of your py files will just
restart the server so that you can see the changes in real time.
Let's go ahead and get comfortable. Open up the application. Get it started. When you're
done or when you see it running, if you're in Codespaces, what happens is it opens up
a port. Sometimes it might give you an error the first time. That's because the order of
the build is a little odd. Maybe just go back to the Codespace and re-click on the, I think
is the 127.0, the address and it will open up on the port. You should see the application.
It's called MusicBinder. I'll give you a couple minutes. If you have any questions, go ahead
and use your sticky tabs or you can raise your hands. I can come by in the meantime.
Do I click this? No. Go up to the top. That is my... Or I go to yours. Go up to the top.
Over here. Are you signed in? Well, I'm... Yeah, you might need to. Now you can go here.
What will it do? Click and open in Codespace. When I went to mine, it said new Codespace,
but it's a different problem. Now it will build. It will take about two minutes. Once
it loads... Yeah, so once your Codespace loads, if it's still loading, it will bring up a
new browser window. It looks like an editor. It will look kind of like VS Code and it will
have a terminal at the bottom. Usually it brings up the readme file first, but you can
ignore that or close it. There will be a terminal window at the bottom. You can type in this
command and then it will start up the server. It will tell you where to... You can control
click, I think, on the address and it will bring up a version of the website. I could
probably... You know what? I probably should have done this. This way. Again, this is the
button here and you'd want to open up a Codespace. If you're signed in, you need to be signed
in to see that button. I'll go ahead and kind of go through this as well just so that you
can get a sense. Any other questions? Is anyone still working on setting up their environment?
Okay, one back there. It looks like we're nearly there. Does everyone who's in so far,
are you able to see the MusicBinder web application? Yeah? Oh, perfect. All right. As you're starting
to poke around in there and you start seeing the structure of the application, it's kind
of meant to emulate a real world application. I try to follow a structure that you may be
familiar with unless you have a slightly different paradigm of building. I know things are a
little bit more opinionated in the Django space, but still, hopefully you're able to
get a sense of what's going on. This is what the structure might look like. Most of what
we'll be doing on the HTMX front will be in the routes.py file. If you're coming from
Flask, maybe that's a view or I think in the Django world, those are endpoints. That's
kind of where we define the logic of what happens when a user goes to a certain endpoint.
Of course, all the templates are in this directory here. That's where we'll do a lot of the Tailwind
CSS stuff. Let's go ahead and focus on the templating. Again, hopefully most of you have
some experience with templates if you're coming from Django or Flask. If you don't, it may
be a lot to get through, so you might miss a few things, but hopefully you get enough
here that you can come back and get a sense or just look through the repo there at how
things are being done.
The template directory, the awesome thing about templates is that you can layer them.
If you're going to have all your meta tags throughout your website, you might just have
one base template. Then you bring that into all your other templates as you do things.
That's kind of what we've done here. I have a base.html file. The underscore there is
just, for me it's helpful, but some of you might not use an underscore. Either way, all
the things you would bring in to the rest of your web application are contained in there.
If you take a look, it'll have all the meta tags and defining the style sheets, et cetera.
Then the meet, if you will, would be in these files, about or catalog or main. That's the
content that users would see. You would bring in the content that's in the base, footer
and header files that are up there. That's kind of how it's structured, just so you get
a sense of it. The header file, for example, contains all the links that you see up at
the top plus the search bar. If you ever wanted to just make a change to the links, you would
just go to that header file, you would change it up, and then it would change it throughout
your website. That's kind of the idea of templates. You don't have to keep redoing things in different
files. You just do it once and you would see it throughout your site.
Rendering templates in FastAPI, again, I mentioned that those endpoints, those views are defined
in the routes.py file. Now, FastAPI does have this class called Jinja2 templates. That's
used to define the template location and the context. That template context is perhaps
the most important thing to keep in mind when working with templates. The context contains
those Python objects that you want to have access to within your templates. If you're
sending over a dictionary or a list or even class objects, you can then use them within
your template and display what you need to the user. It's very, very useful. I think
with... Actually, I do have a slide on that later.
Now, just in case you are already familiar with templates, the main thing you'll see
is the template response from the FastAPI where you'll see this in the routes. Usually,
I'm sending a response that contains the template file. The template file there, like template.html
in this case, would be relative to the directory that you defined with the Jinja2 templates
class. Then the context will always look like this. On the FastAPI side, it must send back
the request object, which is what you're getting from the user. I think Flask does this for
you. You don't have to specify it. Actually, if you look at the different ways that Django
or Flask do the same thing, Django, you do a render and then you send the request. You
define the template file and then you send the context through. Flask, similarly, you're
doing render template. You're defining the file. Then the context is just whatever you
send. I don't think you have to define the request. It's all fairly similar. Hopefully,
this gets you more or less acquainted with how we're sending things through. If you're
noticing things really well, you'll notice there's a library called Jinja2-Fragments.
I do use this in the application. We'll talk about it a little bit later. There's a class
called Jinja2Blocks. That's a drop-in replacement for Jinja2 templates from FastAPI. What it
does is it allows rendering of individual blocks of content within a template file.
Again, let me just say that over. Let's say you have a template file that has a lot of
content. Jinja2Blocks allows you to send just a portion of that template back to the user.
It's very useful with a particular HTML interaction that we'll talk about later. It's not super
required to use HTML, but it can become very helpful because you're no longer having to
split up little pieces of HTML code to split things up. We'll talk about that.
That's all gotten us to the point where now we can really get busy with Tailwind CSS.
How do we make these templates look better? That's the question. I don't know how familiar
all of you might be with Tailwind CSS, so I just want to talk about it really quickly.
Tailwind, I said already, comes with these utility classes that ensure a consistency
in design. For example, one of the things I'm thinking about is it comes with a pre-defined
color palette. Say you want a background color that's red. It has different shadings of red
from 100, 200, 300, 400, all the way to 900 that has very consistent shading. Then if
you're using the same shading of red throughout your design, it'll ensure a very consistent
design. Of course, if you're coming from the CSS world, you might be thinking, well, you
can use CSS classes and all that stuff where you're pre-defining those things as well.
It's similar to that. What I appreciate about it is that your CSS doesn't keep growing really
large. Sometimes when you're working in CSS, you forget that you're no longer using this
class, but it's just kind of growing, and then you don't know which part to delete because
you're like, wait, am I using that somewhere? It can get pretty huge. That's if you're doing
it from scratch. It is very safe to just add and remove those utility classes from your
HTML because what happens is you're compiling or you're building the CSS file that you're
going to use, so it stays as lean as you're keeping your code. If you're only using specific
classes for spacing and color design, it's only going to compile those into the CSS file.
If you're changing things completely, it'll compile again. You don't have to worry about
tooling around in your CSS file. It's super great for this template slash component-based
design. It complements the way that we're building with HTML. That's a great reason
to use Tailwind. One of the questions that comes up with Tailwind is, let's say you're
looking at the links in the... Yeah, go ahead and look at the links that are in the templates
folder that are in the header HTML file. What you'll notice is there's three links, and
those links all have a very long HTML element. People often wonder about code duplication.
You see it's repeated, and we come from a programming world where we don't want to repeat
ourselves. For these components such as buttons or cards, one thing you'll notice is that
structure is just as important as the CSS a lot of times. Even though, let's say you've
created custom classes for these very specific-looking links, what may happen is, let's say you don't
want links anymore, but you want to keep the design or you want to change them to a different
element, you would have to redo the CSS as well as the front-end piece as well. These
complex changes, let's say you wanted to change text to a link, well, now you're having to
change the A element in your CSS. It can become really cumbersome. Instead, you can make all
those changes within the HTML within the respective component. There's this piece in the CSS documentation
that talks about this. It says, components and template partials solve this problem much
better than CSS-only abstractions because a component can encapsulate the HTML and the
style. Again, because you're within your HTML, you can make all your changes in one place.
That's there in the documentation. I will have some notes with a lot of this info afterwards.
If you're missing some of these links, they will be available. You're wondering, how do
I use Tailwind with Python? There's this wonderful library called PyTailwind CSS. Ordinarily,
Tailwind CSS requires NPM. The whole point is we're trying to not use JavaScript. NPM
brings about its own complexity. Tailwind CSS, the team behind it, has also built a
standalone CLI tool that you can build yourself. You can pull that down locally and then use
commands within your terminal. But what PyTailwind CSS does is it wraps that CLI into something
that's on the PyPI website. You can pip install PyTailwind CSS. Now you have a wrapper around
this Tailwind CLI. You can use those commands in your terminal just as well as any other
Python-based CLI. It's pretty awesome. You use the command PyTailwind CSS in it once,
which you don't have to do right now if you've opened up the code space. What that basically
does is it builds the pieces that you need for Tailwind to work, such as the config file,
the Tailwind config.js file. Now there's three important concepts with Tailwind CSS that
I want to talk about. Those are the three here. The Tailwind config.js file, the directives,
I'll talk about that in a second, and the build process. Those are, I think, the most
important pieces. The first one, the Tailwind config.js file, that's what happens when you
run that command. It creates this file in your project route. You might see it there
in the MusicBinder application. This defines where the Tailwind CSS will look for the content.
It looks for those utility classes within a certain directory. In our case, it's in
the templates directory there, and it's recursive. It's looking for anything that ends with
HTML. It looks through those files that are in that directory at build time, and it compiles
a CSS file that then you will be using. That's what the Tailwind config.js file is for, primarily.
But there are other things you see there, like theme and extend. Those are some advanced
use cases, which I'll talk about later. That's an important must-have for Tailwind to work.
But the cool thing is you run that command and it builds it for you. The only thing you
really have to fill in is the content, if you want to. You could just star-star everything,
and it would look through your entire project, but usually you want to point it in the right
direction. The next thing is this thing called the Tailwind directives. This is an input
file that Tailwind uses. The base, the components, the utilities. This is a directive for Tailwind
to know what to build into the output, into the main.css, or however you call your CSS
file. It has to be there. There are some other cool things that you can do with this file,
which we'll also talk about later. You can build it once and forget about it and use
Tailwind at will. You don't have to worry about what's going on here. But over here,
you can also define your own custom styles. You can also define the fonts you want to
use, if you want to use special fonts, et cetera. We can see some of that later.
And then the third piece that's the most important is probably just the build process. Again,
as you're writing these classes into your HTML, Tailwind needs to know about it at some
point. After you've worked in your HTML, created your styles how you want them, this build
process then basically says, look at the input file, which is going to be that directives
file we just saw. That's what I call input.css here. And send it to this output.css, which
is the one that you're actually going to use in your HTML. And then you can also define
there's also a flag. So this is what it looks like in the music binder app. If you were
to run it there, you'll notice that the Tailwind-i, which is input, is pointed to this tw.css
file. That's just what I called it. You can call it whatever you want. A lot of people
call it input.css. And I output it to a file called main.css. And that's the one I'll call
within my HTML. And you'll also see the watch flag. I love the watch flag. It recompiles
every time you save, every time you save a new, anything in that content directory that
we saw. So you make any change, recompiles. It takes like microseconds to compile, so
it's not slowing you down at all. So what I like to do usually is have two terminal
windows open. I have one that's running the application I'm working on, the server. I'm
watching for changes on that, my fast API. Then I have another window with this watching
for css changes. And it's all happening real time. So I'm changing things up, reloading
my browser, and it's instant. So it's great for prototyping and building quickly. And
additionally I did include this command as a startup, on app startup. So in case you
forget to compile, it'll at least compile every time you start your application. Because
sometimes you can build stuff and forget to run this command and then you see things aren't
changing and you're wondering, wait, didn't I just type that in? That happens to me still
even though I've been working with this stuff a lot.
All right, so what does Tailwind look like in your HTML? So it looks a little bit like
this. And at first, again, it'll start looking a little busy. So you're defining a class
and each one of these classes is creating a, again, on build time, it's creating a,
it's creating the equivalent in css. So over here, this development is going to have a
background color of slate 50, which is a lighter color. And I'm also setting the max width
of this screen to large. Again, it's a utility class, so the large is already predefined.
I forget exactly the pixels at this point. And then the h1 class, so the header class,
the header, I'm going to create a text that's 3xl. Now again, as a utility class, all these
things are predefined. One thing I forgot to mention is if you were to not include any
of these classes in your HTML, you're getting a full css reset. So everything looks very
basic without any classes applied. So you're having to explicitly state, I want my headers
to be big. If I didn't have that text 3xl there, then it would just be very like regular
text size, right? I want the font to be bold. I want it to be uppercase. So these end up
on compile time, they end up looking a little bit like this in your css. So on compile time,
the main.css file will have a text 3xl class that has the font size predefined and the
line height predefined. Here's that bg slate that we saw. It looks like max width screen
for large is 1024 pixels. Of course font bold is 700 and uppercase, we're doing a text transform.
So that's all on build time. So if you're thinking about it, you're just typing in your
HTML, hitting save, and this builds automatically for you. If you change anything, it'll rebuild
it. If you want to go to 4xl, this will disappear from your main and another class called 4xl
will appear just instantly and you're not having to go in there and make adjustments
in that case.
So now I want you to go ahead and play around with it. So let's go ahead and let's see.
I want you to go ahead and try to create. Let's see. Let's redesign. Let's redesign
the links. So there's links in the header template, right? You can see how they function
right now. There's a hover effect that puts a little bottom border, I believe, in the
current version of that application. I want you to change those to function more like
buttons, like maybe create a background color for them and maybe do another hover effect.
So, you might be thinking, well, I don't know these utility classes. How am I supposed to
know to do that? So I'll give you two resources that I use a lot. The first is just the tailwind
CSS.com slash docs. They have a search window there on the left and if you're wanting to
know how to change a font, you type in font and it gives you all the list of the utility
classes. It's a very, very, very useful website. I always have it open just to kind of get
a sense of what's available to me. You can even type in color, for example, or BG and
it'll show you all the different utility colors that you have with the actual examples there.
Let me actually show you what that looks like because I get pretty excited about tailwind
CSS, just their documentation. Let's say I wanted to learn how to do background color.
So I just type in background. You'll notice that it already starts putting some things
here. I don't think background was what I was looking for. And here you're typing in
usually the equivalent of the CSS properties. So maybe I'll go to color. There's text decoration
color, text color. All right, what is text color? Here it tells you how you can set the
text color. And notice that it starts with slate. Slate is a predefined color and here
are the colors on the right side. Let me see if I can make this a little bigger. If I keep
going down, here's what gray looks like, neutral, stone. Here's what the red ones look like.
So if I were to type in text red 200, this would be the equivalent here. But darker is
900. Here's the equivalent here and so on. So you can get a sense of how to set things.
Let's say you wanted to work with padding. I want to know how to set the padding. You
click here and you can already see P dash zero is zero pixels. PX dash zero is padding
left and padding right. So you think X axis. PY is Y axis. So you can see that the text
is zero and zero. And then you start adding numbers. So PX dash one would be, it's not
one pixel. It's just a different equivalence. And then it kind of shows you what those are.
So PX one, for example, would be 0.25 REM. So the equivalent of four pixels. So you can
start styling those buttons to look exactly how you want, whether you want larger buttons,
smaller buttons. Try to change those around. But for you to be able to see what you're
doing, remember, you want to be able to have this, you want to have that compilation watching
for any saves that you make to the templates. Because otherwise you're not going to see
the changes in your application. So open up a second terminal window. One has your app
running. One has your tailwind watcher running. And then start playing around with the CSS.
So I'll see if my, this is what my code space looks like. So I would close this out. The
first thing I would probably do is open up a separate terminal. So you can do that here,
if you're not familiar with this. And then that puts two terminals side by side here.
I don't know if you can see that. Let me make this a little bigger. So I'm going to go ahead
and open up the terminal. And the first one I would do the uvicorn with the reload flag.
I will make them available, yes. They're not right now. This isn't, no, this isn't a slide.
This is, I'm just doing this live right now, this screenshare. So again this would, this
command here starts up the application right here on 127.0.0.1.48000. And you'll notice
when I did this the first time, it'll give you this log message here that it actually,
because it is a new code space, it does actually have to download that wrapped tailwind and
it installs it from, directly from tailwind labs. And now you see, because I have the
rebuild command set on app startup, you see that it rebuilt in 396 milliseconds and then
the startup is complete. So now I should be able to open here, if you press control C
and click, it should open a version of the application. The first time it needs to forward
to the port. So here's the application and these are the buttons we're going to change.
Let me make that a little bigger. Yeah, so you'll notice there's a random, it randomizes
the picture that comes up first. So yeah, it might, it might be slow based on the, okay.
So I want us to change these up. So if you're back in the, I'm going to change these up
in here, in that second terminal, that's where I would run this command. And again, it's
a little, it's a little wordy, tailwind CSS. Oh, it's going slow. If you have, if you have
VS code locally, you might be able to open this up locally, might be a little snappier.
And you have to give it the, actually I don't know if you need the app.static source tw.css.
Actually I might need to wrap that in, I think I need to wrap that in, I don't remember if
I need to wrap that in quotes or not. Maybe. I'll just do it this time.
And the output is going to be similar. No, not source, it's going to be CSS. Now most,
most times when you have something like this, again, I like to memorize commands and stuff,
but this stuff you could probably automate with either a make file or however your build
process is, whatever makes sense to you. I also like to have the compilation on that
app startup. Additionally, you can even have a watcher on the, on the template files from
within, from within FastAPI as well, so that reloads for changes in the template as well.
There's a lot of different things you can do. But once you click that, it should do
an initial rebuild. Now when you go to your templates, so you'll know it worked if it
rebuilt once. Now if you go to your templates and you were to go to your header, and you
can see the links here, I mean maybe. So right now I have these, oh, I forgot to tell you
something, I forgot to mention. If you use VS Code and if you use PyCharms, I believe,
they both have really awesome Tailwind CSS extensions. For VS Code you do have to download
it because if you've used the code space, it's already pre-installed for you. If you're
local, you do have to download the extension for Tailwind. But it is, it is a second piece
that I would say, if you use the documentation in another window, you can also use the extension
for VS Code and it is extremely awesome and I'll show you why. So over here, when I mouse
over any of these classes, the extension allows me to see what the matching or corresponding
CSS is for any one of these classes. In addition, if I'm wanting to change a specific, a specific
aspect, so let's say I want to change the background of this, of this button and I start
typing BG, let's say red, and I hit control space. Well, it's a little, it's a little
slow. I think it's because of the, the Wi-Fi situation. What it does is it gives you, it
gives you a, yeah, it's super slow. But even, even if I were just to type BG red 500 and
I hit save, you'll notice, you'll notice the compilation happening in the bottom for, for
each save. And if I go here, and I go to the bottom, and I go to the top, and I go to the
bottom, I feel like everything's going a little. You're saying this part here? Yeah.
So, oh, I see. So, go ahead and open up the template directory. So, go to app. Right
here under app, yeah. And find the templates directory. So, that's going to be right here.
Yep. And go to shared. So, there's one called header. And so, this is going to be your HTML.
So, you can make changes directly in any of the elements to see the changes. You can kind
of follow just the same pattern. So, the, the, you'll see, for example, that there's
a PX3 that's padding. And every, anytime that you mouse over, it'll show you the corresponding
CSS. So, that's what that represents. Has anyone been able to change their buttons up
to see, change them up in any which way? Or any questions? I am not. Oh, yours isn't changing?
Let me take a look. Just trying it out. Okay. And I do see that it's recompiling. That's
interesting. Oh, interesting. I wonder if you're going to be able to do the same website
thing. Yeah, let's see. That might be it. Because I'm seeing down here. That might
be, well, probably. So, let's try that. Okay. So, that's it. So, that's it. So, that's
it. Oh, command, sorry. Oh, yeah, that works too, yeah. Well, what I was trying to see
is if you hit command, it's usually if you hit command, oh, there it goes. All right,
so it's not seeing this. Let's go back. Which one is it? Oh, it's not seeing this. Oh,
it's not seeing this. Okay. Okay. That should be the home button.
That is interesting. It's using main. I wonder. Okay, let me check. So, it's compiling to
main. So, we should be able to see if it actually built it. Yeah. Can you search for BG Red?
I guess it was. So, it is here. That's bizarre. Oh, you know what? I think we're going to
have to go back to the main. So, it's not seeing this. It's not seeing this. So, it's
not seeing this. So, it's not seeing this. So, it's not seeing this. So, it's not seeing
this. Okay. So, it's not seeing this. Okay. So, it's not seeing this. So, it's not seeing
Let me try that.
I don't want to keep you here for so long.
It's all good.
Yes.
Hi, I have a question.
Is that able to change the background color?
For example, the color, it does not,
it's been overridden by the actual background
of this computer.
Oh.
Yeah.
So I'm wondering, how do you navigate this?
For example, I want to change it to gray or orange.
You want it to change the background color?
So yeah.
So part of what I do is I would inspect it
and see which component it is.
So you'll see where it's defined.
So this one, so it has the BG slate here.
So find that and change this to BG slate or BG orange
or something and see it changed automatically.
My question is, because we want to reduce having our code
everywhere.
So how do you manage it in the case where
it was about the background and orange,
there's no point putting this CSS to it, right?
Because it does not ultimately affect the component.
So you were looking at, you were trying to change it here,
right?
So this effector thing has no effect on the component?
Go back to that inspect element and look for header.
See, it's here.
So the thing is.
It's overriding.
Yeah, it's overriding it.
So you would need to change it here and then just remove it
from the header class.
I mean, again, it'll just be based on your own design
element.
So if you're thinking about layering it
and you're doing a full background,
it's just kind of think, all right,
so I'm going to change this.
And then I'm going to put this on top of it
and only change that.
So it might just be a design choice.
I think my true experience of working in CSS
is one of the problems that I have
with finding that as an element that has changed.
That has changed.
I see what you're saying.
I was wondering, how do you mitigate this
when you have multiple and it has a component?
That's a good question.
I'll address that up front.
Thank you.
All right, any other questions?
Could you just help me with one example?
Yeah, I will.
How do you know if there's something wrong?
So you'll see, again, for some Mac users,
I don't know if that solved the problem up here.
Sometimes when you're working with CSS,
there's a whole thing with caching.
So if you make a change, even if you recompile
and it builds a new main.css and you refresh your website,
it's still showing the old thing.
It might be an issue with caching.
I have seen that before.
I like to use the Vivaldi browser
because it is very privacy friendly
and also resets the cache each time you reload.
So that's something to think about.
So I did want to show real quick,
notice how I put in this class here, bgred500.
And now when I refreshed my website here,
you'll notice that the button is red.
That's the only thing that's changed so far.
I don't like square buttons.
They look ugly to me.
So I would go back to that class.
Sorry.
And I would add something called rounded.
Actually, rounded may be large.
And save.
Was that wrong?
Maybe it's not rounded.
It's just taking a while.
Like my saves are taking a while.
They're rebuilt.
Once I see it says done with the rebuild,
that's when I can go back and check.
See how now it's a little more round?
I don't know if you can tell.
So very quickly, I can start experimenting
with different design elements.
I don't really like this.
It's too dark.
Now if I wanted to stay red, but I just
wanted to be a shade lighter, instead of 500,
maybe I'll use 300.
Again, the save is slow.
But see how the extension tells me what BG Red looks like?
So that's helpful, right?
And then if I go back and refresh,
well, that's taking it a minute.
One thing with these demos is you never
expect the slow internet.
Yeah, it's not even responding right now.
But that kind of gets you in a good spot.
Now let's say you wanted to make changes to all of your,
oops.
So the red square appears from the extension with VS Code
that allows you to see a preview of the colors.
So these colors are part of the VS Code extension.
They kind of get a quick sense.
So for repeatability, one of the things I recommend
is using multi-cursor editing.
Now I am a complete newbie.
When I first started trying multi-cursor stuff,
it just seemed really crazy to me.
But when you're working with Tailwind,
it's so useful that I learned it really quick.
With VS Code, for example, if you use Alt and you click,
you now have a cursor in all three places.
So I could do something like BG red 300.
So that's one way to do editing for these lines.
Let's say you have elements all around your HTML
and you just wanted to select certain ones.
Another thing you can do is highlight
a certain piece of the code and press,
I think it's Control-Shift-L. And now you
have a cursor on all matching aspects.
These are just tricks with your editor.
Multi-cursor editing, people who are kind of old school
have used Vim and that kind of stuff might be very familiar
with it.
For me, it was kind of new.
I learned it mostly because I liked editing my elements
quickly.
And once you learn that, oh, man, it's great.
Because now I can do this and save.
It recompiles.
You see, it took 28 milliseconds to recompile just that one
aspect.
Again, if the internet's not busted here.
See, there they are.
And that was just one change and a save.
And I can come and see the immediate effect.
So if you were working in CSS and you were thinking,
oh, let me style a button, you would go into your CSS file.
You would create the properties for that CSS element,
for a button element.
You would go back to your HTML.
You would put that class in each element of your HTML.
Then you would refresh and you would see this.
So it reduces a lot of that back and forth.
You're never really having to go to your CSS file at all.
So that's kind of how that looks.
Now, if you wanted some extra credit, let's see.
You could create a new detail endpoint.
This is only for some of you.
If you feel comfortable with what you're doing,
you could create a new detail endpoint.
So you would go to the routes.py file.
And make it showcase any artist, image, and profile.
To do that, you would use a tiny DB CRUD function,
maybe the get random artist one.
And then make it take up the whole page.
I'm going to go over one more item based on a question
I received back here.
And then we're going to take a quick break.
Not so quick.
Let's take about a 15 minute break, 10 minute break.
But first, before that, one of the questions
that comes up is when you're working in,
let me go back to that page.
Let's say you wanted to make specific changes.
I want to change this background color here.
Or I want to change the header.
What are some ways that you could make changes quickly?
I need to see how this would look green or black or whatever.
But you're not quite sure which element it's in.
You might go into the header file
and change the background color there.
And you don't see an effect.
What's the best way to get a sense of where you are
in the cascading style sheet?
So for example, I have these dark blue.
Or I don't know if this is the slate color here
in the background.
But where is this truly coming from?
And I think that's pretty valid.
For me, it's easier when I'm working with my own code base.
And I've built it from the ground up.
So I kind of know exactly where to look.
But a lot of times, we're sharing code.
Or you're starting to collaborate on a project.
You might only be in charge of a certain component.
And you're not as familiar with what else is going on.
I love using Inspect Element first and foremost,
even when working with Tailwind.
Because that gets me the closest.
I don't know if I can make this,
how can I make this bigger?
Like when I start looking at what's happening
in each of these cases,
I start seeing the class names
that I recognize from Tailwind.
And it starts giving me a sense
of where they are on the page.
So if I mouse over the body class, for example,
and I see Slate 900,
all right, well, this is a background color.
So I get a sense that it's something
that's affecting this entire page.
What I've done is I've cascaded everything
on top of this slate.
And that's what this color is here.
So if I were to find this class
and change it in the HTML,
that's actually on the base class here.
I could go to this slate here and say,
I prefer to have orange maybe.
I hit save.
It recompiles in 22 MS.
And let's see.
See how it changed just by making that one change.
So you can see pretty drastic changes very easily
without having to dig through.
All right, let me find the element,
see what class is referenced.
Let me go to the CSS, find that class.
Let me change that property and go back and refresh
and see if it's been added.
And when you're making numerous changes,
again, once you're in your HTML, you're set.
You don't have to keep.
And what I appreciate as well is
because of the compile build time,
you're getting rid of stuff you're not using
and you're only keeping things you're using.
I think I find that very valuable.
So yeah, inspect element,
the documentation website is really helpful.
The plugins for your editor are also extremely helpful.
And that's pretty much all you need
from the Tailwinds perspective.
Once you get a sense of how the classes are named
and what they do,
you're rarely even looking at the documentation,
especially if you have those plugins.
You're kind of just testing them, hitting save,
checking the effect and just changing things on the go,
adding padding.
Like you can think of how you can affect
the padding element pretty easily.
Like let's say you think these buttons are too close,
you don't like them.
So you go back to the header file and you think,
well, the PX, which is the X axis is set to 0.75 rem.
And I see that because I'm doing a mouse over on this class.
Then I just, oops, I missed that one.
I might want like six.
I hit save.
It's taking a moment again.
There it's rebuilt.
I go back and I refresh.
That actually, the padding element makes them wider.
That's right.
It wasn't the margin.
So if I wanted the margins to be wider,
again, I just go back instead of MX2.
We're thinking six as well.
See another wider part.
And you can play around with it that way
just to kind of get a sense.
And again, this is helpful with the template
component-based design.
Another thing with Tailwind is instead of thinking so much
for individual classes, there's these pre-made components,
some of them on the Tailwind site,
other free component sites.
They just give you like a button component
which has all those pre-built classes.
You just paste it right in
and you have a nice looking button.
You don't have to do much else.
That's another really cool thing.
So it is 10.08.
Let's take a 12 minute break, come back at 10.20.
And if you have any questions, I'm up here.
And again, I'll leave this up on the screen
in case you wanted to challenge yourself
and I'll put on some music.
All right, see you back in 12.
All right.
All right, hopefully you got a chance to stretch your legs,
get something to drink, take some deep breaths.
We're gonna get to the super fun part next,
which is HTMX.
I know we're still, some of us are still kind of testing out
Tailwind CSS.
It's one of those things that you'll get the most out of it
when you play around with it.
So when you have a spare moment,
you have access to this repo, take it with you,
just start playing around with the classes
and changing them up, seeing what's going on.
Now I know some folks have been having issues
with making the change, seeing the rebuild command,
refreshing their browser and they don't see the change.
Most of the time that's gonna be caching.
What you can do is you can look at the main.css file
that's in the static directory,
just to make sure that it's building,
that the class you built is being defined in there.
And then you can view source on the front end.
And if you see that class reference in the HTML,
it means the pieces are there.
It just means maybe for some reason,
the caching is looking at the old version of the CSS file.
That's possible.
But again, come and find me.
I am thinking of maybe hosting an open space
to talk more about some of this Tailwind stuff
and HTML stuff that maybe we can't get in the tutorial.
So if you wanna do that, look for it maybe later
during the conference.
Okay, moving on, HTML.
So I talked about a simple site
and this kind of started as a simple site.
I was just kind of building something from scratch,
a basic hello world.
I wanted to see how far I could get with just Tailwind,
just HTML.
Now, HTML, what it will do
is it will reduce that complexity.
Again, I'm a non-developer that tries to do it at night.
So I don't wanna have to learn JavaScript to do web stuff.
It's too much mental overhead for me.
But I wanna have that kind of modern UI,
that feel of something that's quite responsive.
And if I can do that all directly from HTML,
so much the better.
Now, HTML, I don't know how much you know about it.
If you're here, you may have heard about it
or you may have seen.
One of my favorite things about HTML
is the Twitter account where they have lots of memes.
I could give you some really well-recent,
detailed and insightful things.
And mind you, all of that is there at the htmx.org site.
There's some really great essays
as to why this is a good design pattern,
but memes are so much more fun, right?
Now, again, coming from a lack of experience,
maybe on my end with JavaScript,
I don't know what client-side routing is.
I don't wanna know what client-side routing is.
To me, it makes sense the way we've presented it so far.
A user makes a request from the front end,
you receive this on the server side,
you do what you need to do,
get the information you need to send back
and you send it back to the user.
It just makes sense to me.
I don't see why there would need to be
so much more complexity, right?
So speaking of complexity, how do you install htmx?
You basically copy a file into your project and that's it.
So htmx itself is vanilla JavaScript
that someone else wrote that you never have to look at.
I put it in a folder in my static directory.
I think I called it probably JS, under JS directory.
And that's it, that's really it.
Now you can reference that script within your HTML.
And since we're using templates,
what I did is I included the script source
in that base template.
You see it here under this line particularly.
You would just do a script source
that points directly to your htmx file.
I called this one htmx.min.js.
You can find that in the base.html template.
And that's all you need to get working with htmx, that's it.
I just find that quite a bit easier than,
I think at some point I installed npm on my machine.
I don't know what I was doing.
As a matter of fact, these slides are revealed.js.
So just kidding, I did have a little bit of JavaScript
in this presentation.
But that's about as far as I'll get.
I'll build my slides with it.
What does htmx look like?
This is directly from the htmx.org site.
This is what it looks like in your HTML.
Here we have a button element,
which you may be familiar with.
But then we have a lot of these hx attributes.
The first one says, and sorry if the contrast
is a little odd, hx-post is for the endpoint clicked.
hx trigger is click.
hx target is the parent div, hx swap is outer HTML,
and then the button says click me.
So what do all these things do?
The first thing that we do is we're sending a post request
to the clicked route.
So anytime a user clicks on this button,
it is already sending a post request.
It doesn't matter that it's not in a form
or that it's a submit button or anything like that.
This could be a div element or a p element
or a span element, it could be whatever you want it to be.
This is sending that post request to the clicked route
so we can understand that within our fast API application.
The second thing is the, actually,
it is triggered by a click.
So that hx trigger says that when you click this button,
it's gonna send a post request.
So there's other kinds of actions that you could use.
Next, the target for the response
is an HTML element with an ID of parent div.
So when you click this button,
it's pointing to this other element that has that ID.
It can be wherever you want in your HTML.
And the hx swap point here,
what that means is your response can either
be sent within that element.
So let's say your div element, your parent div element,
you only want to swap what's inside of it,
then you could do it that way
or you could replace the whole element,
which means the outer HTML
that represents the outer element.
So you will no longer have that parent div anymore
if you use this particular command.
So it does all of those things by just defining that.
Whatever response you send back
will go into that element in the DOM, and that's it.
That's htmx.
So it's a pretty great example.
Again, that's on the htmx.org site.
And how do we know what to,
what to do on the server side?
Like how do we know when we get this request
at the clicked endpoint?
How do we know what to do with it?
So htmx sends particular data through request headers.
Again, if some of you aren't as familiar
with some of this terminology,
you can always come back to the recording of the tutorial
as you get a better idea.
But most of you, if you've worked in the web,
you get a sense of what the request headers are
and how to access them.
With Fast API, you can, it's sent as, I think,
a dictionary item, and then you can look
for specific requests headers.
Some of the ones that you're gonna look at
that are sent from htmx, these are just some.
There are many others.
But these, I'd say, are some of the most important ones.
So there will be an hx request that is always true
when the request is generated from an htmx attribute.
So in this sense, because hx request is always true,
in our Python application, we can look for that header.
If hx request, then we just wanna send this response, right?
But if someone navigates to that endpoint,
you might not wanna send just a partial response.
You might wanna refresh the whole page.
That's why that hx request is so important.
Other things that you can send through are the target,
the trigger, and what current URL
is sending this information.
That's all useful, and we'll see how a little later.
But these are just some examples.
More information of that, again, is on the htmx.org website.
What do we do in our code?
It might be something like this.
In FastAPI, you use a app.get or router.get,
and you put the endpoint.
So if it were the previous one, this might be,
instead of page, it might say clicked or whatever.
You define a function or a view in this case
that is doing two things.
First, it's setting the template to somepage.html.
That presumes that someone is navigating
to the page endpoint.
This template, this somepage.html,
might be a full representation of what someone should see.
It'll include the base element and the content.
But let's say someone actually clicked something
that is an HX request.
Then what we're doing is we're using,
if the request has an HX request element in there,
then the template is actually only this partial content
that's going to replace that element in the DOM.
So you might only be replacing
a small piece of information.
So you don't want to send your entire template
to go into that small piece.
That happens to me a lot when I'm testing things out.
I end up with a version of the entire site
in one little window.
I'm like, oh, I must have not checked
if this was an HX request.
That's where the HX request comes really handy.
And again, if you were to go through this again,
we're setting the template to somepage.html.
We're checking if that request was triggered by htmx.
If it was, then we're changing that template object
to the partial content.html.
So then when we send that template response back
to the user, either way it's going to be the correct
based on the way it was requested.
And of course, the context might vary
based on how it's requested.
But this is just a more simplified version
of what's happening.
The somepage.html, again, if you were creating
an entire element, might look something like this.
It's extending the base template,
you're saying whatever you're saying in the body.
You might have a random image there, et cetera.
And then if you wanted to just refresh that image,
maybe that button click was just needed to refresh
this div element that's called random image,
then a regular request would require a full page reload,
but an HX request would then only replace that element.
But in order to replace that element,
you would need that partial content to be
in a separate file usually,
unless you're using that Jinja two blocks,
which we'll talk about later.
But then your partial content HTML
might be something as small as this.
It has only the specific element that would be changing
because the HX request wanted you to replace
that one element in your webpage,
and you don't have to do a full page refresh.
And that's pretty great.
You can see how great that would be in a pretty large website
if you're only needing to change one thing
instead of doing a full page refresh,
you're only refreshing a small element of the DOM
that's pretty fantastic without anything
other than what we've seen.
The fragments that we talked about later,
this is using the Jinja two blocks,
allows you to do things slightly differently.
So instead of having two files,
which one would be the one that we saw before,
the some page.html, in this case,
you would only have one page called some page.html.
But now the template response allows
for an additional parameter called block name.
This means that within that template response,
or I'm sorry, within that some page.html,
if the request comes from htmx,
if this block name will be some name, whatever it is,
now what the template response is looking for
is a specific block name using the same terminology
that Jinja uses for blocks,
and it will only render that item.
So you're using the same template file,
you no longer need two files.
The block name is only triggered if it's an htmx request,
and it'll match some name block in your template, right?
So your template will look like this.
So now it looks almost identical to what we saw before,
except that the random image,
it has a block name that starts right before the development
and ends right after it.
So now when it renders,
it's only rendering that part of the template.
So it seems a little odd now,
but once you start inserting some dynamic attributes
to say the image, if it was a dynamic image,
now you can see how much more useful it would be
to have it all in one file.
Locality behavior, you have it there,
you don't need to go hunting for different files.
Both of those methods work.
We'll see why this method might be more useful
when you're working with kind of a bigger application.
So a regular request renders everything.
We already knew that.
It'll include that content from the base HTML.
An htmx request would then only render
that partial content that is within that block name.
So if you've been kind of paying attention
and you start imagining the types of things
that you can do with htmx,
you pretty much have accomplished a lot already.
You're a full stack developer now, right?
Again, these memes are from htmx website.
Like if you follow their Twitter, it's pretty great stuff.
Most of the things that you're gonna want to do
in UX design is covered with htmx.
If there are additional things,
there are some caveats,
some things that you might introduce
a little bit of JavaScript.
It's okay to do that too.
It's not an either or proposition.
That's one thing to really think about.
If you have already experienced with JavaScript
and it's useful in certain ways, that's great.
But the emphasis here is to try to reduce
as much complexity as you can first
and then add on top of that anything that might be missing.
Okay, so that's gotten us to a pretty good spot
at understanding htmx.
I wanted to show a couple things on the repository.
Let me go here.
You know what, before I get into that,
I just wanted to, someone asked what's going on
with this website to begin with.
So again, this started as a simple site.
I didn't even really have an idea
as much as to what I was gonna be building.
Then I started thinking about something I like,
which is music.
I like music.
And I wanted to kind of deal with a topic
that is fun for me.
So I went to this API, the Discogs API.
I don't know if many of you have heard of it.
It's mostly for music collectors.
I don't necessarily collect records or anything like that,
but it has a pretty good API.
So I went to that API and I downloaded a lot of data
from some of my favorite artists
just to kind of take a look at it.
And I put all that data, again, with TinyDB
into a JSON file.
And then I started thinking about the olden days
when I used to have these CD binders
where I would flip through them.
And I just loved looking at the liner notes
or pictures of my favorite bands.
And it was really cool.
The CDs probably didn't work
because they were all scratched up,
but I just loved looking through all the binders.
So I thought, why don't I emulate that sort of experience
and kind of take a look at
what some of these artists look like.
So I built this site, which uses, again, the Discogs API,
to connect to these images,
which are actually linking to their website.
So none of this is local.
You'll notice it's not even in the static assets.
Most of the time, if you're building a site,
you would have your images either locally
or in a CDN or something.
But these are actually all contained elsewhere.
So anytime I click randomize,
it's actually looking at,
it's actually pulling the image from a URL
that's pointing to the Discogs API.
When you're dealing with API data,
sometimes you have incomplete data
or you're not quite sure what's there.
So it's something to think about in your design,
especially if you're building off of someone else's data.
So I thought it was also an interesting problem.
Can I showcase something that kind of works?
So you'll notice some oddities
when you go to the catalog here,
which you'll notice some names have a,
like a parentheses four, parentheses three.
That's because again,
this is taken directly from the Discogs API.
So it's a user-sourced database, data storage.
So people are making sometimes duplicate entries
for artists or bands.
And I didn't clean the data myself.
I just was using directly what they had.
So you'll notice that over here,
you're seeing like some weird things.
That's why it's like that.
But these are my, you know,
some of my favorite bands that I've listened through
throughout the years, among others,
but I just took a sampling.
I like to joke in my Macedon account,
I was joking about how this might be the first tutorial
that comes with a playlist.
So I will link you to the playlist
that has one song from each of these bands.
And it's part of what you were hearing earlier
when you came in.
So that music is there for you to listen to as well.
So that's what this site is for, just to get an idea.
The homepage is just meant to have a random image
from one of the bands that's on here.
The about page doesn't do much.
It just kind of tells you a little bit of that history.
And the catalog page,
this is showcasing some cool things with HTML.
So I'll show you that now.
Let's say you have a database that has all this info
and you wanted it to populate these cards.
Now you could code that all in yourself, right?
But with a template, all you have to do is load a,
whether it's a class element or just a list of elements,
and then you can build a for loop within your template.
And all you're ever building is one card.
And then it just cycles through your list
and it starts populating just using a flex box or whatever,
whether you're using grid or flex box,
you could do it either way.
And now let's say I wanted the user
to have a little bit more information
about each one of these bands.
So I wanted to populate whatever profile is listed
on each one of these artists
when you click on any one of these elements.
So you'll notice if I click here,
it brings up the profile that's linked
to that particular database entry.
When I clicked here, you did not see a full page refresh.
All you saw was that this particular element
populated the profile.
If I go to the next one and click,
it'll do the same thing.
And I can go to any one of these and do the same thing.
That's all HTMX.
And it's a fairly straightforward HTMX call
similar to what we've seen.
And we'll talk about that in a little bit.
And then the other thing I wanted to highlight
was the search.
Now search is interesting in a lot of different ways.
When you're doing a search to your database,
it's usually someone will type things in and hit enter,
and then it'll do that search.
But how cool would it be if you could send a request
on key press, right?
So what you'll notice first of all,
is that when I click here,
it changes to search results here.
And notice that if I type the,
you'll start seeing that the responses change.
And if I just wanted the album leaf, A,
notice that it is refreshing as I type.
So on each key press,
well, let me rephrase that.
On each key up,
it is doing a post request.
That post request is then making a search in my database,
sending that response back,
and filling up this area here.
One question you may have,
isn't that dangerous with key presses?
Someone's just mashing on their keyboard,
wouldn't that just send a million requests to your server
and just basically bombard you?
Yes, that could happen.
So for this particular active search,
what I do is I put in a delay of 500 milliseconds
before a request is sent.
So if someone is mashing their keyboard,
it's not gonna send a request
until they stop for 500 milliseconds.
So to see this in action,
what you can see is if you're in the,
in the terminal,
you'll notice the requests show up here
because I have a print statement on the terminal.
Notice right here, there's a print statement.
And I don't know if maybe I can do it this way.
All right, so look here on the left as I type,
if I were to just do,
let me see,
notice that there's nothing happening
because I'm just mashing my keyboards, right?
Nothing's happening.
But as soon as I let go, I don't like that one.
If I just do that, notice that there is the,
there is a request that was made down here.
And if I went to type something else in,
it caught two requests
because I paused between the E and the S.
So that's all.
HTMS as well.
You're seeing a very dynamic experience
between the user and the information.
They're typing, they're seeing things change.
It's not doing a full page refresh each time.
It's only refreshing the search results area, right?
And you can still do this check
once you've searched to see it change.
So how is that happening?
I wanted to show you a little bit of the,
at least the route for changing the profile,
just so you get a sense of how that happens.
Most of that, like I mentioned,
is gonna be in the routes.py file.
So I'm gonna go here to routes.py.
I'm gonna hide this for now.
I'm gonna go down to the one that's called catalog.
I tried to put enough information in the documentation there
so you get a sense of what's happening.
I'll try to explain as best I can.
And it should follow with some of the things
we've already seen.
And then I have these little to do items here,
which are some things we can work on
through the remainder of the tutorial.
We'll have about an hour and a half
to work on some of these.
I wanna give you a challenge.
In addition to some of the things here,
there's some issues in the repo that we can work on.
I'll probably work on some up here as well
so you can kind of get a sense of how those are being built.
But I really wanted us to have a lot of hands on time
with HTMX and make sure I can answer
all your questions as best I can.
But you'll notice how this one's happening.
So this catalog endpoint is what we see previously here,
the catalog endpoint.
When we go to the catalog endpoint,
we wanna make sure that we refresh this entire page.
So that's the first thing that we need to worry about,
which is getting all the items from the database
and making sure that they display.
So the first thing I do is I instantiate
a database object here.
So I'm using this utility class that I built.
You don't really need to know much about that.
Again, if you're used to using your own database.
Ordinarily, this just gives you access to a couple methods
that we can use for this application.
So I instantiate that,
and then the way that I get all my artists
or all the elements within that database
is I just built this all items method.
So that gives us a list of dictionary items.
So now we have a ton of, you know,
I think it's 63 artists.
So a list of 63 dictionaries.
We give the template a name, catalog.html.
So that's gonna be there in your templates folder
under catalog.html.
And then we start defining this context.
Again, this is the most important part
of sending the data back to the user through the template.
We're gonna have the request, which always needs to go.
So this always needs to be included.
Then we have this list of artists
that goes into, that uses this name within the template.
To access this list of artists.
You'll also notice an interesting thing here.
This is something that I took for granted a lot
when learning about templates,
which is because functions or methods are objects,
you can actually send those to your templates
and you utilize them within your templates.
So I built these helper functions
that I send directly to the template.
And what these functions do is they take
one artist element, so one dictionary element,
and it gets the information that I need
from that artist dictionary.
So the get website parses through that dictionary
and outputs the URL that I need.
And the reason I did that is because there's some logic,
some of the artists might be missing a URL, for example.
So I have to make sure that I check for that
or make a generic website or something.
Same thing with active members.
The API actually has active and inactive members.
So I didn't wanna send all those through blankly.
So I'm actually just sending this function through
to the template.
And then for each artist that I'm iterating over,
I feed that to this object to get the members
that I need to display on that card.
And same thing with get profile.
Some of the artists did not have a profile listed,
so I need to make sure I check for that as well.
So I'm sending these methods directly to the template.
Here, we saw this earlier.
So this is populating regularly,
but what happens when I have an HX request?
Well, I don't wanna populate that entire thing
into this one little card.
So this is where I do something additional.
First thing I do is I check for the HX trigger.
Oh, yeah, the HX trigger.
So this is one of the headers that we talked about earlier.
Why am I looking for the HX trigger?
So if you remember, the HX trigger
is the element that's triggering this HTMX request,
is the ID of that element.
So what I've done in the template, you'll notice,
I'm gonna bring up the template now.
Notice that this div ID, this whole element here
is that card that you see.
This ID actually corresponds to the artist ID.
And the ID is just, think of it as the database primary key.
That's what the ID corresponds to here.
So now when a user clicks on this element,
this ID is sent back to the route.
It's sent back to the route.
So now I have the artist ID from within that card
here in the backend,
and I make a database call based on that ID.
So now that I have that artist,
I'm changing the template now to this profile template,
which is in the artist profile directory.
And this just defines what that profile looks like
within the card.
So you can make it look however you want.
You could style it different.
I try to keep a similar style,
but you'll notice that here is that get profile method
or function that we pass through.
I'm passing in the artist.
I'm using safe because I want it to generate
if there's any HTML.
And the get website.
So the more info should populate
with the website of the artist.
So if I were to go to explosions in the sky
and hit more info,
you'll notice that it takes me there
to their website, right?
And then going back to the routes.
So once we've defined the template,
the artist, this find method sends a list,
but it should only find one person,
so, or yeah, one artist.
So I am populating the context for artist
with this one artist.
So now my template response includes the template,
which is going to be either the catalog HTML,
if a user navigates directly to this endpoint,
or the artist profile HTML if it's an HX request.
So that's the response.
And the context will be this entire thing.
And I'm going to create a new element for this context,
which is just artist singular that contains the artist
so that I can then get the profile info
for that particular element.
And that's all it takes to produce this type of,
and you'll notice the back button doesn't,
maybe I just need to go back there.
I don't know, how did I?
I get an internal server error when I press back
from one of the websites,
which I fixed in a separate branch,
and I'll show you how I fixed that.
And there's a reason why it gives that error.
But that's what happens.
So that bit of code that you see there,
just this one route is what handles both the generation
of this entire catalog page when someone clicks here,
or the generation of the profile
when someone clicks any one of these cards.
So no JavaScript, no additional fancy stuff,
just pretty straightforward HTML and Python.
All right, any questions on what's happening there at all?
Any confusion?
We're good.
All right, gonna take a look at the search,
and then we'll get our hands
and try to tackle some of these things.
So the search thing is interesting.
We have a get request when someone actually clicks
on the search bar,
and then we have obviously the post request.
So in FastAPI, we can define the get request
with router.get, and here's the search endpoint.
So this, what I wanted it to do is I just wanted it
to go ahead and populate all the artists
when a user clicks into that search element.
So again, we're populating this artist object
with all the items,
and we're sending some of that same stuff.
But I'm also including this Boolean here from search,
and I'll talk about that in a minute.
But I also have this thing called block name.
So this is the Jinja2 blocks thing.
But first things first, we are looking at,
actually I don't even think I'm using this block name
in this instance.
I think I was building towards something,
and you'll notice that I define a block name,
but I never, oh no, I do redefine it here, sorry.
So all I'm doing is if someone navigates
to search on their own, it does one thing.
If they are going, if they are generating it through a get,
through an HX request, then I'm defining that block name
merely to the content.
So that's where that's happening.
So again, navigating specifically to search
would be something like this.
And it's the same thing, it just generates search results.
But if I'm here in the about page,
and I click up here, this is actually,
as soon as I click up here,
this is going to be an HX request.
And this fancy hover stuff is all tailwind stuff.
So you can see kind of the dynamic nature
of things you could do even just with transitions
and mouse over and stuff.
So I'm going here, as soon as I click here,
you'll notice that the search results pop in here.
So that's an HX request.
I can show you in the search.html,
actually no, it's in the header.html,
that when, where I define the search box,
which is one big SVG, I believe.
Let's see if I can find it here.
Yeah, it's this whole SVG here.
Or maybe I haven't.
Where's the eight?
Maybe I haven't done it as.
Yeah, this is it here.
So this HX get is the HX call, the HTMLX call.
You'll notice that it has a target of content.
So whenever this request is sent,
it only, or the DOM element to be replaced
is the content, the block content.
And additional item is I want to push the URL to true.
This is another HX attribute.
So what this does is when someone clicks on the search,
you actually want it to populate here for history
in the search bar.
That doesn't always happen.
Like for example, when I click on these,
you notice that the search, the URL doesn't change.
So you have to think about whether you want
to push the URL or not.
There might be reasons you want to.
There might be reasons you don't.
I wouldn't want to push the URL
when we're just toggling between the profile and members,
but I might want to change it if I'm in the homepage
and I click search, I do want the search to populate there.
So that's why you see that particular attribute here.
So that this all, this all is particularly for the input,
for clicking on that input.
But then you'll see, that's that div ID there.
But then you see that the input itself
has the HX post method.
Here's the HX trigger that I talked about.
So there's a couple of things that are happening
and an HX target.
So the HX post, it's sending a post request
whenever someone comes to that endpoint.
And the trigger is key up, changed and delay.
So you would have to have a key up,
it needs to have changed and there needs to be a delay
of 500 milliseconds before it sends this post request.
There's more info on some of the different triggers
and things you can use in the HTML website.
So we'll look at those later.
And the comma search is you can say,
what that's supposed to be is in case someone hits enter,
it'll actually run the search automatically
instead of waiting for the 500 milliseconds.
So if someone types quickly and hits enter,
it'll do the search.
And then the HX target means that this is the ID
that's gonna change.
You'll notice that it's not, this ID doesn't even exist
within this header.html because again,
this is part of the template.
If I were to go back to the templates now
and look at search, actually I think it's under catalog.
No, here it is.
So there's the div ID here of search results.
So this element is the one that will populate
when someone does start searching.
Which is pretty neat because these are,
again, you don't have to build a whole new template
or anything, it's all happening here.
And what you see here is basically if there's,
if the search is a list,
then for result in results, then type in that name else
for result in results.
I'm trying to remember what I'm sending here.
So let me look at my route search.
I'm actually, did I end up using catalog instead?
You know what?
I ended up using catalog instead for the Jinja 2 blocks.
You also notice in this catalog,
one thing I noticed was if my search results
are only gonna be cards similar to what they appear
in the catalog, can't I just create a new block
that basically says if this is from the search endpoint,
populate the search elements here.
Or if this is from the catalog, do it this way.
So that's where you see in this template,
I'm using the Jinja 2 fragments,
which can specify which items to render
based on what triggered the response.
So notice that context had from search is true.
So now I can say if it's not from search,
do this one thing, else populate the search results.
So now I can have my catalogs ordinarily here
and my search results down here.
I think that's kinda how this piece was done.
Because initially I had separated out the search.
Now I'm trying to remember if I did that
in a separate branch or not.
Yeah, because look, over here I'm just sending
the catalog.html under the search get.
And I think also under the search post.
So I'm not even using that search.html file at all.
What I'm doing is if there's a block,
if it's an HX request, I'm saying only generate
the content block when someone clicks search
and only generate the artist card block
when it's a post request.
So that's pretty useful because you're no longer
having to split out separate files.
I think I built the search.html file to kinda show
the difference of what it would look like.
It might work for your workflow.
Sometimes you might wanna separate things out
just to keep things straight, put them in directories,
especially if you have a certain workflow
that you already use with templates.
Otherwise, for me, having just one template file
that looks at the state of things and generates that way
makes it easier for me.
And that's it.
So then the post request is here.
We looked at the HTML already and it's pretty similar
to what we've seen before.
We're generating all artists and let's see.
Let's see.
Then we're doing, so this is just the database call.
Again, if you're using any database,
you'd do some sort of find or search
or however you're using.
The search key is gonna be name
and the value is the search.
So that search corresponds to the user input.
So each key up with the 500 millisecond delay
is gonna populate the search.
So now each time that post request is sent,
we're finding the list of artists that matches that search.
And then those are the artists that get sent to the template
and then they generate into this artist card.
And that's how we now see them on here
when I just start typing H.
Those are all the bands that have an H in their name.
Or if I was looking for a specific Japanese composer,
and there you go.
And that resets.
Those are some of the more straight forward
straight forward HTML type of examples I have.
Now we have about an hour and 15 minutes
to work on some of these issues.
And there's a secret, not a secret,
if you've gone to the repo,
you might have noticed there's a separate branch
called additional features, I believe.
Some of the answers to those issues
are there in that branch.
If you like to work backwards,
I do a lot of times, I like to see how something works
and then kind of deconstruct.
You can go to that branch to see
how some of these things are solved and work that way.
Or if you wanna try to give it a go,
there in the routes.py are some to do items
under each one of those functions,
as well as in the repo, there's some issues
that are either similar or I think there might be one
that's separate.
There's some that are marked good first issue,
those I believe might be a little easier to tackle.
And there's some more complex things.
After let's say, after about half an hour,
we'll take a really short break
and I'll demo what those additional features look like
and then we can finish off working
to get yours up to speed as well.
If you opened up in a code space,
you might need to do a get fetch all sort of thing
to get that additional branch on there.
If you have issues with that, just let me know.
But again, I want us to kind of take a look at those issues.
Any questions so far?
We're doing good?
Excellent.
All right, I'm gonna put on some music.
All right, how's it going?
Some of you are getting there.
While you keep working, I do wanna,
I do want to kind of show you some of the things
that you can build towards.
You can continue working.
I just wanna make sure we have time to get to some of these.
So give me one moment.
What I've done is I'm opening up,
and I'll put it up on the screen in a moment.
I'm opening up the additional features branch.
Just give me one moment.
Okay.
So now I have, let me make this bigger.
This is the, oh, it might not be the right branch.
I used the wrong,
oh, I'm running too many.
I need to close one of these, that's why.
All right, just give me a second.
I wanted to make sure we all have a sense
of what we can build towards.
And I'm seeing, the good thing is I'm seeing
some different ways to approach some of these,
which is good.
Why is this not?
I might just have to open this up from, okay.
Here we go.
So as I mentioned, the data that I get from,
that I'm using comes from the Discogs API.
And because of that, sometimes I run into this thing,
I wanted to show a lot of images on the screen,
but sometimes I would hit the rate limit,
and then it would give a not found error.
So hopefully I don't run into too much of that now.
I think since we're all working off of different containers,
it won't bombard them, so hopefully that works.
But if you see anything odd, that might be part of it.
But let me get this running really quick.
I was in the wrong, I started the wrong code space.
All right, here we go.
So I'll show you the front end experience first.
There's a, this is the, this should have the
randomized button working so that only the update,
only the image updates.
This would be important in cases where you might have
a lot of content on a webpage,
and you don't want a full refresh,
you don't get that kind of jittery feeling.
So if I press randomize, it's really only
randomizing this image here.
You can see it's pretty snappy.
And again, these aren't even local images.
This is actually hitting a URL and bringing the image
and adding it in here, so it's pretty quick.
So that's the, that's one piece there.
Another to do was, oh yes.
There are, there are, you can use CSS transitions.
Yes, and that is one question that you get a lot
with HTMX is can you make it look a little bit smoother
with the transitions, but yes, using CSS transitions,
some of them are already predefined.
You don't have to do much else other than give it
that attribute in the HTML.
That's a good question.
The about page, when you click in it,
you'll see that it does give you the URL up here,
but all I've really changed is the content here.
So you can see how this might even start looking
like a single page application.
You can create a shell and you're only changing elements
within the application.
It's still not technically a single page application,
but it can function that way.
Each one of these can be set to only refresh the content.
And again, we see that even when you select search
that it only populates what you need to populate here.
One of the to do items was to be able to select one
of these and then when you click back,
it brings back the members.
So now it acts as a toggle.
So you can see each time that you're doing that,
you're sending a get request to the server,
but it's only updating the information
that it needs each time.
Another item that we talked about was the,
I think those were the pieces we're checking.
I do wanna show something really cool.
So one situation you may run into when you have,
let's say a lot of images and you're working
with one of these server side rendering type of situations,
you wanna populate a lot of images,
but you don't want to have to load them all
before your page comes into view, right?
So one thing that we can do with HTMX
is we can create a load more button.
So you only populate certain amount, you load more,
it keeps loading, but even cooler than that
is you can just have a trigger that when an element
comes into view, into the viewport,
it loads a next set of elements.
And then as you're scrolling,
it starts populating developments after the one
that you just populated.
So when I click on the detail link here,
which is new in the additional features branch,
you'll notice that it brings up an image, a name,
and you'll see the scroll bar right here, right?
This scroll bar should only have populated enough
for a few bands.
But notice, it starts getting bigger
as I start scrolling down.
Because what's happening is when it reaches
a certain element into view, it sends a get request
to populate the next element.
So now, when you come to the details page,
you're not loading a bunch of images
that then you have to scroll down to see,
you're only loading them as you need them
as someone is scrolling down.
Notice, the scroll bar keeps popping up, right?
Ella Jenkins sings a lot of children's music,
so that's why she's on here as well.
My four-year-old was here earlier.
Notice, it keeps getting bigger, right?
And I still have not, I haven't hit any sort of snag, right?
Just keeps growing.
I think that's a really cool feature
when you're dealing with a lot of data,
or even if you, let's say you're from the data side
and you have these huge models, there's different ways
that you can interact with the visualization,
loading things as you need them.
Again, you could use a similar method.
You get to the bottom, load more,
or load next, those types of things.
I think it's a pretty useful feature.
I mean, I was super excited just to get this thing working.
Now, one thing that you have to think about
is how do you anticipate what to load next,
and what do you do when you get to the very end?
I think initially, when I had built this,
when I got to the end, it would create some sort of error
because the get request kept looking for the next item
and didn't know what to find.
But there's ways that you can deal with that
on the Python side, right?
You know how to handle exceptions.
You know how to handle different sets of data.
You can get all the way to the very end, which is here,
and we're done, right?
And one thing that you'll notice with the kinds of data
that's on each one of these, like I mentioned,
since this comes from a API that has inconsistent data,
some bands might have Wikipedia entries, but some don't.
So that's all handled through Python again.
I'm seeing if there's a link that contains Wikipedia on it,
and if not, then I just don't display it.
You notice that it doesn't create any sort of visual error.
On the HTML side, I've only coded one detail card.
That's it.
I haven't created a huge HTML file out of this.
We just have one template that's iterating
over all these artists' dictionaries
and populating the information as needed.
Some of these bands have additional images,
so I could potentially add additional HX requests
that allow me to click through and see all the images
associated with the band members.
That's something I haven't done in this particular case,
but you can see how it starts looking a lot more dynamic
as you start building it out.
Again, everything that we've done so far
is either in the HTML or in Python.
We haven't needed to do much else
outside of configuring our tailwind.
I was going to wait a little bit longer
to look at some additional pieces of customizations
that you can do within tailwind and HTML,
but I think we might as well get to them
so I don't miss out on speaking about that.
We've tackled some repository issues.
I had an extra credit here, I forgot about it.
You can add keyboard shortcuts as triggers.
You can make your web application function
almost like a web app.
You could do Ctrl S for search,
or you could make different kinds of modifiers
to keyboard shortcuts so people could interact
with your website.
Could be a really cool thing to do,
so maybe try that out in your spare time.
But one thing you may think about
when you're building with predetermined classes,
as is the case with tailwind,
is what do you do when you need
a little bit more customizability?
Tailwind does allow you to create
your own custom CSS classes,
so you can define those yourself.
And then you can also provide your own color scheme.
So you saw those that are already predefined
for red and blue and fuchsia.
There's so many, but we all wanna be unique butterflies,
and so sometimes we may wanna create
our own sorts of color palettes,
and we can name them however we want,
so it allows you to do that.
You can also use custom and pre-built components.
There's a paid element to tailwind CSS
if you wanna pay for these very professional looking
elements that you just don't wanna build yourself,
but then you can then customize them once you've used them,
so that's pretty great.
And then what's also pretty great about tailwind
is it provides these specific breakpoints
when you're building.
I haven't showcased a lot of that in what I've built so far,
but you can set, you build with mobile first,
design, and then you set breakpoints,
and all you have to do is use, say,
MD for medium screen size, MD colon,
and then provide all the classes that apply
to that breakpoint and larger.
And same thing with large, LG colon,
everything past that would be customized.
So a lot of stuff you can do there.
What you would wanna do is,
here's an example of a custom class
within that directives file that we saw.
So what you're doing is you're calling in
that components layer, which is one of the layers
used during the build process or compilation process,
and you're creating your custom button.
So now, in your HTML, instead of having to type in
PX2, PY1, BGBlue, rounded, Text Slate 200,
now all you have to do is put in custom button,
and it'll do all of that for you.
So that might reduce the verbosity of the HTML element.
Some people might like to do that.
Also, you could just straight up code a custom CSS class
within that directives.
You just would not add it to the component layer.
You would just code a straight up CSS property,
just like you're used to.
So the equivalent of that piece that we saw up here,
so the equivalent of that in CSS looks like this.
They're both doing the same thing,
and you would call them the same way within your HTML.
You would either do custom button or custom buttoner,
and they do the exact same thing.
They're just written differently.
I could get into it, but it matters in terms of
how things are layered in the cascading sheet.
It can get a little bit more down the rabbit hole with that.
This is how you would do that
if you wanted to build your own custom classes
that you can then call within your HTML elements.
And again, forget about the compiled CSS class file,
because you wouldn't need to worry about it.
A custom color palette would look a little bit like this.
So in that tailwind.config file that we saw
that's at the root of your project,
you might have an extension.
So you would extend the available colors.
And then you would add, these are just an example.
You could add a primary color.
So then in your HTML, you would just say
class equals class bg-primary,
and it would always be that color.
So that way, if you're developing with a mindset
of primary, secondary type colors,
you just call that in your class
and you already know what color scheme you're using.
If you wanted to define your own palette,
like we see with the slate or some of those other colors,
here's an example of how you could do that.
Here's a turquoise color palette,
and each one of these levels would be defined
at each one of these hex codes.
How do I get my own color palette?
There's a lot of cool generators online
for tailwind color palette generator
that you can type in red,
and it kind of gives you a whole slew of these.
And then you just pretty much copy paste them
into this config file.
Again, this allows for that kind of customization
you might need if you're being very specific
about the colors you need to use.
Let's say you're working with a design team
and they're telling you what colors you need to use,
and this is kind of how you would do it.
Additionally, I don't know if I have it on the slide.
Yeah, so this is how you would call the primary color
for your text, for example,
instead of having to do text dash BG or text slate,
whatever, you just call the primary color.
But I did want to point out,
I think I didn't put a slide on this,
but there's also a way that you can define,
let me make this bigger.
Let me make sure I have it in here.
In that same directives file,
if you're in the additional features repo,
and you look at the static source TW file,
what you'll notice in here is,
I'm also defining a separate font.
So you'll notice that the font that I'm using here
actually looks a little different
than what you saw initially.
Let's say you don't want to use your system fonts,
you want to use your own font.
So I downloaded this font called Livik,
and you define it just like you would in a CSS file.
Again, this is in that directives file.
I'm creating font face properties
for each of the font weights I think I'm gonna use.
And then in my config file,
so there's a two step process for fonts.
You put them in your directive file,
and then in your config file,
you need to state that you're gonna use
a font family called Livik.
I could name this ABCD, whatever I want to.
This is gonna be the name that you use.
This is the class that's associated with this font.
So now you can use Livik within your templates.
If you look at my,
I think I put it in the base.
Did I put it in here somewhere?
Yeah, see, I define the font for the entire page to be Livik.
So now everything is generating with that font.
That's if you wanna use custom fonts.
So it's all possible.
There are a lot more customizations you can do,
and that's all available there on the Tailwind CSS website.
It's amazing the kinds of things you can do.
And I do also wanna talk about HTMX.
One question I got asked previously
when I was talking about this topic
with a group of people was, is HTMX production ready?
That's the main question.
Now, the advantage you have here
is that you have no outside dependencies,
outside of your Python dependencies.
All you need is a file and your static assets, right?
The vanilla JavaScript file we saw.
It's significantly less complex than a spa approach,
than a single-page application.
You're not dealing with any front-end framework
and having to have two different states.
And it's perfect for any back-end technology.
We work in Python, but you could use it
with any back-end technology.
So if you're comfortable in your back-end technology,
you're comfortable with HTMX.
But does that answer the question, is it production ready?
Can I depend on it?
Now, what I would say is I'm just a lowly business analyst
that dabbles with Python at night.
So you wouldn't have to take my word for it.
But I would recommend watching this video
that's online from DjangoCon Europe 2022.
It's called From React to HTMX on a Real-World SaaS Product.
We did it and it's awesome.
It's this company called Context.
And I will have this link available to you here at the end.
The YouTube is not even all that long.
But I wanna highlight some of these things that,
I think their team was a team of four developers,
one JavaScript developer, three Python developers.
They work in Django.
They actually went from having a fully functional
React website to an HTMX and Django only product,
or mostly product.
They made no UX compromises.
So they kept all the UI that the users were used to.
They reduced their code base from 21,500 lines of code
to 7,100 lines of code.
That is a drastic reduction in lines of code, period.
They reduced their web build time from 48 to five seconds.
So that's a huge, huge increase in productivity there.
Their first load time to interact,
it was reduced by around 50 to 60%.
So you can imagine all that JavaScript net
that's kind of in the way during that first time to load.
I'm sure it helps a lot with SEO and that kind of stuff.
You're getting an immediate response.
And their company deals with very large data sets.
They found, I put data sets instead of data sets,
but they found that they had larger data sets
that were possible with an HTMX application
as opposed to React.
And they lost their JavaScript developer.
So they went from four developers to three,
which it is a huge cost cutting benefit to them
as a company and also no need for additional resources
to understand the JavaScript.
So again, I highly recommend that DjangoCon Europe Talk.
It's on YouTube, but I'll link it to you in a moment.
And let's see.
I believe my playlist,
in case you wanted to hear some of the music
you've been hearing around today
and that you have in,
it's one song from each of the artists
that's in my MusicBinder application.
This is the playlist here.
Again, I'll also give you a place to find that afterwards.
And lastly, we still have about 15 minutes
if you have some questions I can come around.
I just wanted to say thank you all for coming.
I really appreciate it.
I worked really hard to have something
that at least I was excited about.
I hope that at the very least,
it starts spurring some imagination,
some different ways to think about
how you build your web applications.
Again, it's not an either or proposition.
I definitely don't want to learn JavaScript,
but if some of you find that you might find any benefit
like the people over at DjangoCon.
Oh, these are really crazy.
One last thing, I don't have it up on here,
but if you go to pythonbynight.com,
and then up at the top, there's some links up there.
There's one that's called Talks.
If you click on that link, there should be right at the top
a reference to this tutorial here.
I have a lot of resources there that we talked about today.
In addition to the links to the playlist and all that stuff,
I also have a version of this repo
that's a more step-by-step guide to getting to this stage.
It's called SimpleSight, not very creative there,
but that repo has documentation that talks about
how you're building your routes with FastAPI,
how the templates work, and so on.
That might also prove helpful
if you felt like this was going a little too quick
and you kind of wanted to build it yourself from scratch.
You have a little bit more time, then that's also there.
If you have any questions, you can reach me on Mastodon.
There's my handle.
I'll be around all week.
Hopefully, I'll see some of you.
Like I said, I might open up an open space
later during the week so we can do some other cool things.
So that's all from up here.
I'm gonna walk around if you have any questions
or if you feel like you've had enough, you're ready to go.
That's cool as well.
Thank you all.
Thank you.